Okay, hi.
All right.
So before we start, just a friendly plug
to please fill out the GD survey after this talk.
We really want your feedback.
I wanna hear the good, I wanna hear the bad.
Please give it all to us.
And also, please, please, please,
turn off your cell phones, please.
Okay, so let's start.
Hello, my name is Laura DeYoung,
and I'm the Art Director of League of Legends at Riot Games.
I'm a visual designer by trade,
and I've been working in interactive media for 18 years.
And 12 of those years, I have been lucky enough
to work in my dream industry, which is the games industry.
I am still so happy to be here.
Can't even put words on it, but.
Okay, before Riot, I worked at EA,
and I worked at Ubisoft,
helping to direct the visual direction and UI
for games like Far Cry 3, Assassin's Creed 2,
and NBA Street.
And I've been at Riot for four and a half years.
And when I started, I was the visual design director
for League of Legends, and kind of for Riot as well.
And now as art director, my focus has shifted to managing artists
and serving more as a creative stakeholder on League.
And today, I want to talk about a project we've been working on for four years,
and that's building the new client for League of Legends.
And, okay, we just launched our open beta last November,
and we will be launching the client soon to players.
I'm sorry, I still have to say soon.
I imagined I was going to be able to give you a date, but it's soon.
And the project lessons are still very fresh.
And when I say fresh, I mean we've been updating
this PowerPoint right at the end,
based on developments that are happening
back at the studio right now.
So the information we're gonna share is really fresh,
and I hope there's gonna be some lessons for you,
because we're learning some lessons every day.
So the majority of the talk will focus on design decisions,
but I also wanted to share some of the organizational
lessons we learned along the way,
so we'll do a little bit of both.
Okay.
So today I'm going to focus on three things.
So first is just a brief history of the client.
You kind of need that to understand all the work that
went into this.
And then the 11 lessons that we learned.
We learned way more than 11, but I'm
going to just share 11 with you today for the sake of time.
And then the status of the client today,
which by the way is a lesson in and of itself.
All right.
So before we dive into lessons, let's go back.
to 2006, when two entrepreneurial gamers gathered a small group of developers to pour their
hearts and souls into League of Legends.
And it would have been easy to slap a free-to-play game on a web browser, but the team wanted
a dedicated client so players would have a stable, competitive gaming experience, and
the development team could add features and build content continuously without disrupting
player experience.
Right?
So a nice contained experience.
and they launched the game using Adobe Air.
And I've unearthed some old forgotten images
of the first client, and I know some writers,
they're out there and they're kind of cringing
because we've come a long way artistically
since these samples, but I think it's still fun
to look back, and by the way, the next series of images
are a bit of a mix from the very first release
and some different versions that we did over the years.
We couldn't find everything from the very first release.
So from a designer's perspective, this is not really pretty.
But it definitely served its purpose.
Players could see which of their friends were online,
they could chat, and they could invite them to a game.
They could check out their champion roster
and their abilities, augment their character's stats
with our runes and mastery system,
and purchase champions and skins in the online shop.
And most importantly, they could launch a game to the client.
They could play.
But we had designed ourselves into a corner,
and it was becoming incredibly difficult for the client
to do anything else.
Immediately after launch, the player base
expanded far faster than anyone had expected.
And the growth of the game made it very challenging
to step back and dedicate attention to the client.
And teams wanted to add content, right?
Everyone's excited, like, let's add stuff, the game's great.
So they want to add new game modes,
and they want to add champion bios,
and they want to add patch notes, and community videos,
and e-sports announcements, and everything
that you could possibly imagine.
And the team, the dev team, responded to these demands
by slapping on tech, art, and audio
without any clear vision for the UX or the visual design.
And this went on for years.
And we continued to build on the client
because League was always in catch-up mode.
When I got here four and a half years ago,
we were actually still in catch-up mode,
so it was really crazy.
And in 2013, that Band-Aid approach
was really not working anymore.
The League Air client was inconsistent
both visually and functionally.
We lacked a strong visual brand
to tie our different UIs together
and set us apart from other games.
And we didn't have a set of visual style guides
or tools for our developers.
And what that meant was that instead of hyper-focusing
on making really cool shit for our players,
they would spend time reinventing the wheel
for each feature.
So each new piece of content, like new game modes,
or this was the Rune Combiner,
I don't know if anybody remembers this thing,
but I know maybe you wanna forget it,
but it wound up with teams customizing
their visual design work.
So they were like, hey, I got a new feature
and there's no rules, so woo, I'm just gonna do this
the way that I think I should do it.
And the back end was not functional for developers.
It was risky to add or subtract content
because there was a high chance
that any change would break the client.
And this picture I put in this Jenga tower
because I heard engineers refer to the tech
as a Jenga tower.
And you would go and talk to them and say,
hey, can I just swap out this graphic for this graphic?
And you'd get this like, no, no,
you can't swap those graphics
because players might not be able to play the game
if we swap those graphics.
So it really was the Jenga tower.
Not anymore.
But at that time it was.
And the players felt the pain.
And by the way, we shared their pain.
And these quotes that I'm sharing,
this is the G-rated stuff from our forums.
And I'm gonna read it out loud.
At Riot, your client sucks.
GG Riot with your terrible, God-awful client.
And my personal favorite,
I do not know what I did in a past life
to deserve this shitty client.
whoever you are out there, we really want to fix this client for you, I feel you.
So when a project has gone this far, sometimes the only solution is to nuke it from orbit.
Really, that's where we were at. We're like, there's nothing, we cannot polish this turret,
there's nothing left that we can do with this. So we hit the reset button with a dedicated team.
So this is introducing the art team, that we're hungry to make the client a great experience
for players. The LCU team is quite large, it's bigger than this, but this talk is mostly about
the artist, that's who's represented up here.
And we collected 11 lessons from our experience
rebooting the client.
And I hope they will help you examine your projects
from a different perspective, and maybe even
inform your design philosophy and your processes.
And I tried to keep this presentation focused
to around 40 minutes.
So I've packed our years of development
into these really quick lessons.
But before I dive in, an important caveat,
the development process was not smooth, and it was not perfect.
Game development is iterative, and I think a lot of you
know that it's often pretty messy.
So getting to this point has involved a few false starts,
pivots, expected and unexpected challenges, all of which
have led to some pretty hard learnings to us.
OK, so let's go.
No matter how big a team is, I believe the first step
is to identify clear goals.
So having a shared understanding of what you want to accomplish allows artists to explore
different directions while still trying to achieve the same goals, right?
We're all like going towards the same goalpost, we're running in the same direction.
So the goals we established, they weren't groundbreaking, but it gave us a shared understanding
and we wanted the client's visual identity to achieve three things.
First, provide a flexible design for developer efficiency.
represent League's unique and eclectic fantasy world,
and most importantly, resonant with players.
Okay, for flexible, let me explain to you
what I mean by that.
We needed the artistic style to be something
we could dial up or dial down and change
depending on the needs of the product.
So League, it's ever-evolving, it's changing all the time,
and the client's artistic choices needed to be flexible
and provide a sandbox for developers
to continuously add content, okay?
And at Riot, we do aim to craft every piece of art
and make it feel super special to players.
But with the client, we need to balance that
with scalability and systems thinking.
There's not many opportunities to have a one-off
in a design system.
Okay, so represent League's unique
and eclectic fantasy world.
What do we mean by that?
So we wanted the client to not only represent League's IP,
but to actually deepen the fantasy.
So there is so much IP going on,
and we wanted to connect that to players.
and have the new client be a sort of extension of that fantasy.
And then finally, resonate with players.
Our most important stakeholder, players.
In the end, it doesn't matter how nice the art is or how nice the design is,
if it doesn't resonate with our players, we have absolutely failed.
Okay.
So before we dove into design mode,
we had to understand and appreciate the diverse, complex...
and sometimes ambiguous regions and characters in our universe.
So we have 12 regions in League, including a region like Demacia,
which is a lawful, militaristic society of fiercely proud people
who value honor and justice.
And you can contrast that with a region like Zon,
which is a polluted industrial undercity whose wealth stems
from black market traders.
and unrestricted and sometimes really unscrupulous inventors.
If anybody saw the Warwick update that we did recently,
you know these people do some pretty unscrupulous things.
So within these 12 regions, we have a range
of champions and fantasies.
So Garen, a brave warrior loyal to his land
who fights for justice no matter the cost.
I think Garen's kind of boring.
And then my favorite, Orianna.
who's an intricate kind of creepy clockwork girl
and has celebrated feats of superior Piltover ingenuity.
I love Oriana.
And at the same time, we have this absurdly cute Teemo,
who's like a mushroom-tossing yordle
who appears to really enjoy being the ultimate troll
of Summoner's Rift.
And yes, he is the devil.
If you play our game, you know it's true.
Okay, so we have a diverse universe with tons of regions,
a broad range of champions,
and a mix of fantasies.
So how do we achieve our design goal?
Represent League's unique and eclectic fantasy world.
It's gonna be pretty tough.
Okay, so we tried the obvious design choice
in the beginning, super obvious.
Let's represent every region and every fantasy.
Let's try to blend them all together and see what we get.
Of course, that's gonna be great.
But when you try to communicate everything through a design,
you end up communicating absolutely nothing.
So here the team was working with a concept we called
modern fantasy.
So think modern materials mixed with a fantasy shape
language.
And this look was intended to bridge the gap
between high fantasy champs like Ryse
and sci-fi feeling champs like Lucian.
And this concept sort of meets our goals
by trying to represent all of League's unique
and eclectic fantasy world, but that's really all it does.
because by trying to be everything,
it lacked a distinct visual flavor.
And again, we really saw the client as our opportunity
to not just represent League,
but deepen players' engagement with our IP
through visual storytelling,
and this design just wasn't quite doing it.
So, we began to narrow our focus
and identify common themes.
And we started to ask, hey, okay,
so what are the common themes and experiences
for every League of Legends player?
What do they see in every single game?
And that brought us to the Nexus.
So the goal of every League match
is to destroy the opposing teams in Nexus,
which is an edifice of crystallized magic.
And here's an exploration of the concept of the Nexus.
And it's a nice looking design,
but the design did not uniquely represent
League's eclectic fantasy world.
We kind of felt like the crystals could be any game.
And there isn't much of a story to be told about the Nexus,
if I'm honest with you.
It's just kind of like you blow it up.
You hit it and you blow it up.
So we didn't feel like there was much there.
But we did think that narrowing the focus
and finding common themes were the right approaches
to this design challenge.
But we realized, hey, we actually need a narrative.
So digging into the cultural artifacts of specific regions
that brought us to the region of Piltover.
So Piltover is a thriving progressive city
and the cultural center of our universe.
where art, craftsmanship, and trade walk hand in hand.
So Piltover's power comes not from their military,
but the engines of invention, commerce, and forward thinking.
So they're kind of like the innovators of our universe.
We love them.
And our team immediately latched onto this specific Piltover
artifact called Hextech.
And in our universe, Hextech is a superior technology
that harnesses the power of magic
through a mastercrafted mechanical object.
So champions who can't typically control magic or channel magic,
they can do so now with a Hextech device.
That's very convenient.
If you've ever laned against Caitlyn, she has that rifle,
and she has a crazy range.
You can thank the inventors of Hextech
for getting beat up in bottom lane.
OK, so here are Hextech device concepts created
by our world-building team.
And in each iteration of this bow,
the artist attempted to communicate
that a Hextech device is expertly handcrafted.
The blue is a reminder that the source of power
is magic, which courses through the entire Hextech device.
And then this glove, I'm not sure if the bow went,
but anyway, you can see the glove.
The glove followed the same principles,
uniquely handcrafted and visible magic
coursing through the device.
So the team gravitated to this device.
It kind of became our muse, particularly the glove.
And armed with this Hextech theme,
the team started to form a shared narrative.
There it goes, yeah.
Hextech gives a champion the power to control and channel magic.
And we explored the idea of the client being a physical representation of a Hextech device.
So the client could serve as a magical, intelligent partner that navigates players through the
experience.
So it works, right?
It seemed like it worked.
So now we had a narrative that inspired us, which is great.
And it was time to roll up our sleeves and explore this concept as a design.
And at this moment, the client's UX was not nailed down.
We didn't know what the menus were going to be.
We didn't know what all the buttons were going to be
and all the interactions.
And that's absolutely fine.
We really didn't care about that.
We just wanted to get a feeling for how Hextech would work
if it was translated to an interface.
So we keep those explorations super, super loose,
but we always recall our design goals.
And after many iterations,
we wound up with a few options that we kind of liked,
but they didn't quite meet our goals.
And again, provide a flexible design for developer efficiency,
represent League's unique and eclectic fantasy world,
and resonate with players.
Those were our goals.
OK, so on one side of the spectrum,
we had designs that looked like this.
Super lightweight, easy to develop,
easy to develop take on Hex Tech.
So it meets our flexible design goal.
And if you take a look, like those little sort
of white icons in the middle, that
was our one big hint that this was a machine.
So you can see this is about as light as you can go.
And again, this meets our goal of being flexible.
There are no heavy, intricate machine parts
that would be difficult or time-consuming
to design and animate.
And while it's flexible, it did not provide insight
into League's unique and eclectic fantasy world.
And I'll add that I really don't think
this would resonate with players either.
So we have this on one side,
and then on the other side of the spectrum,
we have these runes page prototype that was rich in theme.
It totally embraced the theme of Hextech craftsmanship
and the machine.
And during the review, I just want to say,
we were reviewing this and the team was liking it.
We're all like, oh, this is feeling really good.
And team was on board, kind of like,
yeah, we can keep building on this.
And people were brainstorming different ways
that we could expand this.
And then someone asked, hey, what if we decided
to add another room type to this screen?
So it was like, a lot of quiet, crickets chirping,
and people looking at the floor because, me too.
Because we'd gotten really caught up in this,
the cool factor had distracted us,
and we had lost sight of our goal.
Because the design did a great job of translating Hextech,
but it lacked flexibility.
It's a super, super compact design
with interlocking elements,
which require each element to be rendered
to look like integrated machine parts.
It had to make sense.
And we wouldn't easily be able to add or subtract
from a design like this.
But.
We did see something promising in this design,
even if it was missing on the goal of flexibility.
So we decided to explore each element in this design
and deconstruct them into a visual system
that would meet all of our goals.
So we wanted to kind of take this with us to the next step.
And this is one of my favorite moments of development.
I love this time.
which is deconstructing a visually interesting thing,
concept, whatever, into systems and rules
that will define a design language.
I absolutely love doing this.
So as a visual designer, having a defined design language
helps you make deliberate design choices
throughout production.
It keeps the work consistent and will help you
and your team to understand and communicate
why a design is or is not working.
You will now have a shared language
to communicate with each other.
So it's not just like, hey, I feel like it's this.
It really helps.
So in a perfect world, also, each iteration evolves the design rules and pushes the product
closer to the design goals. So by the way, I do think it's great to have those rules
up front and early, but be ready to dial them in as you make new discoveries during development.
So let's break down together in this room what was and what wasn't working on the room page,
because I really want you to understand all of it. So what worked? We like the sharp-edged
directional magic.
It didn't read like random smoke.
It looked like it had purpose,
and we felt it could be used to reinforce functionality.
We liked some of the shape language
you're beginning to see here.
The design didn't feel like ribbons and scrolls
and familiar fantasy elements.
It felt more like a sharp, well-crafted technology,
and we liked how responsive it felt.
Players are getting feedback
that helps them understand their interactions,
and it was kind of fun, too, so we liked this.
And what did not work?
So the machine metaphor was way too dominant.
If we took all this heavy rendered material and metal
and put it next to a leak illustration,
it would really compete with it.
If you know our splash illustration,
you saw it in the beginning there,
there would be a competition.
And the compact design with interlocking parts
was inflexible.
If we started to change buttons and where things were placed,
we would need to redesign and repaint the whole background
to keep all the elements feeling integrated like a machine.
It was almost like too real.
And also, we need to have a very specific type of artist
around to pull this off consistently.
It's really not scalable, and it doesn't allow us
to leverage all the talent in the team.
Just so you guys understand, League is a really big team.
There's a lot of people on the team,
but the team is all made up of tiny little feature teams,
so there's not a central UI team.
It's not like everything's gonna go through a central group.
It just doesn't work that way.
So that's why we really had to think about scalability.
So from this exercise, we now have a shared understanding
of what's working and what's not working.
which informed our next step,
which is establishing a design language.
All right.
So to create a design language,
we first focused on Hex Tech's two primary elements,
magic and metal.
And as you design, it is so tempting,
it is so tempting to focus on execution,
but before you dive in, I think it's really important
to define the purpose of your primary elements.
Ask when, where, and why you should use
your primary elements.
don't decorate. So our magic needed to be deliberate. We didn't want it to be simply
window dressing, like just smoke, just hanging out, not doing anything. And magic, by the way,
is such a fun concept to play with, and I feel like there's plenty of room to explore and re-imagine
magic for our game. You know, for example, you have bright, elegant magic like Gandalf,
the white that communicates comfort and hope. Thank you, Gandalf. And you can contrast that
to Lord Voldemort with the sharp, erratic lightning spells. You know, it feels really violent.
And then there's room for whimsical, silly interpretations
of magic like an hocus pocus.
We wanted Hextech Magic to feel like a magical,
intelligent partner that guides players through the client.
We want it to be beautiful still,
but we want it to feel like it's guiding you.
So we formed three core tenets for our application
of Hextech Magic in the client.
So first, it's viscous.
Hextech Magic tends to stick around
and has some weight to it,
falling somewhere between water and smoke.
It lingers so players don't miss an important communication.
It's also directional.
So it's always moving towards an intentional path.
So as you see in this example, it's not a poof of smoke.
Magic has an edge that, along with motion,
guides the player's attention.
And this is a really early sample.
If you saw it outside of a container,
you'd also see there's a very clear edge on our magic.
Then also it's focused.
So the highest value or the brightest brights
feel like a gathering of concentrated magic,
and a white hot light is used to attract
the player's attention toward pivotal moments.
And here's the magic incorporated
into one experience in the client.
Okay, so let's imagine that a player cues up for a game.
They wait a moment, and then the client finds
a match for the player, and this prompt
requires the player to accept.
And around the perimeter, we've used an interpretation of magic
to indicate the duration the player has to accept the match.
It starts from one side of the accept button,
ends on the other side of the accept button,
so it kind of frames it.
And also, I want to add that we define magic
as being limited to primary buttons and important gameplay
UI.
So magic serves to draw the player's attention
to key interactions, just like that timer and the button.
So now that we define magic, let's
take a look at the other HexTech elements.
Metal.
So like magic, metal had to serve a meaningful purpose.
And for this design challenge, we
followed the simple rule, which is simple beats complex.
And we studied the hextech concept art.
And these intricate hextech artifacts
were complex and elaborate designs.
They're really beautiful.
And there's so much attention to detail
in every inch of the design.
And we love the shape language that
was happening in these examples.
And we believed we could extract the shapes,
and they would work really well in a UI.
But first, we had to simplify this.
And as visual designers, our job is to simplify the world.
And as game developers, I believe
we should make visual design choices that
provide clarity so players can focus on playing the game
and not fighting the UI.
So we reduced the shape language down to three core shapes.
square, circle, and diamond.
And okay, I know this doesn't look groundbreaking,
doesn't look groundbreaking,
but when you see them presented like this.
But these were the primary shapes we stripped
out of the Hex Tech door concept that you saw earlier
and started layering and combining
to create our shape language.
And here's an example of how we combine these shapes
to create simple Hex Tech elements.
And I'll add that we also made some early decisions
about what these shapes would indicate,
like they do have purpose.
So for example, diamonds are normally used to point players
to a specific piece of important information or an interaction.
So now we wanted to simplify the rendering of the metal
so that it wouldn't compete with our content like the splash art.
So through color, shape, language, and motion,
we felt like we could communicate the metal and mechanical nature of HexDeck.
So how did we do that?
So the way we did that was first,
We chose gold, a color that people associate with quality metals.
It seemed like an easy choice.
We added a soft gradient, so there's a nod to specular lighting.
So it kind of hints at being metal without us rendering out all the metal.
And then a sharp edge shape language that gives the impression
of something mechanical.
So by the way, we're getting into impressions now,
rather than literal interpretations of a machine.
It's becoming more metaphorical, which, by the way,
will be more forgiving.
when you're designing screens, because remember form follows function, right?
It does.
And when you have things a bit more abstract, it can be more forgiving, and you're going
to be able to deliver on that.
Okay.
So also, yeah, there it goes.
We saw a big opportunity for motion to support the idea that this slim, elegant line work
was a machine.
And when you think of a mechanical movement, you think of industrial machinery with weight
and inertia that creates a sense of physical tangibility.
So we decided to apply that physical tangibility to our metaphorical
hextech machine-like line work to communicate that it was a machine without rendering the metals.
This is a very early test. We just had this very simple line work and we worked with one of our
motion artists who just said, hey, let me just take a crack at this. He did this in about two days.
And it gave us a lot of confidence that we would be able to make this feel machine-like.
And here's how it all comes together.
This is the champion select screen where you can see how we're combining all the elements and balancing them with crazy colorful detailed splash art.
So we have at the center a gold metal hex tech ring, which feels like a mechanical lens focusing the champion combined with a magic animation that directs the player's eyes the next interaction, which is the next player picking a champion.
And as we were defining our design language,
engineering and UX were deep in exploration too.
We were all working together.
And by this time, we really felt like
we had to bring everything to the table
and kind of make something together
because we don't want to work in a silo.
So strong artistic, technical, and UX solutions
were being proposed, but we needed to test these assumptions
because we could talk all day,
but we needed something to point to.
The team needed a target.
We needed a North Star.
Like, what are we making together?
Like, we need to see this thing.
So we challenged ourselves to create a sample video
to solidify the vision for ourselves
and also to share it with the studio.
So for this challenge, we created a series of interactions
that the player would experience
getting into and out of a game.
So you're gonna see right now, it's kind of a play game flow
and there should be a game in there, but there won't be.
You'll just kind of see a victory or defeat screen
and then you'll see.
us transition out. So I'm going to play that right now.
We premiered this video at a company wide event and the
entire client team was watching and anticipating.
The heart is the strongest muscle.
Okay.
So company erupted in a standing ovation.
It's actually, I think, one of our best moments as a team at the studio.
There was laughter.
There was legitimate tears.
People were so happy.
I can't tell you how happy everybody was.
It was an emotional moment for the team because we worked really hard on this.
And we were energized.
And we came back and went full steam ahead.
Art, audio, engineering, and UX had this.
shared North Star, right?
We knew exactly what we were making together
and that feels so good, it feels great.
And it often translates to like,
crazy production velocity, right?
Like, we're all on the same page.
And they went back to work,
solving their respective challenges back at the studio.
And that brings me to my last lesson,
which is constantly come back to the table.
So for many, many months,
the visual designers and the UX designers
crafted beautiful designs and beautiful art assets,
but there was one major issue.
Engineering had a Herculean task
of rebuilding the client from scratch,
and they had to launch a product
that would not disrupt players.
And as always with development,
they unearthed technical obstacles,
and their production velocity was inevitably impacted,
but art and design's velocity was not.
So if you can imagine what kind of happened was we all started working together and when
I say the engineers slowed down, I mean we were going forward and they had to go all
the way back and redo a whole bunch of things.
And after several months of work and kind of reworking the tech, the engineers dug deep
into the tech and they compared it to what we were trying to do creatively and they discovered
that for the lowest spec computer, which we call the toasters.
performance was going to be a pretty big issue,
specifically for our motion targets.
And this is really where we made our mistake,
and if there's something you guys take away from this,
I hope you take this away.
And that was in allowing the different disciplines
on our team to fall out of step with each other for too long.
This is something we don't try to do at Riot,
like we actively try not to do that,
but we had a lot of rationalization
about why that was happening,
because the engineers,
they really had to fix some crazy shit, right?
And art and design, they didn't want to just sit around.
They wanted to keep making things.
So our disciplines fell out of step,
and they fell out of step longer than we expected.
We should have constantly performed reality checks
and closely collaborated with engineering,
testing the tech, critiquing the work and the build,
and trying different methods to achieve similar results.
So it's not enough to just bring everyone to the table.
You have to keep talking, sharing,
and testing each other's work.
Like even if you fall out of step with each other,
you need to find time to come back together again.
whenever you can, as much as you can to talk and make sure everything is still in sync.
So, the client is still in beta, and we're analyzing player feedback and pain now. So
let's revisit our design goals and take a hard look at the project. First, provide a flexible
design for developer efficiency. Represent League's unique and eclectic fantasy world,
and resonant with players.
Provide a flexible design for developer efficiency.
Okay, holistically, we believe we delivered on this goal.
This lighter weight Hextech design system
provides a sandbox for developers
to create and launch new content.
And they can do so while maintaining
a consistent look and feel.
So we feel really good about this.
The designers crafted style guides and toolkits,
and by the way, some of them are here today,
so they're gonna be able to share them with you,
to provide guidance to the teams.
And we've shared these style guides on behalf,
so you can check them out there.
Those are the really edited ones.
We have some pretty detailed stuff.
And however, there are some limitations
to our current iteration.
I want to share that too.
We currently, for example, have a super tight color palette,
which is blue and gold, which limits our ability
to communicate different types of design elements
and their purpose.
For example, in the client, we originally
planned to have gold be only used for containers,
like important information.
But sometimes now, it's also used to indicate an interactive element.
And this can be confusing for players,
and it's a direct result of us not having enough colors and elements
even to play with. So that's something we want to revisit.
Represent League's unique and eclectic fantasy world.
We've received positive feedback from players
and the design community on the Hextech theme,
so we feel good about it. We're proud of the design.
But we could have pushed the design further to maximize immersion.
And for example, we're using web tech to build our client,
but we don't want it to feel like a website, right?
We want it to feel like a game.
And we didn't go far enough to update traditional
web design patterns like drop-down menus.
I mean, drop-downs, they suck,
and they don't feel fun or interactive,
and we do have some drop-downs in there.
And then the most important goal,
deliver a client that resonates with players.
The players have spoken.
We have not delivered on this just yet.
And while the theme has hit the quality bar,
players are focused on the most important part
of the client, which is performance, right?
And we've all heard the mantra, gameplay is king.
For our client, performance is definitely king.
And right now, we're making all the art
and technical decisions to maximize performance
for our players, so that's a big focus
that everybody's back at home working on right now.
Here we go.
So this video that's playing right now is our new target.
And this is the target for our first full launch
of the client.
I'm sorry there's no audio here,
because I know the audio really pumps things up.
But this, if you can imagine the last video I was showing,
you can kind of compare and see where we've had
to pull back some of our work.
And after we optimize performance, by the way,
we'll be back to listening to player feedback
to inform future changes,
and also back to improving the client
and adding things back in.
So on League, I'll tell you.
No feature is ever complete, it really is never complete.
We're always looking for opportunities
to improve the experience for players.
So, it's gonna be ongoing.
And there is no secret sauce in understanding
how to improve player experience.
As game developers, we just have to ask.
The world of game development has really changed
and we can get instant feedback from our players now
and I advise you to do that.
So for the new client,
we bake player feedback into production.
So last March, we launched Alpha to get early player feedback.
And then last November, we launched Beta
for another round of feedback.
And that's actually where we got a lot of the feedback
about performance.
And for any League players out there in the audience,
I just want to say thank you so much for testing the client.
Thank you for your feedback.
And we really, really hope,
and we're working really hard to deliver something
that's really worthy of your passion.
So thank you, and please keep giving us feedback, by the way.
And finally,
I just wanted to add this here, that we're taking our design system of Hextech
and we're involving the theme outside of the game.
So other teams have taken our Hextech interpretation
and they've applied it to their products.
So Merch has used it for packaging.
This is a package that we created in collaboration with BunkoPop,
where the team reinterpreted Hextech in print form.
And last year, the team used the Hextech metal language.
and for the Art of League of Legends website,
and for the book.
So you can kind of see it all through that.
So for us, the real test of this design
is in its application, and also in its reinterpretation.
And we're very excited to see how Hextech
will be applied to other experiences
for players in the future.
And that's my talk.
Thank you.
Okay, so I have a bunch of time.
I have about 25 minutes left.
I probably talked too fast.
Sorry.
I'm supposed to be 40.
I knew I didn't talk too fast.
But anyway, I have about 25 minutes left and we have two mics, so happy to answer any questions.
There are two visual designers here with me in the audience from this team named Kevin
and Ted.
They're right down here.
And they have some of our toolkits and our style guides and things like that if anybody
wants to talk to them too and check them out.
So are there any questions?
Hi.
I was wondering if you could speak a little bit
about your choice in typography and stuff like that.
Was that something that happened
after you had settled on your basic shape language
in terms of that stuff and how much iteration you did?
On the typography?
Yeah.
Yeah, absolutely.
So,
When we actually started on typography, even before we worked on the designs, this came
in really early because we knew we were going to have to craft our own font or kind of do
an interpretation of a font because we have so many languages that we have to support.
So for the main font that's even in this presentation, which is Beaufort Pro, we were looking at
the League of Legends logo, which, yeah.
which is very busy, but it's a Serif font.
So that's really what happened.
We were looking at the League of Legends logo
and we were looking for fonts
that would be complementary to that.
So we picked a Serif font
that is reminiscent of League of Legends
and then a Sans Serif font for all of the body copy
because that needs to be very, very legible.
So something with a bit of character
that has that Fantasy League feeling
and then something really simple
that's for all of the body copy
and explanatory text and bios and things like that.
Okay, thanks.
Hi. Hi. Can you talk through the creative process for prototyping and
creating wireframes before visual design is actually applied to the user
experience because I assume you don't just jump right into you know super
complex illustrations and how those interactions are actually created.
So the teams like our disciplines are all working at the same time.
And we definitely have UX designers that are embedded with the team working with the visual designers,
but I will say that there were some times where the visual designers were helping out with the UX as well.
So when I say that the process was very organic,
the UX designers don't hand off finished wireframes to the artists.
That's kind of what we describe as waterfall.
It's not usually how we work, especially not in the beginning.
So when we got to a place where we knew what kind of features we'd have to have on a screen,
they would start putting together some wires
and they would sit with the visual designers,
they'd kind of do it together,
and then the visual designers would start
doing some designs.
And we've had many designers even say to us,
it's not always easy to do a wireframe
if you don't have some idea what the design is.
So I would say it was really iterative,
and over time the wireframes became
more and more like the designs, right?
As the designs tighten up, the wireframe tighten up,
so it's kind of happening at the same time like this.
So that was really what the process was.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Hi.
Yeah, I just had a question about making
really large, impactful visual changes to games.
I mean, personally, I work somewhere
where if we have a game that's generating so much money,
we're afraid to change anything because we have all
these customers paying so much.
So I was wondering about a strategy about,
because there's no doubt that the game looks beautiful
and it continues to.
to do that but it changes so much and I wonder if there's any thought or weighing the risks of
you know making the game that looks even though it's more beautiful looks so different that
players almost don't even relate to it. I was wondering if you could. Yeah that's one of the
reasons why we start releasing things early to players to try to feel it out for them.
You know we start showing them some designs even before the beta saying hey this is kind of the
direction that we're going so we can start getting feedback and also.
giving them a moment to warm up to it,
because change is hard, right?
Change is tough.
Like even if you're changing for something
you don't really like,
and I think a lot of us can relate,
you get used to like a broken tool or whatever.
You're like, don't change it, I'm fine.
And we know this, and we're really empathetic to it.
By the way, we experience it ourselves
when maybe a new splash comes out,
it's our favorite champion.
We're like, wait, what just happened?
And you run over to the artist's desk.
So we are really empathetic,
but what we try to do is just get things
in front of people as early as we can.
That's our main strategy, get things in front of people as early as we can.
And we talk a lot to each other on the floor.
We play the game a lot.
We're very invested in the game.
And we're expected to have our finger on the pulse of what's
going on with our community.
So we read their feedback.
We really do, by the way.
If you guys wonder if we read the forums, we read them.
And the comments get sent around.
When it's like, hey, I think we should fix this.
There's a lot of really unhappy people on the forum.
That's the best thing I can tell you is we just communicate with our community as much as we can and we try to get things in front of them just so they can get used to it and get a feel for how they're going to react to it.
Thank you. You're welcome.
Hi.
Hi. Great talk, by the way. Thank you so much. Awesome information for us.
He kind of asked a similar question I was going to ask, but I had kind of two questions.
how do you filter the amount of player feedback, community feedback, because I know that's
that's probably a lot to deal with. And then leading up into my next, which was how much did
you guys work with other departments on your team, like art departments, whether it was
the effects department and design? Okay, I can answer both. For feedback,
It really depends how it comes in, how hot it comes in,
or how, I would even say how sensitive we are to it.
Maybe we were uncertain about something
and suddenly a bunch of people are talking about it
on Reddit, we're like, oh no, it's true.
And we'll all start talking about it on the floor,
but I wouldn't say we necessarily filter it.
What we try to do is read it and mine for nuggets.
So if somebody's saying, oh my God, I can't
like fucking believe you did this,
like we go through all the cursing and get to the,
A, they're really unhappy with how we changed the summoner icons.
It's not clear, Flash is not clear to them anymore
because we made it too orange.
They're just used to, out of the corner of their eye,
it being bright yellow, and they're unhappy about that.
And then we'll look around for other comments like that,
and we kind of mine for that data.
And then really we just talk to each other like,
yeah, that probably wasn't a great decision.
It looks pretty, but maybe we took it too far as far as gameplay.
So I don't know if that really answers your question.
I don't think we have a set way of going through our feedback.
And for your second question about working with other teams, we did.
So all of those HexTech concepts that you saw,
we work very closely with the Foundations team.
So our Foundations team is like an IP development team,
and they're absolutely awesome.
So they had really kind of rough concepts for HexTech,
and they gave them to us,
and then we started developing the idea of HexTech more,
and then we kind of handed it back to them,
and it went back and forth a few times.
And we loved this collaboration.
It was really fun to have the visual designers and the motion artists working with the concept
artists and developing a theme like this.
So yes, we definitely collaborate whenever we can, and it's really awesome.
We learn a lot when we do it.
It was very beautiful.
Thank you.
Thank you so much.
Hi.
Hi, thanks for the talk.
I have a question about as you're developing the new UI, do you have a separate client
that...
you run the new UI on against the back-end server,
obviously just being able to play the game?
Or do you have a UI mode that you switch between
Hex Tech and the old client?
Like, how do you get that A-B testing, like,
actually done during development?
I don't know if I can answer that question.
Can either one of you guys answer that question?
They're two.
Yeah, so we have a separate build.
Okay.
Separate build.
It's like entirely separate from the original thing.
I'll just repeat it what he says.
Yeah.
Okay.
Are you testing the client with actual players or is it all internal?
So yeah, we're doing currently like right now you can run either version of it.
Yes.
And then we did internal beta testing.
Yeah.
We buy beta and speed warp out.
Yeah, you could play both versions.
You could switch back and forth from one client to another.
Because we didn't want to just flip the switch and suddenly have people go into that because
we knew like this is a lot of players.
Yeah.
And there are a lot of regions.
And so it's very hard to predict that.
And even when we roll out, it's gonna be region by region.
Like we do things very slowly,
because what we don't wanna do is we don't wanna interrupt,
we don't wanna interrupt anybody's ability
to actually play the game.
Sure.
Thank you very much.
Okay, you're welcome.
Okay, hi.
I got two little questions.
And before I want to say,
The new client's awesome.
Thank you.
I've been really enjoying it recently.
It looks really great and everything.
Thank you so much.
I wanted to know, for example, compared to the old client where you had the little watch
window where you could be able to spectate high level players' games and, for example,
the chat that you could collapse and everything, when you were making the updated version of
the client, what decisions were made in order to, you know, what remained in the client
itself?
For example, a lot of people complain.
We're talking about like you can't minimize the little with the players or friends tab so it's kind of weird for them
But at the same time I'm guessing that was kind of intentional when you guys mentioned that you want to be relatively minimalistic to it
But how do you exactly?
Decide what staying and what's not the friends tab was intentional that one that decision
We made a long time ago, and that's a real commitment because you can look at the design
it's balanced with that piece in mind.
And it's really because what we know about League
is that it's a better experience to play the game
when you play with your friends, no matter what.
And I think anybody who plays the game,
you know, me, everybody, it's like,
I don't wanna play Pugs,
I really like playing with my friends.
So that was why that decision was made.
But as far as features,
what we're shooting for is feature parity,
and then we're gonna start adding new features.
So once we ship the client, it's really not done.
If you remember how I described League of Legends,
like a really big team made up of a lot of little teams.
Right now, LCU owns the entire client.
That's what we call a team,
it's the League Client Update team.
They own it.
But what's gonna happen once we release the game
to release the client to everybody,
is that it's gonna break up into small teams
and they're gonna go back to working on new features.
So you're gonna see things popping into the client
over the next few years.
But for now, the most important thing is feature parity.
Right.
And for the second question, now that you guys have gone into this entire thing of developing
the looks of Hextech and everything, how do you think there's an effort going on eventually
to update Piltover Champions?
For example, right now Caitlyn, she's from Piltover, but the guns and how it looks and
the VFX and everything doesn't really feel like the Hextech presented in the cloud itself
mostly.
I think Heimerdinger does kind of fit that because of the bluish things and the desserts
and everything.
And for example, Galio right now has a Hextech skin
that looks nothing like the current precision Hextech.
Are you talking about the old Galio?
I know they're working on a rework.
As a player, I don't know anything about it, but yeah.
Wait till the rework.
But no, I think that the answer is yes.
And as a matter of fact, Hextech's been bobbing
around the game for a while.
There's been the idea of Hextech.
And it's been slowly evolving into what it is now.
I would say a lot of this IP work was really only completed.
pretty recently. The work that we were doing, the foundations team was still working on what
Hextech is. So yes, I think we look for opportunities now whenever we're doing a Champion update.
we look for opportunities to link them back
to all the faction work we're doing.
And I couldn't show you,
we have a lot of faction work that's done,
shape language and color and culture
and everything about the place.
So when you see a new splash come in
and if a champion's from Ionia or from Freljord,
you'll see that there might be some motifs
in the background and some changes
that we're making to the champion
so that they land very solidly
in what we consider now to be the definite look
and feel of that region, that realm.
But it's going to be a slow process because we can't really just update everything at once, right?
Because we're more focused on really gameplay changes that are going to be super important to the players.
So we focus there first and then we just find our opportunities to keep making the art more consistent across the board.
All right, thank you.
And one last thing.
I don't know if anybody in the room here
that was in the late client update has to do with this,
but my dual partner says thank you very much
for adding the potato mode.
It was horrible, it was just killing his PC
every time we played.
Yeah, we're gonna, and that is exactly what we're working on.
So that's great feedback.
That's like the big thing that we're working on right now
is like how to get that all,
how to get that all performing well
for the potato, the toasters, for all of those.
So yes, and the two artists are right down here
if you wanna talk to them.
Thank you very much.
You're welcome.
Hi.
Hi, thank you for your talk.
I'm curious to hear about how the new client
has impacted user player engagement with VIP
for specifically them accessing the news on the client,
the store, or the creative content
that's published on the client.
And is there any room for improvement?
Oh yeah, there's going to be room for improvement.
I think we're still figuring out, I don't know if you've seen our universe website,
but we put up the universe website now that explains all of the regions and there's stories
about our champions and everything's there so we can start getting the story of RRP out
there.
And, you know, we do surveys as well, like asking players how excited are you about the
lore and how much more lore do you want to see.
We get mixed feedback, but a lot of players do want to understand more about the world,
and that's one of the reasons why we do this.
But as far as relating it straight back to engagement,
it's hard for me to do that right now with the client not particularly being finished or out there.
I think it was for us, it's more about, of course, we want engagement, but it's about immersion.
Because before we had so many different styles and so many things going on.
We didn't have factions. You didn't know where these champions were from.
It's hard to be immersed in that.
It's like a kind of a scattering of really cool creative stuff.
So what we're looking for in the game
is having that sense of immersion,
having it feel like everything was thought through
and all the pieces fit together.
Got it.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Hi.
That was really amazing. I got goosebumps looking at everything.
So congratulations.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
I was just wondering how does your team work, your UI, UX team?
Is everyone hyper specialized in their little field?
Or is everyone a bit of a Swiss army knife where they can do everything
and do your artists do implementations or they just leave it to the engineers?
How does that work in a big team?
That's a really good question.
So first, on the type of people on the team, we have both.
We have people who are specialists,
and we have people that are more like a Swiss Army knife.
And like one of our motion artists, Andrew,
he is like everything.
Like he can do everything.
He can do this beautiful motion work.
He can think of tools.
He's very technical.
He's kind of a savant, brilliant guy.
So he is a Swiss Army knife.
And some of us are, we're way more on the art side, right?
Like myself, like way more into graphic design
and art and thinking about design.
So our team is, I think, a healthy mix.
We also have an artist that's really into UX, right?
Who loves, happily bang together his own wireframes
and share them with the UX designers.
So I'd say we have a mix on our team.
We have specialists and we have people
that are more Swiss Army Knives.
And then as far as how we work together,
is that what the other part of the question was?
Like, um...
Do they specifically do UX only or do they dabble a bit in visual?
No, yeah, I would say that there are some people who don't, but like I said,
there are some people who definitely do. So it's just kind of like, it totally depends.
Like Jessica, one of our artists, she's an amazing illustrator, like insane.
Like she does splash illustration as well. She's also a visual designer.
So in the beginning, when you saw that really rendered take of Hextech we did
that looked like a machine, a lot of that was Jessica's rendering.
and she can render way further than that.
That was actually pretty rough
compared to how far she can go.
So that's it, yeah.
I think we just have a mix of people.
We have probably like three or four people
that are more Swiss Army knife,
and then we probably have three or four people
that are more specialists.
So in terms of if you want to expand your team,
what do you look for in applicants or people?
Do you mean for a specific discipline?
Because you have to think that like the LCU team
is kind of a cross-discipline art team.
So do you mean specifically for like a team like LCU or do you mean for a discipline like
motion graphics versus visual design?
Well I guess if say you have a UI artist who is very interested in UX and they feel like
should I show more visual stuff to you or should I show more design stuff or would they
be worried that they can't code any actual UI?
We wouldn't be worried about that.
whether or not you could code,
that would be seen as a plus.
But I think what we usually ask applicants to do
is kind of pick, we talk a lot about being T-shaped
at the studio, so you're deep in one thing,
and then you have interests,
and you have a T-shaped mindset, right?
You understand multiple types of development,
and you have different skills.
So normally when somebody applies to Riot,
we wanna know what their deep T is,
and then everything else, it's, by the way, we love it.
The more T-shaped people are, it's really fantastic,
because.
then they're gonna be able to fill in the gaps in the team.
Like sometimes when the UX designers were too busy,
visual designer could jump in
and help out with the wireframes.
That's very useful because it unsticks the team.
So that's kind of how we do it.
I think that's.
Yeah, that's all.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
Thanks everybody.