Just a reminder before we start to silence your cell phones.
I'm Bronwyn, I'm a technical artist at Valve, and today I'm going to be discussing the what's,
how's, and why's of the content that drives the Counter-Strike global offensive economy.
So what is this talk?
I should first start by telling you what it isn't.
I'm not going to spend a long time talking about the advantages of adding an economy
to your game.
I'm going to assume that the reason you're here is you already have an idea about that.
If on the other hand, that is something you want to learn some more about,
we recently gave a series of talks at the Steam Developer Days on economies.
All that content is freely available to watch on YouTube,
so just head over to steamdevdays.com for some links.
So instead, this talk is about how we generated a large volume of content
with a really small team in order to kickstart our economy.
I'll be discussing the things that our customers value about the economy content
and how that information is helping us continue to make good decisions going forward.
Counter-Strike is an online multiplayer game.
It's a team-based first-person shooter,
and it's had several versions over the last 14 years.
Counter-Strike Global Offensive
is the latest, greatest version.
Like we do with our other products,
we use Steam to update CSGO regularly
as we strive to create the best experience possible.
In a multiplayer game, a big part of having
a good experience is provided by other players.
Our customers generate a huge amount of value
for each other just by participating in the game.
We want to encourage them to keep doing that.
The way that we encourage them is just by providing a bunch of fun and value to them,
and more importantly, by making it easy for them to provide a bunch of value to each other.
Involved products like Dota 2 and Team Fortress 2,
we found that a great way to help meet all of these goals at once is to add an economy to the game.
We can measure the success of our economy by checking in just on a few broad metrics,
and they're maybe not the ones that you'd expect.
After all...
Adding an economy isn't a goal in and of itself.
We're adding an economy in service of our other goals.
So the kinds of things that we're going to check on
are things like player numbers, player retention,
and individual play time.
Because after all, if our customers are having fun,
they're gonna keep coming back for more.
Since Team Fortress 2 and Dota 2
both have thriving economies,
we were able to crib a bunch of ideas from them.
They both use multiple channels
for distributing items to their players.
This gives customers lots of options for getting items.
Having lots of ways for customers to interact with the economy is a big positive
because it means a broader participation.
And economies are essentially multiplayer games.
The more people participating, the more fun it is.
In both Team Fortress 2 and Dota 2, not every item is available through every channel.
This is perfect when the goal is to provide lots of different ways to interact with the economy
and to see how our customers want to consume content.
But it's really difficult to directly compare the value of items in these different categories.
And at this point in CS Go's economy design discussion,
figuring out the value of individual items
was actually really important,
because leaving aside the how for the moment,
we still weren't sure what our customers wanted to consume.
So let's focus for a second on the marketplace.
This is one of the ways that our customers
can get at the content.
Customers can list items from their inventories
for sale for Steam Wallet funds.
The listings are in real currency amounts,
and they're set by the lister.
Because identical items can be listed for different amounts,
there's a constant downward price pressure
as the price pressure makes the supply and demand at a given price point equalize.
So, as a company, we had a unique opportunity.
This was the first time that we were launching an economy
since the market went live.
We decided that CSGO would become our first game
in which every item can be placed on the marketplace.
and individual items can't be bought any other way.
In fact, the only thing that we plan to sell directly
were the keys used to open our case drops.
So in this proposed market-centered economy,
the supply of items comes from our players.
They come from in-game drops,
so the more players we have playing,
the more supply there is.
The demand also comes from our players.
They're only going to purchase things that they feel are being sold for a fair price.
And with enough listings, the downward price pressure of the free market
is going to ensure that a fair price gets found.
So this sounded like a great way to simply ask our customers what they value.
So what did we decide to ship?
We could make weapon skins, character customization.
We could do...
new weapons, or we could just do cosmetic mesh changes
to existing weapons.
All these things have been modded by CS players in the past.
In fact, all the examples that I just showed
are community mods from GameBanana.
So clearly there is a demand for customization.
Whatever it was that we decided to ship,
we needed to create a lot of items
in order to fill out the economy.
So it's important that we make it as easy as possible to do so.
And in keeping with our goal of helping our players generate value for each other,
we'd like to make it possible for community members to contribute items to the game
and make money from their in-game sales.
We also need a lot of variety in order to figure out what our customers want.
We know that economies are more fun when there are more people participating.
They're also more fun when there are lots of items to compare
and lots of different ways to compare them.
So we didn't want to just create items with a broad range of value.
We also wanted to create items that could be valued in different ways
because players with different priorities
can actually care about different aspects of the same item.
So we'll want to keep these goals in mind
as we figure out which thing we want to start with.
The way we choose which of our options to go with
is to assess the benefits associated with each type of product
and then compare that against the risks associated with shipping it
and the resources required to actually complete the task.
At the time, CSGO was actually a really small team.
Our art team consisted of two technical artists,
and that's the whole list.
we are pretty resource limited.
So let's take characters, for example.
We know that customizable characters in TF2 and Dota 2
are really valuable and popular,
but they work best when there's lots of chances
to see the customization.
In Dota 2, the game is top-down, so you get to see your character all the time.
And in TF2, although it's a first-person game,
there are taunts and kill cams that give you lots of opportunities
to see your customization or show it off to other players.
CSGO is also a first-person game, but we don't have taunts.
So the chances to show off your customization
are actually a lot fewer than our other products.
And so the value here isn't maybe as high as we'd first hoped.
There's also a lot of challenges here, and there's a big risk that we could make team identification difficult.
Since CSGO is a team-based game, team ID is a really big part of having a good experience.
So it's possible that someone could have a customized character,
be really happy that they had something different and unique,
but they made everybody else that they were playing with less happy
because it was more difficult for everyone else to tell friend from foe.
It's also...
a big resource investment.
Not only do we have to take time
to try and solve our team ID problems,
but there's a lot of content that needs to be created,
and it's fairly complicated content.
With our small team, it would take a really long time
to make enough content to be able to ship the economy.
That's bad for us, because we'd like to ship something
as soon as possible,
especially something that we have doubts about,
because then we can get data back
that either validates our decision making
or indicates a different direction that we ought to go.
So on the whole, it didn't seem like characters
were the best place to start.
What about new weapons?
It could be really fun having a lot of gameplay variation.
On the other hand, our players practice intensely
with their favorite weapons,
right down to learning the recoil pattern
so that they can learn to compensate.
They're not going to throw away all that time investment
and try something new just for the sake of variety.
That means if we make new weapons,
they have to have a unique tactical value
that's going to attract players to them.
And really, there's only so many different options
that we can provide that are meaningful in variety.
And so actually, the value of shipping weapons goes down the more of them we ship,
which is directly counter to our goal of providing lots of items.
There's also a risk anytime we ship new weapons
that we're going to destabilize competitive play.
That could potentially make our customers so unhappy
that they just leave the game and never come back.
And that's the worst outcome that we can think of.
There's a fair amount of resources required to do weapon balancing to attempt to mitigate that risk,
on top of just the content work required to create the weapon meshes.
So again, it looks like new weapons are maybe not our best place to start.
So what about weapon mesh changes?
There's actually a surprising amount of benefit here.
After all, if you're changing your weapon,
it's something you're holding in your hands.
So even from the first-person view,
you see your customization all the time.
It's also something that could make other players
more happy that you have it.
Not only do they get to see something new and cool
because you're walking around with the weapon,
but if you drop it into the world,
someone else can pick it up and play with it
and have a positive experience.
We did have a couple of doubts, though,
so let's just see what those could be.
So we actually got pretty far along this path.
We customized the Hecka to the AK-47.
We played with it in-game,
and we did find that our concerns were validated.
The first thing is that weapon identification
is made a lot more difficult
with all of these different silhouettes.
It's super hard to tell just by looking at these guys
that the functionality for every one of these weapons
is identical.
And that brings me to my second point.
We were a little bit worried about how it would feel
to have different components that didn't actually affect gameplay,
and the answer is that it felt really artificial.
In the real world, if you changed out things like stocks and grips,
the weapon's recoil and accuracy would change,
and the experience of getting weapon components
that didn't affect the gameplay at all
was actually kind of disappointing.
So we reassessed the risk even upwards from where we thought it was.
There's also a bunch of work here, obviously, just to make the components.
So that leaves us with weapon skins.
At this point, we were getting actually really concerned
because how many different camouflaged weapons can we make
that people are really gonna care about?
But as we got further along in gathering reference,
we discovered that there's a whole world out there
we weren't even aware of.
People make crazy things for their weapons.
Everything from intricate Victorian scroll work
right up to straight up graffiti.
These things are essentially just blank canvases
and that means that there's room for whimsy.
That's not the case with our weapon mesh changes
where those things have to be based on real world components.
For weapon skins, we can make pretty much
whatever we can imagine.
So the benefit is a lot greater than we first thought.
They're also not very risky.
There's a little bit of risk that the color changes
would make the weapon identification
a little more difficult.
but on the whole it's nothing compared to our other options.
And then there's just the work of making the textures,
which is less than any of our other options.
It's also really easy for the community
to make these easier than anything else.
So we have a pretty clear winner.
In the real world, weapon finishes come in a vast array
of styles and colors.
So we already had a really good indication
of how far we could go with creating variety.
Now we just needed a way to make
a lot of things really quickly.
Since both our artists were technical artists,
we did a very typical tech art thing.
Instead of starting to concept
what the weapon finishes might look like,
we jumped right into the task
of trying to make them easier to produce.
We started with a basic idea.
Painting detail into textures takes a long time.
It's a lot of work,
and doing that on a large number of items
seemed really inefficient,
so we wanted to automate the process.
Since CSGO's art style is fairly realistic,
we started by taking a look at real-world reference.
Paint wears off metal in a really predictable way, so there are certain effects that we know we want to reproduce.
For one thing, it chips off the exposed corners and edges.
It wears quickest where it gets the most contact,
and grime and discoloration accrete in the cavities.
And another thing is that when people paint their weapons, they typically don't paint the whole thing.
They're really careful not to get paint in the mechanism, for obvious reasons.
So each weapon has its own characteristic areas where the substrate, that's the original surface of the weapon, is always visible.
So in this case, only the receiver, the grip, and the buttstock have been painted.
There is one thing about this example that isn't ideal though, and it has to do with scale.
This has a really durable paint on it, and so the way the paint chips off is in these kind of larger chunks.
That looks pretty cool on a rifle, but if you tried to apply that to a pistol, it might look out of scale.
And that's an important distinction because we want to ship as general a solution as possible.
Whatever we make, it has to apply to everything.
So we kept looking through our reference and we found an example where the wear pattern is filled with these smaller sized scratches.
This indicates that this has a lower quality paint,
but this scale of detail is going to work well on every type of weapon that we have.
So we're going to try and target this look.
It's pretty easy to replicate all of these features
as long as we have good enough information
about the topology of the mesh.
In fact, the most important things to know
are just the cavity and the occlusion.
That's going to tell us our low points
and our high points for the mesh
so that we can figure out where the paint should chip first.
For our scratches, we can just tile the texture
over the entire weapon.
We can start by just combining the cavity and the occlusion.
The brightest areas are the places where the paint
should wear off first.
This is a pretty soft blend though,
and our scratches need to have hard edges.
So we can just use a smooth step in the shader
to adjust the contrast.
For the artists in the audience,
a smooth step is really similar
to Photoshop's levels operation.
So this gives us our blend between our paint
and our original substrate.
Now's the time to bring in our grime.
We can just do that using the cavity
that tells us where to place the grime.
And the grime itself is another tiling texture
similar to the scratches.
So next we'll add in the ambient occlusion
to get the paint and the substrate
to sit in the same world together.
That's already looking pretty good.
There's one small problem though,
and that's that there are a couple areas
where we have some markings and etchings
on the original weapon that really ought to show through.
I don't think you can see it because it's a bit dark,
but trust me, they're there.
We want to see those even over the paint.
So the cheapest thing we could think of
was just to add them to the ambient occlusion.
Since that's just getting multiplied
over the surface of the paint anyway,
we can get our details back in dark over the top.
So another thing that we saw in our reference
was that the paint wears off quickest
where it's touched the most.
There's no way to know where things get touched
just from the topology of the mesh.
It has to do with human interaction,
so we need to have an artist's control over this.
We added a wear influence texture that is artist-created.
For the most part, we just grabbed details
from the original source texture PSDs,
and then we just painted a couple of blobby details
over the group in the magazine with these big soft brushes.
We spent hardly any time adjusting this mask at all,
and this is the effect that it produces.
You can see, especially on the grip,
the paint is wearing where it's touched the most.
So let's add lighting.
So at this point, we've authored almost no new content by hand.
The only things that we've created are really the grime texture and the scratch texture,
and those things are going to be reused over every single weapon in the game anyway.
The fun part is, since the shader has a wear input,
we can just animate that input
and see the wear crawl over the surface.
This is great because it shows us
that we can get a wide variety of looks
just by editing a single shader parameter.
It was around this time that we started
testing the content in-game under real game lighting,
and what we found was a little bit concerning.
So here's a typical first-person view of a weapon.
I'm showing it without the world or the view model arms just so you can focus on what's important.
You can see that the way that this texture has been authored it calls out all of the edges and plane changes so that even
if we disable
directional lighting all of the plane changes are obvious and you can understand the form really well.
But what happens when we add our paint onto it? A lot of those plane changes just straight-up disappear.
Even with directional lighting, we still have a problem.
Surfaces that have the same normal
but different spatial offsets
still look as though they've been merged into one.
One of our concept artists is a big model-making nerd,
so as we were figuring out the paint system,
he recommended that we check out work by Mink Jimenez.
I recommend this to any of you in the audience.
If you're a texture artist, a shader artist,
check this stuff out.
He's got a lot of amazing techniques
that are actually really helpful.
He uses a technique called modulation.
It gets painted on as part of the base coat
before he adds the details,
and it's used to call out geometric details,
as well as edges and plane changes.
So this isn't exactly lighting,
although some of the directions of the gradients
could be influenced by lighting.
Instead, the goal is to create value contrast
at every single one of the edges.
The details are painted on afterwards,
and they reduce the obviousness of the effect,
but the improvement in the viewer's understanding
of the form remains.
We tried it out.
Truthfully, this was not at all fun.
The process was just to grab an element
and then planar map a gradient onto it.
We then rotate the gradient until it's following
the way that we want.
Some of the more complicated weapons,
like the machine guns, I swear,
these things are like the Death Star.
They have all these tiny little greebly bits on it.
Some of them took up to two days.
On average, about two hours per weapon.
The result, though, it works.
Adding in the modulation shows us our plane changes again.
That means that we can move forward
without having to worry about the paint
destroying the viewer's understanding of the form.
We obviously don't want to just apply solid paints
to every weapon though.
It's a pretty promising start,
but we researched a bunch of different finishing techniques
and decided that our first technique
would be inspired by hydro dipping.
This technique uses a film with a printed pattern on it.
It's floated into a tank of water
and then sprayed with an activator.
The activator dissolves the film
but leaves the pigment behind.
And then you take your primed component
and just roll it through the pigment
to pick it up onto the surface.
We imitate this in a super cheap way.
Since hydrographics have seams in them
from being dipped from multiple angles
and because the weapon's disassembled
before it's dipped anyway,
we can just tile a texture over our unwrap.
If we have seams in the result,
I just dialed up the realism.
So you'd think that the first thing we'd try
would be to replace the flat color from our prototype
with a bunch of different textures,
but that seems so single use.
And in the long run, it didn't seem like
a good first investment because we'd still have to
create a lot of different images.
So in order to be more efficient,
we tried procedural coloration of patterns.
I'm showing this to you really small
because it's super hard on the eyes.
Authoring these again is not super fun,
but once you have one.
you can use it in a bunch of different ways.
So you can change its scale, its orientation,
drive different colors through it,
and create a bunch of meaningful variation,
again, just by driving some shader parameters.
We looked at a bunch of different examples of hydrodipping,
and we found that for the most part,
people don't dip the entire weapon.
They'll take certain components
and just use an accent color on them.
We thought that this look was more appealing
than the head-to-toe camo.
In order to replicate it, we paint a bunch of
paint-by-number textures for our weapons.
So they combine with the patterns in order to create
a weapon-specific color mask.
The colorized paint ends up looking like this.
Everywhere that's blue gets the same color,
everywhere that's green gets the same color.
It transforms our head-to-toe camo gun
into something that's a little bit more appealing.
The results of the composite can be randomized
by varying the rotation and the offsets of the texture.
The wearer is randomized also.
And that means that every single item we generate
with this system is per pixel unique.
So this is all looking really promising,
but this is a pretty expensive shader
and it has a lot of texture inputs,
meaning that it's pretty heavy on memory as well.
So obviously it would be better
not to run this thing every frame.
In fact, we'd like to run it for just one frame
and then save out the results.
I've been showing everything so far in the context of the weapon meshes,
but actually, all of our inputs are just texture information.
And so we can run this thing in a flat plane,
like a render target,
and still get the exact same results.
That's cool because we can just save this out
and use it as a normal texture.
That gives us an interesting advantage.
It means that we don't have to edit any of the materials for our weapons.
We can just swap out the base texture
and still get all the variety that we want.
So our first foray into generating the new texture
through a render target wasn't all that promising.
We had a two-second hitch every time we generated a weapon,
which for a competitive game is plainly unacceptable.
So we asked for some help.
We stopped trying to do everything
with just technical artist
and involved a rendering programmer.
He made some optimizations to the way that we copy
the information out of the render target and save it out.
I'm not gonna go into detail on this stuff.
If you're interested, I can come back to the slide
during the question period.
The upshot is that it only takes about six milliseconds
for a single frame, usually towards the beginning
of a round when it doesn't matter.
And then the rest of the work happens in a separate thread,
so there's no gameplay hitch.
So now that we have a fully functioning prototype,
we felt confident enough to start creating some new styles.
The first reference that we looked at consisted of spray-painted weapons.
We started with hydrographics because it was easier to solve those problems.
Here's the thing, with hydrographics, we don't care if we have seams in the results,
but with spray paints, really, they should be seamless.
So normally we just do a triplanar mapping,
so we project the texture from the cardinal directions and then blend over the surface normals.
This requires having mesh data to work with, though,
and far from having the position and normal information from our mesh,
what we actually have...
is just the flat plane of a render target
with no normals at all.
So what we actually need to do is get all of that
position and normal information into a texture format.
Now the normal information's not that complicated,
we just render an object space normal map.
But you should bear in mind that we never authored
the UVs for any of these weapons for procedural solutions.
In fact, all of the content had shipped
to our customers months before.
So there are some areas here where we have overlaps
or mirrors in the UVs.
This would be a problem if we were shading
with this information, but actually it turns out
to be plenty good enough for just doing the blend
between the different texture projections.
Our position didn't turn out quite that well.
We need a lot of precision here
in order for it to look accurate.
We save out 32-bit uncompressed textures for the position
and it's still not enough.
We end up with some pretty serious blockiness in the mesh.
We solved this by multi-sampling.
We just used a Gaussian kernel to average the positions
and the result is actually pretty credible.
In terms of visual range though,
the difference between hydrographics and spray paints
is not all that large.
So we've managed to add some variety,
but we want to go quite a lot further.
As we were looking at our reference,
we found that another common way
that people customize their weapons is through anodization.
Our standard shader for the weapons
does actually let us achieve this effect,
so we don't need to make any changes
to the way we're rendering in game.
What we do is just tint the specular highlights
by the base texture's color.
And so we can get some nice, juicy highlights like this.
So in this example, the paint's colored red
and baked into the base texture,
and then we just tint the specular highlights
where the paint appears and not over the substrate.
It's pretty, but it looks really weird
having it over the entire weapon.
So remember that mask that we used
to create accent colors for our hydrographics?
We didn't use all the channels, did we?
We still have one left.
So we added another per-weapon mask
to limit the anodization effect.
After the mask is made for a particular weapon,
the only overhead to creating a new anodized style
is just picking a new color.
We didn't stop there.
How could we?
We have so much texture information
that has so many useful things in it.
We haven't taken full advantage of it yet, so we added some more styles.
We finally got around to creating an uncolorized hydrographic.
We also converted our hydrographic and spray paint styles into anodized looks.
We made a solid paint style just using our paint by number mask
to generate a paint that has up to four colors in it.
And lastly, we created a patina style that instead of wearing down
to the substrate, wears to a thicker patina.
We didn't create any new per-weapon texture inputs
for any of these.
We just remixed the stuff that we already had
using our shader.
I really want to stress that this is pretty much
just procedural art.
It's the cheapest kind of art that we can make,
and it communicates the copper material really well.
Is the video playing, guys?
Yes?
Okay, excellent.
It communicates the copper material really well,
and it also looks interesting and different
at all the different wear levels,
and so we've managed to create a game.
a bunch of variety just by driving
a single shader parameter.
So to recap so far, we have a procedural compositing system
that works at runtime that we can use to generate
an essentially infinite number of textures.
In order for the system to work,
we need the following inputs.
The original source texture,
which was authored before we even had this idea.
The cavity, AO, position, and normal.
All of these things are just generated
using out-of-the-box tools from our existing mesh.
We create a paint-by-number texture.
That's done just by colorizing elements of the mesh
and then rendering to texture,
so it takes hardly any time at all.
And then our artist generated wear influence map.
Now we mostly just cribbed some layers
from the original source texture PSD,
so again, this isn't a big time investment.
In fact, the only texture that took a significant time
at all was the MIG Jimenez style modulation.
This guy took, on average, about two hours per weapon.
So if we add all these together,
it took us about a half a day to create a paintable weapon.
Even with a really small staff of just a couple of artists,
that means that we could blow through all 30 weapons
in the game at the time in about a week and a half.
Now this does look like an awful lot
of texture inputs to our shader.
Some of them are grayscale though,
so we just combine them into a single texture
by copying those into the textures individual channels.
The other component that we need,
aside from having the weapon be prepped to be paintable,
is the finish that we're going to apply to it.
What we author depends a little bit on the finish style,
but for the most part, we create a pattern
and then choose the colors for that pattern
and then set just a couple of shader parameters,
like the specular intensity.
Once all the weapons have been prepped,
we can very easily author a single finish
and apply it to any one of the weapons.
Let me zoom in on a random one here,
and you can see all of the detail
that's been procedurally placed.
And I'll show you another variant,
just because they're so darn easy to make.
So a single weapon finish can create a huge amount
of variety, both by randomizing its parameters
and by applying it to different weapons.
At this point, it's time that we stop focusing on the tech
and move on to the art.
Over the course of gathering our reference,
we discovered that people in the real world
create hideous, hideous things.
It really begs the question, what do our customers want?
The game's art style is grounded in the real world
and we've already gone down the path
of replicating some real world finishing techniques.
But there's a really broad range of service providers in the real world
creating a broad range of things that cater to a broad range of tastes.
In our game world, we're the only service providers
and our tastes might not match demand.
So we needed to focus less on the things that we personally liked
and more on creating a broad range of variety
in order to measure people's reactions.
So we shipped things with a big range of aesthetics,
and we deliberately shipped items
that were contentious within the team.
So among all these items, you can see a bunch of things
that are people's least favorite
out of all the test content that we made.
We also shipped an in-game tool for creating finishes
that we call the Workbench.
It allows the community to author weapon finishes
for themselves and upload them to the community workshop.
They've done that with enthusiasm,
creating over 30,000 finishes.
We've already started shipping
some of the highest rated items.
letting our community express their aesthetic preferences directly
by just putting the things they make right into the game.
We call our economy update the Arms Deal Update,
and it introduced the weapon finishes that people can collect and equip
to customize their play experience.
Our initial offering contained over 100 weapon finishes,
all created in-house,
which we've since expanded almost fourfold
with the help of our community contributors.
Each of these finish has random variations created by the pattern placement and the wear,
meaning that there are actually tens of millions of unique items in our economy.
So checking back in with our goals, so far we've managed to meet the first three.
It's really easy to make a weapon finish, the community contributes to their creation,
and we have a large variety of different looks.
Our last two goals are to have a broad range of value.
and to create items that can be valued in different ways.
So to know if we're meeting these two goals,
we're going to have to check our data.
Wealth and finishes are, by definition, luxury goods.
They're things that our customers like to have,
but they're not actually necessary in order to play the game.
In fact, they don't have any gameplay impact at all.
There's plenty of academic discussion on the dimensions of luxury goods.
I've collected together just a few of them that we can use to identify what might contribute
to the value of items in the economy.
So let's start with conspicuousness.
This is the public display of your status as a person with access to luxury goods.
This is a graph of the sale price of a black laminate AK-47 over its first three months.
This isn't privileged information.
Anybody can see any graphs that look like this
for any of the weapons in our economy
just by visiting the marketplace.
You can see that the price is pretty stable around $10,
so that means that the community values this item pretty highly.
Here's another item, the Doomkitti FAMAS.
Prices for this item started pretty high, around $7.50,
and dropped really rapidly over just a couple of days.
Now it maintains a fairly steady price of about $0.07.
So this guy isn't a huge hit.
So what's so different between these two items?
While the finishes themselves are superfluous,
the weapons that they apply to aren't.
So this is a graph of weapon utility
over several rounds of the game.
It shows which weapons get used most frequently.
The status from last October
when we'd first shipped the economy.
The AK-47 has the highest utility of any weapon
in the primary weapon category.
The M4 and the AWP are next, with roughly the same utility each,
and then the rest of the primary weapons don't have a big share.
So our FAMAS is the one that I prematurely pointed to.
That's the one from the previous slide that had a really low price on the marketplace.
You can see it gets used a little bit in the beginning rounds of the game,
but by the time we reach the later rounds,
it has this tiny little share, sandwiched between the much higher utility weapons.
This shows us that if you have a fancy AK-47,
you have a lot of chances to show it off.
And if you have a fancy FAMAS, you don't.
If we look at the prices of weapon finishes
that have the same scarcity,
we can see exactly this breakdown.
The AK's on top, and then the M4 is in the off,
and then a cluster of the rest of the weapons down below.
This shows us that the amount of time
that you spend holding a weapon
influences its value quite a lot.
That's just what we'd expect.
More time holding a weapon means more chances
to show off your customization,
and also to enjoy it for yourself.
So conspicuousness is definitely a big factor on price.
That means that when we create a weapon finish,
just applying it to different weapons
can create a big range of value.
The next item on our list, heritage and personal history,
encompasses things like historic value,
nostalgia, personal meaning.
It's really easy to see how those kinds of things
can influence the real world value of an item.
Things like heirlooms,
items that belong to famous personages,
items created as part of a venerable brand.
But what about in a video game?
Maybe it's less obvious, but Counter-Strike as a product
has a 14-year history.
This is the Desert Eagle,
more commonly known by its nickname, the Deagle.
It was a very popular choice in previous versions of the game,
where it was a weapon with a very high utility.
We have made some changes since,
but last October when we shipped our first round of content,
the utility of the Deagle in CSGO
was actually not particularly high.
In fact, the utility of the P250 outweighs it.
quite considerably.
Since that's the case, we'd expect that the P250
would have a higher value, but it doesn't.
The Deagle's actually the one on top.
It retains its high value because people are used
to valuing it highly.
So this is an example that shows that heritage
and personal history can actually affect
players' valuation of items in a game.
Scarcity is easy to explain.
The less of something there is,
the more value each unit has.
We sorted our items into collections.
Each collection contains items
from different quality tiers.
The quality tiers correlate roughly with scarcity,
so it's more common to get an item
from a lower quality tier
than an item from a higher quality tier.
We do have two different types of drops.
We drop cases and individual items.
The cases can be opened with a key,
and it gives you one item from a collection
that's associated with that case.
So this collection here is from a case,
and this one is made up of individual items.
So we control the rate at which both the cases
and the individual items drop relative to each other.
The thing that we don't control
is the rate at which cases are opened.
We've used our best guess at case opening rates
before shipping the economy
in order to try and balance the number of drops
so that our quality tiers would stay
roughly correlated with scarcity.
But in our first couple of months,
our customers opened way more cases than we'd expected.
And that means that case items are actually more common
than drops.
So as a result, the quality tier of an item
doesn't actually represent scarcity
relative to items that have a different provenance.
So there are two items here that I particularly
want to call your attention to.
This is the red laminate AK-47
and the black laminate AK-47.
Visually, they're fairly similar.
The red one is actually a little bit punchier,
so that's one way that we might have expected
that it has a higher value,
because it's more striking.
It also has a quality tier two tiers above the black laminate AK-47,
so that's two ways in which we could expect it has a higher value.
Except due to the volume of cases opened,
there are actually more red laminates in the world than black laminates.
So the red laminate AK-47, which we expected originally to have a high value,
is consistently around $4 cheaper than the black.
Exacerbating this effect is the fact that if you have a red laminate AK-47,
you're twice as likely to list it on the marketplace as if you have a black.
So scarcity's influence on price is pretty extreme.
In fact, it's one of the clearest predictors of value that we have.
There's one more interesting feature on this graph that I want to call your attention to.
It's right here, where the price of both of these items got depressed.
This is actually on the date where we shipped a bunch of new weapon finishes,
including some for the AK-47.
So the value of the older finishes actually decreased
relative to the new, more unique, more scarce finishes.
We have found over time that as the pool of items increases,
this effect gets a little bit diffused.
But when we first shipped the economy,
it was a pretty obvious drop of a couple of bucks.
In the real world,
quality assessment would be polysensual.
Kinetic feel and smell would give you indications
as to the quality of materials and assembly.
In our game world, our only indications are visual and descriptive,
but we found, to our surprise, that they are just as influential.
We expected that wear would influence desirability.
For one thing, we thought the worn beat-up weapons looked really cool
because we're artists and we think that way.
We also expected that the worn weapons would correlate with this kind of veteran status,
a kind of fictional bonus on top of the aesthetic interest.
Because of that, we considered making our weapons wear over time,
so that the more you use a weapon, the more worn it gets.
Pretty much everybody we showed the tech to had the same idea.
It was a really popular idea.
We wanted players to show off their worn weapons
as badges of honor.
We ended up not doing it for two reasons.
The first reason is that some of the paints look better
with less wear rather than more,
or at least that's how we assessed them.
And so it would be really difficult in order to get
the weapons to always wear towards an ideal state.
The other thing is that in order for people to show off
worn weapons as badges of honor,
they have to represent a significant time investment,
and that means that the wear could happen too slowly for our players to perceive.
Now, we don't want to affect people's inventories in a way that's difficult to communicate,
and so we ended up not shipping that.
Instead, each item has a random amount of wear applied to it at grant time.
The where has a bell curve so that it's most common to get an item with just a middling amount of where.
So the items with the most and the least amount of where have the most scarcity.
Given our previous examples then, we could expect that the items with the most and least amounts of where would have the highest value.
If that were true, our graph would look like this.
We have Val's card on the left and Factory New on the right.
You'd think that there would be an uptick in value
for both of those just because of scarcity.
But almost with that exception,
the battle scarred exteriors, our most worn exteriors,
are seen as significantly lower quality
than the factory new finishes.
This definitely shows that the impact of quality evaluation
affects the price on the marketplace.
So creating our scratched aesthetic
did actually give us a broad range of value,
even if we had originally imagined
the value spread exactly backwards.
So let's finally talk about the aesthetics
of individual finishes.
Aesthetics in the context of luxury
is a consumer's ability to discriminate value
just based on visual characteristics.
We created a broad range of aesthetics
from subdued military styles
all the way to flashy items that were shiny.
So because the game can have a stealth component to it,
we actually expected that players would prefer items
that they felt gave them a better camouflage.
So how do we test our assumptions?
We can't just look at price on the marketplace.
It's way too heavily influenced by all the other factors on this list.
It's also worth noting that the price on the marketplace doesn't capture the total value of the items in our economy.
Less than 2% of our items are listed on the marketplace.
The rest of them are collected and equipped,
and they provide a value to their owners that isn't expressed in dollar amounts.
So let's look at some non-market data.
We added crafting to the game shortly after the economy went live.
Crafting is just taking a number of items
and trading them in with the game
instead of with another player
in order to get a different item back.
We use the fiction of a contract with the arms dealer.
It's essentially a way of trading in with the game controller
instead of the player, and we use specific contracts
that define which items can be crafted into which other items.
We've organized our items into collections.
and we allow players to trade up inside of those collections.
Ten items from one quality tier
will get you a random item from the next tier up.
We can identify our most desired items
by looking at just a couple of factors.
For one thing, we'll look at our crafting data.
We can see which items are traded in
more frequently than usual.
We can also look at the origin of an item.
If lots of them are created via crafting,
we're either looking at the item that was desired,
or we're looking at an item in the same tier
as the one that you hoped you got,
or we're looking at an item that's transitional.
It's something that someone crafted
in order to work their way towards a yet higher tier.
So if we look only at the items
that are created via crafting,
but not subsequently traded in,
this gives us a pretty clear picture
of the favorite items from this collection.
We can further narrow aesthetic preferences
by looking at equip rates.
Items that are equipped at an unusually high rate
that are also worked towards via crafting
give us our best picture of our most loved items.
So for example, if you own a Desert Eagle
with the Cobalt Disruption finish,
you're 16% more likely to equip this one
than any other finish, even if you have lots of them.
So if we look only at the craft targets
that satisfy these two qualifications,
we actually end up with a pretty small list.
Whoops, sorry.
So people like anodized finishes a lot.
More than half the items on this list
are either anodized or metallic.
They also like saturated colors on black
or very bright finishes.
And they also like weapons that have a sleek
kind of spy movie aesthetic.
The easiest thing to see though,
looking at all of these items,
is that most of them have a single predominant color.
I should note that this is really different
from looking at price on the marketplace.
Although some of these items
do have a high price on the marketplace,
that's not true for all of them.
In fact, some of them are worth only about 50 cents,
and some of them are worth as much as, sorry, $30.
Scarcity also isn't reflected very well here.
Some of these items are really rare,
and some of them, there's a lot of them in the world.
So looking at crafting and equip rates for these items
gives us a new window into what players value
about our economy content.
So this covers the high end of our aesthetic range.
What about the low end?
Everybody starts with a default loadout.
As you play, you get drops of weapons with finishes.
The first time you get one,
you are 90% likely to equip it.
At least, that's true for most weapons.
For some of them, even when you get it,
you dislike it so much, you'd rather have the default.
If we look only at the rejects,
we can see, again, a pattern.
These are all camouflage-inspired.
In fact,
These are all items that look like our original inspiration.
So, although we started off thinking that the military camouflage was really cool,
it turns out that what our community really values are finishes that look more like paint guns.
This is great. We needed a reminder that although Counter-Strike is military-inspired,
it's not a military simulation. It's a sport.
When our customers play, they don't aspire to be soldiers.
They aspire to be elite Counter-Strike players.
So maybe it's not that surprising
that the closest real-world analog we've got
to our preferred aesthetic comes from a sport.
If you looked at our content,
you'd assume that we understood this right from the start
and decided to put the bright items
at the top of our quality tiers
because we thought they had the most value.
Actually, that wasn't what we were thinking.
It was a risk mitigation strategy.
We were genuinely worried
that people wouldn't like the bright items.
So instead of thinking of these as being sorted by value,
we originally sorted them by risk.
After all, if you got a rare item,
you'd like it because it was rare,
even if it was an aesthetic that you didn't appreciate.
And for everybody else, if they don't have a rare item,
they're happy because they don't have to see
the bright stuff very often,
because there aren't very many of them in the world.
Well, now we know we were wrong.
Would that have changed our design?
It may have, and let me explain how.
We need to properly map out our design space.
We can think of the facets of luxury
as the axes in that space.
We've figured out the bounds of the axes
by examining our data.
Conspicuousness varies with the utility of the weapon.
Scarcity, oops, sorry.
Heritage and personnel history
from the novel to the familiar.
Scarcity varies with supply
as well as how frequently you encounter an item,
sorry, a finish for a particular weapon.
Quality varies from our original scratched aesthetic
to factory new.
And our aesthetic style,
which was the most difficult for us
to tease out of the data,
varies from our original military aesthetic
to visually salient sports-inspired styles.
The last thing that we want is for all of these axes
to be aligned, collapsing our design space.
That would be possible if we didn't understand
how these axes were defined.
In fact, we'd align scarcity and aesthetics
by putting most of our visually salient items
at the top of our collections.
Fortunately, our design space
has more than just those two axes,
or we could have had a serious problem.
The worst scenario is that each item in the economy
has all the facets of a luxury good,
each in equal degrees.
That doesn't encourage interactions in which players
both feel they're getting the better end of the deal.
Someone's always going to be ahead of you on the ladder
and somebody behind, and there's only one direction
to trade in that makes any sense.
That is the best way I can think of to stifle the economy.
Instead, what we'd like is to have ways
to create value in every axis.
Understanding not only what the axes are,
but how to place an item along it,
lets us determine if we're providing enough variety of value.
Ideally, there wouldn't be any items in the economy
that had perfectly equal value on every axis.
Having that range of value is really important.
We can create a range of items that have
different value on different axes,
and then players with orthogonal goals
can trade with each other, and each feel like
they're getting the better end of the deal,
even if the total value of the items is unequal.
So I could, for example, want to collect rare items,
but maybe I don't care if they're bright or shiny.
Or I could want to collect items that are bright colors.
but maybe it doesn't matter to me if they're factory new.
Those trades can happen even if the value's unequal,
and players with different goals
can value different items in different ways.
So the finer we slice our axes,
the more nuanced trading and marketplace transactions
can get.
By creating our content in a semi-procedural way,
we were able to slice our axes very fine indeed,
creating a broad range of value
and creating value on multiple axes.
So with our players exchanging over 30 million items
with each other on the marketplace so far,
It certainly seems like we've met our goals.
So let's wrap up by checking back in
with our product level goals.
We'd hope that the economy would improve
the longevity of our game,
provide fun and value to our customers,
and make it easier for our customers
to provide fun and value to each other.
Remember that we only have to check in
on a couple of broad metrics
to see if we're meeting our goals.
It's our player numbers, player retention,
and our individual play times.
This is taken from SteamGraph.net.
It's a community website that monitors the numbers
we publish about who's playing what on Steam.
It shows our peak concurrent player numbers daily.
So here's some notable landmarks.
Here are the games in beta.
This is the launch of our game.
And here are a couple of free weekends.
This is the Steam Summer Sale
that preceded the Economy launch.
So after our economy launch, we had a pretty dramatic increase
in peak player numbers, bringing us to regular highs
that we'd only achieved previously by making the game temporarily free.
This last spike here is DreamHack.
It's a big tournament for CSGO with a high viewership.
This game was also on...
Our game was also on sale for this time period,
and that caused a huge player spike, nearly doubling our player count.
There was a large influx of new players around this time and they stuck around at a really high rate.
In fact, they stuck around at a much higher rate than players from previous sales.
And so we can see that not only are our player numbers up, but our player retention is up.
Since that event, we've been able to reach a new plateau of about 100,000 peaking current players daily
and about 2.3 million monthly unique players.
In the aggregate, it certainly looks like we've met our goals for adding the economy,
and individual players are sending us the same signal.
They're playing more frequently and for longer,
which is our best indication that we're providing them with lots of fun.
And as they continue to play together and exchange items with each other,
they're creating loads of value for each other as well.
Our one remaining goal is that we increase the longevity of the game.
Now only time will tell, but with such a large community of returning players,
CSGO's future looks really bright.
I'd like to open the floor for questions now.
So if you have questions, please step up to the mics.
Hi, Rondon.
Hi.
Can we have a little light in here for the audience?
You mentioned that there were only two technical artists, yourself and one other, working on CS Go to bring the economy update.
About how big was the rest of the team, and I'm particularly interested in how the decisions were made to either proceed or not proceed with doing the economy in the context of how many people there were.
So we had, let me think back, around the time we probably had about 12 people on the team total.
that team size has increased since then,
which is good because it means we can do more stuff.
But everyone was really behind the economy.
I mean, looking at the success of TF2 and Dota 2,
we really wanted to improve our player numbers.
Typically after you launch a product,
the product cycle goes like this, right?
You have this big spike at launch,
and then it just continues downwards
until you have this long tail.
TF2 and Dota 2 both have this big spike,
and then they just keep going up.
And that's the model that we wanted to.
to go for, right?
So pretty much everybody on the team
was really pulling for the economy.
It wasn't like we just had technical artists going,
hey, let's make an economy.
Yeah, it was a whole team decision.
I have some links that you guys might wanna check out.
Hi.
One more question.
You have this game mode where you unlock, like.
further weapons, the more kills you earn, right?
Where you start with a pistol, and then you perform your first kill, and then you
use the machine gun and whatnot.
Right, so there's an in-game economy that's a game mechanic
that's totally separate from this kind of meta economy.
And what happens is if you make a kill,
you earn more money in-game,
which allows you to buy a more expensive weapon later on.
And that's actually a good catch,
because that graph that I was showing about weapon utility,
it wasn't actually showing the rounds sequentially,
it was showing how much money you had to buy a weapon
at the start of a round.
So it's not exactly what I said it was,
but I didn't want to explain the mechanic.
I meant the certain, the special game mode where you like start with a pistol and then you perform one kill.
Oh, you're talking about the arms race?
Yeah. Did you like look at stats of players that like only play this particular game mode and how the like purchase of weapons differs for those players in comparison to like Deathmatch players or something?
Um, so there aren't actually a lot of players that play exclusively arms race.
Um, in fact our players, here I totally have a slide for this.
If I can get my cursor back from the other screen.
So we actually have different populations of players.
Let me see if I can find the slide,
it's way at the end here.
So we have players who,
mainly break down into three categories.
They break down into players who play on casual.
players who play on competitive
and players who play on community servers.
And so Arms Race is going to fit
into the casual section of our players.
And we didn't really break it down a lot further from there
because the populations got really, really small.
Okay, thank you.
Okay.
Thanks Bronwyn. I wanted to ask now that CSGO is kind of in a different place than when you decided to start doing
Weapon skin as items if you've got if you guys have considered any of the other
kind of more resource intensive
expansions to it
That stuff is always on the table.
It's just a matter of making sure that we have a goal for it.
We don't want to ship something just for the sake of it.
We want to work towards actually improving
the customer experience.
And I mean, you might be thinking of things
like the character customization.
Until we can solve the team ID problem,
that wouldn't be something that we would want to ship.
So there's a lot of work to do there.
That doesn't mean that we won't consider it.
Okay, cool.
Hi, on your graph there for the DreamHack, you notice a spike in players staying online.
Now, did you guys have the eSports line of your economy planned before you noticed that spike or after?
Oh, absolutely before. Yeah, absolutely before.
For those in the audience that don't know, we sold a special key for a special case.
It was called the eSports case.
We've actually had a couple in that series so far.
And what that case does is we take a portion of the proceeds from that case
and we use it to fund community tournaments.
DreamHack was actually the first recipient,
and they had a $250,000 prize pool that was funded by our community.
And so the community was actually heavily invested in it
in order to go watch it and see the results
of something that they've been caring about all this time.
And actually we just had the second one,
which was EMS1 in Katowice.
That was just last week.
Our peak concurrent player numbers during that event
went up to 165,000.
So, and we were also on sale.
So we'll see how many of those players come back
over the next couple of weeks.
I'm actually kind of excited
because I think we're gonna reach a new plateau.
Okay, thank you.
Hi, I know in the past few months you've also shipped an update that allows players to apply stickers to their guns.
Yes.
And one, I'm a big Counter-Strike player myself.
Awesome.
So are a lot of my friends, but I found that they're a lot more polarizing than the skins.
And I was wondering if that was something you guys knew going into shipping that update.
No.
We had no idea they'd be polarizing.
We thought people would think they were really cool.
Um, there's...
You have to be careful when you're talking about things
being polarizing because there's some data
that you can get anecdotally that isn't actually
represented in players' purchasing behavior.
And so there's a large community,
or actually a large community of players
that never speak up, right?
That are perfectly happy with the things that they get.
And so when we're looking at things to add to the game,
or assessing whether something was valuable
and whether it's working, we can't just look at
what people are talking about in the forums,
although we obviously do read that stuff all the time
and take it into account.
We also have to look at how our players' behaviors
are changing and whether they're actually
consuming the content and enjoying it.
And it turns out that people actually love stickers.
Yeah, for the most part anyway.
Cool, thank you.
In CS 1.6, you guys had spray paint on the world, right?
Yes.
Have you guys considered adding user-customized spray paints,
which obviously you guys will have to monitor what goes in
and what goes out?
And the ability to maybe, like, if I didn't like a spray paint
and I was playing the game, I could actually
spray something on top of that and kind of hide it and so on.
Did you guys consider something like that?
So there were a lot of abuses of the original system
because there wasn't any sort of gating system.
You could just put in whatever you wanted.
And so there were a lot of obscene images
to spray it around the world.
And actually, my favorite and the worst
is that people would take a picture of themselves
there in weapon pose standing against a wall,
and then they would spray it on the wall,
and then other players would come by
and start targeting to shoot there.
And so it was like this weird strategic
kind of emergent gameplay sort of thing.
We're not sure how much value sprays have relative to some of the other things that we could do.
I know that people do want them back because they're, well again, it's kind of a heritage
thing. People are used to having them, but we haven't made any decision one way or the other.
Hello, I was wondering if you could talk a little bit about how knives factored in.
Were they always supposed to be the ultra rare kind of item from these cases and obviously
their effects are just aesthetic?
So knives, yes, we always plan to make them
the most rare items, and the reason is that
these are weapons with an extremely high utility.
You use them in every single round of the game,
you whip them out all the time,
because whipping them out makes you run faster
relative to carrying a heavy weapon right in front of you.
We thought that just giving them out
would be kind of a waste,
because there was such an opportunity to drive value
by making them rare and desirable.
We even see within these guys that there's a value spread, like all the different finishes.
The Fade is the most popular, and then the Slaughter, and then the Karambit is the most
popular knife.
And so there's a good range of value here, too.
It's a little bit worrisome because the value of these items is so high.
Actually, for a long time, we were watching the price of them just keep rising on the
marketplace, which is really scary, because we have a calf on the marketplace of $400.
And so if you have an item that's worth more than $400,
you can actually get the value of it from the marketplace.
And so people end up doing things like taking their knives
and trying to sell them on eBay
and they get scammed all the time.
And it's not really all that positive for players.
Finally, the price has stabilized.
So now they're around like 200 bucks.
So we feel a little safer.
Yeah, we always plan to make those the highest tier items.
And I didn't talk about them very much
because they don't really fit into any of the collections
or any of the other things that we talked about.
And they have such a high scarcity and such a high utility
that they're just off the charts on pretty much all of our other ranges.
Thank you.
Hi.
I was curious about,
so you have some weapon skins that are tracking in terms of kills.
Oh, yeah.
How does that play into, I guess, like the aesthetics of the weapon and everything?
Yeah, yeah, nothing.
Well, so we call these items stat track items.
They're kind of like the strangers from TF.
It tracks how many kills you get.
So I think in TF, your strange weapon
just tracks it as part of the name or description
and you don't actually see it as,
like it's not on your weapon.
We created modules or like, especially on the knives,
they have these little scratched off bits
where you can actually see it on the weapon
and people really seem to like that.
We have found that the value of these things,
there is some value there just for intrinsically,
they're fun to have,
but most of the value of them on the marketplace
comes from their scarcity, which is sort of interesting.
So it's another way that we can generate a range of value.
Does that answer your question, or was there?
Thank you. Cool.
So you have Dota 2 and TF2 that are both free-to-play games.
Yes.
As you guys develop the economy.
Are you able to say what some of the tension that you're running into maybe making CS go free to play or not?
That's a question that we get a lot.
The one thing that we're concerned about that's stopping us from going free to play is cheating.
Right now there's a friction if someone gets caught cheating,
they have to rebuy the game in order to come in and keep ruining other people's experiences.
If the game is free to play, there's no friction at all.
They can just keep rolling over accounts.
And so until we solve that problem.
we probably wouldn't go free to play,
but it's something that we talk about all the time.
Thanks.
Do you make the same kind of assessments
when choosing map workshop levels?
Oh yeah, absolutely.
Yeah.
There are different things that the different maps bring.
There are some maps that are just absolutely gorgeous
and they draw people into those worlds.
And there are some maps that are slightly less gorgeous
but they play really fantastically.
What we do find is that the value of the maps
to the community is almost all about play.
It's like if they play really well.
So you guys, if you're Counter-Strike players,
have probably heard of Cache.
It's a really popular map.
It's a community created map that has,
a really good play style to it.
So that one's really popular compared to some of the other maps
that might be visually more attractive,
but they aren't as popular because the gameplay isn't quite as strong.
All right, I think we're out of time.
So thanks.