Hello, everybody.
Welcome to our talk.
Thanks for coming.
I just want to say I'm Tim Schafer, the president of
Double Fine Productions here in San Francisco.
Thank you.
And I've come here today with several of our cohorts from
Double Fine to talk to you about a big change in our
production, the way we produce games that went over the last
couple years at Double Fine and how it.
some things we came up against and how we solved them.
And it's called Creative Panic,
How Agility Turned Terror Into Triumph.
It's a beautiful slide, Lee.
Thank you.
I want to remind everyone,
if your cell phone rings during this presentation,
we will stop and restart from the very beginning.
even if we're like two minutes from the end. So
please turn off your ringers. And they're, we all
want to remind you to fill out your feedback
forms, cause they are not actually forms anymore, so
that's kind of misleading, that gesture. If you get
your card, you land your.
get your pass scanned by one of the CAs, they
will, you'll get an email asking you if you
like this talk or not. I know it's hard
to give feedback like that. I would like to
recommend fives. If it's a, you know, scale of
one to five or, or ten, I haven't really
seen them yet. So, just wanted, in case you
need to copy someone else's work, those are my
suggestions for the ratings.
That would have been a good slide to show
while I was doing all that welcoming talk.
Because we're gonna miss that right now.
I am here to tell you, my friends,
that we are in crazy times.
That these times we live in,
there are a lot of big games out there.
And that's a picture of me.
And we at Double Fine have made big games, and we
compete with big games.
But the games are just getting bigger.
They're getting bigger and more expensive.
And they take that money, and they buy the top talent, and
the games get better and bigger.
And it's like a snowball that keeps rolling.
It's very hard to compete against for smaller studios.
But there are even the really small studios that also
compete in a way of being incredibly creative and taking
many, many years to make their games and not paying
themselves any money and living out of their basements
while they do that.
And those are, those kind of studios are also very hard for a studio like Double Fine to
compete with, because they have a lot of flexibility with the whole lack of payroll thing.
We've always been kind of an unusual studio in that we're, we're an independent developer,
but we have health care, you know, somewhere, somewhere right in the middle.
We've been comfortable there, except for lately the, the phrase death of the middle has been
going around, which makes us a little nervous.
There aren't a lot of studios left in that middle space.
And we did see...
a lot of pressure, like things closing in on us in a way,
when we're thinking about what game to make after
Brutal Legend.
It's getting harder and harder to sign big games like that,
and there's pressures that, even if you can sign them,
make them maybe not what you want to sign.
For example, publishers are very averse to new...
Very versed in new IP.
When you're investing millions and millions of dollars, you'd
rather place it on a license title or a SQL.
It's in their defense.
It makes sense.
They also want to own the IP, which is something that
Double Fine believes.
Developers should own their own IP and not give it away to
publishers.
And yeah, you should remember to ask for that next time
you're negotiating a contract.
Because I think that's what leads to the best games.
Developers care about their characters and worlds they're
making, and it makes sense.
But it's very hard to do that at these big
budgets that are happening.
And people giving you a lot of money to make a game also
rightfully want to make it safe, make it a good return
on their money.
They want to take out the risks and unknowns.
But Double Fine, the things that really excite us are
these risky things, these unknown doing something that
hasn't been done before.
That's what makes it fun.
So we saw this pressure to take out a lot of the things
that made games fun if we go for these bigger, bigger
games.
So how has Double Fine survived this kind of pressure?
We spent 10 years as a one team studio making one game at a
time, and I was always in charge of it.
And it was very entrenched into our culture that that's
the way we did things.
But we managed to turn the battleship.
This is a phrase I learned at LucasArts.
Every time there was a new president or a layoff or a new
president with a layoff.
would be a big meeting, and the first thing
he'd say is like, we're gonna turn the battleship,
everybody. Which sounded really exciting. Not that, I mean,
it's probably the boring, most boring thing a battleship
could do, is turn around. But, I mean.
So we did manage to turn the battleship into
a fleet of tug boats. Didn't see that coming.
Or, like, bigger, sexier, like, cigarette boats from Miami
Vice, with guns on them. Just awesome boats.
And we did that by using Amnesia Fortnight. Many of
you know Amnesia Fortnight is a psychedelic mushroom, and
we all took it, and it gave us the idea.
Now, Amnesia Fortnight is something that came up when we were thinking about, I heard a
story about a filmmaker in Hong Kong named Wong Kar-wai who was making Ashes of Time.
It was this huge three-year production and his team was getting really, you know, they're
spending a lot of time in the desert, getting really oppressed by this huge production.
And so he took his star and his cinematographer and they went to Hong Kong and they improvised
a bunch of dialogue that later turned into Chungking Express and Fallen Angels, two completely
different movies that were actually really, really some of the most famous movies.
and it was a great break for his team.
And I thought, that's a great idea.
We should do that.
It's right in the middle of Brutal.
We could use a break.
And it's called Amnesia because you totally forget
what you're working on for two weeks.
Forget about Brutal Legend for two weeks
and we'll just work on something else.
It's called Fortnite.
I don't know why.
because it was two weeks. Some companies have done this also, and they do it for one week.
For some reason, I really believe two weeks is the right amount of time. We broke the
whole company into smaller teams. Sorry, this picture makes me laugh.
And we gave each, we had a 60 person team for Brutal,
and we split it into four groups,
and each of those groups had to make a game in two weeks.
And we really wanted it to be a complete experience,
which meant not just like a demo of like,
here's a guy walking around,
imagine he's in a great world, or imagine, you know,
but really, even if it's a small little slice of gameplay,
make it complete, like a beginning and middle,
and let us feel what this game is gonna feel like
that you guys are making.
And it was massive success, I think.
I think for the following reasons.
It gave us a big morale boost.
Everyone on the team loved,
I was walking down the hallway
and I could just feel people being excited
about what they're working on in a whole new way.
There was four new ideas going on at the company
and people were trying new things.
And everyone, it was just, it was great on that level
that everyone was really excited.
And people got to try out new roles.
I think this is Drew Skillman trying out
the new role of God, was that what you're?
People get to try out new roles.
Because when you have one production, one team, and you
have me as a creative director, you have one lead
programmer, and you have one lead artist and a designer,
and there's not a lot of room for people to move up in that
unless I'm dead or get killed or fired or something.
So in order to avoid being killed, we started this whole
process.
So people got to, with four teams, we had four leads,
and four lead programmers, four lead artists,
and people got to, modelers got to try concept art,
because it was just like a two-week thing.
Everybody, no rules.
Anyway.
And we actually ended up with usable game ideas.
We actually ended up with these little demos
that we said, wow, this is really fun.
We could actually ship this or something like it.
And also, as a side benefit, it also saved the company.
Which I love when that happens.
How did that happen? Why did it save the company? Well, we did it twice. First, we did it in
the middle of Brutal Legend in production. We took a break and we did the first initial
Fortnite project. And we did four teams and we came up with these fun prototypes and we
just, we tucked them away. We're like, okay, we're going to come back to this when we have
time. Maybe on the side we'll do some work on these games. We'll ship them later. And
then after Brutal Legend to, actually after Brutal Legend stopped, we did it again with
five teams.
And we said, OK, these are great.
We can do some of these, too, while we're working on
Brutal Legend 2.
We'll just do all this.
But the universe is a tricky, funny place.
And the games industry is no exception.
And Brutal Legend 2 was canceled.
And we were like, that's interesting, because we're
going to go out of business.
What can we do?
What can we do to not, what's plan B of going out of business as plan A?
Let's, we had nothing ready to go.
I had no big idea, because I was working on Brutal Legend 2.
It was supposed to be a done deal.
I was concentrated on that.
I had nothing to pitch.
But then I thought about these nine prototypes we had made.
And there were a lot of really promising, interesting things in there.
And so we picked four of them, and we took them on the road.
And we ended up, it took a little time, but we got them all signed.
And we just shipped them all this year.
And you can see them, Costume Quest stacking, Iron Brigade, and Sesame Street,
Once Upon a Monster.
And that was amazing to have these.
It was really great to be able to take a demo on the road.
And it's so much easier to sign a game when you have a demo.
It made signing go faster.
So today we're going to talk about the process of taking
these prototypes and turning them into full games.
And also the specific case studies of some of the
production challenges that we face.
Because this is a whole new way of doing production at
Double Fine.
It's a big change for us.
And then, um, uh, the exact solutions
that these teams, uh, came up with.
And I'm gonna let these guys talk.
Unfortunately, Tasha, who did Costume Quests,
has, uh, went to Pixar,
back to Pixar, where she came from.
And, uh, she, uh, is not here,
but we have, um, these attractive young fellows
to talk to you.
Ahem.
That's actually the first design of the lamprey
from Rude Legend, I think, with Brad's head on it.
Uh...
We have Nathan Martz, the lead programmer of Legend and the lead of Once Upon a Monster.
And we have Brad Muir from Iron Brigade.
And they're going to tell these stories.
And first up, we have young Mr. Lee Petty from the game Stacking.
And I'm going to have him come up here and talk to you next.
So here's a little peek at what Stacking looks like, just to remind you.
Please welcome Mr. Lee Petty.
Thank you, Tim.
for making sure that was very anti-climatic.
I'm Lee Petty.
I was the art director on Brutal Legend
and the project lead on Stacking.
And I'm going to talk to you guys a bit about how Stacking
started off in Amnesia Fortnight and kind of how
we took it through production and some
of the challenges we faced.
When I got the opportunity to come up
with an idea for a game for Amnesia Fortnight,
one of my first inspirations was a German expressionistic film.
And these were films, silent films from the 1920s.
that were considered pretty experimental in their day.
And one of the things that I always found really inspirational and interesting about these films
is that they had really small budgets.
And one of the ways that they compensated for that,
one of the ways they made themselves interesting and stand out
is that they designed these very unique, highly stylized stage and set designs.
I was also really interested at the same time in a...
coming up with a game that explored identity in some way,
maybe the changing player character identity.
And so I kind of, I did this little sketch at the time
that was kind of fusing these two together about
some crazy character that could wear living masks
and when they put these living masks on,
they would, the rest of the way they would interact
with the world would change.
But that, these things are just a little too dark
and weird for the sort of first.
game out of the gate for me, and I
really wanted to do something a little more charming.
And I wasn't sure where to go, and I
saw my daughter playing with a stack of Russian
nesting dolls. And I thought, well, that'd be really
cool. Those are, they have their own style, and
they're a little bit creepy, which is cool, but
not too creepy. Like, German, anything German, really.
And so I did this little sketch, and I
was like, oh, we're gonna make this. And it
was still let me explore themes of identity, because
you know, what sort of worlds would these dolls live in,
and what's a relationship like?
What does it mean to stack inside another doll?
I don't know.
And from there, I decided that we'd go forward
with Russian dolls, and I wasn't sure,
what do these dolls do?
I mean, there's a lot of things they could do,
and I started thinking of ideas,
and one of the first ideas was, well,
maybe it's a game about gentlemen's hat combat.
And, you know, they would fling hats at one another
and resolve all their disputes that way.
But it, yeah, it's clearly been done too much.
So I, instead I thought of something more, more mainstream,
which was what if they fought German industrialist nutcrackers,
and these nutcrackers would arrive in the land of the Russian dolls
and crush the poor little Russian dolls with their nutcracking jaws,
and yeah.
Again, I was just starting to get into a dark place.
I also remember at the time that we really
only had two weeks to make this game. So
rather than go down these, these roads, I decided
to just focus just on the act of stacking.
Let's make the mechanic, and the idea of stacking
in another doll or within a doll, the whole
focus of the Amnesia Fortnite prototype.
At the same time, I thought,
Well, it'd be really cool to do an adventure game.
I grew up with adventure games, and I work at the same company as Mr. Tim Schafer and Ron Gilbert,
two of the pioneers of the adventure game genre.
I thought I could benefit from some of their knowledge,
and it'd be good to get to it before senility drives it from their heads.
And it was really not a good assumption, but I thought it was going to work.
So, we did the Amnesia Fortnite demo and it worked well.
Tim liked it.
We pitched it.
We were fortunate enough to sign the game.
And then we were like, oh, well, we have to actually make this now.
That's tricky.
And one of the big challenges for us in stacking was that we wanted to do an original high
fidelity game, but we had a really small budget and we had a short time frame, like nine months.
and a small team. And we wanted to do something in this downloadable space that let us do
things that we otherwise couldn't do in big games. So maybe things are a little different
visually and gameplay-wise. And a lot of that comes from the personality of the game, and
personality is important to us. But personality is often expressed in the small details and
the presentation of the game, and that doesn't, that takes a lot of time. So how are we going
to do that?
And we knew the expectations would be high, both internally,
because we had just come off of Brutal Legend and spent a lot
of time with so many characters and really manicuring this
large world.
We didn't want to give up that attention to detail.
And the XBLA and PSN markets, the games were getting more
elaborate on those when we pitched these.
So we needed a way of thinking about making this game, like
how we're going to make this game, some sort of guideline
to keep us on track.
And the term we used was economy of design.
And by that,
I simply mean that we wanted the game to
have everything it needed to feel itself, but nothing
else. No fat.
And we were gonna start this production by, by,
by starting small and growing instead of big and
cut. And that sounds obvious, but actually just about every
game I've worked on has done the exact opposite.
It starts with really over-ambitious systems design, huge lists
of assets, and they inevitably are cut as the,
as the production goes on, but we didn't have
that time to waste.
And one of the ways we thought about it was, let's just relate everything we come up with,
visually, gameplay-wise, narrative, to the core idea of just stacking. And if it doesn't
directly relate to that, that almost physicality of stacking within the doll, then let's just
not pursue it.
And that doesn't mean, though, that we came up with a really tiny feature set up front
and just never did anything and executed on it and we were all happy.
wore money hats. It, it meant that we created
headroom for ourselves that during the production, because we
didn't have much of a pre-production, during the production
we could look for creative opportunities to expand the
game and enhance it.
And one way that this idea of economy design
really made sense, the obvious way, is that the
characters. We basically had one character model for the
entire game.
and rather than, you know, make the characters interesting through lots of variation in the
shape, we just challenged ourselves to do them with the textures itself. We did find,
though, that, that characters, or the players, rather, needed to have some, another layer
of differentiation on top of the characters, because the characters were used to solve
all the puzzles in the game. They were the inventory.
as well as the characters. So we did that by just adding simple accessories and a lot
of hats and canes and monocles and, you know, those sorts of things. But they were very
quick to make. They added a lot of new personality to the game as well and they accomplished
that gameplay goal of recognizability.
And the characters were really cheap to render, right?
They weren't very many polygons.
They had very few bones.
And that meant that we could put a lot of them
on screen at once.
So a lot of our levels had about 100 to 200 dolls
on screen at once moving around, doing their thing.
And that let us create an actual world, which was really
important to us, like we did in Brutal Legend, but in a
much more economical way.
The other issue that we ran into is that we, again,
we love personality.
We try and put personality into our games.
But how do we do that animation-wise with just a few
joints?
And we considered adding animating textures or some
sort of detailed facial animation.
But I thought it would just be really a little too creepy to
have an animating face on a doll.
And it was an expensive choice.
So we just tried to animate just using rigid body
animation.
And it was really charming.
It actually worked pretty well.
And my takeaway is to torture your animators.
Because just give them really strange requests and see what
they come up with.
But they're really clever, right?
They can communicate ideas and emotions in ways that are really long form to communicate
other ways, but they do it really well with simple motion.
And as an example, I had this little dog character in a level and he did a lot of tricks and
did things like walk on his hind legs and back flip.
And so I said to the animators, like, I would really like this dog to drag his ass across
the ground on occasion because, you know, if you've ever had a dog, they occasionally
do that and it's really funny.
And, um, do you think you could do that?
And they're like, the dog doesn't even have an ass to drag.
And I was like, just give it a shot.
Uh, it'll be great.
And, uh, and they did.
And it looked, it looked a little something like this.
This little, let me drag him here.
So, yeah, animators are good.
But the art production really wasn't the only way
that we used economy design.
The gameplay itself centered on a series of adventure game
style puzzles that we called challenges.
And one of the things that made the challenges
a little different in stacking than other adventure games
is that they all had multiple solutions.
The player only had to do one solution,
but they could choose to do many different solutions
for a particular challenge and get rewarded.
And although that sounds like a ton of work,
and it is, it's a lot less than creating unique puzzles,
right, because.
We were able to use the same art assets, the area of the world, a lot of the writing and
set up some of the same dolls.
So we got a pretty economical approach to replayability that way, as opposed to making
so many unique challenges.
And the other thing that was a nice byproduct of that is that it increased the accessibility
of the game, which was a goal for us on stacking, was to make it very casual and approachable.
And I think...
In most adventure games, there's one solution, and if players try something differently,
and it's logical, it just doesn't work, that's sort of a classic snafu.
And in our case, since we had multiple solutions, odds were they were going to find one of them.
And that, that worked out well. The last thing
about challenges that's worth noting is that the solutions,
because they could be done in any order or
not at all by the player, they had to
be designed so they had no dependency on each
other. And the game flow itself had no dependency
on any single solution. So all the way up
to, well, I should say alpha, but it was
probably like a week before submission, we were messing
with the game play and swapping solutions in and
out based on what we saw people trying to
do in, in play tests. And if they were
trying to do something that seemed logical, we
We just made a new doll, coded a solution in,
and then two days later or so, we had a whole new solution.
It worked well.
So we also ran into problems in that we
had no budget for voice acting.
But we had a lot of characters.
I mean, we had a couple hundred unique characters.
I think when I counted, there was about 28,000 lines of
dialogue, a lot of stuff there.
And so I knew we were going to have to put text on screen.
But I was really uncomfortable with that because text on
screen just didn't feel, I wanted it to be cohesive,
thematically cohesive with the rest of the game.
And then I remembered one of my early inspirations, German
expressionistic film.
So.
I brought back the idea of silent films.
And we did all of our storytelling with a silent
film motif, and even complete with dialogue
cards and everything.
And that worked out pretty well, but then we ran
into the fact that we had a pretty small
music budget and silent films are scored and we
couldn't afford to score all these with custom music.
And our, our awesome audio guys licensed classical music and
managed to edit that to the cut scenes as
if it were custom scored music, and it worked
really well.
And it was really awesome to have a
doll fart while Chopin was playing in the background,
which was great.
And, and ultimately this silent film stuff added more
personality for us. It gave us another motif to
kind of weave in with some of the
other influences. We added silent film stacking dolls. We
did our crossfades in silent film style. We, we
played a lot with those themes, the kind of
overacting and all that sort of stuff. And, and
it really just gave us another great angle on
the game.
So my lessons learned from this process are, are
very straightforward, but important. One is to embrace your
limitations. You hear this a lot, and I think
a lot of times it's more of a,
like, ugh.
we can't possibly do. So just embrace it, stomach it.
And that's not really what I'm thinking. Like, the
idea of, we embraced our limitations and by embracing
them we made different creative choices than we would
have otherwise made. And that went a long ways
to giving the game its own sense of personality.
So just work with those limitations. It's probably gonna
come out pretty cool. Like, most, everyone in this
industry is really clever.
And then find your essence early.
I think the amnesia Fortnite process forces you to,
forces you in a very fatherly good way,
to find all of the personality up front.
Don't just prototype the core mechanic
in the gray box world.
That's valuable, yes, but it's much more valuable
to do that and try and get the art look in there
and get the music in there.
So you can see all those connections early on.
And then the team who's making it with you
has a hand in forging the vision for the game.
So when you go right into production,
everyone's on board with the vision
because they helped make it.
as opposed to reading some large document and looking
at a bunch of gray box prototypes.
So I talked a little bit about finding
the essence in your product early and why that's
important.
But next up, Mr. Nathan Martz, project lead
of Once Upon a Monster, is gonna talk about
keeping that vision intact even though the product itself
might have to adapt to a variety of situations.
Nathan.
where you'll learn the character,
mission, and fun with Sesame Street Once Upon a Monster.
Join Sesame Street's Cookie Monster and Elmo
in a controller-free storybook adventure
filled with important life lessons,
inspiring challenges, and friendly new monsters
that even the biggest of kids will enjoy.
Sesame Street Once Upon a Monster.
Hey everyone, I'm Nathan Martz and I'm the project lead of Sesame Street Once Upon a
Monster, the game you can see up there.
And if you really want to understand where Once Upon a Monster started, we need to go
back in time.
We need to rewind all the way back to a time when housing prices could only go up and when
cutting edge internet humor was Rick Rolling and LOLcats.
And by that I mean the amazing year of 2007.
So, back then, five years ago, while the rest of the world was making irresponsible real
estate investments, I was writing the dismemberment code for Brutal Legend.
And it turns out, this is actually not the first time I'd written dismemberment code
for a video game.
It was actually the second time.
And as I was writing code, along with Drew, to dismember limbs and heads and spout blood,
I kind of started to feel like I was done with that,
and I was really excited to think about the next game that I worked on,
as much as I loved Brutal Legend and I loved the team that I was building it with,
that I wanted to do something different for my next game,
that I wanted to explore a different set of emotions.
But I wasn't exactly sure what that was.
But fortunately...
five years ago, I came to GDC and I saw an amazing talk by Tsutomu Kuono, who you probably
better know as the creator of LocoRoco. And it was really inspiring for me to see this
talk by a guy who is so clearly committed to making a, like, fun, positive, uplifting
game. It's one of my all-time favorite games. And I was like, wow, I want to make
a game like that. Except I don't want to copy him, I want to do something that's my own,
that's original, because that's what we're about at Double Fine. So like a lot of us
do, I started sort of with my childhood heroes. I thought back to the people that influenced
me creatively. Bill Watterson, for example, the creator of Calvin and Hobbes, and also
Jim Henson, the creator of The Muppets. And what struck me about both of these childhood
heroes was how remarkably positive they were in their work, that people remember them.
for the amazingly good-natured work that they did.
And I was like, that's awesome.
I would love to do a game with that same level
of upbeat positivity.
You know, I was also learning how to be a really terrible musician at the time,
like remarkably bad.
But along the way I was learning, I was reminded of how evocative music can be
as a tool for creating emotion and expressing emotion.
It's like there are very few things that tap into like our inner selves the way
that music does.
In fact, one day my girlfriend at the time, and that's actually not a photo of her,
She came up to me and she said,
you know, do you ever have like a happy song,
a song that like gets stuck in your head
and you just feel better for listening to it?
You know, and of course I was like,
nah baby, I'm all mad, I don't have happy songs.
But, you know, of course, we all do.
We all have songs that we,
as a game developer, that's as macho as I get.
You know, we all have songs that really move us.
So when Tim came up to me later that year and he said,
hey, I want to do this crazy thing called Amnesia Fortnite.
Do you have any ideas?
I was like, actually I do.
I've got this idea for a game where you experience
the joy of creating music.
In fact, there's this game that I want to make,
and it's going to be an interactive musical toy.
And in this toy, you're going to create
your own personal happy song.
But the thing is, most people.
they're not musicians, they need some help.
So we're gonna introduce them to some friends
who are musical monsters.
And those musical monsters are gonna help them
make their own personal happy song.
Tim was into the idea and we started Amnesia Fortnight.
Two weeks later, we made a prototype.
I'm sorry, I forgot to mention that because we only had two weeks,
it was going to be minimalistic environments, very simple.
Music, monsters, the end.
So we made that prototype, and it looked like this.
An awesome little jamboree of musical monsters in a minimalist environment,
and we called the game Happy Song.
And we were super proud of it, but being Amnesia Fortnight,
we forgot about it until two years later in 2009,
when the end of Brutal Legend was in sight.
And at that time, Tim came up to me, and he said,
you know, hey, let's make a small game, you know,
maybe something in addition to this big game
that we know we're going to do called Brutal Legend.
You know, let's pitch Happy Song as that game.
And I was like, that's awesome.
You know, I would love to pitch the game.
But if we're going to pitch it, we actually
have to pitch it, you know, to the suits, right,
to publishers, that we're going to have to make this game,
we're going to have to make it seem at least commercial.
Yeah. And, and the thing is, like, publishers are, they have reasonable reasons for wanting
commercial games, and the thing is that when we looked at the Happy Song prototype, we
honestly felt like it wasn't commercial. That it wasn't actually going to be a viable commercial
product. In particular, we felt like the Monster Friends were really, really awesome, but the
musical toy was less so. It felt really honestly kind of niche, you know, even for us. So.
So that was really the essence of our production challenge, was how could we adapt the prototype,
sign the game, and preserve the vision, preserve this idea of a game about joy, of a game that
makes you feel happier for having played it.
So we actually did two adaptations of that game.
And the first adaptation was to pitch it.
And the second adaptation was to sign it.
And our first opportunity to adapt the game
was with Kinect, which as you all know,
was announced with much fanfare at E3 in 2009.
And when that came out, we're like, wow, this is a new platform, which is going to mean
new opportunity, a hunger for new IPs.
And it's obviously family-oriented.
Microsoft is making a play for the Wii audience, and they're going to want wholesome, uplifting,
positive, you know, pro-social entertainment for that device.
There's going to be a demand maybe for new mechanics, because like there's no buttons
and it tracks your skeleton.
So maybe we could innovate there.
And in the end, it was a great opportunity.
But the question was, how could we adapt this game about
musical monsters to really work on Kinect?
So the idea that we had to adapt it was to change from a game about just musical monsters
and the joy of making music into a game about the joy of interacting, interacting with other
people and with monsters.
And the game that we were going to make would be a collection of monster mini-games all
about interactions with monsters.
Of course, we wanted to keep what works, in particular the monster friends and a game
that makes you feel happy.
Those are still going to be the essence of the product.
But we had to change some stuff as well.
And the first thing that we wanted to change
was the focus on character interaction.
Where the original prototype was focused on music,
we were going to focus on the connection between the characters
in the world.
And in order to do that, we're going to have multiple activities.
We wanted to have.
a game that where you could play dress up with the monsters,
you could do a posing Simon Says game, you could dance.
All of these things would be ways to interact with them.
And these activities would be more physical
because on Kinect, physical is fun.
So we had to de-emphasize music and emphasize the physicality.
And lastly, we want to take advantage
of the magic of Kinect, that Kinect can see you and pretend
that the monsters could also see you
so that you could interact with them
in a very direct, connected way.
As part of that, we're like, well, if you're interacting
with the monsters, how about also
interacting with other people?
We really love this idea of parent-child co-play, a game
that parents and kids could play together.
So we're going to make all of the activities two-player.
We're going to have a fundamentally
intergenerational focus.
And you can play it with a friend, you can play it with a
sibling, but really we want to focus on a
parent and a young child.
And lastly, that means it's going to be a real world
interaction, but not just a synthetic interaction with the
characters on screen.
As part of that, we realized that our minimalistic environment
wasn't going to work.
In order to contextualize these activities,
we needed an actual world, a place that these activities could happen.
And we were really inspired by storybook illustrators
like Eric Carle and Mary Blair.
We love their flat, two-dimensional sensibilities.
And so we said, well, we're going to have an environment,
but we're going to embrace still this idea of minimalism,
of a 2D, flat, simply constructed world.
And the last thing we're going to do is players are going to need instruction.
They're going to need to know what to do and how to do it, so we're going to add a narrator.
Maybe, you know, a David Attenborough-esque character.
He's going to provide exposition and instruction, but, you know,
because some narrators are kind of strange-looking, he'll be disembodied
and omniscient and, you know, not actually part of the real experience.
So that was actually all awesome,
and we adapted our game.
We made a new prototype.
It looked like this.
And we called it Monster Party, because it
was going to represent this idea of a collaborative
social experience.
And that was all super awesome.
But then another opportunity came along,
and that opportunity was in early 2010,
when I read a Gamasutra article where
we heard Warner Brothers had announced
a brand new partnership.
And the partnership was with Sesame Street,
that Warner Brothers was going to become
the exclusive publisher and distributor of all things
Sesame Street.
Thank you.
So one of the cool things about that was that these were
obviously very compatible values.
Sesame Street is about education and making the world
a better place.
We were about making games a better place.
And in fact, this would be a return to our original
inspiration, not just inspired by Jim Henson, but working
directly with some of his creations.
So as with the Kinect, it was a great
opportunity for our game.
But now the question was, how could we adapt that game for
Sesame Street?
How could we make this game into something that really
felt genuinely Sesame?
So, the idea we had was to adapt again the game and to change it from being about the
joy of interaction to the joy of helping others, of which interaction is kind of a subset.
And the game is going to turn from a collection of activities into a collection of stories.
Stories about monsters with problems who need your help.
in order to make sure that their story has a happy ending.
And as before, we're going to keep what works.
We're going to keep the monster friends,
the interactive gameplay, the parent-child co-play,
and a game that makes you feel happy.
All these things are important, and they're successful,
and they're going to stay.
But some other things, again, have to change.
So the first big change was that the storybook-inspired world
became a literal storybook.
We actually decided to fictionalize the world
as a storybook come to life.
Again, that provided a context for not just the activities,
but also for the stories.
And it allowed us to bridge the real world of Sesame Street
with the fictional world of our game and our monsters.
The second thing that we did was just took our narrator,
this person who provided exposition and context,
and we replaced him with Cookie Monster and Elmo,
that they would now become our guides.
They would have the same function in the world,
but because they're physical monsters,
they could be part of the game world.
And because they're part of the world,
they could be physical and funny and personable
in a way that a disembodied narrator
never could have been.
Lastly, to make a Sesame product meant that we had to be educational. We couldn't, we
didn't want to be the Tickle Me Elmo of Sesame Street video games. But we also knew that
we had to be, you know, entertaining at the same time. And when you think about classic
Sesame Street, you think of numeracy and literacy, ABCs and 123s. Well, for us, that was not
going to work. It's too didactic, it's too dull, it's very age-specific. Instead, what
we want to do is focus on Sesame Street's emotional curriculum, their curriculum about
sharing, empathy, compassion, the identification of emotions.
These things, we thought, would be really consistent
with our original vision of a game about joy.
And rather than just making players happy,
we could actually inspire them and teach them a little bit
about how to be better human beings.
So we made that game, and it looks like this.
And we called it Sesame Street Once Upon a Monster,
and that's the game that we shipped.
So, throughout all this, the biggest lesson that I learned
is that you really have to know your vision in order
to stick to it, especially in difficult changing times.
For us, that was a game about creating joy.
And not only do you need to know your vision,
you need to keep it simple.
It needs to be one sentence or less.
And it should focus on the experience of the product,
not just a mechanic or a hook or an art direction
or a monetization strategy,
but how do people feel having played it?
And once you know that, you need to tell the team
and tell them often.
because if your game is gonna be changing all the time,
your team are the ones really grappling with that.
And if they don't know, if they've lost sight
of what the vision is, you'll lose sight of it too.
And that little beating heart of your game
is gonna go away.
So really, in the end, a remarkable amount of change
is possible.
You can see where we started and see where we ended.
But ultimately, only because we knew and were able to stay
true to the core idea of our vision of a game about joy.
So that's all cool.
It's great to know our idea, our vision for one title.
But we were making four games.
And so how about our vision for our brand?
What were we going to run into there?
And to talk about that, my excellent colleague, Mr. Brad
Muir, lead of Iron Brigade, is going to come up and talk to
you about that.
Thank you, sir. How are we doing on time? Are we okay?
For your freedom. For your family.
For your children.
The MonoVision menace has destroyed our army, our navy, our air force.
Who is left to fight?
Hey!
Hey, I'm Brad.
So I was the project lead on Trenched, and then I was the project lead on Iron Brigade.
So, um, 2007 Amnesia Fortnight, I was in that, uh, the class of 2007 Amnesia Fortnight with
Nathan, and, uh, you know, we were gonna make a game, and my inspiration at the time, I
was deeply involved in, uh, Brutal Legend.
and i really like as a game designer really like uh... core mechanic matchup
that stuff
like deconstructing mechanics from different games and they have a plan
together and see what you get and hopefully it's great
uh... so i was looking at uh... make shooters a lot of mess mecca salt
really love that game. You know there's a lot of customization and the combat's really
fun and I love the perspective and just lots of things to love about that game. And then
I was looking at tower defense games also. I think that's defense grid and I love defense
grid. And there's just so many awesome decisions that you're making when you're playing it.
a tower defense game about where you're going to put your uh... towers and how you're going
to spend your resources and where the enemies are coming from
so i really wanted to like put those two things together in a game
uh... i also wanted to make a game that focused heavily on co-op because uh...
like i think gears of war had come out recently and i was really liking the
trend in the industry to sort of shift to co-op
uh...
my brother had moved away
And this is, that's him on my back there.
And this is like our primary method of keeping in touch.
So I really wanted it to be a game that we could play together.
And I didn't realize it at the time,
but I also wanted to continue that positivity
and, you know, make this a game about love.
It's really important to me that, you know,
much like Once Upon a Monster,
we try to inject more positivity into the industry.
And, you know, how better to do that than with guns and mechs and explosions.
So the Amnesia Fortnite prototype, I really didn't want to focus on the core mechanics,
so I just picked like a very, very kind of off-the-shelf steampunk Britain setting for the game.
So the players are tasked with defending this...
uh... this giant steam factory
uh... and they're piloting these mobile factories and they can make defenses
around the map and there are these uh... zombie robots that will come out at night
and assault their factory
so uh... the game look like this we called it custodians of the clock
uh... and that is the worst name please never repeat that uh... because the
custodian people don't think of a cool guy driving a mech
they think about other stuff
So that would have to change, but a lot of other stuff would have to change also.
So our big production challenge in the game is that, you know, this is a game that's inspired by core mechanics.
And, you know, the players that have played our games, like, you know, that's not very double fine.
Like, that's not really how Tim has always, like, traditionally come up with game ideas and made games.
So, yeah, it's like Tim is a top-down designer.
He comes up with the fiction and the world and the...
uh... you know all of the all of the the dressing for the game in the in the
setting the fiction and all that stuff and then
works down to the core mechanics
and on the on the other way i go bottom up
i start with the uh...
That's weird.
I start with the, that's not what I, come on.
So I start with the core mechanics
and then build from there
and then add fiction and a world on top of it.
So that's the real question is that
can these approaches work inside the same company?
Because, you know, talking with Tim, it's important that we stand for something.
We have all these creative voices that are now, like, being expressed,
and we can't just be all over the map.
Like, we want to make sure that we're still kind of in the same domain together.
So is it possible for the game to be different and yet still double fine?
So we kind of examined what our brand was to people who played our game.
So from the outside looking in, we thought that players really like the stories,
they really like the funny cutscenes that are in the game.
and they really like the characters.
So what was it really?
We kind of thought about it,
and the answer was that we just, we didn't know.
So we decided to, you know, explore this
and try to figure it out before we
made modifications to Custodians.
So the first one, the story, we decided after talking about it
that it really wasn't about a great deep story.
It was more about originality, is
that all these games are set in original fantasy worlds
and that that's very important to our core brand.
So trying to add originality to Iron Brigade.
We're taking the original 2007 setting of Steampunk Britain.
And it just felt a little too prepackaged.
It felt like someone else's original idea.
So we really wanted to attack this and make
the game a lot more original.
So we held the first ever Double Fine Art Jam.
So we grabbed the entire 2D concept art team
for a couple of days.
And this generated a really high number of ridiculous ideas.
So the first one, Scott Campbell came up with this idea
for these giant castle robots.
So you had these chivalrous knights driving these big, huge robots,
and they're super awesome.
But we thought that was a little out there.
Mark Hamer had an idea to use Hieronymus Bosch.
I don't know if you know this guy.
We used him on a lot of his work on Brutal Legend to
inspire the tainted coil.
But he had an idea to make Bosch robots that would be
attacking you, and they're all super creepy and weird.
And then another one that we didn't use, Bagel came up with this idea,
is that there were, um,
he thought that the heroes would be the founding fathers of the United States
and that they would pilot robots that were, uh, you know, giant versions of their own
heads. See, there's the Ben Franklin one and then
the George Washington one is up there and it has wooden teeth.
And that was a little bit too out there, so we just decided that we would cherry
pick the best ideas that came out of there.
Uh, so...
I really liked Lee Petty, the handsome Lee Petty right here,
came up with this idea of like makeshift World War I stuff.
You know, you see this tea drinking guy on his tractor
with a bunch of guns on it and stuff,
and this big smokestack cannon that came off
of a big cruise liner.
And I just thought that was so awesome.
I love the idea of like found technology,
and it really fit the sort of like post-apocalyptic thing
that I was interested in.
And then Scott Campbell had this idea for these TV smoke
monsters.
And so these were like amorphous shapes that have
these TVs in them, and you had to blast the TVs.
And this was the basis for our enemies.
And then Lee also had this other awesome idea that went
along with his makeshift World War I stuff, and that was
these big cruise liners with legs.
So boats with legs, awesome.
And this made it almost all the way into the shipping
version of the game, where the USS McKinley that you see for
the Mobile Trench Brigade has four legs, is a giant aircraft
carrier, and it's awesome.
So we kind of took these three major elements
and put them together, and we came up with the concept
of the mobile trench.
So it's like a small open top mech with the sandbags on it
and a bunch of guns.
You can see the pilot in there.
And then we wanted them to be fighting these TV monsters.
So this was our first stab at both of these.
And then through iteration, we came up
with a more blocky design for the mobile trench
that you see in the shipping game.
And then we came up with a more creepy, organic look
for the mono-visions that you see.
Okay, so we talked about how the, you know, what people really want, like the first core
thing is originality.
So looking at the funny cutscenes, we decided that the second thing was really personality
for the game.
You know, our games have like tons of personality and it's not necessarily about the funny cutscenes,
it's just about like that they're dripping with personality.
So to attack this problem, I decided that I really wanted to involve the whole team.
You know, the company's awesome and Tim Myers is awesome people.
I, I, yeah, I think so.
And your team has been, has been soaking in your company culture
for a really long time.
And that they literally are your company culture.
So if we can take ideas from them and inject them directly into the game,
the game's just going to have a lot more personality.
It's going to feel like a game that comes out of our studio.
So this is Raz.
And he is, yeah Raz! He's a concept artist on the game.
And he had this great idea for using these men's magazine covers from the 40s and 50s.
And this was a really awesome inspiration for the game. I love the over the top manly
men and the machismo. It's like very satirical to take this and sort of make fun of it. Also
a lot of these covers, there's a whole subset of them that I love where it's men fighting
little tiny animals. I don't know, it's very very strange.
But we
We used these and sort of made, you know, we made our own versions of them.
And this kind of formed the aesthetic backbone of the whole game.
You know, using these men's magazine covers, the topography is awesome,
and they're just awesome, I love them.
So this is Chris Journey, and he's the lead programmer.
And he's also in the front row right there.
He was the lead programmer around Trent, Iron Brigade.
And he had this great idea.
Actually, I didn't think it was a great idea at first.
He had this idea that in between the missions,
you're running your trench marine around
on the deck of the ship,
and that you could use the right analog trigger
to like salute.
And I was like, that's the dumbest idea I've ever heard.
I hate you and I would fire you if I could.
But I asked him, I was like, how long will it take?
And he's like, it'll take two days
and one day of an animator.
And I was like, all right, fine, you can try it.
Fine.
and he went and did it and uh... we playtested it and everybody just totally
loved it and they ate it up and it was awesome
and i have since been swayed and our buddies over at giant bomb turned it into this
big like weird meme thing and it was
it really helped us grow the community it was just very like
you know it was it was something unique and original and gave the game a lot of
personality
uh... this is Jeff Solis he is the lead artist of Iron Brigade
and uh... so i had this giant spreadsheet with all these weapons that
i wanted to have in the game and i felt like it was way too big it was like a
hundred and fifty plus or something stupid like that
and uh... i just gave it to him and i was like hey will you you know you wanna
just make of
bunch of these guns
and you know i thought he was going to come back and be like oh i'll give you half
But, no, he was like, yeah, I'll do that.
I'll just do all those.
And I was like, sweet.
And he just came up with all these crazy guns on his own.
There was not a lot of time for concept art or anything.
He was just, you know, cranking these out.
And they all have unique reload animations.
And they're just awesome.
They gave the game a ton of personality.
OK, so we talked about that's the second core thing
for the Double Fine brand, is personality.
So the third one are the really memorable characters.
And, you know, we thought about it.
And it turns out that.
Yeah, it's really memorable characters.
You guys totally nailed that one.
One of the problems was that it's really difficult to
inject character into a mech game.
I'm not pigging on mech assault here.
I love that game.
But the mech is so big, and the human that's piling in it,
that would be a mech warrior, is so tiny that you can't even
see him, and it's really hard to actually get a character
really, really in there.
So our solution was the open top mechs, the mobile trenches.
So if we peel the top off of it and make it a lot smaller,
the human's going to be a lot larger,
and he'll be a lot more visible.
So we can do things like here, he's
drinking a whole bottle of whiskey
after completing a mission, or lighting a cigar with a pistol.
Like a lot of these manly things from the men's magazines
can really shine when the mech's a lot smaller.
Another place where we added more character into the game
was the commander of the Mobile Trench Brigade.
He wasn't really a major gameplay piece at all.
He was just a dude on the ship that gives you missions.
So, you know, we thought about having maybe like one different character for each of the
theaters that you go through and, you know, it was kind of boring.
But then Tim and Peter Chan came up with this idea that maybe the commander can be confined
to this iron lung, which is a really creepy contraption.
And Peter's first take on it...
was a little weird.
He had this upright iron lung that's,
yeah, we're not super into that.
But just going with a more traditional iron lung
that had these little mechanical arms on it
was really cool and created a really memorable character
that you're interacting with all the time on the ship.
And it just really helped us hit that.
So yeah, the Double Fine brand, we really feel like it's about originality,
personality, and memorable characters.
But through this process, we also learned that it's about another thing,
and that's the element of surprise.
And Iron Brigade, as a game, was kind of already doing this.
Nobody really expected us to make a shooter.
But by making it and by going through this exercise,
we just really feel that we want our fans to expect the unexpected.
Like the next game that we announce will just be something
that nobody saw coming, and that's really important to us.
So the lessons that we learned from going through this process,
like you really want to identify your brand as soon as you can.
And it really just helps drive your decision making.
Also, you shouldn't be beholden to what other people think
your brand is about.
It's really up to you to define it,
to really put a stake in the ground
and tell people what it is.
And then also, you should always be
on the lookout for opportunities to apply
your brand's fundamentals to your game
without disrupting its core.
and now we're gonna check out a video of the uh... the transformation of these
three games
uh... from their amnesia fortnight versions into their shipping versions
the
her
you
Oh, hello again.
So just a couple of quick takeaways.
First takeaway is these guys rock.
These guys have a big hand for Lee and Nathan and Brad,
and also Tasha.
That's as well. It was really important to this whole process that I was able to let these guys run their own projects and not have to, you know, they had full autonomy and I could trust them to get these things done, which is really important to it.
I think going into multiple teams like this allowed
Double Fine to become really agile, which led to our
survival.
I mean, I think if we were married to one plan, one type
of game, one platform, one device, we would be out of
business by now.
We now have multiple teams so we can try things.
And if they don't work out, we can move into another
direction, and it's really made us a lot healthier as a
company.
Having multiple teams allows the team, like I mentioned
before, to grow.
Everybody can move up into leadership roles, and we can
try someone out on a two-week prototype without risking the
whole company on them.
And then if they work out, give them.
a bigger project later on.
And as a company, now that we can really diversify, we might
not have wanted to try a licensed product like Sesame
Street, Once Upon a Monster, if it was going to define our
entire company.
Now we're doing licensed properties, or even a Kinect
game, or we're doing a mobile game, or something like that,
because people would think, well, that's what they're
doing now.
They're a mobile game company all of a sudden.
We can have multiple teams.
We can try each of these things.
We can try mobile.
We can try a free-to-play game.
We can try to get money from the internet on Kickstarter.
We can do anything we want, because we have multiple teams
and we're really just sending a recon team out to investigate
that opportunity for us.
And I think the biggest takeaway for me was that
is about core principles not just like how important it is to stick to your core principles when you are doing a major
transition but actually you can use your core principles to make that transition happen. And for me it was finding out
that the core principle of the company the number one thing for me was creativity. And when we had a big blow to our.
financial stability by losing a multi-million dollar project like Brutal Legend 2 and we're
worried about going out of business. We weren't bailed out by some big publisher or an angel
investor. We didn't have a big Kickstarter back then to give us the millions of dollars.
We weren't saved by anyone except for we looked at the team's creativity and it was really
our, the creativity of the team that saved our whole company and that was.
for me, just really a great moment for our
company to know that we could save ourselves with
this thing that we've been working on this whole
time and wanted to identify ourselves with.
So that's the, the, the summary of our talk,
and I want to thank you all for coming
and remind you to fill out your feedback forms,
and if we have any time now, we can
take some questions. So thanks for coming.
So we have, when do we have to get
out of here? Yeah, three? What? We have nine
minutes?
Oh, we're good. Oh, I know, I know we're good. I'm just saying.
So there are these microphones right over here and here.
And I see people are running to the doors where they think the microphones are.
But the microphones are actually kept up here, you guys.
So I want to get really close. First, you over there. Hello there.
Hi. I had a question.
So you had multiple teams for your Amnesia Fortnite,
but you also have multiple people in your company.
How did you decide which ideas to run with?
Like you had your four teams, but there has to be an
initial selection project or process of these are the ideas
we're going to run at.
And I'm sure everyone had an idea, but how do you make that
final selection?
Yeah.
So how did we pick which projects to make?
I mean, we did Fortnite.
We had many talented people in the company.
And there was a combination.
There was one that was like a solitary thing with just my
visibility on the whole company.
There's people I've had my eye on for a long time for
disciplinary reasons like Lee or for, you know.
But there's people who, you know, you can kind of tell like who's got promised, you
know, and you think, I want to give that person a test and see if they can, what they would
do, given a little, a chance, given a shot. And then also sometimes when there's a lot
of, you know, especially we did, we have done it a third time now, and there were so many,
I just invited submissions from the whole company and there were so many that I had
to get a...
kind of a, you know, a little group together of the, um, some of the previous leads and,
and senior people in the company to like look at all these submissions and really talk it
through which one we thought fit the company's strategy, tested the right people and did
the right thing. So, there's a combination of some hand picking but also some, um, just
really talking through with the team of like which ones worked out the best for us long
term. So thanks for the question. Yes?
Did it upset your publisher at all to take people away from the project, Brutal Legend, and have so many people working for two weeks on all these different projects?
So here was, here's the interesting thing.
Um, don't always tell your publisher everything.
Um, I'm trying to figure out the timing on this, because both times, I feel like both times when we were doing Amazing Fortnite, we were, we had the luxury of not having a publisher at that moment.
We had, we had a very dark period in the middle of Brutal Legend where we were, um, you know, publisher free.
Um, which was terrifying. And, uh, um, and also after, after brutal legend, we had, we were, you
know, the contract was over and we had some freedom, but we, um, you know, once we, and
with, and that's something you really, you only, you don't have to worry about the first time
when you're a single company going to multiple projects, once you have multiple projects,
there are multiple revenue streams. It's not, everything's not coming. You can't, no one
founder, no one funder of your company can prove they paid for your amnesia fortnight,
which is really important because.
Anyway, it's part of your overhead of your company, and
it is something that is totally valid to spend your
money on if you're investing in the future.
But basically, you lie and say your milestone is going to be
two weeks later than it really is.
So, next question.
Why two weeks, and would you find it to be effective to do more or less than two weeks?
I didn't bring my maths, my slide rule, which is so I can prove this mathematically perfect amount of time to spend on this.
But it is, you have to trust me.
I picked two weeks actually because of that story about Wonka or why I heard it was two weeks and I don't know why.
Two weeks is this magical amount of time where you feel like you could do anything.
Like when you're like, when's that task going to be done?
I think it's going to be done in about two weeks, because that sounds like infinity, basically.
Two weeks equals infinity.
And I really think it's more,
I think it's important to do two instead of one.
I think one week is just enough time
to get your team in sync and moving.
I think two weeks really to do it
is what helped us get these things
that were ready to be pitched, I think.
Thank you.
I was just wondering, like, where did you start in terms of tech with each of these games?
Oh, that was a really important thing. Where did we start in terms of tech?
It would have been really hard to do this if we didn't have the Brutal Engine engine.
We had the Brutal Engine engine working, and we had tools, a pipeline, and the team knew how to use it.
And so we could just start day one on the gameplay and the, you know, our direction.
We didn't have to worry about...
making an engine any time. But even if you didn't have an engine, there are out of the
box engines you could use. You could grab one of the things that's out there and use
that. I wouldn't start and write a whole new engine from scratch in two weeks. It would
make you spend a lot of time on things that were not right.
Yeah, we'd actually designed the Brutal Legend engine to be
to really a thoughtful separation between game specific code and game independent code.
That's what actually allowed us to basically every Amnesia Fortnite project
has always started with a little kernel we call a seed.
And it's just like the most basic game where like it boots, it runs,
there's a dude, there's a controller input, and then like have fun.
And I think that like some of the architectural decisions we made very early in Brutal Legend.
have allowed us to build a code base that can support everything from Once Upon a Monster
to stacking to trench or Iron Brigade to Happy Action Theater, Costume Quest, you know, it's
a lot of that is just that top level kind of switching in and out.
Thank you.
All right.
Oh, we have one more question there.
So do you think having these predefined divisions of teams
really helped have everyone on those teams
have creative input?
Or do you think it could have been just as good to have
these initial ideas and then allocate resources?
This project needs a lot more artists, or this project is
much more technically demanding, even though the
teams might not have started out all being one big family.
Like are you saying how we split up the team, how we
chose the teams, how do we split them up?
You could have done it differently, and it would have
been more or less creative.
I mean, the way we split up the teams to do the image of Fortnite is that we, we pick
the leaders of the teams and who, and we let them pitch their games to the whole company.
And then everybody got to put a stack rank list of which ones they wanted to work on.
And then every team lead got to put a stack rank list of who they wanted on the team.
And then we made an Excel document that actually calculated points for each things and came
up with this robot-generated list, which was totally not just me filling in slots when
no one was looking.
But, I mean, it was like...
It really was a, we tried to do a balance of what, who wanted to work on what, and who needed who for their project.
And then the way we would pull some people from here to there.
And, and that's how we picked it for the team to be a good balance between.
We just tried to make sure that each team had what it needed.
Some of the times they had, they had a scramble.
I remember Brad didn't have a, was it an animator?
Or you didn't have a concept artist?
didn't have concept artists.
Didn't have concept artists, but I think Jeff or Randy,
some of the guys on your team got a chance to draw
some good concept artists.
Yeah, yeah, that was cool.
Just many hats.
Part of the reason that the original Happy Song prototype
had no environment was I knew I needed a lot of animators.
And so I was like, how about no environments?
And then other people can take the environment artists,
and I'll take lots of animators.
And that worked out well.
And there was some things that were unfair about that,
but it kind of seems like a draconian,
but I think I should learn how to fight for resources
as part of learning how to run a project.
it sounds dark, isn't it? But it's a, it's
a, knowing what your project needs and knowing how
to get it on your project, that's part of
making a game. So that's part of the trial
by fire.
Is there time for one more? That's a wave.
Does that mean go away, or does that mean?
Oh, we're done. OK. We have to, we have
to go away. So I don't have time to
remind you to back our Kickstarter project or the
stacking's available on PC. So I won't say that. So
bye. Thank you.