I'm Kim Belair. I'm a writer, I'm a narrative designer, I'm extremely nervous and I'm the
co-founder of a little narrative development company called Sweet Baby Inc. We do narrative
development in games and kind of beyond and we try to bring a lot of inclusion, diversity
and new ideas kind of to the industry.
So just as a kind of fun fact, last year was actually my first GDC and I first pitched
this talk as part of the program Amplifying New Voices, if anyone has heard of it.
Yes.
I think it's also kind of appropriate that that's where I talked about this because it's
also what my talk is about in a lot of ways.
So hi.
For a little bit of background on me, I've been a professional writer for about 12 years,
but I've always written stuff. I think that's always the way.
But when I was a kid, and I want to start at the beginning here because I think that it's important to kind of give context
to the way I learned about representation as a woman of color,
and I think the way that a lot of marginalized people kind of get socialized when it comes to topics like this.
So when I was small and starting to kind of express myself creatively in either writing or stories or art,
I wrote about myself a lot.
And I would put myself into a lot of art, into a lot of narratives,
and I put my family and people who look like me in all these cool scenarios,
and I was telling all these stories where I got to see myself,
I got to see people who look like me,
and kind of a rainbow of people who were kind of adjacent to me in a lot of ways.
And I think it was really neat and I was really fostered in that.
So when I hit elementary school, I think that I was free to tell those stories
because a lot of the stories that you hear in elementary school are about like,
we should be friends with everyone, we should be inclusive,
we should preach equality and build communities.
And I think this was really, really wonderful.
But then I got to high school.
And suddenly for the first time in my life,
I got told that the stories that I was writing
and the things that I was creating for and about people
who resembled me were not real stories
and they were not right stories.
And this was to the point that I received a list
that I'm sure many of you have received
that was here's a list of authors
and stories that are legitimate.
Here's a list of people and stories that are important.
And as you can imagine, they were mostly men
and almost exclusively white.
And so were the subjects of all these stories, with a couple exceptions of
people who were there to teach lessons to the white male characters, or people
who were there to express pain, or people who were there to be the target of some
kind of hate or conflict.
And if we ever did read, you know, here's a book by like an African American author,
here's a book by a woman, here's a book by a Japanese author, it was for a lesson that was
about this is what life is like as a woman, this is what pain and suffering is like as a Black
person, this is what pain and suffering is like as a Japanese person. And so through that and
kind of unconsciously, I started to learn that books by and about white men were literature,
they were classics, they were important.
and everything else is just special interest.
They're very, very niche.
And then meanwhile, there's like a young me.
And all I wanted out of this whole life was to be a writer.
And I wanted that so bad that I kind of said,
okay, well, what do I need to be legitimate?
And I just internalized everything that I had learned.
And I did that for years.
And I spent like actual years just writing about white men,
because I thought, okay,
I'm making art now because I can look at the stories that are being told that are being
held up as legitimate and as classic and they look like the stories that I'm telling.
And for so many years I did this that I think it was probably only in my early to mid-twenties
that I started to realize that I had internalized this like deeply, deeply uninteresting idea.
that in terms of narratives and stories, white and male are neutral and universal.
And I say that even as a woman of color, so while we don't all fall into that trap,
I say it to illustrate how easy it is for us to take on that narrative
even as people who are marginalized, even as we're fighting.
Because we've kind of created this normal.
that we all unconsciously follow and it affects us even as we advocate for change.
There are things and times like back in the day if you'd asked me,
oh are you doing this on purpose? Are you only telling stories that fit the dominant narrative?
I would never have said yes, but I think that a lot of people end up doing it even as they're
saying we have to do better. And I think that that's actually shown in the way that we manage
representation.
which we still consider it this like deviation from something that is normal.
And representation is this like very, very scary and very uncertain thing.
And if we do it wrong or if we don't do it, you know, accurately,
or if we kind of take a risk, we might get shouted down and that fear is enough to stop us.
And I think like.
that sucks. And it's such a bummer because it's the only way sometimes that we end up
talking about it. We end up saying we're going to share our stories of microaggressions, which I am
going to do today, but we share stories of trauma and of doubt and when we're dealing with narratives
in advocacy, we end up going like, okay, these stories are stirring and they're beautiful,
but they're also very sad and very heartbreaking.
And I think it's important to do that.
It's important to share all of those painful stories
if we're going to actually understand the struggle
and convey the struggle.
But I think today, I'd like to take a moment
and kind of assume the best.
Because I want to assume that all of you
are here in this advocacy talk, because what I've said so far
is already familiar, already painful.
And I want to kind of assume that you have sat with that.
Or if it's not your experience, you've
already sat and listened to that.
in other areas and rather I think than spending the next 15 or so minutes kind of sitting
in that pain, I want to share some examples from my own experience and then kind of discuss
how we can do better and find different and more interesting ways of talking about this
stuff as creatives and as advocates and as people who overall want practical solutions
to these kinds of problems.
So let's talk about video games.
To begin, a lot of the work that I do
is in narrative consultation and narrative design.
And one of the things that I offer
as part of my list of services
is risk assessment and sensitivity reading.
And so recently I was consulting on a project
that was a dating simulator.
and I was faced with a very simple decision point that the writers were trying to achieve
and it was this interaction between the female-identified date and you, the protagonist,
and you could customize your gender, you could customize your appearance and everything.
So the love interest is on a date with you and they ask you a very simple question and it's
what was your ex like?
is a bit much for a first date, but the player can either choose to say,
OK, my ex was a good person, but it didn't work out.
They can choose to say, I don't know if I really want to talk about that.
Or they can choose to say, my ex was a monster.
And choosing my ex was a monster, the woman on the date with you
goes like, yikes.
You must be so immature if that's what you're going
to say on a date about your ex.
Like, you must be.
not over this, you must be figuring something out.
And I think that you lose favor in that moment
with that character.
And I can see where the design was.
Like, I understand that what they wanted to do
was just have a very simple question where
if you respond, your date can say,
I like that, or I don't like that,
or kind of be neutral about it.
But I played through that,
and I realized something that they hadn't really seen,
and it's that,
this question was deeply gendered,
despite the fact that they didn't even intend that.
When we treat, I guess, cis, hetero, male characters
as the default, we end up with questions like this.
And I say that because, while it's a generalization,
when we have those characters and they say something like,
hey, my ex is a monster, what we're being asked to assume
is that that person has a crazy ex-girlfriend.
or being asked to assume that they're being immature
or they might have a real harpy at home.
It's almost like a laugh line a lot of the time.
So I asked, hey, what if I'm playing as a woman?
because what I had to explain very delicately was that if I'm playing as a woman and I'm
assuming that I'm interacting with a woman and we don't know about my ex, there's an
upsettingly high likelihood that when I say to another woman, my ex was a monster, what
I'm referring to was an abusive situation rather than just an immature joke.
And so I actually said, you know what though, don't worry about it.
We can create a condition for this because if you respond to that person by saying,
hey, my ex was a monster, what if she digs a little deeper?
What if she checks and says, hey, is that a pain point for you?
Or says like, oh, is that something touchy for you?
Or maybe says like, do you mean that as a flippant remark?
Because I think that even though this game is light,
it would be a genuinely important moment to be able to express that sentiment in a game.
And when I suggested that, the writing team was like,
Okay, thank you for this insight.
And then they just like, took it away.
They got nervous, and I think that is the problem
that we face when we think of representation
as a challenge that we just need to like surmount.
We could just like go, nope, solved, we did it.
Because we took it away,
and we don't have to face it anymore.
But I thought here, this was an opportunity for innovation.
Here we had the chance to make a woman
who has been victimized, see herself in a game,
be able to express something to another woman in a game,
and kind of actually relate to it.
And we had that opportunity,
we pulled back because we thought it was safer not to push forward.
And after the whole thing was done, the team thanked me again and they said like,
thanks so much, you really mitigated the risk.
And I think that the way that we talk about this kind of thing is itself a problem.
We need sensitivity readers.
We need risk assessment.
And these are, again, important services
that I literally list on every PDF that I send out
to be like, hey, I can do risk assessment and sensitivity
reading.
But I think when we do that kind of work
and we make it seem like what we're doing is being very
careful, being very scared.
we end up just kind of sanding down all the rough edges
instead of building something new
and building something out.
And that means that we feel daunted
when we discuss representation
because we talk a lot about representation
as the mitigation of pain,
but we don't talk about representation as a creator of joy.
Because I would genuinely love just once to be called into one of these consulting sessions
and instead of being asked like, hey, can you tell us how this is going to hurt people
like you, just be asked, hey, what would you like to see people like you do in this game?
What experiences can people like you bring to the world of the game that we haven't seen
before?
What's a cool thing that you want to see from characters who look and act like you?
And it's not the way we're taught to talk about it, but I think it could be.
Because even when we're doing narrative design, we're looking at archetypes every time we want to have a set of answers, right?
We're looking, this is what a rebel would do, this is what a jerk would do, this is what a more straight-laced person would do.
And I think I would love to start thinking about more like, what option can we make for people who haven't been seen?
What can we add?
that provides a new perspective
that we've never explored before.
So I think if we prioritize joy
and start to frame representation
as a new form of innovation,
rather than as pain avoidance
and like surface level diversity,
we're gonna actually start to win a few more battles
and generate moments of actual happiness.
So this is kind of all up in the air, but I want to give an example of what these kinds
of wins can look like, or at least what they have looked like in the past for me.
And I kind of want to say, okay, imagine me now as a player.
Because this is my go-to example, and it's something that I talk about all the time,
and it's the first time that I ever made a black character in a video game.
And this is genuinely embarrassing to relate to a crowd of people,
but for a really long time before this,
when I was offered like a character customization screen,
I was like, well, I can't put myself in there because that...
that's weird and not what video games are.
And so I made some stubbly white dude protagonists,
even when I had every option available to me
because I didn't want to feel like I was putting
too much of myself into this world where I didn't belong.
And it's wild to think about,
I just created Nathan Drake, so I was like,
go, explore every game.
But anyway, the first time that I actually made
a black protagonist was in Mass Effect in 2010.
And that felt really, really great.
And I know that everyone at GDC has seen a lot about Mass Effect.
So many talks talk about Mass Effect, so I think it's very important.
But for anyone who's never played it, I'm just going to give you a little rundown of the first playable area.
Basically, your fully customized Commander Shepard has to enter a space station and rendezvous with two characters.
Jacob Taylor and Miranda Lawson, but you meet Jacob first and for those of you who don't know Jacob is a black man
He's a marine and he's your first kind of like point of contact. So your first interaction with him
You're like crouching behind cover and you're having a close-quarters conversation
And when this happened in the game, it was this really powerful and remarkable moment for me,
because it was two black characters talking one-on-one, and neither of them is cast as a
criminal, they're not a sidekick, they're not a savage, they're not a stereotype, they're not
a gang member. And they're the only two people on screen in this moment talking about something
much greater than them. And it was just like, really, really, really nice. I left off a really.
I was so happy about this moment that I actually took my phone out to text my white best friend
and I was like, wow, it was really just cool to see this scene in this game, can you believe
it?
And I was halfway through the text when I realized, oh, she isn't going to see that
because her shepherd doesn't look the same as mine.
But I texted her anyway because I thought, you know what, I'm going to share this moment
of joy for me and she's my best friend so she has to be happy about it.
And her response, while not surprising, was still very touching because she said,
I've never seen that either.
And holy moly, that's cool.
And I told some other friends at that point.
I was kind of like excited about it.
And they weren't all black, these friends.
They weren't all targeted by this moment that I had experienced.
But they all felt the same thing when they heard me tell my story,
and when they heard that it was a new kind of term.
And the general idea was, holy moly, representation is cool.
But in my mass effect experience, this is almost an accidental form of representation
because it's something that's a possibility.
It's not guaranteed for any player depending on the kind of character in the Commander Shepard that you make.
So I thought, wouldn't it be amazing if this wasn't an accident, but it was actually the intention of the game designers.
What if they actually said, you know what, we're going to set out to create a moment of joy in people who look like this,
people who feel represented by this.
And that I think would be amazing, and it's totally possible for us,
because these are things that we can actually create as designers and as writers and as creators.
And not only are they new, but they're very, very narratively compelling, and I think that's
ultimately what we should strive for. Because the newness of it works not only for those who are,
you know, being immediately targeted, but it works for everyone in that group, everyone who kind of
receives it and has never seen this before. Because keep in mind that when it's new for you,
odds are they've never seen it either. So you're not actually catering to one tiny group,
you're catering to everyone who's going to be playing it. It's across the board.
That's a lesson I think that we keep failing to teach.
Because we keep saying, okay, this one's for you guys,
this one's for you guys, and this one over here,
you can have it.
But we can't keep looking at representation
as we're catering to a tiny little corner
or a direct marketing effort.
It's what everyone, I think, or hope, wants as an audience.
And stepping back, it's not just,
I don't just hope, actually.
I actually think, okay, we all do want this.
And I think, you know, especially the people in this room,
can actively say, yeah, that's what we want to achieve.
But then the question is, beg, why aren't we doing this?
Like, why, when we're talking about it,
when we're so enthusiastic about it, what's stopping us?
Like, why are we still being told,
oh no, that's not what players want?
Why do I keep hearing that it's like an uphill battle
for people to bring representation
to what should be a very inclusive environment of creativity?
And I think there are a lot of answers.
There's the fact that the industry's stuck in its ways.
The industry isn't as diverse as it should be or could be.
We're all socialized in this society
to kind of act against it and to fall into what is normal.
And there's like a dozen other answers
that are all like variations on those themes.
But kind of like a pseudo fun fact about me,
that's slightly fun,
is that I actually have a marketing degree.
And so I wanna put on that like,
very mercenary hat for a second and talk about the way that we decide how we're going to sell the art that we make and
how we're going to approach the audiences that we make it for.
Because I think so often when people like us get told,
you know, from higher ups or from society at large,
this isn't what players want,
it's not a conversation about demographic,
sorry, content, it's a conversation about demographics.
And I think that in our industry
and in so many creative industries,
if you want to look at film and television
and any art form, we start treating our core demographics
as a fixed and static value,
something that does not want to change
and something that is locked in place.
So despite like the changing face of audiences,
despite this.
changing face of conferences like this one, we still look at our core
demographics and say okay they're white, cis, hetero males and we cater almost
exclusively to them. And the problem is that we don't just cater to them like
you know here here's something that we think you'll enjoy, we cater them the way
that we cater to like a picky baby.
We feed them the same thing that we know that they love,
and we keep on feeding it, we're like, here you go,
you love it, eat this, eat this, eat this,
so that then when they get anything else,
they react as a picky baby would,
which is to be like, oh no, thank you, I do not want this.
And we've actually done this so long that what we're...
doing is creating an entire nation of picky babies, and they make us scared to deviate
from what we actually want to do. Just in case, these picky babies don't want to play
our games. And we've made a lot of progress, obviously, like I don't say this to completely
go like, just give up, we've screwed it. But I think it's still amazing that I can be seated
in a meeting and told that out of 12 characters, we already have one black one, so there can't
possibly...
be a second. I get that way too much and I once worked on a project where they had
an all-white cast and they expressed the desire like okay we need to mix it up a
bit how about this character is kind of like stereotypically French so they have
a beret and they have like a striped shirt and I was like okay if you need to
do that can we at least make them a person of color and they said oh no
that would be weird they're already French
So I want to do better than this because I don't say that to be like,
oh, you know what, I'm going to dismiss all the hate and the abuse in our communities.
But I do like to imagine that when we look at white guys,
and there's several of you here,
I think that when we look at you, we say, okay, you can't possibly enjoy this.
But I think they want also, and maybe you want also, to experience new and different
stories.
I think we need to step out of this rule that white men can enjoy fantasy worlds, aliens,
sci-fi, monsters, anything, so long as it's through a lens that looks exactly like them.
Because if that's the kind of person that we're always going to cater to, you're never
going to innovate.
You're never going to change things.
You're just going to keep feeding the picky baby.
And we cannot continue to try to create art under a system that is going to bar innovation
for fear of a picky baby throwing a tantrum.
And I really don't think that it's impossible to change this because as like a woman of color,
I have played with and like empathized with a lot of white men. I have played as Kratos,
who's like literally white. I've played as Nathan Drake. I've played as Arthur Morgan,
and I've loved it. And I don't think it's like pie in the sky thinking to go like...
hey, maybe we can invite white dudes to play as other people and
experience different things through someone else's eyes.
And if they don't like it, we have to start thinking we're not losing,
they're losing, and we're losing because we're gonna let them
stand in the way of our progress and our innovation.
And I think that we need to stop thinking that our core marketing
demographics have to define the exact demographics of our playable characters
and of our cast.
And instead we start to have to assume that players do want new stories.
And that if we bring joy to our broad audience,
it's going to encompass our core audience as well.
And similarly, I think we need to get out of, I'm glad you're here, but
I think that we need to start getting out of just advocacy tracking these discussions.
Because ultimately, we're seeing representation as this abstract idea.
We're seeing it as
this weird kind of thing that we can paint over what we're currently doing, but if we
start having these conversations as facets of narrative, as facets of marketing, as gameplay,
as art, I think that we're actually going to be able to move beyond it because when
we sequester advocacy into this one series, what we risk is like preaching to the choir
and while you guys already know this because you're here.
What's old to us can be innovative to somebody else.
And that's still incredibly important.
Like all of these things I'm saying today, I'm sure you understand, but
you can go out into the world now and other people will hear it from you.
Because ultimately I think that is what we need to figure out.
It's how to bring these discussions out and make innovations and content like...
the way we make them everywhere else in our industry.
But how do we do that?
I think it's one thing in narrative,
because honestly in narrative it's a little bit easier to implement,
because we have the power to go like,
oh, we can build choices that consider, you know,
marginalized identities and just write them into our work.
We can decide to tell stories that present like, you know,
very rare narratives and representative experiences.
And we can kind of work on de-tokenizing our minority characters.
And so in that way, we do have a lot of power to actually affect the change that we want to see
and to work all of these concepts in our material as narrative developers.
But we still work for people, and it's another kettle of fish, I think,
when it comes to the structures that approve these choices.
And we have to look at them a little more institutionally,
because we can write all the stories that we want,
but that doesn't mean that anyone's going to buy them,
anyone's going to market them, anyone's going to let us do it.
So I think I want to use my last section here to kind of outline the tools and
the techniques that I use and that my company has used to make representation
very much a staple of our offering outside of just the work that we do
internally. So first and foremost if you're in creative development
If you're building a world and a story
and you're including characters and concepts
that are borrowed or inspired by or based on the lives
and the lived experiences of marginalized people,
firstly, I would say do not be afraid to create moments
that are intentionally targeted
and designed to create joy in the marginalized.
They are going to appreciate this on a level
that your core audience won't,
but it doesn't mean that you're going to exclude
your core audience in doing that.
Do not make it so that marginalized people
when they're playing your game have to do all the work to create representation
themselves by creating that custom character.
Also, don't fall into this trap that I think a lot of people fall into, which is they think,
okay, don't worry. We can include everyone by making this single default universal experience
that is universally representative. Because usually all that means, as it did in the dating example,
is that you're aiming at your core demographic and you're probably invisibly leaning towards
the dominant societal voice, even if you don't realize it.
And if you're in development and you are part of like that dominant voice,
you're like a cis, hetero, white dude or just adjacent to that,
do not wait until the end to call your consultants.
Bring them in at the beginning and instead of asking them, hey,
is this very racist thing we did very racist?
Or is this deeply offensive thing we did deeply offensive?
Are you hurt by it?
Ask them what they want to see, like ask them what would thrill them, what would bring them joy,
and if you have a team lead, put that request to them very, very early.
If you're a creative working in AAA, which I did for many, many years...
put this stuff up to your higher ups.
And if they don't see the value in what you're asking for
when you ask for consultants, when you ask for research,
go have a coffee with your marketing team
and just terrify them with the possibility
of what's gonna happen if they don't give you what you want.
Because they have to consider,
like I say that all out as a joke,
but it's actually very, very true
because if you start to consider the people
who are player and audience facing
and who have to deal with.
mitigating harm and with keeping the sentiment around their game and their
project positive,
there's like a genuine value that you can impress upon them with
both ethically and financially. You can say this is important
and it's also a valid discussion to have because if you're working with a very thin
narrative budget
and you work in AAA, I think you'll be pleasantly surprised
or dismayed by the amount of money that marketing can give you.
If you're not in AAA, and if you're indie or if you're freelance and you're building a budget because you still have to and you're writing up a pitch,
I would say that you should consider adding the necessary funds for representation into your scope as you would any other item.
When we budget as Sweet Baby Inc., we actually add about 10% of our entire narrative development budget
to hire storytellers and collaborators who can kind of help us
see where our blind spots are,
and if they aren't in this industry,
because a lot of the time people are like,
uh-oh, they're not in this industry,
we can actually bring them in to help us consultants
for areas where like, you know,
they can start learning, we can help them learn,
they can help us learn.
So even if it's just a small part of a project,
all parties are gonna gain something
and you're gonna get a perspective you really need.
Next, if you're in communications or you're part of that scared marketing group,
assume your players want new stories and treat representation as a facet of innovation,
as a selling point.
Leverage your game's ability to explore new perspectives.
And there's always going to be a positive impact in assuming this.
Finally, if you're a studio building a team,
hire diverse creators and pay them.
Please pay them.
And don't stop there either.
Don't just go into creatives with narrative and stuff.
Make it across your team because there are a lot
of unconscious biases in other areas.
But always consider the ways that you can support
all of your people.
So don't just put, we need diverse input.
Explain how you're gonna support them once they're there.
Because none of what we're doing is about ticking boxes
or about a veneer of wokeness.
We actually have to care about making this stuff.
So, to close, for those of you who are marginalized,
whatever space you occupy in this industry,
and I want you to know that I see you and I recognize you
and I'm doing the work along with you,
and if I can suggest to you one thing,
is that you take kind of a moment to think about times
when you have felt seen and representative
and share them as loudly as you possibly can.
Be loud about it, don't be afraid to ask for more of this
than what you've felt and seen already.
Because we have to make sure that our tech and our mechanics
and our teams are heard.
And representation are equal parts of our entire project.
Inclusion and representation are tools for creation
and will shape the final product.
And for those of you who kind of represent
that dominant voice, I want to invite you to be brave
and to be empathetic and to open yourselves
and your teams to the voices that you haven't heard enough.
Because if you do, I think you'll be genuinely amazed by the stories and the new directions
that you'll be able to explore together, and you're going to be inviting people into this
feeling of representation and empowerment that you have been very lucky to enjoy your
whole life.
Because I think at the end of the day, what we have to say is that video games are fun,
and if we work hard enough, we can actually make them fun for everyone.
Thank you.