I have GDC voice, so forgive that.
Welcome, cell phones, evaluations, blah, blah, blah.
Okay, moving on.
We're here for the composer confessions.
We clearly pre-planned the width of the table
relative to the number of people for this panel.
So, just gonna dive right in.
The idea with this,
is to explore some lessons learned in the field,
you know, on the job.
Things that aren't traditionally covered
at things like GDC or in school programs
or master classes or that kind of thing.
Because they tend to be the thing
that you would never think of until it just happens
and you encounter it and then you just have to
think on your feet.
Unexpected sort of lessons, some of which are
kind of interesting and novel and some of which are horrible and painful.
So everyone here is speaking for themselves.
I just reached out to these phenomenal people and said,
hey, if we did this thing, what would you say?
And all of them came back with really different topics that basically said,
okay, cool, just I'm counting on you to show up and know what you're doing.
And so if this is terrible starting five minutes from now,
then you have only yourselves to blame.
So, I'm gonna go first.
I'm Austin, I worked on some of these things,
and my confession, of sorts,
is that it turns out we have absolutely no control
over our listeners slash audience slash players
and what they are going to take away from our music.
And so a shorter way of saying that
is that we don't have the power of suggestion
that we think we do as composers.
So, when we're getting started in our careers and student work and that sort of thing, I
think we spend a lot of time trying to really hone our craft with the goal of creating very
specific emotional and visual responses.
So in other words, we aspire to a very vivid and exact.
images, feelings, etc. in the minds of our listeners.
And I've been guilty of this, where I'll think to myself,
because this music was written to evoke X,
it therefore will forever universally evoke X.
T-Rex versus the Hulk, in the most universal of musical images.
But really, anything in front of you, it's like this water bottle.
I was inspired by this water bottle.
So theoretically, anybody listening for the future
will just form water bottles in their head.
Turns out, that's totally bullshit.
should be obvious, this is why it's a confession.
So, as an example, on Journey, I was aspiring to,
by the time you reach the end of the game,
something that I would call sweeping or soaring,
or if I'm feeling daring, I would want it to feel
exhilarating or even spiritual,
and so this particular excerpt.
Baba, okay. So, actual response.
Stunning music. It really reminds me of Metal Gear Solid's soundtrack,
Here's to You. You should check it out.
So, I did check it out.
This is a real comment.
So, you know...
I think we all have experienced unexpected comparisons,
like, you know, maybe like this or something else.
But people will liken things that they hear to other things
and that is often bewildering.
And in this case, you know, genuinely,
I have no idea what the hell is going on there.
Maybe, again, the goal was, you know,
sweeping and spiritual, and maybe to Nadine.
Here's to you is sweeping and spiritual.
And so in that sense, maybe I succeeded.
I have my doubts, but...
So this was a recurring theme at some point.
So relaxing.
Austin Winery, the Brian Eno of soundtracks.
I've got that too.
It's weird.
Again, I think we're hearing things differently.
I really thought my goal explicitly was to be melodic, soaring, I'll say again.
It turns out I'm actually being super meditative and tranquil.
I have heard the word relaxing about my music so many times, and I don't think I've ever
once tried to write something that was relaxing, except maybe Flo.
Here's another one.
Love me Jenny. Thank God I spotted one like that much later down the road
because I think that's actually a compliment. I think they're actually
trying to be nice and I'm hope that just as a defense mechanism I'm saying
they're not sort of bored out of their mind but I don't know they fell asleep
before they could type a question mark so it's hard to know for sure what we're
even saying.
Point is, Journey was repeatedly called out as relaxing, meditative, textural, things
that I really didn't think was the goal.
And the strange thing is, it wasn't people criticizing it.
They were saying, this is what I like about it and identifying things that it explicitly
was not trying to be.
It gets weirder.
I played this game after I got my wisdom teeth out.
It relaxed me and took my mind away from the pain because I couldn't swallow the ibuprofen
pills.
So I'm like...
I think the culmination was when IGN rated it the number one soundtrack for studying.
Again, this is not something I can have any explanation.
I would not have thought sweeping and soaring is compatible with studying, but this is where
I was constantly learning this lesson over and over.
So it might be something more like this.
I realize I can't predict what people are going to say or what their takeaway is going
to be.
And the bottom line is that's okay.
It better be okay.
We can't control it as much as we think we can or as much as we are specifically trying
to evoke very precise images and feelings and things like that.
We just can't.
One more highlight.
This is from a Journey YouTube upload.
When I'm home, I want to do cooking, work or cooking,
I listen to Bioshock.
Anyone here with me?
I love just showing up.
Truth is, I probably would.
Big fan of Bioshock.
So flash forward.
I thought I'd learned this lesson.
After many years of the sort of incorrect compliments,
I think I probably internalized that a little too much.
So when it came time to do Abzu,
both probably because I probably internalized
some of that Journey feedback too much,
but also because, earnestly, the game had a very,
very different sort of energy to it,
very kinetic, very full of life.
So I said, okay, I want to be very emotionally,
I accepted, apparently, Journey is tranquil and meditative,
and now I don't want to do that.
Now I want to be very melodic.
not meditative at all, really match the kinetic energy of the game.
And I want to pretend that's not because of this feedback from Journey,
but it probably made its way in there a bit.
So here's an example of me not being meditative
and trying to be more overtly melodic.
Okay, blah blah blah.
So after getting about 50 of these, apparently it sounds exactly like Tomb Raider or Tom
Raider.
That's Tom Salta's pet project, I guess.
Should have seen some of that coming, although I honestly had not played Tomb Raider since
it came out 20 years ago, and I went back and was one of those like, motherfucker, I
can actually hear why people are saying that.
So after wading through all of those, here's a review I found on Amazon, and if you look
at the bottom.
They say, this score seems overly intellectual instead of from the heart.
I find the music lines lose me as a listener in the same way.
What I'm trying to say is, I feel lost.
I feel I get lost listening to his newer scores without being able to remember the melodies.
Go back and listen to Flow or Journey and you cannot forget the tunes.
So somehow the less melodic, more meditative score is more melodic than the explicitly
trying to be melodic score.
At least Flo is on the list, which is especially bizarre and helps me try to let it go, because
Flo is just overtly not melodic.
Anyone who says so, I just don't even know where they're coming from.
And this was probably the true culmination, is literal side-by-side comments.
Very disappointing.
It's lacking strong musical ideas.
It sounds intellectual and not from the heart.
I think that might be the same person.
And then immediately below it, I'm crying piles of tears and all this sort of...
So I'm sitting here looking at this, and it dawns on me that it's possible to simultaneously
fail and succeed.
And that was something I had never thought about before, considered possible.
So the bottom line is, when getting into the creative zone and the process, the big confession
was that I...
try to let go of the whole outside world while writing.
But then as soon as the writing is done,
I turn into this monster that's scouring the world
to see if I succeeded in my goal.
Did I actually create?
what I thought I created based on what people are saying about it.
And the confession really is that no good comes of this.
This is not a healthy practice.
We can't control what people are going to think.
We can't control what their takeaway would be.
As my father used to say, you would worry a lot less what other people think if you
realized how infrequently they do.
Actually, I said that wrong and made it sound extremely asshole-ish.
You would worry a lot less what people think of you if you realized how infrequently they
do.
So basically, the bottom line is we should be grateful that anyone is listening at all
and extremely grateful if they like it and then just accept everything else.
I'm going to turn it over now.
To a legend of gay music, as noted.
Composer of classics, Goldeneye 64, Banjo Kazooie, Viva Pinata, about 40 million others, Grant Kirkcope.
Hello.
Woo!
Is it dead? I don't believe it.
Yeah, or the space bar.
Yeah, so thanks for that picture, Austin.
You're welcome.
Yes, there'll be a...
Thank you.
There'll certainly be a chance for that, you know, getting you back a later date, I'm sure.
Yes, yes.
So I guess mine is going to be the slightly cynical version of this talk.
Austin, he said I was a cynical guy, so I'm a cynical guy.
Depressed most of the time.
So my talk is like learning to let go, right?
So I think that, as composers, right, we think that we know the best always,
and who we're working for has not got a clue,
and they're just completely clueless and they don't know about music and all that.
We know best and they're wrong.
But I think that, like I've slowly realized over the years,
that you can't think like that.
Like, the minute you hire yourself out to somebody else,
they're probably going to tell you what to do, and you probably better do it.
Or you're probably going to get fired, and they're going to get Austin to do it instead.
You know, so...
So that's my thing about learning to let go of that ownership,
that I think that you just have to be prepared
to be told that it's not what they want
and you really should try to do it again.
And no amount of arguing with them
is going to make any difference.
It's just going to go, I don't like it and that's it.
Composers by composers, I was best of my composers t-shirt.
So, you know, it's like trying to convince like an Ariana Grande fan to, you know, to like Pantera.
It's just probably not going to happen.
So it's, it's, I guess I learned that, well, I guess, I guess a long time ago,
but it still irks me to this day that I...
people say, Grant, I think it's shit, just do it again.
And like, I really want to say,
who the fuck do you think you are?
I know way better than you,
but you kind of go, of course I'll do it again.
Yes, I'd love to do it again like that, you know.
So I use the analogy of like, you go to a restaurant
and you've been saving up for ages
for this great steak that you've heard about
that you really want to have.
And like, you go to the restaurant,
you sit down, the waiter comes across
and like, he says to you, what are you going to have, sir?
I'm going to have this fantastic steak.
Can't wait for it, I've waited such a long time.
And he goes away to the kitchen
and he comes back a bit later.
Me and the lads in the kitchen have had a bit of a chat,
and we decided that we think you're going to like the chicken better,
it's way better.
And you're like, just a minute, I ordered the steak, I want the steak,
I paid for the steak, and if you don't give me it,
I'm going to go somewhere else that someone will give me the steak.
So I think that's in a nutshell what I think about that whole
kind of composer's no best thing.
Because we probably do, but you know,
you're never going to get that past lots and lots of people.
Is that my bit there?
Yes, right, okay.
get used to smiling.
So I, you know, when they do say it's not great
and you just, you don't want to say,
you want to curse a lot.
you just kind of smile and say,
yes, I'll quite happily do it again.
It's no problem at all.
I do think that it's a really valuable skill to learn.
Like I was working for, I did a movie last year,
and I thought I'd gotten great with the director.
It's all going really fantastically well.
I know all the little demos that I did on the scenes,
he loved and loved and loved and sent me emails.
You nailed it, awesome, awesome, awesome.
I was thinking, oh yeah, I've done great here.
It's just fantastic.
So we got invited to the mix.
thing, the big fight scene, mixed stage, atmos, nonsense, all that stuff, you know.
And it started, it started to go, oh it's too dark, oh it's dark, it's gone so dark,
everything's dark, the music's dark, the movie's dark, we've got to change it, you know, we've
got to change all of it. And I was thinking, we just spent money recording the orchestra,
it was all live orchestra, yeah, you've got to change, oh what's a fiddle?
I need some fiddle in it. Jolly fiddle. Like, you know, really Celtic.
I was thinking, what the shit? You know, there's nothing...
You didn't say anything about the fucking fiddle, you know,
when we were writing it in the first place.
Why do you want a bloody fiddle in it now?
Where am I going to get that from?
I've got a mixed medium with the orchestra.
How am I going to do that like it was irrelevant?
I couldn't say any of that. I just said...
God, I love that fiddle. I'm gonna go and get one right now.
I'm gonna slot it in there.
You're not even gonna notice it's different to the midi, the orchestra.
It's gonna be perfect. I'm doing it.
Like, you know, even though you want to go,
Jesus Christ, man, couldn't you have thought of that
last year when we were bloody well doing it?
You know, like, why did you have to say it right now in the mixtape
when everyone sat there going, oh, God, this is not a fiddle.
Where's this fiddle? You know, it's like that, right?
So I think that you have to get used to just letting go.
And instead of going, what the bugger are you talking about?
I'd love to do that fiddle thing, I can't wait.
Right.
Yeah, oh yeah, here's another great one.
Marketing always knows best.
So, like in dev things, right,
the dev team usually pretty separate to the marketing,
like completely separate.
So, you know, get used to the fact
that you're probably not gonna get to write the trailer.
Right.
I've had this argument a few times.
I always lose.
I've had maybe one once, where, you know,
you're gonna say, wouldn't it be nice
to have some of the themes from the game in the trailer,
and the kind of marketing guy kind of goes,
And why's that?
Well, because, you know,
you've got themes from the game in the trailer,
but it's not an IP, no one knows the themes, right?
So what's the point of that?
So you kind of, you lose the argument by going,
if it's Star Wars, you're probably gonna wanna hear
the themes from Star Wars in the trailer,
but when it's X game that no one's heard of before,
it gives a shit, right?
Like, we don't wanna hear those themes
because I've got this trailer piece
that I've used 55 billion times before
that I can give to my video editors right now.
They can cut to the exact, this generic,
digga digga digga digga digga digga digga digga
digga digga digga digga digga digga digga.
hate, you know, that shit, right?
So like, we've all heard a million times, right?
So, but yeah, the marketing guy knows the piece,
he's used it a bazillion times, give it to the editors,
the good is gonna get on with it, right?
And like, no amount of you saying,
but wouldn't it be great with,
because it's easy for him, right?
He doesn't have to wait for you to write the piece
for the guys to cut the video to the piece you've written,
and maybe get it recorded by somebody,
you can just give him this generic thing.
that he's used a billion times.
I was like, I was actually on a project where
the final trailer for the release of the game
was this piece of music that he used lots of times
after arguing lots of times and losing.
And then he just, literally a month later,
there was a trailer for the next game that we're doing,
and it was the exact same trailer piece
that was on the one that we did.
Like, and I was just like, shit, you know.
Why would you do that?
But no one gives a shit.
No one really cares, right?
It's not like, no one's gonna go,
oh, that trailer piece was great
and that trailer piece is bad.
It's just a trailer, right?
And you know, people spend lots and lots of money
writing these gigantic pieces
for like a 50 billion piece orchestra and a massive choir.
You're never gonna beat win that battle.
So you just have to go, Mr. Marketing,
of course, whatever you like to do,
let's just do that thing.
So it's just getting used to that.
letting go of the ownership.
Because you are a hired contracting person,
just like hiring a pool guy or a gardener
or a mechanic to do that job for you.
That's what they're doing, right?
They're hiring you to do that job,
and you may not get a looking on any of that stuff, right?
It just could be taken away from you.
And it'll save yourself a lot of heartache
if you get used to kind of going,
all right, fair enough.
Because I got really stressed about it a lot of times
and fought over it and lost every bloody time.
So, that's Mr. Marketing Guy.
But that's not the way I wrote it.
So another example, the movie I did last time,
like wrote the music, did the demo,
you loved it, thought it was great.
And then you go away and like a lot of times,
composers don't even get invited to the mix part, right?
It could just be that you've done your job,
you've been paid, goodbye,
and you'll see it when it comes out in the theater, right?
But I did turn up to, I did get invited to the mix thing.
So you find that the producer guy decided
that he thought this piece would go better there,
and he cut the end and put it at the start,
and then took a bit from the end
and put it in the middle to link it together.
And you're like.
But that's not the way I wrote it, right?
I did that piece to hit the beats here,
hit that slap in the face, hit that gunshot,
and it's all just gone to shit because it's not there anymore.
But nobody will love it.
There's no fight against that.
You're wasting your time going,
but I wrote the piece like that, so what?
We like it like this. That's it, right?
You're done. There's no way you're going to win that war.
So it's just getting used to letting go of all that.
And it is hard, right? It is really hard.
And I'm particularly bad at letting go of it,
so I'm kind of telling myself as I'm telling you guys too.
But I just think that...
It's just because you're a contract guy, right?
You are, you've been hired out, and that's it.
You just got to take it.
You might not even get a look in on this stuff.
So that's my thing about that.
Yes, the boss is always right.
So like, you know, yeah, again, this movie did last year.
And it's not a bad experience, right?
I did have a good experience, generally speaking.
But I was in, we're in the screening,
and Mr. Head Dude, who's, you know,
financing, like Chinese guy, financing the entire thing,
Mr. Billionaire, whatever he is.
He spent most of the time arguing about why his name came in the credits,
rather than anything about the movie.
He wanted to make sure that, yes, I know that the credits,
the guy who comes last is the most important man,
so I must be... That big discussion went on.
And he made some passing comment about some music somewhere
that was... I can't remember the comment.
It was so flippant.
But the entire entourage around him shat themselves instantly.
Oh, my God, rip it out! He doesn't like it! Mr. Doodarats!
So the whole thing gets ripped out right in front of you.
Yeah, so he needs to sit there, he's probably forgotten already what he's talked about,
but he only needs to have just been chucked into the bin, like that's just gone right,
because he made some kind of passing bizarre comment that...
No one understood, but felt like,
just take it out right now, it's awful.
And it was like that.
And yet again, you've just got no say over it.
You soon realize that in the pecking order,
composers don't come very high.
Like there's a whole mountain of people
sat above you, producers, and all that nonsense above you
who have got way more say than you have.
And they all shit themselves when the Ked guy blinks.
Right?
So there's all that kind of, you know.
Sitting in your little cave, writing your music, it's all nice and introverted.
You're all sort of there. It's all great.
You may need to take one step out of there.
You're in that land of real world where everyone's got an opinion
and your opinion matters for nothing, right? A lot of the time.
So.
That's another lesson that I learned very recently,
that you just have to let go of it.
There's no point crying about it
or punching the director on the way out,
like I was inclined to do.
So it's a thing that I think you just have to get used to.
The further you go down the path
of becoming a more established, contracting composer,
it's no different than anything else, right?
And of course, you're happy about it, right?
So the gist of my segment here, I guess, is like,
let go of everything, you've written your music,
and sometimes you might get a say in the end of it,
but a lot of the time you might just pass it off,
never see it again until you see it in the finished product,
and it might not be how you intended it to be.
I have to say that my experience of writing music
for 21 years has been pretty good,
I've got most of my way most of the time,
but there are gonna be events
where you're just not gonna win that battle,
and it's like you have to be prepared to say,
not get upset about it.
And I have got upset tons of times, but...
I don't know, I just think you have to,
it could be the best lesson learned, I think,
is to be able to say, all right, I wrote it,
you sort of liked it, it's in more or less
how I wanted it to be, and that thing you wrote
that fits perfectly, when the person sees it,
maybe in the movie theater or the game,
they don't know what you wrote in the first place,
so what they see is what ended up being there,
and they don't know if what you wrote was better or not,
so you just have to kind of accept the fact that that's it,
and you've lost that battle,
and get on with the next thing, and just, you know.
So that's it, my little bit.
Yes, all right.
That was uplifting.
We'll do closed captions for translating all of that as well.
Next, major badass, multi-instrumentalist, composer,
Will Roger II, Esquire of Deaconship, Bournemouth, Shire.
known from work at LucasArts and the Old Republic
to Tomb Raider and Temple of Osiris,
and recently, a new The Distant Light.
Woo!
Thank you.
This space bar'll do it.
Cool, so Star Wars The Old Republic was my first AAA score
and a big turning point in how I write for the orchestra.
In this talk, I'll cover some of the fundamental mistakes
I made in my early approach to orchestration,
how I learned from them, and how I've applied this knowledge
to all my writing since then.
I'd written several indie game scores before working at Lucas, but The Old Republic was
the first time I had a AAA score and my first time writing for live orchestra.
We had a very tight deadline, and so it was also my first time writing extensively for
Star Wars, so there was a lot of pressure to get the John Williams sound right.
I used high quality samples for the mockups and my cues were approved, so conceptually
the music worked well.
But I never had the experience of going from mockup to live orchestra, and I had no idea
of the headaches that these cues would cause.
I wrote for the sound, not for the players, and so I was in for a rude awakening.
We had four other composers and a ton of music to get through in a short time.
Some of my cues were played effortlessly,
with musicians reading beautifully on their first try.
But others, easy pieces left them confused and grumpy and dissatisfied.
So here's a few reasons why.
My first problem was writing parts with awkward entrances
and needlessly unnatural rhythms.
players would have to count several measures of rest
before oddly timed entrances with no obvious backing.
And this led to very unconfident performances
and unnecessary retakes.
I had some cues, like you see here.
This is real, by the way.
This is not made up.
Some cues for instruments just had very inconsequential parts,
writing half the piece just to play only a short passage.
Again, this was because I focused only on the sound
and not on the performance or the players.
And I had some generally dissatisfying parts as well, which.
Yeah, which sounded great in samples, but didn't work when played live.
In this instance, as you see, the harp just plays a single tremolo throughout the whole
cue.
And it was a great texture for the ice planet Hoth, but in practice it was very boring and
very static, and honestly just unacceptable to give to a professional player who'd studied
their whole life.
Speaking of harp...
So harpists play accidentals via pedals that transpose all notes of a kind.
Here I tried a harmonic shift between two hexatonic modes,
which is a very Star Wars-y technique.
But unfortunately, this required six pedal changes at once.
And most harpists only have two feet, so it was actually impossible to play.
And lastly, I had some cues that I just simply didn't proofread closely enough
when I got them back from our orchestration team.
One piece had incorrect dynamics at the end,
turning an ambient piece unexpectedly violent.
And another just had very glitched rhythms
where we had to fix it at the podium, which is a huge time waste.
I learned from these mistakes and studied other scores with a focus on performance.
Before my next score for Star Wars First Assault, I developed strategies to make sure that the
parts were playable, sight-readable, and enjoyable.
Here's some of those techniques.
The first principle I followed was to just make sure everyone has at least something
interesting to do in each cue.
Previously, I might have allowed a harp part to be nothing but glisses for an entire cue,
but in this example, I made sure that they had some melodic doubling to keep things interesting.
Avoid writing awkward entrances at all costs.
These again can lead to unconfident performances.
If you need arrhythmic elements,
a neat trick to try is write it in 4-4,
but use tuplets or syncopation.
Here the strings have scattered entrances,
but it's easy to count in 4-4,
especially with the harp doubling.
Make sure brass isn't being abused with constant fortissimo.
Horns especially need time to rest,
particularly if you need them to make a big entrance later on.
So in this example, from Laura Croft actually,
I remove them from the text here at measure eight
using a trombone to support the trumpet
so that the horns can come in full force later on.
Try writing in fun challenges that sound more difficult than they actually are, showcasing
the player's versatility.
A good habit is to study instrumental etudes to get to know what's guaranteed to be mastered
by a professional.
For example, these wind runs and arpeggio... arpeggiando violas.
Try using cues to provide alternate textural options.
When recording, you can easily adjust dynamics or tacit instruments,
but you can't really add new parts.
Using cues allows you to thicken the textures if necessary.
For example, expanding a solo to a full section.
We should take into account not just the performance,
but also the venue.
For Star Wars First Assault, we were at Abbey Road,
which is big enough to seat an entire orchestra
in two different configurations.
We had two factions in the game,
so we recorded Imperial music in portrait
and Rebel music in landscape.
So to wrap things up, the most important thing is to talk to musicians about any questionable
parts.
Ideally, befriend someone from every section and get their feedback for whatever you're
not comfortable with before it hits the copyist.
Their input isn't valuable.
And as a final note, I also found that keeping reality
and player psychology in mind
helps with sampled orchestral cues too.
Write interesting parts for both foreground and background,
keeping in mind live player limitations,
and a sampled cue will always sound more realistic.
Thanks.
So probably all of us saw Mick win GDC yesterday.
So I don't really need to say anything.
So Mick Gordon.
Yeah.
The first developer came to me and said,
we want some music, you see.
It needs to be modern, catchy, groovy, and cool.
No problem, I said.
I knew exactly what to do.
So I went to my studio and I worked all night
on a dubstep song, Wubz, from left to right.
I emailed them back with a finished track.
I made a dubstep track for you.
I look forward to your feedback.
No, no, no, they said, this is not the music we wanted, you misread.
It was chiptune music we wanted, modern, catchy, groovy, and cool.
That was what we wanted from you.
The second developer came to me and said, we want some music, you see.
It needs to have square waves, have noise, and be retro, too.
No problem, I said.
I know exactly what to do.
So I went to my studio and I worked all night on chiptune music, bit crushing from left to right.
I emailed them back with the finished track.
I made chiptunes for you. I look forward to your feedback.
No, no, no, they said, this is not the music we wanted you egghead.
Sine waves, noise and retro too.
It was heavy metal we wanted from you.
The third developer came to me and said, we want some music you see.
It needs to be aggressive, fast, and hair-raising too.
No problem, I said.
I know exactly what to do.
So I went to my studio and I shredded all night.
Nine string guitars panned left and right.
I finished the track and emailed them back.
I made some metal for you.
I look forward to your feedback.
No, no, no, they said. This is not the music we wanted, you knucklehead.
Aggressive, fast, and hair-raising, too.
Something like Bach is what we wanted from you.
The fourth developer came to me and said,
We want some music, you see.
It needs to be bespoke, baroque, and counterpoint too.
No problem, I said.
I know exactly what to do.
So I went to the organ and I played all night,
doing my best Bach impression, semiquavers left to right.
I emailed them back with the finished track.
I made some organ music for you.
I look forward to your feedback.
No, no, no, they said.
This is not the music we wanted.
You're dead.
I didn't really say that, it's just the best picture I could find.
Bespoke, baroque, and have counterpoint too.
We wanted a full orchestra from you, not just an organ, you fool.
The fifth developer came to me and said,
We want some music, you see.
It needs to be epic, massive, and guttural too.
No problem, I said. I know exactly what to do.
So I looked at my budget and my budget was tight.
But I recorded the orchestra anyway,
a hundred piece from left to right.
I emailed them back with the finished track.
Here is the orchestra.
I look forward to your feedback.
No, no, no, they said.
This is not the music we wanted, dickhead.
Epic, massive, and guttural too.
It is dubstep we wanted from you.
Despair set in, rejection after rejection.
I was failing in my ability to interpret direction.
Developers were giving me the best direction that they could, and I was frustrating them
because I completely misunderstood.
You see, a composer-client relationship is a relationship, alright?
Without proper communication, it ends up in a fight.
Without a shared common creative language,
you're completely alien to each other.
You're not able to tell when you're wrong
or when you're right.
But if you get to know each other,
you'll understand each other,
and you'll be able to combine your might.
When they say jump, you'll already know how high.
The two of you will become partners in crime.
So get to know each other really well, become a great team.
And when it comes to music time, you're going to succeed.
So get to know your clients, be friends, and share a joke.
That is the key to success, my friends.
That's all, folks.
Thank you.
I had no idea that was going to happen.
That was awesome.
the king of indies, Hyperlight Drifter, Fez,
and 40,000 others, Rich Vreeland, aka Disasterpeace.
Hey guys.
So my talk is called Curveballs.
I often find the beginning of a project
to be the most exciting period.
There's a sense that anything is possible.
which has often propelled me down many avenues in search of the thing.
Along the way, Murphy's Law, that anything that can go wrong
will go wrong, kicks in, and I rarely end up where I intended.
Sometimes projects turn out worse, but often in my experience
they turn out different, or better.
During the course of my work on a thing,
there tends to be a psychological transition
from an exciting beginning of boundless possibility
to a starker, more responsible reality.
You bring an idea out of the ether and give it life.
It gradually frames itself and the edges come into view.
And increasingly, the thing,
as I've so lovingly called it, solidifies.
This process is a necessary part of the work,
and it's a part of life too, right?
We have little choice but to persist
through the unending number of curveballs thrown our way,
starting with being born.
And so we do our best to adapt.
The curveballs often take us down paths we would never take,
or could have never imagined.
They open doors for us that would otherwise remain closed,
and they lead us to new conclusions.
They change us.
In my opinion, this malleable process
is often necessary to complete a work,
regardless of whether we see or believe in it at the time.
I find that only in the days that follow
can I truly begin to comprehend its meaning.
When starting work on a new project,
I often set off in the first direction
that sparks my curiosity.
I try to keep the utilitarian needs
of a video game in mind,
but if I'm staring down a new idea,
I seize it as an exciting challenge.
This tendency of mine perpetuates a myth
I can't help but tell myself time and time again.
This will work, right?
Before I know it, I might be neck deep in an esoteric cobweb of systems,
or sinking large units of time into something wonderful.
Or wonderfully inappropriate.
I'm guilty of occasionally forgetting that, when working on a project
with real-world restraints, my ideas have to be grounded in that same reality.
So I spent a few years creating music and sound
for a game called Hyper Light Drifter.
During this time, I had a dream that I would write long,
artfully composed pieces of music.
They would move effortlessly from idea to idea,
all while evoking the perfect expression
every step of the way.
I wanted to write these songs at the piano
and notate them completely before even thinking about
the electronic production or how they would
even be implemented in a video game.
Here I had created a set of goals for myself,
which is often something I do during a project.
But this time, they ended up not suiting me
or the project at all.
First off, I hated using software notation,
and I wasted a lot of time
inefficiently grumbling my way through it.
Second, the piano pieces I had written with all their shifts in tempo, energy, and tone
were very hard to translate to an electronic sound.
They were kind of glued to the sound of the piano.
I underestimated the difficulty of recreating the essence of a performance from a completely
different context.
I've transferred pieces to new instruments before, and thinking this was no different
or assuming, I took it for granted.
Lastly, the compositional style was not nearly agile enough
to keep up with contextual changes during gameplay.
For example, the player would move into a new area
and start doing a new thing.
And the music would be off somewhere else,
expressing some other idea.
It was really hard to find that, by the way.
I was surprised.
It seems obvious looking back,
but at the time I thought I could pull it off.
The path I had chosen proved to be a long, brambly one with a big dead end sign.
It was emotionally tough to put so much time and effort into an unsuccessful direction,
and it took a while to pick myself up and set out again.
I only stumbled into the right solution when I was thrown a curveball.
The developer decided to create a demo.
and I suddenly needed to drop what I was doing
and write music for a very large vertical slice
of the game in a very short period of time.
Granted, it was a curveball I was aware of,
but due to poor planning, it crept up on me in a way
that I think still serves the purpose of this talk.
Feeling urgency, I had to forgo my agenda
and just write something.
Anything.
And put it in the game.
This simple process yielded the best results
and changed the trajectory of the project for me.
And so I learned a valuable lesson.
Sometimes I am too precious about my work.
I tend to inflate the importance of ideas I've devised
before they've ever proven themselves to work.
And sometimes it's hard for me
to let go of those expectations and move forward.
Towards the end of Hyper Light Drifter,
as the pressure really started to mount,
and I was struggling creatively,
I picked up a mantra.
Broad strokes.
Painting with broad strokes
has often been counterintuitive for me,
and it still is.
The rabbit hole is my favorite pitfall,
pun intended.
But by prototyping my work in practice,
not in a vacuum,
and saving detail-oriented decisions for later,
I've started to save lots of time.
The curveballs are frequent now,
but they are more useful than ever.
Thank you.
Finally.
A titan of our industry, the order, Tomb Raider, Dead Space, etc, etc, etc.
Jason Graves.
I hope you guys are having as much fun as we are up here, because honestly we didn't
know what anybody was going to be talking about.
So how many composers have we got out there?
Hands up.
All right, how many of you folks are basically terrified of failing all the time?
Yeah.
My name is Jason Graves and I'm addicted to attempting to fail.
This is Composer Confessions and my confession is I really love to push boundaries and I
don't feel like I'm really doing that if I'm not on the precipice of getting fired, you
know?
Like, how far can I go with what they're talking about, with what they want?
Oh my gosh, that's still up there.
All right.
Prepare now there's been some really nice presentations so far, but I I mean Austin save the the best
graphics interface and everything for last
So I'm gonna talk about a couple of different games from a franchise called dead space and a lot of this
It's probably unknown because it was all behind-the-scenes stuff, but
I'm gonna give a couple of examples and then I'm gonna talk about why I love the idea of setting yourself up for possible failure.
I hate that word failure and I know it was in Composer Confessions, but I see it as more like opportunity than anything else.
So Dead Space 3, I believe.
Um, no, uh, we're, we're...
The audio is not there.
No, that's audio, but...
Yeah, I'm fine, I'm fine, I'm fine.
So this is all music that was not used in the game, and it was all recorded live.
And at one point in time there was going to be this giant spaceship, I'm not making this up,
a giant spaceship of redneck, uh, like truckers from space that you were going to be doing things
with. We were going to do country songs, like space cowboy country songs. We were going to
have all kinds of crazy sort of country...
influence kinds of things in the score. And those of you who are not familiar with Dead Space,
it's very organic sounds that are completely messed up in a very natural way.
People just playing their instruments wrong.
So, as a result, I had two weeks of recording in Nashville with electric guitars, accordions.
harmoniums, pedal steel players, vocalists, all kinds of experimental stuff that I just
sort of pulled some things real quick to play. This is more the ambient stuff, but there was
action in there as well, and it's all country music. It's just, you know, the perverted version
of country music. And it was really one of those moments.
I was like, this is the third one, I feel like I want to do something a little bit different,
and they want to do country, so how far can I push it before they just, you know, say you're in,
you're crazy, you don't, you can't do that. And this was the result, and everyone seemed to like
it a lot, but there was a lot of internal shifting, if any of you remember when Dead Space 3 came out,
it was a little confused, it wasn't sure, is it horror, is it action, what's, what's kind of
going on, and the audio director that came in was like, no, we don't want any country stuff,
and just, just cut everything.
And it was a lot of music.
It was a lot of me pouring my heart into it and working with all these players
and learning all these new techniques.
It didn't make it into the game.
And oh gosh, I haven't figured out anything to do with it yet.
But.
It introduced me to Nashville.
And I became friends with Alan there, who's the contractor and also plays violin.
And I've been there five or six times recording orchestral scores and small pickup things.
And that was all through hanging out with him while we were recording this Dead Space 3 stuff.
And it's really one of those whatever doesn't kill you makes you stronger.
And I try to push as hard as I can, no matter how scary it might be or how much I'm convinced
that I don't know how I'm going to make this work.
If I'm not in that position mentally, then...
it's almost like that's when I operate my best.
That's when I'm really feeling charged
and trying to do something really different.
So I'm gonna go backwards to Dead Space 1,
which originally had a much different idea
in terms of the tone of the gameplay.
And I think it's really cool being composers up here.
Our music is so influential in how people feel
when they play the game.
And the original Dead Space wasn't necessarily super scary.
It had more of a...
of feel.
But it never really worked.
We ended up deciding to throw out like 30 minutes of music
and go with the opposite kind of approach,
where there's no rhythm, there's no melody.
There's like, what can you do to terrify the player the most?
I love talking over my own music if you haven't noticed.
So this is what we ended up doing instead.
Awkward pause, awkward pause.
It's coming.
Now the interesting thing about this music, the first track was all done in MIDI with
me in my own studio.
To do this scary stuff, they wanted to have control over the music but they wanted it
to be scary and there were no aleatoric libraries back then.
And the audio director at the time, Don Becker, said, well how can you give us the scariest
music in the world but let us have control over it?
And I was like, oh!
Ha!
You know, if you want to do something like that, you're going to need to go and give
me all the live budget up front.
Let me go record the orchestra playing all these different sounds and things, and then
give me months to cut it all up and put it together into something, and maybe give you
a demo after that.
But we were on like a six-month plan, at the least, thinking of course he would never go
for it.
And he's like, yeah, man, let's do that.
which that was the ultimate setting myself up,
you know, enough rope to hang yourself
and all that kind of stuff.
And I was terrified the entire time I was working on the job.
I was going to GDC talking on a panel
and in between my panel and the next panel
I was gonna attend, I was going back to my hotel room
and working on orchestration
and trying to figure out what to do with the players.
But I learned so much from all of that unknown territory
at first that I was just completely...
terrified of. And of course everyone says, well, that's why the music is so scary.
No, it's scary because I grew
numb to making it. It's not scary enough. I have to make it scarier.
But just having that sort of drive to
do something different and to really get it under my fingers and feel confident
that
about halfway through the project maybe, you know, I think this is gonna work, I think it's gonna work,
and then usually by the time everything's finished, it ends up working,
but it's not something that's been completely intentional.
It's not something I think that any of us are feeling like,
oh man, we've got this, you know, don't sweat.
I mean, maybe we've got the martini glass and we're like,
I know exactly what you want, don't worry about it.
But inside, we're terrified because we're trying something new.
And I've seen people from Jerry Goldsmith to John Williams.
Bernard Herrmann, I mean, any of these amazing media composers talk about how terrified they
are at being creative, trying something new, putting yourself out there, but the more you
do it...
you're still terrified all the time,
but at least you have a little bit of a background,
like, okay, I've done it before,
I know I'm gonna somehow do it again,
and you just keep moving forward,
and you use all that stuff that you learned
from the last time you internally almost were fired,
even though no one thought that,
and it's the next gig, and you're starting over,
and pushing yourself, and learning more.
So I'm gonna end with a little emoji thing,
and when we go to the last slide?
Okay, great.
Austin.
All right, we have 10 minutes for questions.
Thank you all.
Have at it.
Smartin?
Yeah.
Austin, this question's for you.
Oh, God.
Well, based on your well-documented ability
to write really relaxing music, I
was wondering if you have considered maybe switching
to a lucrative career writing for Muzak and spa meditation
CDs.
Well, I just resell the stuff I do write.
Damn it.
I don't have to even switch careers.
Thanks for that, though.
Hey, guys.
That was a great presentation.
This question is for all of you.
When you have multiple projects you're working on,
especially when they involve different styles,
like one game is going to be completely orchestral,
and another project is going to be like death metal
electronica, how do you approach that?
Like, what's your process?
For me, I try to build up a little bit of momentum on the individual projects so that I can
Give myself like a buffer zone to kind of get into that headspace
So, you know
I might I might work on one thing for a week at a time and then switch if
But you kind of have to figure it out based on you know
What the projects are and what the requirements are but that seems to work for me
I could say panic probably.
About all the things you need to do.
It's like a million different styles and like everyone wants it tomorrow.
Everyone wants it like yesterday, you know.
So I think that you do panic a little bit.
But I think panic is probably quite healthy and it gets you going.
But, you know,
nothing you do is ever going to work out like you think it's going to work out.
Everything you're going to do is always going to go wrong somewhere.
It's always going to be like, I'm going to manage it
and then I'm not going to manage it and you're going to
shit yourself and think, I'm never going to get there.
So...
It's never going to be perfectly scheduled out so you're going to get time to work on
everything. You just got to panic and get on with it. That's it. Make a start.
Yeah, time wise is one problem but for me it's sometimes just conceptually getting yourself
back into that sound world. And like being...
That can be very challenging. I can add that I, for what it's worth, I really love when I
have juxtaposed projects that are radically unlike each other because the whiplash of
shifting gears actually helps make...
each direction of travel feel fresher.
Because if I wrote nothing but the big sweeping
orchestral thing, then it would certainly
get stale and flat immediately.
But if in the middle of that, we're
interleaving all these.
forays into other stuff. For me, I'm wired to benefit from that. I like it. So to me,
the problem you're identifying is a good situation. Also, just ask Jason to hug you.
He does that quite a bit.
We're going to share the mic because I've got four mics down there. I've found that
splitting it up just an entire day dedicated to one project, I think is a good idea.
And then I'm finished that day on that project.
And then I start thinking about the other project
for the next morning.
By the time I get up in the morning,
I'm completely dedicated to that second project.
Or even at extreme times, it's been split during the day.
But I say, at 12.30, I'm working on the other one.
And I try to do the best I can to mentally compartmentalize
those.
OK.
I'm just going to stop.
No worries.
Thanks, guys.
Thanks.
Hey guys. So question, this is coming from a non-professional composer. I'm a game dev that doesn't actually do composition.
So back before the technology became what it was today, people tended to have different areas of games that had loops,
and it was like a 30 second loop or a minute loop of music. Thinking back to like the Zelda N64 days.
Still very much how we do things.
So a lot of the melodies that were there are very, you recognize them, you hear it, you're like, oh, that's that area of this game.
With all these ambient layers and stuff going on, how do you try to keep melodies that you can recognize and that people can recognize in new games that require that, to use that new technology?
Well, I apparently don't write melodic scores, so I'm not qualified to answer that.
I actually have an answer that, um...
might be a little upstream, but I think it's actually up to the design of the game.
Because what I always find is important is to just identify moments in the game where
you can bring music to the forefront, rather than trying to have every single piece be
this incredibly melodic.
I don't think that really works with games anymore.
But what you can do, for example, how many people here have played Red Dead Redemption?
And you know exactly where I'm going with this.
As soon as you go to Mexico and it plays that beautiful song,
that's a musical moment that everyone remembers.
And that didn't come about because they said,
oh yeah, let's have this awesome song all the time.
No, they identified a moment in the story
and in the gameplay where this would work.
And they cut out the AI and they made sure
you couldn't get attacked or whatever.
But everyone kind of came together and they planned for it.
So it's actually something that you
as a designer can help as well.
Yeah, if you pick your spots and you underline certain moments, it kind of gives them, you know, it can give those moments more, I guess, gravitas.
And it's a good thing to, can be a good thing to do with melodies so that, you know, you kind of remember those melodies.
Yeah, I think also a simple trick that I use a lot in both Journey and Abzu, but I use it in general, is...
I treat melodies as big as one shots often when entering an area to the point of like
the Red Dead Redemption example, but it can be even within a single cue where
you know, player comes over the hill, we announce a big melody, but when it loops, the melody
doesn't loop with it, and the sort of support, accompaniment, backing track, whatever, does
loop, which is by design more sort of simple or ambient or whatever the case, so that it
feels like you've just made this giant statement, but you're also not just bludgeoning it to
death because that actually ends up taking away from it.
My favorite example is, I love to take like a ten second excerpt of the Rite of Spring
and just loop it over and over to see just how fast it becomes the...
from one of the best things ever written to one of the worst things ever written.
And so like the loopingness is the problem.
It's not designed for that.
So figuring out ways to be able to make your big statement and then not, you know, beat it to death.
Cool. Thank you.
I think I tend to beat it to death most of the time.
And that's why when we go to PAX, everyone comes to ask for your autograph.
Don't start that.
Sir, Mr. Colvin.
Hello.
So I'm a developer, and I've been that person who's
giving the feedback.
And that person has been giving the brief, so sorry, guys.
I just wanted to ask, what kinds of brief
do you wish you got from developers that you don't get?
Oh, that's great.
I'm just going to jump straight in there.
The thing that annoys me the most is when you're pitching on a project and they give
you a single page that describes the game in a very high level way and they go, so what
would the main theme sound like?
you have no clue what the main theme's gonna sound like.
You have a single page to work from, you know?
To me, the main theme's often the last thing
that comes from the project.
And often, you know, the composer that they choose
to go with can often be selected from that round.
And that's kind of a really weird thing for me.
But it's just kind of what I was talking about,
just getting to know everybody and things like that.
The point I was trying to make there is so,
when you say to a composer, I want you to make it grand,
your definition of grand is completely understood
by the composer that you're working with.
I mean, what I mean is grand, what Rich think is grand, what you think is grand is very, very different.
So it's having that shared, common, creative language that's very important.
And it's always good to like, ask for, you know, some YouTube links or some MP3s
or things that you think might suit the style of game you're working on or whatever it may be.
So at least it puts you in the right direction, rather than just kind of going,
I worked for somebody who said, you know, I don't know what the music should sound like, but I'll know it when I hear it.
And that's a bit like, I could be hitting next Christmas writing this music, you know, it's completely useless.
You get a guy who sends you four YouTube, or one YouTube clip of something that he likes.
You get that straight away, you understand it, right?
You know, and sometimes getting briefs with no MP3s is a bit crap
because you don't know what they really mean by what they're saying.
I've like read briefs that I need to pitch for
and thinking that they're asking for some bizarre combination of...
Something plus hip-hop which it used to be all the time now whatever you write write jazz but with a hip-hop beat write big band
But whatever it is right so like it seems to be stick hip-hop in it
Whatever it is and so you know it's just it's just senseless. They need to send you something
I got some of the same people said we want something that isn't like this, but it's got the right energy
And I was like what?
What on earth is that all about right so just send?
Send a couple of YouTube clips or some MPD's you think are in the right direction at least give us a clue all right
I'll try.
I think we can probably take one last one here and then we're out.
Sort of a personal question.
Sorry, Jesse.
I actually just wanted to give an answer to this guy.
You can do that in your own time, Jesse.
Get your own talk.
If you could name two people, one modern era composer or artist that you really admire
previous era composer.
For me one of the-
You mentioned Stravinsky so.
Yeah, several previous eras.
For me Jerry Goldsmith
is sort of king of kings
but today, these days I have
to say I am in the
club of Johann Johansson
devotees.
That's my answer.
Come on Greg
it's your turn.
Come on.
Well, modern day, I really, I love John Williams.
I just classical, you know, so modern, yeah, thank you.
I've been sticking with films, well, no Stravinsky.
I love Stravinsky, ballet suites and all that stuff.
That's what I first listened to.
I love how programmatic it is and through composed.
And it reminds me of film music.
It tells a story.
Yeah, I'm John Williams' God, without a doubt.
And I guess, I'm a bit of a metal fan,
so I guess like Queensryche or something like that,
Judas Priest, that's the kind of thing that I like.
Probably, I'd probably headbang quite happily to that
for all day long.
And I guess, like Vaughan Williams and Elgar
are my kind of classical guys that I really like a lot.
I mean, I'm another Stravinsky guy, but to list another name,
Hindemith is one of my all-time favorite classical composers,
early 20th century.
And as far as modern folks,
Yoko Kanno is probably my favorite by far.
Anime composer for those who...
I don't really have an answer.
To me, it's all just music.
I love everything.
There's not one specific thing that I like
and one specific thing that I don't like.
It's all the same notes on the page to me,
so I don't have anything.
I'm sorry, that's a lame answer.
I'm going to be a little weird.
I'm kind of similar because I listen to a lot of music.
And maybe nothing particular stands out.
But what does stand out for me is actually
artists in other mediums.
So I was actually thinking of Miyazaki and Mobius, who, for
some reason, visual art kind of speaks to me and kind of
inspires me to write music.
Thanks all for coming.