My name is Cyril Baron. I've been in the industry for about 20 years.
I had a first part of my life in publishing, marketing, working for Atari, Infogram,
and then I switched to production and joined actually Ubisoft Düsseldorf.
in 2012, so about seven years ago.
Ubisoft du Soleil is actually part of Ubisoft Blue Byte.
We are one of the oldest studios in Germany.
We are doing a bit older type of product that Ubisoft is doing,
so big codev on the big brand of Ubisoft.
We have some PC brand, maybe, you know, Anno, you know, Settlers.
And we love innovation.
And actually, so Ubisoft Escape Game is one of our innovation projects.
It's coming out of Ubisoft du Soleil.
Basically, our mandate is to create virtual reality escape games
in the best gaming world of Ubisoft.
And we have actually released two experiences already.
The first one is called Escape the Lost Pyramid.
It's actually based in the world of Assassin's Creed Origins,
and we released that in July 2018.
And we just released, a couple of months ago,
a second experience called Beyond Medusa's Gate,
which is also an escape game set this time
in the world of Assassin's Creed Odyssey,
so back in ancient Greece.
What's special about our games, at least for Ubisoft,
is we are doing them exclusively for location-based entertainment
businesses.
So our clients are actually physical escape rooms.
They are VR arcades, or they are whatever outlets
specialize in entertainment.
So we have some family entertainment center.
We've got some laser tag, et cetera.
Something also which is a bit special in our project is
we are actually controlling the distribution.
What I mean by that is we do not have distributors.
We actually want to have a one-on-one relation
with every single partner.
And we are currently building this network
because in LBE, it's very important
to have very good partners,
and I think this line of communication
is super important for us.
So you know a bit what we are doing,
and what I would like to start with
is to tell you about our journey into VR.
Actually, we operate a bit like a small startup within Ubisoft.
So you see all the teams, there are 21 guys at the bottom of the screen.
We are very small, we need to be very fast.
We want to change the world a bit like a startup.
It actually started back in 2017.
I think we submitted a concept to our editorial team in Paris.
about doing Escape Room in VR and they actually liked it and they told us, you know what,
maybe it's a good idea, we're going to give you a small prototype budget, build a team and try
to prove to us that it could be interesting. So we had three months to create this first prototype.
And then we presented it to Serge, Serge Asquet, who is our chief creative officer in Ubisoft,
and he said, you know what, I like it guys, so please go and start doing the first game,
which we started back in October 2017. So at the time we were 10 devs.
And we actually released, so Escape the Lost Pyramid,
our first game at the end of June in 2018.
And by the time of release, we were actually 16 on the team.
So still very fast.
And actually, our first client started operating our game
on the 1st of July, 2018.
Immediately, the team started to work on the second game.
And at the same time, we were trying
to find new partners to distribute and operate
our games.
This year in February, we actually reached 100 partners worldwide.
In May, as I've told you, we released our second game.
July, we reached 200 partners.
We think we are the market leaders.
There's no official data, but our reach is quite important.
And currently, all the team is currently working on our third room,
which is not going to be based this time on Assassin's Creed
and that we are going to release actually next spring.
And if we find...
one or two missing people we want in the team, we should be 23 by the time of release.
So as you can see, or at least for Ubisoft, we are a very small team and we have a very small
development schedule. Basically what it means is that from the get-go, especially when we are 10,
we had to make lots of production choices to make sure we could deliver on time and quality.
And so basically what we decided is that our experiments are going to be room-scale only.
And from the get-go, we say it's going to be exclusively
for location-based VR.
It was great, because for us, it mean
we could have the same minimum specs for every single partner.
So we did not have to spend as much time to do optimization
if you want to cover lots of different pieces.
And at the time, so it was two years ago,
we said that we would support.
Rift and actually HTC Vive.
And that's today still the two devices that we are supporting
because our partners who have started,
we want to make sure that they can continue to explore our games
year after year.
Also, what we decided from the get-go
is that it's going to be multiplayer only
and actually it's going to be auto.
of four players. Why two or four players? Because we said if we want to do four we are going to do
two times two so we are going to do twice the experience we're going to mirror it because in
terms of design it would be easier and we would be able to actually do that in time. We also said
that it's going to be a one-time experience. There was lots of discussion about can you make
it replayable but it's difficult to do an escape room in a replayable way because it's all about
discovering.
It would require too much time for not enough value.
And we said, no, we are not going to do that.
It's going to be a one-time experience only.
And if we are very fast in developing one game,
it's better to try to do more than one
than trying to do actually replayability.
And for our first and second game, we also said,
OK, we're not going to have NPCs in the game
because we have no animator.
It's more difficult, and we won't
be able to do it on time.
So see from the very beginning, very strong choices.
At the same time, we have some very agile production method.
So basically, the first thing, and one of the most important,
was having the right people.
And basically, all the people I've got in the team
are people who have a very let's-do-it mindset.
We just do the prototype.
We put it in the game.
It needs to work.
So basically, we have a very flat hierarchy
in the team overall.
It's all about weekly sprints.
We need to be always playable.
And we started with a very light project management Kanban
system, which has evolved a bit now that we are more.
But it's still the same philosophy.
Also, one thing that we decided very early on,
and I think it was a very good decision,
is actually if it's a one-time experience
that is going to be played outside,
we're going to do one-time playtest.
So we're lucky because we are in a big studio.
So we are about more than 200 in Dusseldorf.
So we organized a big contest within the company
where a group of four could actually apply.
And since before Alpha, actually people were coming.
playing the game. So basically, we were able to measure and iterate and actually see what was
happening. And that's when, when we started VR, we understood actually what matters is not what
you see or what you see as a dev on screen, it's about what you feel. And making sure that we had
all these playtests from very early on actually gave us lots of knowledge and confidence about
the quality of the experience when it was released outside. So let's talk about how do we create
business-to-business experiences.
for mainstream consumers.
Because one thing is clear is that our audience is actually very mainstream.
If you know Escape Room, Escape Room is for everybody.
It's for all ages, all people.
You go there as a family, you go there with your grandmother,
you go there as a company, it can be a corporate event,
so you can go with your boss, with your colleague.
So basically, it's also for people who have no VR experience most of the time.
Sometimes they don't have video game experience. So thinking about accessibility from the very
beginning was one of our core principles. And you can also see that we've also been testing
at Blue Byte with people in wheelchairs because accessibility is one of the key.
And at the same time that we have this, in terms of audience,
we know that if you do location-based entertainment,
you have some constraints from the business side.
One of them is on the business side,
customers are going to book a 60-minute session.
especially in VR arcade, which means that you actually have
only 60 minutes to learn the game and finish it.
So you really need to think from the beginning
about onboarding the players, how do you finish,
and how you're going to give tools to your partners,
the operator, to manage all the different players.
So this is what we had in mind when we started.
And we said, OK, so what are we going to do?
How are we going to do it?
One of the first things we were wondering is,
why do you go out of home?
Because it's not going to be played at your place.
You're going to have to go out.
And basically, if you go out of home,
it's because you want to meet friends.
Most likely, you're going to meet colleagues.
Maybe you go out with your family.
So that's why, from the very beginning,
we say it has to be multiplayer.
And here, you can see one of the setups is all two or four
players, so that's a four-player setup.
So the game was going to be multiplayer, and I think if you listen to the arcade and looking
through the entertainment, doing VR, they tell you that 90% of the games which are played are
actually multiplayer games. So I think it was a very important decision. And what we wanted to do
is to make sure there was a very strong collaboration in the game. So if you go as a
group, you want to make sure that all together you're going to be working well. And so basically
what I'm going to show you...
is a video of a group of four players in the game.
They are talking to one another and they understand that they have to do it together,
otherwise they are not going to make it. So please pay attention more to what they say than what you see.
Can you stay at the bridge too?
You have to work together guys, right?
You've heard the guy said, oh, we have to work together guys, right?
And it's correct. It's one of the really core principle of our experience.
And one of the rule we have is you cannot solve the game on your own.
If you don't escape room, physical escape room,
sometime you are in a group where somebody is very fast in picking up everything.
He finds a lock, he does everything for you.
So you're watching, but you say, oh.
Okay, so you feel a bit outside and what you wanted to do is at the end of every single experience,
anybody from the team should be able to say, guys, without me, you would not have done it.
And it's important because when you go as a group and you have the satisfaction,
it means that when you come back home or when you go back to work on Monday,
you're going to say that you've done something for your team and you're going to talk about it.
So that was one of the core rules that we've got.
Also, what we wanted to do, if you go out of home,
is we wanted you to do something that you cannot do actually
in your living room.
So of course, it's larger than your living room.
So in our game, if you have four players,
you need four room scale.
So you're not going to be able to do that at home,
or at least not a lot of home are
going to be able to do that.
But what was important for us is to be larger than life.
And I think that what VR offers you,
it offers you to transport people to different places.
So again, pay attention to what people are saying.
Is that Atlas? So imagine, you go back to work on Monday, what you can say is, oh, together
we were with my three friends, we were on a boat in this massive underground cave and we have the
giant statues of Atlas above us. That's the type of emotion that you want to give actually to a
player. So we want them to experience something larger than life. We want them to do something
that you actually cannot do in real life, maybe because it's too difficult.
maybe because it's just impossible or too dangerous. And again that's what people are
doing so you're not going to see what they've done but basically they have to climb something
which is quite steep and they are actually commenting on it.
I wish that climbing was that easy in real life.
And yes, it's amazing.
I think when people actually do that
and they've got this feeling of doing something incredible,
it brings actually satisfaction
to the experience that you are doing.
So this was one of our principle of everything we do.
We want to be larger than life.
We want to be,
to enable you to do something you cannot do in real life.
And at the same time, because of our audience,
we need to make it accessible.
to actually everyone. So how do we do that? What were our design guidelines? First,
we are non-violent. What does that mean? That even though we are set in the world of Assassin's Creed,
you're not playing as an assassin, you're not going to assassinate anybody, and I think it's
valuable because we have lots of feedback from partners, the arcade saying, you know, it's good
to have a game where you can put anybody, you're not going to kill anybody, which is positive,
and we think it was important, especially for our target audience.
Second, what we've done, and it's probably one of the best decisions we made,
even though it was not a decision we've done from the get-go, is we are giving you a full-body
avatar. So one of the first things you do when you arrive in the game, you're going to be in a lobby
all together, you have your avatar, and you see yourself. There is a mirror, so if you wave at
the mirror, you're going to see you're waving. And actually, this is the moment where people
who have not done VR are sold on VR, because at that moment they understand.
Oh, but that's not just a video game.
That's not a gaming console.
That's incredible.
That's actually me.
And we can see each other.
People can talk.
You've got some accessories.
You've got hats.
So you can take the hat and you say, how do I put it on?
And you tell them, well, how do you do in real life?
Oh, and you put it on and say, wow, it's incredible.
It's working.
And I was saying it was not an obvious decision
because when we started, we had no animator.
So basically, you're not tracking the feet.
So yeah, if you look at the animation,
it's not perfect at all, far from that,
but it doesn't matter.
Actually, the benefit of having a full body
is so much better than actually,
it's really selling VR to actually customers.
So I really recommend people
who are not sure about having a real body avatar,
it's really worth it
because it's really making people
enjoy the experience a lot.
Then, if you want to be a manta ray, you need to be as natural as possible.
So of course, as you've seen, people are talking.
Well, you're not in a tutorial to talk.
When we do bow shooting, we put a bow in the whale, we put an arrow,
and I think anybody understands that if you grab the bow, grab an arrow, put it in, and shoot.
It's working. You don't need a tutorial.
It's magical.
Climbing is a bit more difficult, but people get it.
And because we had room scale,
you actually don't need to learn really locomotion,
so it was quite natural.
And actually, we have just two tutorials in the game.
One is for grabbing, so we are telling you to press the trigger
to actually grab an object.
And the second one I'm going to talk to you about.
So at the same time, even though we had room scale,
natural walking, what we decided also is to give you,
in each game, a kind of moving platform for you
so we could actually transport you in a much bigger world
to make sure that you would see more of the universe.
And now I'm going to show you.
So you've seen that Medusa,
which has all the extract you've seen,
you are actually on a boat.
So you've got your boat with your mate
and it's going through the cave.
And actually in Pyramid, this is what we had.
So in Pyramid, actually you have this small platform and actually the platform where all
the players are coming together and it transports you from the very bottom of the pyramid to
the very top if you manage to find the exit.
So you've seen everything is super natural.
And then what did we decide to do?
Ha, teleport.
You're going to say, but that's crazy.
It's not natural.
It's difficult.
It's true.
And that was probably the most difficult decision we made.
We're still arguing about it, saying it's not perfect.
Actually, we decided to keep it mainly for convenience
for the partners.
Because if you have a partner who has a smaller size,
maybe 2 by 2, not 2 by 3.
Well, it's more difficult. We wanted to be able to accommodate,
so we said, okay, we're still going to allow teleporting the game
because it's going to be easier for actually operators to do it,
but we've done something a bit different.
I mean, if you are a VR expert,
when you have a game with grabbing and teleporting,
you will have your two-button control.
So basically, you're going to grab with your trigger
and use your pie or joystick to teleport.
What we've done is we actually implemented by default
one-button control system, which means that actually on the trigger,
You have both the grabbing and the teleporting.
The way it works is, if you have an object that you can grab,
and you put your hand close to it, it's going to be highlighted.
You press the trigger, you grab it.
And if you want to teleport, you need to point at the floor,
maintain the trigger in, and you have an alpha second delay.
You see a line going on, and then you've got this blue circle.
And when you release it, you teleport.
If you are a VR expert guy, when you try your game, you say...
your game is not working. I think there's a real problem with teleporting because I'm trying to do it. It takes some time.
And it's true, but actually if you are a very mainstream person who has never played, who has just 60 minutes to learn, who has never done video games,
you can learn how to use one button in 60 minutes. You can't learn two.
And actually, it really makes sure that for us,
we've seen that everybody has been able to play the game,
even though if they had no VR or no game experience.
And what we do is for more experienced VR players
in our tools for the partners,
they can actually activate by default two button
if you want to, but it's not what we advise
as a main control.
And again, we've been very happy
with the choice we made on this level.
Finally, what we've put in the game is, because it's working really well with Assassin's Creed
in general, is this eagle vision.
And basically, it's kind of replaced the Game Master.
So basically, when you are in the world and you're a bit lost, and it can happen in VR,
especially when you've never done it, if you raise both your hand above your head with
your controllers, we are going to highlight in the world what's important for you to touch
or interact with if you want to solve your quest.
And that's actually quite helpful, because if you don't know, you do that and you kind of find your way through.
So this is all the idea we had when we started Pyramid.
We released it. Of course, we had lots of feedback and we realized that everything was not perfect.
There are lots of things that we could improve.
And actually, we changed a couple of things when we've been doing our second game.
The first thing we've done is we've staged the multiplayer differently.
In Pyramid, basically, you start four in the lobby where you have character,
then we separate you to make sure that you feel the tension, and little by little we put you back
together as a group because you have this notion of coming back together which is very satisfying.
But by doing so, actually on some of the paths,
you were too and you did not have the choice of what you could do.
And it was bad because for example we have some climbing to do
and we know how intensive can be climbing. Some people could not do it but
they had no choice and that was really bad. So actually what
we've done in Medusa is
We have actually changes to make sure that the beginning of every single stage,
you start at four players, you see what's happening,
and you can actually decide where you want to go.
So if you don't want to climb, you don't have to do it.
Then we can still split you because it's really satisfying
to make some small group working together really well,
but you have the choice at the very beginning.
Also, one rule that we applied is we keep the line of sight.
So here on this screenshot, it's from the view of one player.
just on your right there is somebody climbing and maybe you don't see really well but on the other
side you have two other players hugging one another so basically even on this big level
the four players are always inside and why is it important because
we realized from our first game is that when you're lost in VR
you feel really lost. You don't know what to do. If you have to wait, it's a really a bad experience.
But as long as you can see the other players, you can actually talk to one another. They can
actually help you. And basically, you never have the feeling that suddenly you've been on your own
or you're not part of the group or it's different. And by making sure that at any single point,
you can always see the people you always feel as a group, which is at the heart of what we want to do.
One of the things also we've done is, so this help system, you remember that we had,
we actually made it optional, so it's actually actionable from what we call the spectator.
Basically, all the videos you've seen are the screenshots.
It's the view that the partner has using our spectator mode.
which is a tool, it's not made to be great looking,
it's just made for the partner to see
and to follow the way he wants to,
all the different players,
and he's able to act on the game.
And he can activate or deactivate this help system
if somebody wants a harder game or a simple one.
What we also change is...
the time of the experience. So Pyramid, the average completion time is 44 minutes worldwide
and it was too short because when it's 44 minutes, I'll show you after, the distribution of play time
varies a lot depending on the groups and too many people were able to finish it less than 30 minutes
which is too short.
So basically for Medusa, the average playtime, completion time is 54 minutes,
and we think it's right now the optimal time in terms of satisfaction for the different partners.
Finally, in Pyramid, if you've done some escape games,
at the end as a team, you escape,
people tell you, okay, come together as a team,
we're going to take a nice photo,
and it's a cool souvenir and you can post it,
it's really cool.
So that's what we are doing in Pyramid,
but in Medusa, actually, we do it in game.
So basically, I know it's having an electronic photo
in ancient Greece, it's a bit daring,
but actually people love it,
and it's a great memories,
and then...
partners can actually give that to their customers, they can share it and it was something positive.
So this is what the part about more about the choice we made in terms of design and what I
want to talk to you now a bit more is about what the client say, what our partners say because
we have the direct relations so we talk a lot with them because we're actually learning a lot
from the market and actually what does it reveal for the market in general.
So we have a lot of data. We track how players are playing and it gives us some interesting
statistics. So for example, in terms of number of players, and I think we were surprised by this
because if you look overall at our games, you actually have more two-player sessions than
four-player sessions. In escape room, in traditional escape room location, there's
more four players, but in general, for example, in VR arcade, there's more two players.
And I think what we realize is VR Escape Room is a fantastic experience for couples.
Lots of people have the adventure together as a couple and I really, we're always saying now to
our partners, you know, think in your marketing to target couples, to do something together,
because that's really something which is very strong, which you can actually do together.
One of the things that I was mentioning before about average completion time
is you can see the kind of distribution and the difference between actually Pyramid and Melusa.
And having this 54 minutes is really more optimal because you have very few people
who are able to finish before the 30 minutes, where I'd feel a bit too much.
And to actually help partners to manage this, we have a kind of leaderboard, which is not to
encourage teams to be fast, because we want people to take advantage, but it's to be able
to say to somebody who's been very fast, look, you are among the best guys, so you're a great team.
Don't be upset. I mean, you've done so well. I mean, we could not expect you to actually do so well.
In terms of completion rate, there's more people who are finishing the game in escape rooms locations, but...
There's a bat.
We should not think that these people are actually more efficient in doing it.
It's just that traditional escape rooms have a different approach to booking.
So basically, often they don't have just a 60 minute time slot.
Some want to have 75 or 90 minutes because their approach is to say,
I want everybody to finish.
I want to talk to them before.
So they take more time.
And that's actually why there is actually a bigger time, because in general,
there is a very similar success factor between one or the other.
And then what we do, because we have this direct relation
with our different partners, we are doing lots of survey
with them.
So this one is a bit old, because it
was done before the release of Medusa.
But it's still valid in terms of information
that had been shared with us.
So as you can see, in the surveys,
there's a split between Escape Room and VR Arcade.
We have just all been entering about.
our questions. So one of the first questions we asked them is, is the revenue in line with your
expectation? So we were happy to see that 60% say yes, but actually you do realize that for 30,
35% they say it was below expectation, what they got as a result. And so we were asking them,
so why do you think it is below expectation? What can we do about it?
So one of the comments we've got usually is the fact that because we are two or four players,
if you are, especially if you're on escape room, usually you bring groups of five, six people
together, which you actually cannot do right now. And it makes sense because if you put six people
instead of four, you're going to have a kind of better business. So we know it's not something
we can do. But a lot of the comments are not so much related about this, are more related about.
it's still very new, so we still need to communicate. We thought that just because it's
VR, because you have a big brand, it's going to pick up just like this. It's not the case.
And actually, people sometimes underestimate the effort you need to do to market actually VR and
the experience outside of VR. And basically, what we can really see is that there is
not a general happy and acceptance of VR and there are very lots of differences
per venues and per type of consumers and basically you still need to convince
mainstream.
It's quite interesting because some of our partners are doing pretty well, meaning that
some VR arcade are really, because it's a bit different than their traditional model, which is
a pay per minute, this is a pay per session, you book one hour, so it's something different for
them, but some are really trying to emphasize the fact it's different from the typical VR arcade
where you can get access to a big catalog of games, you come from a session, and the one who
market this as an escape room
What they're telling us, it's super interesting for them because they are bringing in people
who would never come, actually.
to a VR arcade because they are not interested or they do not know about it because they don't have
this term of acceptance but they are interested by escape room and if you like escape room
you like a challenge so if it's in VR it's okay you can pick it up but what they are saying is by
doing so actually this guy have discovered that VR is cool and some of them actually are coming
back to the to the location so there is an interest by entering by a kind of a different
side to the market.
What we also ask them is,
do you think you're going to increase the space
dedicated to VR escape room in your venue?
As you can see, lots of people were actually in favor of doing it.
Actually, almost half of these people were people who mentioned before.
that the revenue was below their expectation. So we were a bit, well, we are happy because we
think it's better, but we wanted to understand why is that. And I think one of the reasons we've got
is when we ask them, is the feedback that you got from customers,
on the experiment. Is it in line with your expectation? Is it below or above? And actually,
I think that's one of the reasons. Actually, even though they played the game before,
they know how they are. The feedback they got is actually excellent. And it really shows you that
when VR is excellent, people are doing better. So they see that there is something there which
is going to grow and get better over time.
So actually when you ask them, how bright do you see the future for VR escape rooms?
So it's on a scale from one to seven, you can see everybody's about four.
And actually almost 60% were saying that there is a real opportunity.
And actually something that I can say we've seen on the market, and it's quite new, because
when we started two years ago, we had never heard about this, but now we have many actually
people saying.
I'm going to do an escape room business, but it's going to be solely with VR experience,
because we think it's a future, we think it's working, and actually now we have about 240
partners, eight of them are doing exclusively escape room in VR, and I think it's a trend
which is going to actually continue.
Finally, I wanted to go maybe a bit beyond the data.
Not that I have certainty about how to market and address
the consumers, because it's still difficult.
We still need to learn about it.
But there's a couple of points which I think are interesting.
And if you have some idea, I'm also
interested to discuss after the talk with you
to see what we can do.
One of the first thing we are always telling,
especially Escape Room, is,
You need to explain to people that VR is not a gaming console.
I mean, you're not going to pay $30 to go and play on PlayStation outside your home.
And that's still what lots of people believe.
They don't understand that what we're doing are not video games,
they are experiences. And it's fundamentally different.
And when you are able to go beyond that, when people understand that this is the case,
they have a very different relation to what VR is.
And I think that's one of the challenges we've got is how do we communicate that.
I don't have the solution.
The one thing I know is we should not market it as a video game.
So for example, I'm a bit hardcore on this topic,
but there's not one trailer of our games available outside.
So what you've seen today are the only moving images
that have been produced.
So you have an idea.
But because
they don't properly relate what you do and what you see. It's always below. So I know that everybody
wants to communicate and they say we need the trailer, we need something, but I mean our game
is never going to look as good as the last Assassin's Creed because it's the way it is,
we are not a 2D game. So I don't have the solution, but I think we should not do that. We really need
to market it as an experience because that makes a difference. And the one thing I've seen which is
really really working.
actually is...
you need to let people try.
And that's one of the things that some of our escape rooms
are doing.
When they finish a traditional one,
they go back in the lobby where you have this character.
They just put the headset.
It can be 10 seconds, but in 10 seconds,
the guy understands it's something different.
And something similar I remember,
which I thought was very clever, a surveyor in their arcade,
actually in Torrance.
What they had, they had a very nice arcade,
and he's giving on a big mall down the street.
you have a very big transparent front window and what we are putting just in front is Richie's
plank and basically you could see from the outside people and basically tell you what is this that's
very different it's again going into the direction of this is an experience and it's not just a video
game and that's what is making I think location-based entertainment VR actually successful.
So that's pretty much everything I've got to share with you today.
I think if you have questions, maybe we have a bit of time, I'll be happy to answer them,
or I can answer some afterwards, or you can send me an email.
And if you want to do VR, actually we have lots of opportunities in Ubisoft Dusseldorf.
It's really cool.
And if a French guy is telling you that it's cool to live in Germany, it's probably true.
Thank you very much.