So, my name is Chelsea Howe.
I spent the last eight years in the free-to-play space doing a bunch of different projects
and I'm now working at Alchemy Labs in VR.
And one of the things that was consistent throughout my time in free-to-play was just
that, this idea of time.
It's the underlying foundation for a lot of free-to-play mechanics, and yet one thing
that I noticed was that people don't usually think about time over time.
We think a lot about short-term gains, little spikes, but we don't really understand human
attention and behavior past kind of the daily to weekly stage.
I think one of the major things that I saw was this tendency to underestimate how quickly
humans adapt to stimulus, which is just a fancy way of saying people get bored.
As we see time becoming...
more foundational in things beyond free-to-play
in console and AAA, I think it's really vital
to look at human behavior in psychology
and understand how experiences
can really engage people long-term.
After all, The Holy Grail would kind of be a game
that lasts and is lucrative forever,
independent of developer content.
I don't know how to do that.
If I did, I wouldn't be here.
But here's some pillars.
So I want to start with player engagement over time.
Now when I talk about player engagement,
I'm not talking about any discrete metric,
so no DAU or MAU or some of the other things
that we've used in the past.
When I talk about player engagement,
I'm talking a little bit more abstractly
about the time, attention, and mental effort
a player gives to a game,
regardless of whether or not they're playing it.
So essentially the psychological energy
they're putting towards your game
at any given point in time.
And I wanna start by thinking about this
through the lens of another area of our lives
where we use the term engagement.
After all, marriage is supposed to be this thing
that lasts for life, even if statistically
we haven't been doing a super great job of that.
But the lens of relationship psychology
is still really helpful as we think about our games.
After all, historically, developers wanted to see
players fall in love with them,
to really grab them and get them engrossed,
and for each day to be better and more exciting
than the one before.
And we know that that's not really how relationships work.
But love in the short term does start with infatuation,
and this is the typical peak we see
when players first pick up a game.
We see them binge, we see longer player sessions,
more frequent sessions per day.
But this phase of engagement is inherently transient.
The getting to know you rollercoaster never lasts
because we as humans are designed to adapt
and find patterns.
We're designed to get bored.
This is how our brain optimizes to live in our world.
Even the most beautiful rock in the world
is going to become background noise
if it's on your finger every day.
And that's just a result of how we as humans
process stimulus.
At the most basic level, whenever we receive a stimulus,
we tend to pass it through the list of our basic needs.
Can I eat it, mate with it, or will it kill me?
Once we've done that, our engagement starts to fall off.
We run it against some of our higher order cognitive needs.
And I want to point out that this graph is not accurate.
The peak and amplitude, the rate of decay,
all of that is dependent on different personal factors
and factors with the stimulus and content itself.
I'm going to use those two words,
stimulus and content, relatively interchangeably.
Any piece of content is going to be a stimulus
that evokes some form of player attention and engagement.
Now the other half of this curve,
if we know that the stimulus is coming up,
is this idea of anticipation.
This essentially means that we get engagement
before we actually even give the player something.
Now I mentioned that it doesn't usually look
like a bell curve at all.
But the one thing, regardless of that decay rate
and amplitude or the rise of the anticipation.
is that it's going to go down over time.
It will decay.
And this is just a natural result
of some of our neurological tendencies.
So here's a few different
perception-based reasons for this.
This is a small, small subset.
If you're interested in this,
I highly recommend looking up a few basic UX books
on principles of human attention.
So the first thing that I want to talk about
is that we're hardwired to find patterns in the world.
As soon as we find a pattern,
it means our brain doesn't have to do so much work
and we can attend to other things.
Once we find a pattern, we only pay attention
to the way that some sort of stimulus deviates from it.
This also means that as soon as we recognize
a piece of content that follows a pattern,
we're not going to get the full amount
of engagement we normally would.
We saw this a lot early on in so-called golden mechanics.
It turns out that golden mechanics were really
just easily repeatable patterns,
and the initial spikes of engagement that we got from them
didn't hold up over time.
The next thing we do is that we chunk things.
The iconic example of this in UX
is the idea of phone numbers.
it's much easier to remember three chunks of numbers
than 10 individual numbers.
However, this also means that we don't get
10 individual spikes of stimulus,
nor the sum of 10 individual parts.
We get something a little bit less than that.
You can see this in games in something like Pokemon,
where when I spin a specific PokeStop,
I don't get an individual spike of engagement
for each item that drops.
I just get this collective chunked idea of a PokeSpin.
And I think the biggest one is that we tend to normalize.
Put simply, everyone has a different base emotional level.
And that base emotional level
isn't what determines how we feel.
What determines how we feel on any given day
is the way that the stimulus we're exposed to
deviates from that baseline.
So on the plus side, this means that no matter
how great or terrible your life is,
on any given day, you're designed to exist and survive
to continue moving forward.
So just being able to feed your family
might feel as good as someone with a relatively
low experiential baseline,
as closing a billion dollar acquisition
for someone with a relatively high experiential baseline.
Now unfortunately, if we continue to give people
these spikes, that doesn't mean that we're going
to give them bigger and bigger emotions.
What it means is that we're going to elevate their baseline.
So essentially, just like in Adrenaline Junkies,
the first high that we get is never going to be the same.
Okay, so that sounds a little bit dire,
but I wanna look again at relationships.
We know that some of them have to work.
After all, we still exist.
So what does that transition look like?
How do we get players from that initial infatuation
to a place where they're willing
to be more intimate and committed?
The first thing we need to do is not panic
when that initial spike wears off.
In the early days of getting mass data,
we saw this all the time.
We'd see the slightest little dip in engagement
and we'd set off all of the alarms.
people would get called in the middle of the night.
The end result was that we were constantly trying
to show bigger, better, grander things at players,
all the time, throwing any micro dip in their attention.
Now the result for players was exhausting.
We wound up making our average players feel like
they were missing out, and driving our highly engaged
players into this unsustainable frenzy.
And the downside is that once you start on this path,
there's really not a lot of options besides continuing.
You've elevated the expectations
for your highly engaged players.
You've basically trained them to constantly want more.
At the same time, your average players
start seeing a higher and higher gap
between their experience and the experience
of these highly engaged players.
They start seeing fewer and fewer reasons to stick around.
So instead of more, more, more, more, more,
what we have to do is start looking at ways
to say enough to our players.
Instead of striving for this ever increasing engagement,
we need to get them into a habituated series
of cycles of engagement.
In the same way that we need rest in order to be able
to act, we need relief between these periods
of attentional arousal.
So there's a lot of really common ways to do this.
In a game like Choices, you can read whatever you want,
but you can only read a chapter every few hours.
In something like Wow, you can battle your pets
all the time, but on weekends,
it's going to be faster and more rewarding.
And in something like Clash Royale,
you can continue to attack as often as you want,
but that high reward, the chests, are inherently limited.
And I want to talk about that one specifically,
because I remember being in design meetings
and hearing other designers say,
myself included, actually,
I can't believe how blatant this chest limit is.
They're not even trying to hide it anymore.
And I want to talk about why that's brilliant.
Because another cornerstone of healthy relationships
that are designed to last is trust and consent.
Now, I know that those are heavy words, but we as developers really want engagement.
After all, we live in an engagement economy.
Attention is essentially our coin.
So we really, really want those players to like us.
So we try to get their attention.
And we don't always do it in the healthiest of ways.
Now a lot of us are familiar with M'Chay Tshikszentm'Chay,
apologies, for his work on flow,
but he also did a lot of work on taxonomies of attention.
He said that there are essentially
two categories of attention.
One is voluntary, we choose to attend and focus on something
and the other one is compulsory,
which means our attention is essentially demanded
by some sort of perceived emotional,
biological or social need.
Now I wanna point out that by definition,
compelling attention is non-consensual.
And for that reason, compelling attention will always perform better in your A-B tests.
Of course, forcing someone to do something is going to get you the results you want more
than letting them choose to do it.
And this is why we see these techniques all the time in games.
It's why we see them all the time on TV.
And it's why we see them all the time in our social feeds.
And this is repulsive.
This is using sensationalism and implied risk
to force us to attend to something.
This should infuriate all of us.
This diminishes our agency and our autonomy as humans.
Those are the very things that make us human.
But the data, the promise of profit
is not permission for unethical action.
If you're going to treat data as permission
to act immorally and unethically,
to put your business ahead of the people
that you are supposed to be serving,
then I want you all to think about
what the future is going to look like
in this data-driven world.
If you use data as an excuse,
as a way to alleviate your own responsibility in a situation,
that isn't creating a relationship.
This is 21st century enslavement.
We no longer need to hook people up
to get their physical labor.
but we live in an engagement economy
and we're stealing people's attention.
So I don't care what your data says.
Data is a manifestation of action.
It's a means of tracking behavior
and data is oblivious to the human condition.
Just because you can do something,
just because something would make you more money,
doesn't mean that you should do it.
Because regardless of how ubiquitous these techniques are,
they are fundamentally dark design.
All dark design does is slowly erode trust and faith
in people's autonomy over their time.
And when we reduce people
to just those animalistic impulses,
those things that we cannot control,
we are reducing people to animals.
We are removing their personhood.
And we're already starting to see the horrific results of this.
As our own capacity to focus our attention is lost to this constant barrage of alarm
and fear in media, we are sinking into a world ruled by those fears.
If you were at any of the UX talks these past two days, one consistent theme was that when
we are afraid, we do not grow, we do not learn, and we do not flourish.
So think about what that future looks like.
This was supposed to be about games, so let's go back to Clash Royale.
Everyone was right.
They aren't trying to hide anything.
And in doing so, they're actually giving players more control over whether or not they choose
to attend to a game.
They're letting players decide whether or not engagement is worth it instead of obfuscating
and disguising their demands for time.
When we're clear with our boundaries and limitations,
we're actually being more respectful.
We're being less deceitful, more upfront,
and allowing informed negotiation.
That is what builds trust and faith over time,
even if it can be hard at a stomach at first.
So let's talk about that hard at a stomach.
Let's talk about player perception of time.
Now the role of time in free-to-play games
is essentially a pacing tool.
It controls the consumption of content.
Like any temporal art, pacing is really vital
to a well-designed experience.
But for games that depend heavily
on developer-created content,
it's also one of the only ways to survive,
which means we have a very large capacity
to try to get that pacing in ways that aren't always healthy.
So how do we surface time in a way
that players perceive positively?
How do we integrate it into that healthy relationship
we want to create?
There's a few different techniques for surfacing time.
There's direct timers, and that's exactly what it sounds
like, a little two-hour countdown.
There's indirect inclusion of time,
which is where something might take 200 mana,
and you generate 100 mana per hour.
Again, those are functionally identical.
They both delay your consumption of content for two hours.
But they feel, and can feel, very different.
One thing that affects the way a timer feels
is verisimilitude in context.
Verisimilitude is a fancy way of saying,
does it fit with an existing player model?
If you have something like crops needing time to grow,
that fits with our existing mental model.
It's going to feel better than something like
keys randomly sprouting every three hours.
The other difference between direct and indirect timers
is that indirect timers actually let us have some autonomy
over our time equity.
We build up that 200 mana and we don't necessarily
have to use it on one specific thing.
We can use that investment of time that we have
whatever way we want.
The final way to surface time is implicitly.
So this means that some mechanic in your game
literally takes time to complete.
So something like just walking around
and catching Pokemon in Pokemon Go takes time.
It takes time to move your body
from one location to another.
And this used to be considered the golden standard
in console era.
But what it means is that we don't get any benefit
from a game unless we are paying full
and complete attention to it.
And that doesn't always feel good either.
So essentially what I'm saying is that none of these
are specifically right.
It's all about how you use them, not which one you use.
And some of the most successful games,
the ones that feel the best,
utilize all of these in different ways.
But because direct timers tend to get
that unusually bad reputation, like they did in Clash,
I want to point out another benefit
of being completely up front
with how much time you have
until your next piece of stimulus.
And that's the creation of rhythm and ritual.
Essentially, if we're told every day
that we can come back and get a little bit of new content,
that's going to help create
that habituated cycle of engagement.
That's what we want.
And then ideally, what we do is we layer those over time.
So we create pieces of content at different time intervals.
And as those stack, you wind up
with a steadily increasing curve
that looks a lot like a flow curve.
This is awesome.
So the things that I mentioned previously
were all usually either a moment-to-moment session
or daily types of stimulus.
So I wanna just point out a few examples
of people who are doing longer timescale rituals
relatively well.
In Summoner's War, you have, and a bunch of other games,
you have things that change every day.
So if you need a specific resource,
you can say, ah, I need to come back on Wednesday.
In a game like Hollywood University,
leveling up characters is required to unlock new content,
but leveling up a character can take up to two weeks
at later levels.
In games like Ingress or Neopets,
which has been around for well over a decade,
you have different badges and forms of social signifiers
that can take from half a year in this case
to over a year in the case of Neopets.
Look at that, you just have to have a snow bunny for a year.
Then you have games like Fallen London,
where rewards can stack over multiple years.
So when you come back the next year,
you actually get something
that wasn't available the first year.
And taking this to its most extreme,
you can look at something like EVE Online,
where the total time to complete all skills
is estimated between 18 and 25 years.
All right, so 25 years is a really long time.
It's not something that we tend to talk about.
I've never heard someone look at that time scale
in a design discussion unless I was the one instigating it.
By imagining a long-term relationship with players,
We can start surfacing little things
that help prime them for the idea
that maybe this game is worth more than just a few days
or a week or a month of their time.
If they go in assuming something's going to be
a quick fling, that's probably going to be
what their behavior is.
So I said the word surfacing.
So I want to point out that no matter how many
of these rhythms you have, if you don't surface them,
people can't anticipate them.
And they've done studies that have
shown that people who take pictures of their food
actually enjoy that food more,
specifically because they have that moment
of appreciation and anticipation.
I don't know if any of you guys remember
what Christmas Eve was like as a small child,
but I was pretty sure it was going to last until I died.
So as you design,
remember to give them the ability to anticipate.
Remember to surface things so that players know they exist,
and remember to do it in a way that's not really creepy.
If you start talking about being buried
next to each other on the first date,
that might be a bit of a turnoff.
Okay, so how do you make anticipation
a little bit more sustainable?
I talked about how variety in the pattern
grabs our attention.
Variability does the same thing for our anticipation,
and that's essentially because we're optimists.
If I say, imagine a plate of spaghetti,
you're probably not imagining a few dry,
cracked strands on a plate.
You're probably imagining that optimal version of spaghetti.
You probably imagine a heaping plate
with a little bit of sauce,
and depending on what you like, maybe a few meatballs.
So when there's variability and we know
the potential outcomes, we tend to aim for the best one,
even if that is very, very, very rare.
Now of course this has huge opportunities for abuse.
So again, this is something that you can't
just implement blindly.
You'll see one of the themes about this whole talk
is actually taking responsibility for the decisions
you make as designers and thinking about their impact
on players and whether or not that's
in the player's best interest.
Okay, so there's a lot of different ways to add variability.
One of the most effective, quote unquote,
is variable ratio, which means you tell people
they're going to get something
after a certain number of actions,
and you don't tell them how many actions that is,
and it always changes.
Now that leads to the most engagement,
which means players will do that action
again and again and again and again.
they'll binge, right?
So that's the same behavior as we talked about earlier.
They'll binge and they'll burn out.
Now that doesn't mean that variable ratio is bad.
It means that perhaps if you use variable ratio mechanics,
they should be for a weekend blitz event.
Or one day a week you get this variable ratio.
Because those spikes of engagement are enjoyable.
When you hit your 20th anniversary
and Valentine's Day comes around,
that can be a fun time to spike your engagement,
to do things you don't normally do.
So again, none of these things are inherently bad,
but you need to think very consciously
about the effect on the overall player experience.
If you look at the worst implementation of variable reward,
you get fixed interval, which essentially means
you tell people when they're going to get a reward,
and they tend not to engage as much
until that time comes around.
That is something that is much gentler,
and something that could work as a through line
that's constantly present in your game.
Okay.
So you do all of these, wow, we are running out of time.
All right, I'm gonna switch this into quick mode.
So you have this solid cadence of contents and events,
it starts looking like a flow curve.
But even if we just give people
a tiny little bit of stimulus,
they're still going to wind up with this huge hoard of it.
And that gets into all sorts of problems
once you add social because your elder players are,
you can't ever catch up to them as a new player.
And that leads to all sorts of problems
in this healthy kind of social ecosystem
that I'll talk about a little bit later.
So let's talk about how we can take that progress
and turn it from something that's completely linear
into something that has a little bit more loops.
This is my beautiful art, thank you.
The first one is decay.
So decay is a form of maintenance,
which means a stack goes down over time
and must be continuously boosted.
This is used in Kim Kardashian, where if you don't come back to the game, your partner
will leave you.
It is a horrific experience, especially because they ask you for premium currency to resolve
this.
But again, the mechanic is not negative by default.
In something like Neopets, they use verisimilitude and context, just like I mentioned before,
to make it feel better.
We're used to, in the real world, pets needing food.
So of course it makes sense that I need to consistently feed my pet.
Durability is basically user-driven decay.
This tends to feel a little bit better
because instead of decay being driven by time,
it's driven by things that we do as players.
A great example is tools in Minecraft.
The next one is bounded decay.
So this essentially means that a stat goes down
over time up to a point.
This was something that we saw a lot in old RPGs.
Progress was getting from point A to point B.
Once you hit a save point,
the progress you'd made towards point B couldn't be revoked.
Only the progress between that save point
and the next one could.
The next type of decay is market-driven decay.
You see this a lot in stock markets and style.
What this means is that the actual value,
the actual kind of properties of an item don't change,
but the value changes because of the perspective of others.
So you could have the hottest jacket in the world one week,
and then the next week it's out of style,
the color's wrong, and the cut doesn't look so good anymore.
The next type of decay is other-driven decay.
So this is basically zero-sum.
I think you all know about this.
And then the final type of decay
that I want to talk about is mandatory decay.
So we're seeing this a lot in idle games,
where you actually have to give up all of the progress
that you've made in order to continue.
You do get a little bit of meta-currency at the end,
which then fuels into your next run through the game.
The interesting thing about this is it gives players control
over the pacing of their own experience
in a really valuable way.
Eventually, as you're moving through
that first progress bar in an idle game,
the
return on your time starts to get worse and worse and worse.
You decide when it's no longer worth it,
and when you do, you exchange all of that progress
you've given for that new meta-currency.
That also shucks you back to the beginning
of the progress bar, which as I mentioned before,
tends to be that period where we get
much higher volume of stimulus.
It feels really good.
I also want to point out that idle games
have some of the best retention in the single-player market.
It's a good example of how,
when we actually give autonomy back to players,
they reward us with their attention over time.
Okay, and progress is just one form of satisfaction.
There's lots of different taxonomies of satisfaction,
perma, ocean, self-determination theory,
but progress is always a part of those theories.
And the other part that's always consistent
is this idea of relatedness.
So I wanna talk finally about communities over time.
Any game that has lasted for
more than a few years, has relied on
either algorithmic content, like Solitaire,
or social content, and whether that's a co-op game
or an MMO or something as timeless as sports.
The content, the stimulus, doesn't come
from the basic systems, it comes from the fact
that other people are using them.
Each individual in the world is this infinite well
of potential content, and once you can harness that,
you've got the ability to generate content forever.
It's very exciting.
So how do we make relationships form?
There was a great report out of Project Horseshoe this year
that broke down some of the fundamental pillars
of friendship.
I highly recommend that you read it.
It's based on some psychology studies from the 1950s
that have held up over time, which is always exciting.
The first thing that you need is proximity.
So this means people need to see each other frequently.
So if you've got millions and millions of players,
you need to find a way to shard or subsection
your player set so that people encounter
each other again and again.
When people start to recognize each other,
that builds affinity.
The next thing is similarity.
So this means I need some form of self-expression
that other people can relate to.
This can be as simple as something like Team Mystic
or Valorant Pokemon, and it goes all the way down
to kind of complex badges and signaling tools and,
user customization.
The next thing is reciprocity.
So we need to be able to form a symbiotic relationship,
which means I can do something for you,
you can do something for me.
This doesn't need to be item exchanges.
This is something as simple as a chat window.
I don't know how excited you guys get
when you're talking to someone that you love
or respect and admire,
and you see the little dots in Gchat start to move.
That's very exciting.
That's a form of anticipation and stimulus.
And then the final pillar is this idea of disclosure.
which essentially means that I can take risks with you.
I can express more of myself with you.
And those are some of the underpinnings
for things like trust and compassion and empathy,
which should be familiar as things
that create longer-term relationships.
Now, before we can do any of those,
we have to be able to communicate.
Essentially, if people can't communicate
their ideas and their feelings in your game,
they're not going to be able to build complex relationships.
It doesn't matter if this is private messages,
message boards, chat rooms.
The ability to communicate is a fundamental necessity.
And if you can get that into your game,
the less people are going to turn to outside services,
which means the more your game becomes less of an activity
and more of a place to hang out, relax, and exist together.
Once you've got that underlying foundation,
you can start to look for signs of societies,
and it turns out they look a lot like real life.
You have social activities, cultural activities,
economic activities.
And the great news is that you don't need to build
incredibly complex systems in order to evoke
some of these social behaviors.
We as social creatures inherently tend to produce these
even with basic systems.
As soon as you have a power curve, for instance,
you can start getting different political elements.
If I am more powerful than you,
I can exert some sort of will or force.
I can lead you.
As soon as you get public spaces
and the ability for self-expression,
you start getting cultural elements, aesthetics, fashions.
If people can proclaim things in chat,
you start getting morality and belief systems.
As soon as you have item exchange,
you start getting economies.
You can do charity, banking, investment.
And as soon as you have some form of player customization,
you start getting things like group identities,
specializations, celebrities that you recognize.
And these are all really, really cool things.
But what's that kind of through line?
If we look at player customization,
and I hope that it's bright enough here,
what this guild has done is they've all worn
a black tabard with some yellow pixels on it.
But those aren't just yellow pixels for this group.
Those yellow pixels imply a shared history,
a shared set of values, shared trust and understanding.
Those yellow pixels have meaning.
Meaning means that an item has greater value or greater
importance than what the raw materials imply.
Meaning is psychological value, not physical value,
in the same way that attention is our psychological energy
as opposed to our physical energy.
So to create meaning, players must invest time
and attention into something.
And if they do that together,
it works as a sort of multiplier.
That's why we have religion
and why we love our countries, sometimes.
And so if we want attention,
one of the best and healthiest ways that we can get it
is to enable social structures that generate meaning.
This creates this beautiful upward spiral.
Meaning begets attention, which generates more meaning.
And once you have that escalation,
you have the best underlying foundation
for increased engagement over time.
Meaning enriches life.
It's this innate human need.
And the more we can facilitate it,
the longer our product is going to last.
This is the reason that Facebook is still going.
We fill it with meaning.
We fill it with our friends and our photographs,
our idle chatter.
We fill it with memories and little anecdotes.
We fill it with meaning,
and that investment is very hard to leave behind.
When we give something our time and attention,
when we create meaning together with someone,
and when we're treated with respect and love in return,
that's the true recipe for long-term relationships.
So please be good.
Earn the attention of your players.
Don't demand it.
Be trustworthy.
Communicate clearly and transparently with your players.
Find a balance in the relationship
that works for both of you.
Be farsighted.
Don't follow these short-term spikes,
and don't believe in the long-term success
of malicious interaction patterns.
Plan a journey that's going to last for years.
And for the love of God, please do better.
As we design games that can last for years,
we need to migrate from being storytellers
and content creators into engineers of new societies.
Societies where people trust each other,
or at least know the risks of wandering into wild territory.
Societies where people can play together
and challenge each other and unite together
to form these complex social structures.
We need to be architects, city planners, psychologists,
and anthropologists.
And we need to look towards the horizon
instead of staring at our feet.
We live in an engagement economy,
whether we like that or not.
Attention is our coin.
So please be mindful of where you spend yours
and what you're incentivizing.
When you spend your attention, you
are literally paying attention.
And people are going to use that value that they get from you.
And please be honorable to those that you
ask for their attention.
Our society right now is a reflection of the systems
that we've created.
So go and create systems that are better.
Create systems that are going to help our world thrive,
not just right now, but over time.
Thank you.