Thank you very much.
Welcome to Designing Great Interactive Narrative on Mobile
with these brilliant people.
Ironically, I do need to ask you, first of all,
to turn off the sound on your mobile phones
and just make sure that we're not
interrupting them in their flow.
Questions, we'll have a little bit of time at the end,
but first of all, I'm gonna ask them to introduce themselves
and to brag about a bit of work
that they're really proud of, starting with Cass.
You said you were gonna ask that question
and I totally didn't prepare.
Hey guys, I'm Cass. I'm a director of story at Episode.
For the people that don't know, that's an interactive narrative platform
where we both create interactive stories for free-to-play mobile games,
but we also open our platform for writers to create their own content.
I think I'm actually probably the most proud of is that we are an open platform and I joined
the team right when that was being discussed and kind of helped figure out how to make
it open and how to make sure that everything that we created was something that we could
put live to anyone who wanted to play with it.
So I'm relatively proud to have worked on something that isn't closed.
It's open to anyone who wants to make games.
And I know personally about a dozen women around the world who now make a full-time
living making games on episode, which is cool.
Pretty proud of that.
Hi guys, I'm Marisa. I work for Big Fish Games in a small studio called 3 Minute Games, and
I manage the Lifeline brand. So I think the thing that I'm most proud of is the fact that
Lifeline has been a jumping off platform for several authors. We started with a very small
number and we've now expanded and so similar to what Cass was saying as
It's really nice to be able to help people who have an idea and have the capabilities,
have the tools and the platform to be able to get out there and do that.
So that's what I'm excited about.
Hi, I'm Jon Ingold.
I'm the narrative director of Inkle and one of the two co-founders of it.
I guess the thing we're most proud of is the fact that six years ago we started a company
to make interactive fiction and we're still doing it successfully with even more people
than we originally started with.
But artistically, I'm most proud of probably writing the Sorcery series, which I was the
sole writer on, apart from a little bit of help from a guy called Graham Robertson on part four.
But I also co-wrote a lot of 80 Days and was the narrative director on that,
which is the one that everyone's heard of.
One thing we had a discussion about when we were planning for this talk is what we actually mean by interactive narrative because there's so many different ways that it can be used in gaming.
We actually came up with stories where players get to make an active decision about what happens next, but that's still a really wide field.
So starting with John at the end, could you just explain what it means and how you use it in your game specifically?
So, like, an interactive narrative...
for me has got to be more than the sum of its parts.
It's not enough to be something which has interaction within it.
I've seen the phrase used to describe stories with videos in,
and I don't see that as fitting under the mandate of interactive narrative
because it's not good enough.
And I've seen interactive games where you do get to make little choices, but the narrative
is so under the control of the author, it's so within that authorial scope, that as a
player I don't actually feel like I'm really there for any great reason, and that to me
fails as well.
So I think when we're trying to make interactive narrative, what we're really trying to do
is make a playable story which has a huge amount of player freedom.
within it and
So I tend to be looking for stories that allow the player to make
Discoveries and to have a sense of discovery and a sense of ownership over what they discover within that story
That couples with a sense of responsibility
so ideally a player playing one of our games is usually thinking what have I done and
and worrying that they might have got it wrong.
That slight sense of stress is incredibly important to me.
I think my job as a game designer is the same as my job
as a writer, which is to manage tension in the audience.
So for me, interactive narrative is a way
to generate tension directly in the head of an audience
based on the worry that what they've done
is not the right thing to have done
and that the consequences of what they've done
are going to be things that they will regret later.
Every writer is a very gentle tease or a very gentle torturer,
and interactive narrative is a way to achieve that.
Marise?
Yeah, I think, you know, the key word is the active part of the definition.
You know, reading used to be something that was more of a passive activity,
and then you had choose your own adventure books come on the scene,
and then all of a sudden you were a part of the action.
And I definitely think that with Lifeline, we kind of went, we took something that was
familiar to everybody, a text message, a conversation with your friend.
And we ended up taking that and making a story out of just having a conversation.
And your active participation in that is through messaging that protagonist and convincing
them.
to either go this way or to do that thing,
hopefully not killing them.
But that does put a little punch to it.
And we're kind of expanding that now,
which is really interesting to kind of see
because now we have stories where
you are the main character in the story.
There's several ways that you can kind of do that,
but it's just giving the players,
making them players and not readers.
And that's really, I think, a big part of it.
I think an interesting thing when I think about interactive, just something that John
mentioned is how much in interactive do they need to be able to control the ending of the
story or control the direction it goes in?
I don't actually have an answer.
Versus feel like they are interacting in the experience that they're having.
I think about things like Sleep No More, the interactive theater production in New York,
and like, is that interactive fiction?
The VR game that recently came out, because they don't call it a game, Impossible Hours,
is that interactive fiction?
How much do I feel like I am in control of what's happening and interacting with what's going on?
Especially on mobile, I think we have a generation of new players right now who their life is
defined by Snapchat and their life is defined by Instagram and their life is defined by
really owning their persona and being the person that they want to be.
They're less into following celebrities, they're more into being the celebrity.
And so there's something really exciting about how games can allow people to do that and
how interactive fiction especially can allow people to do that.
And so thinking about, as you guys both said,
with taking action in it, I don't know in this room
yet if we need to create full freedom,
but we definitely need to.
Interactive fiction is creating a space
where I feel like I am in control in places I may not
be in my actual life.
I can try things I may be afraid to try in the real world.
I can explore different outcomes and see the kind of persona
that I want to be.
And having a lot of agency in my experience
is, I think, what just makes interactive fiction very
specific and very unique.
And how do you kind of reach that point in your studios?
What are your writers' rooms set ups like?
You know, what's the situation with writers and designers?
Like, John, I know you kind of do a bit of everything,
but if you could all just tell me, you know,
for the audience who may be,
haven't had the chance to work in that kind of scenario yet,
just how you set it up as part of the studio.
Well, shall I go first?
For us, it's been very much this process of scaling up
over the last six years.
First projects, the writer's room was just me.
And I was both writing it and designing the way
that the writing would be done.
So all of the content that we generated at Inkle
is done using our Ink scripting language, which
is an open source thing now.
But that was originally a very badly hacked together Perl script that I made at some point
in the weekends in order to try and generate output that Joe, my co-founder, could get
running in an app.
And it was a real piece of sticky tape and string programming.
I shouldn't be allowed to program anything, really, but there was no one else to do it,
so I did it.
One of the joys of the company though has been the ability to expand that process out and to bring in new writers.
So we worked with Meg Gyanth on 80 Days and she did a phenomenal job and really supercharged that game concept
from something that we thought could be good to something that was genuinely sort of brilliant.
And that was a real pleasure to be able to enable.
But in order to do that, we had to compartmentalize the problem.
Interactive narrative is very complicated and very open and can go in a hundred different
directions and different styles.
So when we approached 80 Days, we were able to do it because we'd just made a game called
Sorcery 2, which had a full city that you could explore and kind of backtrack in and
meet people and have episodic adventures within.
And I remember saying to Meg at the time, she said,
but isn't the world quite big?
And I said, oh, we've managed a city,
how much bigger can the world possibly be?
It turned out it was quite a lot bigger,
but it gave us a structure,
literally a format that we could write into.
Like this is a city, this is how you start a city,
this is how you end a city,
this is how you cause a change to happen
within the player's statistics, whatever.
Similarly for journeys, they had a slightly more complicated structure, but we could give her that as a template and say,
you don't need to worry about the technical stuff unless you feel like it.
If you just want to write, you can just write. Here's the format, it will work.
If you want to do something more technical, and she did, then go, this is how you can research that and produce more complex content.
We did the same thing again on Sorcery 4, where I hired Graham.
As I said, he was a junior writer who'd never written any professional content before at
all, but he was incredibly good at learning the patterns that sorcery used, which were
very, very weird and very ad hoc structures.
We're currently working on a game called Heaven's Vault, which will eventually end up on mobile
and is a somewhat more ambitious interactive narrative again.
And one of my biggest regrets on that project is that the way that we author it is so incredibly
complicated and it has taken so many iterations to get right that I haven't been able to bring
in any other writers because I keep changing my mind on how to write it.
Which is to say, I think the writers room for Heaven's Vault 2 will be a phenomenally
brilliant place that I'm really looking forward to getting to, but we have to get through
the first version first.
So from us, it's really quite technical actually and it's really not very political.
Mostly once we have a writer, we just tell them to get on with it and be brilliant and edit it when it's not.
Kassimarie, so how is it for you guys? What's the kind of setup in your studios?
Pretty similar. It started very small for us as well.
The original Lifeline was made by one author, one game designer who also doubled as a producer, one artist and one programmer.
And so it was just four people with a singular vision kind of sitting down and making that happen.
And then we started growing immediately after the success of that first game.
And now we added a few more authors, and then the producers started working on our style guide.
We have an awesome narrative design team.
And then, really internally, we're just there to support the narratives and the authorship
that goes on externally, outside of our company.
So we have the rule set that we write, and we're able to take care of the technical stuff.
We'll chime in every now and again, and it's often in regards to making it more of a game
and pacing and things of that nature, but when it comes to the content, we just give
you kind of the platform or the tools, we give you the canvas, and you make the painting,
so to speak.
Yeah, it's interesting. For an episode, I think we took a lot. It's a little bit different.
We took a lot from the TV world. A lot of our lead writers are from a TV background.
We start before we go into a project, we ask a couple of key questions. One of those is,
is this a world our players want to play in? So when we're reading pitches, we're thinking
about there are some pitches that if they're a TV show, they sound great.
But I want to ask, especially on mobile, especially in free-to-play, do my players want to play
in this world?
A second question is, is the act of adding agency what makes it special?
Essentially, we don't have HBO's budget.
We can't invest.
whatever they're doing, $100 million in an episode.
So what we do have is this ability to have interactivity.
So we will ask this question of like,
hey, even though we don't have HBO's production budget,
does interactivity make this feel great?
The answer to both those questions obviously has to be yes.
Um, at that moment we do, do, usually the lead, uh, creator, the showrunner, will start
developing out an outline in a rough pitch, usually with a product manager to make sure
that scope feels kind of appropriate.
When we have those two things down, we'll move into a room.
Uh, usually our rooms are about a week long, and they're focused very much on getting the
core beats of the story down, um, and asking key questions like, what are the key choices
that we want people to be able to make in this story?
And where are the moments that this is really gonna matter?
We aren't thinking too much about small branches.
at that moment. Um, usually in that room, there's the showrunner, uh, and then there's a,
like, supporting cast, usually a writer, and then someone who supports the showrunner's
weaknesses. So our showrunners can be people like me, who's a little more game design
background, but not narrative linear storytelling, in which case my co-person in the room
would be someone with more of a linear TV background. Uh, if we have one of our more
linear TV people showrunning it, I might come into the room to support, um...
and our rooms run for about a week.
At the end of them, the hope is to get a very rough outline.
That said, usually we'll then dive deep on a vertical slice
and do a single episode and just see how it's performing
to understand if we want to invest more.
And for people in the audience who might be kind of aspiring writers or looking to get into this kind of type of game work,
what are some of the key skills or things that people can be developing now that you're going to be looking for when they come knocking on your door for a job?
Kath, we start with you.
I'm starting. You should have Marisa start, she hasn't started yet.
Um, I'm looking for you, writing now, especially with tools like Inkle, with Episode, uh, it's
so easy to go and make a thing. Like if anyone in this room is a writer and hasn't finished
a thing, you can send one of us, go finish it. It's not, it's really not hard to write.
Um, so the number one thing is just be writing. Um, be writing things that
are interactive, that I make great choices.
Think about how the choices feel.
I wanna see, I'm actually more impressed
if you write something short and simple and easy to digest,
but where every single beat feels
like you really thought it out.
You were like, I want them to feel this way
because of this choice.
I've thought about how big the choice space is,
how much variety and diversity it includes.
Um, so that's my biggest thing, is like, create works, create short works, create works where
it feels like every beat is really highly crafted.
Um, for episodes specifically, uh, because this can be a mildly controversial thing,
I love the idea of freemium.
I think freemium has done some things poorly in the past, but I am so excited for how it
can let people get into the game, how we can think about how to empower tons of people
to be able to engage in a medium that used to feel very, very niche.
So if you're going to apply for episode, you probably need to enjoy freemium.
Don't worry, we will get to that discussion.
I know Marisa has a lot to say on this, so I'm going to make John go first.
Yeah, I mean, we don't receive very many pitches from writers, or rather, we don't read very
many pitches from writers.
We get quite a few, but we tend to shut them down quite quickly because we're not in a
position to offer that employment and I don't want to waste people's time.
But the stuff that I have seen, I'd actually, I think I'd echo a lot of what Cass said,
that firstly, you've got to finish stuff.
I don't care about how good your ideas are if you can't finish something.
Finishing is the key skill to being a writer, because actually your first thing is going
to be rubbish, even if you're very, very talented.
Your fourth thing is going to be worth reading, but you won't get there if you keep working
on your first thing.
So if that's who you are, then you're a hobbyist and you're not a professional.
And that's a horrible thing to say, but it's true, and I know it's true, because I'm 36,
and in my 20s I did not have a successful writing job, and that's why.
Right?
Once you finish something, and I think something short is a good idea if you want to be sending it to people who are busy and like don't have much time to get into your world, your characters, we're not going to be very interested in reading a Tolkien-esque fantasy world with a million people in it.
Actually, what I'd like to see, if I ever see a pitch, is two people having a convincing conversation about a single topic.
because that's incredibly hard to write interactively.
It's actually quite easy to write linearly.
And when we see that kind of pitch,
often what we see is a linear story
with some arbitrary choices thrown in
that don't make any difference, which is a fail.
But it's a really clear, clean, easy to digest fail.
So I appreciate that when people send that to me
because I can read it and go,
yep, no, definitely failed, won't give you a job,
thank you very much.
That was a great interaction from my point of view.
Not from yours.
But it is a challenge which if you accept and win,
then I think that can be really convincing.
So, when we hired Meg, I read one of her independent pieces of interactive writing.
I think she has only done one, and I read it, and it very cleverly used the constraints
of the system that it was written in.
It's written in Story Nexus, which was built by Fail Better Games, who made Sunless Sea
and Fallen London, which is...
They're friends, but it is not the most elegant platform to write for, shall we say.
It is somewhat difficult to tame into the structure that you want to apply.
And what she managed to do with her piece called Samsara was build something which very cleverly exploited the weaknesses of Story Nexus
to make something which was simple, effective, but really easy to understand.
Also, it was beautifully written. And that was why we hired her. That's why we gave her a writing sample.
The writing sample we gave her was we said,
go and take this thing called Inkle Writer,
which was like a proto-web version of Ink,
which doesn't let you do anything apart from choices,
and write us a short scene.
And she managed to use her words so well
that reading that scene was a pleasure and full of delight.
The pacing was all wrong,
the length of the paragraphs was all wrong,
but it had some jokes in it,
it had some style to it,
it had some voice to it,
and that was enough to convince me
that she could take on what proved
to be the most significant project that we'd done,
with absolutely no other proof that she could.
deliver something or that she was going to be good at research or any of these things apart from the fact that I knew her
and liked her.
And similarly with Graham when we hired Graham,
he, I met him on a writing course actually, but he was producing a piece of work which was technically very intricate
and that was kind of his focus, but the writing was solid.
But the way that it used the writing interactively was really interesting and you don't often see that from new up-and-coming writers.
A sense of command of the craft.
of the technical craft. I'm quite a technical writer so I really respected that
and I'm really glad we gave him the chance that we did on Sorcery 4.
So yeah I think that's probably it.
It's probably about pitching to the studio correctly though. Inkle is always
going to be a slightly technical place
because the mindsets of Joe and I who founded it. We like doing cunning things
with narratives so if you're pitching to us we want to see some cunning things
but we're also very soulful people so we like human beings
in our stories. And I think you have to find out
who you're pitching to and research that company.
Yeah, that's great advice.
I would say the first thing you should do
is go out and get something that enables you
to write interactive fiction.
Grab the Engel open source platform.
Go to Episode and make something there, or grab Twine.
Twine is an open source free platform
that a lot of users use, and that jumps right off
into my next point, which is find a community
of people who are also doing it.
get to know people around you who are working in interactive fiction.
One thing we learned very early on is that there's a bit of a barrier to entry for the normal writer,
not to say that in like a grouping way, but just somebody who's used to writing a book,
or a short story, or that format, may not have a good time writing interactive fiction.
there's a new rule set and so you have to be aware of that.
And so just getting in there and as both of my fellow panelists have said,
start writing something.
So definitely be aware of also the fact that you're going to have to plan quite a bit
if you want to write something good.
You're going to have to make flow charts.
You're going to have to do a story map.
You're going to have to do decision trees.
You're going to have to keep track of multiple variables
and multiple endings often.
So definitely stay organized as best as you can.
And if you don't have a way to do that yet, figure it out.
And so that's another step as well.
I definitely think you have to have a willingness to iterate.
It's something where.
you're not going to get it right the first time out the gate, I guarantee it.
And having the humility to accept that we all have room for growth is definitely a great
quality for somebody who's going to be a good writer, especially of interactive fiction.
I think we're pretty similar in that it doesn't hurt to have a technical mind or to understand
the technical side of how these games are built.
Maybe go grab some and see if you can take them apart, you know, work backwards.
and figure out why things are happening the way they are and why they're working. Um,
and then make yourself the user. Uh, think about it as a player and definitely, um, you
know, if you would ra- would you rather read a lot of exposition or would you rather, you
Learn that by doing and answering questions and being active in the story.
You can learn a lot when you stop and think about it as a player.
So play your stuff often. You are your own best play tester.
Or get it in front of other people.
That's the great thing about a Twine community is that you can put that stuff out there
and you can get feedback on it almost instantaneously.
Um, we've worked with an awesome resource, Emily Short, she has a great blog, some of
you are probably familiar with her in this room.
Uh, go check it out because she will hook you up with some of the tools that you need
to do this and she'll also give you some of that sense of community.
And then send it to Episodes, send it to us, send it to Inkle and, you know, we'll work
with you and we'll give you feedback.
We're not gonna just leave you guys hanging, so we'll let you know what is working, what
may not be working.
And we can hopefully help you guys move to that next level.
Something I realized to jump in,
because it's also, we're talking about mobile
very specifically, I think if you're looking
at mobile very specifically, you should also be thinking,
and I know we chatted earlier,
so you guys were on the same page, about pace.
Biggest problem I get in pitches is pace.
Immobile is fast.
You've got five seconds.
So how are you getting me hooked in seconds?
A great exercise that I actually ask people about
in my interviews, if you're in an interview with me,
have a prep dancer, is how are you gonna convert
something that was a TV show onto a mobile phone?
If your answer is just like, oh, I'm going to cut some things down, that's wrong.
So think about that you've got this tiny screen, what are you focusing on, what's important
to the character.
If you think you're going to tell the war scenes from Lord of the Rings on a mobile
phone, I'm going to argue with you that you are wrong.
You're probably not.
So how are you going to tell those scenes?
What do they feel like on mobile?
So when you're thinking very specifically with our title on mobile, think about your
pace and think about that device that you're building for and challenge yourself to create
something that was on TV or something that was a movie.
think about how you actively have to change that to make it feel like it's right for mobile.
That'll give you a good set of things to work with.
That's definitely, you know, we wanted to move on to the mobile part.
So, I mean, you brought up some of the great kind of challenges that all mobile games have,
which is pacing, the amount of time a player's going to spend, all the other sort of things
that they could be doing on their mobile phone at that time.
So how do you guys...
change the way that you tell your stories or adapt your narratives so that they do fit that kind of mobile world
and what are some of the things that maybe people haven't thought of when it comes to making great narrative for mobile
and who wants to go first?
I'll jump in because I was going to jump in on exactly that point anyway.
I think one thing that people often don't realize is how incredibly tight the word limits
are on mobile.
I remember talking to Jonathan Myers who was the, I guess, the show runner on the Game
of Thrones mobile app, which was about five years old now, I think.
And he said that his quests were built out of three beats.
The first one was, the first beat of the story was allowed, I think this is right, I think
it was 20 words.
The second beat was allowed 15 words, and the final beat, if you got through it, was allowed 25.
And that was the entire delivery system for the narrative.
And he said every single one of his writers said,
this is stupid, we can't do this.
And his reply would be, yep, yep, you can.
And it was very successful, and it was very popular.
Because you just have to find the rhythm, and you have to find the kind of words,
and the kind of language that fits that,
because that's your job as a writer, is to write to spec.
That's not really any different than writing for the theater or writing for the screen,
which is completely different than writing for the theater, even though it's still people
talking.
And I think that applies to all of our products, even though they're completely different shapes.
Like a lot of my time on 80 Days was spent taking beautiful, long paragraphs of prose
that Meg had written and chopping them in three.
because she tended to enjoy writing a little bit too much.
And so I'd have to put them behind a choice and pace it out
because the pacing is the most important part of that experience.
And I think that really ties into that question
of what the user could otherwise be doing on their phone.
If you're trying to get someone to read something on a phone,
you are competing directly with Twitter.
Now the thing about Twitter is you can read everything on Twitter by accident, and now
it's all awful and you don't want to read any of it, but that just is why you keep scrolling
and looking in the desperate hope of finding something good.
So it's actually not that bad to be better than Twitter.
Everything I write is better than anything you read on Twitter with a very small percentage
error, right?
That's statistically, that's basically true.
But I have to make sure that you actually read what I write.
So if I'm writing things which are shorter than things on Twitter...
then I'm probably gonna win that argument.
But then they introduced videos and images,
and that's a bit of a problem.
So suddenly you have to upscale
and make sure that you're attractive
and visual as well, whatever.
that sense that you are writing words in a hurricane of information to people who do read.
Everybody reads all the time. We read a tremendous amount. The idea that we cannot read is ludicrous.
It's utterly wrong. But people don't read much. They read a couple of words and then they move on
and you have to be able to get people in a couple of words, which is, yeah, it's pretty hard.
Well, and it's funny because Twitter is actually kind of a good tool.
Because if you put everything that you write into Twitter, does it fit or does it go over
your character count?
Also, would it be engaging?
Would people actually want to interact with what you just said?
That's actually a pretty good litmus test for what you're doing when you're writing
an interactive fiction.
Also, you know, think about what people are doing when they're playing on the mobile devices.
They're often doing it in interspersed throughout their day where, you know, they've got a few
moments and then they can kind of sit down and they can do something different and get
their mind off of the rigmarole of daily life.
We've done surveys and Google actually did their own survey
and shared with us that our findings were the same, which
is a lot of people play apps that involve interactive
fiction before bed.
It's the prime time for that.
And it's when you want to wind down.
It's when you want to have a few moments to yourself,
get a cup of tea or get a cup of whatever
might help you get to bed, a cup of warm milk.
And you just want to let go of everything
that happened during the day.
That's going to be a different story
than if you want to amp somebody up
and you want to make them feel really intense.
So definitely think about the application
of where they're playing and how they're playing.
Um, and also the thing about mobile is that immersion can be more difficult if you're
playing things in large, er, small chunks rather than a large swath where you sit down
and play the whole thing.
Uh, so, you know, it's one of those things where if you can do things to make the player
suck them in, uh, you don't know when they're going to come into your game, so you have
to be thinking about that at every point along the way.
And so you should be writing something that should, could always pull them in and make
them immersed.
Yeah.
Um, one really good trick is to ask their name at the beginning of your game and then
just like when you're active listening, keep repeating it back to them.
Hey, player name, how do you feel today?
I'm going to respond to you directly.
I'm immediately sucked in and I feel like it's my personal experience rather than an
experience that some random Joe on the street might be having as well.
that we've started doing a little related to the active listening. We'll look at the
first 50 lines in a story that we're about to put out and we'll literally just take one
line and show it to a random person on our team. And we'll say, is this interesting,
do you want to keep reading? And they have no context at all. They have no idea what
the story's about, who it is, why they're talking to, who they're talking to. This idea
being that a player may leave at any moment and then come back at the next moment.
and they should have a line on screen
that makes them lean in.
They may have even forgotten everything that happened before
because, oh my gosh, how many things
have you read online today that you can't remember
in this room right now?
And so we want to make sure that that line tells a story by itself.
We'd love to do this with every line in our stories.
That's thousands.
So we at least focus in that on those first like 50 to 100,
we are showing them by themselves to people
and just making sure that they all tell a story,
they all ask a question, and they all make me lean in
and want to come back.
So that's kind of just a major kind of thing with mobile
to be thinking about is how engaged
and how you get those people back.
I think your point on when they're playing is important to recognize with mobile.
A premium versus a freemium app they're playing for different reasons, when they're playing
it, why they're playing it.
Just make sure you know your audience really well.
Kind of own who your audience is.
If you think your audience is everyone who likes interactive fiction, maybe that worked
20 years ago when we were a small niche community.
It doesn't anymore.
So think about who very specifically are you writing for and then don't worry about everybody
else.
Get your story out to that person and know who they are and know how to reach them.
and then kind of grow up from there.
And how do you guys kind of deal with,
because I know there's very different products,
but giving people the catharsis of an ending
but then trying to make sure they still
come back at some point.
John, I know it's different for you
because your games have sort of specific endings.
So yeah, how do you guys that are sort of
dealing with episodic make sure that
people are getting that satisfaction
but then have a reason to keep going as well?
My short answer is we don't.
We are episodic content.
We do want to make sure, if you guys ever watched Lost,
one of my criticisms of Lost is it made me feel like
I asked more questions that I got answered.
So we are thinking about in the crafting of every episode,
we think about what's my goal this episode,
what are my stakes around that goal,
and have I accomplished it by the end
based on choices I've made throughout the episode.
And so we ask those three questions with every episode we put out, so that at the end of
the episode, you hopefully have a feeling of like, cool, I learned a thing, my choices
changed something.
But we also then like hyper-focus on that cliffhanger and make sure you have a reason
to want to come back.
We do think about things seasonally, we generally do 12 to 15 episodes seasons.
We write a season expecting there not to be a sequel.
We don't do a lot of sequels.
So we do write being like, cool, you're going to have some crazy ending, maybe you've got
six crazy endings, maybe different characters feel differently about you, and if we have
to write a sequel, that'll be a problem for another day, because we know that if you got
this far, we want you to feel great.
That said, we've looked at our data, I know Microsoft did a thing about data, most of
your players are actually not going to finish your story.
Uh, so now your goal is just to make them feel really great.
while they're playing your story, and then hopefully at that moment that they're about
to leave, get them into one of your other stories, because they're just not going to
finish.
The percentage of people that finish our games is really sadly low.
If you actually want those stats, I can probably send them to you privately.
I wasn't allowed to project them.
But yeah, so just pretend that it's always a great ending, and then get them into something
else.
Yeah, I think that point about people not finishing is really important actually, and that's something that we see a lot in general across all video games.
People don't finish them, but it doesn't mean that people are unhappy.
Most of the games that you will tell your friends, oh, I really love this game, that will be a game that you kind of mean to finish, but you haven't quite got back to yet.
And every passing day you forget how it works, and you found something else, and you drift off.
which is kind of the same as reading books, actually.
Certainly as a kid I used to have a huge stack of books
which were half-read, which I like,
and I'm still reading now,
but I haven't picked up in about 25 years
and I have no idea what they're about.
I mean, our games are very different
than the freemium rolling season model, obviously,
but we still think about this stuff a lot,
particularly at the end of 80 Days,
we deliberately wanted to make a game that was replayable.
So at the very, very end,
the last line of the...
of the story is pretty much Fogg saying, right, let's go again.
Then the app resets.
It puts you in London straightaway.
It flashes at you and it asks you to just tap that London button so that you've already
started your second journey before you get a chance to close the app down.
That's a very deliberate piece of fast flow.
There isn't an option that says, do you want to start another game?
It just does that straightaway.
That said, we didn't expect anyone to actually replay it.
What we thought people would do would be to finish 80 days.
restart their next story, see that they could restart the next story, see that the opening of the story was slightly more efficient than
it had been the first time around because it was responding to the fact that this was their second journey, say,
huh, that's really neat. This game is replayable, and then put it away and never play it again.
Because that's a great place to leave a player, not with the catharsis of a happy, satisfied ending,
not coming out and whooping and punching the air, but saying,
I'm in the middle of an interesting journey that I'm never going to go back to.
That's kind of the best way to leave a player, just as it is for all other video games.
Like, my favorite game in the world is Shadow of the Colossus.
I am still in the middle of that game. I've been in the middle of it four times now.
And I love it. It's great. And that is the happiest place.
I don't necessarily need to see the ending of it at all.
That said, for Sorcery, which was four connected games, the first three parts we really needed to get people through to the end if we could because we wanted them to buy the sequel.
So that was a really interesting challenge. The first game was very quick and pushed you forward. We got a lot of complaints that it was too short.
The second game we made very long to fight those complaints. A lot of people didn't finish it and that was really a problem.
even though we did put a lot of trapdoors in that said pretty much
are you sick of playing this game here's an ending so you can play part three in
a year's time
but a lot of people said no that would be that would be cheating so they didn't do it
which is a bit of a shame
And then part four was an ending, and that was a real pleasure, because we just made it brutally difficult.
Because we could. Because if you actually care, well, you're gonna stick with it.
And if you don't care, I don't really care where you stop playing Sorcery 4 at all.
It doesn't matter to me in the slightest.
Perhaps that's why Sorcery 4 didn't sell as well as the others. I don't know.
But I think that's okay, because probably when it came out, we sold a lot of copies of Sorcery 1, and that's just how it goes.
Yeah, um, we're kind of in an interesting phase right now where Lifeline has, uh, historically
been a premium product, uh, where you paid up front to get the whole game and, uh, we
could kind of relax and not worry so much if you left the app, but we were running into
the same thing that Inkle, uh, ran into, which is how do you get those people back?
Where are they and how do you communicate with them when you have a sequel?
Because, you know, it takes time to develop these and so not having them around and not
having an open line of communication to them is very difficult.
So that decision kind of was a really big catalyst for us to move into the world of
freemium.
We're still learning quite a bit, but what we're really excited about is that we do get the chance to bring them back regularly
and give them these small snippets of a story, and so you might find a chapter that you like, you might find a story that doesn't really resonate with you.
What we do know is that players are very, very focused on a specific genre.
So you want to have a nice kind of smattering of different genres available,
otherwise, you know, players aren't going to have anything to do, essentially.
But, you know, replayability can definitely keep them in a specific story that they like a lot.
And, you know, everybody will kind of find their favorite, and they might come back to it time and time again.
It's like a security blanket.
So we try to make something that might resonate, even if it resonates with a small group of people, then it's done its job.
We also, you know, kind of make it matter a little bit by putting some dead ends in there.
You know, a lot of people come up to me and tell me how many times they've killed Taylor in the original Lifeline games.
Um, you know, and it's kind of a fun little stat and a way to interact with it that's
personal to you.
It's your own personal journey.
Um, so, you know, we're just trying to take what we knew worked for a larger scale game
and we're trying to drive it down into a smaller scale.
And um, those story bumps I mentioned earlier are a huge tool that you can use to make sure
that each one of your chapters is kind of hitting those points that you want it to.
Um, and then we kind of do a cliffhanger bottleneck.
at the end of each of our chapters to just give a little bit of a,
uh, don't you want to come back next time and see what happens next?
So it doesn't hurt us if our players do play all the way to the end. We definitely
wouldn't complain, I think, either on the freemium or the premium side, but,
um, you know, uh, just try and have content that
they can have choices in multiple genres that they can choose
from if they don't resonate with something you're writing.
Yeah, Cass, I know you sort of mentioned earlier that you like how accessible Freemium makes things,
and I didn't know if you could talk a bit more about that and just how you guys sort of make the most of that area that you're working in.
Yeah, um, I think freemium, it obviously, and I know especially in this audience, it has like
its little claws you have to be careful of, um, but I've loved with freemium just the audience
that we're able to reach. Um, I, my 13 year old niece now loves interactive fiction. She would
never have loved interactive fiction if there weren't freemium games on the market. She
wouldn't have known how to pick up a RemPi game, she wouldn't have known how to download
something from the Steam store, just cause she didn't, her peers weren't in those areas, she
didn't, people weren't engaging that, that wasn't the niece she was in in school.
So something I've loved about Freemium is the accessibility that it gives this industry.
It also does make a lot of money, which allows us to pay a lot of writers and allows us to
get a lot of great people.
support for the writing they're doing. We welcome writers to be working on side projects,
that's awesome. Um, and so just the ability to keep feeding this industry, to keep exploring
it, to keep understanding how we do it. I also think freemium right now is literally
freemium storytelling on mobile is at level one. Um, essentially it started taking off
four years ago when episode launched and that was just...
v1, I'm excited to see what the next version is. I don't think it's necessarily exactly how it
looks right now. Um, so I think this idea of like that you can reach a whole new audience with
freemium, um, this idea that they can play kind of no handcuffs on, uh, they can just come in and
dabble and see what it's like, um, and how successful it's taking off and how big it's
making this industry, um, makes me pretty excited.
Um, the major thing you do have to think about that I think a lot of us have probably gotten
wrong, I'll own that we have it wrong occasionally as well, is that freemium means you really
have to make them want to pay for it, uh, because they don't have to.
This isn't something where they're spending $10 and then giving you that $10 to essentially
go along on this journey with you.
they'll leave whenever they want to. Um, I think a lot of games, uh, make that mistake where
they're like, cool, we assume that you're enjoying this, pay us $10, pay us $10, pay us $10 now.
You need $10 to pass this thing. And so it's balancing that line of making sure that they are
loving your story enough to want to pay for it and they don't feel bad if they don't pay for it.
They still have a really great experience while you're allowing them to essentially have an
even greater experience through paying. Um, and that's a really tough line.
that I'm also just excited to see more people start bending and playing with and understanding
how can I essentially, because all of us essentially are, well not all of us, some of you are indie
which is great, I love that you have the ability to release your games entirely for free, but
many of us are in some way asking players for money, be it money up front or money while
playing and so just continuing to explore how we do that in a way that feels good, that
leaves players feeling satisfied, that leaves them really happy with our experiences, that's
I guess why I'm excited about Freemium and I would love to see more interactive fiction
people kind of.
Dabbling in that space. Yeah, and is that changed your mind? Are you know?
Okay, I'm two sides of a coin. Yeah. I mean, yeah, they're very much. I love your games. Thank you
They're very much different. I love your games, too
they're very much different camps, but I I
mean the complaints that a premium developer has against freemium
game design, you know, they're fairly straightforward, they're fairly obvious, they're not controversial.
You are designing with the pay point in mind the whole time. It obviously limits the kind
of experiences you can create, not in a, you know, drastic way necessarily, but, well,
I don't mean, not necessarily in a good way or a bad way, but rather necessarily in a
drastic way. Like, there are certain games you just can't make in freemium because you
can't get the monetization right, so you just don't make them. Well, okay, so it's a slightly
limited space in that respect. Um...
I think the thing that I love about the premium market is also the thing that makes me incredibly
jealous of the freemium market though.
To run a freemium system you need a lot of people paying a lot of attention to the monetization
all the time.
You need to be thinking about how to get your game in front of users all the time.
It is a service industry so you need to be providing an active service the whole time.
The general story of indies who try freemium is that they fail utterly because they don't realize that they need to be doing this.
They assume that they can release a game for free and the users will just find them, which of course they don't.
And they get completely demolished by the industrial scale freemium developers who have the time, the effort, the people and the resources to...
divert all of the attention towards their own products and keep people there. Remember, Freemium is a system that relies on capturing people,
which means they're not floating around in the marketplace for anyone else to collect.
So as an indie developer, Freemium is essentially closed to us. And I don't mind that,
particularly, but I am jealous of
the amount of money that it makes and the amount of writers that it allows you to support and the amount of production value that
it allows you to support. That would be a wonderful thing.
but I know that it's a bit of a poisoned chalice,
or at least it's a nice looking flower
with a huge root system below it, right?
And anyway, what we do is we create.
to
the table.
and when we release Heaven's Vault there will be one game like Heaven's Vault.
And there is sort of a few games that are like Sorcery,
and in a sense I think that's why Sorcery didn't do quite as well,
is that people look at it and go,
oh, I've played that before.
The reality is, actually you really haven't.
There is no game like Sorcery particularly either,
but it's more subtle why it's different.
And I think what I love about premium is that you can produce completely unique games with
beginning, middle and end.
They're like nothing else and then go away and make another one.
And so long as you don't employ too many people or take too long to do it, that's perfectly
financially viable and it lets us do all the experimentation we want.
it just means that we're a bit lonely because there's only eight of us in a room.
And like it would be lovely if I had a writer's room of 20 people, but as far as I see that,
I see that as a problem with the audience. Like you guys need to just be more interested
and interested in interactive fiction. We're doing the best we can, where are you? So I would
like to thrust all of that responsibility onto you lot and take none of it myself,
and that's my strategy for dealing with it.
I think there's something fun too about like freemium can help that, it's like, I love
that I can now send my 13 year old niece to Ingle Games and be like, look, now you know
what this is.
Go play it.
Right.
Maybe what we need to do is we need to start advertising in your games.
Bored of this?
Think it's repetitive?
Come and play an Ingle game.
Thank you.
Bye.
Well we can do the flip, like if this is a little too hard for you or you're getting a little lost, we're here to entertain you at night while you're trying to fall asleep.
It is a terrible shame that we don't get the audience draw that a freemium product can have.
I did a talk at a high school in Cambridge the other week.
and they've had a copy of 80 Days in their library for three weeks, and I started off saying,
you know, okay, so, show of hands if you've played 80 Days. Not a single hand went up,
but one 10-year-old said,
it costs five pounds, so I didn't play it. And I said, it's in the library.
And they said, oh. And,
like, I can't even
get them to play the game when it is free, because it was in another room.
And so the amount of friction there is really quite high.
And these are kids who are interested.
They're in the coding club or whatever.
So I would love to get more people playing the games, but
somehow I don't think going free is the
solution for us for that.
I would like to argue the point though that it is a lot about timing.
The reason that our original Lifeline was successful had a lot to do with the fact that
we saw that Apple Watch was launching and we were, you know, we saw that we had a story
that basically fit that format.
It was small, very bite-sized, it was a conversation, it was something you could play on the go
and so we converted it and as a result we did get featuring from Apple because we were
on one of their products that they were really excited about.
I would say that, you know, Inkle came along in what I would say the heyday of the App
Store.
There were a lot less devs out there, a lot less noise.
And so it allowed some really great products because, you know, Inkle is, you know, I love
Sorcery.
I'm a huge fan.
And the fact that it was in the right time where it could be seen and it could be featured
from Apple because their editorial team would see it, that was huge.
And that probably is a big part of the success.
Now we've kind of shifted over to this free to play side of things, but I kind of want
to issue a life raft to all of you guys out there who might be authors who are interested
in this, is the fact that now it's not, it's okay to work with a publisher.
It's okay to work with somebody who can do all of the stuff that you might not have the
resources for.
Um, Freemium and Free-to-Play both do take large development teams, they take a lot of
up-front work, and they do take deep pockets.
And so, if we can think about that, and if, you know, you think you've got a story that
fits Episode or Lifeline or another platform that's out there, because we're not the only
ones either.
Uh,
just get it in front of them and kind of bite the bullet.
Because once you get it out there first,
once you're a published author, then you can say,
I've done it once, I've learned some lessons,
and maybe even you made some good connections,
and that will definitely help you out
at the end of the day.
Cool, well, I wanted to leave 10 minutes for questions,
so we'll probably wrap up there.
So if you've got anything to ask the panel at all,
please use the microphones,
what their favorite color is,
where you can get in touch with them
to send those pictures
that you probably already started working on,
anything like that, please just come up.
If not, I'll make them talk about
all sorts of terrible things.
Don't be shy.
So I've got a question. This is sort of a general question.
So where I come from, there are like TV writers and, you know,
TV writers work with TV production groups in, you know,
or theater writers with theater production groups.
But there are no...
establish rules or ideas or concepts about how video game writers or narrative writers
can work with, you know, video game companies or studios? And how do you propose that maybe,
you know, how do we improve that in our own country, in our own industry about that?
I mean, so the question was about how to improve the kind of the access of video game writers
to video game companies.
Yeah, because what you can describe is that writers can pitch to you and you can, you
know, work with them project by project.
But in where I come from, I come from Taiwan basically, but you know, a lot of...
Video games are made there, you know, they don't have this relationship with a group of writers or the writer industry, you know
Yeah, I think
Video game writing has always been quite difficult to get into because there hasn't been much space
And when space is limited generally speaking the the walls and the doors are very closed and the companies work with the people that they like
They don't they're not interested in seeing anyone else
they don't want to make opportunities because they haven't got any and
I think, actually, to be fair, the work that you guys are doing in producing spaces that
writers can come in and just do the writing, and also Choice of Games, who do a lot of
interactive fiction on mobile that's more premium, but still very much a published,
and that's incredible work, and it's creating great opportunities for writers out there
and building a genre, and it's really important and really successful, but I don't think it's
anything that a writer can do.
It doesn't matter how good a writer is if there is no space for them.
If you're a great playwright but there are no theatres, there's nothing you can do about that.
You have to wait for someone to come along and prize open that opportunity for you.
And I feel that quite strongly because for myself I wrote a lot of interactive fiction when I was in my twenties and in my teens.
and in the end, the only way I could get any successful career out of it
was to invent an entire company, with my friend here,
in order to publish myself,
which I still resent the fact that no one just gave me a job
because I didn't want to have to do anything.
So if we can pay that forward to anyone, that's lovely,
but it won't make up for my resentment of that.
So I feel it. I feel you.
Thank you very much.
Take one from the right-hand side.
Hi, Julius Harper from the Walt Disney Company.
I had a question about an earlier part of the conversation
where you guys were talking about new writers kind
of breaking into the space.
And you specifically highlighted always be writing
and putting out pieces of writing
that have what you described as meaningful choices as opposed
to kind of the arbitrary choice.
I just wanted to kind of dive into that a little bit more
and ask.
I guess for you three, what were the most meaningful choices that you've had to make
within an interactive story?
I always, let's see, this is a cop-out answer, it's not the most meaningful choice, but the
one that I use a lot in interviews because I think it's interesting is Telltale in The
Wolf Among Us had an interesting choice where you could ask Snow White to keep the information
she had secret or be okay with her sharing it with the sheriff.
This is an interesting example because it's actually not meaningful at all, but this is
why I think it's interesting.
She will tell the sheriff no matter what because that is her character.
She is a good person.
But they wrote the entire rest of the season, like changing your relationship with Snow
White and how much you trusted her and how much she trusted you based on the choice you
made in that moment, which I thought was really smart because I'm thinking about, again, as
a...
all of us are thinking about scope. And like you can't always make every single thing in the world
go in a million different branches, but to watch a company find a way to say like, look, we really
had to write a story where the sheriff found this out, we, we had to, we couldn't get this story
out without creating massive branching where he didn't. But we can write a thing that feels
really, really meaningful. The second that was actually pretty impactful was, uh, mild spoilers
for Life is Strange, the suicide moment. Um...
It continues to stick with me after having done it, and I continue to shake up a little
bit when I get there.
That's when Word actually did change the story, and it changed the story and just really,
they planted all these seeds for it, and they built the whole episode around getting to
that choice, which is just an incredibly powerful way to treat one choice really, really sacredly.
I thought they did a really nice job of that.
Yeah, for me, the types of choices that really resonate are kind of on that D&D scale of
lawful good, lawful neutral, chaotic, all that.
And so like Mass Effect is not a mobile game, but it's definitely a good system.
And you know, you kind of see that in also some of the Telltale games as well.
I really like the fact that I can see my interactions changing based on does the story perceive
me to be evil, good, or neutral?
And
It's really great that you can get this nice spectrum of kind of the differences in a story
and the nuances can change so much to change your experience.
Yeah, I think I would echo what both of you said, actually,
especially what Cass said.
That I have no interest in this concept of meaningful choices
that you hear bandied around a lot, because to me it speaks
to the computer programmer in our players who wants to be
in charge, and wants to be in control, and wants to operate
the levers that run the trains, and wants to understand how
many branches there were in the game, and what percentage of
people went which way.
And I don't care about any of that.
That is all so wrongheaded.
that actually what matters is that they have an interesting choice
because otherwise they are going to do something else with their time
and you can't fault them for it.
And when you are in a story and you are asking what is interesting,
the answer is always the same.
It is characters and human beings.
That's all we actually care about.
So as long as my choice allows me to empathize with a character in this game or affect the character in this game,
if I can be kind to someone or I can be snarky to someone, I will enjoy that choice and be interested.
And if that person responds to me in a believable and passionate and humane way,
I will fall in love with them just a little bit.
And if you do that to a person three times in a row, they will remember your game forever.
And there's no meaning to any of that.
And almost all the good choices in 80 Days don't make the damnedest bit of difference to anything
because it's really just whether you're kind to Fogg about the fact that he's a bit of a dimwit
or whether you're annoyed with him.
But those are fascinating choices because we like that character, because we like human beings.
And somehow when we start to program things, everyone forgets about the human beings in the room,
apart from the writers, which is why writers need to be working in video games,
because they stick their little hands up and say,
hang on, we're people. The computer is just an interface for one person to talk to another.
I find this really bizarre, and I get really passionate about this, because everybody talks
to everybody on phones, right?
You know a telephone?
When you talk to a telephone, it's a little metal box that pretends to have the voice
of your wife.
You are not actually talking to your wife, you are talking to a plastic box that is simulating
your wife.
But that isn't how you think about it.
Because you're talking to a human.
So why in a computer game do we talk to the binary choices and the bits of code?
Why are we not talking to the pretend human?
I don't know what's wrong with us, but there's something wrong with us and we need to fix it.
So, people.
Thank you.
I just wanted to ask, how do you tackle branching narratives?
Like, do you start from a linear point of view and then break off from that and then go back to the main thing?
Do you have, like, for multiple endings, like I know some of the Telltale games,
they have multiple endings. How do you go about tackling that?
Yeah, I think we all kind of use different methods for this.
But for Lifeline specifically, we definitely
have the one main path.
And historically, that's kind of how we've always done it.
And then we branch off of that main path.
But we want to make sure that we give a variety of endings that
are possible.
And so then that one main path becomes three main.
There's a large branch off of that,
and then a third large branch off of that main tree.
And then basically when we're moving over to episodic,
we kind of chunk that up into pieces of a tree.
So, you know, having three endings
tends to work really well for us
because you can have what we call
the good, the better, and the best ending.
The good ending might have some
negative connotations to it.
It might have some outcomes that maybe, you know,
you weren't
expecting, but at least it fulfills the story.
But then you can also one-up it and continue to build on that for different experiences.
We essentially do an emotion map that's linear.
We track a linear emotional experience of the player,
but then we brainstorm what are different things
at each emotional moment that could get them
into that emotional arc.
So most of our players will emotionally follow
the same line, that's our goal,
but we'll try and pitch like, well,
why might they be really excited at that moment?
Maybe this, maybe that, maybe the other thing,
and then we'll draw the lines between those things.
The best story was one where we can actually do this
with the lines, that gets really hard,
and I don't promise that we do that very often.
That does sound really cool, by the way.
I don't know how to answer that question.
It's really, really, really complicated,
and it totally depends on the context of what you're doing.
I think in general, the only glib answer I can give
is you have to play test and ask yourself
at any given moment, am I being offered opportunities
that make sense?
Am I being offered opportunities that are all interesting?
And is there something glaringly obvious
that I should be allowed to do here
that I'm not being allowed to do?
Which doesn't mean you should give the player
complete freedom, but it does mean
that you should think really carefully
Are you trying to maximize the number of times when the player goes?
Yeah, that's exactly what I wanted to do and I can do it and see what happens because if they're predicting the choices
Then it starts to feel like a mechanical game rather than an arbitrary one
And that's that's this that's the sweet stuff and then you just cope with that and the branching for me
It's very much a tool for coping with giving the player freedom. Not a thing to achieve in its own, right?
I don't really care how many endings there are I care about
are the moments satisfactory.
But I'm quite jealous of you guys for having more clearly defined answers and patterns,
because that's quite cool.
I mean, that's coming from a mind of make a bazillion of them.
Yeah.
When you have to work with multiple people, you got to give them the rules.
Really lock it.
Yeah, yeah.
No, I like that.
Here's your sandbags.
Oh, sorry.
I'm afraid we're going to have to wrap it up because that is the end and we will get
kicked out.
There will be, these guys I think will probably hang out in the wrap out room for a little
bit if you do have stuff you want to ask them.
So sorry if we didn't get to your question but they'll be there.
I have something to say.
Sorry.
You spoke about Disruptor Beam's writing team.
I would like to speak on the...
I'm sorry.
I have something to say.
We spoke about Disruptor Beam's writing team, I would like to speak on the...
team is a member of the team that worked on Game of Thrones.
It's unfair to characterize all of us as being somehow not
capable of writing for mobile.
We did an excellent job, and we shipped the game,
which Jonathan Myers did not.
I would like to let all of you know that we
shipped a wonderful game, and that every member of that team
is amazing, we are diverse, and we are fantastic writers.
So please don't take away from this panel that
that writing team was in any way not capable because we absolutely were and I
appreciate that you wanted to give an example but we are not a good example of
that so I apologize but that needed to be said.
Thank you very much. No, I really appreciate the correction. It's just an anecdote that I heard.
I don't know the details of it. I didn't mean to upset anybody.