Hello everybody, it's very nice to see you.
My name is Grace Brooksner.
I made a game called Grace Brooksner Presents
the Haunted Islander from Detective Game,
which I assume all of you have played and loved
because it made $17 million.
Not really.
So my talk today is about how to build games around humour and write jokes that aren't
super generic.
So I'm the creative lead of a studio called Worm Club, definitely a real company.
And we're in the process of making another Frog Detective game at the moment.
So let's get started with some disclaimers.
So let's have a disclaimer.
I can't make your jokes funny.
I can give you tools and ideas for how to structure your jokes,
but I'm not a magician.
I can't turn you into a comedic genius.
Some people just aren't funny.
That's fine.
The other tiny disclaimer with this one is that the talk itself is kind of full of info
and isn't exactly funny, like I'm trying to give you as much information as possible.
So apologies in advance for the lack of jokes.
If you were here for a stand-up routine, I'm really sorry.
There's probably like a weird stand-up bar somewhere.
But this is a serious talk.
So no laughing.
What did I just say?
Okay, so I'm gonna give you a bit of an overview
of what I'll be talking about today.
I'll start with an introduction to myself,
giving some context to this talk
and sort of attempting to prove
that I know what I'm talking about,
which is up for debate.
I'll also be going into genre subversion
and how it's an interesting way to onboard your players
and signal that your game doesn't necessarily fit
in the traditional mold of your chosen genre.
After that we'll be talking about how to write characters from yourself to make them more
authentic and how to make that funny without resorting to offensive stereotypes.
And lastly, just some general tips and tricks about how jokes can be structured,
a kind of 101 on comedy writing for your video games.
All righty, so a little bit on me.
My name is Grace, as we have established.
I guess my most well-known game would be The Haunted Island,
which is IGF nominated.
Please clap. No, don't.
And we're in the process of making The Invisible Wizard,
which is the second game in the Frog Detective series.
So I guess mostly I'll be talking about the process of writing the Frog Detective games
and giving specific examples from those games.
It's also worth mentioning that I've made a pretty big selection of small-scale diorama
games which have a bit of a mix of environmental and physical humour and comedy writing, and
I learned a lot from those games about how to do visual comedy using animation and environmental
pacing.
Yep.
So.
a little bit more background, which not a lot of people know, I did do stand-up comedy for
two years before I got into games. I was living in a small town so like...
the comedy scene wasn't huge, but I was getting booked,
I guess, a couple of times a month.
And my comedy style wasn't like a traditional
sort of comedy, it was absurd and deadpan,
kind of like my sense of humor.
But what I learned doing that is that those jokes
and that style of comedy is
just as funny as traditionally structured jokes. So, I'll be referencing my experience with stand
up a little bit as well. A bit of background on the Haunted Island, for those of you who don't
know it, it made it in about five months with my team. So, me, Thomas, who did the programming and
tools, and Dan. My job in the game was to do the assets and the narrative and the dialogue.
So Dan was the composer and I basically gave him the pitch of like,
hey, I want to make pro-ro, but it's a frog, can you do music for that?
And he was like, hell yeah.
That's my impression of Dan.
So the focus of The Haunted Island was the dialogue and the humor, and every interaction
that we had in that game had to have some sort of purpose behind it, and the biggest
purpose of that was just to make people laugh, because I feel very strongly about games that
are just silly and there for making you feel good, because there's a lot of horribleness
in the world.
The game actually did pretty well considering that it was a very low budget game made in
five months.
like the whole team was just me and Tom basically. I did all the marketing and stuff, so the reception
was really positive from both the players and the critics. I'll be going into a little bit of why I
think that is a bit later. I will mention however that some people were pretty confused by it because
it's not really a traditional game in any sense. It's...
maybe more traditional than my previous games, but yeah, it's not what you expect when you
hear detective game. That response didn't really matter too much to me because there's like a
myriad of games out there for every type of person and I don't think there's that many games like the
Haunted Island, so it's fine. I'll also be showing you, just to give you some background on the
style of game and the tone that I was using for the game, I'll show you the intro sequence.
So let's have a look-a-roo.
Subscribe and Btw many more yet to come!
I'm a genius. Okay, so that kind of segues kind of nicely into the first topic which is genre subversion.
So let's get started. So I guess beginning with this you should really think about how most genres
that are commonly used for games they have a lot of cultural baggage and it can be good and bad but
when you find a genre that you want to subvert
with the right amount of effort and work into subverting it,
you can create something amazing and unexpected.
So as an example from Frog Detective,
I took a genre that has a lot of existing expectations.
So detective games often have moody, noir tones,
like grizzly bodies and chase sequences
and like cigarettes and all that.
And not all of that appeals to me personally as a developer, and I wasn't really seeing the genre subverted in any of the games that I was playing in the way that I would do it.
So I kind of found an avenue there that hadn't really been explored to its fullest extent.
And for me, it's almost always funny to have a genre
that fits the setting of your game, but not the tone.
And for me, that was like an island
with a kind of fake mystery on it.
Everything about the setting had to be translatable to Noir,
but I also knew that the tone
was gonna be very lighthearted and gentle.
And beginning this process can actually be pretty weird, but it's best to start by finding your inspirations in the genre that you're looking at, whether that's games or movies or TV shows.
So get a feel of the genre so that you know what you're working with.
I played a bunch of LA Noir when I was first getting into games,
and it was one of those first games where I could see
the potential for humor in the genre, which kind of doesn't
sound exactly what you think of when you think of LA Noir.
But there's this bit in that game
where the character will pick up clues and just kind of wiggle
it around in their hands.
And to me, that's really funny.
And that was an inspiration for having,
so in Frog Detective, there's a magnifying glass
that you can just pick up and put to your face.
and it doesn't actually do anything, it just warps the image, but it's just part of that role-playing
thing. And it's super goofy because everyone knows that you're not playing Frog Detective
to actually be the Frog Detective, but it's just an additional role-playing thing. And what I found
is that even though it's entirely useless, a bunch of people were using it just to be like,
hmm, yes, is this a clue? You know, literally nothing is a clue.
And so when you're doing your genre specific research,
you've got to find what makes that genre what it is.
So those elements that you find that you decide,
okay, this is what this genre is.
Those are the elements that you'll keep
and use in your game.
And for me, the most recognizable part
of the detective genre is the music and the camera angles.
So I wanted to take those elements as they were
and put them in the game.
So every talk sequence in The Haunted Island has camera angles that are copied from TV shows.
I had to do like a bunch of research into like cinematography.
I just don't care about cinematography but I wanted it to be like...
as close to that genre as I could.
And that kind of amps up the comedy
because it's like taking the visuals of it super seriously
even though it's not a very serious game.
And another element of the detective genre that I liked
was that a lot of detective shows are episodic.
So with a new mystery every episode,
think Poro, think,
Columbo, Sherlock, all those. So for that I gave the game a theme song at the start and a teaser
for the next episode at the end. And basically this step is all about making sure that your
audience knows what you're subverting. So the players need to recognise what the genre should be
so that they know when you're playing with it.
So this is where it gets a little bit trickier.
It is a bit harder to do, but when you start to actually subvert the genre,
that's when it starts to become funny.
The best way that I've found to do this is to decide which parts of the genre
that you don't like.
So in relation to The Haunted Island, one of my biggest pet peeves of the genre is when
detectives don't care about their jobs or are like super rude, but they're amazing at
solving cases.
Like, I just want the main character and everything to be super lovely.
So in the game, the detective is...
like super loves being a detective but isn't necessarily awesome at it.
So detectives are friendly to everyone and apologetic when they're suspicious of someone.
So already with that you have a few more, you have a more pleasant character but there's that
silliness there and how the detective interacts with suspects. And a maybe more prominent change
was that I made it so that nothing dramatic ever happens in the game. So there's no like
murder or grand conspiracies yet.
But I want the story to have an air of mystery without anything sinister actually happening.
I also liked the idea of nobody in the island being particularly helpful or like every sort
of interaction not really meaning anything apart from just like, oh, I need a magnet
if you've got one.
So when you subvert genre, make sure that the elements that you subvert aren't the essential
elements.
Because if I think I had, you know, if I had sacrificed the music or the cinematography,
the genre wouldn't be recognisable anymore.
So it's going back to that step and making sure that the genre you have
is being represented properly, even if it's not being represented fully.
One thing that I want to bring forward into the development of The Invisible Wizard is
managing expectations a little bit better.
So I presented The Haunted Island as a detective game, even though it is a little bit tongue
in cheek.
But the problem was there wasn't actually any detective work, any traditional detective
work.
So people that were...
picking up the Haunted Island to be a detective,
were kind of disappointed.
It didn't, like that doesn't bother me too much,
but it was cited in some negative reviews,
which as we know can impact the success of your game.
So with the next game,
I'm planning to add more of those traditional
investigative, yeah, elements.
of detective games into the sequel to appease that crowd a little bit more.
I think this was like a pretty big lesson for me and while I wouldn't normally care too much,
I think actually leaning into that a little bit more will improve the games.
The other thing is if you really don't want to include these certain mechanics that are
in other games of your genre, you can forego them, but you have to make sure that you signal
it in your store page or in your trailers so that the people that aren't into it will
stay away.
Or don't, because I'm not your dad.
Alright so I'm going to move on to how I write my characters which is probably the thing that I
thought the most about while doing this because I hadn't actually written a game fully before.
So it was like how do I make like 13 people that are not just me every time?
Because I find it almost impossible to get myself into the headspace of someone that isn't me,
or someone that is really far removed from my own lived experience.
And I struggled with this a lot because I would 3D model characters and try to develop their
personality from their appearance. And it wasn't working because all my characters are just like
smiling animals. So there wasn't like a whole bunch of personality just in their visuals.
So what I did is I developed a system for writing unique and believable characters to
help with this.
So when you're writing characters, especially characters that are funny, it's really good
to draw from what you know because otherwise you can fall into the trap of making fun of
people and traits.
Otherwise it can lean into more offensive stuff.
So if you're writing comedy characters that aren't of your demographic, you need to consult
with people from that demographic.
Don't make assumptions about how people are because that can turn into stereotyped and
offensive characters, especially when you're writing comedy.
So if you really want to make a game with a diverse cast, especially a comedy game,
leave some room in your budget for hiring consultants.
And that kind of goes for any narrative game, but I feel like it is quite important for
comedy because comedy can be.
offend like pretty easily.
So, going into the more specifics of how to write those believable characters,
I find the best way is to base them on myself. So, for the haunted island, I took a look at the
part of myself that stems, sorry, the parts of my personality that stem from mental illness,
and I thought about how to translate those traits onto a character.
So, writing from what you know is always going to be the most productive way to make characters feel
real.
So for example, four parts of my personality are that I'm anxious, I'm impatient, I can
be pretty shy, and I can also be quite stubborn.
And they're not nice traits and they're not attractive traits, but you can write from
them.
And when I've written down a bunch of personality traits, I assign them each to a character.
And then I give each character something that they want or something that they like.
And I'll go into detail in this more in the next slides,
but I think giving them a goal gives them a purpose.
So for example, you could have like a super rude character
that really wants a boiled egg.
And then there's like a character there,
that's a character.
And once you have a trait and a purpose
or something that the character wants,
you can challenge your character.
And that's where the dialogue comes in.
So in the games.
I use the detective as a kind of straight man, but not like a literal straight man, just like a
comedy straight man. Yeah, the detective relies on logic to solve these problems.
So, none of the characters in my game are particularly logical, so writing a dialogue
between an odd character and a stable character creates some tension and...
It can be really funny.
As long as it comes from your own lived experience,
as we have gone over,
don't write characters who are mentally ill unless
you have experienced that or you have hired
a consultant. Don't be messy!
I will not tell you again.
So I'll go into specifics about the characters that I wrote and I'll start with Martin because
Martin has probably the most dialogue in the game and Martin is a really anxious character
who just like really really wants to feel safe. So what I did with Martin is I looked at what
Martin was experiencing and I embodied that character while I was writing him and I tried
to figure out what I would do in his situation. So Martin's afraid of a ghost.
And what I would do in that situation is I would like Google it.
I'd be like, is there a ghost?
And then every every positive piece of information that lined up
to what I was experiencing, I'd be like, yeah, there is a ghost.
So in the game, Martin has all these ghost books and he goes through and reads
and he's like, yeah, I haven't seen a ghost yet, so there must be a ghost
because that's exactly what I would do.
Yeah, so I have.
We call it illness anxiety disorder or hypochondria.
But every time I find a rare illness,
I go on Google and I'm like,
hmm, yeah, I have a headache.
Yeah, that's Martin.
And when I embody a character, I have to think about how to challenge those sorts as well.
So the detective, once again, is acting as this straight man that comes in and challenges
and dissects each thought that the character has and that creates that tension and that dialogue.
And that character could fight back, it could dig deeper, it could get offended,
or it could start to agree with the detective.
And all of those paths are really interesting and could be quite funny.
Going on to Mo. Mo is very shy. I'm not the most shy person, but I can be quite socially anxious and go into my shell.
So with Mo, I picked an animation that really represents their closed off and shy nature.
So Mo's kind of like looking down, not really like looking at the detective in the eye.
I think Mo is the character most in the game that embodies the idea of physical comedy,
because it's pretty funny when you talk to Mo and they just immediately close themselves off.
even though they were just happily standing there.
And comedians use body language quite often to change the mood of a set
and physical comedy can absolutely set the tone
of a character without any dialogue so you're immediately going into this idea
of how this character is going to be.
And Mo was also good to write because I sort of became a matchmaker for Mo.
If you haven't played the game, Mo has a little bit of a crush on one of the other characters.
So your job is just to go and like, see what dance style that character likes the best,
and come back and tell Mo. And then Mo practices the dance.
It's very good. I'm a genius.
But when you write a character that wants to make a little bit embarrassing or a little
bit vulnerable, writing the dialogue can be super fun and actually enjoyable to do and
that comedy kind of writes itself.
All right, so let's get into some tips and tricks.
These are sort of general bits of advice that don't really neatly fit into the other topics.
The first one I'll go into is pacing.
Because often people that are new to writing comedy or new to doing comedy,
really struggle with pacing because they don't give
their audience time to breathe after each joke,
and your players need to laugh,
and it is quite difficult to get right.
So we weren't using voice acting in our game, it's all text-based.
So I was reliant on the text box timings to get the jokes across.
One trick that I learned was just to use ellipses to put
beats into your writing. Often when let's players are doing it, you can see it really
clearly if people are streaming the game because they're reading out the dialogue and you can
see where they're pausing to laugh or pausing to let a joke settle in. And it's also when
people are reading, they're doing the same thing. So, good stand-ups kind of do that
as well. So, after they pause after making a joke to be like, hey, this is a joke, you
should totally laugh now. And it can also be good for adding awkwardness or sort of
like.
ending in non-sequitur.
But you don't have to use ellipses.
You can manufacture this pacing with text box animations
or character facial expressions or even camera angles.
I think an example of a game that does this really well
is Breath of the Wild, because when you're talking to people,
they aren't speaking to you.
But there's all these different character animations
that really sell that comedy.
Yeah, and you can use these techniques
to change the pace as well.
So look at games that you find funny,
and you can just copy their pacing
if you're feeling unsure.
The other big advice I'd give with pacing is if you're struggling with it, just take
a break and leave the dialogue for a while.
I do this pretty often when I'm writing because I'm never sure whether a joke is actually
landing because I've been looking at it for too long.
So leave the dialogue for a while and maybe come back an hour later and play the game
and then you'll read it with a new, like with a set of fresh eyes and see whether, you know,
the pacing is off or actually the joke is totally fine and you were just like in your
head too much.
Structure.
Okay, so when making short games, I'm of the opinion that you should try to stick to one
style of humour if you can. Just one that works for you because when you're doing games, adding
a whole bunch of different styles of humour can be a little bit confusing because the player might
not know whether this is a joke or whether this is like just dialogue. And what I did was with
my sense of humour, like I made sure to signal.
it during the marketing and during the promo work and the people that weren't into that
style of humor could stay away because they can see it.
They can see it outlined before they buy the game.
And I think part of the reason that Frog Detective was successful was because I spent a lot of
time signaling the humor in the marketing and the trailers.
So be very clear about what you're doing.
And for bigger games, you can have a mix of different humor styles.
A good talk about that is Zach Johnson's GDC talk about Wests of Loathing.
They made a big game and they could jam pack jokes into it.
Another good tip is structuring jokes that fit with your game style.
I don't know if game style is a thing, but we'll just go with it.
So my game is expirational, so I structured jokes that could have a payoff regardless
of the order that the player sees it in.
So, for example, there is a little note on the notice board in the Haunted Island that
says, where are my sunglasses?
Please give them back.
And then you can find a tiny picture of me with sunglasses on because I have stolen them.
And that joke is probably only funny to me, but it's fine.
And I guess, yeah, more linear games can play with structure a lot more freely.
So think of Night in the Woods, I think that's a great example of jokes having a payoff much
later on.
Because it is a larger game, you can pace out those jokes.
But with smaller games, like, you do want to kind of make it more punchy and you don't
need callbacks as much, I think.
So my last tip and trick is playtesting.
I'm really sorry.
So everyone's favourite part of development is playtesting.
So, yeah, the one thing that I learnt from watching really, really terrible comedians
is that a lot of people don't test their jokes out before they go on stage.
So treat your dialogue like you're an actually good standup comedian
and make sure that you workshop it.
test it out with your players and making things that are funny takes work and not every joke
will land and that's absolutely fine.
With The Haunted Island I had to go back a lot and change a lot of jokes because not
every joke works on every person but I wanted to have as high a success rate as possible
so I was trying to get jokes in there that were more universally funny.
which can be a little bit difficult.
One tip I'd give you with playtesting
is that some people are really uncomfortable being vocal
when they're playing comedy games,
so they don't really wanna laugh out loud.
So when you're playtesting, try and sit in a position
where you can gauge their facial expression.
Because I've had silent playtests
where the person, I can't see their face,
and they're just playing the game for an hour,
and then they're like, that was good, thank you.
And I have no idea if they actually liked it.
But at the same time, I've had silent playtests
where...
the person, I can see their face and they're smiling or quietly giggling and you know that
that's good.
So if your first playtester doesn't get a joke, that's absolutely fine, just try it
on another person.
And if there's still no reaction, try and restructure that joke or change the pacing
of it and then try it on another person.
If it's still not working, just scrap it because it's not worth it to disrupt that flow.
Wow, yeah, once again, really sorry about this picture.
Like, it's supposed to be Seinfeld.
Turns out Seinfeld doesn't have a really iconic body.
So it just looks like a weird, anyway.
Alright, talk done.
Highlight of GDC, thanks for coming.
Yeah, alright, yeah, you can ask me questions if you want.
Oh, you've got to go up to the microphones to ask questions.
That is something that I forgot to mention.
Hello.
I guess I'll go first.
So you were talking about, I guess, the length of games.
Something I'm noticing with my game
right now is that people are just hammering
through dialogue a lot.
Do you have any tips on how to engage people with the dialogue
when you have a narrative-heavy game?
I think that is tricky and it is something we struggle with a little bit, especially
with younger players who don't want to go through a bunch of jokes that are too old
for them.
Something that I've been thinking about with this next game is actually to have two different
dialogue options.
So one for people that don't really like reading and just want all the facts with a little
bit of joke or one dialogue option for everyone that just wants to like go through the game
completely.
So signalling that at the start of the game, it is like extra work because you basically
have to go through and redo the scripts twice.
But I think for people that don't like reading games,
like why make playing a narrative game?
It feels very strange.
But yeah, some people don't like reading
and I don't know if I can save those people.
It's fine.
Yeah, hey, this is going to come across as kind of a self-owned, but I think a lot of
us feel, at least I think I hope it's more than just me, that sometimes humor is kind
of an intrinsic thing and you're funny or you're not or your level of humor is set.
For a lot of other things like drawing, it's like, okay, practice, you get better.
So would you say that you can practice humor and jokes and get better at it?
And what are some ways to think about doing that if you think that that's a good thing
to do?
Yeah, I think like some of it is intrinsic, but there's also this thing of like some people
are quite funny, but they don't have the confidence to be funny. So just own everything you say,
even if it's not even funny, like half of the stuff I say isn't funny. But if you pause long
enough, people get uncomfortable and they laugh. Awesome. Thank you.
So the talk was super interesting. And provided that there's a lot of creative direction in
building the humor of a game.
What would you do in the situation you had to grow and, for instance, look for writers to follow your creative direction?
How you could? It's two parts.
Look for the best way of finding people that you think can fit into that kind of creative direction and humor.
And what piece of advice would you give in the sense of guiding them in a way of getting them closer to your kind of humor?
Yeah, it's difficult because I guess I've written the whole game myself, but I think
if basically in any situation where you're working with a narrative consultant or someone
that's doing the dialogue you should just ask them to do a sample, like make sure that they
what they know, like how they know how to write things that are funny. Yeah, I guess I don't
know if I can answer that question fully because it is it is just me. Sometimes you can just tell
if you're talking to someone with a
your sense of humor is the same as theirs.
So that's, yeah.
Okay, thank you.
Hi, you mentioned that when writing a lot of your believable characters you focus on
Aspects of yourself that could be considered negative traits. I was just wondering how you avoid falling onto
Particularly self-deprecation and jokes of that sort. Yeah. Yeah, it is it can be difficult. I think there's there's a delicate balance between
making a character who is
a really negative part of yourself but I think the biggest thing for me is like having a character
who is talking to them be gentle and be kind so it's never like haha you believe that you have
a weird disorder haha it's like oh like
Hi, you know, this doesn't make any sense.
But with the detective, I'm sort of challenging that character,
but I'm also doing it in a very kind way
to make sure that the whole game is kind of just
about making the characters feel OK about themselves.
So when you have those negative personality traits,
I think for me it's easier because I
know that the character that they're talking to
isn't going to be harsh to them about it.
Yeah, I guess I'm not a super self-deprecating person either.
I think it's just like, believe in yourself.
Oh, thank you.
Excuse me just one second.
All right, so we're about to wrap up.
So this will be the last question here.
But we do have a wrap-up room if you want to use it later.
Hi, on the last topic of testing your dialogue,
I was just curious, so do you only test after it's
in the game or are you ever just testing written lines?
And if you do, do you have a different approach for that?
So I write all my dialogue in the game itself,
so every time I press play, the dialogue will be in there.
I think the best way that I've found to test it
is just to ask Tom, who's the programmer and UX designer,
to just come over and read it through
and see whether he laughs.
Yeah, I think when you're testing it doesn't matter if the game is complete or not.
Just have enough dialogue in there that it kind of makes sense.
I think it is harder to do tests when you're just looking at a script rather than having
like something visual to look at.
It's kind of harder for your brain to be like, oh, yeah, that's funny.
That's a joke.
Yeah.
So try and get it in there if you can.
Thank you.
Yeah.
So we can go to the wrap up room, which is in 20...
18 I think, if anyone wants to hang out. Otherwise, thank you for coming.