Hello everyone, welcome to the GDC Twitch channel.
I am your host, Brian Francis.
I am here today playing a neat little game, not that little, but a neat game called Age
of Wonders Planetfall.
Age of Wonders Planetfall comes to you from Triumph Studios and Paradox Interactive.
With me today, in the lower left hand corner of the screen, is Triumph Studios co-founder
Leonard Suss.
Leonard, how are you doing?
Hi, doing well.
How are you?
It's out in the world and people are not super angry and they seem to like it so that's great.
Nice.
And with me also, saying nice, is Alyssa McAloon, straight from Gamasutra.
How are you doing Alyssa?
I am doing well. Wide awake, wide awake.
White Awake.
Any dogs hanging out there, Alyssa?
She has been bribed by a delicious lunch, so she is over there minding her own business.
You can also bribe me with a delicious lunch.
Readers at home, if you are, you can also bribe me, viewers at home, you can also bribe
me with a delicious lunch if you ever wish to play my ear.
We're here today with Lennart playing Age of Wonders Planetfall.
This is a 4X strategy game that has some turn-based 4X strategy game with another layer of turn-based
combat that debuted just a couple weeks ago.
It's the latest game in the Age of Wonders series, which if you're a strategy aficionado
you may have played before.
It's been in development since 1999 and Lennart, you've been working on this series for like
20 years, right?
Yeah, correct.
Yeah, we started this out in university.
We met with a couple of like-minded friends.
We thought to mix and match a bunch of genres together,
like strategy, RPG, even adventuring at first,
and that's when the Age of Wonders series started to emerge.
Of course, the first games were fantasy-based,
and Planetfall is our first venture into sci-fi.
And also, the first time we...
brought the game to consoles.
What, for you, has development been like?
And how has four years of development transitioned into making this game right here?
Yeah, it was an awful long while.
I think it's almost the longest that we spent on a game ever.
Maybe the very first one, but that's when we were working sort of like semi-professionally on it.
We started off looking at how do we make a new turn-based strategy game.
The idea to make a sci-fi version came shortly after we'd done the fact that we wanted to keep on making turn-based games,
but we didn't want to make a direct sequel to Age of Wonders 3.
We thought it would be a great match to try a sci-fi universe.
Age of Wonders has always been a war-focused game,
with lots of knights and...
Castle sieges and medieval war equipment.
We thought it would be a great match if we try and model all those cool battles
and cool empire building in a sci-fi universe.
So replace archers with marines with machine guns and cavalry with tanks.
Spells with orbital laser cannons.
And we basically started there and soon after the idea started flowing.
But we wanted to do some radical...
shifts as well, including the way the economy works,
the way you basically conquer the map using sectors.
So there's been a very long prototyping phase,
perhaps one and a half year, I would say,
where we started experimenting with these new combat mechanics,
new diplomacy, new economic features.
And when that all was sorted, we went into production.
The game features six unique factions, all with their own tech trees.
So working that out with, you know, detailed units, detailed animations,
sound effects and everything, it's just a big amount of production.
And during the production period, we were acquired by Paradox Interactive,
which of course was a little bit of, I wouldn't say a distraction,
but I would say that it did prolong the development a little bit.
Of course, a lot of senior people during such a process are busy with other stuff.
And then after that, when that acquisition process was completed, we started looking
into, okay, how can we see what can we do more with this type of game?
And soon the idea came along, like, let's try this on console.
It's a new IP as well.
It's not a fantasy IP.
It's called Planetfall.
It's not a sequel.
So we said, okay, let's see if we can transition this on console.
And that's when the entire interface had to be reworked
to be multi-platform friendly.
All those hundreds of windows, pop-ups, panels,
all needed to be changed.
And, yeah, that was probably a year of work, I would say.
Of course, the port itself, multiplayer...
Working on all those different platforms too was a tremendous task.
And that's how those years fill up.
The time flies, right?
Yeah.
With... because this is the first... you've brought games in Overlord to console before,
but this is the first in the Age of Wonders series to come to consoles too, right?
Yes, yeah. I can tell you that this was actually a lot more work
to bring to consoles than a game like Overlord.
The entire control scheme of Overlord was a lot more suited to, or easy to port.
I would say that a turn-based game is very much suited for a console game.
There's just more work involved in transferring all these interfaces.
Yeah, I was going to say, this is kind of like a, this whole genre, like both your
kind of duality genres you have here, they both are kind of synonymous with PC for me.
So it's interesting.
the decision to kind of like branch out into consoles.
And Brian's playing on PlayStation 4 right now, too.
So you can see that like it applies itself well
to the controller and everything, too.
Yeah.
Yeah, it is, you know, there are not many games out there.
I mean, Paradox recently ported Stellaris,
a big Space 4X game to console.
And that, yeah, it was an experiment which turned out well.
Of course, in the past there was Civilization Revolutions on the previous generation of consoles.
And of course we have the very popular tactical turn-based games.
Of course, our game has a very large tactical component as well.
So games like XCOM or Fire Emblem do very well on consoles.
Right on. To move on into the next question, so you go from, you said you wanted to make a new game, a new Age of Wonders game after Age of Wonders 3.
What was kind of the foundation, like you made a sci-fi version of a series you already had.
What was the decision to sort of adapt the series you had for a...
as opposed to building a new IP ground up that would be like strictly science fiction only.
Which you've sort of halfway done, but there's still kind of a fantasy component to it, I guess?
Maybe a little bit, but the IPs are as different as, for example, Warcraft and Starcraft, or Warhammer and Warhammer 40k.
If there's any links, they're very subtle, but it's mainly the reason why we kept on calling it Age of Wonders was...
the gameplay formula is similar.
The split between the strategy and the tactical layer.
So just like you have like the Total War games
or StarCraft and WarCraft, you have the same sort of formula applied to
two different settings, which are not just reskins but actually
the large part of the gameplay
I think has fundamentally changed.
Right on.
Um, uh, what then was kind of your foundation for, I was reading some interviews where you
and your teammates were talking about, um, with making, uh, making new factions.
One of your goals was to make sure that, uh, all the factions that every single unit within
each faction was unique from faction to faction, uh, by comparison in Age of Wonders 3, every
unit has a soldier, an archer, a...
a cavalry unit, kind of that. And then some unique disemerge from there. But that's obviously a big
design choice change to make instead of a top-down structure for your unit to make every single unit
unique. What was the process for executing that? Yeah, it was a bit of a long iterative process,
basically. He started off making
good rich gameplay mechanics that allow for these various play styles, especially when
you talk about units, you talk about combat.
To ensure that the core mechanics, the systems are diverse and rich enough that allow for
various combat roles.
Units that can have more of an assault range, weapons, support units.
units that use cover, units that can fly, units that can yield, units that have all
sorts of various areas of effect damage, units that can hop around the battlefield, units
that can dig, units that can stagger or be immune to stagger.
So it started basically with a mechanic and a radical upgrade of the combat mechanics that we had in Age of Unus 3.
Right on. Alyssa, I'm going to toss the question over to you because I'm trying to juggle a bunch of objectives that just popped up.
So unlike Brian, I haven't had hands-on time with your game quite yet.
So your campaigns, does each faction have their own campaign there?
Yeah.
Okay. So how...
I'm trying to figure out how I want to word this, but with each of the factions being so different,
they're obviously going to appeal to different kind of players.
How do you kind of design those, I guess, to have kind of like mass appeal while also encouraging people to get out of their comfort zones,
while giving people more of what they want when they finish one campaign and going into the next?
I guess, how do you kind of like accomplish that entire beast of making each faction interesting but appealing to as many people as possible?
Well, we obviously have various factions that have a, like a, some of them are more mainstream
I would call, like sort of like a mainstream pop song that is, you know, sort of a friend
to everybody, not too complex, not too quirky.
Of course most games, most strategy games, have what we call the human faction, which
are easy to identify with and when you look at a unit, you sort of see its function.
You know a tank is a tank, a walker, an aircraft, or a ship.
You know maybe they wear, have different types of rifles.
But you know we just use what you get basically.
And you know from there you go into more extreme forms including like alien insectoids,
or you know sort of like cyborg trash assembly.
You can also click on the ability lists to see what they do.
We have a single player campaign, which is basically used as an introduction to the entire series.
Next to that we have the standalone scenarios, which is a lot more similar to your civilization.
open-ended type of gameplay where you choose your victory condition that you want to proceed
and it's sort of like a free-for-all and a lot of people actually skip the campaign and
just go straight into that, especially the more advanced players.
And of course you can also play these scenarios in multiplayer.
But yeah, if you're a beginner to this type of game, we encourage you to start playing the campaign.
Maybe start with human fashion first.
Which is exactly what we've done, as you've no doubt ascertained.
Just a quick reminder for chat, we are happily taking your questions if you've got any for Lennart, don't be shy.
We'd love to hear from you. There's like 20 folks out there, that's a good sign that some of you are interested in Age of Wonders.
I'm gonna go to my question pile. Lennart, what I would like to know...
There was something interesting that was pointed out in one interview,
is that compared to previous, unlike other strategy games, when a game of Age of Wonders starts...
Age of Wonders Plain and False starts...
You don't jump right into your research tree, your exploitation system, is what it's called in this game,
but just like telling your cities what to focus on producing.
You don't jump into those right away with this, it's deliberately staggered out.
Can you walk through the decision to sort of slightly tweak traditional conventions of the 4X genre
and what it means for players to not be diving into those choices right away or every single turn?
Right, okay. Now we have to go to the nature of Age of Wonders and how it differs from the other games.
And basically what, also I think one of the reviewers, I don't know if it was PC Gamer or IGN,
basically said that Age of Wonders is sort of like a fast-paced 4X.
The, what they call turn density, so the amount of things that you do in a single turn,
is higher than in other titles.
So you can fight multiple battles, multiple pickups.
Also, for example, the research times tend to be shorter.
So there's a lot going on.
And part of that comes from the sort of war game multiplayer like nature of the game.
So in this sense, so especially in those early terms, a lot could happen if you
basically open up research and open up the scouting, doing your first battle,
making, recruiting your first hero.
and doing everything in turn one, front-loading that entire turn
before you really get your bearing.
So at one point we said, there's so much happening in turn one,
let's delay research one turn
so you at least get to see the lay of the land a little bit.
Maybe spend your first turn scouting and
see whether or not you have water nearby
or what type of enemies you'll be facing in the first couple of rounds.
And then the turn after you can start making your research decisions based on that lay
of the land.
And the game is a little bit more welcoming to beginning players, so that they don't get
you know, that first turn isn't loaded with all sorts of decisions to make right away.
Right on. Um, what do you think, um, as far as acquiring like, like the forex
strategy genre has been around for a while and some of the games in it are
really popular. Some of them are a little more niche. Um, what do you think
is part of the, and this is sort of part of the paradoxes overall marketing
strategies. What do you think is essential for, for the strategy genre to
grow and to keep acquiring new players as opposed to just sort of, I mean,
like there's, there's obviously value in, in, in.
I'm not sure if that's a good thing.
Well, actually, we've seen quite some growth in the strategy genre over the years.
Mainly it is because gamers say they don't stop gaming when they're 20 years old.
They keep on gaming when they have kids or when they get to work.
A strategy game like Age of Wonders or Planetfall is very easy to wrap around your life because it's turn-based.
Also, for example, with the multiplayer options that we have, what we call the adaptive multiplayer system.
And basically you put your turns in the cloud,
and you can download the turns when you have time to play your turn,
and you can upload it again.
But if your friends are online at the same time,
you can switch that same session to sort of like a live session,
and this game switches to simultaneous turns.
Yeah.
All play at once.
And then say, okay, it's now late at night,
and I'm going to log off,
and the game switches back to the sort of round-robin turn system again.
So that's an innovation that we...
that is brought to by newer technology that allows this type of game to adapt to future
age and hopefully to a growing group of gamers who, you know, even when they become more
mature they keep on enjoying this medium.
That's wild. I remember back in when I was playing Civilization 3 back in ye olde days, when I was 8 years old.
That was the email, you emailed your turns to other players.
Yeah, that was manual. We had to system up well and have things automated.
How did you, what did it take to implement a system like that?
Of course very good programmers with very good ideas.
An AVS cloud system.
Which wasn't around...
And CIF 3, I think.
And, yeah, of course, bandwidth has gotten a lot cheaper.
You know, just because basically we foot the bill for those transfers.
But, you know, like earlier on you paid per megabyte.
So now, you know, the same money buys you terabytes of data.
Mm-hmm.
Right on.
Alyssa, I'm going to toss the question ball to you while I move some tricks around.
I'm really curious about that feature because I wasn't quite the emailing turns to friends thing,
but my sister and I would hurry up and we'd be in the middle of a StarCraft match and have to like,
oh we gotta hurry up and finish this before dad comes in and yells at us to go to bed.
So that's really cool. I didn't know strategy games had that feature, this one particularly.
Oh where was I going to go with that? There was a thought there and it's gone.
I'll come back to it later, but it's really neat and it's really interesting.
Fishy, or sorry, Fish21 in chat wants to know what your favorite part of making a 4X or
strategy game has been after doing it for as long as you have been.
Ooh, well, I think my favorite part is with each iteration, is looking into how we can
like innovate.
Part of the work I enjoy is looking back at
a long-running series, not necessarily 4X series,
just long-running genres,
and to see how they try to survive
and how they evolve or fail to evolve over the years
and why genres or even individual game series
rise or fall.
And that is, of course,
that makes trying to walk the fine line between innovation
and not...
losing the connection with your fan base and trying to innovate.
And that's, I think, one of the main challenges that you have when running the series alone.
And when it comes to For X Design in itself,
it's just the enormous challenge of making a game that is so complex.
And so there's so many subsystems, you know, the economy, the diplomacy, the combat.
And that needs to play out over like...
session can last anywhere from 6 to 12 hours, a typical session.
And you can play it in so many different ways.
And the game needs to be stable and basically adapt to people playing in a particular way.
And that experience, a lot of people come into such a game also with
entire different expectations.
Some people just want to play very casually and do some empire building, build cities,
while others really are super aggressive, competitive players.
who like to digest every little unitability and see how they can use that in their favor.
And they play such a game very differently from the more casual empire builder.
But still, we need to appeal to both of these type of gamers and just having
a game that tries to do it all is a challenge and it's also a lot of fun to do.
And you're picking...
Go, no, you go for it, Alyssa.
I would say picking into that process a little bit.
What's like, obviously you were working on this game for four years,
what's kind of like the iteration, the trial and error process to making sure,
oh, this is leaning too heavy in one direction,
so it's not fun for players who play this way.
How do you make everyone happy without kind of like sacrificing the character of a game?
Yeah, that is very difficult.
I mean, during the process of prototyping,
we basically split the team up into various mini teams,
which all get assigned to work on a particular function.
And especially when.
At first, you don't have the full backbone of the full ecosystem of the game running.
Some of these features are created in a vacuum.
It is very hard to see if such a feature is fun or not.
So you try to simulate an environment and try to role play or maybe board game it or
something, if a feature will be fun or not.
Sometimes you just end up spending three months of a significant part of the team
just throwing a feature away because it just didn't end up being fun.
One of the examples is a sort of large, sort of orbital system that we built,
like an entire sky layer around the planet,
where you could maneuver aircraft, death stars, and satellites and missiles
in order to influence the world below.
But that just didn't work.
It totally undermined what was happening below.
Because there were almost no obstacles there, it sort of turned into a game of its own,
which wasn't fun.
So you just had to bite the bullet and scrap those many man-months worth of work.
But that's all in the game, if you would try something new.
Right on. Fish21 just wants to thank you, Leonard, for answering their question.
And LordSloth jokes that people don't have the resurgence trait in real life.
Leonard, just shifting the line of questioning for a moment.
What would you say was kind of a...
Sorry, that was not a good way to start the sentence.
I was reading one interview that one of the re- another one of the reasons that you all transition to making
Age of Wonders the way- Planetfall the way you did was after Age of Wonders 3
There was kind of a criticism that people wanted more options across the gameplay
That's sort of broadly that builds off what we talked about before about making units unique
But like, you know
They- they're- they're 4x games can kind of get uh, no matter how great and varied they can get
They can also get a little similar you- you build your city, you colonize new cities, and then just kind of
The loop repeats.
What was your process for finding...
We just sort of talked about trying new ideas, but what was sort of your process for finding
new ways to play 4X games, I guess?
To look for new options and new ways to get people into gameplay?
Yeah, when you're talking purely about mechanics, the main criticism on Age of Wilderness 3
was...
that people missed some sort of like, you know, a strict strategy layer depth,
including the economy and the cities.
Like, when you build cities, you sort of follow the same system
and the same strategy over and over again.
And, you know, there are very deep strategy games
where you, you know, intricately manage your cities,
like civilization, obviously, and you make a lot of,
like, little decisions that stack.
over a very long period of time.
And we said, well, the essence of our game is that it's a bit more wargaming.
So we didn't want to have that intricacy
and we didn't want to have too much micromanagement into the city.
So we started to look into a system where you could upgrade cities
and expand in a more sort of like broader strokes
and make very large decisions.
So we thought into dividing the world up into sectors and cities expand by claiming new territories.
That sort of thing led to another, you could easily like on paper, sort of see that such a sector system would have like big ramifications for diplomacy.
So if you, you know, build up the world into these sectors, you can trade them, you can sort of plant a flag and this one is mine.
Instead of having a.
You know, like everything that's just done on a hex level.
So that's, um, that's, that's when the thing started rolling on the, on the world map game.
But it, it, it took a lot of iteration as well as to like how you upgrade all these
sectors, how you attach them to your main colony.
Uh, that took a lot of time and a lot of iteration.
Uh, but, uh, eventually we, uh, we saw, yeah, this, this really works.
And, uh, we hope that the people will.
will like this, although it's something entirely new for our series and I think also in the
genre as a whole.
So yeah, that sort of innovation isn't easy.
It's always easier to say, like, OK, let's take a look at how has another game done this
before and trying to do something different is always painful.
Right on, uh, don't mind me over here, I'm just trying to figure out...
I got a lot to juggle on my plate.
Alyssa, can I toss the question ball your way?
It's kind of enjoyable to watch you try to like, uh, talk and make complex decisions at the same time though.
Um...
This is a little more in the wheezy about strategy games that I don't understand.
Might not, might be a little over my head, but uh Satya in chat wants to know while we're talking
about play styles are there any plans to enable tall play styles? I'm not sure, that's lingo I'm
not familiar with there, so I don't know if you can talk around different play style implementation
there. Yeah going wide or tall is a strategy saying whether you're sort of like specialized
like one city and build it up as big as you can.
Another one is wider by spreading yourself thin and claiming a lot of territory, for example.
That's the difference.
Currently our city upgrade tree is sort of capped with the number of provinces that you can attach to a colony,
the number of upgrades that you can build.
And obviously we're looking into expanding the game in the future.
A lot of these type of games, they are in development for years on their initial launch.
Adding additional options for city upgrades is absolutely something that we'll be looking into.
But first we need to digest and see how people are playing, what are people's wishes.
And getting very solid feedback from the community saying,
we'd like to have deeper city management.
It's something that we can do something with.
And yeah.
I guess like one week now out from launch,
how has that initial feedback been?
How is the reception for the features
you have gone over so far?
I think overall very positive.
We are at around 80% positive user reviews.
I mean, there's some people.
Of course, if you compare it to Age of Enders 3,
and they miss a particular feature from that game,
then we'll say, like, we wish you would have this in this game as well,
or some people think that you might have strayed too far or not far enough.
It's a fine line that you need to walk.
But overall we are happy with the reception and we look at all feedback.
Doesn't matter if it's just constructive or people aren't.
really
scary stuff.
I guess even going into like, I have on my notes here, I have 20 years like circled and underlined.
That's a long time for a studio to be making games and also for one particular series to keep going.
And especially with as much like the IP changes you've made this time around too.
And I guess how did you guys kind of, how did that conversation go over like, hey, what if we do like a slight reboot?
What if we go to space?
Like, how did you kind of worm your dev team into that idea as well as like warming the community up to it?
Yeah, for the dev team, that's of course, you know, the dev team exists out of many individuals.
Some people have, you know, like hopes, maybe, you know, some of them want to go back to
like an Overlord style game.
Others might want to try another genre and others say like, okay, we've invested so much
in this engine, this tool set and the experience from our people that it would be crazy to
to try and swap everything around.
I can tell you that when you make a drastic shift in genres,
going from 4X strategy to action RPGs and back,
it's not the wisest business decision that you can make.
It's fun, of course, but it's a very different type of game.
But it's not good for your sanity, on the other hand.
It's a process that you can, it's part of that, it's just a business decision.
And another one is a decision of like, how do we play to our strength without keeping
things, you know, and keep things interesting for everybody.
It's always very important for us.
What do, you know.
us as a team. What's the level of buy-in for a particular project? We wouldn't want to make
a project where people say like, ah, this is really not my thing and I'm going to quit my job.
Yeah, that's a, we'd be very bad. Yeah.
Let's see, uh, ooh, we got a good question from chat.
Uh, Winsley, I would like to know, uh, why sectors show the resource that can be exploited
instead of icons for the climate and terrain?
Um, or, uh, they are concerned that players are confused when they see the icons on each
new sector.
Um, I kind of have no opinion about if it's confusing or not myself, because when I look
at a new sector, I'm looking at, say, this sector right here, I just see the world ceiling
and I'm like, oh, that's a really good name for a place.
When you click on it you see a couple of icons which indicate the resource potential of a sector, how it can be upgraded.
It doesn't list the output, but it actually lists this particular section.
I've got a very small screen because I'm in Research, Production and 2 Energy.
That one could be upgraded as an energy exportation and then you build energy stuff in order to...
use the natural occurring stuff.
So we basically took that, what is it?
That step that translates resource type
into what sort of resource,
so the client type or overlay type into resource out of it.
So people could immediately see, oh, this is energy
and I'm gonna choose my energy upgrade here.
Right on.
Let's see.
I was going to ask about, you touched briefly on porting this over to consoles,
which is a series first for you guys for this particular series.
And can you talk about maybe some of the UI changes and decisions that were made to kind
of make it more readable on consoles, or so it would work both on PCs and consoles equally,
without negatively affecting the other, I guess?
So one of the first things that we did was
basically
We took a look at all of the interfaces and which ones could be sort of like be the same
with slight modifications like swapping yes no buttons with A and B buttons or whatever.
And then interfaces which needed to have like a radical difference like adding a radial menu
as an example.
Then we started to look at readability and one of the things that we added was interface scaling.
So you could scale the interface up and down relatively to how far you were from the screen
or your screen size. So that was another must-have in order for the conversion to start.
And of course, it also benefits PC if you're playing on a small laptop screen versus a very
nice large 30-inch monitor. So that's another one.
One of the principles that we applied was that we wanted to make the people move the
map as little as possible manually.
So people would use the event list in order to take them to all key actions that needed
their attention.
So you don't need to order a sensor on it, you just select a new destination.
Research is ready, we just got taken to the interface, you can very quickly cycle through
these screens without having to do many manual mouse pointery things basically.
So those are a couple of the principles that we applied. Another thing is like in combat
you select units but then immediately you see highlighted which armies it can hit from a
particular location.
just to avoid the large number of manual movements.
And of course, consistency with other games, like, of course,
you have like mouse and keyboard conventions, you know, when you
scroll the map, you have WASD and left click to select, right
click to move, which is sort of like an RTS thing.
Same for console, you know, you try to use conventions.
You know, use the D-pad and the shoulders for the right type of stuff.
It's always interesting to hear how bringing a game to a new platform
will result in these changes that actually benefit the entire thing as a whole
and not just that new platform.
Oh yeah, I mean, I think there's been a tremendous benefit to the PC users as well.
The amount of QA that we put into this game is massive.
PC players would like to play using controller.
If they use a Steam Box or they just like sitting hanging on the couch.
So we have that option available for PC players too.
The interface scaling is available for PC.
Right on, I'm diving into the turn-based kind of X-Commy combat right now.
One thing, I guess one thing that jumps to mind is that games like X, games that are
dedicated to sort of the turn-based tactical like this are often focused on, there's a
lot of fog of war concepts, like where is your enemy and how is this, but this game
is pretty, like these battles start out pretty out in the open and you're able to make...
You're able to plan two or three steps ahead much easier than you are in those games.
Could you sort of talk about your process for designing these sections of the game
and really how you're able to balance it while still trying to make an overall overarching 4X game that still works?
Cool, yeah. So, one of the first starting points is that we create a war.
We don't create a skirmish between hero characters that you want to keep alive.
Of course, you obviously want to keep as much units alive as you can, but the combats tend
to be a lot more lethal in a game like this.
We want them to be over quicker.
Our combats can involve a large number of units, not just infantry types, but also tanks
and aircraft and whatnot.
So the battles need to be, although superficially, might be a lot more lethal.
sort of looks the same, you've got some cover... you've got your overwatch, you've got grenades
and all that type of stuff, but generally they play faster and they're more deadly.
And that's why, for example, Fog of War doesn't really fit in that thing, because that would
really prolong the typical battle.
Although in earlier Age of Wonders games we did have single player dungeons, or PvE dungeons basically,
which had sort of a cover of darkness, which you needed to, sort of Diablo style,
you needed to go in and explore and find the baddies before you could close them.
Maybe we'll go back to that one day.
Right on.
Going to chat, TheCraftyDog has dropped by and is really impressed with the game.
They are asking about a possible Nintendo Switch port.
We sort of, we try not to, there's sort of, if a feature's not announced it's a little
hard to ask about from a dev perspective on this channel.
But I guess, you know, Leonard, the Nintendo Switch is out.
It's a new thing that people, even Paradox is shipping games on.
Yeah.
Because they've got John Romero's game, Empire of Sin, coming out on Nintendo Switch.
Do you have a Switch? Are you enjoying the platform?
Yeah, I have a Switch. I play games myself, but also with my son.
So we play all the Nintendo titles.
We've got the Mario Rabbids game.
It's like an XCOM Lite type of deal.
That game is so weird. It's great.
That game is so wild.
The XCOM devs were saying it's influencing how they make their next game
and the movement system in that game is really good.
So we see soldiers jumping on top of each other.
I'm curious, what do you think about developing for the Switch?
What do you think has to happen for your studio to be able to tackle that challenge?
First of course there is the overall business proposition.
It makes sense, the cost versus the benefit.
And in terms of cost, our game is quite demanding.
Of course, they can make the Witcher on Switch, but one of the key things is what's in our
game is the AIs would take a lot of time.
So CPU load.
So when you see one of these battles here, they can take up to half an hour or so to
play out a typical battle, or 50 minutes.
But the AI fights these battles as well.
You know, when it's an AI turn and they take over a city of independents, or a little bit of loot that they capture.
The AI actually plays this entire battle using the exact same battle map.
With all of the abilities and everything, just in a fraction of a second.
in hundreds of seconds actually, if you've got a fast CPU.
So, and a lot of these battles can spawn during a turn.
And we already have had to make optimizations
for lower spec CPU machines,
like lower spec laptops, for example,
to keep the speed up.
Well, the switches of course,
In architecture, a handheld device, and the question whether or not we could get everything
like that on the Switch, that's one of the first questions we need to look at.
So ensuring that the CPU load would be manageable.
But the Switch is a beautiful machine, fast machine, maybe it works, but I can't answer
that.
Of course, yeah. But it is interesting to know that the challenges aren't just, say, graphical or getting things running, but allowing the AI to properly do what it needs to do in the background and run simulations like this.
And there's practical things as well, like screen size. If you play it undocked and just go on the screen, we might want to change some interfaces in order to make them clearer when seen on such a small screen.
That's a good point.
We are coming up at the end of our hour here as I try to make my way through
this battle, which he said he can take up to half an hours.
This might be, we might still be playing this battle by the time we're
over given the way I play games.
Oh, burning ground.
That's not good.
Okay.
I think we should website Live Stream and I was like, all right,
you may be able to toggle that but come here, type in live.
Hey, Shi def something,
If you've got questions for Leonard, we are still happy to ask them.
Leonard, I guess here's something interesting.
We're talking, we're playing a turn-based, you know, like, tactical...
This is a tactical encounter.
When you're playing Fire Emblem or XCOM, the percentage chance to hit is very important
because it sort of tells you whether it's a good idea to try this maneuver or not.
I'm still figuring out, in XCOM, you can have a 92% chance to hit and those misses feel
really sour.
In Fire Emblem, you can have a 92% chance to hit and...
Those misses don't really come like 92% fire emblem sort of means 100% like how do you accurately communicate to the player?
What that sort of means
What different hit chances mean? Yeah in a game like this?
Yeah, yeah, so we we don't really skew the numbers
Maybe some games do I don't know so when you have C 90 92 percent is actually 100% Yeah
So we don't
We actually have a very clear rule and that is that
Basically whenever you have a...
There's always a 25% chance to grace, and that starts over 100%.
So if you have a 75% chance to hit, that basically means that you will always hit or grace.
So the 25% will be grace.
And then if you go lower than 75%, that's when the miss chances start to come in.
So if you go to 70%, there's a 5% chance to miss.
So you don't have the extremes that you have a 90% chance to hit or a 95% chance to miss
and you will totally miss the shot.
You will always do some damage.
That's how we solved it.
And of course, one other thing is that a lot of our units, especially when carrying assault
rifles and stuff, they fire multiple shots.
The number of shots depends on how far you move.
So if you stay in the green area for this unit.
A single shot unit.
But if that was a Marine or Trooper, you could have three shots when you stay in the green
area.
And that of course spreads out the damage more.
Right on.
I'm about to do my favorite thing in any science fiction game, which is drop a laser on someone's
head.
Alright.
Woo!
Yeah.
I love doing that.
When's live?
Hey guys.
Sorry.
I would like to know, are there any plans to get the AI to approach auto-combat carefully?
12 vs 4 quote-unquote should never result in a lost unit.
I don't know if that's necessarily true from a how armies work perspective.
If you send 12 people in to fight 4, one of those people might get just totally wasted.
So from a game field perspective, I certainly think it's fine.
But I don't know, they're curious.
They would like to know if auto-battles, which I was using to get through most of the streams
we could keep on the top.
Sort of the top layer.
How do you feel you did with those? Do you think they're accurate?
Do you think it's okay for if you're overwhelmingly abusing the enemy's forces
if you go auto battle to have to sacrifice a unit to speed up time?
Because when you're in here you can make optimal decisions, obviously.
Yeah, I mean, it's up to you if you want to take the risk.
I mean, we gave some sort of prediction how the battle will end up.
I mean, it's purely...
a value comparison, so it's not necessarily how well a particular stack of units is kitted
out to kill another stack.
It's just purely the value that these do, so that gives an indication.
But yeah, some people can't stand a loss, and we're looking into maybe for a future
update, and I can't really promise that yet, but we're looking into ways like if you press
auto and you don't like the results.
You can go back to manual, so you'll have an option to retry.
You guys just shipped this game, we were talking before the stream, you're tossing your own update ideas.
Lots of other games have begun to adapt, everything from, you know, quote-unquote events,
where, you know, Apex Legends is having an event right now, obviously that's an always-live multiplayer game,
but then there's Paradox's really good DLC model, where they sell individual DLC packs.
How have you thought, as a studio leader, even though obviously you've got Paradox sitting there,
coddling you in their great big publisher arms...
Sitting off screen.
keeping games afloat and keeping players interested.
What do you think is sort of the way strategy games can approach existing in a live games world?
Yeah, well, live games for us means interacting with the community, getting feedback and listening
to them and dropping new features both as free updates and as premium content. And
premium content, I mean, you know, not microtransactions. We prefer substantial updates.
We will make some new outfits for commanders, for example.
But anything we do is all about improving the game for as many people and for as long as we can.
Like you say, making a game like this sort of a free-to-play...
experience people have tried that with strategy games but none of us have succeeded in doing
that unless you talk if you unless you consider something like class of clans a strategy game
i mean i do but not you know like it's not like it's different it's different yeah it's different
it's a it's a different type of strategy game there's just quite a few strategies
so i'm just going to relive my my x-wing night last night where i had to
basically even though i was ahead i had to give up a shot on it i may really need to get okay cool
yeah we're yeah
Um, ba ba ba, um, oh, uh, Crafty Dog would like, would like, you know, this is just kind of a fun thing from chat.
They've pre-ordered, um, uh, top tier, uh, oh, geez, something got in the way.
They, they bought the top tier when they pre-ordered and they're looking forward to what you are doing in the future.
In terms of the, uh, the expansions?
Yeah.
And Neoangelhelmet also says it's a wonderful game.
Um, uh, ooh! This is kind of a good question. They mentioned, you mentioned a, uh, the satellite
system that got cut, you know, kind of that atmosphere level. Um, uh, they would like to
know what other kind of features got cut making this game. Uh, when you, like, what ideas were
really good and, I don't know, like, that's something I'd like to know about too. Like,
what else did you have to cut to get this game out the door?
Which sounds grim, but it's always curious what good ideas this one is good.
Well, some ideas were cut and we might want to go back to, so I'm probably not going to talk about those.
Let's see. Well, we went through a couple of iterations of the sector system.
And one of them was that the actual colonists that you had in your colony were slotted into slots
that were actually living inside of the...
and inside of the sector.
So if you lost a particular sector,
you could lose the colonists that were in that sector,
but it was quite a clumsy system.
So we decided to cut it.
Okay, I'm going-
I want, no, I want one.
You want one, you want one.
I want to, Mohammed Kapil in chat
has a question that I wanted to ask earlier,
but I forgot to follow up on.
They were asking about that AI system you said where two AI battles will just simulate the entire thing on the actual map.
What was the decision for doing a more resource heavy way of determining the outcome of the battle versus something like a statistical coin flip or something a lot less in depth but more light on the resources?
Yeah, we had such a system in the old Age of Wonders games because the computers weren't fast enough to do it.
But that led to all sorts of problems because you were basically creating two AIs which
had basically... because you weren't really simulating the battle, you were just like
subtracting army strength.
So you had like one particular unit which was immune to the effects of another type
of unit, but you couldn't really model that.
You know, so like when you played manually, you would get such very different results
from a battle than...
when you played automatic.
And also you couldn't really go back and replay the battle
and see the battle as it would unfold.
There was sort of a simulation without movements
that sort of approximated it.
But in the end, just totally simulating the battle,
yeah, allows you to see a cool replace
and immediately see how the AI did.
Maybe for a beginning player, learn the game
to see how the AI would move stuff.
So basically you debug one thing.
And that's it, you don't have to work on two systems.
One of it is sort of an approximation, and the other is sort of the real AI.
So there's one AI that you write.
So it stays true to the strategy genre versus just a numbers game.
Yeah. That's interesting.
With that, I'm going to start wrapping things up.
Thank you, Alyssa, for jumping in with a good question.
That was actually good.
Thank you all for joining the GDC.
Thank you, Chad, for giving it to us.
I don't want to steal someone's good question. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. You can wrap up now. Stop.
You can't see me. I'm glaring.
Shaking your head.
I'm just shaking my head.
Alyssa, take... you asked it. You can take credit.
It was worded in chat for... anyway.
This is stuff we should not do live on camera. I'm sorry.
Anyway, thank you everyone in chat. You've been a great audience today.
Thank you, Leonard, for dropping by.
Thank you all for watching the GDC Twitch channel.
This is a place where we talk to game developers about the making of their games,
how they get made, because that, sharing knowledge between game developers, is kind of our mission.
Speaking of which, if you are at home and you are a game developer of any stripe or experience or background,
we would encourage you to check out the GDC call for submissions.
The Core Concepts call for submissions closes tomorrow.
If you have a talk idea, if you're at home, if you're lurking out there,
I know some of you people are game devs,
If you are the kind of person who has worked on a game
and has something in the last year
or something interesting to share about it,
we encourage you to submit a talk.
If you do in the next 24 hours,
it can go into the core concepts track.
We will be opening our summits, VRDC.
No, it's all summits, but that includes our VR summit,
our narrative summit, our AI summit.
Those call for submissions is going to open up later this month, so if you are a developer working on that kind of stuff, please submit a talk at the end of the month.
If you're a VR or AR developer, join us in October for XRDC.
For more information on that, you can scroll down and check out GDCconf.com, which also you can use to get over to XRDC.
If you're new to the channel, we would appreciate it if you clicked the follow button, because if you do, you'll get notifications when we go live.
We're talking to a lot of developers, there's some really cool games out there that are coming out in the next few weeks.
I wish I could confirm which ones we're getting, but I'm still working with some great PR folks to try and get those interviews to you.
But rest assured if you hit that follow button you will get a notification when we go live and when we go live we will
Go live with someone who knows more about making games than we do and we know something
We know something about making games right Alyssa, you know about financials
Yeah, I have to write something.
You have to write some financial slip. Yeah, exactly.
So we know something, but we just want you to talk to people who know more some things.
With that, I'm going to resist the urge to just keep playing and just keep...
Just one more turn, it's just scratching really hard right now.
But I'm going to resist the urge to keep playing and sign off.
Leonard, thank you so much.
Thank you for having me. Thanks, everybody, for your questions.
Bye, folks.
Bye.