Welcome to this talk titled improving games accessibility in children's games through
QA, which now I'm trying to say it out loud is a bit of a mouthful.
Hope you're all having a great GDC so far.
My name is Hannah Bunce and I am a test engineer at the BBC over in the UK.
Just some housekeeping before we begin.
Please turn all mobile phones, tablets, anything that might make any noise to silent.
And as I'm sure you're all aware, you will be sent surveys for session evaluations at
the end of this session.
Please fill that in, especially if you like what I'm talking about and want to see more
of this in the future.
So a bit of an overview of the session.
I'm going to give a quick introduction to myself, accessibility, and the BBC children's
games team.
An overview of our problem areas within our accessibility testing and QA.
Our current solutions to these problems and then some, I'm going to leave you with some
future tips and tricks for safeguarding against these problems and how hopefully you might
be inspired to do the same in your studios and companies.
So to introduce myself, my name is Hannah Burns.
I have been a QA tester for about four years now.
I have been working at the BBC as both a test engineer and
what is known as an accessibility champion for 18
months, and I've been interested in accessibility
for the better part of a decade now when I started
discovering that I needed subtitles to hear what was
going on in games.
So what is accessibility? Accessibility has a number of definitions. In terms of general
terms, accessibility is about allowing people to access a thing, regardless of what that
thing is, and regardless of their abilities, disabilities, age, race, gender, anything
that might be a barrier to entry.
And in terms of games, it's about allowing people from all walks of life to access and
to play games, which, as I'm sure quite a few of you might be aware of and agree with,
that the more people who play your games, the better it is for everybody, especially
if you make money from people playing those games.
So what is Games at Children's BBC?
For those of you who might not be aware or who have no knowledge of the BBC, it stands
for British Broadcasting Corporation and it is a publicly funded corporation in the UK
that has an obligation to provide entertainment, information and education to the British public
through a variety of platforms and for audiences of all ages.
We do a lot more than just make Doctor Who and Sherlock, I can assure you of that.
You might be aware of some of our products like iPlayer, the BBC Sport website, apps.
We cover a wide range of content and for a wide range of audiences.
What we specifically do at Children's BBC with regards to games is we provide games
for children aged between 2 and 12.
through these two brands, CBeebies and CBBC.
CBeebies is aimed at preschool kids,
so between the ages of 2 to 6,
and CBBC is aimed at a slightly older audience
of between 6 and 12.
Of course, part of this service is providing entertainment,
including people with disabilities.
So in order to do this,
we have to make sure that our games are as accessible as possible.
So to give you an idea of how busy we are
and how many games we do, on average,
we release three games a month, which adds up to quite a lot.
And recently our budgets have been expanding,
and as these have been expanding,
so have the breadth and complexity of the games.
Naturally, this has had an effect on QA and QA resourcing.
And also, on top of developing and testing these three games
a month, we also develop and maintain
an in-house interaction engine called Iver.
Any British people in the audience might get that joke.
I didn't when I first started working there.
So...
Ah, crap. Sorry.
So when we started looking at our accessibility QA,
we noticed a problem,
which is with this game,
called Something Special, the Looking Game.
This was released in the spring of 2016,
and it was designed to be a completely blinder-friendly game,
primarily through the use of screen readers and in-game audio.
The game, which if we were in the UK, I'd be able to actually show you.
Unfortunately, I can't access the game outside of the UK.
It's a very simple hidden object game.
The main character, Mr. Tumble, who is a hit with kids of all ages and also some adults
with various disabilities, absolutely love this character.
He doesn't decide to lose objects, he just loses objects.
He's enlisted your help to find them around his house.
When you click on an object to find,
you're shown a photorealistic representation of the object,
and then also the Makaton symbol for this object.
The object is then animated to hide behind
one of three buttons,
which are a red, blue, and green button.
We also provide a colorblind mode of this game
where the object will hide behind a square,
circle, or triangle button.
So we don't rely just on color.
So when this game went live, we thought, great, we were shouting about it from the rooftops,
like this was our first ever completely blind-friendly game.
So a couple of weeks later, we received a complaint from a blind player stating that
the game could not be accessed via voiceover on iOS.
It was fine on TalkBack on Android, but just not voiceover on iOS.
After much panicked investigation between myself, the project manager and my test lead,
who were the only people really assigned to the project at the time,
we discovered that the final build we tested actually broke the screen reader functionality.
This final build that we received came in three hours before the game had to go live.
So basically zero time for proper regression testing or any kind of testing.
At that point, we only had time to say, yep, this game loads on a few devices.
It doesn't just crash and burn.
So we went live with it.
And so this was a horrible thing for our team
to have to go through.
It did kickstart the improvement period
that we so desperately needed.
Around the same time, development
started on a new CBeebies app called Playtime Ireland.
Again, it's only available in the UK.
I apologize, because it's quite a fun app.
So the purpose of this game was to bring our HTML5 games into the hands of our audiences.
So parents could download our games, put them in the app, and then take their kids on long
car journeys and keep them quiet.
So now we not only needed to consider games accessibility, but also app accessibility.
And at times, these can be two completely different beasts.
So this introduction of the app also doubled our QA requirements.
One certification period for games to go on the website, and one certification period
to go into the app.
And that's not including the actual app testing itself.
So naturally we ramped up recruitment.
And within a few months we went from a team of three testers to six, which in turn meant
doubling the accessibility testing training.
And whilst the recruitment was going on, we also had some issues behind the scenes with
guidelines.
So the BBC as a whole has a wealth of guidelines for digital accessibility.
These are used throughout our entire digital portfolio.
However, very few of these guidelines actually apply to games, which caused a lot of confusion
for some of our developers, a lot of confusion for the designers, and naturally a lot of
confusion for us testers.
So a lot of our improvements actually came from compiling a games accessibility document
from the ground up with the help of the BBC's digital accessibility team and the resources
available from sites such as gamesaccessibilityguidelines.com.
And we also found it was actually a great way to get UX and QA working together as these
two departments very rarely interact.
So QA is the final boss before going live.
But it doesn't need to be.
We now have QA looking at projects from kickoff meetings
through to prototypes, to alpha stage, beta,
and then final release candidate.
So QA are involved from the very beginning.
And now we also have time dedicated in kickoff meetings
for QA and also accessibility,
and then turn accessibility.
QA.
So this is one of the major improvements that we started was we got buy-in from the project
managers, the product managers, and our content producers to get QA in from the ground up.
So one of our other solutions at the moment is a lot of documentation.
So not much has changed in the practical aspect of our testing.
We still do our manual testing much the same way as we did before.
And we are currently looking at automation solutions.
So the more effective changes have come from implementing more robust processes.
We adopted a certification.
period very similar to what you would see from Sony, Microsoft, and Nintendo.
We implemented this about 12 months ago and it has been a major hit with all of our developers.
So these are just basically a set of technical tests that must be passed before a game is
cleared to go live.
And the biggest of these tests, the biggest section, is accessibility, which is what this
first screenshot is.
It's just a snippet of our accessibility test cases in TestRail.
These test cases just live there.
They are generic enough to be used across multiple projects at multiple times.
And they are written in such a way that any tester can come in and could just understand
what needs to be done straight away.
The second screenshot I have there is just the title page of our Children's Games Accessibility
Guidelines and Recommendations, which is a document that gets sent out to any of our
third-party developers, our internal developers, our UX designers, and basically anyone involved
in the project.
These documents are all hosted in a place where anybody who might even be thinking about
doing a game for us can actually read them and get on board with our ideals before development
even begins.
So more improvements that we've made.
These are what I tend to call the four C's because they're just four things that will
become the letter C. And the first of which is collaboration.
So over the last year we have undertaken two massive research projects in a crossover between
QA and UX.
The first of these research projects was in collaboration with the University of Edinburgh
in Scotland.
with experts in autism.
The second project that we did was a collaboration
with two external accessibility consultants
to do an audit of all of our games, which at the time,
there were over 200 games that these consultants helped
us audit to see how many of our games
could be played with one or two switches.
The first project we found some interesting things
that.
can't talk about too much today, unfortunately,
with how to design for kids with autism
and how to keep them included.
We went to a bunch of specialist schools,
and we gained some major insights.
And it was worthwhile having a QA tester there
to go back and report back to the rest of the QA team.
Because we found this helps increase the understanding
of how and why things have been designed in a particular way,
which in turn improves the quality of bugs
that developers get.
and just all around improves the quality of the project.
So the second thing is to champion accessibility
at all levels.
At the BBC, we have a accessibility champion network,
which at the moment is over 100 people strong.
And these are people from all walks of the project hierarchy,
so from heads of departments all the way down
to developers and testers.
And these people consist of a wide range of technical backgrounds as well.
So whilst creating a network might be impractical within a game studio, there's nothing wrong
with being a champion of accessibility yourself.
The way we like to think of things is that if you can see a way for your games or your
product to be more accessible for your players, speak up.
The results are nearly always worth it.
And then finally, onto consistency.
We found that having documents written in consistent ways,
in consistent layouts, helped everybody
to understand what we were trying
to portray in these documents.
And then communication.
Communication is absolutely key in.
QA and accessibility.
Because whilst common sense normally prevails,
this is a point that most tend to forget.
The open communication lines between the games team and the apps team,
and then the apps team, our third-party developers,
and the apps team and the QA team,
basically you see the picture with open communication lines
with all different teams,
have been unparalleled in helping everybody improve
the accessibility of our games.
And since implementing all of these, we've not had a single accessibility complaint,
and we have released well over 50 games since that original complaint came in.
So as I said earlier, accessibility testing and accessibility design are now actual agenda
items on project kickoff meetings.
And we have found that accessibility issues found
during certification of these projects, of these games,
have decreased, especially with developers
who show enthusiasm for accessibility
during these kickoff meetings.
Another IQA team is now larger than it's ever been before.
We used to have monthly QA meetings.
They were only about 10 to 20 minutes long, just a quick
catch-up to say, oh, what have you been testing this month,
et cetera, et cetera.
We've now increased this to weekly, and we've increased
them to 45 minutes.
These allow us to go into more technical details of what we've been testing and how we've been
testing it.
And it also allows for us to share new accessibility tips and tricks to be passed on to the team.
So the future, there's obviously always more room for improvement.
And whilst we're in a better position than we've ever been with regards to accessibility
and also with regards to QA, we are always looking to make things better.
So the first thing that we want to do is more training.
We are ramping up recruitment again, and naturally we want people to be on board with our accessibility
ideals from day one.
So what we're looking to do is when we hire a new tester, as well as getting them on board
with all of our normal processes, we're going to go through them with accessibility testing,
give them a few tasks to get their feet wet, and just basically help them from day one.
This should be common sense, but again, maintaining documentation is something that our games
team struggle with and I'm sure is an ongoing issue with many other studios.
We have taken it on ourselves in QA to maintain these documentations because normally we're
the ones that need it the most, and if no one else is going to do it, we might as well
do it.
So something that is quite, what I think is quite unique to the BBC is having specialised
working groups.
I founded a working group called AlleyCats, which stands for Accessibility Champion Testers
in the summer of last year.
People who are invited to this group are people who are test engineers, QA analysts, but are
also part of the BBC's Accessibility Champion Networks.
So we get together on a bimonthly basis,
and we learn things from each other about, like,
so for example, some testers from Sport
had a new way of doing automation accessibility testing, which
then they shared with people from another department.
And now that other department, their product's accessibility
has just skyrocketed.
And we like to emphasize communication.
And as said earlier, we found that with having open lines
of communication, whether it's just going up to someone's
desk or through more formal means, having these open lines
of communication is just helping everybody.
And then finally, we want to review our processes on a more
regular basis.
I recommend something between.
two to three months to review your processes, because if you review them, say, every two
weeks, that's not enough time for new processes to sink in and for you to actually see if
they're working or not.
Thank you.
I did go through that quite quickly.
I do apologise.
Any questions?
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
If you have any questions, there's a microphone there,
please use it.
Hi there.
Hey.
First of all, thanks for your talk.
Thank you.
I was wondering, I'm from Lionbridge Game Services,
we work a lot with localization and other languages,
so I'm kind of wondering how much you put
under this umbrella, accessibility,
as far as people who speak.
languages other than English?
That is a very good question that I actually answered after a talk I did on Monday.
I should actually put it in this.
So, as part of our remit to help the British public, we also produce games for Welsh, Gaelic
and Irish.
And these do present unique challenges, mostly to do with subtitles.
I don't know if you're familiar with Welsh at all, but compared to English, there's a lot more characters.
So we've had some unique challenges with regards to the size of subtitles and where to place them on screens.
And I do have some amazing screenshots of a game that was just basically covered in
subtitles in the Welsh language.
You couldn't see the game at all.
So with that, we basically edited the script a little bit.
Obviously, we got permission from all the editorial staff and the brand owners to do
that.
But that's the only unique challenge we've had with regards to language is just with
subtitles.
I guess part of my question is...
Is when it comes to folks who are there in immigrant populations who speak a language
that isn't an official language.
So is that just a totally different department that works on that or is that part of your
group?
No, we only look at English language things and then about five or six games per year
will be translated into Welsh, Gaelic and Irish, which are the official languages in
the UK.
Gotcha.
Okay.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Hi, I'm Stephanie from Vision Game Labs.
We're based in Wales, actually, so Welsh is a thing for us.
I was just wondering, really, when
you were developing the things for visual impairment,
whether or not you had used anything
to determine the level of visual impairment?
or whether that's something that you would like to work on together.
That is definitely something we would like to look at.
We do a lot of testing around colour contrasting
to help with people with low vision.
Obviously, because also with games for kids,
they're full of bright colours and high contrast anyway,
so we're sort of lucky in that regard
that we're making games for kids and that's what kids like.
The colour contrast is the main thing but also, like, the size of icons and everything
because yet again, for kids, children's and games for kids, sorry – we like to keep
the art quite simple and well defined, which, again, is kind of cheating for people with
low vision, but it helps everybody.
I hope that answers your question.
Fab, fab.
And if you want to have a chat afterwards, please.
Any other questions?
Excellent.
Thank you.