Diversity is the mix, woo,
and inclusion is making the mix work.
Who here thinks that we need to improve on our diversity
and inclusion in the games industry?
Lovely.
This is not a talk on defining diversity and inclusion,
and nor to convince you that we need diversity
and inclusion in the game industry.
I'd refer you to...
the GDC vault or ask the neighbor who raised their hands.
What this talk is one studio's how for starting a DNI.
This will be a comprehensive talk
and I will use all my 30 minutes.
Questions will be answered after the talk across this hall
and I would appreciate you filling out the evaluation form.
I'm sure you've heard that already.
This talk is about sharing the D&I journey of Avalanche Studios New York from 2016 to 2018.
I will share lessons we learned, challenges we continue to face, best practices we discovered,
and successes we've had.
This is intended to be a starter kit for you to have a sustainable and active D&I initiative
in your company.
like we did in the New York studio.
Since this is a grassroot initiative,
this talk is specific to the New York studio.
In this talk, I won't offer any shortcuts,
nor magic pill or bullets.
It's not to vilify white males,
who are still the majority of this industry.
Rather, this highlights the importance of white males
to be an active ally in this D&I journey.
There's a lot of heart required to starting a D&I initiative.
Before embarking on this journey,
find out what's your with them, your what's in it for me,
your why for doing D&I.
It could be global competitiveness,
increasing your bottom line, being an ally and advocate,
avoiding lawsuits and bad publicity.
Or like me, you've been unlucky in the lottery of birth
and would like to make things better for you
and others who are also marginalized.
My with them is this.
I grew up thinking that discrimination
is just a part of life and that you don't have a choice,
but to accept that those who are fair-skinned,
rich, tall, and white get all the opportunities
in the world and those that are not are just unlucky.
I grew up in the Philippines, born and raised in the Philippines, and at a young age I've
seen the inequality of life.
I moved to Singapore and was treated like a second class because of my color, which
is brown.
I moved to the U.S. and I'm an immigrant, and I experienced the microaggressions, but
it was only here that I got woke.
I could actually try to do something about the inequality
and make things better for me and folks like me.
Heads up, not everything that I'll share today
may be applicable to your team.
However, the answer is within your team.
It'll make you ask questions after this.
I am incredibly excited to be here and share with you
our ongoing journey with D&I.
The more we explore, the more we find out
that there's still a lot of work to be done.
We are a work in progress.
Here's some background on Avalanche Studios.
The company was founded in Stockholm, Sweden 15 years ago.
New York is the only studio outside of Sweden
and opened in 2011.
Avalanche Studios developed Mad Max,
the Just Cause series, the Hunter series,
Rage 2, and Generation Zero.
I was hired for Avalanche Studios three years ago
and I was ecstatic that part of my marching orders
was to do something about DNI.
Like most small to medium video game companies,
it's a struggle to have time, budget, and resources.
DNI is like, aw, that's nice, but nobody really gives time
and prioritize it, so it easily gets deprioritized.
I am an HR department of one, of a triple-A studio.
So I, too, have an alibi of being swamped.
So in 2016, I kick-started our D&I initiative
by hiring an external trainer to teach us about D&I.
Unfortunately, the training was not satisfactory.
For the one day event.
We were grouped and asked to complete tasks
around New York City.
Draw on the street, duct tape a tree,
copy a tattoo of a stranger,
eat something we haven't eaten before at Chinatown,
invade a store to take a picture,
climb to a rooftop to take a picture.
It was funny when we were doing it,
but the training ended and we realized
we didn't learn anything about DNI.
I felt personally responsible for that failed training.
We did get some of our money back.
The harder part was to gain the trust of employees
that they will not be misled again.
It was fun because it turned out to be a team bonding.
Again, we didn't learn anything about D&I.
This is not to discredit external trainers.
A failed training is actually common
according to the Society of Diversity
where I recently got certified to be a diversity practitioner.
Why?
The trainings are the go-to for starting a D&I initiative, and it almost always fails
because it tries to address a huge and complicated topic, which is D&I, in a one-day event.
The more fatal reason why D&I training fails is most companies just stop any initiative
after a failed training.
So the overarching lesson for starting a D&I initiative
is slow and consistent steps.
So like this baby, they have milk first
before they move on to solid food.
My first immediate lesson for when I started in 2016
after that D&I failed training
is humility partnered with curiosity.
Humility to accept that this is not a problem that can be solved by one person alone.
And curiosity to start asking questions of what will.
So I did one-on-ones, Google Forum surveys, focus groups to find out what our employees
need, what are the pressing issues, and what are the long-term goals.
The second lesson is commitment to transform by the leadership.
This is done through creating and modeling a psychologically safe environment
where people are comfortable to give feedback.
I'm going to say it again, comfortable to give feedback.
We haven't perfected this and this is a never-ending effort.
A few steps that we started were we updated the handbook.
communicated the updates to our employees,
called out behavior through one-on-ones
that do not support this initiative,
and leadership also started implementing changes
suggested by employees.
The third lesson is establishing
internal and external partners.
After admitting that the first attempt was a failure,
I partnered with the leadership team,
our employees, and specific external groups
to boost our agenda.
I'll give examples in the next slides.
The second overarching lesson is diversity and inclusion
go hand in hand.
One cannot work without the other.
So you can't just hire a bunch of diverse folks
and say, good luck, because they will not thrive.
So our two goals are foster inclusivity in the company
and increase diversity representation
in the demographics of our employee.
So what are our actions to foster inclusivity?
If I could sum it up in one word,
it's called it's partnership, or creating partnership.
We have three ongoing internal partners.
Number one is the full support of a leadership who listens.
Having D&I considered in our events was a good start.
For example, in representing the company externally,
one small easy step is to make sure
that there's diversity in the representatives we send out.
In video game development, the industry is notoriously known for crunch.
You don't like crunch too, right? Or overtime? No?
Admittedly, this is a little easier for us because the company already is established
to be a huge advocate of work-life balance.
We have seven weeks of paid time off and our health, dental, vision insurances
are 100% paid by the company for employee plus dependents, including domestic partners.
Updating policies are also vital.
An easy win for us was changing one of our company paid
holidays, Good Friday holiday, which is a holiday for
Christians, to a floating holiday so that others who
don't observe Lent can observe their own holidays.
Establishing our business resource group or BRG is the heart of our D&I team.
How did we start the team?
I scheduled a one-on-one to those who emailed me and spoke to me about the failed training.
I asked them if they were willing to do voluntary work for D&I.
Employees who get it and want to do something about it.
Instructions for a project will remain a priority.
We will meet two to three times a month, and we would plan for activities.
They will not be policing employees.
We started out with eight volunteers and three studio management.
As time went on, there were attrition and addition within the team.
I would like you to be mindful of the word diversity fatigue.
It is a real issue where people get tired and impatient to see immediate changes.
As of this writing, there are six D&I team members.
I'm giving a shout out to our remaining OGs.
Third and important partners are every one of us, or employees, who turn out to be our
allies, creating awareness for ourselves and employees about microaggressions, educating
employees of interruptions during meetings and discussions, and implementing zero tolerance
for harassment, plus educating them on how to be an ally, foster an environment ready
for more diversity.
I heard a comment today on if you're a white male and you want to be an ally, what do you do?
Ask that question to the person you want to be an ally to.
In 2017, we started partnering with the following external allies, the academia,
non-profit organizations, and local New York groups.
We've hired incredible talents from our partner universities.
These employees also help out with school outreach.
Since there are not a lot of guides and materials out there to
Help us make D&I work.
Partnering with non-profit organizations
have been extremely helpful to our cause.
Tapping on their specialities are vital
and time plus cost efficient for us.
Lastly, our local New York video game groups.
New York is home to talented indie game developers.
Our being at events show our support and oneness.
We provide resources through talks by our developers
and we also share our expertise.
It has been a struggle and a balancing act to find thoughtful activities that make our
D&I initiative sustainable and efficient.
A few of our favorite and successful activities are awareness activities.
These are high impact, educational,
and the cost is minimal.
Here are some examples.
Roundtables are made of a panel.
They are volunteers, depending on the topic,
who have stories to tell, and there's a moderator.
We've had good success with our roundtables,
but they require a lot of preparation.
One learning experience for me from a roundtable
is I have an employee who I have difficulty talking to
because at times he has difficulty understanding.
At that roundtable, he shared that
Spanish is his second language, and he felt really bad that his parents didn't speak English,
that he wished that they did so that he won't be in this predicament.
Him having shared that really helped me in terms of communicating with him.
The next one is documentaries.
These are easy and have high impact.
We choose a documentary that's based on a monthly theme.
Newsletters are a collection of research
on a topic that we would like for our employees to know.
Based on feedback, we hired a trainer again,
geared to empowering women and the marginalized.
This time it was useful because it was targeted
and it was specific.
More importantly, our conversations are the soul of our D&I initiatives.
For management, making sure all issues and concerns are listened to
and resolved as much as we can. For employees, encouraging difficult conversations,
help foster a good working relationship with their co-workers.
Two key things to maintain an active D&I initiatives
are planning a monthly theme as focus for the D&I initiatives.
This helps immensely since the D&I team all
have full-time jobs in the company.
Next is sending a feedback form through Google Form.
That's free.
After every event, to know real time if the activity
was effective or not.
I'm going to share and spend some time talking
about our 2018 calendar.
so you would be able to picture what a D&I initiative may look like when you implement it.
I will also share selected feedback from some activities. 2018 was our year two of our D&I
journey.
In January, our theme was global citizens.
We have diversity and nationality being in New York,
and a majority of us relocated from somewhere to work there.
Our roundtable activity was to understand the struggles
or differences and challenges of relocating.
We had four volunteers who are immigrants, relocators,
and people who have worked abroad.
And they shared their personal stories and their struggles
and their triumphs, all to create awareness.
My takeaway was those who have to get visas, especially
in the US, have a lot to worry about
versus someone who's local who don't
have to worry about that on top of their work.
In February, for Black History Month,
we sent out a newsletter educating our employees
on why in the US this is celebrated.
We showed 13th, a Netflix documentary
at a bring your own lunch,
and had a debrief at a lunch the week after.
This thought provoking documentary analyzed
the criminalization of African Americans
and the US prison boom.
In March, for Women's Month, we sent out a newsletter,
watched the documentary Misrepresentation,
a film showcasing the horrifying realities
of female media representation.
Video games as a form of media is powerful
in influencing our audience.
As creators, knowing the misrepresentation of women
is useful for being mindful on what we create.
We had four women as well participated from Avalanche Studios at an external
event in New York.
And a lot were happily surprised that, wow, there are women in Avalanche Studios?
Also, the women in the company started Ladies Who Pastry.
It's a half an hour get together biweekly of ladies to fika and chat.
Fika is a Swedish tradition of a short break or downtime with coffee or snacks.
In April for Spanish American Heritage Month,
we taught our employees how to say the correct pronunciation
of the Spanish words in our game.
Just Cause 4 is set in South America.
For May, we sent out a newsletter
on Asian Pacific Heritage Month.
One of my favorite activities is the Privilege Walk.
You can search this on YouTube.
I think it's the best way to talk about privilege
without going into semantics,
but just share personal stories.
There are 35 questions, all of you start in one line,
and depending on the question,
you either step forward or step back.
And the discussions after that was just priceless.
Another thing that happened in May came from the feedback we got from women,
which was the need for a training for respect in the workplace and assertiveness.
This was in the height of the Me Too movement, and aside from enforcing a zero tolerance in the workplace,
we got a trainer to equip the women and marginalize with skills to face this issue.
My personal takeaway from this is that as women and minorities,
we tend to say sorry way too many times.
So at times, just avoid saying sorry and say excuse me.
Like, sorry, I got this rule in book.
Just say excuse me, I have this rule in book.
It improves our assertiveness.
In June for Pride Month, we had the roundtable where some LGBTQ plus employees volunteered
to share their stories.
Our goal was to normalize LGBTQ plus and hearing a familiar person's story was vital to this
goal.
Their comfort in coming out showed that they trust the organization and that they felt
that they have co-workers who are ready to listen.
We went on a three-month hiatus.
In July, our studio closed for two weeks
for our summer break tradition.
August and September, we were extremely busy
finishing the game.
We restarted in October for Indigenous Peoples Month.
We had a presentation at a company meeting
on what and who are the indigenous people.
We mindfully looked for ways to link our initiatives
to be industry-specific.
Again, info is not readily available.
So for Indigenous Peoples Month, we looked for games that have Native Americans as protagonists
and we made it available for employees to play during their break.
Our final activity for 2018 was Disability in Games,
and we partnered with a non-profit organization,
Able Gamers, to educate us on what we can do as developers
to make games that are more accommodating
to disabled players.
They helped design the new Xbox Adaptive Controller.
We invited them to our studio in New York,
and we also hosted an event where we opened our studio
to external folks so that they can spread the message
of enhancing the disabled player experience
so more people can play.
New York recently passed a law to require an interactive
preventing harassment training for all employees.
We achieved 100% compliance in this educated our employees
on preventing harassment.
I believe that laws can help the DNI initiative in that,
for instance, when you're requesting for more budget,
if it's for compliance issue or purposes,
then the budget is easy to get.
The other New York law that I like a lot
is making it illegal to ask candidates
their current salary.
This way employers just pay the market and not a previous salary, which historically
is lower for women and minorities.
And that was our 2018 calendar.
Thank you.
I wasn't expecting that.
But you think you can do one activity from that list?
Good.
Our second goal was to improve our diversity hires.
Improving our diversity numbers in the company
is all good for creativity.
A common thing to hear from naysayers,
though, is that they're colorblind
and that DNI is not a problem.
And think that we lower the quality of hires
when we start diversity hiring.
Diversity hiring, however, is just
to create a level playing field for all.
Not empowering some while disenfranchising others.
It is just casting a wider net and still hire the best out of that pool.
To cast a wider net, one of the first few things we reviewed were our initiatives in sourcing and recruiting.
First, I conducted an internal interviewer's training with tools and
best practices for interviewing.
Making hiring managers aware of their biases was a goal of the training.
Interviewers are instructed to focus on competencies and potential of a candidate
versus hiring how they normally used to,
which is usually hiring someone who looks like them and are like them.
To expect change, you must change our interviewing habits.
Second is better sourcing process.
There's data to prove that updating the job descriptions
to be gender neutral, providing a description
of what the role is, versus itemizing required
qualifications increases the likelihood
that females would apply.
Best practices include avoiding ninja or bro language
and painting a culture of just always partying and drinking.
Discovering new job sites to post our jobs that would have different reach was another thing we did.
We also increased our referral bonus. We saved on recruitment fees and got quality candidates from referrals.
Third, we are aware that the first thing that candidates look at specifically in the U.S. to find out about the company is Glassdoor.
They are known as the quote unquote enemy of the company, most companies.
We partnered with them instead to make sure that information on Glassdoor about
Avalanche Studios is accurate.
A few of easy updates are correcting what our benefits are and
sharing our activities and news.
Candidates find out about our commitment to work life balance, and
this is attractive to women and those with families.
We continue to work on what needs improvement based on reviews, and
increase our engagement by replying to reviews, good or bad.
The next two actions are for long-term results.
We increased our studio visits.
We accommodated requests for more schools and students
to come to the studio, meet and greet the developers,
and know that making video games is a real job
that they can have.
Same goal of Take Your Kids to Work Day on a grander scale.
The visit includes basic information on what are the different roles that they can be on
a AAA project, and the tools or software that they can start learning and enhancing.
It is heartwarming to inspire and motivate young, underprivileged, diverse kids to pursue
their passion in video games.
We believe that we can have a more diverse pool of candidates in the future.
When we start educating a more diverse group of youngsters,
that video game making is a wonderful possibility and career for everyone.
Just two weeks ago, there were ten year olds who come to the studio and
want to learn programming.
And it blew my mind because their questions are about C++.
And I'm like, what did I do when I was ten?
Fifth, we extended our reach to minorities
and marginalized groups by being present at their events.
Examples are Game Devs of Color Expo, PlayNYC,
AbleGamers, New York City Video Game Critics Circle,
and Animation Project.
We have improved our number of hits and minimize our misses in our activities as
time goes on.
I would like you to be aware and learn from our challenges as well.
The main thing is there are not a lot of materials out there, nor
guides to help us.
Knowing what works for your demographics is the most important part.
And knowing comes from conversations, surveys, asking questions,
being curious, don't be afraid to look dumb.
We often have production schedule conflict because we have a game to finish.
The D&I team has to be mindful of that when planning for activities.
In the beginning of this talk, I shared that D&I requires a lot of heart.
There will be discouragements from others,
primarily because of their hardwired biases.
And thoughtfully looking for activities is taxing because we don't want
to alienate others who are not yet our allies.
We are restricted with not having the biggest budget
in the world to do grander things.
And we've also experienced members of our D&I team leave,
and since it's a voluntary work, we don't hold them back,
and it's never easy.
It is hard work, time-consuming,
but I'm proud to share with you
that this is one of the most fulfilling initiatives
I've been fortunate to be a part of,
and I've learned so much.
I'm happy to report that in two years, our different activities and
partnerships resulted into the following.
We have nearly doubled our women hires.
Our active and sustainable D&I initiatives made noticeable impact to the lives
of all employees, especially the marginalized.
By just casting a wider net, we've hired our first woman programmer,
promoted from within a woman to senior producer.
We hired interns where three out of four were women.
One of the women got hired as a full-time employee.
Our retention rates for women has also been very high.
True story.
We were having our Coney Island trip in June,
and one of the high tech companies,
their names may have book and face in it,
and they challenged us to a tug of war.
They lost the first round and asked for a redo,
asking for more women from our team.
We still won the second round, but I'm more happy
that we have more than enough women
to even participate in a tug of war.
We also have increased our people of color hires to half.
Our activities have fostered a comfortable environment
for employees to give feedback
as to what we can improve in our games.
One African-American employee suggested to change the name
of one of our characters because the original name
was offensive to African-Americans.
A Hispanic employee suggested the initiative
to teach our employee how to pronounce the Spanish words
in our game correctly.
This same comfortable environment led to LGBTQ plus employees saying that they're comfortable
to be themselves and comfortable coming out.
I haven't even mentioned the many ripple effect that we've had to everyone since we started.
The bright ideas that come from our employees and connections we've made are priceless.
These are tangible changes that fuel our efforts.
2019 and onwards, we would like to continue on the journey to the ultimate goal of D&I
protecting our games.
If you could only take three takeaways from today,
here's a summary of what you can bring back
to your organizations depending on your role
immediately when you get back next week,
or unless you're on vacation next week.
For those in management.
Humility is the way for D&I to start.
Without your support, D&I will not fly.
Remain curious as to what would make
your organizations better.
Listen and commit to transform.
For the content developers and creators,
you are the most important part of the equation.
You are most needed to be an ally.
If you don't know how, ask.
Keep the feedback loop by continuing to care
and advocate for equity and equality.
To my fellow HR, our people business needs a lot of heart.
Our best ammunition is creating awareness, exercising compassion,
and continued dialogue with our stakeholders.
Easier said than done?
Yeah.
Worth it?
It will be.
Why am I here today?
I'm not an expert.
I don't work for the perfect company.
Newsflash, there's none out there.
I haven't been working long in video games,
and in this industry, it seems to matter.
The probability of being listened to
is directly proportional to how long you've been in games.
Budget and resources are always scarce.
I'm here to share that in spite and despite
of what we're up against, you can start an active
and sustainable D&I initiative in your company.
I hope you go back to work and implement ideas
from the starter kit, no matter what your position
is in the company.
you can be part of the solution.
It is an uphill battle and some days are more challenging
that it's easy to not do it.
There are days when we step back two times
and we make mistakes,
or others who we work with make it harder.
There's a definite cost to doing nothing.
With globalization and changing demographics,
DNI is no longer a, aw, that's nice.
It is a business strategy that every company,
whatever their size is, must have to be competitive.
Bring the starter kit to someone who gets it
and also wants to do something about it.
This can't be done alone.
Who will you share the starter kit to?
Together, we can all be the change
that we wish to see for improving D&I in games.
Thanks for being here.