Hi everyone, my name is Yaji. I'm the general manager of the O-Pixels brand of Streamline
Media Group. So O-Pixels is one of the brands on the Streamline Media Group umbrella that
focuses and specializes in large-scale 3D production.
I, a bit of a personal introduction, I entered video games as a bilingual project manager
and I worked on projects such as Street Fighter 5, Little Nightmares 2, before I had the opportunity
to grow a new brand together with the Streamline Media Group as a general manager called All Pixels.
And naturally during it was a big shift to going from a project manager to a general manager running a brand.
And it was a total paradigm shift between being very milestone and project focused.
So single project focused to looking at long term and teams focus in terms of longevity.
And it was a huge shift in mindset that was, of course, disorienting at first,
but it was a very enjoyable experience having the opportunity to learn and experiment with different
configurations of teams. And it naturally led me to really think about what makes teams resilient
in the long term, what makes business resilient in the long term. So a lot about business continuity.
And the reason that I chose this topic for GDC 2021
is because it's not only beneficial for the business
owners to have this understanding or bigger
context of what's needed to keep the teams running
resilient in the long term, but I
thought it would be also beneficial for producers
and project managers who don't really have the opportunity
to run businesses from A to Z necessarily on a daily basis
to have this bigger context as their.
running their day-to-day, the ins and outs of production.
It definitely gives you a new eyesight and a paradigm
to look at different things as you are problem solving
because project management is a continuation
of problem solving on a daily basis,
which is why I chose this topic.
So.
Going into the next slide, why focus on resilience?
Well.
Game development scene is suffering a lot from issues such as high turnover, burnouts,
mental health issues, all of which has come to the surface a lot during this pandemic.
And there's definitely a lot of eyes on us and how we do things here.
There's a lot of scrutiny. And it's easy to think that it's all because of, you know,
the pandemic, the coronavirus.
people being stuck at home, yes, to a degree has a factor.
And I think it has accelerated a lot of these issues to the surface again.
But we have to remember that these are the the issues that we have
and the challenges that we have always been facing as an industry
that was prevalent all the way throughout.
So and I thought it was very unfortunate because a lot of people who come into this industry,
they come into it out of passion and love for craft and for games.
And naturally that made me really think about, okay, I am running a brand that focuses on large scale production.
How do I keep this large team resilient over time?
And how do I keep teams that wants to grow their career in games and not necessarily get burned out after two to three years?
And how do I figure that so that we're not just set up for a single success or a single title success or a single product success?
or single milestone or project success but rather business continuity and how we can
all win together as a team so in terms of career growth.
And my values is aligned with the Streamline Media Group's value.
The company mission here is that we're building, our mission is to build a place where the creators
and the fans can come together and make a living out of their passion and make a living out of
the game, the joys of making game. And
that aligned and we're on the same page very fortunately.
And as a result, I had a lot of opportunities to
experiment and have fun with,
okay, how do I configure everything so that our team
doesn't get burned out after two to three years? So it's not just about
winning in the short term, winning this milestone or winning this project,
but us being together and surviving this and being resilient
together in the long term.
So Streamline was founded in 2001 in Amsterdam in an apartment in Amsterdam.
I think that's a.
a story that a lot of the indie developers share.
But I think what's what really set Streamline apart for me
was that they have survived for 20 years,
which in other industries, it may not be much.
But I think in games, after five, six years of being in games as a company,
you're considered one of the fossils, which is hilarious,
but also very unfortunate at the same time, because it points to the fact
that not many businesses and not many teams survive.
after their initial passion or initial fire has died down.
Streamline has gone through throughout the 20 years,
multiple changes.
We have gone through the changes in technology,
changes in console cycles, economic downfalls, 9-11,
global pandemics, global drama.
And it was our resilience that has
made us survive in all of those challenges.
And not only survive, but thrive in all of those challenges.
Continuing to build a product and publish products,
continuing to not only
adapt to different ecosystems but actually build the ecosystem called games combining
the media and technology together in our scene.
So as we were going through that journey as a game developer,
we have started out at one point as a service provider,
and we're now a game developer and a publisher as well.
So throughout that journey, we have definitely
learned how to retain talents, how to attract and grow
top talents.
how to be creative. I think creative is creativity is the word that's overlooked a lot of times
and are very kind of focused a lot in terms of art and design when we talk about creativity
but creativity and how we do business and how we do processes how we build teams.
is a thing that we have learned throughout our 20 years of journey as well. And of course,
how to do crisis management, which was proven very successful. My team and Streamliner has
definitely surprised me in the last year as we went through the pandemic together.
And of course, business continuity. How do we continue leading the industry? How do we continue
building the ecosystem and not just following what's set out there and building our own paths?
So taking a step back, resilience, I think there's many layers of resilience.
There's, of course, individual resilience.
And when I refer to individual resilience, it's talking about VUCA tolerant individuals.
VUCA is, of course, a military term that's used to describe a volatile, uncertain,
complex and ambiguous situations that we like to use here as well, because that's how it feels like sometimes building games.
And these VUCA-tolerant individuals are characterized often by very high emotional intelligence
and their desires to introspect and really understand who they are, where their place
in the world is, what they're motivated by, what drives them, what gives them purpose.
And these individuals are often very value-oriented.
If they believe in something, they'll stand up for something.
And these individuals are very resilient individuals and they will pursue what they want to pursue in their lives.
But then comes a second layer of resilience called team resilience, because it doesn't mean that you have 20, 30 very resilient, very VUCA tolerant individuals.
and your team's automatically resilient.
Because no one can be resilient 100% of the times.
But that's how it feels like, you know,
being in this industry sometimes.
You would have moments of,
where you fall off the wagon, but.
without the team around you to support you and kind of bring you out of there,
it sometimes feels like you're not able to go through it, no matter how resilient you are.
So that's really all about team resilience. It's about building the support network and
the relationship and the structures to help these individuals through their ups and downs.
Of course, everyone has ups and downs.
but kind of shortening their downs, the duration of the downs, so that they're able to rise up
quickly and get back to it through the help and support of their teams.
So this is built by creating opportunities for teams to have real conversations.
And when I say real conversations, I'm talking about really frank and honest conversations about themselves as humans.
And also, you know, they're about their performance, about their work, about their feelings and emotions.
So I'll talk a little bit more later about the exact examples of what kind of meetings we create or what kind of opportunities we create to do this.
But that is essentially what team resilience is.
And then comes organizational resilience, which is a little bit more complicated
compared to the team resilience.
So again, just because you have individuals who are resilient or teams, even teams
who are resilient doesn't mean that your organization's automatically going to
survive and you have business continuity for years to come.
Organizational resilience, it's all about building the infrastructure to allow your business to evolve organically.
So there's a lot of words in there. But when I say evolve organically, we all have sparks of ingenuities or ideas.
and even more so individual resilience who are able to work as a team
because they're constantly talking to each other, inspiring each other,
generating new ideas, new way of doing things, new way of doing business, new way
of doing processes or creating art or new way of
creating games.
So unless your business is able to capture those ideas
and turn them into actual outcomes,
turn them into actual products or processes or business
services or business proposals, these ideas stay as ideas.
And these resilient teams and resilient individuals
constantly need.
to see outcomes of their work.
So unless their conversations and their sparks of ideas
turn into actual actionable items that gets passed
and that
gets passed and turns into an action within their organization,
they're not necessarily going to feel happy in your organization.
So these creative and very diverse and inspired teams
need to feel, well need to actually contribute to evolving your business
model and evolving your products, evolving how you do things to move your
business forward.
then only they'll feel like I'm in an environment where I can succeed.
I'm in an environment where I feel like I have a purpose
and I'm in an environment where I feel like I'm growing.
So this is, in a sense,
what it means to be resilient on many different layers.
And now I'm going to go into different examples or case studies
of what I mean by these.
So first, individual resilience, of course,
a huge thing would be making sure that your hiring process
is designed to find and hire these VOCA tolerant
and high emotional intelligence people.
And I call this process as finding the gems
because it's really that, it's going through
and finding the people who sparks
and shines within your team.
and being open to find them because it will take a while sometimes.
And it all starts with removing prerequisites that narrow down the
diversity pool. And when I talk about diversity, a lot
of people are very concerned or they're
they feel like it's a huge challenge.
because they think they tell me like, oh, you know, when I talk about diversity,
I really, I really just want to focus on, you know, their skills or their merits
rather than looking to hire for the sake of hiring diverse groups.
Diversity doesn't just necessarily mean backgrounds and gender as well though.
It means that you're open to removing barriers that block particular groups of people from
entering your space.
And for us, it means that removing any prerequisites such as you need to have a game degree or game
backgrounds to be able to work with us, or you need to have a certain amount of experience to
be able to work with us. Our team comes from all walks of life. And when I say all walks of life,
I mean I have producers who
Actually myself majored in science,
producers who majored in finance,
I've leads and artists who have majored in finance,
have decided to take up art,
have studied on their own and entered the space.
people from hospitality, entertainment, and all of that links back to resilient individuals
because oftentimes these people have tried and tested many different things in their
lives in search of what they like or what drives them forward.
And having this experience of having gone through this thought process or this
process of finding their purpose in life, it automatically gives them the resilience
because they have already tried and tested many things. They are proactive and they're looking for
what, continuously looking for what they like and they're always thinking about, you know,
what their purpose is and what drives them forward.
onboarding these individuals who have this mindset into your team
would bring you this huge diverse background
that and experience that follows them into
your pool of solutions, finding solutions. So when you're
even when you're looking at trying to solve a resource problem or
trying to solve a milestone problem
Having people that have thought from multiple different angles,
who have different contexts, different backgrounds,
that adds a lot to your solutions pool
and how you look at different things,
how you're approaching a certain issue or question,
which is why we always welcome diverse teams.
Also, our interviews are very focused on and designed to have very open and frank conversations about who they are and their values,
not just about what they have done before, what their skills are, what are the responsibilities and duties you have carried out in your previous workplace,
but focused, especially in the last interview, a lot on who are you as a human and what are you looking for?
And what are you trying to achieve by joining this group called Streamline over here?
Um, and.
That leads to the next point, which is the open applications.
What we found is that a lot of the times
these individuals, these gems that we're looking for
who are resilient often come through interesting routes.
They don't they usually apply for one thing and end up in another place
because through the interview process, we have found that, oh, perhaps
this person could be interesting for this team
or perhaps this person is what you're looking for.
And we refer them a lot between the departments.
So OpenApplication is exactly that, designed to catch people who may not exactly know what they want to do.
or may not exactly have an idea that I want to apply for exactly for this role,
but they know that they want to join us here at Streamline
or they know that they want to join the games industry or the creative industry,
but they don't simply know how to start or they don't quite know
what is their best fit.
So open applications is designed to catch those.
And that, as a result, will immediately open up
and widen your pool that you're looking at to grow your team.
and grow your resilient team.
So next up is team resilience.
So now that you have been resilient individuals,
it's about retaining them.
It's about
retaining them and building relationships and networks and support systems around them.
And as I talked about this before, it really just comes down to getting them ready and
building their muscles for VUCA situations before the situation gets VUCA.
What I mean by that is, for example, before things get hectic, having regular one-on-ones
or organizing roundtable discussions or book clubs and lunch and learns where people are
able to share ideas and share their emotions, share how they're feeling or share their opinions
freely before things get stressful.
That way they get into the habit of sharing, they get into the habit of
knowing each other and giving each other benefit of the doubt
when things get stressful. And that really helps build that resilient
muscles when things get crazy.
So regular one-on-ones is something that we do here in all levels, regardless of who you are,
as an artist, as a lead, as a director, as a C-suit.
All managers and teams have regular one-on-ones with each other for this purpose,
talking about their personal goals, their strengths and their motivators,
and most importantly, their fears.
You know, what makes them tick?
What makes them tick?
afraid because a lot of the times when a VUCA situation hits, our lizard brain comes out
and we react. So unless you have that built that emotional trust bank with each other,
it is very easy to misunderstand each other and that often leads to teams falling out
and individuals.
not being able to be resilient in those situations.
So all of these sessions are designed for that purpose.
Even though they may not always be talking about emotions or feelings,
it's a practice of getting them to talk to each other
and share opinions and actually argue before things get stressful.
One example of that is what we call the NPS.
It's a net promoter score that all managers and leads give to each other
on a weekly basis.
So we'll be evaluating our week and saying,
oh, my week was give a score out of 10.
And we'll highlight any low scores or high scores during a meeting as well
so that individuals are able to share.
what made that week particularly good or particularly bad so that we're able to celebrate
the wins together and as well as share any particular downfalls or fallouts that they've had
and if there's any still any elephants in the room that meeting is exactly
there for people to you know talk it out and before they wrap up the week.
So all of these things are designed to get people to know each other like human to human.
And I think that's especially important as we as an industry, as we adopt this hybrid
model of working from home and working from the office.
You know, when you're not able to talk in person, these exercises or memories or muscle
memories of having done this will really pay off when things get stressful or when situations
turn abooka.
Next up is organizational resilience. So now that you have an individual who is resilient
and they are supported by other individuals who are resilient in a team network.
It's about creating an environment.
I would like to use the analogy called greenhouse, right?
If you want to grow certain types of plants or certain types of cactus,
you need to recreate their optimum environment.
So the optimum environment for these vocal tolerant
and resilient individuals and teams who have high emotional intelligence,
who is very self-aware.
is to allow them to create their own career paths,
because that's what led them here in the first place.
So why not let them continue their paths?
This can mean internal career growth,
but this can sometimes also mean external career growth.
We celebrate people when they get a promotion
or they find opportunities outside of our organization,
if it means that they're able to pursue their career paths
or pursue their goals that they have always had in mind.
Also, it means that deliberately building our business with contingency and space for innovation, growth and experiments.
So I myself is one of the experiments that I'm referring to here.
In 2018, we have introduced the brands.
all pixels being one of them, in order to diversify our revenue,
revenue streams and customer based. So we used to do things all as a group
called under streamlined studios. We used to do pretty much A to Z
of video game development under one studio.
But we have
We have created these different diverse brands as you can see here in the screen.
We have split out our brands and created the new ones to be able to focus and create their own
business paths into different areas of not only video games but in entertainment,
media and technology in general.
So as you can see here, when your business is diversified as this, it creates a safe network
and what we call geometric growth. It means that if one brand is able to grow,
it doesn't mean that their setback is immediately reflected on your business as a total, but you
still have other supporting pillars who is able to continue their operations regardless.
So this diversity, again, is what creates a safe network for you to for you as stakeholders,
shareholders or founders to have a much more receptive mindset and an attitude to anything
that comes up within your organization.
Because we are humans, too.
And it doesn't matter how much high potential your team is or how much potential your team
has, if all of those ideas are going to be.
ignored or not taken up because you're too afraid that it will affect the business.
So it's all about creating the diversity and also creating that flat hierarchy
and being comfortable to hand over that decision making
power and control to areas where it's needed
and those who are able to make those decisions on a daily basis.
and allowing those individual decision makers to really shape your business
as part of being as part of your team.
So to summarize this, going back to the previous slide,
to summarize this, it's all about, yes,
finding resilience and creating an environment,
creating a team where they're able to self-introspect,
self-reflect, and really talk about their goal as a human.
and really allowing them to build a rapport between the teams.
So again, creating that team resilience.
But at the same time, you as an organization
being able to have that infrastructure where you're able to capture all of those individual sparks.
of these very resilient individuals and turn that into actual business ideas or business proposals
that shapes your business forward and shapes the ecosystem and the industry forward. So it's
all about creating an environment and creating an environment where you're able to
not only hire and attract but retain those high EQ and VOCA tolerant individuals within your
organization.
And a lot of this can be applied, as I said, to your individual projects management when you're
doing problem solving. It is a new way of looking at things. It's not just individual wins or short
term wins of, you know, making our milestone this month or making our project or game this year,
but all about, okay, how do I make a decision that will affect the team positively in the long term?
Alright, so that is it. If you have any questions, feel free to leave them in the comments. I'll be able to go through them in the live Q&A session afterwards. Thank you very much for tuning in.