I'm Yukio Futatsugi, and I was a game director and a game designer of the Panzer Dragon series.
And...
I'm Kentaro Yoshida.
I'm a Panzer Dragon Tsubai art director.
And now I'm working in the Granding Kyoto studio.
And now I'm working in Granding, my own company now.
A little promo.
So...
I will speak in Japanese and translate the conversation.
First, I would like to start with the question, what is Panzer Dragoon?
I don't think there is anyone here who needs to answer that question.
As a Sega Saturn software,
it was released in Japan on March 10, 1995.
It was a launch title in the US.
It will be 25 years next year.
So Panzer Dragoon is a Sega Saturn game that was released in Japan first on March 10, 1995,
and then in the U.S. two months later on May 11, which was part of a surprise launch of
the system.
And next year, it will be celebrating its 25th anniversary.
When I joined SEGA a year later,
I was asked to write a proposal for SEGA Saturn.
At that time, the only genres left were drive and shooting.
At first, I chose drive and wrote a proposal,
but the game release was decided a while later,
so the only genre left was 3D shooting.
I said, I'll write a proposal for 3D shooting,
and I made Panzer Dragoon.
So only one year after joining SEGA, the company,
I was asked to come up with a design document
for a brand new Saturn game.
And at that time, I was given a choice,
but the choice was down to only two different genres.
One was racing and the other one was shooting.
And I actually chose racing
and even drafted a document based on that.
But Gale Racer was then greenlit right after that.
And so I had no choice but to really come up with an idea
for a shooting game.
And so this was the beginning of what turned into the 3D shooting game, Panzer Dragoon.
So at the time Virtua Fighter, I'm sure you all know, was being developed at a different team, at the AM2 team.
And I was told it was something I had to see if I was going to make a 3D game.
And when I saw the character models and their realistic movements, I knew that that was exactly what I needed to aim for.
As you know, back then, 3D shooting was all about models that had no movement, like a fighter jet.
I thought that if we could put a soft character in there, it would have a lot of impact.
And most 3D shooting games back then featured models of very hard and sharp-looking objects like fighter planes.
So, in contrast to that, I thought a character that moved like a living creature would stand out.
And then I thought on ideas of what kinds of things I want to try riding.
A dragon seemed like something that anyone would want to ride, and that's how I arrived
at the decision to make a shooting game where you ride a dragon.
These are some sample design documents from those days.
This page is about the play action.
If you look closely, you'll see that it wasn't a homing laser at first.
So they're centered around the action, the types of action that would be available to the player.
And if you look very carefully, you'll notice that we didn't have the homing laser at first.
And we were also thinking that the game's world would fit more into the fantasy genre.
The homing laser was implemented later after we determined that the 3D shooting mechanics made aiming difficult.
And then the world and the setting of Panzer Dragoon was fleshed out
only after the game was officially greenlit.
At the time, there were a lot of 3D shooting games,
but my favorite was Namco's Starblade.
So among all the shooting games that were available at that time,
I was particularly interested and really liked Starblade from Namco.
I wanted to make a game where you can experience the same story.
I was really moved and really impressed by the game's cinematic presentation and how
it offered the experience of a very grand Star Wars-like story.
And another thing that took me by surprise but thought it worked really well was the
lack of background music until the very, very end where you first hear it as you engage
in a showdown with the rival ship.
So playing that game, I thought that if I...
I were to ever make a shooting game that I don't want to make it like Starblade.
So to that point, we landed on these objectives that you see here.
The first one being to show the game as a continuous story that flows seamlessly from
the very beginning to the end.
Secondly, maximize the use of on-screen information to work the player's imagination.
We also decided to add polygons using objects from the game
and since the time for rail shooting is already set,
we decided to make the music to match the game development
and the music to match the screen until we reached the boss.
Thirdly, inserting polygonal cutscenes during interludes that use objects from the game proper.
And then the last one was, we knew that creating a Rail Shooter game,
the time frame of how long that lasted was pretty much a fixed time length.
So creating music that matched the fixed pace of the game's progression
all the way up until the last boss encounter,
much like you would see sort of directed or planned out in a movie.
That was one of our objectives as well.
So for the next couple of slides, I will talk about the visual concepts of Panzer Dragoon.
The visual concepts were created by designer and art director Manabu Kusunoki.
Star Wars, Dune, Wings of Onyx,
and other works that can show the world of the game,
such as the culture of the panther world,
and the concept of the landscape,
were all created by Mr. Kusunoki.
Very much like how things were done, we assume, for Star Wars, Dune, Royal Space Force, the wings of Onimis, and so on,
we created lots and lots of concept materials related to the cultures and the landscapes of this fictional world that we were creating,
and then applied that to the game design.
So I brought some of the actual concept assets from back then.
So I'd like to go through some of these.
So the first one is the 9th century.
The second one is the 9th century.
So the first one is the ancient age.
This term or phrase from Futatsuki-san was our key word.
It carried tremendous weight throughout the entire course of developing
and working on this project.
So basically everything was centered around ancient age.
So anything that didn't fit into the ideas or concepts that initially felt
like they didn't fit into the ancient age became nothing less than natural.
Once we applied that term, saying that this is what it is, this is when it
happened.
In order to build up the interesting elements of this game, we went about making it such that even if it was truly bizarre,
out-of-this-world idea,
we would say, oh no, the player would think, well, if we're talking about the age and age here,
then I suppose it makes sense. And that's how we made sense of it all.
But we came up with white materials that will play key roles in the game,
and they are the structural elements.
A highly advanced civilization that flourished in an age-long past with systematic designs
that used ceramic-toned materials and metallic parts, very similar to mechanical timepieces
and so on, they became what we would call the motif of the overall design direction.
The history of the advanced civilization reflected in the past,
ceramic materials, and mechanical clock-shaped metal parts are included in the design.
Sorry, I translated it first.
Let's move on.
Oh, there are still some.
The motif is still there.
I also remember referring to the Bega illustration I saw in Katsuhiro Otomo's painting.
The motif and the overall design direction that I just mentioned,
these designs were actually largely influenced by a character that was created by Otomo-san,
Katsuhiro Otomo, the character Vega.
And next we have the Empire.
The design of the Empire is based on the design of the modern warplanes and battleships
and the design of the old-fashioned weapons and engines
that were discovered over the long period of time.
So with the Empire, the setting is that this is a civilized country that recovered
from the world once it was destroyed.
So we combined weaponry like the tanks and battleships of World War I, and then
the excavated weaponry and engine from the ancient age.
So it was a combination that sort of created the foundation of the design.
And one sort of key area that I really focused on or wanted to highlight was making these
silhouettes really stand out.
And by doing so, it gave it a sense of massive scale.
And next we have the dragons and the attack organisms.
So for the dragons, they were organic weapons of the ancient age.
So we gave them the same white armor that those of the ancient age would wear.
And for the attack organisms, those were created during...
the ones that were created during the ancient age were given armor,
while the armor was removed for those that were not.
So, in the game, the ones with armor were strong,
while the ones without armor were weak.
And then in the game, they were ranked accordingly.
So the former were stronger and the latter, with the armor removed, were weaker.
And then next we have the world.
So the planet is losing the ability to purify itself and steadily edges towards oblivion.
And the planet ravaged by war is reclaimed by nature as the ages drag on.
After developing these setups like Asterisk, Zubai, that is within the Pantheon world,
we have kept up the standard.
The visuals that make up the world of Panzer Dragoon are realized in both Zwei and Saga
by cherishing these elements of the world's lore.
And so there's actually a little episode here.
The reason that we were able to dedicate so much time to the particulars and the
specifics of the world and the creation here was because
the Sega Saturn's development kits,
they were behind schedule and we had an extra two or three months where
we were unable to proceed with development.
which was ultimately a good thing and it worked towards our favor as during that time we were
able to really flesh out the world in a lot of different ways it was also this time that
we came up with Panzerese, the fictional language of the world.
Take down the PlayStation.
Yes!
So, as we all know, PlayStation, our rival hardware,
was set to launch around the same time as the Sega Saturn.
And it had a reputation for having superior 3D capabilities.
That was no secret.
Even within Sega, it was a hot topic.
And in a way, the Sega Saturn was the ultimate 2D hardware system,
but it possessed the best scrolling display capabilities.
And in order to win over and sort of beat PlayStation's visual presentation,
we needed to showcase the expanse of space on screen.
We designed the levels to be able to show the clouds,
the distant landscape, the water, the desert,
and so on.
So with that in mind, we designed levels
taking scrolling to the max
through vast landscapes with clouds and water surfaces
and deserts.
I think you know this if you are a Sega or Saturn fan,
but the 3D expression of Saturn is made up of transform sprites.
I don't think game developers can believe this,
but 1 polygon equals 1 sprite.
You need to have as many polygons as possible,
and the texture is distorted.
So modern game developers may find this very, very tough to believe,
but each and every polygon is a sprite.
So not only did we need to prepare individual textures for each polygon,
but the textures also warped.
When we were developing Panzer,
the programmer provided us with the original texture mapping tool,
and we used that to map the textures.
So for the development of Panzer Dragoon,
our programmer put together an original texture splitting tool
that we could use for texture mapping.
Also, compared to the PlayStation,
the function of the semicircular surface and the drawing of polygons
were quite weak.
And in addition to that, the Saturn, when compared to the PlayStation,
didn't pack much of a punch in terms of translucency, functionality, or polygon interaction.
But as a result, it didn't have a shiny metallic world,
but it matched well with the dry world of Panzer Dragoon, and we were able to express a unique visual.
That's what I think, looking back on it now.
But looking back at it now, I believe we were able to create these unique visuals that mesh very well with the sort of dry
World of Panzer Dragoon not to not something that's shiny
And sort of glamorous and not that ever I would ever want to go back to that era of game development
But I think it really worked out for the game
Yeah, so if you ask me now to go through that again and make something similar, I would kindly refuse.
But as a result, we created visuals that were impossible on the PlayStation.
I remember going to a PSP event with my game developer friend, Suto,
and I was shocked to see Ridge Racer.
We were both at the station, thinking,
what are we going to do? What are we going to do?
But I have, I'll tell you a quick story.
I do remember going to a PlayStation sort of presentation of their debut of the
hardware with all these titles.
I was there with our programmer Sudo-san and he was working obviously on Panzer
Dragoon. While we were there,
we saw Ridge Racer and we were so blown away.
The level of shock was so big that on the way back we were riding home,
we were riding home, taking the train back and we were like...
What the hell are we going to do about this?
And that's how much we were thinking about and how unconscious we were at Sega about PlayStation.
So even to this day, I have this lingering sort of trauma from those days, from that era,
that causes me to be very, very irritated any time I think about it
or someone mentions the original PlayStation.
And so seeing, I don't know if you guys had commercials out here,
but there are some PlayStation Classic commercials airing on TV.
And it's not pleasant to me.
It's very, very painful to watch.
So, Panzer was released and we made a lot of sales.
We accepted the fun of shooting and the uniqueness of the world,
so we decided to make a sequel that specialized in both.
So even after all that pain that we went through,
the first Panzer Dragoon was very well received,
both in terms of how much fun it is as a game,
as a shooting game,
and the uniqueness of the world that we built.
And so we were told to make separate sequels
that specialized in each of those areas.
After we decided on the story and the general direction that things would go in,
we split the teams into two and they were developed side by side or simultaneously at the same time.
So what we did was we decided on the story and the general direction that things would go in,
and after some of the groundwork was laid for Tsubai, we actually split the teams into two,
and they were developed side by side or simultaneously at the same time.
I was mainly in charge of Saga, and Kentaro Yoshida was mainly in charge of Tsubai.
So, I'm going to let him talk about Tsubai next.
So, I basically led the Saga team, whereas Yoshida here led the Tsubai team.
So, I'm going to hand it back to him and let's talk a little bit about that.
The game system of Panzer Dragoon is a 3D shooting that allows you to move the time,
and a gun shooting that doesn't allow you to move the time.
So the game systems of Panzer Dragoon are primarily a mix of two concepts.
The first being a 3D type shooter where you're able to move your character
and then a light gun type shooter where you don't move.
And during development, the difficulty of combining these two into a single game
is something that I was told, it was called out to me by the more higher,
sort of experienced colleagues and development staff at the company.
In Panzer Dragoon 1, we used half-power moves to put it all together into one game.
But we wanted to do something about the following sequences of shooting.
And also, seeing how we were also telling a story,
we had this problem where someone might think that,
well, if I finish once, I'm done with the game.
For Panzer Dragoon 1, what we did in order to not let that sort of feeling linger on to the users,
what we did was we stretched out the game's length purely by raising its difficulty,
resulting in a game that you could play for much longer.
Obviously, as a result, we did hear a lot of users, players, and fans talking about how the game was too hard.
In the sequel, Tsubai wanted to play the game many times, even though it was a story game.
He wanted to feel the fun of shooting, even though he didn't feel the difficulty.
We had to solve this contradictory problem.
So it's why having narrative elements to it,
but we needed a solution to this very big problem
of how do you make a game
that you want to play over and over repeatedly
and is fun to play purely for its shooting elements
without it ever being difficult.
So, some of the things listed on this slide, on the bullet points,
these are the things that help us sort of resolve that problem that we had.
I think the people who played Tsubaya remember this.
This is a video of the ground stage to create a sense of secrecy.
So, those who have played, I'm sure this is very familiar to you.
But we wanted to figure out a way to really accentuate the sensation of flight.
So the ground is made using a Sega Saturn scrolling layer.
In order to represent flying from the mountains,
we needed to show the ground in locations both high and low.
But the thing is, we only had one scrolling layer to use.
We only had one scrolling layer to use.
So, what we had to do is make smart use of these corners and turns, like you see right
now, going from higher to lower and vice versa, sort of quickly switching the scrolling layer
in between.
So, by doing so, we were sort of tricking the players into thinking that you would see the high and low while you're making these turns and making these corners.
This was a difficult part for the programmer, but thanks to that, we were able to make the players feel the excitement and feel the growth of the Dragon.
So while this wasn't an easy task, I think this was a good resolution that our team,
our programmers came up with. We struggled with it, but we're ultimately very happy.
And we think that it provided the player with both a very high sort of quality experience in
terms of the sensation that you get of flying and also at the same time seeing the dragon's growth.
We also implemented a mechanic that automatically adjusts the difficulty based on the player's skill.
Why we did this is because our director, Kondo-san,
You know, 3D shooting game could be categorized as more of a core game that is not open to
or as easy to get into for someone that is not a shooting game sort of pro player.
So he incorporated this difficulty adjustment system, ADIC, into the game.
By the way, it says automatic difficulty adjustment, but ADIC does stand for automatic difficulty
enemy control system.
And what the system did was it was looking at the players' results,
and it would dynamically adjust the number of enemies, the number of remaining bullets, and so on,
all the while you played. So the system itself was very much ahead of its time.
So, as I said earlier, on one hand we had team Tsuai working on that,
and then I was leading team Saga.
I've been working on games for over 25 years now,
and if you ask me what was the most difficult project I've ever worked on,
I can definitely say it's Saga.
So, let me start off by saying that if you were to ask me
which game in my 25-year career in game development
gave me the most grief,
you might probably know the answer already, but let me tell you, without
even a shred of doubt, this is it.
And the why, then why is it Saga? Why is it this game?
Well, we simply try to do way too much.
So what you see on the slide here right now, I know it's very hard to see.
This is not the initial concept or design document.
This is a design document, maybe six months to a year into production,
trying to explain to the larger group what we are trying to do.
First, we wanted to make a full 3D RPG.
We wanted to make it as simple as possible,
and expand on what we did with Panzer I.
We wanted to make a game where you can experience a 3D model in a movie,
not a shooting game, but a RPG.
So what we were trying to do is to make a full 3D RPG.
And not just that, we tried to take the original
Panzer Dragoon and flesh it out in a way
that would make it into an RPG.
We basically took a game that allowed you to experience
a movie that plays out with 3D models
and try to make an RPG out of it.
At that time, you had games that would render images for the backgrounds and then use model for the characters alone as a means for presenting them more effectively.
A good example that comes to mind is Resident Evil.
So with that as our starting point, we decided to jump on this crazy challenge for ourselves
of creating the entire world in 3D and then making movies in it.
It's a common thought now, but as far as I know,
there were very few titles that challenged this, except for a few PC titles.
Also, it was very difficult to switch from shooting to battle.
Also, to where the title says, to new RPG battles that play like 3D shooters.
This was a massive challenge.
You don't even probably think about doing this.
It was so different from your typical RPG that even after a lot of discussions, a lot of trying, a lot of testing out these test builds, a whole year went by and we had really nothing good to show for it.
So at that point, we swapped out the person in charge of creating the battle system
and gave it to someone else.
And that person is Mukaiyama-san.
He would actually later on go to direct Panzer Dragoon Orta.
So, where you once had what looks like a shooting game,
you're now constantly trying to position yourself advantageously.
In terms of RPG elements,
the fact that there are no parties because the player is solo
is a type change due to Dragon's real-time transformation.
The physical and magical elements are the dragon's attack and the player's attack,
and the various bomb-type attacks.
We replaced the old system with a new one.
And where you once had a game with a single character and no party,
you now have a dragon that can change types and does so in real time.
Not only that, it is no longer just a physical and magical.
The dragon can attack, the player can attack,
and you also have a variety of explosives at your disposal.
These are some of the examples of how we swapped out the mechanics.
At first, we wanted to make a game that was free to move around.
But with the technology of the time, the quality of the map would drop,
and it wouldn't be a Panzer Dragoon-like game.
So we decided to move the map from the right to the left,
and make the map a box garden where you can move freely.
So then we wanted to make a game where you could go wherever you wanted but doing so really harmed
the visual quality of the map and it also wouldn't end up being very Panzer-esque anyway. So instead
we made a system where you could choose which field to go from from an entire map and then
once you were inside you would have a miniature garden that you could move about freely.
We also introduced the concept of time, so you had day and night,
and see the differences between the two.
And you could freely move about towns to a certain degree.
And we also introduced the concept of time, so you had day and night,
and see the differences between the two.
And to that end, we also implemented, we had to use lighting,
making so that you would see the change from dusk to night in real time.
In order to make the city wider,
we had to rewrite the memory so that the user could not understand it.
So we divided the city into two areas
and made it into a long tunnel that connects both.
And if we were going to make big towns,
we needed a way to rewrite things in the memory partway
through without making it obvious to the player.
And what we did there was we created them
so that they would be divided into two separate areas that
would be connected by a long tunnel.
At the time, there were no 3D games like this, so we made them all by hand.
Now, it's just a matter of course, but I think we tried to do this a lot at the time.
So while you may have the freedom to move around some large areas,
it would be annoying if you had to walk all the way over somewhere just to
examine something really small. So we decided to use this lock on system.
One thing we struggled with quite a bit was how to control the camera while
moving around the towns. Um, there weren't any 3d games like this at the time.
So we had to feel our way through everything we did. Um,
these are all things that we take for granted today, but when I think about it,
I am really taken aback by just how much we were trying to do back then.
we decided to create the game's cut scenes in full 3D as well.
Well, after all, we were trying to make a movie here.
And because we had such a huge number of events,
we concluded that we would need to use motion capture
if we were going to make them all.
But back then, optical motion capture was still quite rare.
So we were using magnetic motion capture.
So I brought something. This is actually a video while we were filming the motion capture session for Saga.
So I mentioned earlier that the optical motion capture was rare,
so we had to use magnetic motion capture. But when we do that,
then anything in the area emitting
magnetism gets picked up as noise.
So later on when we had to sort of clean up the data,
in order for us to know kind of the positioning,
we had a grid that you see in the left top, I think, corner.
we had to place a grid so we had sort of a good sense of where things were placed.
So obviously this is the opening scene and you could see that the person is riding the
dragon which is made up of beer cases, the red and yellow beer cases, and you see another person
holding the stack of beer cases because if that person wasn't there it would just fall over.
So yeah we had to use some very creative and sort of smart tricks in order to make that happen.
I'd like to summarize what we did.
Saga has been through so many challenges.
It's only natural that we've been through so many challenges,
but we've been through so many challenges that no one has done before.
So these are only a few examples that I'm sharing today,
but we simply charged a headlong into too many difficult challenges.
We were behind in terms of specifications in each department,
and we've been behind in development schedules for about a year.
So as a result, we were unable to nail down the specifics about the various parts of the game,
and the development schedule was delayed maybe by a year.
Not only that, our staff were so exhausted.
And that led to a lot of conflicts here and there.
With Full 3D, the volume of the game got bigger,
and we didn't have the experience of managing a team of 50 people.
At that time, there was no ticket system to develop the large number efficiently,
so the management cost was huge.
And then management costs spiraled out of control.
The game packed a tremendous amount of volume due to it being in fully 3D.
I had no experience managing a team of close to 50 people,
and we had no ticketing system that we could use to sort of effectively push
the development along with this large number of people on staff.
The quality of the staff at SEGA was very high, so we managed to finish it.
But it was quite expensive, so Team Andromeda had to disband.
So the staff at SEGA are absolutely top-notch.
Everyone is very talented.
And it's only probably because of that we were somehow able to finish the game.
But the team was disbanded because of how much it cost.
Well, for me...
I was about 50 years old, and I thought,
I can't do this challenge now.
Now that I'm nearing age 50,
I would not put this challenge onto myself.
I would definitely not do it today.
But I think I was able to do it because
the whole industry was set up to change the game to something new.
But I think we were able to overcome this challenge back then because of the
new hardware and all the energy and sort of the spirit just across the
industry, not just at Sega, but there was this energy and sort of challenging
spirit that was a very much alive back then.
I can't say I did a good enough job, but at least we hoped to try to make that happen,
and I think SEGA was truly an excellent company,
making it possible to do so many things, but not just just within ourselves.
Yeah, so...
And so we were able to create games like Panzer Dragoon partly because we were young
and then the culture that we had at Sega was that we just wanted to create something.
That was the kind of energy and spirit that was flowing
and that's what made it possible for us to create some really good video games.
I don't know if you know this, but SEGA's company's song is called Wakai Chikara.
Sega was overflowing with youthful energy,
and that's why we were able to make a game like Panzer Dragoon.
Young people don't have much experience,
so they can't imagine the difficulties ahead,
and they end up making reckless attempts.
When you're young, you naturally have no experience,
but you can take on these chances
and just really throw yourself at it.
And without the slightest idea
of how much hardship you're in for,
but that's exactly the kind of recklessness
that really pushed our culture, the video game culture.
We have aged, but we are still young, so we will continue to challenge ourselves.
And moving forward, I want to believe in the promise of this youthful energy.
And that goes for me as well.
Even though I said I'm nearing 50, I may have aged a little bit,
but I'm still young on the inside.
And so I hope to have many challenges ahead of me.
I don't have much time to cover all three games,
but I'll stop here.
So, to cover all three games in the Panzer Dragoon series,
an hour is definitely not enough,
but I hope you enjoyed our talk today.
And we do have a little bit of time for Q&A,
so if it's okay, we'd like to move on to that.
Thank you.
OK, so there are three mics.
If anyone has any questions, please feel free to come up.
Hi.
Firstly, thank you so much for the game.
It means a lot to me.
Is it true that the source code and assets for Saga
have been lost?
Very good first question.
Probably the top FAQ.
Well, actually, Yoshida and I quit while he was making Saga, mastering it and releasing it.
So we don't really know where he went.
So the true story is, so we mastered up Saga,
and then between our master date and our release date,
I left the company.
So the real truth, the true story
is that I don't know what happened to the source code.
However.
I feel like I heard a rumor that it wasn't found,
so it might have been found.
However, I have heard rumors, and maybe everyone here has heard rumors,
that it may have been discovered somewhere at some point.
But forget that I even said that once you leave this room.
Thank you.
Hi, thank you for making this awesome game.
It's one of the reasons I became a game developer.
I'd like to ask how hard it was to make the dragon movement.
Even today it still looks very smooth and really nice.
The tail and the body and swings and the wings.
So could you talk a little bit about that?
I studied from the root as it seems that the most difficult part is to learn how to perform the movement.
However, even now, when I take a look at the Dragon's movement, it is amazingly flexible.
Look at the movement of Kyo, and then look at how each movement was created,
for instance, when the businesses stopped their hard work.
Is it well explained to the viewers?
Yes, it is.
The animation for the first Panzer Dragoon was mostly composed by a designer.
So for the first Panzer Dragoon, the animation was all done by hand by our animators.
And I think you will agree with me that between the first and the second, including the camera
movement, it's quite, there's a leap in the progression or the advancement that we made.
Tsubai's programmer, Mr. Suto and Mr. Nakajishi
were able to calculate the spring quite easily
and that was applied to Tsubai's softness.
That's what I heard at the time.
So from what I recall or what I heard was we had our very, very talented programmers,
Suto-san and Nakani-san, when they started working on Tsui, they were able to figure
out some sort of calculation in terms of how
the wings would sort of really give the flow
and how realistic that would come out when put on screen.
So that would have been perhaps the sort of the magic touch
that they gave.
And so you see the huge sort of improvements
between the original and SWAI.
Thank you very much.
Hello. Could you describe one or maybe a few features that you really wanted to implement into one of the games, but you couldn't due to limitations of the Saturn?
And any one of the three?
Yes.
After all that he said that they challenged themselves so much.
Okay, how about the first one then?
One.
One?
Yes, one.
Well, it's the same for all of them, but the volume is cut quite a bit.
So this applies to not just one, but to all of them.
Basically, the game volume, we had to cut a lot.
So if we had it our way, you would have
gotten a lot more of the game.
For example, in 1, at the end of the map where you fight in the capital,
you might think, huh? The boss isn't here!
But the boss didn't make it in time.
So in one, the last map at the map of Tate,
you might be like, oh, you're playing, and you're playing,
and it's like, wait a minute, where's the boss?
Well, we had to cut the boss.
I was connected to the last boss, so I was being fooled.
But the one who was supposed to be with me was supposed to be the boss and fight.
But I didn't have time to make it, so it was gone.
Yeah, so we simply ran out of time.
We sort of convinced you that there...
was or maybe could have been a boss but then we went to the last boss but initially there
was supposed to be a boss and then into the last boss so we're sort of uh uh not tricking but we
sort of made things up along the way because we ran out of time thank you
So one more thing though.
So Suto-san and Takeshita-san, they came from the arcade side.
So they were aiming for 60 frames per second.
Wow.
Unfortunately, in order to make it interesting they're giving us 30 frames per second,
but in the hidden strat they come up with, still with the 60 frames per second cheat it works.
So while they were aiming for 60 frames per second,
obviously the fun of the game overall
took priority over achieving that frame rate.
So eventually it landed around 30.
But I guess there's a cheat where you can actually
take a glimpse of what it looks like at 60 frames per second.
Does everyone know about that, I guess?
No?
No.
I guess there's a part of the stage where it's sped up and you can see that.
Oh wow, thank you very much.
We have like three minutes.
There was news last year that the first two Painted Dragons will be remade.
So do you have any comment on this?
The remake that was announced?
Remake of the first two Painted Dragons series.
You said that the first two will be remade.
Is there anything you can say about that?
We haven't been told anything about it, so we haven't been involved in the production.
We hope it will be a good game.
So we haven't been, I guess, given a word.
We're not involved.
So all we can wish for is that it turns out,
they both turn out well as a project.
Thank you.
Hi.
You mentioned Starblade as kind of inspiration
for the shooting kind of game that you wanted to make.
When you were making Saga and making an RPG,
were there any other RPGs that were kind of big inspiration?
I really am inspired by Jiro Yamaoka's work.
In Saga...
OK, there was something else.
But we didn't have that, so it was hard work.
And we inspired developers of OpenField a lot!
There was nothing to be proud of.
Sorry, we're laughing.
He's like, hmm, that's a good question.
But it's probably because I can't
name any titles that really influenced or inspired me.
And therefore, we went into this sort of crazy overachiever
concept that we couldn't really pull off.
because that's what we wanted to do.
And then Yoshida-san from the side said,
well, it's only because we were able to do what we did,
I think we actually inspired people to go out and do this more open field,
open map sort of game, like design it that way.
And then Futsui-san was like, you're acting like a boss right now.
Awesome. Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Maybe, yeah, maybe last question we can take. Yeah.
I just had a simple question that was related to, excuse me, Petri Dragoon saga.
Was there ever a plan to have more than one city? I know development was,
you know, rushed, but was there any plans to have more than one city that gets destroyed later?
Well, after the city was gone, it became a different city.
I didn't want to create a new city.
I wanted to change it according to the progress of the game,
but I couldn't do that.
No, actually, we we didn't.
So obviously it was sort of the city was not reborn,
but rebuilt as a different city.
The idea was that that city would evolve
into a different sort of type of city.
We weren't able to get there, but at the same time,
we also didn't have any ideas to have a new city either.
Thank you.
Okay, I think we're exactly at three o'clock, so thank you so, so much for attending.