Yay.
So hey, everyone. Thanks for coming. They want us to tell
you to please remember to silence your cell phones and
also please fill out the feedback form at the end of the
session. And if you didn't, get your badge checked so that you
can do so. So this talk was kind of given a punchy name to kind
of mask the diversity part, to trick people who wanted to see,
you know, a night fight with laser fists in a cave. But, you
know, that won't be happening. But congrats, you are at an
important talk.
This is perhaps a better name for the talk. So who we are, I'm Shawn Alexander Allen, I'm an artist, game designer, writer, new challenger.
Yeah, and I'm Kat Small, I am a game developer with Brooklyn Gamery, I'm also a product designer at SoundCloud and the co-founder of the Code Liberation Foundation.
So this talk is about diversity. But by diversity, we
don't just mean slapping some brown people or women in a game
and calling it a day. Diversity is not just some veneer for your
games to reside underneath. Because when you think of it
that way, it can be easily chipped away at, and it has to
be something that you're not ending at the end, that you're
adding towards the beginning so that you don't end up
sacrificing in the end. I mean, we're not really going for this.
Exactly, exactly. So this talk is really aimed at thinking way deeper about the games that you're making, right?
What the content is, how that content informs the rest of the game.
You know, like we build systems and we're thinking about systems from the get-go,
but are we really thinking about the other parts of our games?
Like who's starring in them? How would they act and things like that?
So we we don't really think through a lot of things like we're thinking about like
you know, our characters shooting, but like, why are they shooting? And, and, you know, like, what,
who's in this game? And, and like, how does this uphold, you know, for example, like real world
stuff that's going on?
So what's in it for you?
So we're going to be talking through lots
of different games at various different success levels,
various different build levels.
We're going to be dissecting these games,
talking about different genres as well,
just all across the spectrum of what we call indie.
And we're going to be examining what creators have done
to diversify the landscape, like how well they did.
just kind of critiquing them, the goods and the bads,
and even the parts in the middle.
And our goal in this talk is to show concrete examples
of thinking, and talking a little bit deeper,
thinking a little bit deeper than just the surface level
of what diversity is.
And hopefully it leads to you getting to broaden your reach,
audience-wise.
community, and you know, even possibly changing the market and
like the people that you're accessing. But we also
acknowledge that this is only a singular part of the equation,
and like, there are other parts to like making games,
obviously. And, you know, this is just one part of it. And it's
kind of not, yeah, so this is why we're calling it subversive.
So we're going to be discussing a couple of things, a couple of
specific games here.
And just to note, this isn't a value judgment on the creators.
It's really just an examination of their games.
We're kind of trying to examine the impact, not the intent,
per se.
So let's go.
So hey, this is catacomb kids. It's a rogue like platformer
with random character generation. It was a kick
starter success. It earned over $30,000 on kick starter. It's
currently in early access. Tyreek plumber is giving talk
here later today. Saw a lot of success from an awesome video
about all the different things you could do with a rock, which
was pretty cool. And the video kind of went viral.
and we've seen a lot of roguelikes that have defined character types, skin colors, etc.
but in Catacomb Kids all of the characters have wildly different skin colors, names, stats, faces, hairstyles
and the kids are barely recognizable as gendered too.
these are some of the kind of randomly generated characters
from just a couple of play throughs of the game. And the
randomness of the kids supports the idea that lack of set
situations with the player characters and it upholds the
idea of random generation in the game's design.
players will have to try multiple character looks. They
won't necessarily get stuck on one main and also they won't get
stuck on a gender choice. You could theoretically really
always try to go for the dude with stats but you might be
sitting there for like 20 minutes cycling through them. So
it's kind of interesting how the random choice means that you
actually have to experience somebody different every time.
And also it's because the kids are, part of the game is like the fragility of life, so the kids die quickly,
so then you just have to go get someone else, and then you don't get stuck on them.
So you can kind of compare this to Spelunky which has an
interesting multi-ethnic cast but you have to unlock many of
those characters. But what's really interesting in comparison
with Spelunky is a lot of people get attached to their main. I
see a lot of turban wearing people picking the turban
wearing character which is really awesome because the
character, those characters don't exist in games generally.
But it's still filled with, you know, like,
random like ethnic stereotypes and you still have to kind of
play the game for a while to find like more brown people to
use. There was something and also then that kind of brings up
how because of the set characters you can kind of pick
like, you know, a black woman who's like a pirate with like an
eye patch but you can only ever rescue these three people and
kind of it's weird that the diversity here is like the pug
is like you have two white people and then a dog. And, you
know, the damsel jokes kind of tired in and of itself.
But what could actually kind of use a little bit of improvement
that I just think about is that, you know, what is the difference
between Christina and Thomas right here? Like nothing, right?
Stats or whatever. But I mean, the fact that the game kind of
assigns gendered names to specific gender roles is kind of
actually not super helpful. Like the game doesn't really actually
gain anything from it.
So another game, we all pretty much know shovel knight. It's
probably one of the most mainstream independent games out
there. I love the game personally. It did over $300,000
on kick starter. And it's been a huge success and I feel like
part of that success is because the whole game has been thought
through on an extra level.
I think more farther than a lot of different games. And it's
very tight design without necessarily becoming suffocating
and trying to force players to play through it in its own
designed way. But the designers thought through a lot of aspects
of the game.
So one thing that was interesting is that they needed
to, there was an article on Gamma Sutra where they came out
and they talked about how they needed to expand the NES
palette, because this is the NES palette and the NES palette
actually doesn't have
many browns in it. So for backer rewards and just for other
things they needed to expand the palette. So this is one of the
colors that they added to the game. And because they were
saying, hey, look, we're going to look at the very basic thing.
So a lot of people look at retro whatever and they say we need to
stick to the NES palette. But the NES palette has problems in
and of itself and they had figured out that they could add
like five colors to actually add diversity to the game.
and they also kind of were using this term gender swap for a while for a new feature
and they actually changed their marketing speak to body swap to make it less harmful
and more inclusive to people.
but then there's the kind of one stumbling brick where it's like, but why are their gender roles
very specified as the main characters? Like why is Sheil Knight the damsel who needs rescuing?
And why is she the defensive person where Shovel Knight's the guy who's the attacker?
And really, like again, what does Shovel Knight gain from being a guy?
Great, so Broken Age. Also probably heard about this game. This game is pretty popular.
So it's got some really interesting things in it, right? Like firstly, it stars a black woman and a white guy.
They don't have a romantic encounter, which is like also...
kind of cool because a lot of times when there's people of different genders in a game, they're
like romantically paired together, so that's exciting. And the other interesting thing about
that though is that it kind of, which is a good and a bad thing because they could have easily
messed this up, it avoids the complexity of like those kinds of relationships and some people call
it like the swirl for example. There's a lot of complexities in there. And so by having, not
having that there, they easily avoided, you know, what could have been a mess.
And it was actually funded without even having protagonists.
So hats off to Tim for actually deciding
to make one of the characters a black woman.
It didn't have to happen, but it did,
and that was really awesome because it showed
that there was some thinking there.
It was a very conscious decision.
And also, like, thanks to the community for not getting angry that there was a woman who
was black, you know, as the star of the game.
Because there were other games where even just the hint of the main character being
not a man, for example, Mighty No. 9, people got super angry.
And the other nice thing about this is that there's actually a black voice actor for the
character as well.
Something that they could have thought about a little bit more is who they were marketing to.
So for example, they could have actually gone to different websites like Ebony,
who also runs a wonderful magazine and there's other traditional forms of media as well
that are kind of like focused at black buyers, and they could have actually had a...
they could have actually done something there and said,
hey, our game is kind of unique,
would you be interested in buying it?
Here's a little bit about the game.
So they could have pitched that to traditional media
and actually possibly open their audience even more.
So on the negative side, there are hair jokes. And we've had enough of those. So there aren't a
lot of black characters in games in general. There aren't a lot of black characters in this
game. And yet we're making fun of black hair. It's already seen as something that's like weird
or like strange or unnatural. And so just adding on this joke, which is also impossible, by the
way.
If it's open, it doesn't shake closed.
Like, once it's down, you have to comb it or something.
So black hair doesn't work like that, firstly.
And so it was really obvious that they had no one to say,
what are you doing?
So that was definitely a negative about this game.
So yeah, I mean, again, another, uh, another, uh,
popular game, it's a rhythm based roguelike. We're trying
not to go too deep into stuff that probably everybody knows.
But despite being like it seems like the super niche game, it
did super well. So that's really awesome. Another game that I
really love. And I really honestly want to know where are
my crypt likes. When are people going to start copying this idea
and start making more stuff with it. And it's also really amazing
that it stars a girl as the main character.
And also it's like the cast of the main like random characters
is really cool because it's variously diverse. They have a
gender non-conforming character who's brown in the game also.
And also their play styles reflect their difference. Like
it's not just everybody is the exact same character pasted over.
But there is a problem when you get to the same character.
this is the co-op character and there's a problem with the
second player co-op character being just a pallet swap of the
main character and it's like she's black, right? But she's
not really a character. Like she doesn't have any thought. She
doesn't have a story behind her. She has another name but that
doesn't actually matter. I mean, the color swap as a two player
character is kind of an old concept.
I mean, no one really bought Luigi as a main character in Super Mario Bros.
Like, you never wanted to play as him.
And all he did was, he was green instead of red.
And so it's like, when you make her black instead of white, it's like...
Like, there's literally nothing about her that's interesting, and I felt like...
I was just kind of curious why. I mean, this is what has been
done actually traditionally. On top the guy is obviously
modeled after Mel Gibson. On the bottom the other guy is modeled
after nobody at all. So like Danny Glover actually doesn't
even make an appearance. And if you actually look really closely
at the in-game screen shot, they have the same head. They put
more detail into his suit than they did in changing his head
and his hairstyle.
And I'm harping on this a little bit because this is kind of
very important. You can't see her on that background.
like her hair and it's a problem that's in film it's in photography uh stockings that come in nude
that are peach and it's like the the generic like the default for film was white people like that's
why like film looks bad with black people that's why people don't know how to make do makeup for
them that's why it's like this whole revolution now but it's funny because when you think about
something and you're just like hey we're just gonna do that it's like she doesn't pop from
the background she's not a main character
and there wasn't a whole lot of effort put into even thinking like maybe her skin and her hair won't be seeable.
She actually kind of got like the real short in the stick like she just is not present.
The next game is Shantae.
And Shantae is also super, it was really successful
on Kickstarter, made over 700K.
It's a platformer starring a female belly dancer.
And so that was really interesting.
On the sad side, it's been a little hard for WayForward
to actually procure funds to make Shantae,
new Shantae games, because it was a female character.
And she also happens to be brown.
So there have been some interesting ups and downs in here.
Now, firstly, I'm really excited about Shantae because it's like really interesting.
It's like a very fun game.
It's very exciting.
It has a female character.
She's also brown.
But things like this happened, where, for example, for a little bit of time, they lightened
her art.
and the fan base was like, whoa, whoa, whoa, slow down.
That's not cool.
She was a brown character.
Why is she now like super light skinned?
And so people were obviously getting really attached
to the fact that there was this brown person
being represented in a game.
So later they actually fixed the color.
didn't really like talk about it very much but they did address
and correct it so that was good on them for actually coming back
and saying okay we're going to change your color back.
But another issue is that if you've ever played Shantae, at least the versions that I have played,
there are a lot of female characters which is awesome, but most if not all of them are like
just scantily clad, they have like very large breasts, they have very large noticeable like
butts and they have like their midriff is showing and they're
just very sexualized. So it's kind of uncomfortable being a
woman playing this game and I personally was very frustrated
when I played it for the first time because I was really
excited for Shante. Again, it's really cool to see this kind of
person in a game.
But then when I started playing it, I was like, oh my god,
every character is like this.
They're all the same model, the same build.
And a lot of the guys had a lot of body diversity and things
like that, but all the women were basically sexualized.
And so that was really frustrating,
because it's not like every woman has
to be wearing completely covered up things,
or every woman has to be wearing nothing at all.
It's really about having a mixture of all of it,
because
some women want to wear revealing things and that's fine and some women don't want to wear
revealing things but by having all of them sexualized it just makes it really uncomfortable
for a lot of women and female identified people to play. More sexy snake women for everyone.
So I guess I'll go to a little vein and talk about my game for a bit. This is a beat em up with
turn based RPG elements and I kind of started out making the game for my like of beat em ups and I
As I worked on it, something kind of happened. I just kind of started thinking heavily about
the need for representation in games and also I needed money so I ran a kick starter, which
kind of ended up making about $50,000. And my kick starter updates highlighted the culture
that I was pulling from like graffiti and trying not to be too ignorant.
about my own appropriation of it.
And it actually kind of got me a couple of articles on Rock Paper Shotgun
when Adam Smith found it and he wrote about how it sounded like New York poetry.
And talking about the importance of diversity in the game
and how it was implementing it got me a lot of other interviews and a lot of fans.
Also want to note that I guess I had like 10...
be like an enemy in the game and five of them were black people
who were like, yeah, I want to really support this game. This
is a guy that I barely know. He's in my friend circle. He
works a part-time job. He doesn't have money. He really
likes Sprite. And when he saw this picture, he wanted to cry.
He was like, holy shit, I'm in a video game. That's really
awesome. And
there's a gentleman in the front seat who I met online through
this game because he was like, yeah, brown people, sure, this
game looks dope. And it's like, yeah, people had this genre
interest, but then they were also like, oh, this guy is
tackling these interesting issues, too. And I mean, so
like also like different games and the feminist gaming
Illuminati logos are in there, along other ones, because
people were like ‑‑
yeah, why not? It was a guy who backed at the logo thing and he
said, hey, I thought a good thing would be to be the
feminist gaming Illuminati and we talked it all out. And so
like we were all on an e-mail chain to get permission to even
use the logo. And then it was like, yeah, so become friends
over this whole thing. And kind of this thinking kind of created
like weird systems dealing with
dealing with oppression, like this class types, like you've
got the main character right there who's fighting a cop and
kind of a gentrifier in like the Lower East Side which is kind
of going through a lot of gentrification. And so then the
class types like the cop is unbalanced. The gentrifier just
makes her more powerful, which is kind of how the world works.
But I also ran into a lot of stumbling blocks just in my own
thinking because I guess of the way writing and thinking about
stuff is like I had this problem where
a lot of the brown people were, because I grew up in the hood,
and I know a lot of people that are in the hood, but I kind of defined them by the hood,
whereas I defined all the white people as more gentrifying,
and that is, it's actually funny because my mom's white, and
she was labeled as a cop by all the Puerto Rican people in our
neighborhood growing up because she was the only white person
living there. But I had to actually rethink a lot of
people's backgrounds and pull some people down and raise some
people up because you can't just define certain people by where
they're from and you can't define people by where they move
and what their intentions are. And then also there's this
character who I specifically had a problem with where like I
defined her kind of by the street harassment that she would get and that was really weird. So I
sat down one day and I was like, man, this is bad. So I kind of actually thought about her as
like, because I actually modeled her like sprites after Wolverine in X-Men versus Street Fighter.
So then I thought about maybe she liked comics a lot and that like, you know, she was
you know, kind of like what happens in life, a bad thing happens and you get suspended from
school and then you're like, you know, fuck this school. So then that was more like of an
empowering thing, like she was a super smart person that just kind of got screwed over by
everything. So because I always wanted to make the enemies have some sort of redeeming quality
because that's also a problem with games is that you just mow down all these people that don't
matter.
Great, so I'm also going to be a little vain.
So Prism Shell is actually a game
that I created with two friends at Brooklyn Gamery.
And so we're actually native New Yorkers,
and we're now all based in Brooklyn,
which is how the name kind of came about.
And we actually originally formed our group
because this game did really well at a hackathon,
and we were like, yeah, let's go with it.
So it's a mobile space shooter with a node-based mechanic,
which you can kind of see here, you kind of jump around.
and stuff like that and it was inspired by games like Gradius
but we wanted to do something for mobile and something with lasers.
So, yay! Yay lasers!
But the other thing about this game is that it stars a black woman
and she's a pilot whose code name is Veretta.
Her inclusion is incredibly purposeful.
I did that because I didn't see a lot of black women in space.
Like, who does that?
So I wanted to specifically have a black woman who's a pilot,
who's determined, but not angry.
I specifically also made her face to look confident,
but not in that way where it's like traditional angry black
woman.
She knows her stuff.
And I also did write about the experience
of designing her for Offworld.
So, something that was bad that I kind of did was originally the
character was way lighter skinned and that was because
there was like this article that came out that was like, oh, in
the future people are going to be like racially ambiguous and
they're going to look kind of like this.
And then I kept thinking about it and I was like, why does whiteness equal the future?
And so I just really decided to say, like, it doesn't matter what we think the future is going to look like.
Here's what my version of the future is like.
Here's my example of a black woman in space, you know, in like a hundred, two hundred, a thousand years.
And the sad thing also was that in order to launch the game without...
eventually hating ourselves. We needed to kind of cut a lot of features because the game just grew in
scale to a point where it was just basically impossible to finish with the three of us in the
time that we had allotted. So we cut the story, but we still wanted to actually show the main
character. So we have her on the title screen, which is also kind of a throwback to games from
like 20 years ago where, you know, they would have a ship and you might have a person who was
like on the box art.
and they were that main character, you knew they were in the ship, so you always know that
Beretta is in there, she's a black woman, she's saving the world.
We also actually put her
in the trailer, and this is something we want to add in later as well in the
actual game,
because we want to just underscore again, this is the person who's operating the
ship and
even though we didn't have time to actually include her background, she's
still there and she's still incredibly important.
Now, the other thing that this actually did was it actually invited a lot of people who
might not have played this type of game to come over and try it out.
We had a lot of kids, a lot of women, and older people as well who were super interested
in just trying out this game.
And it was also very...
interesting to learn how to design like an interaction curve that older people
could understand. Not that all old people can't understand things obviously, but
sometimes some people come in and they're like, oh I haven't tried a mobile
game before, how does this work? So we wanted to kind of make it as inclusive
as possible to people. So we did a lot of playtesting and we just realized that
having this character on the main screen also made it very interesting to a lot
of different people.
So it shows that even if your game isn't necessarily narrative driven, just by having certain character choices, you can actually open your audience and kind of excite people and draw people into your game.
So what we're going to do in the future is the next version of Prison Shell, which we're going to work on.
We actually have already started designing her narrative and expanding upon who Beretta is.
And the game, the first version of the game didn't do 100% well.
Like we got a lot of great press and things like that, but we weren't working with a marketing team.
So the main reason that it didn't do super well was because we didn't really know how marketing worked yet.
And so we learned a lot in that regard as well.
Also just to add that like part of the underscoring is that it was like people
are like man you know brown woman in front of the game that's why I didn't sell
but you know it's like people often need to realize that like white dude
first-person shooters often don't sell there's a lot of them that you've never
heard of
So I guess our conclusions, so creating characters from diverse
backgrounds can invite, include and intrigue people who often
don't see themselves represented. It can make your
work stand out in this industry where, you know, it's really
hard to actually sell things these days. And it also helps
out in this industry where there's all these defaults,
right? People just think of these defaults. And even if you
don't see color, others do. And we all have.
hand and you have to have we all have to have a hand in making games more inclusive because it can't just be like
The brown people and the women making the brown people in the women games because maybe we also want to make like weird
Shape things that are like one-dimensional and that are installations that aren't about the diverse experience
So someone else needs to do that occasionally, too
And you know, we're indies, and that means that, you know, we're not locked into this
triple A hell where we can't change our work, what we do drastically, we can be more agile,
we can create characters that are better, and we really should.
There needs to really be no more games that star all white people.
we should be thinking deeper about the motives for our
characters. Like how can our characters inform our game
design and vice versa. And we're urging that when people make
games that we think about different settings, places and
people who star in our games and also avoid accidentally upholding
oppressive systems while doing so. But we need everybody to be
thinking differently. You can make a game about dogs and cats
that uphold systemic racism. It's actually kind of easy.
Yep. Yeah, so the next bit, we're just going to kind of
shout out some games really quick to check out that are,
you know, kind of interesting, doing a pretty good job.
So Moon Hunters, this actually just launched on Steam. It
starts in ancient Mesopotamian lore and it has a lot of brown
people in it. I don't know why, but people seem to make games
about the cradle of civilization make them all white.
Not anymore. Not anymore.
Read Only Memories, also really interesting, awesome.
And by MidBoss, the people behind GamerX, which is now GX.
So this was Kickstarter-supported,
and it's got a lot of really interesting, diverse characters.
I'm looking forward to seeing how they handle voice acting for them.
know, if you don't know this game, this game is from
Cameroon in Africa. They've actually done a couple of
kick starters. The second one was successful thankfully. I
don't know. It's a very interesting game and we often
don't see games set in African fantasy. It's a little sad that
it has to be an African team that is doing it, but at least
people are actually supporting them.
and Undertale which is also another kick starter game. The
reason I liked this one was clear choices made regarding
gender and skin color so like the main character doesn't really
have very much of a gender. A lot of people are referred to or
like a lot of characters are referred to as they. The
character has brown skin and it's super interesting. Although
then gendering some of the characters was kind of like hmm
but overall it was a really interesting quirky narrative
game that definitely made me think a little bit.
Thanks.
Thank you.