Hey guys, so housekeeping, I have been asked to ask you
to move towards the center and be friends
with your pal next door to you,
and then afterwards to fill out your evaluations.
So, this is so great to be presenting at the Narrative Summit.
I always look forward to being with such kindred spirits for these couple days.
So this session is called Unpopular Opinion, All Narrative is Linear.
Very strategically placed right after a talk about non-linear narratives.
It's going well.
So clearly I was reading a BuzzFeed article
when I wrote this.
So I'm Amy.
A lot of folks give an introduction here,
but I think the best way to know me
is to know how I came to understand stories
and consequently how I approach game design.
So I'll jump right in.
All narrative is linear.
Movies, books, Aristotle, life, songs, the hero's journey,
sports, and even games that seem like they couldn't possibly
be so.
From MOBAs with stories emerging from cooperative gameplay,
to strategy games with compelling core loops,
to branching experiences, to sandbox games, to open worlds,
even to games with elongated aesthetic distances stemming
from ludonarrative distance, all follow the same structure
as all narratives have for thousands of years.
When it comes to our work as game makers,
the core loop is not a story.
It's a possibility space.
Unravel the loop, and you will see a player's actual narrative.
Because until we can change the time-space continuum,
players will always experience narratives linearly.
So what does this look like?
We've seen this structure before.
We all probably have some variation of Mrs. Hodge
in elementary school giving you your first essay
and being told it has to have an introductory paragraph
and a thesis and a few body paragraphs on that thesis
and a conclusion, but why?
It's the human experience, which can be summed up so simply
as tracking tension over time.
Because it's in that life, swells of emotion, good and bad,
over the time we're given.
So maybe that's not so controversial,
that players experience narrative linearly because time.
But I think what is an unpopular opinion
is that this way of looking at games
needs to be central to our development processes.
Because one.
It creates a tool for speaking directly
to the hearts of our players.
And two, it acts as a common language
for multidisciplinary teams.
So what is this language?
We see it clearly in movies.
Introduction.
Girl is sad.
Inciting incident.
Girl meets boy.
A question is asked.
Will girl get boy?
It's always a yes or no question.
Rising action, shenanigans ensue, a series of hurdles related to that main question.
Climax, Drew Barrymore stands in a ball field and after what seems like forever,
she has the most epic camera spinning kiss.
Did girl get boy?
Yes, the climax always answers that question, whether it be yes or no.
Finally, the resolution and indication of what's to come.
For Drew Barrymore, a hint of happily ever after.
It's also the story of life, conception, trimesters, birth.
It's also a sports game.
So my training is originally in theater
and I had a professor who said, he was Bulgarian,
so I'm gonna do an atrocious accent.
He'd say, why would people rather watch sports than theater?
Because in sport, one ball.
In bad theater, many balls.
Meaning, in a compelling story, we're only tracking one thing at a time.
So when I'm in a really good play, I can turn around and watch the audience heads all move
in unison, as if they're watching an invisible ball.
When I learned these narrative rules,
no longer were my plays hit or miss.
Suddenly there was a formula to arrange emotions
into an almost musical composition.
There was this answer I had been waiting for,
the holy grail of timeless tales,
perfectly linear narrative.
Then I joined the games industry.
Y'all messed it up.
With your core loops and your branching narrative charts
and your progression spreadsheets and wireframes
and player metrics and UX flows and even a linear tutorial
or two, which is even more confusing.
So back when I was a wee lass, circa 2013,
I got my start in mobile games.
And I was so excited to take my knowledge of story structure
and make experiences that were incredibly human.
I did learn very quickly that there is a tension between being human and the realities of game
development.
I like the Red Bull and the iced coffee combo on the desk there.
So making games requires translating experiences into software, a language of zeros and ones.
Consequently, top-down ways of speaking about games,
our core loops, our state machines, our metrics,
and so on, are incredibly valuable.
Any developer will tell you that building a game
that actually works is a battle.
But any developer will also tell you
that there's another battle, that feeling of disconnect,
the late-night despair of losing sight
of why a game speaks to our hearts.
That battle is just as real.
For me, my feeling of disconnect came from not speaking
the same language as our team leaders.
Having come from a different field,
I wasn't able to translate these top-down metrics
and loops into something I could meaningfully contribute to.
This is what happens when you get together a bunch of people
who are at the top of their various fields in engineering
and business and design and art and production,
all these people that it requires
to make a game these days.
The language we use to talk about experiences
is anything but linear and anything but standardized,
which is exciting.
I'm a big fan of diversity in all of its forms.
But it also creates a very real tension in communication on teams.
As a storyteller in a zeros and ones world, I felt lost.
So I read Jesse Schell's book, The Art of Game Design,
A Book of Lenses, and I thought he put things really well.
There are progressive games where there's a linear story,
and there are emergent games where gameplay is king.
Books are progressive because you turn the page
and the story progresses, and chess is emergent
because the gameplay emerges from the players.
It's dynamic, it's highly replayable.
I'm so happy to finally understand
how what I did related to games.
But there was this terrifying fear bubbling underneath,
the fear that the closer games got
to the emergent end of the spectrum,
the more my skills were unwanted.
To combat this fear, I went to work making epic storylines
with lore and backstory and nuance.
I'd stay up late creating my narrative vision
and wonder why they couldn't see that.
Epic storylines are exactly what every broad appeal
mass market casual mobile title needs.
One day, someone I trusted pulled me aside and said,
you know what, this game just doesn't need story.
It's hard not to hear that as,
this game just doesn't need you.
Well, I thought, I really only have one option.
I'm going to completely disregard everything anyone says
and make a new theory of game design to prove them wrong.
So here it is.
So Amy's theory on how all games are linear.
We're going to go look at three experiences.
Jaws, Life is Strange, and Minecraft, all on a different place on the spectrum, and
each one getting a little messier on how to prove that linear narrative works on the most
progressive games and also ones that break all the rules.
Jaws.
So truly linear narrative cannot be a game.
A game implies player interaction.
Instead we'll look at the structure of a movie,
one that is expertly crafted to hit
all the traditional storytelling beats.
Jaws starts with a shark attack,
but don't mistake this for the inciting incident.
We have not met our protagonist yet, so it can't be.
Enter Chief Brody.
Now that our hero is here, the call to adventure can happen.
Chief Brody reads the coroner's report, shark attack.
The question is asked, will Chief Brody kill the shark?
Yes or no?
During the rising action, complications arise,
all to do with this question of killing the shark.
First, a child is killed.
Then Chief Brody's own kid is in the water
when a surfer gets killed.
Next Brody and his two sidekicks get on a boat, a big boat.
Quinn the sea dog gets eaten by a shark.
Hooper the oceanographer is in danger.
Brody himself is in danger.
And then, there's the climax.
No question that Chief Brody did indeed kill that shark.
It's dead.
It's pretty dead.
Finally, the resolution gives a hint of what's to come.
So if you actually watch to the end of the credits,
you'll see that Brody and Hooper get back to shore.
So obviously this is a movie,
but if we pretended it was a game
and we took three different players,
they would all have the same linear path
through that experience.
So let's see how that changes
when we talk about Life is Strange.
Life is Strange, stunning game by Dontnod,
published by Square Enix.
You play Max, and Max has the power to rewind time
to make a different choice.
For all intents and purposes,
Life is Strange is a very traditional narrative.
It happens to be branching.
So, this is a whole talk in of itself,
but in Life is Strange, the entire series
has a traditional narrative structure,
as does its five episodes, as does each individual scene.
We're gonna look at the Frank confrontation scene
in episode four.
It's a little microcosm for what we're talking about.
It demonstrates that even with branching narrative,
every individual path follows the same linear structure rules.
Introduction.
All three players have the same experience so far.
Max and Chloe meet a client list
from their friendly neighborhood drug dealer, Frank.
Inciting incident.
Chloe knocks on the door.
No turning back.
Will they get that client list?
Yes or no?
Rising action.
Negotiations begin.
Frank does not trust them.
This is where it splits.
Depending on how you negotiate,
you can either tap into Frank's emotions
and soften him up.
You can upset him and set his dog on the attack.
Or things can go south and Chloe can pull a gun.
These are all relevant to that central question
of getting that client list,
and they all grow in emotional intensity.
Consequently, all three choices are satisfying
and allow for a level of meaningful player choice
that a purely progressive experience couldn't.
Likewise, when we get to the climax,
there are three meaningful choices.
Frank can give the client list willingly.
Chloe can injure Frank, causing him to give it
not so willingly.
Or Chloe can kill Frank
and take the client list off his body.
So, will Max and Chloe get the client list?
All paths lead to yes, but the journey is different.
And finally, in the scenes resolution,
if Frank doesn't die, the girls walk away relieved.
If he does, there's an emotional toll
that is carried through the rest of the game.
Here is the developer's chart of all the branching paths
in this scene.
When I saw this, it blew me away at how much player agency
there is.
But this is a very top-down way of looking
at the scene, which is useful for implementation.
But if we kind of turn it 90 degrees.
You'll see the linear narrative, which is extremely
useful for emotion.
Every player is hitting the same beats, the same
complications, but their story is different.
A developer's ability to map the music of emotions is an
incredible tool, not only for giving players compelling
stories, but for getting a team on the same page.
I'll go into more detail on that at the end of the talk.
For me.
When I started looking at branching narrative
in a similar way that I might look at Jaws,
it was a real aha moment, as Oprah Winfrey might call it.
Because if you extrapolate on this idea
that each player path creates a traditional story structure,
and you consider that each scene, each episode,
and each series also has that structure,
you can extrapolate how these branching
and nested structures could grow infinitely
to become a three-dimensional sandbox-like game.
And that's what we're going to talk about when we talk about Minecraft and emergent games.
At first glance, when looking at Minecraft, it is confusing to see the narrative.
There doesn't seem to be an end.
You choose your play style.
Night and day give some semblance of story structure.
And then there's creative mode.
And where is the story there?
What am I missing?
The open world is a good metaphor for all the possibilities
for paths a player might take.
We often talk about different player types
or different gameplay styles
when we talk about sandbox games.
So why is that in particular so important?
Because suddenly the player is the protagonist,
which makes the player's inciting incident
the discovery of what they're driven to accomplish.
Will I build an epic house?
Will I become the best baddie killer in the land?
Will I connect with my friends?
So as it happens, my friend Catherine
is player type number three.
So I asked her to tell me her experience of playing Minecraft.
So we'll use it to break down what
that looks like using good old linear narrative structure.
Introduction.
I started playing because my friends were playing.
I'd wait to play until other people were online.
We used Discord and we would chat about the game beforehand
and then chat in-game.
So Catherine's introduction is actually outside the game
in this case.
Inciting incident.
We all started in different places
and we had to find each other using landmarks.
So this is the moment her question is posed.
Will I connect with my friends?
Complication one in the rising action.
We first explored what this place was,
a sense of the unknown.
I don't remember having a tutorial,
but I remember seeing nothing in my inventory.
I spun around in a circle thinking, where am I?
Then I thought, lush and green equals safe.
Snowy mountains equals harder.
I should stay in the green area.
So she wants to find her friends,
but she doesn't know the rules yet.
Complication two.
I found my friends and we wanted to build a fortress.
First we built our own houses,
but when a friend left, we built his for him.
We made a huge fortress and incorporated our personalities.
Someone put torches in a large staircase
to make it look regal.
First we used the resources that were there,
but then I learned you can make anything.
So I'd go get things and bring them back to safety.
The goal was to build a house no matter what,
and it didn't hit me until nighttime that I could die.
Complication three.
That first night I was outside, I didn't realize there were creatures and I was not prepared.
I just really wanted to make roofs.
I think it was a skeleton shooting arrows.
I was like, what is that?
Then I died.
I didn't make a bed, so I had to find my friends again.
But I learned and made a bed, armor, and a weapon to fight with.
So while a different player might be focused on fighting and weapons, for
Catherine, this was a means to an end.
Climax.
Then I learned you could set a house on fire,
so we set our friends' houses on fire
and started the process all over again.
So the reason I think this is the climax
is it takes a certain level of friendship
to grief your friend and get away with it.
So for Catherine, did I connect with my friends?
Yes!
Well, I certainly hope so.
And finally, the resolution.
I was focused on my main objective, which was a million ways to get stuff to build with.
You learn to craft, and then there's color, materials.
I thought, now I want to build a purple house.
This changes everything.
I need wool.
I need to dye wool.
So this gives us a hint of what's to come.
Catherine has built her friend community and now is going to master crafting.
But the cool thing about Minecraft is this moment is not just the resolution.
It's the inciting incident for another story.
So you can see if we just take a top-down approach
to analyzing all the different player paths.
Collectively, it looks like nonsense.
But if we translate it into a familiar linear structure,
we can track the music of each player
and plan to put things into the sandbox
that satisfies each intrinsic drive.
Even though maybe the players redefine their story
at some point, maybe player one is playing for a week,
maybe player three is playing for three years,
the rules are the same.
What's different is that I am the protagonist.
My story is the story.
I ask the questions.
So I promised you my theory on game design, and here it is.
All games, from the most progressive
to the most emergent, follow linear structure.
However, we're not really talking
about a spectrum of story structure.
We're talking about a spectrum of identity.
When I talk about the main character, do I say they,
or do I say I?
The spectrum is what is so special about games.
Though, even as I say that, the truth
is most media are transitioning closer
to the I end of the spectrum.
We don't just watch videos.
We comment and post and make it our own experience.
So as our media diversifies, the ability to simplify the truth
of human experience into something we can all analyze
becomes more essential.
So to tie this together, I begin by saying
this approach is important because it, one,
creates a tool for speaking directly to players' hearts,
and two, it acts as a common language
for multidisciplinary teams.
So how do we begin to shift our language?
How do we translate the micro of our separate disciplines,
economies, systems, art, loops, into common ground?
I think like most things in games, it's iterative.
I've seen great leaders and peers with different styles.
One of my favorite examples is an analyst coming up
with a way to look at which animals are players liked best
based on the animal's cuddle-ability factor.
I thought that was such a great example of empathy for the player's story.
It changes the question from, will I get a new animal to, will I get the most cuddleable
animal ever, which is so simple and inspirational for everyone on the team.
So how to shift language could be a session in and of itself, but if I could offer one
takeaway, it would be this moment.
This idea of the ball, the shark, the client list,
the friendship.
Because when you identify what a player is after,
you can open that question up to a team.
Will they get the ball in the end zone?
Will he kill the shark?
Will they get the client list?
Will I find my friends?
The beautiful thing is that there are many paths
to answer that question.
And the terrible thing is that there are many paths
to answer that question, which is why people
are so reluctant to pose it.
But I read this article about diversity recently,
and it argued that the strength of diversity in all its forms
is not that we're kumbaya and we all get along.
No.
Humans are naturally distrustful of anything unlike us.
So we question others' ideas, and they question us.
So diversity demands critical thinking.
And critical thinking has never been more important,
nor has media or entertainment and the stories
we choose to tell.
If you can be ruthless in defining the question,
but open in the path for solving for the answer,
you've created a shared starting place
for a singular narrative with infinite possibilities.
Thank you.