Hello everyone, my name is Nick Yi.
I'm the co-founder and analytics lead of Quantic Foundry.
So three quick notes, turn off your noisemakers,
remember to fill in your evaluations,
and I do have a link for the download
of the PDF of these slides.
I'll give it to you at the end of the talk.
When we were working on the slides for this year,
we were reflecting back on the three talks
we've given so far before.
And one thing we noticed that was almost surprising even
to us was, over the span of the past three talks,
we've actually only spent about 10 seconds
describing each motivation.
We did this to be concise so that we could spend most of our time talking about what
we felt were more interesting things.
How our motivations connect with age, with gender, with personality, and how whether
gamers consider themselves casual or hardcore.
But our use of these short hands and being concise has inadvertently created a negative
space where some misconceptions have been brewing.
So what I'll be talking to you about today
is the dark side of the moon, which
we realized late yesterday would have been
a great title for this talk.
So what do I mean by negative space?
In Jason Vandenberg's 2012 GDC talk,
he asked a super insightful question.
Considering Bottles' player types,
which almost everyone in the game industry is familiar with,
he asked us, what is a non-achiever?
I hope it's immediately clear that despite the positioning in the chart, a non-achiever
isn't a socializer.
Just because someone dislikes leveling up and grinding doesn't mean that they're a social
care bear.
Jason's answered this question.
A player who isn't driven by grinding and leveling up is a contentment player, someone
who is comfortable with the status and doesn't want to be caught up in the rat race.
The most striking thing, the reason why Jason's question was so insightful, is that it's pointing
out something that is missing entirely on this graph.
A non-achiever actually isn't even a dot you can place on this map.
So Jason's question really foregrounded a negative space that had literally become invisible
in the game industry.
It's a blind spot that's quite common across most proposed motivation taxonomies, including
our own, especially when we try to be concise.
And to be clear, by negative space, I don't mean a bad thing like a closet full of zombies.
It's like the elephant in the room that no one noticed before,
despite how much space it occupied. But once someone points it out, you can't unsee it.
So even though we knew about this negative space
in our attempts to be concise when presenting a motivation
model, we inadvertently created and kept
reinforcing this exact negative space.
And because of this, we started getting very similar questions
from folks that stemmed from this negative space.
So questions like, what does low completion actually mean?
What are game examples of games of low completion?
If a gamer scores low on all the motivations,
are they just a disengaged gamer?
And when a gamer has many high scores,
do they just want more of everything?
In our data, we have a way of filling in
that negative space empirically.
So to date, over 400,000 gamers have come and taken
our gamer motivation profile.
Gamers take a five minute survey
and they receive a personalized report
of how their motivations rank relative to other gamers.
Alongside the gaming motivation scores, we also ask gamers their demographics and specific
game titles that they've enjoyed playing.
So we're able to pivot between these three variable sets.
So for each game that's mentioned in the data, we can sample the gamers who've mentioned
that game and calculate the average motivation profile of that game's audience.
So say we're interested in the strategy motivation.
I can tabulate the motivation score, the motivation score
for each game on strategy, and then rank or to the games
by their average strategy score from the lowest
all the way to the highest.
We can then look at the list of games
on both ends of the spectrum to understand
the negative space and articulate the spectrum itself.
So figuring out this negative space is looking into this bucket of game titles and playing
what do these three things have in common.
So it's like someone came up to you and asked, what do Little Red Riding Hood,
Amadador, and Africa have in common.
And the analysis that we went through
is slowly figuring out that the three things
these things have in common is they all have capes.
So in this talk, we'll go through what
we found when we ran through all the tabulations,
chewed on the potential commonalities of the game
titles, and how we've tried to make
sense of the negative space based on our data set.
So let me start with one quick example,
and then I'll keep chatting a bit more
about this negative space.
So let's start with strategy.
We've typically described strategy
as part of a cluster of motivations
that revolves around more long-term
oriented gaming motivations.
So things that take time and planning to accomplish.
Strategy is about the decision complexity in the gameplay,
the amount of information you have to process
to make the next decision,
the potential contingencies you have to anticipate
and plan for, the number of steps and moves,
the time horizon on which you have to plan
and accomplish your goals.
Do you need to plan one step out or 15 moves out?
So I'll be showing you a chart like this for each motivation.
We'll provide some of the more well-known game titles
in the top 20th percent and the bottom 20%
of each motivation ranking.
So in other words, if we took all the games in our data set
and rank them on their average strategy score
from lowest to highest,
what are some of the games in the bottom 20,
what are some of the games in the top 20?
It doesn't mean.
that these games are only played by players with extreme motivations,
but these are games that exemplify the preferences of gamers
with very high or very low scores on these motivations.
So gamers with high strategy...
They want a great deal of decision complexity.
They want meaty decisions that they can chew on
and long-term strategies they can plan out and execute.
So some examples of games that score high on strategy
include StarCraft, Crusader Kings, Europa Universalis.
Conversely, games with low strategy scores
are more spontaneous and reactive gamers.
They want gameplay with lower cognitive loads, shorter time horizons,
and where decisions can be made based on processing only a small amount of information,
or planning isn't even productive at all because of the many randomized elements in the game.
So in our data, some examples of games in this space were The Sims, Disney Emoji Blitz, and Mario Kart.
I want to clarify one thing before I move on
about these scores and these placements.
You can absolutely play The Sims in a highly strategic way.
Say I have a master plan from the start
to create a vampire couple who abducts
the alien baby next door and then plans carnivorous plans
all over town to murder everyone.
You can play The Sims that way.
And that is a long-term plan, and that is high strategy.
What we're tracking here is how the core audience
gamers who say they enjoy these games,
what their average motivation profile looks like.
We're not measuring how a game could be played,
but rather what an audience a game typically attracts,
and thus how that core audience most typically plays that game.
When I say the negative space and the dark side of the moon,
part of what I mean is that when we,
the game industry, talk about gaming motivations,
We tend to have far better developed vocabulary and terminology and nuance for certain aspects
of gaming, and our language is tended to be shaped by how core or hardcore gamers see
the world and things that they want more of in games, and because game researchers and
game designers are almost game players themselves.
This bias has permeated our way of conceptualizing
gaming motivation.
So when you scan motivation taxonomies in literature
in industry white papers, you'll often
find motivations like competition and challenge
like we do in our taxonomy.
For this reason, things that a hardcore gamer wants more of.
So this more of x or less of x way
of talking about gaming motivations
is something that Jason Vandenberg has referred
to as the thermometer model.
And I'll use that term here in my talk as well and expand on that.
One problem with the thermometer model is that it leads people to treat the high end
of the motivation as being more inherently important or valuable than the lower end.
So, for example, we have a tendency to lump everything in the negative space into this
amorphous bland bucket that we call casual.
and they typically leave it at that.
And someone who doesn't like challenging
multiplayer gameplay, oh, they're just casual.
Even when we have other labels for these folks,
they tend to be value negative labels,
so this gameplay is simplistic, it's slow,
it's not a real game.
So our collective language for talking about gaming motivations
implicitly measures how far someone falls from the ideal hardcore gamer.
This is an artifact of the thermometer model,
and that's one thing we're trying to surface and correct here.
Let me show you another example of design,
one of the two motivations under creativity.
In the past, we've described design as the appeal of expressing your own individuality
in the context of a game.
Can I express my personal flair in this game?
Can I leave a mark behind?
Does the game provide me with the levers and the color pickers to really design my avatar
in Spaceship and City?
So you may think that games of low design tend to look bland or generic, but that's
not what we've found.
Let's start on the high end.
In our data, games like Guild Wars 2, The Sims,
and Animal Crossing had some of the highest design scores.
This makes sense, given the large range
of customization opportunities in these games.
But on the low end, we don't find bland or abstract games.
In our data, some of the games with the lowest design scores
included Braid, Super Meat Boys, Super Mario Galaxies,
games with very unique styles and creative visions.
So rather than simply
low or high customization.
Another potential way to think about what's going on
is the amount of aesthetic control
over the game world between the game designer and the player.
How much control is the player willing to cede and relinquish
to the designer's vision?
How willing is a gamer to experience a curated game
experience as opposed to wanting to have
a direct hand in shaping and designing
the world themselves?
Thanks.
Sorry about that.
I'll show you the age and gender breakdowns
for some of the motivations, so the more interesting ones,
and also the ones that contrast well with each other.
Each motivation kind of has its own unique signature
in terms of how it varies by age and gender.
So in these charts.
Each dot is the average here, the design score, for all respondents at each age point.
So each dot is the average of thousands of players.
The orange circular dots are the women and the blue triangular dots are the men.
So here we have design.
It actually peaks very early.
Female gamers are more interested in design,
and the appeal of design drops slowly with age.
And the delta between men and women
stays pretty constant throughout the age span
that we have between age 13 to 60 that we're showing you here.
With all these charts that I'll show you,
you'll notice that there's more fluctuation at the tail end,
at the older end.
This is because we have fewer data points beyond age 50.
So even with the larger data samples,
there's still a bit of jitter there.
So at this point, you may be asking yourself, wait,
so Quantic Foundry didn't know what the low end
of each scale meant until now?
The answer is yes and no.
When we put together the profile app,
we knew roughly what the low ends of each motivation
likely referred to, but we didn't have the clarity
that we now have because of specific game titles
we were able to explore based on the data itself.
Another reason that is that
It's very difficult to ask about the absence of something
in a survey.
The question is very difficult to make sense of
for respondents.
We also didn't want to force false dichotomies
into the model based on our own assumptions.
So for example, we don't ask gamers
if they prefer lots of customization options
or a bland game.
That's a forced dichotomy.
So we allowed the motivation items to aggregate naturally
when we're doing the data analysis
and then to figure out the negative space later on
using the data.
Excitement is next.
We've often described excitement as an appeal
of fast-paced, action-oriented gameplay
with lots of surprises and thrills.
I'm going to take a slight detour into personalized psychology.
Jerome Kagan's longitudinal study of baby temperament is one of my favorite studies
in the field of psychology.
The study began in the 80s, and temperament is a consistent set of behavioral responses
from a baby in how they react to things, because we cannot ask four-month-olds to take surveys.
Kagan found that infants as young as four months of age
developed temperamental differences
where they behave differently to new things,
whether it's new people, new toys, or novel sounds.
So on one end of the spectrum, you
have babies where you put them in a cradle
and you bring out a toy mobile.
And you start jangling it wildly in front of the baby.
And you can jangle for as long as you want.
The baby remains calm and entertained.
And on the other extreme, you have babies who become visibly distressed the moment you
bring out the toy mobile.
And they become more distressed the more you jangle the toy in front of them until they
start to flail and cry uncontrollably.
These temperamental differences at four months of age don't translate one-to-one into introversion
and extroversion when these babies grow up.
So Kagan followed these babies until they were adults.
But these temperamental differences do seem to apply strong constraints.
So the babies who are calm at four months of age very rarely become introverts when
they're adults.
And similarly, the babies who are easily distressed at four months of age rarely become extroverts
when they're adults.
And so what this study reveals is that there's an important difference.
between introverts and extroverts in terms of their tolerance of novel stimuli,
specifically whether that stimulus is entertaining or overwhelming to them.
So introverts avoid parties and crowds because the sensory stimulation quickly becomes exhausting,
draining, and overwhelming, while extroverts love parties and crowds because the sensory
stimulation is entertaining and energizing.
We've shown you before in one of our earlier talks
the linkages between the personality trait of extroversion
and the gaming motivation of excitement.
So we've typically described excitement, again,
as a speed and pacing of the game,
but at its core, it's about the stimulus delta
from one moment to the next.
How much change, whether that's in the visuals,
in the audio,
How much change happened just now is about the amount of novelty and unexpected change
from moment to moment and our desire for that novelty.
This is why surprise is one of the key words in our summary table.
So in the high end.
You have action shooters and action fighters like CSGO,
Super Smash Brothers, games that are fast-paced
and we're constantly bombarded with new information.
And in the low end, we find games that are turn-based,
or even games that are typically played while paused,
like Europa Universalis.
These are games where you have perfect control of the pacing.
If you need more time, you can take as much time as you need.
Nothing in the game world changes
until you're ready for a change to happen.
So in this sense, the game experience is predictable.
Things tend to change in very incremental and gradual ways.
The game state from one moment to the next is very similar.
I feel a little dirty showing you this slide.
But I want to make an important statistical point,
and it's easy to show this via the MBTI.
The MBTI, very briefly, makes a strong assumption
that people have clear preferences along four dimensions.
So for example, in this first dimension,
people tend to prefer
and either be introverts or extroverts.
That's where the E and the I come from in the model.
And so together, these four dimensions
create the 16 possible personality types.
So here's a graphical representation of the MBTI's worldview.
It's assuming that there are two subpopulations, one that leans towards introversion, another
that leans towards extroversion, and there are some people in between, but they're uncommon.
So you can imagine that these people in the middle who are uncommon might feel the need
to come up with a new label to describe themselves, because they're neither introverts or extroverts.
You may have seen these posts on your Facebook wall about ambiverts.
But the reality, based on decades of research
in personality psychology, is that personality traits
all fall along a normal distribution, a bell curve.
So we already had a word for amberverts.
That word is average.
There are two important properties of the bell curve.
So first, most people fall very close to the average.
About 68% of the population falls within one standard deviation of the average.
That's a little over two-thirds of the population.
And very few people fall in the extremes.
Only about 5% of the population falls more than two standard deviations away from the norm.
Because most people fall near the average, the core statistical and validity problem
of the MBTI is that it's ignoring this big hump in the room.
And this, among other reasons, is why the MBTI is poor reliability because people, most
people who are near the center, when they retake the test, their scores, their types
will shift because they were so close to center and they're being sliced in half on one side
of the other.
Of course, introverts and extroverts do exist, but most people have weak or almost no preferences,
and far few people have strong preferences.
Going back to the thermometer model,
another problem with the thermometer model
is that it encourages people, can conceptualize gamers
and gaming motivations in a biased way
because it implicitly measures everyone else
against this ideal hardcore gamer.
It makes it easy to start talking about some gamers
as being lesser than.
So these folks with low scores are not real gamers.
But the reason why I bring up the personalized psychology,
is because the extroversion spectrum
highlights how lower scores are not simply lesser than.
So for example, people on both ends of the extroversion
spectrum have equally strong preferences and attitudes.
And people at the extreme ends of both
are equally difficult to deal with in real life.
So instead of the thermometer model,
the more appropriate reading isn't more of or less
of something, but that there are lots
of average people in the middle and some really opinionated
people on both ends of the extreme.
So more importantly, the thing to keep in mind
is that introverts don't have.
less personality than extroverts.
And it's the same with gaming motivations.
Many gamers have moderate, near-average scores
on the motivations, and a smaller number
have more extreme, stronger preferences.
So it's your delta from the average that largely defines you.
It's the way you stand out from the crowd that are the most interesting and visible
parts of you.
The ways in which you conform to the norm are the least interesting parts of who you
are.
No one will remember you for having ten fingers.
This is why in our blog posts and in our talks,
we always visualize motivations from the norm.
This makes it much easier to identify the motivations that
are very different from the average,
whereas the bars that are close to the average
are very small and less visually prominent.
There's a more subtle reason here as well.
Traits like extroversion, strategy
like in our gaming motivation model,
are entirely man-made constructs, and they only exist and are meaningful in relation to other people.
If you're the only person left in the world, you're neither tall or short, because there's
no one else to compare you to. Similarly, you care more or less about strategy only relative to other
gamers, and thus the population norm is the only meaningful reference point for personality traits
and for gaming motivations.
Community is next.
Community and competition are the two motivations
that fall under social.
Community is about working with other players,
competition is about working against other players.
Community is about shared experiences,
of being willing to not be fully in control of your game
experience, being open to experiencing the game
through someone else's eyes and actions.
There's an interplay here between dependence
versus independence, collaboration versus control.
So on the high end, we see games like Destiny,
Final Fantasy XIV, MMOs, and online team-based shooters
that emphasize teamwork and collaboration.
On the low end, we see games that emphasize independence,
soloable campaigns, and content like Lego Harry Potter
and Farm Hero Saga, games where you're always
in full control of the game experience.
Here's the plot of community by gender and age.
I'll make two points.
We stereotype women as social care bearers,
but between ages 13 through 35,
it's the men who care more about community and teamwork.
There's an alternative reading of this chart,
and I always try to be careful when
we look at the charts for competition and for community.
The apparent delta here could be an artifact of toxicity
in online games, that it dampens the appeal of online games
for younger female gamers, and that it recovers past age 40,
because in our data, there's a shift towards non-shooter MMOs
in that age range, where toxicity is less of an issue.
So that's always one thing that we want to be careful about
in terms of interpreting what these differences in community
and competition may or may not mean.
The thermometer model tricks us into thinking
that higher scores always means more of something.
But the spectrum model better surfaces
that there are always trade-offs going on.
So for example, we could conceptualize high community
as the willingness to give up some of your control.
in terms of gameplay, whereas low community is a desire to hoard as much control as possible.
Laying out both ends of the motivations highlights how there's a give and take,
always a give and take going on, rather than just more or less of a preference.
We're moving on to competition, the other motivation under the social pair.
One of the things that I've noticed about my own gaming preferences
is that I like the strategic gameplay of
CCC's collectible card games like Hearthstone, but I
dislike the emotional state playing against another player puts me in.
So it took me a while to realize that that emotional state
is an acute stress cascade, or what we typically call the
the fight-or-flight response. So anxiety triggers this response, regardless of
whether it's a real bear
or virtual bear.
If your hands ever get super cold
after playing a competitive game,
that's from the adrenaline rush that's
diverting your blood flow to your arm and leg
muscles away from your extremities.
So during the fight or flight response,
our bodies get flooded with cortisol, adrenaline,
which have many downstream physiological effects
to help us deal with or flee from danger.
And even though we're not actually in danger,
it's a carryover effect of old biological circuits
and virtual simulations.
But in the same way that some people like watching horror movies,
they like getting scared, or people who go skydiving,
that mild adrenaline rush is pleasurable for some people
because endorphins are also being released during the cascade.
So one way to think of the appeal of competition
is that it's a way to hack your own biochemistry to get the adrenaline
endorphin rushes without actually being in real danger. It's a kind of
biological hacking.
I find that another useful framing to think about competition is the way we think about
conflict in board games.
So on one end, you have high-conflict games, like Warhammer, where my miniature units are
directly attacking your units and killing them.
There's a middle ground, like in Agricola, where we're competing against each other for
a high score, but we're all largely in our own walled gardens, and I can only indirect
interfere with what you're trying to do.
And then there's the other end where there's no conflict.
There's no rankings, no duels against other human players.
Games that aren't about comparing your skills
or abilities against other players.
So here in the high competition end,
we have MOBAs, online shooters like League and Call of Duty.
On the low competition end, we have games
where there are no rankings or duels
against other human players.
The sorceress that turns into a dragon to attack you
isn't competition, that's drama.
We're on to completion.
The achievement pair is about different kinds
of point systems.
And completion is about quantifiable,
persistent progress and rewards.
It's about knowing how far exactly you are from a goal.
It's about having a clear task with clear instructions
and having a clear way to assess how close you are
to reaching that goal.
So completion can almost always be converted
to a zero to 100% percentage bar, whether by itself
or as part of a larger hierarchy of tasks.
Games that score high on completion
tend to be very task-oriented, with clear, predictable
conversion mechanics between time and rewards.
So in our data, MMOs, especially Asian MMOs,
like Dragon Nest, Aura Kingdom, scored very high on completion.
Games that score low on completion
tend to be more sandboxy games, where there are rules,
but the player has to decide what they want to do.
where the players have to figure out what goals they want to pursue on their own.
Don't tell me what I have to do.
I'm going to decide for myself if I'm going to dominate the world
and how I'm going to dominate the world.
So on the low completion end, we have games like Victoria 2, Kerbal Space Program.
Completion, we've mentioned this before I think,
completion is the most age-stable motivation in our model.
It increases ever so slightly among women
over the age span, and it decreases ever so slightly
among men over the age span.
So as people get older,
the gender difference gets a little wider.
But overall, it's the motivation in our model
that changes the least over age.
Over the past year or so, we've been working with Nico Partners
on a series of survey-based projects.
Nico Partners is a market research and consulting firm
that covers the games market in Asia.
And in one of these projects, we surveyed 2,000 Chinese gamers
and included the motivation assessment questions.
It wasn't the direct goal of that study to do the cross-cultural comparison,
but the data allowed us to do it. So we compared gamers in the U.S. from our dataset
against gamers in China from Nikko's dataset, using the same motivation questions,
translated of course as simplified Chinese.
And we first looked at the differences,
and we found these striking differences
in gaming motivations between the two samples.
So in this chart, China is the gray bars,
and the US is the orange bars.
So in particular, Chinese gamers scored much higher
on the two motivations that we just covered,
on competition and on completion.
And they scored lower on fantasy story discovery designs,
so their creativity immersion motivations.
To give you a sense of the size of the difference here in,
let's do competition.
The average gamer in Nico's sample,
Nico Parner's sample,
cares more about competition than roughly 75%
of the US gamers in our sample.
We dug a little deeper into the data,
and in other places where we expected
there to be differences,
the differences turned out to be very small.
So this is a chart of the motivation differences.
We've shown you this data in a different way in previous.
talks, gender differences and motivations among our full data set.
So we've seen before that the men, the gray bars, they care more about competition, excitement,
destruction.
The women, they care more about fantasy design completion.
We've shown you this data before in a different graph.
So we try to see, you know, do these differences pan out the same way in China or do different
differences come out?
And so here's a chart for the China gamers.
Most of the, so those are the error bars.
Most of the bars are not even statistically different.
Of the ones that are, the only one
that is substantively meaningful is the one in destruction.
So in the Chinese sample, the men cared more
about destruction than the women.
But across the other 11,
there are essentially no gender differences.
Whereas in the US, the Western data,
there were differences all over the map.
So we talk a lot about gendered gaming differences in the West and the American context,
but what this data is kind of hinting and surfacing is that perhaps the gender differences
in gaming that we see in the West may be unique to the West, and that this would also imply that
they could be entirely an artifact of culture and marketing and historical idiosyncrasies
without really needing to invoke biology.
We saw this paralleled with the age data.
So, you know, again, let me talk through the column,
the second column, the US column.
You know, I've been talking about how motivations like competition,
like destruction, excitement,
these are motivations that decline with age.
So these are the correlation coefficients.
In the US, there are seven of the 12 motivations
that have a correlation coefficient above .10.
it's a small to medium-sized correlation. In the Chinese data,
among the Chinese sample, none of the age correlations were above
0.1. So across the age span in China,
the variation in motivations was very, very low.
So Chinese gamers as a whole are very different
from US gamers, but within the audience of Chinese gamers,
there's much less variation than one would expect
based on what we'd previously seen in our Western data set.
What we can say, we'd love to know why.
What we can't say is why these differences
or lack of differences are the way they are.
But there are two things that struck out for us
when you go partners and we were looking through this data.
The difference, especially in competition,
goes against traditional assumptions between individualist versus collectivist societies.
So previous cultural findings in academia would have predicted that a more individualist society
like the U.S. should score higher on competition, but we're finding here the exact opposite.
The second point is that the Chinese gaming market
has been able to develop in a semi-isolated manner
due to a variety of governmental regulations,
such as the ban until recently on Western consoles,
the cultural review of content, the Great Firewall.
Net cafe culture has also encouraged greater adoption
of specific genres of games,
such as online multiplayer games.
And of course, the Chinese market makes its own games,
a large number of them, in fact.
So part of what we're seeing may stem
from the different sensibilities
and emphasis that their games have.
and how their gamers have historically adopted gaming.
So, for example, many popular Chinese games
aren't available or known in the US market.
So these two populations aren't really even playing
the same games to begin with.
We were just talking about completion.
Power is the other motivation
in the pair of achievement motivations.
where completion is about getting to 100%,
power is about constant growth in absolute numbers.
So power is about getting bigger,
getting stronger over time.
It's almost always numbers driven
because you need numbers to quantify how much you've grown.
But power isn't really the end goal.
It's more likely that the appeal is centered
on the journey of growth that is satisfying,
the appeal of getting stronger.
So another contrast with completion
is that completion goals tend to stick around
on a very persistent basis.
The stars you collect, the levels you completed,
they stick with your character or your game.
Whereas power can be more transient
because it's the journey that matters.
So here in high power, we have games like World of Warcraft
and League, and your champion in League
gets stronger over each match.
But then it resets, and you can start it all over again.
And that's fine, because it's the journey that's pleasurable.
Low power is not the lack of growth as much as it is a desire to not be on a treadmill,
to not be part of implicit rat race.
These games here tend to be more about adventure and story.
So example here are The Longest Journey and Her Story.
We've talked about excitement already, and now we're touching on the other motivation
in the action pair, destruction.
We have guns and explosives under the description for destruction, but at its heart, destruction
is about being drawn to chaos and mayhem, the erosion of rules, letting entropy have
its day.
When I was a grad student at Stanford,
and I was showing my advisor Second Life so many, many moons ago.
I was showing him the basics, and we were just about to leave the Newby area.
And he suddenly got very excited, and he asked,
are you allowed to sit on that person?
Can we go sit on people?
That's low-grade destruction.
So it's not surprising that destruction is highest in games
where you can destroy things the fastest, which is shooters.
It's watching order turn into disorder.
We'd have expected that construction
would be the other end of destruction, but it's not.
It's enduring and evergreen world.
So these are games that are reliably constant
that you can revisit over and over again.
Games like Professor Layton, like Myst,
like Animal Crossing.
It's like the virtual.
corner coffee shop that offers a sense of comforting, reliable familiarity.
We had someone ask us recently where we think construction would fit in our model, and we
thought about it.
And we think construction is typically a means and not an ends, and let me talk through this.
So building an empire in civilization, that's strategy.
building a city in SimCity so I can blow it up with disasters, that's destruction,
building King's Landing in Minecraft so I can role-play being Cersei, that's fantasy and story,
and seeing if I can build a roller coaster in Kerbal Space Program, that's more discovery.
So...
We've tried experimenting with survey items related to construction,
and it doesn't quite cling anywhere, we think, for this reason.
It depends on why you're building something,
and construction in and of itself isn't a clear signal.
Destruction is most appealing to the youngest gamers,
particularly the youngest men.
I'm sure you're all shocked.
It then plateaus for about two decades.
It doesn't plummet like competition does.
And then it's only past age 40
that it really starts to drop again.
There's a gender difference
and it gets slightly larger over the age span.
fantasy. The immersion pairs about being part of the game world in different ways. So fantasy is
the willingness to suspend disbelief and be transported to an alternate reality, the desire
to become someone else, somewhere else. It's about the psychological teleportation to another world
and it hinges on the richness of that alternate world, its lore, its scope, and its visual design.
So in our data, games like Mass Effect and Dragon Age scored highest on fantasy.
Again, games with rich worlds and history and lore.
Games that score low on fantasy usually fall into one of two camps.
They're either abstract puzzle games like Candy Crush,
or when they have 3D worlds and detailed graphics,
the worlds and settings tend to be generic and interchangeable.
So like a desert encampment or a rough terrain in a shooter game.
Here we see Counter-Strike, for example, on that end of the spectrum.
I have a story that's hell about fantasy and the adoption of VR.
We ran a survey alongside the Gamer Motivation profile
on VR adoption and satisfaction.
We had about 2,400 responses to that survey
over a period of the past 12 months,
of which 31% were adopters of current-gen, high-end VR.
So one of either Oculus, Samsung Gear, PSVR, or HTC Vive.
So the gray bars are gamers who haven't adopted VR.
The orange bars are the gamers who have.
When we compared the motivations of the two cohorts,
we were expecting fantasy to be a predictor of VR adoption.
It turns out it isn't.
The best motivational predictors of VR adoption
are destruction and excitement.
So people who like fast-paced chaos and mayhem
have been more likely to go out and purchase VR,
fans of shooter games.
This is interesting from a...
disposable income point of view, because VR is currently expensive.
And these two motivations, destruction and excitement, these two motivations
both drop quite fast with age. So older gamers
with more disposable income and can afford VR are precisely the gamers who
have dampened motivational interest in VR. We looked one step further into the
data. So we looked only at the gamers who had purchased and adopted VR.
We asked them, how satisfied are you with your purchase,
with the technology?
And we divided into three groups based on their satisfaction.
So the gray bar are those with low satisfaction.
They are not at all or only slightly satisfied.
The middle orange bar is medium satisfaction.
They are somewhat satisfied.
And the blue bar is high satisfaction.
They are very satisfied or extremely satisfied.
And it's here that we see fantasy along with discovery pop up as being differentiators.
VR adopters who also care about fantasy and discovery
are more likely to be the ones to be satisfied
with their VR purchase.
So an analogy might be what gets people through the door
is not the same as what keeps them happy
once they're inside.
And in this specific case, the desire to be someone else,
somewhere else, isn't enough to get someone to purchase VR.
But if they do make the purchase,
these are the gamers who are more likely to be satisfied
with the technology.
We're here with discovery in the creativity pair.
I often describe discovery as playing games
in the broadest sense of the word.
So it's easy to think of discovery as just the exploration of a world,
but it's actually more about exploring and poking at the boundaries of the game itself
and figuring out what is and isn't possible.
So in this sense, it's about the number of unknowns when you start playing a game,
not just in terms of the geography, the places you haven't seen,
but the rules of what you can and cannot do in that world.
So games that have high discovery...
tend to have lots of secrets.
There are hidden caves to discover, hidden quests to find,
but also lots of hidden or possible interactions
between objects and spells and abilities.
So for example, in Skyrim,
is it possible to become a vampire
and survive without ever killing a person?
I just realized how many vampire examples I have in this talk.
Gamers with high discovery would ask such a question, and games with high discovery
provide the opportunity for many of these questions to be asked.
So games of low discovery, on the other hand, have fully exposed rule sets from the get-go.
It's like chess with very few unknowns in terms of unknown interactions.
No new variables or rules are introduced in the middle of the game.
These are gamers prefer well-defined, well-bounded, unchanging rule sets.
Challenge is the other motivation in the mastery pair, both of which revolve around more long-term
oriented gameplay.
The appeal of challenge lies in wanting to get better at something.
This necessitates a skill component, because you can't get better at something that is
completely based on chance alone.
So high challenge is reflected in the appeal of skill-based gates, barriers, difficult
missions and bosses, system complexity, and above all, the ability to practice and master
a skill.
So in our data, some of the games with the highest challenge.
are Super Smash Brothers, Dota, osu!,
these are all games with complex moves
and reward practice and mastery over time.
On the other hand is the appeal.
is the appeal of, and I'm totally borrowing from Nicole Lazaro's fun case here,
the appeal of easy fun.
And one description that Nicole has given in the past in her model is
fun failure states
that the game doesn't punish you for mistakes,
like ending your game. These games tend to be easy to learn
with few or no skill-based gates and barriers in terms of the gameplay.
Challenge is the only motivation in our model that rebounds after age 45.
It's also interesting that it peaks for men around age 20 before declining, whereas it
declines right away among female gamers.
So these two lines look very different for about 30 years up through age 35, and then
they come together and the gender difference goes away.
This doesn't mean that...
Older gamers are rushing out to pick up Super Smash Brothers.
But it does imply that older gamers may be more interested
in mastering skill-based games and practicing
a game over and over again than we might assume.
Our very last motivation.
Fantasy and story are both motivations related
to being part of the game world.
Story is the appeal of the web of possible interactions and relationships
among a cast of three-dimensional characters with their own histories and their own personal dramas.
It's about the richness of this web of human drama.
So the more characters with their own quirks, with their own psychoses, with their own grudges,
the more potential interactions between characters is possible.
So games with high story tend to have elaborate scripted dramas
with a large cast of characters, games like Dragon Age and Life is Strange.
On the other hand...
Games with low story, gamers who score low on story,
tend to not be interested in character-driven narratives
and stories.
In fact, they tend to go for games
that don't involve people altogether.
So games like SimCity, Transport Tycoon,
that focus on non-people entities,
or games where characters are just pawns
to accomplish goals, rather than characters
with their own motives, histories, and backstories.
I'm gonna close with a couple of things.
I'm gonna throw in another nuance in the spectrum model.
At one point, we were working on a project
related to compliance to medical regimens
for a biotech company.
And we were looking through the literature
on how the big five personality traits
intersect with regimen compliance.
So taking your meds on time, following diet restrictions.
It's not surprising that conscientiousness, which is exactly what it sounds like,
would be highly related to regimen compliance. The one that surprised us was neuroticism.
So people with high neuroticism get anxious and nervous easily and worry a lot,
whereas people with low neuroticism
are calm and relaxed, even in stressful situations.
So you may imagine that low neuroticism
is better when it comes to regimen compliance.
But the data seem to show that both high and low neuroticism
lead to poor outcomes.
If you have a very low neuroticism score,
you may be too blas about risks and problems.
My foot is turning blue.
I guess I'll wait till tomorrow and see if it changes back
color.
And if you have very high neuroticism,
the medical regimen may cause you to worry
and stress out all the time.
Oh my God, did I take the pill yet today?
Have I forgotten to take a pill?
Wondering if you're doing your diet regimen wrong.
And so it seemed like a mid-level neuroticism
had the best outcome, like Goldilocks.
Similarly, the thermometer model.
encourages us to think that the high is good and the low end is bad,
and we've presented you the spectrum model where there are interesting trade-offs on both ends.
But one thing to keep in mind is that at the extremes, you have players who are impossible
to cater to and please. In a normal distribution, the extremes are rarely good things.
My last slide. For all the flaws of the MBTI, it gets one thing right that the big five
gets very wrong. If you've ever taken a personality test and the survey items feel incredibly
judgmental, it's probably the big five. It's the test that seems like it's dying to tell
you that you're lazy, reclusive, depressed, careless, and mean.
Academics hate the MBTI, but they often don't seem to realize just how shitty the user experience
of the Big Five is.
They don't seem to understand that people won't share a personality profile of themselves
if it says they're lazy, depressed, careless, and mean.
To be fair, the Big Five wasn't meant to be a self-discovery tool.
It was designed to be an assessment tool.
And in many cases, you're not supposed to see your own results to begin with.
And that's why it is the way it is.
What the MBTI gets right is the importance of value-neutral language.
And I think that's a negative space we're trying to fill here with gaming motivations because
If the game industry doesn't have a value-neutral way
describing 50% of current, let alone potential gamers,
then that's actually a really big problem.
Imagine if I told you that your new boss is lazy, depressed,
careless, and mean, and then expecting
that to have a good outcome.
Thank you so much for coming to my talk.
Here's the link to the PDF.
Thank you.
And we have about 10 minutes for questions,
and then I've been asked to remind you
to step up to the mics in the front to ask your questions
so everyone else can hear your questions.
Hello, and thank you for the talk.
So one thing I noticed both with the Big Five survey and
with your own survey at the website is that over time, the
surveys are becoming shorter to allow people to take them
more easily and more quickly.
But when the surveys become shorter, the questions become
more difficult.
Very obvious and almost condescending.
So, for example, while in an earlier version it would ask you something generic about your life
and in a vague fashion, later on it will ask you,
do you prefer strategic decisions?
Yes, no. And then, oh, you're a strategy player.
So people, a lot of us who come to those websites, already have an expectation about these surveys
and what we should see in the end. So when we see a question like that, it's
impossible to answer it with a neutral mindset. Do you have any thoughts on that?
Yeah, I mean, a couple of things. It's, there's, let me answer one way first.
You may have a sense of, you know, I think I'm a more strategic player.
I think one thing that we add to that is.
putting, giving you a sense of, on a more quantitative, numerical basis, how different
or how far from the average you fall on some of these motivations relative to other gamers.
So not just a higher or lower yes or no, but relative to other gamers, are you just a little
higher or are you actually way out here on the extreme?
The other thing is that there's just trickiness in assessment tools.
I think there's...
There's a weird version of psychology assessment where it's almost like divination,
where I give you these six colored squares and ask you to pick one, and I can tell you...
You're in love with your brother-in-law.
You know?
There's this vision of psychology as divination.
And I think it's tough that when you
get to the nuts and bolts of it, you
have to ask the most precise and the most grounded questions
to get at the most precise assessments.
And that's just one of these trade-offs in there.
Yeah, but that is a great question.
And one way we try to reduce that fatigue is by reducing it.
But you're right, there are these kind of trade-offs
when you do the reduction.
Please let me ask another question.
Let me have other people, just because we're limited in time,
but feel free to come up to me afterwards and we'll be around
and we'll have you take your questions after.
I just want to make sure that other people have a chance.
Thank you.
I have a question about the national data that you had between US and China and the
gender differences.
Have you seen real world examples of companies that have launched a game in one area of the
world and then completely revamped it to have features in another country and seen real
success?
And conversely, have you seen something where a game that has done really well, say, in
North America with a certain feature set?
completely go into Asia and be completely unchanged
and totally fall off the map.
I just was wondering how what you're seeing
is actually translating to real world success of games
in different markets.
Well, I'll give you a couple of examples
that we've run across.
So we've talked to game companies in China
who are trying to expand in the US.
And one of the questions that comes up is,
what games have they tried to port over
and what their experience has been.
And one common thread has been a lot of the games
in China currently are very, very grindy MMOs
that are much less palatable for people in the West.
That they come across as being too grindy.
Whereas they seem perfectly fine in the Chinese market.
Going the other way, we've seen instances of,
I'm trying to think of the example.
I mean, going back to the very thing
that we were talking about, we actually
have seen this example of a game company
that had a game in the US that had a variety of gameplay
modes, collaborative and competitive.
And one thing we had kind of identified for them
was that the competitive mode was far more appealing
among the Chinese gamers.
But at that point, we didn't have this data.
We didn't have this broader data.
So it was very difficult.
So we'd seen this before, but they were all staring,
and they had to make this very big decision
on we're seeing this come up
in this specific slice of the data,
but are you willing to take that bet?
But now we've seen this broader survey,
and we're like, wow, this may actually be
a much bigger threat that if you're trying
to port a game over in China,
one of the things to make sure of
is that there's a PVP mode.
So we've seen it in the survey data, but we've also seen it in some client projects as well.
Yeah.
Thanks.
Thank you.
Hey, so thank you very much for the presentation.
It's really impressive segmentation.
My question is, I think a lot of the time
we're talking about motivational profile and self-assessment.
There is a disconnect between people
who can survey and build a model of,
and the actual players and their behaviors in game.
And people are constantly trying to tie what, you know,
we have maybe a sample of certain people,
and we created all these different,
12 different profiles.
and we want to map that to a million players
in a certain game based on the way they play.
Do you have any suggestions on tying this
self-assessed, really language-based results
to behaviors in games?
Yeah, it's interesting and it's tough.
I mean, it's tough in one sense because not all games express all motivations.
So you cannot track someone's interest in story in a game that has no narrative.
So there's that missing gap.
But the other thing is, what was I going to say?
I forget what I was going to say.
But the other thing is.
the complexity in modeling that some motivations may be easier,
so competition may be quite easy to infer
based on participation in PVPN ranks,
whereas other motivations may be less possible.
I guess my biggest thought is to make sure
you have a broad base of behavioral telemetry in the game
to ensure the best potential coverage
and predictors of the motivations
before doing the machine learning to do that prediction.
Thanks.
Yeah.
Hey, thank you for a great presentation.
I'm curious, when it comes to challenge,
you mentioned this concept of fun failure.
And I'm wondering if that interpretation requires
that the player understand there'd be a fail state, where
they did something incorrectly, or they made a mistake,
or they know they need to retry.
Or if it just requires that the player understand
there's usually a better way they could be doing it,
and that simply they haven't gotten to that point yet.
I feel it's spectrum, so I think,
and I can't tell which of those
is a little lower on the spectrum,
but I think they're both in that same space of that.
that there may be a failure.
There may be a failure state,
but the game may decide to surface this somehow,
that, oh, you did something wrong,
but it's okay, like a character fell,
but they get right back up.
And I think they're both in that space,
but I don't have a concrete answer
for whether one of the two you mentioned
is a little higher, a little lower than the other.
I think they're definitely both
in the right end of the spectrum.
Hello. Nice presentation. Thank you.
So for the China, the differences between China and the West,
I'm curious if you believe that the sample size was large enough
or if the quality of the sample in terms of the people chosen for that sample...
Yeah, that's a good question. We have this as a blog post on our website
and there's a little bit more detail on the sampling.
Nico Sample, the 2000, they went through a panel provider to get that, and it was balanced
through the different tiers of city, it was balanced by gender.
Our sample, larger, more self-selected, we know that our sample leans towards core gamers,
so 70% of our sample self-identify as core.
We didn't ask that question in the Niko sample,
but we know that more of their gamers
only play on mobile phones.
But in the Chinese context, that doesn't mean they're casual,
because you can play on the mobile phones.
So when we first looked at the data,
because our sample leans towards core,
we assumed that if there were differences in competition and challenge, motivations
that are markers of hardcore gaming personality, that we would see it on the U.S. side, because
our data is biased towards core gamers. So the fascinating thing with how the data turned
out with Nico's data is that, in a sense, it almost sets up the lower bound.
of what the potential difference could be,
because my intuition is that Niko's data
is more representative of casual core hardcore gamers
in China.
So that to me is even more interesting,
because from that point of view,
based on our assumptions and the difference in sample sizes,
in a sense, the actual difference
may even be a little larger than that,
is what my intuition is telling me,
because we had expected it to lean exactly the opposite way.
Yeah.
OK, thank you.
Thank you.
My question has to do with how the population is distributed.
Since you guys have so many, essentially, surveys, answers,
I know with the big five that right now the challenge
has been like, how does the population distribute itself
along the five personality traits?
Like, what percentage is really high on neuroticism,
things like that?
With you, with the surveys you guys have, do you feel you're in a place to say that 10% of the market is strategy gamers?
Or 20% are excitement destruction, so we're leaning towards maybe PUBG or CSGO type things.
Just to kind of, how is the gamer population distributed amongst all these different motivations?
We've done segmentation studies and we've kind of chopped this before in a variety of ways.
We try not to do like the very broadest.
cuts because we know that, you know, our data is biased towards like a core sample. So that's,
you know, within that particular space, you know, we can make a cut. And I think at one
point we did a slide of if you go through the data and you put everyone in the bucket of their
highest index of motivation, what it comes out to be. I forget what the results were,
but we have it in one of our previous slides. So we've kind of cut it up that way.
And I want to say that for men, destruction and excitement buckets came out the highest.
I forget what the percentages were.
And so we have some slides of that in our previous talks that we've touched on.
Yeah. Thank you.
And the very last question.
Hi.
Thank you so much.
This was an inspiring talk.
Thank you.
I was curious about, you're doing these surveys on games
and what people are engaging with, what they prefer doing.
Have you thought about how this expands beyond games
to what should people be doing in their careers, et cetera?
for education, for instance?
Um, so alongside the gamer, the video gamer profile,
we actually have a board game profile,
and then we have this infrastructure in place
to run these surveys and generate these profiles.
One thing we're chewing on...
Nick Ducheneau is going to make fun of me.
I've been saying this for like the past nine months,
is we're working on a broader motivation profile
that we're broadly thinking of a life aspirations profile.
So it's somewhere between,
it's somewhere between a personality profile
and like a values profile.
So something about,
I'm someone who desires knowledge and curiosity.
I'm someone who cares a lot about family.
and nurturance. So that's something that we're chewing on in the background that we may or may not get to because I've been talking about this for months.
And so we'll run through the same process when we get to it.
So we'll run the pilot survey, see what clusters together and see if a lot of people want to take this profile.
Because the thing that we're trying to chew on is
if we can get people to take both gamers,
who take the gamer profile,
also take the life aspirations profile,
then we get these really interesting data sets on,
well, how do gamers want to behave in the broader context?
Are there interesting relationships there
that we can suss out?
Thank you.
And thanks again, everyone, for coming to the talk.