Thank you for joining me today. I'm Andrew Hogan, the CMO and co-founder of Intorca.
I'm going to be talking about tackling cheating in gaming. And whilst it might not surprise you that I'm going to be telling you how important it is that we do tackle the problem of cheating, it may surprise you that I'm going to tell you the way to do this is by looking at how we find cheats. That is the key to it.
So we set up Intorq were about just over a year ago, with a
kind of a promise of making gaming safer and fairer. And
this is supported by three key objectives. First of these was
to find and stop more cheats. The second to save time and
money doing so. And the third to protect the player experience.
Now, I'm sure those objectives, those aims will be talked about a lot over the period of this summit.
And I think that's obviously a very good thing.
And you'd think these are pretty unarguable.
But the one thing that's surprised us a little bit since we launched in Torca,
was that there still seems to be, or maybe not still seems, but there is, there does seem to be
now, almost a sense of resignation about cheating amongst some people in the industry. Almost a
feeling that it's just a cost of doing business and there's just not much we can do about it.
So you can imagine how pleased we were to see cheating featured in the Fair Play Alliance framework
alongside issues like dangerous speech, extremism, aggravation and harassment.
Because it needs to be, because that is exactly what it is, a disruptive behaviour in gaming.
Now, the other thing that we were pleased to see was how the definition of cheating use was broader than it sometimes is.
So it's defined as exploiting the rules of the game to gain an advantage or disrupt play.
This includes individual cheating.
and leveraging AI to cheat at scale.
And then examples given included all the usual ones
like bots, the aim bots, wallhacks, and GPS bots,
but also talked about manual and automated farming, leveling,
boosting, netcode, loot and item finders, and data scraping.
And I think this is really important because it's no good just looking at a little, you know, one
particular niche in the sort of, if you like, in the business of cheating. The whole piece
needs to be looked at because it's also very much linked. We ran a poll just over a year ago,
I'd say, amongst 2000 gamers, and we asked them what would make you stop playing a video game
first? And we had various rounds and the finals between these four.
slow loading speed, too many cheats, toxicity amongst players, and a lack of player support.
Now you can see that toxicity came out as the biggest driver of people, you know, putting their
mouths down and leaving a game. But cheating was pretty close behind it, and both of these were way
ahead of slow loading speed and lack of player support, which were the third and fourth biggest
reasons. So that really does, I think, demonstrate how big an issue cheating is.
It's also worth just highlighting here that the 2,000 players that we talked to,
they were not just PC players. We went into this quite agnostic actually,
and they were people who played all games on all sorts of consoles. So there were PC gamers there,
there were console gamers, and there were mobile gamers.
And I think that's really important because, you know, cheating, just as gaming is evolved,
just as gaming evolves, so does cheating. And sometimes it kind of evolves quicker as well.
So I guess that, you know, in a way, the first question this throws up, if you like, is, well,
how bad is it? So at first glance, and if you just look, go by some of the headlines, you know,
we'll see it in the game, in the games press and things.
You know, it might not be so bad.
The industry might be getting a hold of it quite nicely.
quite well, I should say. Activision have announced back in February that Warzone bans
60,000 cheaters in one massive wave. And actually, that's been followed up recently with an announcement
from Raven Software, who talked about half a million accounts being banned since the launch
of Warzone. Note that's accounts and not players. That's quite important because obviously cheats
will use multiple accounts, so you'll always have more accounts banned than you will players.
But still, you know, absolutely great to see.
And then of course, a couple of months later, there was the bust in Kunshan, China,
which wasn't just featured in the gaming press.
I mean, it was all over the mainstream news.
And this gang was reputedly, I think, responsible for something like
$75 million worth of cheats being sold,
caught in a massive police sting.
And in all the reporting of it, they featured this shot of the ill-gotten gains, in this case,
luxury cars that the gang had managed to acquire, which obviously makes it a great news story.
But interestingly, what it reminded me of is actually my favorite TV program,
which was The Wire. It's The Wire.
Now, for those of you who are also fans,
or have seen The Wire,
you'll recognise Buncombe McNulty there,
two of the main protagonists in the show.
And Buncombe McNulty would spend loads of time
pushing back against their seniors and the politicians
who would constantly be asking
for loads of low-level busts to take place,
to give them their drugs on the table photo opportunities.
And Bunk and McNulty would always kind of push back against this and try and convince them that
there's no point doing that because it just gives the gangs higher up the chance to kind of get away
if you like. And you know they knew that all these photo opportunities and drugs on the table busts.
They didn't really add up to much because there would still be loads of
you know drug trafficking going on. There would still be lots of dealers out there.
And it's not a perfect analogy, but it did remind me when I saw the clinician bust,
it did remind me of it. Because just as there were loads of dealers left out there,
there are loads of cheats, and in particular, loads of cheat sellers out there, as any gamer
will tell you. At the moment, we're monitoring over 150 different cheat sellers.
And that's obviously a lot, but we are under no illusion that that's all of them. I would expect
that number to double over the next six months or so. There are so many more cheat sales out
there than people realize.
And that, for me, is just a great proof point, if you like, of the extent of cheating,
the extent of cheating that's going on out there. I think it's also worth noting that
that is being driven by the fact that cheating is no longer PC only, and that it's
across the board now, and that you will find cheats on pretty much any game you come across,
even else's at it.
And whilst it's sort of easy to smile at the thought of a Frozen as something as innocent
as Frozen being cheated, being pirated, this actually raises a serious problem because
as bad as cheating is when it's affecting the player experience in a big multiplayer,
and that is terrible in the long term, will damage a game's credibility and its success.
This sort of cheating directly attacks the business model that many developers rely on,
i.e. in-app purchases and ad revenue. Now, we may not like ads in our games and stuff,
but developers, some of us, will be relying on that.
And these sites which are offering, you know, modified versions of the games with unlimited gems or ad blocking, etc, etc,
are directly, basically directly attacking that business model.
So it's a really serious issue.
And what I wanted to do now is just talk about some of the reasons why, you know, effectively,
we've got to this place. How have we let it get so bad?
So the first one of those reasons is around, the kind of obvious place to start I guess,
is the rise of online gaming, in particular the free-to-play games. There's no doubt that that has
coincided with a rise in cheating and has driven a rise in cheating.
But as well as the sort of, if you like, just the sort of hard numbers, I think what's particularly
damaging about this is that this cheating often takes place in games like Battle Royale
games where if someone is cheating, they're seen to be cheated by loads of players in
that game, who will obviously then go and talk about it and complain about it on social
media and stuff.
you know, they're not just cheating one other person, they're cheating a group of people.
And this kind of magnifies the problem, this just makes the problem seem even bigger than it even is.
And, you know, and the real sort of, I think the real problem with that is that this encourages a
kind of attitude of if you can't beat them, join them. You know, if you see everyone around you
cheating.
you know, lots of people will eventually just say, you know what, this is unfair, I want to,
frankly, I want to level things up, I want to have the same advantages that they have.
And this is exactly what happened with cheating in traditional sports. And it's,
without a doubt, it's happening in this sort of, particularly in this kind of area of gaming.
And, you know, that's a real, that's a real issue.
It's also to an extent, I think, reflected by some attitudes in the business itself,
where you do come across a bit of a see no evil, hear no evil, speak no evil,
head in the sand kind of stance to cheating. In that it's just kind of,
it's just one of those things that's just, it's going to always be there, just best left alone.
And actually, I think this is brought to life by, if you look at the media coverage given to
cheating, in comparison to the media coverage given to, I don't know, sort of merger, M&As,
and investment, and sponsorships, which get tons and tons of coverage. You can't,
every day there's a new M&A, every day there's a new...
multi-million investment in a developer. Every day there's a brand that's kind of now sponsoring
an esports team or an esports event. But actually, stories about Qiujing are pretty rare actually,
you know, apart from the kind of recent sort of, apart from, actually apart from those two stories
I've kind of featured, there's not been much, there isn't much. And I think in a way it's great
that those positive stories get so much coverage, but we need to be, we need to be realistic and
honest. Because...
if we don't get a grip on cheating, those positive stories will dry up because sponsors,
particularly non-endemic sponsors like Coke and P&G and people, they're going to want to
be associating their brands with sports or gaming events which are inundated with cheating. It's
just not good for them. It becomes toxic. And so we need to be mindful of this.
The third reason that cheating is kind of as established as it is now, I think comes down to
the third parties. The third parties, which in effect, unknowingly maybe, but support the cheating
ecosystem. You know, the cheating ecosystem needs payment functionality, it needs to be able to
market, it needs security.
And because, you know, cheating sites are like any other digital, sorry, any other online retailer,
they need trust. So they go to the big brands for it because they want to have a big PayPal logo on
their site because it's going to make someone feel that much more comfortable inputting their
credit card details when they're buying a cheat or when they're subscribing to a cheat service.
Likewise, being seen to be advertised on YouTube makes them almost seem proper.
And then making the site seem secure and stuff, particularly the rumors that you get around
some cheat sites.
It's ironic, but it's obviously also frustrating when you see these brands on their sites. I'm
sure most of them are unaware of it, but the cheat sites are making the most out of those
business relationships. Now, the good news is this actually does offer an opportunity, I think,
which I'll come to talk about a bit later, but an opportunity for how we can potentially
disrupt the cheating or one way we can potentially disrupt the cheating ecosystem.
Next is the, I suppose, the history of cheating, and specifically the history of
attitudes towards cheating. Because cheating didn't always seem so bad. It wasn't always
frowned upon. It was kind of seen as a genuinely integral part of gaming. You know, when you
watch these documentaries about the history of gaming, and you see people talking about
the first arcade games, I mean, inevitably, they'll start talking about how they used to hack them.
to make them, actually ironically enough, to make them harder
because those arcade games are pretty simple and
were quite easy if you spent enough, if you put enough money into it and played
it enough you'd eventually beat it. So hackers
would work out how to make it more difficult
and then obviously also, you know, and developers also use cheating for play
testing and things.
and this picture brings to life, hackers were sort of heroes in kids films.
Now this is obviously before hacking and cheating became a multi-million dollar industry,
occasionally with links to crime, but it does bring to life how things have changed.
Or have they? Because actually there is still what I call sort of mixed opinions around
how bad cheating is and how we should react to it.
I'm going to show you some posts from Reddit that we saw,
which were about a month or so after the bust in China
that we just looked at.
And it had featured people talking about it.
And I'll just read these out to you,
because it does bring to life the fact
that there's different opinions.
So firstly, I can't believe that cheats and hacks for games are now criminal offences.
What is this world coming to? It is the end times.
Like OP said, if you read the article, it's not the cheaters getting arrested,
it's the organisation making tens of millions selling cheats and hacks to subscribers.
It's always about money. When players are paying for hacks instead of loot boxes,
that's when big business brings out the dogs.
Just because they're making millions doesn't mean they deserve jail time.
Cheating in a video game doesn't actually hurt anyone.
Calling them a gang is pretty ridiculous. People should be able to modify any
software that runs on their computer by default.
I don't think you read the article. They weren't just cheating, they were selling
cheats on a subscription basis for multiplayer games.
So should people be able to modify that software if the intent of the software
is to be played with other people using the same software?
creating an equal playing ground?
What if they compete and win money over people
with unmodified copies?
We're talking about actual real jail
for cheating at video games.
That's not really in line with the offence.
In my opinion, it's another case
of passing responsibility off to the government.
Now, a couple of things. One, I promise you we didn't write those posts in defence of the bust,
but also I think what this kind of, you know, neither side's probably 100% right,
but I think what it shows undeniably is that there are still different opinions about
cheats amongst, you know, amongst, I would assume, honest players.
Now...
The final reason, the final factor, I think, behind, you know, the sort of where we are with cheating at the moment is the is the is frankly, the speed of the cheat industry.
This is how quick they are to market, if you like.
What this graph shows is the noise around cheating.
In the blue line, cheat communities themselves, so cheat forums and things, and on the red line,
regular player communities. And it shows the noise, as I said, it shows the noise around
cheating after a period, you know, when this game suddenly became massively popular last summer,
from pretty much from nowhere. And you can see that sort of, you see the blue line in week four
there, suddenly starts to rise as cheat communities clock on to this game, start cheating it, start
sharing cheats, start selling them.
only takes two weeks for that to start flowing through to the player communities to start
complaining about the cheating on the game. And then you can see for the next few weeks
how those lines correspond pretty closely. There's a pretty close correlation there until
the complaints about cheating just go off the scale as people just kind of frankly just
ditch it. And by this stage, it wasn't even just the player communities talking about
cheating on the game, it was all over the media as well.
and it was a well-acknowledged problem that this game had to sort it out.
And eventually they did, and you can see the lines coming down.
Now as well as showing, I think, a strong correlation between what happens in the
cheating communities having a knock-on effect.
in player communities. What this also shows is that how it was shows how developers can get
caught out and even established developers because this was an established developer
but they didn't have anti-cheat set up for this game or proper anti-cheat
processes and strategies and the results are pretty clear to see.
Now what those factors combine to do
is create what we call the anti-cheat game of whack-a-mole, where anti-cheat teams are constantly
running around trying to get to the next cheat, knock it on the head, reverse engineer it,
and then they're off to another one, not knowing where the next one is going to come out.
And it's amazing because we've spoken to lots of people in the industry and this analogy has come
up so many times, we can't even claim it's original. So many people in the business refer
to dealing with cheating as like a game of whack-a-mole. And that's why we need to do
things differently if we're going to get a hold of cheating and tackle cheating properly.
Now, I was going to say some of you may remember this, but probably not. It was quite a long time
ago, but I think some of you will recognize this. This is an athlete called Dick Fosbury
competing at the 68 Mexico Olympics in the high jump, obviously. He won a gold medal.
The interesting thing is he won this gold medal by doing the high jump in a completely new way.
No one had done it this way before.
Up until then, people did a kind of scissors approach, or they rolled over it, kind of on their side.
But what Dick Fosby realised is by going backwards, he could lift his legs higher,
and therefore clear a higher bar, because the high jump is always about, apparently,
it's always about getting the legs over, is the tricky piece.
Now, interestingly, at the time, everyone thought, what's the...
this is crazy. But you know, obviously, now, we all think they're great in that he's a sensible one.
The interesting thing in this, though, is that he also was taking advantage of a technical
development in the sport. Because up until then, people basically, they the landing area was
basically either sand or some old mattresses. And it was only at the 68 Olympics, they brought in,
you know, like full the full foam landing mats that you now that you see now today.
So it's interesting, as well as his kind of, you know,
his sort of, if you like, the math that he used to work out he could get his legs higher,
there was also a tech, he was also taking advantage of a technical change to the sport.
And I think basically what this, you know, what this for me does is it says what's our
Fosbury flop? How are we going to disrupt how we tackle cheating in gaming in the same way that he
disrupted how you did high jump?
And for us, the Fosbury flop, the equivalent in gaming, is how we find cheats, where we look for them, and how we find them in order to get to them before they impact the game.
It's about going to where the cheats are, going to where the cheats are marketed, YouTube in this case, going to where they're discussed.
So, you know, whether that's Telegram, Twitter, Reddit, Discord.
And of course, going to where they're sold.
You know, whether it's I Want Cheats, no, please, no, bottom right,
the Visa logo there, which is not a plant.
That is that's genuine.
But actually, I think what's interesting about this site is look how professional
it's looking. I mean, that does not look like a dodgy site.
GameProd, another one.
Omega Cheats.
and private keys. And these are just four, these are just four
sites out of those 150 I mentioned to you earlier. So,
you know, really, not even the tip of not even the tip of the
iceberg. But you can already see by going to where they're sold,
where they're discussed and where they're marketed, you can
imagine that's going to be a lot of data coming in. And, you
know,
I mentioned the 150 sites that we're monitoring.
We've also, in amongst that, we reckon at the moment
we are somewhere north of 25,000 different cheat products
that we found.
Again, we know that that number is definitely
going to get larger.
But it gives you an idea of how much data
there is out there around the whole cheating space.
Now, the question is, what can you do with that?
How do you manage to find, how do you
pull that data in a useful way?
And that's why we've created Intalka.
And we've specifically, why we've
created a tech stack, which is made up of custom collectors
and crawlers.
to go out there and effectively monitor the dark web, the web,
and social media 24-7, looking at places like Discord, Reddit,
Telegram, all the cheap sites, YouTube, and indeed,
the dark web as well.
And take all that data and ingest all that data
and then tidy it, categorize it by community,
and measure and evaluate it.
to kind of prioritise by risk for different teams, whether that's legal, game security or
player support, because those are what we see as the three key teams that are going to most benefit
from this sort of data. But so those teams can take affirmative action quicker than they can
today. So if you're a legal team, you can do a takedown much quicker.
So if you're a game security team, you can start reverse engineering against the team much, much quicker.
And then if you're player support, you can, you know, you can proactively go out to your community and highlight a risk, for example.
So we have this text that pulls in this massive amount, or rather pulls out of this massive amount of data, relevant information to
to start acting on cheats and taking action against cheats much much earlier. So we're
no longer waiting for the cheats to impact the game and we're no longer relying on effectively
manual research which we know lots of the developers and indeed some of the anti-cheat firms
also currently rely on.
And as you can see from that amount of data,
automating, automated monitoring is the only way through.
That is, if you like, automated monitoring is our FOSBRI flop.
So let's just have a look at what that looks like in action.
I'll show you how it moves, and I'll
show an animation in a second.
But this is effectively the heart of the Intorka platform.
These are what we call boards.
And these present all the data that any searches you set up.
find. So what I mean by search is if you're using Intalka, you can set up various searches using
our tag system. So you can search by game, you know, Apex Legends. You can search by type of
site, so you can just go for cheap vendors, or you could be more interested in Reddit posts
or YouTube films. So you can do, or you can search actually by cheat, cheat type, so by
aimbots for example.
And you set up all these searches,
and that data is pulled in in real time
and presented on a board like this.
and I'm going to quickly show you, I said animation, it's a GIF really,
I'm going to show you something, which I'll show you someone using this
and effectively what I'd like you to sort of look for is how
quickly you can go from effectively looking at first person shooter
genre board to looking at a specific game
to looking at a specific cheat and then actually being in a position to download
and start taking action against that cheat.
So you can see within just a few clicks, we've gone from looking at all the latest cheats
for sale.
cheats being spoken about across first-person shooters to finding the latest aimbot available
for CSGO. So you can see immediately how we're ingesting all that data and presenting it
in a way that is usable. Now, talking of usability, you know, we are firm believers that data is only
valuable if it gets used. You know, too often everyone talks about having lots of data, but
if you're not using it.
it's effectively meaningless, which is why for us comprehension and shareability
are absolutely key for what we do. And as a result of that, we use a cluster analysis tool
to make this data even easier to share with people within a business, but most importantly,
make it easier to see where the real threats are coming from.
because obviously this is just looking at words can be can be quite hard to do that.
So what we've done is using this cluster analysis tool made it so that you can very quickly see
what the biggest threats are for any game that you potentially will be interested in.
Again I'll show you a little film of someone using our cluster analysis tool.
So very quick.
There you go.
Let's play it again.
Let's stop it.
So that, there you go.
Now, the other thing we wanted to be able to do is make sure our data can be
integrated very quickly.
So we've included, through our APIs, you can set up alerts so that any information that
Intorca pulls in can be integrated into any internal system, just to make it that much
quicker to be able to take action.
And then finally, the final stage of the little demo bit of this presentation,
I wanted to talk about our crawler, because obviously this is all about
the data that we're crawling.
Now, when we crawl a site, we're pulling in something like 50 different
data points behind that site.
You know, it could be, it could be who's providing, what sort of cybersecurity
it has, what payment providers, the ISP, et cetera, it's just all the,
all the information about that site.
But very interesting, and I mentioned this right
at the beginning of the presentation in terms
of these third-party providers.
Because we're pulling in all this data,
we can see which third-party providers are being
used by these cheat sellers.
And what that enables us to do is, as you can see here,
we can see, for example, that paying providers
for this site, gamebtc.com, included PayPal, Skrill,
Westingham, et cetera, et cetera.
And what we're doing for one of our clients at the moment, or rather, what they're doing
with the information we give them, is they're putting pressure on the likes of PayPal and
Skrill, basically saying you shouldn't be working with these guys.
As a result of that, at the very least, the payment brands, for example, in this case,
are no longer working with them.
But actually what's happening as well is these sites, because we're disrupting them so much,
they close.
And even just in the last couple of months,
we've seen something like eight different sites completely
close as a result of this pressure
that we're putting on their third-party providers.
So a direct result of using this data.
So what does this all mean?
Well, we think it helps publishers and developers
monitor more, more cheats, more sellers, more forums, just
more cheating in general.
But importantly, they can do this spending less financially.
They no longer have to rely on three man hours
at researching cheats out there, which let's be honest,
most developers A, don't want to do and B, can't afford to do.
It also means they can act faster and act smarter.
You've seen how quickly we can pull this data in.
And you can imagine that data can be very quickly used to take legal action, to start reverse engineering,
or be a managing from a player support point of view. It also means acting smarter. Because we're looking at the
whole cheating ecosystem and all the cheating that's out there, we can see
when we actually evaluate the anti-cheat action you're taking.
We can sort of see how the level of cheating may be going down in a particular game versus
other games in that market.
So as opposed to a market effect making us think, oh, we're doing really well, no, we
can kind of take that out and actually say, no, this anti-cheat...
the strategy that you're doing is definitely working.
It also means, as I mentioned earlier,
by using the clusters,
you can prioritize your resource and action.
You can see where the biggest threats are coming from
rather than effectively having to guess.
And finally, this means you've got happier players,
there is less complaining,
which means they're less pissed off,
which in turn should mean your colleagues,
in particular players for the community management,
are also happier.
But also because they've got more tools now,
so that if players are complaining,
the player support people managing those problems
will have much more data than they've had in the past,
and will know more about what steps
are being taken to combat it.
And I think that's really important because if we can help those people spend less time
worrying about cheating or having to deal with people worrying about cheating,
that means they can spend more time dealing with these other issues, which takes us back to the
framework. They can spend more time dealing with harassment, dangerous speech,
anti-social actions, and that can only be a good thing.
I'm not for a minute going to sit here and say we can eradicate cheating.
There will always be people trying to make a buck from it.
There will always be people who want to get one over.
It's just it's kind of it's it's it's the way it's the way of the world.
But what we can do is we can reduce it and we can
disrupt the cheating business model and the cheating ecosystem
so that there is less of it.
And we feel that is really important.
And that would itself be a big step.
And I think I want to finish with some words
from the framework itself, which I think
brings to life why it's important,
why we love gaming.
With the advent of reliable in-home networks
and other technologies, online multiplayer games
have become an ingrained part of our social tapestry.
They enable us to make friends and escape
the monotony and stresses of everyday life.
Games bring people together through the power
of shared experience.
We can fight alien invaders, explore distant lands,
plant a garden, or push each other in a shopping cart.
At their best, games reflect the peak of humanity collaborating with one another
across what might otherwise be vast divides. Anyone can belong in a game,
no matter where they are in the world or if they never leave their home.
Thank you.