All right. Hey! All right. Apologies for the delay. It is my great pleasure to introduce
two of my favorite people in the world, one in the flesh, one via the tubes. The tubes.
Mr. Tommy Refines and Edmund McMillan, creators of Super Meat Boy.
Yes, that was clapping. Here, hold on.
Say hi, Edmund.
Hi.
So right now we're just kind of working out.
We're going to have Edmund on Skype.
He's flying in an airplane around the world right now.
So yeah, we're trying to get the satellite link up,
hooked up, and everything.
So once we do, we'll start this little post-mortem thing.
Is it ready?
Yeah, yes, I have it.
All right, hold on.
and I'll swap you over. That's my password. And then this is your microphone. Okay. So
just hold this in front of your mouth.
Oh, okay. All right. Now I'm trying to remember my password for Skype. Excuse me. We aren't
the most prepared people, so there we go.
This is all GDC's fault.
This is in no way my fault.
I was very, very prepared for this, as I am with everything in my life.
Um, can you, can you hear me?
All right.
I'm going to hang up on the phone there.
Okay.
Can, can you hear me, Edmund?
Where's my piece of paper?
This is all fake.
Like the moon landing.
There's nobody in this room.
All right.
Let me uh...
Ha ha ha!
There we go.
Switch mic...
There it is.
Okay, can you hear me, Edmund?
Okay.
All right!
So...
I had no doubts either.
So yeah, this is the uh... ... ... ... ...
or what we're calling the Super Meat Boy Postmortem,
which is more like the story of Meat Boy,
peppered with various good and bad things.
What is he doing?
Yeah, yeah, so, yeah, we're going kind of non-traditional because,
I don't know, just because.
Because we can and this is what we do.
Yeah.
We just read through it.
This is the talk.
I just wrote it over here.
But we've gone through, we've gone through this development and we were so, like, you
know, this meat boy development was so, like, personal and, you know, we were so attached
to it that it really seems kind of silly to write down words that describe it.
We'll just sort of talk about it.
So I don't know if you want to start with the origin story, Edmund.
I'm sure most of you guys know that Meat Boy was originally a flash game that I made with a friend of mine, John McKinney.
We made it in about three weeks.
And honestly, I didn't think much of it. It was just like a little silly platformer.
I didn't think anybody would care enough to shoot it.
For some reason they did. They got really popular.
And there's one of my most popular flash games right now.
My cat will definitely walk into the house and lick me.
Sorry about that.
So yeah, I was involved in a game around that time.
I did a lot of different games and trying with my hard set.
I was able to do something with A-Pen and Publishers.
Because I wanted to do something with Publishers.
And I was able to get the initiative to tend to Microsoft.
But I didn't really work with anybody in the group program at all for consoles.
And that was around the time where I met Tommy, which was actually at GDC.
I think in 2008 or the end of 2008.
And I met him and we talked about making games and it turned out we had known each other for a while.
seven years prior to going to the Harvard Blue-Grams Network.
And we thought, hey, we could try something out.
We made a quick watch game together at one,
and since you order so well together, we decided that
we'd go in and try to pick a console game,
and the game that we thought would be the easiest
and probably the most popular would be Meat Boy.
So that's kind of where it all started.
But yeah, like Ed mentioned, we both had websites a long time ago.
Was that guppy?
Yeah, I don't know what the fuck's wrong with him.
Typical.
Every morning, every single morning there's a dude who pisses.
And it's hard to like, scold him about it because he's so easily cleaned up and it's
like, oh, we have piss going on.
But, yeah, you know.
Yeah, so Ed and I, we knew each other like from a long time ago.
You mentioned we both had websites around the time when New Grounds and everything was starting out.
And we were both affiliates.
We were both linked to each other.
And, yeah, Ed went into the indie world and I went into soulless corporate world.
And, yeah, we both kind of met up and decided, you know,
Well, first we did, uh, we did gray matter together to see if we'd actually work out.
And, um, that was a little flash game that we did.
And that was, uh, I thought it was, I thought it was a good game.
We got a lot of plays. It was pretty good.
Um, but yeah, we decided that, uh, yeah, let's, let's, let's make a console game.
And I had played Meat Boy, and I, I really enjoyed it.
And I, I actually beat it, the, the flash version with the...
control issues and everything that it had, but yeah, it was my kind of game and, you
know, we just sort of, yeah, it just seemed like a natural fit for something to make and
I was coming off of a project that I didn't really like and, yeah, I wanted to do something
that was more related to me.
So it just sort of worked out and that's when, well, you were talking to Nintendo around
that time, weren't you?
I couldn't get a hold of anybody who attended this video.
I would call up Reggie daily, per week,
to try to talk to him about WeWare.
And he just, I never got to talk to him.
And I actually posted that video online,
and actually got an email from the guy in charge of WeWare,
asking if I was serious about WeWare gaming.
I said yes, but at that point we didn't have any money for the kit either.
I didn't have any money myself.
And that was another problem.
I was like, you know, one thing is like Ben, I was like,
how are we going to come up with like three grand to get a kit?
It seems insane.
Yeah.
I ended up doing an expansion pack for Meeple and then covering half the cost.
And then Tommy covered the other half and then we won't be able to get out of jail.
I was already talking to Microsoft because, and this is something probably nobody really knows, but
Tommy, me, Tommy, and Alex were all working on GISH 2 and that was going to be for Xbox Live.
And that looks like we're all kind of merging.
When we started Meat Boy, we were already talking to Microsoft, and when GISH 2 eventually didn't happen,
the whole time we were trying to push Meat Boy to them, and eventually they picked up on it,
but it was something like, we always wanted to do Meat Boy for all the consoles, if possible,
but we had kits for basically every console at that point.
And we were just kind of going down the line and seeing, you know, what was going to work where.
Yeah, we had, um,
when we first started Meat Boy, I actually had it running on
Xbox before I had it running on anything else. Because I started it on
PC and I had already, you know, I had Xbox experience, so when I was writing the engine
I was just, I was writing it, you know, all DirectX and everything, so
porting it over to Xbox wasn't difficult at all. So I actually had it running on that
before I had it running on Wii, and then...
had it running on PlayStation. And, yeah, we were, we were just sort of kind of shopping
it around. We, you, yeah, like Edmund said, we definitely wanted to do it on everything.
And thinking about that now, like, if we would have put it on everything, I'd, I'd be dead.
For sure I would be dead. Like, that's not a joke. Don't, don't. No, I, yeah, I, I almost
died doing this version. And that's only on two things.
Yeah, on like three or four, yeah, I'd be dead.
Yeah, so we had it running on PlayStation and everything.
Yeah, we were, yeah, well, let's see, around that time,
so the first six months of development were actually
me getting the engine working and getting an editor for Edmund
so he could start building levels.
Edmund really didn't touch the game until, well, let's see,
we started in about February, what year is it?
It's 11, right?
We came out in 10.
Now I'm actually having trouble now. Did we start in...
We started in 2009. Like February 2009?
Yeah, because then the year later we were in IGF. Yeah, okay.
So yeah, we started in February 2009.
That's when I was taking the engine for the first game I was working on called Goo,
and I was just refactoring everything.
I trashed everything and I was redoing it.
And that was about six months or so of...
you know, development, getting it up and running and getting an editor for Edmund.
You actually didn't... like, I made, like, one of the first little levels
to test out controls and everything, but you actually didn't make
the first level, I think, until about June.
June or July, I think.
I was just sitting on my hands...
Yeah.
Waiting.
That's what you do, though.
You don't really... you don't really work.
You just, you just kinda, you know, whatever.
I just float around on webcam.
Yeah, float around on webcam and yell at me.
But yeah, so that was around the time, you know, so yeah, I had it
running on WiiWare, and every year, the Wii dev kit, and
we got invited to a summit in London, where they were showing
a whole bunch of games, and our game, we only had, I believe, 12 levels at that time.
It was like 12 levels we had a really early replay system in.
There was no world map.
There was no cut scenes.
There was only Meat Boy.
I mean, it was a really, really early build,
but it was still playable.
Oh yeah, and that's the, actually before that,
we spent, before we actually did any real testing
of levels or anything, we spent,
I spent probably like two months just refining controls
and trying to get controls exactly right and feeling.
as good as we could possibly get them.
And it was just a lot of duct taped physics kind of stuff.
There's no formula to describe the way
Meat Boy moves in the air.
There's no formula to describe how anything would move
like Meat Boy in the air.
So it was just kind of duct taped.
And I made a little thing for Edmund
that he could adjust values to further tweak everything.
But yeah.
See I justified, you know when he jumps off walls,
he jumps.
like faster and further? Yeah. It's because he's pushing with his arms and his legs.
That's good. It's a really, it's very accurate. If you were, if you were going to climb up
a wall or slide down a wall, you would definitely use your hands and legs. That's the thing,
like nobody's doing that. Yeah. Those parkour kids, they do stuff like that.
But yeah, so yeah, we had the controls and everything was feeling really, really good.
Actually, we did have one cutscene. We had the black and white, the first black and white meat boy cutscene.
That's all we had. We had like the intro. Yeah, it looked pretty bad.
I thought it looked pretty, but I don't know shit about art, so.
I wasn't super happy with how it looked, but it was kind of like we were actually crunching for that summit like all week.
And when you're freaking out about it, and that same week was the week where it was like,
the most of the stuff that you were doing, I had no control over, so I had to give myself
something to do.
And that was when I made the comic.
I decided, oh, well, if Tommy's gonna make, you know, all this shit, like, you were doing
the replay feature, and if you were gonna do that in a week, then I was gonna make a
comic in a week, so we could at least give something out, like, at the summit.
improvised a comic book for the game that you we printed out and you took and you're able to hand out and stuff and
But yeah, the summit I remember when you called from the summit you're like, holy shit like people really like this
Mm-hmm, and it was like, you know, you know, maybe
That was the point. I think we both realized maybe we should really make this into
You know something really epic because originally it was something that was just gonna be a hundred levels on on the Wii on the PC
Maybe on maybe on Xbox
It was gonna be something kinda small and simple.
We weren't gonna really add anything to it, were we?
No, it was the no bosses.
Yeah, yeah, no bosses, yeah.
Kind of like the Flash game recently.
Yeah.
The... I think after we saw that it had so much potential,
and it was so fun,
we just decided to go all out,
which was one of the reasons why we kinda
lost sight of the file size stuff.
Yeah.
We'll come back to that.
Yeah, we kind of fell in love with the game.
Yeah.
Totally blindly in love and just went all in and just crossed our fingers and hoped that we'd come out on the other side alive.
Yeah, basically head down, power through, you know, Michael Bluth style in a way.
But, yeah, like coming back from that summit, it was just like this crazy energy.
We had, I've never seen somebody, like we had this one guy from Konami.
and uh...
he was he was playing through one of it's a
level one nineteen i don't remember the name of it is one we've had forever
and he
he kept dying over and over and he stood there
in front of this little kiosk on
i think it was like the twentieth floor some
building or whatever and just played for like forty five minutes
and died over and over and over then the game crashed and then i reset and then
he just went right back to it
and kept playing over and over and over and
uh...
when he finally beat it, he saw the replay feature, and he's like, oh, wow, you guys,
oh, this is awesome, we're going to steal this from you. And I kind of look at him,
I go, well, you're going to have to hurry, because I guarantee we'll have it done before
you did. And that's when we were still going to do like 100 levels. But, you know, yeah,
we just, we came back from all of that and it seemed like a shame not to just, not to
just go all out with it, not to just turn it into, you know.
exactly what we wanted to play and wanted it to be.
And so yeah, when I came back,
came back from London, we...
Yeah, I think, was it, that was like right before,
it was right before TIG Jam,
and then we started doing the alt levels, right?
Yeah, well that was around the same time
when we were going into heavy negotiations.
Like, that was when we were doing the switcheroonie
with GISH2 and everyone else.
Oh yeah, the switcheroo.
We're trying our best to convince Microsoft that Meat Boy is something that people are going to like.
We convinced at least one person and that person really fought for us.
Hardcore.
And that was a fight though.
A lot of people ask, you know, why the hell isn't it on PlayStation?
And of course one of the reasons is that we don't want Tommy to die.
Yeah, we don't want Tommy to die yet.
But aside from the obvious, it was that we are complete unknowns with no power.
Like, how do we walk into Microsoft's office and be like,
okay, you're gonna do Meat Boy, and also, it's gonna be on the PlayStation and the Wii
and everything else, and it's non-exclusive. Now do it.
Like, that's something that can happen.
It was like, this was... we were fighting really fucking hard just to get what we had.
to get to release a month after on PC and possibly Wii
was what we got in the contract and everything else was kind of out the door
and that was as good as we could get. That was like months and months of back and forths
and negotiation. I actually think it was about, because we signed
we signed with Microsoft, it was like January 2010
and we were talking to them in August of 2009 back and forth
trying to
trying to actually get them to sort of believe in the game.
And I mean, it, one of the things I think really, really
helped us in that situation was I already did have it running.
So it wasn't like I sent them a PC build or anything.
I said, hey, throw this on your dev kit and give it a go.
And then, you know, our guy over at Microsoft did and really
liked it and everything.
But, um, yeah, around that time, you know, speaking of like
PlayStation and me not wanting to die, I took, um, I took
about, well,
Yeah, so I got my hands on like a little Sony dev kits, like halfway in between the big
one that looks like a rack mount and a test kit.
And I took about, it was like four days or something, and I took, and I ported the engine
over to the PS3 and I had it running.
And I sent it to Sony, and for some reason they couldn't get it to run.
I sent it to that game company and they were able to get it to run, and I was able to run
it, but for some reason they couldn't.
So I sent them a PC build.
And then we never ever heard back from them.
So when it came time during like Xbox negotiations and stuff,
you know, we kind of played it off sort of cocky in a way.
And we really didn't mean to.
But I have this thing where I constantly have arguments
with people in my head.
It's probably not very healthy.
But like all the time, I'm sitting there and I'm going,
well, what if they say this?
Well, then I'm going to come back to this.
I'm going to blah, blah, blah.
So.
And this was the one time where it actually came up.
So we were talking and they were kind of concerned that,
like, one programmer doing it on two consoles by himself
was going to be difficult.
And I knew they were going to say that.
So I said, well, you tell whoever has a problem with that
that I ported it to PlayStation in three, like, four days.
And they're our backup if you say no.
Kind of cocky, but true.
I mean, it was four days, and yeah, if they would have said no, we would have put it on
PlayStation.
So true.
And then, yeah, like shortly after that, we actually signed with them, and they allowed
us our month of exclusivity, and everything was going good then.
That was right around the time of the IGF, which was, I don't know if stressful is the
right word.
What's worse than stressful?
I'd say one of the reasons I'm not physically there right now is because of the stress of GDC in general.
It's usually like a...
It's...
For like three months prior, I'm already stressing out about it.
And I know when we're in the IGF, and I feel for everybody in the IGF because...
I've been in the IGF many times and every fucking year it's like...
It's like sleepless nights for months.
You know, you're worried about your game making it in,
and then you're worried about your game, if it made it in, getting a prize,
or worried about, you know, talking to people there and the crowds and everything else.
Yeah.
And, you know, GDC is already stressful as is.
But...
yeah the whole IGF experience last year was even extra stressful for us because it wasn't that
it wasn't that we lost it had nothing really to do with us losing losing it was kind of the
after effects where people kept coming up to us and saying hey I was a judge and um uh I didn't
vote for you guys because you didn't need it because you already have a postal deal.
Yeah that one hurt quite a bit because I remember well I
I mean, some of you know, I'm a diabetic.
Like, I'm type 1 diabetic, insulin dependent.
So, like, any sort of stress really destroys me.
And it's unfortunate, but...
So, kind of an awful story.
The night before they announced the finalists,
I thought I was having a heart attack
because I was so stressed out and I was,
I was like, it was, it was so many, like,
aspects of different kinds of stress.
It's like, oh, if it doesn't get in,
does that mean the game's not good
and we're being delusional and we're spending
all this time?
Oh, but if it does get in, that's great,
but what if it only gets in for this?
What if it doesn't get in for that?
Just all these things are going through my head,
then it was like, well, if it doesn't get in,
then I really can't face anybody.
I'm not gonna go to GDC and see all my friends.
Just all these things are going around in my head.
So I'm sitting there and I was talking
on the phone with my parents.
And I was in tears and my heart was racing.
And this was minutes before the midnight thing
where they announced all the IGF finalists and stuff.
Yeah, that was a lot of stress, and then the stress of getting in the judges' build, which
we wanted to show more because we kind of felt it didn't get in for design, and a couple
judges' comments said it didn't get in for design because it was only the first chapter.
So we wanted to show what the game actually was, so we crunched and got the second chapter
in and got the first boss in, and I think we got in a couple cut scenes.
We just polished what we had.
And, you know, we were able to submit that.
And, yeah, so it was just like a ton of stress.
Then coming here to GDC last year was...
I didn't think I was going to make it.
I actually had to have my sister come with me
because I was here and I was...
I felt like I wanted to throw up all the time.
My sugar was bouncing all over the place.
And then, you know, when we get here and we have...
people saying that they didn't vote for us because of little reasons like that.
You know, we didn't need it. We actually kind of did.
You know, yeah, we had a console deal. We didn't have any money.
My bank account has been in the red several times during Meat Boy development.
But, you know, yeah, so and yeah, and then when we got all done with GDC, my A1C,
which is like a three month total of your blood sugars,
it's supposed to be like between four and five.
It was 8.5.
which means it was just riding super high and then going low,
and then, you know, just kind of bouncing up and down.
But yeah, I mean, we kind of just got through that as best we could.
Yeah, it didn't hurt that we also had the pressures of...
I mean, there was just so much pressure.
Yeah, it's just a ton.
And this was just the beginning of it.
Yeah.
Both of us are going from, you know, me especially, I'm going from,
okay, I do Flash games and I do Indie games, and this is my first console game, so...
This is me proving my worth.
And it's hard to avoid that when it's quite literally that.
Like, this is going to show everybody who I am and my value, essentially.
So, you know, no stress there.
And then, of course, the IGF, like Tommy said, you go into it thinking if you don't make it in, you're a loser.
And it's hard not to think that way, especially when there's so much writing on it.
And it's such a weird thing.
For a game like Meat Boy that did so well, both me and Tommy were extremely worried that we would not make it into the IGF at all.
Like, it's just, everybody kind of goes through these things where it's like, oh fuck, you know?
This is my baby, is it totally ugly and I can't see it? Like, is this my ugly freak baby that only I love?
You worry about that stuff because...
You know, it's just like, it's hard not to be, not to fall in love with what you're doing and then lose sight of if it's good or if it's bad.
Yeah.
And I think we just kind of just hoped that it, I mean, like Tommy mentioned, the summits and stuff like that and showing the game really helped us become more confident in the game and really believe in the game more.
Yes.
But the IGF situation in general was very stressful.
It was weird for me too because I was going in...
kind of feeling a bit like I've overstayed my welcome.
And that was one of the things that kind of sucked too,
because a few people, even friends of mine,
said that they thought I shouldn't have entered
because I'd already won in the past.
And I kind of...
Totally forgetting that I haven't won shit.
Yeah.
I don't have any trophies or anything.
But, yeah, it was weird.
And I guess I have.
I guess I have overstayed my welcome a bit.
And that's kind of a sad thing about the IGF,
is that it kind of was.
Like, definitely now I feel like I don't feel comfortable entering the IGF anymore.
But, uh, I guess it's just something you go through.
And I think I entered seven times and made it in six.
So, that's a good run and I had fun while I was there, but...
I guess, yeah, no more entering the IGF.
It's so fucking stressful either way.
Yeah, yeah, that's...
I mean, I'd say a lot of the things that really slowed us down were...
were conventions. Like we did GDC and when we got back from that, that was when Tommy
did his rant as well, which was a high point. We got back from GDC and we were like just
kind of sitting next to each other not working, going like what the fuck, you know, what the
fuck's going on and just kind of like, you know, being sad.
Yeah, it was super sad.
But what we ended up doing was we took that and we just pushed it all on the iPhone situation
and we decided, you know, we're going to pick ourselves back up by basically making a joke
game for the App Store, which was a Me Boy handheld game that looked like a tiger handheld
game.
Yeah.
Which we put up.
We did that like over a weekend and it kind of eased us back into development.
But then right after that we ended up doing E3.
Yeah.
And every time we do these events we have to like...
We have to focus all of our work on the build so we can show it so it looks pretty.
And then it will take away from development overall because we'll end up working on stuff that we shouldn't be needing to work on just so we can show it so it looks good.
So like both the IGF and GDC kind of fucked with our deadline and pushed us back a couple months because we were working on things that were just kind of for show when we really should have been working on core aspects of the game to get moving on.
Yeah, we should have been doing stuff like we should like I think at the point of did we have hell in for E3? I don't remember.
I had just started it.
Okay. Yeah. So we what we should have been doing is making all of the obstacles for the next chapters and working on the bosses and then going back and polishing everything. But we kind of, you know, we just weren't able aren't able to do that when when Microsoft's like, hey, you have a booth at E3.
You don't say, no thanks. You know, not right now. You know, you just don't do that. And
I mean, I've always, I've wanted to go to E3 forever and then having my game there,
you know, it's just like, that just kind of sweetens the deal. So, yeah, that was, yeah,
that E3 build was like, I was trying to fix this one audio bug which I actually didn't
fix in time. And, yeah, it was just super stressful being up.
you know, getting up at like 8 o'clock in the morning and working until 11 o'clock in
the morning the next day kind of thing. Like trying to make sure the build is uploaded
and then my internet would fuck up and that would screw up the upload because I have shitty
DSL and it would upload like 50k and the build is like 160 megs going up. So yeah, it was
just, it was just a lot of like really, really awful stress. But I mean we got through that.
We went to E3. E3 was great. I mean people, it just further...
Whenever we go to those things, and Ed's mentioned it,
but whenever we go and we see people play the game
and not put it down, that took any sadness that we had
and just sort of, it just put it off to the side.
And it said, well, you need to focus on this
because this game is badass and people think it's badass.
So forget all the drama bullshit
and just focus on the game.
And that's kind of what we did
throughout the summer after E3.
But yeah, around July of 2010, is that when Game Feast stuff came up?
I think that's when we...
No, that's August.
Was that August?
Yeah, I know, because it happened around Daniel's birthday.
But, oh yeah, but what we were doing is we were trying to...
We were trying to get the game out right after Summer of Arcade.
And we were in...
Because we were starting to go into bug testing in July.
And yeah, then the promotion came up.
And that's where the most awful part of development was.
Was that part when we had a launch,
we had a tentative launch date that was like fall.
And then Microsoft wanted to do the game feast thing with us.
And they basically told us, you know,
we wanted Summer of Arcade.
We got pushed back for various reasons.
And yeah, we were kind of bummed about Summer of Arcade,
but you know, whatever.
And they basically told us that if we didn't get into a promotion with them, that it would...
we wouldn't... the game wouldn't do as well, you know, because it wouldn't be heavily promoted
by Microsoft like some of our arcade games are.
And, you know, when we heard that they were doing another promotion, we said...
I remember saying, we will make this no matter what.
Because it was still a tight deadline.
It was two months to get through everything.
I mean, all of the bugs, all of the certification, all that stuff.
It took, and I remember looking at the calendar and I remember feeling the panic and I remember
feeling just all of the stress of that and just going, well, and honestly, this is not
a joke.
It's going to sound like a joke.
I said to myself, I said, I will die after this is done.
And I, cause I honestly felt like with the stress and everything that I was, I was going
to fall over.
I was going to have some sort of diabetic coma or something.
and I was going to die. And I just kept thinking, I will push through this and if I can make
it through then I probably won't die, but it's okay if I die afterward.
There was so much pressure. It's really hard to convey, especially now that we can laugh
about it. But like, going in it was quite literally like, okay here's this promotion,
if you don't get into this promotion then the next promotion is going to be, you know.
you know, six months away, so we didn't have any money at all at that time and we had to release the game.
I was negative 800 at that point.
Yeah.
Negative 853 dollars is what I had.
So we were kind of fucked and we were in a situation where we simply had to do it.
And what they were asking us to do was essentially finish a game in two months that would take, that should take like a company four months.
Yeah.
That's like going through all testing, all bug testing and everything, and basically finishing the game.
And once we actually went into testing, the game wasn't finished yet.
And that's when things got really bad.
And this isn't an over-exaggeration, like, the last two months, two full months of development...
Tommy and I never took a day off.
And I don't think we slept for more than five hours a night
for those two months.
So I would go through phases where I'd be getting up,
I'd get up, I'd...
I get a glass of orange juice and sit next to the computer, and like, I've been wearing glasses for many, many years.
And there were times where I, somehow, everything was blurry, and I didn't understand why.
And it turned out, I never put on my glasses, and it made no sense.
It was like, what kind of fucking bizarre loop am I in where I don't do something that's routine every day, but yet I'm in this weird loop?
It seemed like a Groundhog Day situation where I was...
Constantly reliving the same horrible day over and over and over again.
Yes.
And it just seemed like we were just treading water.
And it's just like, what the fuck's happening?
And I was feeling horrible.
And Tommy says a lot of like...
He didn't tell me about his major worries about dying
until things eased up a bit.
Because I think we were both keeping things from each other.
So we didn't overwhelm the other person.
And I know there were...
I think it was the last month of development.
Um, I would, I, maybe once a week, when I was going to bed, I would tell my wife,
I want to stop. I don't want to do this anymore. This isn't worth it.
Like, um, I, I was feeling not only horrible, just from all the work,
but I was also feeling extra guilty knowing that Tommy is suffering even more
because we're at the point where we're just doing bug testing.
And I can't really help in that department.
Like, I can do so much, but...
most of it was just falling on his shoulders and I saw that it just kept piling up and it was just like
yeah it was seriously I would have just thrown it all away I would have said fuck the game you know I don't
I don't want to release this this is just not worth it I don't it was horrible
yeah that's a it's a bad practice in development to
be going through bug fixing as you're implementing features
um I don't know if you guys know this but it is a fact
um because yeah this is this is how this is how my day
consisted this is
I would go to bed. I would have crazy fever dreams about fixing bugs. So it wasn't really
good sleep. I would wake up and fix the bugs from my dreams. Like, that's a serious thing.
I fix so many bugs by dreaming about them, it's insane. But I would fix those and I would
log on to my little Microsoft thing that would tell me the bugs. And there would be like,
oh, let's say, 129 bugs. I'd be like, great.
focus. And at that point I was only eating like one meal a day and my parents were bringing
it to me because they knew if they didn't bring me the meals I would not eat and I would
therefore die. And my parents are kind of fond of me so they didn't want me to die so
they brought me meals. But yeah, I would get up, I would log into that thing and I would
focus. I usually don't listen to music or anything when I'm working. That was the only
time I did because
I get like involved in stuff if I block everything else out. So usually I have like the TV on
or something so I don't, you know, work for like 28 hours straight or anything. So I had
music on, I am fixing bugs and most days I would get the 129 bugs down to 30 or 20. Then
I would go to bed and I would have my fever dreams and I would wake up and there would
be 150 bugs because the testers, they tested all night and all day while I was sleeping
and they found even more shit because as I was...
implementing fixes for the bugs, I was also implementing new features, which meant that
there would be new stuff that the testers would try out, and then that would break old
stuff and this went on for at least a month and a half of pure hell.
So, but yeah, I mean, you know, we got through it.
Somehow.
I don't know.
I do not know how.
I still think back to those months and I'm just like, Jesus Christ.
I guess the human body can just do it when it needs to, but like, there's no way in hell that I could ever
voluntarily go through something like that again.
Nope.
I would never want to put myself through that again.
If somebody said, hey, want to do Meat Boy again?
And, you know, you're going to get the same amount of success.
There's no way in hell I'd do that.
That's so, so insane.
I mean, it's nice now feeling like, you know, I went through something really fucking tough and now I'm more tough, but...
I don't know, in a lot of ways I feel like I'm weaker because now I'm afraid of something like that.
But yeah, that was part one of...
Part one of awful times.
Should I go into part two, Tommy?
Please go into part two.
Alright, part two is the launch.
Yeah.
So, we're part of the Game Feast, and the Game Feast was...
us, Comic Jumper and Hydrophobia.
And Pinball FX.
Pinball FX, which was free.
And we were the last game of the feast.
We were supposed to be the main course is what it was billed as.
Yeah.
Clever.
But we'd heard from different people at Microsoft when we asked,
because you know, we always want to ask, like,
how do the students do it?
On Skype it just popped up and said 12 minutes, bro.
So we got 12 minutes to get through the last four
months of development.
All right, let's go.
So Microsoft basically told us early on, or we heard from a
few different people there, that we were projected as
being on par, like selling on par as hydrophobia, which
worried us because, you know.
In our delusional minds, we thought that we were top dog and we were going to be the one that Microsoft was like,
oh, this game's going to kick ass.
But whatever, we still believed in our game and we were going to push it as much as we possibly could.
Then Hydrophobia came out and its leaderboards were grim.
And I think in the first week, the leaderboards were like less than 10,000.
And if Microsoft was projecting us on par with this game, we were really fucking worried
that we were going to just bomb.
horribly. So the good thing about the Feast though is any promotion that Microsoft gives you, you get like a number one spotlight and you get an exclusive leak so there's no other games to compete with and usually get a review by Major Nelson and so on and so forth. They really push it. So they really push Hyperphobia and it got a lot of press and everything else but it got really bad reviews.
And they had their dashboard placement and stuff.
And then a week later...
comic jumper comes out. And the comic jumper on the leaderboards does a look, does better than
hydrophobia. Yeah it did, it did, yeah, but still kind of, it still worried us. That's not something
that people would be bragging about. Yeah. Again we were worried because we were projected lower
than them. Lower than them, yeah. So at that point we were kind of like, oh well, you know,
like if shit happens, shit happens, uh, whatever.
At least we're gonna get, you know, pushed as much as possible.
Yeah, we're gonna get our spotlight treatment.
Because, like, Comic Jumper had this really nice, like, animated spotlight treatment.
And we were like, oh, okay, cool, well, you know, that's... that'll work for us, you know.
And, you know, going back to the arguments in my head,
kind of knew what was happening... what was gonna happen next.
Because, yeah, little people in my head told me that it was going to happen.
So...
Our, it's our week to launch, well, first, okay, so before our week, which was the 20th
of October, uh, the week before that, that was supposed to be Pinball FX and we were
gonna be the last Game Feast game. Well, Pinball FX got pushed back, so we weren't the last.
Um, that same week, uh, Costume Quest was announced to come out on the 20th also. And
we're just like, what the fuck? Everybody else gets a free week, uh, except for us and
except for, uh, Pinball FX, because they got moved back.
So we're like, great, we're launching next to Tim Schafer's fucking game.
Great.
Okay, well, that's wonderful.
At least we'll get the dash placement.
So the documentary crew was at my house,
and this is going to be some pretty awful footage for the documentary.
But I get up, you know, I am, I guess the term would be shitting bricks,
but something much bigger than bricks.
So I get up, it's launch day.
I turn on the Xbox, no Meat Boy. And I go, well, what the hell is this? I go on Xbox.com.
Xbox.com is down. And I kind of go, figures. So, you know, I'm sitting there and I wrote
an email to our producer. I was all panicked and everything. I'm like, what's the deal?
Are you guys like, are you guys, sorry.
Are you guys like pulling out of all this? Where is our stuff?
And you know, it didn't go up, didn't go up.
Finally went up halfway through our launch day.
And it was the number four spot. It wasn't number one.
What was the, the spooktacular sale,
which was a whole bunch of other games that already came out, was the number one slot.
I believe there was an ad for a Mazda 3 as the number two slot.
Because you all, you all go on Xbox and figure out what car you want to buy, right?
Yeah.
I go and it's either that or the Honda Odyssey.
I know that was all through our month.
I'm like, who the fuck is buying a Honda Odyssey after looking at an ad on Xbox?
Anyway.
Um, but yeah, I was looking, looking at that stuff and, uh, yeah, we were number
four and we stayed number four for the entire week and we were told, we were
told several things, we were like, well, if you, the, the better you perform.
The, uh, you know, the, the better, the better you perform, the
farther up you'll move in a dash.
okay because our first day even though you know
we only had half of our actual launch day our first day was like it was still
pretty decent
and then you know by our second day we our leader boards were bigger than
comic jumpers and hydrophobias so we were doing like super super well
and it just kept going and going and going and and there are metacritic score
at that time was ninety two
And we're like, well, we meet all the things.
Why aren't we moved up?
And they said, oh, well, that's different placement, blah,
blah, blah.
We kind of just got pushed to the side.
And yeah, that's basically how Xbox launch went, is the
reason the game sold well is because of how we promoted it.
We were the ones doing the interviews.
We had the high Metacritic score.
I mean, the help from Microsoft was there in a very
limited capacity.
I don't know if it was like that they were disappointed that the other games didn't do
well or they just maybe wanted to like you know cut their losses or whatever but I mean
it it's not supposed to hurt your feelings because it's business but it totally fucking
hurt my feelings because you know I just killed myself me and Ed just killed ourselves trying
to get this game done and now we're just kind of just put to the side but.
Yeah I mean I think I mean I still think about it a lot.
even talking, you talk to different people there and no one can give you a real straight answer but
the only thing that I can make sense of is that since the Game Feast games did so poorly initially
that it kind of, they kind of wanted to remove, they just wanted to push it, push it away like
Game Feast and there's no more Game Feast and I don't know if anybody noticed but like on all of
our ads there was nothing that tied us into Game Feast at all by the time we launched so it did
seem like Microsoft wanted to distance itself from the Game Feast.
which was fine, but in doing so, it completely removed us.
We tried to push into this promotion, which was to get better promotion,
and get an exclusive launch week, and all this other stuff.
It sounds weird to complain about it, even though we've done so well on Xbox Live,
but it was a fucking mindfuck.
It was really confusing.
At that point, I think we were both kind of so...
fucked up in our heads from development that we kind of were like
very paranoid and it almost felt like are these people out to get us?
Are they just fucking stupid? Like what's happening here? Like what did we do to
them? Did we do something wrong? Because there were a few times where
we might have said things publicly that they didn't like
and I know you just get paranoid and you think
you know are they trying to screw us over because we did something wrong
You know, in the end, I guess you live and you learn.
Now I know what to put in a contract before I sign it.
Yeah, really.
Things happen.
I think we're running out of time, so we should probably like,
you know, just snap through these last couple of things.
How much time do I have?
Five? Okay.
Five minutes, we can do this in five minutes.
We can take questions.
Oh, yeah, shit, we need to take questions.
Hey, how about this?
Want me to sum it up, Tommy?
Yeah.
We released on Steam, and it did better than Xbox.
How's that?
Yeah.
It did a lot better.
Total, yes, Steam outsold Xbox.
It's much easier to update on Steam.
Everybody should love all over Steam,
like all nasty love all over Steam,
because Steam is awesome.
We're closing in at like 400,000 sales now for the game.
We have retail versions coming out.
We are, oh yeah, our WiiWare announcement,
which we've been talking about, is, oh, I think Ed's gone.
Oh, I'm still here.
Oh, OK.
Our WiiWare announcement is there is no WiiWare,
because we made a game that's too big for WiiWare,
unfortunately.
And that really sucks, because we wanted to do WiiWare.
It's just not in the cards.
And I'm not going to do episodic content, so no.
We tried really hard to get a retail version, and we talked to a lot of different publishers about it,
but nobody wants to touch retail Wii at this point in its life cycle or whatever,
and so we weren't able to land that. But we do have 3DS development kits,
and we are going to be working on something for the 3DS in the future.
We don't know if that'll be Meat Boy, but you never know.
It's, yeah, it really depends. Like, everything that we do is very whatever feels right. So
if it feels right to do 3DS Meat Boy, we will do 3DS Meat Boy. If it doesn't, we'll do something
and we'll try to make it super awesome because that's what's fun. You know. Oh, yeah, and
we're still working on the editor and the portal, which should be out very, very soon.
They're basically done. We just have to hook them up. Oh, there you are.
Tommy's working on the editor in his hotel room.
Yeah, actually, I'm finishing it up in my hotel room.
This is my life now.
Wait, there's a cover box in the back.
Oh, yeah.
That's the Walmart box.
Yeah.
Woo!
So they better be good.
Yes, at the mic person.
Oh, sorry.
Yeah.
Well, great job, by the way, guys.
I love the game.
Thank you.
When approaching digital distribution markets,
I noticed a lot of them are private,
so sales figures and such aren't easily available.
How did you guys approach making your contracts,
business plans, and so on for Super Meat Boy,
given that a lot of the information isn't public?
for like say Xbox Live sales, revenue splits and so on?
Oh, um, most, most like, most like revenue splits and everything are just sort of written
in. I mean, and like we said, we don't have any clout because, you know, we hadn't made
anything so, uh, we just kind of took what they gave us, uh, with everybody. Um, yeah,
I mean that's the, and the way we sort of just approached the, the Microsoft exclusivity
stuff.
is we just kind of pushed it to see what we could get away with.
And I mean, it was really, honestly, it's just kind of a lot of dumb luck,
as far as like the exclusivity term and everything, but...
Yeah, we just kind of played everything by ear.
I know it's not the best advice, but...
But that's kind of how we work, as you can tell from the speech.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Yes.
Oh, hey.
Oh.
Yeah, no worries.
A little confusing with two mics.
So there's a lot more pain and agony behind your development process than I could have
possibly imagined.
And I'm just curious, looking forward, if you have any thoughts on how to mitigate that
in the future.
I think the only way we can actually mitigate that kind of stuff is through experience.
We won't have money troubles this next game.
And we...
Admittedly, a lot of the troubles that we had were our fault and, you know, just stuff
like getting, I guess, like, too wrapped up in the game and everything, but that's something
we're actually not going to fix because I feel that's what made the game great, but
the only way to, like, fix the stress and all of that is to, I mean, we're not going
to kill ourselves to get into a promotion next time, that's for sure, and that will
save a lot of heartache and a lot of...
you know, just pressure that's put onto us. But yeah, I mean, experience, you know, just
sort of going through it. And I mean, we didn't bite off more than we could chew, and that
was a good thing. And I think that's something that makes people, that sort of destroys people
sometimes. So, I mean, if you are very much within your own limits, then you'll be fine.
We were just in a compressed timeline within our limits that was, you know, not through
our doing exactly.
Awesome, thanks.
Yeah, I mean the majority of development was really, really fun and really, really smooth.
Like, the only negatives were the things that we mentioned.
You know, that was only a good two weeks in the building.
Oh, and for the record, working with Microsoft was...
Working with the creative side of Microsoft was great.
It was the... I was thinking about it in the car.
The thing that sucked about it...
Everybody that we talked to were great.
The people that we could not talk to were the people that were the problem.
So everyone we worked with was wonderful.
Everyone that was making decisions, not so much.
Yeah, I do think it would be the only negative
that we experienced with Microsoft was just
We got to cut it, Ed.
We're like way over.
Oh, whatever.
Make games.
Yeah, make games.
There.
There's the coffee break and be back in 15 minutes or more like 12.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
I've got another stuff too.
Oh, yeah.
Watch out.
Lots of my stuff.
We're going to play.
Now I'm going to give them the art.
Yeah.
Oh, my God.
We're going to play.
All right.
So let's try this.
Yeah.
OK.
You have to get that.
Yeah.
Like we were playing.
Aha, thank you, awesome.
And that's also my website.
Wow, did you take someone else's business card and scratch it up?
I did, my boyfriend.
That's awesome.
Thank you.
Yeah.
I'll be back. I'm just trying to go to the bathroom.