So welcome. So all week at GDC you've all been, those of you in industry, have been leveling up
your career. But if you're at this session, it might have occurred to you that there's this
whole other career track in academia. Maybe you're wondering if you might want to crossover.
Maybe you're thinking it sounds nice to never have to crunch to meet arbitrary publisher deadlines again.
You get to mentor a bunch of bright, eager young developers who are like younger versions of you.
They all love games and they just want to be in your class and they look up to you like a god
because you've got industry experience and that's where they want to be.
you get summers off, and you get so you can make games,
and not just games for profit motive,
but just wonderful games that come from your heart,
something along those lines maybe.
And if your mental image is something like that,
then you have about as good an idea
of what it's really like in academia
that then grandma's boy has to the actual game industry.
Don't worry though, we've got half an hour here.
So let's cover some reality.
So first and most important thing is that saying
you're a faculty is like saying I'm a game developer.
There are many different kinds
and they all work differently.
First is the adjunct.
Pay is generally low.
It's temporary, not full time.
You have little or no institutional power.
It's a thankless job.
You're treated like you're easily replaceable.
You have no job security past the courses
that you're teaching now.
But a lot of people use it as an entry point,
either to test the waters or gain some teaching experience
and a foothold.
On the bright side, it does tend to require minimal credentials.
If you have industry experience, that's a plus.
You usually don't need to have an advanced degree or anything
like that.
So it's basically the academic equivalent of QA.
Visiting professors are like outside contractors.
It's a full-time gig for a fixed period, usually one year.
one academic year. And like a contractor you have all the responsibility of
getting your work done but none of the institutional authority since you're the
outsider.
There's one important difference between visiting professors and outside
contractors in the game industry though.
In the game industry
outside contractors tend to make more money as base salary because
Yeah, you have to, because they don't get benefits,
because they have these dry spells in between
that they have to cover for,
and so it's understood that you pay a premium on that
to cover their extra costs.
Academics are less nice about this.
So usually it's more like visiting professors
make about half of what a full-time,
a permanent faculty does.
But usually do get benefits.
Sometimes as a visiting professor, you can make the case to renew your contract,
but usually if you like the place, um, that you're at, um,
You'd instead be trying to make the case to convert to permanent faculty from there.
And that's about as easy as being a freelancer and converting to full-time at a company you're
working for.
It usually doesn't happen.
And if it does, it's kind of a trial by fire thing.
Some visiting professors require an advanced degree and they're basically the school's
way of saying, well, we like you.
We'd like to have you teaching here, but not enough to actually pay you what you're worth
or be a permanent employee.
We just want to try before we buy.
Other visiting professors are a way for schools to bring in someone that doesn't have the academic credentials
without getting their kneecaps broken by their accreditation boards because hey, they're they're not permanent. They're they're just here for a limited time
Don't worry about it
And while you're there, they'll try and milk everything they can out of you to help boost their program
Next position goes by two names, professor of practice or
designer or something in residence, like designer in
residence, artist in residence, something like that.
There are some arcane nitpicky differences between professor
of practice and resident, but they mostly work the same way,
which is full time with a split between teaching and
actually making stuff, in our case, making games.
These positions are specifically for people with
field experience, so they typically have lower
requirements for academic credentials.
And there's a focus on actually making games in addition to teaching them.
So it's a lot of a practice what you preach type thing.
Naturally with so many upsides, you might be wondering,
ooh, that sounds awesome.
What's the catch?
The catch is that there's very few of these in existence.
The competition is very fierce, so you're not going to get one.
So this is basically the academic equivalent of entry level game designer
or concept artist or producer.
A few of them do exist.
Not very many.
Don't count on it.
Then there's the lecturer position.
This is a full-time position with an emphasis on teaching,
lots and lots of classes, and almost nothing else.
So this is for people who just want to teach
and then teach some more.
Usually, lecturers are not permanent.
Instead, they're on a fixed-term contract,
sometimes one year, sometimes two or three years,
but you can usually renew indefinitely.
So when your contract is up,
you can try and just keep it going and roll it over.
These vary a bit in terms of course load.
I've talked to some people who teach as few as four courses
per term, others that have taught as much as seven.
And just so you understand the math,
when you're talking number of courses,
a typical course, you're talking about
10 hours of work per week.
That's just to, that includes actually lecturing the course,
you know, or teaching it.
Usually that's just like maybe two or three hours.
But then you have grading, you have office hours,
all these other things.
So it all adds up to about 10 hours a week.
If it's a course you haven't taught before,
add another 10 hours a week of course development.
And I see some of you doing the math in your heads.
And yes, if you start with four classes a semester
and you've never taught before,
that means you're gonna be having flashbacks
to your most recent death march in industry.
So at a lot of schools,
lecturers also have very little institutional power.
So when it comes to things like important meetings
about deciding the strategy for the department,
they tend to be forgotten
and they're mostly invisible to administrators.
So lecturers are kind of like
the academic equivalent of game audio.
That said, like audio, it is still full-time.
You still get benefits.
You still make a living wage.
And in some schools, there is an opportunity
for promotion to senior lecturer and principal lecturer
and things like that.
Some schools do that, some don't.
You would have to ask.
And most schools are willing to substitute field experience
and teaching experience for advanced degrees here
for their lecturers.
So you don't usually need a master's or PhD
if all you're doing is teaching and no research.
Though if you have an advanced degree,
it does help if you have one.
The downside is that lecturers are also rare
and they're becoming more and more rare,
they're disappearing because schools have figured out
that if they just wanna bring in someone
to teach their classes,
it's cheaper to get the adjuncts to do it.
At the top of the pyramid, there's this thing called tenure track faculty.
And that's what most people think of when they think of a college professor.
And this varies internationally, but in the US, the way this works is you're
what's called pre-tenure for a period of six years.
And I always thought that was odd.
Like, you know, it's called tenure.
You'd think it would take 10 years, but it really takes six.
And you have one checkpoint halfway through to find out whether you're on track.
Some schools just use that as a way to give you feedback of how you're doing and what
your strong and weak points are.
Others actually use it as a checkpoint where they can just eliminate you if you're not
making the cut at three.
It depends.
So, that's it.
Thank you.
And when the clock runs out at the end of six years,
then there's basically this all or nothing.
Thumbs up, you're promoted, you now have tenure,
which means you pretty much have to kill someone
to ever get fired or laid off.
You have a job for life here.
Or you're fired GTFO.
Now this sounds like a lot of pressure, and it is.
If you talk to junior faculty in most fields, they'll act like this is the worst thing ever.
But we come from the game industry, and where can you go in the game industry where you'd
get a guaranteed job for six whole years?
I think that's a pretty sweet deal.
Now that is what I am, so maybe you can see my bias here.
That's kind of where the action is.
Now it's worth mentioning some terminology here
because it's different from the game industry.
In academia, if you're tenure track but not yet tenured,
your job title is assistant professor.
That doesn't mean you're assisting anyone.
I don't know why they call it that,
but that's what they call it.
If you get tenure, then your job title changes to Associate Professor.
Now in the game industry, we use the term associate to mean entry level,
but in academia, it means you're finally one of the people we've actually chosen to associate ourselves with.
So it's a good thing.
And after you reach the associate level, later on, at
some point, you can request a try for a promotion to what's
called a full professor.
And then your job title gets shortened to just professor.
So in the game industry, going from associate game designer
to just game designer is entry to mid-level.
In academia, that's going from mid to senior level.
Now if tenure track sounds sweet, there is a downside.
And that is that this is where you usually require at least a
master's degree just to apply.
Sometimes it's PhD or go home.
And sometimes they ask for what's called a terminal
degree.
Now terminal does not mean it's a malignant degree that
kills you, although it feels like it sometimes when you're
going through it.
It just means the highest degree that's offered in your field.
So that does include PhD, but it can also include things like MFA,
Master of Fine Arts, if you're in the arts, MBA for business,
or professional degrees like an MD for doctors or a JD for lawyers.
There's no higher degree you can get for those things,
so those count as terminal degrees.
There's also another position you might hear about from time to time called postdoc, but
unless you already have a PhD, this is not relevant to you.
Basically in the old days, when you graduated with a PhD in a field, you'd either go work
for a company or you'd get a tenure-track faculty job.
But then schools started pumping out more PhDs they could absorb.
so they had to lengthen the pipeline so now there's this like Ponzi pyramid scheme thing
where you've got this kind of sort of position where we like you as a faculty but we're going
to still treat you like a graduate student and then when you're done with your postdoc
then maybe you can apply for tenure track faculty positions or maybe we'll just ask
you to do another postdoc because we're jerks.
So you don't have to worry about that one but you might hear about it every now and
then that's what it means.
Now, if you ever meet someone who's a tenure track or tenured faculty and you want to really
annoy them, you can start by asking, oh, you're a faculty, what do you teach?
And the reason this is annoying is that teaching is definitely one of the things that faculty
do, but we usually do other things, too, specifically research and service.
And for some reason, academics are obsessed with furniture.
I'm not sure why.
But you hear this called a three-legged stool a lot.
So when we talk about teaching, that's not just running a class.
You do have to run the class.
But there's also other tasks that count as teaching,
like designing or pitching brand new courses for the curriculum, which
involves lots and lots of paperwork to describe exactly what you're going to do.
Or taking an existing course and porting it to a new format, like we used to teach this in a classroom,
now we're teaching it online.
Or being on thesis committees for graduate students also counts.
And when you're being evaluated in your job, teaching is mostly judged by student course evals.
Those of you who have been to college remember filling those things out and thinking they're completely useless?
You know, those things.
Downside of teaching evals is we have a ton of research showing that they do not correlate at all with how good of a teacher you are.
But everyone uses them anyway.
And at least there are known ways to game the system, if you want.
Like inflating your grades to keep your students happy, or being male because there's a gender bias among students.
I wish I was kidding when I said that, but I'm really not.
And sometimes you also get peer review, if you're really lucky,
where another faculty will sit in on one of your lectures
for a few minutes and then try to extrapolate
to all of your teaching ever.
Now when we say research, this is a very broad topic.
Well, sometimes it's more broad than others depends on the school.
But generally what we mean is being a thought leader in your field.
So kind of like what you would do at a director level at a game studio,
except you're doing it for the entire industry and not just that one company.
It's the academic equivalent of the kinds of people in the industry who keynote at conferences,
give well-attended and high-rated talks at GDC, the kinds of people who have 10,000 followers
on Twitter and who have a dev blog that everyone in the industry follows, that kind of thing.
And research is usually judged by three buzzwords, so it's kind of like a recursive stool.
And the buzzwords are peer review, dissemination, and impact.
Peer review means we don't just take your word for it
that your work is awesome.
Other people in your field agree that your work is awesome
and they're willing to say so.
Dissemination means you don't just do really awesome stuff
but you also get it out there and tell people
so they can see it.
And impact means that you have some kind of measurable
effect on the field.
Like other people are actually referencing your work
and building off of it.
So how many people here are game designers?
Okay, how many of you have read the MDA framework?
Right? Impact.
So schools vary in terms of what counts as research and what doesn't.
The traditional academic form of research is getting published in peer-reviewed academic journals,
and you typically want a high-quality journal that has a high rejection rate, because that's peer review,
wide viewership, because that's dissemination,
and you want your article to be cited a lot by other people, because that's impact.
Usually, you can count speaking at conferences as part of research.
Again, a high reject rate makes it more significant if you're speaking there.
You can also show impact by numbers of people who attended your talk, people who referenced
the talk later in their work, and also things like audience ratings at GDC or best talk
or best paper awards at other conferences.
Some conferences publish their proceedings in a journal, so you kind of get two for one.
You get a publication and a research, or and a conference speaking.
And writing textbooks can count as scholarship, and your success metric there, for once, is
actually the same as your publisher.
You want the book widely adopted in classes and industry with really high sales numbers.
Bringing in grants is something you might be judged on.
A grant means you're basically saying,
hey, I convinced other people to give me lots of money
to do my work, therefore I have value.
Realistically, if you're consistently bringing in
more money than your salary from the school,
then they're never going to fire you no matter what
because you're a net positive on their cash flow.
Also realistically, most of us who come from
the game industry are gonna have
a really hard time doing that.
Another way to disseminate your work is during exhibitions and festivals.
Having your game nominated for an award at IGF. Having your game accepted to a
festival like Indiecade or Boston Fig or different games or other game festivals.
This is particularly important for those of us who make games and that that is
our primary form of research or scholarship.
And those of you who would like to do research in the form of making games
should now be sufficiently terrified at how competitive these festivals are.
The last leg of our three-legged stool is service. And we use the word service in the same
meaning as community service or public service. This is the easy part. You can serve on
committees at your school, be a reviewer who green lights talks or papers for journals or
conferences, judging games for IGF or Indicade or other competitions.
doing academic advising for students,
being a faculty advisor for student clubs
or organizations like a game dev club,
organizing on-campus events like Global Game Jam
or other game jams,
doing, you can also do service outside of campus
but in the local community, that also counts.
So giving workshops in game design at local high schools
or a local scouts troop, something like that.
You can also do service
in the game development community itself,
doing volunteer work for IGDA, for example.
Surface is easy, and it's a lot of fun.
It's also usually weighted much less
than in your job evaluation than teaching and research.
We usually call it a checkbox.
And there's not actually a physical checkbox
on the tenure form, but it's one of those things
where you just have to put in a few bullet points
that say, yes, I did the minimum amount of service.
Now as game developers, you might have had a lot of people ask you,
oh, you're in games, what's that like?
And of course the answer is, it depends.
Working at a AAA studio is different from working at a bedroom indie,
which is different from AAA,
and even within the same class, like working at Valve is a very different
experience from working at Blizzard, even though they're both AAA.
And this is true of schools too. Each school will have a different emphasis on how they value teaching versus research versus service.
Within each category, what kinds of things they look for.
Every school has a different culture and a different community.
And so, just like with game studios, everyone is different. You're not going to be happy at all of them.
because there is a certain fit for your skills,
for the types of things you want to do, for your culture.
And so it's important to find places that are a good fit
for your personal desires and strengths.
So know what your desires are and what your strengths are
before you start applying for jobs.
And speaking of applying for jobs,
where do you find job postings?
If you've listened to this and you're like,
yeah, okay, I still would like to take a look at.
you know, academia, I'm not running away fleeing in terror.
You know, where do you find job postings?
Well, you know, there are a lot of places.
There are game academic mailing lists
like IGDA's game education SIG.
There are various Facebook groups.
Many of those are open to anyone who's interested,
even if they're not actively teaching
or doing faculty things.
New positions often get posted on these groups.
That's actually the most common kind of post
on the ones that I'm on.
There are also job postings on Gamma Sutra and Game Career Guide, places like that.
Because if you're a school and you are hiring faculty, where are you going to think to put
your job postings? If you're looking for someone with industry experience, you're going to
put it in places where people with industry experience will find it. So you can look for
jobs there. There's also, you're at GDC. There's a ton of schools in the Expo Hall and the
Career Center here. And you can just walk up and ask if they're hiring. Some of them,
that's the reason why they rented a booth in the first place.
And hey, we're game developers.
We already live or die by our social networks.
So if you're in a position to go public with your desire
to cross over to academia, you can just
ask your hive mind of friends on Facebook and Twitter
and other social media, hey, thinking of teaching,
does anyone know any open academic positions?
You can do that, and you'll probably hear something back.
If you want to stay local to where you are, you can also just research the local schools.
Look around and see, you know, do they have a game dev program?
Well, if so, you can walk in and ask, you know, are you looking for extra people?
Or, sometimes you'll see, you can like look at their department and they'll be like,
they're kind of, sort of, want to do games, but they haven't really done it yet, like...
They have a major in interactive entertainment and a couple classes that are like, you know,
interactive media, but you, you know, it's like, but they don't seem to have a game major
yet and you get the feeling that maybe it's because they really want to, but they haven't
found anyone who actually knows how to make games to teach it.
And so you can just walk in and cold call them and say like, hey, it looks like you're
doing some stuff with games or you want to, would you like some help with that?
Oh, and by the way, raise your hand if you're a game developer.
And raise your hand if you're an academic.
So game developers, psst, those people with the hands up
for the academics, they already know
what it's like in academia.
They don't need to be at this conference,
or at this session, which means there's no reason
they should be in this room.
They're either here because they misread the description
or because they're hiring and want
to scout the room for talent.
So you're probably going to lunch
right after this session anyway.
Just ask them if they have lunch plans.
Oh, and speaking of my employer, RIT is also hiring two full-time lecturer positions, one
for a visual artist and one for a graphics programmer, if you think it'd be cool to work
down the hall from me.
I also heard from my friend Brenda Romero, she's also hiring if anyone has gameplay programming
experience and wants to move to Ireland.
There's probably many other schools hiring too, many of them in this room, so work the
room here and on the expo floor if you're interested.
Once you find a good source of job postings, first thing
you'll run into is a wall of required qualifications.
So that's the downside.
And this is a lot like breaking into the game industry.
It looks daunting.
It keeps a lot of people out.
So what do we tell students who want to break in?
We all have that conversation with someone.
Like, oh, you're in the game industry.
I know someone who would love to get into the game industry.
And what do we say?
But they can't, because they don't have any history
experience.
And what do we tell them?
We say, don't let a lack of experience or a lack of a job
or a lack of talent stop you.
Just make games.
And eventually, the experience and the talent and the job
will follow, right?
And the same is true here in academia.
If you want to teach, then teach.
You don't need a school for that.
You don't need permission.
You can find some local kids who want to learn.
And you can teach them on weekends if you want.
You can look for local homeschool communities and
pitch the idea to them.
to say, you know, do enough of you have kids who would like to learn how to make games?
You can talk to local science museums and tech museums and see if they have any, like,
you know, any desire to host workshops that help people to create in the science and tech
areas.
Or you can just talk to your non-developer friends and family.
We all know that conversation that starts like, oh, I have a nephew who would love to
make games.
Right?
And instead of just saying, yeah, yeah, okay, go away, you could say, oh, you know, would
you like me to teach them?
You know or you can put together and run a course online independent of any school
I've did that twice and people are still finding it useful. There's nothing stopping you from doing that
You know it's not like practicing medicine where someone's going to like you know throw you in jail if you teach without a license it doesn't
Work that way
You can find local game dev classes at schools if there are any and find out who's teaching and offer to do a guest lecture every now and then.
Or if there's a student game development club at a local university, you can just offer to run some workshops or lectures for them at their meetings.
They're usually not going to tell you no.
If teaching is your passion, you don't need any school's permission. Just teach.
And just like if game design is your passion, you're going to design games whether you get paid for it or not.
And if you do it enough, then eventually you'll find a way to get paid for it.
Teaching is like that too.
Getting experience in research is a little less obvious than getting experience in teaching,
but it is still very possible, I assure you.
Presenting at conferences, for example.
That counts as academic work.
If you've been in the industry for more than a couple years or so, you've probably solved
some really interesting problems in your work where the solutions would be of value to your
peers if you generalize them, and you can pitch that to GDC or other conferences.
That's research.
but it's also just what we do in the industry.
Like, how many of you in industry have spoken before
at some conference or other at some point in your life?
Quite a few of you, right?
So you're not as much of a noob
as you think you are to academia.
You can also write a book.
Anyone here read Raph Koster's Theory of Fun?
Right?
That's, see, impact again, right?
And you don't need to be an academic to write books.
He doesn't have any academic qualifications.
He just wrote a book and now everyone's reading it.
And it gives you academic street cred if you do that.
Another thing you can do is reach out to academics.
We are all over the place at GDC.
We even have our own summit that took place a few days ago.
And just ask about collaborations.
Now you might be thinking about this,
having this image in your mind
of the ivory tower academic,
the person who just lives in their own bubble
doing meaningless research with no practical application
who just doesn't care, right?
Believe me, that is a myth.
That is an unfair stereotype, especially in games.
virtually all of the academics I know, they want their work to be used in the field.
That's why they became researchers.
It's just that some of them don't know how and would desperately like to consult with
actual game devs so they don't get in over their heads.
Or sometimes you'll find a researcher who does know what they're doing and they'd like
to collaborate with industry because it's tactically useful to have industry partners
on certain types of grants.
Or just because they'd like to work with proper developers again and not just students.
If you can bring extra work to your game dev studio that you're working for now from an academic grant,
that helps your game development career and gets you research experience.
And now earlier I talked about degree requirements.
So for those of you who don't have a graduate degree,
you have options.
You can do the job search anyway,
just with a more limited pool of jobs
that are willing to take your industry XP
and substitute it for academic credentials.
Keep in mind, there are fewer of those
and you're competing with everyone else in the room here,
but that is a possibility.
The other thing you can do is you can go back to school and earn your degree.
Many schools have part-time options where you can take one or two classes per term while
still keeping your day job.
Most of you with industry experience are going to kick the ass of most other applicants to
those programs who are coming fresh off a bachelor's degree with no real world experience,
which means you've got a decent shot at scoring a sweet scholarship to reduce or eliminate
your costs.
Or if you have the means, you can go back to school full time.
That's kind of the all-in option.
But that is what I did.
I saved up over really aggressively
when I had a full-time job in industry
until I had a couple years worth of financial cushion
and was able to just stretch that out
by doing freelance work on the side
while I was doing full-time school.
Generally, the higher degree you have, the more doors in academia will open for you,
but also the longer it takes you to earn the degree in the first place, and the riskier
a proposition it is if something goes horribly off the rails in your academic career along
the way.
At any rate, so it's all trade-offs.
At any rate, if you know that you want to be a faculty,
then the rule is get the highest degree you can,
but know that there are occasionally job postings
with lower requirements, and you should keep an eye out
for those and be ready to pounce on an opportunity.
So it's basically just like when all of you
started out in the game industry,
and it seemed like the only job postings
required three plus years industry XP
and minimum one ship title, and you didn't have any,
and it felt impossible, but obviously it wasn't impossible
because you're here.
So academia is like that too.
So there's a lot more I could say about this, but for a short time period of a half hour session, this is about all I could cover.
I did create some extra slides on the job search process and how to get hired, and I put those on a bit.ly link here,
so if you want to unlock the bonus content for the talk, it's right there right now.
Also, here's my contact info.
I am happy to answer any questions you have over email
if anything occurs to you later.
I field questions from people in industry
about what it's like in academia all the time,
but I can also take some questions.
I think I have time for like one or two questions now,
and I can also be in the session
in the wrap-up room after this.
So thank you.
Hi, my name is Angela Stukater. I'm from Sheridan College, which is located just outside of Toronto in Canada.
And I'm here looking for people who want to teach.
Our probationary...
See, told you.
Yes, this is me.
Probation in Canada at our college is one year, not six.
So it's a little bit an easier slide.
I wanted to ask you though, Ian, about the balance
between work experience and academics.
Yeah.
It's, yeah.
So it's usually on a sliding scale,
but it varies widely by school.
There are some schools that really, really
want the academic credentials, and then the industry XP
is a plus.
There are some that are willing to sub-XP
for academic credentials, depending
on how much you have.
If you're at the creative director,
like director level position with 20 years industry
experience, sometimes you can get along with just a bachelor's
and it's fine.
In the US, the reason it, the reason
The way it works is it's not academic snobbery.
It's that schools are beholden to their accreditation boards.
Schools are accredited, which means
that there's some outside, unbiased third party that
looks at them and says, yes, you are actually
teaching what you say you are.
And you get the stamp of approval
that basically gives them some legitimacy among students
and everyone else.
And the problem is that accreditation boards require you to have a certain percentage of
faculty with advanced degrees.
And so it's just kind of a non-starter for them.
Now I will tell you that sufficient amounts of paperwork can make every problem go away.
So if you are Will Wright and you want to teach and normally it requires a master's
degree and you just have a bachelor's, the school can write enough stuff to their accreditation
board to satisfy them to say this person is justified as qualified.
The problem is that it's a lot of extra work.
Academics don't have a whole lot of time.
So for most people, they're not willing to do that.
And they'll just tell you no.
And really what they mean is, no, I don't have the time to
deal with this.
I think we are out of time.
But feel free to follow me to the wrap-up room later.
Thank you.