Hi, I'm Lisa Brunette and I'm the owner of Brunette Games.
This is Anthony and Dexter.
They also work for Brunette Games.
Originally, this was supposed to be a preview of my talk
for the Game Developers Conference in a couple of weeks.
You may know that it was canceled
because of the coronavirus.
It's in San Francisco every year.
So it's no longer a preview for me to deliver a talk.
And since...
I've been working, especially over the last year, to develop this team of great, awesome people.
In that spirit, I invited them to come in and join the talk with me,
especially since the games that we are going to showcase tonight,
they're the ones who know more about them than I do at this point,
which is the very definition of growing your team, right?
So I'm really excited to have them.
We're gonna talk about three things
that we discuss with our clients absolutely every day.
Conflict, mystery, and connection.
We work mainly on casual three-play puzzle games,
although that's starting to change
as we branch out to other areas.
So a little bit about us.
We're a storytelling-focused studio.
So we're primarily writers.
We do something called narrative design,
which is the design of story in games.
which gets to be a fairly technical skill
because you have the gameplay and the story
that need to be integrated and working together.
So that's a focus, and yes, we do have shirts,
matching shirts.
We didn't wear them because they're in their short sleeve,
they're in the summer box.
But this is the group that needs to dress alike.
And we have that group.
So these are our services.
Narrative design and story concepts.
Dialogue scripts and in-game text.
storyboard cut scenes and voiceover recordings,
task and quest flows, branching dialogue
and choice stats as well.
So even though Anthony has a fantastic voice,
we are actually not the voice over actors.
In addition to this crew full-time,
we have four other people, two part-time writers
we just hired from St. Louis University here locally
in the English department, yay, where I graduated.
and two voiceover actors who work out of their home studios on the east and west coast for us.
One of whom is someone who was born and raised in St. Louis and just went out to LA and is becoming a famous actress.
Pretty neat story, I think.
The first thing we're going to talk about is conflict.
How many of you think conflict, bad word?
Good! You've been trained well.
You're ahead of our developers who shy away from this constantly.
Just today, in fact, we were working with an IP
that will not be mentioned, but is very well known.
And we had to kind of school them on this idea of,
you know, if you want story, that thing should happen.
This is Matchington Mansion, which is kind of our free bird.
It's what everyone wants when they come to us for services.
It made $11 million in revenue in January alone.
In the very beginning of this game, you have your bestie, Tiffany, who comes up and she's
encouraging you because all this door needs is a little bit of paint.
So this is a restoration game where you're going to fix up a mansion.
The first thing that happens is that door falls down.
So that's your little first bit of conflict.
It's not heavy conflict, but it's enough.
It makes it exciting for you, actually, because you were drawn to this game to fix up that
mansion.
You know, we're gamers, we like problems.
This is the developer presenting this,
look, here's a problem, it's a gift to you, now solve it.
The next thing we do is have a bad guy show up.
I know this seems like storytelling 101,
but a lot of developers don't have any bad guys
in their character set.
So when Tiffany fights back, conflict,
and his name is Rex Houston, of course.
And the fact that he has a claim on the mansion
because he was related to the person who gave it to you
threatens the very reason you were brought to this game,
right, to fix up that mansion.
So it's a little more than making the place pretty.
You are there to keep it from Rex
and keep it from being turned into a casino.
So it just gives you a little more motivation.
These are the hooks that draw the player into the game.
It also provides us a way to give a seamless name integration, which can be a little bit awkward in these mobile games.
So we've got this, and I usually use Dinglebutt, but I thought for this talk I would do something safer.
Now you don't always have to have, and we'll admit, this guy, mustache twitching villain, right?
A little obvious, but sometimes those obvious tropes, especially when you're doing something new, this game came out
three and a half years ago and in its genre it had no one had done it.
So we needed something a little obvious to kind of school those players into
you have a match theory game but you also have a story. Here's a villain. You know how this works.
And I'll admit that I'm influenced with boss horror.
So you don't have to have that though. Sometimes the bad guy isn't all bad.
And so we went a little further with the game Lily's Garden.
which in terms of revenue is just under matching to matching.
It came out in the spring of 2019
and it is making about $8 million in revenue.
And all of this is on the Censor Tower
so it's not like secret information.
This guy, Philip Jones, is not the most,
he actually has a mustache but he's not twitching it.
He's not so much of a, he is here to explain
that there's a little.
a special condition.
So you have to restore the entire garden to its former glory in 30 days.
And this is the way that a character who never appears on screen, she's a great aunt, reaches
from the grave.
you have to do the impossible.
So when this pans back and you see
the whole disheveled garden area,
you see that's a pretty tall order.
And of course there are other obstacles
that come across too.
So this guy is an interesting character
in that he's not gonna sabotage you or anything like that.
He isn't really on your side though.
He means business.
Another way that we deal with villains, I'm going to have Anthony talk about, is we started working on a game called Wild Things.
That was tons of fun.
And Wild Things, I can't give you numbers on it because it's only in soft launch.
But in this case, you can have an antagonist or a villain that is an elemental force, not an actual character that appears in the game.
In this case, a...
a storm arises and destroys the land, and that storm is part of that antagonist.
And you're attempting to stop the damage or repair the damage that's been done by this
storm that came out of nowhere.
And then, and so your role is as kind of this guardian angel kind of figure.
There are these spirit animals, and there are the right and there are the left.
And they choose you as a representative of the gods, so to speak, to go down into the wild lands and attempt to thwart the evil designs that are happening there.
And this is essentially your guide character, Mother Bear, who tells you what your task is.
You have to go down to the wild lands, you have to heal the land, and you have to heal the relationships between the parents.
Yes, so this is a new release game developed by Graphite Lab right here in St. Louis.
It's Roller Coaster Tycoon Story, the latest installment of a Roller Coaster Tycoon game.
As the name indicates, it's also their first title to have a moving out story.
What Graphite Lab did is when they came to us to write the story, they had a set of predetermined main characters.
But the one thing they were missing was the billing.
villain character that would be a central source of conflict with the park.
And that character up there is Sam, he's your guide character, much like Tiffany, Matthews,
and Manchin. He's speaking about a character named Lan Follari.
And this is a park that's been around the island for years, and Lan Follari has come in
and he is just wrecked it, he dumps his trash there, because he owns it, he owns it.
He doesn't care. And the big thing about Lan Follari
is that a lot of times in these games, you kind of start out the game with your guide character coming
across and meeting this
big antagonistic character.
But in this game, Sam has already known Lank O'Leary,
they've already been kind of duking it out for years.
And what really makes Lank O'Leary different
is that by the time the player starts the game,
the player has already beaten him.
Lank O'Leary's big thing is that he wants this park
for himself because he wants to turn it into a landfill.
But simply just by starting the game,
the player has already bought that park.
They've already beaten Lank O'Leary
by taking the park away from him,
making him at his most desperate
simply because he just started the game.
Anyway, Blair, he's this kind of central character, too,
where he's not immediately in the game at the start.
He's there, he's kind of pink jagged,
he sees piles of garbage.
So when he does show up, it's a pretty big impact.
That takes us to the next element of storytelling,
and that is mystery.
Continuing on with Rollercoaster Tycoon,
that was absolutely key to building that story,
which that's just a really common theme.
Yeah, so the other thing about...
these patterns that they blend a lot.
So not only does Rollercoaster Tycoon have its antagonists
and essential sorts of conflicts,
but those antagonists can overlap with the mystery,
which we see with another character I introduced
called the Phantom.
And the Phantom was my own personal Scooby-Doo-like villain,
some masked kind of Austrian character
that goes around sabotaging the park.
And he brings this source of mystery
because it's stretched out for so long.
little whispers, little people like, oh, do you see the phantom running around?
And sorry, the big thing though with the phantom is that you have this mascot character. We have
little Tyler right there. He's the big bumbling panda bear on the icon of the game. He's there
where you see the source of all fun and
love and inspiration of the park and by the end of the game you find out that Lil' Tyler
is the Phantom.
And you just go along with this big mystery, not only that he's the Phantom, but why?
And that's something that we discovered through playing the game itself.
So in Wildlands, the mystery of course is, you know,
wild lands, and why would it come from a positive.
In addition, right from the very beginning, Liam hints that he feels some sort of guilt
about it.
That he has some sort of, feels that he must have had some sort of role in the events.
And you don't know what that is, and that's one of the mysteries you're trying to resolve.
And you show up, and you are the keeper, which is the key.
disheveled and all dirty from the storm, and you introduce yourself to him, and that's
how you enter into that world.
Here we use the Sioux letter for the name.
So, better than the single letter.
So, when you're doing this, you're giving, you've got a whole layer of mysteries and
a lot of things, right?
Then after that, it's the question of Leansville.
What was Leansville in its events?
And what did he do, or what does he feel guilty about?
What went wrong in general?
Why did this come about?
Was there some force behind it?
Was there something that was done?
Was there some act on the part of the inhabitants?
And then what can you do as that role of keeper?
What can you do to repair the wildlands and relationship with the animals, with each other?
And finally, because very early on, Liam shows some fear from all over when he encounters
these spirits, as you begin to question, can these spirits really be trusted?
Do they have an alternate agenda?
Are there some good ones and some new ones?
What's that spirit realm like?
And finally, what is this world all about?
What is the central theme of this world?
What's going on?
So then there's the...
One interesting aspect of Wild Things that's a little bit different, and that is it produces
a hero that doesn't want you to solve the mystery, doesn't want the mystery to be solved.
So Liam, our hero, our main character, has his best, bestest buddy, Emma the elephant.
And Emma...
has no guilt whatsoever.
All she knows is something terrible happened to the world she lives in.
She wants to know who caused it, why did it happen, and how do we keep it from ever happening again?
So she comes to one of the encounters where people come across these turtles,
and they have a whole bunch of books from a library.
And she's like, hey, let's look through these books.
We can figure out what went on. We'll do some research.
But Liam doesn't really want anyone to figure out what happened, and so he deflects it.
He tells her, you know, that's really important, but our main goal here is to help out the
other creatures in the wild now, so we need to focus on that.
And these are our turtle characters, they are very slow, so because they're so slow
they usually only speak in one word, sentences, so these very long, evocative words, and that's
all you get from them.
But somehow they still manage to communicate.
You know, Liam says we should help the turtles, and the turtles are very sad because their
areas have been devastated, and Emma advises.
She's like, you're right, you're right.
Let's not do the research, let's help these turtles.
So then comes the role of another game I've worked on called Sweet Escapes.
And as the name suggests, this game is all about sweets, and making sweets, and eating
sweets.
And it follows a group of adorable talking animals as they go around going from sweet shop to sweet shop trying to fix things up.
But one of the differences in Sweetscapes is that it has this originally initially prominent like antagonistic character named Buzz.
And Buzz is the inspector. You know, he will not allow them to open the shop until he's approved it.
Which means case testing about everything they make and eating everything before they even have the chance.
And so the big difference about Buzz though is that he has a role of mystery because he has a
He's entirely own secret role. He's not just the inspector
He's something else and that's something that players eventually start to learn and find out by the end of the first season
Which flips Buzz back around to the other good guy side
Lastly we have connection
Which may not sound on the surface as something related to story, but just hang on there
First thing we notice is that characters connecting with each other is something that players value.
So in this instance, you'd be surprised how many players, even though they're drawn to this as a renovation game,
always choose meet the neighbors over laying more floor.
Part of that is because we're drawn to faces.
We gravitate toward photos of people rather than in animalogics and other things.
But it's also because this is a game.
that there are going to be other characters, that the world that we're playing in is people.
In this case, we've got Edna, who shows us a valuable lesson that connection can sometimes
be difficult.
She's not necessarily the friendliest neighbor on the block.
What this is doing is also introducing a feature into the game.
So remember at the beginning of the talk I talked about how the goal and the story or the gameplay and the story have to be
integrated together. So this is a really really good example in a top-tier game where that's happening to good effect.
So Edna comes in and it's an interesting quirky moment where you're getting to learn that this place is people with some
interesting characters you may be challenging.
But it's also introducing the feature
of visiting another person's mansion.
So here you have a random person that you can go visit.
And the story continues, though.
We have Edna and Tiffany getting to know each other.
We don't abandon this as writers
and have tutorial speak come in in this kind of dry way,
which is like, oh, here's what you're gonna do now.
We keep it related to the story.
Another way that characters can connect with each other is romance.
And this is something that can be a bit brave for a developer to try if you've never tried to do anything related to rom-com.
But it's something that resonates with players, especially when you've got a couple of quirky characters in which those difficulties become quickly apparent.
So in the case of Tiffany and Jack,
we start to see that Jack...
is much more enamored with his work than the mansion itself.
So there may not be a wrong answer.
But the idea that Tiffany or Jack could overcome this obstacle
of Jack's obsession with the mansion over Tiffany
is something that kind of fuels the play for quite a while in that game.
And now we'll talk about another kind of interaction
where the player actually gets to connect with the characters.
When we were first brought on Wild Things, this is one of the things that really, really
excited us about this project, is that generally speaking, when you're interacting with the
characters, you're building something for them, or maybe you're providing them direction
in some manner.
But in this case, in Wild Things, you need to actually directly interact with the characters.
So the very, very first thing that happens is you land in the Wild Things, and there's
fantastic...
angelic keeper being and there's poor Liam, he's been knocked unconscious from the storm,
he's totally dirty and shabby and the prompt is tap on Liam to revive him.
You have the little hand and you tap on him and he starts to shake and he coughs and sputters
and he wakes up. And that kind of interaction happens throughout the entire game, not with Liam,
not just with Liam, but all the other various animal characters that you get introduced to.
So after you've had your first interaction with Liam and you've done your first few builds,
then all of a sudden Liam says, wow, I'm really disheveled and dirty.
And you take Liam and you have, once again, you control this little scrub brush,
and you scrub him and lather him all up and he gets all foamy.
And then you rinse him off and he's all happy and shiny and he dances around
because he's very excited that you've gotten all clean.
And it's really great. It's amazing how you feel like you've really done something.
that you just like if you have a pet and you brush your pet and they're all happy, you
feel like you've actually interacted with this character.
And then, as I said, it's not just Liam.
There's a scene where Emma is really tired and she feels like she needs a break.
So you get a rubber ball and you get to throw the ball and it bounces around and she chases
it.
It's very, very cute and adorable.
And there's a scene with Emma on the skateboard and Liam does the break dancing.
We're always coming up with new things to add in. Oh, can we have the animals do this? Can we have the animals do that? Can we dress them up?
Whatever. So these interactions occur every single time you run through a chapter. You're going to get at least one of these, sometimes two.
So another way you can build a connection with these types of games is through humor.
The most humorous character in Sweet Escape is a penguin.
He eats sweets all the time.
And he has become such a popular character with the players of Swedish Games that he's started his own fanfiction.
Just for his weird comedic random helpers.
You know, like in this scene where he tried to vote himself mayor.
Scoops is a character that people laugh at just because he's so lovable.
He's such a goofball.
That by the time everyone was asking, like, hey, where's Scoops?
Or, hey, you know, I noticed he wasn't in the last contest.
It's like, why the heck wasn't he in the last contest?
He's just a source of humor and you really can't support it.
Sometimes though, a way to really, really make that connection, bring it home, is that
the success in connection is the actual win in the game.
So in this case, especially in Wild Things, one of the primary objectives is to bring
these animals back together.
You're encountering these various animals.
In this case, you've got a little family of meerkats.
This is Mimi and Melvin.
Mimi and Melvin are meerkats and they're six kids.
And...
Minky, Minky and Monkey.
I think that's what it is.
Monkey is a little monkey.
So, you've got the meerkat kids and the meerkats and they run this...
It's a mine but it's also a shop.
integrated, you do all these things to bring them back together, and it all culminates
in a big family dinner.
Because what could be more, we're a family again, than having a big family dinner.
You're actually invited to be with them and sit with them, oh man, that's a lovely family
dinner.
And so you've won that, you've completed the object of this arc, you've succeeded, you've
brought the family back together again, you're rewarded for that.
That's so long, I'm just going to talk to her, okay?
Thank you.
Another way we love to do that is through megajokes.
And especially me, I love my megajokes.
This is kind of one of those moments where we call out the main player as someone who isn't allowed to speak.
So the way a lot of the screen mechanics is pointing out that, yeah, you are the player, you are financially supporting all these characters,
you are the one fixing everything, but highlights the plot that you can't actually say anything to these characters.
At least not in this generation of film games.
So, last thing I want to point out, one of the things that we have the greatest impact on in
the title, Lily's Garden, was creating a sense of a character that never appears on screen.
So, your great aunt, who is the one who bequeathed you this garden that you have to restore,
never appears, but her story gets told through the things that you discover throughout the game.
And here's a photo, she's a very quirky person,
and so this idea of stinging to the bees,
which becomes actually one of the tasks
and the interactions and part of the restoration,
is absolutely embedded in her character.
So to sum up, we talked about three things,
and we actually used an acronym, CMC.
So just think Renegade and CMC.
Conflict, Mystery, and Connection,
these are the elements that we're always talking
to our developers about.
Conflict really does mean bad things happen, and that's okay.
You don't have to see people suffer.
I have a teacher who used to say,
torture your characters.
If nothing's happening,
Heaven is a place where nothing ever happens,
that's boring.
You want to give some kind of confluence,
you have to feel the lows in order to appreciate the highs.
You might meet a bad guy,
but the villain doesn't always have to be a bad guy.
The villain can be an antagonizing force.
Like that storm that Anthony was talking about, or this guy that killed in a panda suit that Dexter was talking about.
Sometimes the quest to solve a mystery can be thwarted by your own hero.
Sometimes the hero doesn't want to mystery you, and that's okay, and it could be an interesting
level of complexity.
Enhancing is a key opportunity for acquisition and intentioning amongst the player base.
Players should connect with the characters.
And sometimes that means romance, and sometimes it means absolutely nothing, but the opposite
of romance.
And the connection is ultimately the win.
It's the victory and success that are important in the game.
All right.
That concludes our talk.
Here's our website if you want to know more.
We're happy to stick around for questions, and I just want to thank...
Anthony and Dexter who literally practiced this this evening at 6 o'clock
as their only prep for this besides the fact that they worked on the games and just had that knowledge in them.
So I hope they did a good job.
Thank you so much.
Applause
Great.
Thank you.
Questions?
So, what do you guys use?
What's your process for writing the stories and creating the characters?
What is that? Do you do storyboards?
What does that process look like to come up with your ideas?
Yeah, it really depends on the client.
So sometimes a client comes to us with a game that they've tested and they're not having the results.
So in that case we have some semblance of story and characters that we need to then fix.
In other cases they come to us and they want to partner and collaborate and so
the roller coaster tycoon story, they had some idea already because obviously they'd have to
pitch and work with Atari to get the thing approved.
But Dexter and I sat down with the Graphite Lab team here in St. Louis and we talked about
the characters and then created the story arc.
So we helped them develop the characters and then we created the arc with them in collaboration,
which was a neat process.
We actually, this is outside these games, but we have worked on interactive novels as
well.
I've done four of them and Dexter's done one.
And with those, you know, it's really more like a novel.
So the writer comes up with it.
I mean, you still pitch and get approved,
and then you tweet based on feedback and stuff like that.
So you're still working with the developer,
especially on the gameplay integration with it.
Here's some ideas on how you might integrate that.
And then sometimes they'll just say,
thank you, that's all, here's a check,
and we'll have our own writer's board on that.
I know for a game like Swayze Gates,
some things we do, I sometimes have these documents
called H-O-V-E, high-level design documents.
So for Swayze Gates, I will plot out the story arcs
of each chapter, and I'll kind of make you
like 10 chapters in advance.
And then we share that document with the team,
and they'll go like, yeah, maybe like that,
and stuff, and flush it out from there first.
And then it's working on a project that has an approval from a very large, powerful company.
And then there's a whole other load in there.
Yeah, that IP.
So that means the client looks at it and gives us feedback.
And then the IP stakeholders, which could have a whole bureaucracy of their own,
have to also weigh in.
So that becomes a very large process.
So we've done the whole gamut.
We have, right now, we have literally one guy and a team in Ukraine.
of like writers, or artists, and programmers,
and it's a very small team,
like almost people working out of their garages,
all the way up to a very recognizable IP
with like Hollywood connections and serious bureaucracy.
So it's a, you never know.
Good question.
Yeah.
So if a client
If Client absolutely insisted that just based on the entire world of the gamer, it cannot be conflict, like,
uh, there's...
for whatever scenario that would be,
is it possible that if you just focused on connection history instead,
that could the weight of those two make up for the lack of conflict within the community?
is the classic mystery. We do have the client I've referred to. We're in a, right now we're
in a conversation in which we may fall on the side of, you know, we don't really want you
to add conflict, drama, real storytelling arcs. Instead what you get is like character vignettes,
which you can do. I play a lot of Farmville 1 and 2.
And if you have two, you'll know there's not a story in Fondle, but there's characters
and they have little backstory kind of things.
So those are vignettes.
I mean, nothing's happening.
It's not like, ooh, there was a conflict.
I had a fight with that person and now I got to do this.
None of that, but it's a vignette and maybe that's enough.
that book shows what keeps you until 3 a.m.
and suddenly you've watched seven episodes
and you don't know why, you get up and go to work.
You know, it's because of that book.
I worked in a previous life for Wizards of the Coast
and we had as a licensor a very, very large company
that was headed by a very powerful personality.
And they made it very, very clear that why
currently can you issue?
It depends on how many students at SLU.
We can broker students.
What are we working on right now?
So we have three for one client.
And then...
It really varies because of the scope.
So, like one client of ours currently we've been
working with for three years. So I started out
freelancing for them.
as a solo and then they kept adding games and then I was getting other games and so I built the team out and we're still working with them
and they have us on two regular ones right now. So anywhere from probably 5 to 20.
Yeah, one of the things that really varies wildly is that you can have a game that can easily take up 20 or 30 hours of a person's time a week.
And then you might have another one that's like, okay, here's five hours of work.
And then the next week it's five hours of work.
And the next week, and the next week, and the next week.
Or the short-term ones where they're like,
look, we know you guys are the experts
and we just want you to weigh in
on why this isn't performing in dark tasks.
So give us 40 hours to do an analysis.
In two weeks, right?
Do an analysis in two weeks.
And then they'll take.
So I'm a thousand levels into Matchington Mansion, and I'm still wondering, will Jack and Tiffany ever get together?
The moment they do, the game's over.
Yeah, I mean, think about like X-Files or Friends, you know?
Or Cheers.
Cheers, yeah.
getting together and break them up and get them together.
We have another one we're working on right now where it's like
there's two couples and they have parallel relationships
and sometimes crossing over and
yeah, it gets complicated.
Like I know, I think it's re-escaped so I'm happy about it.
You know that thousand level markers finally allowed them to be together
through the main characters but like the condition could be that they're not like official.
They have to be like, are there or are they not like the other thousand levels.
Yeah.
romance event.
That's right. It's been a number of levels.
We'll never get to that.
Yeah.
Cool.
Last question.
Thank you all.
Do you guys have certain
strategies for tying narrative
into different types of games, like say
a puzzle game versus like
you were saying, like the visual novel
sort of stuff. Do you guys have different strategies depending on
what genre of game and how you tie that into
Yeah, absolutely. I mean, not to be crass, but you know, if the games don't make money, we all go home and we don't have jobs.
So it has to do with monetization and in mobile games, especially free to play, the game is free.
So then you have to create all these different ways to have the game make money so that we can keep making the game, right?
It's like a chicken and egg thing.
So are these hybrid narrative builder games with a match three or a collapse mechanic?
You've got the monetization around the puzzle, and then how the tasks integrate with that,
and what cliffhangers you might set up.
That's definitely part of it.
In the interactive novels, it's ironic because even though those are so story-driven and
the content is so heavily story, if you play choices, you have to play choices.
So I wrote one of those, one called Failed Secrets, and what I learned from that is
too on another project where you're using story content to monetize and it
becomes very sticky, right? You don't want players to feel like they're
being niggled and dined or anything like that to get the story so there's a real
craft to creating a story and then building on extra experiences that
warrant the extra pay, right? The extra currency value.
So, this hasn't been released yet, this game, but it has been announced, so I think we can
just, in broad strokes, talk about it, which is marrying that narrative storyline with
a game mechanic so that you get two of those...
Choices with a matchstripe.
You can imagine that, right?
So that, the advantage of this is that you still might have premium choices.
course somewhere along the line you're just like, oh man I can get five more stars out of this game.
Just add a little more, just a dollar ninety-nine, you know, whatever. And in those sorts of games
there's an old saying that seems to be pretty true, it's the 80-20 rule. When I was teaching
at Webster I used to teach this, which is that in games like that, 80% of the people who play
your free game are not going to give you a dime, they're just going to grind it. But 20% will give
you some money.
Now of that 20%, it also breaks down 80-20.
80% of the people who give you money
will give you just enough to break even,
and all your profit is in that 20%, 20%.
Those are what they call the whales.
And those are the people who will spend
a very large amount of money on a regular basis.
And then there's the 80% who only spend a little bit,
but they add up.
But they add up too, yeah, that's what you break even.
I love it too, just depends on what type of genre audience you're going for.
Obviously when we get a game like Space Cage, it's going to be a lighthearted game with a lighthearted story,
and funny humor, whereas we get in a novel, it's like a fantasy, more graphic, more violent.