I'm Austin. I'm just going to dive right in here.
And as usual, my favorite part of this kind of thing
is in the discussion afterward.
And I kind of see my job as hopefully posing provocative
or interesting questions or ideas
that we can hash out in Q&A.
So I'm going to kind of blitz through things.
And at some point, I'll probably play a few seconds
of something and say, okay, moving on.
So if for some reason I cut off something that is of use to you or valuable,
please just scream at me and tell me to pause there,
because the whole point of doing any of this
is to share something that is hopefully meaningful and worth hearing.
And if I am circumventing that,
then I'm literally defeating my entire purpose on standing up here.
So, with that said,
last summer we shipped the third of a franchise that I had worked on for...
over six years called the Banner Saga.
That is a wonderful kind of case study
for the success of an indie,
a little fledgling indie that could.
They're one of the sort of flagship Kickstarter games
that I can't overstate the privilege
and joy of having worked on.
Out of curiosity, who here's played those games?
Oh, awesome.
Well, now I know it's like where the intersection of.
turn-based strategy and willing to wake up and be at a 9 a.m. talk exists.
Probably the entirety of that demographic is in this room.
So, okay, good.
I didn't want to spend too much time on the basics of the game
since we're here to talk about the music,
and especially I want to get into kind of the meta story,
the peripheral story around the score itself,
and make it...
about how we were able to do the things that we were able
as opposed to purely just kind of having a musical nerdiness
about themes and that sort of thing.
But we will do a taste of that.
So yes, it all started as a Kickstarter.
It was three guys from Bioware who had basically
gotten fed up with 10 years of working on the Old Republic
and said, we want to make our own thing.
And they quit their job and put this game on Kickstarter
and had the very lucky timing of putting it on Kickstarter.
right when that sort of 2012 magical gold rush happened.
They had already prepared the campaign
to hit the green light when Double Fine
announced their Kickstarter and sort of triggered
an explosion of interest.
And so they were already queued up ready to go
and just hit the button.
And then within 24 hours, they were 300% funding
or something like that.
And they were one of those kinds of stories.
And this was back in those naive, wonderful,
innocent days of 2012 when.
no one realized that there's like a 50-50 chance
that you'll give them all this money
and they'll actually make the game.
And so there was a lot of love and excitement going into it
and I was brought in, in the middle of their campaign
they called me and said, can we show you our game
and are you interested?
And I was blown away immediately.
For those of you who aren't familiar,
you know, this art style of the game
is one of the things that immediately
kind of announces itself to people
and I just thought this is just too fantastic.
So off we went.
an actual post-mortem.
And I'm just going to quickly give you some rundown of the score and the creative choices
that were made.
But I really want to focus on this kind of second point here of the logistical analysis
and how we were able to pragmatically achieve what we were.
The title of this talk is how to make indie sound AAA.
It was really, it was not easy, but at the same time,
it sort of was easy, and that's why I'm excited
to talk about it, and the big takeaway
that I'm just gonna repeat over and over and over
is about embracing your constraints.
It's about finding those things
that appear to be a limiting factor
and turning them into an enabler of ideas and of creativity.
and letting the specifics of that situation dictate your creative vocabulary so that it
becomes itself, it becomes the thing that it could have only been made under these circumstances
because ultimately that's, I think, the thing we're all chasing, especially as composers
at least, as artists in general, trying to make something that sort of is this magical
distillation of truth in that moment.
And so that's only achieved, I think, by...
embracing these constraints.
So I'm also gonna kinda skip around a little bit
amongst the three games and not do
kind of a chronological retelling of the trilogy.
So to start, the most obvious thing about this
is that it's music written for a wind ensemble.
This is a photo from our recording session
of the first game.
And so the first thing that's obvious
is this is not a recording studio that we did this in.
This was the Myerson Symphony Center in Dallas, Texas.
And that ensemble is the Dallas Winds.
At the time, they were called the Dallas Wind Symphony,
and then they decided they were sick
of getting confused with the Dallas Symphony.
And so, now they're the Dallas Winds.
And just for my fellow nerds,
I thought I'd throw in there what the instrumentation was
on those first sessions.
And so, quick story on how we got to this choice is
I had a good, solid two years.
I mean, of course, like all games,
it was supposed to be, you know,
we're gonna make it nine months.
Then six months in, it was like, well, OK, maybe a year.
And then as a year starts to approach, OK, well,
it's for sure going to be at least 18 months.
And then at 18 months, it's like, OK, we're
all about to be broke and homeless.
So two years it's going to be, regardless
of the state of the game.
And so I had a lot of time to think about it and mull it over.
And something that happened that was very fortunate
was, as a way to play test their turn-based strategy mechanics,
they created a free online multiplayer.
called Factions, that was basically just simple 1v1
playing of the game, and had no story or anything like that,
it was just kind of a tournament mode.
So I played that like 150 hours or something like that,
because I would be able to write music,
and then we'd bake it into the build,
and I could go on and play someone
and see how that music reacts
in an actual kind of live fire situation within an hour.
A lot of interesting things seemed to emerge,
and one of them early on was the actual palette.
We...
they had greenlit a really,
because their Kickstarter was so successful,
but the team was really small,
they had said, you know, we're willing to carve out
a pretty substantial amount of money for the score,
but that's all kind of abstract and hypothetical
until you know what kind of score you're gonna write.
So I just kind of said, well, you know,
it's Viking lore and it's about the end of the world,
and so, you know, let's start toying around
with something orchestral.
It's kind of generic to just assume it's going to be orchestra, but you know, I'm a believer that writing is in the rewriting.
So let's just start somewhere.
And if it's garbage, which it inevitably will be, we will start to modify it.
And so I started writing music.
And then at some point, I just kind of took a step back
and listened to it and realized,
you know, I'm not really using the strings.
They're sort of texturally like violins
holding some high notes.
It was all kind of brass corrals and things like that.
And I then had this flash to,
when I was in college at NYU,
there was a world premiere at Carnegie Hall
of John Corleano's third symphony
called the Circus Maximus, which was commissioned.
It was at the time, it was the largest,
I think it still might be, the largest.
wind ensemble commission ever. It's like a 45 minute symphony, all unbroken, continuous music.
for just the most unbelievably huge group.
You know, I love that it's like a 70-piece group,
but they don't have the 40 quiet ones
in the form of the strings.
So, you know, it's like 25 trumpets and 12 trombones
and 10,000 tubas or whatever, I don't know.
And it's all, it's very surround sound,
if any of you are familiar with the piece.
You know, the musicians are scattered
all throughout the hall,
and there's a whole drum corps behind you,
and it's a very immersive and crazy theatrical experience.
I was like 19 or something like that,
and as a composition student,
we were comped tickets to go see this,
and it rewrote my DNA.
It was the equivalent of Bruce Banner sitting there
and getting the gamma radiation burst,
where just afterward, I emerged,
I came smashing my way out of Carnegie Hall,
a fundamentally different composer,
after this experience of hearing that piece.
And because I was an orchestra kid
and a general sort of gamer nerd,
I wasn't one of those band nerds
who thought through this lens.
So, I had this flash of the power of a wind ensemble
remembering that experience, and so I thought,
you know, well, I could try to just do a session orchestra
of wind ensemble, but I thought,
what if I called the conductor of that piece
that I was at Carnegie Hall?
Why not?
Just see where that conversation goes.
And he's like the foremost conductor
for wind ensemble music, named Jerry Junkin,
who teaches at University of Texas, Austin,
and he also conducts one of the foremost.
if not the premier wind ensemble that's professional in the US,
because that's kind of a niche market, right?
Like I say, the premier wind ensemble, and it's like on a list of one.
But still, we'll give it to him.
He's a phenomenal conductor, and he's, as is normal in the wind ensemble world,
he's always commissioning composers and things like that,
because that world craves new music in stark contrast to the orchestra,
which is like, we like to cut things off around Mahler.
I just reached out to him and I said, you know, I'm working on a game and you kind of
changed my life with your Circus Maximus commission and performance at Carnegie Hall a number
of years ago, and I'm curious if there's an opportunity to work together.
I didn't know if he would even write back to my email, and he writes back like five
minutes later and says, let's jump on the phone.
This sounds super interesting.
And so it turned out that it was one of these pipe dreams of the ensemble.
They've released multiple albums, including Grammy nominated or winning albums in the
kind of classical categories.
But the idea of recording a score was one of those sort of pipe dreams that they never
anticipated could possibly be reality, but just they thought would be so cool.
And so it very quickly led to a conversation of, well, let's make this reality.
So obviously there's not an abundance of scoring stages in Dallas, turns out, and all their
albums that they've done have been in this hall, the Meyerson Center.
And so it was like, well, what would it take to record there?
Well, it turns out it's so not easy,
because this is a concert hall.
And this is a classic example where
I'm just kind of letting one conversation lead
to the next, to the next, to the next,
and creating all kinds of challenges,
but saying something will, novel and interesting,
is going to emerge out of this.
Or at least that's the hope as I kind of,
it's like Dr. Strangelove writing the nuke down,
just going, I'm sure this is going to be fine.
And, and so.
One thing I'm going to get to that is going to come up a lot
was that standard practice in a recording session situation,
obviously, is everyone's wearing headphones
and playing to a click.
And they were like, click?
What is this concept?
And it was like, well, to be able to have
a real strong consistency of duration,
especially if there's prelays involved, if I have any kind
of.
electronics or otherwise or multi-layering or if we need to stripe it because we're breaking it apart into
Layered, you know brass separate from percussion for implementation purposes or anything like that and they were like, hmm
Let me get back to you and I start getting these emails about how we found this really cool, you know
Wireless low wattage radio transmitter system and we can get a bunch of wireless headphones for the orchestra and I was immediately like
Yeah, this is a this is this is I'm watching two trains in slow motion heading towards each other
So I said
Tell you what, I'm gonna do this entire score
and not require a click.
That's the only way we're gonna get to the finish line here.
And so that single decision ended up being the foundation
for a lot of unusual things that came out of it
because the constraint was how can I record an ensemble
and do an effective game score
where there's no exact, precise consistency
between even subsequent takes.
of a given cue.
And that, as much as that closed certain doors, it opened up whole doors it never even considered
because it's always the default position to just assume you're gonna record certain ways.
So here's just a little taste of how that sounded.
That was easy.
So another thing I decided to really own is that it's the very opposite of a typical studio recording.
Normally, I'm a big fan of making recordings immersive, where you're deliberately kind of placing the listener inside the ensemble,
where you're giving them a hyper-real perspective that's not actually physically reproducible acoustically,
where you're getting all the detail of...
a barrage of microphones inside the orchestra,
and also your surrounds and your decantry
and all that kind of thing.
But in this case, we didn't really have that option.
So it's like, I'm gonna own the liveness of it.
I want, we're in a concert hall.
Let's kind of make that part of the group.
So it's very much about the ensemble sense,
which is the opposite of how I normally work.
But it led to certain aesthetic considerations.
So that's anyway, that's a little taste from
the very first game.
Another thing I'll just mention is, aesthetically about the game itself, there's a mournfulness
to it that I said I really want this to be very heavy emotionally, but not loud.
I'm not really expecting a loud score.
It should be about warriors who are begrudging the fact that they have to go into battle
and they're weary and they're tired.
story points is that the sun, one of the kind of symbols that the apocalypse has begun
is that the sun has come to a complete stop in the sky and they're just eternally in this kind of noon
daylight and everyone's just getting worn totally ragged by the fact that there's never night, there's never rest
and so the notion that these are
powerful warriors, Viking inspired kind of Norse
but they're not bloodlusting, every time they pick up their sword it's with this
massive sigh in resignation and I thought
you know, 50 musicians playing loud instruments,
you know, like we had multiple timpani,
you can kind of see in the back corner,
you know, we had a timpani section where I'd write a note
and two timpanists would play that note,
that kind of thing.
You get a big body of sound,
even if it's playing a pianissimo
and it just made everything feel really heavy.
I'm discovering a flaw in how I set this up,
where it's gonna try to replay my audio.
Skipping to the second and third games,
we stuck with this formula.
The second one, we migrated to Colorado.
There's whole stories about how we chose where
and all that kind of thing.
I'm not gonna get into that
because it's not really what I'm after here today.
Very similar but not quite identical instrumentation.
And you'll notice also, just for what it's worth,
for those who are band nerds,
we eschewed some of the normal wind ensemble traditions.
For example, the clarinets tend to be the violins
of the wind ensemble.
So a typical.
standard concert band would have like 20 clarinets and so everything just sounds like Sousa marches to me and I hate that and
So I was like we have a normal number of clarinets and I'm sorry to your 20 clarinets that aren't gonna get the call
And have to stay home, but it needs to sound more
orchestral and less
Sousa II but kept the saxophones because I thought you know everyone underrates how
Nasty a sax can get we you know it doesn't have to play jazz and it doesn't have to be
you know, an oompah, it doesn't have to be a lot of the things that it has sort of a
stereotypical reputation for
uh...
and uh... and especially for the second game
where the overall aesthetic got
way darker
And they can really play polyrhythms, which is super fun.
Orchestras tend to revolt.
The third score was done in London at AIR.
This was the only one that was done in a more traditional scoring sort of way, but the reason
I chose AIR over Abbey Road was because...
Air is kind of like a big hall.
It's basically a converted church.
And if you raise the ceiling all the way up
and you kind of make it as live as possible,
it has very similar acoustics.
And also the third one, we had a shorter schedule
and a tighter budget.
And so I actually had to record the entirety
of the orchestral parts of the score,
which was about an hour and 10 minutes of music
in a single, very fast-moving day.
And they can do that in London because they're not human.
And.
So, um, here's a taste of that.
Is that loud enough?
I feel like it should be.
like unfunctiply loud yeah can we are you able to raise it
All right.
That may be as loud as we can go.
The third one was also weirder, as you can hear.
So anyway, it gives you a sense.
So one of the things that ended up being unexpected and unintended
is that there's a kind of slight difference in the sound of each one,
because they were all recorded in different cities, different musicians.
There was not a hell of a lot of continuity, musician-wise,
with the exception of.
There's also a bunch of soloists, and the three that form the kind of heart and soul of it are these YouTube stars.
And part of the reason for that was that having come from Kickstarter, I thought this is a game birthed by the Internet.
This is a game that would never have existed without the kind of communal love of 20,000 initial Kickstarter backers who gave it close to a million dollars.
And so...
how better to kind of place at the heart and soul of it,
surrounded by the bombast and the heaviness
of the wind ensemble, is some singers and a single violin.
The one exception to the no strings policy
would be people whose career is also born of the internet.
The whole notion of a YouTube star
is so beautifully 21st century,
like Peter Hollens as an example,
who lives in Eugene, Oregon, and has,
Approaching 400 million views on his content 90% of which he makes in his living room
And he's just this spectacular
singer and around the time of this he had done a cover of the dwarf song the misty mountains from the
Hobbit film that I saw and was like I
Need this guy in my life. This is fucking beautiful and
And they're all and their videos like this, you know where he's doing the classic
Multitrack self-camera thing and he's just an amazing vocal producer
And then like I said, Taylor, for the one non-string exception.
And I told her, I said, you're going to probably feel uncomfortable,
but I want this to be very rustic and raw and live,
especially given the nature of how we're doing the wind ensemble.
So do you have like a practice violin from when you were a kid
that's just objectively not a good violin?
Can we use that?
And can you like tune it and get it perfect?
And then just sort of loose, just kind of randomly twiddle your tuning pegs.
Then we'll do it.
It was kind of like the...
You're going to be the reason my career ends, isn't it?
That's the look I got.
She did it.
It's awesome.
And then Maluka, who exploded onto YouTube
around that same time, she had done a cover of one
of the Bard songs from Skyrim.
And it's hilarious, because she's generally
pretty shy and very sweet.
And she didn't want to share this recording
and her now husband, which I guess
shows that there's a happy end to this story.
Spoiler.
She was at work one day and he put this video of her that she had made
Online and then went on reddit. It was like everyone check out this awesome cover
I found or something like that totally so she came home from work discovering
She was like a viral phenomenon and didn't have a chance to veto him
And because it's just astoundingly beautiful
I was gonna play you excerpts from all these but I know I'm gonna run out of time if I do so go look up
All of them if you're not already familiar. They're brilliant. I also had a quite a few additional
other solos. One of them that's cool is you can see this little instrument here that's
called the non-christian image. Oh, my mouse pointer doesn't show up over there. But the
horn there is called a bucca horn. It's one of the only kind of known Viking instruments
because there's not a lot known about Viking music. It's just one of those things that
archaeologists
have found instruments but there's no record of exactly what it sounded like.
Obviously there was no musical notation or anything like that.
And obviously also this is not explicitly a Viking game and even if it were, what's
the point of trying to do Viking music?
We want to make something that's a little bit more emotionally universal.
But I am a fan of kind of coloring it and sprinkling it in so it turns out the bucca horn
There's basically one guy in the world that makes them and it's effectively a lamb's horn
And it's like if you want one you have to order it a year in advance because he has to like raise the lamb and then
Do unspeakable things so my friend Noah who collect he's a trombone player who collects instruments
And and he was like I've always wanted to order one from this guy
And so I said he said how much time you have on this game, and I said
I've got at least a year.
And so, he said, OK, I'll check back in with you later.
And then one day he shows up with that thing.
And it's hilarious because it's horrible.
It's basically just a horn that's got holes drilled in it and a mouthpiece jammed on it.
And it can play like six notes and I love it and it's on all three scores.
And so...
Obviously we tracked some percussion.
Johan Sigurdsson was the voice actor from the game
who, he just sounds like a Viking.
And so he's just got this amazing,
like I have his original audition.
He's this Icelandic guy who's like,
my name is Johan, I'm reading for the Bangers saga.
And it was like, yeah, I don't read the lines.
Just, just when can we see you Monday?
And so I said, I really want to write vocals for this guy.
I hope to God he can't sing.
Because it's just going to be so gritty and awesome and delicious.
And of course he shows up and he picks up the part he's sight reading sheet music.
And I was like, what the hell?
That's such bullshit.
But he was amazing.
And just to compliment my YouTube people, and especially because Peter Hollens is like
the ultimate sort of pure acapella glee club, kind of very pure, specific.
The idea of it being even one cent sharp is horrible to him.
So I had to kind of pour salt all over that in the form of Johann.
And then ever in search of interesting X-factors, I have a friend who's a composer and a didgeridooist.
And so I just had him come over to the studio and I said, I really want to make kind of
all sorts of interesting, weird sounds there.
I played a little bit of accordion.
On the second game specifically you can see there was an Icelandic...
By the time we finished the first game and it went really well,
in the meantime this video had gone viral of these guys in Iceland
singing five-part a cappella in a train station, a hymn in Icelandic.
and they're a band called Arsteider that does music that,
to my ear, almost sounds like the band Kansas.
It's sort of like this beautiful, lyrical,
60s ballady sort of thing, but mostly in Icelandic,
and they all play strings and things,
and they produce insanely well,
and so I just cold called them,
and I said, I saw your video,
and you want to record on a game,
and they're all just like, all right.
They're so insanely chill, and I was,
glad you're excited and anyway I'll see you in a few months.
And so wrote a bunch of stuff for them.
In fact, the weird vocals that you heard
that were all processed and strange
in the last clip, that was from them.
And then on the third game added my friend Anthony
in Los Angeles who had just bought,
he's a bassoonist and he bought a bass Sarusaphone.
and sent me a photo of it because he knew that if he sent me a photo I would say,
I need to write for that. I don't know what it sounds like but it looks like a steampunk bassoon.
I mean it's the weirdest thing. It's all these pipes and key switches and it kind of sounds
like a baritone saxophone. It's about a really aggressive, it's just ugly as sin and perfect.
And then I also worked with a wonderful singer from the Faroe Islands named Ivor.
And then another, Kristen Naig, is Kristen hiding in here somewhere?
I will embarrass her extensively.
She knew to avoid this talk.
Kristen plays all the woodwinds.
I had worked with her on Abzu.
She's the featured oboist on that score.
But she plays.
So we created a cocktail.
I sent her a line and I said, will you...
record this melody on basically every instrument you have and send me all the stems.
And then I want to kind of create a composite instrument from some subset of that,
and then that will be our template for the score.
Because I wanted some new sound for the third game that had no precedent in the prior ones.
So what we ended up with was this blend where it would be the melody on English horn,
and then an octave higher than that on like an Irish penny whistle.
And I usually would put a huge amount of reverb and delay
so the penny whistle sounded more like overtones.
of the English horn. You couldn't really hear it on its own. And then, and then she had this
thing called a zafoon, which looks like a garden hose that someone put a mouthpiece on, and it's
just the weirdest sound ever. I'm pretty sure she made that up. And, but there was this nasally thing
that would show up in the stems that was just fantastic. A good, a good partner for the bass
sarousaphone.
And I'm blanking on what the fourth one was,
but we had this kind of little quartet
that everything I sent her would get recorded,
and then I had my sort of, I crafted a default setting
for all four of them to live in.
And then the last thing that is just always way too fun
to not make a point of is our friend Viking Jesus,
who it's actually coincidence
that he would be Viking Jesus,
but he is like a metal musician
who I met through the world of Video Games Live.
Tommy Tallarico and he had done a journey cover of a metal cover of Journey
burning sand and
It was awesome. And so I was like I want to I want to work with him
I need him in my life. And so I wasn't quite sure how to do that
And I thought what about prepared electric guitar, so I'm just gonna if you'll indulge I'm gonna just show you
We did a little kind of behind-the-scenes thing for you
And it's better to just show it in detail.
So in spring of 2012, he went to town and I said,
bring me a giant toolkit of things that I could use. ♪♪♪
Then we decided, what if we went totally over the top,
and you literally sawed this thing in half as a sound?
The sound of you literally cutting through this thing.
And he did!
And I love how he left all of his shit on the desk, so part of the recording is all the crap vibrating.
So that all that crunk crinkling and that's all the guitar.
I mean he sent me a huge amount of stuff and I created a whole kind of effects library out of it.
You'll see it's, and there's Malucca, and there's the sawing.
So that gives you a kind of a sense, and the reason I'm spending a fair bit of time talking
about that is a point that I'm going to get to later in sort of spoiler now.
is the idea of embracing constraint.
Our budget really was quite narrow.
And so I knew I couldn't write like two hours
of orchestral music.
There wasn't enough in the budget
to record the orchestra for two hours.
So you have all these variables
that you could start sliding up and down.
And so one of the choices was,
well, I could do like a small orchestra
for the full length of the score,
or I can save that for the sort of most crucial moments
and figure out ways to bridge the gaps with other.
sounds. And the idea is always to make sure that the score doesn't feel like it's got this schizophrenic
sort of square wave of production value where from one moment it sounds great and it's big live ensemble
and then the next moment it's like sampled trombones or something.
And so by crafting an aesthetic built around things like soloists and
prepared electric guitar being sawed in half.
the score could have ways of distributing itself
over a large amount of time,
where it just sounds like itself at any given moment.
You know, it has intimate moments,
which are marked by just hearing this guitar craziness,
and a single voice.
And you don't listen to that and think,
wow, but where's the orchestra?
Suddenly, it just is organically the next cue.
It just makes sense.
And you have to build it that way from the beginning.
But it's a great way to make the resources
just go all the way to the finish line.
And so I wanted to get a little bit on kind of the nerdy subject,
because this was a really lucky situation where they were planning to make a trilogy.
Of course, it was all contingent on the first game doing well,
because the Kickstarter was sort of genuinely that.
It was a kickstart of this franchise.
We didn't know if it was gonna come off,
but the thing that was so exciting
was that they knew what they wanted this story
to be from the beginning.
So I had my very first meeting with them
in the days after the Kickstarter ended,
where they said, okay, here's how game one is gonna end.
Here's what's gonna happen in game number two,
and here's what's gonna happen in game number three.
And I was able to kind of plant seeds
melodically and thematically from the beginning
that I knew weren't gonna be paying off
for five years or something like that,
if, you know, sort of God willing, as it were.
So just to give you a little sense of.
of that. Here's how the main theme was treated at the beginning of the first game. Purely
the horns and then the rest of the brass. I don't know how readable that is, but it
gives you a sense. Like I said, I was very drawn to this kind of brass chorale vibe.
So, you know, very deliberate, kind of regal, noble, slightly mournful quality.
So then, moving along, by the time the second game comes along, same theme, but, you know,
shit's worse.
We have Taylor as part of the main title now.
So, you know, things didn't go that great at the end of the first game.
But the good news is it gets even worse.
So, third game, I started... it took me a while to figure out what to do here.
So I start off with the recording of the first game.
And then I kind of send it down the drain.
So right now you're hearing purely relays effectively.
And then here's my little quartet of Kristen layers.
Our weird hybrid composite wind instrument.
This one, of course, just gets even.
So what was so cool is I was able to think about this stuff for like five or six years,
which is very lucky, but that's, you know, not that uncommon for the indie world, which
is useful, because it lets me think about how to optimize it to just be as grand and
lush and itself as possible.
And then so jumping off of that, big spoiler.
The thing that was so interesting to me was that this story that was purporting itself
or representing itself as kind of like a Viking apocalypse, you know, Ragnarok kind of thing,
by the time you get to the end of the third game, you realize it's actually kind of like
this Romeo and Juliet condemned love story.
And you had almost no indication of that in the first game, and then little teases of
it in the second, and then finally that's sort of an operating factor in the third game.
And so I thought, well, what if the main theme, this sort of statement of...
brawniness and regal nobility and all of that.
What if that's actually the foundation
of the thematic evolution that by the end
has to become this other thing?
And so I knew I would have almost no use for this
within the context of the first game,
but thought I have to write a theme
that I know can go there eventually.
So you obviously just heard the main theme.
Very simple little bum, bum, bum, bum, bum, bum.
So the first time you really in earnest hear
what I'm gonna do with it is in the second.
in the end credits. Here's a variation on that melody that Malouka sings.
It's a little different though.
So it gives you a se- so then by the time the second game comes along, there's two characters that are
you know, essentially pretending to not really know each other that well in a way and later it turns out like their kind of secret
Love is what's essentially causing the apocalypse
typical and uh, so um, so here's the like there's a scene where they're fighting and I was like, let's use that
And then so by the time of the third game, you have...
you know that's just all the cards end up on the table and you end up with this
this you know this this thing that began
very regal and noble and then has become very kind of
full of love and then corrupted to all hell
And then by the time we reach the end credits of the third game, it all has to kind of come
full circle.
You can hear this common ingredient that's going from one way, and this is happening
in other places, but I'm skipping a lot of stuff.
Another thing to talk about is that, again, the intersection of where logistical and pragmatic
constraints meet creativity and creative decision-making is how we end up making things just become
what they are and that optimize the situation.
So again, embracing the constraints.
I'm going to say it many more times.
And the fact that the score became so broadly aleatoric is...
is part of this because I mentioned before I couldn't record with clicks,
which meant that every time there was a kind of a layering system
where energy level is getting more crazy in the middle of combat,
I didn't have a good way to pivot amongst these layers
because I knew they wouldn't actually be able to loop and sync and crossfade
and do the traditional things that we would do.
And so it became like, well, what if I just created,
I just did after we recorded the main cues,
I took 20 minutes and recorded a whole library of custom
sort of aleatoric clouds and effects.
that I could use to smear these very imprecise transitions
from one performance and one take to another.
And then it just became like,
well, I think just aleatory can be kind of
an aesthetic mainstay of the score itself.
In fact, I remember someone on Twitter wrote something like,
it's as if,
how'd they phrase it?
It was like, it was as if Lord of the Rings
had a baby with the Matrix or something like that,
which was awesome.
And so, to give you an example of an extreme,
In this queue, you can hear how it all flies together.
This here is what you're about to hear.
So like the trumpets, for example, this gesture.
Winds.
And there's that melody again.
So yeah, you can also see that by the third game,
I'd also kind of abandoned the idea of it's quiet and somber
and it's heavy without being loud.
It's like, ah, fuck that.
Fortissimo.
And so just a quick notion of how we implemented it.
I already just kind of touched on that.
But because we couldn't do traditional sort
of stacked stems and layerings and the kind of things
that we would typically do in a game like this,
had to come up with another system.
But then also, the gameplay itself really informed what to do here,
because I playtested the game, as I mentioned earlier, quite extensively.
And one of the things that I realized is that, especially the combat,
where most of this discussion is taking place,
happens in a very slow way.
It's not a real-time thing.
It's turn-based strategy, and it very much moves...
It's unlike, say, XCOM, which is, in my opinion,
XCOM is basically turn-based strategy, the new one.
the new reboot recently, the last few years.
It's essentially turn-based strategy trying to convince you that it's real-time.
Because, you know, it's like the score is super turbo-charged
and the animations have really quick cycles
and it's trying to be as, you know, sort of StarCraft-y or whatever as possible,
in my estimation.
And Bannersaga said, no, let's go for something more methodical.
So this is sort of what it looks like to play combat in the game.
No?
Yeah, OK, I'll click that.
It's not an exciting thing to watch, probably not
good for Twitch streaming.
And so I realized that if the music is overly agitated
and overly crazy, it's really going
against the sort of inward and introspective thing
that you're experiencing.
And then also, it's all very algorithmic.
And very specifically, it's arithmetic.
There's very simple 5 plus 4 sort of math
underneath the hood driving the in-game stats, which is what
we hooked all the music to.
not gonna get crazy into that right now but the bottom line is that we were able
to track using very simple metrics if the player is effectively winning or
losing at any given moment and wrap the implementation around that well the thing
is if someone spends five minutes trying to make a decision about their next move
and they click it and the system instantly knows even before the
animation fully plays itself out if they are now
Losing or winning and if that was sort of a good decision. So if the music
Immediately gives feedback on that. It's actually extremely distracting because you spend all this time and then decide, okay
You know what? I'm gonna rotate this here and if the system immediately is like, ah, you done fuck up you're sitting there like well shit
I yeah, you need you need it to unfold more gradually so that it's an emergent sort of gut feeling and so I realized
We should very rarely ever pivot in the middle of this sort of cycle of the loop.
So think of it more like a turnstile where you make a decision and downstream the track clicks to the left or to the right
depending on where it's going to go next, but the loop had to play itself entirely out.
And so the reason I brought up the...
lack of click track so many times is it led to a thing like this.
So I would create multi-layered cues,
but we would have to record different performances of it,
not just stack.
So here's a combat cue from the end of the first game
where it's built very much around the bassoons.
Because, you know, when am I ever going to get to do that again?
So that, you heard, like, I kind of was talking over it,
but you get this, this, uh...
Uh...
Behave yourself.
It's kind of understated.
Alright, okay, so then layer two, I had the charts marked, you can kind of see, it says
layer two on the conductor score.
So I would tell the musicians, if it says layer two, don't play this next take.
We're doing layer one.
And so they would just sit there.
And then come do layer two, and now, you know, the trumpets...
It's trying to get ahead of me.
The trumpets become the dominant chattering voice, but you'll notice the bassoons are still there. It's not a stem
They're just playing a little more quietly now because they know they're not in charge
So I'm able to actually shape it musically, which was really cool
And then of course that by the time you get to the third layer
You get the idea.
So it led to a lot of, that whole concept led to all kinds of choices that would never
in a million years have made.
I'm going to skip some things because I really don't want to run out of time and I really
don't want to run out of time for questions and I'm already flirting with both of those
things rather dramatically.
So I want to pivot to the logistic side and do a real crash course.
So I will open up the hood here fairly transparently.
Of course I leave off specific numbers.
This is the budget on the first game that I had to work with.
This is my music budget.
And you'll see I spent solidly half the money on hiring the orchestra.
And I pulled all kinds of favors on this.
I parlayed all kinds of favors to make this happen.
Because we were, like I said, this is an indie game financed on Kickstarter.
You know, there are AAA games whose music budget dwarfs the entire budget.
of what this game had to offer.
But they did give me a kind of disproportionate amount of there.
I mean, I had a six-figure number to work with,
which was very outsized relative to the proportion
one would typically have.
But here was the thing is I realized as much as they were offering,
there wasn't enough to do a big, grandiose score,
unless I was willing to not get paid.
And so I basically said...
here's the gamble I'm gonna make.
I'm gonna make an exclusively back-end deal
with these guys, and we'll put everything
that they have to offer into the production of the score,
so that I'm taking the exact same risk
that they are as developers,
because these guys put all of their savings
for two years into making this project.
They received zero money.
They used none of the Kickstarter money
to pay for their life expenses,
and all three of these guys were married,
had families, children in school, all that kind of stuff,
and they said, now we're all in,
and I have this philosophical idea
of not wanting to be.
living a different life from the people I'm collaborating with.
And so I thought, well, if they pay me and I'm very comfortable and luxuriously off of
their Kickstarter money, and they're all meanwhile saying, if this game fails, we have to like
go flip burgers or something.
Because they burned their bridges in their previous job, and they put all their eggs
in this basket.
So I said, I think the score should live in that same headspace.
So it was like, OK.
give me a profit participation, a revenue share on the game itself,
and total control over the soundtrack album,
and in exchange, every single dime, and as it turns out, more than that,
because I just get overexcited and start putting my own money into the score,
is going to go into making this thing sound as great as it possibly can.
But the first one was still a very tight situation,
so I'm pulling all kinds of favors,
which is why the orchestra so heavily dominates.
By the time we get to the second one...
Had a little bit more to work with and also the first game did really really well
And so it emboldened this strategy, so I said guys same proposition
And so but this time things were a little bit more balanced. You'll see the soloists are you know a sizable punch
Something I always am telling people never ever ever under budget this big yellow one at the bottom music prep the sheer amount of copying
And part prep and librarian work
Never, never under budget that.
That's exactly how things go to hell on the scoring stage,
especially on a thing like this where you're recording with non-traditional ensembles.
You know, in London, they have an infrastructure,
but Colorado Symphony and the Dallas Wind Symphony,
you have to show up with your shit together really, really, really solidly,
or it will go to hell because no one there can help you.
They are clueless and it's like,
just sit down and play the notes and I have to handle everything else.
And the third game in London obviously we were able to do things, this is a little bit
more of a traditional make up but it was a similar kind of proportion.
And so it gives you a sense, the entire thing was predicated on taking this risk with these
guys.
Now I'm fully aware that not everyone is going to necessarily be in the same position to
be able to do that but, so you know, you do you.
No coercion meant or suggested, and no, I'm not trying to say this is how it ought to be done.
In fact, I'm sure there are composer colleagues of mine that would say what I did was sort
of professionally irresponsible because it creates the precedent that I would.
effectively work for free except that I would challenge that and say I was not
working for free at all I damn well expected to get that profit
participation especially because I believed in the game I thought they were
making something really brilliant and I said I'm willing to take this ride with
you and in exchange let's put the you know however many many tens of thousands
that you're willing to spend on the score I want all of that to be heard
through the speakers because that's going to be how this game is what you're
doing the equivalent of in your art direction and in your game mechanics and
all that's how to make it
come to life. And you know, three for three games, it was a wise decision.
In fact, the first one did so well that if I had pocketed 100% of the money and done it all with samples,
I would have made less.
And so, not the case with the other two, but you never know what's going to happen with these things.
And so they were razor-thin margins. I had to pull a lot of favors on all three games.
But I think it was worth it because at the end of the day,
I care more about having a final product that I'm really, really...
proud of. To give you an example of the kind of deal that was made is the orchestra in
Dallas, they had a recording engineer they had a long history with and a record label
that they had done albums with. So I went to them and I said, look, I can't really afford
to pay your engineer. I have no extra budget for your engineering crew. So how about this?
If you front those costs, your label gets to release the soundtrack album and you will
make 100% of the initial
however much, whatever it takes to recoup your engineering costs plus interest.
Then from that point, it's stair steps until eventually we're 50-50 partners.
So that I'm incentivizing them to sell the hell out of this album and they're joining
the risk with me.
And they said, absolutely, let's do it.
And the really cool thing with that was that they do these super high fidelity surround
sound albums and 192K ridiculous...
ultra-detailed classical recordings,
and so as part of their normal marketing,
they sent it out to all these audiophile sites.
And so to this day, I get Google alerts
of the Banner Saga being reviewed on websites
that know nothing about games,
but they're like, they're saying,
this album just sounds really great,
and we're reviewing,
and there's one reviewer in particular
that reviews speaker systems,
and he always uses this album as his test.
So it keeps showing up in reviews years and years later
because of the nature of that deal that I made,
and that's.
When it comes to this notion of how to make indie sound triple A, I'm always looking,
if I'm on a project like this, always looking for what's every opportunity, who are the
people involved, what talents do they bring, and how do we mutually incentivize each other
to bring something to the table where we can all do really well.
This is all based on the philosophical precept that everyone is willing to take on risk,
and for some people that's not possible, and for some people that's not interesting.
They would rather just get paid.
If that person has to be involved,
then you carve out more money for them than the rest,
and then everybody else gets to join
in potentially a greater windfall later,
that kind of thing.
And the results of course let you create something that you couldn't just write checks and make it happen.
There's just not enough money.
The resources on Banner Saga 3 for example had to write close to two hours of score.
And like I said, I had one day in the studio at air.
So I said, okay, I'm going to be able to get about an hour and ten music,
which is an insane pace to do in a single day.
But like I said, aforementioned, London musicians are not human.
And that time I was like, yeah, we're gonna use a click.
We're gonna speed this process up a bit.
But I told them, you know,
we're gonna make this very ensembly, but we gotta move.
And so then it's like,
how do I get another almost hour of music out of this?
And that's how you bring all those other strategies of,
well, if I just hear a singer alone acapella for a minute.
you can create a really evocative and interesting piece of music and no player says,
where's the orchestra? This is so cheap.
You don't have that problem.
So I was able to parse things out,
which is a lesson I had first learned on journey really.
So built around these cello solos with a very limited orchestral budget,
but didn't really internalize till here.
So anyway, I know I'm moving very quickly and haphazardly,
but I just wanted to share some of these things because I
really I was changed as a composer in person by working on this.
Franchise I think that these guys who made it are
Really really really amazing people and really amazing game developers, and it was really privileged
experience to work with them and
so that's why for me the big takeaway of
Diving in and meeting them at the same level of their risk and just saying okay screw it
No one here is getting paid unless it does well
Let's all just try to make something beautiful together
I ended up being one of the best experiences I've ever had may may may never be taught frankly
It was so creatively free and
and wonderful and predicated on doing this, but as a result was able to make Indy sound
at least quasi AAA. With that said, I have a few minutes to take any questions. I have
less time than I would like, so if there's anything, I know we have a mic here, and I'm
happy to dive straight into it. And if you ask no questions, it means I have utterly
failed to be provocative and say anything interesting, and I expect your reviews to
reflect that fact.
So, all right, kicking it off.
Hi, thanks.
This was great.
So for Banner Saga 3, did you say for that,
you did use a click?
Yeah.
Just for sake of efficiency.
And just random detail, I noticed
that you had fewer clarinets.
more bassoons for that? I'm just curious if that was a creative decision.
I had, well every penny counted, so I had to make a few decisions where I limited very
specific things just to kind of shrink where I could. You know, I had only one timpanist,
for example, that kind of thing. But that was just, like, where can I make a cut that's,
you know, in aggregate will show up and help but won't really affect the overall sound,
especially if I write conscientiously to avoid duplicating gestures. And so yeah, it was a couple
Generally the same, but a couple little differences.
Yeah, cool, thanks.
Yeah, of course.
Hi, thanks for the amazing talk.
I really liked the bit about where you got
all these weird instruments in.
So I just wanted to ask, do you have ideas
and then the instruments come in?
Or do these instruments then dictate your ideas?
And if that can ever be negative.
just because you have this crazy horn,
do you have to then use it?
Yeah, right.
And it's a good question,
because the corollary question that comes up a lot is,
do you write to the strengths of your sample libraries,
or do you write trying to make the samples
transcend themselves,
knowing that the mock-up may suffer as a result?
And I'm a big fan of not limiting,
the tools are there, truly as tools,
let your imagination be as unbridled as possible.
But there's no question that,
if it's a super esoteric instrument,
it will do things better than other things.
So if I just write for it in some abstract way, absent what it does best, I may not be
using it to its most effective capacity.
Of course I may also be missing the opportunity...
I think if Stravinsky had regarded the bassoon
in only its stereotypical way,
we would never have had the opening of The Rite of Spring,
which no one had ever heard a bassoon really play
that high and gently and weirdly lyrically like that.
And so it's sort of a tug of war between these two poles.
In the specific case, for example, of the bucca horn,
the weird lamb's horn, I think, and literally,
it only plays a kind of quasi-modal F-sharp minor
that is not at all based around like an A440-derived.
It's just kind of like, yeah, this is the closest note to F sharp that I would call that sound.
And so yes, I very quickly realized I have to write to what this thing can do.
Because I can, one note wrong, if I write a G natural, he'll go, I can't do it.
You know, so that very much did dictate a lot of what I was doing in certain areas.
And then in others, you know, I did every once in a while say, I'm going to cheat
and melodyne this thing to be what it needs to be.
and record it, I'd write it half step off from where I wanted it and then just nudge it, that kind of thing.
Move it in its entirety so it's still all weird and out of tune, but it's just weird and out of tune in like G minor instead of F sharp minor.
So yeah, does that kind of answer your question?
Yeah, thank you.
Good, thank you.
Thank you. Did the conductor also not have a click?
So it varied. On the first game, basically, I split the conducting in half with Jerry.
and I did all the rest of it myself on the second and third.
On the second one, I did have a click,
but the musicians did not,
and on the third one, everybody did.
So it was kind of like every possible scenario of none,
conductor only, everybody.
Okay, and the first one too, no click?
Yeah, not really.
I mean, we did run a cable out to the booth,
but half the time I would, and I'd just say screw it,
it's just too, I would rather be more present
with the musicians and just do this that way,
own this environment, own this situation
instead of trying to be half in one world
and half in another.
Cool, thank you.
Yeah, sure.
This is a question about budgets in general.
How much do you feel like the audio budget should be out of a total production budget
for indie up to AAA and does that percentage change?
Indie up to AAA?
Good lord.
Is this like the start of hour two of my talk?
No, like what's the range?
Like would you go from 10% for indie up to like 30% for...
I hear people...
I...
My answer to that is always I'll take what you got.
Because frankly...
I'm not making their game.
I don't consider it my place to tell them how to spend their money because they have
a thousand mouths to feed.
And so, you know, on a game like this, for example, the art direction is extremely tedious
to make.
And so they're going to need, you know, a few support artists around the main guy working
around the clock.
It's just, and it's a game that the art style is.
why people end up noticing it. And so, should, you know,
theoretically, the art budget should dwarf the music budget because it's why anyone's gonna care. And so,
those kinds of decisions are the things that they are grappling with, and I always say to them, you know,
You, you know, I will work within what you've got.
I mean, that's kind of the main MO of the talk, right?
Like, if you tell me you only have $100 to produce the score
and it's something that I feel like I have to be part of this,
then it's like, okay, $100,
there's a lot you can do with $100.
You just gotta figure out what it is, you know?
Immediately, first thought is grab the Zoom recorder
and start making weird sounds
and do things that don't cost that much, you know?
Don't require a big orchestra, that kind of thing.
So yeah, to me, it's, there's no one size fits all.
Every single production, it can even be literally like,
you know.
Far Cry 3 versus Far Cry 4 don't even have to be beholden to the same idea of how much
the music budget should be.
Even within large-scale production, AAA, and one sequel to the next, things can change
dramatically.
I'm okay.
I don't prescribe it.
I'm like, you need to spend more money.
The one thing that was unusual about this situation is on the first game, because of
the Kickstarter, they brought me on halfway through.
So I said to them,
if we make music-specific rewards for the Kickstarter,
can we funnel that money specifically to the score?
So they had a baseline amount that they were basically willing to guarantee me,
and then I offered things like, during the recording session,
you can get a signed part by a member of the orchestra who played.
I didn't think anyone would care about that.
It's like 100 bucks for, you know, the third clarinetist's 4am 25 page 4.
And people, we made like thousands of dollars worth of selling, it was actually, it took
like a lot of, the musicians had to stay quite a bit after the session, sitting there like
god damn.
Actually, they thought it was really cool.
And so that, we were able to funnel more money into the score based on that kind of arrangement
because it was like, okay, well, you know, they basically said, we'll do it, now it's
on you, go sell that.
So like on Twitter begging, please support this and it helped that Journey had come out
like a month later.
So there was a bit of a fervor going on.
And so yeah, anyway, I don't know if that fully answers your question,
but I don't believe in prescriptive budgeting.
Thanks.
My name is Jasmine.
I want to say thank you for this talk.
I really enjoyed it.
I found what you said about putting all the money into production very commendable.
because I'm kind of in a similar position now,
and I wanted to ask you, were you in a position
that allowed you to do that?
Or did you have other projects going on at the time
that enabled you to be able to funnel all of that music,
all that funding into the music aspect of Banner Saga?
Yeah, absolutely, yes.
I mean, it's a two-year period.
I definitely had other projects that I was doing
that were an essential part of the ecosystem of why,
you end up kind of in a Ponzi scheme with yourself,
sort of taking from here and giving it there.
But, you know, I don't think any of us got into this career with the idea being that
it's all going to be very straightforward and easy and 9 to 5 Monday to Friday.
Like I'm in it for the rough and tumble.
And so the idea was, yeah, this is a super high risk.
I'm turning down a lot of potential money up front in exchange for something that hopefully
is vastly more beautiful.
and far more fitting to the game.
It's something that, it's like I feel professionally obligated to do this in a way
because my goal is to make something that is perfect as I can make it for that game in this context.
And this path is the only way I can see to get there.
So it's not even that I want to, it's I feel a certain obligation that I have to.
And, but, yes.
completely and totally is predicated on having been gainfully employed in parallel to that.
And that can be a balancing act because you obviously don't want to shortchange the amount
of time you're spending on this huge risk because then it's like you're cutting your
own idea off at the knees if you're so busy with other stuff that this project that you're
taking this huge gamble on, you don't have the time to actually really flesh out.
So I was very lucky that I was able to survive and I was living okay.
but able to spend enormous amounts of time.
I mean, my Steam build of the game says I have like 300 hours
of playing the game or something like that
because I would just every single day try to figure out
how to break it and make the music better
and just learn more of the lore.
And I'm like a huge fanboy for the game now.
I'm like one of those Tolkien weirdos about their thing
where I'm like, oh, you know that part of the map
where there's, what is that all about?
And they're like, just let it go, man.
And so.
Or they're probably at a point where they're like, we don't even know.
Just go start a fucking wiki yourself and put your own theories.
So yeah, anyway, yes, the answer is for sure.
And that's why I say I'm not trying to prescribe this as this is how it must be done because
I know I was in a very fortunate position to be able to do that.
But that's how I was able to make.
Indie Sound AAA.
I used everything on the table in my life in general
to make that happen, including letting this project
over here finance that project over there,
that kind of thing.
My lifestyle during that project, that sort of thing.
Okay, all right, thank you, I appreciate it.
My pleasure.
I think I'm out of time,
so that was our grand finale question.
Thank you all.