Hi everyone.
My name is Michael Molinari,
developer of a failed game called CityStream,
an experimental live game launched in January 2016,
lasting for a whopping two months before we shut it down.
While this is a talk about the ultimate failure of the game,
there were many interesting things that came out of it,
so I'd like to cover those as well
to help paint a clearer picture of its history.
CityStream was a strange combination of idle games, Twitch Plays games, and real-time DMing.
It was created as a way to counter the experience of earlier Twitch Plays games like Twitch
Plays Pokemon or our previous game, Choice Chamber.
The game was still played via the chatroom of a live internet broadcast, but this time
the aim was to make each player's actions feel like they mattered, no matter how many
concurrent active players there were.
While the game's potential popularity was unknown before launch, we still prepared the
engine to be able to handle thousands of simultaneous players using staggered update cycles and
accelerated variables to compensate.
Our peak player count was around 100, so things never quite took off as we had hoped.
In the previous game we made, Choice Chamber, we added a few viewer interactions that celebrated
individuals.
While they were small successes, we wanted to make a game that championed every action
of every player, making anyone's efforts feel worthwhile.
The most obvious design change was to almost completely remove timed polls and instead
allow players to interact at their own pace, performing tasks as they saw fit.
This ended up being realized as a collaborative city-building game with elements of tower
defense and RPGs.
Each player had their own avatar, responsibilities, stats, and inventory, persistent across play
sessions, and all saved locally on our host machine.
Saving all data to a single file wasn't a very safe or smart method, as crashes and
bugs forced us to keep a daily backup should the world state need to be rolled back.
In one case, some players exploited a glitch overnight for which they apologized the following
morning.
The saved data needed to be rechecked against the previous days to roll back specific players
as a punishment for abusing a broken feature.
While the idea of a job wasn't formally assigned, most players took responsibility for what
they did best, forming a community that did in fact work together as a team.
There was even a player that was present at every stream, every day, for two straight
months.
This isn't to say any given player did one thing while playing, but enough time playing
with the same group of people allowed them to become quite efficient.
Since the game was played from the Twitch chat, there was no additional software to
download, no additional logins to create, and no cost to play.
This low bar for entry excited us, though we soon realized such a feature was relatively
lackluster when the game itself had troubles getting people excited.
Most importantly, it was only playable from one channel,
ours, giving us full control over how and when people
experience the game.
This was especially useful in monetizing the experience
for those who wanted to help support development.
It's not uncommon for a Twitch viewer to want to
continually pay money directly to a broadcaster
to not only show support, but to make sure they can
continue doing what they do.
Players who made contributions were rewarded directly in the game in real time.
Most perks were cosmetic as a way of literally showing support, though there were some perks
that acted as super attacks during battle.
In those instances, the super attack would benefit all players, not just the contributor,
helping to cement the idea of this being a team effort.
We didn't want a player to feel like they were inferior because they couldn't afford
to spend as much money as someone else.
The cosmetic perks were helpful in showing support in the game while advertising their
benefits but weren't quite enough to entice a lot of players.
They were also permanent, missing an opportunity to continue receiving income from players
who wanted to help.
CityStream went through constant iteration, both before and after launching.
We were in a rush from Twitch to launch in time for their Twitch Plays Gaming category,
debuting with the smallest of core loops after a mere six weeks of development.
We would go on to add new content to the game every day for two months, including tweaks
and bug fixes.
Timed polls are a major element from almost every Twitch Plays
game, including our own choice chamber,
but they turn a group of people into a single number,
making an individual's vote not seem to matter.
We noticed in other games that viewers
would participate most often when
their decision had the chance of making them feel special.
For this reason, we wanted to do away with polls completely,
but a few remained for major group decisions,
accounting for less than 2% of all possible commands.
We eventually moved polls to the top of the screen
to prevent city progress from halting
for one minute at a time, a feature request from players
who had a schedule to keep in the city.
All other interaction in the game was done as an individual player, where the sum of
all players' actions contributed to game progress.
To prevent the already flooded chatroom from being more crowded, we added a whisper bot
to have a private chat with any player, informing them of their status, inventory, and other
events unique to them.
This also helped out with the video delay that could range from 15 to 60 seconds, dictated
by a viewer's location and connection.
We actually needed to get whitelisted by Twitch,
so we weren't marked as a mass Whisperbot, which we were.
This worked fairly well, aside from a few nights
when the Whisper servers were down,
forcing us to manually tell individual players their status.
Much of the game's progress was gated by time,
to both add weight to players' decisions
and to make a rather simple game
last far longer than it really should have.
Every action took time to execute,
some taking seconds, others hours.
We encouraged teamwork by allowing most actions
to complete faster as more players helped out.
Diminishing returns were added
where each additional player contributed
less than the one before to prevent a mob of players
from going around completing every task immediately.
Most buildings would perform their functions linearly as players entered, such as offensive
towers shooting lasers equal to the combined powers of all players inside.
Other buildings like the XP farming disco stopped operating if too many players were
on the dance floor, forcing them to manage work and play carefully.
These kinds of things led to emergent specialization,
which was pretty cool.
Suddenly players would have to communicate
outside of regular play to decide
where each one's skills could be best utilized.
Some even created chatbots to automate certain processes,
though they soon retracted them when they realized
how much fun that removed from the experience.
One interesting thing we added was a building that buffed adjacent buildings, but only if
they were all the same color.
This led to players designating neighborhoods, territories, and even having gang wars as
they fought for control of different districts.
Where they were once arbitrarily deciding building colors, they were now arguing over
the benefits of having a chocolate lookout post versus a smoke research lab in a particular
spot.
Tying into the game's end goal of reaching the moon, we had special events occur during
real world moon phases to add to the narrative.
This made players change up their strategies, even planning ahead based on the lunar calendar.
After the game had finished, we had a one-day special revival of CityStream on April Fool's
Day called CityStream.
Extreme! Where all variables were cranked to 11, there were 9 moons and a bunch of rainbows and
explosions. Players accomplished as much that day as they did in the first one and a half months
the first time. Though this can also be attributed to the game actually containing all of its
content from the beginning.
Early on we felt it would become boring to stare at the same steady grid for hours, even
days at a time, and decided to create a narrator, Beep, to connect with players and give them
a focal point for communicating with the game, similar to how you see a green screened human
player in the corner of any other Twitch channel.
Beep was supposed to be driven by AI
to have dynamic conversations with players,
but we couldn't get something so complex
working in the short time we had.
Not wanting to have him have predictable,
canned responses to everything,
we took shifts playing as Beep
to respond back to players directly,
acting as a man behind the curtain.
They loved him so much, we continued DMing as him each day,
making sure to keep players engaged through the mundanity
of crafting a city one resource at a time.
Unfortunately, this meant we had to cut the broadcast
to about eight hours each day, using the rest of the day
to continue working on new content tweaks and bug fixes.
We continued expanding Beep's arsenal of MCing
from a dozen animated emotions to wearing hats
for various occasions, such as a general's hat
during battle and a nightcap when it was time
to end the day's stream.
It was so important to us that Beat maintained this relationship with players that we created
a system to remotely control his responses by sending private whispers to the game via
the Twitch mobile app.
This was especially attractive to us as it didn't require creating additional software.
It allowed us to go out to dinners and functions completely ignoring our friends.
Our original idea was for this to be a 24 hour live channel
that ran itself, only needing to be taken down for servicing.
But with having to play as Beep during the day
and working on the game in the evenings,
our days turned into double shifts.
Combined with poor revenue and retention overall,
this ultimately forced us to discontinue the game
after two months.
We could have continued making tweaks and adding ways to get players excited,
but working 14 plus hours a day at less than minimum wage
made us consider the possibility that maybe we should cut our losses
and apply what we learned in future projects.
That's the only picture I have of our battle station.
That's Chelsea playing as Beep.
The players could actually tell when I was playing as Beep
and when she was playing as Beep
because she was a much better storyteller than I was.
Monetising a game like this was tricky since it was unlike anything else out there.
Not surprisingly, this is where our design fell apart the quickest.
We offered additional cosmetic and gameplay perks to players who subscribe to the Twitch
channel or donated via a third party system.
However, almost all perks were permanent,
offering little reason to continue supporting.
This is a missed opportunity for diehard players
to have a long-term contribution.
We noticed our most generous players
go from throwing hundreds of dollars at us
to tossing a few coins after just a couple of days,
mostly because the game wasn't compensating them accordingly
but also because we never thought someone
would want to donate so much at a time,
thereby never designing for it.
Oops.
It actually says oops on my slide here.
To avoid constant grinding, we added a wishing well,
where players could offer some or all of their inventory
in exchange for a chance at winning big.
Some players became addicted, gambled away everything,
then grinded resources to do it all again.
We tried to break this habit by time-gating
additional wishes after jackpots,
but that simply let them grind more resources
at a casual pace.
We also didn't monetize wishing for legal and moral reasons.
Despite this, there were still ways to manipulate the system,
allowing some players to build entire districts
on their own overnight.
It was a broken system, even after continued tweaking.
Battling was a huge component of the core loop,
where players would stop building to defend the city
from an army of creatures.
Offensive buildings would fire from afar,
while brave players would use melee attacks
and weapons on the battlefield.
and if a creature made it to the city and destroyed a building, it was permanently gone
from the game.
The difficulty of those battles was intended to be automated by a system that accounted
for the number of active players and their combined potential power, curating the experience
to be challenging yet possible.
This system also did not get finished in time, so while we were playing as the narrator Beep,
we were also deciding how and when every battle unfolded.
Even with this human control, many battles appeared either too easy or so unfair we had
to roll back the save file because every building was destroyed.
We improvised these moments to players, usually mentioning a time machine of some sort, but they knew we screwed something up.
Even the final battle had to be painstakingly curated to make sure it lasted more than a few minutes, but didn't erase two months of work.
Unbeknownst to us, some players had been stockpiling on explosives via the wishing well, and decided to use all of them at the same time, defeating the final boss faster than we can give it another health boost.
Another problem that only got worse over time was onboarding new players.
As the city, UI, and commands grew more complex, the game became ever more puzzling to a pair
of fresh eyes.
This was largely because all information had to be on screen at the same time, and a late
game newcomer couldn't start at the beginning.
We tried to ease the introduction via a helper bot and an online manual, but despite the
efforts of these and chatroom moderators helping out, we got this same question up until the
final moments.
How do I play?
We realized this was a problem as soon as we had trouble
ourselves telling someone in person what things to do first.
In addition to our struggles with the game itself,
it was tough for Twitch to promote a game
that didn't present well at a glance,
even with Beep telling jokes in the corner.
Other than a launch day promotion on the front page,
it took one and a half months to create a spotlight feature
to continue help spreading the word.
This isn't necessarily a failure on our part,
unless you consider our designing a game
that doesn't catch one's eye,
but it does help paint a picture as to why we had trouble
getting new players regularly.
CityStream was a fun experiment that certainly taught us a lot about dealing with emergent
multiplayer ecosystems, but a time pressure combined with too many design and UX flaws
prevented it from taking off as we had hoped.
We still believe to this day that all major issues with the game are solvable, especially
after having experienced them fall apart over the course of a couple months.
However, when the final building on the final spot was upgraded to its final level, we called
it the end of Season 1 and sent players where they had always intended to go to the moon.
Our final stream was a two-hour-long rocket ride
through outer space featuring a dynamic rolling credits
of every player who ever stepped into the game's world.
As players rode their rocket tower through space
and collided with passing stars,
they gained the ability to shoot fireworks into the galaxy,
giving back light to a fastly dimming world.
With that, Beep put on his nightcap for the last time,
wishing everyone a good night.
Thank you, everybody.
I believe Adrian is going to be next.
Hello everyone, I'm Adrian De Jong.
I'm a game designer, programmer, business,
marketing person, indie I guess.
I just released Hidden Folks, yay.
But today I wanna, thank you, wow.
So today, now, I want to reflect on the closure of Game Oven,
the studio I co-founded.
In case you didn't know Game Oven,
it was founded by programmer Bojan Androvski
and game designer Adriaan de Jong.
That would be me.
and we were later joined by marketeer Eliene Meuris.
We had an office in the Dutch game garden in Utrecht,
the Netherlands, and we made Fingal, Planet Challenge,
Bamfoo, Friendstrap, Bounden, and Jelly Reef, six games.
We were best known for Fingle, which is a sort of like
Twister-like finger rubbing game.
And some people know us for Bounden,
which is a mobile dancing game for two people.
And it actually has choreography
by the Dutch National Ballet.
I showed this at the Experimental Gameplay Workshop
two years ago.
So my talk to you today will have two parts.
One of what it's like being a company
and sort of our perspective on closing the company
and being a team and all the dynamics
that happened within our team.
Alright, part one, being a company.
So, GameOven was founded by Bojan and I
because at some point I had this prototype, a Fingal,
and it was sort of weird and fun,
and it was just awkward, and we,
Bojan and I both saw, oh, maybe we need to
make a actual game out of this and put it on the App Store,
but to do that, we needed a legal entity.
So we were like, hmm, maybe we should just dive into it
and make a company, and Game Oven was born.
Our business plan became to make enough games
to collectively bring in enough money
to cover the costs of the company, and hope for a hit.
somewhere along the way, and we wanted to run the studio
sort of on the long tail of games.
So long tails usually look like this,
but the thing is, if you zoom in,
this is what you see, right?
So there's various games, and the money they bring in
every day stacks up, and that's what covers
the cost of the company every day.
So Game Oven employed one designer, a developer,
a marketing person, and we usually had
an art or a developer intern.
The biggest challenge to this structure
was balancing prototyping games and marketing
and doing business.
We hired Elina with the promise to overcome that challenge,
but when it got real hot in the oven,
we still found ourselves helping out with marketing.
And looking back at this, it seems like prototyping and actual game development
are much easier roles to mix for one person than making and selling a game.
But this is my gut feeling, I don't have any scientific data on this.
So aside from our in-house roles and skills,
we always required at least a number of contractors
with every project.
So we always needed one or two full-time artists,
a music composer, a sound designer,
a filmmaker to make our trailers, localization company,
sometimes an extra developer,
and for a bound we needed a choreographer,
so that was weird.
But let's talk about costs, because the minimum wage
of one person in the Netherlands costs the company
about 1,800 euros per month.
That is about $1,900.
And this includes taxes and administration fees.
With three employees, rent, software, administration,
and all sorts of little things,
game often costs about 6,500 euros per month.
We think it's not really cool to share
how much our collaborators asked of us,
but this chart can give you a little bit of a sense
of what all these projects cost.
So, yeah, on one side there's the collaborators,
how many of them we needed to make the game,
and on the other side is the studio time and months.
So, Bounden and Jelareef were definitely
one of our bigger projects.
So counting the months on this chart
and knowing that Game Oven existed for three and a half years
all the studio time listed here
doesn't add up to three and a half years.
Because in between these projects we prototyped,
we maintained the engine and our previous games
and we did some contracting work here and there.
But more importantly, this in-between creative downtime,
or project downtime, was still studio uptime.
And it cost the studio as much as working on a project.
So you can imagine what kind of pressure
this put on our creativity.
How can you have peace of mind
when you know you're burning money every day,
and you don't find that next big thing?
And this is one of the reasons we decided to close Game Oven,
because being responsible for the upkeep of the studio
and being creative is damn difficult.
And yeah, we couldn't find a way.
Because, well, let's talk about Game Oven's income.
So in total, more than two and a half million people,
more than two and a half million apps have been downloaded
with grossing about 155,000 euros,
which is about $165,000.
Compared to other apps on mobile stores,
these numbers are not amazing,
but they're definitely not bad either.
Speculating over what drove our game sales,
we think it's...
We think we made unique games and potentially appealing to non-gamers and using phone features in unique ways.
But we were always constrained by the designs of our games to mobile platforms, which already has a lot of competition.
And we weren't really in the mood for a free-to-play business model.
From 2012 to 2015, piracy in our games was just crazy.
So most of our Chinese, Russian, and Turkish players
pirated our premium games, both on the iOS and App Store.
And yeah, especially with Bounden's release,
we were baffled by how much percentage it was.
So, in the end, what we made off our sales
wasn't, strictly speaking, enough to cover the costs
of the studio and pay our collaborators.
And so we hunted for additional source of income.
Lots of subsidies, government grants, contracting work,
Humble Bundle, App Campus, which is or was a program
by Windows to get more games to their platform,
and we won various awards.
So with all these additional sources of income,
about a total of 144,000 euros,
we were actually easily able to cover
the cost of the studio.
And in the end, we probably even had enough funds
to do another project.
So again, Game of Ents income wasn't the main reason
we closed the studio, but rather the pressure
of our monthly burn rate on the creativity
for that next project.
Okay, so that's part one, being a company.
Let's talk about being a team.
Because as founders, Boyan and I had,
you could say, some struggles during our three and a half
years of working together.
And I might present these struggles here
as if they were really straightforward,
but we went through months of reflection
and to try to understand what happened
and why we were occasionally so frustrated with each other.
My deep motivation to make games has always been very different from Boyan's motivation to make games.
I've always had this thing for truly social games,
whatever that means, while Boyan didn't necessarily.
And as an example, Boyan really, really did not
like friend strap, while I consider it
one of my best working concepts ever.
And Boyan became father after Bounden,
money and being sustainable became
even more important motivators to him.
So before Jelly Reef, the last game Game Oven made,
Boyan had not been able to motivate or convince me
to work on any of his game ideas,
mainly because I looked for a social component
in Boyan's ideas that he never focused on.
To me it felt like...
Boyan never understood what he wanted to accomplish
with his games, or that his games didn't have
a bigger vision, and for Boyan it felt like
I never took his ideas seriously.
And this kind of frustration was actually
very difficult to deal with for both of us.
Okay, the other struggle.
I was primarily the face of Game Oven.
I was maybe a bit more extrovert
and better connected internationally.
But unfortunately, many interviews with journalists
presented me as the sole creator of Game Oven's games,
even though they were made as a team effort.
There was one particular interview on Bounden
that hurt Boyan most.
writing about me as the genius inventor of Bounden,
while never mentioning it was made by a whole team.
And this struggle actually came back quite often,
too often as what should be necessary.
Everyone wants to be credited for their hard work,
and so simply making this very explicit to journalists
keeps everyone happy on the team.
So if you're a journalist, please take this seriously.
Like, I actually know for a fact we are not
the only ones who have struggled with this.
Okay, the biggest struggle however,
that we faced resulted from never strictly defining
our roles.
So, Boyan didn't want to narrowly define our roles
as he wanted to have a say in business and marketing
and design as well as being the technical lead.
Having a say in all aspects of running a game studio
for a small studio like that was why he wanted
to be a founder in the first place.
And I think that's very reasonable.
But unfortunately it resulted in a pretty bad,
few pretty bad scenarios.
And I wanted to give you guys three of these scenarios
because, yeah, I want you to understand
how important this was for our decision
to close Game Over.
So after the quite underwhelming launch of Bamfoo, our second title,
I decided after maybe three or four months of prototyping
that Game Oven's next production was going to be Friendstrap.
And this quirky little game with no beef
other than being really awkward and weird,
Boyan just didn't feel anything for making it.
To me, feeling that studio uptime pressure,
it was one of the prototypes with the most potential
we had at that time.
But to Boyan, it felt like he had no say
in whether friendship should be made or not,
but he did feel as responsible for it as much as I did.
But I took the best decision I could,
and I still think we didn't have
any better alternatives back then.
So the lesson here is defining roles comes down to trust
and letting go of the things you too feel responsible for.
One long argument Boyan and I had was about a timer in Bounden.
So at some point during the project,
Bounden took on the challenge of making a timer,
one that should convey where you are within the dance.
But while he was making it, I came to realize,
and I saw in play tests, that the timer
was actually not as relevant
to the broader picture of the game.
And so I...
sort of had to discard the idea within the whole design
and replaced it with a much simpler solution.
But at this point, it felt to Boyan
as if I only wanted to include my own designs
while I was only trying to model
a coherent player experience for Bounden.
And so the lesson here is, I was often not able
to communicate my bigger vision of the game fully to Bojan,
which made it very difficult for Bojan
to understand why his contributions
could sometimes, should sometimes not be included.
And what complicated matters was that the vision
and execution of that vision changed constantly,
sometimes even radically.
So another difficult scenario was Jelly Reef in its entirety.
So from the start, with all our previous issues in mind
and all our struggles in mind,
I wanted Boyan to be the creative owner of Jelly Reef.
And he filled that role well.
But somewhere along the way,
Jelly Reef turned into a procedurally generated game,
which meant that my role for Jelly Reef became unclear.
I wasn't able to help Bojan code it.
I was just not a good programmer like that.
And so not only did I have to leave
most of the design up to Bojan,
I also had to work on a game that didn't align
with my deep motivation to make games in the first place.
And it was at this time that I got us together
and said those four painful words, I want to quit.
Boyan and Alina understood that I was a fundamental member
of Game Oven, so we decided together to finish Jell-O-Reef
and close Game Oven afterwards.
But finishing Jell-O-Reef with a disbanding team
was a nightmare.
Boyan worked his ass off to make the game happen regardless,
but he was increasingly frustrated with the lack of effort
by his team members.
Everyone had their minds on the future.
And in hindsight, I think we should have just disbanded
right there and then,
and even though that felt maybe too disruptive
to our lives at that point.
Okay, so those were three struggles that we had.
But I do want to end on a positive note,
because only talking about our struggles
makes us look like we should have never
worked together in the first place,
but we obviously had super fun times too.
Going to the office every morning
was like a little adventure,
and we'd make something new quickly that day together,
figuring out how the hell to do it.
And even with all the struggles that we had,
Boin and I didn't close the studio
hating or disliking each other.
We've had times where we could punch each other in the face,
but not when we closed the studio.
And in a way, our struggles are...
Still marginal compared to our achievements, I think.
17 awards and nominations for Fingle and Bounden,
major features in the App Store,
stories of relationships crushed and babies made
because of Fingle,
working together with the Dutch National Ballet,
coverage in the New York Times,
the Guardian, BBC, The Verge, Mashable,
and more than 14 and a half million play sessions.
That's a crazy ride.
I want to conclude Game Oven with you.
In contrast to what most people initially think,
Game Oven did make enough money to sustain itself.
So strictly speaking, our game sales weren't enough
to keep us running, but only looking at
one of our sources of income
would be a narrow point of view.
What was difficult for us to maintain
was the rigid structure of a studio,
as opposed to the flexible structure
of hopping on and off individual projects.
our problem was studio uptime during project downtime.
And we worked really hard to close the gap
between our projects, but leaving responsibility
scattered throughout the team, keeping our roles vague,
magnified the pressure between us,
and caused many struggles between us.
And eventually, those personal struggles
made us decide to close the studio.
And ultimately, that is the more
nuanced conclusion to Game Oven.
So I hope you draw lessons from Game Oven, our failure.
And if you have any questions, please do come talk
to me afterwards.
Thank you.
Tim?
You're up next.
everybody. I'm going to go ahead and get started. I'm going to
Oh, hello everyone. My name is Tim Rogers. I am the founder and director of
Interactive electronic object research design development and
Consultation studio action button entertainment I
Am the game designer and director of video ball video ball is a digital sporting good product
Which is available now?
As if this makes a difference.
For personal computers and for PlayStation 4
or Xbox One video game console hardwares.
Somebody commented on the YouTube video
of my talk last year that it sounded like
I had to go to the bathroom.
I really did.
I really do right now.
So, I need to stop doing this.
Alright, okay, so.
Video ball is a four-player sport
in which two teams of two players
each project triangles at circular balls to push them.
Push a ball into your opponent's goal to score a point.
The longer you hold the button,
the bigger your eventual triangle.
The bigger triangles push harder.
Triangles also stun players and eliminate one another.
Regulation video ball is played with three balls
on the screen at all times.
And here's a little video of some experts playing the game.
So, video ball represents an attempt to make
a serious electronic sport.
So through what I can hopefully unpretentiously describe
as a scientific game design process,
we started with simple core rules
and eventually arrived at what I call,
quote unquote, a compact expression of all sports mechanics.
Video Ball launched on 12 July 2016,
and my life has been a garage sale ever since.
One of my earnest goals with Video Ball was...
was, this being perfectly honest now for the first time,
one of the earnest goals of Video Ball
was to make the Burberry scarf of video games.
Up here on stage last year I said
the Muji coffee cup of video games.
That was me being modest.
I wanted to make the Burberry scarf of video games,
a luxury video game.
So you can buy a scarf for a dollar
and it will keep your neck warm.
Or, you can pay roughly $400 for a Burberry scarf.
So why pay the extra,
I never meant to charge $400 for video ball.
So, but why pay the extra $399?
Well, a Burberry scarf represents a perfect intersection
of history, science, and art.
So I personally don't really have any history or art,
but I know a little bit about science,
so I thought that I could, you know, fudge the other two.
So Burberry, the company has existed for over a century.
The founder, Thomas Burberry, invented Gabardine,
a waterproof fabric, which is still appreciated today.
And their trademark check pattern,
their trademark check pattern
is a monolith of graphic design.
So I would define a Burberry scarf as a fine thing.
And this would be what I would want in my video game
that is the Burberry scarf of video games.
So to run through the list, a fine thing is,
not too hot, not too cold, lovely to touch,
beautiful to look at, and wonderful to think about.
So, I am not, however, a ridiculous enough person
to vocalize this mission statement while promoting
Video Ball before it's released, but.
The game's been out for eight months,
and I'm wondering now if maybe I should have been
that ridiculous.
I'm always checking my ridiculousness.
So instead we promoted Video Ball
as a digital sporting good product.
Video Ball will empower the players,
the players are the characters, the game is a thing.
And I'm working on another game right now,
I'll tell you about it later.
And my mission statement just in my head,
that my mantra is video games can be things.
And hopefully that will be my GDC talk in 2018.
That'll be the title.
Video games can be things.
Look forward to it.
Or you don't have to if you don't want to.
Okay, so I got a lot of weird copywriting
out of the Video Ball mission statement.
And my favorite thing is something I said here last year,
which is Video Ball has the best graphics of any game ever.
Because Videoball is a perfect one-to-one simulation of itself.
And this, in addition to being a funny joke,
is also, that was something I sincerely believed.
I thought, why not make a game like that?
Wouldn't it be cool if there was something like that?
So here's how we advertised that mission statement
in the trailer.
And if you want this guy to do a voice in your trailer,
there's a few more tracks.
Think of video ball as a pool table.
Think of video ball as a ping pong table.
Think of your television as a dinner table.
And Videoball is what's for dinner.
Videoball doesn't need fairies, elves, space marines, tanks, or even helicopters.
Videoball has the best game characters ever.
Real human beings.
That's right. When you were born, you were already a Videoball character.
Want a new costume for your Videoball hero?
Put a hat on, buddy. I mean, put a real hat on your real head.
Boom!
You just made D.L.C.
So I, you know, hey, you know,
I thought that was pretty good.
It got a lot of views on YouTube,
most of them saying that the announcer
sounded like he had a stuffed nose,
so body functions keep getting into my PR.
So basically, in keeping with the
put a hat on buddy message,
we made hundreds of shirts, many of them unique.
Most of them unique.
I promoted these shirts on the web,
and I even sold some of them up here
at the podium last year at GDC,
if anybody remembers that.
I would say make some noise if you're wearing a shirt,
though I have surveyed the audience with my eyes
and determined that that would be too much noise.
I actually have the last video ball shirt.
It is a medium-sized American Apparel.
You can't, it's not gonna, I'm sorry.
You're a robust gentleman.
You're tough, you're stronger than me.
So keep in mind that I have diabetes
and I can't afford medicine,
so if somebody wants to pay me for this.
All right, so.
One of the video ball shirts was printed on a 1950s vintage French girls terry cloth t-shirt
and I was very scared to print on this. I have a collection of vintage European sweatshirts
I mean, because lots of people do.
And so this shirt ended up being the object of a bidding war, and the highest bid, and this is a callback,
it was $400.
And the bidder was a person I actively dislike, so I did not sell.
However, pleased with its having obtained a $400 bid,
I felt comfortable selling it for $50
to a wonderful couple from Belgium,
because I like Belgium, and also because they'd promised me
that they would do something good with it.
So, months later, they sent me.
couple of photographs. So upon seeing this photo I realized that in fact my
first daily mistake my entire life had always been not knowing that a statue of
Jean-Claude Van Damme as he appears in the 1988 film Bloodsport literally
stands in a park somewhere in Belgium. But despite Jean-Claude's best efforts
it was already too late. VideoBall had cost me all of my money.
And when the game shipped, I was broke.
I could not afford to spend even a daily hour promoting it.
So, by now you may be thinking,
how can a game with a $400 T-shirt
on a Jean-Claude Van Damme statue
in a park in Belgium be considered a failure?
Well, I'm glad you asked, because strictly speaking,
it's not, because that rules.
Video Ball is not a failure because it is my favorite game.
However, on the other hand, I have literally five
broken teeth in my mouth.
And I dared to have a dental checkup last month,
and the dentist's words were, and I quote,
you've got a lot going on in here.
That's not even a joke.
So, put bluntly, Videoball is a failure
because we spent too much time,
and our message was weak.
Okay, so, and let's get into what I mean
by too much time and week.
So, Thanksgiving weekend 2013, we played video ball
for more or less 20 consecutive hours.
So, video ball was perfect two years before we released it,
and I can't prove this to you
because I don't have two hours to talk.
But, so, I did give a two hour lecture
about why video ball is,
there's a couple people who were at that lecture.
So, Black Sunday 2013.
So two years before we released Video Ball,
some friends and I gathered in my house
in Oakland, California for what we called
the first annual Little Caesars Hot N' Ready Bowl.
Because we're idiots, and because I maybe wanted to die,
we bought four Little Caesars Hot N' Ready cheese pizzas.
This was back when they were only $5, now they're $6.
This economy, huh?
So, among us, we had over 2,000 hours of video ball
experience in the room.
We played at long tournaments on a grand scale.
So this is a very prototype looking video ball
that we were playing.
This was during the game design process,
that aforementioned scientific process.
So we played a long tournament on a grand scale.
So here's a clip of the final round.
You're going to hear a cacophony of voices
shouting bizarre phrases.
I realized today that any game able to provoke this reaction in my friends despite its flaws should have been released as immediately as
Possible instead of us taking extra years to polish it instead. We perpetrated a cataclysmic waste of time
so here's the I
Mean it the game looks like nonsense, but listen to these people screaming. There's a part
There's like 12 people in this room
Somehow there was still two slices of pizza left
At this point.
Oh, what?
Yeah.
Oh!
Oh, yes.
We're back in this.
We are back in this.
There it goes, yeah.
You're back in the sort of app now.
Oh!
No!
Ha ha!
Yes!
Oh, yes!
Oh, gosh.
Eat it!
Yeah!
I would kill everyone.
Get it out.
Boom!
Take this shit down real quick.
Time it!
Get these kids out of my neighborhood!
Touchdown!
Bam!
Boom!
Finish it Tim.
Finish it.
I can't, you help!
Boom!
Yeah!
I got it.
Boom!
Yeah!
Keep him dizzy.
Johnny, go baby!
Come on!
Go!
Get it!
Oh!
Yeah!
Johnny, you motherfucker!
No!
Go, Jim!
Come on, man!
No!
Oh, God!
It hurts!
This is a little longer than I thought it was.
No, I'm not letting you go!
No!
McKee!
You fuckers!
No!
Yeah!
I'm not letting you go!
I'm not letting you go.
Don't let me go.
I'm not letting you go, I'm not letting you go,
I'm not letting you go, I'm not allowing you go,
I'm beating the shit out of you!
Oh my god!
Okay, uh, so...
So...
I look at that and it's like compared to
if the sound were off, I would be like
man, yeah, this game sucks
like, uh
and that's, you know, what I thought then
I'm like, oh, there's a whole lot of stuff I want to do with this game
and, you, I would just forget about that.
the next day, immediately after resuming work on the game, I would forget, for some reason,
what's wrong with me. I would completely forget that those people had that much fun playing that game.
we should have released it pretty much right away.
So that's what I want to talk about real quick here.
We should have released the game simpler and differently.
So let's talk about simpler and differently.
So here's why we didn't release it simple and different.
So the terrifying screams the video ball prototype caused
were so voluminous as to attract a publisher.
So I signed with the publisher because they offered money
and I like that.
The money would be enough for myself, Brent Porter, and Michael Kirwan, my partners, to concentrate on finishing the game.
It didn't seem impossible. It was a game we wanted to make anyway.
I hated the contract work that I'd been doing on the side to support the development, and I liked the guy who was the publisher.
But so what happened we agreed to the publishers expectations, which was simultaneous launch on PlayStation 3 Xbox 360
Steam PlayStation 4 and Xbox one which is a lot of work for three people to do in six months
They also expected cross-platform online multiplayer which
which quite hilariously did not happen.
So we were now being paid to work on
what we'd been doing for fun,
so we subconsciously divided the work
into stuff we had to do,
such as getting it running on all the consoles,
and the unnecessary stuff we wanted to do,
such as graphical polish, new options,
new modes, new arenas.
So we'd somehow decided that we were being paid
just for the boring stuff,
which is a really,
bad trap that we fell into.
And so we kept doing the fun work for fun,
and eventually we were working 16 hour days on this game.
And I crunched some numbers,
and it turns out we averaged about $4.50 an hour
for the work we were doing, which is,
that's pretty bad.
So, and then eventually we took so long making our game
that our publisher went out of business
and we had no choice at this point.
We needed another publisher.
I could get into that, but that's scary.
But so our friends at Iron Galaxy rescued us
and so we ended up releasing the game a year later.
Now one of the bigger problems here with the game
was that our first time user experience
was too difficult in the wrong environment.
I accidentally said user and it says game right there.
Sorry about that.
So we had cultivated an abstract color-coded visual style
because we found this the coldest, most legible way
to inform players and spectators of the events of the game.
Legibility was our primary concern,
which meant the game ended up with a look
that I have described as preschool industrial,
which is this look here.
So the first time players of Video Ball
presumed that the game was as stupid as it looked,
and the disgusted glares I suffered from EVO attendees
left a layer of frostbite on my brain,
which likely remains today.
That's an actual quote from a review.
It's basically Pong made for the millennials,
and I can't get enough of it.
I don't know, millennials are cool, whatever.
Okay, so we had designed our game under a strict law
that it would be all skill, no luck.
The player's first experience is not as important
as their 1,000th.
And we knew that this was not a billion dollar
mainstream idea.
We had decided with conviction that our game
would not possess the immediately understandable metaphor
and simplicity of a game such as Rocket League.
Meanwhile, the press had decided that soccer was in fact
Rocket League without cars
So we could have released our game before Rocket League
We ended up releasing after and eventually players at PAX were shouting to their buddies. Hey, look
Someone made 2D Rocket League.
And our game's, I mean, Rocket League rules,
but I mean, that was people's first, I don't know, I cried.
So it was that first-timers pressed one button
over and over, firing dinky little triangles,
barely pushing balls, or they'd ram into the,
I actually was a...
I was going to show you a video on YouTube, but it's all messed up.
So, or they'd ram into the ball repeatedly and drop the controller in anger when nothing happened.
Some people didn't even realize the circles were balls.
And those who did would recommend,
hey, maybe the ball should move when you touch it, you know, like in Rocket League.
And, you know, again, I was like,
I've done science here, man.
So, video ball requires four players to optimally enjoy,
and so at game conventions,
people don't tend to be walking around with three friends.
And they also, I mean, that's not a diss or anything,
I mean, that's just what I noticed.
And they also are surprisingly not always in the mood
to get into screaming fits with three total strangers.
And if just one player understands the rules of this game
and plays well, the other three players feel terrible.
And I noticed this a lot.
So video ball requires cooperation and observation.
And if there's just one player of the four who's good,
most players are not willing to observe and learn
from the behaviors of total strangers
in the presence of an expert.
No matter how hard.
a guy wearing a Notre Dame football jacket
over a dress screams at them.
That was me at PAX 2014.
That was Christine Love's dress that she loaned me.
So number seven, we put too much stuff into the game.
So in our two years of polishing, we filled the game with a bounty of rules, score variations, music tracks, voice announcements, backgrounds, line variations, ball markers, and 35 drastically different arenas.
We put in an arcade mode for one or two players. We put in one-on-one and three-on-three local multiplayer. We put in AI bots.
We did all this even though we knew for certain the best experience was two-on-two.
So when we released the game, streamers and Let's Players were playing almost exclusively one-on-one.
Furthermore, they never touched the customization options.
Our game ended up looking dinky and plain.
We knew it was actually ferocious and flamboyant.
When we played the game, we saw the 1995 NBA Finals.
When Let's Players played the game,
we saw a lone, untouched field hockey ball
sitting in a tray of fresh kitty litter.
I swear to God we could have remade this menu
if we'd had one more week,
and it would have been perfect to Dave Lang.
I'm not gonna talk about that menu.
That goddarn menu.
There's a very simple solution.
We spent much, much, much less than one million dollars
promoting Video Ball.
We spent zero dollars promoting Video Ball.
Had we spent a million dollars, I promise you,
I would not be here today.
I would be at the Success Workshop next door.
And, uh, the profits would have likely been large enough for me to buy a 1999 Honda Civic Si,
which is vastly preferable to the car I have now, and for reference, this is the car I have now.
I don't think it's safe, it's a Halloween costume with wheels. It's like...
It's like, what if Dracula were a cop?
If you ever see this car driving up out of a lake,
I pushed it in there, and it's coming back for me.
So I had five conversations with venture capitalists,
which I drove this car to all those meetings,
who said they wanted to invest in video ball,
and none of them invested in video ball.
Maybe I didn't give them a pitch that was any good at all.
My plan hadn't been good enough,
and hindsight being what it is,
I now kind of do have a plan, which, you know,
it's a little late.
But uh, so here's the lessons we learned real quick. The most important lesson is that our game is great. We can make great games
And I love this goddarn game man
So it is amazingly easy to lose confidence in yourself when you're tooling around
Alone in the dark with the minutiae of a game which is meant for four live human players
Despite my many experiences with the living room full of friends screaming in ecstasy ecstasy
I could not help feeling an inadequacy which drove me to implement too many modes and too much stuff
We didn't need all that stuff because video ball is great.
The other thing I learned,
game conventions are loud and stupid.
We should not have taken video ball to PAX.
PAX is great for many, many games, but probably not ours.
I reside in the San Francisco Bay Area.
I could have taken the game directly to journalists,
streamers, cool people, colleges, schools,
instead of preparing for yet another laryngitis.
So, showing VideoBall at PAX required a lot of explanation,
and man, that place is loud.
On day two, somebody always came back
bringing their friends, so I could take a break
while they played with their friends,
and then they told their friends how to play.
And it occurs to me now that we already had
a perfect place to show the game, which was.
the Oakland Video Ball Sunday Club,
which I invited people to come over to my house
every Sunday for about eight months
while we were polishing the game.
And it was open to the public.
One week a kid, a college student from Berkeley came,
and then the next week he brought six friends.
That's like six people you're getting on a bus
to come play a game at a guy's house.
But I should have taken that as a sign,
but here's a photo of some people playing video ball
at the GDC 2014 Sunday Club.
Dan Tabar took that photo, I love that photo.
Yeah, so it's so clear to me now,
we should have shown the game at university-sponsored events.
We could have taken it to events.
I showed it at a high school,
and it was way better than showing it at PAX.
Should have done more of that.
I could have sent, kids were asking me,
I call them kids, because I don't know,
they're in college, and I'm...
I'm almost 40 years old.
And so the kids were asking,
hey, can I have a build of the game to play with my friends?
And I was like, man, no.
I should have done it.
I should have sent a stripped down build
and let them evangelize the game for me.
I don't know.
I don't know, man.
And then we went on to not even let online players organize.
So this is like the worst thing that we did.
Our online was divided into ranked and exhibition.
And then further divided into one-on-one,
two-on-two, and three-on-three.
This was an utter waste of time
and a flagrant display of idiotic hubris.
You can't just make an esport.
An esport has to happen.
and we should have left it at two on two,
won arena, and made all matches ranked.
By including a triple A's worth of options
in our online multiplayer for our game,
we could not afford to advertise.
All we did was dilute matchmaking into oblivion.
So that was a huge disaster.
So here's a comment from a review.
This is an actual line.
I can't recommend video ball on the basis
of its online multiplayer, however,
because there don't seem to be too many players
playing it online at this point.
So, you know, if you would recommend it,
there would be people.
This was like an 8.8 out of 10.
Like what is, 8.8?
I don't know.
So, finally it's very clear to me
that we could have made a dumber game,
and I use the word dumb very, very affectionately.
I love dumb games.
I love the abstract nature of video ball.
I love its devotion to its concept.
It's my favorite game.
That's the kind of person I am.
However, maybe it should have been
the professional edition.
of a much loopier, floppier, cartoonier game
full of vehicles, characters, special weapons,
anime girls, loadouts, modes, graphics, costumes, hats,
and a robust, roguelike single player mode.
That's Video Ball X right there.
Thanks to Dan DeSalt for that fan art.
So a wonderful man named Waseem Salman
referenced Frank Lloyd Wright
in a beautiful essay about Video Ball, and I blushed.
However, a student who had attended a two-hour lecture I gave at DePaul University
about the scientific process of balancing video ball speeds and timings
such that the average match was three minutes in length later sent me an email celebrating my
process as one Bertrand Russell would approve of.
I almost passed out.
I know and appreciate Bertrand Russell as an expert of many occupations.
Yet I take it this specific student's comparison saw video ball as the electronic game equivalent
of the fact that Bertrand Russell and Alfred Whitehead in their book Principia Mathematica
famously wrote 362 pages, proving that 1 plus 1 equals 2.
That's, that's a, I don't know anybody who's ever read that book and I haven't either,
cause why would you? I already know that.
You know, I'm like, I'm, I'm, uh.
So, uh, uh, basically that's a rule of thumb.
Unless you already possess financial security,
consider any comparison between your video game and the work of Bertrand Russell
to be the darkest possible omen.
But can I save Videoball?
Uh, well Videoball's primary concern is timelessness.
It runs at 300 frames per second and 8K resolution.
Uh.
I mean it does.
That sounds like, I promise I'm not joking.
So if our game is meant to survive intact
as good design for at least a thousand years,
calling it a failure and giving up after eight months
is quite frankly, a little bit ridiculous.
So we can simplify the product.
We can remove most of the menus, no more arena select,
leave in only the basic arena.
Sorry, but you.
That's where video ball was born.
It was pong for the millennials.
No more rules options.
Every match is two on two.
Three balls first to 10, no time limit.
We gut the matchmaking.
Every online match is two on two.
Three balls first to 10, no time limit.
Every match is ranked.
There's a pattern here.
No more customization.
All the visuals are all random all the time.
We make the game free.
We support it with tasteful ads.
We tasteful ads we always intended for video ball to be a digital sporting good product. You know like a principal blank t-shirt
So here's a version of video ball video ball white label as we call it
We have done for various clients and organizations who want their their own
Branded video ball we did this for PAX
2016 we were the final round of the Omega Thon and PAX East
So yeah, then we can take on sponsors, build an audience.
I don't know.
If I were giving my pitch to...
those venture capitalists a year ago,
this is what I would have told them
I wanted to do for the promotion.
And if eSports happens, it happens,
and if it doesn't happen, it doesn't happen.
So if you're a venture capitalist with no common sense,
and you'd like to talk to me,
my Twitter DMs are always open.
And that phone number right there, it's not fake.
So photograph this if you must,
but please do not tweet my phone number.
So in closing, Videoball is a failure
because I need insulin.
In closing, video ball is not a failure
because it is my favorite game.
And if you'd like to play it at my house on Friday night,
or Saturday afternoon, or Sunday evening,
or if you're around next week,
my Twitter DMs are always open,
and that phone number right there is not fake.
Please do not tweet my phone number.
Thank you.
One more thing. One more thing. Truck hick. Truck hick. Okay, bye.