Go ahead and get started.
Thank you, everybody, for showing up.
I'm not sure if Troy and Sarah Lynn are here.
I know Donna's not here.
Those are the folks that organize the community summit.
So I really want to thank them.
It's really cool that we have this as a resource every year
to come together and talk about what's going on in community.
I know I look forward to it.
So I want to really thank them.
My presentation is called Closing Down Game Communities,
How to Plan a Dignified Breakup.
I thought this was a really important subject to talk about because I found, I work for
Lionbridge Game Services and we work with a lot of different games and so of course
this comes up more often just by virtue of the fact that we're working on several games,
that a game does have to close down.
And there really isn't that much written as far as best practices about how to do this.
And we've learned a lot over the years doing this and so I thought it would be.
a good way to share some of that knowledge.
Now, that being said, I realize there are folks in this room
who also work in community and who have also been involved
in closing down game communities.
In fact, I would love to see a show of hands
if anyone has ever been involved in that process,
actually shutting down a game community.
Excellent.
And then how about anybody who has played a game
that has shut down and you've been a part of that community?
Yeah, so I mean it happens.
It's a game is a life and it ends.
It is a relationship and it ends.
So it's something that you have to be prepared for.
So it was really important to me to talk about this
and have a discussion.
So I'm gonna try to leave about five to 10 minutes at the end.
So if anybody has anything they wanna contribute,
even from your own personal experience doing this
or any questions, I'd love to have a discussion at that time.
So I have this quote up, it is better to have loved and lost than never to have loved at
all because that's what you want your community to feel at the end of this process.
You want them to feel like it was important that they were a part of this.
It's better that it happened and is over than that they were never a part of it in the first
place.
And I'm going to touch on this several times
throughout the presentation.
But really what you're trying to do
is move people from this feeling of just rage and sadness
to nostalgia.
That's where you want them to be in the end of this process.
And I have this first part because I hold it true,
whate'er befall, I feel it when I sorrow most.
That's not always there when you see this quote,
but it's important because you want people to feel this way
even when they're at their saddest,
even when they're feeling their worst.
You want them to still feel this way.
I have an example here from StarCraft.
This I think really gives a good example of how you want your fans to feel at the end.
You want them to feel like they were a part of something important.
They're glad that they were there, even if they were kind of special, that they were
and others weren't.
And that it's something that they wish that they could explain to other people, that your
legacy is going to live on in a positive way.
Of course, Asheron's Call is a game that shut down recently.
Landmark's another one.
I have this up because I feel like this shows really,
there is a personal relationship between people
who play your game and the game itself.
People feel like, especially if it's been going on
for a really long time, like they grew up there
or like they went through a significant part of their life
with that relationship with your game.
And so all the more you really need to be respectful
and thoughtful about how you break up.
And then I just have this up because I have a really good friend in Seattle who is just
diehard Seattle Sonics fan and literally to this day he still puts up a happy birthday
to any person who was ever on the team ever.
It's been 10 plus years since this game left Seattle and still it's something that is in
his heart in which he, there's still a legacy for the memory.
So, relationship respect.
It's really important to think about the fact
that your long-term relationship, reputation is at stake.
You may have other games, you may have a brand that's associated with other games,
you may even as somebody who works in community as a community professional,
carry this reputation to other jobs that you take for other games.
So you need to think about that.
Now, of course, you wanna do a good job and
be thoughtful because that's the right thing to do.
But also, it will affect your reputation.
They've been feeling it for a while too.
There have probably been lots of rumors
about the fact the game's gonna close down
and you are gonna have to deal with this fact
that some people are gonna feel
they've been made a fool of a little bit.
That's something you're gonna have to address.
And get it together before you speak.
I cannot stress that enough.
That's really what is gonna make the difference.
If you're thoughtful in the way that you
conduct this process, it's going to change,
it's gonna make the outcome much more positive.
People are gonna feel that you cared,
you cared enough to have things be coordinated
in this end phase.
So at the beginning of any, when a closure is planned,
you need to put together a closure timeline.
So some things to really think about when you're putting that
together are that the communication is synced
across channels.
So that's social media, forums, official, unofficial,
English language, non-English.
All channels need to have this closure announcement made
in a way that is synced.
You also need to make sure that your PR, customer service,
marketing are all on board.
Because as you know, as far as your players,
your customers are concerned, it doesn't matter who's speaking.
It's your game.
Internally, sometimes we start to think, oh, that's PR,
that's marketing.
But they don't care.
If somebody in marketing is saying one thing
or customer service saying another, it's confusing.
And it gives an impression that you're not
being thoughtful about how you get this information out.
The other thing is really that everyone knows when and what to say internally at
your company, even people who aren't really typically client facing all the time.
Everybody, because of social media or just really because of the way that people
interact and communicate, they are going to be talking with people about what's
going on and you need to have a time when they are given a direct message and
really they know what the company line is as far as what's going on.
And one thing really I need to stress, which it can be overlooked, unfortunately,
is that the registration is disabled by the team.
So as soon as you make the announcement that the closure is going to happen,
you have to make sure that no more people can join and
play your game.
That looks really bad if you forget that step.
messaging so tailored to the channel and that all of the roads are going to lead to your closure FAQ and I'm going to talk a
little bit more about the closure FAQ later, but you need to make sure that your messaging is in line with
with your community. So as part of your closure plan, you're also just going to put together something that
if you don't already have it, catalogs, who's in charge of,
and what all your channels are.
Again, official and unofficial,
because fan sites on Facebook can be just as powerful,
or even more powerful, than your own official sites.
And when you tailor the messaging,
The more personal you make it, the more it's going to have an impact.
For example, if you have a group of Russian folks that meet up at a bar and
they always meet up at a certain time, drink a certain beer, whatever,
you reference that beer when you are making this closure announcement.
Just every little thing that you can do to really show people that it's personal,
and it is some big corporate branded messaging,
it's going to make the impact that much better.
So some key points to hit in the Closure FAQ are why, when,
what about all my stuff, what now, and can we still talk?
So why?
You're going to have to address it.
People are going to ask, why is this happening?
Now, you can't always be exactly direct about what's going on.
You can't give them financials.
But it's something you're going to have to address.
They want to know why it's happening.
When it's going to happen and you want to put time zone,
you want to put exact time.
Again, you want people all around the world to know
that you aren't just thinking about West Coast US
when you put this time up.
You are thinking that people need to know
what it is in their own time zone.
What's going to happen to my stuff?
Now that's a big one.
There's in-game currency that people have invested,
time and money.
You have to have a plan laid out
as far as what is going to happen and in what time.
What now? This is when you have to be a little bit careful with if you have other games you can push people to the other games but you want to not come across as too salesy or marketingy, especially at a time when people are feeling bad.
So it's something to be careful about.
And then can we still talk? How long can people keep talking with you?
through the channels that they currently are?
When does it switch over to customer service?
Do you even have that option?
These are things that you need to outline.
This is not a complete version of FAQ,
but just minimize so that you can get the gist of it.
So some other things to think about are reasonable questions.
You all play this game too, so what are some things
that you would want to know?
The tone, I used to work for Lego on the Lego Universe game,
so of course in that game,
when we were closing down that game,
we spoke to people from the point of view
that they were children, mostly children playing this game.
You have to keep that tone that you had otherwise
in your community and carry it over into the Closure FAQ.
Again, pushing people to other games.
And then disabled comments is really important.
You're gonna have plenty of spaces.
online, again, social media, your forums, other forum topics, etc.
Where people can discuss what's going on.
So this is not about stifling conversation.
But you wanna have one place where it is pristine,
where you have exactly the message that is coming from your company.
Which you can change if you need to later on, but
where there's no distracting comments coming in about people.
who are saying what is up there is wrong,
or arguing about it, or whatever.
That can go on in other spaces,
but in your closure FAQ,
you want that to be completely controlled by you.
So we've got some examples of what I think are FAQs that are done right, and also this
is still live, the glitch shut down.
I thought they did a really good job of, again, keeping the tone of how their game, how they'd
spoken with their community otherwise, and addressing all of the major issues in a thoughtful
way and a way that showed they cared.
And then I've got LEGO Universe up here.
Again, I thought we did a good job on that.
Number two, I think it's a really good example
of the tone or thinking about your audience
because why I love LEGO Universe.
For a kid, the world revolves around them.
So they're like, I like this game.
How could it be shutting down if I like it?
So you really just need to make sure
that you're speaking directly to your community
as you would otherwise.
Adapting editorial calendar.
So you're going to want to tailor your campaigns in such
a way that you're not just going to throw everything out.
Once you make the announcement that the closure is happening,
you don't just stop at every fun thing you've ever
done in your community.
But you're going to tailor it so, again,
moving people from this feeling of rage to nostalgia.
So I just have an example.
I got a very simplified active community
for a little game about zoo animals
When you have an active community, you all know what you're doing is you're trying to
get people excited about what's going to happen in the future.
You want suggestions for new things.
You want them to be showing what's going on right now in the game and inviting people
and having live...
live gameplay with the moderators and all that kind of thing,
map ideas for new worlds.
That's something when things are active,
but when you've announced the closure,
you're going to want to change that.
But it doesn't mean it just is no fun anymore.
But what you want to do is you want to take people,
take their interests and move them
towards celebrating what they have done.
So you can do tribute campaigns.
You can.
have perhaps, if you had live play with the moderators,
maybe now the moderators put together a topic in the forums
where they talk about their favorite people
who they played with and what they did and all that.
Again, just moving it to this place of nostalgia.
So, once the closure announcement has been made,
that's when.
you need to start ramping up your moderator hours.
So again, this is to the extent that you can do this.
Sometimes that's not possible,
but it's really important at this time,
if you can, to do that because.
This is going to be the time when all of these negative comments are just flooding in and
you have a lot of people who are not really contributing positively to the conversation.
So this is a time when moderators are really, really important to go through and make sure
that what's coming in is productive.
Support your team.
This is something that's really important to me as somebody who manages people who work
in community because if you work in community you do really have to have a very thick skin.
There's people saying really mean awful things to you all the time and to each other.
And so of course to some extent you have to kind of be built for that if you're working
in community.
However,
working through this kind of experience can be really more than that and it really can take its toll on people who are
day in day out
dealing with
talking with people who are just completely
enraged so as a manager you really want to make sure that you are
Reaching out to people one-on-one who are on your team.
If you can, if you work in an office together,
get people together.
If you work in a virtual team, which is often the case,
especially these international communities,
have more video chats.
Send pictures of kittens with hats on.
I mean, just really try to engage with people
and recognize that this is a tough thing
to have to work through.
The other thing is reaching out directly to positive users.
Now that's something that in community
that we're doing all the time.
We're always reaching out to people
who we see as positive influencers.
But in this case, it's another time
to really refocus on that
because you're gonna find people will emerge
and sometimes they're surprisingly people
who otherwise haven't been as active.
But they're people that really, for whatever reason,
this is where they shine.
They shine in helping people through this kind of experience.
And you want to focus on those people, contact them directly,
but also publicly really give them a lot of attention
so that they'll inspire others to do the same.
And then updating the FAQ and messaging as needed.
This is really important, too, because you
need to be flexible in your messaging.
Like I said before, the closure FAQ, that is controlled by you.
But if nobody is understanding what's
going on on a certain subject, that
means that you've written it in a way that's not clear.
And so you need to go back there and update that, and even
possibly push out additional messaging
if it really was unclear.
in a way that is just gumming up the community.
So in the final two weeks,
again, this is part of the closure plan.
You wanna have this all really timed out perfectly
and make sure that everybody in your company knows
exactly when all this messaging is going on.
You push out additional messaging via all those channels
two weeks prior to the closure.
the same in-game messaging and also email, basically any way that you have, any means
that you have to contact your community, you're going to do that two weeks ahead of time,
one week ahead of time, and one day ahead of time, and then of course at the time of
the closure itself.
And your community is going to notice that this is being done in a methodical way.
Again, going back to this whole thing about showing that you are thoughtful in the way
that you are carrying out this process is going to pay off.
And then this is the end.
I realize I'm going a little bit too fast here,
so we'll have lots of time for questions at the end.
But what you wanna do in the end is button up financial.
So make sure that all of these, the in-game currency,
anything that you've outlined
as far as how this should take place.
has taken place and things are refunded, any kind of disputes that are going on have been
resolved, and then you're going to close down all of your channels and make sure that
Although there is some dispute there depending on,
well, it depends on how much ability you have
to keep your channels open,
but usually you're gonna wanna shut down
all of your social media channels,
all of your forum except for the FAQ.
If you have the ability to keep it live for a little while,
that's just gonna help some people who are confused.
And then look forward.
You can take pride in what went right
and forgive yourself for what went wrong.
There are going to be bumps along the way.
That's just how it is.
And even, of course, if you do it perfectly,
there's always gonna be people that are upset.
That's how it is in community.
But as a person who works in community,
you have to be able to take...
Take what you learned from this and move on and just be proud of yourself
that you've done the best job that you can and shown respect to this community of people.
And that's just a little plug because we're having a party.
Lionbridge Game Services is having a party on Thursday, 6 to 9 at the Press Club.
I really wanted to make sure that everybody at the Community Summit knows about this
because it's free food and free booze, so I know how community people are.
So come on by and it's just a couple blocks from GDC.
And actually I have little tickets up here if anyone wants that as a reminder.
But that's really all that I had.
I kind of, I wanted to give some time for discussion again,
knowing that people in the room I'm sure have experience.
with this kind of thing. So if anybody has any questions. Oh, I'm also supposed to remind people
that there is a survey that's going to be sent out to you after this is over. So if you could
feel, please fill it out. Yeah. And if anybody has any questions or comments or has something
that you've had as a personal experience, I would love to hear it. Hi.
I actually work for Total Rock Studios as a community manager at the time when our contract
ended with Evolve Stage 2.
I can say before I ask my question, one thing that went over really well was we did a video
beforehand.
I interviewed all the devs talking about their experience in that nostalgic way and how they
felt and also reassured the community that good things were to come and it seemed to
go over really well.
We also took a picture of everyone that was close to the community because we had about 60 devs that were constantly communicating with them on the forums and discord and we held up a sign that thanked them.
That's awesome.
It went over really well.
Yeah.
But my question to you would be.
When you've moved on and you're working on a whole different other project,
and you still, every time you post on social media, you get those kind of like upset comments,
what's the best way to handle that so it doesn't seem like you're pushing your other content,
but you're, you also care about how they're feeling, but you want them to know and understand, like,
empathetically, we're still, you know, moving on and we're trying to survive in the studio and do things.
that we can to keep doing what we love.
It's not that we don't care about the old project.
So I'm going to repeat the question.
I think what you're saying is when you have another game that
is active and people continue to go back and complain
about the fact the previous game is already over, what can you do?
Well, I mean, to some extent, there is just the.
I feel for you kind of reaction that you can give.
I mean, if they're saying,
if some of their comment is about the new game,
you can of course speak to that and then say, sorry.
And if you have questions here or in some cases,
Another kind of fan site has sprung up that's not official that you are cool with.
You can push people to that, even for games that have closed.
They still live on in these other ways.
But there's not so much you can do.
I mean, that does, of course, continue to happen, especially when you are a company
that has several games.
That's just going to continue to happen.
But I think the main thing is like what you're saying, is the empathy.
Just tell people that you're feeling for them.
Thank them for their...
that they loved the game, you know?
And eventually that will end.
But I do think at that point,
I mean, I guess it depends on the length of time it's been.
I think there is a certain point where it is okay
to start getting a little bit more pushy
about marketing to the new game.
I guess, or just, hey, have you seen this?
Wow, check it out, in a more overt way.
But yeah, I don't know, is that helpful at all?
Yeah, no, it's not so much that we're trying to market,
but we just want them to know that it's like,
look in our shoes, we're just doing what we love.
Right, well, I guess with that, I wouldn't get too,
even though they will get personal,
I wouldn't get too personal in a way that is like,
you know, could be perceived at all as defensive, I guess.
Yeah, yeah, I would just say, you're sorry for,
I would put it on them more in that you're sorry
for their experience versus, you know,
we're sorry that it happened,
because it had to happen
for all the reasons you've outlined.
Yeah, it seems to, they've been adapting.
It has slowed down, so it's a tough one.
Thank you.
Cool, yeah, thanks.
Hi.
Hi, I'm Sam Elsbrandt, a student.
So, really great presentation.
Thanks.
Throughout all that you showed us
what community managers should do.
My question to you is, what are some of the mistakes
that you see happen often that community managers do
when they close down?
Well, I think the biggest mistake can be eliminated by that closure plan,
which is that things are not coordinated.
So one thing that I forgot to mention when I was talking about that is,
some of the departments, marketing, customer service,
they might have automatic emails.
that go out. If you, for example, don't have that coordinated and they have some sort of
auto messaging goes out that is as if the game is still going on, that is still in the movement of
acquiring new people, that looks really bad. So that's not necessarily a community manager
mistake, but as far as the entire process, that's a mistake that can be made.
And then, yeah, I mean, taking it personally
and maybe getting overwhelmed by the situation
and getting into this kind of,
can happen in any kind of situation
when you have a group of people.
I mean, at a restaurant happens when, you know,
if your boss thinks everybody sucks,
then all the waiters think everybody sucks too.
You know, like you kind of like get in that kind of feeling
where it's like, they're all against us.
So I think a mistake that can happen is people can get,
they're just getting pounded on by these horrible.
really unreasonable comments all the time,
they start to get into the space where they don't,
their skin isn't thick enough and they lash out.
So I think those two things really,
again, having things very clearly defined,
who's in charge of what in a timeline
and having that predefined,
that will eliminate most of the mistakes.
Thank you.
Yeah, you're welcome.
Hello.
Hi.
So you mentioned that people, you know,
the company creates a world.
And people come in and they develop a lot of sort
of emotional investment and even economic assets.
And then the world gets closed down.
And so it just made me think.
Suppose I was the governor of Hawaii and a bunch
of people came there and they built buildings
and got to know everyone.
I just decided that it wasn't working for me.
So I kick everyone out of Hawaii and I blow it up
and send it under the ocean.
My thought is, why do the game companies close these places down instead of just releasing them into the wild?
Why don't you let people sustain their game?
Right, I think in some cases, actually with Glitch,
they did, I think they actually did
release it into the wild somewhat.
So some companies do do that.
It's mostly, I think, has to do with brand,
ownership of your own brand.
So, you know, if you release it into the wild and then it turns into some alt-right something,
you know what I mean, like then it's associated with your brand, it's a big, big risk.
So that is, you know, again, speaking to the thing I was talking about as far as people
thinking it's you no matter who you are.
It doesn't matter if you would say to somebody, oh, that's actually not my game.
They're going to see that mark on there and that character and they're going to think
it's you.
So that's really, that's the main reason.
Good question.
Yeah.
I'm Garrett.
I'm a producer with the Army Game Studio.
And while not entirely shutting down a game, what would you say, with the steps, like,
we're seizing development, but the game's still going to be live.
It's on the live support, it's bug fixing.
How do you message that without everyone going, oh, it's done, bye, and just walking off?
Well, I guess it depends on what your intention really is with the game.
You know, I mean, if the intention is to keep it going,
I would be transparent about that.
If your intention is not to keep it going, I would.
This gets into the question of your overall business plan,
because there's only so many resources
that you can put on any project.
So if you have other games going on,
and this one isn't really going to make any more money for you,
or it's not going to be a focus, and you're probably
going to want to have fewer campaigns, less moderation,
whatever, anything that costs money,
and put it to your other games.
You know, if you're planning on, really are planning on keeping it going long term, I
would just, you know, based on what kind of need you need for moderators, community managers
for it currently, I would base that plan on that going forward.
But if you really are planning on closing it down, I would start to, again, it depends
on.
how much you're able to tell people,
but I would start to ramp it down
and save your resources for games
that really are gonna be making money for you.
Okay, thank you.
Mm-hmm.
I have another question. Sure.
When you close down something or you cease development,
emotions are really high, and sometimes,
as you all know, community members
have invested so much emotionally in something.
When it goes away,
Is there any advice you can give when they're kind of imploding
and people are reaching out to you from the community talking about
even something as serious as suicide based on it
or that everything they're like is going wrong and it's just one more thing
or I know you mentioned nostalgia.
I guess that would probably be the best way to take it,
but I wasn't sure.
Well, when it comes to people talking about suicide,
you should as a community manager have...
guidelines in place already how to deal with any threat to one's own self or others.
So I would continue on that same plan that you have.
And as far as people imploding otherwise in a way that isn't dangerous, same thing really
is to reach out to people and talk about.
the good old days, basically.
I mean, you should be doing that individually,
but also with the way that you put together
your editorial calendar, that you continue to push people.
If people are just like, so sad,
I don't have the whatever X thing to do anymore.
We, you know, hey, we just started a contest
that is the best moments from that.
Let's take a look at it.
Okay, wonderful, thank you.
You're welcome.
comes to suicide and most of it was very unfeeling.
So it was almost cold.
So it was hard to, to the point where other community members
were reaching out saying,
please help this other community member.
I would, I'm happy to talk with you directly about that.
That's actually really very important to me, that subject.
And it's something that you have to have in your guidelines,
exactly, a phone tree, what are local resources, what people
should do, volunteer community managers and moderators.
There should be a very exact plan
about how to deal with that.
It shouldn't be left for the community
to help each other out.
It's pretty dangerous.
Yeah.
Mm-hmm.
Hello.
Hi.
My name is Alex.
I'm working on a game that will close at the end of the year.
But for contract reasons, it's actually not doing bad.
And the users will be very surprised because of that,
because they know it's doing all right.
They know it's the same number of players
we had one year ago, or stuff like that.
And we are not quite allowed to tell them
that it's happening for contract reasons.
Do you have any advice in this case?
You mean it's like IP?
You're not allowed to renew the IP?
Yeah.
That's a good question because, yeah, I mean, it is one of the things you have to address that.
I guess I would say, you know, kind of the catch-all weird diverting resources to other games kind of thing.
I mean, you can always kind of go that way.
You can't say that the game isn't doing well.
You can say that, you know, even though it's popular, it doesn't make sense for us financially, which is true.
It's tough though. It is tough when you have a really active, thriving community where there's no guess that it's coming.
But yeah, that is the truth. It doesn't make sense financially if you aren't going to have the contract anymore for that IP.
So yeah, you have to be kind of vague, unfortunately, because you can't talk about that directly.
Thank you. And I have another question.
being a free to play games, we have the free to play players and the whales.
And do you think so?
I'm thinking maybe in the last month that everybody should have access to what the
whales previously had to the what we could buy on hard currency.
Oh, sure.
Do you think this is a good idea or maybe it would make the whales even more angry?
I don't think so. I mean, no, in fact, that's I didn't include that in here,
but that is something that you can do at the end is just pretty much make it like,
all right, everybody can have whatevs. I mean, cause it is the end. I mean,
a whale, the whales, they shouldn't be mad. It's like the last month, you know,
I think of course you will, again,
there's always going to be some people who are that way,
but I think generally more people are going to be happy if you do that.
So I would say go for it. Yeah.
And then I think this is prior, oh, the last question.
Wrap it up.
Yeah.
As you probably know, PR is a little on the abrupt side
when it comes to covering your game while it's live,
and man, they jump on it
as soon as you make the closing announcement.
Sure.
How do you take steps to control the damage
when you have media or gaming media cover closure,
especially when it's outside of your control mechanisms,
like within your own communities?
What steps have you seen that works?
Not to throw anybody under the rock, paper, shotgun.
Some of the more, they make a business out of slandering
some of the game companies and stuff like that
when they go down.
So the question is really like the folks in the media,
what they do with the story that your PR department
has put out, like them taking it and?
Whether you put out a PR or not.
Like if they catch wind through game communities
that a game goes down, boom, they put you on blast
on the front page.
Well, I think part of to prevent that even from happening
in the first place is to take control of that message
and send out a press release.
Because if they're catching wind of it,
that would mean your closure plan has kind of gone awry.
You know what I mean?
If they're catching wind of it from your community
versus having received a direct announcement
or seeing that there's actually a press release,
I didn't mention that here, but there should
be a press release live.
on your website, then they are going to be kind of making up stories from rumors.
So that's the one thing.
But of course, again, there's always going to be people who want to sell more banner
ads or whatever and kind of make it more sensational than it is.
The only way there is, again, to just direct people to the correct.
information. If you have your PR folks, depending on the size of your company,
should have probably direct relationships with some of the people at those
companies and reach out to them directly, correct if they have information that's
wrong. But there's only so much you can do to control that other than just again
have a coordinated messaging in the first place and then also having a place
where people can refer to you for the correct, you know, information from your
company.
So I'm sorry, so you would basically, so even if we make all the announcements
and everything internally, social networking, would you suggest actually
sending out a traditional PR to the media?
Yeah, definitely.
Okay.
And having it on your website live.
Okay, thank you.
All right, well thank you.
Thanks everybody for attending.