I think we have to start.
And welcome and good morning everyone.
My name is Philip Ericsson and I work as a sound designer
at EA DICE in Stockholm where I've been for like four years
worked on both Battlefront titles and Battlefield.
And during this talk, I will talk about the heroes,
sounds for the heroes of Star Wars Battlefront 2.
And these are the topics that I will cover
during this presentation.
I will talk about the sound design direction that we had
for this game.
And I will go through some challenges that we had during
this production.
I will show a lot of examples, both video and sound.
And I will go into detail, showing you the systems that I
made to create these sounds and play them in the game.
But first, let's look at some real gameplay video stuff
that contains a lot of different abilities, heroes, and action.
Enjoy.
Oh
How many heads did you miss?
So, the sound design direction that we had for this game was...
We wanted to try to get as far away from the game sounding
gamey and let it sound more real, believable, immersive,
and really put you in a galaxy far, far away.
It was, of course, the most important thing
to stay true to the Star Wars universe
and make the game sound like the movies.
We wanted to support the stories and create feelings
and enhance the characteristics of the heroes and the villains.
And it was very important for us that it sounded like the sounds were actually created in the world,
interacting with the materials, the different environments and the characters,
like the newer Star Wars movies, for example Rogue One.
And this made the soundscape feel a bit more realistic and a bit grittier,
although we at the same time strived to make a very clean and dynamic mix and readable for the player.
Some challenges that we had,
one of the big ones was mixed eras.
We didn't only have the original trilogy,
the prequel trilogy, and the sequel trilogy.
We also had stuff from the cartoons,
and you could say that we also created a new era
with the single player story with Iden.
And we wanted these to sound different from each other
and make their individual contrasts stand out
while still treating them
with the same philosophy to make them fit
into the shared soundscape.
In order to handle all the abilities
and the scope for this project,
we needed to create smart solutions
that would help us deliver fast,
but still maintain high quality.
So we created some versatile systems
that could handle many different types of ability sounds.
And these sounds, they shared strategies.
And this system made it a lot easier to iterate.
And you could do both general changes to all abilities,
as well as individual tweaks per sound.
And this really helped both the design process
and maintaining the sound throughout the project
and the mixing stage.
We also wanted to focus a great deal on the gameplay feedback.
We created a mix that was less compressed and clean and a lot
more readable, with clear distance feedback
and directionality and other important gameplay indications.
So as I said, the mix was less compressed,
and it left more space for each sound.
And it was easier to give the power
to a sound where it was needed.
We also made distant content for all the abilities.
And they are affected by the environment where they are
created as well, where the sounds are created.
And we also do a thing where the enemy sounds are higher in
priority and louder than your friendliest sounds.
We also really tried to focus on making different
perspectives, so for example, when you are being affected
by an ability, that was something that was important,
and also dealing and taking damage so that you got
feedback from that.
We also in the sound design wanted to create clear
characteristics between the heroes and the villains
as well as an individual character's own sound signature
so that you could easily spot enemies.
One thing that is very hard when working with Star Wars
is the lack of variation and also the gameplay abilities
being different from the reference in the movies.
And we always try to take the reference from the movies
and try to expand, find elements, and recreate sounds
and a variation in perspective, but still
keep the character of the reference sound,
but just making it fit gameplay, basically.
Sometimes there was no reference or very vague reference in the films,
but we needed to use the same recipes to make them fit into the Star Wars universe.
Lucasfilm, they also wanted to approve some of our sounds,
and something that was very important to them was that the Force sounds didn't sound too magical,
too techy, or too similar to Marvel.
And we tried to use the same principles as Ben Burtt, Matt Wood and David Accord to get the same feeling.
And the direction from Lucasfilm was often less is more, or the more believable it was, the better they thought it was.
In the game as well, sometimes the abilities
have very little visual feedback.
So a visual representation of an ability
could just be an animation with a hand being lifted up
in the air, like Darth Vader's force choke, for example.
But the sound still needed to provide
the diffuse but yet expected sound.
So let's move on to the examples.
And I will give three examples.
I will start with Kylo Ren and his ability Force Freeze.
And for this example, I used almost exclusively
the sound effects from the movie stems,
and he's from the sequel trilogy.
Next up is Darth Maul from the prequel trilogy
and his ability Force Push, which had a clear reference,
but I needed to make a hybrid with new sounds.
And last but not least, Luke Skywalker and Force Repulse.
And this had never been shown in any movie,
so I had to come up with a completely new sound,
but it still needed to sound original trilogy.
I will show you a few scenes from The Force Awakens
with Kylo Ren's Force Freeze.
So yeah, Kylo Ren and his ability Force Freeze,
which surprisingly freezes the opponent
for a duration of time,
which made this a looping ability,
it could differ in time.
And as you saw, this ability had very clear reference
from various scenes in The Force Awakens.
And I could base my sound almost entirely
on the sounds from the movie stems
and the sounds that Lucas or Skywalker Sound
provided me with.
Just a gentle massage to make them fit better into the game
and some added elements for different perspectives
and added variation.
So when I started working on a new hero for this game,
I always just wrote down a few words as a sound design
direction for myself mainly.
And for this character, I think Kylo Ren is, of course, evil.
But he's still afraid as well.
The sounds that David Accord made for him for the movie, they have a musical tone to them.
They sound modern but also very distorted. So I started with extracting the sounds from the movie
stems and I was quickly able to just make a loop out of the sounds.
And I decided to split this looping sound into a noise
layer and a tonal layer.
And I will play you an example, and then I will tell
you why I did this.
So the first sound you will hear is the reference from the
film and then my split loops.
you
So why did I do this?
Since I split the loops, I could play them in two
different samplers.
And I could have set them in time from each other.
I could also apply different randomization, like LFOs and
the pitch and the amplitude, and just make a lot more
randomization with quite short loops.
And I could also route the tonal bass layer.
into the subwoofer or the LFE channel
without making the crisp noise layer unclear.
After this, I needed to find some more variation
for these sounds that I had extracted.
But I of course wanted them to have the exact same feeling
as the rest of the sounds.
And especially for the affected perspective,
I needed to add some sounds.
So I started searching and I found this boomy Canon sound that had the same kind of tonality
and very nice tone to it.
And I also did some sound effects recordings myself.
I bought this huge party balloon and I took my LS100 Olympus recorder, handy recorder
And I just pushed the membranes straight into the balloon
and then ripped it away.
And this made a really nice ripping sound.
And I just added some distortion on that, and then
it sounded quite a lot like Kylo Ren.
I will play those two examples as well.
Yeah, and after this, I basically just categorized
the sounds that I had for the different perspectives
and the different things that I needed to provide
for Kylo Ren's close perspective,
the distant perspective, and also when you are
being affected by the ability.
And this is how it all sounds.
I will play the singles sounds first
and then a combined variation.
And now let's look at it in game because it doesn't matter if it sounds good as a single sound,
it needs to be in the mix and it needs to fit there.
So the next example is Darth Maul and I will start with
showing a clip from the Phantom Menace.
So yeah, Darth Maul from the prequel trilogy and this ability Force Bush had a clear reference
as you saw during the fight with Obi-Wan Kenobi.
But I wasn't really able to use this sound for the game because the gameplay ability
was quite different.
So I needed to make a hybrid that hopefully worked equally well.
And again, I started with the sound design direction.
And to me, this character is angry, fast, silent.
He doesn't speak a lot.
He's furious and lethal.
So I took the reference sound and sort of analyzed it and I found out that it's a soft kind of explosion with a lot of flanger on it.
And I wanted my sound to also keep that character of course, but I wanted it to sound a bit more 2018 and a lot more punchy.
So what I did is I created some new explosions with flanger on them.
And I will play the reference sound and then my new explosions.
And to be honest, when I started making this sound, I had a bit of a struggle to find a way and really know what I wanted to create.
So at DICE in my studio, I always have an SM58 microphone just lying on my table.
So I can always grab it and just make sounds with my mouth and stuff.
So what I did was that I booted up the game and just
performed a sound with my voice.
And this is very silly, but it helps.
And it makes just your thoughts or your sound that
you have in your head, you can get it into Pro Tools or
whatever in a very sort of fast way.
And then you can start taking it apart and replacing it with
other sounds.
And we'll play you the recording that I did.
And you will hear that it's actually not that far from the
last, from the final result.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Roar, roar, yeah.
Bhai bhai yah!
Very silly.
So after this, I started thinking about what kinds of sounds that I could use to replace this
and some evil sounds I wanted to create. And one of the most evil sounding things, I think, is
feedback. It sounds super, yeah, scary. So I recorded some feedback basically in my room. And
then I also wanted to add some more sort of prequel-y tone to it.
So I got some synth sounds that Ben Mintow had made.
And it added some raw power to it and the prequel character
that I wanted.
And this sound is basically very simple.
It's the flanged explosions, the feedback, and the synth
sound, and nothing too fancy, no fancy plugins and anything.
And this could easily have been done by Ben
Barrett very early.
And I will play you the feedback recording and then some of the synth and then those two combined as well.
This is probably very nice for you who are hangover as well.
Yeah.
And now let's listen to the whole sound with the flanged explosion as well and the distant variation.
Let's look at it in game again.
And my next example is Luke Skywalker and since this ability doesn't exist in any movie,
I will start with showing a clip from the game as well.
So, Luke Skywalker and the Force repulse. And as I said, no reference at all from anywhere, so I had
to come up with a completely new sound, but it still needed to sound very much like Star Wars,
Luke Skywalker, and just expand the universe in a respectful way. And my sound design direction
for this guy was powerful, trustful, dominant, natural and humane.
And I started with doing some sound effect recordings for this ability and I wanted to
record some earthy tones, some sort of air sounds and the force from the ground because
this ability basically has a charge up where the ground starts rumbling or like an earthquake
and then after that you have the force repulse explosion and for that I recorded some slinky.
And I will play a few of the sounds that I found.
I found a baby alligator sound that I pitched down a lot,
which sounded quite cool.
And then some of the slinky stuff as well.
And I also used my balloon for this, for some air crackles.
So yeah, let's listen.
So that was my start.
And I had to create a lot of content for disability because
I had a
the charge up or the sort of force from the ground sound
as a separate one shot, and then the force explosion as one.
And I needed to create first close
and distant perspectives for these sounds.
And also they were quite modular in game.
So for example, if you were outside,
you got debris effects and stuff like that.
If you were inside, you didn't get that.
So I needed to provide the sound that fit
with the VFX and the visuals in the game.
So we'll just play all the content that I made for this ability with the earthquakey stuff and the
force repulse explosion.
Let's look at it in game again.
I will do a quick conclusion on just the sound design part,
but then I will talk about the system.
So it's not done yet.
The sound design direction, I think,
really helped making the sounds, especially
in an early state of the sound design,
just to find the right path.
And it feels like it's always good to think and search
with an emotional direction in mind.
The movie stems and the sound assets that we received from Skywalker Sound were extremely helpful.
Even though we had to add a lot of sounds and change them, it provided us with a very good guide and also with a solid bass.
Unique sound effect recordings to try to find and record
what is actually needed for a specific ability
and tailored for a specific ability.
It's always nicer to record something
that sounds Star Wars or sounds correct for the ability
than trying to shape something into sound,
sounding correctly.
Less is more.
The more in world and the more natural the sounds were,
the better they fit the soundscape, it felt like.
The basic sound design technique that we used made it feel like we were just an extension of the creators of Star Wars from the beginning.
And the vocalization sound design really helped. I will definitely use it in the future as well.
So let's move on to the systems.
So for this project our general philosophy was to make master patches.
So we made master patches for explosions, blasters,
star fighters, hero abilities, all the big categories.
And we had a lot of sounds to make for this game,
so we needed to create solid, shared systems
to be able to handle the large amount of sounds.
And for the last Battlefront game,
we made a lot more unique solutions,
but we couldn't really do that this time.
And this also helped keeping consistency.
So the sounds were more consistent, and also between
different sound designers, since we all had to work on
different parts of the game.
Also, these shared systems, a lot of sounds, they share
sounds as well.
So it wouldn't really make sense to redo that logic for
each sound and tweak it every time.
And this also helped the mixing process because we could do general changes to the whole category of sounds
or otherwise just go in and tweak individual sounds very fast.
And we had a thing called a sound patch configuration.
So each sound had a sound patch configuration, which
inherits properties and parameters and values from the
master patch.
But it lets you switch out the sound assets that are used,
even the ones that are shared, actually.
And you could enable and disable various layers.
And you could tweak chosen properties from the master
patch, but still maintain the foundation of it.
So this is the master patch for hero abilities.
And I will just quickly go through and tell you
what these red boxes are, and then we
will zoom in and go into detail what they could be used for.
So this is a SFX layer, an add-on one-shot layer
for the main force element.
And this is the main force element.
also one shot. And this is the loop SFX layer, an add on layer to the main loop part. And this is
the main loop part. This box handles reflections and this abilities, I've said that so many
times, debris. So, let's zoom in on this box. So, this is the main loop part. And this is the
And just quickly first, an explanation what it is that
you're looking at.
So these boxes here, we get a bunch of values from the game,
triggers and stuff.
We do logic, processing, math to modulate the amplitude of
the pitch.
And then we send that into the sampler, or
sound player, basically.
math and the logic that we have before it will make the sampler play the sound in a
certain way. So, with that, this layer I generally just added to give some gameplay feedback.
And in this example I used it for the force choke ability. So when Darth Vader catches
someone in his grip, then I play a one shot sound and it could sound like this.
Let's move on.
The force main element.
And this consists of three samplers.
One force close, one force tail, one force distant.
And the tail one is for the looping abilities.
If I wanted to play a stop sound or a deactivate sound
or something like that.
And I didn't need to have a distant one of that one
because it felt like I could instead just fade out
the loop of distance.
I will play you an example from Forest Lightning.
Let's start with the forest close.
And then the tail sound, or the stop, deactivate.
and a distant variation.
Cool.
So the loop SFX layer.
This was very neat, because I could just add an element,
but keep the main loop quite.
like as a foundation. I could also do stuff like fade in over time, pitch over time, increase the
pitch for example, which I did for the four stroke ability as well. So if you're caught in a grip,
I will slowly fade in the loop with the bone crackling and also increase the pitch slightly
so that it becomes a bit nastier and it could sound like this.
And the next layer is the main loop layer.
And it consists of two samplers.
And they could fade in and out of each other seamlessly,
depending if you're running towards the sound or away from
the sound.
And the example that I will play here is an ability called
dark aura.
And I will start with a close one.
and then the distant.
Let's move on to the reflections.
A very important layer because this
really makes it sound like it's coming from the world and the sound is
being created and reverberating through the environment.
And these sounds were all shared amongst all the ability sounds,
but I had the possibility to turn it off if I didn't need it.
And we had five different area types for this game.
Field, forest, canyon slash urban, indoor small,
and indoor large.
And I will play two samples per each area type.
The debris. These sounds were also shared amongst all the ability sounds, and the same as the
reflection, so I could just turn it off if I didn't need it. And we had a lot of different
debris sounds for different materials, but I will just play three of them. Rock, snow, and vegetation.
Something that was also good with both these layers were that I could play them, for example, on the
start sound. I could also play them on the activate or the tail sound so I could use this for
different abilities. So let's move on to the processing or the DSP.
This box handles the LFE filtering and this was a new approach for us.
In previous titles we had always had a specific sample playing for the LFE but this was a
bit more costly.
You needed a specific sample, a sampler for the LFE and it could also cause face cancellation
and stuff like that.
So we tried this approach for this game and I think it worked out really well.
We could also, for example, ADSR the LFE send so that way it
didn't rumble too long in the LFE to keep it clean.
And this part is the distant filtering.
And this just helps gluing the close sound to the distant
sound, and also then after a while on further distant,
making the distant sound even more distant.
And this part is a slapback delay that we do with raycast.
So we have four raycasts on the player.
And so these raycasts calculate the slapback or the delay time.
And this really helps gluing the noisy reflection layer
to the more tonal force layer.
So I just route the force one shot, for example,
through this.
And this is, of course, depending on the environment you are standing in, you will get a different
slapback in quad.
And this part is a flanger.
And this I mainly used for the looping abilities.
So on angular velocity when you move your character, I add a slight flanging effect
just to make it get some variation.
And also it sounds a bit more Star Wars.
And these are the outputs.
The LFE output in the top, the object output placed where the
sound is created, and last, the flat slapback in the quad.
And as you see, I didn't show you the whole patch,
actually, so there is a big block over here that I need to
go through before we're done.
And this is also extremely.
important. It's a cam shake and a pad rumble, or the sound driven cam shake and pad rumble.
So I could shake the camera and add pad rumble to my abilities and this really helps making them
powerful. And I could also with this one do it on the start sound, on the stop sound,
I could also do a slight cam shake throughout the looping ability, for example.
And uh, just to make it a bit more clear what I meant with the sound patch configuration. So, we
looked at the master patch and then I take all these values and parameters and shared sounds
and stuff and the, the sound patch configuration inherits those things in this view that you
see. So, the sound patch configuration.
And I could configure chosen parameters.
And this sound patch configuration have sound slots
so I could switch out the sounds, even the shared assets,
if I just wanted to change one of those.
I could enable and disable various layers.
And this also made it a bit more optimized.
And this was also where I could start and stop various layers
from each other, offset from each other.
I could do the cam shake per sound.
And since I can't go into too much detail,
I will just show you a picture of how it looks.
And then if you are interested in more,
you can look at the GDC Vault.
Martin Loxton from Frostbite Audio
had a presentation about it.
And the presentation is called Smart Sound Design Using
Modularity and Data Inheritance.
So I will show you a few clips of how
the area types work in the game and the materials as well.
and another video with how we handle the distant processing and also if the sound is created
indoor and you are outdoor for example.
So let's summarize.
For this game, we had a lot more heroes.
You can see it was more than twice as many.
And to make around 180 WAV files with around 5 to 10 variations,
so it was a lot to create.
And we wouldn't have been able to do this
without the sound patch configuration
and the shared systems.
We also focused a lot more on the gameplay feedback
and added content for distant sounds for the abilities
and the affected perspective, as well as
dealing and taking damage.
And we took one further step in making it even more in-world
and with the debris and the reflections
and the raycast-driven delay.
And the mix was a lot less compressed, as I said,
and more focused, and a lot more readable for the player.
And this was a big improvement
from Star Wars Battlefront, the first one.
Questions you have?
Thank you.
Let me get started. I have a few. Um, let's see. Boop. Maybe someone here has a question already.
Right? Uh, hey, great presentation and great sounding game. I enjoyed it a lot. Um, for the
indoor and outdoor, are you marking this up manually or you're detecting this procedurally?
Yeah, we are marking it manually. Just with areas.
Alright, so now I got it.
You mentioned that there was very little visual feedback for the abilities
and that Lucas didn't want it to be magical.
Yeah.
How did you do that with the gameplay guys and you to make sure that it was still readable?
Because I imagine it was especially hard for the game designers to make sure that
even though there's nothing visual there, that the mechanic was clear.
Yeah, that was a hard question actually.
Yeah, I'm familiar with it.
Yeah.
I'm not really sure, actually.
Like, I collaborated with game designers a lot.
So sometimes maybe they didn't actually
need to have a super visual VFX for anything,
because the sound could provide that sound,
and you could easily know where it came from and stuff
like that.
And I think also Lucasfilm probably
wanted the VFX and the visuals to be quite sort of.
down to earth and simple as well in a way. Of course there are very sort of magical looking
things as well but yeah I think it was just a combination so if we could do it with just
the sound and the animation it it worked. Was it something that you gameplay tested a lot and
did you iterate on it like that? Yeah yeah absolutely yeah we created a lot of abilities
that we sort of scrapped as well and just had to start over.
So we were playtesting a lot and just finding the right path.
And on the question about actually the relationship with the gameplay guys and the visual guys,
because you mentioned that the sound was driving the camera shake, which from a perspective
of making it really work, sounds like a great idea.
But I can also imagine that some of the people in the design team or possibly on the visual
side might have a bit of a problem with the sound team being responsible for the actual
camera.
So how did you handle that?
Did they have some control over it after you guys, or did you just...
No, it was just me basically, but of course I also showed them what I did.
And they also do some cam shake actually, but this was more for the actual moment where the sound is the biggest.
But it's very hard with the camshake especially because some people don't like it at all.
And of course it can prevent very fast gameplay.
But it really does make a difference for the feel of the ability.
So we just found the right path and not too much but we didn't overdo it either.
Was that only for the multiplayer or was that also for the singleplayer?
Also for the singleplayer for sure.
And you mentioned that
you couldn't have the unique solutions that you could on the previous project.
Was that simply because of the scope increase and the same amount of time?
Yeah, we had a lot less time and we had to create a lot more sounds.
And we tried to make shared systems for the first one as well,
but after a while it was like we had a lot of new gameplay features and stuff like that,
so we just had to make it.
So we made a lot more sound patches with specific logic in them.
But this time it was like, okay, so we have at least stuff to base on, like the first Star Wars game,
so we could make those systems shared and just improve on those so that we could use them more easily for different kinds of sounds.
Cool. Thanks.
Thank you.
Hi.
Thanks so much for the talk, and great talk, great sound
examples as well.
I have a curiosity about the close and distant perspective
specifically in terms of the asset creation.
So as a process, is it more about finding different sounds
to work from, or is it more of a processing thing
that you do within your DAW, or is it a mix of two?
It's a mix of course, but for example the explosions, like a real explosion,
it will sound different depending on how far you are from it.
So I always try to completely change those sounds for example
But also try to just with the plugins and stuff
Modulate or like create the sort of a real world behavior for I mean some of these sounds are quite
Strange and there are not like a recording of these on distance, so I had to make something that that worked
But yeah, we do try to change a lot of sounds so that they sound
Distance
Thank you.
For the filtering LFE technique, was it really just
using the filter as a crossover?
Was there any additional massaging processing to
optimize the effect?
It was a crossover.
Exactly.
And then we don't send the full sound into the LFE, we can
just send a little bump of it so we can do the attack.
We don't have to rumble it all through the subwoofer.
Terrific.
Thank you.
Hi, so I have a thank you for the talk.
I have a couple of questions.
So additionally to the different samples
for the different perspectives, did you
add some real-time processing to the sounds?
Like do you still have, do you add reverb in real time?
Or is it just like the, yeah?
Yeah, we do add reverb depending on the area that you're in and then also the stuff that I showed
with the DSP processing like the filtering and the slap backs and stuff like that.
Okay. Yeah. And did you have variations for like when you're playing a certain hero and when
you're against a certain hero or is it exactly the same sounds in both cases?
What do you mean exactly?
Like, is there a difference in the sounds you play when you're against a certain hero?
Ah, I see, I see.
And when you play it, or is it exactly the same?
It's the same, but when you're in third person, like you have the camera, you know, you are the character.
Then I play certain sounds, or you most of them.
or you get the close perspective all the time of course but if you were
uh... an enemy or a friendly and uh...
the hero runs around you will get the different sounds all the time so.
Okay so the perspective makes the work for uh... yeah exactly.
uh... and uh... so I uh... some sounds are really uh... long have a pretty long tail
especially like Luke Skywalker's you can hear uh... the echo in the distance so what
happens to to that kind of stuff when you have the full mix and uh...
everybody's like firing and etc.
Yeah, I mean you can't do that for every sound but it glues the mix together as well and makes it just have a sort of depth to it.
But that was quite a specific case, that was very long.
But it was a very powerful ability and I wanted it to sound big so then I made it big.
But we do sometimes as well, if you have a tail in the sound,
we can make the release time shorter.
Or you make the tail shorter, for example,
when you're indoors, so that you can add the indoor reflections
on that instead of having the thunder tail.
But is it something that you drop for example if you have too
many uh person firing and uh some explosions so maybe you
don't want to hear the tail that time? Yeah. Uh I mean our
HD uh our system uh does that for us basically. And also some
scoping. Okay. And last one um so you work um the your custom
audio engine is like you work 100 percent in it or do you uh
okay. Yeah. So there is no wise or uh stuff like that. No. Not
Thank you. Thank you.
Hello, thank you very much for the talk.
I'm wondering because there's so many super,
very natural locations, like you're on Hoth,
and there's the snow-covered canyon, or you're on Endor,
and there's all this foliage.
What kind of recording was done to make those locations seem
like they're real?
Was there a lot of field recording done?
Yeah, absolutely. A lot. I always have my recorder with me and I know that Ben Mintoy, he went to
Iceland for example, recorded the real mud pits for the first game and also snow and stuff for
Hoth. So we tried to go to the real locations. We also went to the Redwood Forest and but we
also tried to base it on what Ben Burtt and these other...
fantastic sound designers made.
So we take their recordings and then we might change them
and put in new content so that it sounds a bit fresher maybe.
But yeah, a lot of field recording.
Thank you.
Two more questions.
First, what was your memory budget
and how did you meet that using the swapping out sounds?
Like how dynamic was the?
the loading and unloading?
So the memory body that I can't remember...
It was...
big enough.
Big enough?
And second question, how big was your sound team?
Like both sound designers, audio programmers. It seems like maybe
the sound designers here are doing a lot of like programming.
in the tool?
Yeah, we were, I think we peaked on like 12 people from Dice, but then we collaborated
with Motive and Criterion as well.
And so I think in total, Rosa, how many were we?
Like 25-ish?
Yeah.
Rosa is from Criterion.
Cool, thank you.
Yeah.
Hey.
Cool, thank you.
Yeah.
I had a question about the dynamic mix. I didn't see any
nodes in your master patch that sort of alluded to an HDR system
or the mixing I would imagine.
with all the force powers and the low end,
the clutter of the mix had some challenges.
So how did you address that kind of dynamically in the mix?
Yeah.
So we do the HDR.
We set the loudness or the priority of it in the outputs.
So there are no nodes for it, basically.
But yeah, we're.
definitely needed the HDR to figure this out and also in the game mode, Heroes vs. Villains,
there are a lot of sounds playing all the time and they are of course quite huge as
well because you are all heroes. So yeah, it was a tough one. But it helped a lot with
the HDR system. That I can tell you.
Hey. So for every power, how many baked variations of every sound would you make for one
perspective? I think, yeah, as I said in the conclusion, I think I made around five to ten
variations of every sound. But then of course there were cases where I had a lot more
sounds or I just found a lot more variations and then I could create that. So.
some sounds probably had, I don't know, 25 even.
So it could vary a lot, but that's sort of the ballpark of how many variations,
so that you don't get too much repetition.
And as for one power, how much time would you spend making just one power?
A day, two days?
Yeah, I think like a day or something.
Sometimes I had to redo and of course I iterated on it, but...
Yeah, I would say maybe a day.
Or half a day sometimes when it was quick.
And a lot longer sometimes as well.
But yeah.
Reverb-related questions.
So for reverb, are you guys programmatically sort
of generating your reverb zones, or are you hand-tuning those?
And how many reverbs are you running?
We are hand-tuning all the areas,
and then we can set an IR reverb to that specific area.
And I think we can have three IORs playing at the same time,
but that's, of course, extremely costly.
And also, they can't be too long, because I did that once
and I had a crash and people were angry.
It sounded very good, but the game crashed.
Yeah, I bet.
Thanks.
Yeah.
Thank you so much for coming.