Hi everybody, I'm Dimitri. I've been in game development for about 15 years now, and I've done stuff like design casual games, produce casual games, design mobile games, start a game company that makes mobile games, be the GM of a company that makes social games, be the GM of Zynga New York, and work on a giant console franchise which shall remain nameless.
Before all of that stuff, though, I went to grad school and studied architectural history.
So that weird combination of backgrounds is why I wanted to talk about
something we rarely talk about in this business, which is not the games that we make,
but the places in which we make them.
So before we start looking at some of those, let's take a super brief look at some history.
The office you work in didn't spring fully formed out of Ralph Baer's head or his garage.
Like the games themselves, commercial office forms have a long history,
which I'm going to go through in about three slides.
The first serious influence on game development offices starts with the modern factory.
This is one of the first times that we see a need to put a lot of people in a limited
space to perform repetitive tasks without moving very much.
Pretty soon, an industry springs up around trying to make these movements even more efficient,
and between that, the desire to have employees under something like constant surveillance,
and the growing costs of commercial real estate, you wind up with something like this.
Just to get this out of the way, this is an open office.
Every 20 years, this gets reinvented.
And every 10 years, everybody decides that it's horrible,
and there's a bunch of pushback against it.
And for the reasons that you see here, surveillance,
paternalism, and cost, especially cost,
open offices are not going away.
Sorry.
So instead of starting another debate about studies
show open offices suck.
Let's take them as a given for just a few minutes and talk about how we can make this better
rather than pretending we'll be able to abolish it completely anytime soon.
So, besides factories turned into open offices, another ancestor of the modern game development space is this, the art studio.
These spaces started out as places that were just optimized for light, great big giant windows, and ease of access to supplies.
But starting about the mid-20th century, the idea of the studio as a social space
and eventually as an art object itself,
starts to gather some steam.
So signifying that you're a creative
through your workspace is an old idea,
but we also have Andy Warhol's factory
to thank for a lot of what we expect
for someplace that's called a studio today.
And the third major branch in the ancestry
of game development spaces is the science lab.
These are utilitarian spaces
that also have great big giant windows
and are devoted to experimentation.
Laboratories are where computers first started to show up in the workplace
and the total takeover of the desktop by computer equipment
was very much birthed in the lab.
This is what, yeah, you see the timeline
of what an engineering space looks like.
This is what an engineering space looks like right now.
And this is also what every other space
looks like right now.
So what you probably started to notice
in these last three slides is that
despite starting down three very different paths,
these workplace types wound up
at a really familiar destination, rows of desks.
So the key differentiator is not what the rows of desks are,
but what you surround them with and how you arrange them.
because the rows of desks themselves are really the nucleus of the commercial workspace.
So in an industry famously on the cutting edge of technology and culture, what have
we done with all those rows of desks?
Unfortunately the first answer is a bunch of bullshit that nobody likes.
Last year this guy, the amazing Kyle Drexel of Wargaming, helped me to run a survey about
game industry workplaces.
And I guess this is already kind of spoiled by the factoid
at the top of the slide.
But one of the big takeaways from that survey
is that most game developers don't really
like their workspace.
Here's why.
There's sort of a bunch of reasons.
Reason number one, which kind of surprised me,
was it's just too noisy.
It's too noisy.
About 30-odd percent of game developers
thought their workspace was too noisy.
And this obviously has to do with the fact that
When engineers were to design a perfect workspace,
they're going to come up with someplace that allows them
to get into that flow state that everyone is after.
When designers design a perfect workspace,
they're going to design a space that
allows them to collaborate and talk to each other.
And artists fall somewhere in between.
Marketers fall somewhere on the phone.
This obviously has a lot of different applications.
So personal space.
This is a little bit more out of folks' control,
but it was the number two thing that people talked about.
We're on top of each other.
There's no privacy at all.
And that doesn't necessarily have to mean
our desks are packed in next to each other,
or we wish we were madmen and had giant offices
and just gonna drink booze all day long.
It does have something to do with how the space is laid out and how people perceive this space.
Importantly, because these are, you know, this is survey results here, so whether or not you can do anything about it,
this is what people are thinking about the space that you've created for them to work in.
So, even though everything is super tight and super crowded, this is like dichotomy number one in this list.
We're still never near the people that we need to be near.
We have to walk all the way across the office to get to HR.
We have to walk all the way across the office to get from one part
of the engineering department to another.
The bathrooms are at the far side of Mars.
This is a consistent problem.
And of course, the classic, there's never a meeting room.
There's never a meeting room when you need one.
There's never one when you don't need one.
There are.
Too many for people that always get all the meeting rooms
they want.
I have some more slides about this later on in the deck,
but just know that meeting space and collaboration space
in general, even if it's not a private meeting room,
is very important to folks.
This list is seven or eight items,
but these are the tops out of 200 different things
that people whined about in the survey where I asked them to.
Visual privacy is surprisingly important to folks. This isn't just, hey, I don't want to feel like my
boss is looking at my monitor all the time, but also just the capacity to be looking out at your
monitor and at your workspace and not seeing chaos right behind it. So everyone can see
everything, sure, but also the fact that you can see everything is really distracting. So a lot
of different...
a lot of different approaches in the case studies that I take a look at to
to kind of try and figure out that problem. This one actually came up more
often than I thought it would, and I guess that's down to game developers
being game developers, but
yeah, a lot of people don't just think their offices just are shitty.
They're ugly, they're boring, they don't have any games in them.
That was a stunningly high
frequency complaint. There's no place for us to actually play games.
There's a fine line, which you'll see a little bit later on,
between there's no place and you're trying to turn this place into some kind of weird fun prison.
But that came up a lot.
And then the light level issue.
This is very simple, very basic, but programmers need a different amount of light
than artists, than designers, than people who have to look at giant lists of stuff.
all day long, the people that are testing your game, etc.
So one crucial factor in workplace satisfaction
that came up again and again and again in the survey, in my individual interviews,
was the organizing principle behind how these rows of desks are laid out.
There are two main schools of thought about how this ought to be done,
and most respondents' offices use either one or the other,
in almost exactly equal proportions.
Everyone working on a specific project is clustered together,
regardless of what they do on that project.
In the departmental layout, artists sit with artists,
producers sit with the producers, design sits over there,
engineers sit over there, even if there are two or three
different games that they're working on.
It's pretty clear what the advantages and issues
with these approaches are.
If everyone working on a game is sitting together,
you don't have to go too far to find and collaborate
with the other devs who are working
on the same problems as you are.
As we know from those factory studies 100 years ago,
the less you have to physically move to get your job done,
the more efficient you're going to be at doing it.
Of course, the main drawback here
is the very reason why the departmental seating
model exists.
It's very easy for people to get siloed
when they're only thinking about their own problems.
And you quickly lose the advantage
of having 30 engineers who are these top class guys and gals
working together if only 10 of them ever talk to each other.
And another 10 are sequestered over someplace else.
They never talk to each other.
That's.
the knowledge sharing gap becomes very, very huge.
So as a result of that, you get this kind of third approach.
Some workplaces, but usually, but not only,
those with large or flexible physical spaces to work with
have adopted a hybrid model in which the groups most
likely to work across all games sit with one another
in as central a location as possible,
and the devs working on a single game primarily or only.
sit together on the periphery.
Now typically these central services departments
include groups like marketing, most business functions,
some artists, some QA, and very often a tools
or a game engine group.
Now to be clear, none of these approaches
are the right way to lay out an office space.
I'm not trying to claim that.
First, you have to actually fit your staff
into the physical space that you've got.
So some of these approaches might not be appropriate.
And none of these might be appropriate for your office.
In theory, you could design some kind of crazy
four-dimensional model where everything
perfectly overlaps at acute angles,
but it's very rare that you can actually
implement something like that in the space you've got.
Although I will mention one at the end of this talk,
that a giant company that everybody loves to be named,
Never, has worked out and a lot of people actually like it.
So that's in the tweetable takeaways portion.
So let's take things out of the realm of theory for a minute and then look at a few examples of how some game companies of varying sizes and with varying giant Scrooge McDuck piles of cash deal with these issues.
The first one is everybody's favorite company, Zynga. These guys had a building that existed already that they needed to work with, but it was basically a giant open shell. The key word is gigantic.
Zynga was only a bit more than half of this office,
but we're talking about 12 NFL regulation football fields,
or nine World Cup football pitches for you people
that like the right kind of football.
Each employee has a lot of space in a workspace this size.
So none of you might know what square foot per kind of feels
like, but trust me, 140 is, in New York, you're like,
forget it.
That's heaven.
Heaven. Good. Sorry. So the model that Zynga tried to follow with this was a version of the hybrid plan,
where the game teams sit together and the central teams sit together, and each of them had an open seating area
that surrounded a small core of collaboration spaces of various sizes.
The problem that Zynga tried to address in the most obvious way was that ugly or boring issue that we talked about.
So like a lot of Silicon Valley startups made good, these guys bought into the office as
playground model that has come to prominence in the last 20 years.
Seriously, Zynga went absolutely goddamn bananas making their office into a 12-year-old boy's
dream.
And we'll come back in a few minutes to what influence that had on their employees and
their outlook.
So once you left the common areas of Zynga,
the offices don't look that much different
from any other corporate workspace.
They have more knickknacks, both employee and company supplied.
But other than that, it looks kind of familiar
to anyone who's built software.
Here's how they tried to deal with the key issues
that we identified a few slides ago.
So noise, they had it a little bit easy.
They just had a lot of square feet,
so they could give each employee a lot of square feet.
And that dramatically reduces the noise because of physics.
visual privacy you see a lot of the time they tried to
They didn't use
a particularly intense methodology for this, but did what a lot of companies that have
prefab office furniture do, which is to get these angled desk pods that you can see here.
This is not a perfect solution as you can see, because from where the photographer is
standing you can see everybody's monitor and it also looks like pure chaos in the background.
But it is a lot better than the triangle shirtwaist factory stuff that you see a lot of other
people do where it's just a sweatshop, rows and rows and rows of monitors.
Collaboration space, they had a ton of space,
so they could have a lot of collaboration space.
And here, again, they tried this hybrid layout
where each game team has a physically distinct area,
as do the central services folks.
But crucially, within that area, the arrangement
was non-standardized and was driven by the folks
at the top, the general managers of those games.
Make sure that you note that was driven by leaderships,
because that will come back in a minute.
So what was the overall approach?
Basically, Zynga is trying very, very hard
to make everything fun and playful.
The idea, of course, is that if the employees are having fun,
it'll be easier for them to make more fun games
for the customers, and sometimes this worked,
and sometimes it resulted in cognitive dissonance
and forced fun and lots of hate.
So this can be absolute cultural poison,
but it wasn't the only challenge that Zynga faced
with the approach that they chose.
It's really expensive to do things like this.
And when revenues turn down, the ball pit starts to look goofy.
Scalability, there's only a certain number
of people that can fit on the water slide.
When you get more people, you can't
make the water slide any bigger.
And importantly, as we were saying before about management
being able to call the shots on how things moved around,
this interferes with humans' nesting impulse.
People want to have some degree of agency over their space.
We see this over and over again.
And this is actually a pretty commonly mentioned issue
in white papers and studies.
People want to have some control over their space.
When you take that away from them, it's not good.
it just sort of increases their degree of nervousness.
So a lot of the sort of hipster ad agencies
where it's like, well, you don't even have a computer,
you just take a notepad and draw on it
and sit in the corner and lie on the fake grass
or whatever it is that we've got,
that doesn't often work out.
If you're particularly interested,
there's a white paper by guys called Fleming and Sturdy,
which is called Being Yourself in the Electronic Sweatshop.
new forms of normative control. That's in Human Relations, which is an academic journal.
I'll give you more information on that if you want it at some point.
But so let's take a look at a second space.
Space number two is Three Rings.
If you've never been to a meeting or a party there,
this place is really unique.
The studio is owned by Sega now, but when they opened this office,
it was an indie.
And they started to take a really dramatic approach
to one of these classic small developer problems of how
to build out a white box.
They had a giant Class B loft, really common.
You probably have one if you have worked at a small developer.
It's just an empty white box.
It was about, I guess, 1 10th of a football pitch, so not huge.
And key to this is that what you're about to see here,
this steampunk submarine thing, is half of their office,
the back half, which was completely redesigned.
The front half stayed very similar to its original build.
This is intentionally cozy.
So they actually had quite a bit more space
than they wound up slicing up and giving to the employees
on purpose, trying to sort of increase
the effort for collaboration by packing everybody
into smaller spaces.
So that's quite intentional.
And they divided their space up into these small group
work rooms, little pods with four or five folks in them
that would be a department working on a game,
but not giant.
one giant team of 35 people.
So even small companies, especially in San Francisco,
wound up in this perk arms race.
According to Three Rings, however,
it was practically impossible to hire engineers
at this point, and the office actually
was a key marketing tool for them.
So despite superficial similarities,
this is really a very different use
of architectural playfulness than what we saw with SingIt.
It's also important to note that though
the steampunk aesthetic was completely pervasive
in the front half of the office,
This was definitely the party in the back portion of the Three Rings office mullet.
There's a much more straightforward space on the other side of a wall that you can't see here.
And that has largely become home to the business type functions versus the design and the artwork,
which are going on in the submarine.
And that's maybe the most literal case of architectural determinism that I have ever seen.
And it does affect the employees, and we'll see how in slide or two.
So here's how Three Rings approached those big game
development workspace issues.
Very different to what Zynga did.
And they did a couple of things that a giant corporation really
can't do.
Well, for example, they knew that they
weren't going to have a huge noise problem,
because they had a relatively good sized space
and very few employees.
That's one way to solve that problem,
but it's not a call you can necessarily make.
For visual privacy, they actually
partitioned up their workspace and faced the desks
towards walls and partitions.
in order to avoid the problem of having you looking out at, you know, a sea of monitors
with visual chaos behind them.
Their collaboration spaces, actually as you can see on their layout here, practically
all of the office space in this area is designed as a sort of small, informal collaborative
space.
And then they also have a...
a secret library room that you enter through a bookcase that
was a conference.
Really, this office space is tremendous.
So pardon me if I'm just like goofy about it.
The light level was very clever here.
They have these big curtains that you
can see over their large loft windows.
And they have custom made light fixture covers
that mute the fluorescent lights.
So you can kind of adjust the lights in a way.
a much more granular way than you saw in a space like Zynga or in a lot of Class B office space.
And here they have their teams in separate spaces, but they kind of have a sort of miniature version of the hybrid
with individual groups inside teams parked together to encourage collaboration with them.
Unfortunately, they actually only had one private collaborative space.
but a lot of this space was available for public collaboration.
So the TLDR is that through salesmanship and smart design and luck,
Three Rings was able to give themselves a completely unique environment
that functioned as a calling card that explained how the company works
and how they think of themselves as you walk through it,
as a visitor or an employee.
The major issues that arose, though, are something you probably have already guessed.
Once you have a steampunk submarine in your office,
your company is kind of like about having a steampunk
submarine in your office.
And that introduces a bunch of risks around changing tastes,
for example.
You're maybe not always going to want a steampunk submarine.
Packing all of these people into tight spaces on purpose
can obviously introduce some issues as well.
And the fact that you're sort of basically
stuck with what you've got.
Tom Schofield, who is one of the principals at Three Rings, told me,
the way we thought of it was, anything works in here as long as it fits in a steampunk submarine.
So it's a little bit deterministic, but obviously there's some big upside.
So the final case study that I'm going to take a look at looks at a totally different type of space.
This is a very different space, a very different budget, and a totally different set of requirements.
This is New York's Waka Waka, which is a game development co-working space and incubator
in the trendy Lower East Side, located in a former storefront tattoo parlor.
This space was inherited and tweaked, but in a lot of ways it's the same type of space
that it was when it was an art gallery a few tenants ago.
It's a small open room, and it's long and narrow, which rules out a lot of the desk
layouts that we talked about before.
Though without any real permanent walls, it's quite flexible and it has a second story and a tiny little yard that can be configured in a few different ways.
So, check this out. Even a 2,000 square foot office makes an amenity play in its own way.
So that maybe tells us something.
People like to say that they don't care about perks that much, like this cool little backyard.
But again, we see a significant effort to maximize the available resources.
Waka Waka doesn't have much furniture in it at all,
but what is there is high quality and extremely stylish.
Flexibility and minimalist chic are just overflowing here.
And this sort of underscores the aspirational aspect
of workspace design.
Is it showing two different things or something?
All right, cool.
So we don't actually really design a workspace
around our employees so much as we
create a space that looks like it's already
home to the type of people that we want working in it.
And whether that's a feature or a bug,
we kind of, that's up to us to figure out.
So how did Waka Waka address the big issues?
It's harder for them than for Three Rings or Zynga
because they couldn't really choose much about how
their space is laid out, about what materials it's made out of.
It's really noisy if there are a lot of people in there.
The whole thing is made out of polished concrete.
Now they've done what they can about that.
As you can see, even the desk is made out
of noise baffling material.
And they've got a bunch of noise baffles hanging on the wall.
So they are smart about it.
As far as visual privacy goes.
there's really only two options.
You could have everybody facing directly into a white wall.
Not great.
Or you could have everyone sort of looking
at a maximum of one other person.
And that's what they did.
For a collaboration space, this is kind of tricky.
The studio amenities and infrastructure
are shared between everyone that's in there.
It's kind of a big open space.
They have a little area in the back
that you can sort of see there that has a couch.
And
Their backyard is also sort of an ad hoc collaboration space,
as is their downstairs.
But ultimately, there aren't very many walls.
So there's a limit to what you can do.
Now, the layout, of course, can change.
Other than getting new giant desks,
they can switch things up.
But at the end of the day, there's
not much solitude that's possible.
So what the core of WakaWaka's workspace approach
is about allowing small independent teams
to work in close proximity to each other
and share facilities that they could otherwise never afford.
This office signifies to potential coworkers
and to those visiting that the people who work here
understand the indie game aesthetic through and through.
It's sparse, but precise, and above all else,
it's elegant in both functional and visual design.
So this works to attract like-minded collaborators.
And it immediately tells a compelling story to, for example,
visiting publishers who are attending meetings with the developers that are based here.
This approach definitely comes with some real challenges, however.
The space is small,
and there's no real layout choices.
So the various privacy concerns are magnified tremendously.
There's also the question of scale.
If you succeed here, you kind of have to leave.
So this randomizes the balance of the people in the space,
and that can be a huge issue in a workspace
that's only got about a dozen other folks in there.
The materials we talked about, it's all polished concrete,
so they couldn't really do too much with that,
but they kind of ran with it
rather than trying to fight against it.
It's TBD how well that works out.
And then on top of the challenge
of people scaling out of the office.
You really have to trust the curation instincts of the people
that run this space.
Now, this particular workspace is run by game business
veterans.
But if that's not always the case,
then you could wind up in here with whoever
they were able to get to fill the seats in order
to pay the rent.
So at last, here are the tweetable takeaways.
I'm going to put them up there one by one.
So maybe wait till the end if you want to take a picture.
And I'll also make this whole deck available digitally
if you want it as well.
So let's try to distill some of the most significant findings from my research and the survey and the interviews and these case studies.
So we'll continue this conversation with each other and the rest of our discipline and maybe for some of you with the people you work with as you contemplate the design or redesign of your own development space.
First, disciplines differ. Now this is huge.
Engineers do not have the same requirements as designers or artists or marketers.
If you have one type of space for all of these different types of folks, you're setting yourself
up for a big challenge.
Even in a small studio, you have to do what you can to make sure that there's quiet space
and collaboration space available and that they're as distinct and distant physically
from each other as possible.
Privacy. Too much noise, as I mentioned, was the number one thing that people mentioned
in the survey, but close behind it were a few different types of issues around privacy.
Physical privacy and visual privacy are separate, and they're both very important. Game developers,
like everybody else, don't want to feel like they're being monitored in a time and motion
study by their bosses all day long. So if we're already going out of our way to provide
jellybean foot baths delivered fresh daily by Uber...
It's irresponsible not to contemplate providing phone booths or arranging your monitors so
that people can read Kotaku when they're burned out for a few minutes without worrying that
they're going to get fired.
There are better ways to find out if your employees are shirking their responsibilities
than by fixing all their screens towards the boss.
is an important and enormous part of what we do.
About a third of the folks we spoke to said that their offices needed more
meeting rooms.
When we change the phrasing to talk about general collaborative space,
that number shot through the roof. So people are
are empathetic. They don't want to disturb their colleagues. A lot of times
folks just
flat-out won't talk to people that they would benefit by talking to
because there's nowhere to do it without disturbing somebody else.
There are a lot of innovative ideas
about how to make this work, even in a really low square
footage space, like the backyard at Waka Waka or some others.
So if you're interested in going into greater depth
on this particular issue, drop me a line.
I'll give you my contact information,
or you can come up to me afterwards,
and I can offer some concepts for you.
As I was researching this topic and speaking
with interior designers and architects,
I kept hearing over and over again
how important it is to consult with the people that
are going to use the office during your design process.
The impact of coming in on a Monday morning and having everything be in a totally different
spot or of seeing people roam around with measuring tapes and lasers taking measurements
and jotting things down without knowing why they're there.
or what's going to happen to your workplace is huge.
That's that nesting instinct that we talked about before.
And we know this.
This is community management.
This is usability testing.
And we do this in our games.
If you're designing a space, take some time
and talk to the people that are going to be using it.
Although a game can sometimes be a passion project
and a work of one genius's singular vision.
It would be pretty unique to imagine an office space that way.
So don't do it.
Personal space.
We've mentioned this a lot and this is something that you probably have less
control over in your space, just down to raw square footage concerns.
But even in really small areas, remember to do what you can to, you know,
just alter the layout.
Make it possible for people to feel like there's a little bit of personal space.
Even if that just means, in a couple of places I've seen, literal actual phone booths put
up in the corner so that people don't have to, you know, hover over by the kitchen to
make a phone call.
This helps people feel like they have some control.
So about that super scheme that I mentioned before.
So a hybrid layout.
So this is one of these very popular companies
that everybody loves.
Designed this system where there are pods of about four to six
people with desks.
Each one of those pods is self-assembled,
but it's always from the same game team,
and sometimes within the same discipline.
Each pod has a separate meeting room.
and a small separate private collaboration area,
as well as being located around a central space
that everyone can just kind of rotate their desks into.
In case you happen to have a jillion dollars
and can build out a space that works like this,
the people that worked in that space
gave tremendously good reviews.
So that's something to think about.
And then lastly, perks.
I have a lot of data from the survey about this,
but here's the bottom line.
You have to have something.
The lack of space to play games in I mentioned before
was mentioned about a fifth of our respondents.
People notice when the office is super square,
but there is definitely, definitely such a thing
is too much of a good thing.
About 33% of our survey respondents said that the reason they think their companies provide
them with these fun perks was to keep them at their desks for longer hours.
So even if this is not true in your office, you have to take into account that some people
are going to think that it's true.
So remember that before the guys show up delivering your three-story water slide.
So, we probably don't have any time for any questions at all, but this is my contact information.
If you can't see it, just walk up, I'll give you a business card.
And there's also a room that I can go to where I'll just stand outside and talk to you.
It's, what did you say it was three?
2002, so maybe I'll go there.
Hey, give me a good rating.
Those people will email you stuff,
and it'll say give me a good rating,
so give me a good rating.
Thanks, everybody.