Hello everyone.
Hello and welcome to the level design and Hitman guiding players in a non-linear sandbox
game.
Today we're going to talk you through the journey that we had with our tutorial and
the guidance system that we implemented in the latest installment of Hitman.
And this doesn't work.
Excellent.
My name is Jakob and I'm a principal level designer at IO Interactive.
I've been there for 13 years, made a number of Hitman games,
Hitman Contract where I was a scripter,
Hitman Blood Money where I was a scripter,
and I also worked on a tutorial.
And then Kane & Lynch where I turned into level design
and became owner of the tutorial again.
And then we had Hitman Absolution, where I became the lead level designer and also did some work on the tutorial.
And then last, as principal level designer, I also designed the tutorial.
So that's what I'm going to talk about today.
Yes, and my name is Mette, and you can all hear me.
That's great.
I'm a level designer at IOO.
And while Jakob, he was making amazing titles,
I was going to school, like literally.
I started in ninth grade when Jakob started at IOO.
But since then, I've gone to the University of Aarhus,
where I studied interaction design, where I got my master's.
Then I went to DADU, where I was a game designer,
and I went to Academy of Art.
I produced a few tablet titles and I learned how to paint a little, and then after my thesis
I got my dream job at IOO where I designed the guide.
The agenda for today, first of all we would like to introduce Hitman of course, and then
the level Showstopper, which takes place in Paris, which is the big level that we launched
in March.
Then we want to talk about the closed alpha report, which was quite a pillar in our development
of Hitman.
Then we want to talk about the mission, which is also going to function a little bit as
an agenda, where we talk about the tutorial and the guide.
And then hopefully we'll have time for questions.
Alright, so what is Hitman? For those of you who don't know, Hitman is about 1847, the guy on the screen here.
He's a highly trained assassin and he travels the world and kills people for money.
The game is a third-person creative stealth action game.
And it's an episodic game, which means that we're releasing it in episodes, roughly a month in between.
The first one went live in March, and that allows us to engage with the community in a whole new way,
where we can look at the content and actually react to what they're saying about the game,
and how they play it, and what they like and what they don't like.
And also, today we're actually releasing a new episode, so there's a launch party, we just shipped it three hours ago.
The game is a lot about disguises and social stealth. That's one of the key mechanics we have in it.
It's about infiltrating and going close to a target under disguise.
We also have a very, very, very important part of the game, and that is the freedom of approach.
We don't tell you how to complete the missions.
It's almost like a puzzle game where you have to figure out how do I get away with murder.
So if you want to use explosives, that's one thing, that's fine.
If you want to use poison, that's fine.
If you want to use your sniper rifle, that's also fine, just as long as the guy dies.
These are the five games that led up to Hitman.
I just want to talk about Blood Money and Absolution for a bit.
Because from a level design perspective, these two are different.
Blood Money had these open sandbox levels where, again, you had a lot of freedom of approach.
Hitman Absolution, we did more kind of small levels, like 70, and then divided by checkpoints.
So they were a lot easier to kind of digest for the player.
But this time we wanted to combine the sandbox missions from Blood Money with the AI fidelity and the game mechanics
that are a lot higher fidelity than what we saw in Blood Money.
So we want to combine the two into Hitman and just to show you guys what it looks like
I have a trailer that will kind of explain a bit
The essence of a sandbox game like Hitman is freedom of approach
Where you go, how you infiltrate, who you become
Knowing which disguises give you access is key
But beware
Some individuals are more observant than others.
Hey, who are you?
Hey, hey, watch out!
Be prepared to improvise.
Where is he?
You see him, anyone?
Yeah, where the hell did he go?
As you experiment with your play style...
We lost him!
Each hit can go from bloody murder...
...to a genuine masterpiece of assassination.
Complete mastery of a level is rewarded.
As your skills evolve over time, so do your options.
Prepare equipment in advance,
and plan the perfect hit.
New locations will appear over time.
You will travel the world.
New missions, new targets.
Some targets only ever surface once, for a limited time.
When they are gone,
they are gone forever.
Yes. Our story today starts with our alpha build.
This was the first...
time the public outside of IOWA actually got to play the game and we of course weren't
finished but we created this palace that you see here. It's a four-story building located
in Paris and there's a surrounding garden and this is the entire level. The palace has
a complete interior so there's a lot of square meters to kind of knock yourself around with.
The mission for Agent 47 is to infiltrate the palace to eliminate Viktor Novikov and Dalia Margolis, the two targets.
When the mission starts, you start out front and then you're on your own, so you have to figure out how to pull it off.
Viktor Novikov, he roams the ground floor where he is attending his fashion show.
He's a fashion brand owner.
And then on the side he's running this spy community where they sell secrets in this secret auction on the top floor of the palace where Dalia is.
And then we, in the alpha build, we sent this out to the players.
They have a lot of things to do in the palace.
There's a lot of items, hammers, disguises, fire extinguishers, fireworks setups, a diorama.
There's escape helicopters, rat poison in the basement.
So there's tons of options and ways to go about completing your mission.
So that we gave to all the players.
But what we got back was that some of them, they actually did fine.
Yeah, thanks a lot man, real considerate.
But others, they did it like this.
That is Viktor Novikov, head of Sanguin and ringleader of Iago. Quite the wisdom.
Yeah, so Dahlia and Novikov won and Hitman 0.
They didn't use the palace, right?
Yes, and then we had the closed alpha.
We were really, really proud of what we were presenting to the players in this build.
The closed alpha is the first time we went live.
Hitman is a live game, so we wanted to do that as early as possible in the process.
And this was absolutely the biggest user base ever who got to play our level.
We knew maybe this would be a little bit tricky because there was a lot of stuff in this level
and we knew that they didn't have a tutorial, we didn't have any guidance, and we were of course working on both at this time.
We already had prototypes.
And our fears were confirmed, and maybe with a little bit on top.
They didn't really have a good understanding on how to navigate.
They had a hard time getting an overview.
and they just generally found it very, very difficult to approach.
We were prepared for this, kind of.
But what we were not prepared for was the fact that they felt that the level was empty.
When you are presented with such a big level, it can be a little bit intimidating
and you can feel like a tourist sort of just being dumped there,
and that can be a little uncomfortable.
And we realized that maybe they were just presented somehow with the tip of the iceberg.
Maybe they didn't know how to find all this stuff.
Because we knew it was there, we were pretty sure, because we put it there.
So maybe we should do something in order to make sure that they could find it.
So the direction became, make the best Hitman tutorial ever,
and teach the players to think like Hitman.
and also design a level guidance system that would help them find the rest of the iceberg.
But it was very important for us that we wouldn't like shove it down their throat.
We didn't want to force their hand.
So this became the mission.
Wanted to teach them how to operate the game.
Wanted to teach them the Hitman fundamentals of the game.
And we wanted for them to be able to set their own goals,
because for us that really felt like that was,
that was what it meant to think like a hitman,
to kind of, you know, find those possibilities,
those weak points and think,
hey, I'm gonna use that later.
And then the second part became,
well, we need to show them the iceberg,
we need to find a way to illuminate it.
And we need to encourage replay while we do this.
So yes, now Jakob is gonna talk a little bit
about the tutorial.
Yes.
At this point we had the showstopper that you just saw, and then we had a prototype of the tutorial.
And the tutorial is, the idea is that it's set in the past, it's 20 years before the game.
It allows us to peek into the background of Agent 47 where we've never been there before in the story,
so we also give something new to the fans about 47 and how he was trained and where he's coming from.
So the idea was to create the ICA, which is the agency that employs Hitman, to create their training facility.
And what they do is that they create these training mock-ups where you could then, you know, get taught like Hitman would be taught.
So what we did for this prototype is that we kind of, we imagined that this is all the mechanics in Hitman games, so the way we looked at them was that, okay, they can be roughly divided into these five categories.
We have the ever-present ones, we have the item-dependent ones.
Ever-present ones is like running and crouching and all the stuff he can do without, it's like you and the controller can do.
Item dependent ones, that's things that require specific items that unlock new kind of actions with 47.
And then we have the environmentally dependent ones such as agility, drain pipes, cover systems and all of that.
And then we get to the juicy bits which are the NPC dependent ones.
Of course you need people to subdue and kill and all of that stuff.
And then on the far right we have the NPC alert behaviors which is when they get angry, right?
There's something that we also want to do.
So what we did was that we looked at this and then we created a number of test chambers
where the idea was that each chamber would then be an isolated kind of proving ground
for a specific feature so we could teach you how to throw stuff, we could teach you how
to subdue people, all of that, and then have them in small compartmentalized chambers.
that wouldn't affect each other because what we saw in the showstopper is that when they
get spotted, then the entire thing cascades and then they affect the entire level by getting
spotted in one corner.
So here we could harness this chaos and have it under control.
And then we gave that to the users and the users tested it and it was pretty fine.
They got the idea.
But then we looked at the level and it's like, okay.
This tutorial is not really representative of the game,
right?
It's like we're distilling it into some very simple
mechanics, but when we add everything together,
the complexity just explodes.
And the tutorial didn't do this, so they weren't really
any better.
They just got a little more time to actually try it.
So it was back to the drawing board.
We sat down and looked at each other and said, OK,
we need to do something about this,
because we have to change the way we think
about this tutorial.
So we came up with the mantra, you fight as you train.
It's an old saying in the army that you fight as you train.
And the idea is that once you get stressed,
you lose all ability to reason.
So we need to have all the reactions on you,
kind of deeply inside you, so you
don't have to think about the stuff.
You just do it.
So we have to create as real a training scenario as we can.
Then we need to build sandboxes because that's what the game is.
So we condensed the showstopper idea into a tiny sandbox,
which is the drawing that you're seeing here.
This is a paper prototype I made where I just cut up papers until I get the shape that I want.
But this is what we need to do.
Then we need to team up with the user team, user research team,
and do rapid prototype testing, where we just do it every second week,
punch out a new build, try it out again, with a smaller group of people.
And then we need to stop calling it the tutorial,
and instead we're going to rebrand it to the Prologue.
And now I have to say the Prologue for the rest of this talk.
That's going to be a challenge.
Because this is something different.
Because people came to me and said, OK, Jakob,
we're going to put this in the tutorial,
and we're going to put this mechanic in the tutorial.
They had this linear compartmentalized mentality
about the whole tutorial.
So we had to call it something else.
So what we came up with was a new structure
for the opening of the game.
Part one, the arrival, where we kind of open up
the scene, the whole training session.
Part two, the training, where we learn Agent 47, and the player
mostly, how to be Agent 47.
And then we have a final test, which is the second sandbox of the prologue, where we will test his skills.
I'm just going to go through each of these parts.
The opening of the game, that's this helipad.
And this is the ICA training facility.
It's a concrete construction far up north.
And 47 is just dropped there by helicopter,
and then he's on his own.
And so is the player.
So we don't tell you how to do anything.
Nothing really happens here.
It's just nice and cold.
and then your job as the player is to figure out, okay, I'm in control
and then you need to find the door up here. Sorry,
things are getting ahead of myself here. There we go.
So you just have to... I'm out of power.
I'm not. So you have to find the door that leads inside the facility.
I am out of power.
Yes. Sorry about that.
All right, so one step back.
47 on the helipad.
Learn how to navigate.
Learn how to use the camera.
Enter the facility.
Then we have part two, which is the guided training.
And this is where the juicy bit of the teaching actually happens.
to the untrained eye this looks exactly like the drawing I've shown before and it kind of is
but this time we actually sat down and then we found the meaningful mechanics to learn the player
in order for him to kind of do a hit so this was about infiltrating eliminating and exfiltrating
so instead of just going through all the mechanics one by one we picked the ones that you need
in order
You pick the ones that you need in order to complete a mission.
And then we created a story for the mission that you have to infiltrate this yard in order
to eliminate the owner who's an art thief.
And then all of a sudden there was kind of a small story there all of a sudden.
And then it turned into that these missions that they do at this ICA facility is actually
reenactments of former hits.
What we did next was, okay, but we need to add the rest, right, because it's a sandbox.
So we have all the things surrounding this as well.
And then in order to help the player do this, we then used a guide which is kind of pointing
you towards the next point in your mission example here.
So the requirements for the Prolog training here was that it has to be a real sandbox
mission.
We've just been through that.
We need a very, very robust guide because at this point...
you haven't played any Hitman so far.
So we had to make the guidance system,
the thing that tells you what to do, very, very robust
because things can go wrong, right?
And in my experience, there's three different ways
to play a game, right?
You do as we expect you to, or you do...
your own thing because you want to see how far can you push this game until it breaks.
And that's fine with us because then you're in on it and you're breaking it on purpose
just to see what happens. That's fine.
But then you have the last group of people, which are these people who really want to play your game
but they somehow mix it up and they get confused.
It doesn't really work out for them.
And those are the ones that we really have to take care of
because those are the ones that are going to throw away the controller and say,
I'm done with this.
And then, yeah, so those are the ones that I'm very, very careful about doing this guide for.
So it had to be taken into consideration that you would play it backwards or infiltrate in a different way.
Then it had to be easy but not boring.
We have a wall of difficulty in the showstopper we learned,
so again, instead we need to kind of get them on board and have them, yeah, get them rolling
and actually have a small success experience here to begin with.
The only way to fail is death.
You can't play the training mission wrong, right?
That would be kind of weird in a way, that we punish you severely.
So the only way to actually get punished is if you die.
We do not feature Cripple you, which means that we're not cheating with what 47 can do.
He is as real as he is when you play the showstopper.
That's a very important thing to us, because otherwise you wouldn't train as you fight.
Fight as you train.
And then we only want you to kill the target because Agent 47 is actually a very, very professional assassin.
So in the fantasy of a lot of, especially the fans, then he is only going for the targets.
He doesn't kill the cleaning person to get the disguise. He finds other ways.
A quick breakdown of the first play through here, right?
We start outside the yacht.
And again, it's made of plywood.
It's not a real yacht.
It's something they built inside this facility.
And you're told off by the guards.
You can't enter here, they say.
All right, cool.
I need to go in.
You do some infiltration.
You do some agility.
You go to cover.
And things are prompted using different systems.
We have this prompt up there.
And then you subdue the mechanic, you drag him away, you get his outfit and now you're on your way onto the yacht.
Here we push a sign about threats.
We had a hard time getting people to understand these dots, which is kind of the easiest way for us to actually communicate that these guys know who you are.
So they can see through this guy, you have to be very careful about that.
And as a result we saw people infiltrating and what they did was that you have the guy over here.
who's a threat, if he sees you then he's going to get angry.
And then people were gluing themselves to the car over here, so that really worked well.
We teach you how to use instinct to locate the target.
We follow the target and then he is rejected again.
So, okay, my disguise is no longer valid up there.
I need to get a new one, so now you need to disguise yourself as a crew member.
And here we actually, yeah, the throwing thing wasn't really a part of the original pan,
but we added it because it's really fun.
So the poor guy, he takes a wrench to the head and then, bing, and into the freezer.
So hide body and yet another disguise.
As 4070 is taking on disguises, he opens up new options in the missions where he can use the disguises to his advantage.
So in this place he's blending in, which means that he's taking the role of someone in the game.
And in this case he's taking a role as the bartender, and the target is standing right there in front of him.
So now we're very, very close, but as you saw before, if I just get out my gun here and just start shooting,
then it wouldn't work, so we can't do that with the player.
We follow the target into his office, and it's a bit hard to see, but there's actually a bodyguard denying you access here.
So, again, you're denied access.
Okay, your disguise is not good enough for this either.
You sneak around, climb the window, and we prompt you for cover again.
We prompt you for inventory, how to shoot and aim.
And then the target is off, and then it's about exfiltrating, it's about leaving the yard.
No one notices this when you shoot the guy.
And then once you're off, then it's find another way off, because of the threat.
And then crowbar, lock doors, and eventually complete the mission.
So this playthrough was designed in a way where we knew from Absolution that we had to show, we had to ask the user to do things several times in order for that to kind of stick and become something he would do without thinking about it.
And in this case, we had three times we told you about threats and three times we told you about sentries because that's core of the design and of the level design.
This is this whole who has access where, the whole disguise gameplay.
Twice cover hide body and change disguises and some climbing through windows.
And then once we had the... actually down here we have the gun, right?
Which is... yeah, interesting in terms of what we think is important, right?
So we put a lot of effort into getting the players to understand the disguise gameplay.
After that, the training wheels are off, we have a final test.
No guidance.
in a way, but not heavily tutorialized.
And then we introduce you to the player guidance system. In this mission, Agent 47
have to eliminate a guy who's being flown away in
this jet, and you have to figure out how to get to him.
And that involves using the ejection seat.
And it also wraps up our story, so the whole training at the ICA, one thing we do when we start the mission,
we meet Diana, and then here, when we're back at the helipad and we talk to Diana, we give 47 his name,
and eventually he leaves, and he is on his way into this showstopper 20 years later.
So now the flow looks like this.
That's fine. We had the arrival, we had the training, we had the final test.
And then the showstopper and people were playing this and trying it out and it worked fine.
So that kind of checked off the Hitman fundamentals. Excellent.
So now they know how to infiltrate, they know how to eliminate the target,
they know how to exfiltrate and that's fine.
But we were still lacking the set their own goals
because we really felt that that was important for them in this giant showstopper context.
They had to figure out how to do, kind of figure out what they wanted to do.
If we just looked at mechanics again from before, as I said before, we handpicked the mechanics we thought was important enough for you to actually put into the training, but we didn't put everything in, which means there was something left out.
The most important ones were actually this one, the NPC alert behaviors.
Again, we saw people getting stressed out when the AI became angry at them, when they were trespassing, when they were discovered doing something bad.
So this was very much about...
they haven't actually seen this.
So when things go wrong in the showstopper,
they're still going to see new things
they haven't tried before.
So they needed more training.
So we literally asked them to play the level again.
And we give them a different briefing.
That was the idea.
We sat down.
OK, so we need to give them a new briefing.
We need to explain to them that now they have to do it again.
And people were like, OK, again.
And the idea was that before, we had the guided play-through
with the guide.
But this time, we wanted them to kind of seek out
other things in the mission.
Again, set their own goals.
Find these other things.
So we created a challenge prototype, which was an alternate version of the yacht.
I just stripped out the guidance system that was on top of it and then inserted some items
and we just had a vanilla version of the yacht.
And we created a challenge paper handout because we decided that, okay, this is actually, this fits very well with our challenge system because we hadn't talked about that in the player's perspective yet.
And the challenge system is the way that you progress in the game. You level up your locations instead of leveling up Agent 47.
This is how you unlock all the good stuff, fancy explosives and fancy sniper rifles.
So this would also be a great opportunity for us to actually show the player the challenge system.
So we designed a group of challenges for the player that would be deliberately simple and easy.
And they would also be deliberately kind of revealing about themselves.
So find the rat poison on deck 0, I think it's called, disguised as the yacht crew in level 0.
Then we have eliminate the target, drown the target in the toilet.
And the tricky part about that is that actually requires the rat poison.
So that's a thing you would have to find out for yourself.
generator, use that to distract the guard. Fiber wire the target instead of just shooting him.
Disguise yourself as the target's guest. So we kind of pointed you in a lot of different directions
inside the game as you were playing this. We threw in some extra items, so when you start up,
then 47 is placed in front of a table with some explosives, a lockpick, some coins.
And then behind him we had assault rifles and shotguns,
so we could kind of give you all the tools that we kind of wanted you to play around with
and get an understanding of how the game worked.
There was still tutorialization in this version.
We created these, we used the pop-ups because as before, this is the same pop-up you saw
with the thread.
But this time it was telling you about how to place explosives in the world.
So whenever you picked up an explosive, this would pop up only two times in a lifetime
and then it would disappear forever.
So even if you kind of tried it again a bit later, then you wouldn't get this.
Then off to user test, and we, the first prototype was just a piece of paper with these ten challenges, right?
So it's like, they played it, the mission started, and they say, okay, now you get this piece of paper and these ten challenges,
and you have to complete some of them, and then complete the mission again.
And then all of a sudden we saw them roaming around the yard.
they actually began to set goals for themselves, right?
So they picked a couple of challenges,
and then they began to explore the app
to find these solutions for these challenges
that they were using.
And as they did that, they actually stumbled
on the other things in the challenges.
So all of a sudden, they were connecting
the dots in their head.
They began to, okay, so there's also the generator over there.
So armed with the knowledge of the first playthrough, the layout of the yard,
then we actually had them kind of go nuts here.
And some of them they actually, because we later on created,
so it would prompt you again if you wanted to train more when you did this.
And because there were still unchecked challenges, of course,
some people had to go back because they had to find them all.
We also learned that the setting was very, very tolerant.
It's okay to do experiments in this place, because as I said before,
when the Paris fashion show level kind of cascades into chaos,
it feels very expensive. You're breaking something very, very, very expensive.
Whereas here, it's a plywood yard, right? That's fine.
So that worked really well, plus the whole training metaphor
that he is there for the seven to get better,
that actually also resonated very well for these people.
And then, last but not least, we also got into the NPC reactions, where they provoked the NPCs in ways that would be very, very hard for us to actually tutorialize and use the real gameplay without heavily scripting it.
So they got the reactions from the characters in the game as they would react in the showstopper.
So again, we taught them something real, something that would be exactly the same when they would be playing it inside the showstopper.
So this is the final version we ended up with.
The arrival scene, a guided playthrough,
and then again the freeform playthrough,
and then the final test.
And that then allowed us to check off this one.
So now it goes.
Yes.
Let's see if this one works now.
Yes, it does.
Thank god.
OK, so now we're back and standing
in front of the showstopper.
We're a little bit better prepared this time.
We've got a nice suit.
We've still got a silly hat.
Oh, sorry.
But yeah, but things will be fine now.
So now we just have to concentrate
on making these experiences visible,
as I mentioned about this iceberg
that we had to illuminate somehow.
And if you look at other games that are doing the same,
they often make quests.
If we look at a quick breakdown of a quest, you often have a guy saying,
hey, I have information for you, there's something cool over there, you can go and get it.
You travel great distances and you may come find a clue that will then unlock a conversation
that you can have with a person somewhere else.
You'll go and find this person and engaging in this conversation will activate
maybe a sequence or something that will then...
lead you to a new cool location where there's a boss fight.
And when you're done with the boss fight,
you will get the treasure.
This is a classic breakdown.
Not all games, the sandbox games, of course, doing this.
But this is how one of these could look.
And if we look at what really defines these types of quests,
they're often story dictated.
They have this checkpoint structure often.
Some kind of clue will unlock something
that will unlock something.
And that's completely OK.
Often they are a part of, or they are, like a big epic quest of sorts, that will maybe go on for a longer run.
And they have these unique endings.
Now if we look at how quests would maybe look like in Hitman, and if we look at Hitman in general, it's not story dictated.
That was kind of one of the goals for Hitman, that we didn't want to make it story dictated, we wanted to make it more free.
Anything can happen at any given time.
This is something that's a little bit frustrating sometimes as a level designer,
but also what makes this game so awesome and unique.
Anything can just happen any time. You can kill everyone.
And that's actually a problem when you're making a quest,
because someone could just go missing.
We want to encourage replay, and often these big unique quests, they don't really...
they want to give you this one really really cool experience.
Of course we have lots of stories that can be replayed, but in general this is more about that
one time when you meet it that's going to be really awesome.
And of course all our quests have to end with target eliminated
We're not looking at unique endings necessarily. Well for each mission that is that is sort of your your goal
We want you to kill the guy get out of there. So
We want you to to kill and we want you to do it again and again
And when we look at this kind of structure,
we realize that it was strangely applicable
to the movie Groundhog Day.
Don't know if any of you in here have seen Groundhog Day.
I'm guessing maybe you have.
It's from the 90s.
It's a great movie starring Bill Murray,
who is trapped in a time loop.
he has to experience the same day again and again and again.
Yes, and when you realize that you have to do it again,
like in this tutorial, again, really,
it can give you that kind of emotion
that's going on in his face.
But there's also this really, really positive sides to it
because all of a sudden you get this amazing control
because you know what's going to happen.
at any given time.
You know exactly when that waitress is going to walk through the door, you know exactly
when Novikov is going to go smoke, and you know just where the sniper barge is.
So this can be an incredible empowering tool that we had to use in a nice way.
But you can also design it in a bad way,
where this constant recognition of patterns
can become a little bit unbearable,
maybe to the point of you just wanting to kill yourself
or rebel for the sake of rebelling.
That's the negative side of it, and we didn't want to,
of course, design for that.
So if we look at Groundhog Day quests,
we knew that they had to be optional.
That was one of the big problems that Bill Murray is facing,
that he is feeling trapped.
We don't want to give you the trap feeling.
It had to be something nice that you
could do if you wanted to.
We want them to be flexible because anything can happen.
You can kill everyone and anything,
and you can do whatever you want.
So it's a playground.
We wanted it to continue being a playground while still having
this sort of having this guide there.
And then we needed to be consistent.
Again, you need to know exactly when
Novikov is going to go smoke.
That is really, really important.
So with these things in mind, let's look back
at our little quest breakdown and see
what it would look like if we tried to shove that
onto Hitman.
You probably don't want to walk up to the guy
and say, hey, do you know how I can kill Novikov?
Or you probably want to hear two people talking
about a secret meeting somewhere.
some guy who's in town that no one has met yet, so you can easily take his place.
We don't want you to travel great distances, we want you to infiltrate.
Instead of like classic sandbox games, often very, very large.
Ours are large for Hitman, but we want you to really engage in the space that is there
and not spend hours traveling.
Clues are fine.
We can take that directly.
We can have conversations with people.
That's OK.
We could use that in our quests.
But we want you to be incognito when you do it.
We want you to use social stealth,
change disguises, and so on.
And we can use cutscenes.
Sequences are fine, as long as you can get out of them
very fast.
And there's no cheating, because everything
needs to be consistent.
That was one of the rules.
So we cannot teleport you.
We cannot just end the next part of the sequence
somewhere in the back of the garden.
That's not OK.
We don't have a spice.
We don't do that now.
And for the treasure chest, we would
like to make sure that we leave the player in a spot
where they know what to do next.
But we don't want to hand everything to them.
Again, we want an autonomous player.
We want real hitmen.
And we want to keep encouraging them.
So hitman quests became opportunities,
because that is what they were.
They were opportunities to get close to your target.
This is an example of an opportunity.
and this is the the helmet crew grow the male model opportunity and where you can
listen in on these two
uh... stylists and i don't think you can see them who's talking about helmet crew
crew this new model in town
and he kinda looks like you
which is really practical
uh...
And when you run around in this world and you can listen in on these conversations,
and this is where we have the opportunity of revealing.
Again, you can't just walk up and say,
hey, tell me how to become a male model, because I really want to kill someone.
We need to let you sort of feel sneaky and listen in on people
who are having this conversation and really empower you in this Groundhog Day.
So, we needed some kind of system where you would still choose to track it, and we wanted
to have a system that will, again, illuminate the iceberg, show you this is interesting,
this is something that you can use.
So we have the opportunity of revealing that then becomes opportunity revealed, where you
can then track it directly and say, yes, this sounds great.
And of course, there's volumes and stuff, so if you run away, it's fine.
Nothing's going to happen, and it's going to be available for you later in your menu.
Because we really want you to play, and not stick around if you feel like you have to.
Yes, so here you come into the menu where Diana will give you her briefing and explain to you why this is such an important opportunity.
Because here you can take Helmut Kruger's place, obviously, and then have a secret meeting with Dahlia, who's one of your targets.
And these are the different opportunities
that we have in the level.
All the blue ones will lead to Dahlia.
The orange ones will lead to Novikov.
We wanted you to be able to just browse through it.
Again, we want to show you content.
And this is such a great way to show your content.
Instead of just saying, we have a huge level.
There's lots of stuff.
Have fun.
We can say, well, this is a huge level.
There's lots of stuff.
Have fun.
And you can just go in and choose one of these
if you want a little tour, again,
if we use the tourist metaphor.
Because these will definitely take you
around the whole level.
So if we continue, you find Helmut Kruger.
That's one of your opportunity steps.
You have to investigate him, find out what he's up to.
This is one of the clues that we have from the quest breakdown.
And you hear that he's on the phone with Dahlia,
and he's planning to meet her.
And she says, call me back later.
So I will tell you then where the meeting is.
And that's also practical.
Then you become Helmut Kruger and get rid of the body, because that's part of it, right?
We don't tell you to get rid of the body.
That's something that you can just do.
We just tell you to become Helmut Kruger.
Then we ask you to call Dahlia.
You find her phone, or his phone, and then you call her and you say, hey, you want me
to come up now?
And she's like, no, it's essential that you walk the runway.
We want you to have a little fun while doing this.
So you get your makeup on.
And in the classic style of Hitman,
you can also just subdue that poor stylist instead.
You get your Hitman on, you get your makeup on,
and then you have to walk the catwalk.
Yes, and you walk the cat.
I'm not going to show the video.
You have to go and play it.
So here you walk the catwalk, and then Dalia
thinks that's awesome.
So now you can go and meet with her.
And this is actually where we're going to sort of step back
and say, great, you've earned it.
Now you're alone with her, and you can do whatever you want.
Her assistant is leaving, she's great, Helmut, good to see you.
And then you can sit down and do all this role play with a huge conversation, and you
can just, you know, take your time, think about what you want to do, or you can just
shoot her in the throat.
I realize this is a bit extreme, I didn't notice I was aiming at her throat.
There's also a nice poison opportunity, I can really recommend playing this one, it's
lots of fun.
So.
When we design opportunities, which is also a really
important lesson learned, we're also designing how to fail it.
Again, we have a pretty extreme environment.
It's very organic.
Anything can happen.
And that means that this guide needs to be flexible.
And we need to then say, well, you can't do it anymore.
Because what if you accidentally dump his body with the outfit
into the river?
then it's gone. Right? You can also just meet Helmut while being him. That's also a little
strange. Um, you can also shoot the people who's going to reveal it.
then you're not going to hear about it.
And then we can't really say that we can guide you anymore
because we don't really have our reveal anymore.
That's lost forever.
But in this case, you can actually still play it.
The guide will sort of shut down and say, well, now we
can't do this anymore.
But you can keep going if you know it by heart.
Yeah.
So around Paris, we have a bunch of opportunities spread out.
You saw them in the menu.
And these are some of the points where
you can listen in on conversations,
all the yellow ones for Novikov.
And in this case, it's also all conversations.
And this is an example of a static reveal.
This is the guest list that will tell you
which room Shigel Ghazali is living in
and will then help you become him, basically.
This is from the other side.
Yeah, we have them spread out.
And we also, the opportunities allows
us to show you some really cool sites.
The pavilion here in the garden is one of those cool sites.
And you can also have this really awesome moment
where you can blend in as a bodyguard
and participate in the super secret meeting
and then get a little alone time with Novikov afterwards.
So, sorry, that was very loud.
The opportunities allowed us to really show the players
the iceberg.
But now we really had to make sure that we were still
encouraging replay.
Now this led us to some design principles.
And I may say up front that we broke all of these,
and that is why we have them.
Lesson learned.
Information should never be a prerequisite for progression.
An example could be in the Helmut Kruger opportunity
where you hear about the meeting.
In the beginning, when we did this,
Kruger would only drop the phone if you
had heard about the meeting.
There would be no phone unless you knew about it.
That's not a cool way to fix things.
Of course, we fixed it very quickly,
made sure that wouldn't happen again, because that
doesn't support consistency.
That was one of our rules.
And be very mindful of this.
If you are doing anything similar,
make sure that you use real things in the world.
Use items.
Use anything else.
Just don't use information if you want this playground.
Opportunities should let go before they kill.
Again, I kind of mentioned it before.
We want this autonomous player.
We wanted them to have fun.
But this also brings me back to the whole fail condition part.
Let's say that we told you to kill Dahlia.
Well, we told you to kill her in a very specific way.
And we told you to listen to some of the conversation
and then stand up and shoot her.
That means that you have to fail the opportunity
if the player does anything else.
And that is kind of a, that's a tall order.
And you shouldn't do that to your players.
So think about what you're actually doing
when you make these type of guides,
because you may end up giving your player
a really bad experience.
The opportunity should always be available, even without the guide.
Yeah, that's just, again, the consistency.
You don't want the guide to be dictating anything.
We don't want the story to dictate anything.
We want the level to dictate it.
We want the player to be able to be in control, and not the other way around.
And then we added some technical changes to support this.
We added the persistent bool, which
brings me back to the phone.
Once you've heard it the first time,
the persistent bool will become true.
And this is across all playthroughs.
So when you go back, he will definitely have that phone.
We also use this for all of the reveals.
So if you've heard it once, you never have to reveal it again.
You can still go over and listen to them,
and the widget will show up and all that stuff,
because we wanted players to feel that consistency
in the HUD design as well.
But you don't have to.
You can just skip that step and go right ahead.
And we added an Intel HUD message.
We had Intel along, but it wasn't very prominent.
So we decided to push it a little bit
to make sure that players felt like they had that option as
well, instead of just using opportunities.
I'll show you an example in a second.
And then we added different levels of guidance.
So you can decide if you want full opportunities,
if you want to have this minimal version where we don't give you
the marker in the world, but only the objective.
And it's up for you to find out how you want to do it.
Yes, and this is an example of Intel.
This is Fireworks Schedule.
You read it, view Intel, take you to the menu, and here you have a description.
These are kind of all the little parts of the opportunities, and if you are that type
of player who just wants to investigate on your own, we encourage you to use this instead.
The compromise, yes.
I call this a compromise and not the perfect solution,
because it really is a compromise,
and it's something that we keep adjusting.
what is the most important part?
Is it the sandbox, or is it the guidance?
And we also have replay value on top of that.
So, fancy.
So this is something that you constantly
have to adjust, because there's always
some really, really cool idea about some narrative part that
would be great to do.
And then you have to think about, well,
what would that do to sandbox?
And then what would that do to replay value?
And this is something that we do all the time.
It's not that we made up our minds and then we said,
go, everyone, this is a template, design, design.
Every time we have a new opportunity idea,
we sit and we talk about this.
Every time we add a step to an opportunity,
we talk about this.
This is a constant readjusting,
and it's something that we're still working with,
thanks to our episodic model.
We can keep adjusting this.
So, yes.
So we managed to show them the iceberg
and still encourage replay in a balance
that we were happy with.
And we got really, really positive feedback.
We're really, really excited about this.
And we were also personally very happy with the result.
So that was awesome.
It seemed that they managed to find the iceberg, which
is exactly what one is to do.
And it felt like they were prepared to find it.
So it was awesome.
Yeah, so we just want to wrap up with some learnings that we made.
You fight as you train turned out to be very true for us.
It turned out to be the right way to teach people how to play Hitman.
Make it as real as possible and we just used the right space for that
because if we had done that this in Absolution and asked you to play the opening of that once more...
that would kind of break down because that's the story mission right so you
would kill an important person that you have to do it again and then it kind of
loses all meaning. But in this case we managed to create these sandboxes that
would actually behave as the real game because it was the real game.
We like prototyping a lot.
It worked really, really well for us.
Here, we teamed up with the user research department,
as I said, and then we did rapid, rapid, rapid prototyping.
So I would punch out a build, run down,
and then have it evaluated the same day.
And then two weeks later, we would do it again.
And then paper versions, I am a believer in paper versions
of anything before you go digital,
because it's a lot easier to cut your paper in half
and just paint on it.
If we do a live game, then go live early.
This closed alpha was the first time people outside IOH
had contact with our game.
And that is also what allowed us to do
these pretty dramatic changes to the tutorial.
Because all of a sudden we saw a lot of problems that we could fix before we shipped.
So, highly recommended, because this is also a kind of internal fight-as-you-train exercise,
because all of a sudden we have to release content outside,
and we have to make sure that we have servers, that we have deployment methods,
that we have the development team behind it, the online team.
So all of this became the same for ourselves.
We had to do it the right way.
Oops.
Yes, and as I mentioned before, adding a guide in a game like Hitman means designing fail conditions.
Please remember it if you're ever in the same situation as us.
It's just really important and it saves a lot of heartache to do it as fast as possible.
And then sandbox guidance means compromises.
I already said that a lot.
And I'll say it again, because it's important.
But it's OK.
It's OK with compromises.
They're actually pretty great.
It really makes you wonder a lot.
It makes you discuss a lot and talk
about what is actually the core experience that we
want to create with this game.
Why are we doing it?
And the constant adjustment keeps you sharp.
So, yes.
That was our take on how to guide the player
in a sandbox game.
Thank you.
Yes, as usual, as you know, there is time for questions.
So if you have some, then please raise your hand.
There's one in the back there.
I'm sorry about the sound, by the way.
I hope you can all hear still.
You're all OK.
Hey.
OK.
So two questions for you guys.
First, I have noticed that the list of opportunities
is break down by color.
But I was wondering if you guys are doing by difficulty as
well.
And if you do that, how are you differentiating those?
And the second one about the.
guns blazing approach? Is it a no-no from the get-go, completely out of the game, or
are there going to be opportunities that actually allow the player to do something like that?
Allow the player to do something like what, sorry?
Guns blazing, all guns blazing.
Oh, guns blazing! But you can always go guns blazing. I mean, you mean like from the get-go?
So like a guide just saying go guns blazing?
Accounting in one of the opportunities that you...
Also, like I said, we're not just like, we're like encouraging you to go guns blazing.
Well, we kind of have this no kill rule in the opportunities, which may sound weird since
it's a hitman game, but we really, really want you to be able to choose your own style.
We don't want to pressure you to do anything you don't want to do.
But I think like.
I mean, you can really go guns blazing if you want to.
And we also don't want you to limit yourself to opportunities.
We want you to go out there and have fun.
As a general rule, we try to avoid telling you to kill a lot of people, because some
people really want to do the opportunities, but still go silent assassin and do it in
their own way.
Your first part of the question was?
Yeah.
Sorry.
I'll be sorry.
I was wondering if the opportunities are differentiated in difficulty by you guys, and if you reward
the player specifically for competing one opportunity over the other.
Can I start?
Yeah.
Well, we have, let's say that we have an opportunity that we know is very, very difficult.
We have one in Paris, the light rig opportunity.
It is kind of difficult, and we actually just started in the roof.
So it's behind like layers of trespassing.
So we're trying to do a little bit more in that style.
So we say that the really hard opportunities may be further in or something like that.
But we try to vary them.
So yeah, does that answer your question?
Do you mean like categories?
Like saying level, like this is difficult, this is more...
And if the player completes a difficult opportunity, he's rewarded differently at the end of the mission, right?
Ah, okay.
The opportunities are all, I think they give the same amount of points to your XP when you complete them.
So they're not differentiated in that way, no.
But they could have more challenges associated to them.
Yes, there could be challenges.
Yeah, that's true.
So if it's long and complicated, there's probably more challenges associated.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Yeah, we have one up front.
I just want to ask, I was speaking to someone yesterday and I didn't know about this but
there was a certain amount of controversy that was generated by Eidos, Stroke, Square,
Enix, appropriating the Black Lives Matter thing for the DSX game that's coming out,
like it's called All Lives Matter. I don't know too much about it but with regards to
the political climate, how much of what's going on in the real world, how much of that
affects .
uh...
the design of your games for example
obviously has like uh...
you shoot a woman in the neck and you know you
assassinate like a black person
so I just wanna know like
I think that's a
very very very very good question and and and thank you as everyone
we are also just people right
and and I believe that this
game and this character is, he is an anti-hero, right? So what we do is that we actually give
the moral dilemma to you as a player, because the people that we are going after in the
story are the bad guys of our universe.
So what we do is that we actually hand the responsibility of the mission,
kind of how we perform it, that's your kind of morale,
because everything is designed in a way so you don't have to kill these innocent people.
Again, it is something, we are in this moral zone of how do we go about this.
I hope that answers your question.
Yeah, I don't have a problem with it.
There's just so much blowback that's happening.
Yes.
I totally understand.
People have too much time on their hands.
Anyone else?
Oh, someone over there.
Yeah.
Say something.
Hi.
Basically, I was wondering, because you
showed how the users kind of interacted
when they didn't have the prologue with the level.
They just went in and killed the character.
How did it change when you added the prologue?
Did you have to do some blocking gates as well?
Because initially, they could just
walk through the main entrance and just kill the character.
Did they instantly know after the prologue to not do that?
Or did you also change the level design?
Well, what we typically see when a seasoned player plays the mission, when they have knowledge
about how to approach the game, is that they rarely actually enter through the main gate
at the first thing, right?
That they'll know that the target is just in there just by looking at the thing, right?
So they will seek out the surroundings.
So the example I showed was kind of like the worst case.
Of course, we saw people who were infiltrating and experiencing and playing around with the
game.
But we didn't change the...
There was one thing we learned from the Alpha, and that was if you went right,
there was this place where we had a fence that was guarded.
And what would happen there was that people would approach the fence,
get told off by the Sentry guys, and then, because the layout was a dead end...
they wouldn't turn back, they would actually just keep pushing forward and then climbing the fence and then getting into a lot of trouble.
So what we did was that we pushed the fence a bit back because there was an opening in the garden, a kind of fence,
so they could get up to the guy, get dismissed, say you can't enter here, and just continue to their right.
So there were these kind of changes where we discovered some bottlenecks, but we didn't, we don't want to block you off in this setting here.
Oh, yeah.
This will have to be the last question.
Hey, thanks for a great talk.
So my question is, how do you go about user testing these things?
Because it's a very big sandbox, and as I say,
there's lots of stuff you can do,
and everything interacts with each other.
And I mean, you could watch a video of every.
player playing the game but that's probably a lot of work and you probably
had a lot of alpha testers. Yeah, that also takes many years. Yeah, exactly, so how do you go about that and do you have
like some metrics that you go about or do you do like just kind of a
questionnaire testing?
Yeah, we do several different kinds of user testing, right?
The ones that I talk about, the rapid ones,
we also have bigger user surveys where
we interview a lot of people.
They play the game and there's surveys.
And then we also have, we send out questionnaires
to the players and ask them directly.
And we also have a user panel where
we are in kind of continuous dialogue with the players
about how they do it.
So that's the user testing thing.
Anything else to add?
Well, that and then we also, like, we're doing an episodic game.
That means people are playing the game in their own homes right now.
So we have a very, like, we are really trying to listen to the community.
And we spend a lot of time just finding out what people are saying
and how are they feeling? Do they like it? What don't they like?
And we have a lot of people who's spending a lot of time on that.
So, so, yeah, so both with user research, but also just listening to our players.
Great.
That was the last question.
Thank you for coming.