Hi, I'm Kyle Pittman. I'm a graduate of the Guildhall SMU. I
worked at Gearbox Software for six years, and in 2013 my
brother and I founded Minor Key Games, and now we do indie
development. Today I'm going to be talking about jumping in
video games. The principles I'll be discussing can apply to
platformers, both 2D and 3D, but they can also apply to
first-person shooters or endless runners or really any sort of
game that has a jumping mechanic.
Our goal is going to be to move away from the trial and error that occurs when we start by defining physical constants up front.
I've had this experience in my own development, maybe some of y'all have had a similar experience,
where you're working on a new project and you say,
alright, let's start by defining gravity.
We'll say gravity is 9.8 meters per second squared, real world physics, that's a good place to start.
and then we'll choose a jump velocity relative to that.
And maybe we'll tweak these numbers a little bit.
Get something that feels sort of in the ballpark
of what we expect our character's jump
to look and feel like.
But then maybe we send the build to friends
and get some feedback that says,
jumping feels floaty or jumping feels heavy.
We go, okay, how do we respond to this?
How do we tune the feel of our game
without potentially breaking things,
you know, five levels down the road
because suddenly your character can't jump high enough
to reach a platform
or can't jump far enough to clear a gap.
And what we would like to do instead is start by describing
a jump trajectory in terms that are familiar to us
as players and as designers.
I know that I need to jump this high.
I know that I need to jump this far.
And from that description, derive the mathematical,
sorry, derive the mathematical parameters
that we need to model this in code.
So we'll start with a few assumptions.
We're going to be modeling our player character as a massless,
frictionless particle in a vacuum,
because game programmers love those, right?
We're not going to worry about air friction or drag yet.
We could bring those in later if we want to,
but we're going to keep things simple for right now.
Collision bounds don't matter whether you're using a box or a sphere or a capsule, whatever.
The math is going to be exactly the same.
We're going to be representing our player character's state
as a position in space,
a velocity that they're currently traveling,
and a constant downward acceleration due to gravity.
So let's look at gravity.
Gravity is the one and only external force
that's acting on our player character.
It's constant over time, so if we graph this out,
it's just a flat line, and we can write this as an equation,
F double prime of T equals G,
and G is our gravitational constant.
Now from physics, we know that acceleration,
velocity, and position are all related to each other
and that they are derivatives and integrals of each other.
So if we know acceleration at any time,
we can integrate with respect to time to find velocity.
So we'll go ahead and do that.
And this gives us a function for velocity,
f prime of t equals gt plus,
we have to add an initial condition anytime we integrate,
and we call this v naught, this is our initial velocity.
When we graph this out, it's a descending line,
and in fact the slope of that line
is our gravitational constant g.
We can integrate once more with respect to time
to find a function for position, so we'll do that.
And this gives us a function for position,
F of T equals one half G T squared plus V naught T
plus we add another initial condition
when we integrate P naught.
And this is our initial position.
And throughout the rest of this talk,
I'll be assuming that our initial position is zero,
that we're jumping from a ground height of zero,
and that term just sort of goes away.
But it's important to understand why that's there.
And when we graph this one out, you can see it sort of has a nice smooth curve to it.
It's sort of what you would expect to see if you plotted your player character's jump over time.
In fact, this equation is just the textbook physics 101
projectile motion formula.
If you were asked to solve a physics problem about how high
in the air is a baseball five seconds after being hit by a
batter, this is probably the equation you would be using.
And all that we did to get there is we started by saying
gravity is the one thing that affects us, and we integrated
twice with respect to time.
Now this equation has another cool property,
which is that this is a parabola.
Algebraically, we can define a parabola
as f of x equals ax squared plus bx plus c.
And substituting these values,
you can see that our projectile motion formula
does fit that description.
And what that tells us is that the position
and the path our player character follows
as they are traveling through the air
under the influence of gravity is a parabola.
So necessarily, any properties of parabolas
that we can identify would also hold true for that path.
So let's look at some properties of parabolas next.
Every parabola is symmetric about an axis of symmetry
that intersects its vertex,
what we would think of as the peak of the jump.
So what that tells us is that the duration of time
from when we leave the ground
to when we reach the peak of a jump
is going to be the same as the time
from the peak of the jump back down to the ground again.
Every parabola is geometrically self-similar
to every other parabola.
And what that tells us sort of intuitively
is that if we can find a sufficient set of constraints
to describe a parabolic jump trajectory,
for instance, a vertical axis of symmetry
and desired height and distance,
there's only one parabola that could pass through
that set of points, that could fulfill those constraints.
And finally, the shape of a parabola,
whether it's very wide and flat, or very tall and narrow,
this is entirely dependent on the quadratic coefficient A,
which in our projectile motion formula is one half G.
And hopefully that intuitively makes sense as well,
that this would depend on gravity.
As gravity gets stronger, we expect to see
a steeper, sharper fall off on that curve.
For reference, the B and C terms of this parabola
would be the initial velocity,
what we could think of as the tangent to the jump.
and the initial position, which is sort of just a
translational offset on that graph.
So, understanding that our player's jump trajectory
is a parabola, and understanding some of these
properties of parabolas, what we can do next
is start designing a jump on paver.
And for right now, we're gonna be talking about
standing in place, jumping straight up,
and falling straight down.
We aren't jumping sideways through space yet,
but we'll get there.
So for right now, our x-axis is time.
So we'll draw a graph of what we want our player's
jump trajectory to look like and we'll say
we have some height that we want to.
And we'll call this height h.
Maybe you have a platform that's 50 units off the ground
so you want your jump height to be a little bit above that.
Next we need to answer the question
how long does it take us to reach that height?
And we'll call this duration t sub h.
Now because we know every parabola is symmetric
we know that the time at which we land
back on the ground again will be two t sub h.
Now from this description, what we would like to do
is calculate the mathematical properties
that we need to model this jump in code.
And we need two things, we need to know gravity
and we need to know our initial jump velocity.
So we'll start by looking at velocity.
We go back to our graph from earlier
and we say at time zero,
we have some initial velocity v naught.
We don't know what that is yet,
that's one of the things we want to find.
At time T sub H, our velocity is zero.
This is the peak of the jump.
This is when gravity has pulled down hard enough
that we are momentarily weightless
before we fall back to Earth.
And then at time two T sub H,
this is just as we're landing on the ground again.
Our velocity is equal in magnitude
and opposite in direction to our initial velocity.
So this is negative V naught.
So we'll look at this point in the middle here,
where time is T sub H and velocity is zero.
And we'll substitute these values
into our function for velocity and solve for V naught.
And sort of skipping to the end there,
what this gives us is a solution
for our initial velocity V naught
in terms of gravity, which we don't yet know,
and the duration to the peak of the jump,
which we've defined in advance.
So next we need to find a solution for gravity.
So to solve for gravity, we'll go to the graph of position
that we just drew.
We start at a height of zero at time zero.
At time t sub h, we have some desired height h,
and then at time two t sub h,
we've landed on the ground again.
Our height is zero.
From the previous slide, we know that we can express
our initial velocity as a function of gravity and time.
So we'll substitute these values into our equation for position.
And again, we'll look at this point in the middle where our
height is H and our time is T sub H. And we'll solve this for
G. And again, sort of skipping through all the math there.
What this gives us is a solution for our gravitational
constant g in terms of the height and distance,
or in terms of the height and the duration of the jump.
So that's one of the two things we were wanting to find.
Now that we have a solution for gravity,
we can go back to the previous slide where we wrote
initial velocity in terms of gravity,
and we can substitute this in.
And this gives us a solution for initial velocity,
also in terms of the height and the duration of the jump.
So to review, I know I'm skipping through a little bit
of the math here quickly, but if you're taking notes
or taking pictures on your cell phone,
this would be probably one of the slides
you'd want to remember.
What we've done here is we've described a jump trajectory
in terms of the height and in terms of the duration
that it takes to get us to that height.
And from that description, we can calculate the gravity
and the initial velocity that we need
to model this jump accurately in code.
So this is cool, this gets us some of the way to our goal.
But as long as we're speaking about the height of the jump,
it would also be useful to speak about
the distance of the jump.
And we can do that, but we need to introduce
another parameter, which is how fast
do we move side to side.
So I'll be calling this lateral speed or foot speed.
Depending on your game, depending on your application,
this might not be a constant value.
You might have some ramp up and ramp down time
in your foot speed.
You might have a different horizontal speed
when you're running on the ground
versus jumping through the air.
But for the purposes of this talk,
whatever the maximum horizontal speed
that you could reach as you are moving through the air,
whatever that is, that's the number we want to use.
It's also important to note here that you need to keep the
horizontal and vertical components of your player
character's velocity separate.
If you're making a 2D platformer, this means keeping
your X and Y values separate.
If you're making a 3D platformer, whatever your up
axis is, whether that's Y or Z, you need to keep that
separate from movement in the horizontal plane.
And when I say keep those separate, what I mean is if
your player is running really fast sideways and they press
the jump button, you don't want to kill that horizontal
movement and jump straight up.
You want to keep the horizontal movement going and just add a
vertical component to that.
We also have this relationship among three parameters now.
Previously, we were speaking about the duration of the jump,
the time to reach the peak of the jump, T sub H. Now we're
going to start talking about the horizontal distance that
we cover.
on the way to the peak of the jump. And we're also going to be
talking about our foot speed, V sub X.
You can pick two of these, but the third one necessarily has to be a function of the other two.
So for my money, I think it makes the most sense to define the horizontal distance to the peak of the jump,
and define the foot speed, and allow the duration of the jump to be a function of those.
Just because when we're talking about the duration of a jump, usually we're talking about
fractions of a second, and that's not necessarily the most intuitive thing to speak about,
or the most intuitive thing to design up front.
So just as before, we're going to draw a graph
of what we would like our jump trajectory to look like,
only now we're jumping through space.
So our X axis is distance rather than time.
And in fact, you could draw this graph
over a representative scene from your game,
especially if you're making a 2D platformer.
You could say, well, I have a platform this high,
or I have a pit of spikes that's this long,
I know that I need to jump that high
or that far to cross those.
So we're defining our jump now in terms of the height,
but also the distance horizontally that we cover
on the way to the peak of that jump,
and we call that X sub H.
And then we have our lateral foot speed,
and we call that V sub X.
So just as before, we want to find gravity,
and we want to find initial velocity,
because those are the things we need to model this in code.
And to do this, we're going to take the equations
we found previously for those values,
and make some substitutions.
So on the left here, we have a substitution for T sub H,
the duration to the peak of the jump.
We can rewrite this as X sub H,
the horizontal distance to the peak of the jump,
divided by our lateral foot speed, V sub X.
On the top row, we have the equations we found previously
for initial velocity and gravity.
And on the bottom row, we've substituted that T sub H term
with the substitution from the side.
So again to review, this would probably be one of the slides
you'd want to get a picture of.
What we've done is we've started by describing
an ideal desired jump trajectory in terms of height,
in terms of distance, and in terms of how fast
our player character moves side to side.
And from that description, we can calculate gravity,
and we can calculate initial velocity,
and we have everything that we need
to model this jump in code.
So this is pretty cool, this gets us a little bit further.
But at this point, we're still talking about
very perfect parabolic jumps.
And while that might be true to real world physics
in the case of this massless frictionless particle
in a vacuum, it's not necessarily the most fun
or interesting or good feeling thing for a video game.
So what we'd like to do next is start looking for ways
that we can break the rules a little bit
while still relying on these properties
and knowing that we can design our jump
and trust that we're going to reach
a certain height and distance.
And to do this, we're going to start thinking about our jump
trajectory not as a single parabola, but as multiple
segments of partial parabolas.
And to give you a real world example of a game that does
this sort of rule breaking, in the original Super Mario
Brothers,
I think this was mentioned in Steve Swink's book, Game Feel.
In the original Super Mario Brothers,
Mario runs and jumps and flies through the air,
and he reaches the peak of his jump,
and suddenly gravity triples, and Mario falls like a brick.
Now there's nothing real world physics about a sudden
increase in gravity at the peak of a jump,
but that treatment is part of what gives Mario
his characteristic trademark sense of weight.
Along with a slow ramp up and ramp down time
on his sideways movement, it's what makes him feel
different than other video game characters.
And we'd like to look for ways that we can
bring those sorts of unique characteristics
to our own game.
So, let's look at an example.
We'll take the same example of falling faster
beyond the peak of a jump.
We can start by drawing a jump trajectory
exactly as we have in the past,
in terms of height and distance,
and lateral foot speed, but that's not shown here.
But once we get to the peak of the jump,
we'll break it there, and we'll draw a different curve
on the other side, a different part of a different parabola,
one with the same height, but a shorter distance.
Now from the materials that we've already covered,
we have everything that we need to calculate
an initial velocity and a gravity
for each part of this trajectory.
We only need the initial velocity for the first part
as our character's taken off from the ground.
But what we would do then is we would apply
gravity over time for the first half of the curve.
And when we reach the peak of the jump,
in code, when the vertical component of our velocity
goes from positive to negative,
we would switch over and start applying
the heavier gravity corresponding
to the second half of this trajectory.
And when you play this back in real time,
you would see your character follow a trajectory
just like this.
They would fly through the air,
have sort of a nice smooth ascent,
and they would reach the peak of their jump
and fall much faster.
We can do a similar thing for variable height jumping.
variable height jumping tends to be communicated to the player
in terms of
hold the button down longer to jump higher.
But the way we would think about this in code
is we would treat the maximum height
that the player could ever reach as the default.
That's where we get our initial velocity from.
And if the player releases the jump button early,
before they've reached the peak of the jump,
we switch over to a heavier gravity value
to reach the peak sooner.
So in this graph here, where the line goes from blue to red,
that's the moment where the player
has released the jump button.
You can see another outline of blue, an outline in blue in the back, and that represents sort of that maximum jump height that they could reach if they kept the button held down.
You can see another smaller outline in red, and that's a minimum jump height.
If you were to just feather the button on and off again for a split second, you would still want to cover some distance.
So that's where this minimum jump height comes from.
And that corresponds to the gravity that we use to bring the player character to the peak of their jump sooner.
Now once we reach the peak of the jump,
we have a few options.
In this graph, I show us reverting back
to the original gravity, so we have sort of
a nice smooth descent on the other side.
But you could also remain at a heavier gravity value
if the player had released the button sooner.
Or you could even combine this technique
with the one from the previous slide and say,
regardless of whether the player released the button early,
we always switch to a different falling gravity
beyond the peak of the jump.
If you're implementing double jumping or any number of multi-jumps, you could define each stage of the jump as a separate parabola.
Define these in terms of height and distance again, just as we have in the past.
And calculate an initial velocity and a gravity for each stage of this jump.
In this case, you would need to know the initial velocity for that second part, because you would be treating that just like a jump from a standstill in that case.
So throughout this talk I've been mentioning that we need
two things to model a jump in code.
We need gravity and we need initial velocity.
So let's talk a little bit about how this works.
With initial velocity, as soon as the player presses
the jump button, we want to apply that to the player
character's current state.
But again, it's important to note that you want to decouple
your horizontal movement from your vertical.
You don't want to kill horizontal movement and just
jump straight up.
You want to keep horizontal movement.
going and apply a vertical component to that. Gravity
needs to be applied over time so for that one we need to talk
about integration.
Generally speaking, integration solves the problem of
we have some previous game state
and then there's been some passage of time
and we want to predict with as much accuracy as possible
what the next game state is going to be.
In any engine or any framework,
you're going to have the same sort of integration
with this passage of time.
This might be a variable amount of time,
it might be constant,
it might be sort of obscured a little bit,
but that's always there
and your math does need to account for that.
So the easiest way to do this is with Euler integration.
We increment our position by velocity
multiplied by dollar time.
We increment velocity by acceleration
So this is easy to write, but it's not very stable.
And in the worst case scenario,
the player might perceive a difference
in the way their character handles.
For instance, if a lot of stuff is happening on screen
and the frame rate drops.
And those are the sorts of inconsistencies
that we would like to avoid.
So on the far end of the spectrum,
we have the Runge-Kutta methods,
and RK-Far in particular.
I don't have pseudocode for this one
because it tends to be very wordy,
but I would point to the Gaff Runge Games article,
Integration Basics, as a really great overview
of what this might look like
in an actual game development scenario.
However, my takeaway from that article,
and from some of the comments on that article,
is that if all we're doing is dealing with this sort of
projectile motion, the Runge-Kutta methods
are way more complex than what we need.
We can actually find an integration method
that is every bit as accurate,
but much, much simpler to write.
So let's take a look at velocity of relay next.
The way velocity of relay is written,
you start off similar to Euler integration,
you increment position based on velocity,
but then we have this term,
one half acceleration times the square of the delta time.
Then you calculate a new acceleration value
as a function of position.
You increment your velocity by an interpolation
halfway between the previous and new acceleration values,
and then you commit the change to acceleration.
So this is interesting, it's definitely simpler to write
than Runge-Kutta methods, but it's not necessarily
applicable to our situation, because in our case,
gravity is mostly constant, except for those few places
where we've chosen to break the rules
and increase or decrease gravity.
So maybe we can simplify this a little bit further.
What's also interesting to notice here
is we have this one half acceleration
times the square of the dollar time term.
And that sort of recalls our original projectile motion formula.
And in fact if we think about it in those terms, we have this projectile motion formula
and that already answers the question of given any set of initial conditions, for instance
the previous game state, we know with 100% accuracy where our player is going to be at
any time in the future.
For instance, after this delta time.
So if we were to simplify velocity of relay,
assuming a constant acceleration,
this would actually correspond directly
to our projectile motion formula,
and we could trust that we are getting
100% accurate results.
But what about those times when we do deliberately
break the rules a little bit,
and we say we've reached the peak of the jump,
we increase gravity.
How much error do we accumulate in those cases
if we were to just naively integrate this way,
assuming a constant acceleration?
That error would be on the order of the change in acceleration
from the previous frame to the new one. Multiplied by the
square of the dollar time. Now when I ran these numbers on one
of my own games.
This error was about half a pixel.
And this isn't something that would accumulate
over an entire session and eventually
throw things out of whack.
This is a one time offset that gets zeroed out
the next time your player character lands on the ground.
So I would argue this is a perfectly
acceptable amount of error.
And if you've been using Euler integration,
and if you're dealing with projectile motion,
I would recommend giving this simplified
velocity of relay integration method a try.
I think you'll be really happy with the results.
So to review, our goal has been to move away
from trial and error, move away from defining
physical constants up front, and move in a direction
where we can describe a jump trajectory
in terms that are familiar to us as players
and as designers.
I know that I want to jump this high and this far.
And then we want to lean on those abilities
to craft a unique...
individually characteristic jump trajectory
that can give our particular game its own unique feel.
And we still can trust that it's going to feel
rooted in the truth of gravity constantly
pulling our player character down.
So, whoops.
I'll plug my own game here real quick. I have a game on Steam.
It's called You Have to Win the Game. It's free, like actually
free, not in-app purchases free. And it uses most of the
principles I've talked about here today. So if you have a
chance to try that, hopefully you'll like the way it feels and
be convinced that this is a good method to follow. You can find
me on Twitter as well, at Pirate Hearts. My websites are
minorkeygames.com and gunmetalarcadia.com, another
platformer I'm making that uses all of these same principles.
But that's it for me. Thank you for your time.
All right, I guess we do have time for some questions,
so if anyone wants to come up to the mic there.
Can you put up the slide for the last
specific question?
Oh yeah, absolutely.
Yeah.
I guess I wanted to ask really quickly,
I know you briefly mentioned Super Mario Bros.
as a way of, as an example of good jumping.
Are there like any other games you want to mention
that have examples of good or bad jumping?
I haven't analyzed others as specifically as that one,
but I would point to Super Meat Boy as a really good example
of having a unique characteristic sort of floatiness.
But floatiness necessarily doesn't always feel good,
but they managed to make it feel good in that way.
I think it was a combination of the way the character moves,
but also interacts with walls and has wall jumping
and all those sorts of abilities.
Thank you.
Thanks.
If anyone else has another question, I guess we have time
for one more.
Let's thank Kyle.