Hi, this is game designer and eSports personality Chris Tang.
A decade ago, we began the Classic Tetris World Championship to answer the question,
who is the best Tetris player in the world?
It's since become a surprisingly well-loved eSport, even though we still use old hardware like this to play a 30-year-old 8-bit Nintendo cartridge to get the job done.
So, how did we get here?
Our format has evolved, making the most of the game's mechanics, quirks, and simplicity,
while emphasizing the human element and embracing our explosive memes.
Building an inviting, positive community has grown the scene for a game version that may otherwise have been forgotten.
So, maybe something can be learned from our journey and be applied to other games to make
them even more viable for esports.
I'm hoping to inspire you to bring out the competitive heart in your game, esport, or
community.
Come check it out Thursday, March 21st at 5.30pm in Rome 2016.
I'll see you all there to make it BOOM Tetris for GDC!