OK.
Cool.
Great to see that you came here today.
It was the toughest possible competition, Diablo 3
post-mortem in the other hall, and Friday afternoon.
So thank you for showing up.
My name is Fred, and I have the privilege
of being the CEO and president of Paradox Interactive, which
has been growing really rapidly in the past two, three years.
And you might know us from titles like Crusader Kings,
Europa, and Versales, Cities Skylines, Magicka.
And today I'm going to talk about business models.
And I think that in our industry,
we don't talk about business enough.
So I used to work more with games 10 years ago,
when the studio was small.
And I was kind of, even if I was the sales and marketing
guy all the time, I still was a part of the games development
team as well.
But the more I moved out of the games development team,
the better games we started creating.
And even more so, the better business we started making,
because I could focus on what I do best.
So my goal of today is to actually make
more game developers talk about business and business models.
And this is one of my favorite all-time quotes
from Warren Buffett.
Price is what you pay and value is what you get.
Because all markets are basically imperfect,
because we value things totally different.
So someone might value Europa Universalis
at the price of $2,000, because they're putting 4,000 hours
into the game.
Some other people might value this at $1 or $2,
because they'd like just to see what it is,
play it for a little while, and then let it be and have it
in their Steam catalog.
Now, price discrimination doesn't allow us to do that, to charge exactly what people
want to pay for something.
So all markets are in some ways imperfect.
But once you move into a digital world like we're in, most of us in here, we move away
from retail boxes, we can start experimenting much more, both on the pricing side and on
the business model side.
So I'm going to show you some models that we use at Paradox, how we start with a game,
how we integrate the business model, and how we integrate people around the business model,
the value creators that we're working with.
So we are not the only ones making value for our own titles, for our own games.
And starting just by, like, I'm going to use a few words that I come back to here,
and maybe some of you are not familiar with these words,
but business model.
Once you hear that, what is a business model?
Well, it's basically how do you make money?
So even if you don't talk about business models,
you will have a business model in your company
if you have revenue coming into the company.
The second one is value proposition.
And value proposition is the promised value
that you're supposed to deliver to a customer who's
going to use your product.
And that has also been approved by said customer.
And the value chain is everyone who
creates value to put together the value proposition.
Are you with me?
Cool.
This is all CEO art as well.
Did I mention that?
I made this presentation myself, so it might look a bit so-so.
So when you build value chains and business model,
you have to start somewhere.
You have to start like, where do we start talking about this?
Where do we start building our business models?
And the first thing you should talk about at your studio
or whatever business you run is, how do we want to make money?
Not only what are we charging for the products, but philosophically, how do we want to make money?
How do we want to sell our products to our customers?
Like, at Paradox, we've said that we do not want to monetize frustration.
That's one of our key pillars in our business model.
Meaning that, if your character dies in Crusader Kings 2, you cannot buy him back for a dollar.
That would be a bit so-so, because people would be frustrated, right?
And then you can pay your way out of that.
We don't think that's a good way to approach a brand.
So we want people to pay for our games
when they're at, like, really stoked to play something new.
Also, getting the team excited about the numbers.
Start talking about the numbers.
Saying, what are our goals with this?
Not only on the money side, it could be other key performance
indicators as well.
But just get the team excited about the numbers.
Because once we started to get our development team more
excited about the numbers, we started to make better games.
Fact.
You also need a customer approval.
I'm going to get back to this as well, because the customers
are a part of everything you do all the time.
They will have opinions about it.
They will tell you when they think you make mistakes.
And they will turn on you if you make enough mistakes
in a short while.
Also, get the customer engagement
so that they will drive the process further.
Not only approval, but asking like,
how can you help us evolve our business models
and our value proposition, and both.
So intro, we start with the games, right?
Because everyone here, how many are game developers in here?
Hands up.
Most of you.
And the people who work in sales and marketing, anyone?
Few as well.
Any media?
No media, that's good.
Then I can speak freely, that's very good.
Good, we start with the game.
So when we look at a new game, we
look at something from the internal studio,
or we look to publish something.
We talk about three things.
And the first thing is, do we have the passion to do this game?
Do we think that we have the people who will walk 10 extra miles
to make this game really good?
The second one is market.
Is there actually a market for a game like this?
If there's an established competitor, for example,
you can always look at the competitor,
but if you're creating something new,
you have to kind of second-guess if there's a market or not,
trying to quantify it.
But still...
And the third one, obviously, is skill.
Do we have the skills to do this?
Passion is not enough to actually complete
the project that's going to be world class.
So you need the skills to do it.
Do we have the resources to actually pull through?
The resources are not only on the development side.
It's also on the sales and marketing side.
We've had numerous discussions.
This is 10 years ago.
But still, whether a good game sells itself.
How many in here would say a good game sells itself?
Anyone?
Yeah, a few really brave souls.
That's good.
So let's look at our funnel.
How tight is the Paradox funnel?
When we look at new games and new time, how critical are we
about new concepts coming into Paradox, or old concepts, for
that matter?
I once was pitched a game called Fish Tetris, which was
you should match fishes against each
other to remove them.
That's one of the most terrible pitches I've ever seen.
And that's one, probably of the 400 in here, 401, specifically,
something like fish tetras.
Those were the pitches received total in 2015
to Paradox Interactive, 401 pitches in total,
which is more than one pitch a day.
And of the 400 pitches, 20 went to the Green Light Committee
for further research.
And the games that we are actually signing for further,
like up until prototype, is between one and three.
Probably all three of them.
But at least one of those projects
will be closed before it reaches prototype stage.
That's how tight the funnel is.
And then you go over to what are the reasons for declining
so many games.
First of all, there are genre issues.
We have decided what makes a Paradox game.
And I'm going to come back to that with even more C-E-O-R.
We stand for something.
And if the game doesn't stand for the same thing as we do,
we can't sign the game, no matter how good it is.
Then you have pillar issues, which
is very, very game-specific.
And then you have, of course, development issues as well.
Is the developer not the right developer?
We don't think they can actually make this game happen.
Just to give you a glance on how we work.
The first thing we do when we look at a new game
or look at a new project overall is setting the vision.
And a vision is really important
because when you look at the wall
and you see the vision every day, you can unite your team.
There are a couple of good visions out there.
I mean, we use for our upcoming space game Stellaris.
The galaxy is vast and full of wonders.
So what does that say when you look at it?
It says that it's kind of different from our other games.
because Europa Universalis is...
there is no exploration in that game.
So the implicated thing in Solaris is that it starts with exploration.
For example, they can interpret this in many different ways, of course,
but you can unite the team behind the vision.
My absolute favorite vision, I think it's the vision at least,
that's what I heard, is for Gears of War.
And, very easy to understand,
Marcus Fenix is a badass.
That's good.
Why is that a good vision?
Because when you look at Marcus Fenix,
you see he's a badass.
The artists who work with Marcus Fenix
knows that he should be painted as a badass.
He doesn't open doors.
He kicks doors in because he's a badass.
So everything in the game design,
everything in the art,
everything in the level design
implies that he's a badass.
Everyone can get behind that.
So why do you actually set this vision,
and why is it so important?
You help the team find the direction of what they do.
It's really easy to communicate to your fans.
It's part of your marketing plan as well.
You can find angles in the marketing that actually
explains the vision and even deepens it even more.
And of course, you identify the priorities as well.
You can talk about what's the most badass of these two
choices that we have.
And how do you set this?
A vision is not easily completed.
The worst visions you can ever have
is this is going to be the best strategy game ever.
No one has a clue what they're supposed to do.
It doesn't set an angle.
It doesn't set a direction.
It just says it's going to be really good once it's finished.
Or the best World War II game ever made.
It's a terrible vision.
Terrible.
Could be a statement, or it could
be a general feeling that makes up your visions.
And the people making it should be everyone involved
in the team.
And I'll get back to that as well,
why it's so important to mix and match teams
between not only development, but also sales, marketing,
and all other parts of the company.
Dreaming big is the next step.
We feel that, OK, we're doing something new here,
something new, cool, that people should be excited about.
So we'll dream 18 to 24 months ahead.
The game is already out there.
It's a big success.
Everyone wants to play it.
So who is playing this game?
If it was a book written on this game, who would write the book
and what type of book would that be?
Who would be the author?
Would it be Stephen King or would it be Ernest Hemingway?
Wear it.
Like, how do you cosplay this game?
How do you make the game have a soul?
So when someone goes to PAX to show off to their friends,
what do they actually wear?
Watch it.
It's obviously a TV series.
Maybe is it Netflix or HBO?
Is it R-rated or T-rated?
And who's the director for this TV series or a movie?
Build it.
How do we actually get our fans to build things for us?
What do they build in the game?
How do they present it, et cetera?
Preach it is really important.
It's like, what do people say about this game
when they're trying to convince their friends to play it?
When we released Europa Universalis 3, our whole tactic was anti-marketing.
And why do you call it that?
Our whole marketing angle was,
maybe this game is too hard for you to play.
And people were like, really? I'm gonna show you.
So we found out that the way most people learned about Paradox Games
was they saw other people playing the Paradox Game
and they asked, what are you playing?
Never mind, I don't think you would get it.
And that provokes a lot of people, obviously.
Some people would be like, OK, OK, I get it.
I'm stupid.
I can probably not play this game.
Other people would be intrigued.
And those were the people we're looking for.
And of course, this summarizes it into a lifestyle.
You'll live it.
You'll live the game.
And so this is the dreaming big scenario
that we're using, first the vision, then
how do you dream about this?
Which takes us into my game pillars,
which is what actually makes up the game
and how are the different departments of Paradox
involved in what the game actually is.
And if we start with what is the game pillar,
we have seven different game pillars.
The most important thing about every pillar of our games
is the player value.
You always start with discussing what
is the right for the players.
And the problem with our industry
has been for a long time that there are a lot of big egos
with artistic ambitions.
It can also be a positive thing, but when
it comes to player value first, it's a really big challenge.
And I know I'm one of these egos as well.
Sometimes you have to just put it away and do
what's right for the gamers.
The second most important thing here is the paradox value.
Like, for us as a company, what value does this pillar have?
And how does it match with the gamer value?
If we're working with an external developer,
what's their value in this?
Or if the internal studio paradox, what's their value?
Marketing value, the marketing department,
why should this be exciting to them?
Why is this core pillar a really good thing for marketing?
And of course, the people working in sales,
working with our partners, working with Steam,
Microsoft, Sony, et cetera.
Why should they be excited when they're trying
to sell and present the game?
Does it make sense?
So we're trying here, our most important feature
of all is replayability.
for people to pick up and play the game again
and have a different experience.
There is something new that they didn't experience before.
And the most obvious thing for that, for the gamers,
is that they get a lot of bang for the buck.
It's a lot of value for the gamers.
And the big thing for Paradox is obviously
that we get highly engaged customers, people
who play our games over and over again,
provide us with feedback, and it creates a positive spin
of developing the game further.
The development value here is that you can continue for a long time to continue to develop the game and make it even better.
If you have high engaged fans to play it over and over again, people will continue to support your development.
The marketing value is obviously it's easier to reach the customers because we know they're in-game and we know they're following our social channels, our email channels and everything.
It's very easy to communicate to all the gamers out there.
And the sales value for the people handling the partners
is the attach rate.
So if you release a new piece of DLC or an expansion,
you know that a certain amount of the people
are actually playing the game every month or every day
even are going to buy this expansion or DLC.
So business-wise, it actually makes sense.
We also say that.
We are hardcore. We're in the hardcore segment of the gaming markets.
We're not making any casual games. We're targeting niches.
And the player value here is to feel smart.
Right? The whole, maybe you can't really play this game, feeling.
But you can. And you feel smart. It's like being a part of the Illuminati.
Only that you're a Paradox Gamer instead.
Which is almost as good. You don't really rule the world, but you do it on your computer.
It's like an interactive version of Illuminati.
The value for Paradox is obviously
that there is limited competition.
So we don't face, we're not going up against Zynga or King,
in this case, to buy new customers all the time.
So it's a limited competitive space.
So if we make really good games, we
know we can keep the gamers.
The dev value is that there is no bullshit in here.
They can pretty much do whatever they want,
as long as they get the gamer approval.
So it's not only data-driven, but driven by what
the gamers say as well.
In the marketing value, it stands out.
So it's not just another copy of a copy of a copy of a game
that is trying to churn out new things.
It's actually something that stands out
and has a marketing angle.
And the sales value is obviously that the lifetime value of this is going up,
because the hardcore gamers play more.
I'm gonna run through a little faster here, but we do functional reform,
which means that the game doesn't have to be triple A quality
on the side of graphics, for example.
Which means that for a player, you don't need the latest and greatest hardware to play the game.
For us, it's a good return of investment because graphic costs a lot of money.
So we can keep the risks down and still keep the upside,
because if a lot of people play the game, we still make a lot of money.
So the risks are lower and the ROI can be really great still.
The dev value here is small teams.
You can work in small teams where you have a lot of say,
so a lot of responsibility.
This doesn't fit all developers.
I know that.
But to the people who want to work in small teams,
where actually your opinion counts,
this is the perfect way to do it.
So game pillars and everything else with the vision
is not just to attract people.
It's also to define who should not be a part of this.
So if you like large teams, where you only
work on gun sounds for two years in a row.
this is not going to fit you.
So it's really good to be upfront about that as well.
Marketing value, messaging there,
and market accessibility on sales.
We say that we want to make our games accessible,
which you might laugh a bit at.
If you look at the interface on Crusader Kings 2,
it's kind of daunting,
but we're working on this core pillar a lot.
We've identified it as important.
So player value is no frustration.
And for us, value for the whole company
is that we reach a wider audience.
The dev value is that the stickiness of the product
is going to increase.
Because if you learn the game quicker,
you're going to keep on playing.
We've seen that on data as well.
Market value is that you can explain the game.
And the sales value is the promotion potential.
Because if you have all the other things,
the promotion potential and to sell at a lower price
increases a lot as well over time.
Creative is a little bit fuzzy, but give the ability for people to create their own things like modding, for example, in the game.
Make it easy for people to make YouTube videos. That's the creative part of this.
So for the gamer, it's a self-expression thing. People love to do things. So people make mods without being paid, right?
The Crusader Kings 2 Game of Thrones mod is a super ambitious product.
And they can't charge for it, because HBO would shut them
down, which is reasonable, because it's not their IP.
But still, it drives a lot of traffic for us as well.
Like I was touching here, it's a lot of value
creation for Paradox.
If you just allow people to go crazy with your products,
they're going to create a lot of value.
And taken together, we have 5 million registered Paradox
customers right now.
It's increasing by 300,000 a month.
Collectively, they are obviously a lot smarter than we are.
We're only 200 people at two offices.
So if we can combine the thinking of five million people
instead of just being 200 creating things,
we're up for something good going forward.
For the devs, it's a good way to find talent.
We find sometimes people who made mods for us,
made YouTube videos or whatever to help us out
and to carry the company forward.
So you could call it a recruitment process as well.
Obviously, it's free marketing.
And the potential, I mean, user generated content
is like a swearing word right now,
after the Skyrim debacle and all of that.
But still, we've used a lot of things created by people
to sell them to our other users.
And they get really well paid.
So there's a huge potential that is, to a large extent,
untapped, except for Valve, who does it really well for Dota 2,
for example, and for Team Fortress.
We have high engagement subject matters,
like history is one of those,
that people are super engaged, like World War II,
which means that they can nerd out.
So my, it has a backside as well.
So once you start a thread on the Hearts of Iron forum,
Hearts of Iron is a World War II game,
which is, which do you think was the best tank
during World War II?
You have to close the thread after an hour
due to flame wars.
Which is, but the nerding out thing, I got,
Hearts of Iron is a good example,
because we had a lot of technologies and generals.
I don't remember how many, but thousands of them in the game.
So I get an email, this is 2006, from a player saying,
the following mistakes in the game
makes your shit game totally unplayable.
And there's a list of things, no bugs listed at all.
Things like, German felt howitz cannon, nine centimeters.
You say deployed February 43.
True date, March 2, 43.
Stuff like that.
And it's great, because they really help us by doing that.
So I just sent an email back saying, wow, that's great.
Here you get some download codes for helping us out.
And he replied, oh, that's good.
Thank you.
So by nerding out and by creating
these high engagement subject matters,
people will engage even more in your game.
We think, at least.
These are ours.
The switching cost from the game is higher.
So it's harder for a player to switch to another game that
is made by a competitor if they're not making
the exact same game as a copy.
It's also rich on materials.
So it's really easy to find new material for the game
that you're creating.
So you're not having to make up new things or new IP.
You already have an existing audience or a fan base
in that space.
And obviously, you can find a lot of tie-ins as well.
So this is my proudest moment of this presentation of CEO art.
Look at all the imperfections right there.
This is the full slide if you want to take a picture of that.
And I'll move on in three, two, one.
Here we go.
So why we move over to the business stuff.
That was the game stuff, how we make games at Paradox
from a business angle still.
I have some Paradox developers in the audience,
and they would tell you a totally different story
than this one.
how we make a game.
This is my perspective, on the business side.
So why do you want to make a business model?
Why do you want to visualize to people
how the business model looks
and what you're trying to do with your business model?
First of all, it's a naming convention.
If you use the same words for the same things,
you will work in the same direction.
So, in our case, is Steam a partner or a channel?
It's really important because if we have the words just wrong,
we might just misunderstand what we're doing.
The other thing is that, is there actually
a receiver on the other end for this product?
Once you start analyzing the business model
and dig deep, which we're going to do in a moment,
you will see, is there really someone who's
interested in playing this game?
It helps you to focus a lot as well.
If you visualize the whole business model on a big screen
like this, you will see quite clearly what do we need to
focus on to make this a big success.
And the fourth one is that it encourages use of data.
Because once you start talking about business models, you
will figure out that some people only have opinions.
It's my opinion that.
I actually banned that word from our management meeting.
I said, you can't have an opinion,
because it's worth shit.
You can have a thesis.
My thesis is that the things are like this.
Opinions, no.
Thesis, OK.
If you have data, you can say, the data backs up,
and I base my thesis on this data.
But maybe your thesis is wrong, so the data
is showing something else.
That's also how you put it, the naming convention.
No opinions.
Then we make what we call a business model assessment.
We ask ourselves seven simple questions about the game
that we're about to look at.
The first is the product switching cost.
How much does it cost for a customer
to switch from your product to a competitive product?
How much emotional investment, financial investment,
forum time investment, and other relationship
has a person actually invested in this game?
And how easily would they switch to another game?
How do we have to screw up for the people
to actually leave us and never come back?
That's the first one.
The second one is.
what's the potential for recurring revenue in this game?
It has a lot to do with the core pillars that I just presented,
like the replayability.
If the replayability is high,
the recurring revenue potential is much higher, for example.
Earning versus spending.
Do you make money early in the process,
for example, through a Kickstarter?
Or do you make money after the game is released?
How does that look?
It's a risk assessment.
Do we as a company have a game-changing cost structure?
If we compare to our competitors,
how large teams do they have?
What's their marketing budget?
How do we spend our money?
Are we smarter with our money than our competitors are,
but we can still keep the same quality?
To what extent do other people or are other people
allowed to add value to our games?
Modders, for example?
YouTubers?
So how do you make other people do the work for you?
It's also a cost issue to some part,
because if you have 1,000 YouTubers creating videos
for you, you don't need a marketing department.
Or maybe you need a marketing department,
because you can get up to 2,000 YouTubers next week.
So to what extent do others do the work?
And the final one is, how scalable is the product?
And by scalable, it's a buzzword here in San Francisco
specifically, but all over the world.
Scalable basically means, can I sell one more product
without adding any extra staff?
How scalable is the business model?
And the final one, how protected are we
against our competition?
Is it easy to like, how do we see that,
the protection against competition?
These seven, we rate them from 1 to 10,
and then we try to see how can we actually
make this even better?
And how do we integrate that in the game design?
We make the assessment sheet, and we apply it
on the game design sheet and see, wait,
can we do something here?
Is there a potential to do any of these seven a lot better?
Which brings us to the whole visualization of what a business model looks like.
How many people recognize this model?
Yeah, quite a few are working with it, that's good.
What I want to say, if you start in the middle there,
those of you who know it, maybe know it as good as I do,
but the value proposition is the number of,
this is available online, it's called the Business Model
Canvas by a company called Strategizer.
I've been to a few workshops on that, and I'm still a novice,
but we're trying to get there.
So the value proposition is the sum of products and services
that your company provides for a customer.
They are being sold through channels, as you see there,
to the customer segments.
And the customer relationships is
how you approach your customer in terms of communication.
Email, social channels, direct phone calls, hopefully not,
but still.
And down there to the left, to the right, is the revenue.
How do we actually make money here?
On the other side is key resources.
What do we actually need to make this product or value
proposition a reality?
Programmers, artists in our business, for example, game
designers, and the key activities we need to engage
in to make this value proposition happen.
And what partners do we need to actually carry this through?
On that side, it sums up the cost structure.
And if the revenue are higher than the costs, it's a
profitable product.
Very simple way to put it.
So we work a lot with this model.
Just placing Post-its on this business model canvas,
moving them around.
And you will have to, all the time,
to invent your business model.
Because there's something called the Icarus paradox.
And it means that you're a victim of your own success.
So once you've succeeded big time with something,
and you don't change it over time,
the customers will feel that they own this game more than you do.
So you will get your core audience to turn on you
once you start changing things in the business model.
A company is only in one of two stages.
One is development and the other is stagnation.
So once you reach your peak on your business model,
you'll start to stagnate if you don't innovate.
There are a lot of companies out there in our business who
does not innovate.
I'm not going to name any of those, because I'll probably
be sued.
But I'll name a few companies who are really good at
inventing this.
Look at Blizzard, for example.
They released World of Warcraft with a $15 recurring
revenue every month.
And they kind of realized this business model is growing old.
So what did they do?
Invented Hearthstone, which has a better scalability, high
switching cost, everything.
It's even better if you take the business model assessment
that I just showed.
Hearthstone is even better than World of Warcraft.
And World of Warcraft is a really strong one.
So Blizzard is one of those companies that are always
inventing their business models as well.
So by making Hearthstone, which is totally different from
World of Warcraft, they don't really need the customer
approval in the same way.
So if you're only working on one game, and you work on the same business model all the time,
the customers will have their say all the time.
And if you do something too strange or too weird, they will turn on you,
and tell you you can't do that, and you'll have to back up like 50 steps again and start over.
With a slightly damaged reputation as well.
So...
When you design business models, it's
interesting that you don't need to talk about business models.
You can talk product, you can talk model,
and you can mix and match the teams.
When you talk about the business model at the abstract level
that this is, the former screen.
you can have people from marketing discussing a game product because it's so abstract
and then they can take it back to the team, like what are the overarching goals
rather than what is the actual game design and they could take out the different parts
of the business model, give it to the people in different departments and let
they do the interpretation work but you've agreed on the overarching goals.
You can work a lot with constrained creativity,
that you box in things and say,
we will start only in this part of the business model canvas
and work from there.
If you take, for example,
six pieces of H-stud Lego, like this one,
six pieces of that, and combine them, for example,
you can only combine these six pieces.
How many ways can you combine them?
It turns out it's 915 million different combinations.
That's pretty cool.
Like, you would say, oh, I can only work with these six studs.
That's impossible.
No, you can do a lot.
So if you go back, if I go back to the former one here,
you can start in any of these squares right here
and start working on a business model or on a game.
Say that you start in revenue streams and say,
let's make a game where we have to charge $10 a month
for people to play it.
How would that look?
How do we fill the other parts of this,
and how do we write the game design based on this business
model canvas?
Or you can start in the customer signals.
You can start in the channels.
It doesn't matter, as long as you do new things and innovate.
And the most important thing is not
to make new projects based on this.
It's more of a thought process.
It's more getting people to think this way,
the way they approach problems.
I'll move on.
Which moves us to when you take out the value proposition and the customer segments out of this equation,
you get the value proposition canvas. This is also available online.
And the model with a little head there, it says customer jobs.
So when a customer picks up your product,
what are their expectations that the job to be done for them is fulfilled?
If you take a drill, for example, if you buy a drill, that's a very good hardware tool.
What are you actually paying for?
If you're a Marxist, you would say you're paying for the plastic,
you're paying for the iron,
and you're paying for the transportation of the product to the hardware store.
But what are you actually paying for?
You're paying because you want the hole in the wall in your house or apartment.
Nothing else.
It's a customer job that needs to be fulfilled.
There are two other things here on the customer side.
One is pains.
What is the potential pain that people will feel
when they buy this product?
What are their worst fears when they look at your product
and they're about to buy it?
And the gains, what are they hoping
to achieve that is even more good, like good side effects,
by having your product?
And on the left side here is how do you actually make a
product that matches the jobs, how do you relief the pains
from the customers, and how do you enhance the gains.
So now I'm going to show you the value proposition we did
for Europa Universalis 4.
You ready?
So on the right-hand side there, let's start with the
customer jobs.
One of them is feel smart.
People want to feel smart.
They want to also be challenged, strategy gaming-wise.
You could make a mod, for example.
It's good.
Typically, you could take this down to three to five different
in each square.
It makes it easier to look at.
If you take the pains, for example,
one of the apparent pains we've seen with our games
is I'm not sure I'm going to be smart enough to play this game.
I'm not sure that I will actually understand
how to play this game.
And a few of the gains are like I can engage in a great
forum, for example.
I'm a part of a big community that has a lot of fun together.
And if you match that on the other side, one of the pain
relievers we have to do is how do we make a good tutorial?
How do we make it easy for people to come into the game?
YouTube videos, for example, interactive
tutorials, part of that.
The gain enhancers, like how do we make it even easier to
contribute to our forums and to sign in and to be a part of
it on the gain enhancer side.
And the product is obviously your Open Universalist 4.
So this is a way of toying with your own ideas and
getting quantitative and feedback from
the community as well.
You can read what people are actually
writing about your game.
Media, for example, Steam reviews, and put them here.
We see that 50% of everyone is saying that the character
creation is not deep enough.
Do we agree with that?
And how do we sort it out if that's so
important to our clients?
Great.
I'm going to have one more management models.
I'm not a big fan of these management literature books.
They're just going to change everything forever.
So blue ocean strategy, how many are familiar with that?
Right? Blue ocean basically means that you should move out of the competitive space
and move into space where there's no competition.
And you do it by four simplified steps.
And we did this for City Skylines straight off.
And I'm going to tell you exactly how we did it.
So it consists of four building blocks.
I'm going to check the time, sorry.
Four building blocks, which is...
First of all...
What features do our competitors have, in this case,
SimCity 5, that we can eliminate completely from our product?
And that is costly for them to create as well.
So we save money and take away a feature.
In our case, it was that the game was always online.
They put a lot of money into making it always online.
And we said,
What would be the reasoning?
If you're making a customer job out of this, what's the
reasoning of always being online?
We don't think there is one.
We think what they looked at was the value for EA to be
always online.
They probably wanted to track the customers and
see what they did.
So we said, OK, we also want to track what our customers
are doing in the game.
Can we do that without being always online?
The answer was yes.
So good.
Out the door.
Simple as that.
Reduce.
What features do we think we can reduce to such a limit
that we save a lot of money without ruining the game
experience?
There are a lot of examples of this in Cities Skylines,
SimCity example.
But in this case, we had 200 buildings in our game
when we released it.
They had 800.
And that's a huge budget difference.
Create.
What features can we add?
that is of high value to the customers,
but is not present in the current product.
For us, it was, for example, modding.
We knew that the SimCity modding group
were desperate to have a game with modding in it,
a modern city builder.
That also took care of the problem
that we had fewer buildings.
In 24 hours, we had more than 2,000 mods for Cities Guide.
So ta-da!
Right?
Took care of the problem.
And what factors should be raised above industry standard?
We don't need to outdo them totally,
so we put a lot of effort into the management layer of it.
We said, people want to play.
They don't want every individual simulated
because it's really costly.
So we'll put a management layer on it.
and more abstract how you actually run a city, which
can have really interesting side effects once you start
following individuals in Cities Skylines
and make a lot of funny stories, which is also
a side thing with emergent gameplay and all that.
I urge you all to see a really PC gamer article which
is called The Cities Skylines City with Only One House,
where they try to simulate the Sims in Cities Skylines.
It turns out very weird, I can tell you that much.
But it's almost an extra value, because it creates new, weird,
emergent gameplay stories as well.
So it didn't matter to people that much.
And if you divide this into two groups,
it's on the cost-saving side, the red ones,
and on the cost-increasing on the other side.
And you have to balance this in a very good way.
So basically, if you walk through the process how
we work, just recap everything I said so far.
The product mission comes first.
The value proposition comes second.
And if the value proposition is not good enough, we will
have to start over with the product vision, because maybe
they're not matching together.
You look then at the project scope.
Can we actually pull off the value proposition
with this vision?
up to the prototype phase.
And after prototype, you're fairly sure
that the whole team understand exactly what they're supposed
to do, the marketing angle, the sales benefits, everything.
So everyone in the organization will be on the same page
if it's done right.
I'm not saying we're doing this right all the time
because I have Paradox employees in the audience,
but we strive to do it right.
And if the prototype is not good enough,
you just go back to the value proposition and say,
can we redo the value proposition
and see if it fits better for the next prototype?
Is it even worth doing a new one?
And if you take game design versus business strategy,
because it's basically the same thing.
Typically, when you run into a problem with a product,
it has a business side and it has a development side.
It's not opposite.
It's actually the same.
So we take the Crusader Kings 2 example.
We have developer problems and we have business problems.
The problem with previous versions of Crusader Kings
was that every time we released something for it,
it was different versions for different gamers.
Which, on the other hand, on the business side,
caused lower attachment rates for DLCs
because you needed all the time to upgrade your game.
The developer problem as well, this is actually Europa.
Europa Universalis 3 was a game released before Crusader Kings
2, so all the problems come from Europa 3.
The multiplayer support, because you have different versions,
you couldn't have multiplayer support in a good way,
which made the business problem that customers
weren't satisfied because it was not
a full and complete product in the eyes of people.
The developer problem also, which stemmed from different versions, was that it was problems to adapt the mods to all the different versions,
which made the business problem that you had lower engagement rates on the people there,
because they knew that maybe I can't download this mod because I have the wrong version and whatever, I don't really care.
So, our solution to that was actually, every time we release a DLC,
You download the whole game, and you get 50% of it for free,
and the rest you unlock.
But all the content is in there, so everyone is basically
playing the same version.
So what seems like a really simple solution actually
took a lot of thinking, because both these things
had to match in together.
If this was only something that would
have been solved from a development standpoint,
I'm not sure that we would actually sort out
the business problems.
We could have found something completely different that
took care of the developer problem,
but what didn't make sense business-wise.
Which takes me to the final part, which
is the value creation part.
And we have coined an expression that we call games
as a platform on the value creation side.
And value creation-wise is a gaming ecosystem
created by you that continues to grow
without your own involvement.
So basically, it's a self-serving system of gamers.
Team Fortress 2 is the best example in the world of this.
So when you talk about value creation,
like, who is actually creating value in this process?
And what are the two key rules
for how you make it possible for people
to create value for your game?
First one is, if you make it easy for people to create
value, for example, mods, you're on the winning side of
the games industry.
If you make it hard, if you lock people out, you're on the
losing side.
If watching a YouTube video of your game adds value to the
gamer rather than spoils the whole game, you're on the
winning side of gaming.
Those are the two golden rules of value creation
and how your game is created and how it affects your game design.
So it's not only about creating the value
and how do you actually attract the people who create the value.
Simple.
First, lots of replayability, a lot of good mod support,
dedicated people who take care of that.
a YouTube friendliness. We talk a lot about what's the YouTube moment of this game.
Like, why does someone finally, or just all of a sudden on YouTube, cry out in like laughter or
something like that? What happens in the game when that happens on YouTube? Because that is what
people are actually watching on YouTube.
Also, a game that creates stories,
so you will tell your friends what happened in the game,
and you will be intrigued to create more things that
are happening and engaging in the game.
And the most important factor of all,
let the people who create value in your game
also make money from it.
You can split it up in between you,
because after all, it's your game,
so you should have some of the money.
But there are companies who are blocking people
from putting up YouTube videos as well.
Don't do that.
suicide.
That was my walkthrough for today.
I just want to summarize everything I said.
I wanted three hours here, because I
wanted to go deeper in on everything like this.
But I'll summarize everything we have here
in a few bullet points.
And I'd be happy to answer any questions if you have any.
So the first thing is, choose and set
the vision for your game.
And don't set a bad vision, like we're
going to create the best RTS ever,
because it's a crappy vision.
It's really bad.
And a bad vision is actually worse than no vision at all.
So if you don't feel that, you should read an article saying,
that's named, How to Write a Mission Statement That
Doesn't Suck.
It's a great article.
And it says everything you need to know
how to write mission and vision statements.
And it's really hard to do this.
And it's really frustrating.
But it needs to be done.
Start thinking about how do we, at our company,
integrate the business design with the game design.
How do they affect each other?
What are the synergies?
And what are the points where we don't really agree,
and we have to choose in between which thing is the right way
to go?
Start including, if you don't already do that.
Include the value creators, because they
are your best friends.
Make your game live forever.
If you take those three above, it
will live for at least 10 years.
And the most important thing in our business, my closing words,
is to have a lot of fun.
Because if you don't, it will show in the game,
and no one will want to play it.
Thanks.
Thank you.
Thank you again, Kairon.
Thanks.
Thank you, everyone.
Thank you for coming to this talk.
Hope we'll see you at the end of the year.
Thanks a lot.
Thanks.
Cheers.
Thank you.
Really?
It's Friday afternoon and all, you're longing for the beer?
Hey, how's it going?
Thanks very much for the talk.
So on the subject of value creation,
I don't know if you deal with this a lot,
but I have sort of a concern about the idea
of physical merchandise creation and how
you handle that side of things on the fan side.
So with the rise of things like RedBubble and other fan sites
and community sites where people can
submit their own artwork or variations on your game's
artwork, how do you kind of handle that stuff?
you mean people who monetize on your game without telling you?
Exactly, like someone who's going to make a Crusader Kings 2 shirt and sell it on a
Redbubble site without your explicit permission and stuff like that.
I think it's really important to put down...
to own your brand as well.
So you need to be very clear that, of course, you can sell
this, but we need a part of the revenue to continue to
develop the game and everything.
So there's nothing strange about that.
You should just tell people that.
We're really up front with that.
So as long as people do it just for fun, it's OK.
If they start monetizing it, we want in on it, because
still, we made all the hard work.
So I don't think that should be a problem.
Cool.
Thank you very much.
Always, when you communicate with value creators, it's very
important not to start with a lawyer.
Right.
Because a lawyer is a very aggressive way to approach someone.
So if you get a cease and desist letter, people might just post it online and say,
look at these assholes.
I'm just trying to do a lot of fun stuff here.
So send out an email saying, you know what?
This is our take on the situation.
What do you say?
Just be reasonable and nice.
And most people will actually, yeah, they will understand the situation.
Cool.
Thank you again.
Hi, you talk about high switching costs as something that you want to have in your game.
I'm wondering if you can talk a little bit about basically the things that give a game a high switching cost
and games that, things in your game that might take away from that.
A game that has high switching costs?
Yeah, yeah, just basically like what practices you think tend to promote that.
And just to clarify by the way, it seems like mainly what you're talking about is...
Basically like sunk time and sunk cost this psychological barrier people have to kind of pull away from that are there
Other elements to it than that as well. Absolutely there are several different ways you
There are several different switching costs one is for example
Financial if you put a lot of money into something you will continue like supporting that typically so psychologically
Once you put one dollar into something you'll continue to support that
And that's why consultants like to send an invoice as quickly as possible,
so they can continue to just invoice you, because you'll probably be immune to invoices after a while.
I've seen that happen all the time.
But if you take a game with high switching costs,
the two MOBAs that are the biggest ones have really high switching costs.
And the reason for that is, I play League of Legends myself a lot.
I could never switch to Dota, both because the mechanics are too complex and I'm not smart enough,
but to all you Dota 2 players out there, feel that you're better than a League of Legends player.
But I've learned all the characters in the game.
So I know exactly all the moves.
I know exactly how to attack and how to protect myself
from everything.
So that's a perfect way of saying
that gameplay design and character design
actually adds a lot of switching cost to a game.
OK, cool.
Thanks.
Okay, cool. I'll let you go.
Friday beer is for everyone. Take care.