ready to go? Should we do this? All right. Hello, everybody. Thanks for coming. My name is
Frank. I look like that. I'm putting my Twitter bio up here because I think it's the best
description of my job I've ever given myself. I like to call myself an archivist and historian
with a game dev day job because it turns out that's not really a job that pays bills or
anything. So I was born back in 82.
I'm going to start this off, I should say, with a little bit of a mini bio.
Just bear with me, it makes sense.
I was born in 1982 with an Atari in the house, but really my first love was the mighty
Nintendo Entertainment System.
I don't know if you guys have ever heard of this.
antiquated device before. This actually came out originally in
1985. I was kind of a late comer. So, you know, I had a
couple of games. My neighbors did, too. I played them. It was
a toy. I was a kid. But more than that, I had a subscription
to Nintendo Power. This was actually my very first issue.
And it was bimonthly at the time, meaning this is the
entirety of what I read for about two months.
And I really think of my curiosity and appreciation for the breadth of what video games had to offer started here with this issue
reading coverage of games with weird titles like clash at demon head and and
Thank you for that one clap for classic demon head
River City Ransom was in this issue. That was a cool-looking game. There's a game here called
Dino Wars about, like, mech dinosaurs. And I remember, I think a lot of us did this sort of
tracing along the map with my finger, like imagining in my head what these weird games must
be like to play. So, you know, that was my childhood. And then I became, you know, a dumb
teenager and I started playing with one of these instead of a controller. I kind of grew out of
games, whatever that means. I think times were kind of different back then.
There wasn't really a gamer culture that I was a part of.
They were just toys and I grew up,
which was kind of dumb in retrospect.
But that all changed in 1998 when I got my first computer.
It looked something like that.
I couldn't find an exact picture of my model.
I also looked something like that,
so a little bit kind of like that.
I had long hair.
And along with my first computer was my initial access to the Internet, which, yeah, woo,
AOL 4.0, yeah, 100 hours free.
So this is kind of what the Internet looked like back then.
And with my access to the Internet, I started looking up things I was kind of nostalgic
for, like those video games I used to play when I was a kid.
And I discovered something amazing.
You could download and play Nintendo games on your computer.
This is, I'm sorry, this is not Genesis.
This is in fact Nesticle, which was the premier
Nintendo entertainment system emulator of the time.
The word, if you don't get the joke,
rhymes with a certain piece of anatomy
that's on about half of us.
The mascot of Nesticle, as you can see here,
is the fecal lord, or shit man,
depending on which part of the screen.
you're looking at. The icon there is a bloody hand that's
actually dripping. As you can see, this was sort of the very,
very mature emulation scene at the time. But Nesicle ran NES
games I grew up with in various degrees of accuracy, coming to
go. In full speed on my computer, I was able to do
which was bonkers back then. That was amazing. There was no
digital distribution worth a darn yet. These were cartridges
that I barely came across. But, you know, so I started playing
the games I grew up with. I played the games I rented back
then maybe. I played the games that my neighbors had. But then
I was like, wait, I can play the games that I read about in
Nintendo Power. See what those are about. So Clash of Demon
heads turned out, wow, that was a really cool game.
River City Ransom, that's almost even cooler.
Look, this guy's gonna hit that guy with a tire.
That's amazing.
And then Dino Wars. ♪♪
The Clash of Demonhead was really good, though.
So I started realizing that I wasn't alone in this.
I was getting really interested in what older games were
and what they had to offer, and I wasn't alone.
There was an emerging sort of retro gaming community at the time.
These photos are from Classic Gaming Expo 1999. I couldn't find a picture of gross little
teenage me in any of the archives, but this is what the show looked like. This happened
to me in my hometown of Las Vegas, and I met a lot of people who shared my interest in
this old stuff and in exploring the deeper back catalog of our past. And, you know, I
discovered things that even went beyond the games I had read about. You know, there was
stuff that only came out in Japan, like Irem's Only Diver. It was a great game.
There's weird unofficial stuff. There's a Christian-themed Zelda clone where you throw fruit
at Satan to murder him. It's amazing. And there's porn on the Nintendo. That's amazing. Like,
what a wacky world that I was suddenly finding myself into. So, you know, I started sort of
wondering where these images come from, and I started thinking about what else was out there
that I was missing. And it was around this time that I...
I remembered a special I'd seen at one point in my life.
I think it must have been on AMC or something
about the movies that we've lost.
According to the Film Foundation,
over half the films made before 1950 are gone,
and about 80% of the ones before 1929.
I don't mean you can't.
buy these on DVD.
I mean, they're gone.
They don't exist anymore.
And that terrified me.
I mean, I wasn't particularly a film buff,
but the idea of these works just disappearing forever
and never being recoverable, that's.
scared the crap out of me. So I started wondering, is anyone
doing this for games? Is anyone making sure that video games
aren't doing the same stupid shit that the film did to make
their heritage disappear? And, I mean, yeah, there were people
doing this. We didn't call them archivists. We didn't call them
digital archaeologists or anything that belongs in a
museum. We called them software pirates is what we called them.
And we still do, it turns out.
But, man, I saw what was going on and I wanted to be one of
those software pirates. I wanted to be in on the ground
floor because I understood at the time, and I still believe
this, that we can't leave preservation up to the content
owners. And the only way to ensure this stuff was safe was
to make sure it was easily accessible to anyone. But I
wanted to be an effective pirate.
I didn't want to do like the little niggling things that
people can do.
I wanted to really strike.
And I started thinking, which games were the most volatile?
Which games were in the most danger of disappearing if no
one did anything about them?
And the conclusion I came up with was games that never
actually shipped to stores.
This is a very small selection.
of the games for the Nintendo entertainment system only.
They never actually shipped.
And, you know, nowadays, yeah, games get canceled
because they're crap, usually, or they're unfinished.
Nintendo era, the NES era, was kind of a weird time
because
Nintendo's policy meant that you could only release five games a year if you were a publisher.
Games were so cheap to make, and they were making so much money,
that they would just throw everything at the wall and just come up with the five best ones, basically.
So a lot of games that didn't ship were actually good games, or at least interesting,
but for one reason or another, they just didn't ship them because they had better things to do.
These games, these would still sometimes exist in playable
form on what collectors would call prototype cartridges.
So these are temporary things that are disposable,
that are made to be used temporarily.
They're actually stored on EPROMs, which are temporary media.
So these cartridges for games like these,
like, you know, that is the only copy in the world
anyone knows of of California Raisins
for the Nintendo, for example.
These are games that there might only be one left of
that's just slowly dying, and that's horrifying.
And it's not like these are just unknown games,
there were weird games like Bio Force Ape
that were discussed in Nintendo Power.
Not that exact same issue, but later on.
So.
So I dedicated myself to this. I started sort of tracking down,
you know, working with collectors to track down these
prototypes, talking to programmers, you know, who might
still have something in their garage. I started a website in
2003 called Lost Levels. And this was, you know, my first
attempt at really preserving video game history. I
recognized at the time
that preservation was more than just a playable binary of a
game. Game preservation to me is also everything surrounding
the game, the people, the stories, the history, the
ephemera. So what I did was in addition to frankly pirating the
video game online for everyone to download, I also, when I
could, which wasn't very often because I wasn't a very good
journalist yet, tracked down the people who actually worked on
them to get the story behind them and find out why they
didn't come out.
And sort of unexpectedly, people took notice of my work.
I was writing articles and so were the other people on my
team, but I started getting work.
I started freelancing for magazines and reviewing games
and stuff.
I suddenly found myself a video game journalist, which
was cool.
In 2005, I took my first job at a website that some of you
may have heard of.
It's called Gamasutra.
If you weren't around back then, yeah, that really was
the color scheme.
I had nothing to do with that.
I took an editorial job here in 2005.
Simon Carless, who's still around,
he's actually running this conference,
took a chance on me, which is really cool.
But, you know, even as I'm doing this journalism stuff,
my primary interest in anything I do related to games
is preserving its history.
So, even at Gamasutra, I sort of took that with me.
I started a column where I would track down
people from the industry's past
who weren't so active anymore and just kind of,
kind of ask them what they've been up to, sort of get their
story, because I felt like if no one did that, if I didn't do
that, no one else is going to.
Like, for example, this is sort of a rare, modern
interview with Mike Berlin, who was a very influential
Infocom game author.
He also created Bubsy the Bobcat, the butt of many
jokes, but Bubsy was OK.
After Gamma Suture, I worked at a company called Game Tap.
We were a Turner broadcasting product.
We were a games on demand subscription service,
which is an idea that's still way ahead of its time.
But again, you know, working there,
a lot of what I did was help make sure
that these older games were still in print,
that they were still around,
like Castlevania, for example.
But like I said, way ahead of its time, didn't last so long,
kind of went under.
So I actually went back to editorial,
I got a job at 1UP.
Again, just bringing that history thing with me,
like wherever I go.
That's what I secretly want to be doing.
And every job I've ever had, it was an excuse
to stay close to preserving history.
That's just the guy.
I am. So even at 1UP, I started doing more oral history reporting. This article is fantastic.
Please look it up. I love it. I had a column at Games TM magazine in the U.K. every month
about game history. I actually went back to Gamma Sutro because they had better colors
now, so they let me back in. And I did articles like this one, just like this gigantic article
trying to figure out when Super Mario Brothers was first sold in the U.S.
don't actually know. I can't substantiate that date. That's
really weird to me. But now I'm making games. So for about the
last three years I've been at a studio on the other side of the
bay called Other Ocean. I work on a game called IDARB. Some of
you might have seen me give a micro post-mortem of this last
year with the lead developer Mike Micah.
I am still the only person to direct an official game
based on the Sharknado film franchise.
Sharknado the video game, which, thank you, Keith,
which you can no longer download on the App Store.
for less than a year. It's not because it was bad, it was a
licensing thing. The last project I worked on just shipped
is called Mega Man Legacy Collection. So again, you're
kind of seeing a trend here, right? Everywhere I go, I try to
veer it toward preserving history. The idea with Mega Man
Legacy Collection was we wanted to create a boutique package
and really preserve these games for future generations in a way
that made sense commercially. We will get back to Mega Man, I
promise, but I want to get to the point of what we're all here
about.
really dirty word, emulation. Evil, evil emulation. I think
emulation has gotten a bad rap over the years.
I think that we all, not all, but I think the industry and
even our consumers have a really basic misconception of
what emulation is.
What emulation is, and I'm simplifying it a bit, emulation
is software that makes a computer act like a different
computer.
That's it.
It's a tool.
And it's a great one for many uses.
Emulation is not illegal.
It's not threatening.
It's not unprofessional.
It's not lazy.
It's not the same thing as software piracy.
It's not free.
But this is the perception that people have.
And when we first started going around to clients
pitching the idea of bringing back some of this NES
back catalog, what we commonly heard from them
is that we couldn't emulate a Nintendo console
without Nintendo's approval.
The implication being that there was something
inherent to the NES that could not legally
be replicated in software.
And that the only place you could legally emulate
an NES game was on a piece of hardware
marketed and sold by Nintendo itself.
But you know what?
No emulator has ever been ruled illegal in a court of law.
That has never happened.
And in fact, they tried, but we'll get there soon.
But still, this persists.
And in fact, Nintendo's legal page right now,
if you go to their website, has this language that I looked.
It's been up there for 16 years.
years now about how the distribution of emulation,
it's going to ruin the industry.
It's like the worst thing that's ever happened.
I'm paraphrasing because I can't look behind myself
without talking to the mic.
But, you know, notice this last question where
how come Nintendo doesn't take a step
toward legitimizing emulators?
That's like asking why Nintendo doesn't legitimize piracy.
It doesn't make any business sense.
except they actually have legitimized emulators by selling you emulators.
The virtual console is nothing but emulations of Nintendo games.
And in fact, if you were to download Super Mario Brothers on the Wii virtual console,
so on the left there is a ROM that I downloaded from a ROM site of Super Mario Brothers.
The same file has been there since... it's got a time stamp on it of like 1996.
On the right is Nintendo's virtual console version of Super Mario Bros.
I want you to pay particular attention to the hex values that I've highlighted here.
That is what's called an Inest header.
An Inest header is a header format developed by amateur software emulators in the late
90s.
What's that doing in a Nintendo product?
I would posit that Nintendo downloaded Super Mario Bros. from the Internet and sold it
back to you.
Like, not only could no one prove that there's anything wrong with emulation,
like Nintendo is pirating its own ROMs and selling it to you.
But let me put this back up on screen for you.
No one has ever ruled emulation illegal. It's never happened.
But regardless of that truth, it was actually cheaper for us to come up with a method
to circumvent what was technically emulation
than it was to hire a lawyer to prove this to our clients.
clients. So that's what we did with Mega Man Legacy Collection.
We came up with a workaround. It works really great. The
result is that we can now run original NES games exactly as
they would run in an emulator, but without actually emulating
the CPU on the user end. It's a lot of extra work for the exact
same goal. It's kind of a waste of time, if you ask me, but it
got us a project. So, okay, when and why did emulation become a
dirty word?
I don't know that there's an easy answer to that,
but I think it all started in January of 1999.
I'm gonna let a young Steve Jobs
at that month's Mac World tell you why.
So we're really, really excited about games,
and again, our goal is to have
the best game machine in the world.
Now, this is another game machine.
It's the most popular game machine in the world.
Wouldn't it be great if we could play
some of those titles too?
Hmm well at Macworld today
Connectix is introducing the virtual game station. It is software
It is software that they're gonna sell for $49 that turns your Mac into a Sony PlayStation it plays
This was huge. The virtual game station was the first emulator to run commercial PlayStation
games at playable speeds. It was also one of the first commercial emulators, as Steve
just said. Thank you, by the way, Steve. They sold it for 50 bucks. And I read a report
that said they made $3 million in revenue selling this emulator. But it's not just
to display PlayStation games. This was the first time in history that you could play
contemporary games that you could buy at Best Buy in full speed on your computer.
And, you know, it only ran real disks. You couldn't do pirated
software on it. But, of course, the hackers got around that
really quickly. And then just a couple weeks later was the first
Nintendo 64 full speed emulator that ran commercial games on a
PC. Came in January 28th, the first and only release of this
emulator. It was compatible with 17 games at the time, including
The Legend of Zelda, Ocarina of Time, a title that had just hit
the American shelves two months prior.
two months prior. You could just download a seven megabyte file,
which even at the crappy speeds we had back then was an
attainable thing. There had been some discussion of stuff like
MAME before this, but this is really when you started seeing
emulation in the headlines. And the impact on the amateur
emulation world is huge. Before this, I think emulators were
primarily seen as tools to relive the days of gaming's
past, sort of a gray market.
piracy tool for niche hobbyists.
Not really something that the industry took notice of,
but all of a sudden people could download console games
that were on the store shelves at that moment
and pirate them for free.
Console piracy has always existed,
but the barrier to entry was high enough
that this was a niche segment of the market
requiring special hardware or modifying your console.
for the first time in history console games were on the same
level as PC games as far as ease of use to pirating. So this is
when you started, this is when that discussion became public.
This is when lawsuits started getting thrown around. In fact,
Sony did take Connectix to court and, well, they lost.
The judge over a year and a half trial or something like that
found that Connectix was not violating any of Sony's
trademarks or patents.
And, you know, it's funny, like, this was not just a Sony versus
Connectix case. Sony was backed by Nintendo and Sega in this
court case. Like, this was the console game industry versus
emulation, the court battle. And emulation won. Sony tried again
with an emulator called BLEEM. I don't know if anyone remembers
BLEEM.
That got thrown out, too.
So the two times that I'm aware of
that an emulator's ever been challenged in court,
it was found to be fine.
So if you were a software publisher
that owned games that were originally published
on vintage Nintendo hardware,
this is the best thing that could have happened to you.
All of a sudden, the doors were open.
You could start republishing your content
wherever you want.
You're no longer locked into Nintendo's ecosystem.
And yet,
This is a list, this isn't entirely scientific, it's just a quick Wikipedia scrape. But these
are third party games available on Nintendo's virtual console right now for the Wii U and the
3DS. These are games not published by Nintendo that you can buy emulated versions of on
Nintendo platforms. There's 156 of them. The next slide is going to highlight which ones of
these you can buy on platforms that aren't owned by Nintendo.
Oh, that's interesting. Huh. Those look familiar. There's
absolutely no reason for this. This is lost revenue. There are
150 classic games here that we know have had all their rights
cleared for redistribution because they're for sale right
now. All of these can be in print everywhere forever for a
pretty low up front investment and emulation is the key to
that.
Emulation is, I'm just going to read the slide, emulation is the cheapest, safest and best way
to republish an older video game on modern hardware. Thank you. There are pros and cons.
It's cheaper and safer than porting. There's no source code required like traditional
porting requires. Emulation for the most part is portable and cross platform. The development
you work that you do to emulate a game is directly applicable to getting other games to
work.
And the games play just as they did back in the day, exactly as
they did. Cons, they play exactly as they did back in the
day. It's very difficult to fix legacy bugs. You can't really go
in and easily change, you know, system limitations that would
require, that would make games flicker and stuff like that.
It's even harder to add new features than it is to fix bugs.
and you can't really easily add new levels
unless you're going in and directly hacking the binary,
which people do, but we don't have time for that.
And potentially, potentially, there's a higher CPU
requirement than a direct port would require,
but for vintage consoles, it doesn't really matter so much.
But yet, we continue porting, and I would argue
that porting, by its nature, will always be
a derivative work, that is not the original work,
that is a remake.
You cannot port a game without sacrificing something that was
in the original. There will be new bugs, there will be
inconsistencies, there will be flaws. And while sometimes the
only valid option, porting a game from source and expecting
100% faithful reproduction of the original is both a pipe
dream and a financial black hole. As nice as extra features
are to have, a ported game is not the original game, it's a
remake. While remakes can be great complementary pieces to
the original work, that original work should also be available.
I reject the notion that a classic video game needs a new coat of paint in order to be valid.
I think, and this might be a controversial opinion here at the Game Developers Conference,
but I think video games are an undeniable part of our history and cultural make-up
and they should be preserved exactly as they were, blemishes and all.
This is a game called DuckTales Remastered. This is a remake of
an NES game called DuckTales, strangely enough. Pretty cool
game. They did a great job redoing the art. They changed a
lot of stuff. This is the original DuckTales. I like this
game even better, but maybe I'm biased. I'm kind of old. The
problem is you can only get the remake of DuckTales.
the original is just gone. It's been out of print since 1989.
But, and you know, like, maybe that's okay. Maybe people
prefer the remake. Maybe we don't need the old one. And
maybe we should throw away the original King Kong because that
Peter Jackson version is way prettier, right? Like, who
needs the old one?
This is a re-release of the first Zelda game from Nintendo.
Nintendo changed the script at the beginning.
And yeah, that's a much better script.
It's much better translated.
That's probably what they originally meant.
And maybe Lucas originally meant for Greedo to shoot first.
Let's just keep that and throw the original away.
Sometimes companies do try to toe the line between a remake
and an original.
This is a screenshot from The Secret of Monkey Island,
whatever it was called, special edition?
Special edition.
And these are remastered graphics. They're new. And this
is the original that's in there. You can switch back and forth
kind of like that, but in a better effect. Whatever you want
in the game. And this is cool. Except that ain't even the
original Monkey Island. The original was a 16-color EGA
version. And that version is unavailable anywhere. That is
the version directed by the game's director, Ron Gilbert,
the only one.
That is the version with the art by Mark Ferrari that was drawn over for that other version.
Like, that's the real Monkey Island and we can't play that.
And, you know, so even when they try, like, you can screw it up.
And again, I don't know, maybe people prefer the additional 240 colors and the CD soundtrack over the MIDI.
And maybe they like Pride and Prejudice better with zombies, so we should just kill the original.
I mean, what's the point of it?
I want to make a point that I don't think I'm just a
particularly nostalgic person who likes old games and that
there's no market for them. I think old games are very
popular right now. Here's that same DuckTales game being played
in 2014 on Awesome Games Done Quick. This is an incredibly
popular event where speed runners play through games.
Tons of people watch them. How much? There's 40,000 people.
A couple years ago, watching someone play the 8-bit version of DuckTales.
And, okay, yeah, 40,000 people are probably always watching that stream, no matter what game's on there, right?
I went to YouTube a couple days ago, I searched for DuckTales NES, and just filtered it over the last week.
There are several new videos over the last week of this one random NES game that I picked.
It was a popular game, but I picked it randomly.
And this is a game that people still want to play.
And the only legal way they can do it
is to go on eBay and do this.
It's to get a vintage NES console that spits out
the 240p signal that most of your damn TVs
don't even support anymore, and to get this collector's item
cartridge.
That's the only legal way to play DuckTales.
And that's weird to me.
But I don't know.
Maybe.
Maybe there's not much of a market for content from 1989
anymore. So let's do a little quick study. This is IMDB's most
popular films of 1989. I didn't even bother scrolling down the
pages, just quick exercise. So I think Batman and Ghostbusters
may be unfair comparisons. Dead Poets Society, pretty good movie
but not really DuckTales. I think the most DuckTales
equivalent here would be Uncle Buck.
Uncle Buck was a John Candy Macaulay Culkin vehicle.
It was actually a pretty good movie, I think.
It's one of those movies where I think I've seen it,
but I'm not sure.
I have positive feelings about it for some reason.
So, as you might imagine, at the time it was released,
you know, whatever formats made sense at the time.
There was VHS, there was Betamax in the middle,
there's a LaserDisc version.
So did Uncle Buck make the transition
to the future formats?
Oh yeah, there's a widescreen DVD,
there's...
probably a full screen DVD for people who are stupid and don't
like the black lines. They even reprinted it with slightly
different packaging. You can get it with Brewster's millions.
You can get it with Brewster's millions and also stripes. You
can get it with whatever the great outdoors is. You can get
it with the great outdoors and also whatever that is going
berserk.
You can get it in a classic comedy pack for cheap. You can
get it on Blu-ray. If you're a true Uncle Buck connoisseur, you
can get it in 1080P on Blu-ray or on Blu-ray with a digital
copy. There's a variant there, too. You can get it with Fletch
on Blu-ray. And it's more than just physical. You can get it
digitally however you want. You go on Amazon right now, you can
get it. You can get it on iTunes. You can get it on Google
Play. Get Uncle Buck on whatever Cinema Now is. But you shouldn't
get it on Amazon because it's $14, which is more than the
other ones.
Voodoo. You can go on YouTube and just watch Uncle Buck. You
just pay YouTube some money and watch Uncle Buck right now. Go
on Flixster where it's even more expensive. You can buy it from
Microsoft and Sony on their video game consoles and watch
it. And yet you can't buy DuckTales. And there is, it
turns out, a new HD version of Uncle Buck, but they didn't go
and get rid of the old one. They kept the other one in print
because it's still valid.
But okay, maybe DuckTales is an anomaly.
Let's look at 1989 in video games on Wikipedia.
This is their list of what they consider notable games,
the editors of Wikipedia.
I would argue for several more than this,
but you know, this is fine.
This is a good starting point.
It's just a quick exercise.
Great stuff on here, right?
There's 16 of them.
So those are all of them.
How many can you buy right now?
Think about five of them.
That's a respectable, what, like 30% or something?
How many of these can you buy in more than one place?
Oh, that's interesting.
Theme just keeps coming up.
OK, but how does that actually compare to film?
All right, here are the top grossing films of 89.
We don't know the top grossing games of 89, because our
industry is shit at tracking sales.
Sorry if you're young.
But these are the top 10 grossing films of 89.
period. How many of those can you get right now? Oh, you can
get all of them right now. But how many of them can you get
cross device, cross platform? Oh, you can get all of them,
cross device, cross platform. Every one of these, you can rent
an SD, you can rent an HD, you can buy an SD, you can buy an
HD, with the exception of Little Mermaid, you can't rent Little
Mermaid. All of them are on Blu-ray except for Look Who's
Talking. I'm sorry if you're a huge fan of Look Who's Talking.
But, like, these movies have always been in print, and games could have been the same way,
except that we demonized emulation, and by demonizing emulation instead of embracing it,
we've devalued our heritage. Emulated classic console games are now presumed free. By not
embracing it as a tool, we've relegated the majority of our past to piracy, and that's sad.
Not because I weep for the lost revenues of corporations, but
because this has had a direct impact on keeping our very
history alive, on maintaining the franchises that we love, on
supporting the creators that made them, and all of this
could have been prevented if we'd embraced it instead of
fighting it, but we messed up. This is not to say there's no
such thing as commercial emulation. There are releases.
I just pulled a couple examples here. This is on the Humble
Store.
SNK recently started selling emulated versions of its classic
games for the Neo Geo console. These run in a browser. They run
wonderfully. The emulation is great. They're $8 a pop. Totally
bare bones, though. There's no online or anything. I don't even
think you can reconfigure your buttons. But the games work only
in your browser. So you're sort of limited to what you can do.
but there's stuff on consoles too. There's the arcade archive
series from hamster. These are wonderfully emulated as well.
Exclusively on the PS4. They do one of these a month. They're
also $8 each. And these are just two examples. There's others I
could name. There's project egg in Japan does MSX stuff.
There's the occasional semi-random emulated games on
mobile marketplaces. Someone tried to sell Bubsy on Steam for
some reason. And of course there's Nintendo's virtual
console. But I don't think these work to keep the games alive
because these piecemeal releases are very limited. They're
usually on a single platform. The selection is just bizarrely
random because it's just the stuff people happen to be able
to clear the rights up for easily. They don't tend to add
any value. And in the end...
they're selling you a ROM for $8 and there's a certain audience of people, emulation savvy
people, who have this stuff for free and are playing it in a superior experience with stuff
like MAME. And I think that we've sort of considered these people a lost cause. Like,
oh, those are the pirates. They would never buy the games. But I challenge that notion.
people who love old games enough to go out of their way to make them play, that is, that
should be our target audience. That should be exactly who we're selling to. These are
my people, and if I can sell to them, I can sell to anyone.
So at Digital Eclipse, we have a specific approach. We make
boutique packages for fans and collectors. Our approach is to
sell them with as much source material as is possible to sort
of stick in the package. Create a package with a lot of added
value, stuff it with as much as we can, sell it on every
platform that makes sense. As I said when I relaunched, when I
helped to relaunch Digital Eclipse last year, because it's
actually an old brand that we just brought back, we're
We feel that classic video games deserve the equivalent of the Criterion Collection, a curated selection of important pieces of history restored to their original condition, packed with bonuses to help contextualize and celebrate that work.
For certain games, I think this kind of package has significantly more sales potential than simply selling a playable ROM.
So we were fortunate enough to find a partner in Capcom for
Mega Man Legacy Collection, which was our first attempt at
this. Legacy Collection collects the original six Mega Man games
for the NES. We wanted to create a package that would provide
value for anyone interested in these games, even if they
already owned them or emulated them or whatever. We wanted to
create a collector's edition that fans would want to keep on
their shelves, you know, even if it wasn't physical, just
mentally shit in their shelves, I guess.
include anything we need our hands on.
I want to quickly show off some of the features
that we added to this effect.
This is not a sales pitch.
I just want to show this stuff off because it's cool.
So this is the museum that's in the game.
Fortunately, Capcom kept a lot of the original art, so there's a lot of promotional work.
These are from a marketing guide. This is concept art.
Look how cool this is. You can zoom in on these things.
There's something like 800 pieces in the package, which is awesome.
This is a screenshot from a prior re-release
of the Mega Man games. This is the complete works for the PlayStation 1. It was only ever in Japan.
This is a cool feature that Capcom did back then, back in 99
or whatever it is. It's called the Database.
This collected every character in all the games, showed you their stats, what they were weak
against and gave you a description which provided back story. Which is really cool because this
back story to these characters was never reprinted anywhere else in any other language other
than Japanese. So we ported that over and we made that HD.
And we helped translate it into six, I think, languages.
But we also added another feature while we were at it,
which was, because we could,
you could just go ahead and practice fighting one of the characters from the database,
which I think is a really fun thing.
Mega Man, of course, known for its soundtracks,
so we wouldn't be doing our jobs if there wasn't a soundtrack player.
My only regret is not calling it Sound Test, which was what they called it.
And this is what we call the challenge mode.
We wanted to give people a new way of playing the game.
So this is the section from Cut Man's level in Mega Man 1.
That portal right there, that's not in the original game.
We added that in.
When you enter one, you actually get thrown
into a different section of a different stage.
The idea here was it's a time attack speed run mode
that makes you think about the games in a different way.
But more than that, I'm gonna switch
to a different challenge.
This is a challenge against the Mecha Dragon boss
from Mega Man 2.
So, it's a time attack, and at the end, after I win here, thank you very much, that was
me, 28 seconds, it's not terrible, you get a result, you get a badge, you get to save
your replay, but more than that, there's a leaderboard, so you can go and instantly watch
how the fastest person in the world killed MechaDragon, which, I probably should have
recorded the whole thing, but I cut it off, I'm sorry.
But more than that, getting back to the criterion thing,
artistic intent was important to us.
So we actually created modes that simulated the CRT
televisions of the time.
It looks better in 1080p.
The 720p squashing kind of messes with it.
But there was a TV mode.
This is sort of the best of both worlds.
We call it monitor mode.
that retains the scan line skipping in the aperture grill
but none of the fake noise of the composite mode.
The reason we did that stuff is because we feel that
there's no way of really knowing
what the artistic intent was of those sprites.
I think even if you rounded up
all the original Mega Man artists and asked them,
they wouldn't be able to definitively answer like,
Oh, yeah, we assumed there would be some TV noise, so we drew the sprites that way.
So we tried to make all those options available, because I don't think there's any way of really
nailing like this is what these games are supposed to be like, so we left that option
open.
That's really important to me, and if you guys are doing emulation packages yourself,
please do that.
So these features add a lot of value, but more importantly,
they did not add a significant cost to the development
budget.
Our intent was to show that you can have the perceived value
of an HD remake without having to invest in the extreme
expenditure that those require.
Because all of our code was written in-house and our code
base is cross-platform, we were able to put this entire
package together with a core team of just about three
developers, give or take, in about eight months.
And we also ported it to the 3DS and that was its own product.
But again, small team, very lean.
We got it out and it works.
And the result was that the fan outcry was so significant
that they made a physical version
that they hadn't planned on.
People want this stuff.
This works for Mega Man.
I don't think this works for Ninja Kid,
which was the example we gave earlier
from the arcade archives.
You know, I would buy the heck out of a Ninja Zajamaru Legacy Collection.
I would.
You know, the games are really neat, but I think I'm a very small audience.
So I don't think you can really justify this treatment for every game.
I think it has to be a franchise that people already know and love.
But I don't...
I think there's another way.
Here's how to keep every game in print on every platform without
spending a ton of money basically forever. We're going
to circle back to Uncle Buck for a minute. Hi, Uncle Buck.
So how is it that Uncle Buck has remained in print across all
these different platforms?
Is Uncle Buck just worth more money than the NES version of
DuckTales?
Maybe.
Maybe it's got a better audience.
But I think it's a lot simpler than that.
Uncle Buck remained in print because video has format
standards that are very inexpensive to quote, unquote
port to.
I think the biggest upfront expense in keeping a movie in
print is, sorry.
My computer is not happy right now.
But I think the biggest expense in keeping a movie in
print is the upfront cost of digitally scanning it.
Every film has to be scanned, digitized, and cleaned up.
But it's not really that expensive.
But the thing is, once you have a scan of a movie, you
have a master file that is very, very easily
portable to any format.
You'd probably send a raw file to Amazon, and they just push
a button and encode it and push it live, and that's it.
So you have this method of getting it really direct.
copy of the movie that's more or less pristine and you have ways
of deploying it very easily. And you know it's real sad that we
can't do that for games, right? We have no notion of scanning a
game. We have no notion of codex for games, right?
No, of course we do.
Video games are just binary files.
You can make a perfect copy of a game easily.
It's actually in a better state than film.
And guess what?
You often don't even have to do the work of digitizing those games
because the pirates have done it for you.
So just go on the Internet and take it if you want to.
I posit that an emulator is just a video codec for playing video games,
and we've got to start thinking about it that way.
Or, if you prefer, I think a video codec is nothing but a filmstrip emulator.
And this is the mindset that I think this industry needs to be in, in order to push, you know, our back catalog back in print and make me happy.
So, you know, every time we release an old game, we sort of reinvent the wheel.
And we port it or we build an emulator from scratch, and just all this wasted effort for no reason, with one exception.
All right. So here's an interesting selection of games.
Does anyone know what the common thread here is between these
games? Yes.
They are not just all PC games.
They all run on MS-DOS, which was Microsoft's pre-Windows standard.
These are games you can buy digitally right now.
There's a large number of companies represented here.
There's Apogee, Activision, Bethesda, Electronic Arts, LucasArts, which is Disney now.
It's still weird to think that.
But in addition to all being run, you know, native DOS games,
they have another thing in common. They're all using the
same emulator. This is called DOSBox. Does anyone know DOSBox?
Yeah, DOSBox is sort of the premier DOS emulator. It can
run DOS games of a certain vintage at full speed on just
about any modern computer. It's a great piece of tech, but more
importantly, it's open source. It's distributed under a GPL2
license. What does that mean?
you may ask as my computer loads it. Well, GPL2 license means
there you go, look at the green. Open for commercial use. It
gets a little bit complicated, some moving parts of it, but
essentially you can sell a DOS game with DOS box.
And all you really have to do is include DOS box in the package.
And that's what everybody does because it's easy and it's free.
And you know, these games are now in print again because there
is an open solution for everyone to use. I looked at GOG.com and
my rough count is they're selling about 140 DOS games
right now. And you know, a lot of the classic catalog that
people remember and want is represented already. And when
it's not, you know, people figure it out.
and they get it up there. They've done a great job of keeping these games in print.
Now, if only there was a DOS box for everything else, right?
Some news happened a couple weeks ago. Some of you might have missed it. Some of you might have not.
MAME just went open source on March 4th of this year.
MAME, as you may or may not know, is the standard for arcade board emulation. It emulates
thousands of them. I mean, I don't even know what the count is anymore. And it's been around
since 97. And if you read the text, it is now being distributed under that exact same
GPL-2 license. We are now in a situation where we can use MAME for commercial releases, and
that's not all. In May of last year, MAME absorbed its sister project, MESS.
What MAME was for arcade games, MESS was for everything else.
This is a list that's going to load any second here, I promise,
of drivers that are in MESS right now.
MESS is basically like every console and computer ever.
Look, there's 2,176 of them.
Like, between MAME and MESS.
Basically everything is covered in some form.
Now, I'm not saying MAME and MESS are perfect.
There's a lot of inconsistencies.
The emulation usually isn't the top notch for consoles
in their MESS slash MAME equivalent,
but it's open source.
It's code base is out there, it can be contributed to.
you know, just about any game can be run through MAME.
And, you know, if you think about this,
it's basically a video codec for video games.
We're already kind of there.
We've already begun the process internally
of porting MAME to our own tech.
I don't know if, you know, we have no commercial products
that we're using it in right now,
but I wouldn't be surprised if that happens.
And I would be shocked and frankly a bit offended if we're
the only ones that are smart enough to do this. But, you
know, we're just, we're a studio. I can imagine someone
like an Amazon forking MAME, bringing it in-house, bringing
it up to snuff and bringing games back to the level of,
well, Uncle Buck. Where, you know, I can envision a future
where we respect DuckTales for the NES as much as we respect
this John Candy classic.
I want to thank you all very much for coming to my talk. It's about all I've got. A couple
reminders. You will get an e-mail to evaluate me as a speaker. Please rate me as you see
appropriate. Please, these are your takeaways. There is an audience for old games. How to
print games are lost revenue. Emulation is cheap and accurate. Embrace the emulator. And I
will now open it up for questions.
If we've got no questions, are we done here?
Oh, I think the microphone in the middle is where you want to go.
Yes, John Paul Dyson of the Strong Museum of Play in Rochester, New York.
How can I help you?
Thanks.
So what do you think about commercial versus, say, what the Internet Archive is doing with jazz music?
Oh, yeah, yeah. This is a great point.
So a lot of these games are...
absolutely easily playable in your browser right now. They are kept in print unofficially,
but the point I'm trying to make is that commercial emulation has its value, too. I think that
especially for products like we make.
where the idea is to gather the ephemera and the materials
and really make a collector's edition
and really preserve the game properly
beyond a playable binary, I think you need money.
I think money needs to be invested in that.
And I think that commercial emulation can coexist
with the quote-unquote unofficial emulation.
But thank you for bringing that up.
Again, the pirates have it covered.
I was a pirate myself.
I kind of still am.
I don't mean to imply that commercial emulation can somehow
be better than amateur.
I don't think that will ever happen.
Yes, Kyle.
Hey, Frank.
Hi.
The legal cases you cited are from 15 or 16 years ago, I think?
Yeah.
If they did it again for, like, the NES emulators inside MESS.
Do you think Nintendo's going to have a problem with it?
Maybe they'd be able to prevail this time
if they took it to court?
No, I don't think there's anything that you can show for,
I mean, using the NES as an example,
I don't think there's anything in there that you can show
that violates any of Nintendo's patents or trademarks.
And in fact, something about that case is that that case was
able to prove the legality of reverse engineering a BIOS chip
for the sake of emulation.
That was established in that case.
That's on paper.
I don't see a problem in any way.
The only problem I can see is if an emulator distributes the
unaltered BIOS from a console, because that is code that they
don't have the rights to.
emulating a platform and not using any code that is proprietary, I don't see how that can be
challenged legally. I think it would have been done by now.
I was one of the original developers of MAME, so I really appreciate this talk.
I really appreciate the work you're doing.
I appreciate the work you're doing.
I assure you that all the developers of MAME, they were the first to run on buy
in any kind of officially licensed collection.
So we started things like StarROMs, you know, came and went.
Yeah.
But I was curious, you mentioned that the Capcom collection for MegaMan
wasn't actually an emulator, but it was very faithful.
What, yeah, you're still like, well, how did you do it?
Oh, how did we do it? Okay.
So like I said, we sort of found a work around
that wasn't technically emulation,
but had the exact same result.
And basically what we did was,
internally we were emulating the game,
but we statically recompiled it into C,
so that we weren't shipping any emulation code.
We were just doing the exact same things
an emulator would without actually emulating it,
and everyone seemed satisfied by that.
So that's what we did. It's silly. It's really silly. But I
will say that that did give us some unexpected advantages when
we were making that challenge.
It allows you to make modifications.
Yeah. So like, you know, it became a little bit easier to
modify the game and we could do things like draw a portal in
game space and have it scroll because we know exactly where to
interrupt in the code because we can look at it.
Thanks.
Hello.
Hi.
So in the spirit of preserving history,
do you think that it's still true
that the most at-risk pieces of history
are the ones that never made it to shelves,
like you mentioned earlier?
Or are there new targets in 2016 where you're thinking, wow,
we're at risk of losing this stuff?
You trying to get me to talk about PT?
I don't know anything about it.
I'm just curious.
Can everyone hear the questions in the mics, by the way?
I'm supposed to repeat them.
So that example I made, I was thinking specifically
of the NES, or maybe a little more broadly,
of console video games, of that vintage.
I still believe, absolutely, those are the ones most in
danger of disappearing.
But in terms of the broader scope of game preservation,
what do I think is in the most danger?
I don't think we've really solved the philosophical debate
of how do you preserve an online experience.
And that is something way beyond my scope.
I would refer you to Henry Lowood at Stanford for their
efforts on that.
Another example I like to give is, it's not just MMOs when I
say that, it's like Farmville, right?
Like, even if you hate Farmville, is Farmville preserved?
Can we play the first version of Farmville anymore?
Or does Zynga even have that, right?
So, you know, I think there's bigger problems to solve.
And I think those debates become more philosophical
than technical, because at that point,
you're just kind of questioning,
what does it mean to save a game?
So for online stuff, maybe it's just a whole lot of video
footage. Maybe we start. JP over there had a great quote in an
interview once where he thought of it more like preserving
baseball history where it's not, you know, you don't preserve
like all the players in the stadium and everything, but you
preserve everything that happened. And I think for
impermanent games, I think we should think about it more than
that way.
Cool. Thanks.
Yeah. Thank you.
Hi, Frank. Given the challenges you faced with static
recompilation versus actual emulation and the skittishness
of the companies that you were talking to prior, how would I as
somebody who wants to get in on something like this using
emulation convince, say, a Capcom or a Konami or a Square
Enix to do something like this via emulation?
This talk will be on GDC Vault in 30 days.
We can start there.
But, I mean, you're asking me to solve for you the problem
that I myself have not solved yet.
So I really don't know how to answer that for you,
unfortunately.
But I think bringing this discussion public, and then
shaking people and saying, look, emulation is good.
Emulation is good for you.
It's not piracy.
It's a tool.
It's the best tool.
I think really making that stuff public and bringing
that to light, I think, is the first step toward that.
And.
you know, hopefully my company will help further that. So
that's what I would say to you. And on a slightly different
note, Super Star Wars is now available on PlayStation 4. It
is, it's true. That was done by Code Mystics, in fact, and I
have not played it, but I understand that it's a really
good emulation of it. So I believe, yes, that we have, we
now have Super Nintendo emulation on another platform,
which is real good news for everybody. Thank you.
Heather, regarding the context of what you put in a preservation, sort of a pack like
Mega Man Legacy Collection, what pieces of information did you wish you were able to
get or like what questions did you have that you wanted in the collection and what would
you want answered in future collections that you might not be able to get?
So our goal was to contextualize the games,
because I feel that that's important to preserving them
in the way that I think of preservation.
And what I think was missing from Mega Man
was developer insight.
And there were several challenges
in getting developer insight for these particular games
that I really can't get into.
But I do feel that that piece was missing.
So we had this concept, again, of what would a Blu-ray
collector's box set of Mega Man be like?
And I think all of those games would have
director's commentary.
And unfortunately, we were not able to put that in.
But in the future, yes, absolutely.
I think that's an important piece to put in there.
That said, I also think that it's more than just the making
of the game.
I think it's also the selling of the game that's a
compelling part of the story.
I would love to do many documentaries that maybe dig up
old news footage and stuff like that or photos of people
playing the games back in the day. I think there's a lot more
ephemera that we don't really think about when we think about
containing a game in a package.
I should say also other development materials other than
art, too, like design documents, things like that.
Like anything that's still around.
You know, I often think about when I talk about preserving
these other ephemeral pieces of video game history,
I always think about the Blu-rays I have for classic movies
like Casablanca and Citizen Kane where you listen to the,
that's not director's commentary,
the historian commentary, right?
And they're like citing studio notes.
that went back and forth that still exist
that are in an archive that they can access.
And I don't think we have an equivalent of that
in the video game industry, other than,
you know, we're starting to.
I'm gonna mention J.P. Dyson over there
at the Strong Museum again.
You know, there are certain organizations like his
that are starting to collect the paperwork
and the ephemera around games to make sure
that stuff is accessible to researchers.
So, you know, I think that's an important part
that I would love to start including in future collections.
First of all, this was a very good talk. Thank you for doing
it. Secondly, my question is concerning price point. So
recently my little company was part of an effort to release
what most would consider an older game on Steam. And this
was a PC game and whatnot. And it was priced at around $30.
And there was a decently significant amount of pushback
against this.
Against the price point.
Against the price point, yes.
And so I'm wondering, what do you
think would be a good price point for like anything?
I'm not answering that.
Or maybe, did you get any pushback on the price point for
the legacy collection?
Well, we didn't set that.
So this is entirely a work for hire situation.
So we pitched the project to Capcom.
We got them on board with it.
But ultimately, it's their product.
We just made it for them.
So all that price point stuff was way out of my hands.
I think it should have been more.
frankly, like if you want my personal opinion.
But that is because of the presentation of it,
and I think giving it that higher price point
gives it that more of a boutique feel.
But that said, I suspect that $30 is a high price point
for an individual older game,
which is why I'm suggesting these two alternatives, right?
Which is either actually make a big deal out of it, right?
Like make a really boutique collectors thing.
or get us to the point where getting these games running
is just such a cheap thing that we can do the Spotify
of video games or something, right?
Like I think both of those are effective solutions.
And man, I meant to talk about Napster in this talk
and I forgot.
And one little comment about piracy.
Yeah, so my first project was a quote-unquote dojin title
that a lot of us were afraid wouldn't even sell 10,000 copies
because, hey, you know, it's Japanese independent games.
They get pirated.
Uh, to hell and back.
Five years and 450,000 copies later, I've gotten hundreds of
e-mails about people who pirated the game, pirated our release
of the game, were impressed by it, and then bought the game
because they liked it.
Absolutely.
Yes.
And I'm sorry to interrupt.
Pirates will be customers.
Yeah, absolutely.
Thank you.
Thank you for pointing that out. And in addition to that, I think this industry has all but
ignored the concept of a secondary market for its games. I think we just release a game
and those are the sales we get and then we walk away with our tails between our legs.
Whereas every other industry repackages its content because it's easy to do so.
So, yeah.
Okay. Thank you.
Thank you.
a lot of good questions. I guess I just wanted to ask a point of
clarification. So it was really interesting to see you mention
that INEZ header on super mario.
I think I heard you talking about it on Twitter a while ago.
When did you first find that?
Oh, I did not discover that myself.
That was discovered on, god, which forum?
I think it was the Nest dev forums is where that was first discovered.
But I did validate it myself as of last night.
Which Super Mario that's available from Nintendo?
Wii Virtual Console is the one I looked at.
Wii Virtual Console, interesting.
A lot of other questions that were already asked.
And to be fair, there's no guarantee
that they downloaded the ROM, but I
don't see any alternative for there
being an INS header in a Nintendo product.
I'm sad this has to be the last question, I guess.
There might be one more.
Okay, cool, cool.
If you hurry up, come on, come on, come on.
Okay, so basically my question is, so obviously you're doing a lot of technical workarounds
to get past the issues regarding certain copyrights with regards to BIOS and such.
At what point do you think it becomes necessary for game developers and sort of the entertainment
software?
like consumers to get together to try to lobby for changes with regards to copyright law
a la Lawrence Lessig.
I don't think we're strong enough to do that.
I really don't. I don't think that the video game industry as a, you know, I don't think games are
old enough that we're going to be able to do that for quite a while. And, you know, but I would
also agree with Jason Scott, who was like last year's video game history talk guy, that who cares.
Like, that stuff's on the internet archive, it's not in your hands, just go play it.
But I don't think, like, I think the commercial sales of older games, you know, has appeal
and I think it's a positive and we should do as much of it as we can, but I don't
think that, and this is just a personal opinion, not the
opinion of my employer, blah, blah, blah. I don't think that
that is the only way to save a game. I think the games are more
or less saved. My concern with commercializing them is that I
want them to stay alive in the public consciousness.
Thank you. Probably last question. No more? No more. No
more questions. But I will be, where's the room, the, like,
after room that we can talk in?
It's like down the hall that way or something. There's a room
they set aside. I'm going to walk toward it right now. If you
guys have any further questions, I'm happy to talk to you or if
you just want to say hi. I had to talk then, too. Thank you
very much for not going to the Ms. Pac-Man talk and instead
coming here. I really appreciate that.