Hello and welcome to this session, Crush the Norm Diversity Rules.
It's a session about diversity and inclusion in games.
First of all, I hope you can turn off your mobile phones so we don't get disturbed.
We are from King in Stockholm, Sweden.
My name is Kiki Olofsson and I am Senior Studio Art Director for Candy Crush.
And I'm Kris Adolfsson and I'm a Brand Creative Studio Art Director.
Let's start with a quick check in.
What's your relation to this topic, diversity and inclusion?
I want you to show with your fingers one to five,
and the scale is one, I haven't really thought about it,
to five, I'm already very interested
and have some knowledge.
So put your hands up now.
Ah, good.
We have a mixed audience and it will be easy
for all of you to follow because the presentation
is on a basic level.
Okay, why do we have this session?
King is a company known for casual games with candies and cute characters.
Even so, we've had our challenges when it comes to diversity and inclusion.
We decided to do something about it, to educate and enlighten people
so they can reflect and make informed decisions
when creating or using game characters. We've been running this workshop at King
for a while, leading to games teams opening up their
eyes for the subject. More concretely...
creating less stereotypical characters,
like stronger female characters,
and broadening ethnic diversity.
In this presentation, we'll look at examples
from popular culture, both positive ones and pitfalls.
We'll also get personal and look at mistakes
that King has made in the past.
We'll develop a test, which is used to test
how diverse a game is, and you will get to try it out later.
That's the.
the screens on the walls.
So what do we want to achieve with this session?
The goal is to empower you to make important decisions.
And it's not about setting limitations.
It's about creating new possibilities.
And most important of all, this gives you the opportunity
to be leaders and not followers.
And if everyone in this room starts thinking about this
today, imagine what we can achieve together
in less than a year.
Let's design games for everyone.
no matter where they are or who they are.
If you want a diverse player base from all over the world,
you will need to think big and crush the norm,
because everything we do adds to the world we live in
and the world we play in.
So why replicate when we can work against stereotypes?
A great saga needs all kinds of heroes, and that's it.
So what is diversity?
It can apply to many different areas,
like age, body type.
culture, disability, ethnicity, gender identity, sexual orientation,
socio-economic background or class if you will, mental health and religion.
And diversity is closely connected to equality, feminism, anti-racism, accessibility,
intersectional analysis and human rights. All good things, aren't they?
And if we want a greater diversity, inclusion is the way to go.
An exclusion is the opposite to inclusion.
And if you take it to the extreme, exclusion is discrimination,
as some groups that don't fall within the norm are repeatedly rejected.
And that's how the norm is maintained and reinforced time and time again.
And the yellow and the green dots on the outside of the big circle represents those who are excluded.
And let's take a look at inclusion instead.
Hold on, because this is an advanced PowerPoint animation.
I made it myself.
So, see what happened there.
The circle was expanded to get a better mix,
room for more variation and to be more inclusive.
And of course, inclusion doesn't mean
that just everyone needs to be represented at all time.
especially not in a game with just a few characters.
It's more about having a greater variety and a more true representation.
We get more types of characters that our players can identify with and get to know.
And in the end, that's just more fun.
Where do we begin?
Our output reaches millions of players of all sorts, and we have a unique chance
to make a difference by showing a diverse world in our games.
So...
To do so, we need to make conscious decisions.
So let's explore a character universe
with a wide range of options.
And before continuing, I want to make clear
that the pictures we will show,
it's chosen because they are understandable examples.
It doesn't mean that all characters in that game or film
are good or bad from a diverse perspective.
You need to investigate your own assumptions and presets,
who you are and how that affects the work you do.
It doesn't necessarily need to be your own culture that affects what you do.
It's also about the mainstream culture that we're constantly fed with.
For instance, do you use a white man as a foundation when you create a new character?
And do all women have the same body type, slim and curvy?
And yes, let's investigate.
Have you by any chance only created characters of the same cultural background as you?
So remember to always question all stereotypes.
Ethnicity, this is an interesting and embarrassing example
because this is actually from a King game
called African Rainmaker, released six years ago.
And it's a typical example of an African stereotype.
And does the personality and looks
go beyond ethnicity cliches?
No, they don't.
And that's what we call typecast.
And don't worry because we've taken this game down.
Age.
Some people might think that you can solve the age spread by adding an old evil witch.
Well, it doesn't really work like that.
And when it comes to gender, a female character needs more personality than just being a woman.
If you strip back the gender traits and looks, is there anything left more than a blank canvas?
If not, you need to go back to the drawing board, and the Smurfs really should.
disability, an evil pirate with a wooden leg.
We've seen that before, haven't we?
Think bigger, because people with disabilities
can be heroes too.
And when it comes to sexuality and romantic motivation,
Mario saves the princess over and over again,
but maybe we don't have to limit us to that.
What if a girl can save a girl or a boy can save a boy?
There are so many things to build an original character with,
so let's explore the toolbox.
No one ever successfully fought a war in a bikini,
and really, clothing that calls attention
and sexualize the female body
is not necessary for most narratives.
On the other hand, have you dressed all male characters
in all covering cool and tacky wear,
functional clothes, and heavy armor?
Don't get stuck in old rats, you have to mix it up.
A good rule of thumb is to compare
the clothing between genders
to unlock stereotypical representations.
This is a positive example from Assassin's Creed Syndicate.
The male and female twin assassins
have same kind of clothes, armor, and weapons.
Are all males dark and brooding
and all females happy and colorful?
Sure, you can use blue for boys and pink for girls,
but there are endless possibilities
for color schemes that can be used.
And if you go for a cliche,
you could at least play around with it.
This is a great example from the film Inside Out.
And look beyond the usual suspects.
Fat doesn't mean lazy,
and smart doesn't need to wear glasses,
and someone that looks like Prince Charming
isn't always the good guy.
This is Faith, a plus-size superhero we all can admire
because she has tremendous psychic powers.
A diverse game world includes short, tall, chubby, skinny,
curvy, athletic, disabled or non-disabled,
and characters of different ethnicity.
Professor Xavier from X-Men is using a wheelchair,
but this has never held him back.
He's one of the most powerful mutants in the world.
And watch out for those archetypes.
They're great at telling stories,
but they might take you down a beaten path,
something that the player has already seen before.
The healer doesn't always have to be an older woman.
The hero can be someone else than a white male,
and the savage can be European.
And remember the supportive characters in the background.
I don't know if you have seen Game of Thrones.
I don't want to spoil anything, but they really have an interesting and often very surprising
mix of characters.
There are some principles to guide you.
Decide the character personality traits and narrative first.
Which story do you want to tell and with which characters?
After this, you can decide the gender, ethnicity, body type, and culture.
And always aim to let the body, look and poses of the character reflect the personality and narrative.
Aim for a well-balanced group of characters.
And last but not least, always ask yourself, did I recreate the stereotype and if so, why?
And remember, with an original character, it's easier to create a strong and recognizable brand.
So we've developed a test to see how inclusive and diverse a game is, and it's called Diversity Space.
And this is how the test looks like. Exciting, hey?
So you start by identifying the norm, and here we use the norm for action games developed in the Western world.
The same norms are almost always applicable for productions aimed for the Western market.
So the culture is Western, ethnicity is Caucasian, age is like neither young or old,
women are usually younger than men.
Ability is non-disabled, sexual orientation is heterosexual,
and body type is stereotypical,
and that is slim and curvy for women,
and athletic or body-builder types for men.
And gender identity, male is the norm,
women come second, and all others are very, very uncommon.
So the norm is the green area here,
so that's a really, really tiny diversity space.
And now we're going to test some characters
from the game Overwatch from Blizzard.
And this is Sarja, she is an unusual character.
Her design actually emerged from a demand
from players to Blizzard for a greater diversity
of gender, body type, and ethnicity.
And let's take a look at her diversity space.
Culture, she is Russian, so that's not very common.
Ethnicity, she's Caucasian, so she's on the norm.
Age, she's 28, so neither young or old.
Nobility, she is non-disabled, so she's on the norm there.
Sexuality, you can't see this on the outside,
and there is no information on this,
but she does have some queer vibes,
and there's been some rumors in the community,
but we need to put her on the norm.
And body type, she is a bodybuilder,
and all those muscles are unusual for female characters,
so let's put that quite a bit from the norm.
And gender, she is a woman,
so she is in the middle of the gender scale.
All in all, she's got quite big diversity break.
diversity space, breaking the norm with gender, culture, and body type.
And this is Lucio.
Starting up with culture, he is a DJ living in Brazil, so he is a little bit out from
the norm.
Ethnicity, he is black, so I'll put this quite far out.
It's not that common.
And it's not the scale from white to black.
But Caucasian people are most common, and Asians are more common than, let's say, Indians.
Age, he's 26, so that doesn't stand out from the norm.
Ability, he is non-disabled, so he's on the norm.
Sexual orientation, don't know anything about that,
so I'll keep him on the norm.
And body type, he is athletic, and that's expected of men.
And gender identity, he is a man, which is the most common.
So looking at the diversity space,
he has got a sharp point towards ethnicity,
and a little stretch in culture,
but he doesn't stand out from the norm much
in any other ways.
And then we've got Torbjörn.
He is a Swedish weapon designer.
That's not super common, but it doesn't stand out from a culture point of view, so I'll put him close to the norm.
And he's white, so nothing on ethnicity.
He is 57, so he is older than the most.
He is disabled and has got a prosthetic arm, so we'll put this quite far out on the ability scale.
We don't know anything about his sexuality, so I keep it close to the norm.
And body type, he is a person with short stature.
So that's a bit out from the norm.
However, it's not that uncommon with a body type like that
together with a lot of muscles in games.
And he is a man, which is most common.
Looking at the diversity space,
he does stand out a bit from the norm.
This is when it gets interesting,
because by combining the characters in the diversity space,
you get an overall picture of your game's inclusion level.
So for this being only three characters,
we got quite a good spread in the diversity space.
So good job, Blizzard.
And remember that the whole diversity space
doesn't need to be covered.
Just avoid having all characters huddle up in the middle.
And do you think this could be a useful tool?
Hands up if you do.
That's super, because you're going to test this out soon.
But first, over to Kiki.
And remember, even if you have developed characters
with a big diversity space, you can still have stereotypes.
Would you say that these characters
are stereotypes in any ways?
Hands up if yes.
So, let's take a look at some pitfalls
to keep you on the right track.
The angry and brutish black man is one of the most common stereotypes in games.
Let's do something more original.
And the representation of women in games are often embarrassingly uniform.
These are the female characters from Tekken 6.
All of them have very stereotypical body types and clothing that emphasize that.
And we are doing something similar in our King games.
This is from Shuffle Cats.
All those Jazza cats looks awesome.
But don't they look a little similar?
So let's compare them with the Tomcats.
And the Tomcats are allowed to have
a lot of different body types, expressions, et cetera,
which is usually the case with male characters.
So let's compare again.
It's quite obvious, isn't it?
And we have whiteness, that's clearly a default
in a lot of games, the Witcher is one of them.
And sexualizing poses is another pitfall.
Make sure that the character's body, look, poses, et cetera
reflect the character personality traits and narrative.
This is an example from Overwatch
that you might have seen before.
It's made quite a buzz as the pose
doesn't go along with her personality.
So be mindful of what you're doing
and watch out for those stereotypes.
And let's end on a more positive note.
There are games which stay clear from pitfalls
and challenge norms.
This is an example from Journey, who
have created a game with a character
without a clearly stated gender.
They have been thinking big, and they have crushed the norm.
Some other positive example, this
is Faith Connors in Mirror's Edge.
She is a powerful Asian woman and has the leading role.
Watch Dogs 2, which takes place here in San Francisco.
They have been working actively with the representation
of diverse ethnicity and touch upon subjects like autism.
And we have the upcoming game, Last of Us Part 2,
with the story that includes LGBT characters.
So now we're going to do the workshop.
you are going to take a closer look
by trying out the diversity space method,
and we will look at four games.
Clash of Clans from Supercell,
Call of Duty Infinite Warfare
from Infinity Warden Activision,
Super Mario Run from Nintendo,
and The Legend of Zelda Twilight Princess from Nintendo.
So.
To make it easy for you, we have decided that the norm is the same norm we were talking about earlier, the Western market.
So we want you to look at the characters and discuss and draw the diversity space sections for each character,
and you use one color per character.
And you have the workshop material towards the walls,
so if you just go to the flip charts and team up with like four people or so in each team and you start the exercise.
and then one group from each game will present the results.
I think it went quite well, we thought it could be super unorganized, but I think you
got something out of it.
It was a bit chaotic.
First we're going to look at Clash of Clans.
So we have a team that has accepted to present their results.
We have asked the team, yeah.
You can come up here if you like.
Maybe you should, where is your chart?
Oh, do you want me to bring it up?
Yeah, maybe.
That's good.
It will be a bit difficult to see, but you get at least...
Sorry.
You find it easy to do the exercise?
Was it a lot of discussions in the groups?
It was good.
And there are no correct answers.
We are all different, and we assess differently.
So, we did Clash of Clans, and what we talked about is that the game is kind of pretty normative.
The only characters that really seem to diverge are the first character, just in terms of...
gender identity, well not gender identity, sorry,
incorrect one, culture and ethnicity,
and then everything else is pretty normative,
even coming down to the body type,
kind of like we all discussed with male characters
in that they tend to have a variety of physiques,
and kind of general buff physique here.
And then with the two female characters, two and four,
kind of almost the same exact body type,
generally a more narrow waist.
but same sort of chest, shoulders, figure,
normally what you would expect
in a lot of female character designs.
All of them were able-bodied,
and then the only other thing that stood out
in terms of variety was that there were two
female characters, and that was pretty much
the only point that we gave it
for the variety of five characters.
And the other teams who were looking at Clash of Clans,
did you have similar results or you thought differently?
About the same?
OK.
Thank you.
I think this serves for a round of applause.
Yes.
Thank you.
And then we had, sorry, I'm just messing up the.
Yeah, Super Mario, would you like to come up?
Hi, so we discussed Super Mario Run and we found that the game had some points in some
areas but completely lacked in others.
So where the game lacked is in ability since they're all non-disabled and in sexual orientation
as well since they are all presumably straight.
Where the game was a bit more diverse is in gender identity.
Two of the characters are female, which is, well, you know,
a little bit outside of the norm.
When it comes to culture, Mario and Luigi are both Italian,
which is still like Western,
but it's not the most represented type, we presume.
So we put them just a little bit on the, like out there.
And age as well, we, like Mario, Peach and Luigi are all sort of not neither young or old,
but both Toad and Toadette are children, so that is, you know, just a bit outside of the norm, I believe, we put them.
And then we have...
body types as well.
So what we noted here is that Mario is short,
like he's actually shorter than Peach.
So we gave him quite a high score for that.
And also that the characters are,
they're not necessarily very muscular,
they're more like, you know, rounded.
So yeah, we gave it quite high points for that.
Even though we didn't give it like,
Very high marks because we said that this still like,
the art style of the game still is rounded as well.
So even though it's not like super muscular,
it's still not far out from the norm of the game.
Like it's still pretty normative in that context.
So we give it like, yeah,
pretty high marks for body type.
But yeah, and also in ethnicity,
none of them differ from the norm
since they're all white and Caucasian, so yeah.
So that was our results.
Great, thank you.
Awesome.
And then we have a team looking at Legend of Zelda.
Cool, so our team looked at Twilight Princess
and the Legend of Zelda.
And there was a bit more variety here maybe than the previous teams.
We kind of...
So, Zelda and Link are very kind of traditional,
fit into the norm even like despite the maybe kind of mythological influences of the game,
but especially Link is very, you know, western, kind of feudal-ware.
And they're both very traditional body types and seemingly sexual orientation.
as well, and ability of course.
Ganondorf, we kind of gave a midway in culture,
and kind of high in ethnicity, because I mean,
he's definitely not traditionally Western.
I guess the game, he's almost like a feudal Japanese.
Interesting, you know, I don't really know what.
What? So that's great. Adds diversity. Age, he's in the don't really know stage. He's still in the
prime of his life, at least for a male character, so we kind of rated it a bit off the norm,
but mostly very, very tightly there. I guess it's midna. It's midna, right? Yeah, okay.
Yeah, great. She's kind of like an interesting one and kind of, you know, enlarged the sphere
a lot, I guess, because as somebody pointed out, she's, you know, she only has sight in one eye,
which is interesting. Her body type is quite different, even though somebody pointed out
that within the context of her, kind of, she still has some feminine traits, even though it's,
But yeah, no, no, she was definitely the most
kind of diverse character and added a lot to the sphere
which was very narrow just after Link and Zelda.
So yeah, that was our findings.
Thank you.
Thank you so much for your motion.
And then we have the Call of Duty team.
We had the same session for Activision Blizzard yesterday.
We had a studio summit, so that was very interesting.
Yeah.
So we were looking at a Call of Duty game
and we found that two out of the five of the characters
are really normative, they were exactly on the bubble.
So four and one were on there.
We also had one female character, which was, it took the gender identity out a little bit.
And then a black character, which took out the ethnicity.
And then we said that having the robot on the team actually expanded the sphere a lot
because the culture was unknown and ethnicity was unknown.
Yeah, actually having the robot on the team
posed probably our most difficult decisions
for determining what to put on this
because there was debate,
because not all of us are actually that familiar
with this particular Call of Duty game.
So there was uncertainty as to whether or not
it was an emphasis on robotic prosthetics
or just the use of a robot character on the team.
But it does stand out in terms of.
ethnicity and I guess gender identity because it's sort of abstract and out
there. Does it have a gender? We looked at it and more or less if you take that
head off the body there it still fit into a very muscular male archetype in
terms of its body design. Sexual orientation could be asexual, not too
sure exactly with that, but otherwise for the most part very boring group of
people aside from Mr. Robot there.
I was actually a little disappointed because when I was standing further away from our smaller picture,
I thought number one was a Latino female and I was like, that's not as bad of a spectrum.
And then I got closer and it's exactly the same as number four and
completely diminished the diversity of gender pools and cultural identifications.
I mean, the one thing I'll say in defense for this game is
just considering the context of the play, at least for body
types, is simply the fact that it is a military-oriented
game, so you do need to have athletic people and people
that are fit for service out in the field.
So I mean, they don't really have much leeway there for
that.
So I'd actually challenge that.
OK, cool.
They participate in sporting and military within operations
that have all body types.
Sounds cool.
Good input though.
I guess my only, I guess I was kind of sad,
well the fact that we haven't played the game
actually made it give us some hope
that there was something different about those characters
like the sexual orientation.
So we were kind of putting dotted lines there
and hoping that the game designers
actually made the right choices
to make that game do it diverse.
But if they didn't, then it would be very sad.
Thank you.
I also want to mention another initiative from King.
We are partnering for the second time with Diversity.
to sponsor a scholarship program for 10 European female talented students to come over here to GDC.
And this initiative gives them an awesome opportunity to network and attend exciting sessions
and further on hopefully a career in the gaming industry.
They are sitting here in front.
I hope you reach out to them afterwards and maybe give them
your best tips and tricks or other opportunities.
Thank you.
So did you find the content in this session meaningful?
You liked it?
And did you get any new insights?
And do you think it will be useful for you
to look more into how diverse and inclusive your games are?
good, that was what we wanted it to become.
So we have some time left, and if you have some questions,
we will try to answer them.
I think we have a microphone in the...
Test, test, okay.
Hi, I just wanted to know how long
you've been focusing on this in King?
Like, is this a new initiative you've been doing?
Or how long have you actually had a focus on this
and your games, have you been looking into this
from the design states and all that until you,
you said you mentioned you had some games
that weren't very diverse and you kind of killed those off,
but I mean, when did you start this process?
In fact, we started, it was one and a half year ago.
When we invited Anita Sarkisian to a King for Market,
that's like a conference we have for whole King.
I really liked her talk and started to think that is there something we can do in our games?
Usually the King games are not very character driven. It's more about candies or vegetables or something else
But we are going more towards games with characters. So we felt that why not like start before it's too late
And we have been out in all studios so far,
and we have had a session for them.
So we're really trying to go towards the right direction.
But as you could see, sometimes we fail anyway.
But that's at least our plan.
And we haven't, this is not our,
this is something we have done ourselves,
like on the side, because we just felt
it was a very important topic.
Yeah.
Any more questions?
Hello.
Hello again.
I don't really like taking up a space
in these kinds of things, but I just wanted to say,
I think the tool is really cool.
One of the things I noticed though is that
there's so much difference in how people interpret it,
and there's so much complication in terms of
whether you take in the context of the game or not.
And I think that that makes a really big difference
in how we look at.
doing this in different communities and what tools they have.
I don't have a question, sorry, just kind of like feedback a little bit for folks in
the room who might want to use it, I guess, in terms of, like I'm really happy that you
mentioned the context is also important.
So we were doing Peach and we're like, well, she's a damsel.
And so do we want to give gender points for the fact that she's a damsel and she's stereotypical?
And so I kind of think of this a little bit like the Bechdel test, which is the test to assess whether a film has...
Oh my god, this is a thing I know really well.
If two female characters can talk about anything else than a man.
Which is a super great starting point for folks to understand that and I think that this tool plays that same kind of role which is a great starting point to get teams talking about it.
But then layering on the pieces of like who is the character like you were saying and I'm wondering if there's a way to integrate that.
which is not an answer now thing.
It's a really good input, and I think that the diversity space is a tool
that is mostly to be used by game developers and narrative and game artists,
so they are aware of what they are doing.
But as we mentioned, you can still have a really big diversity space,
but all the characters are stereotypes,
so you would need to check that as well.
Yeah, absolutely. But I think this is awesome. Thank you.
Thank you.
Any more questions?
So I would like to know your opinion on
what someone might think about
in regards to people's reactions to your diverse cast
that you create in video games or in whatever,
so that you're not just filling in a checkbox kind of thing.
Because...
while that's not necessarily what you're doing,
it might be what it appears to be.
And so I'm wondering with,
as long as it makes sense in the story,
should you just go for as much diversity as you feel like?
Or do you want to kind of watch
to make sure that it's not just like,
here's one of this type,
and here's one of this type kind of thing.
Like, what would you say to that kind of an idea?
It depends on how many characters you've got in a game, of course.
And it would be really strange if you ticked all the boxes in only one character to have it done with.
So it's more about getting a greater variety.
And you don't need to do it in all characters all the time.
But just if you recreate the stereotype, you should be aware of why you're doing it.
Does that answer your question?
Yeah, that is.
OK, hi.
So you mentioned that at King, you've
all been thinking about this more
and trying to focus on this more.
I'm curious if you've generally gotten a lot of buy-in
from everyone on the team about trying to pay more
attention to this, trying to improve inclusion and diversity,
or if you've gotten some pushback, some resistance,
and if so, how you've dealt with that,
how you've tried to bring those team members on board
with supporting this.
Mostly we've got a lot of buy-in, both from the games team and from our brand team, but
I think we're taking it baby steps.
We haven't like overhauled the whole company yet, but yeah, it's a good start at least.
And we're just looking at a mid-core game
that we're developing right now.
And they're like, oh, check this out.
We have so many strong female characters.
And just at the first look, I'm like,
but they all have the same body type still.
Maybe this big gorilla could be a female instead, et cetera.
So even if they really try,
it's easy to fall back into some kind of.
safe area that you have to challenge yourself.
It's really an ongoing discussion and learning process for everyone.
We are not perfect at all.
My question is kind of, you might have exactly the same answer because it's very similar,
but I've heard of some companies where there is pushback regarding like,
hey we designed all these cool, you know, diverse characters,
and then someone will come in and say, yes, but we have, you know,
A-B testing and data that says like, these generic characters perform way better with our audience
because, whatever, you know.
Like, sort of when people are...
planting a stake in the ground and saying we have this
particular reason that we want to keep things within the
norm, how would you push back against that?
Absolutely.
We have that challenge as well, especially if you do
character testing one by one.
You don't see the whole character set up.
You only see one character.
And then people tend to go for something they know.
They go for a stereotype because they like it.
But if you have a whole character set up, and that's
what you test.
there's usually much less reactions on things that falls outside of the norm.
So I think that's the way to go.
And it needs to be a will in the company or in the team that does it as well.
A drive for it.
That you are willing to take some risks maybe,
because if you just go by all the tests,
you will never challenge what we have.
And I think sometimes the players, they don't know what they want to have.
They are.
so used to those stereotypes, so they want it.
But if we present them other options,
maybe they start to reflect more of themselves
and find it more fun to have a wider character base.
And there is an urge for more diverse characters.
Players are actually asking for it actively
and now is the right time to start
thinking about it actively.
Thank you.
Hi there, I thought this was a really interesting tool
and could possibly be used in educational spaces.
I work at a university that focuses on game design.
And I was wondering if there's a resource
where educators could access both your set
of cultural norms and the graph for the diversity space?
You can email any of us and we can send it to you.
And we're, hopefully we can do it as a digital tool.
as well so you can add in like 50 characters and you can get a heat map where you actually
see where you got most diversity.
Yeah I think it would be a really great way to start conversations about diversity in
our program.
So thanks for that.
Sounds great.
Hi, so this exercise that we used,
there were a lot of different metrics for diversity.
There was gender, ability, body type.
Have you, do you focus on all of them systemically at King
or are you finding some more difficult
to expand than others?
I think we're not that story driven yet at King.
So sexuality has never come up as a point.
Mental health hasn't or religion.
So there's a few points lacking,
but we wanted to do this as covering as possible.
So if you've got a really strong storyline
and it's clear for players,
I think you can actually check in
on all the points in diversity space.
All right, thank you.
Thank you.
Any more questions?
Okay, great.
Thank you for your time.
It's been awesome to have you here.