this. So cameras. Whoa, that's loud. Historically cameras in games have sort of been an
afterthought for a lot of game teams. Game plays and cinematic.
Usually it's sort of a last minute thing to assign it to somebody, give somebody ownership over the cameras.
And oftentimes that person doesn't have a lot of real world camera experience.
it's getting better but we still have a ways to go to catch up to film and television. So what
I'm hoping to do in this pretty brief talk is give a basic understanding of how cameras work
and function. Move on to how that applies to composition and then wrap that up with how that
ties into games. Excuse me.
First a little bit of info about me. I've been animating for games for just about 14 years now.
These are some of the games I've worked on. Many of which you can find in the... Oh, people are
supposed to move in towards the center if you can. It's getting crowded. Thank you. Yeah, so
these are the games I've worked on. A lot of them you can find in Jay's bargain bin that he
talked about.
14 years, I spent about 9 years at EA, a lot of sports games. I then moved to Square Enix, was
animation director on Hitman. And I am now in LA at a company called Robotokey where we're
working on Human Element right now. It's a first person survival game. Much of my career has
been spent in cinematics, focused on a lot of story telling through characters, through
cameras and a lot of those fun things. So let's jump right into it.
As animators, when we begin animating a character, we're looking at a lot of reference. We
gather a lot of our photos and videos and stuff like that. Thumbnailing. Even running around
the studio doing our own moves, acting like goofs. Thanks, Zach, for the video. But how often do we
do this when we're about to animate a camera? Is it still going? Let's watch the whole thing.
how cameras work and how they function,
the language of cinematography,
it's remained largely unchanged for decades.
And we've grown up seeing our stories told
through the eyes of these physical cameras.
So because of this,
CG camera can often fall victim to the same thing
that characters can, and that's the uncanny valley.
You can see this a lot in films like the bullet time sequences
in the Matrix films.
Sometimes it's maybe a little more subtle,
like a Michael Bay film.
But I think if we can understand the basic physiology of how
cameras do function and work, then we
can apply that to our CG, which will help us create
some more believable movements, some more believable
compositions.
At first cameras can seem really daunting. There's a lot of moving parts, a lot of controls,
even CG cameras have tons of things to key frame. But really when you break it down into its
simplest parts you only have a few things to control. You have the lens, the aperture, the
shutter speed and where you position it and how you move these cameras. So for lenses, it
it doesn't, sorry, move this.
When it comes to lenses, choosing a longer
or shorter focal length isn't just about
how far the camera happens to be from the subject.
Every lens distorts the image in a slightly different way.
Shorter focal lengths give you a wider field of view,
but also creates greater depth and separation
between your focal points.
A longer focal length gives a much narrower field of view,
but it also flattens the image, as you can see here.
Um, this is something to keep in mind, especially when you're shooting characters. Uh, as
your lens can distort the, the facial features and sometimes take the character off model
before you've even animated it. Uh, this is the difference between a 300 mil and a 25 mil
lens. Uh, and you can see how you can easily break your character without, uh, being careful
about how you choose your lenses. Uh, when it comes to aperture...
It refers to the little diaphragm that controls how much light enters the camera. What it also
does is it changes the depth of field. The area considered in focus is called the circle of
confusion. That's that little place between the two brackets there, the focal point in the
middle. If you change the amount of light coming in, you adjust the circle of confusion there.
And you can see how
letting in more light, moving the focal point closer
or further away from the camera can also affect this.
Unfortunately, in a lot of games,
this is what our depth of field ends up looking like.
We've got a very distinct range that's
perfectly in focus, then a sharp drop off,
and then a place that's evenly out of focus.
You see this used a lot in games,
especially as a tool to highlight something
or separate it from its background.
If our goal is immersion in the universe, anything that sort of reminds us that we're looking
through the eyes of a CG or simulated environment kind of breaks that immersion.
Another unfortunate side effect is this miniaturizes your characters
or your environment a little bit.
They look like little toy figures instead of something
that was shot through a physical camera.
Sorry if anybody here is from Rise.
I just called you guys up.
Instead of relying solely on depth of field to focus the
viewer's attention, we could be using a lot of the other tools
we have on hand. We've got lighting, use of negative space,
leading lines, contrast of tone and value. Limbo here, for
example, was a great use of negative space and contrast of
tone.
This next one from Rise is actually a really great shot.
They framed the character in the doorway,
used sort of a contrast of detail,
the character in the foreground's highly detailed
where the background is starting to use more abstract shapes
and leading lines and contrast of tone
sort of draws you to the character.
This last one's another really great example, but on the opposite side of the scale. It's quite evenly detailed. There's a
saturation of detail across it, but what they've done is
they've used a lot of tonal contrast and leading lines.
You can see the branches leading in. The brightest point in this image is
where they want you to look. Even the characters driving in towards us, those two guys on the upper right.
another really cool thing, how they've used contrastive tone
is if you look down sort of the center bottom, there's a guy
there who's also an enemy wearing red in a green forest.
So he stands out clearly, doesn't belong there, he's not
part of that. Something to pay attention to. Sorry. So
The third thing we have control over is shutter speed.
So typically in games, this isn't something
that's as illustrated as often as it could be.
We're starting to get there now with our newer engines.
This can be represented a number of ways.
Exposure, motion blur, even frame rate.
As I said, we're not using them so much now,
but modern engines are starting to take motion blur
into account, and it is helping.
smooth movement out and again create a more believable experience.
The last main area we have control over this is where we position the camera and how we
move it. As I mentioned before, cinematography and camera work hasn't really changed much.
That language we're very used to seeing and we're very used to getting our stories through
this. When something breaks really sharply from this, we can run into that issue of the
uncanny valley again.
never more evident than at the start of the CGI craze. Flying cameras and crazy slow-mo
sequences. I'm not really selling their creative use short, but just because we can do
something in CG doesn't mean we should. Always. So the tools that we use for film are fairly
basic. There's jib crane, tripod, steady cam, dolly. There's a lot of other stuff that
these are constraints we're accustomed to viewing these
through, but how often do we rig them like this? We do this with
our characters, we study their physiology, where all the bones
are in a lion, a giraffe or anything, but we don't typically
do this with cameras. I wanted to show this short clip from an
Assassin's Creed trailer. If you could pay really close
attention, they've...
They've really added a lot of subtle organic dirt, basically,
onto the camera.
And it feels like there's a physical cameraman
in the scene filming this.
Adding just a little bit of that goes a long, long way
to creating a believable experience.
Just let this play out.
but it's really nice, the subtle movements, the little imperfections, because at the end of the
day, when we watch these, regardless of how smooth they try to move the jib crane, how smooth
the dolly tracks are, there's still a human operating that camera and there's still little
imperfections that go into that movement. So taking these basic mechanics, how a camera
functions, let's just move on to composition.
By now, most everybody's heard of thirds, the rule of thirds.
It's a pretty safe bet that just placing your focal point,
your character's eyes, or something
along any of those intersection points
is going to create a sort of a pleasing composition.
But I want us to start thinking about why we're choosing
to put that character there.
What is the purpose of that?
I've got a couple more to show for this.
But what are you trying to elicit from the audience?
What are you trying to communicate?
So example for this shot.
Feels a lot different than this one.
I've used the same shot, same expression, same rule,
same rule of thirds, but in the first one.
I'm up against the edge of the frame and there's not a lot of
movement, nowhere to go. It actually has a sense of wonder,
there's something fantastic in front of me. Whereas this one
there's sort of a sense of impending danger, there's
something about to crush me. Really it's just using the same
thing but just choosing to use different scale and different
position on the frame. I love this shot. This sequence if you
haven't seen it, everybody's seen Forrest Gump, right?
It's a very, very deliberate use of thirds.
Forrest has been running, he's been running for over a year,
I can't remember exactly how long,
and he gets to the end of his run,
and he's run out of frame,
metaphorically, visually, everything.
His return home is behind him,
and it's a great representation
of how he's just hit the end of his willpower,
his whatever journey he was on.
What also sort of emphasizes this in the movie is that almost the entire movie,
and I encourage you to go back and watch it,
Forrest is framed dead center in the frame for most of the film.
Anytime there's a big.
sort of changing moment for him and his character arc or anything like that, then he starts to be
put on a third or so. There's movement in the frame, but for the rest of it, he's a very neutral
character in his universe. It's the external characters that are the sort of extremes in his
life that come in and out. And this is such a great sort of illustration of that being very
deliberate with how you choose the thirds. One of my favorite characters, directors who most
notably uses.
composition in a very deliberate manner as Wes Anderson.
Any of his films are absolutely just a course on how to use
composition to tell a story.
So one common issue that we do run into is the unintentional use of tangents. Tangent, the
dictionary definition of a tangent is a straight line or plane that touches a curved or curved
surface. But sort of for our purposes it's more of a general.
thing that any time two lines touch but don't cross over. You can see this a lot in film and
TV and when used deliberately it's great because it draws your eyes exactly to where you want to
but a lot of times this is done unintentionally and it can take the viewer's eyes away from what
you wanted to them. Some common sort of uses, you can see this like heads touching the top
of the frame. This is a very, very common one. You can either
crop in or pull back to get rid of this, but your eyes are sort of drawn to these intersections.
A couple more shots of heads touching the top.
How much control converging lines have over the viewer's attention is something that's
actually been measured. There are several companies that test all sorts of things
with eye tracking software and they can see what visual stimuli draw people's attention.
and they've created heat maps to show this.
And you can see on here, there's a vanishing point at the end of the tracks.
They were drawn to that immediately, but now there's a point of contrast
where there's movement and a darker object in the scene, and they're drawn to that.
And you can see, as this camera pans through this shot,
when there's ambiguous space and there's not a lot of focal points,
you see them darting all over, darting all over.
The size of these is relative to how long they stayed on that area.
But you can see they're searching, searching, searching.
They're finding contrast points, finding contrast points.
Then there's movement, and they're on it.
and it's really telling how people sort of see your stories
and to be very deliberate about what choices you're giving them
to focus on is super, super important. I'll let this finish
out. But you can see as it goes behind the building now they're
looking around, looking around.
A while back, Chris Roman storyboard notes from The Simpsons was circulated a lot, and
this became sort of, I think, a little bit taken too literally. A lot of their notes
were that to always switch from a two-plane focus to more of a three-plane, always show
three planes to create a more dynamic angle.
Using this you can usually get pleasing shots, but you're ignoring the use of a lot of other uses of
space. So you've got limited, flat, deep or even ambiguous space. Flat space in its most basic
definition is a two dimensional thing. There's not a lot of perspective or vanishing points. The
opposite side of that is deep space.
one or more vanishing points, spacing and scale of objects
or focal points, creating the feeling of depth.
Limited space is sort of a combination of the two.
You can kind of think of it as a diorama.
You've got multiple planes of two-dimensional space
playing on different layers from the camera.
Wes Anderson, again, uses this quite a bit.
Hitchcock did a lot as well.
The last one is ambiguous space. This removes any cues of depth and places the viewer in a much
more uncertain state about where they are. And this can be a very, very useful tool for
creating unease in your viewer. A lot of these can be used to sort of elicit specific
reactions, like I said. Using too much of any in a sequence can do the opposite. You can
start to devalue what you're trying to accomplish.
but juxtaposing them next to each other,
creating strong contrast, then you can maintain that.
You could use this in a game.
Say you were making a game where half of it
was spent inside a mech or inside of a base,
but the other half was spent in a large open world.
Contrasting that with sort of a limited or flat space.
But then when you're out in the world,
it's much stronger if there's dynamic angles, wide angle
lenses, and things like that, instead of always shooting
like Michael Bay and everything's a beer commercial.
So, flat space, deep space are often used to, plus story
moments, flat space is also used in a lot of comedy, you'll
notice, to punctuate the comedic moments. Deep space is very
dramatic, very emotional.
Other tools you can use, negative space and contrast of tone or value. Negative space is a
low detail, sort of blank space next to a high detail or strong silhouette. Another tool,
contrast of tone or value, using light and dark, contrasting colors, draw the viewer's eye to
where you want them to look. Another example.
This also employs vanishing points and leading lines to just suck you right into where he wanted you to look.
The opposite, this is a good example of ambiguous space.
Sometimes you don't want to create a sharp, sharp thing.
You want more of an ambiguity in your shot.
You want to show that your character is in a safe place.
If there's continuity of tone and pattern like you can see here.
This is a great shot.
Zach Braff's character is in sort of a very ambiguous place
in this point in the story. He's returned home for a funeral. It
really conveys perfectly the feeling that he wanted to give
the viewer at this point. Even the choice to place him sort of
dead center in the frame was very deliberate and effective. At
this point he's sort of juxtaposed with his expression.
It's perfect. Such an awkward shot. And it's really, really
memorable. Alternatively, if you reverse this.
you can make the character feel a bit more tense.
And this is such a great shot that sort of echoes
who these characters are and what split sides
of his personality.
You see Edward Norton framed.
It's all grays.
It's very linear.
Everything's perpendicular.
You see Brad Pitt's silhouette.
Everything's jaggy.
It's bright, saturated colors.
Even got the brown doorway.
He's not quite framed properly.
So you can see it's a visual representation
of who these guys are as characters.
So moving the camera during the shot should also be a very
deliberate choice. If done without consideration, maybe
too frequently, you could again, you'd be diluting the value and
the effectiveness of the tool that you have. For example,
it's become really, really popular to do first person
cameras. This sort of POV style movement says to the viewer that
they're looking through the eyes of somebody that's in the scene.
And if this is not what you're trying to convey, then you're
sort of...
you're diluting your currency. Battlestar Galactica was I think a big reason why we've got a
lot of these crazy rack focuses and stuff like that these days. Again, if you use this too
much, Michael Bay, you're just, it's confusing, it's tiring to watch and you're sort of, what
did I do? Michael Bay, right?
All right. So all this is fine for cinematics but what about gameplay? First person game
with a camera is the character. The limits on what we can get away with are quite limiting.
FOV and depth of field. Any time you take controller away from the user, you run the risk of
breaking immersion. Any changes you make need to be done subtly in a very natural way.
it's very easy to pull the character out. Small changes,
going from stationary to faster movement to illustrate speed.
Going from indoors to outdoors, because sometimes it actually
serves gameplay as well to have a greater field of view. And
sometimes you can get away with a little bit of control, taking
control away from the user to interact with objects in the
scene, but it does need to be done in a very subtle way. I
think this is just about done.
One more.
As you can see here during the roll, or during, yeah,
interacting with this electrical box,
you can see it took control, but it was a very fluid control.
And third person.
have a little more control over the camera and where you place
it. You can see some differences here when entering and exiting
cover situations or actually there's a good spot here where
as he goes indoors in this watchdog clip. You can see we
push in a little bit more. Creating more of a confined
feeling. It's a very deliberate choice. You can also, to
communicate objectives or things like that, you can take some
slight control away from the user.
they do this in combat sequences
uh...
So regarding field of view, it's a common misconception that FOV size is directly related to
motion sickness. Like this. This is basically I just took a camera and I constrained it
directly to the head of a character running. Wider FOV sort of reduces this, but it's just
movement relative to what's in frame. We were looking into this a little bit at Robotoki and
one of the teammates sort of realized that if you stabilize the horizon,
you don't need to eliminate the movement, but it actually does reduce, well he was getting
violently sick one day because somebody changed the value in a camera during our play test and
he couldn't play it for more than two minutes. This is the exact same thing, just with the
horizon stable. There's no difference in the camera movement at all, but it's a much more
stable experience. All I did was stabilize the rotation relative to the horizon.
Why this is, I think, is because as humans we've evolved a number of stabilizing mechanisms to maintain sort of visual stability on objects, whether it's a predator or prey or anything like that.
There's some really complex things that do this. We've got the vestibular ocular, vestibular colic, and vestibular spinal, and that all works sort of in tandem to maintain still head movement, still eyes.
And if anything breaks that, we start jittering around and rotating the camera wildly.
It's counter to that.
And it feels unnatural, we feel queasy, and you've, again, you're watching a Michael Bay movie.
Um, it's, it's, again, it's an evolutionary thing and, uh, it's hard to run away from a bear if you can't see straight, so.
Um.
I think that is just about it. I'm going to leave you guys with some reading material.
This was very light coverage. This is something that could take forever to cover all the little
bits.
I cannot recommend these two books enough. Bare bones camera
course by Tim Schroepel which was one of the first books ever
given to me when I started animating. It literally is a bare
bones book. There's stick figures to illustrate how to
frame things. It's a great short read. The next one which is a
bit more advanced is a visual story from Bruce Block. I had
the chance to see him speak at a SIG graph once and completely
changed how I look at composing shots. I definitely
suggest reading that. As far as websites, check out the seven golden camels. Mark Kennedy who
writes this is a story artist at Disney and he was the lead story artist for Tangled and it's
just so full of amazing information. Definitely go check that out.
And that is about it. I think I have about five minutes for questions. And as always...
Is that not showing up? There it is. Yeah, you can... I love talking about this stuff, so feel
free to contact me or come grab me afterwards. And yeah, maybe four minutes for questions.
No questions.
All right.
That was perfectly clear.
Thanks.