Hi GDC and welcome to launch day, the emotional cost of releasing a game.
I'm really honored to be here.
Thank you so much for letting me come speak about this topic I feel really passionate
about at the Indie Summit.
I'm Lucy Morris. I'm the studio and creative director of StarCult,
which is a small indie studio based out of Wellington, New Zealand.
And I'm really looking forward today to exploring some of these,
you know, quite secretive topics around the launch of periods that we go through.
Just to be clear, I'm not going to be talking to you about how to release your indie game.
There's an almost infinite amount of resources out there and think faces on the best ways
to go about this and anything that I say at this point I feel is probably just replication
of those things.
But what we don't see a lot of analysis of is the emotional and non-technical side of things running up to release
and the struggles that come directly after launch, especially for smaller teams.
After my studio released our first title last year and the dust had settled a bit, I thought
about this a lot and I wrote a Medium article as kind of a cathartic activity.
So I wanted to get these complex and difficult emotions about this period out and also to
see if I was alone in these struggles as we navigate this honestly really difficult environment
that we launch titles into at the moment.
In terms of I wasn't alone and the article seemed to resonate with quite a few people.
So this is a talk on things that we went through, experiences that we had and how to prepare
yourself and your team emotionally to release an indie game.
What I strongly believe is that there's a gap in our knowledge that...
It strikes us how to navigate launches in a way that's sustainable to us and sustainable to our teams
and ways to protect ourselves from some of the more unforgiving parts of this gauntlet that all of us are running through.
Therefore, this is a talk to prepare yourself for that time,
especially from the perspective of a team from a country that's
often left off of maps and popular media,
and a tool to jumpstart discussions on the sometimes unrealistic expectations
that we set for ourselves, as well as those that others set for us in our launch windows.
So in August 2020, we released our first title, Best Friend Forever, on PC and Nintendo Switch.
I won't go too much into the game itself in this talk, but for brevity's sake, it's a
dating sim crossed with a dog care simulator. You pet the dogs and you pet the owners.
To give some context for the tips on this talk and the findings that we found, I'm going to
tell you a little bit about our timeline and the challenges we encountered
and also the emotional reality of launching a game during COVID.
I acknowledge full-heartedly that in New Zealand we've been really lucky in terms of our government's
response to the pandemic, but I think it would also be remiss not to talk about the emotional
cost of launching a game in the current climate and ignore the elephant in the room.
The pandemic is something that has affected and is affecting everyone and will continue
to do so for the foreseeable future.
And this also has an impact on the non-technical aspects of our release cycles.
It's affecting us emotionally and physically.
And in addition, if anyone listening to this has even worked on a game or released a game
during the pandemic, congratulations, because it has not been easy and I am very proud of you.
So this was our planned timeline.
The studio started up in 2019 at the start of the year.
We spent a month setting up the studio and hiring,
bouncing around ideas what the project would be.
And on February 2019, we started full production.
Generally, I was aiming for pretty tight production timelines of smaller projects in which we
could spend about a year to a year and a half producing something that would then in turn
give us more runway in terms of diversifying our game portfolio and future-proofing the
future of the studio.
So we announced, planned for an announce around August and moving into pre-production slightly
after August with the intention to release in 2020 on Valentine's Day, which would be very
fitting for a dating sim. Unfortunately, our actual timeline ended up something like this
and I feel like this timeline might be quite relatable to anyone that's been navigating
release cycles recently.
So this is how we headed into 2020.
We were battle weary and we were utterly exhausted from all the storms that were
weathered. As you can see, you know, at the start it was pretty predictable and
it was cohesive to our timeline.
In August, we announced the project for Nintendo Direct at Gamescom.
And then in 2020, we encountered like a few normal roadblocks that a first game studio
would encounter and I think that pushed our first release date back a little bit.
But at the start of 2020, also COVID started up, so we announced a delay in February that we
wouldn't be able to release on Valentine's Day. We pushed it back to May 14th.
In April, New Zealand went into strict lockdown for five or six weeks,
where we weren't allowed to leave the house except for our state mandated half an hour exercise,
or to go to the doctor or the supermarket.
And this was two weeks after we received a new programmer from Australia.
We had to pack down our new office that we had just moved into, move back home, and...
This was a really difficult period for us as I'm sure lots of people listening to this can relate to
having to maintain the same sort of production output, but have your
working life and personal life completely upended while you've got these, you know, international pressures going on.
So May comes around and we have to delay again.
Things are getting blown out.
The world is reeling from what's going on.
Timelines are impossible to predict.
And the one good thing about this period
was that community was largely really supportive
of these delays.
At least consumers largely seem to understand
the struggles that everybody is going through
in terms of COVID right now.
But this was demoralizing.
We managed to hit out of production around late May and
hit it into post-production.
And then in August, 27th, we managed to release, and I still
can't quite believe this happened because it just, it's.
so hard to release the game during during this late in the middle of this
climate. I am so proud of my team and like sometimes I still think about how
amazing and
impressive it was to be able to get this game out with all these challenges going on in the background.
It shows immense mental and emotional fortitude to achieve something like this.
And then we moved into live ops afterwards, which was quite an intense period, the immediate
post-launch maintenance period.
And I feel like this is really when the emotional cost of development was at its highest.
It was a really intense and difficult time.
And around November, the intense live ops kind of ended,
and then it just went onwards indefinitely in terms of supporting the game.
Like, technically, the game is still not complete because we are always updating it,
we're always adding patches, we're always adding extra content.
So...
It's not really, is it ever really done?
I guess is the question.
So heading into release window in August,
we were already tired.
We were at the usual end of Project Fatigue
where the last 10% takes 90% of the work.
And this was also our first title.
So we poured a lot in trying to make the game,
make our mark as a lot of indies do with their first title.
We were demoralized from announcing delays and pushing back our release three times.
It was an understandable disappointment for my community.
It was a disappointment to us because we just really wanted to share what we have been working
on.
And outwardly, it seems like delays can mean a reprieve in terms of work,
but as developers, you understand that a delay just means a longer time
until the payoff of release.
It means a long time working on the same project and a longer time
before you see the revenue generation from the game, which is,
you know, a studio owner is an extra stressor.
We were already demoralized from these delays, and we
really wanted to share what we thought was like a utopian story that the world needed at that point.
We were already stressed
mostly because there were so many unknown surrounding release and this was true before COVID.
But especially during the pandemic these stresses were exacerbated in terms of
you know, whether it would be received well, what the reviews would say, what issues might be cropping up that need triaging and patching.
But also because we had encountered so many roadblocks coming up to this point,
it almost felt like when is the other shoe going to drop?
Not knowing how external partners were going to manage their own processes
amidst their own COVID situations, which is super difficult to navigate.
Not being able to estimate timelines
when dates are like the holy grail in the games press cycle.
not being able to perform at the same level of quality and finesse as releases pre-COVID,
you're expected to still meet that bar, despite the fact that the world stage is completely different right now.
But we were excited because we'd been working on this for a year and a half.
We were passionate about it. We loved the project.
and we had seen people love playing it at shows, we had a community that had started to build around
that that was very supportive and very kind, and we just wanted to contribute this positive
story to a world that was currently turned upside down. And we were glad it was out, but it wasn't
done. We pushed the button and it released, but it's never done once you do that. I'm definitely
not saying anything in this talk just to be clear that this is gospel or anything, but
Personally, my experience of this immediate post-launch time period was the most difficult
part of the whole production cycle. Even bug squashing and other roadblocks that we encountered
wasn't as draining as this was.
launches your one chance at the moment to legitimize the purpose of your entire production cycle,
a year and a half of work, the investment of a significant period of time to create one thing,
to prove your concept fully in terms of realization and reception,
and likely your biggest chance to make your mark with this artifact.
And as in recent past we can see the zeitgeist coming back around and sometimes that does happen.
It's super rare and the botched launch is something that never fails to make headlines in games.
It's all in all at once and launch has an immense amount of pressure tied to it because of this.
So, Pain Point 1, I feel the emotional cost of launching games
encompasses several pain points.
The first of which being the end point of production
is becoming extremely ephemeral.
Some of the emotional drain from these launch windows
definitely seems to stem from the amount of unpredictability
that comes with pressing the release button.
The immediate period after launch can be busy keeping up with press, communicating with the community.
These are all incredibly time-consuming and sometimes exhausting activities that come at the end of an already full development cycle.
But even aside from that, it seems like...
we're almost going towards games a continual service,
not the sense that games are a service and free to play.
But the amount of work that is involved post launch
to stay competitive in this market,
compared to even say five years ago,
is growing considerably.
So I did a very scientific survey on Twitter.
I asked a few questions to developers
who had released at least one commercial title.
And these are some topics that I've been thinking about since release, and even now, almost a year
later, still releasing patches, still releasing content, still releasing seasonal content to
eke out some exposure in sales. And although this isn't quite the traditional sense of
Games as a Service as I mentioned, the endpoint of games is moving further and further and further
out.
We are a continual service if we want a fighting chance these days,
and we are providing continual support, and in a lot of cases,
updates and content if we want to be seen.
And this has a cost, like not in terms of...
this is more work that I have to do, but you never really get closure on things at the moment if you
want to buff your long tail or if you are super interested in maximizing the worth of your game
over time.
So the first question, did you patch your title within 24 hours of releasing?
This includes making a patch build, submitting it to a platform review queue,
or making a patch build and pushing it to users live.
75 people surveyed, 76% said yes.
So this already shows that there is a very like on-call nature in terms of
games, that there is a very immediate expectation that issues are supposed
to be fixed very quickly.
And that I feel is another pressure that we have to acknowledge here.
How many patches did you push within seven days of release?
54 people responded and 85% said one to three.
And I acknowledge this question's very broad
because we don't know the length and breadth
of those patches.
We don't know how big they are
or what amount of development time went into it.
But I still think that this shows
that there is a significant amount of work
immediately post-release that comes from
just a place of almost unrealistic expectations of our time and our ability to respond to things
quickly. If you want to be
Featured in a holiday sale, you need to update your game with holiday themed content.
If you want to capitalize on momentum after release, like here, you need to keep a watchful
eye on issues that crop up, issues in Steam reviews, and plan into production where feasible
to mitigate these sorts of things happening after release.
you want to fix them, you want to add content, and if you want to keep your community happy,
you need to be almost on call, watching the social media channels, keeping an eye on emails,
vetting content creators, doing interviews, responding to reviews that present issues,
stay on steam. So production and launch are really only the tip of the iceberg in terms of
production cycles.
and it plunges us straight into this games as a continual service cycle that feels like a
hangover after the already intense period of development. Have you built or pushed a patch
outside of your normal working hours for your title, after hours or overtime? 57 respondents
with 75% saying yes. I feel like this is also concerning because it is showing that
we have that on-call nature after release, we are so worried about how negative things like bugs or
less than stellar experiences, which I'm sure no developer wants their consumers to have and is
more than happy to fix, the pressure from having to fix these because of the impact of things,
of like say negative Steam reviews.
is becoming more and more of a pressure, and we're having to respond to it quicker and quicker.
We're expected to be continually responsive in launch windows, turn things around at an almost
inhuman pace because that launch window is so critical, and then to a lesser extent around
the windows of visibility in the events to follow, say like summer sales.
It's now expected to launch patches immediately, if not within a day of finding an issue.
Launch bugs, as we've all seen in the press, can make or break a title, and losing that
edge to negative reviews, no matter how quickly or easily the bug is fixed, can impact your
title's entire lifespan.
That combined leads to this huge nebulous on-call pressure that we have to respond immediately,
we have to be constantly vigilant, that we have to be...
just hugely emotionally invested.
And I think this is definitely something that we should talk about a bit more.
Pain point two, post-launch on top of pre-production is painful.
It's not just about releasing a game.
While you're knee deep in this pool of lava that is post-launch,
you also have to have the brain space to be directing pre-production on the next thing.
And this will depend on how you run your studio, but as I mentioned at the start of the talk,
I really wanted to have tight production cycles.
So...
have a good foundation to move forward into the next project as quickly as possible.
So I had to have the brain space to be creative and look towards the next thing.
The presence of mind to learn from my mistakes from this launch and be objective,
while also knee deep in this lava.
I have to be able to support and guide my team towards our next shot to sustain the studio
while looking at this miasma and wondering if I caused them or if it was my fault or something I
could have done better for my team, something I could have guided us to avoid. And that period
post-launch, especially for people directing, is incredibly confronting. If things go wrong,
we've...
we feel bad. We feel sometimes guilty or ashamed or, you know, if only I had worked harder I could
have caught this. If only I had done X, Y, Z then, you know, this process might have been easier.
And I definitely felt a lot of that after the game came out.
But at the same time, I want this difficult feedback.
It's just on top of having to be intensely creative, overlapping with pre-prod, that
is intensely difficult.
That's the dichotomy that I experienced after launch.
It's hard and it's exhausting and it's the most difficult thing I've had to do
is to be objective and be a buffer for the team
while also trying to tap into a very exhausted,
creative part of me to move forward into the next project.
And.
I think it can't be understated that often we're creating emotional work at a large emotional
cost to ourselves, which may not be immediately apparent, but definitely has become more apparent
to me going forward.
The release playing field is now less level than it ever was, and I feel like this is
the biggest hurt that I continue to feel in terms of release, but the one I feel is also
most unlikely to change, because this is mostly out of our reach.
you are expected to perform at the same level of finesse, of quality, as anyone did pre-COVID.
You were judged on the same playing field as you ever were, and the reality is that
that playing field is not level in terms of...
team size, you were judged in the same way, regardless of world stresses.
It's been very, very difficult to reconcile the fact that we're being judged
the same, having struggled through a release and a pandemic than before.
Regardless of team resources, regardless of where your staff is located and what your
time zone is.
For instance, Launch Window is a very North American time zone centric and we often found
ourselves being up at four in the morning to action things, which is exhausting and
it's another physical and emotional commitment to make to this process.
And regardless of connections, like who you know, what publisher you found.
depending on where you're located in the world as well, like there could be very few or quite a lot
of options open to you. And regardless of experimentation, in terms of production,
I've often noticed that experimentation and subverting of genre is very welcome when
you release. That is very much not the case. And when expectations are subverted and money is
involved, the reception is quite different. So...
I just found the entire playing field quite uneven in many ways.
And it's very easy to sit here and say, hey, that's unfair.
We're all in the same boat.
And we should recognize that and know that we are all in that same boat.
We are all working to some time, like this standard up here that we might not all be
able to reach because of anything on this list.
And we will be judged the same.
And I think
This will tie into a point I'm going to make in a second, which is be kind to yourself and be realistic.
Paint.4 launch was about making wrongs right.
And that is good, but it eclipsed enjoying what rights were right for us.
If you're a community manager, or if you're like the head of a studio or planning biz dev,
you'll have to kind of just wade into everything negative about the game when it launches.
because you have to, because you need to react to it and you need to action those things.
When positive or negative reviews dictate so much of our worth and future viability on storefronts,
you need to digest these narratives and engage with them.
And that is super important.
But I think it's also important to acknowledge this overwhelming and draining.
This is something that you've worked on for a long time.
It is natural to feel like this process is difficult.
And that's not to say don't fix bugs.
Definitely do fix bugs, but do it sustainably.
We wanted this feedback.
We only wanted our consumers to have the best experience.
And yeah, like anything touched with sweaty human hands
that came out with flaws and imperfections.
We released eight patches in 77 days
with 40 to 50 fixes as a team of just four.
And we responded to bug reports via email, Twitter,
Facebook, Discord, Steam forums.
We monitored email channels and we itemized quality of life feedback so we could give
our consumers like an actionable plan going forward.
And we wanted to give them the best experience, the experience we wanted them to have.
And at the end of this highly charged marathon, we were just like heaving for breath at this point.
And it is hard, like you want to enjoy this imperfect, sweaty creation, but instead of like
sitting there and just looking at it, you've immediately got to be going, right, what's wrong?
Let's, you know, let's fix this issue. Let's make everybody happier because you want to.
Have you felt pressured to create a patch outside of normal working hours,
after hours or overtime because of negative reviews, complaints or social
media pressure? 50 respondents, 70% said yes. I feel like
This is also something that we should be talking about.
This is people saying that they feel the need to work on call because of the negative impact
that these expectations are having on us and on our games.
We obviously need to create a more sustainable system where we can
work on these things healthily and not create such
unrealistic expectations for ourselves.
Do you currently have any negative reviews on your product on any platform for issues that have since been patched?
46 respondents, 76% say yes.
This is also important.
We have all of this pressure on us, and even despite our best efforts,
it can still result in things that negatively affect our long tails
that might not always be super accurate.
And I'm not often one to talk about Apple, but having reviews
that are only reflected in terms of the latest patch or the latest update,
might be a way to get around this.
I don't know, I'm not here to create new game platforms or anything,
but there are definitely issues in this ecosystem
that we should probably discuss.
What would we change for round two that we could have changed?
A lot of this is kind of out of our hands. But change one, we would have sort of facilitated
better peer feedback and pre prod or early production, specifically peer feedback. We had
tons of consumer feedback, but that imbalance really worked against us when we when we launched
and we saw that there were some, you know, issues with design and systems that I feel like only
an experienced peer probably could have caught beforehand. So
I came up with this amazing Venn diagram, very artistic.
This is what you need in pre-prod to early prod,
which is the Holy Grail of feedback.
You want it to be feedback you can action, feedback that's realistic
for your team's resources, your production timeline.
And, you know, if you're at a point in production, the things
that might be suggested that are difficult to implement
because they are simply the nature of game development, you can't do everything.
Feedback you can trust from peers that have experience, that know what they're talking about,
that can save you from walking off any cliffs accidentally that they might have done in the
past and avoid you replicating easily avoidable mistakes.
And feedback that's constructive.
Very important.
We don't just want people to tell us,
hey, your game sucks.
The ultimate sweet spot is things
that you can actually implement from sources
that you can trust and that you can rely on
and that are constructive in a way
that actually allows you to take action
and implement those things.
But getting this good peer feedback is hindered by our weaknesses and not giving
good feedback. It is not easy to give good feedback.
And this is something we really need to work on.
not being able to receive feedback objectively, not wanting to hurt feelings,
few established channels to get that grail feedback, and the fact that good feedback
takes time and effort, which a lot of us are lacking. And it was cathartic and relieving
to hear compliments about our game but we honestly needed more critical grail feedback
to save this pain down the line.
I had relief to help outside our time zone working hours and launch window.
Again, we were in GMT plus 12, everything went out in PST time zones.
We were working at 4am.
It was crappy.
Manage expectations and be kind to ourselves,
realizing that that playing field isn't even,
taking time to appreciate the successes that we've had
and the things we've managed to achieve is really important.
Block out time for that in your team to do this
and be mindful of what you've accomplished.
Have a bit of post-prog plan for both mechanical
and non-mechanical needs.
This involved, you know, things like self-care, protecting the team, hiring
that comms person to be a buffer between the negative feedback and translating
it when the team might be feeling raw, I think is really important.
And keep talking about this and not forgetting the value you bring with the
launch, platforms are lucky to have you.
And we should be talking about these things to hold them accountable.
So a summary, seek support and counsel from others who have been through the process.
Be kind, be realistic, make sure that you realise where you stand in terms of trying
to achieve these very, very high expectations.
What kind of state the world is in at the moment.
Plan forward for extra support, blind spots, buffers and time zone issues.
We definitely would hire a community manager or a comms manager to go through
all of this feedback and all of these channels after launch and really help us
not just in terms of being awake when we're not, but also being able to be a
little bit of a buffer when you're in this launch period and feelings might be
raw and, and.
you know, tensions might be high because it was definitely a difficult time for us.
Work constructive peer feedback into your production cycle from an early stage.
So accessing peer knowledge, not being afraid to expose designs and receive
critical feedback, even though you might be protective and very loving of your
systems.
This is definitely something we're actioning going forward into our next project.
And we definitely, I specifically have to be less precious about receiving feedback
because in the end, I want feedback that I can trust that's actionable and that is going
to give the game the best shot in this really difficult environment we're launching into.
That is super helpful and peers don't want you to be replicating their mistakes.
So that was a lot.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you want to contact me, you can email me here.
And best of luck with your launches.