So I'm Carol Shaw.
I'm going to talk today about reclaiming my soul.
And it's really about why it's a very personal talk.
It's not a real production talk.
There's not going to be a lot of specific information.
You probably won't need to take any notes during this talk.
But it's about why I, after working
in free-to-play mobile social games for about four years,
decided to stop doing that and go back to work in AAA games.
So I want to be really clear about what this talk is not
about.
I'm not going to talk about how trashy and crappy free-to-play
games are.
I don't actually think that all of them are trashy or crappy.
And it's definitely not a statement that people
should stop making them and abandon it as a genre.
I think there's a lot of really talented people
out there that are trying to make good versions
of this style of game.
I met a lot of them in my time in that genre
and working in that genre.
So you know.
It's definitely not that.
In-app purchasing, just a little background.
In-app purchasing launched in October of 2009.
I started working in mobile free-to-play
in February of 2010, so not too long after that.
I worked on a game.
My first game was We Rule.
We'll talk a little bit more about that.
And it launched on the iPad 1 when that went live
on April 3rd of 2010.
So about as far back as you could
be making free-to-play games, because it's a super young
genre, I've been doing it.
So that's why I have a little bit of experience.
Felt like this was a good talk to give.
You know, oops.
Back, back, back.
Anyway, but I also want to be clear.
This isn't a puppy, how cute puppies and kittens
and how awesome the free play genre is.
I have a lot of complaints about it.
And I'm going to get into those.
I have a lot of things that just kept me up at night.
They were things that I questioned
about whether this was the kind of game I wanted to be making.
So this is definitely not how much I loved my time
making that type of game.
And really, why did I decide to stop making them?
That's a big part of what this talk is going to be about.
And a lot of it was because it was keeping me up at night.
I was sitting, laying in bed, awake,
and wondering if the types of things
that I was doing in the games I was creating
were actually good experiences for my customers.
The industry was very good to me.
Working in that genre was really good.
I got to work for a lot of great companies.
And I got to make some money, and I
got to learn a lot of new things all the time.
But I developed some concerns.
So Laura Lin, when she talks about stopping
making social games and moving into different genres,
she had a pivot point.
She had a feature somebody asked her to make that she felt.
Specifically, she can point to that one feature and say,
that's when she decided to stop doing that type of game.
For me, it was more of a slow burn.
Took about maybe 15 months or so of really asking myself
questions and trying to determine
what I wanted to do next.
And this is a great example of why
free-to-play social mobile games is not necessarily
the right place for me right now.
It isn't specifically about this game,
but I am the wrong demographic for this game.
And if I had stayed doing free-to-play mobile games,
I would have had to play this game,
and I would have had to play it for hours.
I would have had to study it.
I would have had to spend a lot of time thinking
about how did they monetize.
They made a lot of money, and they're still
making money from this game.
I mean, Glue had their quarterly call last week,
and this game made 54% of their revenue.
Their second game is Deer Hunter, also a game
I'm not a great demographic for.
But, I mean, it's phenomenal, but it's also, I felt disingenuous because I don't want to
play this game.
I didn't want to spend my spare time, you know, thinking about Kim Kardashian.
It just wasn't for me.
I know there's probably a lot of people that play it and enjoy it, and I wish them well.
But again, you know, I would have been bored by it.
I didn't want to feel as though...
You know, I was giving my time to something,
and I probably would have had to pay money towards it as well
to get a good idea of what the opportunities for monetization
were.
And it was more of what would have been a study of business
and not really a study of game design.
So I wanted to stop playing games.
I wanted to start playing games again and stop studying them.
I wanted to do things like go to different tracks.
So for the last couple of years, for all the GDCs,
I've gone to the business and marketing talks
and some of the production talks.
But these are the icons for the community, the production,
and the design tracks.
And these were the kinds of talks
I really wanted to start going to again.
I didn't have a lot of reason to go to a lot of these talks
when I was doing free-to-play games
because I'm an executive producer.
And my job is actually to think about how to make money
in those types of games.
You know, now I get to go back and kind of go back
to my roots and think about the things
that I'm passionate about in game development.
So in my talk description, I said
I would talk about five things that I
found to be frustrating about the free-to-play genre.
This is easily the number one thing
I found to be very, very frustrating for me.
Minimum viable product is.
It's a lean startup.
It came from a lean startup.
It's the version of the product which
allows a team to collect the maximum amount
of validated learning about customers
with the least effort.
Eric Reese is the founder of the Lean Startup Movement.
And I think that this is actually a really great way
to make software.
And to me, it wasn't a great way to make games.
I didn't want to turn out any more games that I felt
were incomplete on launch day.
I wanted to get to a point where it was a.
You know, it could be reviewed by a critic,
and they could actually analyze it.
And the critic wasn't going like, but there's
got to be more, and I know in six months
it'll actually be a full game.
So for me, I wanted to move from the idea
that there's this circle in the lean startup movement
where you have ideas, and you build, and you code,
and you measure, and you get data back, and you learn,
and you kind of keep iterating on that process all the time.
And they're all fairly equal in importance.
You know, for me, I wanted it to look more like this.
I wanted to spend a little bit more time on the upfront side
and a little bit less time looking at data
and understanding how to monetize
and how to extend the retention of the game.
So I wanted to focus on, you know, in the future,
I want to be focusing much more on ideas
and writing good, solid games.
Like, I want to put out not buggy games.
A lot of the social mobile games are, you know, I play them
and I'm like, oh my god, did they QA this?
Because I just don't see it.
And I don't want to do that.
I want to QA my games and turn out a high quality product.
So this is a sort of embarrassing part
of the free to play genre, as fast follows and clones
and sometimes outright piracy.
It's a sign I should drink some water.
So.
This is a something this is again. It ranks as one of those things that kept me up at night. I didn't want to be
Contributing to part of the industry that felt like it was cheating my fellow developers out of their creativity
So you know like oops?
So you know all of these games are variations on
you know, this game, Clash of Clans, which was, in fact, a variation of Backyard Monsters
from Facebook.
The Supercell guys are awesome.
I think they made a very high-quality game.
They've actually been pretty nice and given credit where credit was due to Backyard Monsters
on Facebook.
The disclaimer is, I worked on Backyard Monsters for mobile, so I was very well aware of what
it was like to be making a copy of another game.
Because in a lot of ways, Backyard Monsters was chasing Clash of Clans, even though Backyard
Monsters had actually come first, but on Facebook.
So for me it was this really interesting experience of knowing that Clash of Clans was number
one in the boards, nobody else was beating it, but we were going to try and make a game
based on the background of the game and see if we could, you know, beat Clash of Clans
at their own game.
It wasn't successful.
It wasn't a successful game and it was pulled down and it was the last free to play title
I worked on.
And I, you know, I learned a lot from it.
I had a great team.
Again, this is like...
Not about the people that make the games, but it's about the kind of games that are getting made.
This is the even seedier underbelly of Fast Follows and clones.
All three of these games have just pretty much been outright cloned.
Dream Heights from Zynga, they did, you know, the Tiny Tower guys did a great thing.
You can go search for it online.
That's a, you know, frame by frame of how Dream Heights looked so much like Tiny Tower
and played so much like Tiny Tower.
I play a lot of threes.
I think it's an awesome game.
And I was sad to see that 2048, which came out afterwards
and was very, very similar to it,
just really stomped it, where people just thought
2048 was the original game.
And I wanted those developers who did threes to actually get.
credit for their work.
But really, maybe Spryfox was the one
that really pissed me off the most
and made me just question the people
that I was working with in the industry.
And there was a lawsuit, I think it was settled.
I don't know the details about how that happened.
But I mean, that was a really frustrating moment
because I love Triple Town and I've given money to that game
and I want it to be successful.
I want Spryfox to keep making games.
So I don't want other companies to come in and kind of stomp
them by stealing their ideas.
And if there's any one thing that just frustrated me
and kept me up, that was probably
one of the big ones, this slide.
All right, so like I said, I'm a producer.
And producers think about money.
So who knows what this quote is from?
Nobody, really?
Star Trek, Lloyd's home.
But, well, Scotty said it to Kirk when there was the whales.
But for me, I had to think a lot about whales
because I had to think about how to make money.
And for the purposes of this talk,
I'm going to use every play came out with a report a couple
weeks ago where they defined whales
as people who spend $50 or more per month in a game.
And the important part of the statistic for me was that they make up less than 1% of the customer base
But they represent 29% of the revenue
You know, that's not something I felt like I wanted to work with like that means as somebody who's trying to create a business
I need to focus because it's 29% of my revenue. It's almost a third of my revenue
that I need to be considering those players
and understanding their motivations
and trying to move them in the direction
that I want to go and kind of watch that direction.
And I didn't want to do that.
I didn't want to ignore 99% of my customers
so that I could pay attention to this 1%
so that I could make sure that 30% of the revenue
didn't go away.
Keep having to unscrew it.
Just throw that.
So for me, this was a real eye-opening experience.
I want to be able to make games that
are going to look out at the whole audience
and understand who they are and be able to cater to all of them
and try and give everybody a really delightful, great
experience.
But when you're working on free-to-play games
and you have to focus on your whales,
that can be a huge challenge.
Also extremely challenging is user acquisition
and discoverability.
I don't think either of these problems have been solved yet.
I think there's lots of companies
and there's been a lot of businesses
created to try and solve both of these problems.
But they're not solved.
I still think random games can show up
and Apple might think they're awesome and feature them.
And there doesn't seem to be any specific way
to make that happen for yourself.
Like, I worked for really big developers,
and sometimes we'd get featured and sometimes we wouldn't.
And then last week, some friends of mine
that are like four small indie game developers,
their game got featured, and it was awesome.
I was super happy for them.
But I have no idea how that happens.
So you can't really plan for that.
And user acquisition is very expensive.
So this is a slide from Fixoo.
It's a little bit old, so it's from September.
But if the average price is between $1.50 and $2
for a loyal user, and that's somebody
who's going to log in at least three times to your game,
that's a very high cost that you're
paying to try and get those customers to see your game.
I think like 300,000 games in the app store right now.
So getting seen is really hard.
So user acquisition becomes really important.
And because no one's really nailed how that works, you have to think a lot about this.
And to me, that wasn't my core competency.
It's not what I've spent my career understanding and learning how to do.
I like to make games and I like to think about mechanics and game features.
how to do production and get products out the door
and make them high quality.
This is not that.
Thinking about user acquisition was so far out of my realm
and having to learn about it just wasn't fun for me.
And I appreciate that it's fun for some people,
but it really wasn't fun for me
and I didn't really wanna spend a lot more time doing it.
I didn't really want to spend a lot more time thinking about the alphabet soup of acronyms.
So when I worked at Njimoko, every morning I would get up and I would pour my coffee
and then I would sit down and I would start looking and filling out a chart with all of
these numbers to understand how my overnights were, how my weeklies were.
And again, I didn't come in in the morning and schedule a brainstorm.
I didn't come in in the morning and talk to my art director and see what was the newest
art for the next content pack release.
I sat down and looked at these numbers and that just stopped being fun for me.
Like originally I think it was kind of fun and then it became not so fun.
All right, probably the biggest and most important thing for me
about the free-to-play market and thinking about what
I want to do better, I don't want
to use analytics to drive addictive behavior.
I think it's kind of one of the banes of the industry
is that we are able to do things like use A-B testing.
So I love this one.
And the key word in this is trying to A-B test your way
to a magical product.
And it's the magical product that I'm after.
But it is impossible, I think, to use A-B testing or true
multivariate testing to try and get
to that point of that magical product.
It will take you forever.
I think that there's a use for A-B testing
and a use for multivariate testing.
But it's really about how you're going to educate your design.
It's never going to solve your problems.
It's only going to help you point out
where there are problems.
I don't think that's how the industry uses it.
I think there's an over-reliance on this type of testing
that can blind an organization to the fundamental
shortcomings in their products.
And to me, that's not good.
That's not something I want to be a part of.
I want to see the forest, not just the trees.
This is what I like to use data for.
So sorry, this slide's a little washed out.
But this is a level distribution slide from WeRule.
And to me, when we pulled this data
and it came along with a lot of additional data
about what actually was happening
at these specific levels.
But you can tell that there's like a huge peak of people
that are stuck at level 39.
This is when we had the levels go up to 50,
eventually they went up to 80.
And this was a pretty important thing.
We looked at this, we compared it
with when we thought people were churning out of the game.
And we actually used this to modify the game to make it
hopefully more fun for players.
We didn't actually even look at how it impacted revenue.
Like, I have no idea if the people at level 39
actually paid their way, if this was a paywall
that they paid their way out of.
Because we just didn't look at it for that.
And I'm happy that we didn't look at it for that, because I want to think in terms of
how to solve these problems for what the customer is experiencing, and, you know, could we have
made more money off of that?
Maybe.
But again, you know, I didn't want to use the data for that.
I wanted to use it to help make a more delightful experience for my customers.
I work at Telltale Games now.
We make episodic narrative games like The Walking Dead.
We're working on a Game of Thrones game as well, which is very exciting.
But with Telltale, we specifically don't use any data
to drive addictive behavior at the company.
This is an example of the choices screen that you see.
Has anybody played a Telltale game?
Yeah?
Oh, good.
Awesome.
So at the end of the game, you see the choices screen.
And while the designers and while the producers
can look at this and kind of understand the branches
and where people went down the game path,
what we really hope it does is tell the player,
hey, there's this other way you could have played the game.
Maybe you want to go back and play it that way too.
A lot of other people maybe tried a different path than you.
We're premium games.
We don't make any money if they replay our game.
It doesn't matter to us.
All that matters is that we think
that they're going to enjoy the experience.
if they replay it and kind of go down another branching path.
It also helps us build community,
which is something I've always been passionate about,
is having community built around games.
And this is a great way to start conversations on the boards,
because people will come in and say,
oh, I didn't choose this path.
What was your experience doing that?
And it just sort of fosters conversation
and interesting explorations of what the game can be
if you play it a different way.
Another thing I really like is achievements.
So I've been playing a lot of Two Dots, which
is a free-to-play puzzle game.
It's probably my favorite free-to-play game.
And I've given them money, so I've monetized in that game.
I think it's a great game.
I recommend that you go check it out and have fun with it.
You can totally play it without spending any money,
or you can spend a little money and get some cool power-ups
and stuff.
No game is ever going to be made or broken on whether you include achievements with your
game.
Like, it's just a fact.
It's not going to make a good game better, and it's not going to make a bad game worse.
It's just a thing that you can include that some of your customers will enjoy.
I think it's a fun way to introduce humor, where even if your game doesn't have humor,
you can make humorous achievements that people can talk about.
And again, this is another way that you can foster community.
And, you know, it forms another bond between you and your customer, and it forms a bond
between the players.
So on this one, I didn't take a screenshot, but you can flip over to the other players
tab and sort of see what your friends have been doing, so you can connect on Facebook
in this game.
And they also do a nice thing where you, when you're leveling up in the game, you see your
friends, sort of like Candy Crush does.
But again...
This for me is a great way to use data because what it does is it motivates the player to
have more fun.
And that's really what I want to spend my time using data with and I don't want to spend
as much time
using my data to figure out how to monetize my customers.
In fact, if I didn't have to use the word monetize ever again,
I'd be pretty happy.
Also, I think that this may be the last time I publicly
have to use the word funnel.
I never want to use that term again, either.
And I think that I understand why they exist,
and I understand why people chase them down.
But again, I don't want to put my customers in a funnel.
So this is a slide I did a few years ago for a talk I gave
about how awesome data was and how you should use it
to manage your funnels and monetize your customers.
And I've circled a couple of things,
it's really hard to read, I'll post my slides up later.
But these are the things that I take with me going forward as the important pieces of
data that I would like to continue using.
I'm super curious about engagement, like where do my customers turn out of my game, like
where are the problem points that I want to try and resolve.
That's something I'll always want to understand.
I think user segmentation is pretty interesting,
like who are my customers, who's playing my game.
And I actually am a huge, huge fan of player relations.
Like again, I like building community,
but I also feel like you should build a good customer service
organization, particularly if you're
doing some sort of free-to-play game,
but really for any type of game.
So that kind of leads me to what I've learned
and what I will take with me.
Some of the data points that I review
are things that I'll take with me.
But some of the other learnings I have
are really around things like demographics.
In the four years that I was working
on free-to-play mobile games,
I saw the demographics shift pretty radically.
Like a lot more people play games than used to play before
and a lot more different types of people play games
than did before.
And going back to work on...
a series like The Walking Dead or Game of Thrones,
that might be something that you would not
consider that lots of different types of people would play.
But a lot of people watch the Game of Thrones.
And I expect that there's going to be
a lot of people across different age groups
and across the genders that are going to play this game.
I particularly have enjoyed seeing more women playing games, and I think that that's something
I'm going to always keep in mind and make sure that developers are continuing to push
in that direction as well.
This is one of the greatest transitions or time periods our industry has gone through.
Another big piece for me has been looking at how games are
sold.
So I do a lot of online work.
I'm an online producer, primarily.
I think about how to connect users to each other
and connect them to my games.
But I also think about how to sell games and distribute them.
The shift between digital and physical goods
has been pretty radical through the years.
It's kind of hard to read.
It's from between 2010 and 2013.
And so it's getting to be where there's more digital sales
than there are physical sales.
And I think that'll continue.
I don't think physical games are necessarily gonna go away.
I'm definitely not of that camp.
But I do feel like digital distribution
is a huge opportunity to get to more customers.
And I think mobile has driven that a lot.
And that's something that, you know, particularly when I went to Telltale, I thought was interesting
because they do primarily digital distribution throughout the season.
And then when the season's over, they create a physical disc that they also distribute.
So it's kind of the best of both worlds for me.
And probably the last thing that I will take with me, so this is a funny, it says hopeful
parents at the bottom, they're watching their child play video games and thinking about
his bright future as a video game player of mostly Super Mario, I think.
And for me, I wanted to think about what my career path was.
I mean, I've been in the industry for over 10 years.
Before that, I did stuff on the web and online industry
for another six years.
So I've been doing tech since like 95, I think.
So I'm always thinking about what's next
and how to decide what I want to do next.
Excuse me.
When I first started looking at video game companies,
I looked at the games that I loved
and that I wanted to play more of.
The Sims and SimCity were the first games
that I played that I stayed up all night playing.
So, sorry, a little dry this morning.
So for me, going to Maxis and working on games like SimCity 4 and The Sims 2 and Spore were
no brainers.
I felt very passionate about those games.
I loved the creative aspect.
I loved the community aspect.
It was a really easy decision for me to go there because it was my passion.
It was very easy for me to follow my passion.
And then I went and worked on a bunch of these free-to-play
games.
So there's up tops the Enchimoko games and the KickSide game
at the bottom.
And I didn't ever feel the same kind of passion.
What I did feel was this excitement
and this just general wonder at all of the new information
that was always coming my way.
It's a great and vibrant new industry.
And with that brings a lot of interesting new learnings.
But I never felt all that passionate.
It was like that Kim Kardashian game.
Like, I just didn't want to play it.
I didn't leave work and want to go home and play my own games.
And when I started looking around for companies to join,
I realized I was playing a lot of The Wolf Among Us,
which I am, again, like it was kind of a weird game.
I'm not a big Fables comic book fan.
I'm actually not a big comics person.
Hopefully that won't get me thrown out of the games
industry.
But I loved The Wolf Among Us.
I just thought it was a really interesting game.
It had some interesting characters in it.
I loved seeing the branching storylines.
And then when Game of Thrones was announced,
I am a huge nerd about the Game of Thrones books.
I've been reading them for years and years
before the show came out.
So it was kind of a no-brainer for me
to kind of go and apply there.
And one of the great things about it is I
feel like I'm following my passion again.
I feel like, you know.
If there's one thing I will take away from my time doing free to play, it's that I didn't
feel passionate about it and I really wanted to feel that way.
I think when you do game development, you've got to love what you're doing or it's just
not going to be genuine.
So we are ‑‑ oh, wow, I am four seconds short of 25 minutes.
It's amazing.
We have to get out of this room.
There's another talk in here at 12.05.
I'm going to go hang out in the wrap‑up room, which is in 5.05, if you want to come
talk to me.
Thanks very much.
you