Hi, thanks for coming. So yeah, my name is Patrick, as you can see up there. I'm the
developer at Dry Cactus, and we're just a very small studio based in New Zealand. We
made a game called Poly Bridge, and we released it at the end of June 2015 on Steam Early
Access, and we had a few unexpected and unusual things happen, so that's why I'm here today.
Specifically, these are the most interesting things.
So you might have seen some of these pop up on some social media such as Reddit or Twitter
in the last six months. What we did with the game was kind of integrate a replay sharing
tool that made it very easy for players to share their little moments with their social
media timelines and posts and wherever. And it had a very welcome, unexpected kind of
flooding effect in the sense that we didn't really anticipate the kind of exposure we got
through social media and how that translated to sales and financial viability of the game.
So what I'm trying to do today is kind of go over some stats and try and identify the link
between exposure on social media and how that translated to sales and how eventually it
created this kind of feedback loop between content creators on Twitch and YouTube and
people sharing on Reddit and so on.
First of all I want to have a quick intro what the game is
about because I don't expect most people to know about
Poly Bridge. It's a very simple bridge building game at core.
I'm a big fan of bridge building games. It was one of my
favorite genres when I was a kid. Particularly the pont
effect series if anyone is familiar with that from chronic
logic. It was the best bridge building game ever still.
So we took a number of ideas from those games. We did try and take it in a different
direction though. So as you can see from some of the images and also these
screenshots specifically, we tried to kind of take a step back away from the
seriousness that are bridge building and kind of physics games in general. And it's
a trend that's been going on. You can see it like in the hugely successful Kerbal
Space Program, for example, is
while super realistic with all the physics and so on, it has a more playful approach and makes it
look less hard and less kind of engineering which is a big barrier I think to adopting these kind
of games. So one of the first choices was to have a simple aesthetic style, limited color palette,
make it a bit childish and just when you see the game I didn't want anyone to say, oh this is like
it's an engineering game, it's not my kind of thing. So we tried to break down that wall first of all.
Along with that came some other choices like we tried to make a safe space for players
as we're calling it so we don't punish failure in any way. If anything we try and encourage
kind of trying this, trying that. It's very quick to try a bridge, it collapses, I'll
try another strut and move this thing around and kind of make it very easy to
You can iterate on your bridge design instead of feeling punished for failing.
So, no failure. Along with that, Adrian Talents, who is a very talented composer based in Canada,
did a really nice soundtrack which goes very well with creating the mood of, we call it
anti-rage soundtrack because the game does really, really well.
push the button sometimes if you have to spend 45 minutes tweaking a bridge design and it keeps
collapsing. It's not much fun. So to try and counter that feeling of I want to kill the game
developer, we put this kind of soft, mellow guitar instrumental soundtrack which is really
nice. The niche is this word that is tossed around a lot. There might be some other developers
here who kind of focus on niche design. It's a bit of a broad word. It doesn't really mean too
much.
Bridge building game is kind of a sub niche of the physics building niche in itself. What I did
when I started this project a couple of years ago and I was alone, it was shortly after my
partner became pregnant and I had to decide what to do with my life. It was either find a
job and do that kind of thing or try and do another game. The only successful game I had
done previously was a bridge building game. Taking the lessons learned from that, I
really thought I will just do a kind of game.
small niche game. Eventually the scope got bigger over time. It's something that many
other developers feel the same. If you're going to make a game and you don't have much
money, try and do a niche game. That's what I did. It paid out in a way. Along with that,
the sandbox was a big thing. Very trendy as well. Low poly is trendy. We tried to identify
trend so to speak in indie games and what players want. So sandbox was a big thing. So you're not
limited in content to what the game developer gives you but you can kind of do your own thing.
It's integrated with Steam Workshop and so on. And the other big word, community, which means
nothing and everything at the same time. We kept tossing this word around as we were designing
the game, developing features and deciding what to do and what direction to take it in.
We kind of thought community has to be kind of the foundation of this game for it to have a long term longevity and viability and so on.
So throughout the game design we always try to keep in mind how can this feature specifically work and integrate itself with the community forming and building that community and kind of, and keeping people happy at the same time.
Yeah.
Okay, so again, just to get an idea of what the kind of style
is, a very talented artist whose name is Javier, he's based in
Spain, and he's here with us today. Came up with this kind of
low poly style, very limited color palette. Hopefully it's
inviting to the eye, you know, it's not like an eyesore, and
when you see it, you might think, oh, it's cute. It's
something a bit different, at least for a bridge building
game. So I think that contributed a lot to kind of the
exposure we got going, you know, moving forward.
So community, you know, we kept tossing this word around,
not really knowing what to do with it
and how to try and build a community
and have people actually positively interact
with us as game developers and between them
and kind of take the game in a new direction.
So this is just a short recap of some of the choices we did
as we were developing the game.
The main one being the replay recording and sharing,
which is kind of why I'm here today.
So I'll talk a bit more about that shortly.
Along with that we integrated some other tools. The gallery, so when you share a replay in the
game it goes to an anonymous online gallery where people can log in through steam and rate,
comment and filter through submissions for specific levels.
It kind of gives the content creators that give the replays to our gallery a bit of feedback
because you get kind of your little star rating and comments occasionally.
And it just allows kind of other players to see what people are doing.
And the most important thing for us as developers is that we're able to see very, very quickly
what kind of ideas people are coming up with when playing the game.
And this has been a huge factor because as we moved forward with development shortly
after the early access launch.
We were able to see all these new ways, kind of, and new mechanics to play the game that we weren't
aware of. And by doing so we kind of then started designing levels and designing features of the
game that brought that into the game. So a very good kind of feedback loop, so to speak, was
created between the early adopters of the game and us as game developers in trying to kind of,
you know, everybody's happy at the end of the day.
Another thing we did was the feedback tool. I attended GDC last year and there was a talk from one of the developers of Subnautica.
which is that kind of underwater diving game. And they had a whole talk about how they
developed a feedback tool that allows players to send a little item of feedback without
ever leaving the game. So a panel just pops up. You can say if you're happy, sad or medium.
You can give them a comment and it will also send a screen shot and the debugger log of
what's going on behind the scenes. So when a player identifies or a bug happens,
Hopefully they will send us a little feedback item saying this bug happened, I'm not sure why.
And I get to see the debug log and I can hopefully identify why the bug kind of happened.
So it's semi bug tracking, semi kind of feedback and again the loop between the player and the
developer kind of trying to narrow that gap and make it a bit more kind of meaningful for
players to interact with the developers.
Again, the sandbox and the workshop, a huge part of building the community, because that's
where the community forms is when people get to design levels.
and send them up to the Steam Workshop specifically in this case and players can download them.
So along with that we also created the link between the Steam Workshop submissions and
the replay gallery. So it's starting to kind of pay off now so to speak and seeing lots
of replays. So as a player of the game if you make a sandbox level and you submit it
to Steam Workshop for other people to solve, you can then see when a replay is submitted
for your level you can see what players are doing with your own level. So this kind of
gives.
This level designer type of feedback is rarely seen in other
games which I think is a bit of a shame because you design a
level, you just send it out and often you can see maybe some
comments but in this way you can actually see the bridge designs
that are being made with your kind of layout and it makes a
really kind of nice feedback and tiny in the community.
And replays. So just a little bit talking about the replay and kind of the technical
implementation without going too deeply into it because there's lots of stuff out there and I'll
be more than happy to answer any questions later about the more technical stuff. But what we're
doing is we're always recording footage as the simulation happens. We record that at 15
frames per second.
for technical reasons and also because animated gifs or gifs,
depending where you're from, kind of a standard of 15 frames
a second.
It's, you know, the animated gif is a very ancient file format.
It's like from 1990, I think.
So it's not very well compressed.
It has a very limited color palette, which is 256 colors.
The files get very large very quickly and obviously the challenge there was as we were
recording footage it goes into the VRAM so we can't obviously take up too much VRAM otherwise
lower end devices can't play the game and also when you go and upload the file itself you want
it to be quite small because it doesn't you don't want to take like you know a minute to upload a
replay it kind of breaks the flow so we you know kit plays quite small.
So we're recording footage at all times.
This kind of was a choice to try and break down that wall.
I was talking to many other game developers
who are doing similar things.
And some of them are saying, we put these tools in,
but we're not seeing the kind of interaction
that we were hoping for.
And it's often because they require you to log into your YouTube account. You have to do all
these extra steps which players are just, they're not going to leave the game to go and upload
something to YouTube or to the social media platform. Some of them will of course but
you're just like a good
90% making it up, obviously, of people will not just bother pretty much.
So what we try to do is you never have to leave the game.
With a single click, it generates an animated GIF of the buffer that has been recorded over
the last 10 seconds, and then it saves it locally or it can upload it to our online
gallery which I talked about, and social media.
We have Twitter integration at the moment and are working on some other ones.
So once you authenticate the first time in-game...
You just press a single button, share it, save your replay, upload it to your Twitter timeline,
to the online gallery, to your local hard drive, so then you can repost it wherever you want.
And that created the whole kind of feedback loop which we weren't expecting. If you're
interested in the tick, it's open source. It's actually Zach Bart who's a developer on
Zachtronics and recently released TIS 100 and InfiniFactory. He actually wrote the
encoder and he's very kind to give it to me and then it was released open source in a
Bitbucket repo. So it's up there for everyone to use. It's C sharp obviously. Not
obviously but it's C sharp and it comes with an example to integrate into Unity very
quickly.
So definitely, you know, if your game allows for this kind of
feedback, number one recommendation would be to
integrate something like this and think about it, you know.
So, yeah, covering this, what I'd like to then go on to see
is the more financial kind of aspect of the game.
So this is a bit of a confusing slide, so I'll give you a few
seconds to try and kind of make sense of it.
It was hard for me to identify the timeline of events so it was even harder to try to
communicate it in a meaningful way but this is the best I could come up with at the time.
You can see on the left you have a linear timeline and on the right is a meaningless
diagram of how ‑‑
things kind of feed back into each other. It's very hard to say this first happened on a
Twitter feed and then it faded into this Twitch stream which then meant somebody posted it on
Reddit and then the YouTube guy came along. So it's just, you know, I just thought it's just a
feedback loop between all the different platforms and the content creators that use those
platforms. But what did happen though is the first kind of month is kind of what you're seeing
in the left timeline. So we launched into early access. That was the 30th of June.
We had some positive reviews because we had worked with a small PR company to get some people
playing the game early on and do some YouTube videos pre-launch which helped hugely I'm pretty
sure. So on launch we had 15 positive reviews I think and a bunch of YouTube videos were already
out there on launch day which was a very big thing in kind of creating the positive image of the game.
So along with that, shortly after launch we started seeing a very steady stream of content
going on the Twitter timelines. Lots of people sharing the replays on Twitter, which were
then getting retweeted and kind of starting the snowball effect of exposure of the game,
which is ultimately what obviously we were trying to get, because with exposure comes
potential sale. But without exposure, you're probably nowhere, unfortunately.
So then we started seeing more YouTube content coming through. The first Twitch stream started
happening and kind of generating pretty sharp spikes of sales when the Twitch stream was
happening. Reddit was the main one, as we're going to cover shortly. And then shortly after
the Reddit kind of top page, we started climbing up the Steam charts and were in the top ten
for a couple of days, which obviously created more interest. And you can see quite a while
down the timeline, we then started getting mainstream media coverage.
So it's a bit unusual but it's something that's been shifting so much in the last couple of
years is you no longer aim as much for getting that coverage from Kotaku, Gizmodo or IGN.
Personally what happened for us was seeing the coverage from mainstream media would bring
virtually, it was impossible to identify when an article on IGN, how that would translate to
exposure and sales. It wasn't even noticeable on the sales graph. While if you see a Twitch
stream or a Reddit post that gets upvoted a lot, you see a very, very clear spike in sales. So
as an indie developer, I guess you're aiming more these days for getting the exposure on
social media and with content creators on these new platforms and not so much with the
traditional media, so to speak.
Just because the level of exposure you get is nothing compared to what you can get with a Reddit post.
So to try and kind of bridge the gap, so to speak, funny bridge
pun, between sales and exposure on social media, what I thought
I was going to do, what I'm doing, is looking at the first
30 days of sales. And so with these 30 days of sales, as you
can see here, so quick stats, in the first 30 days we sold just
over 50,000 copies at full price, which is $1,199. And it
made a bit over a half million gross in revenue.
This is aggregated data from the two platforms they were selling on, which were steam and
humble. So what I did here was identify these kind of little events that happened the first
month. You can see. So our L is the launch. You can see it kind of goes up a tiny bit and
then it starts coming down. And until we hit T1, that was kind of
what launch was going to be. If we hadn't integrated all the social media and replay sharing
in these community tools, I'm pretty positive this graph would have just kind of stopped at
the L and slowly gone down and just held there.
what happened instead are these other events that you can see
obviously kind of crushed the launch cell. So we're going to
dive a bit more deeply into these. So we're going to ignore
launch but you can kind of launch. We had maybe on launch
day about 300 cells and then 250, 200 and so on. So it's
going down pretty quickly. So we have T1. T1 is the first major
event. It's a twitch stream.
We peaked at about 2,000 viewers as you can see from the graph. While these are daily
sales, the first 30 days, these are now hourly sales. So you can see on the left we're tailing
at about 5 to 10 sales per hour on that day. And then we get a huge spike. It's about 80
on the first spike and about 100 on the second spike.
What's quite interesting with Twitch, which might be obvious to some and was not obvious to me because it was quite new to me, the whole Twitch stream and YouTube and so on.
With the Twitch stream, you often get these spikes of cells during the Twitch stream and as soon as the stream ends, you kind of just go back to where you were.
So it generates a small and short-lived spike of cells.
Potentially it generates a longer term interest in the game because people talk about it to
their friends and cover it on YouTube and so on. But as far as immediate visibility
of increased sales, there is virtually none. You just see the spike and it goes back down.
So that was the first Twitch stream and pretty decent spikes and we were very happy at the
time. This is very unexpected. Wasn't really anticipating the game picked up by Twitch
streamers but it was pretty cool.
So the second spike, T2, is just here. That's another Twitch stream.
This was a larger twitch stream. It had about 16,000 concurrent viewers at its peak.
Similar effect. We're tailing at about 20 up to 50 sales per hour because of other
like YouTube was starting also to pick up. So daily or hourly sales were kind of
increasing slowly on their own. But then the twitch stream happened. There was the
one spike as you can see in 200 there. Shortly after that twitch stream another
twitch stream with slightly fewer viewers. So that's the second kind of hump you
see after the 200 mark.
But again, interesting to see how the end of the sales graph
kind of matches the beginning of it. So we had the spikes and
then we went back down. A couple days after, when I was working
on the game, so we released the game and I was somewhat
obsessively looking at the stats. What you can do on a
Steam store page is link a Google Analytics tracking code
so then you can go on your Google Analytics dashboard and
see what's going on. You can see how many people are viewing,
from which platform they're coming.
there's some issues around tracking where traffic is coming from but overall it gives you a
very good idea. And what I was doing, I was keeping a little window open with the live stats
so you can Google Analytics tries to tell you how many people are currently on your page.
And that was a way for me to try and identify very quickly when something happened
because like these Twitch streams started to happen and other events were starting to
happen and it was very important for us to try and keep track of.
what's generating a spike in sales and so we can kind of leverage on that in the future
and try and make features that encourage that kind of thing to be shared or whatever.
So a few days after the second Twitch stream I was looking at my live stats which were
generally hovering between 30 and 40 live concurrent people on the store page and I
just turned around and it was about 1500.
And I was like, hmm, there's something suspicious going on.
And because I'm not too much of the digital generation,
I was aware of Reddit, but I did not frequent Reddit as such.
So I wasn't too familiar with how it works and what goes on.
So a friend of mine sent me a text saying,
you should check out Reddit.
And then I saw at the top of the front page on Reddit,
there was a Polybridge GIF, which is the one you actually
see in a top right.
Incidentally, that's as you can probably tell, kind of a physics glitch.
What's happening there is that the monster truck has infinite friction on its wheels.
So when it hits the edge, it just kind of has to go somewhere and it flips wildly back.
Somehow, it actually re-does a thing and hits the flag and wins the level.
So it's kind of a, you know, a very happy glitch, so to speak.
It was the first Poly Bridge gift it got.
Lots and lots of traction. It got upvoted so much that it was top front page on Reddit for any
person subscribed to the gaming sub or also just anonymously browsing Reddit. So you can see the
spike there pretty much. These are hourly sales. We shot up to a maximum of 350 sales for an hour.
And interestingly enough, when it goes back down, it doesn't go as down as it was at the
start. So Reddit has, because it's obviously a Twitch stream, it doesn't end suddenly.
Once you drop down the front page, you still have a certain amount of visibility. And that
just created the phenomenon of the meme, so to speak.
Somebody actually published a page on a website called knowyourmeme.com and
polybridge gift sharing became kind of a very niche meme where people would play
it and say here's how an engineer plays polybridge, here's how a student plays
polybridge, here's how whatever my job title is plays polybridge. So we started
seeing like some various things and it just translated to huge sales and
It kind of just kept growing and when a Reddit feature would drop off front page, it was still like holding, hourly sales were still holding very well.
It wouldn't just drop out of nowhere. So definitely the fact that it got picked up by Reddit players was the main thing that drove sales.
running a bit short in time so very small stats. Might be relevant depending on what you're
trying to accomplish. On Reddit these are stats that are new to me. They're a bit hard to find
so that's why I thought it would be useful to share these. So on the left you see the top
ten Polybridge gifs that come up on Reddit. They've accumulated roughly 12 million views.
Probably a few more.
If you want to go, if you're aiming for the front page, you
have to get at least 2,000 votes, up to 5,000 if you want
to be on the front page and not only on the top of the gaming
subreddit. When we did get a front page gif, it would
easily generate 1 to 2, even 3 million views. If you think
about just, we're independent developers, we're trying to make
a small game and suddenly we're getting 4 or 5 million views
every couple of days just through reddit. It was just
so insane for us.
What is hard though, because on Reddit you just share your little gif, luckily most people
would at least put the name of the game sometimes. But if you want to then find out more about
the game, most likely you're just going to go on Google, search for Polybridge. So it's
very hard for us to track direct traffic from Reddit to the store page.
It's kind of guess work but it's pretty obvious when you look at the sales stats and how you
see a Reddit thing and you see the spike in sales. But it's very hard to say track the
long term life of a Reddit kind of feature. The other thing being YouTube. Lots of videos
on YouTube for some reason or another are very big in Brazil and some other South American
countries.
Top nine are from non-English speaking countries.
And then PewDiePie did kind of a very short video and misspelt the name of the game.
Thank you.
But still, it had a few million views.
The top 10 videos accumulated about 70 million views.
There's 20, whatever number, thousand videos have been posted.
And YouTube does have a very long-term impact on sales, but again, a bit hard to track because
generally...
Players don't seem to click on a YouTube link and then go and buy the game.
They might be interested, but later on they'll Google it.
And so it's hard to track the direct correlation between a YouTube exposure and how that translated
to sales and how many people, you know, what percentage of people actually bought the game
and so on.
And this is the Dancing Banana, which you might be familiar with.
This is the top result if you do a Google image search of animated GIF.
So I thought it was relevant.
If anybody has any questions, there's a few mics or you can just shout out and I'll repeat it.
And also, because we're all kind of running out of time, I'll be across the room in the wrap up room if anybody wants to have a chat or whatever. I'm very open.
So other than having in-game videos and GIFs making it easy to share, other than that,
to get the Twitch players to stream your game or the Redditors to post and upload your game,
what can you do to enable, what can you do to make the Twitch players play your game
and the Redditors to post it and upload it?
It's a bit of a hard question I guess. So I'll just repeat the question real quick in case nobody heard it for the video.
He was asking what can we do to try and encourage Twitch streamers or raditors to actually share the content.
So what worked for us was trying to knock down those barriers with the sharing.
So within the game, it's literally a single click and half a second and then you can keep on playing.
And then it saves your gif locally and uploads it.
So I think that was what created the initial interest in the game and as far as Twitch streamers go, we really didn't do anything though. We didn't reach out to Twitch streamers. It was just natural discoverability through the social media platforms that did everything pretty much. It was largely not anticipated on our part.
Mostly a mistake to be honest, it just kind of happened.
It was a very happy accident so to speak.
But we did contact, two weeks prior to launch,
we worked with Evolve PR and they contacted some YouTube
and some Twitch streamers as well, but kind of smaller channels.
The ones that I covered as far as the events and the sales graph
that we looked at, those were completely organic
and they were larger streamers that normally covered Minecraft
specifically and for some reason they decided to cover,
they were all friends I think, and they just covered it.
Yeah, so kind of organic in that sense.
I think just because so many people were sharing these gifs and then doing it on Reddit as well,
just because they felt like doing it.
There was not an encouragement on our part necessarily to do so.
Yep, sorry.
I think I was going to ask something similar, but how do you think this will affect the next game that you have in development, knowing that this GIF stuff and this Twitch is actually a really effective marketing strategy?
So the question being, how is this going to affect our future development on other games with the GIF sharing and so on?
Specifically, we're not working on the game. We're a very small team, so we're still in early access.
So we're just working full-time on this. If I had to take a guess, though,
I would try in any future game I work on, the core design will be keeping in mind
how a player can own the content that they're making.
This worked really well in our case because you're building a bridge, and every bridge is a bit different.
So when a player...
see something funny or it's quite ingenious, they feel like they own that content. They
came up with that bridge so it's going to motivate them to share these moments and that's
a huge factor which other games have tried to tap into but maybe because they're quite
linear and the end result is going to be the same for everyone, it's not a personal experience
so I'm not going to be motivated as a player to share. So yeah, definitely kind of keeping
in mind the game design with the player owning what they're doing kind of in a sense.
Hey, Patrick.
Great talk.
I'm curious if the analytics you put in to track your spikes
and correlate them with social media stuff,
was all of that or most of that in ahead of time
when you launched?
Or did it become apparent that, oh, the stuff
is feeding into each other.
We better start to investigate it more.
Yeah, so question being what we did with the analytics pretty much and whether we had them
from launch and so on. Well, I'm not the biggest adopter or I don't really know much about
analytics, so luckily when you set up a steam store page, you can get a lot of
So all the analytics come from Steam pretty much. So you can set up a Google Analytics code in your
Steam store page and then that's pretty much all I did. As far as timing, I set up pre-launch
because it seemed to make sense and it was recommended by some other developers. Otherwise,
I probably wouldn't have been aware of it.
And yeah, so that's kind of all I did. I just put up the Google
Analytics tracking code and then I would keep a close eye on live
stats specifically and then also getting an idea of how many views
did we have yesterday on the store page and what percentage of
those views came from a specific platform. The problem though
being that it's very hard to track direct traffic because of
the way you discover a game on Steam specifically.
It's very, very vague where the traffic came from.
So for example, if we track traffic from Reddit,
it says it's like 3%.
But it's obviously way more than that.
But because people go through Google search engine
to actually find a store page, there's
that disconnect, which is very hard to make sense of.
But that's all we did, really.
It wasn't too much in the analytic space.
It was just keeping an eye on what's going on.
It was useful for that.
Cool, okay, thanks.