So today we're here to talk about
unpacking player spending in free-to-play games.
First, I'm gonna tell you a little bit about me.
Who am I?
That's a great question.
I'm VP of Insights and Analytics at Kongregate,
and I do some other stuff other than games,
and I've had a fair amount of experience in the industry.
And I have great help when building decks.
So, telling you a little bit about Kongregate first.
So, Kongregate has been around for 13 years now.
We started as a web platform.
We're also a mobile publisher.
We have over 200 million mobile installs since 2013,
over 10 million monthly active users, over 60 games published,
and over 120k games on the web.
And a lot of the data that I'm going to be using today
is from those games.
So.
What's really interesting about being a publisher
in a web platform is that we get access to a lot of data.
So we can do these analyses across many, many games
and get some understanding on general trends
across all of these free-to-play games.
Some games that we've published, Adventure, Capitalist,
Animation Throwdown, I'm going to use both of them
a fair amount today and a couple of other more recent games
as well.
So what can you expect today?
I really hope I can deliver on that promise
of analytics and insights,
and be able to share with you as much data as possible,
go into a little bit deeper analysis,
intermingle some examples in there.
Hopefully it's a lot of data that is very useful
and that gives you not a checklist of best practices,
but more of a framework on how to think about monetization.
My goal is not to give you,
hey, go implement this feature, this feature,
and this feature.
That's up to you on how you do that.
My goal here is to give you ideas and inspiration
on develop what works best for your game.
All right, so to warm up a little bit,
and please don't be shy,
we're among a small gathering of friends.
Can you please raise your hand
if you've ever played a free-to-play game?
Cool, leave them up, leave them up, leave them up.
All right.
Can you put your hand down
if you've only played a free-to-play game for work?
Cool, awesome.
Can you, okay, lower your hands.
Don't get tired.
Can you please raise your hand if you've ever spent
on a free-to-play game?
All right.
Plenty of hands, but not as many.
And you can put them down.
Can you raise them again if you've only spent for fun,
not for work?
So.
way fewer hands.
And even though it was a fair amount of hands up there,
you can see that it was a small group of people
or a smaller group of people.
And this is even an audience and people of the industry
that know how things happen, how the sausage is made,
why you should spend,
and it's still a small percentage of people.
So that is basically why we're here
to talk about spending in free-to-play games.
So, over the years, the free-to-play industry has really matured how we think about monetization.
We've learned things over the years.
We've diversified our revenue sources.
But at the end of the day, you know, even looking at our own revenue sources for Congregate,
in-app purchases are still a big chunk.
We've been able to diversify this.
it's still extremely important.
And throughout all these years,
one of the things that I was googling
for preparing for this talk,
and I was like, okay, let's see
what the conventional wisdom is on the internet,
because obviously that's a source of truth.
And most blog posts and, you know,
deconstructs from 2012 to today,
they all kind of have two big pieces in there.
Most players will never spend in your game.
And most revenue will come from a small, very small,
percentage of players.
But now we know, IAP is important.
But where do these learnings come from?
We should not take these at face value.
We should continue to validate whether this is true, and
we should be able to understand it further.
We have more data now.
So first, I'm gonna start by validating some of these
kind of conventional pieces of wisdom.
And then I'll dive into understanding what's happening
with spending patterns and free to play spending.
So a little bit of a philosophical question.
Can anyone that walks into your game can become a spender?
And it is a question that's hard to answer.
But we can at least look at some data
to better understand what the patterns and trends tell us.
If we look at percent buyers, we split this across genres
of games that we've published at Congregate,
and we looked at how many players have ever spent.
And looking at it by genres, we have a few games
that are casual and hyper-casual, idle incremental games.
So you can see that the ranges are different,
but it's still a very narrow band.
In fact, most games see kind of a max of 5%
of players will ever spend.
So it kind of does validate that idea
of a very few percentage of players
will ever spend on your game.
But I wanted to validate this a little bit further.
So I looked back to kongregate.com,
as I said, we have a lot of games up there.
So I took the same time frame, 2014 to today, or yesterday,
and I took the top 500 games.
And it's a little bit of a busy chart,
but at the bottom, it's the rank by revenue,
and on the y-axis is the percentage of payers.
And what we can see here is that most games fall on the 1% to 3% buyer rate.
So it validates what we're seeing on mobile games and
across many, many more games, a bigger pool of games.
And we see there a little bit,
few games going up 5%, 6%, but it's still this narrow band.
I will caveat a little bit this.
Looking back, kind of 2010, 2011.
2012, Kongregate did get a lot of Asian MMOs uploaded
and very popular on the platform,
and those games, I exclude them intentionally
because they have very different mechanics
and they do see very different metrics.
And at that point, we are seeing
kind of go beyond those ranges,
but it is not representative of like
the majority of recent games that we've seen.
So, this took us to a next question.
are some players more likely to spend than others?
So is there something there that some players
have this inclination to, or higher likelihood to spend?
So what we did here is, you know,
looking at our games in the portfolio,
see have they gone from one game to another?
Have they spent in both games?
All right, so taking the total spenders
have ever spent on a single congregate game on mobile,
we saw 40% play two or more games.
And from there, 17% of those spend on at least two games.
And while this doesn't give us a concrete answer,
what it does start hinting at is that
these players are not your random player.
If we were thinking about that 5% that, you know,
you're any player on the street,
or likelihood of them spending,
only five of them will ever spend,
in this case, it's much higher.
So it is starting to tell us something about,
you know, there's certain players that are more willing or,
come in with a different expectation on whether they will spend on a game or not.
All right, so to summarize a little bit what we've seen up to this point,
our conventional wisdom holds, I would say.
Some players are more likely to spend than others.
And this is what gives us that narrow band of spenders or percent buyers.
And I have a little note there that says,
please don't call them whales.
This is a call out to a talk from
Congregate CEO Emily Greer.
She gave many years ago, and I really, really like it
because calling them whales kind of
takes this human piece out of the person,
we're just like hunting for whales,
and they're much more valuable to us than that.
They're real people that are passionate
about the games that we're building,
and we should treat them with that respect.
All right, so.
Other than that little side note,
the reason we want to talk about spend on monetization
is because, at the end of the day,
free-to-play lives and breathes out of being able to monetize.
So successful games, you want to live operate your game
for many, many, many years.
And the way to grow your game is grow your LTV,
grow your ARPU, that is, you want to maximize
your player's lifetime value,
or some people call it average revenue per user.
And yes, but how?
Or how can I measure my progress?
Or how can I focus my efforts?
If lifetime value, I can only measure it
at the end of the lifetime, how can I focus
into knowing that I'm changing and moving the right metrics
and putting the right content into the game
that's gonna give me that result?
So it all starts with a KPI letter soup.
Some of us are very used to just throwing acronyms out there.
And in fact, what I've encountered is that
some companies use them in different ways.
So I wanted to kind of just go through them quickly
so that you know what I'm talking about.
So we start with ARPU, Average Revenue Per User,
and I'm gonna use that to also
kind of reference lifetime value.
We have ARBPUPU, average revenue per paying user.
So this is all only your payers.
We have your percent buyers.
Some people call them percent buyers,
percent payers, percent spenders.
ARBDAO, average revenue per daily active user.
So this is once you start looking at daily metrics.
ARPT, average revenue per transaction,
so how big are those transactions?
Conversion rate, some people call it first-time spenders,
some people get confused with conversion rate
and percent buyers.
Percent repeat spenders, so once they spend once,
do they spend again?
Number of transactions, retention, lifetime sessions,
MAU, DAU, whew, but,
The first acronym I used was KPI.
And we forget that the first part there,
KPI is key performance indicator.
So how can I be measuring my key performance indicators
if I'm looking at 20 metrics?
So the rest of today, I'm gonna spend digging into this
to hopefully unearth what we can actually think of
as our key performance indicators for monetization.
And it starts with understanding
that not all KPIs or metrics are created equal.
Some will give us more insight than others.
Some will give us more actionable insights than others.
And some are more relevant and more aligned with your goals.
And for today, that goal and what we're talking about
is increasing your ARPU or your LTV.
So what we can do to understand this is determine
which KPI matters the most.
So how can we do that?
Back to our goal.
We want strong ARPU.
What we can do is figure out which KPIs
have a strong relationship with ARPU.
So in that case, if we move that KPI,
we will hopefully be moving our ARPU.
And...
At the end of the day, we can focus on these
to get the most out of the time that we're spending
on our roadmapping, live operations,
content generation, new feature releases.
And how can we do this?
So it is time for some correlation analysis.
So, what does this mean?
You can learn all the math, but you can also go and use Excel or R or Python
and actually do this very easily and quickly.
And we can model the relationship between two variables,
in our case, two KPIs.
And the question that we're trying to answer is,
can one KPI influence the other?
And we calculate our R-square.
What does it mean? Why does it matter?
What r-square tells us, and I'm gonna use,
I'm gonna show you the r-squares
of all the correlations that I did,
is if we are close to zero,
there's no relationship between the two things
that we're comparing.
If it's one, you're like predicting the future almost.
But there's a perfect correlation.
I've never seen that.
All right, so which KPIs?
have a strong relationship with RBoom.
And I'll keep coming back to this.
And similar to how I showed the percent buyers by genre,
I will be showing all of these KPIs and their ranges.
And one thing to keep in mind is that
it doesn't mean that a game within that genre,
because you might be like looking at this and be like,
oh, I have an idle game, and it's not that number.
It's higher or it's lower.
games can fall outside of these ranges.
What I try to do is narrow it to the most frequent behavior.
So, before we jump into our first correlation,
I wanna kind of go a little bit through
how to read a bunch of the charts
that we're about to look at.
So, in every chart,
the dots
signify one game, and the color is a genre.
The reason I did this is because for some correlations,
we're gonna go a little bit deeper and split it by genre,
because in some cases, that starts to have an impact.
On the x-axis, we're gonna have what we call
the independent variable, which is basically
the thing that we're trying to see
if it impacts the other thing.
And, sorry, transitions, okay.
And on the y-axis, we have our dependent variable.
One quick technical note for the math nerds.
In this case, monetization variables tend to be curves,
which means that a linear regression wouldn't have worked
for all of this analysis.
So the numbers that you see on the axis,
that's why I left them super small,
because they don't mean anything.
I actually transformed the numbers
to take the logarithm values and be able to do
a safe linear regression that actually means something.
All right, with that out of the way.
time for some correlation analysis.
First, we looked at sessions.
And it all starts there, right?
We need players playing the games.
And I used sessions as a proxy for engagement.
The reason I did this is because it's universal
to all games.
And you know, you could do retention or days retained,
some other types of engagement,
but different games will measure it a little bit different
and it will impact that.
So, I chose this, you can choose another metric to do this.
So, on the correlation, what we saw is a correlation
or R-square of .46.
And asking our correlation meter,
it said that it's pretty good.
And the reason it's pretty good is,
it's really hard, especially in kind of more
behavioral analytics, to get to higher numbers.
Like some other fields will want to aim for much higher
before they call it good.
But for behavioral analytics,
getting to this 0.46 range
is already a pretty good correlation.
And if you think about it, this makes sense.
The longer someone is in the game,
the more they will probably spend.
All right, so that's good.
We wanna keep players.
But we're gonna be talking mostly about monetization.
Next, I looked at average minimum price point
that players spend on.
So what this means is on average for a game,
what's the lowest amount that players spent?
And what this means is it's either
we're offering very low price points
if the number is very low,
or the lowest price points are the most popular ones.
Here's our pretty graph.
And asking a,
looking at the R-square is .31,
which.
It's not great.
And the reason I wanted to look at this
is because I often hear people say,
you know, you just need to get a player to spend,
even if it's at a low price.
Just get them to spend 99 cents, and then you're good.
And this actually tells you that that's not the case.
Let's go to the flip side, max price points.
Same approach with max points.
The reason I wanted to look at this is some teams
are scared of prices.
And the reality is, don't be scared of high prices.
Don't be scared of offering items and content
at very high prices.
If you have the right offering, players will wanna buy it.
So looking at our R-square, 0.6.
That is really strong.
So, low prices, not great.
High prices, great.
Now let's look at the average.
So, for this I took average revenue per transaction,
that's what the acronym means.
And this is the average transaction size, basically.
And looking at our R-square, 0.5, that is?
Really good.
So what this is telling us is that
the higher transaction size on average,
the higher the ARPU we'll see.
To recap what we have so far,
sessions matter.
This is where it all starts.
Make a fun game.
We're gonna talk a lot about monetization and revenue,
but what really matters is to start with a fun game.
And price point matters.
They really matter.
So we're gonna take a little break from correlations
and dig into pricing.
All right, wanted to start with
low concept of this is your game.
Your game is kind of like a monopoly.
It's its own economy.
You are the only person offering those goods.
So if you are Animation Throwdown,
you are the only one selling gems and jiggity-whats
and golden turds and all sorts of other funky things.
And you need to look at your game
to determine how to price your game.
So, how should you decide your game's pricing?
It all starts with elasticity of goods.
What does that mean?
Well, there's two types of goods.
Imagine your gems, animation throwdowns gems.
If we were to decrease the price of our gems,
and a revenue decreases, that means that
we might have gotten more purchases by lowering our price,
but the revenue decreased,
so the gems are what we call elastic.
Basically, demand moves with price.
Now, if the revenue decreases,
sorry, that was revenue increasing.
So revenue increases, more purchases.
Gems are elastic.
Revenue decreases.
Purchase go up slightly.
People are excited about this.
But not enough to make up for you dropping your price.
What that means is that gems are inelastic,
and you can think about that way.
Is it moving with the price elastically or not?
So,
Which one is gems or virtual goods?
And the reason this is important is because it helps us understand
how fluid you can be with your pricing.
For this, I am taking an example or case study
from one of our games, Adventure Capitalist,
by a studio up in Canada called HyperHippo.
And this is from about a little bit less than a year ago.
So, about a year ago,
the team had a first-time buyer special,
prize at $7.99.
And they,
they were wondering what happens if we lower the price?
We'll get more people to buy it.
What happened?
Let's look at the first purchase rate
because this is a first time buyer bundle.
And what happened is that demand just went up like crazy.
So way more people were buying this.
Even legacy players that had never converted,
you know, people that had been playing for a year or longer,
had never converted, saw this special and went for it.
But, did this actually help revenue?
For this case, we can look at our ARPDAU
and average revenue per daily active user.
And I will caveat that games are messy ecosystems
and try to control this information as much as possible
to look at just one piece of one segment in the game.
Right when the price was lowered,
our ARPDAU declined drastically.
which means that our revenue declined.
So back to our original question.
Are virtual goods elastic or inelastic?
Well, purchases went up, check.
It did not compensate for the price drop, check.
Revenue declined, check, unfortunately.
So this starts hinting at virtual goods are mostly inelastic.
And I know that you're all very worried
that revenue declines, so good news.
The team identified this quickly.
They reacted right away.
Always good with the capitalist world.
Another question I often hear around pricing is,
okay, cool, elasticity, inelasticity,
I don't understand that econ,
but what if a lower price point
will help me get players to spend again?
So maybe it's not all about that single purchase,
it's about what comes after that.
I get them to spend once, they spend again.
So for that, I looked at
repeat purchase rates.
So starting with the overall portfolio,
looking at the second purchase rate.
And what we see across all our games.
So we had seen, sorry I'll show split by genres,
but just the average across our whole portfolio, 50%.
I'll use that as our baseline.
And then we'll compare it against
What these buckets are is the price point of the first purchase.
So someone spent, their first purchase was between $1 and $4, they'll fall under that
bucket.
And we'll see if they have a lower second purchase rate for lower prices.
They don't.
It's slightly lower.
So for that lower price point,
we don't see better chances to get a second purchase.
When we get to the five to 10 price range,
it's about the same as the overall portfolio.
And higher price points, much higher rebate spent.
This means.
that lower price points do not increase repeat spend.
We found that our sweet spot, and that's why
you see that most of our games fall under that,
is between five and $25.
But it really depends on the game.
So what I would recommend is that you find your sweet spot,
the sweet spot for your game.
It might be a little bit higher,
it might be a little bit lower.
Next, there's another piece to purchasing
and the first purchase that players see,
which is that they set expectations.
So looking at how high or low is the second purchase
compared to the first one, what we see
is that most players, that first bucket, 48% of them,
their second purchase will be at a lower price point
than their first purchase.
32 will be right at the same price point,
and only 28% of them will spend at a higher price point.
So, if you price too low your initial offers,
you don't give yourself or your players wiggle room
to go down on that price point.
back to AdCap, because they kind of did this.
So looking at lifetime transactions,
based on their first purchase,
and I have the players who spent,
their first purchase was that $7.99 special,
that new $2.99 special, and then everyone else,
that first purchase was somewhere else.
And what we see is that for those who spent
their first purchase was the lower price point.
They have higher number of transactions
throughout their lifetime, cool,
but the revenue per transaction is lower.
And that results in the overall RPPU for those players,
or the average revenue per paying user,
so how much they're gonna spend in their lifetime,
was much lower, as you can see.
So, these two things combined tell us
that price anchoring is a real thing.
What does this mean?
Anchoring is that it's a cognitive bias that we humans,
even if we're like, no, I'm not gonna do that, it's there.
We use the first piece of information
to make future decisions.
And remember, your game is your monopoly.
So it means that a player only has your game
to make comparisons.
So the first prize or the first offer
that you present to that player will really
set the expectations and perceptions
and impact the decisions that they
will make for future prizes.
What this all means is don't set too low of a bar.
It's not going to help with repeat spending.
and it's not going to help with, if they do repeat spend,
with what are they gonna choose to buy
on that second purchase.
Cool, Tammy, so should I just increase
all the prices in my game?
No, it is a careful balance.
And the price that you put in front of a player
has to be justified by the value that you're offering.
So, to summarize our little pricing detour,
correlations with ARPU,
low price points or minimum transaction size doesn't matter.
Having higher matters.
Average transaction size matters.
Games are mostly inelastic.
And watch out for price anchoring.
Now, back to our correlations.
Our original question was relationships with ARPU.
And next up, we're gonna look at percent buyers.
How many players will ever spend on a game?
These are the ranges that we had already talked about.
And asking our correlation meter,
holy smokes, that's very strong.
And that's fairly intuitive, right?
The more players I have spending, that's better,
but it's also good to see it in the data.
And back to this idea that what I started with
is that only a narrow band of buyers will ever spend.
That is true, but it is still important
to make sure that you're getting those players.
And I have one more correlation for you with ARPU,
which is Average Revenue Per Paying User, or ARPUPU,
my favorite one because it's fun to say.
And you can see that in this case,
the ranges are pretty different
as you go from genre to genre.
All right, so let's look at this.
.69, that is really strong.
But the ranges were different for different genres.
So I went down and separated this by genre
and see how it impacts the correlation
between your Rppu and your Rppu.
Midcore games, that is very, very high.
What does that mean?
High investment per payer really matters
for these mid-core games.
And it is fairly intuitive, right?
It's games where players come with the expectation
that they're gonna go very, very deep,
both in gameplay and spending.
For idle games, it's actually still really strong.
And I wanted to have this because there's
this misconception that more casual games, it
doesn't matter as much.
It does.
Encouraging this strong investment per payer
is really important.
And for casual games, not as high, still decent,
but it also makes sense.
You have a wider audience, and it
relies on different monetization mechanics.
So to summarize, RPPU, or investment per payer,
also matters, and it varies by genre.
So we already saw that percent buyers and RPPU
are really, really important.
So I decided to go in and say, ask the question,
which KPIs have strong correlation to these two KPIs
that really matter?
And starting with sessions, sessions and percent buyers,
very strong, it makes sense.
Again, the more time a player spends in a game,
the likelier they are to invest in the game.
Next up, repeat spending and RPP.
And in this case, what it means is
that enabling steady investment from players
who wanna spend will give you a long,
a high investment from those payers.
So you wanna get them to that second purchase.
You wanna get them to that third purchase,
that fourth purchase.
You wanna really get them going through that funnel.
And splitting that by genre.
A lot of people forget to track this second purchase rate, and
it's very, very important.
You already captured the people that were willing to spend, but
you wanna make sure that they're satisfied with their purchase.
Now, how can you measure that?
A very good way to measure that is, do they spend again?
So keep percent repeat spending in mind
when you're monitoring your KPIs.
Quick example, and I'm gonna go super quick through this
because I think I'm running out of time.
I wanted to use Animation Throwdown as an example here
because we see that they really have
best-in-class repeat spend.
And this is by a studio up in Chicago called Synapse Games.
A little bit of history about Synapse
is they have three CCGs, or card collecting games,
in the market already, and they've iterated
taking what's working from those games to the next one
and improving what isn't.
In 2013, they released a sci-fi one called Tyrant Unleashed.
The next iteration in 2015 was trying to reach a broader audience,
kind of a fantasy theme, Spellstone.
And in 2016, we released Animation Throwdown with all five IPs
and a lot of very fun ride in getting that ready to launch.
So looking at their second purchase rate,
so I'm just highlighting, this is the purchase funnel,
but I'm just highlighting the second purchase.
Tyrant Unleashed had incredible repeat.
purchase rate. So from all the players that spent, 75% of them spent at least
another time. That is huge and it kind of makes sense. It was a very niche, hardcore
game. So next iteration, Spellstone, we saw a little bit of a drop but still very
very strong. 67% for
spells down with a more approachable theme,
but still very strong monetization metrics.
In Animation Throwdown, 62%, it's still really strong.
More than half of the players who spend once
will spend two times,
and we were able to reach a bigger audience
even though the metrics took a small hit.
So it was kind of this balance between reach
and strong monetization.
Why and what do they do to be able to kind of repeat this
over the course of the years and multiple iterations
of the same type of game is their live service strategy.
So it has a very well-defined,
and this is for animation thrown out,
I just took a month, for example, or six weeks,
very strong and well-defined cadence of events.
and just quick info on the structure of a card
on animation throwdown.
There's skills, we don't care about those,
attack, we don't care about those, and traits.
You can see there's no numbers there.
The other two are self-explanatory.
They're gonna do things against your opponent.
But traits, are they useless?
And they're not, but they're only useful for a limited time.
And this rotates.
So part of that LiveOps cadence has become,
for all these games, to grant a specific bonus or penalty
or something special happens to a trait
for a limited amount of time.
And what that does is that it creates this
puzzle-solving mentality for players.
They want to find the right combination
that will give them the most powerful deck during this time.
And you can't read that on the left,
but that's a Reddit post that as soon as a new bonus
was announced, the drunk one, people started posting,
like, just help me out.
What's the best combination?
What are the best combos that I can put together?
How should I optimize my deck?
so at the end of the day,
that they can have the strongest deck.
So, part of this is timing also
the offers that are presented to the player.
And this is something that the team has iterated on
very much, and finding the right cadence
of what types of exclusive cards should be offered
to match that active trait.
In this case,
Original design that Animation Throwdown had
was this box idea, which has a bunch of boxes.
You spend, you pull a card, and you can keep spending.
And basically, you can go through the whole box.
It literally is as if you're pulling things out of a box.
In some, there's more kind of weak cards
than super strong cards.
But the idea is that, you know,
you pull everything, in this case,
nine, I don't know how many cards they had,
but if you pull everything out of the box,
you get all the very, very strong cards.
And what we see is that there's a very even engagement
with these boxes.
So the most committed players will regularly spend
to get those cards from these boxes.
and it creates a very steady gem sink.
So you see kind of these ups and downs,
that comes with the release of a new box.
But on average, you can see that throughout
week over week over week,
it is a very, very steady sink of gems,
which means that ultimately is people will need more gems
and spend more in the game.
Now if we look at just high spender players,
it is much higher, it is actually 2x.
So that tells us that your big spenders
are going even deeper.
In fact, 70 to 80% of the gems spent on these boxes
come from those spenders.
Just to summarize real quick, and I apologize
that I didn't get a chance to go a little bit slower on this,
but it's really important to have a regular and deep content
updates.
And what you'll see is that it will give you
what we call strong depth of spend, which
means that players will want to go and do
that second, third, fourth purchase.
but only if it is a good purchase.
So remember that.
It's not just giving them things.
It has to make a difference on their game.
And the way that we can measure the success of this
is by looking at repeat purchase rates.
And at the end of the day,
spending players will want to spend
if it's worth it, again.
All right, so back to correlations.
This is the last one.
Which KPIs have a strong relationship with percent buyers in rppu? In this case, rppu.
And I looked at lifetime time transactions.
And the idea here is that, you know, it's not only about big purchases or getting them to that second purchase,
but it's also about those multiple purchase. So
many many more after the second one and hopefully you win by doing that.
and the correlation is super strong, .72.
That is one of the highest that we've seen.
So you want to increase the number of transactions
that players are doing throughout their lifetime.
And I'm going to go back real quick to Animation Throwdown
for an example on this.
Recently, the team actually iterated
on the design of their boxes.
So the boxes that we just looked at,
they've been running those in all of their games.
And in December, they tested a new type of box,
which is called tier boxes.
So tiers guarantee cards.
You buy more, you go up tiers.
You're at a higher tier.
the prize goes up.
So it's kind of like a step, you're going up that ladder.
But the higher that tier, the better the value.
Kind of reduces a little bit of the randomness.
And just as an example here,
in this case, you can buy for 200 gems.
After you buy that tier, you are gonna go up
and it's gonna be, I think, something like 500,
and it's just gonna keep going up.
and the best card is always there in front of you
so that you really, really, really want it.
All right, so looking at,
back to that percent DAU buying boxes, what happened?
Well, on green we have our regular boxes
that we had looked at,
and in orange we have tier boxes.
During the testing period,
and even as we added it into our regular cadence,
it increased tremendously.
So what this started saying is,
you know, there's a similar system,
but it's more approachable.
You're getting a breadth of players,
more players are engaging with the boxes.
But is that good?
Is that actually going to help,
you know, bring in more revenue?
So if we look at gems spent per engaged player,
we saw lower gem spend.
Is that bad?
Well, it's a balance, right?
We had talked about this.
So when we look at overall gem spend,
you can see that in orange,
the tier boxes have much higher gem spend,
generate more, a bigger sink of gems.
So, the lower starting price point
gives a much higher engagement,
and players, and we found the right balance
between approachable and scaling that system.
So what we saw with that is this breadth,
kind of what I was talking about.
Once the boxes, you can see that when it was tested,
percent first-time buyer went up.
And then once it was added into the regular cadence,
it also went up.
And didn't I say I wish we didn't focus on this too much?
Still something that we want to optimize, right?
But what we also saw was increase in average transactions.
So we also created more depth.
more players are spending,
but they're also going through more transactions.
So it's a little bit of a win-win, right?
So, quick summary there.
Iterate and test different approaches.
I think that's very important, and we talk about,
you know, found really good monetization strategy,
and you go all in, and you wanna kind of take a step back
and iterate and test different approaches.
You can find the right balance between
getting more players to spend, so finding that breadth,
and getting them to spend multiple times,
so getting that depth.
And in reality, you can increase both
without underpricing your game.
Because once again, spending players
will want to spend if it's worth it.
All right, so, to summarize a little bit
of what we talked about today,
some players are more likely to spend,
this is still true,
This is the nature of free-to-play games.
And that percent buyer rate is a narrow band.
But when optimizing monetization, go deeper.
Think beyond percent buyers.
And don't call them whales.
And what are your KPIs?
So go back to that.
Went through a bunch of correlations.
And we want to think about what's key.
So key.
Our percent buyers, it still matters.
This tells you that a player who is willing to spend
comes into your game, they're enjoying it,
and they see the value there, and they give you a chance.
Our PIPU percent repeat spenders in number of transactions
tells you that after that first purchase,
they saw the value.
it's kind of their stamp of approval.
They were satisfied with their purchase,
and they're willing to spend again on your game
and go deeper and really, really go deep into your game
and take it up as a hobby many times.
All right, so if you don't remember anything else
in all the numbers that I talked about
and all the KPIs and the alphabet soup,
remember that.
It all starts with a fun, engaging game.
Don't underprize your game.
And spending players will want to spend,
provide the content that lets them do that,
go deeper, and feel good about it.
Thank you.
And I think we have five minutes for questions.
Hello, thank you very much for an awesome lecture.
I just had probably one question.
When you showed the graph of dependence between the price
of first purchase and the percentage of players who are
repeating to make second purchase after that, isn't it
just kind of a bit biased?
Because when you make first purchase really cheap, it kind
of accumulates very large user base within it, including all
those low spenders, like those who are super rarely spent.
So it's kind of biased by cohort.
And it's like, I don't know.
And like those who are willing to spend $100
on the first purchase, they like,
of course they will more likely spend more
because they're just this small golden cohort of whales.
It is, and sorry, the question was,
if when you look at the second purchase rate,
isn't it the buckets are a little bit biased?
And the answer, it is.
But part of that is because
it's not going to help you to get those,
kind of what you were saying,
the low-spending players that are only going to spend $1.
You're undervaluing your game because they're not
going to repeat spend again.
So part of it is, in many ways, don't even
providing those offers.
OK, thanks.
So did you run anything, any A-B tests on that as well?
Or was it just looking at the same game and conversion points?
We've also ran A-B tests.
This is the most recent example that we had,
and it was kind of a relearning in many ways.
We've ran multiple tests, and we've always
encountered that same result.
Thank you very much for being so open and sharing all the data.
It's amazing.
Thank you.
You mentioned there were key performance indicators,
and you gave us a whole bunch of alphabet soup.
I had a question for you around DAO and ARPDAO,
because you mentioned it at the beginning,
but then it never showed up in any of the other analyses.
Is this something that's more of a red herring?
Is this something that we shouldn't be chasing
when we're measuring performance?
Or is that just sort of your dependent variable
at this point?
So, ArpDAO, I have strong feelings about ArpDAO.
And the question was that I showed the alphabet soup,
and then I had ArpDAO and DAO in there,
and then almost never talked about it again.
And so, ArpDAO is a, I have strong feelings about it
because it's a really bad metric,
because you're looking at your revenue
and your users on a daily basis.
and what happens is that it's aggregating everyone, right?
But in your game you have players
that have been playing for one day, that just installed,
and players who have been playing for 100 days,
or hopefully two years,
and their behavior is gonna be very different.
So by aggregating all of them, you are...
effectively not getting a lot of insight.
It's much more vanity metric.
When it really becomes useful
is when you start segmenting it
by those kind of milestones or player ages.
So if you're looking at your ARPDAU for your new players
versus your midlife players versus your elder players.
Thank you.
Great talk. I just want to ask you about price elasticity.
So you just, you kind of summarized that in general virtual goods are inelastic.
In previous data I've seen on games, it was highly dependent on the price.
So we kind of used a rule of thumb where like below five bucks prices were inelastic
because people didn't care whether they spent one dollar or five.
But above that you did start to see some, you know, elasticity in the prices.
Do you, have you found anything like that or is the, you know, rule of thumb kind of changed?
I think part of it is also, sorry, is the price elasticity, is it kind of a rule of
thumb across everything, or you were mentioning that if you go higher in prices, it starts
becoming a little bit more elastic.
And I think that's why I have kind of the mostly,
because it's not entirely inelastic.
So it also depends on the game.
And it also depends, I think,
on who you're presenting those offers to.
So yes, I think they're mostly inelastic
kind of as a broad umbrella,
but you will encounter situations
where you need to be a little bit more careful about that.
Cool.
Thanks a lot.
Hi there.
Thank you for the talk.
It was very good.
So much like you were talking about R squared sort
of being lower because games is a messy business,
from one math nerd to another, sort of how
do you deal with sort of like the variables not being ideal,
like p factor and things like that?
So I just sort of wondering your general philosophy
for sort of measuring math and things like that.
A lot of it is, we use ranges.
So math, the question was from one math nerd to another,
games are messy environments and how do we deal with
the R scores not being perfect and other types of variables.
And a lot of it, we have a luxury of having
a portfolio of games, so that also helps us
in having ranges, so it's kind of a little bit of a cheat
in that way because we can.
look at these behaviors and these analysis across multiple games,
and determine when a range is good versus a range is bad.
Thank you.
All right. Thank you, everyone.