My name is Brian Intihar.
I'm a creative director at Insomniac Games,
and I am so happy to be here today.
It's kind of fitting to be here with you
because it was 11 years ago at GDC of 2008
that I actually got the call
that I had gotten the job at Insomniac.
I was literally having lunch two blocks down the road,
second admission, when the call came in.
Now making the move from journalism to game development
was extremely daunting,
but it was hands down the best decision I've ever made
in my professional career.
I've been in Insomniac for almost 11 years now,
which is crazy.
I started out in the community team,
and I quickly transitioned into production,
and then for the last four and a half years,
I've been a creative director at Insomniac.
Now, I can't tell you how thankful I am
that Insomniac was the first job I had
at the development studio.
Before coming to Insomniac, as a journalist,
I had done a bunch of stories on them,
and knew what a great place they had.
You know, obviously, they won a bunch of awards,
but I can tell you it's even better
once you're inside those doors.
Now before digging into the creative challenges
that we faced on Marvel's Spider-Man,
I want to give you a bit of history on the project
and probably answer the question I get asked
more than anything else.
How in the hell did Insomniac start working
on the Spider-Man game?
So it was the fall of 2014.
Insomniac was finishing up the title that we were working on.
It was Sunset Overdrive for the Xbox One.
I was the director of project management on it.
And during the final days, some of our longtime Sony producers
were in the office visiting our president CEO, Ted Price.
And during that conversation, they asked Ted,
so what would you think about working in a Marvel game?
So just coincidentally, I happened to be in Ted's office
shortly thereafter.
I think I was actually giving him an update
if we were gonna make our goal date or not,
based on how many bugs we had.
And he actually relayed the conversation.
Ted is a very open individual about the beings he has.
And so I decided to say,
I'm just gonna answer the question for him.
Hell yes, we wanna make a Marvel game.
And I actually, to this day, this is what I said to him.
I go, I would give my right arm to work on a Marvel game.
And that's kind of what I did.
See, this is actually my arm that the character rigging team,
they scanned for development of our muscle blend shapes
on Peter.
So when Peter flexes his forearm in the game, that's me.
So depending on how you look at it,
I did give my arm to work in the game.
Or you could say, I'm Spider-Man.
Now, one of the great things about working in Insomniac
and having a leader like Ted is that he never
wants us to work on something we're not passionate about.
So at the next company meeting, which was a few weeks later,
Ted was giving us an update on what
was going to be life after sunset like
and what were some of our possible projects working on.
And I'll never forget what happened next.
Ted simply put up that red brick Marvel logo, that iconic logo,
and you could literally hear the whole room gasp.
Even though Insomniac had never worked on a licensed IP
in its then 20-year history, as some of you know,
now we're celebrating 25 years this year,
it was the right project at the right time.
For starters, we were extremely excited
to be working with Sony again,
and our longtime producers, Connie Booth,
Grady Hunt, and Mark Cerny,
who had been instrumental in the success
of both the Ratchet and Resistance franchises.
We also hit it off right away with the new Marvel's games team,
which was led by Jay Ong, who are a super passionate bunch
and wanted our help in bringing a new era to the brand.
And lastly, Insomniac is full of diehard Marvel fans.
We felt confident that we'd create something truly memorable,
the Marvel game we always wanted.
Now, early on, we talked about this game
being the biggest Marvel game they had ever made,
the first of many memorable Marvel gaming experiences
from this new group.
Expectations were going to be high.
That's exactly what we wanted to hear.
We weren't talking about just making the best Spider-Man game.
We literally, from day one, were talking about,
we want to be a game of the year contender.
So we had the publisher support, the IP support,
and the internal support to move ahead.
Now early on, we had those discussions
about which Marvel characters we were passionate about.
We talked about a variety of them.
And no, I can't tell you which ones we were talking about.
But even in that first conversation with Ted,
I said to him, we got to do Spider-Man.
As Bill Roseman, who I'm going to mention a couple times
in this presentation, he's the Marvel Games VP
and creative director, told me, Spider-Man
is the Mickey Mouse of Marvel.
No Marvel character is as popular as Spider-Man.
No Marvel character has impacted as many fans
as the friendly neighborhood wall crawler.
More importantly, this character fit our studio so well.
If you think about it, Spider-Man stories
feature so much heart and humor,
just like our Ratchet titles.
More recently, Spider-Man puts a huge emphasis
on traversal, gadgets, and fun, imaginative characters.
So did Sunset Overdrive.
I remember one review calling us out saying,
man, it'd be great if they made a Spider-Man game.
Well, the guy was right.
And lastly, Spider-Man is an underdog,
and being one of the last independent studios
still making AAA console titles,
we consider ourselves an Insomniac underdog as well.
So soon thereafter, we made it official,
and told the team we were making a Spider-Man game.
Now, in all my time at Insomniac,
I've never been as excited to work on a project.
While Ratchet and Resistance
were the reason I came to Insomniac,
I had a very personal connection with Spidey,
and I'm sure some of you did as well.
See, I was the kid who grew up in front of the,
watching TV in my Spider-Man underoos,
yes, I actually had them,
and watching Spider-Man cartoons.
I was the kid, when my mom was trying
to get some shopping done,
the only way she could do it was
to give me my Spider-Man action figure,
that actual action figure that could tell you how old I am,
and I would actually pretend to swing him
from clothes rack to clothes rack
while she was getting some shopping done.
And then later, I would think about it at night,
like, could you really use a web line
and swing through New York City?
As I got older, I started reading the comics,
and to this day, I still anxiously await
every new Spider-Man film.
So not only was our studio bringing my favorite Marvel
character, who just happens to be one of the most iconic
characters in all of pop culture, to the PlayStation 4,
we were also aiming to deliver at a quality bar
of all the other Sony first title titles.
And as you know from their pedigree,
that quality bar is amazingly high.
And one more thing, I was gonna be the creative director,
a first time creative director.
I think our Peter Parker said it the best
in our first trailer for the game.
No pressure, right?
Now the good news is that four years later, Marvel's Spider-Man proved to be an extremely
successful game for all parties, for Insomniac, Sony, and Marvel.
It's already the best-selling Insomniac title in the 25-year history.
It's the fastest-selling PlayStation title of all time, selling 3.3 million copies in
three days, these first three days.
And I'm really proud it garnered the critical success
we were looking for.
We're an 87 Metacritic.
And when I made this slide, 140 nominations and 90 year
in awards.
And while that's all that great, the sales numbers,
the critical success is great, there's
nothing more gratifying than seeing the impact it's
had on our fans.
For example, we were stunned and overwhelmed
and didn't ever expect the fantastic images that
would come out of players using photo mode.
We were both amazed and somewhat shocked
by the cosplay the game inspired.
Thank you, shirtless Spider-Man.
But this was the best.
We found that one of our fans, after playing the game,
started volunteering at his aunt's homeless shelter,
just like Pete does for his Aunt May.
When your game encourages players to be better people,
that's truly special.
Now here's another spoiler for you.
Making this game was hands down the most difficult, intense,
and emotional experience I've ever been through
in my professional career.
Even though the game being a huge success,
we faced our fair share of creative challenges
along the way.
So today what I wanna do is discuss those challenges
across three separate journeys.
First, we're gonna dig into the character journey,
which we'll look at the creative challenges
that we face working with such an iconic character
that's been around for more than half a century.
Next up, we'll talk about the game journey,
which will detail the creative challenges
we face specifically with the narrative.
And last, I'll discuss my journey,
which will dig into the creative challenges
of being a first-time creative director.
What I hope you walk away from today's talk with
is through our experiences on Spider-Man,
you'd understand the challenges we faced,
how, why, and we initially failed, and we failed a lot.
and the skills and approaches we use
to eventually conquer them.
Ultimately, I hope you can walk away from today
with a better understanding of how you can apply
those lessons to your own game,
whether it's a licensed IP like Spider-Man,
a new IP, or a follow-up to an existing IP.
So let's kick things off with the character journey.
As many of you know, the friendly neighborhood Spider-Man
has been around for a very long time
and across so many different mediums.
There's been 55 years of comics,
so you can imagine the challenges we had on the story side.
six standalone live-action movies,
and another one underway in July,
nine animated TV series,
and just since 2000, 12 console games.
So with a character that's been done so many times
across so many different mediums,
the challenge we had in front of us
was finding that right balance
of giving players something new,
but also not angering them.
And like I said, it didn't take long to fail there.
I, as the creative director, assumed everyone
and was introduced to Spider-Man just like me.
They went through these phases.
You start out in front of the TV
in your underoos watching cartoons.
You move on to the comics when you start reading.
And eventually, you may hit the movies.
I mean, in my opinion,
this is the best superhero of all time.
And of course, everybody loves superheroes, right?
This is just the way it's supposed to be.
But I quickly learned I was being completely naive.
What I learned is that some, as a kid,
started watching the cartoons and simply stopped right there.
Others got into the comics and eventually gave them up.
But I think what was the biggest surprise to me
was learning that some people's knowledge of the character
began and ended with that first Spider-Man movie trilogy
by Sam Raimi.
And this wasn't just true for the people
outside of our building.
It was actually true for Insomniacs as well.
And early in development,
this led to disagreements amongst the team
and some folks not buying into the game I wanted to make.
And what I began to realize is that what people wanted
was a Spider-Man that they had in their own head,
the version that they had built up over the years.
And you better not mess with that.
And as Twitter shows, if you mess with it the wrong way,
they're gonna let you know about it.
So what did we do?
We simply dug into and defined the DNA of the character.
We asked ourselves, what were the common characteristics
of Spider-Man, regardless of the medium people consumed?
And like I said, we spent a lot of time with Bill Roseman,
Marvel Games' VP and creative director.
talked about the character and if you talk to Bill,
he knows Spider-Man better than anyone,
and I would say he probably knows Marvel better than anyone.
And for our first exercise was this group activity
where we literally broke down the duality of the character.
What you see here is the result of that exercise.
On the Spider-Man side, he's known for that iconic costume,
which Bill says is the best costume of all time,
his spider powers, his ability for web swinging
and crafting gadgets, and of course, his sense of humor.
Now on the flip side, you have Peter,
who's just as important.
This constant battle of power and responsibility,
his love of science, his relationships,
and especially early on, this kind of idea
of like he's somewhat of a loser who becomes a superhero.
Now, funny story about this exercise.
So if you've ever met Bill or seen him do an interview,
he's really passionate, and he gets amped up.
And he was so excited about this topic,
he literally started drawing this
in one of our conference rooms.
But what Bill didn't realize was that wasn't a whiteboard.
He was literally writing on the wall.
So he, and the thing is, he was so amped up,
we didn't have the heart to tell him it wasn't a whiteboard.
And so we actually just ended up painting over it,
and that's Bill, and that's why we love him.
From there, we further solidified the DNA of the character
to help ourselves fully understand
and how to portray them in the game.
When it comes to Peter, he's very relatable,
vulnerable, and somewhat awkward in that cute way.
When it comes to Spider-Man, he's confident, resilient,
and uses his humor to deal with stress.
But it wasn't until something I remembered
in my very first conversation with Bill
that things really fell into place.
So my first conversation with Bill was on the phone.
It was roughly an hour.
I swear to you, I took about 10 to 11 pages of notes.
And he provided such great insight on the character
and why to this day Spider-Man remains so special.
And during that call, he'll say something I'll never forget.
Something that literally would provide
the creative foundation for everything we did in the game.
And I remember actually circling this in my notebook.
The best stories are when Peter's world and Spider-Man's world collide.
Look at any of those mediums that I talked about.
That statement holds true.
If you only deliver the superhero fantasy,
you aren't doing the character justice.
Peter, the human story, is just as important.
And his relationships across both parts of his life make for the best drama.
This probably holds true for Spider-Man and Peter
more than any other superhero because he's so relatable.
He's not a billionaire like Tony Stark.
He's not a god like Thor.
We all kind of can see ourselves as being Peter.
And this clarity really helped the team get on the same page.
It also helped us be much more confident
in the creative risks we wanted to take with the franchise.
And what I want to do today is share with you
three examples of how this helped us define Spider-Man
with an insomniac twist.
So let's start with Peter's age.
Now, when most people think of Peter Parker,
they think of him as the 15-year-old high school student.
But not in this game.
We actually made him a little bit older.
First of all, we knew the high school version
had been done a lot, and coincidentally,
we found out later, when Marvel got their hands back
on Spider-Man, they were gonna do a younger Spider-Man,
so it's good we could distance ourselves.
And we knew right away from reviewing, doing reviews,
people were tired of origin stories.
So we decided to make him 23 years old,
which we felt was a great sweet spot.
First off, it allowed us to explore a time in Peter's life
that wasn't as familiar to people.
Personally, this was a very impactful time in my life.
Around the same time I had just graduated college,
I was living on my own for the first time,
paying my own bills,
trying to start a career as a journalist,
and I felt like others who played the game
could really relate to that.
It also let us touch upon mature themes
like mentorship and partnership
that helped make the story much more emotional
while also raising the stakes of the world.
And lastly, he wasn't so old, like married with kids,
that fans couldn't identify with him.
Next is Peter's job.
Again, if you ask a lot of people,
they probably think of Peter as just that photographer
of the Daily Beagle, continually getting yelled at
by his boss, J. Jonah Jameson.
However, we decided to go the scientist route.
For starters, it was a much more modern take on the character.
It plays much more to the character's strengths.
Remember, as I mentioned in that chart,
Peter's a really smart guy, and he loves science.
But more importantly, it tied very heavily into our goals
of delivering a very human story
within the world's colliding concept.
In the game, Peter works for his mentor, Dr. Otto Octavius,
who he inadvertently helps make
into the city's newest supervillain
and his toughest threat ever.
Those mechanical arms, that's because of Pete.
And what's great about this, what really was nice
was that because we dug into the DNA,
we understood the character,
this was a storyline that was completely unique.
You cannot find Peter working for Otto
in any of the comics, any of the movies.
Last up is the game's supporting cast.
While many of Peter's core relationships stayed the same,
we wanted to put some of them in new, unfamiliar roles
to help support this coming-of-age story,
Peter's journey in becoming a young adult.
Mary Jane Watson, she's mainly known as the model,
the actress, the club owner, but in our universe,
she's actually a reporter for the Daily Bugle.
Norman Osborn, he's typically known as the head of Oscorp
and also another famous Spider-Man role.
But since Oscorp, he's moved on
to be the mayor of New York City.
And this time around, Ah-May isn't sitting in Queens
waiting for Pete to come home and make him wheat cakes.
She's actually in the city
helping run the Feast homeless shelters.
And again, this is a great example
of how we could deliver the world's colliding concept
because the Feast shelter is owned by Martin Li.
Martin Li happens to be Mr. Negative.
If you've played the game,
he's one of the biggest threats in the city.
So you have Peter, Martin Li, Spider-Man,
Mr. Negative, again, world's colliding.
And last, we have Miles Morales.
Now, the last time we saw Miles,
I think he was winning an Oscar for Into the Spider-Verse.
But before that, before we knew that Miles was going to blow up
like that, comic book fans really
knew him as that Spider-Man from another universe.
And what we thought was our game was, again,
how can we make our universe feel unique?
What happens if Peter and Miles actually
lived in the same city?
What if Miles was the 15-year-old?
What if he was the Spider-Man fan,
and he actually didn't have Spider-Man powers
in the very beginning?
And if you played the game, you know what happens at the end.
So what are the takeaways here?
Whether you're building a new character from scratch,
working with a well-established one like Spider-Man,
it's good to remember the following.
Define your character's DNA as soon as possible.
Not only will this help create a solid,
creative foundation early on,
but it'll provide clarity for your team
and increase buy-in for your creative vision.
It's also going to help your entire team,
and even yourself as creative director,
when it comes to time to make decisions
throughout development.
This includes setting priorities.
For example, does this particular mission,
feature, mechanic, help support
the pillars of your character?
It'll also help you in determining game features,
especially when it comes times
to choose which ones to elevate,
as it'll all have to do, which ones to cut.
And also, I promise, this is going to make your team much more autonomous.
They won't be coming to you, consulting the creative director or even your writer about
every single choice they're going to make because they're going to know the character
as well as you do.
And solidifying the DNA of your character will also act as your compass for how big
of risks you can take.
You'll know how to answer questions like,
how much can you change this character
from what someone already knows?
Can you put this character in this particular scenario?
And when they're in this scenario,
how will the character act?
What decision will they make?
As I've detailed today,
and especially if you know what we did with one character
at the end of Spider-Man,
you know we had to answer those questions.
And remember, at the end of the day,
you're never gonna please everyone,
and that's totally okay.
For example, throughout development,
I had a number of people on Twitter message me
saying that we ruined MJ by not making her an actress
or model or club owner.
And I can tell you, this can be really hard to hear
because when you're as passionate about the franchise
as the person on the other side of the tweet
criticizing you, it can hurt.
But again, at the same time, I felt very confident
that based on the homework we did,
the core of the character was still in place
and the change of her profession was the right move
for the story we wanted to tell.
Of course, it didn't hurt that many people also messaged me saying,
hey, they really loved what we did with MJ.
But I think it's really important to remember that everything you do,
especially with a character so well-known or a well-established franchise,
there's just no way to please everyone.
Now, it's one thing to understand the DNA of the character,
but it's another thing to actually take that knowledge
and put it into the game.
When it comes to the game journey,
the second journey I'm gonna talk about today,
it's fair to say that every single department
on this project faced that struggle at times.
From programming animation,
we knew getting traversal feel right
was one of the most important things,
if not the most important element
of any Spider-Man experience.
On the design side, we really want to push this idea when it came to combat, that Spider-Man
was more of this acrobatic improviser, not just another muscle-browned brawler.
And when it came to the UI, with Peter's natural tendencies
to create his own tech, we in Marvel art director Tim Tsang
wanted this idea of more of that homebrew feel
to come through in the UI.
And the good news is there's several talks at GDC this year
that cover a lot of these areas and many more.
I really recommend checking them out.
But what I want to do today, specifically,
is talk about the challenges we faced
on the narrative side of things.
Now the first challenge was big because we knew it tied so much to the character's DNA.
How do you balance Spider-Man's sense of humor with wanting a very emotional story with high
stakes?
As any Spider-Man fan will tell you, a big part of what they love about this character
is his sense of humor.
But as all, we're all creative people, especially writers, they know humor is extremely difficult.
Another complication was the medium.
This was not a 30-minute TV show or a two-hour film.
Just to complete, this was an open-world Spider-Man game,
and just to complete the main story, it took 20 hours.
That's a lot of jokes.
Now, so we not only did we need to find our tone,
but also our cadence.
And obviously, Spider-Man is not unique in this regard.
Every game needs to do this.
When it came to VO, early milestones had him quipping
before and during, after every fight.
I figured, hey, this is what Spider-Man does.
This is what people are gonna expect.
We need to do this.
But it became painfully obvious that there was no way
we could write enough VO lines
where it didn't end up feeling repetitive.
And the frequency led to even the good VO lines
just to become annoying over time.
Now here's a footage from a very early milestone
that shows a quip-happy Spider-Man.
Bad guy, corner pocket.
Butterfingers.
Down already.
Who's been putting protein in his own meal?
So I can tell you right now that bad guy corner pocket line,
that played pretty much every single time he threw something in the game
and it's like kind of burned into my brain.
Now in the cinematic front, we also struggle at times to find that right sense of humor.
Our goal was to make Spider-Man very likable,
but early on, he could come across
as either a wise-ass or even a jerk.
Now the scene I want to show you is very early on in Act 2.
Peter's trying to track down Mr. Negative.
He actually goes over to MJ's house.
She's going to help him out.
So he's cooking dinner.
And this is a moment where MJ really opens up to Peter,
confesses that she wants a bigger role
in trying to take down Mr. Negative,
even wants to be his partner.
And right before he answers,
something's going on with the food.
He runs in the kitchen.
And this is how the rest of the scene plays out originally.
Now I want to warn you, this is very early version.
There is no facial animation and the lighting is very temp.
So just remember that.
Not again!
Hey, it's your crime system thingy.
Looks like a residential break-in.
Charles Standish.
That sounds familiar.
Oh! Oscorp CFO.
Wait.
Wait, you don't think this has anything to do with Lee, do you?
I guess he does.
So for me, we have this strong emotional moment
between MJ and Peter.
She's opening up, she's confessing something to him.
As soon as he gets his information, he just bails.
And to me, this just came across as
he's a little bit of a jerk in this scenario.
And it really wasn't until we got off the page
and really started testing everything in the game
that we understood what players were experiencing
and what we were trying to achieve.
Did we really find our clarity and our tone and voice.
This is how we discovered that constant quips
during every random combat sequence were gonna work.
But more importantly, this is where we discovered
that situational humor, humor written
for a very specific moment,
was the right approach for our game.
For example, early in the game, we have a mission
that's basically a tutorial for the crime system.
But thanks to our writer, Ben Arfman,
he took this rather dry moment in the game
and was able to craft something pretty memorable.
And with that, Spider Cop was born.
From his elevated position,
Spider Cop spies his destination,
a second surveillance tower.
Are you narrating yourself?
What? No, of course not.
Chief never did understand Spider Cop.
Thought he was a loose cannon.
Already regretted it.
So that's so good.
So one more note about that mission.
I was actually talking to Ben last week.
And I asked him, I go, Ben, how many versions of the script
did you work on before we got to Spider Cop?
He goes, 15.
15 scripts.
So you're going to hear me say this a lot today.
I'm sure you're going to hear it a lot at GDC.
Iteration makes all the difference.
Now here's another one.
At the end of the Grand Central Terminal mission,
Spider-Man's trying to slow down a runaway train
and his webs snap.
Listen to how he reacts.
That totally worked last time.
So not only was this video line written specifically
for that situation, but we also recognized
that we could give a little wink and a nod
to a very memorable Spider-Man 2 movie sequence
that was somewhat also involved with the train.
And remember that scene I showed you earlier
about MJ's apartment, where he kind of bailed on her
like a jerk?
Well, the good news is that we were able
to go back to that scene, and the writers and animators
said, you know, we could just tweak the very end part of it
and really increase his likability
with some classic Spider-Man humor.
And this is how that played out.
Hey, it's your crime system thingy.
Looks like a residential break-in.
Charles Standish.
That sounds familiar.
Oh, Oscorp CFO.
Wait.
You don't think this has anything to do with Lee, do you?
Sorry to cook and run.
Did...
Did you just leave your clothes on the kitchen floor?
Uh...
Where do you want me to, uh...
Just a couch is fine.
See you later?
Yeah.
So another thing about that scene I just remembered,
the whole walking backwards thing,
that was just our actor, Uri Lowenthal,
just doing it on set, wasn't written.
And another thing is just let your actors have fun on stage
and they're gonna make it better than ever you wrote it.
Now what we do with that apartment scene
ties into our next creative challenge on the game journey,
character and story comprehension and cohesion.
So you spend all this time with your writers,
your developers, your producers,
and your partners working on a script.
Everyone is bought in and you're feeling really good.
But now you're in the middle of development
and you're spending thousands of dollars
on performance capture, processing mocap data,
and not to mention getting your internal cinematic team
ready to make these scenes look and sound beautiful.
But then you start playing and seeing everything
in the game and boom, there's big problems.
Worse, the schedule is already packed
to get the rest of the game done.
our failure was not planning enough for change.
And I feel like a lot of this falls on me
because of the first time creative director,
which I'm gonna talk about more in the next section.
I became so obsessed with nailing everything on the page
that I underestimated how much it would eventually change
once we got in the game.
I didn't anticipate this many issues arising
and I didn't plan for needing this many edits and reshoots.
Here are just some of the narrative issues
that we found both early on
and as late of nine to 12 months before ship.
Act two had large gaps with no humor.
The Miles Morales character wasn't as likable
as we were hoping for.
He came across as more of an angry kid.
Otto's turn into a villain wasn't as believable
as we hoped.
And we weren't selling Otto's master plan,
his plan to get back at Norman Osborn well enough.
Players couldn't go back and think about and go,
oh, that's how that all adds up now.
So what did we do?
We asked for help.
We asked for a lot of help.
First off, we had to go to our publisher, Sony,
and ask for a lot more performance capture days
in order to complete a bunch of reshoots.
And now they could have easily said to us,
sorry, you got a specific budget,
and you gotta make do with what you have.
I know that happens a lot.
But luckily for us, it was the exact opposite.
The support we received from our Sony producers
to go ahead and make those story changes was unbelievable,
and I can't thank them enough.
In addition to our publisher, a huge amount of help, as much,
came from an internal team.
On Insomniac's from literally every single department,
whether it was writing, animation, design, everywhere,
we're looking at our existing scenes
and saying, how could we strategically edit, or maybe
add something to the very end, or the very front?
And this is, I really feel like, when
Insomniac's truly at its best.
So here's an example.
After that train sequence, Spider-Man, spoiler,
takes down Mr. Negative, and he has this short scene
with MJ where he's just texting her back and forth.
And originally, this was just, we had a budget for it,
it was gonna be short and sweet to the point.
And luckily, during this time, we were trying to fix
some of the humor issues and kind of more
that humor story, the writers and animators said,
you know what, we already have this budget for this scene,
what if we just extend it a little bit?
rewrites some of the dialogue to sound more like how people
really text, and then have him doing Spider-Man things
while he's texting, because that's what Spider-Man would do.
And also, hopefully, this will help address
some of the lack of humor criticism.
And this is how the scene eventually turned out.
This is Mary Jane Watson.
Please leave a detailed message,
and I'll get back to you as soon as I can.
Hey, it's me.
Let me know when you want to talk.
Texting isn't talking?
No, no, no, no, not that kind of over!
Please say no, please say no.
Ha! Okay, okay.
And not okay.
What is there to figure out?
Oh, you think?
And that scene was never supposed to be like that.
It was supposed to be about a 10 second scene,
and now that's probably one of my favorite scenes
we ever worked on.
And that's what I say by,
it's something I'll talk about later,
once you hand over a problem to your team,
the magic they can make is just spectacular.
It's one of the best parts of game development.
So when it comes to takeaways,
I believe these hold true for a new IP and existing one.
Go beyond the script and get off the page
as soon as possible.
It's unrealistic and quite unwise
to think that you can script out the whole game
and just go ahead, shoot, and record it.
Continuous iteration and place testing
is how you'll discover the correct tone for your game,
the right cadence for humor, and see if the overall story
is clicking for players.
This is going to sound obvious, but have as many people
play the game as much as possible.
Playtest internally, externally.
If you have the availability of usability labs,
user research, take advantage of them.
And also, don't be afraid to get story feedback when
you have really early builds.
When it's your own developers recording Scratch video,
it's when you're using your Maya Play Blast
as cinematic stand-ins.
You can find it a lot, even when you
don't have all the bells and whistles of a shippable polish
game.
And something I believe holds true for not just Spider-Man,
but for any game, situational humor
is more effective than jokes.
A little of the latter can make a big difference.
And lastly, something I talked about was schedule and plan
for change.
We were really, really fortunate to have that support from Sony.
But we know that's not realistic in every situation.
Some games have very tight budgets,
and that's what they have to deal with.
So something I kind of thought about as a postmortem
for this game was things that you
can do from a production side to help deal with change.
Early on, block out unknowns from the schedule.
I know the instinct is to plan out everything
to the last hour and the last resource,
especially when you have someone like me
as a creative director who's going,
we're gonna, it's gonna all fit, right?
It's gonna fit, it's gonna fit, it's gonna fit.
You know, we're gonna go get this story done, right?
But in reality, no one can predict,
even a former producer, now a creative director,
how much stuff you're gonna have to need to address,
how much stuff you're gonna have to change.
So really, hedge your bets.
And more importantly, and this is especially
for the producers and the crowd,
hold onto those unknowns for dear life.
Don't start filling them in
while someone, the scope of the game gets bigger.
More often than not, as I mentioned,
things aren't gonna go as planned
and something will slip or something in the story will change.
Do whatever you can to not eat into the unknown block.
And while your CD may be irritated at first,
and you may have some tough discussions about scope,
I can promise you that they will thank you down the road.
And I just have to remember that in my next project.
And if things are going wrong, own up to it as soon as possible.
One of the worst things you can do is let your production partners be the ones
pointing out the problem.
Bring them into the fold as early as possible to help you right the ship.
Delaying that inevitable conversation will only make things worse.
Now, the last part of this journey I want to discuss today is specifically my journey,
the journey of being a first-time creative director.
I'm sure you've all heard this famous Spider-Man line before,
with great power must also come great responsibility.
In some ways, I feel like that really captures
what it's like to be a creative director.
When I became a creative director in Spider-Man,
I knew this would be like no other game I ever worked on
and the expectations would be amazingly high.
From day one, our goal was to make the best Spider-Man game
we've all been waiting for.
You wouldn't just hear that from our fans,
but also from our own team.
And again, we weren't talking about just making
a great Spider-Man game.
From day one, we were talking about,
could this be a game of the year contender?
This was also when Insomniac forced 4A
into making a license game.
And once people thought about our previous titles
and the quality of those titles,
there was gonna be a lot of built-in trust
that we would get it right.
We didn't wanna mess with that.
And the In Insomniac we trust was actually something
fans created and created a hashtag,
which every time I saw it would make me sweat.
This was also an unprecedented collaboration
between Insomniac, Sony, and Marvel,
and in one way or another, each one was taking a risk.
So while I understood the responsibilities
of being able to make a great game,
I either underestimated or quite frankly didn't know
the other responsibilities that came
with becoming a creative director.
And while I was unbelievably excited about this opportunity,
I was also unbelievably petrified.
Early on, I was asking myself questions like,
so I came from a production background.
Would the team believe I could be a creative director?
Right off the bat, we were talking about this being
the biggest and most important game
in Insomniac's 25-year history.
Should someone who's never been a CD
be the one leading the project?
And this is something I seriously asked myself
and even talked to my wife about was,
what if I go down as the person who screwed up Spider-Man?
Will I even have a career after this?
So as excited as I was to be working with
one of my childhood heroes,
I was also petrified and worried that people would figure out
that I wasn't the right person for the job.
I'm sure you've also heard the phrase,
fake it till you make it.
That did not work for me at all.
And this started really early in development.
I remember one of our first project meetings with Sony.
We were just really high-level talks.
And for some reason, I was off that next day.
And I called Ted Price, our president.
And I said, hey, Ted, how do you think it went?
And he goes.
Could have gone better.
And I was like, oh, well, could you tell me more?
And he started mentioning all these things that happened.
Like I was interrupting pretty frequently.
I wasn't open to ideas,
especially when we were very early in the brainstorming phase
and other things.
And this really, really blew me away.
And I don't think of myself as a very rude or closed-minded
person.
I hope that's not the case.
I don't think so.
And I remember I was driving home the Pacific Coast Highway.
My sister was actually in town.
I was visiting her.
And I started to realize that after talking to Ted
was I was trying to show Sony that I was confident
in my ability to do the job.
Actually came across as cocky and somewhat of a know-it-all.
And this really shook me.
And what happened next, in some ways, was even worse.
During the next few meetings with Sony,
I actually became very hesitant
and was constantly concerned
that what I was gonna say next.
Result, I was so worried about offending someone,
whether it was Sony or even a fellow Insomniac,
that I didn't come across as a leader with a strong vision.
Again, I wasn't in a very good place.
Now on this game I was very fortunate to have Mark Cerny
as one of my Sony producers.
Mark is an industry veteran who's been involved
in several previous Insomniac tales.
And aside from his producer duties,
Mark pretty much became my mentor.
I remember one day early in the project,
he asked me to go out to lunch.
It was almost like he could sense someone was off.
And during that conversation we talked a lot
about the industry, the role of being a creative director,
other CDs he worked with,
and he's worked with some really talented people.
And he emphasized to me that I had to find
and develop my own approach to leading this project.
So I thought a lot about what Mark said.
And what I began to realize was that I
had this fear of this overwhelming feeling
that I had to have everything figured out
about the game before anyone ever asked the question,
again, because I doubted myself.
And now, sure, all creative directors
need that strong vision of the game, which I believe I did.
But you also need people around you to help cultivate
that vision, perfect that vision,
thus giving you confidence to sell to a larger group.
What I needed to find was my leadership team.
And that's exactly what I did.
I began leaning on folks like Ryan Smith, our game director,
who's pretty much been my partner in crime
for the last decade.
And I joke, but it's true, and he hates I say this,
but I'm gonna say it anyway.
He pretty much taught me how video games were made,
along with Doug Sheehan.
Jacinda Chu, our art director,
who I had the utmost confidence could help define
our visual style for our world and characters.
Jon Paquette, our lead writer,
who is probably the most patient person
I've ever worked with,
and one of the best collaborators
any creative director could ask for.
And then there's Bobby Coddington, our animation
director, who no challenge is too big for Bobby.
And what I loved about him was that he
would push me as hard as he would push his own team
to make something incredible.
And then there's Scott Mahalik, our lead project manager.
And I've known Scott since he was a teenager.
We worked together at GameStop.
And to tell you how old I am, it was called
Software Etcetera back then.
And what was great was he was always looking at the game
from two perspectives.
Of course, what we need to get done
is ship the game on time.
But because he was such a big gamer,
and I valued his opinion as a gamer,
he was also helping provide guidance on decisions
that would make the game qualitatively better.
These people, and several others
who became part of my leadership team,
like Doug Sheehan, our lead programmer,
and Cameron Christian, our lead designer,
are who I leaned on to help perfect this vision
and make me feel much more confident
in the creative direction of the game.
Now the next creative challenge of my journey
was collaborating with multiple stakeholders.
Most projects have two, your developer and your publisher.
But us, we had a third, Marvel Games.
Now on the positive side, all three groups
were extremely collaborative and shared a common goal
to make the best game possible.
And as you might expect, we received a lot of feedback
from the game from Sony and Marvel.
And sometimes there were differing opinions.
And that's not unusual.
If you come to Insomniac and you put three people in a room,
I can guarantee you they're going to disagree on things.
And that's normal.
That's what eventually makes things better.
That's game development.
But here's where I failed, and I failed miserably.
Hands down, the biggest failure I had on this project.
When issues were brought up by our executive team,
Sony and Marvel, I routinely would go in a room,
either by myself or with one or two people,
and try to solve the problem.
I would rarely bring it to the larger team.
In my mind, I was protecting them.
Like I said, we were talking about this being
the biggest game Insomniac ever made.
They already had so much work.
They already had a lot of stress.
I didn't want to burden them with something else.
But I quickly learned I was actually
doing the complete opposite.
I was actually alienating myself from the team.
They would make jokes like, oh my God,
it's been like a month since you've been
at the back of your desk.
And I learned, quite frankly, I was pissing them off.
So during development on Spider-Man, we actually
had an off-site leadership meeting
where all the execs, the leads, and directors came together.
And during that meeting, we talked
up a lot of different things.
But actually, at one point, actually, it
turned into how I could be doing a better job
as creative director.
And after two hours and taking a lot of pages of notes,
it kind of felt like this.
Now they kept saying, hey, we want to be more involved.
Come to us with a problem.
We're going to help you solve it.
And I also learned in this meeting
that I actually had the same habit of when I had
my own feedback on the game.
I would go right into solution mode
rather than saying the problem.
As this clip illustrated at the very end,
it was a real eye opener for me.
And truth be told, this was probably the most,
the toughest meeting I've ever sat through at Insomniac,
but it was probably the most informative.
So the answer to this challenge was full transparency
with the team and letting them be the owners of the solution.
After that meeting, any time we got feedback
from Sony or Marvel, it was sent out immediately to the team.
If I had my own issues with the game,
I would talk directly to the lead and the team
about my concerns.
I tried really hard to just state the problem, not
the solution.
And what I found was this was actually really freeing.
I had much more time to actually play the game,
look at it from a much higher level, big-picker perspective.
And when the team did need me to jump in on something,
I actually had the time to do it.
I feel like a good example of this was our combat system.
As we entered the final phase of development,
there were still some things we wanted to work on in combat.
And I quickly recognized, based on that feedback
I'd received during leadership meeting,
they did not need another cook in the kitchen
on a daily basis.
So what I basically did was I gave them
some high-level thoughts on what I thought about combat.
And I said, hey, anytime you want
someone to play the game and give you
some outside perspective, I'm your guy.
So that's pretty much what I did.
Every Friday afternoon, I would install a build on my dev kit.
I would take it home and play the game.
And I pretty much just write up my impressions on anything new
and send that feedback to our game director, Ryan,
our lead designer, Cameron, and our lead combat programmer,
Adam.
Again, I tried to focus my feedback
on my impressions and the changes I was having,
not giving them solutions.
So this gave the combat team complete ownership
at the task at hand.
And I gotta say, they did an amazing job.
And it sounds like really easy right now,
but I still struggle with this every single day.
State the problem, not the solution.
And of all three journeys we talked about today,
this is probably easily the most painful to look back on.
But I hope this is a section that all aspiring
creative directors can keep in mind
and learn from my mistakes.
And remember, even as a creative director,
it's okay to have fears, doubts, and insecurities.
But don't let them overwhelm or consume you.
Find people to help you improve
and be more confident in your vision,
even if that equates into some tough love.
Be transparent with your team.
Don't try to be a superhero and overprotect them.
It will most likely backfire
and lead to a very uninspired team.
So share feedback from your production partners
whenever you receive it,
and then hand over the problem to your team.
Get them invested in coming up with a solution.
I will bet you, more often than not,
what they deliver will be better
than anything you can imagine.
That's one of the magical parts of game development.
Now, I know there's some insomniacs in the crowd today,
and they know I like to end my presentations
with one more thing.
So I figured I'd keep that trend going today.
I want to tell you guys a story in the final moments
of development.
We were about six weeks away from gold.
It was after E3, and I was in a room reviewing
the final boss fight in the game, Pete versus Otto.
Now, this was hands down the boss fight
that went through the most iteration.
A lot of restarts from both narrative side, design side.
But I remember in that moment,
even with little bugs here and there,
some lighting issues, some sound effect issues,
I remember sitting in the middle of the room,
people flanked around me,
and I had this giant smile on my face.
I even think someone said, why are you smiling?
And because in that moment, I said to myself,
this was the perfect collision of Spider-Man and Peter's
Worlds colliding.
In that moment, I saw everything finally coming together.
The writing, the music, the animation,
all were elevating the stakes and the emotion of that moment.
In that moment, I saw that the team had not only
created a great superhero adventure,
but also a memorable human story, something
we were pushing from day one.
And in that moment, I started to realize,
maybe for the first time, that the team had faced and overcome
our creative challenges.
As I mentioned earlier, this was a coming of age story
for Peter, but honestly, it was one for me
as a creative director.
Like Pete, this game presented me
with a number of challenges.
I suffered a lot of failures, as I said.
But eventually, thanks to a number of people
in SOMIAC, Sony, and Marvel,
we developed different strategies on how to conquer them.
In the end, it's just like Peter relying on MJ,
Miles, and Aunt May to help him fully realize his potential.
As you return to your own studios
to continue work on your current projects,
I hope my talk today can help you overcome
some of the challenges you're either currently facing
or will face in the months and years ahead.
Thank you so much for coming here today,
and I hope you enjoy the rest of your day.
I've practiced that about 45 times and I finally hit the exact number I wanted.
So, good.
All right.
And if anybody has questions, feel free to fire away.
Hi.
So, I have to ask, with the release of Into the Spider-Verse, when you watched it, was
there anything that you were like,
Dang it, we should have done that.
I mean, I think just more admiration for what they did,
from the art style to the banter between all the characters.
I think they just took some big creative risks.
I know, thinking about how many playable characters we had
and all the different Spider-Men,
when I heard about they were doing the idea of Spider-Verse,
I was like, how are they gonna juggle and make sense of that?
Because it's a kind of a complicated storyline,
especially if you've read the comics.
But I think what was amazing is they took that complex situation and made it very, very
simple to understand.
And again, I think what's great about that story is, again, you have that great superhero
action, but at the end of the day, it's a very human story about Miles and learning
to be a superhero.
All right.
Thanks.
You're welcome.
Oh, I'm going to go that way.
All right.
So we've heard a lot about the heroes of the game today, but I'd like to talk a little
bit about the villains.
What were some of the biggest creative challenges introducing the Sinister Six?
a lot. I would say, or I probably would say, one thing I didn't talk about in this talk,
but we probably spent as much time, if not more, on getting the villains right. Something
we talked about is we wanted them to be the heroes of their own story. And that's why
we spent so much time with Otto.
You know, you see him, obviously,
the first time you see him, a lot of Marvel fans will say,
hey, he's gonna become Doc Ock.
And then what we did was, we purposely
humanized him a lot to the point
where I wanted people to say, was he
gonna become the villain or not, almost like hoping he doesn't.
And obviously he turns. So we spent
a lot of time, and then we realized,
how do we elevate the stakes? How do we
show a more mature Spider-Man who's been, a more
experienced Spider-Man who's been doing this for eight years,
let's give him his biggest threat ever, six villains
at the same time.
I would say the same thing on Mr. Negative.
We spent a lot of time, how do we humanize,
how do we make him much more relatable,
not just a mustache-trolling villain
because he wants to destroy the city
for whatever reason, right?
So yeah, I think when you're working on something,
any game, if you can make your villain
as interesting as your hero, it's a win-win.
Awesome. Thanks for sharing your experiences. It's really cool to hear all that stuff.
Could you elaborate a little bit more on the game design or gameplay side,
like some thematic areas you tried to focus on or core pillars of design?
Sure. I mean, well, I think the first minute we knew we were making a Spider-Man game,
we had to say those webs better attach to buildings.
I mean, I think the thing is we wanted to make sure that we didn't want to make a hardcore game.
It was about...
Spider-Man, everybody, Spider-Man is such a well-known over the world.
We want to make the game as accessible as possible.
Obviously, have a level of skill, but we beat in our brains over and over again, make this
game so everybody can feel like a hero.
And with more skill, they feel like a greater superhero over time.
So we really, from a combat traversal to our boss fights, we really want to keep that across
the board.
And then it's just, you know, balancing.
the superhero nature of the character,
but then also how can we make someone like Peter
or Miles or MJ playable?
So again, not only thematically saying
we want to make a human story,
but also delivering that in gameplay as well.
So from Peter working at helping Aunt May a feast
to actually working in the lab,
to being MJ in the Grand Central Terminal,
to Miles being chased down by Rhino,
we want to make sure all those elements were in there.
Awesome, thank you very much.
Welcome.
Thank you very much for the talk.
It was excellent.
Appreciate it.
Thank you.
So I'm curious.
You mentioned earlier some of the deliberate new stakes
that you put in the ground for this version of Spider-Man.
Aunt May running the homeless shelter,
and reporter Mary Jane, and so on.
Did you have challenges working with Marvel as the IP holders
making those changes?
So you just asked the second most question I've ever
gotten asked about Marvel.
No, I mean, actually.
That was the thing that probably surprised me,
because probably a lot of people were thinking,
like, oh, they're the license holder.
They're going to put all these restrictions on us.
And they quite frankly didn't.
They were actually more pushing us to try new things
more than anything, because the worst thing I didn't want,
I think we all didn't want people to say, like, oh,
I read that story.
I've read that story already, or I've seen that in a movie.
So they were actually pushing us to.
to go try different things.
The thing we talked about a lot was
respect the DNA of the franchise,
but not be afraid to mix things up.
For example, you know what we,
if you played the end of the game,
you know what happens to a certain character, right?
That was a big deal, and I actually thought
there's no way in hell that they're gonna go for it.
And we actually went back and forth
about whether that person was gonna have that fate,
and I remember we went on holiday break.
and coming back.
So originally, that wasn't going to happen to her.
You guys probably all know what happens.
And so originally, she was going to be saved.
And then I came back, and I sat down
with Bill and Eric, our lead producer on Marvel.
And I said, hey, I had some people who
are new to the studio play it.
they feel this way.
I haven't slept all vacation because I think that this needs to happen.
What do you guys think?
And they said, we're actually having the same thoughts over break.
Let's go for it.
And because they want to make sure, did we earn it?
It was more about earning the things we wanted to do and having reasons for it rather than
just like, we didn't want anything to be out of shock value.
So once they understood that and we were laying the track
for things that were gonna happen,
they were very comfortable with some of the risks
we wanted to take.
So they were great partners.
I also think for us it helped that they're only 15 minutes
down the road from our offices.
So like anytime we would go one or two more emails,
we're like, can you just come over?
And we would just come talk about it in person
and we would solve it pretty quickly.
So they're great partners and we loved working with them.
Cool, thank you.
Thank you.
Question.
Yes, so you mentioned planning for unknowns
and keeping a set amount of time scheduled
for whatever you need it for.
Was there a point in production, like near the end,
when you're going, oh, that you found some unknown time
left over, and you're like, oh, can we
start using this to add to the game?
Or how do you deal with that?
Because any developers want to make the game
as best as possible.
How do you deal with, we have extra time,
but we can't use it.
So.
What I talked about is something I wish we did more of.
I don't think we planned enough for unknowns.
Like, I think that, and it's funny,
when I was a producer, I remember on Sunset Overdrive,
I actually had unknown blocks.
But what happens is, the game kind of just grows naturally,
and you're like, I'll just start filling in
those, that unknown time.
And then what happens is you're filling in for scope
rather than filling in for things
that are actually gonna not work.
So I think that,
it's just this constant battle, not battle,
but it's conversation you have to have with your team
to say like, I know you want more,
but you're gonna want rework rather than more.
And that's something like,
part of me putting in the presentation
was to like force myself to remember this going forward
of like, more doesn't always equal better.
Iteration and rework actually leads to a better experience.
So I just think it's something like.
you gotta do it before you can actually achieve it, I guess.
Like, you just gotta, you know,
I can imagine, like I mentioned Scott,
I could totally imagine me going,
you're crazy, just do it, do it,
just add it to that schedule.
I hope he pushes back on me going forward.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Question.
Brian, thank you so much, just for working on the game.
You're a really cool dude, and I gotta say,
like, Spider-Man brought me to tears at the end of the game.
So my question is,
Your characters are all very emotional, and I was just wondering, do you in your studio
get just as emotional working on it?
I've cried in meetings.
Yeah, I definitely have teared up when I've seen certain scenes.
I've also probably cried to say, can we please do this?
But no, I mean, hopefully you guys can tell,
I'm pretty much an open book, and I wear my emotions
on my sleeve.
And our goal was to make it a very emotional story.
Like, we wanted the highs of the humor,
but we also wanted that very relatable human story.
So us having moments where that were pretty.
tough to watch.
What I knew when some story themes were clicking
is like that final scene that you see in the game,
one of our actors who was actually not in that scene,
she actually ran off stage
because she couldn't watch the actual recap.
And I was like, all right, well,
we're doing something right here.
It's probably one of the reasons why I fought
to keep that scene.
But yeah, I mean, we're in a very collaborative studio,
we're a very emotional studio.
I think that's what you can see in our games.
I wouldn't want to go on this journey with any other people.
What you see is Insomniac's version of Spider-Man
definitely thrown through.
That's awesome.
Thank you very much for everything.
Thanks for the question.
Hi, you somewhat referred to this a little bit earlier in your talk, but I wanted to
ask about when you're working on a product that is something that you have a lot of experience
within your past, you're super passionate about, and not just you, but literally everybody
on the team is the same way.
How do you help...
focus that energy to stop people from going off in many different directions
because everybody has super excited and wants to contribute their own ideas and
things but it can easily get out of hand. How do you help focus that in a
productive way?
I think two ways.
One is the pillars of your game.
Establish the pillars of the game really early.
Like, we talked a lot about this game being a grown-up
Peter Parker, so a 23-year-old, more experienced
Spider-Man, this idea of a human story.
We talked about a superior Spider-Man.
We're really leveraging the idea of acrobatic
improvisation, the swinging being very accessible.
When people start to fan out and come up, bring it back to
the pillars.
If it's supporting the pillars, go for it.
The other thing, again, is mentioning
the DNA of the character.
Once you define that DNA of the character.
Like you said, if it's someone like Spider-Man who's,
like you said, so many different ways
you can come to this character,
bring it back to across any medium,
are those attributes still there?
And if they don't, just say, hey, no,
this isn't the DNA of the character we're talking about.
I know you're passionate about it,
but this is the way that we're thinking about it.
It's a really fine line because you want,
you don't wanna discourage somebody, right,
from coming up with a great idea.
But just my advice is bring it back
to the pillars of the game,
bring it back to the DNA of the character,
and more often than not, I think the,
the conversation will go in a positive direction.
But, you know, it's one of those things,
it's a struggle, like I said,
it's the Spider-Man or the character they have in their head,
it's hard to,
you don't want to upset that,
so I think you go back to those pillars in the DNA
and you'll be in good shape.
All right, I have one follow-up question.
Sure.
How do you get people aligned behind those pillars and that DNA that you've established?
Because you know...
You stand in front of a microphone and you go, this is the way we're making it.
No, I mean, I think if they see how passionate you are and they understand that you believe
in the character and you're passionate about doing it right, that they will follow.
And then also, like I said...
Handing, because when I pitched the game originally,
there are so many things I didn't know
what was gonna happen.
So making them invested in coming up
with how we can solve it,
how we can bring this character to life
through the story, through the missions,
through the world.
Once you give them ownership of it,
they're much more invested to be part of that team.
So I just get, bring them into the fold
as much as possible to solve those problems
that you will eventually face.
Thank you.
Hi, so you've talked about creative and character pillars a lot and how it's really important
to stick to them and evangelize them throughout the project.
Were there any pillars that you had to make major pivots on or change or abandon as you
went through?
Yeah, I think one of the pillars at the end of the game, at the beginning was, I think
a city with a mind of its own.
We wanted to push more of some of the world systems
that we had, and we just, at the end of the day,
had to make choice on priorities and scope.
And we knew right away that we wanted to make a superhero
that felt really good from a combat traversal standpoint.
We wanted this very human story.
We just said, hey, this is where we're gonna put
our emphasis right now, and some of the world elements
may not be part of that original vision.
So we still put a lot of time, and I'm really proud
of the things we did put in our world.
But we probably didn't achieve the first thought I had in my head.
Maybe I was over scoping from the start.
So that's probably where we had to make some,
I mean, I mentioned the idea about features and priorities.
That's one of the choices we had to make.
Thanks.
Yeah.
We're there.
Hey you, I saw you yesterday.
Well, hello, good to see you again.
Thanks so much for doing this talk.
But one thing that really stood out to me about everything
you just said that I thought was really interesting
is you talked a lot about your personal journey,
kind of as you were, as a first-time creative director,
going through this process.
And you mentioned a lot of things
that you had to learn and things that you're currently learning.
So based on that, as someone who's a writer and producer,
and also trying to make sure I learn things
and hold myself to account to improve,
do you have any particular strategies in your head
that you go to when you're like,
well, I want to make sure I keep doing this,
so this is what I should do to hold myself accountable?
Actually, sometimes I lean on other people,
like other people on my team actually remind me,
like Ryan Smith, he's the game director that I work with,
he will, sometimes I'll get in the habit of like,
oh, I'm gonna go solve this, and he's like,
no, what if we do the brainstorm?
And I'm like, oh yeah, let's get the team together.
And then I just did that last week.
And it totally worked.
And what came out of that brainstorm
totally helped on something we're working on.
So again, I think it's sometimes asking other people to say,
hey, if I start doing this, remind me that I'm screwing up
and get me back on track.
So that's what I started doing.
Thank you.
Oh, we're done?
Good to see you again.
All right.
Oh, I can, I can, I can ask,
you can ask the question after, for sure.
All right, well thank you everyone.
Thank you so much for attending.