Good afternoon.
Note to self, don't schedule yourself opposite destiny.
So this is Patrick Zadel.
Patrick Zadel is a former professional e-sports athlete, e-sports player.
He's retired about a year ago.
He's 23 now, I think.
And when he was playing, he realized, wow, sometimes my ears ring a lot.
And then they started ringing more.
and then they started ringing more, and he did some Googling, and he realized, I have tinnitus, which is a constant ringing in his ear, and now the ringing doesn't go away, so he's now got permanent tinnitus.
And after some more Googling, he kind of realized, I think I gave this to myself.
So Patrick's game was a tactical five-on-five shooter, where hearing footsteps is his paycheck.
So in order to hear those really, really quiet footsteps that are asymptotically, logarithmically soft away, far away, he would crank the volume like insanely loud levels so he could hear those quietest footsteps.
But of course, when the flashbang grenade goes off next to him, it was really, really loud.
So a combination of playing really, really loud, because that's what his paycheck depended on,
and the fact that he plays for long hours.
He practices, he plays.
He realized he gave himself tinnitus.
I met Patrick in Geneva this last summer at the World Health Organization.
I started doing some pro bono work for them last May or June because they're very interested in video games as a potential source of hearing health problems.
And they've created something called their Make Listening Safe initiative to look at hearing health for the population in general.
And it's a big problem.
Hearing health
The inability to hear well has all sorts of downstream health ramifications from increased risk of Alzheimer's, depression, not to mention, of course, the fact that people are not able to enjoy the work that we all create here.
So who here either has an iPhone or an Android?
Yeah, 100% of hands go up.
I don't know.
You'd have to ask that question.
Has anybody with an Apple Watch ever had this pop up?
Yep.
Angles go up.
So a couple of years ago, the World Health Organization, working with Apple, working with Google, and working with the ITU, actually created something, a specification, for hearing safety on these sorts of devices.
People listen to music with their earbuds in.
They listen for too loud, for too long.
They've got their watches to tell them things,
And they implemented what's called the WHO ITU H.870 spec, Guidelines for Safe Listening Devices and Systems.
It first came out in 2019.
It was updated recently in 2022.
Here's the World Health Organization version of the spec.
Here is the little bit more buttoned up ITU version of the spec.
I kind of like that one better.
But what it does is it specifies, amongst other things, under what circumstances should devices that play music to your ears either provide some warnings or notifications to the user, to the listener, or perhaps automatically lower the volume down, which we'll do in some cases as well.
So that was a very, very successful initiative.
They got something into devices that virtually every person carries through this WHO ITU 8.870 spec.
through their Make Listening Safe initiative.
So what are they doing now?
They deliberately left video games off of the ITU 870 spec.
They just felt they didn't know the space well enough.
They wanted to get something out.
What feature are you going to cut in order to ship?
They cut video game systems and devices.
So they are in the middle right now of writing a, there's no number for it yet or anything,
but writing an analogous specification for us in the video game industry.
So they started the ITU, WHO, Global Safe Standard for Listening in Video Game and eSports initiatives as part of the Make Listening Safe campaign.
So a goal is to create a spec kind of analogous to the one adopted by Google and Apple.
Another is that they do have an awareness campaign.
They just published an article.
It got picked up by most of the press in January about hearing safety in general.
So there's community awareness going on.
And also, they started reaching out to the development community, which is kind of how I got involved, again, to help them better understand how people play games, how people make games, how game systems work, and so on.
So that's kind of what they're doing.
And like I said, part of what they're going to likely be working on are what would analogous features to what we have on our iPhones and Apple iWatches and so on, what sorts of things would we put into things like game consoles or gaming devices and so on.
So that's part of what they're doing.
We're not going to talk really too much about that, except that if you are interested in that, I'll have some contact information at the end.
Let me know.
By all means, we would love you to be part of the conversation.
So one of the things I also did want to do was reach out to us, to game developers, particularly those on the audio side of things.
And towards that, for example, at GameSoundCon this last October, by pure happenstance, the head of this initiative at the WHO, Dr. Shelly Chadha, happened to be in Los Angeles.
And she actually took an Uber.
I invited her to become part of my opening remarks at GameSoundCon this year.
And literally, she took an hour, hour and a half Uber from southern LA up to Burbank, where she spoke for 10 minutes, and then went back to doing the business that she did.
So they're very, very passionate about this particular thing.
And her big point is that this is a very real threat.
WHO estimates that 3 billion human beings will have significant hearing damage in their life if things don't change on their current course.
And for us in games, it's kind of an interesting thing.
There's nothing necessarily more about games that makes games more damaging to your hearing than, say, watching a movie or something like that.
But we do kind of have a bit of a triple threat here.
One is that if we are successful, people play our games a lot.
I think Baldur's Gate is about 120-hour playthrough.
I certainly know people, very, very close family members who play many, many hours a week, tens of hours a week.
So that's one of the problems.
Not problems.
It's a success of us, but it's a potential thing to worry about that people play our games for long periods of time.
They play at loud volumes.
Many people play games pretty loudly.
And they're playing with headphones.
By the way, that's a chat GPT image, the guy with the sound waves coming out of his ears.
We got more.
And studies show, and in talking with some of the publishers and so on, that about half of our customers, about half of our players, play with headphones on.
That's up a significant amount from a dozen years ago or so.
In fact, so much so that a lot of us mix our games with headphones on as well as with speakers.
I had coffee with Emily Ridgway at Valve, and she's got this wonderful tree of headphones that, because they all sound so different, she wanted to figure out, oh, what do these different headphones sound like?
What sounds sound good in them?
So headphone listening is definitely a very, very big thing.
And to be frank, biology is going against us.
It's fun to listen loud.
This is another chat GPT image.
This is make me a realistic picture of somebody rocking out loudly while playing a video game.
Not super careful on how they count hands, but.
But so it turns out that there's part of our, we don't use it for hearing, but it's still part of our auditory system called the sacculus.
The sacculus is in the inner ear that's particularly sensitive to low frequencies at high dB levels.
Again, we don't use it for hearing, but it does sort of activate at about 90 decibels.
And it's got a connection to the hypothalamus.
And yeah, that's the part of the brain that deals with hunger, sex, and sort of hedonistic responses to things.
So it literally is more pleasurable to us to experience loud.
And anybody who's played in a band or been in a concert or loves Mahler without brasses blaring, it's just something, yeah, something that's really cool.
So it's something that we are definitely fighting against.
It's, we kind of want to turn ourselves up to, this is the first meme I ever made.
So for this talk here.
All right.
So how does this, you know,
Super, super good on the biology.
This is what it looks like inside our ears.
I'm sure we've all heard that we have hair cells in our ears.
We actually have two different sets of hair cells.
Those top hair cells are called the inner hair cells.
Those are the only hair cells that are actually connected to nerves.
So those are the ones we actually use to hear.
Those bottom hair cells, those three rows, they're called the outer hair cells.
Their job is simply to mechanically amplify sounds.
We'll get to that in just a second.
But it's really that top line that is the thing that changes vibrating air molecules to transducing through the three bones in our inner ear to liquid in our cochlea that wiggle these hairs.
This is how we hear.
And of course, if we listen for a little bit too loudly for too long,
this is what happens.
In fact, the hairs stay bent over, and our body determines that they are dead, and that they don't regrow.
Instead, actually, literally, like a scab forms over where they used to be, which is why there's empty space, not sort of, you don't see the dead hair cells there.
So, those outer hair cells are really, really important.
Without our outer hair cells,
This would be our limit of our hearing.
So we literally would hear nothing below 60 decibels if we did not have those outer hair cells.
The outer hair cells act as a nonlinear amplifier for, and this is the curve that represents the amplification, it's a mechanical amplification that the outer hair cells do that bring the level of the vibrations up to the point where our inner hair cells can actually detect, move enough so that we detect sound.
And in the audio world, this is an upward compressor.
So literally, mechanically, we're providing variable gain.
At very, very soft levels, we're providing lots of gain.
At higher levels, our auto-rehearsals provide little or no extra gain.
And this is why, by the way, if somebody is hard of hearing, you don't shout at them.
Because the upper range of their hearing is normal like anybody else, it is just that the softer sounds are not amplified up to the range where our inner hair cells can actually detect sound.
So this is why hearing damage is so insidious.
They say an ounce of prevention is worth a pound of cure, except in our case, there's no cure.
So it's kind of problematic.
So the thing that you want to track if we're talking about either our own hearing health or our players' hearing health is dosage over time.
It's like a Geiger counter.
You can be exposed to so much radiation for a certain number of minutes.
If you're exposed to twice as much radiation, you better be in the room half as long.
And it's just like that with sound as well.
And this is called the equal energy principle.
If I listen for four hours at 80 decibels on Monday and two on Sunday, that's the same as if I had listened for six hours in one day.
And here's an example, by the way, of some LUFS output from a couple of different games.
The second one, it's a little bit more steady, very, very high levels, where
dynamic range of the first one gives a lot more opportunity for our ears sort of to breathe and so on.
So the WHO and international standards have come up with what are safe listening levels?
How loudly can we listen for how long in a recreational setting?
There are different numbers for occupational settings, right, where there's a factory stamping machine going 24 hours a day.
For recreational listening,
What they have settled upon is 80 decibels A-weighted, DBA, for 40 hours a week.
And every three decibels of increased listening level halves the amount of safe listening time.
So at 86 decibels, it's not 40 hours a week that is safe.
It is only 10 hours a week that is safe.
And at 100 decibels, it's like five minutes, six minutes that is safe.
So the WHO did a survey and also a survey of literature to kick this thing off.
And one thing that they found was people, when they are playing games, are playing louder than 80 decibels.
And they're playing for, in some cases, more than 10 hours a week.
So people generally are listening at unsafe levels.
Certain subsets of our players are playing loud and playing for long periods of time.
They do set different levels for children versus adults.
That's what the mode two was, is the same thing but for kids.
So it's definitely a little bit of a problem.
So some of the other results of their surveys were people did not perceive themselves as being susceptible to hearing loss.
That makes sense.
Gamers are, for the most part, kind of young, and young people kind of feel pretty invincible in general, much less for something where slow dosages over a period of decades will result in hearing loss when they're 75 or 80.
So that kind of makes sense.
They do believe that reducing volume would limit gaming enjoyment.
A year ago, I would have rejoiced at that statement.
But it is something we need to keep in mind.
Like I said, we're fighting against the sacculus and the fact that it's more fun to listen loud.
That said, half of the response to this survey said that they were interested in learning more about this thing, because it's sort of like smoking.
People do not want lung cancer, so they realize they shouldn't smoke.
And so, yeah, I kind of want to know more about that.
Yeah, this is kind of the survey of the results there.
Now, some listening habits that they have.
These were done on Windows systems, and the average volume setting was 56%.
56% on Windows system volume is about, I measured it just the other day, I think it's about minus eight decibels from peak.
So they're down a little bit.
21% listen at high or very high
volume settings, where high was defined as the system volume was greater than 60% or very high, greater than 80%.
So one in five people, system volumes while they're playing games are pretty loud.
Of course, one thing that was kind of cool is three out of four said they believe that sounds are either extremely or very important.
That's yay us again.
So that's good.
But it is problematic.
Right?
Time spent with gaming is associated with higher odds of hearing loss.
That was one of the findings of the survey.
People who game more tend to start to have some hearing problems.
Gamers who played more frequently were more likely to game at higher volumes.
So that's that double whammy of dosage, right?
Time at a certain volume times the level at which you are actually listening.
Four, five, and ten reported having heard ringing in their ears after playing a game session at least once.
So there's definitely some things to look at here from a safety perspective.
So as game developers, are there things that we can do to make people play the games we have?
We want them to play long periods of time.
We want them to hear our stuff.
But are there anything we can do?
And to be frank, this is an open question.
This is one of the things we're trying to figure out.
This is a new topic for us.
Right, we haven't thought of this, another chat GPT image, except I did Photoshop the Wwise mastering plug-in into the Thought Bubble there.
So yeah, this is not something, I don't know about you, I had never really given this a second thought.
So it's not something we had thought about, the exception being Rob Bridget, who has thought about this, of course, because Rob Bridget has thought about everything.
But it does seem kind of close to some things that we have worked on.
So accessibility, loudness standards.
Boy, I remember being at the Fairmont talking about loudness standards at GDC.
listening environments like nighttime mode, audio customizability, advanced audio settings, these sorts of things.
And again, you know, several years ago, Sony, Microsoft kind of joined forces to help create the mix recommendations that standard minus 23 lefts we're kind of at right now.
A lot of games have very cool audio options with headphone bass boosts and different kinds of customizability.
This is from, is this from God of War Ragnarok?
I think it is.
Yeah, of course somebody here knows that.
So yeah, different levels of dynamic range, right?
So that if I don't want my gunshots to be quite so loud, maybe I can play my game at a more limited dynamic range.
Some devices actually do implement some of these warning features already.
This is the manual from, I forgot if it's Oculus Go or Oculus Quest.
But to prevent hearing loss, do not listen at high volumes.
That's warning in the manual.
And actually, you will get a visual alert if you've been listening in this VR experience, in some VR experience, for too loud for too long.
Now, there obviously are a lot of challenges.
The biggest is the last mile problem.
It's all good for us to talk about how we create our games and the volume levels we set.
We don't know what the person's headset is, right?
An 80-ohm headset versus a 30-ohm headset versus a 250-ohm headset are going to be massively, like orders of magnitude different SPL levels to the eardrums.
So WHO is fully cognizant of that.
There are some initiatives to try and deal with that that are kind of fun for us long term, like headphones that tell you the exact SPL level that are going to the ears, which we can then do things like, you know, Fletcher months and compensated listening, its volume controls and things like that.
So those are a little bit down the road.
But their idea is that we can make a meaningful impact while working on a little bit longer term solution.
So what we have here is a call to action.
The idea of this talk, it's a 30 minute talk, so it's a quick one, is just to introduce the topic to the industry a little bit.
We had a little bit of a panel at GameSoundCon on it, continuing it here at GDC.
So part one is just, if you're interested in being part of the conversation, come join and be part of the conversation.
We'd love to get your input on this topic in general.
Consider hearing health in the same way you might consider accessibility, or those sorts of things.
Or it's something maybe we can start thinking about.
How might we change a little bit of the way we make our games, not to diminish the content we want to make, the emotional content we want to make, but with just something like this in mind.
I think also being aware of how our players are listening to our games could be really helpful.
There's a lot of not, we have a lot of opaque areas where we're not really quite sure what's going on.
So telemetry data, audio analytics, right?
Have your games report back to you, back to home base, what people's volume slider settings are at or what their system settings are at and things like that.
Play testing, trying things out to see how it affects how loudly people listen and so on.
And the kinds of telemetry data we might want to collect.
Are you listening on a headphone or speakers?
What options are people setting?
And again, this is non-intrusive stuff.
This is stuff you can just get by calling APIs.
USB versus analog.
What's the level of chat versus game versus sound effects versus music and so on.
Game volume settings, system volume settings, things like that.
So another interesting call to action might be thinking about what kind of features might you want to implement in your game
that could lead to a lower sound pressure level experience for the player, less loudness at the headset, without compromising our experiences.
Loudness setups, more granular audio sliders.
Back to Patrick, when he realized that he had literally damaged his hearing, he wrote a little piece of Windows software.
He's a programmer, too.
And what this piece of Windows software did, again, the game he did was a five-on-five tactical shooter.
Which means that unless you win There are long periods of the game where you're just spectating right you die you're out of this round until the next round And he realized hey when I'm spectating after I've been killed I'm still hearing the game at this full volume and so he simply wrote a piece of software that detects when He is dead
And it literally reached into the Windows system volume and lowered the Windows system volume by like 15 or 20 decibels.
And then when his software would detect that he was no longer dead and active in the game, it would bring it back up again.
So things like that might be something, you know, that was something he implemented so that he could practice.
He can't use that kind of software in a tournament, but when he was practicing, he would use the software such that
He could still get the experience, but only when he wanted it.
He didn't need that high volume dose when he wasn't even active in the game.
So things like that.
If you are an educator, definitely call to action for you all.
There's lots and lots of areas.
We could sit down and think of 15 to 20 either undergrad or master's thesis projects, things like listening habit studies.
the effects of left level on an in-ear SPL and you know what if we make our logo screens louder or softer how does that affect how loudly people play their games user behavior for different all sorts of studies that kind of could be done so if you're an educator and you have students who are interested in hey I might want to publish a paper that you know how we call this talk how to get a paper referenced by the WHO in three easy steps just make it about hearing health and video games
I can't guarantee anything, but boy, that will be read by the WHO within days of it being published.
Another call to action, be nice to your own ears.
What this graph is, is what's called TTS, or temporary threshold shift.
So when we expose ourselves to loud sounds, like
I remember being 22 years old and mixing my band in the studio, and it was cranked up, and it was rock and rolling.
It was really fun.
After loud exposure to sounds drastically changes the frequency response of our ears.
So this is 115 dBA, which is pretty loud.
That's a loud band at a club, but for just 20 minutes.
After that,
You've got a 50 decibel notch at 3 kilohertz, which totally is going to screw up your mixes.
And even 24 hours later, that top green one, even 24 hours later, you've still got 6 or 8 or almost 10 dB of a notch in your hearing a full 24 hours after going to a concert.
So yeah, long sound design mixing sessions, excessive levels will distort your hearing.
So take care of your own hearing.
You know, many mixers and so on never go anywhere without earplugs.
You mix, you're really loud in your mixing session, the next morning you come and listen to your mix, like, why is it so bright?
Well, it's bright because while you were mixing at the end of the night, you had a giant notch in your high mids there.
So if you are interested in this topic, drop me an email.
This goes straight to my inbox, hearing at gamesoundcon.com.
And with that, I'll open it up to any questions anybody might have.
Yes, please walk up to the microphone so that the folks at home can have a chance.
And we've got like four minutes for questions before we take it to the walk-up room.
Yes.
Hi.
Thanks so much for putting those in this presentation.
I'm just curious with regards to VR headsets like the Quest 3, the in-headset speakers, it's going to be very difficult for them to produce low-frequency information.
And as we discussed today, or as you discussed today, gamers like to hear, or everyone likes to hear that low-frequency information to make it feel good.
What would be the best practice to help reduce the chances of harm from players trying to boost the volume on their headset speakers to get that sensation?
Yeah, that is a great question.
And my guess is I saw Scott's cell phone out here.
My guess is there is like half of a team at Metta working on that.
Getting low frequencies out of small transducers is challenging.
And we do want to try and make sure our systems aren't designed such that people overcompensate.
for not having the low end by just cranking it up really loud.
There have been some attempts to work at this.
One is use of things like max space technologies, missing fundamental phenomena and so on.
But yeah, there's no perfect solution for that right now.
So yeah, it's a great question.
And it's a creative challenge that we need to solve.
OK, thanks a lot.
Again, thank you so much for all of this information gathered in one place.
I'm curious what you or the WHO might be doing with eSports tournament organizers or leagues who will often put on a secondary set of headphones on top of the in-ears that a lot of the competitors are using for communications or in-game sound in order to blast white noise or pink noise at them to mute the audience, basically.
Yeah, that's a great question.
If you're in an eSports tournament, first of all, you're probably wearing deep in-ear monitors, over the top of which you're wearing acoustically, minus 30 dB things, to which they sometimes pipe in white noise so that the gamers don't get an advantage by listening to the shoutcasters, the announcers announcing the thing.
That is definitely something the WHO is looking at trying to have some more safety standards around for players, because it's not healthy for players.
Now, the only mitigating factor is that that is a pretty small scenario.
It does not happen in the context of numbers of human beings playing video games at loud volumes.
It's a very, very small thing.
But it's definitely one of the things that they're working on, and it's probably one of the reasons Patrick's hearing got as bad as it was.
I think we've got time for one more question before we take it up to the wrap-up room.
Yes?
Hi.
From what I remember, the monitoring standard for speakers is around 85 decibels, at least for film and TV.
Yep.
and I'm not sure if there is one for headphones, but I was just wondering if in order to protect your own hearing and make sure that your mixes are as good as possible without the effects of
losing like having that notch effect that you were talking about.
Would you recommend a revision to that standard and or a different
Behavioral change in terms of when you're mixing like Doing like a one-hour session here and there rather than a two-hour session like like wood spacing it out help Any long-term effects during during the week when you're working on a project
Yeah, it's a great question.
I definitely would not go as far as tell the entire audio industry that they should change their mixing level standards.
That said, taking breaks is an important part of the mixing process.
Again, it gives your ears a chance to rest.
So 80 decibels is the recreational.
85 is actually the occupational, so if you're working.
And that said, again, when we mix to 85, that's kind of where dialogue level we want to have.
it's
you
has enough softs versus louds that I don't see that as probably being an issue, as long as you take breaks.
Yeah, you need to give your ears a rest, not just for your hearing, but for your profession so that we're not making mixing decisions based upon the colorization because of TTS.
It's temporary threshold shift it's called.
So thanks so much.
Thanks for showing up and being interested in this topic.