Hey there, my name is Jason Grimblatt and I'm co-creator of a game called Caves of
Qud that's currently in Early Access.
Caves of Qud is an open-world, science-fantasy, roguelike epic where you chisel through a
layer cake of thousand-year-old civilizations.
Last year at GDC, I talked about procedurally generating in-game books.
This year, I'll be talking about generating whole in-game histories.
When you start a new game of Caves of Qud, a new history is generated as part of the world creation process.
Important places and artifacts that come out of the history are instantiated in the game world and placed on the world map.
Then, as you explore the world, you learn about the history bit by bit, by visiting historic sites, by talking to NPCs,
and by examining cultural artifacts like shrines, paintings, and engraved items, such as this dagger.
I plan to talk about how we took something as dauntingly complex as history and proceduralized
it in a way that jives with our design principles and the handwritten lore we'd already developed
for the game.
I'll use examples from two other games that generate history, Dwarf Fortress and Epitaph,
to define some patterns I see emerging in this blossoming subfield of procedural generation.
Finally, I'll point to some resources that'll help you procedurally generate histories in
your own games.
I hope to see you there!