All right, hello.
A couple quick reminders.
One, please turn off your cell phones.
Two, don't forget to fill out your survey
if you like the talk.
If you don't like it, don't fill it out.
Just kidding, fill it out either way.
And three, I would like to acknowledge
that we are currently being in San Francisco Bay Area.
We're occupying indigenous Ohlone land.
Just a quick.
something to be aware of.
And then before we get started, a quick note.
It's a perilous time that we live in right now
in the United States.
Fascism is creeping in and the Muslim travel ban
as well as the proposed border wall
I think are xenophobic bullshit.
And I just wanna take a second to appreciate
what a privilege it is for all of us
to be able to come to this conference
and to talk about games and to think about this.
There's a lot of developers who perhaps don't feel safe coming to this country and for very good reason.
And it upsets me that the current climate in this country and institutionalized racism
is discriminating against fellow game developers from being here, as well as fellow human beings.
Uh, with that being said, hi. This is Level Flow for a video game mixtape. I am Akuma.
There's my couple social media handles. Um, I also have a hashtag if you want to live
tweet any of this you can use hashtag GDC mixtape. Um,
you can see there I made a game called Freakin' Weekend,
or I'm finishing up at the moment.
We showed it at IndieCade last year,
and I'll talk more about that
and how it works with video game mixtapes shortly.
Quick couple notes about myself.
I'm from Los Angeles, I'm an LA native.
I'm part of a collection, a group of,
a community of indie game developers called QuidgeCity,
and I've been making games for about
three and a half years now.
And I'm also alumni of USC,
the University of Southern California,
specifically the School of Cinematic Arts,
their Interactive Media and Games MFA graduate program.
So, hopefully a lot of you saw the title,
Video Game Mixtape, and were kind of intrigued by that.
So we wonder, what is a video game mixtape?
And perhaps one day we'll have a vocabulary that doesn't rely on antiquated media.
to talk about games and what we're doing,
but for now it's fun to explore that.
So I would say that a video game mixtape
is an intentional collection of mini-games,
and the sum is greater than its parts.
I have mini-games in quotation marks
because I feel like the term mini-game
is a little problematic.
Mini is inherently inferior,
and it reinforces this capitalist idea
that the value of a game is related to its length.
I do like the term vignette games,
but video game mixtapes
aren't necessarily made of all vignettes,
so for now we'll just stick with mini-games.
So here's our track listing.
You can see we got through the intro,
we're going currently through what is a video game mixtape,
and I have a couple other tracks.
here, so we got some good stuff for you.
And before we go deeper, let's perhaps take a step back
and think what is a mix tape?
I think most of you here are old enough to have experience
whether it's on a cassette tape form or a CD,
some form of mix tape.
But basically you would record your favorite songs
onto a tape or a CD.
Perhaps you record them off the radio
or from another tape or from a computer.
But it took a while to make this physical media,
so you put a lot of thought into it.
And though I do want to see games that bring together
works from a bunch of different authors,
I think that'd be kind of hard because every code,
the code that everyone used to make games,
it's all separate.
So compiling that would be very difficult.
And besides, I'm a little bit more interested
in looking at the modern hip hop mixtape.
So here's a few hip hop mixtapes.
from the last couple years.
And hip-hop mixtape, typically you have a rapper
who's rapping on every track,
and they have guest producers, they have featured artists,
they have other musicians in,
and these guys are recording,
and women, they're recording dozens of songs,
so you can put together a mixtape to show off your skills,
to build up hype for your commercial album
that you're gonna release,
and really to show off your practice,
and your hustle, and your progress.
And I think that's a really cool
model to look at when we think about games.
So how could we adapt this format?
Well, thankfully it falls in line with,
I don't know if you've seen this Ira Glass,
he's a DJ with NPR,
and he talks about, you know,
we have this skills gap where we have taste,
good taste in games, as I'm sure a lot of you here have,
but the things that we make when we start,
they're not quite as good as what we like to think of.
So he advocates making a high volume of work in order to close that gap.
And it also falls in line with what,
this is Adriel and Rami, two people I met
my first year at USC, and they were talking about
doing a game a week, so this idea that you make
one game per week, and at the end of the week,
you toss out, or not toss out, but you just
competently abandon what it is that you made,
but it's just, you're rapidly making things
going through this process.
You know, think of the idea, prototype it,
test it, make it, refine it, repeat.
And I think that that's, you know,
really falls in line with this idea of
video game mixtapes. So that's what I did. I had to make a game while I was at USC for
my thesis. I had a year to put together a project. So instead of making one, I decided
I'm going to make dozens. I'm just going to make a bunch of little things and allow that
to build up my process. And then you can see I tied it together in this mobile phone interface
and all these little icons represent the different apps.
And in some ways too, this is my rapper struggle album.
You know, just very much struggling financially,
going through school, being a long distance relationship.
A lot of things were going on at that time in my life.
So, you know, this is sort of therapy in form of art.
So, you know, making a lot of things.
And I perhaps took that a little bit too much to heart.
Here's my Unity project folder where there's just tons
and tons of projects and actually counted recently.
And in the last year outside of freaking weekend,
which is my,
my thesis, I've made like 20 other game projects,
or 28 depending on how you cut them,
which is like crazy to me.
And not all of them have been released,
a lot of them are just kind of like really solid prototypes,
but again, it just speaks to this method of practice
to improve our skills.
But a couple notes,
if you are gonna make a video game mixtape,
you would want, rather than this,
to have all of your games inside of one project folder.
Um, and make sure your naming schemes are tight because a lot of times I just rely on typing to
search for the files that I want. As well as, um, don't fear short game experiences, especially
when you're making a mix. Uh, this is Joey Ramone from the punk band The Ramones. Um,
And a lot of punk rock songs can be very short,
but we don't really call them mini songs, right?
They're just songs, it's just music.
And there's a nice quote that I like
where someone asked Joey Ramone
about why the Ramone songs are all so fast,
and he said, or why they're all so short.
And he said, we actually play very long songs,
but we just play them very fast.
So I love it, I love that he flips it.
It's all relative anyways, what does it matter?
We should just make what we wanna make.
uh... this is the freaking weekend inspirations mix time you might
recognize some of these games are not going to go into
all of them but a lot of these games have the sort of uh... mix feel to it or
they
uh... variety of gameplay or in the gameplay a lot of times is really
relaxed as well so it's not like you
run the risk of losing or failing or not getting it as you play, you're going to get through
a lot of these experiences or they do something interesting with music or sound.
And for me, I realized that a lot of these influence my style to not just make experimental
work but things that are experiential.
So it's about the metaphor of what it is that you're doing,
but we want to use simple and fun mechanics to do that.
So we're gonna use the language of gameplay.
We're gonna use the language of feedback and juiciness
and teaching our player different things
in order to have them do these kind of metaphors.
And then the secret for video game mixtape
is before the player gets bored,
or normally when the difficulty would increase,
we just move on to the next game.
And that was side A.
Here we're gonna flip over the tape.
And move on to the B side, where we got Freakin' Weekend,
Lumpo, and Spooky Game Snacks.
Some other examples that we can look at.
Here's our updated track listing.
And actually, there's a typo.
Six and eight should be flipped.
But never mind that.
But yeah, Freakin' Weekend, I mentioned earlier.
This is my video game mixtape, my most personal one.
You can see it's in a mobile phone interface
and when people play it, it's like you're going
through someone's phone or perhaps you're performing as me.
So they're a little bit intentionally vague
as to who the player is when they're playing this
but it's very much using the affordances of the phone.
I wanna look at first a couple of micro examples
of level design of what I made
and then we'll look at the macro
of how they all fit together.
So here's an example, I'm sure a lot of you have,
you know, relate to coding and making games,
using Unity perhaps.
So this game I just sort of copied my setup from home,
and you know, you can type on,
if you look at the bottom phone,
you can see you just typing on the keyboard
and the text shows up.
So very much just about, you know, the joy of typing,
if you can get into typing code.
But you know, you can't type anything wrong,
you just type this, text shows up,
and then you can move on to the next.
level to ask if you want to save it and then you can move from there.
And a lot of these games that I made is just reflecting on my life, thinking if this was
a game, what would the mechanics be?
What would the player be doing?
What type of emotion would I want to tell doing this?
I made another game about...
meditation. I went to this Buddhist meditation retreat a couple years back and it had a pretty
big impact on me, talking about mindfulness and breathing. If you time your breathing to that
GIF up the top, if you feel anxious or whatever, it can help you to just relax. So I thought,
how can we turn that into...
a game and gameplay mechanics.
So we thought of this idea where you're touching the screen
and you're growing the circle,
sort of similar to what the shape is doing.
And then we put some mantras of people,
what they meditate, could meditate to,
thinking about in the back of your head,
as well as some fun visuals to really show,
to convey and teach this mindfulness breathing mechanic,
if you will, but the player is actually doing
the physical breathing while they're touching the screen.
I made a Gamergate game about Twitter, what it's like to have a Twitter hate mob descending
on you, because when I was working on this project, that was definitely...
Hap going on, I haven't, so in this game you can swipe to move the camera and when you
look at these little anime and game avatars they like cuss at you and say really mean
things to you.
And I wanted to create this sort of audio assault for the players, so as they clear
a certain number of them, or as they clear them more show up, and as they clear a certain
number of them I have different things that trigger, different audio things to make the
player feel paranoid, different things that I do to the environment.
to really ramp up that tension.
And I thankfully have not been the subject
of a Twitter hate mob, but back in the day,
I wrote a blog about this game
that had sort of racist imagery in it,
and a bunch of people descended on the comments
and said pretty awful things.
One of my favorites was someone saying,
fuck, Alejandro Cuadra, that's my legal name,
but this is from PSPGamers619.
And I think it's funny because it's 619 and not 69, like, I don't know.
I think it's funny now to look back at it, but at the time, too, it didn't feel good,
it felt pretty awful, because I was like, oh, my career is ruined, I can never work
in the games industry again, but obviously that's not true.
But you know, how do we express that feeling, how do we convey that to a player in gameplay?
A couple other examples is I have a game where you're rolling a joint and you're breaking
up weed and you blow it out the window.
And if you live at home with your mom, that's what you do when you don't want her to smell
it is you blow the smoke out the window.
So I wanted to put that in a game.
I have another one at the bottom.
You can see you're rotating this phone and as you rotate it, it's like a kaleidoscope
and the different shapes move.
That's my 94 Civic.
in there and you can tap on the diamonds, tacos will show up at some point.
It's a music toy, so as you rotate it, different notes will play and the beat's playing.
So it's really much just, you know, like a music video almost.
And it's a way that I could also make an homage to driving without actually building a driving
engine and having a whole driving game, because that's way too much work.
As well as I have here messages, a lot of these are actually from my phone at the time
when I made this, like what were the latest responses and messages I had with my friends
and I put those in there.
But it's done to do world building because people might read those snippets and be like
oh I wonder what that was about.
So it creates this whole sense of world even though I don't go through like explaining
or resolving some of those things, it's just to kind of make everything feel a little bit
more believable.
As well as I can put in different...
ARG or different mini games where you're messaging people
back and forth and different story elements
we can reveal that way.
And I also have the little star button at the bottom
and that's how you can navigate back
to the level select screen.
So some of the games they kind of channel you through
and some of them you can press it
and it'll knock you back to here.
This is my level select screen.
All right, so we made this example
but I made a bunch of pieces, now what do we do with them?
This is Sergei Eisenstein, who is a Soviet filmmaker and film theorist.
So you talk about this thing called montage, and there's other names for it now,
or people think of montage as being something different,
but the idea is that the order that people see different images in film
will affect how they interpret it.
The preceding image will influence what they think of the next one, etc.
So we can use that to our advantage.
Humans, like, we love stories.
We love hearing stories, we love telling stories,
we love thinking stories and figuring things out.
And that's great because then we can just put out
these different elements and the player,
when they play through them,
they're gonna start to figure out,
okay, what's the story, what's going on here?
So we don't have to be explicit about it as designers.
We can have it be intentionally vague
and still have a general idea of what we want it to be,
but we don't have to be explicit with it.
So it's great because it gives you a lot of freedom.
But yeah, montage.
So we can take like the uh coding game here and in the game after you test the game, the
phone pops up and you look at it and it knocks you or now you're playing the game or you're
testing the one that you are supposedly working on. Um and you can see this one's you
know sort of modeled after uh Space Harrier and Star Fox and some of these other games.
And this one, so if you look at the action beats,
the typing one's kind of fun, but it's kind of a lull too
because you're just kind of exploring this little space.
And then this other game where you're flying,
there's a really nice song that plays
and there's all this sort of more action
and it's intentionally a little bit more gamey
in that there's like a combo meter and like money,
but at the end there's a surprise twist
where I flip it on its head.
So we have this fun transition
and now we have a little bit more action going on.
So how do we move from this to another game?
Well, since we're using a mobile phone,
what I do is I have a little.
notification pop down to tell you that, oh, people responded to your message on the
Twitter or as I call it, Critter app. It's like creepy Twitter, so it's Critter as
opposed to Twitter. But, um, let you know that that's been updated. So when you tap
on that, um, banner, it then opens up the Twitter app. And then now we go from
having, you know, a higher, um,
state of tension a little bit to now we ramp it up dramatically so the player's
now getting really intense. I've had people say how
affecting playing this was because you're just hearing all this
negative things being said to you and even though it's not like personalized
explicitly towards each player
there's still that feeling where people internalize it.
So it's like, oh, okay, now I have the player in this sort of heightened state.
What do we do with that?
Because how do you, what do you go to next that doesn't seem kind of trivial or doesn't, isn't kind of weird?
So it seemed obvious to then go to the meditation game afterwards.
And I like that because it gives the player a tool that they can use to come down from...
not just like a literal tool in the game, but also like an internal tool that they can
use to, you know, sort of recollect themselves.
At one point I had a jump cut that took you from the Twitter game to the meditation game,
but people found that to be very disorienting, especially when they're trying to process
all this sort of negativity that's happening.
So instead I had another banner that pops down to tell you, oh, your meditation app
has been updated, so now you can tap on that.
to go or if you go back to the title screen,
the meditation app will be available as a new icon
for you to try out when you're ready.
So creating that space in between the apps
was really important to give the player
a little bit of room to process,
a little bit of room to breathe.
And then it's also like traditional game design
where you have a really intense gameplay moment
so you might have something where you're in a town
or you're doing something that's much more relaxed
to sort of balance out those more intense moments.
It can't be intense all the time.
So, you know, we want to take into consideration what's the emotional arc of the player.
Another example, so we have this weed smoking, rolling a joint, light puzzle game, which
is actually like a lot of work to make this one because apparently not everyone knows
how to roll a joint.
Some people didn't feel comfortable doing it.
Yeah, so I thought it was just funny, but it was a lot of little tricks I had to put
in here to sort of teach people how to do that.
And after you, you know, roll it, it goes in the first person and you can look around
the room.
You find the phone.
You pick up the phone.
and it goes into the driving game.
So, you know, now's this question,
this is kind of a more psychedelic game,
so is the player high right now?
Am I high right now and you're playing as me?
You know, it's intentionally vague,
but you know, there is some,
I do want you to think, you know,
that the weed effects carry over into the next one.
And then midway when you're playing through this.
you know, this psychedelic driving game,
I decided to interrupt it with a phone call from mom.
So then you have to talk to my mom,
and you have, you know, little chances
or options of what you can say to respond.
And I thought that was kind of funny
because like, who's gonna wanna play a game?
Hey, you wanna play a video game
where you talk to my mom on the phone?
Like, that sounds really stupid, right?
are not stupid, but like, you know, you're not gonna maybe,
only a special type of gamer
might be initially interested in that.
So I thought, how can we trick people
into having this conversation?
Well, we can bait and switch them.
You start off with a weed game.
Hey, that's fun, this is funny, look at me,
I'm rolling a joint, you know?
Oh, cool, now it's all trippy and psychedelic, oh shit.
Like, I've had people play the game
and then hand me the phone when it looks like it's ringing
because they thought that someone was calling me.
But it's like, I don't know,
that's part of the game, keep playing.
You know, so you kind of trick them into doing this.
And then most people then would say,
oh, well it's really like kind of.
boring, but not boring in a bad way, but in the way that it actually does feel when you
talk to your parents and they're telling you all these things and you're just trying to
move the conversation along.
So that was like a fun way to transition between those.
And then a secret slide here, the work in progress.
So I have a video chat one that's more just about the frustrations of video chat.
So you can see that as one.
Number two is sort of this sex dream that I had,
or that I wanted to make,
or actually it was like a sex scene,
but I wanted it to be about consensual sex.
I wanted it to be like healthy relationships
and stuff like that,
but I thought how can I work this into this game
because it seems kind of out of left field.
So my thought was what if we have
you know, the scene where you're doing a video chat,
and then when we jump into that one,
it's implied that it's more of a dream,
because then it puts it more about myself,
and like what I'm thinking,
as opposed to, you know, suggesting that it's with my partner
or something else, because that's a little bit weird.
And then after that scene,
we go into where you're in the room,
you're by yourself, and then you see a helicopter outside,
because for any of you that live in the hood,
a lot of times it's not uncommon
to wake up in the middle of the night to a helicopter
circling around your neighborhood looking for somebody.
So that was like an emotional beat
that I wanted to put in as well,
to kind of...
switch up the flow.
And then the last scene, I'm working with my friend
Paloma Dawkins, and we're doing this sort of like
mini adventure game, and it's not, you know,
just one scene, and there's things you can click on,
there's dialogue, and you know, a little bit of a sense
of progression, and this is an example too,
of when you make video game mixtapes, what you can do,
or at least when you're making these sort of short vignettes
is as a designer, I can build out the system.
She actually just drew a bunch of sketches
when we were hanging out, and then I chopped up
those sketches and put those in just so you can see
what the game's gonna look like.
So then I'm building out a lot of the pieces and then showing it back to her and then she comes back in and puts
The art in and that's kind of the beauty too is because when you're making these small pieces
I'm not asking an artist. Hey, do you want to commit to my project for the next two years and do all the art for it?
No, hey
Do you want to come in and do your magic on this one piece and just do a couple drawings and I can make them
work and do
You know make it work for what we're trying to do
uh... but yeah that's that's another chapter uh... here's update and as few
other examples that i want to look at
uh... this is lump of this is a
game that i made with a very talented artist uh... amy
Amy Huang, and she did some of the art on Freakin' Weekend.
So for here, we went through a similar process,
and she kinda got what I was doing
with the Freakin' Weekend as a mixtape,
so she kinda went in and did her own thing.
So we have these vignettes,
you can see you're putting stickers on the phone,
and it's like a gift from somebody.
Oh, it's about, we made this for the Yuri Game Jam,
so it's about, you know, unrequited love.
yeah, you know, attraction crushes between two people, or two youth.
So one, they're, you know, watching TV, and as you click on the TV to change the channels, it progresses the dialogue.
And then the bottom one, you can see, you click on the bottle caps, they fly around.
And all these mechanics were kind of driven by this idea of being in the suburbs and being
bored and how can we build a game around that. So we just got together and jammed and knocked
each of these pieces out. Um, this one's a little bit different though because it doesn't
really require a certain order. If we can weekend, I do want you to play every piece in a
certain order for the montage to make sense. But this one, they're a little bit more free
form. So you have, we have this order that we want you to play them in that where we list
the apps on the top right, um, from top to bottom.
But any order that you play it in doesn't really matter.
A lot of people have done let's play videos, and it's
kind of cool to see people explore them in different
orders, but everyone kind of gets the same themes and the
same ideas.
After they played a couple of them, oh, OK, I'm starting to
get what that means.
And this is available on itch.io if you want to
download it.
It's free.
L-U-M-P-O.
And this is also on itch.
This is Spooky Game Snacks EP.
So I made a bunch of little short,
I did this for Game-tober, something that I guess I made up,
but Inktober, people were doing in October,
drawing a day, so I thought it'd be kind of fun,
what if we made a game a day?
And not like a crazy game, but like a one-button game,
a one-interaction game.
So the first one is Pumpkin Butt,
that's in the top left corner.
And that one, you tap on the pumpkin and it explodes.
It's called Pumpkin Butt because I'm not a good modeler,
so I couldn't make it look like a real pumpkin inside,
so because it looked all round,
I'll just change the title, it's called Pumpkin Butt.
And that's intentional.
But that one, you know, you just press it, it squishes,
makes a really good sound.
But it's just kind of like on or off.
And it's juicy, but you know, there's not a lot of room
for player exploration.
So we have Candy Corn is Gross, which is in the top right corner
where you're just clicking around.
And you can throw candy corn in the trash where it belongs.
Or you could throw it on the floor and other places.
And you can see in the bottom corner I have these arrows.
So rather than having this forced progression,
when you're ready to move on from this game to the next one,
you can click on the arrow and it'll move you along.
The bottom left one is Coco de Paleta,
which is a coconut popsicle, Mexican popsicle.
And when I made this in October,
it was like 85 degrees in Los Angeles.
So it's like super hot
and it doesn't feel like autumn at all.
But I thought it'd be funny to have a...
you know, a little snack break halfway between these five pieces.
And then afterwards, the fourth one is Spider Friend.
And that one, you're talking to the spider, and then you realize it lives in your ear,
and it's kind of gross.
But, you know, a chance to kick up the narrative a little bit more.
So one is just kind of this, the pumpkin to draw you in,
the candy corn to make it more playful and give you more room for self-expression,
the paleta to kind of take a break where you click and it just eats itself and then it falls,
the spider one to have a little bit of a narrative kick where all of a sudden it's like,
uh-oh, now what's going on?
And then the last one, I call it Glitch Kitty,
and that one you play as a cat on a broomstick
flying over this world, and you can wave magic in the air.
And my friend Clover in Sea Life did a really great song for it.
It's about a 45-second song, and at the end, we fade out to the title.
So I really like it because I feel like it's a nice crescendo and climax,
and we have this song that sort of caps off everything
and really does make it feel like what I call an EP,
which would be an extended play in music,
but, you know, for our intents and purposes,
it's another video game mixtape.
And a lot of these ideas stem from this guy,
or at least I take inspiration from this guy.
This is Gunpei Yokoi, who designed...
the Game Boy and the Virtual Boy and he's a, working for, worked for Nintendo,
a late, late designer, but, um,
he talked about lateral thinking with withered technology, and that's this idea
that we have all this technology available to us now, it's cheap, it's
accessible, we all know how to use Unity, there's lots of documentation,
uh, our players, they know how to play screen-based games, they know how to play
games on their phone, uh, so if everything's so accessible
and affordable, then we should think laterally of what...
kind of stories you want to tell,
let's use it to tell stories in innovative
and new ways that people haven't done yet
rather than always chasing the cutting edge.
Everyone's gonna always chase after that.
Did you saw the line for the VR talk next door?
It's like down over to the bathroom,
but I'm very grateful for all of you to be here with me.
So VR is super expensive for developers
as well as for consumers.
So if you stick to withered technology,
we can make things that are certainly more accessible
to the larger group of people.
So to wrap up, a couple of keys to video game mixtapes.
One is to embrace the creative freedom.
So as you make it, you can just make whatever you want.
Just make a bunch of little pieces and you know,
you can figure out what it's going to be as you make them.
You might notice trends in your art or what you're interested in.
And you'll figure out the order as you make it.
Some of these seem like they're well planned out, but it's not.
I just made a bunch of things that I thought would be kind of cool
and then I figured out later how can we start piecing them together
because I had to show some work to my class.
Okay, I have three.
Let's just piece them together and come up with a retro script,
a story as to why.
But just remember that the players are going to figure out, or they're going to make up
the connections for you so you don't have to be explicit with it.
And it's the diversity of experiences is what's really going to enhance the mix.
Two is to keep it flexible and modular.
The beauty about working in this way is if,
like for me, I got like way better every couple months
that I was working on this project,
so I could just quarantine all the bad code.
Like, oh my God, why did I code it this way?
Well, it works, so we'll just put that in the corner
and not touch it anymore,
not build any systems on top of that.
But, you know, we have this piece that works,
and then we'll just make sure the next piece that we do,
we're gonna code it and organize our files
in a much better way.
And if you make something cool later, it doesn't have to be a ton of work to implement it because
it's a mix so you can just add in this cool thing afterwards.
As well as like I mentioned earlier, it's a great way to get collaborators to work because
you're building these small pieces and it's much more visible and tangible for them how
they would fit in.
Oh, I need you to make this art look better, I need you to do a song for this little piece,
I need you to do...
sound effects or code to make some of these things smooth and out.
There's a lot that we can do, you know, to respect people's times,
both for our fellow developers as well as for the players.
Get in, do your thing, and get out. That's a big part of it, right?
You don't want to just linger too long on one piece
because someone might get bored or...
you know, I think it's good to err on the side of caution because you could say, oh,
have you played my game? No. Okay, well it just takes a couple minutes and then you're
done versus have you played my game? Cool, well it's a 60 hour experience and you can
start off, uh, in the first town or whatever and, you know, people don't have the time
for that. Um, so explore the system, uh, with each piece that you're making, uh, but keep
everything moving so that it stays interesting.
And then lastly, especially for younger game developers,
I trust that the process will build your style
and your game development chops.
You know, we're doing repetitions here,
we're making things, we're making a lot of things,
and we're not really concerned about the outcome
of how good they are, if they're gonna make a lot of money,
or anything, we're just focused on this small little piece.
But it's like, you know, making an over-scoped game
or any game that we think is regularly scoped
is like running a marathon.
And for a lot of younger developers, it's like,
well, have you ever worked out before?
Have you ever exercised before?
No, but I think if I run hard enough I can just make it work, right?
Like, no, running a marathon I don't think works that way, right?
You have to work up to it.
So I really believe in this process to build your chops, to build your style,
because things are going to emerge as you start to...
after you get to the 20th thing that you've made,
you're going to be like, oh, I have a style now.
Here's the updated track listing.
Just have a quick outro for you.
A year ago I showed this at the Indie,
I showed Freakin' Weekend at LA Zine Fest
and a journalist said to me that
it was the most immersive experience he had.
He said, it is wildly creative in how it deconstructs
the traditional video game experience.
I also think it speaks compellingly
to each player's personal life and modernity,
though it is autobiographical.
There's also an aspect of voyeurism
to the game that is magnetic.
And he sent me this and I'm just like,
wow, that sounds great.
Like, sure, that sounds wonderful.
Like, this is my game, okay.
And I think it just kind of,
it's validating for what I did because, again,
I just made all these pieces
and started to string them together,
and then he was able to absorb and abstract
all this meaning from it.
And it's very much intentional,
but it just, you know, when you're knee-deep in it,
it doesn't really seem like some of these things
will come across, but.
he got it. Uh and my other favorite hot take on Freakin' Weekend is when I showed it at IndieCade
last year. A Japanese game journalist played it and I asked if he wanted to write about it after
playing and it was mainly in regards to the weed scene but he said uh maybe if I wrote about your
game I would be fired.
And I thought that was great because,
you know, not that the game is bad,
but it's like, cool, I'm doing something.
I'm doing something that's provoking people,
doing something that might be controversial.
And I think that, you know,
in terms of making video game mixtapes,
there's a lot of room there for people to explore.
So, thank you.
If you make a video game mixtape, please send it to me.
I would love to play it and see how you interpret
some of these ideas.
I think that some of what I'm talking about here
is very much influenced by a lot of my colleagues
in Los Angeles and other people that I've met.
So, you know, video games, a beautiful thing
because it's global.
So I want to see what you have to say
and what you have to make.
If you want to also have an update
when Freaking Weekend's out,
you can go to freakingweekend.com
and I have a mailing list you can leave me your email
and I will get back to you.
When it's done, do we have time for no questions?
One question?
Any questions?
You don't have to.
One?
Are you gonna ask a question?
Yes.
No, I just want to rap.
You want to rap?
Have you ever thought about doing this in the context of Glitch City, where maybe you
guys independently assemble some sort of, I guess it wouldn't be a mixtape as much as
like a now this is what you call music kind of thing.
I've thought about it. It's kind of hard though because everyone's sort of doing their own thing and time is money
so it's hard to ask people to step away from their main project to work on something like this.
But that's why I think if I did a lot of the work and just kind of had them come in and just do something for a couple hours that could work.
Another idea that I want to explore is doing a...
Beautiful Corpse, is that what they're called?
So just have a Unity project open
and everyone can just take turns going up to it
and adding something to it.
So that's like the closest I've thought of it.
But in the future, as I think as some of this
is more explored and more mainstream,
hopefully then more people will get it
and want to put time into it
and we can figure out ways to make it work.
So thank you.
But yeah, thank you everybody for listening,
for being here.
I hope you have a great rest of your conference
and fill out your surveys.
Thank you.