Hello and welcome to the 23rd Annual Independent Games Festival Awards,
and also the second official digital version of the awards ceremony.
I'm your chairman, Kelly Wallach, and yeah, it's been a year.
It's definitely been a year, and you know, we miss you all so much,
but it's been really lovely to stay connected through all of the games,
and all the work, and the contribution that folks put into
keeping the IGF alive this year.
So I really wanted to give a special thanks to all the judges,
and jury member, and the staff.
who helped make this possible and also of course to everybody who sent us in their games.
It was a really, really great bunch of games this year.
So it was really heartwarming and lovely to see everyone's work that got submitted.
I also wanted to give a special thanks to ID at Xbox,
who is our supporter for the IGF this year for making this all possible.
Yeah, and a big congratulations to all the finalists and nominees,
the honorable mentions and...
Best of luck.
Really looking forward to seeing the winners
and to celebrating with you all.
And hopefully we'll be able to see each other again
in person soon.
But until then, miss you, good luck, and enjoy the ceremony.
All right, bye.
Hi everyone, I'm Victoria Tran, Community Director at InnerSloth,
creators of Among Us and the Henry Stickmin Collection.
I am super honored to be your 2021 host for the IGF Awards this year,
which, like most of life for the past while, has been all online.
So how do you start a speech about a year like this?
Am I right? Am I right, everyone?
This past year...
sucked in so many ways and I'm honestly a little bit afraid to celebrate and a little bit
afraid to do this because I don't know what to say to make it better and it feels almost
disrespectful to be celebrating like this at a time when so many people have been through a lot,
are currently going through a lot, and have been ignored for so long. An award show won't mitigate
any of the pain that people have gone through and that we're still going through but I think there
is a certain...
type of power in being here, watching the awards show together.
I genuinely hope that you can celebrate watching these awards with us and also just celebrate
where you are right now in moving forward and taking action as I've seen so much of
the industry do, whether it was for Free Palestine, Black Lives Matter, or any of the other causes
that we've gathered for.
Especially as someone who works directly with players.
Oh, I'm gonna cry.
I have seen first hand.
Oh my god, how much you've changed their lives and how much you've saved them and how much you've saved me
um
Ah, oh, sorry, okay
Staying hydrated is really important everyone
This is a celebration of indie games or as the epic and apple lawsuit called it
Items that are so offensive, we cannot speak about them here.
Well, it's too bad that all games are cancelled now. I don't understand tech sometimes.
But look, I could go on and on, but this is a celebration of indie games and the nominees,
and I cannot wait for you to see all the wonderful games and to see who takes home an award.
So let's just get the show on the road.
To kick us off, we have the nominees for best
For Best Student Game, Student Gamers just remind us that, yep, they will always be more
talented than us, there are so many new ideas coming into the indie game space, and honestly,
I'm really grateful for that.
Make sure you pay attention to the nominees in this category, because this will be on
the final exam.
Why am I stroking this?
Best Student Game.
Vessels.
Developed by Local Space Survey Corps, LLC.
John Baxa.
Garrett Hale.
Alex Polito.
Caleb Mills.
Dofermante.
Developed by Tucana Interactive.
Luca Laumberg.
Sandro Hallberger.
Timo Farke.
Zvi Sausch.
some old stuff developed by pao fan harry weizhong chen haku minyan sai emmy sheffield
rainy season developed by nasa
Symphonia, developed by the Symphonia team.
Hodder, developed by Patelier Duchoux, Dominic Koneczny.
There it is.
We are the team of Vessels, the local space survey core, LLC.
And we are so excited that you have selected us to win
this award for best student game.
We'd like to extend thanks from our team who couldn't make it
today, Caleb, Travis, Nick, Kim, and Erica.
This was a labor of love.
It was the brainchild of one John's backstop.
And we all worked really hard to make that vision come true.
Hi, Mom.
Thank you so much for choosing us to be the best student game.
We wanted to make an intriguing game, something
that captures a little bit of the human experience
and morbid curiosity.
We greatly appreciate your support.
We could not be more proud of our team
and excited that you would honor us with this.
I know I'm not the only one that has appreciated a good soundtrack, especially while I'm working
and a boss battle song comes on and I'm like really productive.
All I'm saying is that audio can make or break a game, whether that's sound effects or the
OST or literally anything else.
So keep those ear balls...
Ear balls.
Keep those ear balls open as we hear who the nominees are for best audio.
excellence in audio
say no more developed by studio
marios winter are you kidding me
katrin radke cut to commercial oliver olrich
blind drive developed by lo-fi people yori politi i hope you made life
Sunlight, developed by Creole Byte Studio.
Martin Kvala, Adrian Tingsted Huesby, Kamakura Aru.
Genesis Noir, developed by Carol Kat Den, Skillbar.
Spiritbearer, developed by Thunder Lotus.
Eric Shaw.
Olred Corbet Trudel.
Nicolas Guérin.
A Monster's Expedition Through Puzzling Exhibitions,
developed by Dracnyk and Friends.
Ellie Rainsbury.
There it is.
Genesis Noir wouldn't work without the audio,
and we happen to think it's the best part of the game.
We're so happy that you agree,
and thank you so much for this honor.
Yeah, Tom, Vincent, and Joe from Skillbard did all the music and sound design for the game,
and they worked tremendously hard to make everything sound really great, rich, and reactive.
Thanks for working with us, and you really helped take the game to the next level.
We really also want to thank the musicians and vocalists who contributed to the soundtrack.
Josh, Salim, Freddie, Chris, Clive, Kitty, Sarah, Angus, the Deep Throat Choir,
Elton, Nadia, Noah, and Oki. Thank you.
Our next category shows off the games that are able to stop those button mashers from continually hitting A to skip dialogue
or ones that are able to tell stories without even uttering a single word.
Narrative stays with us, touches our hearts, and live on in the moments that we carry with us.
These are your nominees for Best Narrative.
Lost Words Beyond the Page, developed by Sketchbook Games.
Across the Grooves, developed by Nova Box.
Geoffroy Vincenze, Nicolas Fouquet.
Genesis Noir, developed by Feral Cat Den.
Boomerangi Generation, developed by Origami Digital.
Naftali Faulkner.
Thor Heemskerk.
Haven, developed by The Game Bakers.
Emerick Toa.
Pierre Bobinet.
Audrey Leprince.
In Other Waters, developed by Jump Over the Edge.
Gareth Damian Martin.
And the winner is... ... ... ...
... ... ... Um, kia ora everyone. Uh, thank you for the win on the narrative award.
Uh, you know, I'm pretty blown away with that.
I think, you know, the game started with no story and then it, you know,
developed one along the way with sort of the environmental storytelling and that.
I think one thing I guess I would like to share around that is basically a little bit of a...
a thing why I did that in the game and it's just I guess this this little frustration I have where
a lot of times indies will make these really great ideas for stories and then or ideas for games where
the gameplay is just awesome and then it almost feels like you need to sort of tack on a story
that ends up being text-based which adds a lot of work and a lot of extra dev time and I think
you know the reality with this game is you know
It won this award without any text at all.
And I think it's a kind of thing where I think, you know,
we can all sort of start to think about
what stories mean in games
and maybe try to explore different ways of telling them.
I want to thank Playism for taking the risk with us, being a new developer and all, but also
you know it was one of those moments where I could say things to them and they understood it
and I think that's just that shared cultural context around a lot of this stuff, but
you know they took a risk with the sort of more indirect storytelling I wanted to do,
not sort of spelling things out or
foreshadowing things too early and you know I'm sure everyone who's played it
enjoys the story for that and I just want to say thank you to them for that
and I think it's one of those things where we've got more stories to tell in
the future so me and Thor and you know I think it's this kind of thing where you
know if stories are coming out of Lismore
You know, I think anything can be told, can't it?
Thank you.
So this next award is a little bit
like a popularity contest to whoever wins.
Congratulations, you're pretty popular.
There's a lot to be said for a game
that is able to create a really strong community
that cheers on its developers
and encourages others to do the same.
I'm a little bit biased because I work in community,
so I think it's really great that these things can happen.
And the winner is... ... ... ...
... ... Hello everyone,
I am Mateo Alaisa, I am the director
of Aarog, and I'm very honoured
to receive this award
on behalf of the whole
team of Hermanos Magia and
Leap Game Studios.
I must thank especially my team, the help I received from Luis Wong and Sol Sanchez,
as well as Gabriela Laisa and Vania Castagnino.
This is a very significant prize to all of us and for the industry in Peru.
We hope that we can still deliver these messages to you and to the world and keep talking about
deep meanings in games.
Thank you very much.
Are you hydrating?
I wasn't joking.
Good design can make you see ordinary things
in new, fantastic ways,
like envisioning a conversation as a card battle
or creating a genre called Sawcore.
Anything is up for grabs,
and we're all just players in their game.
These are your nominees for Best Game Design.
Excellence in design.
Developed by Kitty Kallis,
Jan Willem Nijmer,
Teri Velme,
and dos1.
Shady Part of Me
Developed by
Doos Diziem
There is no game, wrong dimension.
Developed by Rami Apaisal.
Pascal Camisoto.
Signs of the Soldier.
Developed by EchoDog Games.
Dayala Katanright.
Holly Rothrock.
Zach Vinas.
A Monster's Expedition Through Puzzling Exhibitions, developed by Draknik and friends
Alan Hazelden, Benjamin Davis, Jamie Perconti
And the winner is...
I'm especially happy that we got the excellence in design, because Teardown started as a technology
experiment with no particular game in mind at all.
And it took almost a full year of prototyping to come up with the right idea, find the right
setting and getting the design in place.
It was a very long and bumpy road, and we almost gave up along the way, so thank you
everyone who saw the potential in this when it was just a bunch of videos on Twitter.
Without your support, Teardown wouldn't exist.
Also, huge congratulations to everyone on the team.
We're a very small group of developers,
so everyone's contribution is really important.
Also, special thanks to all the fans,
the modding community,
and everyone else who made this possible.
Thank you.
Whether it's pixel, 2D, 3D, voxel,
art is everything we imagined we would share with the world.
Great art can really pack a punch, whether it's in the first 15 seconds of a trailer
or within the hours and hours of gameplay.
Oh gosh, um...
These are your nominees for Best Visual Art.
Excellence in Visual Art
Genesis Noir, developed by Feral Cat Den
Aral, developed by Fermanis Magia and Leet Game Studios.
In Other Waters, developed by Jump Over the Age, Gareth Damien Martin.
Shady Part of Me, developed by Douze Diziem. ♪♪
Hall of the Sea, developed by Out of the Bloom.
Tatiana Delgado.
Manuel Fernandez.
Daniel Nombela.
Carto developed by Sunhat Games.
Li Guo Chen, Huan Hung Chen, Chia Yu Chen, Eddie Yu.
And the winner is.
Creating the visual art of Genesis Noir was a huge technical and creative challenge,
and we're so happy that the work is resonating with so many people.
Thanks so much for this honor.
We must thank Marcin, Pedro, Mercy, Dave, Audrey, and Mayo.
You guys elevated the simple black and white art of Genesis Noir
and filled in the Big Bang with detail and richness that I couldn't have done on my own.
Also huge thanks to Adria, Jeffrey, Stephen, and Sam
for your huge technical contributions that enabled us to pull this off.
We couldn't have done it without you guys.
Thank you.
Reject what you think games can be and embrace the absolute chaos of the human imagination.
These are your nominees for the Nuovo Award.
Nuovo Award.
Blazeball.
Developed by The Game Band.
Nightmare Temptation Academy, developed by Lena NW and Costco Dream Girl.
I don't wanna go another day.
Let me out of this place, out of this place, like a freak on display.
That Night, steeped by Blood River, developed by Taylor Switansky.
Airplane Mode
Developed by Back4Them
Hosny Auji
Ben Costrell
Laurence Ricklin
Corey Bertelsen
Welcome to Elk
Developed by Triple Topping, the Triple Topping team
Umurangi Generation, developed by Origami Digital.
Nathalie Faulkner, Thor Heemskook. ♪♪
Chasing Light, developed by VidGen Inc.
Bae Sang-hyun.
Crystalline
Gail Boris
Roman Anselmo
And the winner is...
Thank you to the IGF.
The new oval award is synonymous with so many games
that have inspired us over the years.
This honor is something that we would have never dared
imagine possible.
We want to congratulate our fellow nominees.
It's an honor to be named alongside each of you.
These are all incredible and super innovative projects.
So please everyone who's watching play all of them.
The three of us are only a few members
of a much larger band.
So we accept this on behalf of everyone at the game band
and thank our teammates for all the love,
dedication and talent that they put into Blaseball
over the last year.
Joel, Gabe, Roldan, Elena, Corey, Bria, Cedric, Stephanie,
our anchor, Quinns, our ambassadors, Cat and Sam,
our newest band member, Lonnie,
and especially our sluggers and our keepers
who have given so much of themselves,
who work hard every single day to care for it
and shape this growing community.
Making Blaseball with this team.
has been a rare, immense joy amid what was otherwise
a really difficult year.
We also need to thank our families and our loved ones.
This game was a Hail Mary.
It was by no means a sure thing,
and your constant support and encouragement
really kept us going.
And we want to thank the fans as well.
You know, we share this award
with the entire play small community,
from Play Small Cares,
all the work that you've done to raise real material support
for worthy causes under the Play Small banner.
to all the data crimes and the independent projects
from Cibber, who have helped buoy our technically
limited game, to all of the independent artists
and fellow fans who bring their joy, care, and creativity
to Placeball.
Placeball is an ongoing dialogue with the community.
We're so grateful to have the opportunity
to commune with you through this absurd little game.
You continue to surprise us.
You continue to delight us.
And we're so excited to venture into new eras together.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
Hi everyone, I'm extremely honored to present the Seamus McNally Grand Prize nominees for this year.
Last year, I never expected to receive this award, and it meant so much to me to even be nominated for it.
Indie games have been a huge source of inspiration for me, ever since I discovered that they were a thing.
I remember thinking that it was incredible that one or two or a handful of people could put together a game
and release it on their own without a huge studio or a ton of resources,
and thinking that maybe I could do that someday.
And since then, game development has only become even more accessible, and we're just seeing so many more games.
Games that are willing to do things differently.
Games that are personal and human, and games that push the boundaries of what a game even is.
And this is the festival to celebrate and champion those games.
So as someone who has always looked up to the games in this festival, it really is an honor to present the nominees.
So without further ado, here they are.
Seamus McNally Grand Prize.
Paradise Killer, developed by Kaizen Gameworks.
Ollie Clark Smith.
Phil Crabtree.
Rachel Noy.
Teardown, developed by Tuxedo Labs.
Chickory, a colorful tale developed by the Chickory team.
Genesis, developed by Carol.
Umurangi Generation, developed by Origami Degro.
Naftali Faulkner, Thor Heemster.
Spirit Bearer, developed by Thunder Lotus.
Nicolas Guerand, Joe Gauthier, Alex Boyer,
Alexander Monette Martin.
And the winner is...
Anyway, I want to thank everyone today for the win on the grand prize at the IGF.
This is a huge accomplishment that, you know, we're really happy to, like it's blown us away.
And when I say us, I mean, you know, me and Thor. Thor being the composer who totally smashed it
with the soundtrack, getting the tone of that right for the stuff he composed and
just the general mood of the music. You know, I want to thank
players as well with this. I think, you know, that they've been really able to sort of help
us move into the space. And, you know, I don't think it's a coincidence that we won this
with them because, like I would just say that there has been a lot of times where they've
really helped me out.
I've really not been afraid to ask questions and they've been able to provide me with all
the support on that.
So I want to really thank them.
Just a car going past and I would just say it has been a really rough year for a lot
of people.
That's why I'm recording it outside so we can all remember what that looks like.
But yeah, I'd like to thank not just Thor and Playism, but also my partner for putting up with my late hours.
I'd like to thank Professor Norm Sheen for sharing with me a different way of doing design, which ended up in forming this game.
I'd like to thank Julia Faulkner for, you know, sitting and painting with me all those times.
And, you know, everyone else sort of met along the way.
There's literally a giant list, you know.
This is an indie game that was made by, you know, one to two people.
But, you know, the people that we are, are always informed by the people we meet along the way.
So, you know, we never downplay in that respect.
So I'd just like to say once again, thank you for this grand prize win.
And, you know, here's hoping for next time as well.
And that's it. We are at the end of the IGFs.
Thank you for tuning in from wherever you are.
And to the winners, huge congratulations.
And to the nominees, huge congratulations.
And to people who weren't even nominated.
Also, giant congratulations.
Just take all the congratulations.
It takes a lot to put out a game and you did it.
But, but, but there are also a ton of people
who aren't recognized at these awards.
So to all the people who do QA, community managers,
localization, UI designers, moderators,
and everyone else who often gets overlooked in these things,
thank you for doing what you do.
You fricking rock.
We would all be perishing without you and I am very passionate about thanking you right now.
Have an award. Here you go. I'll photoshop an award right here. Or here. I'll photoshop two awards.
that I guess I have to hand draw so that I don't run into any IP contractual errors.
Congratulations! You've won these awards!
And as a little bit of a parting message,
I hope we all can continue creating a home for people.
And that we continue amplifying and supporting diverse stories and the people that make them.
To dream and care so much about the world you create.
Thank you for giving so many of us a home.
And finally, a huge thank you to our IGF Platinum sponsor,
ID at Xbox.
You make this all possible.
Thank you for supporting indies.
Woo!
We did it!
Ah!
Bam!
Hi there.
I'm an exorbitantly paid Canadian
with an overinflated sense of self-importance
here to host the industry's most important awards, which
No, not that one.
Oh, no, no.
I see now how that could have been confusing.
OK, hang on.
I'll take it from the top.
Hi, everyone.
I'm Sam Maggs, and welcome to the 21st Annual Game Developers
Choice Awards.
As a dev myself, I'm honored to be hosting these awards,
especially in a year when we needed games more than ever
to help get us through quarantine.
Personally, my sanity was saved by phasmophobia,
no matter how ironic that may be.
I also want to preface this ceremony by saying that while I understand that it might be uncomfortable
or even confusing to see a woman on stage for the entirety of a gaming event, I have
donned the customary blazer over graphic t-shirt in order to make everyone feel as at home
as possible.
I contemplated also being terrible at reading teleprompter, but then I remembered that I'm
filming this in my own office and I don't have one, so.
This is as good as it's going to get.
The GDC Awards are the premier accolades
for peer recognition in the games industry.
And what's that?
Marketing says we have to launch right now.
No, I thought we had another year in development.
The awards aren't ready to...
You know what?
We're fine.
One second.
Yeah, we're ready. Let's go.
Hi, hi, is this executive leadership?
Hi, yeah, it's Sam, the host.
Yes, that's me, hi, hi.
I think there might've been a bit of a mix up.
See, we are here to celebrate games that already came out,
not to get hype over games that haven't come out yet.
You know, it just seems counterintuitive
and maybe a little bit disrespectful to the whole.
Uh-huh, uh-huh.
Yeah, yeah, I mean, obviously I want people to suck up to me and show me exclusives, but I'm not, you know, I...
No, no, no, no, I'm not being argumentative. I...
No, I'm not getting emotional. I'm just a woman. This is just what my voice sounds like.
No, I'm not not being a team player. I just...
Yes, we will talk about this later.
Okay, uh, thanks so much.
Um, uh, in the meantime, let's celebrate all the premieres that people loved that came out over this past year.
best debut.
Kinetic Games, nominated for Plasma Phobia, Daniel Knight.
Origami Digital, nominated for Umurangi Generation,
Nathalie Faulkner, Thor Heemsterk.
Phobia Game Studio.
Nominated for Carry On.
["DANCE OF THE SUGAR PLUM FAIRY"]
Cold Symmetry.
Nominated for Mortal Shell.
Andrew McLennan Murray.
Anton Gonzalez.
Vitaly Olgarov.
Dmitri Harkin.
Nodding Heads Games.
Nominated for Rajin, An Ancient Epic.
Abhisol Singh.
Shruti Ghosh.
Ian Mudd.
No, no, I got it. I got it. Let's try it. I can do it in one. It's fine.
Okay.
Hmm.
Our next award is absolutely poggers.
These nominees dabbed on their competition.
So get ready to get gatchy hyper and spam Ws in chat for-
No, I can't do it. I can't do it!
It's gonna age super badly. It's not even good now.
Do we really want to be using memes in our-
No, I mean, I think streamers know that devs appreciate them enough without us having to talk down to them like they're-
Wait, what award is this even for anyways?
Oh.
Ahaha.
Uh, well.
Big thanks to all our subs who voted with their bits for our Audience Award!
Yay!
And the winner is... ♪♪ ♪♪
♪♪ ♪♪ Thank you so much for this audience award.
Of course, all of us that make video games, we started out as members of the audience, right?
We played video games that moved us emotionally, that really excited our creativity,
and inspired us.
to want to pay it forward, to make games ourselves.
And so getting this award, it means that
with Ghost of Tsushima, did a good job.
And that feels amazing.
I know from all of us at Sucker Punch,
we want to thank you for giving us your time.
There are a lot of fantastic games out there
and you played Ghost.
Hopefully we've inspired you to go forth
and make the next game that inspires the next person
and so on and so forth.
Because video games are beautiful and we should all pay it forward.
Best Technology.
The Last of Us Part II.
Developed by Naughty Dog.
Published by Sony Interactive Entertainment.
The Naughty Dog Development Team.
Half-Life Alyx.
Developed by Valve.
The Half-Life Alyx team.
Dreams.
Developed by Media Molecule.
Published by Sony Interactive Entertainment.
Ghost of Tsushima, developed by Sucker Punch Productions,
published by Sony Interactive Entertainment.
Microsoft Flight Simulator, developed by Asobo Studio,
published by Xbox Game Studios.
Alain Goullet, Lionel Fuentes, Sebastian Locke.
This is.
Hi, my name is Jörg Neumann.
I'm the head of Microsoft Flight Simulator.
When we first unveiled the trailer for the new simulator back at E3 2019,
we could have not imagined the positive and wonderful response from the community.
From our global preview event to our tech alpha and betas,
to launch at many world and sim updates, it has been an amazing journey.
It is humbling to see how many fans have embraced the sim,
and this award celebrates the passion the teams at Asobo,
Xbox, Bing, and many others have for this franchise.
I would be remiss not to recognize and thank all the many talented developers who have contributed to this franchise over the last 39 years.
And the contributions go beyond the core development team.
So many third-party developers have elevated and expanded not only Microsoft Flight Simulator, but the genre as a whole.
With many amazing mods and add-ons that delight fans around the world.
On behalf of every developer who's contributed to Microsoft Flight Simulator, thank you.
Where do you even start with Tom Fulp?
I...
The guy's a legend.
He's done more single-handedly for the gaming and entertainment industry as a whole than...
And there's not enough time in the day, is what I'm saying, to talk about Tom Fulp.
But we'll try anyway.
Um...
Tom Fulp.
Husband to a badass wife.
Father of two awesome kids.
Three, if you consider the black sheep, newgrounds.com.
The lost boy that never quite grew up.
See you don't talk about Tom Foulke without bringing up Newgrounds.
So years before YouTube was a thing, Newgrounds was the website where you would go to find
all of the newest cartoons and games from your favorite online creators.
And it was all a completely self-regulated system.
All judgments, all content had to go through an approval process that was regulated by
the users.
It was amazing.
No one had quite seen something just like that before.
It's where you went for everything.
By everyone.
And it still is.
Even now, after Adobe's closed its doors on Flash forever,
Newgrounds is still somehow thriving.
It's a testament to the man's enduring image of what games and entertainment actually are.
And what began as a basement-run website in the mid-90s has now...
over the last decade become the industry foot in the door for hundreds upon hundreds of creators
trying to get into the games and animation industries, or even just entertainment.
People like myself, who owe everything to what Newgrounds has done for them.
Tom also co-founded The Behemoth, the game development company,
and you know them if you've played Alien Hominid or Castle Crashers.
That's right. That was him and
He didn't just oversee production. He made those games. Look at the end of the day Tom Fulp may not be the
father of the internet, but
If you've ever shared your creative content online for other people to enjoy, or opened up your browser to see how far you could launch a cartoon animal.
If you've ever quoted to your friends,
We're on a bridge, Charlie!
Or, I like rusty spoons!
Or, all your bass are belong to us.
If you've ever done any of these things, if it applies to you, then Tom Fulp is the father of the internet that you know.
He's also a hot dad, so that's kind of cool.
Congratulations, Tom.
Hey everyone, it's really great to be here.
All my life, I dreamed of making games,
but I dreamed about it the way a kid dreams
about being a superhero, where you don't think
it would actually happen in reality.
So it's kind of surreal to be here right now,
winning this award and having gotten to make games.
So I'd like to thank GDC for choosing me.
It's been a huge honor.
If it wasn't for Flash, I don't know if I would have had the opportunity to live out this dream.
And I think a lot of people share the same sort of story.
Flash and the internet was a game changer that allowed people to make games who otherwise
might not have, and that energy is what drove Newgrounds and continues to carry it forward
to this day.
I'd like to thank Ross Snyder for bringing his programming expertise to the Newgrounds portal,
allowing people to instantly publish their games in animation, which was a big thing in the year 2000.
It's really exciting times, building out that system.
I'd like to thank all the pioneers who shared their flash on Newgrounds.
We were all kind of inspiring each other and making each other up our game all the time.
Along the way, I had the good fortune of teaming up with John Baez and Dan Paladin to form
The Behemoth, where I got to make console games like Alien Hominid and Castle Crashers.
And it's been really rewarding to see other people from the Flash scene go along the same
sort of journey with their games like The Binding of Isaac, Among Us, Rogue Legacy,
Super Meat Boy, and now Friday Night Funkin'.
There's been a lot of twists and turns along the way, including the death of Flash.
With that, I'd like to thank Mike Welsh and everyone who works on Ruffle.
Ruffle is an open source Flash player that's bringing more and more Flash games back to the
web. And over time, we risk losing a lot of games to history. So I think we should all thank everyone
working in game preservation in general. Increasingly feels like preserving old games is just
as important as making new games.
As for me, I'm still making games and I look forward to sharing Nightmare Cops with everyone when it's done.
And for all of you working year after year on your own dream games, I see you and good luck and we'll all get there eventually.
To wrap this up, thank you again for this award and I'll see you on the internet.
Our next award is for Best Narrative.
As a game writer myself, this category is...
Oh my gosh.
Oh my gosh, that's our publisher.
Oh, I'm so sorry. I have to take this.
Hello?
You, the writer. I'm glad you're free.
Um, actually, I was kind of in the middle of something, but...
Have you ever watched Titanic?
Uh, yeah. I mean...
Wonderful. I've just watched it for the first time today.
I feel like you should rewrite everything to be more like the movie Titanic.
You want me to rewrite the GDC awards so they're more like... Titanic.
Yes! Exactly. I'm glad we're on the same page.
It's just that I'm actually currently presenting the GDC awards, so it feels like
it's a little late to be making that kind of like fundamental change to our-
Right! I know you can do it. I'll check back in an hour.
Right. Well, while I get to work on that, here are our nominees for Best Narrative.
Best Narrative.
Kentucky Route Zero TV Edition.
Developed by Cardboard Computer.
Published by Annapurna Interactive.
Ben Favre.
Jake Elliott.
Thomas Kamenzi.
Final Fantasy VII Remake.
Developed by Square Enix.
Kazushige Nojima.
Cloud.
Stand there and pretend you can't hear the playing crowd out in vain!
the Naughty Dog development team.
Take a look.
I thought I'd do an outfit change.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, what do you think?
With blazer or without blazer?
You think you want to see without blazer?
Okay, okay, hang on, hang on.
I'll digit it.
There, what do you think?
Yeah?
Better without, I think without blazer?
Yeah, okay, we'll mix it up.
We'll do without blazer, okay.
Here we go.
Games would be nothing without the beautiful soundscapes created by our incredibly talented audio departments.
Plus, their soundproofing needs mean they always get the best and most private offices in the studio.
And for that, the rest of us are immensely jealous.
Here are the nominees for Best Audio.
Best Audio
Developed by Supergiant Games, Darren Ford.
The Last of Us Part II.
Developed by Naughty Dog.
Published by Sony Interactive Entertainment.
The Naughty Dog Development Team.
Doom Eternal, developed by Kade Software, published by Bethesda Softworks.
Hugo Martin, Marty Stratton, Mick Gordon, Chad Mossholder.
Final Fantasy VII Remake, developed by Square Enix.
Makoto Issei.
Ghost of Tsushima
Developed by Sucker Punch Productions
Published by Sony Interactive Entertainment
And the winner is
I want to say thank you so much to the Game Developers Choice Awards.
It is really incredible to be honored in a category with these incredible games.
And this is Regis here who helped bring Cerberus to life along with the dogs of several other
team members.
So I want to say thank you to all the team dogs for all the love and support on this
project.
And I want to say thank you to our incredible families for putting up with a lot of this
work being done in our homes towards the end of the project.
And I want to say thank you to my incredible team at Supergiant Games
for being some of the most wonderful and talented people that I know.
And it is really a joy to do what I do every day
and to be able to call it my job. So thank you so much.
VR and AR games are more realistic than ever, completely disrupting our idea of
what reality even is.
Hi, this is Jason Schreier calling from Bloomberg News.
Uh, hi?
Yeah, I'm just calling for comment on a story.
What kind of story?
So I've heard from two sources that this awards show is a bit of a disaster.
Really? I mean, it's gone a little off the rails, but I don't think it's too, like-
Do you want to chat? I'd be happy to keep you anonymous.
I'm in the middle of hosting!
Yeah, I just think our readers deserve to know what's really happening here.
You know I can't talk to you! Oh my god, how do I turn this off?
They're calling this the Anthem of Award Shows.
Ugh!
Can someone please call IT?
What even just happened?
Um, anyways, here's our nominees for Best VR AR Game.
Was that even real?
Best VR AR Game
The Walking Dead Saints and Sinners
Developed by Skydance Interactive
Peter Ackman
Mark Domwitz
Todd Adamson
Jesse Young
Paper Beast, developed by Pixel Reef, Eric Chahi.
Dreams, developed by Media Molecule,
published by Sony Interactive Entertainment.
You will not save him.
Don't worry, it's unloaded.
It's unloaded now!
All this is my fault.
I never told you.
I couldn't. I'm so sorry, baby.
It is my distinct honor to introduce Laura Lynn.
I count her as a close friend, an amazing game maker, and a superlative human being.
Laura Lynn has quietly been elevating the work of anyone with the good fortune to be
her teammate over the last three decades.
Her humility, talent, and perseverance are in such abundance that she has enough of
each to share with everyone around her.
After a couple of attempts at starting her own companies,
she eventually joined another studio on the design team,
and soon thereafter became the lead designer
on Full Spectrum Warrior,
where she and her team delivered a top-tier squad game
in the vein of XCOM that delivered innovations in gameplay
and user experience that garnered best-of noms
and player adulation on its release.
Not content to rest on her successes, she moved over to Sony Online where she became
creative director of an ambitious MMO, Free Realms, aimed at bringing a whole new audience
and generation of players to the game, as well as a new way of involving those players
in their own storytelling.
It's hard to overstate the accomplishments and success of Free Realms when it released in 2011.
It was free to play, play-available the web, player advancement was multifaceted and not solely dependent on combat,
avatar customization was expansive, player self-expression and cooperative storytelling were at the center of its goals and its successes.
It was wildly popular, reaching over 10 million players at its peak.
We're still seeing reverberations from this title 10 years on throughout the MMO and free-to-play sectors.
More recently, she really landed as chief creative officer.
Skydance Interactive, where she explored and set the groundwork for innovative storytelling in the
wildly successful VR title, The Walking Dead Saints and Sinners. Without the foundation
Laura Lynn had laid, it would have been easy to let the technological and gameplay accomplishments
of Saints and Sinners overshadow the humanity of the game. Throughout her career, Laura Lynn
has challenged herself and her teammates and her craft at every opportunity, looking for ways to
further storytelling and interactivity in that eclectic marriage that is game making.
Modern game making is a collaborative effort, one that benefits from people who know how to bring out the best in everyone on the team,
who always keep players in mind as we engage in our craft, and who never lose sight of the excitement that playing games can bring.
I can't think of somebody who better embodies this and more deserves recognition for modeling what a game maker should be than Laura Lin.
Congratulations, Laura Lin.
I feel like saying thank you isn't nearly enough,
especially considering the people
who have gotten this award before me.
And that thank you isn't just
for the Game Developers Choice Committee,
but for everyone I've ever worked alongside
and everyone who's supported me over the years.
I genuinely can't wrap my head around this honor.
But in this moment, I also can't help thinking of my path to get here.
As a young kid, I always thought attractions like Pirates of the Caribbean were magic,
living, immersive stories.
But then around 1980, I got this weird new game called Adventureland from my home computer.
It was a text adventure, a living story that was actually interactive,
where I could make choices and those choices mattered.
Now, that was magic.
I immediately started making my own text adventure, a romance game where you were stranded on
an island with a cute guy, because I was 16.
But even then, I knew exactly what I was supposed to be doing with the rest of my life, making
games.
But how?
So I did a bunch of other stuff, but then in 1993, everything changed when I played
Myst.
They'd made a living, breathing, interactive world, and now it looked real.
I couldn't take it anymore.
I taught myself 3D graphics, I improved my scripting,
I made a demo, I sold it to Microprose
and started my own company.
And then two years later, my very first game was canceled.
My second game was canceled too,
so welcome to game development.
It's been almost 30 years since then,
and 41 years since I first played Adventureland.
And I still get up every morning, a couple hours early,
even if that means 6 a.m., so I have time to play games.
And even now, after all this time, when I sit down to play Returnal or replay Prey or
dive headfirst back into Mass Effect, it's still magic.
So I'll leave you with one thought.
We're all wizards.
All of us.
No matter how experienced we are, no matter what our role is or what kind of games we're
building or who those games are for, we all make magic.
But that magic comes from unexpected places.
I never studied computer science or art in school,
and the concept of game designer as a role
didn't even exist back then.
I was almost 30 when I started my career in games.
In most companies at that time,
I was one of one or two or maybe three women
in the whole company,
and almost always the only woman in a leadership role.
So I know what it's like to be conspicuously different,
and yet, here I am.
We all have our own paths, our own ways to create magic for our players.
And each one of those unique paths brings something special and new
to the game and the team and the company.
So my wish for all of us individuals and the industry as a whole
is that we'll keep taking risks and we'll grow and we'll welcome fellow wizards
of all types and all paths.
There's something to learn from each of us and in each of us, there's magic.
So thank you again from the bottom of my heart.
And now for everyone's favorite part of the awards ceremony.
I'm sorry, does that say commercials?
No, I mean, I'm just confused.
Like video games are the biggest selling industry in the world.
I mean, we bring in like three times what box office does in a year,
over seven times what music does.
Why would we need to sell ad space during our awards ceremony?
Where's all the money going?
Right.
Right. Okay, well, we're cutting that, and instead, this airspace is just gonna be me,
smiling to camera, and saying,
UNIONIZE!
And now, the award for the industry's biggest money maker,
accounting for nearly half of all money brought in by video games, period,
Best Mobile Game.
The Pathless.
Developed by Giant Squid.
Published by Annapurna Interactive.
The Giant Squid Team.
Genshin Impact.
Developed by Mihoyo.
Haiyu Kai.
Legends of Runeterra, developed by Riot Games.
Jeff Ju.
Andrew Yip.
Alba, a wildlife adventure, developed by us too.
Published by EID Publishing.
If found.
Developed by Dreamfield.
Published by Onepurna Interactive.
The Dreamfield Team.
Hello everyone, here is Hao Yutai.
As the CEO and producer of MiHoYo,
it's absolutely thrilling to accept the best mobile game
of GDC Awards for Genshin Impact.
It was a crazy idea to bring the open world
adventure experience to the mobile platform back in 2017.
We made the launch of Genshin Impact
in September last year.
and was surprised to see Genshin Impact has been well received by our fans globally.
So here today, I'd like to share this award with every team member
who has been working hard enough on this project.
And most importantly, a big thank you to our fans globally
who've been living in and supporting us.
Without you, we cannot be here. Thank you.
We have another award on deck here, but I just got a ping on Slack.
So hang on a second. Let me just bring this up here.
Okay, it's from Chad, our chief visionary creative.
Okay, let's see what he has to say.
Hi, Sam.
Been doing some thinking.
Okay, I've been in the industry about 20 years now,
and I've just had my first daughter.
Starting to think that maybe women are people.
Haven't gotten too far into it yet,
but we should pivot to make the awards about a middle-aged man
becoming a father.
and dealing with his own daddy issues.
You are probably not the best fit for this, so...
Uh-huh.
You know what?
I'm just going to set my status to away
and pretend that I never saw that.
Okay.
So, since creative leadership is clearly having a moment,
why don't we go ahead and take a look at the games
that were objectively beautiful last year that we all loved?
Oh my god, I'm gonna get fired.
best visual art.
Gen Z.
No, this...
...affords!
The Last of Us Part II
Developed by Naughty Dog
Published by Sony Interactive Entertainment
The Naughty Dog Development
Ori and the Will of the Wisps, developed by Moon Studios.
Published by Xbox Game Studios.
I am 8-bit Jeremy Britton.
Daniel Van Leeuwen.
Mikhail Rakhmatov.
Cyberpunk 2077, developed by CD Projekt Red.
Published by CD Projekt.
Hey everyone, it is an absolute honor to win this award for the best visual art.
You know, it takes an entire team of, you know, super creative people at a studio, years
of dedication and hard work, you know, a specific style and, you know, way that you'd like to
depict a place like Feudal Japan, and honestly a lot of collaborating with
you know, team members that maybe we've never worked with before.
So I want to thank all of our consultants and our teammates in Japan
that helped us make this game and give us feedback all over the, you know,
the course of making this game over the last few years.
And I just want to say thank you to our team, the character artists
and environment artists and the concept team and the animators
and, you know, the visual development team, the lighting team,
as well as the graphics engineers.
Thank you so much for everything you've done to make this game great.
Thank you for this award. We're honored.
Uh, no, I don't think so. Why?
The guy who made that sitcom cracked the code on narrative.
He solved it. He made a chart.
We'll use this to plot out every intro for the ceremony.
Every intro?
I mean, I'm sure the chart is great.
It's probably just one of many tools in a writer's toolbox.
Like, you know, if someone had really cracked the code on storytelling,
we would all be doing it, so.
Every other department I can measure their progress on a grid.
Ugh.
Contractors. At least I don't have to pay you royalties, benefits, healthcare, really anything.
Okay, well, while I figure out how to read this thing, here are the nominees for Best Design.
Best Design
Ghost of Tsushima
Developed by Sucker Punch Productions
Published by Sony Interactive Entertainment
The Last of Us Part II
Developed by Naughty Dog
Published by Sony Interactive Entertainment, the Naughty Dog Development Team
Eyes on me
Hades, developed by Supergiant Games.
Animal Crossing New Horizons, developed by Nintendo EPD, published by Nintendo.
The Nintendo EPD team.
Half-Life Alyx developed by Valve, the Half-Life Alyx team.
And the winner is...
Thank you for this Game Developers Choice Award for Design.
First, we want to thank the video game Rogue,
and all the Rogue-likes that came after it,
which inspired us to see if we had something
we could contribute here.
We also want to thank our team,
who elevates everything we do,
our players in early access,
who gave us invaluable feedback,
and finally, our test maps.
We spent a lot of time in our test maps
trying to figure out what Hades would be,
and when you're doing that,
you have no idea that it's going to lead
to something like this.
So on behalf of Gavin, Greg, Eduardo, Alice, and myself, thank you so much.
Let's take a pause now and remember those co-workers, colleagues, and friends whom we
lost over this last year and remember the ways in which they added to our industry and to our lives.
You
Thank you for watching and for everything you do for us each day, we love you!
Based on the One Two Seven zodiac sign, this is an eastern zodiac animal.
I don't want to introduce the Innovation Award. No, I don't want to. Okay, fine, if it's so easy,
then why don't you tell Naughty Dog they're not nominated for a whole category? Yeah,
yeah, that's what I thought. Mm-hmm, that's what I thought. Fine, fine, you know what,
fine. Here, nominees for the Innovation Award. So I'm gonna go hide under my desk before the
Sony snipers find me. Bye.
Innovation Award.
Microsoft Flight Simulator, developed by Asobo Studios,
published by Xbox Game Studios.
Georg Neumann, Sebastian Locke, Damian Huzak.
Dreams, developed by Media Molecule,
published by Sony Interactive Edition.
Half-Life Alyx, developed by Valve.
The Half-Life Alyx team.
Fall Guy Ultimate Knockout, developed by MediaTonic.
Published by Devolver Digital.
Hades, developed by Supergiant Games.
On behalf of Media Molecule, I'm very glad to accept this Innovation Award.
I'd like to thank our friends and family at Sony for supporting us along this journey.
And, as always, it's the community that I have the most thanks to.
In many ways the success of our innovation in making dreams has been to empower the innovation of our community
and it brings us joy every day to see the things that they're making.
Now, any Game Awards ceremony wouldn't be complete without a deeply awkward celebrity cameo.
And for this year's GDC Awards, have we got a surprise for you.
So please, help me in welcoming...
What do you mean we don't have Mercer?
Well, what are we supposed to do?
He's the only voice actor anyone recognizes.
I don't know what we're supposed to...
Okay, fine, fine.
You know what? Fine.
Everyone, please help me welcome my producer, Leslie, to the stage.
What?
Why am I on camera?
You are now our celebrity guest!
Say hi to the crowd!
Hi. Listen, we're way off the timeline here,
and unless we do some serious triage,
we're not going to be able to end the show in time.
Did you make a Jira for that?
Producers do more than make Jiras.
Nothing would ship without producers.
I'm sorry?
Are you saying that without producers,
game writers would just throw down a bunch of random shit
that is completely unmakeable in-engine
and just assume that's gonna end up on screen
because we have a god complex?
Yes.
That's exactly what I'm saying.
Whatever, I have no idea what you're talking about.
Anyways, here's 14 unicorns swimming through an ocean of golden flower petals to announce our Game of the Year.
We can't afford that.
What?!
Game of the Year.
Animal Crossing New Horizons. Developed by Nintendo EPD. Published by Nintendo.
The Nintendo EPD Team.
The Last of Us Part 2.
You all know the drill.
Developed by Naughty Dog.
You alive?
Published by Sony Interactive Entertainment.
The Naughty Dog Development.
I really hope you make it.
Developed by Valve.
The Half-Life Alex Timm.
Developed by Supergiant Games.
My brother.
Ghost of Tsushima.
The Mongols took it.
Developed by Sucker Punch Productions.
Brazilian.
Published by Sony Interactive Entertainment.
She can out-shoot any samurai I know.
I'm coming with you.
Now, send them to their ancestors.
Do you deserve death?
I hope not, my lord.
Then you're safe.
I can't let more of our people die.
Thank you very much for the Game Developers Choice Award
for Game of the Year.
I am here with most of the core team that worked on Hades.
In 2012, we were really lucky to earn best debut
with our first game Bastion
at the Game Developers Choice Awards.
And all of us who worked on that game
are still working here together today.
on all our projects and I don't think we ever thought we'd be back here again, much less in the company of last year's most beloved video games.
On behalf of our whole team and all the vital and new voices we've added who helped make Hades what it was,
we are just really grateful that people liked Hades so much.
It was a privilege to work on it and to make it at all.
We want to thank our audience for all our previous games, who encouraged us, and also
to the fans of Hades in our early access, who gave us feedback that was really, really
critical to helping finish Hades out.
Thank you to our partners and the platforms who helped Hades find an audience, and to
our families who love and support us.
It feels really, really, really, really good to make them proud with a huge honor like
this one.
Thank you.
Thank you guys.
Thanks for joining us everybody.
And a huge thanks to Katie, Blair, Leslie,
Jason, Sandesh, the jury, the crew,
and everyone who worked so hard on these awards.
So if you haven't clicked that X yet,
please hire me to write your game
because I am afraid that I'm going to be blacklisted
in the industry after this.
So, someone.
Please.
Okay, bye! ♪