I'm going to be talking about building an inclusive tech lab, how we did it, and why
you should also do it, and tips, tricks, and things that we've learned.
But before we dive into that, let's tell you a little bit about who we are.
So hello, I'm Tara.
I'm currently a Mixer Program Manager
and also the Head of Accessibility for Mixer.
But along with Brandon, I am one of the
Gaming and Disability Community Leads at Microsoft.
I'm also the Co-Director of the Game Accessibility Conference
that happens the Monday before GDC, so it just happened.
And we're looking to expand.
We're trying to get one in Paris later this year.
We decided that yesterday, less than 24 hours
after I'd done my other conference.
They were like, but what if you did another in Europe?
I was like, you guys are the worst.
Please just let me calm down.
But my background before that was in AAA game development.
I've been in the industry for 10 years, as of St. Patrick's Day.
But enough about me.
What about you, Brandon?
Well.
My name is Brandon Zahand, and I'm actually a release manager at 343 Industries, working
on all things Halo.
But I'm also a gaming and disability community lead at Microsoft.
I've been in the games industry about 15 years, but I've been working with the disability
community about 20.
I have a background in studying American Sign Language.
So with that being said, what are we going to talk about today?
Well, first, we're going to tell you how our lab even
came into existence.
We're going to give you a virtual tour of the lab.
Then we're going to talk about the things that we kind of
learned along the way as we were making that lab, and then
things you can do to make your own inclusive tech lab.
So, and Tara, I'm actually gonna ask to switch with you
because the glare on the screen is,
woo, making reading some of these notes hard.
So, Gaming for Everyone started in 2015 at Microsoft.
This movement, this affirmation of the fact
that we wanted to make gaming fun for everyone,
regardless of race, ability, gender identification.
And the whole.
The point behind Gaming for Everyone was really to build relationships.
We wanted to build relationships with our customers.
We wanted to build relationships with our colleagues internally at Microsoft and our partners
to figure out how we can better understand what it means to make safe, inclusive game experiences.
Gaming for Everyone is about taking ourselves out of our comfort zone.
It's about looking at our products and our services through a whole new set of lenses.
And it was in that spirit which we created the Inclusive Tech Lab.
Now it's easy to forget that between 10 to 15 percent of the world's population live
with some form of disability.
That's staggering.
And those disabilities vary greatly in terms of how they impact people's day-to-day lives,
including how they game.
So first and foremost, our goal was to bring awareness to disability, how it can be a barrier
to gameplay, and how being excluded from gaming can have a significant impact on an individual's
life.
Now, once people understand what it means to be a part of that gaming and disability
community, to understand why gaming and accessibility is important, we then have to educate them
on how to design inclusively for that community.
To that end, we realized after many discussions...
We needed a space.
We needed a space dedicated to learning.
A space dedicated to developers and community advocates that could come together and ideate
on ways to make Xbox a place for everyone.
A space to share best practices and missteps, as well as think creatively on how we can
make games not just accessible, but enjoyable for as many people as possible.
A space that developers would leave energized, educated, and ready to go back to their teams
to share their knowledge, the things they had learned, and inspire them to do great
things.
Now, unfortunately, being crammed in a tiny conference room
is not really conducive to education and energizing.
Those tend to be more draining and disheartening.
No, I totally love all of the meetings where we all
are sitting at a table around computers, totally
engaged with one another.
What are you talking about?
I know, right?
We wanted to try something a little different than that.
So what we decided was we were going to create a space that was comfortable.
It was going to facilitate creativity and community.
And we wanted the room itself, the space itself, to exemplify inclusive design.
Now we realize that by building out such a dedicated lab,
we could not only ensure that we met all that criteria of education, empathy building,
but we could also use it as an embassy for the gaming and disability community.
A place where they could come in and feel at ease sharing their open and honest feedback with us.
And hopefully...
By building out such a dedicated space, we could
demonstrate to the world that we were serious about being a
leader in inclusive gaming, with the hopes that others
would see that commitment and choose to join us.
So with that being said, let's show them the lab.
All right, so when we give a tour of the Inclusive Tech Lab,
we actually kind of have it divided into four quadrants.
And when we go to give us a tour,
we actually break it up into the four quadrants.
So I just have pictures of the four quadrants
to go with you through today.
So we're going to start with our inspiration wall, which
is the first thing you see when you walk in on the left.
So we've actually had a version of this inspiration wall
since.
the very beginning, before the lab was actually a lab.
But I'll get into that a little bit later.
So for us, it's really important to have a constant reminder of what we're doing and
who we're doing it for.
So SpecialEffect is a charity in the UK, and they work with a lot of gamers with disability
in building custom controllers and custom solutions for them.
And as you can see here, these are all pictures of people that they've actually helped.
And later, if you want to come talk to me, I can share the Twitter so you can get more in-depth,
closer visuals of what's happening here.
But they're doing a lot of work.
They're cracking controllers.
They're wiring things in real weird ways.
It's pretty amazing.
But what's really important is there's a huge variety here.
So for us being able to see the solutions they are coming up with lets us see the challenges
that they're going through and then when we can see that challenge we can try to think
of new ways to make it easier for these guys.
Because all they want to do is game, and we want to help them game.
So an example kind of of this, like, what problems are they facing,
how do we come up with a solution, is I mentioned a lot of them
are wiring multiple controllers together.
So what if we made that easier?
Boom!
Copilot!
So Copilot is a...
So, this is a way on Xbox where you can take two controller inputs and have them shared as one input.
So, for these guys, rather than having to wire two controllers together to operate maybe one with, you know, the left arm and one with the right foot,
they could use Copilot and have the system do essentially the heavy lifting of wiring together.
Now, they don't have to break their controller or wire them, or void the warranty.
So, this was just a kind of example of how we can see their challenges and figure out how to make it easier for them.
Directly across from the inspiration wall is our demo space.
So we actually have four demos.
We have spaces for four demos.
We have three set up right now.
And for us, we know a lot of developers,
I mean, almost all developers, are problem solvers.
And once they understand what the problem is,
and they understand the challenge,
they'll come up with solutions.
So with these demo spaces, we have an opportunity
to show everyone who comes in what we're talking about.
And it can be so much more impactful
than just trying to describe the problem.
So these are three of the demos that we actually have right now.
And I say right now because we do switch them up and change them from time to time.
But I'm going to tell you about the ones we have right now.
So on the left is the QuadStick.
It's a 3D printed, puff and sip, Kickstarter-backed controller.
And it's fully operated with your mouth.
So a lot of the times we have to introduce people to the fact that
You know, some people aren't using the standard controller,
and some controllers that these gaming,
these gamers are using are very different
from what we picture as a controller.
So we have that there so people can see,
like, you need to break your notion
of what a controller looks like or feels like.
So in the middle, that's a picture of our IS-free setup.
So the black part folds down to cover the monitor,
and the user is able to experience and understand
stuff like how someone may be using the narrator
to navigate on the Xbox.
And then on the far right, that's actually our Rocket League
demo with a custom controller setup.
And I'll go into a little bit more detail later
about how exactly that works, but it's another way
to show people how to play a game with inputs
that they're probably not used to.
And all of these stations give the lab guests a different way
to experience games and think about how other people may
engage with the game.
So the third area is really our meeting space.
And like we said earlier, we wanted to make it a warm and welcoming space because we don't want people to come in here and get bored. So it has plenty of chairs. That's actually a surface touch screen, which by the way, has like a glitter pen that you can draw with. Not that I ever derail meetings to use the glitter pen.
But it also has a microphone, it has a camera set up for remote meetings so we can connect
with our teams in different locations.
And by hosting meetings in the space, we're literally able to put the attendees in a position
where they are completely surrounded by accessibility and accessibility thoughts.
Something else that's actually pretty cool is our third party hardware test lab is off
this room.
So when we're hosting meetings with these third party teams, we actually do it in here.
And so they get to see that we're dedicated to accessibility.
And we really hope that it makes them think about what they're building in new ways and
maybe new uses for them because we're putting them in the space to talk about their hardware.
And we also use this space for what's called inclusive design sprints, which I'm really excited about.
We basically will host a team and subject matter experts about whatever we're talking about
and developers from those teams and let them learn from each other.
And it's very inspiring for our developers because they, again, they get to see what people are doing to engage with our product,
how they're engaging with our product, and get to hear directly from the consumer the problems they're currently experiencing.
We actually just did one for Mixer last January,
and I was incredibly proud of the team.
All right.
So Tara was kind enough to let me do this slide
because this is one of my favorite parts of the lab,
and that is the living room experience.
You know, when I came to 343, it kind of hit me.
I was sitting in front of a computer working on game development,
and I was...
It's 18 inches away from that monitor.
But let's think about it.
How many console gamers are actually playing 18 inches
away from their monitors?
Not many, right?
I mean, the majority of console gamers are sitting in
their living rooms, or their bedrooms, or their caves.
Most of us are 6 to 10 feet away.
Actually, at my house, I'm 11 feet away from my TV.
And we're using stereo speakers.
We're using surround sound receivers.
We're not using headphones.
And so
You know, obviously, when you're sitting farther away from the screen,
it's going to be harder to see detail, to read text.
But beyond that, there's other environmental factors
that can more easily impact a living room setup.
Glare from lighting, similar to what I just experienced earlier.
Background noise, viewing angle, acoustic properties of the room.
All of those things can make it more difficult to see or hear
what's going on in a game for everyone,
not just somebody with a disability.
So what we did here was, with the lab, when we set it up,
we wanted to be able to try out all sorts of room
configurations.
We used adjustable lighting and furniture that can be
easily rearranged.
That way, we're able to ideate on ways to better deal with
some of these typical environmental issues.
We also use this space to test out the latest and greatest
audio visual technologies.
Because those latest and greatest technologies often
offer us some additional capabilities to explore as it
relates to using them for accessibility.
So in the picture here, what you're looking at is a 4K,
75-inch OLED TV.
It's hooked up to a Dolby Atmos 5.1.4 surround sound
system.
And not only do games and movies sound and look amazing on this system, but we've been
able to discover that there's some things we can take advantage of with those technologies
that can make gaming much more inclusive.
As an example, with Dolby Atmos, the ability to render audio objects in 3D.
as they relate to the specific environment in which you're sitting in can produce a level
of fidelity, audio fidelity, that can make audio navigation systems, audio cue systems
for those who are visually impaired or blind incredibly accurate and helpful when dealing
with various different types of gaming situations.
And speaking of latest and greatest, AR, VR, MR,
they're all incredibly exciting new technologies
that gaming is taking a part in.
But strategies and best practices for designing these,
there aren't a lot of them out there.
Ian Hamilton, who's a well-known game accessibility expert,
has written an article that covers some of this stuff.
But there's still a lot of exploration
going on in this space.
So we dedicated a section of the lab
just to VR and to future technologies.
Now, the thing that's really important to call out here is that we have lots of products
that aren't made by Microsoft.
You know, of course, we have HoloLens, we have some of the AR devices we partnered on,
but we also have an Oculus Rift, we have a PS4 VR.
And the reason for that is we don't pretend to know, or to say, you know, we don't pretend
that we know all the best ways to tackle all these inclusive design challenges with these
new technologies.
It's important for us to see how our partners and our competitors are tackling those issues.
We want to understand what the gaming and disability community believes to be the best
practices regardless of the platform.
So how did we get here?
This is obviously something that didn't happen overnight.
We didn't just wake up and have an inclusive tech lab,
although that would have been awesome.
And I'm sure, you know, Evelyn and Bryce over here
would have been super excited to just wake up and it existed
rather than all the hard work and, you know,
legwork they had to do to make it happen.
But it's actually a really interesting story
on how we went from nothing to...
A dedicated inclusive tech lab.
So this was not a straight line or a clear-cut process.
It had a lot of growth, learning, exploration, and it definitely evolved over time.
Like there wasn't a road map.
Like it was, you know, the whole way like, okay, well this seems like a good idea, or
this seems like a good idea, and learning.
So for us, it really started with inspiration from a popular charity for gamers with disabilities.
So AbleGamers has something called an expansion pack.
AbleGamers teamed up with Humble Bundles, SteelSeries, ElectronicsArts, Jinx, and Corsair
Components.
that would be donated and installed as permanent fixtures for places like group homes, special
needs, day care facilities, and long term living centers.
And these packs were intended for facilities with multiple special needs patients.
These donation bundles included assistive technology,
specialty controllers, and of course, great video games.
And the first expansion pack was installed
in a pediatric specialty care unit in Hopeville, Pennsylvania,
and it had great success.
So they had quad sticks, they had adjoint controllers,
which is a controller where you kind of do all the remapping
on the hardware, switches, and so much more.
And this really inspired us.
It was like, how do we kind of take their expansion pack idea
and make a space where we can teach developers using it.
So for us, our first stab at the lab was actually
what we now refer to as an arcade.
So funny enough, although I wasn't a Microsoft employee at the time,
I was actually there for the first arcade.
So every year, Microsoft has the Ability Summit.
Which is all about accessibility and so this year in 2016
That was the first year that game accessibility was introduced into the speaking lineup, which is actually why I was there
So for the arcade we had a range of specialty controllers, simulators, and information. Going through the pictures here
We had a setup made by Warfrider Engage
So, we're going to start with the first prompt.
We had Brandon wearing motion-restricting gloves.
We had Bryce demonstrating the quad stick.
He's actually playing Forza, although you can't see it in that picture.
We had Brandon demonstrating the quad stick.
was actually the first version of the inspiration wall, where we had all of the pictures of
special effects.
So that, for us, has been there since day one.
And after the Ability Summit, the team took the setup
and kind of did pop-up versions of it in,
it's called the Commons, it's like where
there's like studios, A, B, C, D,
that have a lot of Xbox people, and then in the middle,
there's like, essentially like a mini mall
full of restaurants, and they were just doing
pop-up versions of it there, so while people
were going through, they would see it.
So it's a high-traffic area, special at launch,
and at other opportunities, but it was clear that,
you know, this little pop-up station wasn't enough,
like it wasn't permanent, it wasn't as strong
as it could be.
And then, like, we got lucky.
What really came next was the opportunity.
We were craving a permanent home, and we just needed a space.
But where would we get space?
Where would it go?
Lucky for the team, there was actually, like, a workout area that was kind of being underutilized,
and people were thinking of getting rid of it anyway or moving it.
And that was our time.
We were like, ooh, wait, wait, wait.
We would like a space.
And because we had the arcade and we'd been carting it around
the whole time, we'd basically been working to legitimize the
idea and the work we were doing.
And we're like, oh, but wouldn't it be great if that
thing we keep doing had a home?
And it showed why it was important and why we deserve
to have the space.
But, you know, beyond the fact that there was a space that was opening up,
part of it was being in the right place at the right time.
Not only has accessibility been on the rise in the games industry for the past few years,
the dramatic increase in both features and awareness,
there was also a culture shift happening within Microsoft.
So in 2014, Satya Nadella became CEO for Microsoft.
And after that, Microsoft revised its mission statement to empower every person and every
organization on the planet to achieve more.
But for Satya, accessibility is very personal.
His first son has severe cerebral palsy.
So I'm just going to quote him on Microsoft's accessibility work.
Our work in accessibility has an incredibly deep meaning to me personally.
Our family's experience has required me to continually hit refresh on my emotions and all my outlook.
And it is in this constant quest for renewal that I realize,
despite the fact we are making progress, we still have much to do quickly for so many.
And so the fact that that was how Microsoft was starting to think about accessibility,
and we were showing up and being like, hey, hey, hey, we'd like a home,
we got really, really lucky.
So kind of what we were doing was fitting in line with Satya's goals, empowering everyone,
and it also was right in line with the Gaming for Everyone commitment.
But it does take more than just being in line with your company's ideas and messaging, right?
So for us, we needed to get executive sponsorship, someone, you know, at the leadership level
wanting to back us.
And we were actually really lucky in that we got that.
So really for the lab, like, something like that needs...
And it needs people who care to do the legwork,
but having support from the top down
is also incredibly important.
So for us, getting the executive sponsorship
was about three things.
So first, showing the need.
And this is how you guys can get executive sponsorship,
by the way.
So showing the need.
People were learning from the arcades,
but the arcades weren't always around,
and we didn't have a space to learn or explore
because it was temporary.
And
We needed to show that there was a goal.
Like there was a craving for learning
and we wanted to innovate
and the space would help us do that.
But you know, it's also really important
to know how to measure success.
And success in an inclusive tech lab
could be so many things.
Maybe it's the amount of people who visited the lab
or the amount of inclusive design features that shipped
or the number of developers
who now know one more thing than before.
And we kind of had to learn, you know, what is success for the lab?
Yeah.
So, yeah, learning.
This whole experience has been about learning.
And it was, it's been, you know, putting together the lab was an incredible journey.
And the learning.
All along the way, constantly.
Looking back, some of those learnings,
they seem pretty obvious now.
Some not so much, but we want to share with you guys
some of those learnings so that you have a head start
if you decide to make your own dedicated inclusive technology lab.
All right, so this is the audience participation portion of the presentation.
So first off, how many of you guys have seen those pregnancy simulators?
You know the ones with the big bellies that you strap on, right?
All right.
Now, quick question.
Can anyone in the room who has had a baby and thinks that those simulators fully and
accurately represent being pregnant, can you guys just raise your hand, you gals, anyone?
No?
Not one?
Yeah, you see...
So if they don't, why do we have them, right?
Well, they give us a lens by which we can try to better
understand some of the challenges of pregnancy.
But look, it's not the same as being pregnant, right?
And the same goes for accessibility simulators.
We have goggles in the lab to simulate visual impairment.
We have earplugs to simulate audio impairment.
Gloves, you saw earlier, that simulate fine motor
impairment.
All those things can give us a better sense of ways we might
be able to tackle certain challenges, but they will
never accurately reflect what it's like to have one of
those impairments.
So while we may use them to think creatively about product design,
it's important to know that we never use them to validate designs.
Validation needs to be handled by those who understand accessibility challenges firsthand.
I can't stress this enough.
We do not and never will role-play disabilities in our inclusive tech lab to validate products.
Now, that wasn't something we necessarily learned when we were building the lab, but
what we did need to learn was how to relay that message to individuals who were coming
into the space.
That's why we always curate our lab tours and why we have signage, like the signage
you see above, that clearly explains this very important principle.
So we've obviously just told you that having simulators wasn't enough.
So we really did want to show authentic rigs.
So we had the pictures of everything that was happening with special effect.
And our first thought was just like, let's take that and put this here and then let people
see it.
And our first Rocket League set up was so much more complex than the one we have now.
We were really trying to replicate what we were seeing on the wall.
We found out it was way too much for people.
It was way too different.
So if you haven't been using that stuff and then you go to use it,
it was incredibly intimidating and people were basically in, like, shock.
And what we were trying to say wasn't getting through
because they were so focused on this crazy thing they hadn't seen before.
So we really needed to back it up and make it more approachable.
So we basically learned less is more.
And this was the end result.
So this is our current Rocket League station.
So in this setup, Gas is the foot pedal
that you can see on the floor.
The player still is left and right using the two blue
and green buttons about knee height.
And there's the joystick on the arm,
and that's used for jumping.
And that's it.
This, uh, Rocket League is an easy game with simple controls,
and using a pedal for gas is already really natural for most people,
so this demonstration was much easier for people to use
and experience than what we had set up previously.
So you just have to show people the change,
you don't have to go for the huge, crazy rigs, like,
just a little bit to kind of challenge what people are used to
is totally enough.
And something else that we learned while building these crazy rigs is, although people find
a lot of this stuff cool to look at, we actually didn't need to invest the money in it.
So on the left is the Adroit controller, and it's made by Evil Controllers in partnership
with AbleGamers.
I mentioned it previously.
So that controller is $399.
A 500 gig Xbox One S is $280.
So that controller, to play games on Xbox, is literally more expensive than the Xbox
itself.
And I'm not saying, to be clear, I'm not saying this is not a good product.
And for some players, particularly on a PC, this is very, very important.
We just found other things that we could use instead.
And this was, to call it out, this was really the first controller of its kind
that did hardware remapping like that.
So that was great, and the Craftsmanship was great, but we just didn't need it.
We also have the QuadStick, the Puff and Sip controller,
and that also costs $399,
although there are other ones specifically made for first-person shooters
that cost more than this one.
And that piece of technology also works fine, no problems with it.
But it's not something we have people demo.
It's mostly there for show.
Like, we're not going to have person after person put their mouth on this thing in the lab.
We could have had a picture.
Right? Like, I mean, germs. They're real.
And then finally, we also have the X keys.
Now, don't get me wrong.
This box actually does a lot of stuff.
And if we're going to buy one of these items, buy that one.
It's also the cheapest at $125.
We just found that we haven't really
been using it in the lab.
So these are three things that are expensive that we purchased
that we're not doing much with.
We could have just done it with this.
So what we do use in the lab all the time is our modified Mayflash arcade stick.
Ours has been modified to have additional ports on the bottom.
The joystick itself is like $80. We paid more than that for ours
because we had someone modify it for us.
But, lucky for you, while one switch was making ours
he actually created a walkthrough on how you could just buy a Mayflash stick and
edit it yourself. So that's the short link at the bottom.
If you want to do it and go DIY.
That's his walkthrough.
So our arcade stick is actually what powers our Rocket League demo.
We have all the switches just plugged into that controller.
So switching gears a little bit, one of the reasons that accessibility experts have a
love-hate relationship with regulations, well, I'm going to give you, I'm just going to show
you why.
So I told you we wanted to build an inclusive, accessible
space, right?
We wanted to make sure that our lab was
entirely ADA compliant.
And that included not just our demo stations, not just our
tech, but things like the door.
We wanted to make sure the door was ADA compliant.
So when we did, we looked at the ADA regulations.
We said, ah, 32 inches, fantastic.
We're going to make our door 32 inches wide.
So we did.
And immediately after we started inviting community members in, we realized we had made
a huge mistake.
You see, the problem is that 32 inches, while being technically compliant, it's not wide
enough for certain scenarios.
For example, someone in a large power chair could still have difficulty navigating through
the door, or maybe someone in a smaller chair with a service dog, or someone who was blind
and being assisted by another individual.
So we redid the door.
It's now 47 inches wide.
This is the actual, this is the after picture.
So you can see it's 47 inches wide.
And then we added a separate section that's about two feet
wide that we can open as needed.
Now this is the crazy part.
As Costco, the single one-time largest cost for us, for the
lab, was that door.
So.
It just goes to show that A, think about this
stuff early on in your designing, and B, a
compliant experience is not necessarily a good experience.
Now, not only did we want a good experience,
we wanted a fantastic experience, right. And we wanted
to pay a lot of attention to details to
ensure that we had a truly inclusive space.
So we thought about things like furniture.
We knew we'd have to rearrange furniture for demos when we
brought in users and power chairs.
So we picked a couch and chairs and tables that were
light and easy to move around.
But that being said, we also made sure that every piece of
furniture was sturdy and stable so that you could use
it for support if you had problems standing or walking.
For wheelchair users, all of our demo desks have adjustable
height, and they have no obstacles underneath.
So people can roll right up to the stations.
Now you'll notice that all of our chairs and couches are in bright colors.
Now that wasn't just because we were trying to make it look pretty.
The fact is that those different colors contrasting against the dark floor
can make it easier for somebody with visual impairments to find a place to sit.
In addition, other things we thought about when it came to visual impairment are information
sheets in the lab are printed in braille as well.
We have a soda fridge, and in that soda fridge there's dividers that have all the cans lined
up and the label for each type of soda is in braille as well.
We even thought about putting in things like stands for people to place their canes while
they were sitting and playing games.
Now...
For those with sensory processing considerations, we put in adjustable lighting.
Color, temperature, brightness, it can all be adjusted to best suit individual visitors.
And those lights are all connected to an automation system that can be controlled with voice,
so that users who have troubles operating switches can control those more easily.
Now all of this being said, we learned a lot.
We still have a ton more to learn.
That's why we're regularly bringing the community into our lab.
We've brought in groups from a variety of NGOs, such as Cerebral Palsy Foundation, Seattle
Children's Hospital, and they have helped us not only ideate on ways we can make gaming
better for everyone, but how the lab can be a more inclusive and more welcoming and more
effective space for promoting our message of inclusive game design.
It's not an exaggeration to say that every single time we've brought in the community
into the lab, we've learned something new about inclusive gaming and our inclusive tech
lab.
We're also still learning that there have been some unexpected benefits that we didn't
think we would get from the lab.
So for example, we never intended to use the lab for recruiting.
But somehow, word got out, and recruiters heard about it, and we started getting these
requests to bring potential recruits through the lab.
And we were kind of surprised, asked why.
Well, it turns out that there are a lot of people
who are really inspired by Microsoft's new mission
of empowering every person and every organization on the planet
to achieve more.
Especially millennials seem to be really intrigued by that mission.
And our lab is a tangible representation of that commitment.
Another cool factor that we weren't kind of expecting was the fact that the lab would
afford us opportunities to get our message out via channels we might not otherwise get
access to.
So, for example, we've had opportunities to partner with organizations like GameStop to
highlight the space and bring broad awareness to the need for gaming and accessibility.
This screenshot was a video that was put together for GameStop TV.
It features Bryce and Evelyn, who were the masterminds behind our lab.
And this has been featured in over 7,000 retail stores.
So, wow, what an amazing way to get our word out that we never thought we would have.
So now that you've seen our lab and how it came to be and what we learned in the process,
I know all of you are like, oh my God, I'm ready to go make my own lab right now.
All right, we got you.
So that being said, we know not every budget is created equal, and so we kind of have tips
and tricks on how you can replicate what we've done based on, you know, the different resources
you may have available.
So we're going to kind of talk about small or non-existent, medium and large budgets
today.
So look, if you don't have the budget for a dedicated space,
or you're just in a really small space,
you can do what we initially did and put together
accessibility arcades.
As mentioned, they're temporary pop-ups
of assistive tech and educational materials
that can be used to educate folks
on the basic concepts of gaming and disability.
Now, again, they aren't ideal, as you won't get all the benefits of the lab,
especially that notion of having an embassy to bring the gaming and disability community
into to introduce to your development teams.
But they can be a good place to start if you can't secure a permanent location for your
lab.
So, you're going the arcade route.
Again, I want to reiterate what he just said.
Don't worry if you can't make a full lab.
Having just an arcade can be fine.
And don't worry, I have been there.
So before I was with Microsoft, I was working with Gaikai,
which is the cloud services division of PlayStation.
And I made an arcade with practically no money
and just wrangling up literally whatever I could find
at home or in the office.
So let's talk about ways you can do that and be successful.
So when I worked at GuyKai, I didn't have a budget, but I had people who were interested
in accessibility and a special occasion, Global Accessibility Awareness Day.
And I made this little mini lab based on what I could find in the office.
So what did I do?
So...
We had PS4s, we're part of PlayStation, so that was pretty simple,
and a copy of Uncharted, a hugely popular game.
So Uncharted has a whole accessibility menu with tons of assistive features,
and I had a pair of the vision-simulating goggles,
which, by the way, you can totally make on your own.
There are tutorials where you can basically take some welding goggles
and some, like, saran wrap and make them yourselves for cheaper
if you don't have the money to buy them.
So I had a stand that literally had Uncharted and its assistive features and some goggles to try to get people going.
I also just reached out to some other people.
So I mentioned Warfighter Engaged earlier.
I just emailed them and I'm like, hey, I'm doing this event.
Do you have anything I can show off?
And they're like, yeah, sure.
And they sent me controllers.
I also had another specialty game rig set up from another
charity called Game Changer, which helps children game
during long-term hospital stays.
I also got a guest speaker.
So there was a Twitch streamer named Handy, who has no arms
or legs, but plays first-person shooters.
And he was local.
And I was like, hey, I would love for you, while I'm
setting this up, just come and talk.
Like, just tell your story.
Again, that was free.
When he came, like, I was like, I can't pay you,
but here's, like, all the swag I can find in the office
to give out.
Like, and that worked.
We also set up a colorblind station with two iPads.
So in that picture is Ezra.
He's one of our programmers who is actually colorblind.
And he ran into problems all the time
because even our internal tools didn't always
have a colorblind mode.
So we took my iPad and then my husband's iPad,
On the bottom one, we had some puzzle game going.
And on the top one, we had a colorblind filter.
And so we were basically telling people to play the game looking through the top one.
And they'd be like, well, I can't play it.
And I'm like, right, that's Ezra's life all the time.
Now you get it.
So we also had two laptops that were running,
and basically what we did was we were having people race
to try to get on the company Wi-Fi using the screen reader.
Like, that was it.
It was actually a really popular station,
because most game devs are gamers,
and therefore competitive.
So people wanted to win.
And then I had all of the information materials
I could find.
Anything that was out there, I just printed it up,
and I left it on the table.
And so all of this, it was like $100.
And some of it is.
Got out of my pocket, right?
Other than like the free swag I stole from the office.
So, you know, we have this great day
where I had a lot of people come up to me
and tell me how much they learned
and I didn't really spend any money.
So it can be done.
You have tons of stuff I am sure in your office
that you can repurpose for just a day.
Absolutely.
And you know what?
If you don't have something, ask for it.
Seriously.
We didn't have an unlimited budget when we built our lab.
And look, chances are you're not going to either.
But we were incredibly fortunate that we have these
amazing partners that we work with that do peripherals, that
do televisions, that do audio systems.
And we just reached out to them and said, look, we're
doing this thing.
And we've got a finite budget.
And it'd really do a lot for us if you could help us out
and showcase some of your equipment here.
And at the same time we could use it to help demonstrate accessibility features.
And people said yes in droves.
And it's really cool because not only do we get the win of having that, you know,
being able to put our budget somewhere else,
but then those people get to show off their equipment in a really, really cool sort of way.
I cannot tell you the number of times people have left the lab going,
oh my god, I need to have a Dolby Atmos system at home.
To the demo we do with the Dolby is like.
Amazing.
I know, right?
I've been trying to convince my wife.
I'm not, no luck so far.
But it's not just donating equipment, it's donating time as well.
I mean, as an example, our lab is run by volunteers.
We handle scheduling of the space, we prep for events, we manage the tours, we give presentations,
we keep all the demos and documents up to date.
It is a ton of work, I'm not gonna lie.
But there's five of us volunteering, so between it, we're able to handle it.
It's also just a great opportunity to educate people as well.
As people volunteer, not all of our volunteers
started out being accessibility experts.
But there were people who were curious to learn more,
and now they've grown their knowledge and their area of expertise
by working in the lab.
So again, don't be worried if you don't have money
for a dedicated lab manager.
But maybe you do have some money, not all the money, but some money.
You need to be smart about where you're going to be spending it then.
And to be honest, we really recommend that you spend it on PC and PC accessories, as
this is where most of this technology is working best currently.
So if you're going to purchase these items, again,
don't dive into buying the most expensive, fancy custom stuff.
Just get something like the Mayflash,
do the DIY updates, and, you know,
get some simple switches for it.
And if you're going to have issues pitching this space as a standalone lab, think of someone
you could be a roomie with.
It would be totally reasonable to share the space with some user researchers.
Sharing is OK.
That's fine.
And if you're making an accessible space, think, you could then have play testers with
disabilities come in.
user research.
So, win-win, right?
And another good thing to invest in is, really, a nice set of headphones, if you're not going
to get the Dolby system.
You're probably not going to get that, right off the bat.
But you want to make sure that you can replicate stereo sound experiences as well, for those
who have low vision or are perhaps blind.
And finally, find some great examples of media on what you
want to teach people about.
We're lucky enough that we have multiple demo stations.
You may not be, and that's OK.
Sometimes finding a video, a pamphlet, any of that, and
having it kind of shovel-ready to show people is all you're
going to need.
All right.
Well, let's say.
You just got a whole bunch of money.
I don't know where it came from.
You're not asking.
You've got it.
Let's spend it.
OK, so the first two, we kept debating on which we
wanted to have first.
Whether it should be make this a meeting space or hire staff
for the lab, I eventually just gave up debating
and left it as is.
So invest in making this a meeting space.
As I've said previously, being able to bring people in and have them have ideas and a place
that they can talk to their people, and like I said, even bringing in people who maybe
aren't there to talk to us about accessibility that we're just like, oh, the only meeting
room that was open is our inclusive tech lab.
That's awesome.
And that's a win.
So any money you can dump into getting a camera, a great audio setup for Skype calls or whatever,
do that.
The like I said the other thing is really important is like if you can hire even a person to run the lab invest in it like I said so it takes us 5 volunteers to keep the lab like running and.
We're constantly stretched super thin so like everyone has a meeting on Monday or like OK these are the events in the lab that's happening like who can do it today and we're all just like.
I don't know and even just managing the calendar for the lab is super hard because like.
We're so popular.
But it's almost a problem.
We're almost too popular for our volunteers to be able to handle.
And I think if you guys make a space, hopefully you'd have the same problem.
Literally hiring someone.
The other thing is like having multiple demo stations is great, especially if you have
multiple people going through the lab.
You can have people doing different things at the same time, and it really keeps people
engaged.
And the next one is making conscious decisions about your space.
You know, we invested in making our door better, you know, figuring out like, oh, well, this carpet maybe is really hard for wheelchairs for some reason, like spending the money to make the room a better place.
And that kind of leads into the idea of like ADA compliance plus plus.
Like we said that, you know, compliant isn't always a good experience.
And so if you have the money to go beyond, like invest in it,
it means so much to have a space that everyone can truly be in and be comfortable.
Because that's not always something that happens all the time.
The next one, like, if you can manage to get the Dolby, like, get it.
We had a slide earlier when Brandon was presenting of the living room space,
and on the couch was a guy named Sightless Combat.
He is a blind gamer who was actually playing Killer Instinct in that,
and he was able to play in that room because of our awesome sound system.
And so you can actually enable a lot of experiences for people with low or no vision by having
truly awesome surround sound.
So like, yeah, it is super cool, but it's also super useful for the space.
So invest in it.
And then the final thing is decor.
We have a really sexy room.
GameStop filmed in there because it looks awesome.
We have other media stuff that gets filmed in there,
which means more people see it because the space looks great.
So if you have that extra money, make it sexy.
People want to use it.
And I really can't understate how great the lab has been.
The inclusive design sprints have taught
so many teams so much.
And this is actually a picture from Mixers
that we did last January.
And I was so proud of my team.
But what I saw happening with my team
is happening with other teams.
And it's gonna keep happening with more and more teams.
And we're building stronger bonds with the community
and has really helped us show that we care
as Xbox and Microsoft.
We care about this community.
And it gives us a place to focus on the feedback
that we've been giving.
And, you know, what we've made and what we have coming
that originates from or around this lab,
like, I can't wait to see those ideas go live.
And funny enough, we actually have some,
like, when I'm talking about so much has happened,
like, we have some data on that.
Yeah, so for those of you
who are a bit more data-oriented, like myself,
these numbers, I think, are really helpful
in showing the promise of a tech lab.
In five months, just five months, we've had over 3,400 individuals come and visit our
lab to learn about inclusive game design and accessibility.
Now 61% of those were visitors from internal at Microsoft, designers, producers, executives.
We've even had members from our other core businesses such as Windows and Office come
by and take a look.
Our teams are drawn by that unique experience the lab provides and the opportunity to ask
really tough design questions in a safe, comfortable environment.
Everyone always comes away better educated about our gaming and disability community,
how to engage them, and the best ways to meet their needs.
Now, 39% of our visitors, that means, are external to Microsoft.
So that's, again, NGOs, advocacy organizations, academics, business partners.
Even local school groups have come by to tour the lab and to collaborate on ways we can
make our gaming more inclusive.
Not just at Microsoft, but across the entire industry.
And regardless of whatever we're doing in the lab,
whether it's a tour, a video shoot, a design meeting,
or even just a party, our goal is always the same.
Let's educate, let's build empathy,
and grow and support our gaming and disability community.
So, with that being said,
our one ask, come visit us, okay?
Our lab is public. Please.
Doesn't matter who you work for.
Doesn't matter if you're within the industry or you're
with an advocacy group.
We just want you to come.
Visit the lab.
Check it out.
We'll share best practices.
Let's find ways to partner.
Let's ensure that gaming for everyone is just that.
Gaming for everyone, regardless of how you play, where
you play, what platform you play on, and what abilities
or disabilities you may have.
So with that...
Let's take some questions.
We have a microphone right here.
And since we're being recorded, if you have an
opportunity to ask a question, please come up to the mic.
Did we really do that good of a job?
No one has questions.
I knew it.
We explained everything.
Oh, we've got one.
All right.
Two things actually.
In terms of doing it the cheap way,
some other things to look at are artist and actually quilting
tools for the grayscale capability.
So they're tools that they're basically
clear plastic, green-red filters,
that when you put them on top of something,
it causes it to look like colorblindness.
It's actually used by artists for grayscale
to balance artwork.
Digital artists tend to not be aware of it.
They tend not to use it.
Physical artists do.
So that's another thing.
You can go to a quilting store, you can go to Joann's,
you can go to my favorite place,
which I'm not wearing today, is amazon.com,
and pick up those kind of tools.
The other thing, yeah, so it's,
they're 20 bucks, something like that,
so they're real cheap,
and it's real easy to set up in a lab.
The other thing you can do is also,
statically, use your phone, take a picture,
and then use the grayscale out of the photo app.
I think that's very similar to when I was showing the
what I did at PlayStation. Essentially, I had that app running in real time
in an iPad with the other one under it doing the same thing. Because for me it was really
important to have people try to play the game rather than
just seeing a picture. I can show you a picture and be like, ah, which one would you move?
But then the experience of watching people actually trying to play when
they couldn't see the colors, it was more impactful than just...
Here's a picture of what this game looks like.
But, I mean, you bring up such fantastic points, right?
Like, the fact of the matter is you don't need to go invest
in some $500 colorblind simulator, right,
to start educating people.
There's really great tips and tricks that you can do.
I mean, I never even thought about, you know,
getting those filters from Joanne's.
My wife goes there all the time.
I'll be attending her next visit,
so that's fantastic.
I'll look completely clueless, but I'm sure...
I'm a carrier. Both my kids are colorblind. My dad was colorblind.
Wow.
So I've had to live with it my whole life.
The other piece is, can you talk about the curb cut effect?
How has this changed the games of the teams that have gone through this?
and actually resulted in improvements for all players.
Wow.
Because that's really where the payoff is, right?
Because...
Oh, yeah. Go ahead.
I was going to say, that's really where the payoff is for the broader audience,
because I struggle with convincing my leadership that we need to go do these things
until you can prove to them that, like, all players benefit.
Well, so I'm going to let you take this, but one of the cool stats that actually came out
at the Game Accessibility Conference is everyone has this idea that, oh, accessibility features
are only for gamers with disabilities.
So it's like, well, for Assassin's Creed Origins, they actually showed the data that was something
like 63% of players were playing with subtitles on.
I'm not a statistician, but I feel like 63% of the people playing that game were not deaf.
I don't know.
Not right.
But that's just showing that there are more people using these features.
But yeah, no, we've definitely had ideas and things we've done in the games that we can show.
Well, and Tara can talk about Mixer, but since that's not technically a game, I thought I might talk about it.
I'm going to talk about it from my experience working at 343 and with other game studios.
We do these inclusive design sprints.
One of the funny things about game development, especially AAA game development, is usually
if you're working on something, it takes a few years to get out the door.
I'm not going to be able to talk about any specifics right now in terms of anything you've
seen that's...
It's not showing up yet because we just put the lab out recently.
What I will say is this.
When we bring people into that lab and we start talking about inclusive design, what
immediately comes up, almost always, is, oh, wow.
You know, there's a tiny change here.
There's a tweak here that we can make.
We already have this thing.
If we just tweak it one more degree, we can all of a sudden
have this accessible feature.
We see tons of that, right?
So it's fantastic, because I'm seeing game devs who have
already thought about features that can have some really
inclusive potential, some really accessible potential.
They just need one extra step, they come in, they make those connections, and we see them
starting to make those changes.
So it's great to help.
It's been really valuable in terms of helping people knock out some of those low-hanging
fruits of accessibility.
Go ahead.
One additional thing.
The lab is shared with our partner partners.
We bring our partners to the dorm all the time.
And recently we-
Evelyn, can I actually ask you, because they're recording us.
Yeah, sure.
I'm going to ask you a question.
I'm going to go to the mic.
We're lapped.
I don't think you want to talk into Brandon's neck.
So one of the things that we had was a hardware partner that came into the lab,
and they were pitching a particular accessory,
and once they walked them through the tour of the lab,
It fundamentally changed how they thought about their product,
and it changed the pitch for the product
to be inclusive forward.
And they went back to their developers
and started thinking more about how that really influences
the products that they bring to market.
Thank you so much for your questions.
Appreciate it.
All right, who's next?
So I had my students bug me.
Oh yeah, no, hey, I hear you.
So I'm a teacher actually building a lab.
Oh wow.
And I was more interested in what sort of findings you've had for your
developers because I have a lot of students that have a lot of these same
disabilities and I was wondering if you'd had any findings from your time
bringing teams through for the developers at your studios.
So I think.
For us, we don't want to be like, hey, this is how you should develop your games.
It's presenting the challenges that the like.
So in your case, like showing people what the students are doing.
So when we were looking at what Special
Effect was doing with the crazy controllers, we like, OK, how do we make that easier?
I don't think I said it.
So from the other side, for your actual developers that are disabled.
Oh, OK.
Yeah.
I think one of the fascinating things about the game industry right now is that we're
thinking a lot now about accessibility in games, and that's fantastic.
I mean, I've seen more...
The momentum in the last two years outdoes anything I've seen in the previous 13 years
of my career.
But the fact of the matter is, is that...
middleware tools okay game development tools are lagging behind actually right
so even I've noticed yeah right so it's absolutely something we talk about when
we're talking about game development and it actually it's surprising how often it
comes up when people say
Oh, man, you know, I'm building in this engine.
And it's just really, really difficult to implement
that feature in this engine.
Those sorts of conversations are being had.
Internally, we also have a lot of our own internal development
tools that we use.
And as you're starting to go through and run these tools
through some of the simulations things we have,
and we're showing people how to build,
you start to find those problems really quick.
So yes, we try to not just talk about inclusive game
development in terms of the end product for the customer.
But the tools need to be accessible too.
The engines need to be accessible too.
Because we want a larger group of people who identify as disabled,
people with disabilities, in the industry making the games.
And the only way that's going to happen
is if we make sure those tools and those engines are accessible to them.
Yeah, and we also totally understand that, like, it is great that we are making tools
to make game development, or games themselves more accessible, and the stuff that we're
putting out on the Xbox.
But we also know we're the end of the line.
Like, by the time you've gotten to us, like, if you hit a problem with the engine, you're
not making it to us to begin with.
So we recognize that it's great we're doing all this stuff.
But we need to have conversations and partnerships with people who are before us and earlier
in the pipeline to solve those problems.
Because if you are having the problem trying to use a screen reader with Unity, well, you're
not going to make a game.
So you're never going to use our text-to-speech API, because you literally didn't get to us.
Yeah.
A couple of things I'll mention about that is you specifically asked about developers.
We have found that when we brought people that are within Microsoft and go through the
lab, it does two things.
One, we have some existing game developers who have not self-identified as having a disability.
And they've been inspired by the space and gone back to their team and disclosed their
disability to the team, because not all disabilities are visible, obviously.
And that has further educated their teammates about why it's important to invest in the
tools that we use on a daily basis and the methodology that we apply to actually how
we do development.
The other aspect that Brandon and Tara did talk about was the recruiting aspect.
We have found amazing success, unintentionally,
having young developers coming in from all over the world.
We've had student groups from all over the world come in, Beijing.
We had folks coming in from Norway and Sweden.
And young developers were inspired by that and went back to their educators and
curriculum creators and recommended that they actually build some more.
information in their curriculum specific to accessibility.
Absolutely.
Thanks, Alan.
Next question.
Hi there, thanks so much for the session.
Oh, no, thanks for coming.
As a reminder, if you love this session,
please rate us five stars when you fill out your survey.
For sure.
This isn't her first rodeo.
Sorry.
Go on.
Okay.
So basically I have access to some space in town.
So here, the small space.
So that means I fulfilled at least the first condition of running a lab.
But aside from that, it's hidden, it's not in SOMA, it's just like an average neighborhood.
So I'm really interested in knowing the sorts of any kind of study cases I could take upon
to know, could you run a lab in a non-HIP neighborhood, much smaller scale, those kind
of things.
Yeah, well you know, we run our lab in probably, you know, I...
I don't know if you consider Microsoft hip or not.
But we're in a studio, like in a small area,
and one off in Studio B.
But in terms of spaces that are outside of a specific studio,
like in neighbors and whatnot, we actually
don't have any studies on that.
That would be a fantastic thing to look into.
So after this talk, why don't we sync up?
I'd love to chat with you more about what
you're thinking about.
And there might be some opportunities.
And we can certainly try to track down some more
information, but today.
This is still a pretty new concept from what we've seen,
and I personally am not aware of anything that's been done
outside of a studio or anything like that.
Oh, that'd be great.
Yeah, and it goes for the same for any of the audience here.
And if you guys want to, any persons here want to collaborate,
I will be happy to talk.
Fantastic.
All right, stick around then.
All right, hey, thank you guys so much.
We appreciate it.
And have a good rest of your conference.
Thanks, guys.