Hey guys, welcome to the panel, Prompto's Facebook.
How Buddy AI auto-snapshot your adventure
in Final Fantasy XV.
Okay, so we start very simple questions.
Who in this room have played Final Fantasy XV?
Great.
And maybe for those who haven't played yet, let me summarize this system a bit.
So in Final Fantasy XV, an open-world game,
your friend Prompto took a picture for you during your adventure, and the picture he takes is not an old classic screenshot,
but a stylish smart photo as seen by him inside the game.
And with our built-in SNS interface, since release of the game last year,
his photos are overwhelming internet, Facebooks and Twitters,
having us promoting our game.
So today we will talk about these features
and maybe we won't go through deep into mathematics and algorithm stuff
but we will tell you about the design aspect of these features
and I'm afraid maybe we don't have much time left
but you can always you know just ask me question outside the room or
email me
Well, talk about me.
My name, my real name is Prasad Prasad Wittayagan,
which is, I think it's too long.
So you can call me son,
just as my friends and my coworker do.
So my name is son, nice to meet you.
And I came to Japan 12 years ago, and I specialize in emotional AI.
I like to combine arts and AI together to create emotional feelings by AI characters.
And now I'm in Square Enix Tokyo, Business Division 2.
You can see on my shirt here.
It's Business Division 2 shirt, studio shirt.
And so now I'm a game designer for Final Fantasy XV,
and I'm in charge of body system and AI.
So if you play this game,
you will know Prompto, Gladiolus, and Ignis.
Well, I'm in charge of them.
I make them, I create their thoughts,
their moves, their action, their talks, everything,
including the system relating to them,
just like camp scene or photo system.
So, okay, let's start this panel,
but let me tell you to turn off your my wife phone
and don't forget to reply in the evaluation mail
at the end of this panel.
Okay, we'll start.
Okay, so Final Fantasy XV is an open-world RPG
where you can experience continuous road trip
with your best buddies.
And when we designed this game,
what we feel important the most is the UX,
the user experiences.
So you can see, all system and all designs,
all features in this game are there
to maximize the road trip experience for the player.
And of course, when we're talking about road trip,
we're talking about photos.
However, it's difficult to make players take photos inside of a game.
You know, everyone likes photos, but not all might want to take them.
But luckily, I was born in Thailand,
and Thai people are well known for their photogenic characteristics.
And, well, I have several camera geek friends who went on a trip with me.
Without being asked, they just take lots of pictures of me for me.
And that isn't bad.
Maybe I'm photogenic too.
So...
We get a new idea that it would be cool if one of your friends inside your party member
can take a picture for you during your road trip.
And Prompto is so kind as to help us.
So that's the beginnings of Prompto snapshots.
Okay.
Now we talk about the goals and policy because we need concrete goals to make a game a good game.
So we have three goals for Prompto snapshots.
Which are...
First...
the photo must serve as an achievement for the experience of players.
So when you've been to a new location, you get photos.
You meet a new character, you get photos.
Been there, done that, anything, you get photos.
Well, for memorable moments with your favorite characters too,
and also unmemorable moments like when Joker Boy is hitting you,
or when you were sent flying through the air,
or when you were turned into a stone.
Well, anything, anything that you will recall,
and you see the picture at the end of the day,
and you will say, hey, this is my adventure.
This is picture of my gameplay.
So this is first design policy for us.
Our photos must be able to express
the player, game's players.
Number two.
So this is my own policy,
but I believe good games should tell more stories
than what has actually been made or been told.
Just see this picture.
Well, you can imagine that he was reading this.
And we didn't make the scene, but you see it.
And that's the trick.
So I used it a lot in the camp scene and in picture.
So we just make photo of them joining,
enjoying themselves together.
And then people see this picture
and they imagine what happened before
and imagine what happened after that.
And they will feel that they're having fun.
And they will feel that this road trip is fun.
And the good thing about this is that
We only make one frame of motions, but you see a lot.
And that's a trick.
Also, when you see a picture,
well, automatically, people will create their own stories.
And, you know, everyone's stories might be different,
might not be the same, and that's perfect
because you can have a space for you
to create your own characters
and personalize stuff inside your head.
And one more good thing is that when we have two characters outside and they're posing together,
you can get illusion of life, as if they actually have their own private life and they're chit-chatting or flirting with each other just outside the screen.
You just don't see it, but they're alive. They're living.
So this is our second design policy.
The photos must be able to stir and wake your imaginations and enrich your road trip adventure.
Number three.
It's our gameplay sharing.
So despite the widespread use of social media,
I believe the gameplay sharing are still limited
to a very small group of players.
You know, because it takes effort to watch the clips
and it takes effort to take a good screenshot.
However, with prompter snapshots, you know, it's all auto.
So...
Well, just to share or not to share, that's the only question you have left.
And we want this feature to be a new benchmark for gameplay sharing for the next generation.
And to do that, we must ensure that our photos are unique and fun.
And of course, if you have luck, you get a unique and fun picture.
But however, we game designers believe that luck can be designed,
such as we give this kind of picture.
So normally Ignis wears glasses, but sometimes we give a picture of Ignis without wearing
glasses.
So when the player gets this, they feel that they're lucky and they want to share this
to other people.
The same goes for some rare facial expressions and rare emotions.
This way we can create luck for the user.
Or we can even do this, having players create their own luck by recreating a thing called
Prompto's snapshot skills, which you replenish a tech bar inside the battles and Prompto will
take a picture of the monster for you. And if you're lucky, he will do selfie monsters.
In this way, users can try to set their own, you know, snapshot environment and they can try and
create their own luck. And when they get a good picture, they can, well, upload it to the internet.
And also, one interesting thing is that you don't need good picture to make people want to share.
Like this.
Well, it's a very bad picture, but it's fun.
So, we shared it, and there's nothing bad about it.
Also, in this kind of situations, when some jerks...
ruining all your souvenir shots.
You know, it's happened once in a while,
but yeah, when it's happening, it's a game, it's fun,
and everyone like to share it, and we're happy with that.
And the most, and the best thing that happened
is that when Prompto is the photographer,
he can turn all accident into entertainment.
Everyone just laugh and say,
ha ha, Prompto, you did it again,
and well, that's happy for us
because we chose the right person to do the photographer.
So this is our third design policy.
Our picture should be unique and fun,
filled with pleasure and surprise,
and encourage social activities.
These are our three design policies.
So we get policies,
and now we have to design the system itself.
So there are lots of process before we have a picture.
Start from triggering, which, well,
Humans have several reasons to take pictures and to simulate it.
We need several kinds of triggering.
Start from what we call coincident triggers.
It's based on the concept that if you have cool actors doing cool moves,
then it should be cool pictures.
So we have the animator evaluating the animation they have made.
in score in term of interesting or not and then I evaluate each character in term of this character
interesting or not and we combine together and then every frame in the battles we calculate the
score and try to maximize the score while fitting well as many characters into the frame as much as
possible and when the frame and the score is high enough we can be sure that that's cool pictures.
And we also have event triggers, so we snapshot when we're sure that we can express the player
adventure when we shot this time, like in cinematics, or in special, well, interactive
events, or when you reach new destinations.
And three, we have a thing called Wim Tickers.
It's based on the concept that, after all,
you don't need reason to take picture of your friend,
do you?
Well, I do too.
When I have camera in my hand, I just take picture of my friend.
No reason is needed.
And usually, you get good picture
because your friend is good looking, and he has nice hair.
So that's the technique.
Well, after is WIM.
But although we say WIM, there's a pattern behind this.
So actually, we take WIM triggers only
when there are no other triggering events around.
So this way, WIM trigger can help
us to control the distribution of the picture during the day.
So it ensures us that we can get a picture in the night
or in the evening when the sunset is beautiful.
And also, when there are no interesting events around,
we can create one.
Even the boring cave could be fun if the characters look fun.
And that's it.
And also we have menu triggers,
so like souvenir photos or the skill snapshot
in battle that I just described to you.
So you can see that these four triggers
Actually matched really well with the three design policy we had, well because we designed
that way, but you know what I like to say is that no trigger is perfect, but combined
together it can answer the requirements we had before and it can simulate reason for
people to take photos.
Now we go to next step of theme selections.
Now we have decided when to take pictures.
Now we have to decide what and how to take pictures.
And that is a theme.
Each theme has its own styles,
own subject choices and framing algorithm.
So there are up to 20 themes inside this scheme,
but to make it simple,
let's say we have three big category.
We call this joyful category,
wonderful and exciting category.
The Joyful category focuses on snapshotting characters,
like portrait, or open, two-shot,
together, driver, or selfie,
anything that will make the character look appealing.
And wow, the theme, well, why the category, wonderful,
focuses on the world itself, and using wide angle,
like when you're running, or riding jogger ball,
or in the car.
And this category, exciting, will focus on the most mirror of the combat,
like one-on-one or battlefield itself.
And it usually uses strong tilt to simulate the situations.
We also have preset theme because in cinematic we can't just show everything that happened
behind cinematics.
You know, the artist will just angry at me.
And sometimes we do this too and we feel that it's worth sacrificing the uniqueness for
the sake of perfect background, like to fit this waterfall inside the pictures.
So that's finished the scene selections.
Now we do details enhancement.
We have to do this because sometimes reality can be boring,
nothing happens, but you need variety
and life into the pictures.
So the key is that we separate rendering in the photo world
and rendering in the game world apart,
and then we can secretly change the things
inside the photo world without having the player
realizing what happens inside the gameplay world.
And we can do things like this, having Noctis facing us and smile, she's.
And it's really amazing that just making the character she's really improve the believability of the photo you get.
It's seen that, well, you know, humans are eye contacts after all, I guess.
And then we can do posing and saturations,
or we can add things, well, bodies to do interactions.
And of course we can do this.
Adding Gentiana, photo bombing.
Well, she's a mysterious woman
who appears time to time in the photos
when actually she wasn't there.
And we add her in because I think it's fun.
And you know, when people get Gentiana,
they feel they are lucky
and they want to share this photo too.
And then we do framing calculations.
We do it by using the bone information and the collision environment to create a good frame for each picture.
Each theme has its own frames and we won't go through them here, though.
But please know that we try to use Prompto's position as much as possible for the sake of believability.
And then we do knowledge presentation.
It means we try to embed as much information as possible
into the picture.
What, who, when, why, how, into the picture.
And then we use the information text
for the further operations, such as post-filtering.
Well, I like Instagram and lots of filter here
and Prompto also use filters to the photos too.
But the problem is there are some filter
that doesn't match well with some photos like this.
You know, you don't want monochrome selfie, right?
It doesn't look good.
Or in this case, how do we call this?
I think it's...
Japanese photo booth blooming.
It's for a beauty purpose, not battle purpose.
So we don't want this to happen a lot in the game,
so we used information text to screen this property out.
But after all, it's preference,
so you can tune that inside the setting menu.
And then we do auto-albuming.
At the end of the day, Prompto will show you what happens during the day with his pictures.
And we don't want the user to spend too much time looking at this, so we try to reduce
the number of pictures from 8 to 12 pictures per day.
But do you know that we actually took more than 20 pictures per day, and we have to delete
some pictures away.
And to delete the right picture and to keep the right picture there to express one day
is tricky.
things. Considering this, we have five pictures here and you want to choose only four and delete
one. Which one should we delete? Ten seconds.
Well, there might be no one answer,
but for us, we use information tags.
And we feel that we should keep some information tag
that is interesting and unique, like jogable,
like sunset, like night, or like battles,
while we should delete some that are redundant,
like running or broad view.
So the answer, we try to delete this picture.
Yes, yes, you're right.
But things get trickier when we have lots of pictures around.
So we need a proper algorithm.
So we make our own algorithm regarding redundancy score
and uniqueness score, which can earn its own panel.
But OK, we won't explain them here.
But OK, we do some trick to get a big picture for you guys.
And then we do things like this when we show you the pictures.
Why is your face so fat?
I'm not fat! Selfies make it look that way!
Yes, we play conversations.
Stylish is always welcome now, it's nothing special.
And we try to make this conversation as much as teenager conversation as possible.
Picture perfect!
God damn it!
So the key is that to make the player feel that they are actually inside the campfire
and look in the picture with the buddies, not looking through UI.
This is all for road trip experience.
And this concludes our process for Prompto Snapshots.
Then, what do we get?
So I believe what we would get from this is the most powerful storytelling tool.
One of the most powerful storytelling tools in Final Fantasy XV.
You know, there are some guys who say things like this,
RPG is a story.
Well, Gladiola doesn't say that, though,
but a lot of people say this.
And for me, I think it's half correct.
The other half is, RPG is storytelling.
You know, story and storytelling, it's come together.
And you see, when I was a child,
I played Final Fantasy VII, and when,
okay, spoiler alert, when Aerith die,
When I reached that, I cried a lot.
And since then, I wanted to be a game designer
to make a game that made people cry.
Because I believe crying during entertainment
is one of the greatest happiness mankind could have.
And so now I'm here, making a game,
making Final Fantasy.
So.
The problem is, can we really rely on storytelling by cinematics and linear level scripts as we used to do before?
When Final Fantasy XV is a story about bonds and brotherhoods, and we are an open world game.
So how can we possibly persist on doing the storytelling
with cinematic linear level script
when players spend more than 99% of the time running
or fighting monsters inside a world map with their friends?
So if you want to do storytelling of brotherhoods
and bonds inside open world map, do it in the gameplay.
And that's by AI, and that's by using photos.
That's my answer.
And photos have their own power, their own magic.
They can create emotional pulse.
So.
All the information in the picture just come sudden to you and strong enough to create
some power inside your heart.
Especially in the very last part of this game when we want to do a storytelling of the loss
of friendships, the loss of brotherhood.
Well we can't tell you much because we don't really want to spoil you but it's difficult
to do storytelling of loss because you know it takes time to accumulate but you need some
trigger to release it.
And to make people feel lost is easy, but it's difficult because people can't recall what exactly has been lost.
They didn't see the picture.
And that's when the photo came in.
I believe photos are time machines.
It can bring us back.
to the very moment the picture was taken and it stirs our memory and make us recall the
old day and it tells us that that good old day will never ever come again.
And that strong punch, that strong emotion pulse is strong enough to make the player
who are really into our game cry.
We've been lucky.
And I think we're lucky.
And so...
Well, we come to the last part, so I want to share with you the lesson I got from making these features
because Prompto Snapshot is a very challenging and very new
too new, so we have our own lots of problems that I think I could share
The first thing I'd like to share is that you need to sacrifice something.
You can't do everything, especially when you're trying to make a new feature or new things
that no one actually knows how far we could or could not go.
No one knows the scope.
Then there will be lots of temptations coming in from the outside, from the inside.
And if you don't have a very concrete goal, you will go astray.
And then you will spend time doing things that you don't really want.
So, try to hang on to your goals, make it clear.
For example, for Prompto Snapshot Temptation 1,
why don't we have Prompto improve its photo skill?
Which sounds good, and of course, costly.
So, we revise our design goals again.
With express gameplay, well, maybe not.
Story imagination, maybe not.
Encourage SNS, maybe yes.
depends on the skills.
So we know that we should engage into this feature,
but not too much.
Just enough to answer our goal will be enough.
So our solution is that Prompto will not improve
its framing algorithm because no one will understand,
rather than we give them new filters
and giving selfie unlocked or self-shot unlocked.
And this watch make way much happier for the user.
They can use it to post in the internet
and we can get our goal
and we can sacrifice only one thing.
Temptation 2, why don't we allow players to freely instruct
from what and when to snapshot?
This sounds very great.
And this kind of temptation comes to me a lot from outside
when we are developing it.
So we revise our goals again.
Oh, it's costly because we don't have interface.
You have to be able for a user to tell what and when.
And we don't have any buttons left.
in the controllers.
And also, when you point the camera to someone,
normally people do the V sign or maybe do,
no, no, don't take me, anything.
And that's very costly.
And then we revised our goals.
And well, since the user take it, it might express gameplay.
It doesn't stir imagination, but well, it's unique.
So it's good.
So we feel we need to do this.
So the solution is that.
we make prompter snapshot skill in battles.
Because in battles, we already have interface
for telling the buddies to do what and when.
And the monster do not do V signs, so it's very cheap.
And I second something, I find that we cannot have prompter
take picture by our instructions outside the battles,
but we get something and we reach our goal,
and that's, it's enough.
Well, Temps of Entry, why don't we have the buddies playing posing animation in an actual
gameplay with our goods too, and very costly.
And then we reveal our goal.
No.
So, the key is, you must be very clear about what you really want, because when you know
what you really want, you will know what you don't really want.
And if you can't sacrifice what you don't really want to get what you really want, then
just do it.
Number two.
Be a researcher, but be a producer.
So I am an AI researcher too, and we AI researchers,
well, let's say.
Making AI is fun and we have ego to try to answer all the problems with AI.
And we try to do this too with Prompto Snapshot.
We try to challenge 100% AI framing.
And one big task we have is to put the landmark into the frame
to create sense of locations.
We try, you know, light direction calculating,
try to fit the moon, try to fit the mountain and the lake into the frame.
But, well, it didn't go well.
And...
Well, so...
I turn myself from researcher to producer and I say,
well, we might not be able to finish this
before the shipping end of the game.
And so we give up and find a new way,
like using semi-preset camera.
So the location of the character is preset
and the directions of the photo is preset,
but then you calculate AI framing from that point.
What you get is that you get variety of pictures,
but all the picture has the landmark location
inside the frame.
So, as a producer, we are successful.
But as an AI researcher, are we defeated?
Are we failed?
Maybe not.
Because, you know, with all these picture in,
user wanna know or maybe wanna care
which picture AI calculated or preset.
No, no one cares.
It's just fun, you know.
So, that's one good answer I have.
And also, the last thing I'd like to share with you is that
when you're doing a new thing, it's
really hard to share the final visions with other people.
So don't give up, and time will tell.
Because now in this day, when everything is finished,
people come to me and say, well, Prompto Snapshot is great.
They say to me, and I'm happy.
But during the time of developing,
many, many people just say that this feature doesn't work.
You know, it doesn't help a game to be fun or anything at all.
And it's my job to try to convince them every day, every day.
But it's difficult because Prompto Synapse Shot is not about making photos,
it's about making photo experiences.
And we can't share experiences unless we finish making it.
So, what I'd like to say to you guys is that if you guys are challengers and you're trying to make new things that no one knows before,
be prepared for not being understood, be prepared for critics and naysayers.
But if you're believing you're the right thing, the good thing, then just walk tall and struggle and never ever give up.
So, to put it in simple, be a researcher, be a producer, you can sacrifice something but never give up.
And that's the key to making something new, I guess.
At last, before I show you the last picture,
let me say that, well, at the very end,
the last, that's my email.
You can email me to talk with me with anything
I'd like to discuss.
And our studio email, Business Division 2,
we are looking for the challenger too,
so if you have, you know, you can email us.
And, well, this is our last picture of my team,
snapshot team.
Without this guy, this feature could not ever come true.
So, thank you very much.
Can I have just one question?
And then we do other Q&A outside.
I have a question.
So I used the feature a bunch in the game,
and I noticed that Prompto would take lots of pictures
of the main character mounting a Chocobo.
So I'd get butt shots of my character mounting a Chocobo.
And I liked the picture.
I saved it.
So after that, it kept showing me pictures of.
my butt mounting the chocobo over and over again. I was wondering is there part of your
algorithm that is it my fault? Like is it because I saved that picture and because I
liked the picture of seeing my character's butt that it keeps showing me? Did Prompto
keep taking pictures of that because it thought that's what I liked?
Well, it's not purposely, but there are reasons.
So we try to keep prompter locations as much as possible.
So if me and you ran too fast and prompter couldn't run in front of you,
and that's the reason, so maybe you should run slower.
Yeah, I usually am in a rush to jump on the code, so that could be my fault that way.
But I was wondering if there was any code that you wrote.
No, no, I don't like bots.
Thank you.
OK, so I think we run out of time,
but I'm really happy to discuss with you guys,
maybe outside the room or maybe here.
So see you then, and enjoy the rest of the panel,
and enjoy our game too.