Hi, and welcome to the 5th Annual GDC Animation Boot Camp.
This is the clap part.
I'm Mike Junglee, lead animator at Volition and co-founder of the Animation Bootcamp.
And I wanted to reflect on my approach towards creating an animation community.
It's hard to believe that five years ago there wasn't much of a game animation community
presence here at GDC or, hell, really anywhere.
The only time animation got talked about was by non-animators, usually about chasing after
ever more realistic facial animation.
which would always lead to a bunch of animators
getting salty online because after marketing,
that was marketing talk, not process.
After this cycle happened enough times,
I realized we can't get those people
to stop saying what they're selling.
We needed our own platform, a stage.
And for developers, there are few stages larger than GDC.
So armed with my naive optimism
and my own selfish desire to learn more,
I reached out to animators that I knew and respected
with far more experience and talent
to see what GDC could offer us.
We put together a pitch, myself and seven others,
and we got a day all to ourselves
to define what game animation meant to us.
After overwhelmingly positive feedback for the boot camp
and more animators wanting to present the next year,
we knew the train was not only on the tracks
but barreling along.
The next year we had 10 speakers,
then 11, last year 23, and this year 22,
which tells me we've probably hit peak speakers in a day.
In the span of five years, we went from seeing only a couple of people define what animation
means to the industry as a whole to now dozens speaking on the topic.
And not just from the purely aesthetic side either.
It also encompasses tech and design and all of the things that go into making characters
come alive.
And with this platform, the community that has grown from it has really been the best
part.
I look out into the crowd here and I see so many familiar faces from years past.
The boot camp has become as much a family reunion as an educational experience. More
important than the knowledge we walk away with, it's the bonds that make us stronger.
But growing it beyond just this one day is necessary. Yes, we all have our various social
media networks to stay connected, but how do we capture the enthusiasm and inspiration
past one day a year? How do we get more people involved? Ideally, I want everyone that loves
what we love to be involved in this.
I recently read Thank You for Being Late by Thomas Friedman,
which really cemented my mindset when it comes to information sharing.
In a world where everything is accelerating at the speed of Moore's Law,
fully embracing the speed of change is how you adapt and grow in our craft.
The days of getting good at one thing and living off that thing for the rest of your
life are passing us by.
The rate of how quickly things change means we need to be continually learning and growing
our craft.
You can complain about the good old days when all animators had to do was just sit down
and open up Maya or Max or whatever and animate, but that's akin to doggy paddling in white
water rapids.
We all need to learn how to ride a kayak.
Hell, maybe even a skiff.
And because all of this can be a scary thing for someone to do on their own and businesses
that thrive and make money off of the old approach of taking that knowledge and walling
it off and owning it are often too afraid, slow or unwilling to help, it's up to us,
the community, to help each other out. To provide the tools and knowledge needed to
keep us all from gulping down water when there are boats all around us that we can get into
and ride this information wave together. And this here is where all of that starts.
At GDC today, we have the boot camp,
which has 22 speakers across 10 blocks of talks
with five and a half hours of knowledge sharing overall.
Every talk in here speaks to the different approaches
and skills needed by different animators
across the industry to bring a character to life.
And during the main conference,
there are even more animation talks, as you see here.
Since the bootcamp is only one day,
but the enthusiasm to share is so large,
more and more talks are appearing at the main conference.
I'll personally be practicing what I preach
on Wednesday morning at 9.30 a.m.
about Agents of Mayhem in the West Hall.
And while we're lucky to be here,
this is only a fraction of the larger
game animation community who couldn't be here.
And democratization of knowledge is a key component
of staying afloat with the wave of accelerations.
The first step to help them all out is to take pictures and notes of everything you see and share those with the hashtag GDCAnim.
The second step is the animation exchange happening tomorrow in partnership with Twitch,
in which we've programmed eight more hours of all-new talks with over 30 speakers to be streamed free and live to anyone with an internet connection.
Tomorrow from 2 to 10 p.m. Pacific Time, animation is taking over Twitch.
Animation Exchange is the perfect example of adapting to the needs of the community
because getting two days at GDC hasn't been possible and the outcry for more talks and
more affordable options is one that has not gone unheard by all of us.
And Twitch has been gracious enough to fully support our vision of open knowledge sharing.
And then past that we have animstate.com which we've envisioned as a hub for all things game
animation online. I know we sort of dropped the ball with this last year so this year we've
reached out to more of the community to help because many hands lift all boats if you'll
forgive me mixing my metaphors here.
And if you have a strong vision for what you want this community to be or you want to get
more involved, there's nothing stopping you. This all started with one person reaching out to
seven others. We decided to build a boat, join in arms and take a ride down the river. And now
none of us will ever let go, Jack. So if you feel like you're treading water as it rises all
around you, this is where you can find your life raft. This is where you can find your
community. Come aboard. We're expecting you. Thanks and enjoy the show.
I'm panicking, guys.
Thanks.
I mean, I know, but how does this work?
The mouse isn't... it's a track pad.
Oh, God.
I read off my phone again, because that's how I always practice, because I only have
one monitor.
So, you'll forgive me here, getting set up.
All right. I'm going to be talking to you about how all students know nothing and all
game devs are jerks. It's easy to spot a student. Like Neo finally seeing the code of the matrix
you see the pattern. The same questions over and over again. You get used to being accosted
for feedback and in turn used to hearing why that feedback is wrong. And in time you'll
come to peace with simply tuning the stupid out.
But students, don't be discouraged because you're undereducated.
Everything's okay because all working developers are assholes anyway.
Trust me.
Furthermore, they're easy to spot too.
Conversations are tediously one-sided.
Everything you say is wrong in some way and there is no tolerance for your inexperience.
Devs spend more time checking Twitter than making eye contact.
And you start to recognize they're already too salty about the industry to really be
worth the time it takes to flag them down.
You should be at ease knowing that you're younger, hungrier, and typically nicer than
they are.
Okay.
We're off to a bit of a rough start here, but can you blame me?
I can all but guarantee that everyone in this room has felt some semblance of these impressions
at this point in their career.
And if you haven't, well, this could be the week for you.
I would like to know who, as a developer, please participate, has been fed up and maybe
a little sad after having left a confrontation with a student.
Yeah, come on.
And students, past or present, who has wound up in a precious conversation with a working
dev only to leave thinking, fuck that guy.
Where have these sentiments even come from?
I am in this unique headspace right now where I can vividly recall feeling the crushing
disappointment of meeting a developer who didn't give me the time of day and yet I still
presently find myself capable of seeing students around and thinking, ugh, I just don't want
to deal with this right now.
Does anybody else remember the roundtables of three years ago, the students versus developers
civil war?
Well, to me, it's painfully memorable as a time I watched a community I longed to be a part of,
verbally thrash and tacitly label a community I was still a part of as uneducated millennials,
without questioning for a second whether or not they may have been a little out of touch.
And I've seen many more students harassing developers in the middle of important,
even private conversations with their peers,
who've clearly slipped away for five seconds of alone time
and felt myself cringe thinking how exhausting it must be to be here,
and how tragic they no longer get to experience this in a carefree, self-indulgent way.
Nobody wants to act like this.
Students are obviously trying to learn,
and as a dev, I know I do want to help.
But if someone comes up to me asking, how do I animate?
I get annoyed, and I've pretty much typecast myself
as the permanent freshman around here.
So what do we do?
Well, as Mike just mentioned, this community
is still relatively new, and that means change is possible,
if not inevitable.
If I can do something to help even a few people in this room today,
I'd like to think it'll eventually snowball into a brighter tomorrow.
So I want to help students, or anyone eagerly looking to level up their career,
talk to other professionals in less confrontational ways,
and I want to help devs speak to students without being exhausted
or inadvertently making ourselves out to be jerks.
So, students.
Get over it.
There's no shortcut for hard work.
That means stop asking for them.
Don't ask about the pencils someone's using
with an inclination.
It's the tools they use that got them where they are.
I spent my entire education studying Maya
and I haven't opened that program
for more than one minute in three years.
Meanwhile, as a professional,
there's a certain part of your career you take for granted
simply because you're naturally inclined to work hard at it.
Please do your best to have patience.
Aren't you here to learn too?
How much did you learn only after you got your first job?
Plus, if you don't want there to be so many students bugging you,
then maybe there should be more entry-level jobs.
I know that's not necessarily up to anyone here,
but I bet a lot of this grief would go away
with opening an appropriate outlet.
Students could be like, hey, OK, I get it.
I'm new.
I don't know a lot.
But I'm not desperate, all right?
At least I'm working.
We can sculpt these noobs into the kind of colleagues
we want to work with.
Students, I know it's scarce out there,
but desperation's not attractive on anybody.
Learn to read the room.
There is a time and a place for serious reviewing.
Leave the tablet in the hotel room for the night.
Definitely leave the 30-pound pro gaming laptop
in the room for the night.
Yeah, we see you standing at the end of the bar waiting for someone to come get a drink alone
so you can pounce on them for feedback and please, maybe a job?
There are other important parts to working as a professional that don't involve your reel,
and typically places like GDC are better for making those kinds of connections.
And devs, try to remember where you came from.
I'm not saying you need to become best friends with someone 15 years younger than you, but
think about what even five minutes of conversation could mean to them, where no matter what is
on your resume, the mere fact you have a job makes you an idol to them.
Don't be the kind they regret meeting.
Obviously, this is all rather over the top, extreme language into response to this community's
collection of horror stories, but it's first thing Monday morning and what a better way
to get the blood pumping than trying your hand at insulting a room of your betters.
But from this, it is my utmost desire that this week you take a look at the folks around
you, not just your buddies from years back, and maybe make some connections you might
not have otherwise made.
I'm talking meaningful interactions.
Don't just network.
Don't fucking network.
Talk to people.
Be interested in them.
Get to know them.
Talk to me.
I'm in the first talk of the week and I have nothing better to do after this.
There were a lot of closed doors in 2016.
Let's start this year by opening a few in return.
My name is Lana Byszynski.
I'm an animator at Blizzard Entertainment for Heroes of the Storm.
Thank you very much.
Oh, right. This is, I guess, the first slide.
All right.
All right, so I'm Matt Kahn. I'm CEO of MidBoss,
and we do a couple different projects.
Recently, our game, Read Only Memories, just went on PS4 and PC.
We also run the gaming convention,
the LGBT gaming convention, Gamer X.
So today I'm going to talk a little bit about just political messaging and kind of how you
go about pushing your message and if it's better to do it in an overt way or if it's
better to be subliminal and what the costs are associated with each. Basically weighing
the best way to get your message out while also weighing the market.
To do so, we're going to be looking at the implementation of marginalized voices and underrepresented themes in interactive media
and how strongly they're emphasized or prioritized.
Other mediums are doing this well. This is not new.
If you look at TV shows or comics, a lot of other mediums are actually doing subversive work really well.
For instance, with Empire, on Fox, you have a gay POC who's...
an on-camera lead in Jamal. And despite being a show about hip-hop and big celebrities,
it also works in intersectionality and deals with issues like mental health and complex
queer issues. With Steven Universe, this is another show that I think is doing subversive
political really well. At the surface, it may seem like a show about a young boy fighting
evil, but actually deals with
lesbian space rocks and non-traditional living relationship.
That definitely is something that was not worn on the surface.
Even stuff like Young Avengers, it's a comic book, they fight evil, they fight crime.
But it also deals with, there's numerous queer characters and it showcases their lives in a way that is not othering.
It's very kind of like, yeah, they're just another part of the team.
But when you do games, you have to be careful about how you put your political messaging. If
you're too overt, you're only going to hit a certain audience. And when you only hit that
certain audience, that audience, you're limiting yourself to a very specific niche of people.
With games like Mario is Missing, you could say that their messaging was overt, but
probably only hit a certain specific audience. Even with games like My Ex-Boyfriend the
Space Tyrant, this is a good example of a game that's very overt with its political messaging
in that it's clearly what the...
the creator wanted to create, but people who might not be outside of the intended audience
probably would not play that game. So a good subversive game theoretically is a game like
Mafia 3 because even though it's a pretty cut and dry crime game, it introduces themes
like racism through the gaming play style. So like when you commit crimes in white neighborhoods,
the police come faster.
like that. Games like Overwatch, which is a first‑person competitive shooting game, also
showcases a globalist team of do‑gooders. Their unity and friendship across social and
economic bounds is kind of a political statement in itself. And also Tracer just came out,
which is pretty cool.
even games like Mortal Kombat 10, even though it's a hyper violent game you have female
characters that are top tier fighters and they even have a gay character who is referenced in
the story and he's still a badass and killer like all the other ones but he's just cool and
badass but also he's gay and proud of it.
So really quick, I want to show you another, so I talked about some subversive games, but I
also want to talk about post-struggle games. So these are games that kind of jump over the
political ramifications of a lot of their choices. And usually they're made by younger
designers. So like in games like Stardew Valley, you can just kind of marry anyone you want. Or
in Undertale, there are sexual characters, asexual characters and gay characters and poly
characters, a wide range of people. And so while this is great, there's definitely some issues
in that it doesn't directly address any of the problems. It just kind of...
moves past them, jumps over those issues.
that we live in. However, these can also be great because it shows young people a better world,
a world where there's potential realities. So if you look at a game like Burrito Galaxy 65,
they have a non-binary lead and they're just treated as another person in the game. That's
something that's really cool for young people to be able to look at and be like, oh, cool, I
can see that world. So I think there's benefits and negatives to doing post-struggle things.
So we do a couple of different things. We run Gamer X, the LGBT focused gaming convention.
We've learned there's a lot of different ways.
that you can actually bring people in. We do stuff like genital bathrooms and having
pronoun stickers and stuff like that. It's really low cost and it actually allows you to get a
lot of benefit because it brings a lot of people in who might not be interested.
With our game Read Only Memories, we use a lot of the same tactics where we have things like
gender pronouns and things like that at the beginning of the game that don't really affect
the gameplay of most players, but for the people that actually use those things, they feel
that much more engaged and feel like they're part of that world and that they belong there.
Generally, I say if you're making games, try to put in a political message, if you want to,
because people generally like things with a message.
there's a very loud minority that say we don't want politics in games but games are art and
like any art politics are part of it. Subversive can be very appealing because when we make
games and for a lot of people if you want to make things as I was saying earlier if your
political messaging is too overt potentially it might not reach that same audience. So when
you make things that are subversive you can kind of reach a wide audience and kind of slip
your message in. However subversive can be negative because sometimes when you're too
subversive you're actually perpetuating a lot of the same issues and stereotypes that you're
saying that you.
trying to fight against. And a lot of times if you're trying to make your characters too
mainstream, you're actually kind of taking away what makes them special and telling them
they just need to be like everyone else. But ultimately only you know you. You've got to
decide what you want to make and what matters to you. And you need to decide if you want to
try to make a game that makes money or if you really want to make a political message. And
only you know what you're willing to drop off a little bit and add a little bit more.
But yeah, I mean, I think just have confidence in yourself.
But in general, make what feels right, figure out your goals,
what you want to say and achieve, but also allow for
agility, and I think you'll have a good time.
You can reach me at MattCon, M-A-T-T-C-O-N-N, and I really
appreciate letting me be part of this.
Thanks.
OK.
Bringing fans into the development fray, my name is
Mariel.
So, I work at Lab Zero Games as the lead animator and art director.
And at our studio, we've had the experience of crowdfunding a game and a half.
We funded DLC for Skullgirls and we got funding for our next game after Skullgirls called Indivisible, which we're working on now.
So, you might know that part of the deal in crowdfunding is that your backers expect a certain level of transparency.
In exchange for making your game happen,
many of them want a look behind the curtain
to see how it's all done.
And teams take a lot of different approaches
to transparency.
Some provide write-ups and emails,
some provide gameplay videos,
some stream their development,
and some provide nothing
and they run far, far away with your money.
For us, though, we like to stream development
whenever someone has a couple uninterrupted hours to spare.
So we'll stream ourselves working on whatever it is
we're doing to Twitch for anyone to come out and hang out
and chat.
For me, as animator, that means I
get to stream myself animating.
I don't get to do it as much as I'd like,
but I actually really enjoy streaming
because it helps me focus when I know people are watching.
No more one minute that turned into maybe 10 minute Twitter
breaks.
It also helps people learn exactly what goes into making our games with no actual effort
on my part.
I'm just letting them watch my screen while I do it.
I think it takes a lot of the mystery out of it so that people better understand our
process.
Like, for our games in particular, which are 2D hand-animated games.
People would think they're like Newgrounds flash animations or that the computer magically
makes in-betweens for us.
So when I stream, they actually get to see me painstakingly draw every stupid frame.
And also what's nice about having another dozen or hundred pair of eyes is that sometimes
the chat will spot things that you don't.
Which is kind of hard to admit because of course you think you know everything, but
also I found that there were times that I didn't.
I was animating a taunt for one of our characters in Skullgirls named Valentine, where she sucked
on a lollipop.
But then the viewers chimed in and said, Valentine, her official bio actually says that she hates
candy, so she wouldn't have a lollipop.
And I had actually completely forgotten, and so I had to change it to a chocolate bar.
I was animating a wrestling move for one of our characters, Beowulf.
I had keyed out poses that were physically possible, but as I started to actually animate
them, I ended up animating his arms in a motion that wasn't physically possible.
And I didn't even realize it until the chap kept yelling at me.
And we have this character, Sara Bella, who has giant sentient arms on her head that when
they're not the focus of the animation, I kind of fudge what they're doing.
In one animation, I had accidentally started to animate the arms clipping through a hoop
she was sitting on and the chat helped me figure out a solution.
And just generally, opening up your work,
to let them chime in, you can actually learn things
that you didn't know about.
I learned about wrestling moves for Beowulf,
or someone can chime in and comment on the music
I'm playing and I can learn about something else.
But it's not all fun and games and getting work done.
It's easy to fall under the trap of not getting
anything done because you got sucked into the chat.
You definitely need to resist the temptation
of jumping in to talk to everyone,
even though it's nice to be engaged.
You also need to be aware of what you can and can't stream
or what's even interesting enough to stream.
Sometimes my work is just organizing files
or writing emails and that's no fun.
And you don't want to stream big spoilers either
because you want your players to have something new
to look forward to.
These are just a few of my experiences
but the overall impact it's had has been really beneficial
to our games and the communities around them.
We get new people all the time who just saw a retweet
of a stream happening and get introduced to our work.
Because of that and our willingness to engage
and open up to anyone willing to listen and watch,
I think we've built a really solid community
around both our games and our team
with new people coming in all the time.
And it's rewarding for me too
to see people engaging with our work,
even when it's boring stuff like me
trying to figure out how to draw a hand.
And it's a nice excuse to tell my coworkers
not to bother me because I can shout back
that I'm streaming so they need to leave me alone.
And hopefully, by being transparent about our process,
we can also encourage newcomers to start creating
their own games, since now they've seen a huge part
of what goes into game development by watching us stream.
And I think that when we get more people
becoming interested in creating new
and different types of games, we all benefit.
Whether you're a developer or a fan,
more games and more communities around them
means more stuff for all of us to play.
My name is Meryl Cartwright. That was my micro talk. Thank you.
Okay. Let's do this thing. Hi, everybody. I'm Matthew Russell. I've made games for Valve
and Epic and now Amazon Game Studios. I'm here today to talk to you about engaging with
your community, especially when your community thinks something that you've done to your
game, like an update, DLC, or patch.
really, really sucks. To do this we need to take a step back and see what community was like way
back in olden days before DLC, before weekly updates, before games as a service, before user
generated content, hell before games were even video games to have a community around.
Back then, a person or a group of people made a thing like a movie or a TV show.
That thing went out into the world to be consumed.
People bought it and they consumed it.
The closest to a back and forth dialogue were reviews by people who had their own TV shows
to basically tell you if something sucked.
Then in the late 70s and early 80s, we finally saw the rise of video games, first on consoles
and then on home PCs.
But like other entertainment content, everything was primarily a one-way street.
A studio made a game, shipped it off to GameStop, and then they got started on the next one.
But with the introduction of PCs like the Commodore 64 and Apple II, and don't forget
BASIC, all of a sudden people like you and me...
Okay, people like me because I'm old, we had the opportunity to start creating our own
totally radical video games.
But and on top of that, PCs saw the introduction of something called the Internet.
This let people from around the world who had common interests like video games connect
with others.
Not only could people talk about games together, but then they could also start making games
together and this ushered in a whole new world of collaboration.
But like I mentioned before, video games were pretty much status quo when it came to how
they were created and shared with the world.
Really just one way.
Bulletin boards and then eventually forums gave players the ability to create and share
their thoughts, scores, secrets, and exploits.
It wasn't until the concept of games as a service though, with both subscription based
and free to play games, that we saw the relationship between player and developer become really
dynamic and kind of dramatic.
Can you say SWAT?
No.
I don't think so.
Today's player developer relationship really isn't anything new though.
To see where its roots came from we have to take a look back at the concept of art patronage.
How this worked was a really wealthy benefactor would pay an up and coming artist or like
a great master to do nothing but create art.
How fucking cool is that?
Am I saying you're the next Leonardo da Vinci or Michelangelo? Probably not. But you could be
the face of whatever project you're working on, especially if you are part of a small indie
team where everybody wears a lot of hats or if you're in a big studio that really pushes for
transparent development with their community. Well, you found yourself in a position to
engage in this dynamic new relationship. What now? Well, first, you need to know your
potential audience. You've got two. Group one, trolls, leave them under the bridge. They
just crave attention. Group two,
pretty much everybody else. Well, almost everybody else. A thing to consider about everybody else is
some of those folks, they want to tell you what's wrong with your game and that's fine,
but then they want to tell you how to fix it. And unless you read their comments and you're like,
holy crap, you've got to work here now, you can kind of leave their feedback as don't respond to.
Now what? Well, remember, you can always say nothing. Seriously. This is always your first
best option. Anything you say is the verbal equivalent of gas on a fire. I mean, how many
times have you seen a developer reply to an email or a forum post only to see it become part
of an article on a website?
If you feel like you absolutely have to respond to someone, first find out if you really are the right person to do it.
Unless you're specifically given the go-ahead, you should never speak on another department's behalf,
like design, art, animation, marketing.
Marketing people will kick your ass if you try to respond on their behalf.
So it turns out that you are the right person.
Well, here we go. Remember what I said before, though.
And I can't stress this enough.
You can still say nothing.
It's better to keep your mouth shut and have them think you're an idiot
than to open your mouth and kind of prove you are an idiot.
So, despite my previous suggestions, you're committed to responding. First thing to do,
leave your ego at the door. It isn't about you. Your update or patch screwed up a game
that they spent 30 or more hours a week playing. If you take it personally, you've missed the
whole point of why they emailed and you've kind of already lost.
Respond with humility and transparency. If you treat them the same way you would like to be
treated, more often than not, one of two things is going to happen. Either first, they won't
respond at all. This happens more often than you think. Or two, they'll do a complete 180 and be
like, holy shit, I didn't know real people responded to this.
During your exchange, try to find out what actually made them mad, like you nerfed their
favorite character. Outside of trolls, most people are writing because they genuinely love
your game, which is now kind of really their game, too. If you can find that thing, you'll
have common ground. This is an opportunity to have a genuine interaction with them. You can
take someone who once called you a complete dumbass and was probably Googling how to
swap game dev and turn them into a legitimate, like,
outspoken proponent of your studio and your game. But you're not going to make everyone
happy. It just doesn't work that way. And as long as you're humble and transparent and know
when to keep your mouth shut, that's fine. You'll know you're good and you'll be fine when all
of that stuff shows up on Kotaku. And it will. Thank you very much. Have a great GDC.
Hi, my name is Gabriela Vera Ojeda and I am a freelance animator and co-director at Dames Making Games,
a non-for-profit based in Toronto that supports women making and playing games,
and I'm here to talk about how important engaging with local communities is.
So reaching out to a local games community can prove helpful
when you're facing times of uncertainty,
whether it's learning more about how the industry works,
wanting to refine skills,
or simply needing support during stressful times.
Communities can be pillars that hold us up.
Being a member of a local community
helps keep that community active.
and an active community can continue giving back resources to those who need it,
like myself when I first decided to get involved locally in Toronto about two
years ago when I was still in college.
As a student, I stayed inside my college bubble
for a fairly long time, but once I stepped out
of that comfort zone, I found a lot more resources
that I used to improve my art and animation skills.
I wanted to focus on my studies as much as I could
to develop my skills and graduate with a strong portfolio.
In my second year of college, I had gotten exempt
from a couple classes, so I decided to set aside that time
to get to know my community better
and prepare for post-graduation life.
I signed up to volunteer at events throughout the city while also honing my creative skills.
I immediately felt very motivated by the people I met, artists and designers who had been
in games for long, as well as those who were in a similar position as me.
New to the career, new to the community, not quite sure how or where we fit in.
This was quite the change from my original plan.
Go to college, keep my head down, work hard,
graduate, get a job.
I can be very shy at times.
I'm definitely not the loudest voice in the room
and this is my first time meeting most of you,
so avoiding community stuff seemed ideal
if it meant more time to animate.
But I found out that wasn't challenging or fulfilling enough,
and even though I am an introvert at heart,
I was curious to know what I could do to get involved
with something while I was still a student.
Getting out there and lending a hand at these events
showed me their importance in how it builds community.
During this process of volunteering
and trying community stuff out,
I was also looking to find a particular space
and community I could be a part of,
then sticking to one that felt right,
which is how I ended up joining Dames Making Games.
Even though at times balancing community involvement
and college were difficult, it was worth it.
College helped me develop skills.
Getting involved with my community helped me
sharpen skills I would need to give back to my community,
like not being scared of speaking from strangers.
And as a Latina immigrant, my community empowers me and supports my voice,
as well as others who belong to marginalized groups,
giving importance to our stories and experiences.
Amplifying these voices will always bring positive changes.
And both from my personal experiences and in experiences within the community,
supporting marginalized groups makes a community stronger
and creates a healthy and inviting space.
After all, we are stronger together.
To reference an example, Dames Making Games focuses
on women, trans, non-binary folk,
working in and playing games, offering events,
workshops, and mentorships.
Most recently, our 15th member game jam, FetFatal5.
It's a priority to have a space
that is both safe and welcoming.
Collaborating with other organizations is also key.
Running workshops aimed at marginalized groups is great,
but it's important to work together
so all communities move forward.
and the content is both respectful and benefits those who it is aimed at.
Dames Making Games has been organizing in DigiCade for two years,
a program run in partnership with local Toronto group Indigenous Roots
to offer a long-form program to Indigenous women interested in making games,
providing them with the space, equipment and mentorship to do so.
If members thrive, the community also thrives.
Living the purpose of community in the hands of members gives a chance for everyone to shape community according to its interests and values.
This also ensures members get the support that they need.
I realize that I can be dedicated to both my art and my community.
While I was reluctant at first to get involved with anything relating to community,
I very quickly felt its impact in how I communicated with others
and how I prioritized my time in general.
In conclusion, reaching out locally is important because it's a chance to get involved
in ways that can impact you creatively
and an opportunity to find support among artists and developers in your area.
My personal takeaway is that as a younger artist,
it has inspired my creativity and my passion
for being involved with communities
that support marginalized groups,
communities that give us opportunities to grow,
inspiring us to keep going.
And had I dedicated myself only to work and nothing else,
I would have never had a chance to.
have some of these experiences that influence me creatively,
having those very unique connections will never hinder work.
It will only strengthen it even more.
Thank you.
This is working.
There it is. Okay. Good morning. Good morning. Holy shit, there's a lot of you. My name is Gwen,
and I'm a technical animator. I've been in the industry for about a decade now.
Most recently, I co-founded a small studio in Boston, and we launched
The Flame in the Flood one year ago today.
We have... We're up for two awards at the IGF.
Yeah, but I'm not here today to talk about that.
The topic today is community, which is fantastic.
I'm really glad we get to talk about this.
Communities are wonderful.
There's absolutely no negatives being a part of a community, and I want to go over several
of the benefits that there are to being in a community.
The first thing I want to talk about is how beneficial engaging the community is for your
skill as an animator.
I remember when I started out as a student, I thought the time I would spend animating
would make me a better animator.
But it turns out the time you spend on social media makes you a better animator.
And so I think I'd like to talk about how to do that.
I think the first thing everyone here should do
is to go on Reddit and find all the subreddits
that have to do with gaming and animation and follow them.
Then I think you should find like several hundred people
to follow on Twitter.
There's Pinterest boards, websites, Tumblr blogs,
there's people Twitch streaming themselves
and there's YouTube videos with tips and tricks and shorts.
And you need to look at all these resources
because the reality is resources
are what's gonna make you a better animator.
And every now and then you're gonna find some resources that are truly fantastic,
like no bullshit, Christian's YouTube videos are actually really good.
Like, they're fantastic.
And they might inspire you, like if you watch his videos,
you might be inspired to make better animations,
or something better might happen.
You might be inspired.
to make your own YouTube videos.
And this is great, because if you're doing this,
then you're engaging the community directly.
I mean, you're engaging the community as a YouTuber
rather than as an animator, but that's what you want.
Because in reality.
It's the likes you get on your videos and the number of views and the content you make
that's not animation that really determines your skill as an animator.
You'll know you're making it when you're making Twitter polls and podcasts.
And I can hear you.
I know what you're thinking.
You're like, but Gwen, I want to animate.
I want to be an animator.
Shouldn't I be animating?
No.
That's the wrong idea.
It's talking about animation.
It's thinking about animation.
It's reading about it.
That's what makes you a better animator,
and the community will help you get there.
There's other benefits to being in a community as well.
For instance, the collaborative problem-solving
we do as a community is really beneficial.
When you're looking through all these YouTube videos, you're going to realize
that we've already got a lot of these things figured out. Like if I want to animate a
character landing, I know exactly how a character should land. It's been drilled into my head.
I've seen it over and over. And I think that's fantastic.
Because we troubleshoot these problems together,
we save so much time and energy as developers.
And honestly, I think the best case scenario
is when we all come together as an industry
and we turn game development into a collaborative experience.
You have to understand, I'm an Indian,
even when I was in AAA, like the hardest part
about making a game is pre-production.
Figuring out exactly what it is you should be making.
You have all these goals and like you want to eat and you just can't figure out what to do and it's very stressful.
But fortunately last year we came together as an industry and we realized
we just need to make a character-based shooter with MOBA elements.
And it's really comforting when your livelihood comes from your art to know that we
have all come to this conclusion because that means it's probably right.
Oh, God, I forgot.
The best part about being in a community
is, of course, the feedback you get.
And I don't just mean the animation community,
though the animation community
and the game development community
will give you great feedback,
but the gaming community, man, they go above and beyond.
Like, they're great at reaching out
and letting you know what they think.
They'll find you.
They'll write you emails, they'll write you reviews,
they'll find you on Twitter,
they'll find you on LinkedIn, that's weird.
oh, here's a fun thing, they can, so when somebody on Steam decides they want to return
your game and they want a refund, they can write you a little note to let you know why.
Like here's some of the things people have written us. The letter T. Character so ugly
I shat my pants. Wow, we had an impact there.
And some people get a little stressed out by this.
I know it seems like when people give you these reviews,
what they say they want, and actual metrics,
and purchasing data don't align at all.
But that's the community doing you a favor, really.
And I think the best case study for this is Warframe.
Warframe is a game that,
one of the highest grossing games on Steam last year.
It did super well.
And the reviews are quite negative.
But the gamers put so much time.
and energy into reviewing that game.
They really did the research,
and I think that's why Warframe is such a good game, really.
And I think the devs appreciate that.
And so in conclusion,
I hope you've learned three things from this talk.
I hope you know that you should research
as much as possible.
Use social media for this.
I think you should know
that you don't need to reinvent the wheel.
The community has made the perfect wheel.
Use the wheel.
And I think you should immerse yourself
in the feedback directly from your gamers.
I hope you're a part of all these communities and I hope you go ahead and follow me.
If you'd like to be part of my community, I'm daragoldfish on Twitter.
I have a podcast called the Dialog Box on iTunes and obviously I have a YouTube account
with tips and tricks videos.
Check them out.
Have a wonderful conference.
Here you go.
Thank you.
it's making sounds. Okay, there we go. My talks, I guess how I figured out how to be part of a
community, it took me a long time. So here we go.
All right. Hi, I'm Matt Majors, a loner, a rebel. I attended Cal Arts to become an animator
nearly 20 years ago. It worked and now I am. I've worked at a few places, Rhythm and
Hughes and Weta, and now for the last 14 years I've worked at Pixar. I love working at
Pixar now, but there was a time I didn't and I couldn't figure out why.
I spent my first 10 to 15 years both in and out of school so obsessively focused on being
a great Pixar animator that I neglected nearly everything else. I was finally part of a community
that I had wanted to be part of so badly but I wasn't feeling a part of it. By the end
of my 10th professional year, I was burnt out, tired of animation, tired of the wonderful
community I was so fortunate to be part of, tired of not understanding what my voice was
in the art I was making. If I'm going to make something, oh, jeez.
Where are we going here? Slide burnt out. There we go. All right. Sorry. Yeah. You wouldn't
realize that I work on computers all day every day. All right. So anyway, if I'm going to make
something, it damn well better be good. Otherwise it's not worth the effort. I love to
improve and I love to see the before and after difference. The question was, how do I
improve if I feel like I'm done? So I started asking what next? Am I going to be a park
ranger?
I knew I'd invested more time and effort into this than anything else in my life, even skateboarding,
and I spent way too much time doing that.
So there must be something I love about animation, I just needed to find it.
I needed to make something different of my own.
I love games, so I decided to try developing one.
Imagine you're all deeply aware of this. Developing games is really damn hard. But it was
great. I was talking to a lot of new people who had different talents. I was using my
animation sensibilities and design skills to answer questions I hadn't asked let alone
answered before.
I iterated the ever-loving hell out of that game, a full 23 versions of three completely
different mechanics over the course of five months.
As it started to wrap up, I didn't really feel I had anything viable, but I learned
a lot and established ties to a new community and was realizing that maybe animation was
in my future.
Meanwhile at Pixar, I got lucky and landed a spot on the Inside Out team.
I decided to take four months and focus on nothing more than animating and getting to
know more people with the intensity I'd use to pursue my game.
That way I could really answer the question, do I want to be an animator?
I focused on making every bit of animation the absolute best I could. I struggled to
find the same truth in my work as I had in my game. I ate lunch with different people
every day because I enjoyed meeting new people while working on my game. I communicated as
clearly and concisely as I could about every aspect of my job. My take away from those
four months, animation is fucking amazing.
Finding the truth in your work is the best way to enjoy it. Interacting with a variety of
people is great. Critical thinking and problem solving are everything. But I still felt I
didn't necessarily understand my voice. I love to cook. I do it every day on weekends. I go
nuts. It's physical. It's mine. The sear on a piece of meat. My call. Ingredients I use. My
choice. However, cooking for yourself isn't really that much fun. I'm feeding people. Their
reaction matters. It's communication.
I love riding skateboards too.
Ramp or street skating today, up to me.
Throw myself off this massive flight of stairs
if I really want to.
However, I like to skate with friends.
I like to be part of a community.
For some reason, I've never asked myself this,
but one day I realized,
how do I know when and what to do
in these other pursuits that I love?
It's what I like.
That's how I know.
How do you think it should be done?
That's the most important question.
That's what sets your work apart from everyone else's.
Before becoming burnt out, I worked in a vacuum of my own making. I was so focused on
trying to be great, I was ignoring everything else, including myself. You can't become great
by trying to be great. You can, however, find the truth in your work, that thing that gets
you excited, and use that to make your work the best it can be. Whether you thought it was
great or not is not up to you.
The only thing you've got is yourself. Your mind, your thoughts, your actions. It's a weird
message for a talk on community, I know, but it's true. If you're approaching your job, your
friends, your communities from a point of view other than your own, you're not giving much and
you're getting even less. So it's your decision. However, when you're working on someone
else's project, that work is only yours to a point. How the hell do you deal with that? Well,
Your first pass is everything.
This is your moment to make your work
what you think it's supposed to be.
Do that, make damn sure it's clear,
it communicates your ideas about both physics and feelings
and fits well with the work around it.
By doing this, when you get direction,
you'll know where you've been
and it makes it that much easier
to talk about where the work needs to go.
you have a point of reference. If not, you'll be chasing someone else's ideas through a void. So
get the hell out of your rut. Learn something new. Maybe it's about animation, maybe it's
about architecture. Just do and learn other things. You'll gain new knowledge and you'll
gain the ability to observe what you do through a new lens. This will help you understand what
you want out of your work more.
Once you understand what you like and where you're coming from, interacting with your
community will be a hell of a lot easier because you'll have your point of view as a starting
place. You'll be a point of reference instead of part of a mob. So I love cooking,
skateboarding, developing games, animating and I love the community of Pixar. All those
things I thought I was doing by myself as a loner, a rebel, I was doing them with and for
people. I finally understand what I need out of it and what I need to give and I finally
understand how to be part of the community. Anyway, thanks everybody.
Hi, I'm Tim Borelli, Animation Director,
wow, that's a good start, at First Strike Games,
and Lana asked me to share a personal story
about GDC last year, and so I hope I don't fuck this up.
Every year, like many of you here,
I look forward to GDC, and specifically this boot camp.
Last year was no different, except for one minor difference.
And if I could write a letter to myself
about any one thing that day, it would be this.
You suck, and that's okay.
Hey, past him.
Right now, you're probably on the phone
talking to your boss.
You'd been enduring repeated texts from work all morning.
The bootcamp is more important than work,
you thought to yourself.
But what you didn't realize, though,
was that those texts were mostly from your team.
They were telling you that they had just been laid off
and want to know what the hell just happened.
So there you are, listening to the voice on the other line,
about to find yourself in the same boat as them,
laid off over the phone with no warning.
and no severance. Soon you'll get a ton of texts asking what happened and realize that
you should probably call your wife before she finds out through Facebook. Her only reaction
will be to say, I just got my knives sharpened. Can I go to your office and pick up your stuff?
It'll be a good reminder of why you married her. After getting off the phone, you'll keep
it to yourself and bury yourself in the talks of the day. You'll even keep live tweeting
for the folks who are not there. That's what this community means to you. It's stronger
than any layoff.
That said, the layoff will still affect you, but you won't see it coming. You'll freak out a
lot, crying in your room more than once, as it's the first layoff you've ever experienced.
You'll even run the animation roundtables and think, you did a pretty good job. When you
get the reviews in a few weeks, Tim, this will be your first sign. You'll also learn that
getting laid off during GDC isn't the worst thing that could happen. The people around you
will put you in touch with recruiters and friends and friends of friends looking to help.
you'll make new connections and rekindle some old ones
and try your best to help others do the same.
Once home, you'll start sending out your reel
to the places you spoke with during GDC.
You'll be fine, you say, you're not a dick
and your reel is pretty good, right?
But it's been two days and all you'll think is,
why aren't they knocking down my door yet?
At this point, you will not yet realize that you suck,
but that's okay.
as soon you'll start getting extra work requests. You'll be asked to take a test and say, sure,
I'll do a two-minute cinematic sequence with two characters acting and interacting and it's due
in two weeks. Fucking A, I need a job. You'll also be asked about tech art roles, something you
hadn't done in years. And Tim, as much as you like posting Instagram videos of yourself all the
fucking time, talking about your pythons is the last thing you'll want to do.
you'll have lunches with studio heads to see what you're looking for and that'll make you
realize that you have absolutely no clue. The people you are with right now will reach out to
help often. One will give you an amazing critique of your reel and you'll tell them next year
you see that you felt like you let them down.
Like, you let a lot of people down because your reel wasn't as good as he and others
had hoped it would be.
But don't worry, though.
Eventually that will light a fire in you, but not before you finally realize that you
suck.
You suck at wanting to look for a new job, at even trying to find a new job.
You'll find yourself caring more about helping old co-workers land on their feet than you
on your own.
And soon, Tim, you'll get depressed and you'll start drinking a lot.
too much to the point where you'll get sick and you'll need to stop for a while. You'll step
away and start concentrating on yourself and your family. You'll do other things like
photography and lifting and helping your wife and it will work. Through your wife's
company you'll talk to game devs almost daily and remember that feeling of community that you
had at GDC when this all started. You'll spend time outside of that lifting shit and
hanging out with your dog, picking up his shit.
Importantly, you'll start to care again and one night you'll decide that you're going to animate
one thing every day and post it on Twitter. Your blockings and breakdowns will be absolute shit at
first, but keep at it. You'll get feedback from this community and be motivated by everyone's
encouragement. You'll still suck, but at least now you'll know it. And Tim, you won't believe it,
but not long after you'll get a message from Mike Bithell. He's been following the hashtag and will
ask you to join his next project. Just wait until you see the concepts. It's a boy and his dog.
You're a boy with a dog. So yeah, you'll say, let's animate some fucking dogs.
You'll give him your rate and he'll take it right away.
You should probably learn how to negotiate that shit better.
You'll pick up more work like that
and realize that freelance isn't something
that everyone should do before working in a studio,
that learning how to divorce your emotion from your work
can only help you in a team environment.
And you'll tell them during next year's GDC.
Your old team will drag you to coffee weekly.
Brad Clark will help with tech art problems
and you'll learn to value those relationships more.
Through all of this, you'll watch others
going through layoffs and...
Tim, make sure you do what you can to help.
Reach out, because you'll remember what it was like
to be where they are.
And while freelancing will be great,
you'll miss the daily interaction with teammates.
Soon you'll be approached to join a new company
with an incredible team who reminds you of everything
that you love about making games, and you'll take the leap.
It won't be perfect, and you won't expect it to be,
but it won't suck, and that's okay.
P.S. Tim, next year, make sure to let everybody know that this letter wasn't just for you,
but it was for them.
Any one of them could find themselves feeling like they suck at work, at life, at giving
GDC talks.
Tell them that, yes, things might suck now, but the community that we build up around
ourselves will be there to make sure that it's okay.
Thank you.
Thank you, Tim.
All right, so like I said, my name is Shabazz Shah.
I'm a senior animator at Telltale Games.
Now, if you've played Telltale's games,
you're familiar with the story-driven gameplay
where you, the player, are given a choice
to interact with an event that's taking place on the screen
or to interact with another character in the game.
Now, what's so compelling about this gameplay
is that we make those choices in our lives every day,
and every day is a new opportunity
to choose how you interact with others.
Now I had an old animation supervisor, and maybe he'll end up hearing this, Jeff Shue,
he brought the animators together before a production one time, and I'm going to paraphrase
here but he said something pretty awesome.
He said to us, he said that this job wasn't about you or your demo reel.
And that what this production was about was working towards creating the best possible
product that we could together.
Now what I thought was so great about this was it was a reminder that when we put our
work first, we focus only on our work, we put our egos before everything else, we fail
to create these collaborative communities within our teams and within our companies.
What we end up doing is we forget that everybody around us equally has an opportunity to affect
our careers or our lives in some way.
What we end up failing to see is that everybody around us has a valuable lesson to teach the
company and that everybody around us can teach us something.
You're going to work with people from amazing studios,
from across the country, from all walks of life,
and from even across the world.
And you yourself are going to be one of those professionals.
Now, this experience is invaluable.
And what we can do is we can find these opportunities
to share this experience and to share that knowledge.
So here are some ideas on what we can do
to build collaborative communities within our teams
and within our companies.
Doing animation demonstrations,
where a new member of the team gets up
and presents a lecture on a workflow or a tool.
We can have after-hour type animation challenges
for animators to work on their craft,
as well as provide feedback to each other.
even doing social, more kind of casual meetups and events
where animators can get to know each other,
and even allowing time for animators to get involved in R&D
so they can collaborate with other departments as well.
It's important to remember to be inclusive and proactive
in this company, in your company,
and also within your industry.
And working collaboratively means
getting out of your chair, unfortunately.
Sorry, that's the sad part about it.
But what we wanna do is I'll let you decide
who the beauty is and who the beast is,
but it's important to remember that we need
to develop relationships outside of our departments as well.
Start collaborating with TDs and effects artists
and programmers and designers and producers.
These collaborations greatly increase
the value of our final products.
And it means not relying, as I mentioned,
on chat and email and getting out of your chair
and starting those conversations.
and creating those opportunities.
Attending company events, getting to know your coworkers,
and remembering to always behave in a professional manner,
of course.
Now the thing is that experience, it can't be taught.
And the connections that we make in this room,
in events like this within your company,
the collaborations that we create
are just as important as working on your specific skill
for your career.
Now Stephen King once said that we never know which lives we will influence or when or why.
And I think that this is so true, especially when it comes to our coworkers.
Bill Nye once said that everyone you will ever meet knows something that you don't.
And it's a great reminder to keep a humble attitude in our careers as we recognize that
everybody around us has something that we can learn from.
So to close, I just want to tell you guys that we're all in this together.
And that the collaborations, creating these collaborative communities within our teams
and within our companies helps us push this industry and continue to make it great.
It allows us to have these fun, exciting jobs, but it also helps us build lifelong relationships.
Thank you.