Hello, everyone.
Welcome.
First of all, thank you very much, Andrew, for inviting me.
This is my first time at R Director's Bootcamp,
and it's been six years since I talked to GDC,
so I might be a little bit rusty.
Thank you all for showing up.
This is quite an audience.
I don't remember I've ever seen a room this full when
we did Killzone.
So let's first do full introductions.
My name is Jan-Bert van Beek.
I am the studio art director and animation art director
at Guerrilla Games.
And as you may know, Guerrilla Games
is part of Sony Worldwide Studios.
So that's a group of 14 very, very different game developers
from Naughty Dog, Guerrilla, Media Molecule, Polyphony.
that all work together to make the first party portfolio of Sony.
Now, we ourselves are Guerrilla, we're based in Amsterdam, lovely city.
And as you may know, the last title that we did was Horizon Zero Dawn,
which was also our first open world action role-playing game.
So just to get an idea, who has played Horizon?
Very good. Who has finished Horizon?
Who has platinumed Horizon?
Thank you very much.
Glad to see that our lead designer has a platinum.
So before we start, let's start with a reminder of what
Horizon is.
And here's our E3 trailer from 2016.
We know we weren't the first ones here.
Our stories speak of the ones that came before.
The Old Ones.
The world of the Old Ones was so different than ours.
They had built incredible cities.
With towers that reached the stars.
But a darkness came.
And their cities turned to graves.
And without them, the land started to change.
Their great cities faded away.
And in their place came new life.
Over time, one by one, the tribes came to these lands.
Some, small and humble.
Some, powerful as kings.
They say my tribe was the first.
The first to hunt.
The first to raise our bows.
For this world was never ours.
We've always shared it.
A dangerous balance between man and machine.
There's the herd.
It goes on and on and on.
So today I'm going to talk a little bit about the
Our Direction Horizon.
But before we go there, I want to talk about the
idea behind Horizon.
We get this question a lot.
Where's the orange of the idea?
Where does this idea of a young girl hunting robo dinosaurs
in a post-apocalyptic world come from?
And that all started in 2010, when our studio asked us, the
development staff, to pitch ideas for a new game.
Before that time, we had worked on Killzone
for almost a decade.
And Killzone, for those who know,
is a first-person shooter that is set
in a dark and dystopian future.
And while Killzone had been moderately successful,
it never really was a great hit.
So after about six of these titles, we needed to reconsider.
Is this really the best way to use our development team's
time, talent, and effort?
And some of you may have heard of the term franchise fatigue.
So unlike movie franchises, games
tend to get better with their sequels.
And that is basically because over time
and over multiple titles, development teams really
gets much better.
They get better at understanding the technology.
They get better at understanding each other.
And they get better at understanding what makes
their particular game tick.
So unless your company has a very high turnover and staff,
it's usually the case that the same people, the same team,
work on sequel after sequel.
Sometimes, as in our case, maybe more than a decade.
And then at some point, that team
gets tired after overworking it.
Although your knowledge and the team synergy and the skill sets
are all at peak performance, the results are sort of diminishing.
So after all, how many different games
can you make about a bunch of space Nazis
with red glowing eyes?
So let's reboot completely.
Let's start from scratch.
Let's take all of our learnings, the learnings of my first IP,
and see what we can do when we all start from scratch.
So first, let me tell you a little bit about Sony in itself.
Sony has quite a unique structure.
It's fundamentally bottom-up.
So Sony doesn't really tell the studios
what kind of games they make.
They let that figure out themselves.
Of course, there's a little bit of typecasting going on.
Naughty Dog tends to basically make action shooters.
And Goliath used to make first-person shooters.
Polyphony makes racing games.
The God of War team makes God of War.
And so.
So figuring out what we're going to make is really up to us.
And in Guerrilla's case, we apply that structure all the
way down to the core of our process.
So we go to our own development staff and ask them
what kinds of games they would like to make.
But before you try this at home, it's probably good to
understand that this level of creative freedom often needs a
lot of guidance to be successful.
I'm not sure how many of you are familiar with this diagram.
It's the double diamond design process.
It gets used a lot in complicated processes
like service design.
And to be honest, Becky.
We didn't actually know that this was a thing
until we had made the game.
And then we heard about it, and we were like, oh, that's
kind of what we did.
So in hindsight, we did this instinctively.
But it makes a lot of sense.
So if you think about it, the pitch process
that I'm about to describe is this discover phase.
And you want to go as wide as possible with the ideas
that you gather.
And then as you go forward, you go narrow again
as you try to define a core of a game.
And then you go sort of broad again, wide again.
It's sort of this cycle of adding new ideas
and then subtracting the bad ideas.
But even in the discover phase, you
need to have some sort of direction
because you need to go somewhere.
Otherwise, you just get this explosion of creativity.
And then it's really hard to define it down again
to what the focus is of something.
So I'm going to describe a little bit,
making how we focused our creativity.
We put together this brief that went to everybody
in an entire company with a very specific mission.
Develop an epic and cinematic character-driven game universe
with intense action-packed gameplay,
strong storytelling set in a distinct and rich universe.
Yeah, good luck with that.
So it's a really, really big statement.
And it's actually pretty open.
What it mostly says is don't come up
with a mobile puzzle game.
And because we have all this creative autonomy as a studio,
we felt an enormous responsibility
to do this right, not just creatively, but also
strategically and commercially.
So the nine-page briefing that we sent out,
we concluded a whole broad range of topics.
We didn't exclude any genre, but there
were a couple of considerations that people needed to take.
First of all, Begi, you know.
Think about this from Sony perspective,
maybe what is missing in their portfolio.
And of course, maybe one thing that was missing
was RPG and action RPG.
And there were other considerations like,
okay, we're good at some things.
We have really good tech.
We have good experience making with combat mechanics.
We're good at making pretty arts.
We have maybe a very good team of concept artists
and a very good design team as well.
But, you know, what can we do, maybe, with all these things that we've learned doing Killzone
and come up with something, maybe, that uses or that leverages that knowledge
without, maybe, just doing the same thing over and over again?
And, of course, maybe we discuss other things as well, like, you know, market saturations,
certain trends that were appearing, a whole bunch of different things
that people could take into consideration.
But mostly we asked them to think really big.
The ambition for this new concept
was to create a world that would be rich enough
to explore in not just a series of games,
but potentially also books and movies and onwards.
Make you really think about franchise building instead
of making just a single game idea.
In total, we received about 30 to 40 pitches.
This is just a very small sample of what we could still find.
And so what was kind of.
All it is, we didn't really specifically ask them to come up with ideas that were as
opposite as possible from Killzone,
but it's more something that sort of naturally came out of the process.
And many of the pitches that we got, they hit on recurring notes.
There were certain themes that we all gravitated towards.
So, very clearly we were done with dystopian worlds
full of glass and steel and concrete and bullets.
And instead we wanted to build very lush and very rich worlds.
I guess making sort of like, that's what franchise fatigue does.
You can sort of want to make the other thing.
But thankfully, we weren't really done with robots and mechs.
We love that, we love a healthy dose of cool science fiction machines.
But mostly we wanted to create something that was very unique.
Something that has a positive tone to it.
Something that felt very fresh, something that would be eye-catching, evocative, and
mostly something that would stand out in the marketplace.
And Horizon clearly stood out.
from all the different concepts that were pitched.
It was by far the favorite pitch among our own staff.
And also, when we showed a couple of concepts
to our colleagues at Sony,
everybody said like, make this one.
Making it sort of, it's weird
and you're probably gonna fail,
but you know, it's at least something new.
So, what was it about Horizon that drew people in?
Now, to some degree, we're still trying to figure that out.
But we've got a couple of ideas.
First of all, it had a lot of very contrasting elements,
lots of juxtapositions that created intrigue and tension.
So let's take a look at some of Verizon's many themes.
First of all, it is a world where the flow of time
appears to have been reversed.
We've got a primitive age that has come
after an age of high technology.
And it's a world where the world of science
has become the world of mythology and magic.
And it's a world that questions the definition of life as we know it,
where the artificial has become the natural.
Now, usually going for high-concept science fiction is a very, very hard sell.
But thankfully we got some help from James Cameron.
In 2009, Avatar came out and it showed the whole world
that the audience are still interested
in very high concept science fiction.
But in order to succeed,
it needs to deliver something new and fresh.
Now, Avatar, although it's a science fiction movie,
it's actually a back to nature story.
It's about a space faring civilization
that clashes with the tribal inhabitants
of a far away world.
And it's a world where they celebrate this.
They celebrate the magic of nature.
So it's science fiction, but it's very relatable,
and it's also very relevant.
It asks a couple of important questions,
like whether technology and nature are opposing forces.
In the years before Avatar, there
was a sort of reassurgence in the appreciation
of the natural world.
You may remember the Planet Earth series,
the ones about the oceans, a whole bunch
of these very lush, beautifully made documentaries.
And ironically, it was actually new technologies and film
technology that made these things possible.
So we saw this aspect of new technology
actually heightening the natural experience
instead of fighting it.
Then basically, on the other side, became aware of the flip
side of technological advances, the notion
that if you push nature too far, it might just
basically push back.
And this created a new type of apocalyptic end
of the world scenario.
So there are a couple of apocalyptic scenarios
that have existed for very long.
You've got the very old ones from the 50s and the 60s,
like the alien invasion, or the nuclear war, or the zombies.
And then sometimes, maybe, new things
come into fashion because of new societal fears.
So now we have movies about global environmental collapse,
or the rise of the machines, or smart monkeys.
In any case, there are many different types of stories that describe the events of apocalypse.
They all focus on showing the events that are preceding it or during the apocalypse.
And to some degree, most of them are actually disaster movies.
And now when we get to the post-apocalypse,
we suddenly see this enormous loss of conceptual variety.
What we pretty much end up with is wastelands
with lots of bad people.
They tend to be dark, decrepit worlds
filled with constant danger,
and most commonly, actually the biggest danger
is other people because other people are bad.
And so it's all about trying to survive
in these harsh worlds.
This sort of end of the world scenario,
it has certainly fascinated storytellers
and audience alike for a very long time,
but these worlds, these are depicted,
they've become very overly familiar to our audiences.
And Horizon promised sort of like a different view on that,
a different view on the apocalypse.
So it's a common notion that the end of mankind is automatically the end of the world.
And of course, the reality is that that's very far from the truth.
Our planet has survived something like six total near extinctions of all life.
And life tends to come back every single time.
It's the Michael Crichton thing. Life finds a way.
And so, Horizon promised a new sort of escape from the dreariness of the post-apocalypse.
Basically, we started describing it as the post-poke-apocalypse.
And maybe there's even a post-post-post-apocalypse.
So it's a new type of world.
It's not a dystopian one, it's not a utopian world either.
But it's one that sort of blossomed on the ashes of our world, to call it, to say it very prosaic.
It's a world that isn't really concerned
with the past anymore.
The apocalypse in Horizon has become the stuff of myths.
Those dark days are over and life has moved on.
So in some degree, Horizon offers like a hopeful view
of the end of civilization.
One that's not about morbid display of death,
but one that highlights sort of new and brighter worlds
that comes after all that death.
And within fiction, there aren't many stories that really
explore the world that comes after.
And creatively, that helps to some degree,
as the audience doesn't have a lot of expectations
about these worlds.
So it allows you to be a little bit bolder
and use surprise and intrigues to interest the audience
with something new and unfamiliar.
But the stories that do exist, they often add a very fascinating ingredient to the post-apocalyptic mix.
And that's mystery.
Almost in every one of these, there is a detective story going on.
It's the question of what happened, who done it.
And those setups are usually very intellectually compelling to an audience.
They get to mentally explore this world.
They get to mentally explore something that's unknown and mysterious to them.
And in that regard, it's a real proper adventure.
But it's also harder, especially from an art directional point
of view, to make that believable.
If it intrigues the audience, but it
doesn't make sense to them, they're
not going to keep engaged in your fantasy for very long.
And that's the ultimate trick of production design,
that production design has to pull off,
to create a world with a sense of authenticity
and believability.
Now, in our visual design process,
we generally avoid rushing towards an end visual.
It's something we take a lot of time to really research every element that's part of the sum
that makes up the final piece of key art.
So we don't just throw everything together at the same time,
but we very slowly layer the elements carefully together.
A key inspiration in our process was Alan Weissman's book, The World Without Us.
Who has read this book?
Very few people, thankfully.
That's why we got to make Horizon.
So in this book he describes a scenario where suddenly all humans have disappeared from Earth.
And he doesn't really explain why, because that's not really that important.
But one of the things that he does in the book is that he very carefully describes the process of how
all traces of mankind, all evidence of mankind over the ages will finally disappear.
And there's this nice little moment at the end of the book where he describes, maybe, the last thing, maybe, that will remain of humanity.
Who can guess?
No, it's the Voyager.
Because when our sun finally goes supernova,
this thing is literally in another galaxy.
So we started to recreate that process.
We took a typical American Midwestern town,
because why not, and started to visualize
what would happen to that.
So in Horizons' background story,
the apocalypse destroyed all biomatter.
So it's a completely lifeless desert,
and all the soil has turned to sand.
So we started studying what would happen to buildings,
to villages, to cities in these type of desert environments.
And of course, you'll see some really typical patterns.
Roofs start to collapse, then the walls,
and then the facades basically collapse.
But sometimes arches and columns stay around,
that's why we still see them in some of the ancient ruins.
And chimneys, for some reason chimneys stay up forever.
Thousands of years even,
the landscapes are littered with them.
And also because there's no fiber in the ground anymore,
there's no roots anymore,
maybe the soil itself starts to move like a liquid.
It becomes sand dunes, it starts to move around.
So it starts to flow around buildings,
cover them as the wind pushes it.
And these shifting sands affect the ruins of course,
maybe they push the ruins, they fill the ruins,
they change everything about the landscape
till it's been completely changed.
we started imagining how life would return.
It would probably first spring up in places
where the soil can hold water.
The moment that rains come back, and then life
starts to spread everywhere.
And then you'll end up with something
like this, where it's very much buried and overgrown
at the same time.
And this is the key of making it look like 1,000 years
instead of like 50 years after the apocalypse.
The whole notion that the landscape itself
would have vastly changed.
And then we took it a little bit further,
hundreds of years further.
So at some point, you've got skyscrapers
that start to crumble and they become hills again
because of the alluvial lines around them.
And rivers, of course, change course
and start to cut new canyons through the structure.
And the whole landscape becomes unrecognizable,
but very old feeling at the same time.
The following movie that I'm about to show
is the first art benchmark that we created.
So this was back in 2014.
She'll bear making one of the artists working on it, one of the two artists working on this.
So this is about one year into production and about two and a half years before we go to release.
You
you
The old Nipple logo.
So if you're interested in how we made this,
Gilbert will be doing a talk on Friday.
So this is my plug for his talk.
So the final combined results of all these elements
is one of Horizons' three conceptual pillars.
And I'll explain a little bit, maybe,
what we mean with the pillars.
So at Guerilla, we use a game design process
that we call the pillar mythology.
The game pillars are a set of key statements
about the intended experience.
And it takes quite a bit of time to craft these pillars,
as all the wording of it is carefully tuned
until all the pillars say exactly
what the creative intent is.
So there shouldn't be one word too many,
there must not be a word too less.
Every single word, Becky, that's in there is there
for a reason.
And so Horizons' environment with its wilderness
and its overgrown ruins is one of these pillars.
And the other two pillars are about tribal culture
and the machines.
And of course, Becky.
the fourth implicit one, making that as alloy.
So remember the double diamond?
These pillars sit at the midpoint of the double diamond.
It's the smallest, most compact way
of describing the core experience of the game.
The pillar statement that we have of the tribes
was the one on screen here.
And as you can see, it's quite a mouthful.
But one of the key observations that we
from the art directional team, making took out of it
is that it's talks in pluralities.
Sorry about that, not my native language.
So, it talks about cultures and stories and characters.
It's really about volume.
So our job wasn't just to design one rich tribal culture,
but actually a whole range of them.
And a pillar doesn't just have subtext about volume,
it also implies diversity,
it implies distinction and believability.
And especially believability can be very challenging.
Now the process that we use to achieve believability
is something that we call intrinsic ideation.
because we love pretentious terms.
Now, some of you may have heard about the rule of cool.
The rule of cool states that things are always cooler
if you just keep adding other cool stuff on top
of your cool idea stuff.
And the problem, of course, with this
is, basically, that it completely
destroys the believability of any idea,
as you keep adding and adding more mismatched ideas to it.
Now, I already see you guys thinking,
basically, aren't you the guys that added robot dinosaurs
to a game?
So I'll talk about that later.
Intrinsic ideation doesn't allow you to just add cool stuff to it.
Everything you design has to be there for a reason.
And there has to be a reason why it looks the way that it looks.
So before we started designing describable cultures,
our first question was, how does culture develop in the real world?
So we studied a lot of theories, and actually,
maybe John, our narrative director, says maybe that we're probably
the group of people with the highest density of reading
Guns, Herbs, and Steel in the world that he knows.
And maybe, anthropologists maybe don't agree on everything,
but they do agree on a couple of things.
And one of the common things that they do agree on
is that culture is all about resources.
So the resources that an environment provides,
that's what defines a culture.
So let's take a look at one of the tribal cultures
in Horizon, the Nora tribe.
So this is a tribe that lives in the Rocky Mountains.
And so we can sort of say, well, OK,
what does the environment tell us about this tribe?
So for one.
Mountain train isn't really suited for agriculture.
So without farming, food will have to come from hunting.
So most likely, we're looking at a hunting-gathering
lifestyle.
And without agriculture, there's also a limit on how
large a tribe can become, because there's no real way of
creating surplus food and storing it.
So also making it smaller tribes, people tend to do
everything.
There isn't really space for people to specialize in
tailors, or carpenters, or tradesmen, or video game
developers.
So, making it sort of limits, making it a variety of professions that you see there
and making what that means for the things and the tools that you see as well.
And then of course, making it our high mountain passes,
and that makes traits much higher.
So, you can expect to see making it as people tend to be quite self-reliant
and also a little bit weird or stranger.
Actually, sort of what you see with a lot of people making it have grown up into mountains,
they tend to be a little bit weird.
Now...
Also in our background story, a couple of important narrative
as well as game design decisions were made.
And for one, there was a clear statement
that there weren't any large animals anymore.
So there weren't any cows, there weren't any horses,
there weren't any bears or mountain lions.
So our designers started from there.
What do these limitations mean for, for example, clothing?
Because that means that you only have small heights,
you only have rabbits and you have foxes,
all kind of tiny patches.
So that basically means that all your clothing
needs to be compiled out of these smaller things
and you end up with very much patchworks.
And also we figured maybe...
They won't have cotton.
Cotton is actually quite hard to grow.
But they might have wool.
So maybe they would have to do something
with wild mountain goats.
And although weaving might be too complex,
because that requires very complex equipment,
they would still be able to braid and knit things together.
And so we also figured out that if they were able to do braiding and knitting,
they would be able to make rope.
And so let's see how important rope can be for them.
Because it's an important thing that you need for hunting.
You need it for traps and bows and fish nets and all kinds of hunting gear.
So I'm going to guess these people are quite good at using rope and making stuff with rope.
And then, frankly, from that, it's sort of imaginable that they would use rope in all kinds of other key elements in their construction techniques.
So it would be a way, basically, that they would put larger wooden structures together and even, basically, extend that to architecture.
Of course, architecture itself, there's a lot of trees in the mountains, or some mountains.
So that again informs what they would be building from.
They wouldn't be making things out of mud or stone.
They would be using the most pliable material they could find around.
So as you can see, we're sort of layering these elements on top of each other in a logical structure.
Everything is there for a reason.
Now as this process of ideation continues,
you start to get the outlines of a culture.
But the problem is, in our earliest things,
making the thing starts to look very mundane.
Making an image like this would just as easily
fit in the world of Lord of the Rings or in Game of Thrones.
But there is, of course, making one truly unique element
in the world of Horizon.
And that is sure to have a very large impact
on the development of all cultures.
And that's the presence of these giant animal-like machines.
So for example, what effect would it have on clothing?
Now, in some degree, these metal plates are sort of like bones.
And bones are actually quite bad for making armor with,
because they break and are quite brittle.
But what would happen, if you start
using these armor plates in our clothing,
would that make sense?
So we started experimenting with this look where the metal
parts would be embedded in their clothing.
And that actually started to make sense.
This would actually be a feasible idea for them.
So we began experimenting with ways to include them in older
hunting gears, looking at how these elements would mix and
how they would connect to the existing elements that were
already there.
And then, of course, there's tons of variation and there's
tons of balancing.
How you go a little bit too far, you end up with a
science fiction game.
If it's not there at all, it's barely noticeable
and it doesn't really have any big impact.
So over time, we managed to basically get this sort of
final result that we felt basically was both authentic
to the culture, but also created a distinct look
for the world of Horizon.
Now, so through this technique of intrinsic de-identification
we managed to create quite a wide variety
of different cultures.
Cultures that were all very distinct from each other
and it all fitted with the environments of the tribes
and it gave Horizon a very unique and visual identity.
So the next thing that I'm going to show is one of her trailers where we show a little bit more of the tribes.
When they told me to raise you, I didn't ask questions.
Why am I an outcast?
Who was my mother?
Always you pushed for answers.
Push yourself.
Here in the valley, we may be outcasts, but it's safe.
Out there, girl, you'll be lost.
You are nowhere to turn, or who to trust.
You'll be chasing a riddle into a wilderness of mysteries.
The world of the Old Ones.
What secrets lie buried beneath their crumbling ruins?
Why Earth is ours no more.
These questions, Aloy, the tribe has forbidden.
What if the answers are worse than not knowing?
You can help.
Or you can get out of my way.
Then be ready for the darkness.
And be careful.
What you bring to light...
How do you know it won't bite back?
Outcast! You came from nothing. You will die a nothing.
I came from somewhere.
Identity confirmed.
Even if it destroys me.
I will see this through.
Okay, let's get back to the robot dinosaurs.
So when we started the design of our machines,
our inspiration started with the types of machines
that we had designed for Killzone.
Military, industrial design,
clearly machines that were designed for war and destruction.
Something that would be very alien,
something unnatural, sort of like monsters of war.
And we played around with the idea of making them half broken.
They're a thousand years old, so robot zombie monsters.
Playing with things like strange way of movement and locomotion,
so sort of like nightmare creatures.
Now, we were still using a version of intrinsic ideation.
And one of the things that we started to emulate
was how military design firms work.
when they approach a design challenge like this.
So we even role-played that a little bit,
that process of making the type of commercials
that you typically see with military contractors
and what they would produce.
So usually, they tend to be very gung-ho,
look at our cool system thing.
So here's one of the movies that our team
made to sell their initial idea of what
the robots could look like.
When you invest in a GDLS vehicle, you know your investment is a sound one.
And that investment extends well past the date your vehicle is delivered,
because you have the assurance that Through Life Support,
one of the premier product support programs in the industry, is behind you.
A program you won't find anywhere else.
Because keeping you mission ready is what GDLS Customer Support is all about.
I think this inspired our narrative team a little bit,
Becky, about FIRO Industries.
But the thing is, Becky, that this didn't work at all.
We made some of these prototypes.
And what we found, Becky, was that the emotional core
experience was just completely off.
So, when we look back at one of the pillars, it told us something really important about the core experience.
And that it was about hunting.
And fighting against these sort of robot monster zombies machines.
It didn't make you feel like a fighter, like a hunter.
It made you feel like a warrior, like a soldier fighting in the world of Terminator.
And also it clashes with another pillar that we have.
The designs failed to come across as something
that was a life form.
In fact, they came across as solar soulless machines.
So we decided to scrap everything
and start from scratch.
So we needed a design for the machines
that enabled our players to feel like hunters.
And at the same time, maybe that they needed to feel alive
and they needed to feel the dominating.
So maybe it was time to look back at another point in time
where there was actually another dominant life form.
And sure, when somebody suggested,
let's turn all the machines into dinosaurs,
a lot of people got very, very worried.
Because this is sort of like the rule of cool, right?
This is a problem.
It's Vikings hunting robot dinosaurs.
It's completely ridiculous.
But still sort of reductantly, we decided to try it out
and just see what it would look like and feel like from a
concept art point of view.
And then, as it happened, something started to happen.
None of these things made intellectually any sense,
but the imagery that we created worked emotionally.
This whole silly idea of a primitive mankind
hunting high-tech megafauna just clicked.
And everybody got very inspired,
and it just tapped this treasure trove of ideas.
It really perfectly encapsulated this feeling
of being a hunter of very dangerous prey.
By using familiar shapes, such as the famous T-Rex,
everybody immediately understood their relationship to it.
If something really big and dangerous stands in front of you,
maybe you understand that it's dangerous,
but you don't need to explain it
through complex animations or backstories.
So it might have created some level of intellectual confusion,
but the emotional clarity was there.
It was sort of like an extra interesting juxtaposition.
There was a lot of concern about the ideas of robot animals.
Maybe it was a little bit too strange, a little bit too alienating for our audience to accept.
And thankfully, real life has some precedence in this whole notion, this idea.
So these are of course making the famous movies from Boston Dynamics
that make these robot dogs.
They also always kick them.
So if you're ever wondering, Maggie...
Why the robot apocalypse happened? It's because of this guy.
So there's this movement or they're making this philosophy in industrial design which
they call biomimetic design. And it's an industrial design philosophy that carefully looks at
nature to solve certain engineering issues.
So the notion behind this philosophy
is that if you have millions and millions and millions
of years of evolution, the solutions that
tend to come out of that are very highly efficient
solutions.
A famous example of this biomedic design
is a problem that Japanese engineers
had when they tried to solve the famous bullet trains.
Now, when they first made these things,
they would send them into tunnels.
And the moment that they hit the tunnel, there
would be these air pressure events which literally
ripped the whole train apart.
And that's bad for passengers.
So they were looking for a solution,
and they got their inspiration from the beak
shape of the kingfisher.
Because this is a bird that, once it
hits the water to catch a fish, it almost makes no splash.
So this is a perfect sort of evolution
that created the shape, the most efficient form
of hydrodynamics.
And once they took that shape and put it
on top of these trains, the trains didn't fall apart.
And people were happy.
Now there's other versions of biomimetic designs as well.
Maybe on your flight in, you took a look out of the window
and you saw, maybe, these strange ailerons
on the tips of airplane flames.
Well, this is sort of where they come from, maybe.
It's something, maybe, that birds of prey
has as well, because it reduces drag,
because it does something strange with the turbulence.
So.
When we were designing with the tribes,
we talked to a lot of anthropologists
and we figured it might be interesting
to talk to engineers,
engineers who are working in robotics.
So we went to the Technical University in Delft,
which is local to us.
And not only did they confirm, maybe,
that indeed biomimetics is a large, large part
of modern robotics.
But they were also using algorithms that mimic this process of evolutionary design itself.
So they would create a design and then have it cross-breed it with successful versions
of itself until it would converge to the most efficient designs.
And you get some really interesting things out of it, because they look very oddly organic.
So it's not really art imitating life, it's art imitating technology that's imitating life.
So it seems very logical that our very advanced robots would sort of converge to the shapes
that we see in nature as well.
If you think about it, wheels could have evolved in nature, but only if roads would have been
a naturally occurring feature as well.
But in a world where you only have mountains and tree stumps lying around, it makes a lot
more sense to make it have legs.
We also basically asked them if nature could be improved upon.
Are there any design mistakes or evolutionary processes that didn't go to the most optimal form?
Are there any sub-optimal solutions in nature?
And they explain that internal skeletons is one,
if you think about it.
So all the soft tissue is on the outside,
and then your hardest part is on the inside.
This doesn't really make a lot of sense,
because it's just too fragile.
And also, if you break one arm, that's done.
In nature, that's pretty much game over.
You're dead.
So why put all this soft, vulnerable tissue
on the outside, and then create these sort
of single points of failure?
Is there a better solution for that?
Yes, nature has better solutions for that.
So exoskeletons, basically, are much more sturdier.
You have the protective aspects on the outside.
It's just, you know, if humans would look like this,
they would be a lot less attractive to each other,
I guess.
And so we started to use these concepts of biomimetics,
artificial pneumatic muscles, algorithmically generated
reinforcements and exoskeletons, and started
exploring a look that would make these machines believable.
But it's not just about the efficiency of the biomechanics
that influence the shape of living things.
Often, a creature's niche in an ecosystem
is also what drives these evolutionary processes
that adopt certain shapes and behaviors.
And we wanted to show a large variety of different machines,
each with clear and distinct shapes and behaviors
that were coherent to the function
that they would have in our ecosystem and in our game.
So one of the first ones that we tried to design
were the Watchers,
and they would be the guard dogs of our ecosystem.
This was a sort of class of machine that would function as walking alarm bells in terms of the game design.
And one of the things that we found out is that we could actually change the shape of these creatures quite a lot
and still communicate what they were to do.
They didn't literally need to be dogs or meerkats to communicate their function.
So one of our designers proposed this idea of making a snake on legs.
So it would be able to run really fast on two legs,
but then maybe if it needed to look,
maybe it could just maybe sort of slide up its tail
and look above things.
So yeah, a snake that's able to stand on the tip of its tail.
Now the key thing to get this to work,
because it would be not really a known creature,
would be to get the behavior right.
Because if we got that right,
we figured that the audience might be able to
understand them and see them as something beyond a machine.
So we see them as something like a living creature.
Now here's a movie that I have, maybe that shows a little bit, maybe about the first prototype
and actually the first animated robot that we had in the game.
So this is almost six years old, six years ago.
And it shows the first watches that we had.
And maybe when we had this, maybe we knew that we could make any game that we, any robot that we had.
Oh, it's not playing.
Yes, Horizon was called at some point.
So this proved to us that this was the way forward.
Not only did our robots feel alive,
but you could even empathize with them.
You could understand their behavior.
You could sort of, by the way that they communicated,
you could anticipate what they want, what they were for.
And also, it made you feel like a hunter.
You were studying these things.
You could study your prey and understand it.
So that sort of made the decision for us.
So we were thankfully able to rationalize
our intellectual disbeliever way
and align it with the emotional clarity that we felt
when we first started thinking about robot dinosaurs.
So our cognitive dissonance was resolved
and the crisis was averted.
And that was time to basically codify that
into the DNA of Horizon.
So at that point, it became about animalistic machines.
Let's take another look at a movie,
that shows these things a little bit more.
from the perspective of the game.
Sorry, little one. I couldn't let you call for help.
Perfect day for a hunt.
This is going to be harder than I thought.
Okay, those canisters should be full by now.
Just a couple more.
Oh, someone's angry!
Gotta get under it.
Stay still!
All right.
Time to shut you down!
The stories don't tell where the old ones went.
They don't tell us why the machines rule these lands.
But they warn us...
that this balance cannot last.
The storm is coming.
And I will be ready.
So a quick pro tip, if you're ever
making a three-minute long trailer against an unscripted
AI creature, take your time.
This took us about 160 takes to get it right.
So arguably, we could now design any machine that we wanted.
But we still felt it would be better
to stay with existing or extinct creatures.
We felt maybe that it gives a way for the player to anticipate the machine's behavior a little bit more.
Because if it looks like a giant T-Rex, it's probably going to act like a giant T-Rex.
So, for example, we designed our version of a terror bird.
This is a bird that lived about 10,000 years ago in South America and it hunted horses.
How cool is that?
So we had our visual style defined.
And it actually is now quite easy to come up
with what the look of a machine would be.
But it's often unclear on how it would move.
And it would be even harder to imagine,
maybe, how it would attack.
So for example, how would a terror bird attack?
You would figure, maybe, like, oh, it has a giant beak.
So it's probably uses its beak.
Now, there is this aspect from paleontology
where they tend to study sort of.
contemporary relative of extinct creatures and then
theorize their behaviors of it.
So roosters are sort of like contemporary mini-me versions
of terror birds.
And they do this when they attack.
They're actually quite nasty.
So you see how they sort of wait for you to turn and then
attack you in the butt.
So this inspired our game designers and animators
to try something very familiar.
And so this is the attack that ends up in the game,
sort of nature-inspiring, the attack sets in our game.
And then ultimately, this is how it ends up in the game.
So ultimately this design process enabled us to create a very large variety of very
interesting and evocative creature designs.
Covering everything from dinosaurs and other extinct creatures to bisons, wolves and giant
birds.
So the last thing that I'm going to show today, before we go to the Q&A, is one of our last
trailers.
This one was specifically created to communicate the concept of being a hunter and it shows
off a lot of our machines in action.
Let me tell you what's out there.
Vast reaches of wilderness.
Untamed.
A rugged domain.
Majestic, but lethal.
It belongs to them.
The machines.
Steal beasts who rule these lands.
And guard the secrets buried beneath its crumbling ruins.
If you hunt these wilds, no matter how skilled you are, no matter how clever,
You will become the Haunted.
Can you brave that challenge?
Can you pass that test?
If you want to survive,
you have to make the kill.
Only then can you bring to light
the deep secrets of the Earth.
And thank you very much.
Yeah.
All right.
Anybody has any questions?
I think please step up to the microphone.
I've got a question.
Hello.
Hi.
As you're searching for new IP stuff,
it looks like you had tens and tens of ideas up there.
What was the morale of the team like while you're
kind of wandering through the desert,
sort of away from the safety of this known IP
that you guys have done for 10 years?
In general, everybody was really excited.
It's a once in a decade opportunity
to start at the birth of a new IP.
So a lot of people were very interested in taking part
of that.
And of course, people get disappointed
if their idea doesn't get picked.
That's certainly a thing there.
But in general, it's actually really good for morale.
Great presentation.
So my question is whenever someone pitches the ideas,
let's say you guys had 25 different ideas,
I know there's hierarchy in the studio.
There's level of how expert you are in your craft.
But my question is whenever someone pitches it,
how much are they in creative control throughout the?
like whole process or is this just the pitching idea and then it's the regular team.
So yeah, you know people that pitch stay involved as stakeholders within it.
But of course, if you have
you know, a junior programmer making pitching a great idea,
it doesn't necessarily mean that he has the skill sets
to also maybe be the game director on the entire process
because that requires different skills.
So usually when this happens, people pitch the idea,
but then maybe it gets taken over by the entire team
and there is more of a clear structure in place.
Okay, cool.
Well, hello.
It was a very interesting and in-depth presentation.
It was really, really awesome to learn how,
like how kind of like life itself
influences into the designs, into the futuristic,
and into this juxtaposition of futuristic
plus animalistic aesthetics.
So I think that's really awesome.
And my question was more about like the design pillars
that the team uses at Guerrilla.
Like do these design pillars are always changing
or do they stay practically like the...
like the same in almost all the developments of the of the
aesthetic of the game.
So the theory is, or the idealistic presentation,
that the pillars never change.
Of course, they do slightly get tuned over time
to make it fit better.
But they are our design bible.
So preferably we don't like to touch them,
because they are so core to our idea.
OK, thank you.
Hi.
So what I thought was really interesting
about the entire design process was
kind of the logical train of thought of, like, this
affects this, and this affects this.
And it seems like it almost takes, like,
the suspension of belief.
Like, it seemed to be really difficult to balance
the point in which you can.
you should stop the logic kind of aspect and then start adding like a ridiculous element
to your game. So what point would you say did you start thinking, oh, let's kind of like...
Well, that's kind of hard to say, Beghi.
You might be over-rationalizing things in certain cases,
where you stick too much to your established design process
and philosophies, and then you end up with something, Beghi,
that's missing something.
So in a lot of cases, Beghi, it's also gut instinct.
You have your sort of professional experience,
and your gut instinct, and your own tastes and preferences,
Beghi, that you can fall back on.
But of course, those aren't necessarily
shared by the entire team.
So you then go into a process that's
much more about convincing each other instead of sticking
to the process.
It's difficult to say when exactly that needs to happen
or if there's a point where that needs to happen.
Thank you.
Hi.
First, this is one of my favorite games.
Oh, thank you.
Thank you so much for bringing it to us,
and thank you for this presentation.
My question is,
I'm curious as to, once you arrived at the...
the function and the design of these machines,
how did you work their purpose,
their narrative purpose into the story?
How did that affect their design?
How did that interact?
So it's something, maybe, that we always push,
so make sure, maybe, that they have a function
in their ecology, but in some cases,
maybe it's really hard to balance that, maybe,
with the design, maybe the combat design requirements.
So it's something, maybe, that we want to do,
but it doesn't always match.
So in a couple of cases, maybe,
sort of like, well, it plays really well.
It doesn't make a lot of sense, but it plays really well.
So let's do it anyway.
You shouldn't make it stick to sort of idealistic to the idea
that it all has to make sense.
Thank you.
Thank you again for the talk.
It was very informative.
I was wondering, with all the creature designs,
there's so much love and there's so much thought
into all of them, and with the rush of AAA production,
I was wondering if processes like outsourcing
helped the core team just focus
and really bring out the best in those ideas,
or how did that help with the core team?
So, yeah, we do quite a lot of outsourcing.
Most of our cinematics are outsourced.
Almost all of our modeling and texturing is outsourced.
So it is, what we tend to do is stick to what we feel is our core business,
which is designing games and developing games,
but not necessarily making art assets.
So there is an aspect there that by outsourcing certain aspects,
we can stay focused more.
Wonderful. Thank you.
One more question. I just noticed.
Is it one more question? Okay, one more question.
Yeah, actually my question was sort of related.
I was wondering about the scope of the creatures,
because obviously this game is also your first attempt
at the open world, so there was quite a lot of problems
to figure out there on this side as well.
There is so many creatures in the game,
and they're all kind of different.
I wanted to know about how did you decide,
and when, with design obviously, because they probably
required some stuff from you guys as well.
Like, how did it work?
Like, did they give you a list of types of enemies?
Or like, how did you guys solve that?
And then, obviously, how did you scope that?
Because it's ridiculous, like, the amount of stuff.
Very good question.
Eric, our lead designer,
I think we'll be having a whole talk about that.
But yeah, it's difficult. These things are very expensive.
They take a lot of time to work or to make.
The Thunderjaw in itself was an 18-month process,
from concept to full delivery.
At some point, you get all the ingredients together,
and then it becomes really easy to make things.
Once you've got all your mechanics there,
once your design structure is there,
it becomes a lot easier.
But in the initial phases, it's very murderous to go
through those processes.
Yeah, it was like that demo that you showed there.
It was very interesting, because it's, I think, very
rare to see that in E3 demos or whatnot, that the scope of
the demo is much more on the character and the tech and the
animation and the systems than the usual environment art.
The actual environment is not that big.
Yeah.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
So thanks, everybody.
Hope you enjoyed it.