All right, hello, everybody.
I guess we're live now.
Cool.
For those of you who don't know me, my name is Peter McConnell.
I'd like to thank Damien and Scott for inviting me to speak.
I've been writing music for games now for about 25 years.
So I guess that's why I was invited
to speak about this subject, which
is, what can we learn from?
the classic era of game music
and uh...
the classics we hear a lot about on these days
we remember some of these titles fondly
Oh, by the way, I didn't talk about what I've actually done, I guess.
Well, I worked for LucasArts for a bunch of years.
And after that, I scored, in LucasArts, I scored games like, or helped to score games
like Monkey Island 2, Indiana Jones and the Fate of Atlantis, Grim Fandango, Full Throttle.
After that, Psychonauts, Sly Cooper series, Broken Age, another, the Kickstarter from
Double Fine.
and a hearthstone for Blizzard Entertainment.
So I've, you know, been lucky to be doing this for a while.
And I do have, I guess you might say,
some kind of a perspective on all this
that extends for more time than I'd care to admit.
So, King's Quest, Wing Commander,
Seventh Guest, Myst.
Does anybody remember these games?
They were pretty cool and it was an exciting time because it was a really new industry.
And by the way, does anybody know who this guy is over here?
Oh, come on.
Okay, he announced the longest running TV commercial in the history of television for
the Columbia Collection of Classics.
Classical music.
Remember, even you!
Even you can own the Paul Vetsian dances by Baradine.
And his name, for extra credit, anybody know his name?
He was Mr. French in Family Affair for one time.
John Williams.
And speaking of John Williams.
My experience in this business started working for a company owned by George Lucas.
Not really this George Lucas, I think, but more like this George Lucas.
And as I said, we did some titles that I'm still very fond of and proud of in those days.
you know, it was a really, it was a really interesting time
to, to be in the business, and I think
it's worth, if you want to think about now, because I do hear a lot of people
talk about,
oh, the golden age of games, you know,
they just don't make them like they used to, you know, you know, when you had to
only work with eight bits,
my goodness, you had to write a good tune, and now it's all about the production,
right? I'm sure you've heard stuff like this before.
And, you know, there's a grain of truth to some of that, but I think there's also a healthy amount of salt to throw over your shoulder when you hear that kind of stuff.
But it is worth remembering what it was like, because some of it is amazingly like now.
So, in those days, games and virtual reality, I don't know if you remember virtual reality, but it was sort of like games, only more exciting sounding.
They were a niche software market, right?
It was nerd culture.
It was a very, very, very few, you know, kind of, in a way,
elite group of people who were into it.
And, you know, I did not go to the first GDC,
but I did go to the second one.
And the second GDC had about 250 people at it,
and it was at some hotel in San Jose.
And 50 of them were us folks from LucasArts, which, that was about the size of the company then.
And we all wore these little red fezzes, like Morocco Mole.
Guys, anybody know Secret Squirrel?
All right! Geez.
There's at least one other baby boomer in here.
So we all wore these fezes that had the LucasArts logo on them.
And it was just kind of a way of saying, you know, we're pretty wacky,
and we're all kind of in this cool little team, and we all work together.
And we'd actually go to company meetings, and George Lucas would be on stage,
and there would be ILM over here, and there would be Skywalker Sound,
and over here would be LucasArts with their red fezes on,
and no one really knew what to make of us.
But it was all kind of a reflection of where games were in the big picture at the time.
They were something that was about to happen.
They were not something that had really happened yet.
And space in those days—I'm supposed to have a big picture of a floppy disk here,
but you can't find floppy disks anymore.
And we shipped all, you know, we shipped the Monkey Games and Indie and so forth on floppies.
And if you can imagine that, and you know, when we worked on our new sound system, the
fact that it took an entire floppy disk was this horrible, horrible thing.
We had to really, you know, just...
advocate for a new sound system intensely because of the
uh... what was at the time a huge space uh... hog right
but anyway
cd-roms came along and changed everything they promised
vast amounts of storage
there were lots of
claims about how much data you're gonna be able to get on one which sort of
turned out to be overblown
but they still changed
the industry tremendously
and uh... audio hardware
The Sound Blaster just being invented, right?
High, basically the state of the art was 2D, 2.5D,
kind of like that picture you first saw from Monkey Island 2.
And 3D was the future.
Wolfenstein came out and it was a, you know,
it was a game changer, as it were.
Takis, we actually called them Takis.
were a novelty, right? And, you know, we were doing the voices ourselves, you know.
Mmm, Yoda I was, mmm, right?
And so it was very in how it was.
We tended to be small as a whole.
And Lucas is not exactly maybe reflective of the entire
industry in some ways.
But in others, it very much was.
Small group of very young people sort of getting
together and inventing things from their bootstraps.
And what this meant was, first of all, budgets were tiny.
We went lo-fi because we had to.
I mean, if we'd have had surround sound to work with,
we would have worked with surround sound,
but what we had was 8-bit audio cards,
and even worse, the PC speaker.
Necessity, therefore, was the mother of invention, right?
And we wore...
many hats, right? I was hired to program, to help design and program the interactive
music system at LucasArts, as well as to write music for it. And that was, you know, it was
very common in those days, unfortunately in some cases, but for people to wear, you know,
many hats from being, you know, programmer to tester to voice actor. And we were in-house.
And this is one of those things where it's not so true now for some of us, but it's very true for others of us.
We were in-house, so we had time.
We had time to come up with stuff.
And George Lucas actually sort of explicitly
Went to the board and said of Lucas art said, you know
I don't care what you do for this amount of time just do cool stuff
And that was kind of an ideal job to have where someone was telling you hey, I don't care what you do
Just do cool stuff
By the way that changed
So one of the things that we did with all this time was,
hey, let's make an interactive music system.
Let's do cool stuff, right?
So the challenge in those days was to basically leap out
of a really crappy little speaker
and get people's attention and satisfy
a really picky cadre of nerds.
I myself, I got into games because I loved Zork.
Does anybody remember Zork?
Okay.
Those MIT geeks who then became Infocom.
And anyway, a whole different deal now.
Now, we've grown up as an industry.
We're now officially entertainment.
We used to be kind of like software, entertainment, not really sure which.
It's entertainment, I would say now, with a heavy software component.
It's a huge mass market phenomenon.
It's stuff you see every day on the news.
There's a game section in Rolling Stone.
We affect major companies' bottom lines.
I mean, the idea that Halo or Kinect affect Microsoft's
bottom line, to me, boggles my mind.
If you compare that to, you know, I mean, admittedly, George Lucas is a big famous guy,
and he's got a big famous company, but there's 50 of us, you know, and we're tinkering on
these little things.
The idea that that would come to where we are now today is just amazing to me.
The cloud now offers direct access to just about everything in the whole universe.
You know, quite a contrast to the old CD-ROM.
Audio hardware is now a tiny version of home theater.
What you can do on an iPhone with audio blows away anything.
The most hi-fi game stuff could do in 1991 or so.
And wait a minute, space is an issue?
Yeah, well, if you're in mobile games, it is.
And one thing I will say is.
Space is always going to be an issue from the floppy disk to wherever there's always going to be some little thing in our business
That is cutting-edge and new and is all about getting it on to some even tinier little space than it's been before
Low res looks like a skipped a little bullet point there, but low res 2.5. D are now
2d and 2.5. D are now hip
and retro and cool and
But so is 3d of course
So what this means is?
budgets
They might be small and this did anybody see Brian's do you guys were here for Brian Schmitz talk or it the
the
broad span of projects in this industry is just amazing now.
And so you may have these little tiny projects, little mobile projects,
or you may have these ridiculously big budget projects.
We wear slightly fewer hats than we did.
Again, this applies more to some of us than to others.
Invention means creating your own necessity, because we have access to a lot of cool stuff now.
I have a studio that I would have killed for back in those days.
And we go lo-fi not because we have to, but because we can.
Because it works for the project, because it's cool.
And we're often out of house, and that was an interesting thing in Brian's talk as well.
We're often out of house now as opposed to in-house.
We get brought in very quickly sometimes on a project, and schedules can be insane.
And yes, they were always insane.
Not sure they were quite this insane.
But we still like to innovate.
We still want to make the music cool.
We still want to do new stuff.
So the challenge now is to rise from a sea of content, vast, huge sea of content, to
grab people's attention in the mass market and still satisfy a really picky cadre of
true believers.
So what was it like?
I think it's worth, when we go back...
and look and see if we can learn anything from the beginning, the beginnings of time, as it were.
What was it like culturally? Well, it was a lot like college, only more so.
When we, when I was hired at Lucas, we used to have parties, basically, where you would try out new, someone would,
people would have ideas for games and they would code them up, and then we'd have this thing called a pizza orgy.
where, and this is a real picture of a real pizza orgy.
And, you know, the idea being that if it's not fun at a party, maybe it's not that fun.
And so everybody would play the game at these things, at these, and, and give their feedback.
And that was sort of part of the culture there.
Fun was a big, huge part of the culture.
The tools we had to work with were.
really rudimentary, okay? They were consumer and hobbyist level tools.
Pro Tools 1.0 came out in 1991.
It cost six grand,
and guess what?
We didn't have it.
It was deemed too expensive
for the kind of work we were doing.
Most of the tools we used were in-house.
NIH, everybody knows what that means, right?
Not invented here.
If you get something from off the shelf, you're not a sufficiently cool cowboy programmer.
You need to make it yourself.
And part of that was a necessity, because we didn't have tools to do the kinds of things
we really wanted to do.
So, uh, the good point about that is you got an intimate connection
with the results of what you were doing.
You didn't, it was a very sort of integrated process in terms of
creating audio and implementing it and then experiencing it.
And I will get to that in a little more detail in a bit.
And one of the hats that, um, we wore as composers was the mechanics hat.
We would actually, you know, to use the sports car, um...
analogy, we would work on the car, get out and drive it for a while, get out and work
on the car, drive it for a while, and that allowed us to create tools that really worked
well for us.
It also did mean we spent a lot of time creating tools and maybe not quite as much time as
we would like to have been writing music.
And we do all that, as I said, because it's cool.
We're interested in doing something really creative.
But also because we have to, because there's no choice.
OK.
Now I'm going to actually get into an example here of a tool.
Our interactive music system was called IMUSE.
It stands for Interactive Music and Sound Effects.
The term now is adaptive.
So sometimes I'm going to say adaptive music, and sometimes
I'm going to say interactive music.
I mean the same thing.
And we had a tool that we used for composers called iMac.
And sorry about the confusion.
This was invented before the iMac was invented.
And it was just our tool that we ran on the Macintosh to
help us create our music and then actually hear it in a
context very much like the game without having to bother
the programmers.
So what it let you do is create buttons
and associate game states
with those buttons and then place those buttons on a map so you could see how
all the
pieces of music and the states in the game relate to each other.
And, um...
That was very useful because it was, you know, it was very visual and it was very immediate.
You could trigger, you would press a button, trigger audio files with behaviors, which were then entered into an H file.
Anybody code C in this room?
Wow.
See, in, in, in, in whatever, 1992, I think probably most of the hands would have gone up.
So an H file is just something in the C language.
And what that did is it provided a customizable layer of logic
between game states and music states.
The programmers would be programming the game. They would simply be setting
state codes.
We'd be here writing our music
and then
also implementing
this layer which is essentially equivalent to Y's or Fmod now
of
something that would interpret those game states.
And then we'd also be using this tool to visualize what we were doing.
We could test the interactivity without doing a build of the game.
I would write stuff for Grim Fandango
and then
you know basically minutes later be testing the transitions between
various pieces in the game and just seeing
kind of how it fit together in the score.
And the thing that was cool about this visual thing is
for adventure games, which is the type of game we were mostly working on,
a mental picture of the universe,
of all the places you can go,
because you're constantly going from one place to another
in a, uh, in an adventure game.
That mental picture is really nice to have a visual for.
And, um, again, it gave this sort of visceral connection
between, uh, the composer and the actual audio experience
that the listener was ultimately gonna have.
And I'm gonna actually, um, take a little...
detour here. And we're going to go...
How many of you guys are...
How many of you are too young to really remember this screen clearly?
I wonder.
So, there's an ancient Mac
being emulated in my modern-day laptop here.
And here's our little tool. It's called iMac.
And when you launch it...
Oh, my goodness! Look at all those errors. Remember those errors?
Don't worry. It's OK. It's OK.
It's all right. It's cool.
So, this is the script that I wrote for Year 2 of Grim Fandango.
And what you would do is you would...
I think it's under this menu. No.
There it is.
You could create a button simply by...
Let's try a new sequence.
No, it doesn't like that right now.
Anyway, you would create a button.
You would enter a little code into it.
Then the button would appear on here.
You could draw these lines just sort of
as a mnemonic device to yourself.
You could remember what rooms connect to which other rooms.
And then you could play a piece
and then play another piece
and then listen to the transition actually execute.
And...
When you did this, this corresponded to stuff.
Do I want to do it in an H file?
Right.
And this is where we would enter all the data.
Just by hand.
It really wasn't very hard.
You basically listed all the pieces of music.
And then transition types.
And there are a bunch of codes that gave information about how
the transition was supposed to behave between
different pieces of music.
Is that a we're almost?
Oh, five minutes.
Holy crap.
OK.
Anyway.
So very quickly, right now this sounds like this, which
isn't very good.
Oh, I don't hear anything.
Oh, well.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, sorry, that's a bug.
It works on a G4, but it doesn't work on my emulator.
But you get the idea of what this was.
And what it really allowed you to do
was to just experience, essentially,
what you were doing without having to code up the game.
It was a great tool, and I wish we had more stuff like it now.
So let me go back into.
Let's go to here.
So takeaways.
Five minutes takeaways coming up here.
First, there's stuff to throw out.
OK?
No, not that.
Or that.
That's the real boring story, by the way.
I think in some ways it's a nice thing that we don't have to wear as many hats as we used to.
I think those of us who are working on really, you know, cutting-edge small projects can appreciate, though, that it was cool to wear a lot of hats.
So, so, just beware of how many hats you're wearing and, and, you know, don't wear more than you have to, but don't wear too few either, really.
Yeah, see, that's guys wearing too many.
Unnecessary tweakery.
You know, we were given this mandate to do cool stuff.
And, you know, without a clear fear of the bottom line,
there was definitely a certain amount of self-indulgence that
went on, which we could have done without.
Pennywise and pound foolish.
Sometimes when you're doing a small project, when you're
doing a
you know, something by your bootstraps, you will economize in places where you should
not. I really wish we had bought those Pro Tools systems, OK? Would have been nice. We
had to wait till Grim Fandango to get them, I think, if I remember right.
But good takeaways, right? The spirit of invention, I think, is something that is, can sometimes
be lost when you have a lot of resources.
And one thing that I think I'd like to sort of try to get across is this idea of, well,
if necessity is the mother of invention, but you don't have a lot of necessity in the sense
that you have a lot of great resources and you have, you know, a lot of possibilities
of what you can do, what do you do with that?
Really interesting thing is to essentially create your own necessity make your own
Self-limiting decisions that focus your statement. Okay, so Frank Zappa every year used to send flowers to Edgard Verraz
Now I don't know if you guys know who Edgard Verraz was
But he wrote all of 14 pieces in his entire life and yet somehow by writing just 14 pieces
He had more impact than most composers of the 20th century. He was an amazing composer
Igor Stravinsky at a time when people were getting totally complex and wrote, you know,
and writing atonal music, Igor Stravinsky decided to write a symphony in C. What a great
idea.
He, a lot of time, he used to just simply restrict himself by note choice.
And how that translates to us today.
I think the idea of sort of self-imposed necessity or self-limitation is just remembering that
high production values don't necessarily make art, right?
And in that sense, Laura Shigihara, original Plants vs. Zombies composer, you know, she's
a genius.
perfect set of sounds, which are not big, but they're small, because the game is not big.
It's small, but it's wonderful. That kind of creativity, I think, is something that, you know, you only get
once in a while, and it reminds me of that time. And since a lot of us now are working on
mobile projects, or we're working on
you know, independent or so-called casual projects.
I think that's a great thing to keep in mind.
Nothing wrong, by the way, with having big resources.
I mean, I do not think there is a wasted note in the Halo score.
That is awesome.
I don't want to try to get too, like, reverse snob here.
Finally, there are just sort of cultural things.
Like I said, learning to wear the right number of hats.
I was glad I did the programming.
I was glad I did the music.
I really did prefer to do the music in the end,
and I was glad to be able to finally get
the one part of things to the point
where I could do the other more.
So it's great that we don't have to do, I'm being cut off.
Be in-house even when you're out-house.
Pretend like you are part of the team even when you are working outside
of the house, because more of us are out of house now than used to be.
Not in the out-house, as Brian said, but out of house.
And finally, make it fun.
You know, it's all about, I really, really look.
back finally on the spirit that we had in those days of just fun.
And I think there's a lot of that still today, and it's something we never want to lose.
And I'll take questions if we have time.
If anybody has a question, they could probably come up to the mic.
That would be the best way to do it.
We actually have a 30-minute break after this.
Oh, okay.
Cool. Oh, okay, so I didn't have to race like that?
Oh, okay, well, I had some very profound things that I went through very quickly.
Yes.
What do you make of the whole retro revival that sort of has been happening,
where, you know, a lot of these music for games are starting to sound more like 8-bit?
Do you think something was lost in the high production values?
Why do you think that's happening?
Well, it sort of goes to my point there about, you know, what do you do in this time when you can do whatever you want, right?
And I think it can be great and it can be annoying.
And the thing is to try to, the question is, is it done with the right spirit?
Is it done with a respect for the original sound or the original intent?
Which may be, like for instance, Grim Fandango, right?
I was so proud of that game when it came out, but I winced every time I heard the stuff
that wasn't live.
We did not have a budget for that.
I am not nostalgic for the fact that we did not have a budget to do an orchestra for Grimm.
There is nothing great about that.
One of the best gifts to me as an artist was to be able to redo that with a live orchestra.
Of course we try not to...
Get into colorizing film as it were right. We don't want to ruin the original
The original feeling but we want to be able to do what we wanted to do so so does that answer your question?
Sorta.
And it's like, what about the,
you're talking about like the chip tune thing, you know?
I'm talking about projects kind of like Fez,
where it's like, it's trying to bring back, I guess,
a lot of the stuff that was good about it,
I mean the self-imposed limitations, you know,
now it's like we have to self-impose them,
whereas before, you know,
so I guess I was just wondering your take on it,
because, yeah, I don't know.
Yeah.
I think,
I think retro stuff is awesome.
And I'm, first of all, I'm grateful for the attention to stuff of that time, because I think, you know,
we have, one of the things, you know, Tommy Tallarico, Video Games Live,
one of the things he does so wonderfully is he reminds us that we have a culture,
that we have a history, that we have literature now, a body of work.
And part of that body of work is, you know, the original Mario theme.
And part of that body of work is God of War.
And I think that, if you're asking, well, is it kind of gimmicky to do, and yes, sometimes
it is kind of gimmicky, but it can be done right so that it's like, hey, check this out,
this is like a body of, this is part of our canon.
You know, I think that's cool.
Cool.
Thank you.
Hi, just out of curiosity, there's a tool called Max MSP,
and I was curious if you found that as a suitable substitute
for setting up and kind of putting together the room idea.
You did notice that that resembled Max a little bit,
yes.
Max was too geeky for us.
We found it did a lot of things that we weren't very interested in.
And I've done performances with Max, and I have a lot of respect for that whole ear-com,
you know, tinkering with electronic music.
It was a little less grounded in the type of things that we wanted to do, though.
What we wanted to do was...
basically imitate a pit orchestra.
There's a performance on stage, there's a conductor,
he's watching the performance, and he's like conducting,
he's like, measure 32, now, right?
And that's what we wanted to have.
And that's not Max.
That's my news.
Cool.
And FMOD and WISE and a lot of the tools that we have now,
and EXACT, and I mean, it's, you know,
there's been a lot of stuff coming down the pike since then.
Thank you.
You talked a lot about programs where you had to program them yourself.
You programmed them yourself, like WMAC.
Is there still value in doing that,
or would you rather be leaning on Pro Tools
in those modern programs of today?
I think there is actually still value in doing that.
It depends on what you think you're going to get out of it.
Right? I mean, specifically...
Well, do you mean like the thing I showed you?
How I'd like to see that happen today is I'd like to
see Y's allow you to create buttons.
and not have to deal with object-oriented programming when you're trying to write music.
Sorry, guys.
One thing that we were very big on was not only getting under the hood and making it cool inside,
but also having respect for the fact that when you're trying to...
write music at three in the morning,
and it has to be done tomorrow,
and you want to do something cool,
the last thing you want to do
is get out of your right brain,
that's the creative one, right, supposedly,
and go to that other brain and start writing C code.
So we wrote C code, but it wasn't very much.
Anyway, yeah.
Hi, what new games are you playing,
and who do you feel like is pushing
the genre of adventure games?
Well, I'm kind of biased on that one.
You know, I think Tim Schafer is the most amazing game designer who ever drew breath,
so that's just my, and I have worked for him for many, many years, so I think that's, you
know, so I'm sorry for Peter.
Sorry.
Thank you.
Hi there.
You brought up Super Mario when back to like old school music and that got me thinking about how
it seems like there's a recent phenomenon like a certain philosophy of game writers where you have
to avoid the repetitive. Like you have to make sure that if they're going to be stuck in the
same spot for like five minutes then you can't have anything that's too repetitive or anthemic
otherwise it just gets grating. But then you for the same token you also look back on these older
games for like the Nintendo like the Super Marios and the Zeldas and the Pokemons.
And all that, like, what really makes those is the sort of mus— is that very anthemic sort of music that goes along with it.
So I'm wondering, like, is that style of, like, very anthemic, melody-driven music in-game,
like, is that really just sort of, like, fading out at this point?
Or is that really just some small sector that think it is?
Oh, no, I don't think so at all. I think a lot of people are doing melodic, anthemic—
I mean, yes, there's just so much variety now.
There are situations for which just dust isn't appropriate,
you know, something that's more atmospheric or dark or action-oriented.
There are parts where you don't want to be,
a melody would be distracting, right?
And then there are other parts of the same kind of game
that need to be very, you know, righteous and thematic.
And so, no, I think...
I'm not, I don't really subscribe to,
oh those were the good old days.
You know, you know, you take a guy like Frankie,
when you have lived and loved like Frankie has,
now that guy could sing a tune, right?
There is sort of that feeling maybe
about the old game music.
And it's true when you.
only have a sound blaster to come out of,
and it's got to sound good on an AdLib,
the tune had better be good.
That's absolutely true.
But that doesn't mean the tune can't be good now.
And part of the challenge of, you know,
this sort of wealth of opportunity that we have
is to kind of keep that simplicity in mind.
And that's sort of where we get back to the idea
of imposing your own restrictions.
All right. Thank you.
All set?
All right.