Before I kick off the talk, I would just like to ask the question,
why I even talk about this topic,
why I think it's worth your time,
and that comes from my day-to-day business.
I do run a PR marketing agency for games,
and we work with clients and studios from all over the world
and with really different experience levels.
And usually when they come to us,
they have quite good ideas of certain things.
They know that the trailer is important.
They know a store page is important.
They know they're going to need a press kit.
But when...
we go into more details and say we need to work on GIFs,
we need to have a good PR plan about GIFs,
what do you think about that?
They often look a bit like that.
Because I do think GIFs still have a bit of a reputation
that they're just memes, and there's a lot about jokes,
and it's basically just something for babies.
And some of it is true,
that's definitely something GIFs can be,
but that's not everything GIFs are.
There's way more you can do with it.
So here's just a couple of scenes of different games
that we either worked with or I really like in GIF form.
And I think what you can see there in a couple of seconds
is that.
Those are really short clips, but already you can probably see which games you like of those,
which you would want to find out more, which one you maybe don't want to find out more.
But we just watched eight games looping through one and a half times,
and you probably already have quite good connection to some of them.
So I think that's the real power of GIFs.
That's really what drives the format.
that you get so much information across really, really quickly.
And that's really helpful in a lot of channels.
For example, it's not uncommon for a tweet
with a nice GIF to do really well,
get thousands of retweets.
We're going to talk about Imgur today.
If you reach the front page, you can get hundreds of thousands
of views.
If you happen to land on the Reddit front page,
you can get millions of views.
We do deal a lot with PR, as a PR with journalists and influencers,
and our success rate of getting pitches through with them
while having a nice gift is way higher than without them.
And you can also give on storefronts,
or Steam for example, or on Kickstarter,
and that of course can mean more money, more conversion.
And I think it's also at the moment that gifs are more relevant than they used to be.
There's a couple of factors for that.
One is that there are just way more games than there used to be.
There's always more games coming out and more and more and more.
So the attention span, I think, of a lot of parties,
be it publishers, platform holders, players, press, and so on,
their attention spans are just really short.
So often you just have a couple of seconds to really convince them about your game
or at least get them interested to find out more.
And if you watch a couple of other talks from this year's GDC and read current blog posts,
I'm sure you're going to notice that something we call the grind is more important than ever.
it seems that for a lot of games, the most secure way to have a successful launch and
successful phase is to build your own community. And to build a community, you need to have a
constant output and constantly get new people in from new channels. You constantly need to break
out of your little bubble and reach more people. And that's what we call the grind. And GIFs are
really useful for that because if you work for trailers, for example, they're really expensive to
make.
They did a lot of work, a lot of effort.
If they don't work out, that's a big problem.
If you make a couple of GIFs and one or two don't work out,
that's fine.
So they're just easier to produce,
and this is helpful in the current environment.
And I think that the whole philosophy of that
the grind is really important is also supported by Steam,
because they make wish lists very important at the moment.
So really, working a couple of months
hard to break out of your bubble,
to reach a lot of people, get a lot of wish lists,
is just really important right now.
So what we want to talk about today is three topics.
We want to talk what a good GIF looks like,
how to make a good GIF, and where to post it.
Before we do that, we have to get a bit of an awkward topic out of the way.
That is how to really pronounce GIF.
Because some people say GIF and some say GIF.
So I really wanted to know how to really pronounce GIF, so I went on howtoreallypronouncegif.com.
And they say you say GIF, so like GIF but without the T. So I'm going to say GIF.
And it looks like there's a lot of people that feel really strongly about this.
So strongly that you can buy T-shirts and stickers.
I don't feel strongly about this.
If you want to say GIF, that's totally fine by me.
But I'm going to go with GIF for today.
And what was the another thing?
It's more like a definition for the talk today.
I see GIF more of a philosophy than a file format.
And what I mean by that is obviously GIF is a file format,
but sometimes you just take a short video
and post that on Twitter.
Sometimes you use Giphy, sometimes you use some HTML format.
And for me, that all counts as GIF.
So when I say GIF today, I just mean like a short video clip
of your game that you post somewhere.
And before we start off, a few things that might be helpful to know about me.
My name is Thomas Reisennecker.
I really like having my name in Flamethon.
I also founded a PR agency in Brighton, UK.
I've worked in PR for years, worked on over 70 titles in the beginning,
quite big ones like League of Legends and Paladins.
And now we really focus on, with their own agency, focus on premium indie games
like Orwell, Omno, Heaven's Vault, Burying My Love, that kind of game.
Which I think gets me in a quite good position
to talk about a topic like that, because we deal with a really
big quantity of games.
And obviously, if you work on so many different projects,
you also get a lot of different data
and see how different campaigns work out.
And working with those small indies,
they really work on a budget often that's very tight.
So they really depend on really efficient communication
methods.
So what does a good GIF look like?
If you just want to know what a GIF needs to look like,
I got it on the front page of Reddit.
If I would know that, I would not be standing here.
I would be on an island having a cocktail.
It's really hard to figure out what really connects in a GIF.
I've thought about it a lot.
There's not one universal template you can take.
I think it really boils down to figure out
what the core of the game is and then
test a lot of different things to see what resonates.
I think that's a really important part.
So while we can't put up a formula how you make the perfect GIF,
we can go through different GIFs that hopefully inspire you
and show you different categories you can go down and experiment.
But it really comes down per game,
what is the ideal GIF for what it is, I think.
So GIFs can be really good to use for gameplay GIFs.
This is the most simple form of a GIF, I think.
It's just recording gameplay footage.
And it can be really useful, for example,
to show really complex gameplay mechanics.
That's a game called Eastshade.
It looks really beautiful.
You walk around, you take pictures of the landscape
and they're transported into paintings.
And if you describe it in a sentence,
that probably sounds a bit boring,
but if you see it like that, it's really great.
So within one second,
you can really see how that game works.
Another way, a certain type of game
that just works good in GIFs,
if a game just looks really cool,
this is my friend Pedro that works excellent.
They have a really big social following.
It's definitely also made to look cool in GIFs.
And another way to work with GIFs,
with the format and take the most out of it is, I think, funny games work quite well.
If you have a narrative game, if you want to have a certain scene, it can really help to
just have one or two lines and a punchline. It's really good to get that across.
There's of course bug gifs, I'm sure you've heard of them, I'm sure you've seen them.
There's a game called Water Golf and while they just look funny, they really can go big.
You see some numbers here, here's another one from a game called Overland
and all that happened there is the dog got really big and that got a thousand retweets.
And there's no formula or like no preset how you can create funny bug gifs.
I think the lesson to learn there is...
whoever works on the game and can encounter bugs,
I think they should be equipped with the program
and the programs and the knowledge how to record GIFs.
Because when it happens,
that just takes a couple of seconds to record
and they can really give you a big PR boost.
It's really a shame to not have just that setup
to record those GIFs.
There's of course also joke GIFs.
Here's a really good one, Sony Santa Monica.
They were really great with God of War GIFs.
And there's also event-related gifts.
Here's one for Valentine's Day.
And I think those are really funny.
Those are great to entertain your community.
The only thing that's important there
is that people need to know what your game is already
so those gifts work.
So I would always say those are more important for
more established brands than completely new games.
Another gift category that I think is often
overlooked is asset gifts.
That just means using assets like a little banner
on a Kickstarter page,
little game description banners on a Steam page,
like you see on the left or on the right,
just showing more or less a menu, a bit in motion.
It can add a lot to just have the moving elements
that makes it look way less boring.
So I think that's a really great way to also use a GIF format.
Then there's something called main GIFs,
and that's probably one of the most important slides of the talk.
I highly recommend making a main GIF for every game you work on.
And what we see, what a main GIF is, what my definition of that is,
it's just, it's a mini trailer.
And we use that in loads of different ways.
We use it to pitch to investors, to publishers, again to press,
we show it to players for really important news.
That main trailer, that main GIF, is like a little trailer
that shows off the most important aspects of your game.
really have a good think what you want to show with the game.
On the top left, we see, for example, Omno.
And for that game, it was really important
to show off the animation nicely.
That's why it has quite high frame rate
and to show the different environments.
Below, we see a game called Hamsterdam.
And for that game, the goal was clearly
to show off the cute protagonist,
but then to show a lot of gameplay variety.
So you have a lot of really short shots,
but you just see there's loads of different stuff in the games.
And those are quite visual games.
So those main GIFs are easier to make.
But then let's have a look at a game that is maybe less visual.
It's called Heaven's Vault. It's an adventure game.
It looks nice, but there's no explosions in it.
There's a lot of walking, a lot of reading.
And what we made here is that we, A,
want to show a big variety in scenarios and sceneries.
That's why we have a lot of different scenes.
But the other thing we want to get across
is that the game is developed from the developers of 80 Days,
which was a very successful game.
So that's a big plus for the title.
And also it has a really interesting gameplay mechanic
where you decipher, where you translate a whole language.
And that's something that's really complicated
to show in detail, but we can spell it out in a sentence
and hint at it.
So the goal here really is not that people fully
understand how the mechanic works,
but how to get the top level pitch,
like the one line what's really important about this game.
So within a couple of seconds, you
have that tiny trailer that explains a really complex game.
Similar here for a game called Gladiobots,
which was a really big challenge to get that GIF nice,
because in the game, you have an AI editor.
where you program an AI for your robot,
and then you press play and your robot's fighting the arena.
So that means half of the game is a menu.
It's just an AI editor.
So that's obviously visually not the most attractive thing.
So here it was really helpful to work with text in between,
really explain how the game works,
have that split screen in the beginning.
And again, imagine getting that game described in text form
versus that little GIF.
I think it makes a really big difference
to get across the core of what's important about this game.
So what makes a good GIF? I think there are a couple of core rules that I try to follow.
One is definitely it has to be eye-catching.
Don't start with like a long black screen. Just like go right in.
Have something, have your best scene in the beginning because a lot of people are just going to scroll through it.
And if it doesn't have anything cool in the first second, that's about it.
Always assume that people don't know what your game is.
Even if you've already had a couple of big tweets, there's always new people seeing your stuff.
I think a good GIF has to work for newcomers as well.
It doesn't need to be complete, as we saw with Heaven's Fault.
It just needs to be enough that players understand
what the core premise of the game is.
And really important for all the social media things,
of course, is that people love that stuff versus just liking
it.
So if you can pick between making one really, really
cool gif or 10 to 20 average gifs,
always go for the one that people love.
That has the potential to be shared.
On social media stuff that is just OK
is just not quite worth it.
So, how do we make pretty GIFs?
That's actually easier than I think
that a lot of people would assume.
Step number one, we wanna record a GIF.
The quick and easy way to do that
is with an on-screen recording tool.
It's a little program, for example,
like GIFCam, Screen2GIF, or for Mac users, Lightscap.
And those are all free and basically they just give you like a little window on screen
and then you can record whatever is under that window and then you have a GIF.
And that's it.
So if you want to make a bug GIF that takes a couple of seconds, it's really great.
There's also programs like OBS, Fraps or QuickTime where you can record video footage of those
at that window and that's maybe more important if you want to have a really sophisticated
GIF and want to edit it later.
And the really bare bones thing to get a GIF
is if you have a YouTube video or a YouTube trailer,
and you just go to giphy.com, and you put it in there,
and you literally set down the duration and the start time,
and then you have a GIF.
Like that's from the Untitled Goose Game.
I just made that yesterday.
That took like 20 minutes to do.
20 seconds, sorry.
So it's extremely easy to, if you already
have a YouTube link with Giphy, to just make one small GIF.
Pros, if you want to make a really, really quality GIF or a quite challenging one because
you maybe need to find a certain file size, you're going to have to cut it in a video
editor.
There's loads of different video editors.
Usually for the purpose of a GIF, it doesn't really matter which one you use as long as
you're comfortable with it.
If you want to go mega hardcore, Photoshop can also edit frame by frame.
Next up is just some editing tips.
Those are not very scientific,
but I've been just making hundreds of GIFs over the years,
so this is like my top tip collection
of what I do when I edit them.
I really don't like having watermarks on GIFs,
like little logos just in the corner,
because they often look a bit markety,
and it really doesn't help
for a lot of social media stuff and pitching.
If you have a lot of really short scenes,
which happens in GIFs,
I try to leave them at least on for one second,
because I think everything below that
is really hard for the eye
to just get what's going on in the screen.
I really avoid having gameplay and text at the same time.
So I try to have either or because it's always,
it's just such a tiny window where you see most GIFs.
If needed, if you need more space
or need to cramp up more content in a short GIF,
I sometimes speed up GIFs by 10%.
Obviously it really depends on your game.
If you make a super realistic golfing game,
maybe don't speed it up by 50%
and the golfer goes like that.
But if you have a narrative game
and the cursor moves a bit quicker, that's probably fine.
First frame is really, really important.
Never ever have a black screen as a first frame.
The reason for that is often when GIFs don't load
for some reason, if there's preview windows,
you're always gonna see the first screen.
So if there's any issue, that first screen
is a screenshot that shows up instead of a GIF.
And the next tip is start with something eye-catching.
We had that short in the beginning.
And I think that's also something Hollywood does quite a lot.
If you look at trailer from really big blockbuster films now,
they often start with like a five second summary
of the real trailer and then the trailer starts.
And that, I think, is related with just getting the attention span of people immediately.
That's an example of a game we made in trailer form, actually, for Omno,
which starts really slow and it tries to build up moods.
And we thought that's not going to cut it.
And that's why we cut in the third scene where the guy falls down.
You just see animation really quickly.
Well, it's really important to get that mood across for the game.
We want to see, we want to definitely show people the animation straight away.
So I think just having a really strong scene just in the first one or two seconds really helps.
And that's a really practical gif.
I really like a trick.
I really like that. Recycle your trailer into multiple gifs.
If you can, you finish your trailer first.
And then you take a trailer and cut out 30 seconds of that
and make a teaser trailer of that.
And then you cut out 10 GIFs out of that and the main GIF.
So with that one big trailer asset
that you need to do anyway, you immediately
have a whole bunch of small assets with no extra work.
Step number two after recording and editing a GIF
is now we want to compress it.
And there's a website called easygif.com.
And it's so good. I don't know why it's so good.
It's a bit criminal. It's for free and you can just
upload your GIFs and
move a couple of sliders around and see how it compresses,
how the image quality changes, how big the GIFs are.
It's so good for really like precisely compressing stuff.
I love it.
If you compress things, if you want to get to certain salfies, it's really important to just figure out what is the most visual aspect of your game and then go from there.
Usually there are three things that fight with each other, which is the frame rate, the length of the GIF and the resolution.
So if a game is like Omno and the animation is really important,
you want to probably have a good frame rate.
If you want to tell a little story, a little joke,
but it needs to be a bit longer, you want to have certain length.
If you have a game like Eastshade that looks like a really nice painting,
then you probably want to have a nice resolution.
And there's a good chance you can't have all three of those.
So just make sure you know which one you want to have.
Personally, I'm usually aiming for 10 to 20 frames per second for GIFs,
sometimes 30 if it's really important about animation.
I try to make them 5 to 15 seconds long.
For emails, I usually use 500 pixels in width and for social media, usually 600.
If you don't want to do step one and two and go to step zero
and just let the community do the GIFs,
that's also an option.
I think there are surprisingly little games that do that.
A really famous example, I think, is Poly Bridge.
They have a really good GDC talk about that
that is on the vault and on YouTube.
And in the game, you build a little bridge,
and it's physics-based,
so there's a lot of funny stuff happening.
And with the built-in GIF generator,
people were sharing GIFs like crazy,
and there was a really good marketing tool for them.
Just from their slides, their top 10 posts on Reddit got 12 million views.
So that was definitely worth the extra worth.
So in my opinion, if you have a physics-based game or a game where people can create stuff and funny things happen,
really consider putting a gift generator in there.
There's also a good evolution from that idea,
from a game called Nebartus.
And they took the idea one step further.
So for the Kickstarter, they had a demo.
And the demo had a gif generator.
And if you generate a gif in there and then tweet about it,
you can win free copies of the game.
So they really get people in to play and share stuff,
while they can also win something.
So it's quite nice for the players, I think,
but obviously also great from a PR point of view.
So where and how do you use those gifs?
What is the best way to do that?
Well, there's a lot of channels where you can use GIF.
And if we would go through them one by one in detail,
we would be here for a whole week.
So for today, I'm just going to pick my top five channels
that I think you can make the most out of your GIFs.
And also for that, I have to say, it's a roadmap.
And it gives you some tips per channels.
But it's definitely not a complete thing.
Because there's just so much to do per channel
that I'm sure you're going to find way more detailed talks
about each of those.
So my favorite one to use GIFs really good is Twitter.
And the one really good thing about Twitter
is if you have a good GIF,
you can really break out of your social media bubble.
So if you get a lot of retweets,
if you get a lot of likes,
your tweets start showing up on timelines
of new people you've never heard before.
So it really helps to just reach new players.
Really good on Twitter is also that movements on timelines
stand out quite a bit.
Here's an example from Polygon Treehouse,
a studio in Cambridge.
And they just have a tweet here with text
versus the same with an image versus the same with a GIF.
And you can clearly see that the one with motion
stands out the most in a timeline,
especially if you think how you use Twitter,
you just probably scroll through like that.
So it really helps having that first second animation going.
There's also some stats like David Whealy from the first tree set,
when he shared a GIF versus a screenshot, people were sharing it 10 times as much.
So I think it's really worth having animated GIFs,
even if just promoting a blog post or a small menu or something.
Even then, I think having some kind of motion is really important.
I highly recommend just experiment with screenshot set today.
It's a really popular hashtag.
It helps you to break out of your social media bubble even more.
I would try to do that as often as you can.
And I think also engine text, that's UE4 for the Unreal Engine
and hashtag made with Unity for Unity is a fantastic source to get more traction.
If you use that engine, they like your GIF and they retweet you.
You get a lot of, you know, a lot of new eyes on your game.
And you can do that quite a lot.
And that, I think, is the beauty of Twitter,
that you can basically post as much as you want.
Like, obviously, 10 GIFs per day.
But if you post one per week over a long period of time,
that's totally fine.
The people that follow you on Twitter,
they want to see your stuff.
So they won't be offended if you tweet regularly.
And it can really help to reach new people.
In terms of file format, GIFs on Twitter,
autoplay and decompression is quite predictable,
which is nice.
So autoplay is a big plus.
If you upload on mobile, you have a 5 megabyte limit
from desktop 15.
And I usually go with a.
a pixel width of 600.
There's different preferences that people like.
Some people also like to post more like square GIFs
so they look better on mobile.
I just prefer a YouTube format.
But I think the important thing is the 600 pixels in width.
Also mind that if you post a GIF on Twitter,
often you would have that little logo in the corner
that says GIF.
So if you don't put anything important there,
otherwise you have to reformat your GIF a bit.
You can also upload short videos on Twitter.
If they are under 6.5 seconds, they will auto-loop,
which is great.
They also have sound, and you don't
struggle with file restrictions, which is also great.
One thing, however, I will say that is Twitter sometimes
compresses video really weird.
So if you use video, check if it looks good.
And if it doesn't, maybe go for a GIF instead.
Facebook also added GIF support a while back, but I think it's way harder to reach new people with Facebook.
So I just mentioned here that GIF also works. I usually cross post on both platforms, but Twitter is usually the one that gets way more traction.
I think a really underrated platform is Imgur or Imgur.
Don't know how to pronounce it either. I say Imgur now.
If you hit the front page, which is not too hard at the moment,
we have a quite good success rate
because I think it's not so saturated
as the other networks.
You get easily 80,000 to 200,000 views.
What's really popular there is something
that looks like on the right, which is blog posts that
are quite personal.
And usually what we do is we have a nice headline,
we have a first GIF, and then we describe in a sentence what
is the game.
And then we have another GIF, and then we
describe in a sentence what happened in that GIF,
and so on.
And you usually have four or five GIFs,
and then you say goodbye.
Really important on Imgur is that you have a really good headline in the first frame
because that's the only thing that shows up in the preview window.
That's how people are going to find you.
And if they upload you enough, then you go trending.
In terms of file sizes, it's really generous.
You can use up to 200 megabytes per image or per video, up to 30 seconds long.
And Imgur converts GIFs into videos anyway.
So you might as well just use videos because it's a bit better quality.
If you are not familiar with Imgur yet and you want to start a new account, it's no problem at all.
It's great for Twitter and Imgur that you can just go in fresh and if you have good content,
it just gets shared and you can really reach new people.
However, they have really strict spam filters.
So in the beginning, don't post any links.
You get a notification once you are mature enough on the platform,
so you can post links, but don't do it in the beginning.
Also, hashtags are really essential, especially game dev and gaming.
This is how people find you in Imgur.
So what I would recommend is having those longer blog posts
for whenever you do a big update, a big announcement,
and just post small little GIFs on Twitter
if you have a good one in between.
Reddit is a bit like the Holy Grail of posting a gift because, you know, on the right we saw one
that has 1.6 million views, the first tree got over 3.5 million views and 50,000 views on the
store page of Steam. So that's really good. The downside of Reddit, however, is like it's really
hard to be successful on Reddit.
but it is doable.
One of the most important things is obviously
they have the self promo rules.
So only 10% of your posts can be about your work
and your game.
So you have to just be part of the community,
talk to people, post in other subreddits.
So you hit that quota.
That's why it's also advisable to start an account early.
And I think.
The big one is each subreddit has different rules.
They all work a bit differently.
They all have different moderators.
If you really want to take it seriously on Reddit,
I think you really have to work through those rules,
look at the community for a while, start talking to them
and just like don't go in and try to market your thing,
but really try to be part of the community,
but it really pays off.
Often really personal headlines work where people say,
oh, I've been working on my game for five years,
for like two years I've been working with my wife on my game.
All that kind of stuff is usually good to just get people's attention
that really that I'm a small indie dev or I'm a developer,
I'm passionate about that.
That's the kind of stuff that usually works.
You can upload direct video or you can upload gif-like gif-icads.
The only thing that I would never do is put YouTube links or store pages on Reddit.
That's stuff that usually doesn't fly well in most subreddits.
And for Reddit I would also say be part of the community but don't overthink it.
It's the same with Twitter. Just post stuff and see what sticks.
Often you have a quite good idea of what is popular about your game,
but I tell you there were so many times when we were super surprised
what is actually the thing that people get really excited about your game.
The next one, point number four, is emails.
And this is a pitch email we sent to press
of a game called Lachledian Skies.
And it's an all right email.
It has like bullet points and bold writing and links.
So it's quite well formatted for what it is.
But now we look at the same email
where we changed the game description with an actual GIF.
And then you can see that that email isn't only way shorter,
it also looks way better because suddenly
you can understand the game mechanic
that is really complicated to explain.
So my definite top tip for GIFs is put them in emails right away.
We use that if you pitch to press, publishers, influencers, to your fans, newsletters, all that kind of stuff.
I think whenever you promote your game, putting that GIF right in is really, really helpful.
One warning that not all email programs support GIFs and really it is Outlook that doesn't support
it too well especially older Outlook versions than UseOne does. So depending on your target
group you might need to think about that. If for some reason you only mail people with old Outlook
maybe don't use GIFs but if that's not the case go for GIFs.
Again, mind the first frame.
If a GIF doesn't load in an email for some reason,
it will take the first frame as a screenshot and just show that.
I usually aim to have a GIF between 1 and 4 MB in an email
or up to 8 MB if you want to push it.
For example, if we email influencers, YouTubers and streamers,
we go up to 8 MB because often they're going to work on PCs anyway,
on desktop, and they have good internet connection,
so it's not a problem.
But if you deal with mobile users, that's maybe a bit much.
And here are the dimensions of a post, GIFs and emails usually try to aim between 350 and 600px.
And the last point is store pages.
Steam supports GIFs officially for a while now,
which is great.
You can use them in banners or just to show your game.
This is House Flippers, a really great example,
and they show the game mechanics in a two-second GIF
and make it look really interesting, I think.
You can also use GIFs in community updates,
which is cool for updates,
and you can use them in the award section.
The only thing is that the whole Steam page
shouldn't have more than 15 megabytes of combined assets.
And the last point is Kickstarter.
You can use gifts as well for banners,
for game gifts, for rewards.
And I think really important there is,
we here we have a Kickstarter page
and you're gonna get a lot of traffic,
but only a very small section of those people on your page
will actually click on a video and watch it.
So what I would highly recommend
is just having a gift quite on top
that those people that don't click on a video
or don't necessarily wanna watch it,
still see your game in motion.
And they don't have any file size limits,
but of course, keep in mind that you don't put up
like five gigabytes of GIFs, because then the site probably
just breaks.
So just a summary slide for the end.
Plan your GIF is step number one.
I think really important to plan GIFs properly in your PR plan
and save time so you can actually make them.
Prepare for main GIFs.
Remember the rules for the GIFs that keep on giving.
If you go into GIF making, firstly, you want to record your video with on-screen recording
with the different tools we talked about. Then go to compression, easygif.com, highly,
highly recommended. And think about which aspect, which visual aspect out of those three is the
most important for your GIF. Always keep in mind, if you have a trailer, recycle it,
make 100 GIFs out of it, really useful, why not? And whenever you do a GIF,
mind the first frame and make sure the first frame is really good.
To posting your gifs, Twitter is my favorite channel.
Movement really stands out there and you can experiment
and break out of your social bubble a lot.
Imgur is at the moment really good for games to reach people.
First frame is important.
Headline is really important.
And never ever forget the hashtags
because otherwise your posts just disappear.
On Reddit, there's no easy rule apart from try to really be part of the community and
try to understand it, live with it, write comments and see how other people do stuff.
In emails, always post GIFs in them if you can, but really mind the file sizes.
For the Steam store page, the same.
Really great to use GIFs, but wouldn't go over 15 megabytes.
And on Kickstarter, I would definitely focus on the top GIF just under the trailer so people
see a game in motion anyway, even if they don't watch the video.
Thanks a lot for listening.