So yeah, my name is Kyle Bunk, and I am an animator at Fractice Games at the moment,
which we generally use 3D animation, but yeah, my presentation has nothing to do with 3D
animation.
It's actually involved in pixel art.
So I want to give people kind of a little bit of a background on myself.
So
This is before I even entered college or anything like that.
During my early days in high school,
I would hang out in a lot of these spaces,
like DeviantArt, especially Newgrounds.
And from there, I kind of taught myself a lot of things,
like Flash and sort of traditional animation stuff.
And this is actually the oldest thing on the internet
that I've ever made.
It's like...
It's not even really animation.
It's more just clip art, just moving.
And it was from an English project.
I had to recreate something from Macbeth.
And I did it pretty accurately, but I had Macbeth say the F
word at the end for some reason.
I don't know, I thought that was really funny at the time
when I was a kid.
And it worked on Newgrounds.
But from there, I kind of wanted to do something more,
that's what I wanted to do professionally.
So.
I ended up going to a two-year school in Delaware
with the intent of transferring those two years
into a bigger college, like Pratt Institute,
or Academy of Arts, or SVA, or something like that.
But unfortunately, because of just personal financial
constraints, I couldn't do that.
So I had to find other venues to kind of express animation.
So I ended up going to Animation Mentor,
where I transferred most of my 2D skills
into 3D animation.
And that ended up landing me in a job at Gameloft,
which was their studio in New York City,
until they closed down.
And then I've been looking for work for quite a bit,
until I was picked up by Firaxis,
where I worked on the expansion for XCOM 2.
But in between that time, I actually was looking for work.
But I was also doing these pixel art things over the time.
I would do these over the internet.
And I'm actually wondering, how many people
have actually seen my stuff?
Oh my god.
That's a lot more than I thought.
See, I get the numbers on my phone,
but I don't actually see people.
So it's kind of nice seeing an actual number.
And here's more.
So I'll let this play for a little bit.
So the reason why I wanted to go over my background
was just to tell you guys more what I went into.
like pixel art knowing, because I wanted to do pixel art.
I had a lot of friends of mine who were really into it,
and I kind of wanted to jump in.
But I had to kind of know my limitations.
Like I knew animation just through 3D,
and like my days doing pencil and paper animations.
But the main challenge for me is that I wasn't really a designer.
Like, I couldn't really come up with a character, like an original thing.
So that's kind of why most of my animations are, like,
based on existing properties, like Overwatch.
And, um...
Past that, like modeling, texturing, and rigging
was a kind of game development pipeline
that I'm not really familiar with.
Like I know enough to do some basic effects,
but to do anything like sort of pixel art sprites with 3D
was kind of outside of my realm.
And another thing that was very different
was when I first started doing animation
during like my high school days,
the internet was really different.
Like you would have...
like animations would actually last quite a bit like flash videos would be
two to three minutes or like even longer and nowadays everything is in a gif
format so everything went from like two to three minutes to like three seconds
so i had to really fit my skills into a different
sort of medium that the internet sort of became
So what I want to say is that whatever you know,
whether it be traditional animation or 3D
or whatever it is, you should really base your pixel art
on that skill set that you have.
So I have three different examples.
I have this sprite from King of Fighters.
And that's basically using modeling, texturing,
and that standard pipeline that you
can make really amazing stuff out of it,
but that just wasn't my skill set.
And I wasn't really an illustrator,
so I couldn't do the amazing backgrounds that you
would see in Hyper Light Drifter.
But for something like Marvel versus Capcom,
where the characters are relatively simple,
but also have really robust movement,
I could kind of pull off something like that.
So.
I think what I want to say is that you can be creative with pixel art no matter what
your skill set is.
And I actually included Mortal Kombat sprites because those are basically just mocap people
with cool costumes, I guess.
So if you're a good costume designer, you can do that.
And even mixed mediums, like you have...
Oh my god, I can't believe I don't know his name.
Is it Sub-Zero?
It is.
I feel like the ice would be obvious.
But yeah, you have something that is basically a motion
captured guy, or not really motion captured,
like an actual person doing an ice blast.
And then somebody had to do the animation for the ice
on top of it.
And you can get really cool results with that.
And for those of you who have seen my Mercy pixel art,
I don't know if many people know this,
but a lot of the effects that come off of her
were actually done in the Unreal Particle System.
And it was like the first time that I actually
used something outside of just straight up drawing it.
Usually the way I start is I, this is for like my McCree animation, I wanted him to do like a roll and like a gun shoot backwards.
So there's actual footage of me kind of rolling forward and going backwards and it's like not really that great to be honest.
but it was better than nothing.
So to kind of go on top of that,
I looked at other things that really inspired me.
Like one of my favorite animated sequences of all time
is the Asuka final fight from End of Evangelion.
And there's like this really cool role
that was done by Mitsuo Iso.
And I wanted to incorporate a lot of that as well
into my role for McCree.
So, but before I even go into the animation process,
I wanted to figure out kind of the design.
I know I said I wasn't really a designer,
but something that already exists
is a lot easier to do that.
So I kind of just came up with this still image
that I was gonna worry about animation later.
So with a still image,
I also kind of figured out the colors
that I was going to use.
So.
I would use something called index colors, where basically I would just restrict myself
to the set number of colors, and I think the number here is like 32 colors, so it would
be 32 bit, I guess.
I don't know if transparency counts, but...
So indexing your colors is actually really important
for pixel art, because if you get really far
into your animation and you realize, wow,
that red kind of sucks, you can actually go into your palette
and just do a color change, and it'll
change every frame simultaneously.
So you don't have to go back and recolor everything.
So if you do want to do pixel art like this,
definitely do that first.
So.
When I do animation, oh, wait a minute.
Oh, there's a slide transition.
So something that I think a lot of people are fascinated with
is that I actually use Flash to do most of my animations,
not just because I originally started out on Newgrounds,
so I kind of have a bias towards it.
But also, vectors don't do this.
When you do pixel art, you can't really rotate or scale anything.
If you rotate it, the pixels, they just kind of get messed up.
There's just not enough data for it to cleanly translate.
And if you do this enough, you'll just kind of end up
with a mess of pixels.
Don't even think about scaling it,
because scaling it just absolutely destroys it.
So that's important to me as a 3D animator as well.
I want to be able to not only draw my stuff,
but to also be able to rotate, translate, and scale
these things just in each frame to be
able to get the best possible movement.
So for a while, I do stick to vectors.
The thing that stinks about.
Being in vectors for a while, though, is that whenever you export your thing into a more
pixel program, you end up with this anti-alias hell image, where everything is just really
blurry on the edges and even on the inside, which looks fine in most art, but in pixel
art it's kind of hideous.
But we'll worry about that later.
That's kind of another step.
So in actually doing these animations,
I keep in mind a lot of these principles
of making sure that your pose and your animation
just stays very clear, just based on a silhouette.
And even the effects I make sure read really well since.
You know, it's only going to be seen on one end.
I don't know if 3D games worry about this too much,
since you can see kind of the character in every single angle.
But for something like this, it's
really important to nail down your silhouette.
And I even have a bad example of a silhouette.
This is like midway of McCree's roll.
There's like a frame where you just can't,
he just turns into like a giant black ball, which
I wish I could figure out.
But.
So another thing is making sure that you're
spacing your frames.
I haven't done the effects yet, so you
see the crappy placeholders there.
But spacing is really important, because without it,
you get a really awkward movement.
The image to the right is just all the spacing just
put the same.
And you can see that it looks really robotic looking.
She goes into this anticipation, and then lifts off,
and then she just.
rises kind of slowly.
It looks really robotic.
So definitely when doing things like this,
keep in mind your spacing.
So smearing, this is something I don't know if 3D games worry
about too much.
But in 2D games, when your frame rate is really limited,
it's pretty important when you do a big transition.
between frames like the top frame you can see when the character is lifting his sword and swinging
down it just kind of blinks to it and it's kind of jarring just because like there's not enough
frames to be able to show that actual sword swing so for something like that I would actually put
in a sphere it sphere smear just to kind of communicate that motion blur
And it also is really good for sort of hitboxes if your sprite is intended for a game.
Smears also don't really have to look particularly good.
Here are some of my worst smears in all of my animations.
And actually, fun fact on Facebook,
somebody paused on that Genji pose and then posted it,
and he's just like, look how big his butt is.
I felt really embarrassed, and I stopped doing that.
Yeah.
So.
But with that said, when you're doing an animation,
you should smear as much as you can.
I don't think people pausing on your animations
and saying, look how bad it is, a smear shouldn't really
stop you from doing that.
Another thing is overlapping action.
I'll show you a GIF that I did that is pretty much nothing
but this.
But I wanted to show an example of when you don't
have overlapping action.
When you have all of your.
parts kind of just swinging and just translating at the same time, you kind of get something
really weird looking, like it doesn't look natural.
So when you do something overlapping, you really do want to break up the timing as much
as you can.
So this is the animation that is basically nothing but overlap.
The way she grapples with her hook.
pretty much beyond that.
There's not really any movement besides the actual hook itself.
So everything is overlapping with it.
And you can kind of see a very close relationship
between this and the previous example that I showed.
And I did want to go back and try
to remove all the overlap in this animation,
but it would have been just way too much work,
and it just wouldn't have looked good at all.
So.
Doing the animate, so once you do the animation stuff,
that's when the cleanup begins,
and it sounds as tedious as it is.
Basically, you have to go to every single frame and do this.
So, usually starting out with,
sorry, losing my train of thought.
So, when I showed you guys the,
like badly anti-aliased image.
The way that I usually kind of fix it up
is just to do like a general marquise,
like a magic wand effect around everything,
and then just expand it one pixel,
and then delete everything.
It usually gets rid of most of the anti-aliasing, but.
Like, it might take away more than you want,
but when you're cleaning up the edges like that,
I think it's better to take away more and then add later
rather than take away too little
and you just seeing like blurs still on the edge.
So, I don't know if I actually mentioned this,
but the program that I primarily use
for all this cleanup is Aseprite.
It's a program that is on Steam and I really recommend it.
It's like $15.
And.
It has a really robust timeline if you want to do pixel art
on your own.
So from there, once I remove the anti-aliasing from the borders,
I try to go into the colors and try to really define them
in the very beginning.
In this picture right here, there's
a very clear distinction between the green hues
and the bright pinks.
I burped there.
and the black silhouette in the back.
So from here, I'm just basically trying
to break up all the colors from one another
and getting rid of all the aliasing from the drawing.
And also another note, remember alpha channels.
A lot of my original GIFs were pixel art,
but they're all rendered on a white background.
Because I didn't think that people would...
I figured they'd just be used on the internet.
You know, people would just share them on the internet.
But it turns out people like taking these sort of animations
and putting them on their Twitch streams.
And because of that, you really do need that transparency
for something like that.
So if you do pixel art, like just do a transparency.
Don't put it on a white layer.
So...
From there, after I divide up all my colors,
I really have to think about how to do my shading
for my sort of style.
There's different things that you can do.
You can do hard gradient, which is basically
you just go ahead and you try to find the color
that's in between the two,
and you just kind of make this banding look.
Or you can do something called dithering,
where dithering was something that was done a lot back then
because of color restrictions.
Like a lot of game artists, they wanted to have this sort
of gradient, but were really restricted by color,
so they had to do this.
And in some cases, it looks good,
but I find that a combination between the two looks best.
So here's an example that I kind of pulled off the internet
like an hour ago.
of a sphere that uses both dithering and also banding.
I think it's an interesting look, and you can kind of play around with the different
amounts of whether you want dither or band.
So what I ended up settling in on was actually more banding, just because...
The hard thing about dithering is that it looks kind of strange when you animate it.
I think there's a way to do it, but for me it was just such a pain, like, making sure every dot
lined up, like, each frame. So I ended up just going with a sort of banding,
sort of hard gradient with my final output. So...
And yeah, I did say that going frame by frame
and doing these cleanups is just as tedious as it sounds.
But there are ways to kind of save time if you can.
Like something that I did with my Diva animation
is I actually made a 360 degree turnaround, which
every frame of this is drawn.
But I can just take pieces of it and reapply it
into my animation.
So.
Here's an example of that, where she lands and turns around
and flies off.
I'm able to just use all those pieces
into the actual animation.
And it saved me more time in the end
to just do that 360 degree.
And then also, if I want to do another one,
I have that library.
And I can just kind of paste it on my frames wherever.
So.
Another thing you can save time on is just straight-up cheating.
This actually happens really fast in my Mercy animation.
She actually spins her staff, and these frames are right next to each other.
Like, the tip of the staff, it just magically teleports to the other side.
But it doesn't really matter, because it goes so fast, nobody's, like, ever caught it.
Until now.
So...
Oops.
But yes, as is 2D animation, you should definitely
take advantage of the liberties that you get with this.
Because this is something that I think
is very hard to do with 3D.
Like with the amount of technical restraints
and rigging and stuff, there's a lot
that you can do with 2D animation.
So definitely don't forget that.
And so we're back to this gun.
And.
Here's the one thing that I find that is really nice about the data loss that you experience
with reusing assets and translating and rotating things.
Like, you kind of have to go back and clean it up
a little bit.
But the resulting image, you kind of
have a new picture in and of itself.
So if you do want to have an arm that rotates or something,
you don't have a bad bone animation
where it's just a vector sort of translating.
Like, it actually feels like every frame
is new because you did end up doing that cleanup.
So I guess that didn't really save you time.
So the next thing I want to show you
is a more sort of advanced thing that I've done very
occasionally, but I didn't have the patience
to do this all the time, was sub-pixel movement.
So this is basically when you're moving pixels,
you're super restricted with the amount of space
that you can move an object.
So something that, so say like you want to actually make your image move half a pixel.
Well you technically can't move half a pixel. So what you can do is actually break up the pixels
that go up or translate within your animation and even have colors in between. Like you can see
in the highlight there's
like kind of a mid-tone between the highlight
and the actual color itself.
So it does give the illusion of half pixel,
when in actuality it is not that.
So.
So one thing I want to say is some good resources that really
helped me out with this process was,
I don't know if many people are familiar with Miniboss'
sort of pixel art tutorials.
But this guy that goes by the handle of Saint11,
he's been posting these really cool pixel art
tutorials every week.
And they've been really, really, really
helpful for the things that I've been doing.
And also, if you just want more reference for sprites or sprite
animation, you can also go on Fighters Generation.
That just has a huge collection of fighting game sprites
from all different sorts of games.
So those two websites have proven invaluable to me.
And other thoughts?
These animations do take a long time to make.
I've been getting better and better at it, so they've been taking me a month rather than
like two to three of them.
But I think the main takeaway from this is that I want you to be able to do pixel art
based on whatever knowledge base you have.
I'm a traditional animator.
That started off on Newgrounds.
So when I do my pixel art, it's always
in the realm of animation.
But if you're an illustrator and you
want to get into pixel art, you should try out
pixel backgrounds or illustrations or whatnot.
And another thing that was very valuable for me
was just to show people my animations.
Even if they weren't animators, they always
had a really interesting opinion.
of how to improve my animation or what was not working with it.
And that has really helped me out in this whole endeavor.
So thank you very much.
That's the end of my talk.
So...
Wow.
I have six whole minutes left.
So I guess I can take questions, I guess, like if anybody has any questions to ask me
about my process or just anything related to this.
What frame rate do you prefer to work in?
I prefer 30 frames a second.
That's just what I use in games.
I'm just really used to that frame rate
that I've just stuck to, 30 frames a second.
There have been cases where 30 frames just wasn't working.
So I would just make the frames even faster.
So I'd get a really weird number, like 38 frames a second.
But the thing is, it's going on video,
so it doesn't really matter as much.
So yeah, I'm pretty fluid when it comes to frame rate.
Hello.
You say you use banding to do shading.
Do you typically standardize how many bands in your gradients
to use?
On a larger model, would you use more bands?
My main thing is just not to go crazy on it to the point
where it's literally a gradient.
At that point, it's like you're defeating
the purpose of using pixel art.
But usually, I have like.
one or two bands in the middle, that just kind of works for me.
I think the Diva one, I only really used a highlight,
a mid-tone, and then a shadow.
And for the most part, that works
with most of my animations.
Thank you.
How would you say your exploration in this way
informs your day-to-day, like, day job?
I actually started incorporating 2D into my pipeline for 3D.
I will shoot reference, but then my reference isn't good, as you've seen.
So I'll actually go into Flash and actually make a crappy stick figure animation to kind
of just give me an idea of the timing that I want.
And from there, I'll look at both the reference
and that animation and try to bring that into 3D.
So I guess that's how it's affected my day-to-day job,
is that I actually do use traditional animation
for my planning.
The program that you use, it's called a Sprite,
or what is it again?
Hey, I don't know either.
It is pronounced, it's like a Sprite, I think.
Let me go back to the slide.
I can show you how it's...
The question I have is, what did you use before that?
Because I'm just now hearing about that,
and I feel like Photoshop is pretty difficult,
and that's all I've been using so far.
Yeah, the difficulty with Photoshop is that
the layers and the timeline are very separate.
They're very separate entities.
Aseprite is the way that its layers are,
like, its timeline and its layers
are kind of on top of one another.
So it's a lot easier to kind of maintain and edit
your timeline in Aseprite.
So.
And it limits your amounts of colors you can use too,
it seems.
Yeah.
Yeah, you can actually go in and.
restrict your palette count if you want to.
And it even comes with pre-built ones.
Like, you can actually go in and it has, like,
the original Game Boy.
Like, you can actually set your palette,
and then, oh, I'll just do that.
Yeah, it's a really handy program.
Nice, I'll check it out.
Thanks.
Mm-hmm.
I think that's it.
So.
Thanks, everybody.