Hello and welcome to this talk, How the Industry Can Change the Games or Bad Narrative. I am Dr.
Rachel Cowart. I am the research director for TakeThis. For those who are not familiar with
TakeThis, we are the first mental health non-profit to form serving the gaming industry and the gaming
community. We seek to de-stigmatize mental health challenges and provide mental health
information and resources.
My role at TakeThis is in research and education.
I am a research psychologist by trade.
I'm also a science content creator on YouTube,
Zeitgeist, where I talk about the science of game studies.
I speak there and on virtual stages
like this on a range of topics relating
to the uses and effects of digital games
and specifically their impact on physical, social,
and psychological well-being.
As you can imagine, I've spoken a lot about the narratives in and around games,
but never directly to the industry itself, and that is what brings me here today.
I'm here today to discuss the discrepancies between what we know in the research community
about the uses and effects of games and the narratives that we are told by the world around
us about the uses and effects of games.
Now, one thing that's often missing from discussions like this
is the role of the industry in the creation and sustainment
of these narratives, specifically how research collaborations
between academia and the video game industry
have the potential to catalyze societal shifts away
from the inaccurate negatives we receive from society,
inaccurate narratives we receive from society,
the what about the children, and towards more accurate
and nuanced discussions that reflect scientific reality.
the utility and fun and joy of video games.
Common discourse in and around games has been fueled by moral panic
for certainly as long as I can remember. For those who are unfamiliar with the term
moral panic, a moral panic is an irrational approach to observable and quantifiable
phenomena that can best be understood as separate from subjective evaluations.
This definition is clearly the academic in me, but I will clarify.
So moral panics are rational approaches to a problem because at their core,
they're about ascribing a easy solution to a complex problem that can best be
understood as separate from subjective evaluations refers to the fact that moral
panics are ascribing an easy solution without taking the time to try and
understand the issue from a more subjective approach, a subjective evaluation.
Now, video games are certainly not the first new technology
to face moral panic.
We've seen these kinds of panics come and go.
We've seen it with Dungeons and Dragons, and comic books,
and Elvis's Hips.
But what sets the moral panic about video games apart
is the fact that it's the longest standing
moral panic of our time.
The moral panic around video games
started to pick up steam in the early 1970s, well,
the late 1970s, really, when people
were concerned about the weird activities that were
happening.
in dimly lit arcades that were gaining in popularity
across the globe.
Flash forward 50 years, five zero years later,
and the moral panic about video games remains strong.
And we can see this in the way that video games continue
to be represented in pop culture.
For example, the classic episode of South Park
about World of Warcraft, or more recently,
poor unhealthy Thor playing video games in Avengers Endgame.
You see the pizza box and the energy drinks and he's quite aggressive when he's playing in the movie.
The stereotype and the representation of pop culture hasn't really changed much over the last 50 years,
but perhaps more striking and ubiquitous is the prominence of moral panic in and around games within the news media.
Now, there's no shortage of examples I could draw from the news media,
but here are just a couple to kind of show you the range of what we see about games in the news,
from the generally innocuous kind of blanket statement,
video games are bad, to the more specific and ever pervasive narratives,
like the link between video game violence and specifically video games and mass shootings.
particularly when it comes to young male offenders.
Now this is classic moral panic, ascribing an easy solution
to a complex problem that doesn't consider
subjective evaluations.
For example, with the violence in video game narrative
not considering the role of frustration tolerance
or previous exposure to violence or peer delinquency,
all of which have been found to contribute to real world
violent behaviors.
Unlike video games, which for the record,
have not been linked to real world violence.
And there have been hundreds, if not thousands, of studies examining its potential contribution.
Now that's just one discrepancy between science and society when it comes to the narratives around
games and perhaps the most pervasive example of the moral panic driven, driving the games
are bad narrative. Here's another example.
In January 2021, I made some waves when I took to Twitter
with this moral panic-fueled headline
that was printed on the literal front page of The New York
Times, if you had a physical copy.
The title is, Children's Screen Time
Has Soared in the Pandemic, Alarming Parents
and Researchers.
I mean, those parents look disappointed.
Look at the expression on their faces.
Now, this article did focus on screen time generally,
but games had a starring role because, of course, they
As with all articles that came before it, it was far more moral panic than actual science.
This article was particularly upsetting to myself as a researcher because it was specifically
discussing increased video gameplay during the first part of the COVID-19 pandemic lockdown,
when many researchers were preaching about the potential of not just social screen time,
but video gameplay specifically for social connection and stress release and social play,
but I died.
So here are a few snippets from this article in case you happen to miss this one.
Here's the first. Classic moral panic. You see here at the bottom the cost will be
borne by families because increased online use is associated with anxiety,
depression, obesity, aggression, and addiction to the medium itself.
Again, for the record, none of these claims are strongly supported by the scientific literature
when we're talking about games specifically, and I wish I had more time to go into that
because that's my jam, but as I mentioned earlier, I have an entire YouTube channel
dedicated to that if you're interested more in the science of games and their uses and effects.
Another quote is the negative framing of escapism,
which is classic.
We see here, Dr. Radesky said,
the mingling of all these functions
not only gives children a chance to multitask,
it also allows young people to escape
from any uncomfortable moment they may face.
If they're doing schoolwork that bores them,
she said, they can easily move into a pleasure cocoon
by watching YouTube, chatting with friends,
or playing a game.
I personally love the idea of a pleasure cocoon.
I found my pleasure cocoon of choice on Netflix recently.
and I know I'm not the only one, but we see she's talking more generally about screen time here.
Now historically video games have been specifically singled out as a negative escape because no one
really ever has anything bad to say about escaping into a good book or even an old Netflix binge,
right? This is really kind of an old hat when paired with video games and another consequence
of moral panic in the media.
Research has found that games, YouTube videos, books, Netflix, anything with Henry Cavill are cathartic forms of escapism
associated with stress reduction and mood management.
This was my favorite part of the article, so I had to mention it.
What are you going to do when you're married and stressed? Tell your wife you need to play Xbox.
I feel like if this was a live event, I would pause for laughter here.
Because yes, games are fantastic stress relievers,
which I'm sure many of you watching here today can attest to.
I know for me, nothing gets my stress and frustration out
like saving a town heroically or toiling away on my Stardew Valley farm.
And again, the research supports this.
So why am I belaboring this point?
I'm sure you're all very familiar with the reputation
that games have in popular media and culture.
The reason I'm bringing this up today
is because you may not be aware
that researchers have been actively working
to combat this moral panic and misinformation
about games for the last 50 years.
And despite the wealth of information we have generated
as a research community, we have largely failed
to make any significant long-term change
to the public discourse.
Case in point, the continued link between violent video games
and real-world violence, despite a lack of scientific support.
And to be honest, if anything, the moral panic
in and around games has continued
to intensify over the last five decades,
alongside its continued rise in popularity.
So why is this the case?
Well, there are several reasons.
First, the moral panic plays into our human nature.
To be cognitive misers or lazy thinkers,
we want an easy solution to a complex problem.
And that's really at the heart of the moral panic.
But also, games researchers are not the best
at reaching out to the public.
First, in terms of having access to press and public relations,
but also being able to express scientific information
in relatable and understandable ways.
You did see my definition of moral panic earlier.
wasn't particularly relatable or understandable. But perhaps more foundationally, the moral
panning narrative has failed to change because our research simply isn't good enough.
The narrative remains, at least partially, due to limitations in our ability as a research community
to dispel many of these myths in systematic ways. But the good news is that many of these
limitations we face as researchers could be overcome through collaborative efforts with
industry partners.
There are several players at hand when it comes to shaping our understanding of what games are and what they are not,
and consequently, the public discourse or narratives that we have in and around games.
There's the public, there's researchers, and there's the industry.
Information that derives from and is largely discussed within the public sphere
comes from stereotypes, pop culture, news media, personal experience, and anecdotal evidence.
This is why we have that South Park episode and why oftentimes when I'm interviewed at least one
question starts with, well I know someone who, and it's a question about violence or addiction.
Now, some of these sources of information in the public sphere
are informed by the work of researchers
through academic work and press and general advocacy.
Perhaps less informed than I would like them to be.
And of course, as we noted before,
it tends to focus more on the negative than the positive.
But somewhat informed nonetheless,
some information gets through.
Now the industry is another contributing voice
to the narratives around games.
The work of the industry is more insular,
far more so than what we see in academia,
which is saying something,
because you know academics like to live
in their ivory tower.
The industry's primary potential contribution
to the narratives and discussions about video game
uses and effects are things like user research
and other proprietary work.
However, this kind of research remains exclusively
within the particular walls of any particular studio
and doesn't really trickle out to either researchers
or the general public.
There are some exceptions to the insular nature of the industry
work, like the occasional general advocacy and outreach.
For example, what we see with the Raising Good Gamers
initiatives established by Games for Change
to catalyze positive change in the culture and climate
of online gaming.
They have several industry representatives
that serve on the advisory board for this initiative who
actively contribute their expertise and data.
This is a great example, but these kind of collaborations
are really rare.
Now, apart from collaborations like Raising Good Gamers,
the only other exception that I could
find to the insular nature of the industry's contribution
to the narrative about games is the ever-elusive practice
of data sharing.
Now, I know that made everyone sit up straighter, start
sweating, or both.
So what do I mean by data sharing?
Sharing information about a game.
whether it's about in-game actions, transactions, or player information
that is collected from the developer or publisher of any particular game
and shared with researchers from outside the particular
developer or studio, researchers from universities or organizations.
Why is data sharing important?
Because high quality data is the greatest limitation
that researchers face in game studies
and the most significant roadblock
to combating moral panic thinking and the games
or bad narratives.
The work of researchers is limited by the resources
we have access to, and our greatest limitation
is access to representative and robust data.
Lack of access to high quality data creates a range of challenges and limitations.
Firstly, it impacts our research designs. The vast majority of the work in game studies
assesses a snapshot of players, for instance. It collects information from a singular moment in time
rather than following the same players over time, which would allow for a better
assessment of change over time and examine potential cause and effect relationships.
A lack of direct access to players limits our scope of work.
Representative samples of players are difficult to come by in the wild,
and typically we have to rely on what we call snowball sampling,
which is posting a request to participate on social media
and hope that other players share in their networks
and the recruiting efforts snowball.
This kind of method tends to recruit the most keen players,
the most active players, rather than a representative variation
in player samples, which is part of the reason why so much work
in game studies has focused on the extremes, the most involved
players, because that's what we're most able to recruit.
Lack of players access also impacts
the number of participants we can recruit.
Sample sizes are a consideration.
If I'm lucky, I get 200, 300 maybe respondents to the work
that I do.
And it's hard to draw robust conclusions about,
you know, like.
2.5 billion gamers from a sample of 300.
There's also the impact on data that we can't even collect.
For example, researchers have to rely heavily
on self-reported data of time played rather than server log
data.
This is the difference between asking how many hours a week
do you play games versus knowing how many hours somebody logged
in Overwatch last week.
This is less than ideal, particularly
as we are terrible estimators of the amount of time
we spend doing it.
Having active collaboration with industry partners
could remedy all of these limitations.
Access to representative samples of players,
heaps of them, access to gameplay data,
and strengthen the ability for us as researchers
to generate more cohesive and accurate narratives
about the uses and effects of games.
Now, the next question that I'm sure you have in your mind is why should the industry bother
working with outside researchers? We don't have these limitations as members of the industry.
This is a you problem, right? You might also say, you know, outside researchers are kind of annoying
or terrible at time management and have different goals and no money. First of all, harsh. Second of
all, I have excellent time management skills.
But the truth is, researchers from the outside bring objectivity to the table,
which is key for informing public discourse.
Of course, game companies can write a white paper and say games are great.
That's to be expected.
But working together with outside objective research partners that can make
independent evaluations, you know, from academia or from non-profit organizations, for instance.
That's where the real power lies.
It's about working collaboratively
with researchers who can make independent evaluations
with the support and resources of the industry behind it.
It's about working together to understand
the uses and effects of games as digital social interactive
medium.
Working collaboratively through data sharing
is how we go from this to this.
It's how the networks become integrated,
our fronts united, our Triforce completed.
That was a missed opportunity to use a Triforce reference.
It's also how the dialogue starts to shift.
So I'm going to give you a couple of examples.
First, an illustration of how limitations
in the work of researchers have led to inaccurate narratives.
This 2020 paper looked at the estimation of iPhone use.
In the abstract, it says, among a sample of 325 iPhone users,
I told you sample sizes would be small.
They're hard to come by big sample sizes.
We found that participants misestimated
their weekly overall iPhone use by 19 hours
and social media use by 12 hours.
correlations between estimated use and well-being variables were stronger than the correlations
between actual use and well-being variables, and the degree of inaccuracy in estimated use
was associated with levels of participant well-being and amount of use. What does this mean?
First, we're terrible estimators of time, overestimating by almost 20 hours a week of actual use.
Now, keep in mind, almost all studies in technology use, but game studies specifically,
use this methodology of recalling how much time that you spent doing it.
And that estimated use was associated with negative well-being outcomes,
but actual screen time wasn't.
TLDR, self-report data can be widely inaccurate
and skew the findings and narratives
towards the negative, perpetuating
the moral panic in society about well-being and technology.
And yes, the same has been found when
it comes to games, which I'm going
to talk about in a minute.
Now, what happens when you have hundreds of papers using
this methodology of self-reflection,
finding negative relationships between well-being
and technology, whether it be iPhones or games?
You find someone compiles them into a very popular book that
fuels a new wave of moral panic.
which then gets passed on to popular culture,
news media, and ingrained in the public,
and the cycle continues.
And as I mentioned, yes, the same can be said for games.
And this has put us in a position
where we're playing catch up
to these very ingrained, skewed, and inaccurate negatives.
It's narratives, not negatives.
It's an uphill battle,
but not one that can be overcome in isolation,
because we've been trying for 50 years.
Now, I know the proof is in the pudding,
so here is your dessert.
This paper was released in 2020.
In this paper, Yohannes and colleagues
assess the relationship between video game play and well-being
in a unique way.
They analyzed players' actual play behavior
through a collaboration, a data-sharing collaboration,
with Electronic Arts and Nintendo of America.
In this study, they surveyed players
at Plants vs. Zombies, Battle for Neighborville,
and Animal Crossing New Horizons.
for their well-being and play motivations during play
and merged their responses with logged gameplay data provided
by the companies.
What did they find?
On average, players overestimated their gameplay,
just like we saw with iPhone use by two hours,
further supporting the idea we were terrible estimators
of time.
When it came to looking at the relationships between video gameplay and well-being,
the researchers found a positive relationship between playtime and well-being.
It was significant and it was positive using the server data.
But when they used the self-reported estimates,
the same positive relationships only remain for players of Animal Crossing
and not plants versus zombies,
highlighting the importance of objective rather than subjective playtime data.
So contrary to the fire and brimstone,
we often hear when it comes to the impact
of video games on well-being,
the researchers found a positive relationship
between gameplay and well-being.
They found that players who objectively played more
over the last two weeks also experienced greater well-being.
As discussed in an interview, one of the researchers on the team, Andy Shabilsky, noticed, if we
look at the bottom three sentences here, if you play Animal Crossing for four hours a
day, every single day, you're likely to feel significantly happier than someone who doesn't.
This doesn't mean Animal Crossing by itself makes you happy, he added.
Forty years of previous research has suggested the longer people played, the more unhappy
they were.
That's not even the best part.
Because they were provided with objective play data,
the researchers were able to look objectively
at the relationships between well-being and playtime
and ended their paper with this nugget of goodness.
Although our data do not support causal claims,
they do speak to the broader conversation surrounding
the idea of video game addiction.
The discussion about video games has
focused on fears for a large part of players
becoming addicted.
Given their widespread popularity,
many policymakers are concerned about the negative effects
of gameplay on well-being.
Our results challenge that view.
The relation between playtime and well-being
was positive in two large samples, large samples,
because they had access to players from the companies.
Therefore, our study speaks against an immediate need
to regulate video games as a preventative measure
to limit video game addiction.
If anything, our results suggest that play could be an activity that relates positively to people's mental health,
and regulating games could withhold those benefits from players.
The magic word, regulation, right?
This singular paper, powered by collaboration with the industry,
contributed more robust evidence in the last 10 years of research done in isolation
against regulating games as a safeguard for players.
It also got an incredible amount of PR.
This study was lauded by the press.
I mean, look at these headlines.
Did you ever dream you would see so many headlines
about video games with the word good in them?
These headlines were only possible, excuse me,
were only possible because of the industry collaboration
with research partners outside of their four walls.
Data sharing allowed for independent evaluation
of the data from researchers from the Oxford Internet
Institute to demonstrate strong evidence
between the link between play and mental health.
Having industry support also brought weight and clout and more legitimacy to the strength of the
paper and the findings discussed within it, which in no doubt contributed to the increased press
coverage around it. The industry has such an opportunity when working together with researchers
outside their four walls to change and rehabilitate the narratives in and around games,
and these headlines are case in point.
Having active industry research partners is key to moving beyond this moral panic.
Now, by not partnering with external researchers, the industry is limiting their ability to craft a more accurate,
not moral panic driven, narrative in and around video game effects within broader societal context.
Aren't you tired of the games and violent old hat?
I am.
And there's also a whole other range of things to explore
like games and mental health and games and learning
and games and social connection.
Working together is how we get from alarmist headlines,
like the one from the New York Times,
to more nuanced and accurate headlines,
like we see here in relation to the Oxford study,
that reflect the utility and reality
that the role that games play in our everyday lives,
whether it's about our well-being or games and learning
or social connection or family connection.
My hopes with the example here was to highlight
how critical of a component the industry is.
for creating more balanced and informed narratives around games,
and how collaboration can start to pivot conversations about video games
away from moral panic fears and towards a more accurate understanding of what
games are and what they are not.
To be clear, this is more than just about good PR.
The repercussions of having the power of industry behind this work
will have wide-ranging effects for both science and society.
For science, providing researchers with industry-collected data
allows them to produce more robust research with higher external validity
that more accurately reflects the uses and effects of games.
This has a range of effects for society.
Having more robust research, consequently more press about the research,
will start to shift the games or bad narratives from the bottom up
to more accurately informed.
public opinions. Another societal consequence, well-designed and executed research, is the
foundation for political and policy debates around games, which we didn't touch so much on today,
but is equally rooted in moral panic. This is from 2021. GTA blamed for recent surge in
carjackings in Chicago. As I'm sure many of you are aware, this headline was discussing
a recently proposed sales ban on byline video games because of
of links, presumed links, between simulated violence in games and real world violence,
which I mentioned briefly is not something supported by the scientific research.
This policy decision, putting a sales ban bill up for debate or vote over
Fart God I Don't Think It Got Very Far This Time, was based on bad science.
Researchers and industry share the same goal when it comes to promoting well-informed,
evidence-based decision making. And working together, we can create a strong foundation
for it, as we saw from that closing quote in the Johannes article. But to do that, we have to be
more engaged in independent research with outside organizations. This is how together we advance a
more active advocacy agenda, which benefits us all and is clearly needed.
Games are tools and pretty freaking great ones at that.
Tools for fun, tools for connection, tools for learning
and not tools for carjackings.
But in not working together,
the industry is missing the opportunity
to be a proactive partner
and shifting the narrative away from moral panic
and towards a more accurate and nuanced discussion
that reflects scientific reality.
It's about advancing an advocacy agenda
based on good science,
based on the best science that we can produce.
And we do that by joining together.
Like coffee and a donut, we are better together.
And we must join together if we're
going to rehabilitate the narrative of games.
Think I'm the coffee in this analogy,
because I feel like games have to be the donut,
because everyone loves a donut, right?
Thank you guys so much for coming to this talk.
If you are interested in reaching out,
if you have any questions or comments,
or are now inspired to start some research collaborations,
please do reach out.
This is my email, my Twitter,
the URL to the Psych-I's YouTube channel
if you wanna learn more about the science of games.
And of course, if you wanna learn more about Take This
and all that we do,
are looking for mental health information and resources,
please visit takethis.org.
Thank you.