So my name is Greg Street.
I head design on League of Legends.
Players call me Ghostcrawler.
They call me worse things as well, but we'll get to that.
I've been asked to remind you about keeping an eye on your
phones and filling out the review forms at the end of
the session.
And here we go.
So I want to start by explaining the title, Balancing
League for Every Player from Bronze to Bengi.
This is Bronze.
Within ranked League of Legends, there are seven
tiers.
Bronze is the first one.
And at the opposite end of the spectrum, this is Bengi.
His name is Bae Seong-Eun.
He's currently the jungler for a Chinese e-sports team
named Vici.
But he's better known as a three-time world champion
with Korean team SKT.
He's very good at League of Legends.
So this is the challenge.
How do you balance a game where the skill differential
between players isn't like 10% or 20%,
it's 1,000%, 10,000%.
The pros of League are exponentially better
than people just starting out.
And this is me.
I started life as an oceanographer.
That actually isn't me, but that's the kind of stuff I did,
dropping muddy things off the back of boats.
It was before digital cameras.
I got my start in game design working on the Age of Empires franchise where I was at
Ensemble Studios for ten years.
From there I went on to World of Warcraft where I led systems design for about six
years.
And I've been at Riot Games working on League of Legends for the past three years.
On all three of these franchises I either oversaw balance directly or was
accountable for it. I've been doing this a long time.
I like to nerf things.
I use a crab as my avatar, getting back to the Marine theme.
This is Ghostcrawler.
And more recently, I've switched to the Rift Scuttler.
And this is League of Legends.
Hopefully, most of you are familiar with this, and that's why you came.
But just in case, it is a 5v5 MOBA, free to play with cosmetic content.
We like to think of it looking like the image on the left,
but of course, it actually looks like the image on the right.
I'm going to use a lot of League examples in the talk today, but not everything.
And I'll mention some other games as well.
My hope is that this topic is broadly applicable to the kind of games you guys work on
and not just a story of League of Legends.
And this is a champion. This is Leona the champion.
League has 134 champions. We add new ones every year.
Champion is a unique character with a passive and four different abilities.
We often abbreviate these abilities QWER,
which I say because I'm going to end up calling them QWER.
That's just our shorthand.
I'm going to talk a lot about champion balance,
because champions are kind of the basic molecule
by which players interact with League of Legends.
So a lot of the balance considerations that we deal with are about champions.
So my topic outline, why is balance important?
I'm going to cover this super quickly because I'm going to
make the assumption you guys are kind of on board with this
concept already.
How we balance for different skill levels, balance for a
massive audience, and then finally, I'm going to spend
the majority of the talk talking about how tactically
how does Riot balance League day to day.
And I'll try to end with plenty of time for questions.
So why is balance important?
I like the definition that Game Balance is a contract with the player.
Because contract implies a business transaction where players are getting goods and services for their payment.
And it can be literal payment if they're purchasing a character, but it doesn't have to be real money.
If you play a warlock in World of Warcraft, you may have 10 years invested in that character,
and you want some guarantee that Game Balance isn't going to stop you from playing her.
Now League is a competitive PvP game with a very, very small PvE component.
And skill in League is supposed to matter.
This is why players play League of Legends, to demonstrate their skill.
And we don't ever want the state of balance to trump skill.
When you have a game that's imbalanced, it makes it too easy to solve the game.
And if you have a game that is very solvable, players tend to get bored.
And when players tend to get bored, they stop playing your game.
Options are also really good for longevity.
If you have a game like League that we hope that players
interact with for a long time, once they get tired of playing
one champion, there's a lot of other ones out there that they
can try out.
Now, Riot as a company cares a lot about player trust.
This is something we focus on a lot.
We try to be very player focused in every decision we make.
And if the game is in an imbalanced state for too long,
that kind of suggests to the players that we don't care.
And so it's kind of violating, you know,
trying to hold up player trust as being so important.
Now, tragically, balance is really hard.
And as important as it is for your game and for players,
the development cost is super high.
And I'm going to talk throughout the rest of the talk about why this is
and some strategies and tactics that may help you mitigate it.
So balance for different skill levels, part two.
This is what a pro championship of League of Legends looks like.
Pros can do amazing things that we mere mortals cannot possibly conceive of doing.
And balance at high skill level, and especially at pro skill level,
is really different from balance for the rest of the game,
and certainly for newer players.
And I'm going to talk about some of these differences that manifest in any game
that make it difficult to balance for extreme skill differentiation.
So, next few slides I'm just coming at you with a list, be forewarned.
Some of these are differences you don't want to avoid necessarily,
but you do want to be aware of them.
So to start off, you can break down player skills being tested in a game into a lot of different buckets.
Things like good decision making, good team communication, fast reflexes, and so forth.
Now one of the biggest differences between highly skilled and normal skilled players
comes in execution difficulty.
As developers, we sometimes balance, often balance, the power of an ability
with it being difficult for a player to pull off.
So this is a basic skill shot, League of Legends is full of them, rather than...
clicking on the enemy target with your mouse and then just hitting a button that will always hit them,
you have to line up the attack and take into consideration things like, you know,
leading them, predicting where the enemy's going to be, and so forth.
But it's not just skill shots. Anything involving timing or multitasking or often just the speed of clicking,
you know, APM, is much easier for highly skilled players.
Some of the ultimates in League of Legends, the R ability, are channeled.
And a channeled ability, you can think of the champion as like winding up, casting a spell.
And during that time, if they get interrupted, it either cancels a spell outright or it might have a diminished effect.
This is Fiddlesticks, our evil, magical scarecrow.
He has an ult called Crowstorm where he summons a lot of crows, but he does have to channel it.
And this is the kind of thing that...
makes it a little harder to use at the pro level because, or even at highly skilled players,
because it will get interrupted.
You have to keep in mind when you're talking about these, you know,
1% of skilled players,
anything whose cost is easy to interrupt is going to be interrupted.
And anything whose cost is hard to pull off, they will pull off.
It's not just feats of dexterity, though.
Skilled players understand the higher-level strategies of the game as well.
They can pull from a lot of knowledge,
including knowing strengths and weaknesses of champions almost reflexively.
This is Garen.
He is very powerful at the lower tiers of League of Legends
and not so successful at the higher tiers.
He likes to hide in bushes and spin around in circles,
which players call spin to win.
It's very effective if you don't know how to get out of it.
At higher level, you can crowd control him
and it kind of shuts him down.
We'll talk a little more about Garen in a minute.
So, going way back to my roots at the Age of Empires,
this is one of the first balanced nemesis I ever faced.
Two of the most powerful traits you can give
a unit character champion are long range and fast movement.
And the two together is amazing.
Cavalry archers were the bane of my existence
on Age of Empires.
There's a reason the Mongols were so effective with them.
You run up, you shoot, you run away.
They're experts at kiting.
It makes it very difficult for other units
or other players to be able to catch up with them.
This extends to League of Legends. We have champions like Vayne and Lucian who are highly mobile yet ranged.
And skilled players who are great at micromanagement are going to be able to do a lot of damage with never having to take damage themselves.
Now this is an interesting one. Most league players experience the game solo.
We have matchmaking. We'll find you a team and we'll find you an enemy team.
But organized play is a very different experience.
And of course anything professional is organized play.
These guys play together all the time. They have plays.
They can almost read each other's minds.
You think of like a buddy cop movie where the two cops enter a building
and they immediately know to cover each other's blind spots.
Lowelow, on the other hand, because they don't have the guarantee that someone's going to help defend them,
tend to gravitate more towards generalists.
This cute critter here is Kog'Maw. He's a classic glass cannon.
He can do a ton of damage at range, but if you get up in his face, he crumbles very quickly.
And as you might imagine, it's difficult for players in solo queue to be able to effectively utilize him
because they just don't know that their team's going to be there backing them up.
Highly skilled players are really good at manipulating your economy,
and getting an economic advantage in any game can often be really powerful.
In League of Legends, we see this as gold funneling.
So basically, in League, you kill things, you get gold,
use the gold to buy more items to get powerful.
And the idea is that everyone kind of rises in power as the game goes on,
and more skilled players rise a little faster.
But skilled players, we see this definitely with pros,
can kind of have a lot of the team avoid getting gold
to make sure that one player gets a lot of gold early.
So they have this really powerful spike,
and even though it's only one player on the team,
they can leverage that to get an advantage.
In World of Warcraft, we would see this with the high-end guilds when they would raid,
would do things like, we're going to pass all the gear to the main tank or to, you know,
a really important DPS character.
And this got to the point of running alt raids, where a group would run a raid,
all the gear would go to one player while everyone else was on their alt,
they'd switch to the next player and so on and so on, using different raid instances.
It's hard to stop, it's hard to design around that,
but it makes balance very difficult for these high-end raiding guilds.
AI-dependent power.
We love to put turrets in our games.
So here is Heimerdinger from League of Legends, Torbjorn
from Overwatch, and the engineer from Team Fortress.
The problem with AI power, in this case the turrets, but it also could be like
your character has a pet.
AI power just doesn't scale really well with skill level.
If you think of the power as a pie chart,
the AI part of that power takes up a big part of that pie chart. It doesn't really
change depending on whether you're talking at lower or high skill level.
So as developers, we have to kind of choose where we're going to tune those turrets.
And if we tune them to be very, very powerful at high end,
they're just going to crush lower end players.
On the other hand, if you do what most of us do and make them
relatively reasonably fair at lower levels,
at high levels, they're just not going to see them get much play.
Strong windowed power. This is one of those cases where as developers we often
make the cost of like, yeah, we're going to give you a lot of power but it's going to last for a really, really short period of time.
The more skilled players won't waste that time. Even if it's a really small window, they can get a lot out of that.
This wormy looking monster here is Baron Nashor from League of Legends.
When your team kills him, you get a buff to sieging the enemy base,
which is a great way to shut down a game.
And at high end...
Baron absolutely decides whether a game is won or lost.
But lower skilled players can easily waste this buff.
They die, they don't get their group coordinated,
the buff eventually ticks away before they're able to leverage it.
In World of Warcraft, shamans have an ability called Bloodlust, which increases group haste for the entire group.
And skilled teams are really good at uniting all of their cooldowns to fire off at once.
Your trinkets, whatever your personal DPS or healing cooldowns are.
And I'm sure this still happens, the groups will all line up and pop their cooldowns at once for a gigantic power spike.
Particularly at the start of the fight when everyone's still at 100%.
Be really, really careful of your early game.
This is a great opportunity for skilled players to get an
advantage that later snowballs and makes them impossible to
stop later on.
This goes along with the cost of, but you might make a
mistake, because the more skilled the players are, the
less likely they are to make a mistake.
Their gameplay really can kind of approach perfection.
In regular play, someone has a chance to get back in.
But at high-skilled play, the game may be over as soon as
someone gets a slight advantage early on.
You see this in real-time strategy games, too, like Age
of Empires or StarCraft, where a small economic advantage
earlier just pays lots and lots of dividends
by the late game.
So I've talked most of it game design.
But let's not forget, we're mostly talking about software
running on hardware.
And there are limitations.
We recently did a study to look at play rates and win
rates of certain league champions according to
different ping rates.
And we found that.
We found that the, it's back.
A place like Korea, which has a really good internet,
actually allowed players to use different champions
and have different win rates than maybe somewhere
like the US where everyone's bouncing off
the same servers in Chicago.
You can mitigate this a little bit by doing things
like making sure there's a little bit of space,
like instead of giving players a fraction of a second
to execute a command, you can extend that to half a second
or something like that, which may help
overcome latency problems.
So this is a pretty nuanced issue I'll try to walk through.
Tactical errors at extreme peaks of skill
tend to be really rare, which means that who wins
can often come down to who makes a mistake first.
Like, two teams are playing perfectly, somebody misclicks,
and that is the entire game ending right there.
It can be really exciting as a viewer,
but you're kind of left with this hollow feeling
that it really wasn't the more skilled team that won,
it was just the person who didn't make a mistake.
So my lesson here is make sure that you have high-level strategies that high-level, high-skilled players can exploit, as well as tactical considerations.
By tactics, I'm talking about things like where you're positioning your character, when you're, you know, using your different abilities.
High-level strategy is more about, do we want to have a, you know, an early power advantage, do we want to try to sneak in their base, are we going to split lanes, things like that.
If you have higher-level strategy, the game won't just come down to misclicking.
So I highlighted some of the differences in trying to
balance for both highly skilled and
normal skilled players.
But now we're going to make that even more complicated by
layering on the effects of a mass audience.
Any competitive game, any PVP game, is going to have a skill
differential among players.
If you're a small indie developer and you have a small
player group, there's still going to be an enormous
disparity in their ability to play your game.
But League of Legends has about 100 million players.
So that skill differential can get really large.
Our bell curve has really long tails at both ends.
And on top of that, we make our lives extra hard.
He's saying the guy controlling the other five
units almost won.
Because in League, everyone plays by the same rules.
This is different from, say, basketball, where the point
lines will change depending whether you're at amateur
college or pro play, or a game like golf where there are
different tee boxes that different players will use.
This is important to us because there's a virtuous
cycle in League of people viewing the game and then
playing the game and wanting to view the game again.
And by viewing, this could be e-sports or streaming or any
games players are watching on the internet.
If you're an Asghar fan, chances are good that you're not out racing cars on the weekends.
I don't know, maybe some of you are.
But most people, that's kind of a sport they participate in as viewers, not necessarily as participants.
We think this is important because in League, players look to the pros to get better.
If I'm trying to learn jungling, I might look at, you know, what are the kind of items that Bengi picks.
He certainly knows what he's doing.
And there's also this aspiration of the path to pro.
Doesn't apply to me, because I'm old and my reflexes are shot.
But for younger players, they have this promise
that if they just get good enough at League of Legends,
they may make it to the big leagues
and someone may pick them up for their e-sports team.
As an aside though, I just want to offer a counterexample that
while messy, multiple rulesets do have some benefits.
We get into situations sometimes as developers where
the problems are really over-constrained.
Like, we can't buff this unit for the high end because it's
already too dominant, but players at the low end can't
necessarily use it.
I just want to throw that out there, that it's not
necessarily cut and dry, that one ruleset is the
only way to go.
So I'm going to spend the rest of the talk talking at a very
tactical level about how Riot balances League of Legends
with all of that in mind.
This is the secret sauce.
I'm going to try to be as frank as I can about what we do
behind the scenes, because that's why we all
come to GDC, right?
So first, we have a philosophy.
And I really encourage you to get your studio, your team,
your designers aligned on your goals and values.
Not just as a development studio, but on individual
projects as well.
If you have a shared philosophy, it really helps to
arbitrate the tough calls.
You aren't debating, are we OK with this, kind of in the
heat of the moment.
You already know what good looks like.
So then when you're missing that target, you can react.
It also provides precedence for the teams of tomorrow.
Game development tends to be a highly mobile career.
People will leave studios or leave teams
or move to different teams.
And I feel like we spend a lot of our time doing archaeology,
like trying to understand why did the developers who
worked on this game two years ago make this particular decision.
So if you have goals and values that you can particularly
publish someplace and make sure the whole company understands,
it can help to mitigate some of that.
So for example, these are the league design values.
I won't go through them all here,
but we do make sure that the changes we make
are aligned with these values.
The idea is that hopefully we're making the game better
over time rather than just doing this kind of
one step forward, two step back thing where,
oh, we made a change, oh, that was a bad change,
let's make another change, oh, that was another bad change.
I mean, don't get me wrong, that still happens for sure,
but the intent is that we're making progress.
And it's not just design values.
Riot has values.
League of Legends as a product has values.
There are values for particular, you know,
very small project.
It could be as narrow as,
hey, we really need to nerf Leona's late game.
And then, once you have that philosophy,
make sure you actually do stick with it.
We really like to work this way because it helps to mitigate against designers tinkering.
And by tinkering I mean someone's driving into work and they're like,
I had a crazy idea, let's do this and see what happens.
That could be fun as a designer, it's really pretty painful for players.
And it also solves the mythical, oh I had a bad game last night,
Leona beat me so I'm going to go in and make sure the team nerfs Leona.
Players think we work that way.
So instead we're trying to solve specific problems
like X is too strong in the laning phase
rather than, hey, something popped into my head
out of the blue.
Now as an aside, Riot as a company really likes to work this way overall because it helps to empower our teams.
It makes the growth of the company more scalable because instead of the same decision makers
kind of having to swan dive into every single discussion that's going on,
we can spend our time getting aligned on what the values are,
and then the teams can go off and make the decisions themselves without having to like,
reopen every discussion because we've already kind of agreed on what the high-level goals are.
But you won't always get it right.
One of my leads the other day said,
even the best design that you've really thought about
and beat up probably has about a 70% chance
of hitting your bullseye.
So having a risk mitigation plan
can help to avoid panic when that happens.
You need good KPIs and key performance indicators.
You need to understand what you're going for here.
If you're nerfing a champion in League,
do we want to see her drop rate go down by 2%?
Are we worried players aren't playing this champion
because they're too complicated?
They don't understand the synergies between their abilities.
When you have good KPIs, it helps that you can agree.
if you've missed your goals rather than debating, did we miss our goals or not.
You immediately evaluate, okay, we missed our goals, and then you can enact the plan.
For example, when you make a new champion, the champion designer might say,
her weakness is supposed to be that she's not very strong in early lane,
so if she ends up being a lane bully, nerf her Q, and that'll kind of skew her back towards the late game.
Now we do focus on a target. We aspire to balance for all players,
but being able to focus helps us avoid insanity.
And this is particularly relevant because we patch the game very frequently
and don't always have a lot of time in between patches.
We do look at outliers at all levels,
but I'll kind of walk you through the sweet spot for game balance.
So if you look at how many players the changes are impacting, imagine the bottom scale here is number of players in a particular tier.
There's a lot of bronze players, fewer silver players, only a few dozen pro players in the world.
And this other axis is sensitivity game changes.
So we change a champion's attack by five, a newer player isn't even going to notice that.
They're much better off just playing ten more games.
That will improve their win rate much more than anything that we're going to do in terms of balance.
And then you can see the sweet spot here where these two curves intersect
is right around high platinum, low diamond.
That's kind of an area that we think we're impacting a lot of players still
rather than the super rarefied air of the Challenger Master Pro tiers.
But we still do look for outliers at all levels.
If Garen or Master Yi is stomping Bronze, we'll take action there.
If there's a champion that's 100% pick-ban at the Pro level,
we'll try to take action there as well.
Now...
Players will assume that you should and do balance for high ELO only.
That's the important thing to a lot of players.
They don't necessarily understand why you're making changes that will help out less experienced players.
But this would remove a lot of the 130 champions from those players.
We do have to constantly reinforce the goals of balance to all within the community.
I'll watch prominent streamers discussing the state of balance in League
and they're always talking about, oh well now the pros are going to pick this or that,
what is Riot thinking here?
A lot of this stuff is publishing, and by publishing I mean
the messaging you're sending to your communities to make sure
they understand what your goals are and why you're making the wacky changes to the game that you're making.
Now interestingly, pro balance itself is largely about viewers.
We don't want to make life terrible for our pros, obviously,
but when we make a change, it's often with the idea of our viewers
having a fun time watching League of Legends.
We will make changes if, for example, the game gets a little stale
and viewers are saying, yeah, it's still fun to see the end game,
but I skipped the first 20 minutes because it's really boring.
That might lead us to make a change.
In this case, balance could be fine, but we just think that, you know.
the we're going to hurt our virtuous cycle of viewing and playing and viewing
if people start tuning out of e-sports.
I want to stress again, this stuff is hard.
You can't hand this to one guy at the end of the cycle as a part-time job.
Believe me, I was that guy in Age of Empires.
It doesn't work.
Certainly not with the expectations for players these days.
It really takes a dedicated team.
And I realize that may be challenging if you're a smaller
indie dev, in which case I would say you're just going to
have to leverage the feedback from your players a lot more.
It's going to be hard for you to get tuning right.
So if you ship your changes, listen to what players are
saying, and then react to that.
And I'll talk a little more about that in a second.
So.
The team structure for League of Legends, we have a dedicated live team.
These are the men and women who are largely responsible for patch-to-patch balance.
You can think of them like the first responders or the MASH unit.
Someone is bleeding on the curb, they have to get out there and fix them.
They deal with problems that can't wait for a holistic or systemic solution.
They got to get in there right now and fix things.
We patch every two weeks.
Since you all are game developers, you understand
that that doesn't mean they actually have two weeks to
make changes.
When you take into consideration things like
build stability and QA testing and localization, often they
have three days to decide something's amiss, make
changes, test those changes, make additional changes, and
then get it out there to players.
Our live team is backed up by a play test team of very
skilled players.
Many of these players are ex-pros.
The playtest team is critical for us to get early impressions and data.
You can think of it as being able to deploy your patch early or having a beta even before your beta.
I've been able to create a playtest team at all three
studios where I've worked, at Ensemble, Blizzard,
and now at Riot.
It can be a hard sell when you're trying to convince the
studio to hire.
In this case, we need over 10 players to be able to play a
10-player game.
But it's worth it when you consider that the designers in
QA who are probably in the trenches can't play the game
all day long.
They have to actually sit at the computer and make changes
as well.
So without someone playing the game constantly, you may only
get two or three games in during the day.
Again, I understand for a small studio or an indie dev,
this isn't going to be feasible.
And as a warning, high ELO players are going to suggest
high ELO changes.
You just have to keep that in mind when they're talking
about, hey, I thought of a way to fix this that's probably
going to fix it for them and not necessarily all the rest
of the skill tiers.
I talked about how we had a focus team, and we focus on a
target ELO, but we also have a focus target time.
Just as with our professional game, ranked play in league
follows a season.
The ranked season turns on, players progress, and then at
the end of the year it turns off.
And we know that systemic changes, or even things like a
new champion launch, we recently launched Camille.
Her win rate did not hit our targets.
We know these changes are going to compromise balance and disrupt the game for players.
This past preseason we made a massive change to the assassin characters in League of Legends.
This not only involved individual champions, but their items, their masteries.
We even changed the way stealth works, since stealth is really tied into assassin characters.
And again, we do this deliberately, make these kind of disruptive changes knowing that it's worth it,
but also knowing that balance will take a hit.
And during these times, players are going to say,
WTF, Riot? Why is your balance team asleep at the wheel?
When really, we've made life hard on the balance team by making all these other changes to the game.
So we try to constrain the most disruptive changes to pre-season and mid-season.
Messaging here is super important so the players understand what's going on and understand that,
hey guys, things will be a little crazy for a while, we're putting plants in the game,
we're trying a new pick-ban system, whatever.
We know that's going to come at a balanced cost,
and because we patch quickly, we're going to try to get things back to a stable place.
Now, I have a few slides here on using data.
We gather a lot of data, right?
It has a really powerful insights team,
and they help us to collect a lot of analytics
about the game, and then help us to interpret that as well.
I know I talk about win rate a lot.
That is an important stat for us.
We target a 50% win rate for champions at all skill tiers,
but it's not the only stat,
and it doesn't tell the entire story.
The story here is that most players do not think that
Yasuo is scary, funny, or cute.
But they do think he is a badass, powerful, unique, and
maybe beautiful in North America.
So here's an example of win rate.
But we're looking at win rate by skill level.
So on the left of each of these curves is the bronze
players, and at the right is kind of
challenger master tier.
You can see a character, a champion like Veigar, hovers at around a 50% win rate.
It does go down a little bit at high ELO, but overall, we're pretty happy with that. That's not too bad.
Whereas Twisted Fate here, if you are a bronze player, that's not a great champion choice for you.
You're probably going to lose a lot, while as you climb in ELO, his win rate's going to get pretty respectable borderline overpowered there at 55%.
Next to him is Garen, who I talked about before, and you can see, just like I promised, his
win rate goes down a lot as you get to the higher tiers of difficulty.
And I also have Aatrox here, and the asterisk is because he appears to fall off a cliff
and go down to a 40% win rate, which just wouldn't be acceptable.
But what's really going on here is the sample size is very, very low.
high tier players just don't even play him a lot.
So the data we're getting from that isn't awesome.
This is just an example of you have to really look at the
data, not just make assumptions.
Oh my god, his win rate is low.
We have to buff.
Similarly, here are
the number of games on a champion, irrespective of ELO.
You can see a character here like Aurelion Sol.
Your first game of Aurelion Sol, you may lose.
In fact, you may lose a lot of games with Aurelion Sol
before you really understand what's going on
with this champion.
The far right on this slide could be 40 or 50 games,
which is a pretty hefty commitment for a player.
On the other end of the spectrum
is a champion named Volibear.
After you've played Volibear two or three times,
you've probably seen about all that Volibear has to offer.
This is not the sign of a really well-designed champion,
and he's the kind that is up for an update at some point.
Now, Aurelion Sol is not awesome either.
That's a really steep skill curve.
We would rather the win rate not be so low at the low end.
This is why it's so important to interpret your data.
If you're playing against a Lee Sin, a popular jungle
champion, the player you're playing against may very well
have three times the number of games that you do on that
champion, because it takes that long to get good at Lee
Sin, so if he's showing up at all, you may be playing
someone who really knows what they're doing.
In this case, it's not that Lee Sin is overpowered.
It's just you're playing against a very experienced
player on that champion.
This is why you have to look at things like win rate based
on games played and win rate based on ELO to really
understand what's going on.
Here's another example.
Pro champion choice has an immediate effect
on the rest of the game.
Once we see a pro player pick a champion,
we know that Spike is immediately going
to show up around the world.
It's interesting. Part of it, I'm sure, is just, oh, the pros are really, really skilled players.
If they know that this champion's good, they're probably good.
I also think it's players kind of hate to be accused of not being up to date.
Sometimes I think players would prefer to be known for poor skill
than to be known that, you know, they were uninformed.
Everyone hates to be wrong about things.
So when you see particularly silver, bronze, silver, gold players pick up these pro choices,
it's going to be an ineffective choice for them,
because they're not going to be able to pull off the things that the pros can pull off.
This is, uh, Froggen is known for picking Anivia.
And speaking of Anivia, she's a great case study for why you
need to use your judgment to make calls.
We don't use machine learning to balance League of Legends.
We hire people that can use their own experience as game
designers and QA to help make these decisions.
Anivia often turns up red flags, where her win rate can
be as high as 55%.
Yet we think if we nerfed her, players would be like, why did
you nerf Anivia?
She's not a problem.
And when we reflect on that, we agree with them.
Like, she has reasonable strategic counterplay,
meaning that you can counterpick her in champion select.
And she has reasonable tactical counterplay,
meaning that when you're actually out on the map playing,
there are things you can do to avoid her spells.
So is she a balanced?
The data says yes, but our gut says no.
And this leads to another topic,
which is that we don't share our data publicly.
We didn't do this on World of Warcraft or Age of Empires either.
The reason is we were scared that we end up dictating choices to players.
If they see that a champion has a low win rate, they may just not play that champion.
And really, we'd rather players just play League of Legends and have fun,
and not obsess about becoming armchair statisticians.
On the other hand, as a developer, or as a player, it feels really flippant when the developer says,
well, that's not what our secret data says, and we're not going to show you our secret data.
Makes it very hard for a player to argue against it.
And it's possible that we could provide context. We could say, look,
yes, this item build looks good on paper,
but that's only with a really strong team coordination that you may not have in solo queue.
So I just want to present this as an ongoing discussion.
We're not changing our stance on this immediately, but we do
discuss it a lot internally.
And maybe it would be an interesting experiment.
So when you detect a balance problem, how do you know what
to change?
In the case of League of Legends, it could be the
champion, it could be the item, it could be the mastery.
This is the pregame system for League of Legends, similar to
Talents and WoW.
Is it the strategy players are using right now?
Is it the synergy with other champions on that team?
There's an example of Poppy, this cute little yordle
with the big hammer.
We recently updated Poppy. Objectively, it was a really good rework.
Super happy with the way that came out.
But her win rate did spike.
And it spiked at the same time that we changed one of our masteries.
This is Courage of the Colossus, the green guy here.
Courage of the Colossus gives you a shield when you crowd control a champion.
And Poppy has a lot of crowd control.
She's already pretty tanky. With Courage of the Colossus,
she would get this shield and become even more tanky.
It felt overpowered. We knew we needed to do something.
And we debated a lot. Was Poppy the problem or was Courage of Colossus the problem?
We definitely needed to nerf Courage of Colossus.
The question was, did we also need to nerf Poppy?
We went back and looked at the data in this case, and we saw that
her win rate had started to spike even before the Courage of Colossus changed.
So in this case, we did change both.
We nerfed both the Mastery and the Champion at the same time.
And if we hadn't done that, we would have had to, like, go in the next patch,
and she still wouldn't have been fixed.
I'm a big advocate of playtesting your own game.
Having a playtest team, having a lot of data from players,
is no excuse not to play the game yourself.
If you don't, you'll miss stuff.
You won't really understand the player experience.
Numbers just can't tell you the entire story.
And sometimes it's going to be really obvious.
You're like, oh, I understand the win rate of this champion.
It's because nobody can tell what's going on with their
spell visuals.
They don't know if they're standing in the fire or not.
On the other hand, I want to caution you not to go too far
here in the other direction.
it can be really easy to take your experience as a player
and assume that applies to all players.
And I definitely see this happen
when as a development team matures,
meaning we're all getting older,
it's easy for us to forget just how many games
and how engaged some players can be with our games.
So don't play one game and make a lot of balanced decisions
based on that one game.
This is in fact how we used to balance Age of Empires.
We would go play a game, make tuning changes,
go play another game, make tuning changes.
Just doesn't fly, I think, anymore.
I try to play League every day.
I don't always succeed.
I've been at GDC, not playing a lot of League right now.
But it does help to stay in touch with what players are
talking about.
This is the best slide in the deck.
I'll just give you a second here.
I think the best thing is that he's just kind of, assuming
it's a he, he's just kind of commenting.
He's like, oh, I just noticed this.
Kind of surprised me.
No judgment call there.
You do need to listen to players. We listen to our own forums, Reddit, Twitter,
rioters who tell us they noticed something wrong, pros, streamers.
I could give you an entire talk on leveraging player feedback.
This doesn't mean always do immediately what the players are asking for.
You'll often be really sad if you do that.
But, you know, ignore them at your peril.
They're giving you feedback. They want to see the game improved.
You do need a good solution for other regions, other languages.
And again, smaller studios may struggle more with this.
Riot is fortunate enough that we have regional offices in
all the countries where League is played.
And we rely a lot on those teams to tell us, hey, did you
know that players in Vietnam are talking about this problem
in the game that may not have filtered out
to other regions yet?
That helps us to kind of pay attention to what Vietnamese
players are saying, because I certainly
can't speak Vietnamese.
Like many companies, we also use beta tests for the changes we're going to put out.
Betas are really good for bugs, and they're really good for impressions.
So a player may say, wow, this is complicated,
or I'm not exactly sure how I'm supposed to be using that.
In general, sweeping statement here, but in general,
betas are not good for balance testing.
And the reason is because players understandably don't try that hard.
If they're going to devote 10 hours this week to your game,
they probably want to spend time in the actual game,
not on your beta realm, trying things out that may very well
never get shipped at the end of the day anyway.
So you end up with smaller populations, which means
matchmaking is not awesome, and so forth.
I will add that on World of Warcraft.
Testing the PvE game, meaning dungeons and raids, worked pretty well on beta,
and that's because the high-end raiding guilds would want to get a jumpstart on the content and practice.
So in this case, practicing did actually work out for them.
But the PvP balance feedback from World of Warcraft beta was about as not helpful
as the balance feedback from League of Legends betas.
I would also discourage you from trying things like,
oh, well, we'll bribe players to play our beta.
You may get a short-term spike in engagement,
but overall, you have to be really careful
to not motivate odd behavior
just because you want them to play a lot of games.
We also just ask players, we don't necessarily wait for them to come to us.
We do player labs, we bring players into the studio, have them play a game,
then ask them about their experience.
We do this a lot, say, for new champions or champion updates
or crazy changes that we'd like to make to the game.
We have a micro-survey tool that we leverage extensively.
Anyone who's played League of Legends very long
has probably gotten one of these surveys after a game
asking, hey, did you like this change?
What do you think about that?
It's really interesting to look at how the survey feedback
changes over time, how it changes in different regions
around the world.
This last preseason we added plants to the summoner's rift map that players can interact with.
There's somewhat of a random element to the way plants spawn,
and when players first heard about this they freaked out,
and they thought, oh we're adding too much RNG to League of Legends, it's going to ruin the game,
this is, you know, sky's falling.
And nowadays, our surveys are showing that most players are
pretty happy with the way plants ended up.
So I'm not saying players are dumb by any stretch.
I'm saying that we didn't necessarily set their
expectations for what the feature was going to be.
So now that you have goals, data, and player feedback,
this is the basic iteration cycle that we use.
Make changes, gather data, gather player feedback, make
more changes.
You may have to go through this cycle a few times.
Let's take Nidalee, for example.
Nidalee is a champion that can turn into a panther, which
makes her very fast.
She can also throw a spear.
So guess what?
Nidalee is our cavalry archer.
And just as with the cavalry archers, we have trouble
balancing her.
So we'll make a change, doesn't fix the problem, make
another change, doesn't fix the problem, and so on and so
on, spoiler, she still isn't right.
Sad Nidalee.
Sometimes problems can't be solved through tuning.
I mentioned before that the live team is like our first
responders.
They can get to the scene of an accident, but they can't
fix traffic patterns.
They're not empowered to rewire the stop lights to try
to create fewer accidents overall.
We do need sometimes to go through and make more systemic
changes.
We do this a lot through champion updates.
Ryze is kind of infamous here for a champion that we just can't get right.
We'll make a change, we'll put him out. He still is too powerful at high ELO.
Too weak at low ELO, we'll make another change.
And this goes on over and over.
As a last resort, you can basement champions.
We hate to do this because it feels like it's violating a lot of the player trust
about being able to play the champions they want to play.
But it's also not fair to players to give them a champion
that is just going to ruin the experience for everyone.
Azir is a very, very challenging champion for us to balance.
It probably stems from the fact that he can do so many
different things.
He doesn't really have weaknesses that you can
exploit.
If we tried to tune him, given his current set of
abilities, his win rate may be 60% at pro and 30% at bronze,
which I'm probably exaggerating there.
But he's definitely a hard to balance champion.
He probably just needs an update and needs to lose some
of what he can do.
So winding down here a little bit.
I've talked a ton about balance, but I want to stress
that balance isn't everything.
And as a systems designer, you can definitely fall into the
trap of looking at everything through the lens of balance.
Champions can be balanced, meaning their win rate could
be perfect, but still really frustrating.
And here are three examples, Riven, LeBlanc, and Yasuo.
Yasuo's win rate may be totally fair, and enough
players may think he's bullshit that they stop
playing the game, which is not.
As a developer, you don't want to say, but he's balanced.
Likewise, remember that players pick champions for a lot of different reasons.
I mentioned the pro example with Froggen's Anivia earlier.
This is Jinx. She's a very popular champion to play.
Her abilities are cool, her thematic,
you know, she's kind of an anarchist riot girl, really resonates with players.
We know that Jinx is always going to be popular.
It's not necessarily because she's...
unbalanced, and in fact right now she's a little weak of anything.
If you look at her play rate and conclude, oh, people are playing her too much, we should nerf her,
you're just going to make players sad.
Being on a balanced team is hard.
The balanced team is going to hear a lot about how terrible they are.
Is LoL going to suffer the same fate as WoW because of Ghostcrawler?
Burnout is really frequent.
You're giving this team one tool to solve every problem.
It's like, here's a wrench.
No matter what happens, you have a wrench to solve it.
Players and even co-workers are going to focus a lot more
on failure than success.
And there's never a break.
As I said, we patch every two weeks.
So as soon as the team is like, OK, we've made some changes
for patch 7.5, now let's start patch 7.6.
There's never really an off cycle.
Some of the solutions we use are to offer side projects for
folks on the team.
So not everything is can I buffer nerf 5 attack damage
here.
We also try to rotate folks off the team.
That's good for their sanity.
It also helps to add some of the knowledge they've learned
about balance to other teams as well.
And finally, tell them they're doing good.
They're going to hear a lot about how much
they're screwing up.
So it's great to reinforce with these guys how important
their job is.
Because they're honestly not going to hear it often from
players, even when they legitimately are doing well.
So in conclusion, balance matters for longevity
and engagement.
I would encourage you to understand why certain factors
affect balance at different skill levels.
I would encourage you to have a philosophy.
Don't just make changes based on data, but making changes
against checking against your goals.
And iterate, iterate, iterate, and follow through when you
don't get something right.
You're going to screw up a lot.
I screw up a lot, Wright screws up a lot.
Follow up when it does.
Having a good relationship with your community will help.
We work really hard on this because players will give us
the benefit of the doubt when we do make a mistake.
They won't doubt our intentions,
they'll just doubt our competence a little bit.
Good luck, and with that,
I'd be happy to take any questions.
Thank you.
Hey. So when nerfing things, how do you mitigate the kind of
feel bad effects of loss aversion? Do you actually take
that into account in making your design decisions or is that
mostly a PR community management thing?
I mean, it is a community management thing,
but we involve the people making the changes as well.
I think that's a very real concern.
And I think as developers, we don't always
pay enough attention to it.
It's really easy to focus, again,
on let's make that 50% number show up for every champion
and to forget how it's going to feel for players.
One thing to avoid is the Nidalee example, where you make
a change, you don't quite hit it right, so the next patch,
there's another nerf, the next patch, there's another nerf.
That starts to feel really bad for players.
They know every time they're going to open up patch notes,
they're going to see a nerf.
I'd encourage you in those cases to make sure you get it
right, if you've tried a few times, or let it ride for a
little bit, kind of let them recover.
We also work really hard on our patch notes
to provide context.
Like, look, it's not that we hate Nidalee, it's that we're
trying to solve this particular problem.
I also think Riot, like many studios, is a little too quick
to nerf and a little slow to buff.
I mean, nerfing is much easier than buffing.
But when you offset that a little bit, it's not as
negative experience overall.
It's a great question.
Hi, you mentioned...
Sorry, I'm stealing the microphone. Thanks.
You mentioned basementing?
Yes.
What does that mean? Can you explain that?
That means you...
Your champion is such a problem in the game
that the only thing to do is just nerf the crap out of them
so the players aren't going to play them.
Players who love that champion will play them, will probably still show up in lower tiers.
It's a really shitty thing to do, particularly for players who love that champion.
But you also, it's hard to justify having that character in the game ruining the experience for everyone else,
just so the players that love that champion can do it.
Quick follow-up, how do you handle messaging around that?
Is there a strategy there, or do you just do it quietly and hope people keep quiet?
My general policy is to be as honest with players as you can.
They're smart.
They're going to figure it out.
They're not going to buy your bullshit excuse.
So in those cases, I would say, look, we screwed up.
We can't make this character or unit or whatever game
you're working on.
We can't make this healthy right now.
We're going to temporarily kind of park them, and we are
going to get back to it.
You do need to follow up.
You just can't leave them in that state forever.
We did that once with a champion named Olaf, and
players still call it Olafing is the verb.
Thanks.
Hi, great talk. I have a question about the amount of champions you have and as the meta progresses
Some of them will will be underrepresented
So when you're doing updates like buffs and nerves, do you usually look at the underrepresented?
Champions and buff them so they could be more relevant
We look at champions who have a lower win rate and try to buff them to stay relevant,
assuming that we can do so in a healthy way.
Galio is a champion we're working on right now.
His abilities just aren't that exciting.
Volibear is another example.
So we'd be hesitant to buff them excessively.
We don't buff champions just based on low play rate.
We have champions like Urgot.
He's a creepy dude.
We don't necessarily want to see Urgot as popular as Jinx.
That's part of why players like to play him, is he's a little
weird.
So in that case, we're fine, as long as there are players out
there that love that champion.
All right.
Thank you.
You talked a lot about how higher play rate on champions.
So for example, if a player plays a champion a lot,
their skill will increase with that champion.
So if you take this and you add it to the fact
that there's 130 champions and only six bands
for ranked online, it seems as if you're
encouraging one tricks.
Is that intentional or is that kind of a side effect of?
It's a side effect and I hate it and I think it's one of the biggest design challenges
you have to fix in League of Legends overall.
If you ask a skilled player, how do I get better at ranked, they'll tell you, be a one
trick pony.
Find one champion, play the hell out of that champion, know everything there is to know
about that champion.
And that is effective, and you will increase your win rate
and probably the tier you play in.
Unfortunately, it leaves a huge variety of the game
unavailable to you.
We try to offer all these champions
for a lot of diversity.
In fact, we know that people who play more champions tend
to stick with the game longer and say that
they're having more fun.
You can imagine burnout is probably higher when you've
played 300 games with Vi.
You can imagine that when Vi gets nerfed, you may just
churn out of the game rather than switching
to another champion.
So I don't have good solutions to that.
It keeps me up at night for sure.
Thank you.
So I had a question revolving around champion tiering, which is just this sort of construct that other players have constructed to say these champions are tier 1, these champions are tier 2, which basically represents like pick these first and these guys are niche and these guys are useless.
Do you embrace champion tiering and say we're building this guy to be tier 1 and this other guy is some really niche...
counter and that's okay and he's not going to be high pick.
I guess it revolves around are you striving for even pick rates or do you sort of embrace
the tiers? No we don't strive for even pick rates.
There are champions that are really good at particular things.
Shen is a good split pusher. If you don't enjoy split pushing or
that strategy currently isn't super powerful in the game
he may not be a great pick.
We want that a player who loves a champion to have
opportunities to play them.
It feels terrible if you love this champion, you've invested
a lot in them, maybe you've spent a lot of money on skins
for this champion, and now you feel like you just can't play
them, that's a really terrible experience.
And then I had a request from another gentleman to go back
to the conclusions page.
I think he wanted to take some notes.
There we go.
Hey, how's it going?
Hey.
You talked about not only having a philosophy,
but following it.
I'm wondering if you can give some example actions
of what you've done to incorporate your philosophy
into your team, so it's actually part of the culture.
We talk a lot about it, for starters.
I make sure that we reinforce with the team.
We give teams a lot of autonomy at Riot.
And so then when someone makes a mistake, we'll retro it.
We'll talk about it.
Like, did we make this change to this champion
because we really thought players would embrace it?
Or did we make this change to the champion
because you thought it was fun as a designer?
I mean, sometimes good things come out of that.
But again, I feel like it's not super fair to players
to just use them as our playground like that.
We retro things, we talk about what went wrong,
we try not to beat up our teams too much for mistakes,
unless there's kind of a repeated pattern
of making the same mistakes and not learning from that.
So is it really on the onus of the leadership team to make sure they're hitting those talking points then?
Yeah, absolutely. I describe my job a lot. I do not balance League of Legends. You wouldn't want me to. It would be a travesty.
What I do is I talk more about creating an ecosystem in which good design decisions get made.
So I try to make sure people are thinking about things in frameworks.
And then, frankly, we just hire good people and smart designers and try to make sure they're aligned with our high-level values
and then turn them loose and get out of their way.
Thank you.
First, thank you for your inspiring presentation.
I'd like to ask about the balancing of champions
in several stages.
Like, for example, you nerf one of them,
you see that it's not enough,
or it's over the edge,
and the next iteration you buff it a lot.
So which way do you prefer?
Do you take one champion,
apply some changes,
and then let it sit for a while?
and come to it later, a lot later probably,
or do you try to iterate in successful patches
until he's perfect?
It really depends on the situation.
As I mentioned a little bit ago,
I caution you not to like,
nerf the same character over and over again.
I mean this happened on World of Warcraft as well,
where we couldn't quite solve a problem,
and so patch after patch there's another,
you know, feral druid nerf or whatever.
Nerfing tends to be easier than buffing, particularly when
you're looking at a situation where we have 10 champions that
are OK and one outlier.
And players are always like, well, why don't you buff the
other nine to be equal to that win rate?
That's just a lot harder to do.
If you keep missing the mark, you need to step back
and understand why are you missing the mark.
Is your data collection flawed?
Are you just changing the wrong thing?
Are players adjusting as quickly as you can?
Sometimes it does help just to step back and see what happens.
It can take the community a while
to develop a counter strategy to a dominant strategy.
We do try to, you know, we describe our relationship to League's balance as curation.
Like Riot doesn't kind of let it out in the wild and then whatever happens, happens.
We do try to step in when players are experiencing too much pain.
Thank you.
Hi. I wanted to get some more of your thoughts on the...
the relationship between viewership and changes.
Like one contrast to traditional sports like soccer,
there's no balance changes to the game.
It hardly ever evolves.
But on the eSports side,
every time you're making a change, balancing,
I know you mentioned that you do keep
viewership into account,
but how much relationship is there?
Is there a risk of them getting out of touch with the game
and then not understanding what they're watching?
Yeah, absolutely. We do, you know, we have to take that into consideration when we make changes.
We know that the changes we make are going to affect the pros.
One of the things we try to do is, you know, keep them in the loop.
Like, as part of the discussion, like,
hey guys, just want to let you know, we're thinking about making this change,
you know, what's your reaction?
We don't let them balance the game for us, but we do want to get their feedback,
because they're very in touch with that.
We also know that making systemic changes, like for example,
not that long ago we changed the dragon in League of Legends
to actually be five different dragons that kind of spawn at random.
We rely a lot on our casters and analysts to help explain this to viewers.
We have Riot is Blessed's very exceptional talent there,
and they can kind of help bring players along on that journey
to understand what's going on.
It's a very complicated game.
Thank you.
Hello, I wanted to ask about if an AI controlled champion
being good in high ELO and low ELO,
like how would you balance that out
if it's very popular on the low ELO?
It's challenging.
We have a champion named Ivern, who's like a happy tree guy,
who has an AI, a boulder creature named Daisy.
And he's been pretty popular, pretty high win rate recently,
despite the AI.
I think that's because not that much of his power budget
is tied up in the AI.
He can do a lot of cool things in addition to that.
So if you want to have a champion that uses a lot,
a character in your game that uses a lot of turrets or AI,
I would say just make sure that the power budget is
pretty small there.
OK.
I think we have about three minutes left.
If we run out of time, I'm going to go over
to the wrap-up room, which is right by the escalators
to the left.
Different countries have different preferences in aesthetic choices and champions they might choose.
How does that play into how you decide, because different countries have different playstyle choices as well?
Yeah, absolutely.
Overall we've found that players are players, and
if a champion is cool in one region, it tends to be popular in other regions as well.
There are definitely regional differences.
Chinese players love big guys with swords. We probably couldn't make enough big guys with swords.
A character like Jinx, who's like this anarchist rebel, that archetype just doesn't resonate as
much historically in their culture as it does, say, in the West. And that's fine. We know
there's going to be regional differences. Some places are going to embrace a champion more than
others. We try to offer diversity there. We do have 130, so hopefully there will be something
for everyone.
But do you actually make any choices saying,
this country may like this aesthetic,
and we want them to maybe try different play styles.
So we're going to actually give them this aesthetic
with a varying play style.
One strategy we use that can help there
are the champion skins, which change the look and sometimes
the voice of a champion quite a bit.
So we can introduce a champion or a line of skins
that
you know, has to do with a holiday or historical event in some country,
knowing that they may not have widespread appeal,
but those players are going to love it.
Cheers.
How do you feel about players and fan sites gathering and sharing data
in order to help each other to play the game?
That's a really good question.
I mean, overall, I don't begrudge them from doing that.
It totally makes sense why players
want that information, particularly given
that we don't provide it.
The challenge is that sometimes the data is wrong.
And in those cases, as developers,
we don't have the bandwidth to go debug it and explain
to players why it's wrong.
So we end up just kind of waving our hands and say, oh yeah,
that data is bad.
And then players are left scratching their heads.
This is why we're talking a lot about,
does it just make sense to offer the information out there?
For example, a lot of the fan sites that offer data on League
only look at high platinum, which is not going to tell you
the whole story because very few of us are high platinum.
Maybe we have time for one more question.
Are we good?
All right.
Thank you very much.