Good afternoon, everybody.
Welcome to my talk, Design in Detail.
First, I'd like to thank GDC.
And I'd especially like to thank them for putting me up
against the doom post-mortem.
I'm sure that our audiences don't overlap at all.
So please turn off your pagers.
And this is an advanced design talk.
I'm going to talk very fast.
We're going to cover a lot of stuff.
If you don't get it all, don't worry about it.
We're going to put the slides up.
And I'll stick around for questions
for a long time afterward.
And I'm just going to wait until somebody laughs
at the joke that's on the screen.
And then, thank you, Marty.
And then I'm going to go on.
So who am I?
I have 13 years of industry experience,
mostly as a game designer on all of the Halo games,
especially the first three, with just a little bit
on ODST and Reach.
I did.
The balancing of the campaign difficulty and also the multiplayer side, as well as the
tuning of all the weapons, characters, vehicles, and other gameplay elements.
My opinions do not represent those of Bungie management, which is probably why I don't
work there anymore.
So last year I gave a talk that was inspired by this painting.
It's the Sunday afternoon on La Grande Jatte.
And what's really interesting about this painting is the closer that you get to it, the more
detail comes out.
And so...
That inspired me to do a talk where
I took a really trivial detail from Halo,
examined it exhaustively, and tried
to explain the design process behind it
and draw universal conclusions from that.
It was a pretty popular talk, so the GDC guy said,
come back next year.
You can do any talk you want.
So this is going to be my talk about what
non-designers need to know.
No, I'm just kidding.
GDC wanted a sequel.
So I was looking around for inspiration,
and there's a great series, actually,
of paintings by Monet, where he paints haystacks, which is not
maybe the most inspiring object.
But what he does is he paints them
from several different angles, during different seasons,
different times of day, under different lighting.
And so his theme was to revisit the same subject matter
multiple times.
And so my idea was, I'll revisit the same design decision
over several different games.
Last year I spent a little bit too much time on the abstract.
I didn't get to the meat enough.
So I'm going to start right in with the detail.
And any time I get abstract, I'm going to have blue slides
so you can tune out if that's an issue to you.
So the muzzle velocity is the speed
that the projectile comes out of the gun of the plasma rifle,
which is sort of the alien SMG.
It comes out in bolts.
That's the name of the projectile.
Legendary difficulty, which is the hardest difficulty
in the game.
across the Halo franchise, and if you don't know what Halo is, I don't know why you're
here.
So isn't this the same talk as last year?
How much more can you say about a weapon projectile?
Well, the sniper rifle was primarily a multiplayer talk, whereas this is going to focus largely
on single player.
The sniper rifle is shot by the player, whereas the plasma rifle is predominantly shot at
the player.
I talked a lot about active flow, sort of cadence and rhythm and firing a weapon.
This is going to be much more about reactive flow, the environment's effect on the player.
The sniper rifle was primarily balanced for a competitive environment, whereas the plasma
rifle is tuned for a difficulty level.
Which brings me to the most, I think, important point.
The last year's talk was about balancing, and this year's talk is about tuning.
So what's the difference?
Well, balance is really fundamentally about longevity.
It's about being able to play the game indefinitely
without the developer having to change things or fix things.
And so what you do is you design an element in passes.
You try to keep the game in a state that
is continually playable.
And then you release it to the community,
and they remove all the stuff they don't like.
And what you have left is something
that at least some small set, if you're lucky,
is going to continue playing indefinitely.
And it has nothing to do with fun.
In fact, most of the time, once the community gets done
with the game, it isn't fun anymore.
On the other hand, tuning is all about fun.
It happens all at once.
And usually, if it happens for one player,
it's going to happen for most of your audience.
And it needs to happen before release,
or it's just never going to happen.
It's very wispy.
It's hard to nail down just what exactly is fun.
And that's one of the things I'm going to try to tackle,
the blue chunks.
And it has nothing to do with balance.
A lot of times.
precisely because something is unbalanced is the reason why it's fun.
So you know how looking back on Star Wars, you thought it was about Luke, and really
it's all about Darth Vader?
Looking back on Halo, we could have named it Plasma Rifle because really that's what
it's all about.
So before I start getting into Halo 1, I want you to imagine that you're standing on a stage,
much like I'm standing on a stage, and you're in a room full of people, and they're laughing
at you.
Now.
If you're doing stand-up comedy, that's great.
If you're doing nude modeling, not so good.
If you're doing a GDC talk, as long as it's only some laughter.
So really, context is what I'm trying to get at here.
It colors every experience that you're going to have.
And it's very individual.
It has to do with your personal history
and what skills and experience you have.
And it really determines what you're expecting,
what your standards are.
You'll find that for a single game,
they often share a context.
They have a shared background and expectations.
And it's completely outside of your control.
Perhaps you can choose your context
by choosing your audience.
But most likely, you're going to inherit an audience
that you're going to have to please.
So when we started Halo 1, we looked at our competition,
which was Warcraft 2, until we stopped being an RTS.
And then it was Quake 2, which has some really unique sort
of.
visible projectile weapons, and some really common guards,
and just a ludicrously fast space marine.
We played a lot of tribes, which has similar kind of weapons,
and also this jetpacking, ludicrously fast space soldier.
Unreal, even more unique weapons,
and a really fast space soldier.
And then we looked at even our own game, where we had the four
which shot this slow projectile.
He was a really fast security officer.
So another aspect of context that you need to look at
is the community that's formed by your audience.
For us, it was going to be Myth fans,
but we weren't really sure they were
going to be action gamers.
Are they going to be into Halo?
There were Mac gamers who, at the time,
were feeling a little betrayed because we were going
to be on Microsoft's console.
And there were Marathon fans, but Marathon fans
totally embraced the mouse.
And were they going to be able to switch over
to be with a controller?
On the other hand, we had this new Xbox community,
which we didn't really know a ton about.
We thought it was gonna be younger,
so maybe less sophisticated.
And they were gonna have to deal with controllers,
so how was that gonna hurt their input?
So we decided we're gonna try to bring
both of these audiences in.
But it turns out the most important context
for the plasma rifle is the in-game context.
So in the story, the plasma rifle is used
by the Covenant Elites,
which is sort of the backbone of the Alien Menace.
It's their assault rifle.
And technically we couldn't push a lot of enemies on screen.
So each of these guys had to be pretty powerful.
So we needed a kind of a potent weapon.
In multiplayer, we really wanted to use every single player
weapon in multiplayer, not just because then you'd
be playing the same game in both arenas,
but because we didn't really have that many weapons in Halo 1.
But we didn't really have a clear idea
of what the multiplayer role was going to be for the plasma
rifle.
Now in single player, there's two things that are important.
One, it's the most common scavenged weapon.
So in Halo, you're always picking up weapons
off the ground.
And since a lot of the enemies use it,
you end up using this weapon yourself quite often.
And also, it's the most common enemy projectile coming at you.
Which means for difficulty, since it's
the most common enemy projectile,
it's a very large factor.
As goes the plasma rifle, there goes the rest of the game.
And actually, when it comes to the franchise,
it's the most common enemy projectile.
And it's sort of astounding how.
an entire series can be defined by one element,
but if it's gonna be one element,
it's gonna be that thing
that you're constantly getting shot at.
So of course, if you know anything about me,
you know I'm really into paper designs,
and so I'm not gonna show you the paper design
for the Halo 1 Plasm Rifle because it was terrible,
but here are some choice quotes.
It misfires in the rain and does AOE damage underwater.
We didn't have rain and we didn't have water,
and that was the first line,
like that was the most important thing.
The primary trigger is an instantaneous visible beam, which is not how it ended up at all,
because it's not fun to get shot at something that travels instantaneously.
You're supposed to hold the second trigger to charge the overcharge, except for Halo
doesn't have a second trigger, so I don't know where that came from.
It's more effective than other weapons against energy shields.
You know, we got some of that in there.
And it also disables mirror fields
faster than any other weapon except for the disruptor.
And there's no mirror fields in Halo.
And I don't know what a disruptor is.
So clearly, we had a very vague understanding
of what this weapon was supposed to be.
OK, blue slides.
Here we go.
What is a fun activity that you're
going to be able to engage with this weapon in?
So first of all, and these are going
to be the three R's of fun, it needs to be reactive.
It needs to be a repeatable activity.
And it needs to be reliable.
So what do I mean by any of that?
Nobody can have fun for you.
So fun requires that the player participate.
And if you're going to participate in something,
it needs to be interactive.
So that means that in order to be fun,
something has to be reactive.
It needs to be repeatable.
I'm sort of known for saying that Halo
has 30 seconds of fun, which we repeat over and over.
But I could have said that Halo is fun for 30 seconds.
And then something better changed,
because you have to play that 30 seconds exactly over again.
It's not going to be very much fun.
And so what this activity needs to do is resist habituation.
What is habituation, you may ask?
So I just got back from the Caribbean.
And being from Seattle, when we first got there,
the sun felt very, very hot.
And after a little while, it stopped feeling so hot.
I didn't notice it anymore until I got a horrible sunburn.
And what was happening there was I
My nerves and my skin were getting habituated to the sensation of the sun.
And habituation is the reduction in sensitivity when something happens over and over and over again.
Now you might think this is bad as in the case of a sunburn,
but it's actually extremely important as I found out later when my sunburn started to heal
and it itched madly and I couldn't sleep and I couldn't have a conversation
and I couldn't even really think straight because I couldn't do anything but feel my skin.
And if you didn't have habituation, you would feel like that all the time.
Habituation is also a really crucial learning tool.
So when you see something in a game over and over and over,
you get habituated to it.
You stop noticing it, and you start
noticing the differences between the experiences that
allow you to analyze them and come up
with different strategies.
But it's also the designer's mortal enemy.
Habituation makes you bored.
So what you should be going for in a fun experience
is predictable enough that you can habituate to it somewhat
and learn it, but not so predictable, not
so habituatable.
that you get bored.
And finally, it needs to be reliable.
It needs to be fun every time for as many people as possible,
ideally.
And it turns out these kind of reliable activities
are extraordinarily rare.
And you probably participated in most of them
by the time you were five or six.
What do I mean by that?
You didn't throw a grenade before you were six,
hopefully, unless you're breaking the ESRB.
So grenades are.
staple of Halo gameplay. But really, when you look at the experience of throwing a grenade,
it's really close to Peggle, which finds its roots in games like Arkanoid. I mean, how
many of you are itching for that ball to go right up that crack and then bounce off the
ground? If you don't know what Arkanoid is, maybe Angry Birds is a better reference for
throwing grenades. Which goes back to, like, in physical activities, like pool, you know,
what angle do I have to hit the bumper at in order for, to make the pocket?
Which, even, you know, even when you were a little child,
throwing stuff in a waste paper basket.
It's all that same kind of fundamental activity
that you could just do forever.
So maybe you're not convinced.
What about melee?
It's another Halo staple.
Really important part of the game.
Never gets old.
Just like it never got old in Final Fight.
Just like it convinced you to hit all those stupid Flash banner ads.
I couldn't, I couldn't find the Punch-a-Monkey.
There is no actual copy of that on the internet anymore.
Which, when you think about it, is really just a callback
to Whack-A-Mole.
And Whack-A-Mole is just a machine playing sort
of a violent version of peekaboo.
This is my son, and he's super cute.
So I wanted to use him in my presentation.
How about the Warthog?
The Warthog, way slidier than any actual vehicle,
just like in Mario Kart.
which is very similar to skiing, which is just like sliding around in your socks.
Or in her socks, preferably.
So why are these things fun?
There's a book called The Brain That Changes Itself, and it talks about people who have
suffered mostly brain injuries or birth defects that use practice and rote skills to sort
of regenerate their brain tissue.
And it says that a trained or stimulated neuron develops 25% more branches, increases its size,
and it gets a lot more blood supply going through it.
And so my theory is that just like physical exercise is fun just for the sake of exercise,
mental exercise is fun in the same way.
So if you look at dodging, which is something that you did when you were a child,
there's lots and lots of things that you're doing.
You are...
You're detecting movement in your peripheral vision,
and you are tracking objects as they move across the space,
which translates really well into 2D in a game like Commando,
for instance.
But it's even better in 3D, where
you're trying to take the non-linear change in size
of a projectile as it comes toward you and determine
when it's going to intersect with you
and predict its trajectory, or determine the closest point
that it's going to reach so you know exactly
how far you have to dodge.
So.
Just a quick tangent, the conventional wisdom is that 3D sucks.
And maybe the technology isn't there yet, but eventually games are going to be in 3D
and they're going to be way more fun because they're going to tap more directly into those
brain circuits.
OK.
Games, other than Halo, are fun for this reason.
So your brain is really good at pattern matching and actually has, like, physical hardware
for that.
So that explains things like Tetris.
Predicting complex systems with an almost intuition level
is common.
You have special circuits for determining a rate of change,
and especially comparing one rate of change to another.
So if you've ever tried to see if your healer's mana was
going to last longer than a boss's life in WoW,
that's what you're doing.
Path planning is pretty obvious in a game like Pac-Man,
but it's also when you're trying to complete three or four
quests in an area, you're trying to do it most efficiently.
Your plasticity is sort of how you make new connections
that you never had before.
I think Portal probably stretched everybody's brains
a little bit.
And finally, another thing that you're hardwired for
is to have a theory of mind to try
to get inside somebody else's head, which
is very useful in something like Street Fighter
or even a slow game like chess.
So back to reality.
OK.
So we need something that's reactive, repeatable,
reliable, that exercises your dodging circuits.
And so we rewrote the plasma rifle paper design
to say it's a high rate of fire gun that
shoots plasma bullets that travel
at a fast but dodgeable speed.
So that mechanic works itself out in this way.
We don't want it to be too fast.
We want to give you enough time to dodge.
And also we want it to be slow enough
that it's a continuous motion, because we're actually just
throwing up 30 still frames a second.
If you can't connect those in your brain
into a single, believable, real object,
then you can't engage those dodging circuits.
And we gave it a really visible contrail,
which was especially useful in the PAL version,
actually, where it's harder to dodge because you're
getting fewer updates.
But we didn't want it to be too slow.
I mean, it's sort of comical if the bullets are just
hanging in air.
And we still want you to experience
all those near misses.
So that just brings me to a sort of a fundamental definition
of game mechanics, where you divide the potential gameplay
into two parts, actions that are permitted
and actions that aren't permitted.
So Mario cannot jump over the flag.
Mario cannot run left.
There are just things that Mario cannot do.
This is good, because it allows us to constrain the game.
But the problem is that one mechanic isn't a game.
It's not even really interactive.
If you only have one constraint, then you're
not making any choices.
I recently made my first Flash game, and it's Pac-Man in a line.
Basically there's no ghosts, there's no maze, you just eat all the dots, and it's boring.
So if we look at a Halo mechanic, let's say that there's a mechanic where your hand-held
weapon, it beats distant enemies, right?
And so if they are distant, then you win, if they're not distant, then you lose.
sort of a contemporary design theory is that, excuse me, that you should layer new mechanics
on top of this one. And if you layer off enough mechanics, then you're going to make a game.
And if your game isn't fun, then you should layer on more mechanics. But I really think
all that does is give you a larger number of choices that you aren't making. So what
I suggest is that you want to have
mechanics that support each other, sort of like a tripod.
They're leaning against each other.
And all the area inside is the gameplay.
And so a sandbox game has a huge area.
And maybe a more linear game has a much smaller area.
But at least there's lots of different possible places
that the player could be at any given time.
So that means that the projectile mechanics also
need to be supported by AI mechanics.
So they lead to your peers.
And we had them fight from the open
so that you could see them fighting from the open
and dodging.
And that would teach you to dodge.
We also made them shoot directly at the player,
because it's a lot easier to dodge something that's
coming straight at you, rather than
trying to figure out which direction you're
going to need to dodge.
We gave them a little bit of small error,
so it wasn't quite as predictable.
And they also shoot in bursts, so sort of like a fan pattern.
Doom, doom, doom, doom, doom.
They kind of swing it across.
But they don't track the player during a burst.
So if you start dodging a burst, you're
going to be able to dodge the rest of it.
The player mechanics also needed to support this.
So instead of having the blazingly fast super soldier,
we had an agonizingly slow super soldier,
mostly relying on the acceleration
of going left to right.
You have to anticipate what you're going to dodge.
You can't just immediately move out of the way
as if you were a Ferrari.
And we also had a narrow field of view,
which is not a common thing at the time.
PC games had the crazy fish eye.
views and the reason is it makes objects that are distant in the middle of the screen feel
like they're much closer and larger and that allows you to track projectiles a lot better
because instead of being really, really, really small and then all of a sudden being huge
and in your face, they're actually increasing as they would in the real world via inverse
square law.
We gave the player shields which recharge after a short time.
So that means if you're dodging and you get a couple shots, it's not that risky.
And so we actually increased the amount of damage that a plasma rifle will do against
shields.
But at the same time we gave you body health that doesn't recharge, so we wanted to preserve
your life by making you do a little bit less damage to body.
When it comes to difficulty in Halo 1, it's pretty straightforward.
We had these red elites and they were like tougher versions of the blue elites.
They shot more bursts, they shot longer bursts, so they're a little bit harder.
And we had a global weapon damage scale, so on Legendary.
everything did about twice as much damage to the player.
So mechanics are universal.
If the game designer writes down plasma rifle bolts are dodgeable, then they are in abstract
mechanic land, but they need to be calibrated to make them personal and effective in the
real world.
These are the actual numbers that create the experience that the mechanic is describing
and make the plasma rifle dodgeable for a certain player.
So in Halo, it was calibrated for me.
Actually, I've said that before.
Actually, it's not precisely true.
So ask yourself, and hopefully you're not already asking this of yourself, why did you
come to this talk today?
Confabulation!
The truth is that you can't recreate your subconscious mind in your conscious mind.
It's like trying to emulate an Xbox on an Atari 2600.
It just doesn't fit.
And so what you have is an internal model, which you use to guess at your own motivations.
Usually it's pretty accurate because you have a lot of experience with yourself.
But what you should do is also build one of these internal models for the player.
That way you can predict the player reactions and so when you're calibrating, you're calibrating
for this little internal guy that you believe is what is representative of every player.
So this is my job.
It's also the series of steps that led to the calibration of the plasma rifle.
The process for me usually goes like this.
I make my best guess, which in this case was 10,
because I had no idea.
10 is world units per second, which
is a unit of measurement that means absolutely nothing to you.
And then I would try the extremes.
So I would try 20, and I'm like, wow,
that is almost instantaneous.
Or 1, and I have to wait for the bullets to get to me,
and sometimes I forget they're there and fall asleep,
and then they hit me.
Um, so then I narrowed in on the value, so I tried five, and that was better, but it
was still way too easy to dodge, so I moved to 15, which, oh, that is too fast, and then
I moved to 13, which is totally dodgeable, until I tried to pay attention to something
else and shoot back, and then I'm getting hit again, so I turned it to 11, which felt
really good, and then after a while it kind of felt too good, so then I bumped it up to 12.
Twelve.
So the, uh, experience.
that your calibration gives you is something that you need to test and use your research,
obviously. For us, we found that players could dodge the plasma bolts and that felt really
good for them, but it had some unintended consequences in Halo 1. First, they were fighting
out in the open, so they saw more of the enemy behaviors, which is good, but they also died
without seeking cover because they wanted to only fight out from the open, which was
not so good. And then it was also extremely broken.
So basically, you can always dodge the plasma rifle
in Halo.
And this is why.
If you aim directly at the player as an AI,
and the player's moving, you're going to miss.
So you could solve that by trying to lead.
The problem is, if they zigzag at all,
you miss by even more.
If your projectile is dramatically slower
than the player, then this is not a solvable problem.
And basically, if you know that this is the case in Halo,
you can break the game pretty badly
on pretty much every difficulty level
and in every encounter.
So that's bad.
When it comes to multiplayer,
we had added movement stuns.
So when you get shot by the plasma rifle,
it makes it so you can't turn as fast
and you can't move as fast.
And that was to compensate for the fact
that it just wasn't, you know,
you couldn't use it at a good range
because it was traveling so slowly.
But an unintended consequence of that was that movement sound was really annoying.
It works okay in Counter-Strike when you're gonna get shot three times and then die, but
in our game when you could take a lot of hits, you would just have to sit there and take
a lot of hits, which conflicted with the Halo flavor quite a bit.
It was also horribly broken because you could use it on vehicles, which... whatever.
It was a short development cycle, what can I say?
Now when it comes to Legendary, this is kind of interesting because the Plasma Rifle, as
all weapons, did twice as much damage.
So that made Legendary very difficult.
Had some unintended consequences.
Basically the difficulty scale was stacking with the material scale I described earlier.
So against shields it was actually doing almost four times as much damage, which meant that
it was taking down your shields almost instantly.
The way this was badly broken.
was, so dodging was not actually any harder.
So on normal, you could dodge back and forth,
and every projectile would miss you.
And if a couple hit you, that was fine.
You just take cover.
In legendary, you could dodge back and forth
in the exact same way.
The same number of bolts would hit you, and they would kill you.
So we weren't actually making the game harder.
We were just making it more punishing.
But luckily, we got a chance to fix everything in Halo 2.
So again, we're looking at the competition.
Ghost Recon came about that time.
And it was different than an Unreal
and that had instant projectiles.
It was really encouraging you to fight from cover.
Rainbow Six came out and it also had instant projectiles
and fighting from cover.
And Counter-Strike, and S.W.A.T., and Medal of Honor,
and Minerva, and Call of Duty, and Kill Switch.
So basically we're seeing a trend here.
People want instant projectiles and fighting from cover.
We looked at our own community.
And the Halo 1 pistol is.
really unbalanced and really popular.
And we think that's probably because, hey,
it's an innocent projectile.
Legendary is also, like I described before,
completely unbalanced and very popular,
which means that people enjoy the fighting from cover,
even if it's excessively punishing.
So we talked earlier about how fun requires participation.
And what that means is that fun requires buy-in.
Basically, people will play the game that they want to play,
no matter what.
I did the Halo 1 tutorial, and before giving you a weapon in the original version of the
tutorial, I would throw you into combat, and the idea was, it would teach people to run
away.
What we tell people was, run up next to a guy and let them shoot you to death, because
you can't figure out how to kill them because you can't, because you don't have a weapon
yet.
People will, they go with their expectation over any kind of hint text or recommendation
that you can make.
Again, the most important context tended to be in the game.
The elites in Halo 2 were not the faceless enemy
that they were in Halo 1.
In fact, sometimes they were your allies.
And at some points in the game, you
were actually playing as an elite.
And so they needed an instant projectile weapon
in their arsenal.
Also, in single player, we decided
since dodging is not fixable, maybe we'll
emphasize fighting from cover a little bit more.
And in multiplayer.
Since movement sign is just not fitting with the game,
again, we want to have some sort of instant projectile
on the plasma rifle, or at least much faster projectile.
Which brings me to interlude number two.
So every Christmas, I ask my grandma for a subscription
to Edge Magazine.
And every Christmas, I get a subscription
to GamePro Magazine.
Thank you, grandma.
But lately, it's paid off because GamePro is actually
turning into a very good magazine.
And recently they had an article called The Psychology of Shooters.
And in it they describe a study done by a pair of researchers named Andrew Przebilski
and Scott Rigby where they modded Half-Life and they had one version where it was bloody
and horrible and guts and violence and one version where it was non-violent.
It was sort of like a game of tag.
And what they found was...
that both versions equally satisfy the basic needs that they were looking for, which were
competence and autonomy. And you can read this either in GamePro or on Jamie Madigan's
blog, psychologyofgames.com, which I heartily recommend.
So their eventual sort of conclusion was that shooters satisfy human needs, and because
both bloody shooter and tag shooter both satisfy competence and autonomy.
They're both equally fun.
But we all know that Tag of Duty would
not sell.
And I believe the reason is that our
needs are much more complex than simple competence or
autonomy.
And I figure out everything with graphs, so
let's make one.
Why is, is, let's see.
So dodging is a competence, right.
It's something you get good at.
Why is it way more fun to dodge on normal than it is on legendary,
when it kind of cheapens legendary if you can just dodge everything?
And covering is always a choice,
but why is it a more interesting choice on legendary when you really don't have any choice?
You have to go take cover.
And why is it more fun to dodge grunts and more fun to cover from elites?
And why is it more fun to dodge if you're playing aggressively,
and it's more fun to cover if you feel like you're wanting to play defensively?
And my answer is that competence in a shooter,
specifically dodging, is much more fun
when you're under low pressure.
And autonomy is much more fun when
you're trying to tackle a problem that's
much more difficult.
So when games satisfy these complex needs,
that's when they are really fun.
And this complexity comes from the context
that the needs are being satisfied in.
Now, we already found out we can't control the context,
because that's part of the audience.
So what we have to do is match our fun activity to the context
that those players are already experiencing.
So for instance, context can make an activity feel natural
when the activity flows out of the context.
Some great examples of this, Assassin's Creed.
There's no question in anybody's mind that this.
is intending for them to sneak, and it feels the world really, really ingrains in you that
you should be sneaking. I think the best example of the last year or so is Super Meat Boy.
That poor guy is designed to die over and over and over and over again.
But a context will also make an activity meaningful. I think this is what Clint Hocking was talking
about in his talk yesterday. I'm still processing it, so I'm not exactly sure. Rescuing the
princess for making it through a mission or becoming the Pokemon master.
So what we did back in reality,
where we split the plasma pistol and the plasma rifle bolts.
So the plasma pistol became the slow, dodgeable version,
the plasma rifle became the faster one that forced you to cover.
And then on different difficulty levels, we sped up the projectile.
So on normal, the plasma rifle's still dodgeable if you're far enough away,
but on legendary, it's never dodgeable.
And we changed the AI mechanics, again, split them.
So the grunt kind of fights like your kid brother,
like they shoot straight at you and they're really easy to confuse.
If you hide, they come and look directly.
Whereas the elites are a lot more cunning.
They lead the player.
And because they have a faster projectile, that's OK again.
They track during the burst so that you
have to consistently dodge the entire burst.
And also, they suppress you before they come search.
So what that means is if you take cover,
they'll shoot at the cover and shoot around
where they think you're going to be coming up.
And they'll do that for a good 15, 20 seconds.
before then coming up and very carefully,
from usually as far away as they can,
peeking around the cover to see if you're still there.
We had two protagonists in Halo 2.
There's the Chief, and we stopped displaying his health
because what we wanted to do was make it so that
as soon as your shields were down, you ran for cover.
And you ran for cover with this feeling of,
oh my goodness, this is really dangerous and scary.
But then we...
increased how fast the shield recharged,
so you didn't have to stay in cover for very long.
Because in Halo 1, you could just stand out of cover
and dodge back and forth until your shields came back
and you were shooting the whole time.
It's a little bit more boring to stand behind a rock,
so we wanted it to take less time.
We even moved the shield meter right
next to the motion tracker.
So you could be crouching behind cover,
looking at your shields and at the motion tracker
to see if somebody was coming around the cover after you.
For the Arbiter, we experimented with an invisibility,
where he could.
turn itself invisible for just long enough for his shields to almost start recharging,
with more or less success.
So I already mentioned that shots travel faster on Legendary, but we also changed how the
weapon damage scale works.
So first of all, it's per weapon now.
It's no longer global on Halo 2, which meant that the Plasma Pistol we could make do a
little bit more damage, but not really significantly, whereas the Plasma Rifle we could make do
a lot more damage, but totally going to drive you into cover.
Turns out this is a terrible way to balance difficulty, but I didn't know.
that at the time.
When we were calibrating, oh shoot, we didn't calibrate.
Sorry about that, Halo 2.
So almost at the end of the project,
our AI counts got cut dramatically.
We had to strip objects out like crazy.
And we had very little time to recalibrate any of the weapons.
So they ended up being about 15 world units per second.
So slightly faster than Halo 1, and then
a legendary much, much faster.
So the normal experience of the player playing in Halo 2
was that they can dodge grunts pretty easily
and at least force them to cover.
So far, so good.
Unfortunately, because we had to remove so much cover,
there wasn't enough.
And a lot of times you'd be fighting guys
that were supposed to drive you into cover,
and there was maybe one piece of cover
if we remembered to leave it in there.
And because we had introduced Havoc in Halo 2,
sometimes that cover would move.
So they would throw a grenade at you,
and your cover would go flying off the cliff,
and then you'd be completely exposed.
But that's not why it was totally broken.
Why it was totally broken was because of the suppressing fire
I talked about earlier.
The AI would over-focus to a ridiculous degree.
And I'll try to explain that.
So basically, the way to always get the advantage of Halo 2
is to take cover and then pop out at a different spot.
So if the AI is shooting at you, you go behind cover.
Then you pop out on the other side.
And then you get two or three seconds to shoot at them
before they shoot back.
And then they start shooting at you,
and you go back behind the cover,
and you pop out on the first side.
And it takes two or three seconds
for them to figure out this tactic,
and you can just do it over and over and over and over again.
And if you ever played Legendary,
you almost certainly figured this out,
because it's the only way to get through.
As far as multiplayer, the faster projectiles
that the plasma rifle had were great,
because they made the weapon useful at range,
and we removed entirely the idea
of movement sound from the game.
Unfortunately, there was a bug that meant
that if you were carrying an SMG,
which was everywhere in Halo 2.
And a plasma rifle, you were doing almost twice as much
damage as anybody else.
It was intended to reduce the amount of damage,
but that wasn't fixed until the patch.
And it was totally broken, because if you
put two plasma rifles together, you
could basically drop some of these shields almost
instantaneously.
And also, because the projectiles
were moving faster for the player,
the plasma pistol overcharge that we added,
that's where they got the term noob combo.
So.
On Legendary, the experience is actually harder.
It's not just more punishing.
It's actually more difficult to dodge.
Unfortunately, it is still more punishing,
and especially on Marines.
If you're playing Legendary on Halo 2,
your Marines lifespan is about 10 seconds.
And it was totally broken because we
had engagement distances that were very far, which
worked fine in Halo 1 because the AI would.
close on you until its kind of slow projectiles were effective.
But those projectiles were effective at a much farther distance.
In fact, they were effective at a range beyond what even the player's weapons were effective
at.
And so when you get something like a jetpack elite wielding two plasma rifles, which we've
already talked about is unbalanced in multiplayer, and then you add a 4X multiplayer on top of
that and they're jumping around and they have recharging energy shields, you get a game
that's really, really way too hard, especially my level.
But luckily, we got to try it again.
Our competition, as you can see, lots and lots of military games, and several of them
feature cover systems.
Now, our community at this point had been almost entirely single-player focused story
guys, but with
Halo 2 and Xbox Live, we started to get a much larger multiplayer community until they
were given about roughly equal weight in Halo 3.
And Halo became known for that kind of free-flowing combat that Halo 2 had got us, you know,
dodging and sidestepping and covering.
And so a cover system where you're sticking to cover just really didn't fit for us.
We decided against, we figured our audience was established enough that we could sort
of start ignoring the competition a little bit and going our own way.
But again, the, the in-game context was the most important.
There's no enemy elites in Halo 3.
They switch sides on the Covenant, and so sometimes context is not outside of developer
control, but it is outside of designer control.
And that means there's no enemy plasma rifles, because the Brutes use the Spiker, and the
Jackals use the Carbine, and Grunts use the Needler, and so nobody on the enemy side is
using the plasma rifle.
So does that mean my talk isn't over?
No, it means an interlude.
So pretty clearly, Halo 2 was a misstep.
How much of a misstep is up for interpretation.
But I spent a lot of time after Halo 2 ships.
I went on a soul-searching journey
to try to find out what should we have done?
What would have been fun?
I looked at lots of industry resources.
Raph Koster says that games are edutainment.
Will Wright says games are exploring a possibility space.
Far be it for me to disagree with Will Wright.
Sid Meier says games are a series of interesting choices.
But when I looked at all these descriptions
that designers were giving, they're
describing their own games.
Not really every game.
It's certainly not Halo.
So I looked into academia.
I hope there's not too many academics in here.
I may not make it out alive.
I just picked one of their definitions at random.
Games are an exercise of voluntary control systems.
in which there is an opposition between forces confined by a procedure and rules in order
to produce a disequilibrial outcome.
Yeah.
These guys aren't giving us a definition that is super useful.
What they're doing is dissecting games into their various components, which is good for
categorizing, not so good for building something that defies categories.
I'm a philosopher by background.
That's what my schooling is about, so I just kind of leave.
through some of my old philosophy texts, Aristotle,
talks a lot about catharsis and sort of how entertainment
is about bringing yourself back into balance.
That's interesting.
Pascal says that games are a distraction
from your imminent death.
Wittgenstein says that games cannot be defined,
which is not helpful, because then he says,
because you already know what they are.
And he's just trying to make a point about language.
And so that doesn't help me at all.
My final conclusion was that game designers should be philosophers.
I think it actually helps you sit outside yourself and understand what you're thinking.
But philosophers are not game designers.
Csikszentmihalyi, in his book, Flow, says that flow, or some people could translate
that into fun, is the immersion of the self in an activity.
And he talks about the autotelic experience.
And that basically means...
What you're doing is completely pouring into yourself,
and it has no purpose apart from yourself,
even if it's accomplishing some other goal.
Two other psychologists, Dessy and Ryan,
talk a lot about self-determination theory,
which is that human needs motivate people, which
includes players.
They focus a lot on intrinsic needs and extrinsic needs.
I think their research is great, and I
think Flo has a lot of great insights.
But I sort of have a different take on the categories,
which I will attempt to explain with a graph.
So if you try to find a couple of orthogonal ways
to classify needs, you'll find that some needs are need needs,
meaning if you don't have them, you feel rotten.
And some needs are want needs, where
if you get them, it's a positive emotion, but if you don't have them, you're not sitting
around miserable.
And I decided to call those requirements for the need needs and aspirations, for those
that are more positive but also optional.
Now, clearly games are not, you're not going to die if you're not playing a game, so games
probably provide aspirational needs of some kind.
I also sort of played off of flow.
and the idea of autotelic activities
to come up with two new concepts of endotelic and exotelic.
So telic is from telios, which means sort of like the goal
or the end.
Endo and exo meaning inner and outer.
So basically, you have things that you
do because you want a goal that comes from outside.
So that's like cake, right?
I want cake.
it's going to end up inside of me. And I don't really care how it's provided. I don't really
care if I made the cake, as long as it tastes good.
Whereas Exotelic is actually I'm being used for something. So a lot of causes and religions
are based on this. But much more humbly for games, it's just my skills are being used
to make something happen. Which is why games need to be interactive, so that you can participate
in them and cause something to happen.
So I would put games into this upper right quadrant.
And fun is the positive emotion that you get
from meeting those needs.
So if you think back to the graph,
fun is that quadrant of meeting an exotelic aspiration.
A game is a series of constraints
on an activity that reliably and repeatedly.
meet that exotelic aspiration for a specific audience.
And I'm pretty sure that I just said that games are about fulfilling your dreams,
so I'm going to go back to the red slide, sorry.
So what exactly is the exotelic aspiration that a plasma rifle is intended to fulfill?
Well, I think you have to describe these needs sort of
poetically, they're not necessarily something reduced to a technical term, so
the first one is I think they make the player feel like they're on another level.
They're making their enemies look dumb, and running rings around them is a good sort of
trope.
You want to manipulate your enemies and frighten them and play with them before you kill them.
I think the plasma rifle also fulfills the aspiration to be cool under fire.
You're facing danger, and it's real danger, but you approach it with like kind of a discipline
and you don't panic and you do things just the right way and you end up winning.
And also...
the plasma rifle is all about turning the tables.
So the enemy's trying to use the plasma rifle on you,
and you take it from them, and you
use it on them and their friends much more effectively
than they could.
Turns out, this is not just about the plasma rifle.
This is about every enemy weapon.
So even though Halo 3 doesn't really
feature the plasma rifle, the legacy of the plasma rifle
goes through to all the other enemy weapons in the game.
So for almost every weapon.
that the enemy uses in Halo 3.
It's slower for enemies.
Basically, they start out a little bit slow,
and then they accelerate, which gives you plenty of time
to see where it's coming and then dodge it.
They also have ramp up time, so the rate of fire
actually increases the longer you hold on the trigger.
But it's much faster for players.
So the player in Halo 3 always uses the speed
that the AI would have on Legendary,
and that includes multiplayer.
When you're firing a weapon, you don't, as a player,
care very much that it starts out slow,
as long as it gets to a quick speed very fast,
so you have the range that you need.
And players don't burst fire, at least not in the short bursts
that the AI does, so the ramp up isn't
as much of a factor for them.
This means that the player can always turn the tables
on the enemy by picking up their weapon
and using it against them.
The AI for grunts is comically incompetent.
They're always running away and panicking and putting
their arms up in the air.
We made sure that you could kill them with a single melee attack,
so you can kind of jump down amongst them like a cat
amongst mice and just start swinging.
But the elites, on the other hand, are dangerous,
but it's a manageable danger.
We added an idea in the AI of out-of-cover firing.
So when you first emerge from cover,
they're going to take a little while to start shooting at you.
They're going to shoot at you in shorter bursts
with longer durations between them.
But the longer you stay out of cover,
they're gonna start honing in on you,
they're gonna be more accurate,
they're gonna shoot more often,
they're gonna shoot with less time in between shots.
And so, what this meant was that
for a while you could stay out of cover,
but after a while, without you even noticing it,
because you probably were habituated,
the AI would just suddenly be able to start hitting you
and that would drive you back into cover.
We reduced the damage scale on Legendary,
that global damage scale that was so high before.
because we just decided that damage is not the right way to make a game harder.
I believe that the right way to make a game harder is to make it faster.
So, the same experience slowed down becomes easy.
The same experience sped up becomes harder.
The projectiles go faster, the AI fire delays get shorter,
in fact the entire combat cycle gets faster, so it's probably like 22 seconds of fun or something like that.
And this emerged in a concept we call reciprocal difficulty.
So basically, it's a form of dynamic difficulty,
but it's not handled by the computer or the AI.
It's actually driven by the player.
So the more you push a Halo encounter,
the more it pushes back, which rewards risk.
Because if you push really hard, you
can break through very fast, as long
as you can handle how hard it's pushing back at you.
But at the same time, it forgives failure.
So as soon as you withdraw, it withdraws.
You'll notice in Halo, the AI don't really chase you very much.
And we don't punish you at all for risking and then failing and running away.
Your shields come back, your health comes back.
The AI resets, basically.
So I recently read a really fascinating book called Sleights of Mind, and it's a couple
of neuroscientists who go into the world of magic, and they try to learn everything they
can from the techniques that the magicians have.
to figure out what's going on inside of the brain of the people that they're fooling.
And one of the things that they talk about in the context of a pickpocket is that you
have a spotlight of attention.
And anytime you attend to one thing, you are ignoring virtually everything else that is
not happening in your spotlight.
So that's the tunnel vision that we describe.
And magicians exploit this feature mercilessly.
The doves fly up, and you all look up, as most of you probably looked up just because
they went like that.
And then over here, they're doing something else.
And I figured, you know, if magicians can do that,
if they can use distraction, then a game designer
should be able to do the opposite in order
to kind of hyper-focus while they're calibrating.
So just a random smattering ideas
on how to focus your attention.
I always create custom test spaces
so that nothing else is going on except for the thing
that I'm trying to calibrate.
You obviously can't ship a game that way,
because eventually you need to try it all together.
But I found that it helps you focus and not
get distracted on the other things that are broken.
if they're too fun, get distracted just playing the game.
I use post-it notes, so if I'm balancing the plasma rifle,
I'll put a post-it note that says plasma rifle on the screen.
Right now I have one that says talk faster.
I stare at Rorschach tests and try not to see pictures.
I don't know, this is like the equivalent of last year's mouth
noises with the warthog.
But I feel like if you can train your brain to go into a state
where it's not looking for patterns,
you'll be able to see.
specific patterns and put your spotlight directly on them more effectively.
You need to avoid habituation.
The way I do that is I take periodic breaks.
Again, the custom test spaces are great for that because you play through it, and then
when you get to the end, you just take a break.
Or maybe you try tweaking something else.
Sometimes I'll intentionally break something.
I usually don't check this in, but I'll just...
I'll just break something and play the game with a broken plasma rifle for a while, so
I habituate to something else, and then when I put it back, I'm more sensitive to it.
And I also do total recalibrations, and this drives producers nuts.
But I'll basically save off a copy, blank out everything, and try to retune it from
scratch.
And then I'll compare the two, and I'll say, oh, these are really close.
I bet you that's, you know, right.
Or hey, these are totally different.
And then I kind of have two things to compare.
people can tell me which one they like more.
So at the end of all that, in Halo 3,
14 world units per second, about 75% faster
on Legendary and in multiplayer.
The normal experience was that even on Legendary,
you can dodge for short amounts of time,
but eventually you have to return into cover.
The unintended consequences of this
was that we started to see players sort of standardizing
how they were playing.
even on normal or on legendary, different quality of players,
they would kind of have the same pattern.
And we would see that a level was
taking about the same time for everybody to complete.
And it wasn't badly broken, which was a good thing.
In multiplayer, people started to use the plasma rifle
more often because it was faster and it was more effective,
especially when combining arms with teammates.
We saw people want to use the alien weapons more,
and they want to play as elites more, which was useful later on.
And again, not badly broken.
The legendary experience, legendary is very hard.
It's supposed to be.
But it's not punishing hard.
It just requires a very high level of skill.
And so we saw people, especially reviewers,
that were playing on higher difficulty levels
were giving it a higher score.
And we also developed this bizarre sub-community.
where they play solo legendary all skulls on it.
You know what the skulls are.
I mean, that makes it incredibly hard.
But at the same time, it's still doable
because we're not cranking up the damage
to ridiculous levels.
So hopefully not badly broken.
Which brings me to ODST, which was named Halo 3 ODST
for a reason, because the sandbox didn't really change.
Which brings me to Halo Reach, where the plasma rifle was
reborn as the plasma.
So our competition was pretty clear.
We, by that time, had a large collection of sub-communities.
So there's the multiplayer-only community.
There's the people that just wanted to jump into Forge.
Firefight was really popular.
And one of the sub-communities was Halo developers.
Basically, almost every member of the original team
had already moved on to the next big thing by then.
And fully half of the Reach team was hired after Halo 3 shipped.
So that meant, to some extent, Halo Reach was made by the community, for the community,
and they were very in tune with what the community wanted.
Which brought up things like Elites versus Spartans, where they wanted total weapon parity
between the Elite weapons and the Spartan weapons, which meant that they needed an Elite
assault rifle, which is what the Platinum Repeater eventually became.
and that meant basically all they wanted for that game was the instant projectiles
because otherwise it just wasn't fair.
It's hard to hit a human with a dodgeable projectile.
And they really were intent on going back to the feel of Halo 1,
back to fighting elites, they removed dual wielding,
there are lots more plasma rifles in the game.
So according to the Halo re-strategy guide,
did I mention I didn't really work on this game?
The plasma rifle's primary purpose
is to disable the shields of close, you know, forget it.
I'm going to take a lesson from the plasma rifle.
I'm going to kind of dodge this one.
It's not fair for an ex-Bungie designer
to talk about the decisions that the current design team made.
And I'm almost out of time anyway.
But you find that in the middle of the project,
things were very different than Halo 3.
But by the end of the project, they had sort of
veered back in the direction of what we had at the end of Halo 3.
So conclusions.
Tuning and balancing are not the same.
Balance is about longevity, especially in multiplayer, and tuning is really the craft
of making something fun, which is, depending on which theory section you agreed with, specialized
brain circuit activity, or performing a skill in a natural, meaningful context.
or meeting exotelic aspiration.
The tuning process, first you understand your audience,
either by choosing it or inheriting it,
because your audience is inseparable
from their context.
Then you find their exotelic aspiration, or the activity
that they want to do.
You choose a fun activity that is reactive, repeatable,
reliable.
And keep in mind, these are rare,
and that's why you're going to very rarely invent
an entirely new kind of game.
Then you integrate the mechanics so that they support each other
and calibrate the values to your internal player model,
sometimes starting over from scratch.
And then verify the experience through user research,
and hopefully nothing is badly broken.
And now I am out of here.
I don't really have time for questions.
We have like 30 seconds left, which is not.
enough time for the first questioner to usually get out their question.
So if you have them, you can email me at Jamie Griesemer.
I have a lot more time on my hands now.
And I'm also writing in more detail on a lot of this stuff on my website, thetipofthesphere.com.
And I have plenty of business cards up here.
If anybody has any questions they want to email me, or if they want a personal version
of this talk, or would like to offer me a job.
Thank you.