Hello, welcome, and thank you for coming.
This is creating living, breathing key art
for your front end.
My name is D. Reid Monroe.
I'm a presentation director at Ubisoft
here in San Francisco, but until very recently,
I was actually at Telltale Games for five years
where I was the UI director.
Can I begin by just getting a show of hands real quick?
Who in the room works on UI or is responsible for UI
or front end development in your studio?
Okay, cool. It's about half, maybe.
Well, regardless if you raised your hand or not,
I think it's important we start with this term.
So we're all on the same page.
I'm defining front-end key art as
the primary animated audio-visual
within your video game front-end.
Or, to put it more simply,
it's the first thing you see when the game boots up.
It's the living, breathing visual behind the menu.
It's Batman in Arkham City, the black and white alleyway from L.A. Noire, and the Phantom
Thieves in Persona 5.
And while I could happily spend all my time up here on stage pointing out examples of
what front-end key art could be, it's important to note what it's not.
Front-end key art is not marketing key art.
And while they can be similar and often are,
the two, I believe, have fundamentally different roles.
It's marketing's job to get the player into the game,
where it's the front end's job
to get the player prepared to play the game.
So over the next 30 minutes,
I wanna focus on just the front-end key art.
And hopefully pass on an appreciation
both for its promise, but also the path to creating it.
I'm gonna do this by very quickly outlining
why I believe front-end key art is important.
Next, I'll identify the things
that great front-end key arts do,
so that they're successful.
And finally, I'm gonna share with you
some of my work at Telltale Games,
as well as some of the lessons I learned along the way.
So without further ado, let's begin, shall we?
Let's break this question down.
If you one day find yourself being asked
to defend an investment in front-end key art,
consider these points.
Why is the front end key art important?
Well, for starters, it's a guaranteed first impression.
The end user has to come in through the front end
to play the game.
Or another way to look at it,
it's the last opportunity to shape your audience's opinion
before the game begins.
Secondly, if your game's a success, knock on wood,
your end user's gonna return over and over again,
and they're gonna see the front end key art a lot.
So it's an investment.
Thirdly, as I mentioned just earlier,
the front end has a responsibility
to prepare the player to play the game.
And the front end key art can do that,
and I'll get to that in just a bit.
And finally, the front end key art
is an opportunity for your title to stand out.
Destructoid, in their review of Telltale's
Guardians of the Galaxy game,
reserved the first six paragraphs
to discussing just the front end key art.
While the press generally tends to forego UI
and only harp on it if there's an issue,
this review proves that the UI team
can make a notable contribution to your game
with the front-end keyer.
The answer to this question is simple.
Great front-end key art prepares the player
to play the game.
And regardless of your platform, budget, or genre,
I believe there's just three things
that every front-end key art can do
to fulfill this responsibility.
Prime, inform, and adapt.
Prime is most commonly executed of the three.
It's about preparing the user emotionally
for the experience they're about to have.
For example, it's the endless mayhem of Space Marine.
Here, the key art is essentially a giant love letter
to its core combat and puts a player in a trance,
priming their blood list, getting them ready for the game.
But Prime can also be about subverting expectations, seen here in Kanan Lynch 2.
Here the key art does the opposite of Space Marine, and contrasts the violence within
the game.
Instead of embracing the game's tone, the front end smartly stays at arm's length, and
serves as the necessary pause before the plunge.
Inform. Inform is the flip side of Prime, where Prime is about triggering an emotional response,
Inform is more cerebral and about challenging the players to think.
Here we want to teach them something, show them something they don't know,
give them information that will color, affect, or influence how they play.
It doesn't even have to be overt. Perhaps it's subliminal?
Like Overwatch's lovable front end.
Blizzard could have easily scripted it to show you your favorite character,
or perhaps the character you played last, but they didn't.
Instead, the characters randomly appear and inform,
perhaps on a subliminal level, your next character selection.
But what's smart is from time to time the key art does double duty,
and also informs players about the latest events and content.
So good.
Dirt 2, on the other hand, informs in a completely different way.
Here, the key art informs the world and brings a whole new perspective to what would merely be a driving game.
It also provides important context like, where are we and why are we racing?
And thirdly, there's adapt.
If your key art doesn't update, what kind of a message does that send to your users?
If you want your user to come back again and again, then your presentation should adapt and evolve.
like spec ops the line here.
Each time the player returns to the front end,
we see the key art update to show both the passage of time,
but also the visual consequences
from events within the game.
Or it's the swapping environments of Valve's Portal 2.
Here, the entire key art is replaced with new environments
as the player progresses through the game.
And kudos to Portal 2, as even their loading screen evolves.
So there you have it.
Prime, Inform, and Adapt.
A good key art will do one of these, perhaps two,
but a truly great, successful front-end key art
will strive for all three.
Would you like to see my favorite example that does that?
I'm cheating a little bit.
While not a video game, HBO's Game of Thrones opening credit
sequence epitomizes what a great front-end key art should do.
Each week as returning audiences tune in,
the sequence primes, heightening the viewer's anticipation
with music and visuals.
It informs, reminding viewers of location names, sigils.
And it adapts, reflecting omitted locations,
as well as adding new ones.
But what I also want to show you is something else.
Note how the opening credit sits.
It's positioned between marketing
and the individual episodes.
Each one is very different,
however each one is essential to the overall experience.
Now compare that with a video game front end,
which is also positioned between marketing and its content.
In both examples, neither the left, marketing,
nor the right, the content, can do what the center does.
And that's why I love this example.
HBO's Game of Thrones credit sequence
demonstrates two things extremely well.
It does a great job at preparing its audience,
and it's unafraid to become something altogether unique,
and that's what a great front-end key art
should strive to do.
Now, for the rest of the time I have here with you today,
I'd like to share with you not only some of the work
that I've been fortunate enough to make at Telltale Games,
but also five lessons I learned along the way,
making Front End Cure.
During my first week at Telltale Games,
one of its co-founders, Kevin Bruner,
pulled me aside to his office
and taught me this important lesson.
He explained that production and design constraints
on the Back to the Future game
ended up minimizing the role of the DeLorean.
And when they finally realized it,
it was too late in development to change the game,
but the front end, which had yet to be finalized,
could perhaps compensate for this oversight.
And so the DeLorean became the front end key art.
And by doing so, they made sure an underrepresented aspect
of the Back to the Future brand got its due.
Kevin's takeaway here was that the front end
could be used to pave over any perceived holes in the game.
And we used this approach on Telltale's Minecraft story mode.
Once again, the development of the front end started late,
and this afforded the UI team the opportunity
to see the game for what it was,
and not what it intended to be.
And just like in Back to the Future,
an important franchise aspect was underrepresented.
Our version of Minecraft had very little blocks and building.
So I began looking at ways to show building in the key art
and quickly landed on time-lapse construction.
I then discovered, perhaps not surprisingly,
that the Minecraft community had already modded
the original game to achieve this effect.
So pitching this idea was as simple as ripping these videos
and suggesting we do something similar.
Voila.
And so for season one and season two of Minecraft Story Mode,
the key art was time-lapse block building.
While I'm happy with the results, I'm actually more proud of how this underrepresented aspect
ironically circled back around into the game itself.
You see the time lapse effect was so successful that they wanted it in the game.
And so portions of the game were reworked at the 11th hour to take advantage of the
key art's new block building tech.
Now our characters were mining materials and building up structures in the game.
As a wrapper of the product, the front end is ideally suited
both from an end user standpoint,
but also a development standpoint
to surface and ensure these underrepresented pillars,
characters, concepts are seen.
Asking yourself what aspects of the product
are underrepresented gets this process started
and should be the first question you ask yourself
when you roll onto a new project.
When Saul Bass, the renowned graphic designer
most widely known for his film posters and title sequences,
submitted his poster design
for the horror classic The Shining,
he could have easily with his clout
sent over a solitary design.
But he didn't.
Instead he sent over four.
And that started a chain of correspondences,
excuse me, with the legendary director Stanley Kubrick,
where they collaborated and ultimately
hammered out the treatment we know today.
Why I love this example is it shows that even the best guys in the industry rely on options.
Options don't show indecisiveness, but instead allow your creative partners to discover the
best ideas.
Saul Bass needed Kubrick's insight, just as Kubrick needed Saul's ideas and perspectives.
Multiple options facilitates the involvement
of key creatives and returns strengthens the end results.
But that's not the only reason you should prepare options.
It gives production the confidence
you're ultimately making the right choices.
But it also provides additional opportunities
to show off your or your team's strengths.
But last, and perhaps most importantly,
you never know how those multiple options
will pay off down the road.
For Minecraft, the time elapsed concept shown earlier
was just one of many that we pitched.
And from the unselected, two were repurposed
and ultimately found a home within the game.
One of those was this concept
of projecting imagery on blocks.
At the time, I was experimenting with
rendered texture in our engine,
and thought the simple, iconic Minecraft cubes
could serve as canvases for images and videos.
The other was a mind descent.
Once again, here was another underrepresented idea.
We had very little mind in our Minecraft game.
And so I made a parallaxing descent from cards.
And at the same time, I was eyeing two telltale stables,
the stats and the credit screens.
which served as each episode's conclusion.
Both were basically flat and static
and ripe for reimagining,
especially on such a playful property like Minecraft.
And so the individual stats became the sides of the cube,
and the credit scroll was now the mind descent.
And they were stitched together with a fun transition,
giving Telltale perhaps its most unique end flow.
The lesson here is that simply developing multiple options
has numerous benefits, and perhaps this is a no-brainer.
But it's how I tackle all the projects,
and if you can afford the time to explore them,
I'd argue there's no healthier way to start.
On Batman, a Telltale series, like all my projects,
I opened up the front-end key art
to all members of the UI team,
challenging them to bring their best ideas to the table.
The process begins with an initial brainstorming session
where we look for those underrepresented ideas,
but we also look for differentiators.
Those ideas are then grouped into related buckets,
and individuals are free to sign up and explore
the concept bucket they're most interested in.
Of all the concepts worth pursuing on Batman,
it was duality and comic panels that bore the most fruit.
Unlike Rocksteady's Batman, Telltale's Batman was going to embrace its comic book roots.
And I would render, we would render the game using two nightlights.
So this comic panel's concept was about highlighting that distinction.
But in the end, we ultimately spearheaded, uh, selected a more daring duality concept,
spearheaded by one of my talented UI artists, Hane Lee.
Telltale's Batman for the first time in a video game was gonna treat Bruce Wayne as an equal to Batman.
And so this concept was about highlighting that split role using light.
It's kind of like a magic trick.
There's a mask that comes in just as the shadow hits the face and reveals the Bruce underneath
Batman's suit and vice versa.
There's actually a couple lessons here, like create a process that can involve others,
but the primary lesson is make sure you look for and lean into those differentiators in
addition to looking for those underrepresented aspects.
Differentiators are those aspects that set your game apart, and if they're strong, they're
going to make for really strong key art.
My first project at Telltale Games was The Wolf Among Us.
And early into production,
marketing released this teaser image.
Despite the character being off,
what was truly troubling is it promised a different game
from what the dev team was actually making.
If you played The Wolf Among Us,
you know that it's a colorful detective noir
and not whatever the left is promising.
Now in marketing's defense, the image was early
and they had very little to work with,
but still it speaks to a disconnect between the two.
Further complicating things was the source material.
The popular Fables comic book series
was associated with these fabulous covers.
Not only did each issue completely reinvent the brand,
but they looked nothing like our game's art direction.
So there I was caught between the game marketing wanted to project,
the colorful game the dev team was making,
and the game that the Fables fans wanted.
I tried to create something that I thought would please everyone.
And I thought I had it.
We were going to see our hero.
his inner wolf come through his glowing eyes.
And we got very close, but there was just one problem.
Marketing couldn't stomach the bright, cycling colors that the dev team was pushing for.
And in our defense, the game did take place in the 80s,
and we were in the midst of that 80s aesthetic revival.
Hotline Miami had just come out, Drive had just come out.
And I knew in my heart to get people to swallow the fact that our heroes were Snow White and
the Big Bad Wolf, we almost had to trick them into thinking they were cool and exciting.
However, in the end, I was coached into safer territories, resulting in the compromised
color scheme we shipped with.
to you soon.
The lesson here is be aware, but not beholden to marketing
and your precedence.
I kinda need to remind myself this lesson
every once in a while.
Don't be afraid to create and fight for something
that is counter to expectations if what you're making
is ultimately faithful to the game itself.
While an awareness of marketing and precedence is important
and almost essential, they shouldn't dictate
the front-end QR.
As I showed earlier, marketing and the front end have different jobs and they don't have
to be always on the same page.
It's okay.
Way back before you guys were born, on my first game, the WALL-E video game, I foolishly
presented two front end key art designs that couldn't be made.
One concept took the film's rough Pixar color script
and tried to bring it to life.
However, it wasn't feasible.
We simply didn't have the bandwidth to create
what was essentially a cartoon for the front end.
And the other concept was like a microfiche-like dive
through this robotic imagery and blueprints.
This one couldn't be achieved technically.
Our pipeline didn't support Z movement or depth of field.
So in the end, I wasn't able to deliver on the success
that either concept promised
and learned this sobering lesson.
What you pitch has to be producible.
Skip forward 10 years to Guardians of the Galaxy.
Unlike WALL-E, all of Guardian's key art designs
were conceived with the limitations
of both a single implementer and art engine in mind.
And the winning concept was pitched as an anti-Age of Ultron credit sequence.
Instead of pulling further and further out to see our heroes heroically pose together,
we would instead see the Guardians of the Galaxy as the dysfunctional family they were.
And it was this early test that made the pitch possible.
Our confidence with the engine allowed us to prove that a single implementer
could essentially pull this whole thing together with little to no animation support.
Resulting in this.
It's all rolling and riding, it's slipping and sliding, it's magic.
And you, and your sweet design.
The lesson here is keep yourself honest and prove that your ideas can be accomplished.
preferably by you if possible, because in the end,
you might be the one actually driving the front-end key art.
That's not to say you can't ask for help or pull favors.
For example, in the Guardians of the Galaxy key art
I just showed you, it had a professional lighting,
VFX, and animation pass, but we made sure
to keep that work contained, and limited to just polish.
So, we're now at the end of the talk,
and I'd like to leave you with this.
While not evident to the end user,
the front end key art's ultimate potential and success
depends on your production's outlook.
If the front end is viewed as just a utilitarian speed bump
on the way into the game,
well then, that's what you're gonna get.
But if you want your front end key art
to be truly integral and a successful part of the product,
there needs to be a willingness,
a concerted effort by you
to champion its potential within the office.
It's not easy, believe me.
And at times you might feel like you're alone, fighting for resources or permission.
But if you persevere, you'll find yourself with ownership of an important cornerstone
of your product.
One that can be just as memorable, just as important as any other part of the game.
Thank you.
I got 1227, so I think there might be time for a question or two if there is.
Hi David.
Hi.
First of all, thanks for this high quality presentation.
Oh, I guess it's one gig, the PowerPoint.
I think I might have the right.
Yeah, but it's worth it, I think.
So, I love also the relationship you...
made with Game of Thrones for the three elements,
prime, inform, and adapt.
I was thinking about your opinion
about adding interaction on top of that.
I know there is already the interaction with the menu.
But how about a small thing in the background
that the player could potentially control,
or I don't know, like the lights or?
Wow, that's a good question.
I think, I haven't gotten that one yet in all my times I've given this talk, but you're
absolutely right.
I think one of the advantages of the video game is that it is interactive, so it can
evolve.
That's something that marketing typically can't do, you know, once they print the poster,
it's done.
But absolutely, interaction is one.
We had one key art design for Minecraft where the hub or this key art was actually interactable.
You could walk around and move things.
Another good example is Dirt 2, right?
As you're navigating the menus, you position the camera throughout the RV.
So absolutely, that could be a fourth hidden pillar there.
Thanks a lot.
Oh, hey.
Hi.
Great talk, by the way.
Thank you.
I have a question.
As you said before, marketing art and front-end art could be different.
Yes.
That's okay.
So what can you advise about UI which is used in front-end key art?
How is it connected with UI in the game?
That's a good question.
It's okay to say that that can be different as well.
I think ultimately it needs to be faithful.
It's a flow, right?
You start on one end where you don't know anything
about the game and you're pulled in.
And so marketing has one job.
And then you're committed to the game,
you're invested, you buy it,
then the front end has to prepare you to play.
And so it has a completely different job.
And then vice versa, you then get in the game.
now you have to actually play the game so the UI has a whole new set of responsibilities, the
HUD. And I think it's okay if every step of the way it changes as long as it's doing the best
job it can. Hmm? Thank you.
Hi, thanks for the awesome presentation.
I think it was equally as beautiful as some of the front key and key art stuff that you
worked on.
So, thanks for that.
Just a real quick question.
Have you worked on any VR or AR related stuff, mostly VR, and how have you tackled front
end key art for players that are in that situation, you know, just getting started with the experience?
Any tips or tricks you would suggest?
I wish I had some.
I've never even thought about working on VR.
So that's a whole new dimension.
I would imagine that just like interactivity is a pillar, then maybe your perspective is
a pillar.
Maybe somebody next year will come back and do an amendment to this talk.
But yeah, I haven't really thought about it.
Thanks.
A lot of good stuff.
I think this might be the last one.
Thank you.
Yeah, you made a pretty big distinction
between marketing key art and front-end key art.
But a lot of the concepts you presented to me as a marketer,
I think, are pretty compelling.
So I'm curious to know if you have any thoughts about how
a marketer might collaborate with a front-end designer
to kind of unify that experience.
Yeah, yeah.
And I think there's no reason why they couldn't be similar.
I think part of it is.
marketing's job, they usually come in so late,
they have a different perspective, the game is different,
sometimes the front end people are so early,
so things may have changed,
but I would hope that if you are afforded the opportunity
or the connections to reach out to the front end developers
or vice versa, that you guys could get in sync early on
and maybe meet regularly to kind of see
how things are progressing, because the game will change,
you know, features will get cut.
And you ultimately have to do the best job for your responsibility.
All right.
Thank you.
Thanks, everybody.
Thanks for coming.