Welcome to Loot Boxes, Legal Pitfalls and Loopholes.
My name is Will Bucher.
I'm an IP litigator for a law firm, Debevoise & Plimpton,
in New York City.
That's a fancy way of saying I help media companies, mostly
video game companies, when they get sued.
And then I also spend my days helping
those companies avoid situations that might get them sued.
Today, we're going to be talking about regulation of loot boxes,
and we're going to focus on three regions, the United
States, the European Union, and China.
And I'm going to be talking to you about where there are
regulations, and in the countries and regions where
there are regulations, what you need to know about them,
and what you need to do to modify your game so that you
can release in that jurisdiction.
This is a business and marketing talk,
and so for the first 27 minutes
of this half an hour presentation,
that's gonna be focused on the rules
and how you can avoid them.
For the last three minutes,
I will talk a little bit about, as a community,
how we ethically wanna use loot boxes,
but the focus of today's presentation is on the rules,
because I wanna give you the tools
and let you decide how you wanna use them.
Before we can start talking about loot boxes,
we have to get on the same page about what a loot box is.
And I think that question is a little harder than it appears at first.
Most of us have an idea of what a loot box is in our mind.
We might think of the stereotypical, you pay money or some green gems for a box
that has some randomized items.
But the truth is, there's a lot of chance involved in everything we do in life.
And I could argue that anything on this screen is a loot box.
I'm not going to go through each of these items,
but I want to point out a couple of the items that
are on this screen.
In the middle there, you see just sort
of a procedurally generated monster.
We've had these in games for decades.
And the mechanics are actually very similar to a loot box.
The player gets a random assortment of items.
Most of the time, those items are bad.
Sometimes they're really good.
And so there's some similarities there.
Loot boxes really aren't that different from something
we've been doing for a long time.
What about that last example, right?
I call a car a loot box, right?
Let's say I invest in Bitcoin and I hold all that Bitcoin
until I can afford my Lambo and I go to the dealership
and the dealer says to me,
do you want the extended warranty?
And I say, no, I wanna save that money
to invest in more Bitcoin.
And 366 days later, my drive train blows out.
I'm out half a million bucks.
But no one is trying to say that
I have to take the extended warranty.
No one's trying to regulate that practice,
but we face chance in everything we do.
And because it's so hard to define what a loot box is,
the answer to what a loot box is in today's presentation
is it depends on the regulator.
We see regulators governing loot boxes in different ways.
And that's because I don't really
think loot boxes are a problem in the game development
industry.
But I do think some loot boxes are
symbolic of some very real issues we face.
I think some loot boxes create compulsion loops.
These are skinner box mechanics that keep players playing much longer than they actually
want to play.
Some loot boxes are symbolic of pay-to-win mechanics,
where players feel like they're not
being rewarded for their time or their skill,
but just the money they put in.
Some loot boxes are used in outright fraud,
and a lot of loot boxes aren't transparent.
It's not clear to the user what they're going to get
and what their odds are.
And so when we see loot boxes regulated,
we actually see them targeting these four other practices.
So with that, let's start with the United States.
Now, the United States gets a reputation
as a country where corporations make all the rules
and there's no consumer protection.
And in the case of loot boxes, that's absolutely right.
There is no government organization, no agency,
none of the 50 states that place any formal rules
on the use of loot boxes.
But there actually are some rules
on the use of loot boxes in the United States,
and those come from private companies.
Those companies are the ESRB, that's the ratings organization
here in the United States, and Apple through the App Store.
If you have a mobile game that you're selling on iOS devices,
Apple has rules you're going to have to comply with.
I'll put a little asterisk here.
That doesn't mean you can just commit outright fraud.
If you're lying to your consumers, that's illegal.
And that's been illegal for over a century, centuries,
very long time.
So don't use this as an excuse to do otherwise illegal things.
But there's no specific loot box regulation.
So let's talk about those private company rules.
So for Apple, you must disclose the odds by item type.
And Apple defines loot boxes as mechanisms
that provide randomized virtual items for purchase.
So Apple's sort of, there's three requirements
to be in the loot box bucket.
Has to be virtual item, has to be randomized,
and has to be for purchase.
I think that sort of lines up
with most of our notions of loot boxes.
And when I say disclosed by item type,
what I mean by that is think of sort of the classic game
that has a common item, rare item,
an epic item, and a legendary item.
That's what I mean by type.
You don't have to list every single item
and the odds of getting each and every item,
but you have to list them by categories
when you're selling on the App Store.
What about ESRB?
How does the ratings organization define loot boxes?
Well, they sort of don't.
They lump loot boxes in with any in-game purchase.
And the requirement for ESRB is that you include an in-game purchases label underneath your
rating.
I put an example up there in the lower right-hand corner.
That's what the in-game purchases tab looks like.
And that's an effort for transparency.
The people who use ratings most are parents.
And what parents care most about is how much is their child going to spend in the game.
And they want to know if their child is going to spend more money.
They don't really care that it's in the format of a loot box or a randomized capacity.
So now I'm going to break us into a hypothetical.
I find it's easier to think about these ideas in a context
that might be more similar to the one you would face in your
own company as a developer or publisher.
It's not going to be particularly complicated.
But in our hypothetical today, we have a game developer,
ShadyCorp, and they're releasing a game, Drawn Out
Chess, and this is a classic game of chess, but it's
monetized by selling skins, specifically selling skins
through loot boxes.
They release the games with no disclosures,
no consideration of the regulations.
And a month later, an employee spots the issue.
This actually happens a lot.
People realize after the fact they're doing something wrong.
And the question is,
what does the developer do here as a company?
Let's start with ESRB.
What does Drawn Out Chess have to do
to comply with the ratings?
Well, if they're ESRB rated,
they have to include that sticker.
But in my hypothetical,
this game is actually only being released on Steam and iOS.
And what that means is they don't need an ESRB rating at all.
Most games published today are not rated by the ESRB
because neither Steam nor the App Store
require that the games be rated.
Okay, so what about for Apple?
Well, for Apple, there needs to be a disclosure
by item type like I talked about.
So that means ShadyCorp needs to divide their items
into categories and list those percentage odds
for the players.
They can't actually formally backtrack.
Apple says that the disclosure has to be before the purchase.
So there's actually no way to become compliant here.
And somewhat frustratingly, Apple
doesn't have formal rules for what you do when you mess up.
So my best advice to ShadyCorp here would be fix the game,
start disclosing in advance, and then do nothing else.
And then if Apple comes talking to you, apologize,
negotiate with them, work out a solution.
But there's actually no formal process
for how to remedy a violation.
Okay, here are some takeaways.
I know it's sometimes helpful to sort of have bullet points.
Feel free to take photos of these slides.
Takeaways for US regulation are ESRB requires disclosure,
but there's no requirement that your game
actually have an ESRB rating
for most online sale platforms.
All iOS games must disclose odds by item type.
That disclosure must be prior to purchase.
And there's no regulation on loot boxes,
but that doesn't mean other laws don't apply.
So now let's talk about the EU.
So in the EU right now, there's country-specific regulation.
That means every country in the EU
gets to make up their own decision.
Some countries, Germany, France, even PEGI,
which is the equivalent of the ESRB in the EU,
have called for EU-wide regulation,
but right now we haven't seen any of it.
So that means right now, other than two countries,
you can do whatever you want in the EU,
just like in the United States.
The two countries that have rules are Belgium and Holland.
In Belgium, it's illegal to have any acquirable item
where chance is involved.
So Belgium defines loot boxes as the purchase with real money
or with paid virtual currency.
That's sort of like the green gems, the premium currency
in your games, and where chance is involved.
So you can sell items directly to players,
but you can't sell these sort of randomized loot boxes.
Holland is actually a little more permissive.
Holland makes it illegal where the item is
acquirable with real money, where there's
chance involved, and where the final prize is transferable.
So you actually have some more options in Holland.
Oftentimes, the two countries get lumped together.
But I think it's actually much easier
to operate in Holland than it is in Belgium.
So we'll continue our hypothetical.
Shady Corp expands its drawn-out chess offerings to Europe.
What do they need to do and where?
Well, the answer for most countries is simple.
They don't need to do anything.
For Belgium, the answer is they probably need to put a geofence on the purchase of their
loot boxes.
They can publish their game, but they can't have those purchasable loot boxes in the game.
For Holland, ShadyCorp has another option.
They could either geofence the purchase of the loot box.
Or they could prohibit players who have IP addresses in Holland from transferring their
items.
So you could still have those loot boxes in your game as long as the player can't transfer.
And oftentimes it's more profitable to restrict the transfer of the items after the fact than
to restrict the outlight purchase of loot boxes.
I think what these different regulations highlight, and this may become more important in the
future if we see other jurisdictions implementing regulations, and this is my third bullet
point on these takeaways here, is that when you as a developer or publisher are building
your game, you want to make sure every feature of your game can be toggled on and off, or
at least every monetization feature.
Because if you're in a position where you can't turn off
the sale of loot boxes, then that
means you just can't sell your game at all in these countries.
You're limiting yourself from a market that
might still be profitable despite the regulations.
So as you're building your game, build
with these considerations in mind
that there are rules that are different by country
and that those rules may change over time.
Other big takeaways are, in Holland, you have a choice.
You can restrict the transfer or the sale of loot boxes.
In Belgium, you have to restrict the sale of randomized items
for purchase.
And then sort of my final point is I've seen these calls for EU-wide regulation.
I don't expect it to happen soon, although you ask 100 lawyers and you get 100 different
opinions on that.
So so far, the sort of takeaway has been there's not a lot of regulation and it's pretty easy
to get around it.
China is sort of a different story.
In China, loot boxes are regulated by two different organizations, one with a focus
on content and the other with a focus on monetization and mechanics.
We're going to start by going through the formal rules and then we'll talk about sort
of how that ends up working in practice.
So formally on the monetization, you cannot have a randomized event, right?
China defines a loot box as any randomized event.
That seems a little overbroad, doesn't it?
That seems like everything I put up on that first slide
in the presentation today.
But you can't have a randomized event
for purchase with real money or virtual currency.
This might be a translation issue.
I think virtual currency actually
means paid virtual currency.
We haven't really seen any enforcement against games
where you just have the gold you collect naturally
through gameplay.
But formally, it says any virtual currency.
So as written and as translated into English,
that could be even the currency you only
can earn through gameplay.
Second rule is the virtual items or services that you offer
have to be obtainable by other means.
What are other means?
That could mean that you could get it through gameplay,
you could get it through randomized drops
from killing monsters in the game.
You could have it so that the only way to get the item
is to purchase it outright from the store
or get a loot box.
So you can still have items that are only purchasable
through real money,
but there has to be some other way to get that item.
And then the third requirement is no compulsion loops.
These are like sort of Skinner box mechanics.
We'll talk about in our hypothetical for this country
about what that might look like even in the context
where you weren't directly selling the loot boxes.
But that's not all.
China has regulations on disclosures
and these are super onerous regulations.
The first is you need to provide information about the odds for your loot box up front.
And that information is not like Apple where it's by type.
You're formally supposed to list your odds of getting every single item in that loot
box.
Now, that may just mean that you're taking the number of items that are in a category
and dividing that category percentage to list them, but, you know, it is a more formal requirement.
But not only do you have to list your odds in advance.
Those odds have to be transparent to users.
That means it's easy for a Chinese user to find those odds.
Can't be complicated, can't be at the very bottom of your page,
click here to see the odds.
Basically, if they run a search for those odds,
they should be able to find them.
And then the final requirement, which is incredibly labor
intensive, is that every game is supposed to keep for 90
days and publicly make available the results of every
single loot box outcome in their game.
Thousands or millions of outcomes kept in a chart, and
it's supposed to be publicly available.
Now you might be thinking to yourself, well, I bet you 50
bucks, you can't find a single company operating in China
that does that.
And if you're thinking that, you'd be up $50.
I searched through the top 20 licensed games in China,
and I wasn't able to find it.
And so then I called my colleague in Hong Kong.
I said, look, maybe it's a language barrier.
And my colleague in Hong Kong couldn't find a single game
that did that either.
So I think what you see in China is a lot of rules,
but really inconsistent enforcement of those rules.
And the truth is, whether or not you
can offer a loot box in China depends
on whether the government likes your game.
So now we're going to come into today's last hypothetical.
And this has to do with dynamic odds adjustment.
So it's March, and Shady Corp's game is doing well,
but they want it to do better.
And so they're going to engage in dynamic odds adjustment.
What do I mean by that?
That means adjusting the odds of the outcomes for your loot box
in the hopes of denying the player what they really want,
so they keep buying more loot boxes.
This can target a specific player.
We might have data and metrics that tell us
about an individual player.
But that sort of odds adjustment can be done on a wider basis.
So in our example, it's March.
St. Patrick's Day was Sunday.
And ShadyCorp realizes their players really
want to play with their St. Patrick's Day-themed chess set.
And so previously, when you got one of their legendary chess
sets, there was an even chance of getting a pirate chess set,
a ninja chess set, a Halloween chess set.
but they're gonna adjust the odds
so the odds of getting that St. Patrick's Day chess set
go down.
And not only are they gonna do that,
they realize no one wants a Halloween chess set in March.
So they're gonna increase the odds of that chess set.
And the hope here is that the players
don't get what they want,
and so they keep purchasing more loot boxes.
So let's talk globally.
Is this practice legal?
What does ShadyCorp have to do to make it legal?
Well, in the United States.
Yeah, currently you can do this.
Even Apple's terms, right, only require disclosure of those top-level categories.
And here ShadyCorp isn't changing the odds of getting a legendary item, they're just
changing the odds a level below that, within the odds.
So they don't even need to change their disclosures to comply with Apple's terms.
It's conceivable that they might get an action for fraud
brought against them.
But if they have a good lawyer, they're
probably going to be OK right now in the United States.
What about the EU?
Similar answer, although I'd say EU courts are
sort of more favorable to sort of creative legal actions.
So even though there's no strict law prohibiting it,
probably slightly riskier in the EU.
Obviously, you can't do this in Belgium.
I think you could still do it in Holland,
as long as you didn't restrict transfers.
So what about China, the country we just talked about?
Well, this violates the formal rules for a lot of reasons.
First, it's a purchasable loot box.
But even if there was geofencing for China,
so that the game didn't have purchasable loot boxes there,
this would still violate their rules,
because this creates a compulsion loop.
Even if the only way to get the loot box was from gameplay,
this encourages the players to purchase the loot box,
to get more and more, because they're never
getting what they want out of it.
So that's sort of where the compulsion loop rule
comes in in China.
But of course, as we've seen in China,
particularly with the disclosure requirements,
often those rules aren't enforced.
So maybe the answer here would be
to work with a partner in China who has influence,
although that's less successful than it used to be.
So our takeaways for Chinese regulation
is no loot box is purchasable with real money
or virtual currency.
There's flexible and unclear rules that give the government a lot of enforcement power.
And there's a particular focus from the regulatory entities on preventing these compulsion loops.
There's disclosure requirements that exist in China and in Apple's requirements, but
in practice, these requirements can be designed around or simply ignored.
And then that final point is I'd recommend working with a partner who's established in
China if you're doing these practices there.
So to wrap up my presentation today,
how are loot boxes regulated?
Well, it depends on the regulator.
But there's no major regulation in Western countries
outside of Holland and Belgium.
And there's inconsistent enforcement in China.
And that answer is right.
But there's also a second right answer,
which is how loot boxes are regulated
depends on what everyone in this room does going forward.
Just because as of March 2019,
there's no loot box regulation
doesn't mean there won't be tomorrow.
And whether you realize it or not,
as a developer or a publisher,
you're a part of a collective dialogue
about how we interact with our players,
our customers, and about how we wanna be regulated.
And so I urge you going forward
to be careful how you use loot boxes
and to take simple steps to prevent problems.
Have parental controls that can be enabled
so that young children don't purchase loot boxes.
You can reach out to players who you think might be exhibiting problematic behavior and
who you also think may not have the money to be doing so.
The simplest and most important thing you can do is when your colleagues or your friends
or your parents talk to you about loot boxes, don't paint it as a black and white issue.
Don't just say loot boxes are okay or they're bad because the truth is it's not loot boxes
that are a problem.
which the problem is when loot boxes are used
to do other things, when they're used to create
those compulsion loops to keep players playing longer
than they want to, when they're used to create
pay-to-win mechanics, so players can't win
from their skill or time no matter how long
they play the game.
Loot boxes are a problem when they're not transparent,
when players don't know what's going on.
And when we frame the discussion as solving
these other problems, I think we realize
that there's all sorts of game mechanics
that can run into these issues.
And the key is how we use the mechanics,
not whether we use them.
To be clear, I'm not worried about a world
where this is regulated.
I don't want this regulated, but I'm
OK with it being regulated.
But I'm concerned that the people who
are going to pass the regulations aren't gamers.
They're not lawyers like me who spend their days working
on these issues.
And that instead of getting this regulated,
what we're going to get is all of this regulated.
And by having those thoughtful discussions,
by shaping the dialogue in a way
that highlights the real issues,
while acknowledging that oftentimes loot boxes are fine,
we can prevent entering this world
where all this is regulated.
Thank you so much.
I really appreciate you taking the time
to come to today's talk.
I've put my contact info up on the board.
I don't know if we have time for questions,
but if we don't, I will be in the wrap up room.
There's tables down the hall right outside of 305.
I'm happy to stick around and talk about these issues
for as long as you guys would like.
The other reminder I'll give you
is to please fill out your feedback surveys.
Last year after I presented, I'll say I was really impressed
with the detailed feedback you gave
and the positive feedback about what I could do better,
what I could do more of.
Hopefully I've incorporated that this year
and I'll try and incorporate it next year too.
So thank you so much, guys.
Oh, I don't know if we're, no questions?
Yeah.
Yeah, we have five minutes left.
Oh, okay.
So, more than welcome.
So I'll stay up here and ask questions until the...
Yeah, no, I just had a quick question of, I was just wondering how, you know, do you
see this as evolving? I mean, there's all the, you know, there's definitely everyone's
sort of, especially Europe, has, you know, had a lot of sort of privacy rights and a
lot of, you know, movement on other fronts as far as, you know, rights of the consumer.
Do you see this as like, oh, we've kind of settled down or, oh my gosh, it's changing
every year?
I think it will change.
I don't think it's going to change in the next year.
Now, who knows?
Maybe next year there'll be presentation loot boxes,
everything I said last year was wrong,
and there'll be a bunch of changes.
But no, I don't think short-term change is likely.
But I do think we're going to see very slow movement
to recognize these issues.
At least in the US, the FTC is holding a workshop.
They've yet to set a date, but sometime in the next six
months, they'll have a discussion.
And I'm hopeful that's going to be really valuable,
because they'll have the opportunity
to hear not just from parents and players who
are having issues on their side, but also from the developers
about what they're doing.
And I'm hoping what we get to is a place where they identify
a couple really bad practices and prohibit just
those really bad practices, and otherwise let
us do what we want in our games.
So that's where I see it going.
That's where I hope it's going.
And I don't think we're going to see any legislative change
in the next 12 months.
Thank you.
Yes.
Thank you, by the way.
Great presentation.
I was wondering if you could provide some more detail
on defining or proving or disproving a compulsion loop.
It sounds like it's rather subjective, something
that might be compulsive for me, might not
be compulsive for someone else.
So how do you kind of navigate that?
Sure, look, I think that's a fabulous question.
I think that highlights a reason I
don't want to see a Chinese-style regulation
in the West, because it's really hard to define those things.
I will say sort of the counter to that is,
you know, going back to my slide in here, I'll...
You know, going back to this slide,
it's clear the desire here is to get the player
to spend more than they would spend
before you adjusted the odds.
And so although it is hard to define,
there are cases where it's pretty clear
that's what you're doing.
And I'm not exactly sure how I would design a regulation
to prohibit this sort of stuff without being over-inclusive.
And like I just said, I'm hoping that the FTC is
thoughtful about that, that we have a discussion.
And what we result with is very targeted rules.
that sort of prohibits specific practices.
But I agree, it's hard to define, and I think one
of the challenges you face operating in China
and with that sort of regulation.
Okay. Thanks.
Yes.
I was curious about that definition of transferability
that Holland is using right now, if that's
exclusive to just primary marketplaces,
or if there is like, in my mind, there
is the same ethical quandary if you're
aware of an active secondary marketplace out there,
and you still implement that design choice.
I'm curious how they're kind of drawing the line now.
Sure, so transferability, I think,
is distinguishable from marketplace.
So the line is, do you enable users
to transfer between accounts?
We recognize that users could sell their whole account,
but as long as your game prohibits
any transfer of the items between accounts,
other than selling the whole account,
there's not much the player can do.
And I don't think it's your job to regulate
that third-party marketplace.
But you don't get to go away and say,
oh, we have our terms of service that says, oh, you can't sell
it, but you can transfer it.
That doesn't work.
If it's transferable at all between accounts,
that's a problem.
So that's pretty much the line we see in Holland right now.
Hey, you mentioned talking a lot about fuzzy language
with a lot of the China laws.
We found that we've struggled a lot with that
in Taiwan and Japan too.
There's a lot of fuzzy language
that our publisher is pushing for.
Do you have any tips on how to navigate
when you are encountering foreign language barriers
and there is fuzzy language in the regulations?
Sure, so one strategy is to work with a partner who understands them.
And when that isn't working, to be honest, the best strategy is to formally not be in
that marketplace.
So, most games downloaded in China right now, for example, are not officially licensed games.
And those publishers don't officially market in China.
They just put them up on Steam, and the users use VPNs,
and they get around the government restrictions,
and they download them.
And so there's sort of this all-in or all-out approach.
Like either you're working with a partner,
you're hiring lawyers, you're actively interfacing
with the government to figure out what works.
And for large companies, that works well.
For small companies, for companies
that are sort of still emerging,
honestly, I think the best practice
is to not formally be in that market.
but then still hope that your player base
builds an active community.
And that's very luck driven, and it's frustrating.
But honestly, I think that's the best solution
if you don't have the funds to really engage.
Thanks.
So it seems that.
Kind of the major problem with the hypothetical
is a non-flat rarity within the types.
I was wondering if you think it is arguable
that wildcard systems, kind of like Magic Arena's system
where you're accumulating a wildcard
that then gives the player a choice,
allows you to get away with non-flat rarity schemes
easier than without such systems.
Sure, I mean, that's an interesting question, right?
When you say get away with, let's start with,
these are Apple's requirements.
And my understanding is the magic platforms
that currently exist are not yet on iOS.
Maybe they're moving in that direction.
But at least as of when I was last playing,
it was PC only.
So there's no formal requirements
they have to comply with for Apple.
I'm not sure it makes it easier to get around,
although you'll notice here I put magic cards up here.
And I think what's really interesting
about how Wizards of the Coast is doing magic,
there's actually three different models.
You have physical cards that are transferable.
You have digital cards that are transferable
on their old platform.
And now their newest platform has digital cards
that aren't transferable.
So we sort of see them moving towards a regime
where they're not transferring.
And certainly in Holland, right,
I guess that sort of gets around the issue
because you don't have transferability.
This is probably a long way of saying I don't have an answer for your question.
I haven't really thought about how wildcards affect that.
I'm sort of skeptical that you could just include wildcards and get around it, but right
now it's sort of the wild west anyway.
Hey, thanks for the presentation.
Is there a noted line, bright or otherwise,
or substantive difference with loot boxes
that are for purchase versus granted
as some sort of progression that you've seen,
meaning more lax restrictions on things
that are used to be rewards that you can't actually purchase?
Is there a delineation anywhere?
Sure, absolutely.
Certainly in Holland, I mean, throughout all of Europe,
there's a delineation.
You can have progression-based loot boxes
in both Holland and Belgium, so long as they're not
paying real money for it.
In the West, what we see, almost all the entities attaching
some requirement to is real money.
Even the ESRB, which sort of lumps them
all in with their general purchases,
the key is that you're paying money for it.
In China, no, there's not a distinction there.
And in fact, those additional rules about compulsion loops
mainly apply to those sort of mechanics
because you can't purchase them to begin with.
So the only time that compulsion loop rules
are going to come into play is when you're offering
those boxes through gameplay.
Thanks.
Awesome, well, perfect.
We are right at the end time now.
So thank you so much.
I appreciate all your questions.
I appreciate you all coming.
And again, I'm going to go down to the tables outside 305
if you want to chat some more.