You guys ready to get started?
Hey, Lee!
Awesome. Well, welcome.
It's a privilege to be here on behalf of our amazing development teams in Seattle and in Alaska
to represent a very special project called Never Alone.
It's so good to see a few friendly faces in the crowd.
And I'm happy to be here spending time with you today
to describe quite a special project that we've been on
for the last two and a half years.
Quick show of hands, how many of you
have heard of Never Alone?
Amazing.
OK, this is going to go great.
How many of you played the game?
All right.
How many of you finished the game?
OK, good.
We're doing good.
We've been learning a whole new way of making games and have experienced a depth of purpose of game development that none of us ever thought was possible.
So it's incredibly exciting to be here among peers to share a little bit about that experience.
I recognize that everyone's very busy today.
There are a lot of amazing talks going on.
So I'm going to give a quick overview of what we're going to be focusing on today.
We're going to introduce Never Alone
and the people who inspired the creation of the game.
We're going to focus on the game's visual style.
I have a very special guest here today who's going to take the bulk of the talk.
We're going to discuss how we achieved true infusion of a culture in a game
and discuss the impact that the game has had around the world.
My name is Sean Vessi.
I'm the creative director on the project.
If you had told me at any point over the last 20 years while I was working on games about
blowing shit up, I would have told you that someday I'd have the opportunity to do something
that I love to do, make games, but make games that have lasting, meaningful impact, I would
have told you you were crazy.
So it's a bit surreal for me to be here talking about the adventure we've been on.
I'm here today and I'm happy that you to meet a colleague and a good friend of mine, Dima
Varjovka, our art director.
Hey guys.
Dima worked tirelessly to appropriately represent the spirit of a people.
He and the rest of our team became students of their culture and traditions,
and he managed to develop a truly signature visual style
that's garnered a tremendous amount of attention from players around the world.
I'd also like to introduce you to, virtually, to a woman named Gloria O'Neill.
She is the President and CEO of the Cook Inlet Tribal Council.
She and her leadership team should be credited with the original vision of creating a game
to share and extend her culture's mythology, values, and worldviews.
And she challenged us.
to make a game that would catalyze the curiosity of a modern gaming audience
to develop a hunger to learn about world culture.
And that's what we set off to do two and a half years ago.
We're members of E-Line and a newly formed company called Upper One Games.
We develop games for evolving minds.
We believe that games can offer curious gamers
eager to expand their worldview,
fun, entertaining experiences.
And the kinds of games that we want to make
require being adept at forging lasting partnerships.
These are a few of the groups, the foundations,
and organizations who we work with on a regular basis.
Folks like the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation,
the Public Broadcasting System,
the Smithsonian.
But one of the deepest and most meaningful partnerships that we forged recently is with
the Cook Inlet Tribal Council, who introduced us to over 40 Alaska Native elders, storytellers,
artists, and social entrepreneurs.
These people are featured in the game through Cultural Insights.
You get to hear from their voice aspects of their culture that are contextually relevant
to the gameplay that gamers play.
These ambassadors gave us their time, their experience, and their wisdom, and most importantly, their trust.
And we took that trust very seriously. It was a serious responsibility that we felt that we had as game developers to uphold their values and to create a game that would make their community proud.
And we're tremendously grateful for the opportunity to have such wonderful, creative collaborators.
I'm going to play a quick trailer for those of you who may not have seen it to get a sense for kind of what we were after in making the game.
Don't do it!
So many of you may not know this, but the game's fiction is based on an Inupiaq legend
called Kunuk Sayuka.
It was passed down for generations and told to us through the oldest living relative of
a man named Robert Nasrik Cleveland.
He's the man pictured here.
He was a master storyteller who died in the 70s, but he passed down the story of an endless
blizzard and a young protagonist.
who goes out in the world to find the source of the blizzard
and ends up being challenged to restore balance to nature.
The game explores the theme of interdependence.
It's a central value of the Inupiaq.
And it's explored through the two main characters
of the Inupiaq girl and her unlikely companion,
an arctic fox.
Each have respective skills and abilities
that they have to work together to overcome obstacles.
At this point, I want to turn it over to Dima,
who's going to discuss the visual style of the game.
Thank you, Sean.
I'm happy to be here, guys.
And before I start to talk about the visual style,
I would like to go a little bit and tell about my background.
So I've been in the industry more than 15 years now,
working on different kind of games for various platforms.
But I've never been part of such an amazing project
as Never Alone.
It's truly a creative project.
My background, I'm a traditional artist, and to find a project like that is really something special.
I grew up in Odessa, Ukraine, which is like a beautiful place on the Black Sea.
I graduated from St. Petersburg Academy of Art with a master's degree in fine art and architecture design.
Early days of my career, I started to work like a...
game designer, sculpting toys for various clients.
One of them, like lots of them, it was Disney.
I worked with Hasbro.
metal and many more. And I come to the realization that if I can do it in clay, why can't I do it on a computer. And I learned the computer and the first job was at Zuper Interactive, back then it was a small company. And I've been a key member and I started working as a character artist and become a lead artist running a bigger team there.
Work on titles like Solcom, the entire Solcom series, Mac,
unit 13.
And now I'm happy where I am.
I'm working at Eli Media, working on games like Never
Alone, culture games.
So let's talk about the visual style now.
What is important?
Like any new project you start, you need to be inspired first.
Like you really need to know what you want to talk about.
So you need to set some goals.
In our case, it's probably everyone wants to make a game
really beautiful, special, to find some kind of a special,
unique look that stands out from the slew of games coming
out every year.
But most important thing, because this game is about
people, about certain culture, this visual style needs to
reflect the culture.
Needs to reflect the people.
We need to reflect what they're.
motivation, what their values are, and the other thing is important to kind of capture the beauty of the place where they live.
And kind of more, the third one is like universal, but like any visual design you do, they need to support the actual design of the game.
And to support and extend the gameplay experience.
But first, before saying how you want to really create the game, what you really want to put there, you need to figure out who first, and then figure out how to do that.
Because lots of people, including me back then when I worked in another company, just...
You're thinking how to create the shader, some kind of a
special subsurface scattering here and stuff like that.
But you're really not thinking why you're doing all that.
It might be not necessary, what kind of message you
wanted to deliver.
And to us, because the message is about the culture, we really
need to go and study who these people are.
I'm going to give you really basic information, something that you probably can find online.
And it's important to understand who these people are.
They live in Inupiaq.
It's Inupiaq people, Inupiaq culture.
They live all the way up north in Alaska, at the very, very top.
And it's total, like around 12,000 people live up there.
Live in a harsh environment.
Like average temperature in the winter, minus 21 degrees.
It's like, it's not that it's average.
That means sometimes it's minus 50.
First time we went there, it was minus 35.
And it's cold.
Like, I live like in St. Petersburg.
I never experienced that cold ever.
So like, it's like minus 35, you don't know what to do.
It's like five minutes outside, you don't,
you want to go inside.
But how these people live, they're still practicing
like subsistence living.
So they hunt.
And it's two different groups.
Like one of them live on the coastal, the other people live
like inland.
And based on where they live, people from Kostel, they harvest seals, whales, all sorts
of sea animals.
And people from inland, they harvest caribou, different types of birds.
What's very special about these people that we kind of like noticed, and that's something
that we wanted to put in the game and translate that, these people incredibly...
War.
Like, they, like, because even though they live there, their hospitality, like every
time we come there, they just, like, invite us to their houses.
And willing to share their wisdom with us, willing to tell their stories.
So for us, it's like, it becomes like almost our family.
And also, like, these people have very rich and incredible tradition of storytelling.
That's something, like, we're like, okay, that's worth to tell.
That's worth to, like, share the stories.
I jumped here, but I will say that's the Barrow.
Barrow is like, that's the first place when we went there.
It's Barrow, Alaska.
That's where we went.
It's like the most northern place in Alaska.
It's like 5,000 people live there.
You can imagine, that's where Seattle, that's
where we travel from, all the way up there.
Like when people say, when are you going again to Alaska?
I'm saying, it's not just Alaska.
It's to Barrow.
And it's very necessary to pull out your phone
and to show where it is.
Because we went to Alaska 12 times, we went to Barrow three times, and it's a special experience.
We went first time in the winter, and it was dark.
It all, like the whole day dark.
It was a window of like maybe two hours when the sun rise, and then you go to the, we went to pizza,
and then like another hour and the sun goes down.
You're like, okay, that's it, that's it.
Something that you can't experience anywhere else.
And then we went in May.
That's the picture I took.
That's one picture.
It's 2 PM.
And the other one is 2 AM.
It's like light all day.
It's like stepping out onto the planet Hoth.
Exactly.
It's just like you're in a different world.
What we did over there.
We met with elders, first of all. Elders, there's a huge respect there for elders.
And people like, the image that you see here is like Sean talking to Nene Gray.
She is one of the daughters of Robert Cleveland. He is the storyteller.
And what we did there, we would talk to them, we kind of trying to get like what the essence
we wanted, like what's important about the culture.
Because what's on the surface everybody understands, yeah they hunt, they do certain things, but
for us it wasn't the goal.
We really wanted to show something special, something that they potentially can lose.
And that's their spirituality.
And we also talked to kids, because kids, like, talking to kids is always fun.
You're asking them, like, what's your favorite story?
Tell us the story that you really like.
Because we were looking what, to find the right story, story that we can tell in a game.
And kids told us lots and lots of stories that...
Help us to kind of understand what is important to them.
What is the character there?
Like, for example, one of the characters, like little people,
it came straight from them.
Like, we were asking, like, what do you want to talk?
Like, tell us, like, the character that you want.
Like, what's the special kind of a character?
And all of them, like, it's a little people.
Be afraid of them.
They live somewhere around us.
It was interesting.
So what also we did, we met with artists.
I personally, I mean, because I'm artist in my background,
like I am a sculptor.
So to me, meeting the people that I,
I was introduced to the Inupiaq art, to Inuit art,
way back when I was in academy.
And I also carved in a soapstone to see actually,
and meet people who behind the scenes,
so like to meet with them and talk.
It was an amazing experience.
So that's on this image.
It's John Huffley, a really good artist.
He showed me his latest work, and we
talk about overall what's important for him,
and kind of like he shared the ideas.
That all gave us the ideas, what we wanted to put in the game,
what we wanted to translate in the game.
We researched the art.
And if you look at the art, like,
Just what stands out?
Stands out like they have like very original composition.
They're using like unique materials,
materials that's only in that land,
like ivory or baleen.
They're mixing materials.
But the most important thing,
what actually stands out to me,
is the quality, the really like handcrafted quality,
every piece.
You feel the love, you feel the warm hands of the people, the creators, the artists.
And even though we're creating the game and it's digital, one of the big goals is to bring
this quality into the game.
We don't want a digital kind of like impress somebody, look how it's glowing, look at this
effect.
We really wanted to bring this love into the game.
And it was like one of the goals.
We talked to the scientist, and that's Aaron Crowell, amazing guy.
He studied Alaska and Alaskan people 20 years.
And we were lucky.
We went behind the scenes in the Smithsonian Museum in Anchorage.
He showed us different tools, explained to us how people live, too.
It was very, very interesting.
And we participated in a community event.
Like, just by looking at this image, you're probably thinking, like, what is that?
What's going on there?
We were lucky, it's not happens every day, but we arrived with Sean and the same day
they caught the whale.
It was 2 o'clock in the morning, even though it's bright, that's how 2 o'clock in the morning
looks like.
We were part of that, so we're pulling the whale with the community, 40 feet bowhead whale, and celebrating with them.
It's like everyone there on the snow, kids, elders, everyone.
It was very amazing.
Like, I can talk one hour just about that, because all my friends, they're asking specifically that part.
We try Muck Talk. Muck Talk is a whale blubber.
The way they cook it, they just throw it in the snow and it sits there for an hour and
it's ready to eat.
It was interesting too.
So we got inspired.
It was like all these trips gave us inspiration.
That's something that I said at the very beginning.
Inspiration.
We got that.
The next step, mood board.
So we need to, like, I really like to, like,
it's a lot of thousands, pictures, videos,
so we put everything on the wall.
It's a long wall.
That's one of the examples how the wall looks like.
And we look at that, what stands out?
What is important?
What we really wanted to tell, how, what's,
like the colors, right?
The northern lights, something really special
just need to be there.
People.
Wearing traditional clothing, for sure, yes.
And clothing, like, it's all fur and animals.
We, like, art, the traditional art.
All that need to be in the game.
How to do that?
Let's find out.
So that's one of the first images I drew,
but it's kind of a special image to me
because that's the image that kind of gave us the direction.
That's the image that's connecting the real world
and the spirit world.
It's surreal.
It's not like how we did the spirits in the game,
but this picture has the soul.
It's something that we're like, OK, I
wanted to make a game like that.
So it was a very important one.
The second one also, like it's desaturated, the water, because
it's a lot of water there, how it looks like the boat, water,
and for the contrast, the white fox.
This image, I don't know how many people saw, but that's the
image of an ice floe in the shape of a whale.
The reason why, because in European people, they really
believe everything alive, everything has a soul, and land
because it's all like.
And in this case, I tried to imagine how, if that's an ice
lull, how they will move.
And they don't necessarily need to move like ice lulls,
because they have a soul.
They can move some kind of different.
Also, the beautiful water of Arctic Ocean,
you can't pass that.
It's just amazing colors.
We have that in the game, too.
And that's one of the first images
when we start to draw.
Just the idea of how the village looks like, what's in the village, what's the structure there.
We researched two pigs, what kind of boats they have, and kind of the first understanding how to make the characters, what kind of style.
So that's important work, right?
I show you five images, and now I
know what kind of game I wanted to make.
It's important to go through that process.
So what we want to do, we want atmospheric to capture
tundra, the space.
We want a soft rendering.
We want authentic colors.
We're basically using the colors that's there from ice, from
water.
And handcrafted feel, the one that's very important to me,
that I said, because this love needs to be
translated into the game.
That's important quality.
That image we took in May, that's how Tundra looks like.
Amazing, beautiful, atmospheric, moody.
But wait, we're making the platform a game.
Good luck to make the platform a game in that environment.
There's just really nothing there, right?
Like it's no variety.
OK, what I'm going to do?
What you really want, you want that.
You want something to jump on, to jump off.
You work out how to get it.
It's ice.
It's gray.
So we were really lucky.
We started to research the Inupiaq land
and we find this place.
It's called King Island.
King Island is a fishing village.
It's built on the steep slopes.
It's built on the island on the steep slopes.
And it's just amazing.
Look at the structure.
Looks really interesting.
Something that I didn't see before.
And it's perfect for platform.
It's like a platform, right?
Like you're like, yeah, we want to use this.
That's great.
The other thing is this. Trees. But the thing is, like, first
when we started the project, everybody said, like, oh, it's
no trees there. It's like, it's too north, too far north, no
trees. But actually, in Nupiak land, because it's so big,
inland, they have the area called Anaktuvik Pass. And
Anaktuvik Pass, actually, they do have trees. That's the image
of Anaktuvik Pass. That's where it's located. It's between
River, Anaktuvik, and John River.
The way actually our story, the person who translated the story, he is from Anaktuvik
Pass.
And we were happy about that so we can use branches as platforms.
And iSlow, of course.
Just look at this image.
Isn't that inspirational?
Just by looking at the image like that, somebody said, make a game about this.
It's easy to make a beautiful game just by looking at the image.
It's colors coming out, it's atmosphere.
different shapes. For us it's like a clay. You can build whatever. It's a sculpture in the water.
And for designers it's like they can do whatever they want.
It's like really good material to work with.
So we found the locations.
And we start the project kind of like, OK, we know where we go.
We know what we want.
We know what kind of colors we wanted to do.
And that's the image on top.
That's real images from Bearer.
And below, that's kind of the image from the game,
early image from the game.
But important to have kind of a palette.
Like I don't want to, like when.
I give the, like we're working and trying to figure out like the range of the colors.
You not go and use like all the colors in the world.
Like you really like that's my range, that's what I'm going to use.
So for Tundra that was the range.
And we start the process.
So that's how the game looks like.
Like at the very beginning it just looked like that.
Oh, sorry.
What's happened?
Hang on one second, sorry guys.
We crashed the system. It was awesome. Awesome. Covered. So
That's how we start. The game built in 3D, that's important.
Like, we used Unity, we didn't know Unity.
We started the project, it was two artists, me and a really good friend of mine, Casey McDonald.
And we'd never, I mean, all my experience is 3D games.
I don't know how to do 3D games.
And we choose, okay, let's learn at least one thing, Unity.
Let's not figure out how to do 2D games.
So we use 3D.
And that's how it looks.
It's not bad from the beginning, but how you can
improve, what is important.
First thing we did, we did the vignetting.
So I'll just go here and just show what vignetting does.
It's kind of framing the whole thing, and it's easier for you
to see what's important.
You're looking at the characters and the character
path. But when you look at the background, and the background,
this kind of noise.
Especially that the game that we're building, it's a 2D game.
You're going from left to right, up and down.
You can't really travel in depth.
There's too much of an information.
You don't need to go there.
It actually suggests you to go, but you can't give you a
different vibe.
Not the right vibe.
So what we did was blur everything.
We used a depth of field.
And that was one of the ideas, to make a really soft rendering
game.
But it also helps you to focus on the character,
focus on the path.
And everything else is there, but now I
don't need to go there.
I don't know what's there.
And the third one, very important in my opinion,
is to highlight the path.
I will go here and show you what the highlight.
Yeah.
So highlight the path, critical.
Because it kind of tells you, like, you go right, especially
when it's a ledger, so I'll show you more examples later on.
But that's kind of finalized the look.
So when we got that, that's the formula.
That's the formula of Never Alone that I just
showed you in five minutes.
It's easy to explain to the artist.
The only thing, we built the game.
I do like my normal day, I do like 5-10 paint overs every day, just paint on top.
Like I grab the screens, if I see something like not following the direction or some too
much things going on in the background, distracting, I will just erase that, smooth it out, change
it and then just put it in the game.
But that's the process.
I think it's a simple one.
So it's another palette that's a village palette, a little bit
warmer, real images over there, and the game is down there.
So again, we set up the range of colors.
And that's the image from the game.
Very important is composition.
We were lucky because we have control of the.
camera, we know where is the character going to be.
We really said, OK, I wanted this bridge.
I wanted people to see it, because it's about to collapse,
or collapsed already.
You need to be there.
I want to compose the shots.
And because of the nature of the game, you can do that.
That's huge.
Ice caves, another palette.
One of my favorite.
And you see, I explain to you the path that we highlighted.
If you look at the top of the ice flows, it's highlighted.
And how we highlight, we're not using,
actually it's also important, we use only one light,
directional light.
Everything else is painted.
Painted in vertices, so we paint vertices.
And that's the artist, they paint the vertices
to tell you I can come out on the left
or I can come out on the right.
I can't go in depth, I can't go anywhere, I can just do these two things.
Frame the shot, and now it's big, if something big is about to happen, we need to understand
what to do, how to solve the puzzle, frame it.
Coastal Village palette, also an interesting one, because the whole palette is desaturated,
it's very dark, the only thing is saturation comes from the northern lights.
Very bright and green.
So again, it could be really dark, but look at the planks.
We highlight the planks.
It's not realistic, but it's a nice contrast to have in the
image.
That's amazing creatures, that's amazing story, and this story I really want you to hear directly from the community.
That's one of the examples of our Culture Insights. We have 40 minutes of Culture Insights.
We actually recorded 40 hours of Culture Insights, and we boiled down to only 40 minutes.
But through the whole game, lots of you guys already played the game.
We kind of like...
unlock culture insights. To me it's like it's really really special
material so I wanted to share specifically this story.
When I was young my mom whenever the Northern Lights came out she just whistle
Boy they come alive just keep whistling in that Aurora Welsh
Just like, you know, you can almost hear it.
And then she explained to me a little bit later that those are children.
And children who've passed away when they're children.
You don't want to draw them in too much, you know, is what she said.
Because then they could play football with your head.
Play Eskimo football.
And that's what they want to do.
They're always playing with children up there.
Don't play out without your hood on.
If you don't have your hood on, the Aurora person is going to come down and chop your
head off and play ball with your head.
It wasn't like they were trying to do bad, you know, or it was like a scary story or
anything like that.
It was just that's how it was, that's what it was.
Great story, right?
I would like to talk now, let's go to the character development really quick.
How we develop characters.
First, inspiration that comes from Inupiaq art and from the real people.
On the right you see the little girl wearing Inupiaq parka, traditional clothing, made from the caribou.
on the left you see the art. It's traditional art. It's the sculpture and the graphics.
So the whole process, because we wanted to represent the culture, not to create some
kind of a unique looking beautiful girl. The girl or people that actually
reflects the culture.
If you're looking at the row in the middle,
they kind of fit. It feels like it's from the same world.
And that was the very important quality.
Even when we present our thinking behind our characters,
that's how we present to the community.
We're not just doing this kind of looking goal like we want.
We present it like that.
And for them, it's like, first of all, it's interesting to see our thinking process.
They're like, it's not like they even realize, but they're like, yes, that's what we like.
We really like the characters like that.
Because it's very subjective. I spent like 10 years working on the characters.
It depends what you do. Some people want this, other people want that.
North Korea. I worked like Sokom and it was like the girl from South Korea.
And for them she's beautiful, but for Europeans not.
And it's like a lot of different things going into that.
But I want to talk. So like it's the main characters, girl and the folks.
And...
important? Like, golf, she is like a brave girl, going on
this journey, fearless, and fox as a companion has like other
qualities. Very cute and very fast, small, can get in a small
places, playful, but...
It wasn't that easy for us to figure out why, first of all, why we did the GIL.
Lots of people said that they... not like lots of people asking, and that was kind of a debate, even internally.
why we're not making a boy, why boy is not the main character.
And we felt like, because it's not a kind of violent game,
it's a game about you to understand the world,
tune to the world, to figure out what's around you.
We felt like golf is the better character
because we don't have weapons, we don't fight,
we're not doing anything kind of fast and violent.
But the other reason, so like it fits better for this kind of a game, and the other reason we feel like
girl characters, female characters, are very underrepresented in the game. So if they're
presented, they're presented like in such a kind of stereotypical way that we really would like to change.
Third one, very personal, we all like Sean has two daughters, I have two daughters, but
I never play games with my daughters.
Because like all my experience before it was like shooting games, they have no interest
to play games like that.
And like we thought like if we'll make the game where the girl is the main protagonist,
it's a high chance.
And actually in fact that's the first game I played with my daughter.
We enjoy time together.
So it's like.
That's why. And the fox, it also wasn't that easy for us to
decide because at the very beginning we said yeah we do
want to have a fox but when we showed to the community members
that's a girl and that's a fox they liked it but some of them
approached us and said you know what?
Here in Alaska, we're really teaching kids not to play with fox because they have rabies.
And maybe you can change the character on something else, like a dog, or maybe a wolf,
or maybe an owl.
And I even did like this, like images, started kind of thinking how it's going to look, drew
like different variations.
But it wasn't just images.
We spent three months of the development redesigning the game, making the game with a bigger animal,
or the wolf.
It's kind of like we had to change the design and we did it, but still we were not satisfied with the result.
It kind of feels like the goal becomes less important, the other character, the wolf, becomes stronger and more powerful.
And that wasn't the goal. We wanted the goal to be more important.
And we came back after presenting the new design, presenting everything, but we said we really feel the goal...
And the fox is a better combination.
It's better to build this warm feeling between them.
And that's what we ask them for permission.
And they say, OK, you did the job.
We see what you're talking about.
And they agree that we can leave the fox in the game.
So that's kind of my process of concepting the characters.
It's not like I did it before for other games,
but for this one it feels like really natural.
I drew all the images in black and white,
just kind of a fast sketch just to get the proportions and stuff.
But the thing is, because in that kind of style,
it instantly starts to look like it's indigenous kind of images.
Lots of people mistake it,
they're saying that some kind of indigenous artist did,
or like a native artist.
So that's why I'm kind of a little bit proud.
I said, like, after two years and two and a half years
of development, I didn't learn the Inupiaq language.
I learned a couple words.
But I learned how to draw in Inupiaq.
So people don't even know.
And I wanted to show you, like, this character that's
a bad guy, guys who know, like, it's a manslayer.
And like I said, like, because people really warm there,
like, they're.
We wanted to, like, even the bad guys shouldn't be, like, really a monster or the kind of,
like, he's bad, he's chasing you, but, like, we don't want to make him, like, evil.
So I have a feeling if I will sit with these guys around the fire, I would be able to kind
of chat with him and he will warm it up.
So that's also kind of part of the design.
And besides just the normal characters,
we have supernatural characters.
Characters that can shift from animals to people,
and from people to animals.
So I wanted you to hear from our writer, Ishmael Hope,
what the story, why that happens.
Also, I want to say, tomorrow Ishmael is going to be here.
He's a great guy.
He's a writer in our game.
And he's going to do the presentation at 4 o'clock,
I believe, with Sean, talking about the stories.
And let's.
We are taught that there's no hierarchy.
It's not everything else.
And then.
Man, you know, humans on top and they're separate from everything.
We're taught that everything is equal and that all the animals have a human form or
can be seen in a human form.
And so they have just as much or more intelligence.
You know, in fact, have a lot to teach people.
And so that's how these transformations can happen.
It's if the animal wants you to see it in its human form.
There's a story where a man comes up to an ice hole
and then realizes there's another man in his parka
that's got stuck in the net, you know,
and he's just stuck like that.
Oh, can you let me out?
Please help me.
You know, and so then he lets the man out, but then realizes that was actually a seal.
That was a seal man. And just because that seal wanted that help,
that seal allowed itself to be seen in human form.
It's great.
That's, uh, on the left, that's one of the characters like that.
Ookpeck, he transformed from...
a person, it's kind of, owls in Inupiaq is like wisdom.
But the process is the same, creating them also based on the Arctic Dolls and masks and
real people and it's like the image, kind of the sketch of him and that's how he looks
in the game.
And that's the people that I said, little people, the people that the story that we heard from kids, and then we start to ask all the other people.
And they, they really like, seems like believable because like I asked the lady, she was like around 55 and tell me the story of how she'd been chased by the little people.
And I like started asking like more like, tell me like how, how big they are.
And she's like, like that.
I
think
the underground and they're coming out and they steal things. They're kind of a leprechauns in
a new world. They're very strong too. They can lift the caribou and can lift like big rocks like that.
And that's how that looks in the game. Them stealing drum.
So now I would like to talk about world of spirits.
And that probably was one of the most challenging things for
us to do, because worlds of spirits, at the very beginning,
we designed the game that way so you can be in real world,
and then you can go in a spirit world.
And our designers really wanted to have the button there that
you can press and go in one world, and then press one, and
then go to another one.
And they wanted to have this control.
controlling these two worlds.
And it was compelling design, and it worked.
But when we show it to the community and to Alaska guys,
and they were like, we like that.
What do you guys think?
And they're like, listen, and look at us.
And they're like, you know, it's not that easy.
It's no button in the world that we can press and go
from world to world to another.
It's not on demand.
It's something.
It's a one world.
Where it's like spirits and real world, they believe, coexist in one place.
And to see them, you need to earn it.
You need to kind of be good, you need to be a good hunter, you need to respect the community.
You can't really press the button, it just gives them the wrong feelings.
And we're like, okay, that means we need to change.
And that's actually one of the examples of how we work with the community.
Because of that kind of conversations, their advice is we need to change the design.
And that's not just to change one image, it's just change our thinking, how we think about the world.
And that's a big deal.
And I want to add, like, that's one of the most inspirational.
I really like you to hear about Sila from the community,
because it's a very interesting and very spiritual video.
Sila is the weather.
It also means the atmosphere.
Here's the luna, or the land.
And it's anything from the land into the moon, the sun, the stars.
That's Xilla.
It's very spiritual, and we have a relationship with Xilla.
Xilla has a soul, in the same way we do as people, in the same way animals do.
I think spirit helpers in and of themselves are really about how we're connected with
things.
And so it may be that there is a spirit helper that shows themselves as a bird to show you
the way home.
Or it may be a spirit helper that actually decides to show themselves with the face and
body of a man instead of their animal form.
And so I think one of the things that's hard to understand is that it's not one way of
seeing things.
It's a human reaction.
And so I think that's one of the things that we need to understand.
And I think that's what we need to do.
I think that's what we need to do.
It's one way of knowing you're connected to everything.
We've always had that spirituality of everything around us.
It's the interaction you have with the air you breathe,
the ocean that you gather resources from,
the rivers from which you gather fish,
the tundra from which you pick berries,
the animals that give themselves.
It's all of that.
It's beautiful.
So how we develop the spirits visually,
it's also inspired by the art.
That's one of the examples.
And I will show you the image that I
drew for one of the sketches for our spirits in the game.
And that's how they look in the game.
It's very important, not just how visually, but also
how they move in the world, like very slow,
kind of dreamlike moving.
That's another example of Spirits, quick sketches I did.
But important to have, like, they're not just a platform.
There's something livable, something lives in this world.
And that's how they look in the game already.
I'll go a little faster, but that's another example of them.
What you see right now here is...
Screamshaw. Screamshaw, like a lot of people really like how we did 2D animation to tell this story, but I wanted to tell you how that happened.
What Screamshaw is, it's a very beautiful form of art, traditional form of art for Nupics.
And it's one of the ways they tell the story and pass the story from generation to generation.
So they carve on baleen or ivory.
And when we saw this piece in Anchorage Museum,
it kind of caught our attention.
By just looking at that, it feels
like it's some kind of a story there, something going on.
And we're like, why not to tell the story that way?
Why not to take that kind of a quality of the screenshot
and tell the story?
And I remember when we were flying on the plane,
I did really quick drawings, like a storyboard,
what we can do.
And then we develop.
This kind of style for that so you can animate and our talent and I made there and Fanny
Kind of breathe the life into them and we create
Their screenshots
So what I wanted to tell you about the importance of the
inclusive development.
Like that's me wearing the snow goggles.
But this image is just, I like that, but it's kind of a
symbolic image for us.
Because that's what, when we put these glasses on, we're
trying to pretend that we are in NuPyX.
Trying to understand what they see, how they see the world.
That's the whole process.
The whole process is not us.
We have the idea.
Let's do that.
The process is what they see and how
to share what they see with the rest of the world.
So without this kind of work, we wouldn't
be able to achieve what we achieved.
We wouldn't be able to achieve the look of the game.
The most important, authentic look,
the look that represent the people who live there.
I wanted to say that we got blown away by the reception.
We nominated so many awards.
We like, buffed the next week.
Like today, we game.
We have a lot of games awards here and DICE awards.
But the most important thing, we also have many, many publications,
but the most important is the reception from the community.
And that's something that really touched us and moved us.
Because when people see the game, they really feel that that's the game.
about them. That's the game that represents them. And that was the goal. I want you to
hear what this young gentleman, we met with him in Anchorage during the Youth and Elders
Conference, and I want you to hear what he said.
As soon as I heard the native words, I'm like, man, holy cow.
A slice of culture.
This is cool.
And 25-year-old Vincent Gregory was instantly connected.
This is the way I want to teach right here, exactly this way right here.
It's really nice.
It makes me feel happy to be a native.
Marty Glazer, Channel 2 News.
So what he just said, he said, it makes me be happy.
It makes me happy to be a native.
It's very powerful if somebody actually happy to be who he is
and actually be proud of their culture.
And I think we couldn't ask more.
As a result, I think we achieved everything what we
wanted to achieve.
We made some people happy.
I think I'm satisfied with all this and we want to make more games and we want to make
more happy people.
I wanted to say Kiana and I wanted to say thank you everyone for being here and listening
to us.
Good job.