Hi everyone, thank you so much for coming now I know it is late in the day, the jet
lag is hitting me hard, so I'm going to try to stay awake for the next hour, but seriously
thank you so much for coming at this time, I don't go to talks at 5 o'clock, that's ridiculous,
so you're all amazing people.
So, today's talk.
I did a talk yesterday,
I don't know how many of you were at that one,
but my talk yesterday,
I talked about how badly games are selling on Steam.
It's obviously a problem, it's been a problem for a long time,
but right now it's especially a problem,
and it's a problem that many more people
than ever before are trying to solve themselves.
One of the numbers in my talk yesterday was that I worked out that roughly, just less than 10% of people who are actually releasing games on Steam
essentially are actually making enough money from even just the first month of sales to even continue comfortably on making games.
I mean obviously that doesn't count people who are just kind of doing it as a hobby aside a full job etc.
But if we're talking about actually being in the business of making games,
the vast majority of people aren't able to sustain themselves.
But there are ways to get into that top 7.
A part of the talk I gave yesterday was me essentially saying that, yeah, games aren't
selling so great on Steam, but when people are doing the legwork and they're making a
good game, there are still plenty of people out there who are happy to buy games on Steam.
You just need to be putting the right things in place.
And I guess by being here at this talk.
you are probably one of those people who would like to be one of those top 7%.
Good for you!
Um...
So, I'm Mike.
Uh...
I have been, um...
working in video games for a long time.
I used to write about video games.
I actually went to uni doing computer science to make video games,
and it turned out I was really, really bad at it
because I just found it boring.
So then I decided I'm just going to berate other people who make them and became like a critic.
And as part of what I did when I was writing our games, I did a lot.
I started writing for places like Gamasutra.
I started to do a lot of talking to developers, working out why their games sold.
Then I started to dig into numbers and I found all of this stuff fascinating for some weird reason,
because I'm a lunatic.
And then that sort of led me on to getting hired by the publisher TinyBuild.
We did a bunch of stuff there and had some pretty decent success,
which kind of backed up my egotistical theories.
And then last year I thought,
I can do this myself, it's easy.
Decided to start my own publishing label, No More Robots,
and I've gone gray since then.
So it's been going okay as No More Robots.
I've been using maths, I guess you guys call it math.
to work out how to make games sell.
And I released our first game last month
called Descenders, a downhill mountain biking game
from the beautiful people at Rage Squid, a Dutch studio.
And next week I'm announcing game number two,
which is causing me even more stress, hooray!
So here's just some rough idea of why you should remotely care about any of the words I have to say.
So Descendants came out on February 9th and since then the game has essentially made more money in its first month than Rage Squid's previous game made in its lifetime.
which is fantastic for me because I love the people I work with, I especially love Rage Squid and I wanted to secure their futures
and just in the first month of the game we have definitely done that which is absolutely lovely.
And a lot of other people have been very interested in the game as well, we've been working with Xbox on special...
Behind the scenes things we've been talking to oculus about a vr version because everybody asks for a vr version
Um, I don't think they realize how much they're going to throw up when they actually try to uh to ride a bike in vr
Um, we've got this massive discord server around the game who are
feverish about every single little thing we do.
And it seems like we're gonna make some decent revenue
by the end of the year for the game
across those two platforms.
I mean, the plan then is to bring it to PS4
and Switch and all kinds of things.
So it's gone all right,
which is like a massive sigh of relief for me.
Can you imagine if I just started my own publishing label
and bottled it on the first game?
That would have been really awkward.
So,
So, when I was putting this talk together,
whenever I put talks together like this,
I always try to envision things that you guys
are going to want to know.
And I know that a lot of the time,
people want to know about the basics.
And I've done loads of talks about the basics.
You know, things like is listed here,
just writing press releases.
How do I get YouTubers to care about my game?
How do I get the press to cover it?
Does press coverage do anything?
What can I do with my Steam page?
I decided when putting this talk together that I'm not going to talk about those things
because they've been done to death.
Again, like I say, by me.
If you just go on the GDC Vault, which you have access to with your badges, and enter
my name, you'll see too many talks from me on these things.
So if you want to know about those things, please, a lot of that stuff is still super
relevant.
You can go look that stuff up.
What I really decided I wanted to do was...
talk through when I was setting up No More Robots and when I was trying to decide how to make
Descenders sell, the things that were important that I think ended up being massively important
to what I did, whether I was purposely doing them at the time or not.
because I think that everything I'm about to talk about is...
some of it will be... some of it will end up being a little bit vague,
some of it will be, you know, sort of may or may not apply to you,
but I think a lot of it is just stuff that when we talk about marketing,
we don't really talk about a lot of these things.
So anyway, the main... so the main six points I'm going to talk about...
The one thing that rides through all of these things is that I absolutely hate it when I see people saying that it's all about luck.
And I've seen people say, you just need a bit of magic and all this kind of stuff.
When we were going to announce and release Descenders, I knew it was going to sell.
That might sound egotistical, it might sound like I'm just bigging myself up.
it's because we had done all of the right things and we knew how to position
it and we knew what to do with the marketing for the game that at least X
number of people were going to buy it. I mean eventually more people bought it
than we had hoped for so that was that was nice and you could and of course I'm
not gonna say there's zero luck involved of course there's a sprinkle of luck as
well you know some games will absolutely explode while other similar games won't
do
There's always luck involved in everything, but to say that it's all luck and to say,
oh, you know, some of these biggest games, they just, they got lucky and this game just
was unfortunate, I don't believe in that at all.
And I think that a lot of it is just negating the need for luck, really.
So yeah, these six points here, I'm literally just going to go through these things one by one
and explain exactly what I mean by them and why I think they are super important, especially now.
So number one, working out what is exciting about your game. So here's the thing,
you think that you know what is exciting about your game, but you are wrong.
And that might sound flippant, but I will honestly bet that at least three quarters
of the people in this room who think they know what is exciting about their game are
wrong about what is exciting.
And if I talked to them about their game, I'd say a thing and they'd say, oh, I hadn't
really thought about that as being the exciting thing.
What a lot of people do, and what I sometimes do as well, and have to talk myself out of doing is
you decide on a thing that is exciting about your game, a feature maybe that's exciting about your game
and it is, okay? It is an exciting thing about your game that you think
but it's not forward-facing exciting, it's not like public exciting
it's exciting maybe in a technical standpoint, or it's exciting as an additional thing
But what you actually need is you need the thing that's exciting and it makes people
actually then want to give a crap about your game.
I always need to have stupid terms for everything, so what I like to call this in my head is
the hook and the kicker.
The thing that you are thinking in your head is exciting about your game and maybe the
way you've been selling it is probably the kicker.
The problem with the kicker is that no one will check that out unless you've hooked them first.
You need the hook first to actually reel them in.
That's a stupid metaphor, isn't it?
You need to actually get them and then you hit them with the other thing that sort of seals the deal.
Uh, example.
With Descenders, when we were first talking about how to sell the game,
we were constantly talking about the procedural stuff in the game.
So the whole point in the game is that every single level you ever play in Descenders
is procedurally generated from a string, like a seed of numbers.
And there's hundreds of millions of levels in this game, right?
And the technical stuff that has gone into making that is honestly incredible.
And the guys at Rage Squid are...
just geniuses, but here's the thing,
if I describe this to you, I don't think that on the spot,
I would hook you with that.
I think you'd be like, oh, that sounds pretty impressive,
that sounds kind of cool, but from talking
and telling people about this, it was obvious to me
that it was cool, but it wasn't actually making them
remember the game or want to check more stuff out
about the game.
It turned out that when I just straight up told people
it's a downhill mountain biking game, as stupid as that sounds, I'm literally just
describing what the game is, that was actually way more interesting
to people because they don't know other downhill mountain
biking games, there aren't any. And then if I followed that up with, oh
and hey it's got procedural...
generated worlds, they'd go,
how does that work?
How could a bike game have procedural worlds?
And then I'd have the conversation.
Or then maybe they'd go and check out some more
information. Without
those two things together,
they
complement each other, right? If I just told you
it's a downhill mountain biking game, you might be like,
oh, cool. If I just tell you it's procedural generation,
lots of games are doing
that. The two things together...
work such that you actually come out of the conversation maybe wanting to see some more.
This is what you need to be trying to find, basically.
You need to...
That line you keep saying to everyone, right?
That line that every single time someone asks you,
what are you making and what's that game about?
Think about that line that you say to people.
Is it actually interesting?
Like, is it an actual interesting line
where if someone said that to you in a bar tonight
where you're obviously going to go and do that tonight,
when someone does that, are they going to go...
me and want a card and then or are they gonna be like okay cool do you know if
there's anywhere else that has a free bar so this is this is honestly the
thing this is and with every game I'm working with I'm tirelessly just trying
to work out what is that exciting line that has these two elements in it where
I go it's this cool thing and by the way it's this as well and make them want to
read more it's it's it's just one of those things where it's
I honestly feel like this is such a simple point and yet
we just all still get it wrong, right?
I still get it wrong.
Even when I was first doing descenders,
I was getting this wrong.
It's so easy to not get this line in place
in the first place.
you need this. And the thing with this as well is that it can actually then end up just helping you
through all of the decisions you make, not just on the marketing side, but on the design side as well,
right? It can really help to kind of hone in on, all right, well, what is the game? It's this thing.
So these features are the most important thing that we need to be talking about.
So yeah, have a real think about this. So once you've got that,
Let's say you're at the point where you really want to get people interested in your game.
The main problem I think that a lot of people have at this point is,
you'll put out a trailer, or you'll put out a website, or anything like that, a press release,
and it might do amazingly. I've seen people put out trailers that have got quarter of a million views.
Absolutely fantastic.
The problem a lot of the time is that then people,
this quarter of a million people watch the trailer
and then they go.
I was pretty cool.
And then they just go somewhere else on the internet
and your game is forgotten five minutes later.
And especially if you're announcing your game
and six months later you're launching,
six months later they're not remembering your trailer.
They've seen a million other trailers on YouTube.
They've seen trailers as ads on YouTube.
They're not gonna remember your trailer from six months ago.
So what are you doing to make sure that when they watch that trailer they've actually then got somewhere to go and something...
It's going to be a small number of people, right? Those quarter of a million people aren't going to want to connect with your game.
But even if just 1% of those people want to connect with your game, that's a massive number of people who, if you could get them and contain them somewhere...
uh... then uh... that would be pretty nice
uh... the answer that i have found
uh... is is as simple as discord
uh... i started experimenting with discord
two years ago.
Anybody who knows me knows that I always try to
stay on top of the things that I think are gonna
kind of be the next big thing.
And Discord at that point was already massive,
but it was massive mainly for players.
There was some developers on there,
but it was a great place for,
I mean, just like IRC and not a crap,
it was not a crap Skype basically.
But the thing with Discord is that
they have a lot of users, I don't know if you know this.
They've got like over 100 million
registered people on Discord now.
And that is a lot of people.
And so I decided, after I'd done a bit of experimenting,
I was trying to, when I, at the company I was at before,
we were trying to sort of collect people together
who were excited about our games into a Discord.
And it was fine.
We got a few hundred people in it, maybe.
But the problem I realized very quickly is that if you don't give people an incentive to join some kind of community like that,
then they don't.
And it's funny actually, I feel like a lot of the time there's so many talks and panels and everything on
how do you look after a community, how do you maintain a community?
No one ever does a talk or a panel on how do you start a community?
How do I get the people in the first place?
And that is the big question and it turns out the answer is give them free stuff
Magic I know so so I decided I would try and do this
I would try and give them a bunch of actual reasons to join a discord so when we announced ascenders last year
I said, look, if you want to be part of the closed beta for Descenders, you have to join the Discord.
I had no idea at that point how I was actually going to get them in the beta, I just wanted them in a Discord.
So I did that. What I also did was that I decided that wasn't enough and I needed to build some kind of meta game.
I should say, by the way, I've just realized I keep talking about Discord as if you all know what it is.
Just in case there's people in the room who aren't aware.
Discord is essentially like another one of those chat programs, right, where
people can join servers and they can make channels and they can do voice chat
and they can do text chat. It's not that Discord did anything crazy different to
all the others, it's just that they did it in very clever ways and they got a
bit lucky as well and they've got lovely people working there as well which
always helps.
Um, so, uh, okay, we're up to speed on what Discord is now.
So, what I decided to try and do was create a game in the Descendants Discord that people
would then want to play before...
Descenders came out.
So that's what I did.
I made it so that when someone joined the
Descenders Discord, they couldn't see any
channels, except this one channel called
Pick a Side. And in the game, there's
three teams. And I made it so
that before they could access
anything in the Discord, they had to pick one of
these three teams out of the game.
and it gave them all the information about these three teams but it told them once you've done it
you can't change again and they pick a side and then it would open up the rest of the discord and
give them special channels as well and it would also change the color of their name to the color
of that team in the game and put them in this like tribe mentality and then we started pitting them
off against each other each week doing community challenges who can do the best fan art who can
come up with the best this the best that
And this stuff made people stick around,
because even though they had no idea how the game played yet,
and they would have for another six months,
they desperately wanted to win every week.
And they wanted to.
We made it so that they'd get special emotes,
or emojis, I don't know what you call them.
You'd get special ones of those each week,
depending on which team won.
And all of this, I mean it took some work, I'll admit.
It was a lot of, and I learned a lot about community management very quickly
because about 5,000 people ended up joining in a very short space of time.
But here's the thing, when we got to the launch of the game...
Those were thousands of people who were super into not just the game, but us as well.
Because they had this direct line to us.
And by this point, there was all sorts of memes that they'd made around us, the developers, myself,
because they felt like they had this super close connection to us.
In fact, when we launched the game, we launched it 20 minutes early and only told the Discord server.
and then I realized the launch discount hadn't been applied.
It wasn't going to be applied for another 20 minutes.
So I said in Discord,
Oh, just wait 20 minutes, the launch discount will happen.
And we sold like a thousand copies of the game
just in the first 20 minutes
because Discord people were so adamant
they needed the game right now
that they didn't care about the 10% discount.
When you have...
a community base like that, that is already prepped and ready when the game is going to come out,
that is a useful tool to have. And the cool thing is as well, they're still there now,
and they're causing the long tail of the game.
to go on even longer. I've launched many games that I've never seen.
Normally it's like, up here for the launch and then...
This game has been like this. It's continuing to sell because these people are bringing their friends in.
It's honestly been one of the craziest things I have...
Out of everything I've put together for making a game, it's one of the things that has worked.
the most well. Apart from having a great day on sales,
we've had a lot of situations as well which I hadn't sort of envisioned were going to occur.
So for example, all of these people just desperately wanted to give us positive Steam
reviews immediately as well. So within like a day we had like a 94% positive rating on Steam
because they'd all plowed it with positive Steam reviews. Whenever someone would leave
a negative Steam review, people from the community would comment on it trying to help them.
and then end up flipping negative Steam reviews into positive ones.
And I didn't have to do anything to make that happen. These people just did it themselves.
And a lot of people, if people had problems, they had bug reports and all this kind of stuff,
they came in the Discord. We've got a channel called Bug Reporting that could go in there.
All the bug reports are right there. They're not clogging up the Steam forums where it just,
you know, obviously normally Steam forums just look like, you know, hell basically.
So it kind of helped clean up that place as well.
I don't work for Discord, honestly.
I know it looks like I do.
I'm just, I honestly, it's honestly one of the most,
the most brilliant things that has happened
for people selling games, I think, now that there is now
this centralized place where you can
collect people together.
But like I say, you just gotta make sure
that you actually give them a reason to do that.
Now what I want to talk about here was streaming.
So I've done many talks about streaming in the past,
and streaming is obviously still an important thing.
It's more important than ever maybe.
So here's the thing about streaming.
It used to be, you know, like a couple years ago,
a few years ago, you'd try and get big streamers
to play your game, right?
And then someone big will play your game
and you get a nice spike.
YouTubers as well,
we'll talk about YouTubers with this as well.
What you need to know now is that that doesn't happen anymore for Descenders.
Not even for last year it hasn't been happening and anybody who's launched a game in the last year
and maybe has had a big YouTuber or streamer will know that there's just no spike at all anymore.
You know, we've had pretty much every single massive streamer play Descenders in the last month.
and we'll have an okay day that day, you know, it might be elevated slightly but there's no spikes
at all. People watch streamers and youtubers for the streamers and youtubers now, they don't watch,
they don't make purchasing decisions based off
I mean it might be that they watch multiple YouTubers or streamers, see your game multiple
times and then when it's on a 25% sale go, oh I remember Lyric playing that, maybe I'll
pick that up now.
That's possible, but you don't get the immediate, Lyric is playing this game, I need to own
this game thing anymore.
That doesn't happen.
So if you are trying to base a marketing around that, do not.
I used to suggest that people do...
You know sort of do twitch integration and you know chat integration and special like twitch games and all that kind of stuff
If you are going to do that stuff don't spend a long time on it. I would honestly suggest
Because I don't think you're going to see much in return
Do it as like a?
cool little side thing maybe, but yeah, I honestly don't think it's worth putting the effort anymore.
Now, the reason why I've listed Mixer here, and I'll explain what Mixer is because I'm
discovering this week that not as many people have heard of Mixer. So Mixer is
another streaming platform, I think it used to be called Beam.
and it's owned by Microsoft.
And Mixer, Mixer's definitely smaller than Twitch,
but Mixer is interesting because it is essentially
Twitch.
three or four years ago.
It's kind of, it's growing rapidly
and it's having a lot of resources put into it.
And because of that,
it's very difficult to get any traction on Twitch anymore
because Twitch is very focused on streamers, right?
And now the front page is always these massive streamers
and starting off as a new person,
it can be very difficult to get some traction on Twitch.
Mixer, it's a lot easier to do that now.
And it's especially a lot easier for developers
because even though, as far as I can tell,
Microsoft aren't screaming so much about this,
they, on the Mixer platform,
they're very much supporting developers a lot.
I started talking to the team there
and they said, I had no idea they were doing this,
they said to me, oh yeah, we can give you a developer account on Mixer.
And I was like, okay, yeah, sure you do that.
And I got a little verified tick on there.
And then the next time I streamed,
I went front page on Mixer.
And they just feature developers on the front page of Mixer just by you being a developer
and you streaming on Mixer because that to them is like you supporting their platform
over the other bigger ones.
And I mean in the last, I've been streaming Descenders every single day for the last month
and I've had like over 200, nearly a quarter of a million people watch these streams, which
is bigger numbers than I was even getting on Twitch.
And especially if you've got a game coming out on Xbox as well, it's amazing because
the streams, the front page streams appear on the Xbox dashboard as well.
So when I'm on a stream and I say, hey is anyone from Xbox watching, the chat goes crazy.
And we're aiming to have Descenders out in roughly about May.
So this has been a massive thing for me.
I've got all of these eyeballs from Xbox players where normally it can be quite difficult to specifically get people who play on Xbox, right?
You just hope they read some press or they look at a forum.
Now I have a direct line to people who are playing on Xbox and they're watching my game on Xbox.
and they're saying, oh this seems really cool, I'll buy it.
And I'm saying, yeah, please do.
So if you're releasing a game on Xbox, 100% get on this.
If you're not, I would still heavily suggest
that you get in touch with Mixer.
They have been, honestly, nothing but amazing, really.
All right.
So, this one, this one I find massively important, but I'm going to have to explain it very well.
I think that the, I think a good number of people don't do a very good job of the way
that they actually give off a vibe about their game.
And what I mean about that is that the way that your game is shown in public and the
way that people perceive it.
will eventually determine how much value they think...
I know this sounds horrible, I know this is the kind of words you don't want to hear, right?
But you've got to think about these things.
Is the way people perceive the actual value of your game,
and when it launches, whether they think,
am I going to buy it in a sale or could I not be bothered?
Because we hear this all the time right now,
that people don't buy games at launch, they just wait for sales.
I think a lot of that has to do with this image you do for your game.
So, for example, and I'm going to show you this chart now, right?
This chart here is a thing that is in my head that I'm going to have to explain.
And I have had this in my head for like a year now.
And it might make no sense, but it makes perfect sense in my brain.
So I'm going to try to explain it to you.
I think that there are...
three different categories of the perception that people have of games in their head.
People, when they look at games, they immediately, just from about a trailer,
they watch a trailer and they immediately in their head put it into one of these three things.
They either decide that's an indie game or they decide, oh that's, I call it AA, but you know,
lots of people have, it's the mid-tier essentially, right? And then they've got, oh that's a AAA game.
And I think it's really important to know not just which one you fall into,
but then also to know what that means for your game.
I talk to a lot of developers who are either pricing their game wrong or they have what
I believe is like a double A game but they're treating it like it's an indie game.
When I was first talking to the RageSquid guys about Descenders, they were showing it
to me and they were saying, they were saying, oh we think we can probably charge about $15
for it.
and we'll try and get on some of the indie sites
and all this kind of stuff.
And I thought they were mad
because the thing that I was looking at,
I was looking at this and saying to them,
what are you talking about?
This is not a perceived indie game that you have here.
This is what people would perceive as a AA game.
This is the kind of game
where people would see a trailer for this
and they would think,
oh, I'd pay a bit of money for this.
And I remember when we launched the original trailer
for the game, there was YouTube comments saying,
I'd only pay $40 for this.
It's that kind of thing, and they couldn't believe it.
I mean, eventually we've ended up charging $25 for it,
and we have had no, like we've had barely any people
saying this game is too expensive.
It's really important to know where you are on this.
If... a lot of the time you'll just know, right?
A lot of the time you know with your game whether it is going to be classed as indie in people's eyes.
And that's absolutely fine.
The next game I'm announcing next week I believe is going to be perceived as indie.
But then...
It's when people are in between this indie and AAA one,
they're at the top of the indie one,
and they could actually move on to the next one
and have this whole new audience.
It's that where you really need to think
where exactly you are on these,
because it can make a massive difference for you.
It can make an absolute massive difference.
I think being perceived as a AA game
has helped us in lots of ways with Descenders.
and it has directed the way that I sell the game.
The next game I'm announcing, which is more of an indie title,
I'm definitely going to be selling it in very different ways
the way I've been selling Descenders because of this perception, I think.
So yeah, it might not seem that important to you,
but please have a think about where you fall on this.
So I said earlier that I do not like relying on luck.
I think that anybody who tells you
everything is luck-based is wrong,
and you need to put everything in place
to make sure that when your game comes out,
you're not just sitting there and hoping.
and praying this is going to sell, which I think is what the vast majority of people...
I'm sure there's plenty of people in this room who have released games on Steam and have sat
on launch day and said like, oh people think it's cool! It's the wrong thing to do. You
used to be able to get away with that. You can't anymore. You absolutely can't anymore.
So the Discord stuff I was talking about was a perfect example of making sure that you are reducing the risk.
We knew when Descenders launched, we could see the numbers, we could see how many people were active in our Discord.
We could see, we could see exactly, well not exactly, but roughly how many people were at least going to buy it in week one.
Things like Steam wishlists.
It's kind of a common fact now
that you normally in your first month
sell your wishlist kind of convert
somewhere around between 7% and 12%
somewhere around that.
So if you are building Steam wishlists
and you get to 30,000 wishlists
then you know that in the first month you are most likely, unless your game for some reason doesn't match this model at all,
which, you know, I guess it can depend on the quality of the game,
but you would hope to at least be converting those into about 3,000 people.
It's this kind of thing where it's...
It's horrible, but it's all a numbers game.
If you have the numbers when the launch day comes,
and you know that at least X number of these people
are going to buy it, you can then
use that to flow into more people.
If you're completely just relying on,
oh, I hope people see the game on launch day,
it's really bad news.
The other thing you can do is try
to get as many.
people involved who are influential and try to get them to put skin in the game.
What I mean by that is that you have to do that horrible thing that no one likes doing
where you just start really doing all of those horrible horrible cringy things.
I'm pretty sure you know the kind of things that I'm talking about.
The things like, for example, just trying to talk to every single person possible.
It's funny, whenever I tell somebody, for example, that I have a tweet deck set up that has...
multiple columns where I'm tracking,
just looking for the word descenders,
looking for the word rage squid,
looking for this, looking for that.
And whenever someone tweets, within like five minutes,
I'm tweeting back at them.
I'm DMing them, I'm sending them this,
I'm sending them that.
People, some people react really badly to that and they say,
oh it's a bit much that isn't it?
It's a bit weird that you're doing that.
It's like, it's a bit creepy in a way that you're just sort of,
you're kind of watching over anybody
who ever mentions your game.
Doing that sells games.
You should do it.
even if it makes you feel all weird inside and horrible,
if someone, I cannot tell you the number of times I've seen someone tweet about Descendus saying
oh this seems pretty cool, don't know if I'll pick it up though
and I've tweeted back at them just saying something like
oh thanks for saying that, that was really nice, it's cool that you considered it.
and then they've tweeted a screenshot back at me saying
oh it's really cool you tweeted at me i bought it now
that singular tweet just just made us another 25 dollars
and it it blows my mind how often that happens
especially with like streamers i see a streamer saying yo i've seen this
descenders games around and i'll immediately just dm them a
key i won't even ask i'll just
get in their DMs and I will send them a Steam key and then tweet at them saying
yo you've got a Steam key in your DMs now and they'll, they'll like, they'll all of a sudden
in the next two minutes I'll see, I can just imagine them at home just like being like
what? They just follow me and then they say oh my god thank you so much and that evening
they're playing the game. It wasn't that much effort for me to do that.
It helps that I enjoy doing that. I must stress, like, I'm a weirdo and I enjoy doing all of this stuff.
I appreciate there'll be lots of people in this room who are just like,
I do not have time for that, that sounds so boring.
But doing these awful things, I feel like there's a reason why we find them awful.
and sometimes you just gotta grit your teeth.
Another one, just emailing people asking for stuff.
People hate doing that.
Every single deal or anything I have put in place for the senders,
I emailed multiple people asking for stuff until they got back to me.
Everything with Xbox, I emailed Xbox over and over and over again,
sending them this, sending them that, sending them builds of the game,
being like, well, can I meet you?
And setting things up, showing them face to face that I meant business with this thing.
And then every single time I see even a minor opportunity, I'm jumping all over it.
And, you know, a year later, now Xbox are like, okay, well,
it seems like maybe he's going to be able to make this sell.
on Xbox so maybe we should, you know, support him quite well.
And this has happened multiple times. We've done stuff with NVIDIA, all the stuff we've been doing
with Discord, obviously I've been then trying to, after I've got into Discord, talk to those guys.
Again with Mixer, me just emailing them and saying like,
hey is there stuff I can do on Mixer? And then coming back and now just because I asked.
I'm getting hundreds of thousands of views on Mixer, and that wouldn't have happened if I hadn't just asked.
Asking is hard, I know, I know it can feel really hard to just...
Because a lot of the time it's like imposter syndrome, right?
You feel like, they're not going to care about my game, they don't care about who I am.
Don't go into it thinking that, because the thing you're making is super important.
And if you truly feel like it's this massively important thing to you,
go and show other people it's important as well.
Go and talk to everybody and ask for things.
The vast majority of the time when I just ask for free stuff.
People give me free stuff because I guess people find it hard to say no.
So really just honestly do it.
You'll be surprised at how far it can get you just emailing people and asking for stuff.
The final thing after all of this is to just be realistic.
So again, these are numbers from my talk yesterday.
The average game on Steam is making about $30,000
in its first year now.
So, what you need to be doing is, you need to be imagining, if my game makes $30,000
in the first year, which is entirely plausible, what am I going to do about it?
Or, what can I do right now?
To be able for this to be okay
essentially
So I mean this it's it's a tricky one right there's no easy answer to this. There's there's plenty of
There's plenty of things you can you can consider
You don't want to
You know this there's certain things on this list that you don't just want to hobble into your game. You don't just want to
go, well, we'll probably run out of money here,
and if we're only gonna make that much money,
let's just do early access.
Early access obviously makes sense
for certain types of games and not all the ones.
Multiple platforms is a massive thing I keep telling people.
Like, a lot of people just don't think
that they're gonna be able to get access to Xbox dev kits.
or they're not going to be able to find someone to help them port that kind of stuff.
Xbox give away free dev kits.
They literally will send you two free dev kits.
All you have to do is just sign up your game with them and they do that.
Or at least they do in Europe.
I'm talking as if I know what happens in America,
but if you're in Europe, that's what they do.
And there's plenty of people around as well
who are throwing funding into this.
There's loads of local things.
Again, I'm talking from UK perspective here, unfortunately.
But as far as I understand, there's lots over here as well.
All that said and done,
if $30,000 in the first year
isn't going to be enough to support yourself or a team,
then you absolutely should have that horrible conversation
of is this sustainable for us to be doing this full time?
And if it's not, then what do I do, essentially?
But it would be, it's just a very bad idea
to not consider all this stuff.
I know it's grim, and I know it's very,
like, ugh, just a horrible way to kind of,
get to the end of this thing, but you do need to think about this stuff.
Otherwise, you could just get caught out in just horrible ways.
I've seen too many developers put everything into a release,
and then it's maybe not gone as well as they're hoping, and then they've realized...
oh god I've got no plan and obviously you get massively depressed whether after a game
launch whether it's done well or not.
So you don't particularly want a double whammy of badness.
Right, I'm done, I promise. I know I've talked forever.
This is, if you just want a too long didn't read or if you fell asleep a little bit and checked your phone a little bit during that, I don't blame you.
Here are the important points.
I mean, the main ones, the main things I would honestly say that have worked amazingly for the Descendants launch,
the Discord stuff I was talking about, the Mixer stuff I was talking about.
getting all the deals in place with Xbox, even just getting those guys to help us out has been amazing.
And then really...
just unfortunately just doing the leg work, just gritting your teeth and really doing the stuff.
I appreciate there'll be lots of people in here as well who just don't have the time to do a lot
of this stuff or just don't want to because it's boring. If you are one of those people,
that's fair enough. I would suggest then you find someone to do it for you.
Put it this way, right? If you work with a publisher or someone like that, yeah, they're going to take a cut of your game.
But what is worse, right?
100% of a small number or 70% of a large number.
You really need to weigh up whether or not you need someone involved in doing this stuff because it's so important.
And if you don't do it...
there is a high chance that unfortunately
your game isn't going to do as well as you would have hoped.
I feel like I've ended on a really
down tone. I should have prepared a joke for this part, but
whatever, that's all you're getting. Alright, thank you.
God, I talked forever, didn't I?
I think I have like four minutes left
if anybody wants to ask a question.
There's microphones here and here.
I would love questions.
Hello.
So first of all, thanks for the talk.
That was awesome.
And your previous one yesterday was also very informative.
I was wondering if, so you talked about Steam wish list
as a way to use it as a KPI, or a predictive measure.
So I was wondering if there's any other KPIs
that you keep your eyes out for,
and any other ways of.
seeing basically measuring success or predicting a measure of success and whether you've with
your with no more robots whether you've seen a scenario where you have those kpis and a title
that's just not meeting them and that you've had to can or change the strategy um
So I guess the obvious one, I feel like I keep saying this over and over again, but I feel like a big obvious one for us was the Discord stuff.
We could see exactly how many people were in the server, how many people were active in the server,
and we could see as well just how many people were feverish in the server as well.
So we were pretty confident at the kinds of numbers that we're going to convert from people who were in our Discord to sales there.
And we kind of coupled that with wishlists as well.
But I wish I had started the mix of stuff earlier as well,
to be honest.
I wish that I'd gotten on that, because I
feel like that would have given us a massive bump.
A lot of the stuff was just centralized
around those places.
There's obviously plenty of other ones,
but these are the ones that I felt like.
I could really core focus on,
and that wouldn't just grind us into the ground.
I, to clarify, I love looking at numbers.
I love like working out all of these things,
but I think you just end up,
you just end up getting a little too
into these kind of things, don't you?
And you start to see numbers in your sleep a little bit
if you start to worry too much about this stuff.
So yeah, that was enough for me really.
Hello.
Hi.
Thanks again for the pair of talks.
No worries.
Very, very good stuff.
I hope it wasn't too rambly.
I felt like it was quite rambly but I...
It was the right amount of ramble.
So general, I guess.
Don't worry.
I'm sorry.
Sorry.
So, I have a question about you kind of touched on giving off the right vibe when it came to your game.
And one of the main things that you focused on was a price point.
Yeah.
What else goes into that?
So...
I think that in general people price their games too low.
I've been seeing developers all day
and pretty much every single developer I've talked to today
I've told them that their pricing,
you know, like everybody puts in their little kind of debt,
don't they?
Like, we reckon that a launch price of $10 or $15.
And pretty much every single person I've talked to today
I've said, you can charge more than that by the way,
you know, like, and a lot of it comes down to
things like genre and
For Descenders, when we announced Descenders,
we were hoping that we were giving off the right vibe.
And when it turned out we were,
and we started to get comments like,
I wouldn't pay $40 for this.
That was a pretty good, that gave us a good sense, right?
Of what kind of price we could charge.
I honestly, looking back, feel like we could have charged
more than $25 for it at this point.
And we maybe could have pushed it to 30, but.
But that, I mean, that's by the by, but a lot of the time I would suggest to people
when they're trying to decide on the price to take what kind of game they've got, look
at all the other games that are coming out on Steam right now, but specifically look
at which ones are doing well with...
Not like the massive ones you kind of cut those ones out because they're all you know
A kind of miracle workers when you look at sort of the mid-tier games, which are doing pretty well
I'm making you know sort of half a mil for themselves in the first month
a lot of the time those games will be, will surprise you, they'll be priced a little bit
higher than you think. I saw a strategy game today and the guys making that said they were
thinking they could get $15 for that. I said to them,
I bet you could get $25 for this.
Strategy games on Steam right now sell well.
Like a lot of the time, strategy games,
because it's very niche and it's very PC gamer.
If you look at the prices of those kind of games,
they are priced higher.
Because people who play those kind of games
don't mind paying a little bit more.
They are like hardcore PC gamers.
So yeah, it's honestly, it's doing just a lot of research and really asking yourself,
can I ask for a bit more? And remember as well, the people who you've gathered around the game
before the launch.
they'd honestly pay anything.
Like, and that's not to say, you know,
you should exploit them or anything like that,
but it's more like you dropping the price,
you going, ooh, I'll drop the price by $5 just in case.
They don't care.
They absolutely don't care.
Like I told you, all these people bought our game
when it didn't even have the launch discount on it.
They just wanna play it.
So why discount it by,
if people weren't gonna buy it at launch,
that extra $5 off, is it really gonna pull them in?
And yet adding an extra $5 onto your price, it sounds like a tiny amount, but you sell
an extra 10,000 copies of your game, for a lot of people that could be a whole extra
year's worth of living.
It seems like small numbers, but I think it's honestly really, really important to think
hard about it.
Okay, thank you very much.
Hi, thanks for the talk. In regards to developing a community pre-release, do you have any insight
as to what's the best time frame for that in terms of not doing it so early that you
risk losing interest versus so late that you have no time to grow?
I think we announced Descenders too early.
We announced it in July last year,
and then it came out in February, which is.
Seven months.
What is that, like seven months?
Something like that.
I think that was too long.
It felt like it dragged a little bit,
and I wonder if we lost some people along the way
because it felt like it was too long.
We split that time up a little bit with the community,
you know, the weekly community stuff,
and with We Run Air.
a closed beta for the Discord people in October.
But yeah, I would honestly say six months is the longest.
I think that between announcement of a game
and actually launching a game,
the sweet spot is somewhere between three and six months.
Sometimes depending on what your game actually is.
I think that's enough, it's a decent amount of time
where you can build up a little community,
but you're always telling them it's coming very soon,
I promise, it's coming very soon,
and not have them disappear too quickly.
Okay, all right, thank you, that was very helpful.
Hey, thanks for the talk.
You touched on YouTubers and Twitch streamers don't really convert well to game sales, they're
mostly there for free entertainment.
What is your view on media outlets and previews and reviews?
Do you see a bigger tick from those kind of companies?
No, not for a long time to be honest.
I was giving talks about this years ago and I was saying that the press don't really ... ... ... ... ... ... ...
do much. For us, just to clarify, it's still well worth getting press to talk about your
game and getting YouTubers and streamers and everybody. Just because they don't do spikes
doesn't mean they aren't causing... I think that Descenders has plateaued at a nice number
of sales per day.
thanks to all the coverage.
Because now when someone, if someone sees it
and they search for the word Descendants,
they see all of these articles talking about it.
They see it on this website, that website.
I think that helps to sell it to anybody who's coming along.
But no, not for years to be honest have I seen any sort of spikes out of specific press
talking about my games.
Yes, thanks.
An interesting thing actually is that when we announced Ascenders,
we ended up getting about I think like 125,000 views on the trailer like in the first month.
About...
40,000 of those came from Games Press.
And about 85,000 of those came from Bike Press.
And that was about two outlets.
Gotcha.
Go for the Bike Press is what you're saying.
So just get in contact with the Bike Press.
Confuse them.
I don't know, put a bike in your game.
Worked for us.
Thank you.
Hi.
Hey there. Um, so earlier in your talk, well, thank you for giving this talk,
by the way. Um, let's see, uh, earlier in your talk, you talked about, uh,
like asking.
asking a lot for like partnerships and stuff like that.
It seems like you took a pretty fearless approach
and coming from a Northwesterner,
the problem that I find in simply just asking for things
is that there's a ton of perception
around what the response might be.
So then my question to you is,
would you prefer just recklessly asking for things
because you don't know what might happen
or would you prefer a more tempered approach
depending on the type of game that you have?
Well, what's the worst thing that could happen
if you ask though?
Like if you ask someone, if you go to someone and say,
I want this, can we work together on this thing?
The worst that's gonna happen is they're gonna ignore you.
Or you're never gonna burn a bridge or anything
by asking someone for help.
The worst that's gonna happen is you'll feel a bit shit
because someone didn't get back to you.
The best that's gonna happen is they're gonna say,
all right, cool, let's jump on a call and I'll suss you out.
And at that point, you've got a window.
You're right, I do...
I can be a bit reckless with all this kind of stuff,
but I think it works, to be honest.
I think people actually appreciate
a direct approach sometimes.
I guess reckless was a little bit too reckless.
Yeah.
I would say more courageous, I guess, forward thinking.
I guess I'm struggling for words here.
No, it's like I was saying, I honestly, I think...
I think it's one of my personality pro points that I feel okay doing this.
All the stuff I was talking about, you know, doing the horrible, like, cringey stuff as well,
for some reason, at some point in my life, I decided I didn't care.
I appreciate that a lot of real human beings with actual emotions
find this stuff hard and find it hard to just ask.
just get over it, just honestly, just ask.
Because like I say, everything that happens,
you make happen.
No one has been coming to me,
trying to just being like,
hey, can we help you with the success of Descenders?
I have asked and asked and asked
and made every little thing happen by asking.
So just, just, just do it.
Just try it.
Just grit your teeth and try it.
Start asking for stuff.
If it doesn't work out for you,
ignore me and go back to not asking for stuff.
But just, just for a month, just for a month.
Just try it.
What can happen?
For a month.
Just try asking for things.
See how it goes.
And if you hate it, fine.
But maybe it'll change your life.
Feel like this is turning into some kind of life seminar.
Don't be human.
Yeah.
You can do this.
That is what I would say.
Alright, cool.
Do it!
Is what I think Sheila Booth said.
I guess before I give the mic over to the next person, you mentioned earlier about getting
dev kits.
I was going to say can confirm, because I had a pretty epic freakout when I, like the
game that I'm working on managed to somehow become a part of ID at Xbox, and I had a pretty
epic freakout when they showed up at my door.
Yeah.
Because I thought...
But then there'll be loads of people who don't ask that kind of stuff.
Yeah.
And how easy was it?
It was actually pretty easy.
Yeah, I mean you had to fill out a bunch of horrible forms, right?
Because you can't get anything like that without filling out a whole bunch of forms, but you
did the horrible form filling out and then this thing turned up.
And then two giant white boxes showed up at my door.
Yeah, they're pretty big.
Cheers.
Hello.
Hey, just echoing previous sentiments, I was at the talk yesterday, really enjoyed it,
wasn't planning to be back, but here I am, so thank you very much.
And so you mentioned all the benefits of a Discord community, you sort of sold me on
it, but having not seen your previous talks, I still feel sort of unclear on how you got
that initial bunch of people to be there.
What are the steps involved in that, and if it's your previous talks?
Yeah, maybe I didn't explain that well enough.
So, what I was trying to say was that
you need to give people a reason to be joining the Discord.
And the way you do that is that you tell them
that to get this free stuff you're going to give them,
they have to join the Discord.
The free stuff for us was doing a closed beta
through the Discord.
we from the moment we announced the game we said we were going to do a closed beta very soon
and we said that the way to do that was to sign up in the discord the the press reported on that
and a lot of those people do i have to stop one more question okay cool um and a lot of those
a lot of people then if they read the article on a press website and we're interested in it
then click the link to the discord
people fall away right because most people won't click the link to discord in the first place
and then of those people most people don't have discord so you end up only getting a small funnel
of people
But even so, a small funnel of people for us was thousands of people.
But you got the word out through traditional press outlets and things like that.
Exactly, yeah.
And then around about the time we were doing the closed beta as well,
you know, in the like couple of weeks we announced the date for the closed beta,
we got another surge of like a couple of extra thousand people
back into the Discord again because we said,
this thing's coming out for free in two weeks,
here's how you get it.
And another bunch of people came in.
So...
Yeah, it's surprisingly easy to get people to kind of want to be part of your community
if you're throwing free stuff at them.
Thank you very much.
Who knew?
Hi, apparently we only have one more question.
I'll try and make it a good one.
It better be great.
You mentioned finding a publisher or other partner to do the annoying and or cringy work.
Yeah.
Do you know anyone who's interested in publishing games?
And if, or more generally, suggestions for finding
and connecting with those sorts of people?
Yeah, I mean, when it comes to that kind of stuff,
everybody's looking for different things.
The main thing that I'd say is,
if you're working with a publisher.
make sure that you're getting a good deal, to be honest.
One of the main reasons why I did set up my own thing,
and in fact, why it's called No More Robots,
is because over and over and over again,
people were telling me when they work with indie publishers
or whatever you want to call them,
they'd sign up, they'd maybe not sign,
they'd sign a deal which was maybe not great.
and then they'd never talk to that person ever again who signed them
because now they were passed along to another part of the company
and then it was like, okay cool, we'll hear from you in six months then
when you've got the build ready and then we'll push it out.
It's... if you're going to work with a publisher, do some...
heavy scoping of them basically. Talk to, email every single dev who has worked with them
and say what's it like to work with this person because you don't want to, it can be exciting
right if someone's showing interest in your work and is saying hey let's work together we'll take
this this revenue share and then we'll put it and it might sound amazing but then when you sign with
them you realize oh crap like they're not doing anything and they're the worst. I hear that all
the time.
And it can easily be remedied by just making sure
that you email people who have published with them before
and saying, are they okay?
Are they cool?
And if they say no, then you don't
because it's never worth selling your soul.
Did that answer your question?
Pretty much.
Okay, good, right.
Thank you very much everybody.
Thank you.