Good morning, everyone. Welcome to the Skyrim speedrun.
My name is Brian Francis, and if you need to refer to me in the third person,
my pronouns are he him.
Today, we're going to be watching Bubbles Del Fuego do a speedrun of
The Elder Scrolls V Skyrim, while former Bethesda 3D artist Jonah Loeb
commentates and tells the stories from his time at Bethesda.
Bubbles, Jonah, would you mind introducing yourselves?
Bubbles, go ahead.
Oh, thank you.
Yeah, I'm BubbleStuffFuego. I speedrun a lot of things.
If you've ever seen that, I've done like probably eight different AAA titles at
GDQs before and at ESA and some stuff at like other publications and
things and lots of fun for a long time including a lot of Bethesda games like
Fallout 3, Fallout 4, Skyrim, Oblivion. Today we're doing Skyrim.
Jonah did a lot of work in that game. You can introduce yourself, Jonah.
Biggie Bubbles.
Hello, everybody.
My name is Jonah Loeb.
I was a character artist at Bethesda Softworks
for seven years, where I made most of the creatures
and monsters for games like Shimmering Isles,
Fallout 3, Skyrim, and Fallout 4.
And these days I'm doing my own thing.
I do art education.
I'm very active on Twitter and Instagram,
and I make a lot of art, traditional art or otherwise.
And up until this year, I was...
diving into attending cons, and then they all got canceled.
What's a con? I don't even know anymore.
We're in a virtual conference.
I don't even know.
We apologize to Jonah for character artists,
not 3D artists, sorry.
Oh, no worries.
For those of you at home and chat,
thank you for joining us.
I'm seeing some faces in chat,
like Melissa Sawicki and Ben Fried.
I just want to remind folks,
feel free to ask questions for Jonah.
I'll be grabbing them.
If you want to know about his time at Bethesda,
if you want to know about his art styles,
go ahead and do that.
So before Bubbles gets started running, I want to just sort of explain what we're doing.
Why are we doing a Skyrim speedrun? Speedrunning is an incredible aspect of the video game community.
Runners get together to raise money for charity and take time to explore games in new and
fascinating ways that elevate and explore all the hard work that went into them.
And sometimes they just break stuff and it's funny.
The Elder Scrolls V Skyrim was one of the largest RPG releases of the century, to the
point that we're probably going to see it ported to the PS5 and Xbox Series X.
That's not confirmed news, that's just me speculating, but if I'm wrong, like,
I'll be very surprised to be wrong. Its system-driven design shows the incredible
craftsmanship of Bethesda Softworks, and of the games we're running this week,
it's the one where the line between bug and feature is blurred even if you're not speedrunning the
game. In Skyrim, you can live your own adventure, and sometimes that adventure involves running
around doing 360-degree spins.
Again, Jonah will be taking your questions during the run, drop them in chat, and I'll
be pulling them for him.
For that, you can also ask questions for Bubbles if you're a dev and you want to know how runners
approach games like this.
With that, let's get started.
Bubbles, blow our minds.
Hi, I'm here and I'm right in the animation.
area the art there's Jonah character oh we got the nose we got the credits yeah
ah snuggled right comfortably comfortably in the middle I've never never checked there before
all right uh all right so there's a long cart ride in the beginning of Skyrim and um and then
you have to create a character which is pretty specific to the run so um a high elf is nice
because they're tall and there's a ratio between height and uh movement speed in the game um
as of course, as we all know.
I think it's something to do with how long their legs are,
honestly, it's like their stride.
And it's funny because like in Oblivion,
you would think like the wood elf would be fast
because it's, you know, it's their type of character,
but they're really short, so they're not really.
And so on, so the high elf is fast.
And so things will get started immediately,
as you can tell by the thumbnail of the save file.
We just finished making the character and as soon as you gain movement speed,
your head gets off of the chopping block.
Um, and I guess we'll immediately jump into the face of the dragon that Jonah
designed and so things start off really fast.
So I'm just going to start off with an infinite running glitch.
And, uh, by preserving my run speed through a quick saves and quick loads
and, um, and then get out of here.
Right on, let's do it.
So you can start the timer, I guess.
I guess I'll run a timer.
We didn't.
Oh, yeah, it doesn't speed or not.
You don't have to.
It'll look a lot better if you don't.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, you're going to break the world record.
All right, there's the dragon.
There's the wing and we're gone.
Whoa, already.
I'm shocked.
You know, Jonah, when we were doing pre-show for this, you said you laugh whenever people tell you
about Skyrim bugs because you've played, quote, the buggiest version of all Bethesda games,
because obviously you're playing them before release. And this still beats your expectations,
I guess.
Yeah, absolutely. I mean, it's very funny to watch other people encounter all these bugs. And you're
right, the line between bug and feature is so thin with Bethesda games. I think people understand
that these games are so big and so complicated. It was so many different variables that a million
different things can happen wrong.
And so there is an enhanced level of acceptance
on the community's part.
But for that, we would like to thank the community
because not a lot of games would get past
that certain hallmark of bugginess.
But yeah, I mean, I'm always impressed
to see the new ones that are there,
but I will not, I just can't bring myself
to feel that bad about them, you know?
Because they're what they are.
Ooh, I posed that skeleton.
How neat was it playing this game and sort of seeing your own models just pop up every time?
Like a brief like hey, it's me
Yeah a little bit a little bit
It's funny cuz today I see the thing and then I kind of remember I have a flashback to work in there to the time
I was being in the thing and and of course as an artist I see something also, but I'm like, oh, I wish I I
Wish I'd done that better, you know, I wish I'd like man if I can go back, you know
Yeah, um, I have a question for bubbles while you're running. It
comes from Dom Harrison chat. What can a dev do to aid this
speedrunning community for their game? They the Dom says, Oh, we
can add split, you know, split timers and things like that. But
bubbles. Is there anything else you would want Dom dad to their
game?
I guess like
Trying to make your game good for a speedrun is like, it never works.
Like whenever someone is like, I love speed running.
So I made a game that's perfect for speedruns.
Like that's, that's not really how it works.
It's like trying to make the best movie ever, you know, it, it, you can't,
you can't plan it, you know, sometimes there's a little bit of a suggestion to
it, like portals are really awesome speed run and it's of course got like
a speed run mode built in.
So it's, you know, it's not really a big surprise, but...
I just want to point out that in the run,
we just watched you wait a specific amount of time to get a specific horse,
which is just, that's just never how I think about playing these games.
And the horse is vertical.
And you're gone.
Um...
Oh boy, oh boy.
That's the troll.
Oh my goodness.
I don't even understand what I'm seeing right now.
Let me work for Bethesda, I'll find this stuff.
Wow.
With this, I guess the thing about speed running is so often is,
is you're, you're finding ways to break the game, you know?
And yeah, it's pretty amazing.
Yeah.
And there's a lot of different ways, just even just what happened just now,
running so fast, the geometry of the setting couldn't load in.
I've had that happen, you know, I remember I was testing Fallout 3.
Oh, I posed that jogger as well.
I was testing Fallout 3 and I posed that troll.
And I was running and running and running and the landscape became more and more barren around me.
And I thought I was entering a very small, very isolated area. And I kind of just finally stop
on this one dark patch of earth. And I'm like, what? There's nothing around me. What's going on?
And then the house just like loads around me, but not the interior of a house, just the exterior
model, but the inside of that model. And then I was just stuck. And I was like, oh, I get it.
The whole landscape had not loaded. I get it. Okay. So it's everywhere. They're everywhere.
Also, also remember that this is, you know, 2011 was nine years ago.
And so a lot of these, you know, it's, it's, things are not quite, I think, I
think there was, there's this greater tension between hardware and software,
you know, and what could, what could run what?
So, yeah, I'm in combat.
This is really weird.
Oh, is it affecting your run?
I mean, it's not going to be a problem, but I was just like, oh, that's interesting.
Jonah, we're going to pull some questions from chat for you.
Please.
From Lori Warfield, would like to know, when you were working on Skyrim,
did you have a favorite character or prop that you worked on?
Lori, thanks for asking that question.
Did I have a favorite character or prop?
I was really proud of the giants.
You know, my intention with them was to create something
that did not inspire desire to just murder.
I wanted, you know, what I really like about designing creatures
and characters and monsters is creating
something that will stir the imagination. To me that's more important
than just creating something
that the player wants to click and kill and kill.
So I really enjoyed doing the Giants
because they seem very human.
I really enjoyed Alduin's final form,
although the process of getting there gave me tendinitis.
I was working so hard and so many extra hours.
And I really liked the Draugr.
They just...
Sometimes the most effort should be put into the things that you see the most.
Not even the biggest assets, but the most common ones.
You know, the Goombas of the world.
Yeah, that makes sense.
Our next question comes from Josh Good.
What type of art pipeline did Bethesda have during Skyrim's development?
How heavily was engineering involved to assist artists in building the tools where needed?
It's a good question, Josh.
The art process was generally, we
worked from a concept sketch.
That's my mammoth.
Concept sketch to a 3D model, and then we
iterate from there and then create the final.
model. Now some things like the Spriggan that I created, I worked not with engineering per
se, but with a world artist, an effects artist named Mark Tier, and we kind of collaborated
on creating this almost like a beehive effect with the kind of the buzzing lights everywhere.
So we...
We didn't collaborate as much with engineering as I would have liked all the time.
But I definitely, whenever there's a particular character or creature or something that is,
has, that needs these special things, like, like, like the Spergen, you know, with, with glows on,
you know, whenever we get the idea that whenever she brings out her claws, they light up green,
that kind of thing. That's when a direct collaboration is for sure encouraged.
But I think people also frequently...
overestimate the size of Bethesda Softworks, the manpower there.
During Skyrim's creation, I think on average over the course of the project, I think we had
9500 people on the team. And so there's not as much bandwidth,
usually, as you want to be able to collaborate back and forth
on things. And not everything can be given all the same
amount of attention because the world is just massive. But I for
sure, and I know myself and others
we're very certain that when something required that attention,
we would get it from our desk,
walk across the building and talk to a programmer and try to get,
or a level designer or whoever,
and try to get that support and feedback and collaboration.
Because the best things in game design happen when people work together to make
something cool.
Right on, yeah, and that's so different in a world now where I think more, I don't know quite what the state of ZeniMax is.
ZeniMax has owned so many studios now, and I think Bethesda is still, from my understanding, Bethesda Softworks itself is still pretty siloed,
but they're not the only company, you know, so many games now ship with the help of not just, you know, multiple internal studios,
but external studios too with contracting and such.
uh... yes that's my peanut gallery comfort uh... walls that's correct i
think in the picture
in the background bubbles continues to just
roll through like a demon
uh... in this massive world over the slow animation of getting a car
which i'll linger on for just a moment
uh... a question from someone named carly velocity
who's sitting in the room with me, says,
I've never known a single person who finished Skyrim
since it's so easy to get lost doing side missions.
Have either of you actually finished Skyrim?
And that's for both Bubbles and Jonah.
I didn't at first.
I mean, like, same thing with Oblivion,
just like Thieves Guild, Dark Brotherhood,
side stuff, and then you're out of there.
Yeah.
I did not.
I, you know, because most of the time I spent playing that game was pre-shipping.
so much of my job for the months and months and months after production had started and we were
just ironing out bugs and polishing and massaging things into place, my job was to just play the
game and report books and do little fixes on this and that. And so very frequently,
I got very far, but very frequently you get quite far with a character, you really fall
in love with it and everything. And then they'd say, well, you know what, enough things have
changed now.
that we're starting a fresh build and you need to you need to start a fresh build
if you're going to continue to do this.
And so enough stops and starts over the course of the playtesting.
And I just wasn't I just never got around to finishing it,
which is funny because I never got to see my own
Alduin like love, like get killed.
But I created the whalebone bridge, everything in Sovngarde.
And, you know, and I've I've watched videos of it,
but I never actually played it and I never got that far.
Right on.
I love that For Whatever Reason Bubbles keeps reloading this horse speed glitch.
And so every time we see his hero run through the world like this, it is appropriate because
someone in chat put in Green Hill Zone theme starts playing, which is a reference to Sonic
the Hedgehog, of course.
So we don't have that music on hand, but if you in the chat would like to just picture
that in your head while this little guy runs around that this is Sonic the Hedgehog in
Skyrim, you can do that.
Um, Jonah, Ben Free would like to say that they love your pen
and ink illustration and the splash of golden red.
Thank you. Thanks very much.
What's going on in the run here before I do anything interesting
looks like we're doing some fast traveling.
Ben just you know, I just I recently got this larger print
of a print of mine done like literally came in just last
week. So that one turned out pretty good. It's a nice print.
The nice print.
Jonah, are there any particular challenges, this question comes from Melissa Sawicki,
are there any particular challenges you have when working on character art for different
iterations of an existing IP?
That's a good question, Melissa.
So since I've worked at Bethesda and moved on to contract work and freelance work, I do make
assets for different kinds of games. And, you know, so for instance, I've worked for a little
while on the System Shock remake. At the moment I'm working on Crowfall, which is coming out
shortly. And essentially it requires different art styles. And so it really, you know, I try
to be careful because I think, you know, in a game like Skyrim...
When I worked on Fallout 3, for instance, I was able to really polish up my abilities
in character design and character art and the workflow there at Bethesda.
And then with Skyrim, I was really able to unleash my artistic self and be the artist
that I wanted to be. So then my art style then contributed to Skyrim's art style.
So going on to other projects, then I actually have to be cognizant of the fact that my art style
it might not be theirs.
And so I often try to spend a lot of time
trying to pay special attention to the art style
they have going on in that, in their own game,
and really try to, and I'll ask the art directors,
you know, for feedback on like, what matters?
What's important?
What do you guys rely on?
can you give me some color swatches that you use a lot, that kind of thing, because
as much as I like doing my own thing, it's really important to listen to employers and really figure
out what is important to them, what they're trying to prioritize in their own game, and really lean
in that direction. So yeah, it can be quite complicated trying to adapt to different
gameplay styles, but I think it's really important.
to do that both for client happiness and as an artist and as a game designer, it behooves
me to try new things and to learn other people's new techniques and to stretch my own styles
because a lot of aspects of art, no matter what the art style is in particular, are similar
from game to game to game to game.
You know, ideas like shape, line, form, color.
these things all have a unique kind of visual power,
but the way they're used becomes the language,
the visual language of that game.
And so I definitely try to put a lot of emphasis on whatever they deem to be important,
and I try to head in that direction.
That's such a cool answer.
Bubbles, where the heck are you?
Do you even know?
There we go.
Uh, yeah, I'm, uh, in Helgen right now.
I'm in the beginning of the game.
Gotcha.
Um, let's see here.
Go ahead.
I'm with us.
Go for it.
And now we're going to Riverwood to meet up with Delphine and he's going to
have that conversation about, uh, about, you know, here's the dragon born.
The dragons are back.
And they go in that, you know, meeting in the end.
Roger that.
Yeah.
I remember this is one of the, it's funny.
You were just in a conversation a second ago and I'm sitting here going, I have
no memory of this, of this conversation.
And now you're at a point where I'm like, oh yeah, I've played this 20 times.
For all the times that you restart Skyrim, just cause you're like, I feel
like changing things up today.
Um, uh, what's your Jonah, what's your favorite software for
character and prop development?
I would say my favorite software is ZBrush.
I think it's definitely a program with a steep learning curve, but I think if it wasn't
for this program, I'd have had a lot harder time getting into the industry.
And I think knowing ZBrush was one of the things that got me a job at Bethesda.
Because at the time it was still a new program and a lot of people didn't know it even there.
And it's just really cool for like modeling and sculpting.
You know, I think I'm probably my own work is best known for all the little detail I
put into the surface of things and all that.
You know, the jogger, the giants, the mammoth, the dragon priest, et cetera, et cetera.
And a lot of that comes through in this program called ZBrush, which is basically just a sculpting
program.
And so as somebody like me who is.
I'm very art-centric and technically speaking, I'm pretty garbage when it comes to talent.
I was definitely probably the worst at computers at Bethesda Softworks,
excepting the concept artists who didn't have to do anything with computers if they didn't want to.
It was definitely a really nice entree for me into the game world, being able to sculpt and
think about things from this perspective.
3D perspective. Oh, the Wabbajack. I made that.
Oh, you made the Wabbajack? I did. I did. We didn't know we had no concept art for it.
And so I just asked. That's so much cooler than a dragon.
I asked the concept, I asked one of the designers, I was like, do we have any,
I'm supposed to do the Wabbajack. Do we have any concept art for it?
And they said, no, not really.
And so I was like, well, you know,
one of the first things I ever did at Bethesda Softworks
was I made the three faced Shiogoroth,
like gateway to the Shivering Isles.
That was one of the first things I did at that company.
And so I was like, I'll just use those three faces
and just use those to create the staff.
So it came together well.
I made the Spriggan Matron as well.
Bubbles, you just passed through one of my favorite areas
from Skyrim, that artifact, like Quest in the North.
Yeah, we just go through that whole glimmer system backwards. Yeah.
So we're just going to go to the elevator that we leave.
Wow. Every time you come back to this horse,
I swear, like my brain just breaks a little.
Yeah, I don't even understand. This is so confusing.
Well, I may crash.
I'll ask you to explain. I made that troll as well.
I'll ask you to explain exactly how this horse elevator works later
when you're not speedrunner.
Yeah, I gotta close the program. It's the second crash of the month so far.
Oh yeah.
Whenever it's a black screen, it's not my visuals cutting out or something.
It's a feature.
It's a, well, it's something. It's not a feature, not a bug.
It just works.
It's Skyrim.
Um, uh, David, uh, Boston Hardy, um, says they remember that door.
I don't even know what we've been like stuck at like five doors by now.
Um, and it sure slows down the speed run.
Um, let's see if there are any other fun questions from chat.
Uh, remember to keep them coming folks.
Cause yeah.
Yeah.
Anybody can chat, please.
Please.
Deliver from you.
Not that we don't love just like reacting to the elevator, the horse elevator.
Did you make this moose?
I did not make them this now.
Oh, who made the moose?
Uh, I.
I am not sure. I don't remember. I don't know.
Whoever made the moose, thank you.
It's a glorious moose.
Look at that ragdoll go.
I'm trying to fly from the stables into the Mazark shaft.
The temple, I don't remember the name of it exactly, but.
Um, Jonah, here's an interesting question from, uh, if you have unlimited funding for a patch
and one month to finish it, um, what would you choose to improve? I guess this is interesting
because you're specifically referring to, um, to character art here is what we're discussing, but
you know, everyone wants to improve their, their work all the time.
If I can have a patch having to do with character art.
Yeah, that would improve something you worked on. You go, man, I wish I could update that.
Um, man, that's a great question.
Um, I would like to update Alduin's texture.
I think, I think it could use, it could use some, some love.
I've actually, I've actually, um, made a remastered version that I've put up
on art station that you can, that people can see, um, if they want, but
I would love to get that updated.
And actually, you know, the patch that I would want wouldn't even be my art.
Not that I don't have a ton of art that would need it.
It would be on the animation system.
I would love, because I think an artist is sometimes only as good as the animation system
that the character is based on.
And so I would love to see some really fluid, smooth animations of these characters because,
you know, I literally could improve like.
There's literally things I would like to improve on every single creature, but I think that
what would really give us the most bang for the buck would be to see all these things
move more fluidly, all that.
And again, it's...
Skyrim was made by a team of 100.
And so it's like, when you look at it again,
like Assassin's Creed,
even the original Assassin's Creed was made
by a team of about 400.
And so it's just,
and almost exclusively,
they're all animating people and movements.
So there's so much fluidity and so much room
for just like realism and interaction, et cetera,
in those games.
And then a place like Bethesda,
at the time we had like,
five animators and they all had to and there's like there's dragons and there was mammoth and
there was a zillion non-human things um to animate and so there wasn't there wasn't the
resources that we could dedicate um to really enriching that system and i would love i would
just love one day to see that. Bubbles congrats on making it to the watchtower. Hey thanks.
Even though it took like 10 tries it was still 10 times faster than
going through Blackreach and all that stuff.
Yeah.
Blackreach was just actually,
it wasn't even like necessarily part of the plan,
I don't think, I think it was just created
by one of the level designers
and then it was just integrated, I think,
into the main quest.
Okay, so since I'm going kind of fast,
I'll just literally stand here and explain stuff
because we have plenty of time.
Yeah.
This is an Elder Scroll
and I've been playing for probably like 10, 15 minutes.
Mm-hmm.
Hey, it's the game.
But so all that horse stuff.
So I, uh, a lot of properties transfer over through saves.
Like if I am getting off a horse at really high speeds and I'm flying off of it and
I make a save in the, and then I, while I'm in the air, I load a save, I'm going to
fly really fast and that save I loaded.
as long as they're both in third person because they have different like
physics uh like collision properties um based on the perspective i think
but um and it kind of resets every time you go between first and third person
um wow that is mind-blowing yeah so and the reason i kept going back to
that helgen cave like i went from esbern back to the helgen cave is because i
made a save file
on the outside of the cave right in the beginning of the game.
That's the first thing I did was jump out of the place and make a save file outside of the cave.
And then after I rescued, for example, Esbern, I made a save,
and then I loaded this save, and then I went through the cave here.
And as the same time I went through the cave, I paused, and I went to the main menu,
and then in the main menu, I loaded the save where I had Esbern rescued.
And so when I enter the cave...
It's got this character in there, the one from this save file.
Uh, it's called the load warp.
Um, I discovered that I discovered that on accident, um, like four or five years
ago in oblivion and it also exists in fallout four, um, yeah, where I went
through a door and oblivion the same time that a notification popped up.
And so I had to.
click yes on the notification and then I went through the door.
But while the notification was up, I loaded a save file cause I was like,
all right, enough practicing time to start a run.
So I loaded the save file for my first run and then my character that should
search should have started the game when on the other side of that door.
So I was like in handcuffs and stuff and yeah,
that's so cool. That means like you, I mean like that's such a, such an accident.
So it's like a one in a million moment to that's now affected how you do all
your runs.
Like I think that's why I was so excited to like make this happen was because like those accidents, you know, define speed running but
The developers don't want those accidents. They want like the perfect
I mean skyrim is sort of the exception because they want k, you know, I jonah. I assume there was an air for chaos, but
um, yeah, but there's still some like, you know, that's not how it's supposed to work. Um,
Uh, we're gonna pull some more questions from chat. So bubbles. Thank you
That was watching jonah's expression. There was was
Yeah, so that was the two main biggest things.
I don't know why my neighbor was banging above me.
I don't think he was sending a signal.
I think he was like...
Oh, that's a...
Yeah, if your neighbor barges into your apartment, that's okay.
You know, like, that's okay.
The run can stop there.
Okay, so we're going to pull some questions from chat while we restart the...
while the run gets going again.
Sean McPherson would like to know, Jonah, what is the best and easiest way to learn
and get into normal, bump, height, etc. maps from your experience?
So normal maps, bump maps, height maps.
Do you have an answer for that question?
So I render a lot of those things.
I mean, actually, to be honest, I render exclusively
normal maps from high resolution files.
So when I take something from ZBrush
and it's three million polygons,
I can then transfer that using,
recently I've been using Marmoset,
but in the past I've used Crazy Bump
and other programs to generate normals.
So we get a lot of that work done from projecting,
projecting one model on top of another
and rendering a normal map.
I don't often render height maps or bump maps these days.
In fact, I haven't rendered a bump map
for almost the duration of my career.
Only when I was learning CG
was I starting to use bump maps
because I didn't know what normal maps were.
And for anyone who's just curious,
bump maps are grayscale images
that wrap around an image, a model,
and then when light hits that.
model, they tell, they say, you know, what pops out, what pops in, or what appears to
pop out, what appears to pop in, so that when light hits an object, it can appear more three-dimensional
than it is.
A normal map does the exact same thing, but it says what pops in, down, left, right, up,
you know, whatever.
So it's much more like a 3D access of things.
So that just gives much richer results.
So I will often work from ZBrush and then bring that high res model,
project it using a projecting software. Um, like I said, previously,
it was something like, um, uh, what I used to use.
Um, I forget these days I use Marmoset.
Marmoset render is a great program, super fun,
and it's really good at baking textures. So.
Yeah, and by the way, for anybody who has any further questions or I don't clarify things enough,
feel free to hit me up on social media. Happy to answer what I can.
Right on, yeah. Marie Stumba would like to know, how was the character creation modeling divided
between team members at Bethesda? Did everyone have specialties or a region level they worked on?
Do you have a specialty? I guess that's actually like a good production question too, like how do
you organize the billions of assets that make up Skyrim?
Yeah, so our art department was divided up into environment art, world art, and character art.
And within those things, within world art, for instance, we have people who create effects like
clouds, water, etc., mountains, skies, down to housing.
wall hangings, silverware, cups, that kind of thing.
And then you have, on the character art side of things,
you have people who make characters,
all character related things, armor, weapons,
that kind of thing.
And then there's animation as well.
And I think, and I don't know if it's considered
the same departments.
No, it's not considered the same department,
but physically when I was there,
we had the concept artists in the character art space
as well.
Within that, within that, for my job, my job would be to take a piece of concept art
that was kind of, had been a result of a back and forth between the art director, a lead designer,
and the concept artist, and then I would take that piece of art and I would basically
make sure that I knew, you know,
cause I like to riff on things.
I don't like to just create exactly what's in the concept art
because for me as an artist, I'm kind of like,
well, where do I fit in?
You know, I'm not just the,
I don't just transmute from 2D to 3D.
I like to invent, but I will ask the art director
or the lead designer or whoever, you know,
what are the elements of this concept artist art
that the artist has made?
What's your favorite?
You know, what do I,
basically making sure that I am not eradicating
that which really like,
inspires them. And then that also lets me know where I can feel free to tap dance.
So within that, within my job, I would then take that piece of two-dimensional concept art and I
would make it into a three-dimensional model that was fully textured. So I would make the model and
the texture, and only when that was all polished out would I hand it off to the animator, and the
animator would go to work on that.
So I would say at least a place like Bethesda,
it's small enough that everyone has to wear multiple hats.
And so for sure, I had to,
you know, it's not it's not divided down to like, I do the model,
you do the texture.
It's really like if you're if you're a character artist or a world artist
or whatever, you are doing both
except for the animation that you pass on.
And that includes rigging.
Before we move onward, I just want to process that that Jonah Jonah was giving us like such good deep cuts there that I
barely had the brainpower to look at my monitor and realize that Jonah or bubbles had picked up a bucket and
Used it to pass through an entire for somehow use it to pass through an entire castle
Finishing the sequence that we saw right before here
So, my brain like just broke a specific fraction of a percent watching that.
And I was just like sitting here listening to Jonah going,
I am listening to this wonderful team dynamic get explained while there's a game
that I thought I understood just breaks in front of me all because of a bucket.
And we got married.
Oh, we got married. Cool.
Hey, congratulations.
That's amazing. Mazel tov.
Well, we're not married yet.
It's my follower and our marriage is happening soon.
Well, I'm wishing you guys the very best.
Thank you. I really appreciate that.
Um, this is my dragon, by the way.
I mean, this I mean, with the dragon, I enjoyed making parts of next.
Yeah. What what what what did you enjoy about like
like what makes this so special to you as an artist?
about this particular asset.
You know, he's the one dragon except for Alduin who talks to
you really talks to you.
I mean, Odoving talks to you but not too in-depth and he basically
uses the exact same model as the other dragons.
I just gave him a reference colors from like a Kawasaki motorcycle
to make Odoving.
For Parthenax, he had a much more washed out bleached old thing going on, and he's a character.
And so I got to, I thought the concept art was great. You know, the way his scales look like a
beard, but still look like just scales that grew out was a really brilliant way of aging a dragon.
And I got to put a personality into his face. And I was actually surprised at how much
the audience seemed to actually really like Parthenax. So yeah, I had a fun time making him.
It's also interesting because Parthenax shows up really deep in the game to the point that I'm looking at the sequence and going,
I think I maybe hit this on my first run, but I haven't seen him since.
So the fact that it speaks to, you know, it speaks to your work that, you know,
players are able to connect with him, even though as Bubbles is so wonderfully demonstrating,
like Skyrim is this open book for people to throw themselves up against.
Um, that's a mixed metaphor if there ever was one. So for chat,
we are still taking your questions. We just wandered into
some specific topic areas for a second.
I'm gonna do something pretty, if you don't mind pretty
complicated. So I thought I would just spend like, like a
second explaining what's gonna happen. It's gonna make it's
gonna make no sense. So I got married because if you can't, if
you if you cancel a marriage,
canceling a marriage
will initiate the signal to the character of like,
hey you can move now. And so if we're in the middle of that Elder Scroll
cutscene with Parthenax watching the history repeat itself and stuff, you
know, in that time travel moment, we can't move. It's a cutscene where we
have to stay still. But if we can activate that cutscene and
then cancel a marriage like right after
that, then we can move around during that cutscene.
And so the way that we do that is enter this wedding room and
pull out the Elder Scroll at the same time.
So you're destined to get married and you're destined to get divorced.
Yes. He gets really mad.
If sometimes there's like sometimes there's routes with multiple marriages.
And so you come back to him and he's like, how could you do this to me?
And then he's like, all right, I'll marry you again.
This is an emotional rollercoaster.
My goodness.
So now we're in the cutscene.
We're bouncing back and forth between breaking a marriage
and using that marriage to fling yourself, you know,
through time and space,
which isn't how that's supposed to work.
Thank you for that explanation, Bubbles.
You, once again, just every five seconds,
I just have an existential crisis, thanks to...
Uh... I go here.
I am going to...
That's a lot of stuff I gotta do.
Right on. I'm going to go ahead and grab questions from chat.
Um, uh, Danny Cizek, uh, that could be Cizek.
I am not 100% sure on the pronunciation.
Uh, I would like to say for texturing, we'd like to ask Jonah for texturing
material design, was there a concern about targeting a certain realism standard?
If so, how did that measure to get, get measured across the studio artists?
Which I think is an interesting question because even though Skyrim
doesn't have a realistic look, it certainly has like the 3d models of it.
Have a
Specific to oh did something surprising surprise you yeah
I should have put my swords away before interacting with that carriage or my game crashes
I know it doesn't make any sense, but yeah, no no no makes total
It makes as much sense as everything else this run. This is why we make quicksand
Jonah, do you want to answer that realism question?
Yeah, can you ask that question real quick, the short version of that question?
Sure thing. For texturing and material design, was there a concern about targeting a certain realism standard?
If so, how did that standard get measured across the studio artists?
And that comes from Danny Chizik.
I see, I see.
Danny, you know, there wasn't the harshest metric when it came to that.
I think
Bethesda games already have a particular style, which definitely
is meant to sell realism.
I don't think, I know for, you know, I can speak for myself, attaining, making something
feel real was very, very high on my list of things.
And that doesn't just mean, like, getting all the textures just right, but it really
comes down to making characters and creatures that have...
a sense of weight that have a sense of age, you know,
where the skin wrinkles and folds in a certain way,
you know, to really make it feel lived in,
as if this thing existed before we, the players, even encountered them.
So that was my own personal attempt.
Oh, I made Alduin on that wall as well.
If anybody owns a collector's edition of Skyrim,
and they have that sculpture, then awesome.
But I, so there wasn't a particular metric that,
you know, the art director typically oversees that
and makes sure that everybody is kind of on board
and attaining a certain aesthetic.
But thankfully, you know, when you're inventing fantasy,
there's not a ton of one-to-one, you know,
contrast between like, oh, well,
you definitely got the dragon wrong
because we all know what dragons look like.
So it's much more about making it feel real, making it feel believable, but also kind of
going off script a bit. I'm definitely a fan for going off script for inventing and I think I'm
relatively known for making something that can sell as real but have
not quite a realistic feel, more like painterly feel
or expressive feel, but yeah, there wasn't,
there was not, in answer to your question,
there wasn't like a very strong across the board way
to measure that.
I think it's just the job of the art director
to make sure that things feel unified enough
that everyone, all the different artists
who are working on the team are creating something
that looks, I'm so confused,
all these dead dragons everywhere.
So yeah, the things basically hold together enough, you know, so
Bubbles, why are there so many dead dragons?
It's the great dragon war
Yes, it's the flashback with the Elder Scrolls. That's right again. I
Have played a hundred plus hours of Elder Scrolls never saw that. Sorry Jonah. That's okay. I have seen I have gotten that far
Because it's main quest nobody plays this. No, I said, I know I know it's a strategy
You gotta find those jewels.
I mean, that's my favorite thing.
That's my favorite thing about Bethesda games in general.
That's part of the reason I joined
the team and, you know, or wanted to, you know, set out to,
is because I just loved the fact that you can just go anywhere.
This is a very common idea these days.
But when I first got the game, Morrowind, when I was in college,
you know, I literally was Googling, you know, I really I really want to play
a good RPG, you know, Final Fantasy is not available on PC.
and I'm not even sure if I want to play Final Fantasy,
but you know, what are the good RPGs out there?
And I Googled top 10 RPGs.
And they had this game called Marwen,
which looked totally weird, totally alien.
And I like Weird and Alien. I like seeing things that I've never seen before.
I don't like too much classic fantasy because it's, you know...
For me, the whole purpose of fantasy is to see something and experience something that I've never experienced before.
And if fantasy is just dragons... Sorry, dwarves and elves...
I get kind of frustrated.
The Barwon really, really got me hooked.
And then what I didn't understand, which I only saw recently...
We just... your power of Alduin got sent to the sky.
Don't worry, guys.
So, this is a bug that can happen if you Lotus Save during the Alduin fight, when he's flying around.
This is the current patch, by the way, so...
But...
I know that's not your department, Jonah.
But if you load a save during the Alduin fight, he can just perch and never come down or be active again.
And so it can end the run completely.
But I have a backup for when that happens.
Specifically for when that happens.
So what happens normally is he lands and you just kill him pretty quickly.
You just hit him in the wing and then he talks for a second.
And so this is the backup save.
Look, this is...
Typically he would land like he did before and I would get him.
I would stunlock him on the wing over and over again.
If you look at my stamina, I can do this repetitive attack with both swords by initiating with
both clicks of the mouse and then just tapping so I don't consume the stamina.
Wait, yeah, it worked on the first one.
So yeah.
So I'm never consuming stamina.
Yeah, it's only going up.
Yeah, so that's the power attack combo infinite thing that you do.
It's because we used to play as the, uh...
I'll load this save just so I'm not out of sync with my timetables.
But, I'll, uh...
I'll use that
to fight pretty much everything in the run. But the only things I fight
are, uh...
Alduin and then Alduin again.
Jonah, sorry to where we sort of rolled
out here through the road.
It's OK. It's OK.
I broke my mind.
We're going to. Yeah.
I mean, we were just watching our
again, constant existential crises.
Yeah. I don't want to like,
I don't want to like, you know,
go to the end of the run
to explain everything that happened.
Yeah, no, this is good.
No, just jump in whenever,
because usually what I'm trying to,
you know, maintain a narrative and.
answer your questions. I'm usually part of my brain is just watching kind of like quietly exploding.
Oh totally, yeah.
So it's all good. All I was going to say was that when I first discovered Morrowind and
Bethesda Softworks in general, open world games were totally new. And so I really early on got into
not...
finishing the main quest. I was just like, the whole point of this is for me to discover
adventures. And I really felt like, I thought the team did a great job with Skyrim with that. I mean,
really, really, there's so much magic to explore and to see. And then I actually thought that
Fallout 4 was awesome at that. You know, I just, I jumped into Fallout 4 and I was just,
was immediately just loving all the side quests, et cetera. I don't know. Yeah.
Um, going from chat real quick, Bubbles, you have a fan here, uh, Eric, uh,
Billary, Billary, there's a J in there and I really don't know how it goes. I'm sorry, Eric.
Um, uh, they love to see Bubbles speed running and they love these questions in discussion too,
so we all get a shout out there, but you know, Bubbles, I wanted to give, uh, give your fans some time.
Um, uh, Jonah, you did not work on the VR edition, right?
You were gone from Bethesda by then?
Yeah.
Okay.
So Steve, can you, thank you for asking about the VR version.
Um, sadly, however, we cannot answer that question.
Um, Danny Chizik is here again.
Did you and the team ever encountered differences of opinion about the best
way to present a character or scene and how did you resolve them?
That's a good question.
Certainly.
I think that those kinds of things happen all the time.
I wasn't always, I was not usually a part of this discussion on how scenes would unfold.
Of course, playing the game I had some of my own feedback.
And sometimes I was listened to and sometimes I wasn't.
And sometimes that was a question of, they had a differing opinion.
Sometimes it was a question of just bandwidth.
We just didn't have, we recognized that there was an issue and we just didn't have time to fix it.
I'm trying to think of a particular difference of opinion that may have resulted in some
kind of conflict, but I can't think of one that occurred per se.
There's definitely like course corrections that happen.
So for instance...
you know, I, you know, when the concept art for the Spriggan looked a lot like a dry ad,
you know, she was just a woman kind of made of wood with glowing green light. And I just thought
that that's that was too standard fantasy. And I added, like kind of
an extra joint in the legs, gave her kind of stag legs, gave her huge horns, and then I
collaborated with the effects artist to create this like beehive look and feel. And
other things like that, you know, where you're kind of going off script.
And whenever I did that, I would make sure that that was okay.
You know, you don't want to just piss everybody off by just inventing.
And so I always, you know, and, and, and, and it takes time to make an art asset.
So as you're developing an art asset, you're often checking in with your, your
lead, um, to make sure that what you're doing, yeah, go through all those.
I love that.
It's one of the best things about the game, is just running across those huge tables.
The funniest thing ever is I've had record-paced runs die to running across that, and then
I would kick a plate in the air, and I would accidentally try to talk to Ulfric Stormcloak
the same time that I would press E, as the plate would be in front of my vision.
So I would accidentally steal something.
Oh no!
And it's such an ordinary bug, like that's what happens in Skyrim,
is you try to talk to someone, you steal something, and your normal play is interrupted.
Which is beautiful and chaotic.
It is so, like, yeah, exactly what you saw there, but I kick a plate,
and it intercepts my interaction press with the Ulfric, and the...
And then these guards all pull out their weapons because I stole a sword.
Excuse me, sir. I meant to say hello, but instead I took this plate and put it in my bag
They take food stealing seriously.
They really do.
They do.
Probably what we should have done is make it so that like when you try to
when you click on something and it's stealable, you should have to like
hold down the button an extra second to make it happen or something.
I feel like button holding came a couple of years after this
because I remember in 2011, you know, the other games of the era
because Assassin's Creed kicked up around that.
Assassin's Creed two kicked up like a couple of years before by 2011.
I think we were heading into, you know, revelations from that.
But we keep giving shout outs to Assassin's Creed today.
But you know, Halo Reach was out around this time.
And I distinctly remember like a couple of years later,
it was a few years before like hold down button to confirm an action
or an interaction was popularized in game development.
And then and then it was everywhere.
And now it's like, you know, I'm playing Ghost of Tsushima right now.
And it's such a common interaction that game.
You want to talk about a game that has good art.
That game is beautiful.
It looks unbelievable.
Yeah, unbelievable.
And so much of that is like lighting and environment.
And it's stunning. It looks stunning.
We're gonna grab a question from Michael Gibbs here unless bubbles
Is there anything else you want to break our minds with before I grab it?
Well, this is the peace council and if you notice all this stuttering and flashing that I've been doing this game that's happening right here, too
That's quick save quick loading and that's been around since probably fallout 3
It was first noticed that fallout 3 was broken when some Japanese player with fallout 3 was noticing that like
Every time he loaded a save file
nothing was loaded in for a second except for the character. So you could go through a wall real
quick if you loaded it next to a wall. And then somebody, an American runner named Craftlab,
integrated that over with quick saves and quick loads because it was available on the PC.
And ever since then it's been pretty broken with every Bethesda game because they kind of
recycle everything. And that's why load warping also works on like several of the games. But
Peace Council is going to be pretty boring. I'm just skipping the dialogue.
I appreciate the quick load anecdote.
Jonah, for your part, here is a question from Michael Gibbs.
Did you have any part in the Skyrim character creator?
Yes or no?
Quick yes or no.
No.
OK.
We're going to skip the rest of the question then.
Sorry, Michael.
But thank you so much for watching.
Yeah.
But I will say this, that when Skyrim started out,
the character creator, the characters
were pretty gnarly looking.
And my friend Dennis put a lot of time and effort
into that character creator.
And so many of the sliders and the abilities
to change face paint, face size, et cetera, was due to him.
He worked his butt off, for sure.
Dennis Mejiones is his name.
He worked very hard on that.
Big shout out to Dennis, do you know if he's still at Bethesda?
He is. Yes, he is. He is.
So if you didn't let the character creation system, it was not his fault.
It was due to the technical limitations.
If you do like it, it is that is that is due to him.
I mean, other people did, you know, other things like, you know, this guy,
Charles made it's like awesome, like hair in the game.
That's like is is just looks so much better than what we had before.
But then it's just put a lot of effort.
I think he was just profoundly unsatisfied with what we had and just
dedicated all kinds of extra hours to making the system work.
And so, yeah.
Right on.
Uh, just another reminder for folks in chat.
We are still taking your questions.
We've got some time left in, left in the run here.
Um, uh, bubbles.
Would you refresh my memory on how much time left we're expecting?
Um, I would expect somewhere between 20 and 25 minutes tops.
We that's such a, that's like the right amount of time to get some more questions.
And so we will.
We will take them. Jonah, we can get a little serious here while we wait for the Peace Council to wrap up talks.
You mentioned before about how you wound up with tendonitis as an injury from working.
People don't think about game development as a business with injuries, but the human body.
is poorly constructed and fails us in specific ways. That's why I'm sitting in a chair that
looks like a race car chair because my back was having issues working from my old chair.
How as an art, I think we've actually had a couple of GDC talks about managing, you know,
art is such an intensive process. Like it's so focused, you're constantly doing small hand
movements with things that were meant to club, you know, at best, maybe bow and arrow. But how
have you as an artist have like managed your physical health alongside your, your creative
health there, you know, like?
That's a good question. I think that it definitely extends to artists and programmers alike and
anyone who's sitting at a computer all day. Yeah, so I had sustained this injury working on Alduin.
He was behind schedule. I was referencing a meteorite in creating him, his surface texture,
so every inch of his body was pitted and whatever. And so then I had to...
create the low polygon version of all that.
And it was just very strenuous.
A lot of clicking, clicking, holding, clicking, dragging,
clicking with one finger, clicking with two fingers.
And I ended up falling behind and falling behind
and then just really hurt myself.
And actually, within a day of finishing Alduin,
I just had to stop.
And I was out of the office for three weeks, et cetera.
You know, we forget that that we humans, and especially we gamers, are animals.
We're not just, you know, brains with fingers that can move.
were animals. You know, when you look at your dog and they don't go for a walk that day,
they are profoundly depressed and very upset. And I think that we as artists need to remember
that we have bodies that need to be tended to. And so, you know, I got that injury right
around when I was 27 or so, which is about the age that a lot of mortal people realize
that they are mortal. You know, for the first time in their youth.
their body is suddenly failing them.
I had discovered from an art perspective
that a couple different things helped.
I did a lot of PT, and the PT helped to a fair degree.
A lot of stretching, a lot of icing of the wrist.
I think people forget that icing
is not just for pain management,
it actually accelerates the process of healing.
And so that was one other thing I did.
And I really took to stretching.
doing a lot of stretching and that helped out a lot.
Ultimately, what I did discover is that the problem wasn't in my wrist, which I thought
it was, even though the result was tendonitis.
The problem was in my spine.
I had a whiplash injury from back in the day that apparently between these two vertebrae,
the nerves that come out from between the vertebrae, because between each vertebrae,
we have nerves that shoot out into our bodies that control our limbs, that control our organs,
etc.
And it was those two vertebrae that I had this
compression in with the nerves that go to the tips of the fingers. So I think it was
partially due to overwork on my part.
and partially due to just poor posture and mismanagement
and sitting too long without taking breaks
and not moving myself and getting my whole body stretching.
These days I put a lot more effort
into getting out of the house, going for a walk.
These are the things that loosen up, not just,
they don't really loosen up your wrists per se
or your fingers, but they will loosen up the bigger,
more central and more integral parts of the body.
So.
To people who are looking to reduce their own physical strain, often that starts farther
up the body than you think it does.
So really focusing on your back, really focusing on your neck, making sure that you're, you know,
that you're getting some very basic flexibility up there will do a lot of help. So when I'm
experiencing wrist pain, often I stretch my chest, you know, against the wall or open it up,
and that reduces the pain further down the extremities.
Take care of yourself, watch out for your physical well-being, really respect the fact that you,
you know, whether or not you care to admit it, you're an animal and you need to treat yourself
as if you were your own pet. And take those fundamental care of these basic aspects of
yourself. That is generally good advice. Bubbles, we've gone from the Peace Council to a dragon.
What exactly are you doing to speed this particular part up? We're going to capture
Oda being so we can go to Skuldaufen.
and find Alduin.
And so there is a trick where you can shout while you're opening the door, and then you
get him in the first available second that you enter the stream, but I couldn't line
it up, but it's okay.
So I just got him the casual way.
JGYou still got him trapped while doing these insane feats.
Let's see here.
Uh, we have some more questions in chat.
Uh, Danny, we will get your question, but because you know,
we've gotten a lot of yours, we're going to grab Gabe, uh,
Pofkers, Pofkers.
Uh, do you have any favorite stretches?
Would you be willing to demonstrate a couple?
Uh, wow.
That's I hadn't thought of being able to do that on the stream, but yeah, if you
have any stretches that like help we, uh, you know what actually gave, we're
going to pause on that.
Um, we do have a GDC talk on the GDC vault that should be free to access.
That is about.
Um.
name it is about stretches that you can do.
So I'm going to go look that up while we get another question in for Jonah,
and then I'll put that in chat.
So we're going to let that be the guide for it,
because we have a whole talk about it.
And Jonah doesn't have time to
ethically get you through some helpful stretches in five minutes
because the five minute education on that is probably not enough.
So we're going to get to Danny.
Your question does come up
between concept modeling, rigging and animating.
How long was the average pipeline for characters in terms of days,
weeks or months?
Um, you know, it depends on the assets.
So something like the dragons, um, I was given, I believe, 32 different
illustrations of dragons, uh, to make, to, to, to reference, uh, before I made,
um, the dragon.
And so I actually couldn't even tell you how long that took.
I think that that took.
you know, probably I would say maybe a month or two to generate all those different images,
of which I referenced about three or four to create the final model.
The first time I made a dragon was, it took me almost three months, but that was because
it was a very iterative process.
You know, oftentimes the aesthetics that we want to go for, for instance, a really, really
long neck, et cetera, you know, when you're actually fighting the dragon and you're, you
know, early on when you were attacking this thing.
you're attacking it and it's facing you and so the head is right in your screen and the body's 40
feet away and so it just looks like a giant cartoon bobble head just like in your face the whole time
so like you know there was a bunch of these large scale iterations
The average monster or creature would take me about a month.
You know, that's about three, four weeks,
sometimes five, depending on the complexity
of the art asset.
And then from there, we get into animation.
And animation typically would also take about a month
to create the basic set of animations.
But invariably, there were lots of iterations
over the course of development.
I mean, all of the time, animators had to return
to
the original art asset, the original animation,
and just keep tweaking, keep tweaking, keep adding,
keep bug fixing, that kind of thing.
And so from start to finish, from concept to finished
product, I would probably just round up to about four months
because, and half of that being.
well, maybe three months, but half of that being animation,
because animation is just very time consuming.
It requires a lot of polish to get right.
Yeah, so usually it would take me between three
to five weeks to finish something.
You know, if it was something easy,
like just a circlet, you know,
I made the circlets with the gems in the game,
that took me two days.
The Dragon Priest that we just saw,
that took me about a month,
because it's a lot, you know, very complex uniform.
Yeah, so and then and then again, and so and then some
things, you know, the concept artist spends a couple hours on
and the art director might be like, yeah, perfect. That's
great. Exactly what we're going for, you know, or they might
take a month. So it would you know, you can you can usually
more or less scale depending on the complexity of the art asset
and go from there. So from anywhere from eight hours on
something to a month of concepting anywhere from
12 hours of modeling and texturing to five weeks.
You know, and I'm not counting the dragon
in that large guesstimation
because the dragon was so exceptional
and required such a mountain of labor.
But I can guarantee you that the animations of the dragon
took forever for the artist to make
and allotted back and forth.
It takes a while.
And when you think about all the different creatures
and non-human things.
You know, all the things that don't share a skeleton.
It's a lot of bandwidth for a small company like Bethesda.
That makes sense.
Speaking of animals, I forgot you were like humans or animals,
or I forgot to mention it, as some of you may have noticed, my animals,
my cats, whose GDC talks were rejected.
If you follow our GDC Twitter feed,
wonderful talk submissions were rejected, have been hanging out with us.
if you want. I don't, there's nothing productive about that. I just, they've been hanging out
so good on stream. I just want to share. Okay, we've got about 10 minutes ish left in this talk.
Danny, thank you for joining us. I can see you've got to head out, but that's,
thank you so much for asking these questions. Yeah, I can only just keep saying, keep asking
questions because the ones I've got are just my own. Otherwise, otherwise I'm going to keep
talking about my cats. The game's just about to end. Oh, the game's just about to end. Cool.
We have a couple minutes. We can take a couple more questions while Alduin gets finished off.
We can also admire the beautiful Alduin model.
Admire it for 3, 2, 1, and we're done.
And we're done.
And there goes...
Look at the wings, though.
There goes 6 months of my life just burning up.
I got it on medium graphics just for you.
Oh, thank you.
Medium whole graphics.
Bumped it up from low to me.
All those little meteorite, you know, inspired bubbling.
I don't know, I forget the phrase.
Oh my gosh.
The verb.
Yeah, a little cratering.
Yeah, that's the thing about this is, you know, as a character artist and as a 3D artist.
you know, I might spend a whole day on the underside, not the whole day, but half a day
on the underside of a character's foot, you know, and knowing that, you know, 99% of followers,
of viewers won't ever, ever see it or notice it, but it's always worth it for that 1% of people
who actually take the time to look at a model and check it out and see what's going on. Because
I invariably get comments from people or questions about like, oh, I noticed this,
I noticed that. And I'm like, cool, cool. So I'd spent that time like for you. Now I know,
like didn't go totally to waste.
It literally, I mean, like, hey, we'll take the, you know, we'll take six seconds of appearing on a GDC stream to entertain folks and entertain entertains bubbles and entertains folks at home.
We'll take it.
Bubbles, let me know when you want me to stop the timer because it is.
Oh yeah.
When Alduin dies, it's not like when his health bar went to zero, it gets stopped.
It's cool.
We have, we have no idea what the time was then.
It's just about one hour.
Um.
Anyway, yeah, let's take a couple minutes. Bubbles, feel free to show off any other tricks.
We've got, we'll say, we'll give it another three minutes here and then I'll ask for us to be
quietly sunsetted and I'll read an outro. But we'll get a couple more questions in. Thank you.
Thank you, Christina Pigeon, for hanging out. We appreciate your company.
Matteo Fasano would like to know, could you elaborate on your modeling workflow in ZBrush?
Is it important to have 2D drawing skills for making complex models?
That's a good question. I get that a lot. No, it is not important. It's not vital.
It's always helpful. It's always good. You know, I think a lot of problem solving
comes through in two-dimensional art. So you can figure out a lot of things by being able to do
that. But no, I've seen some amazing 3D... I mean, I know a lot of amazing 3D artists who do not do
2D art.
I'm always of the mindset that art is complimentary and so that the things we learn when it comes
to like 2D art, whether that's...
Oh my god, this is hilarious.
What is that?
That is that scary.
You made this Jonah, come on.
Who threw it off?
It just works.
This is your fault.
Oh my gosh.
It's getting worse and worse with every moment.
Oh my god.
I'm so sorry.
Yeah, so it's, and then with regards to my workflow, I always work from the most simple
to the most complex.
So again, my work is known for being quite detailed, but I will always, always, always,
you know,
take a cue from, oh my god, this is so disturbing.
I will take a cue from movies like Pixar,
that this and that, which were,
they are really so good at conveying so much with so little,
you know, so much like design,
like so much with like the big shapes and big forms.
I will take, so anything I make,
I start off with a very, very simple set of shapes,
and then I go from there.
And so that's one thing I really like about,
ZBrush and about the sculpting process is that I get to create something very basic,
very simple, and then continue to add on.
more and more complexity.
So I always have these different scales of design.
So when you look at the lines of the dragon's head
in this game, for instance,
a lot of the contours of the head flow together.
So even though the dragon is very visually complex,
a lot of the shapes of the throat,
of the spines on its back, they all flow together.
And they form these very, very simple layouts.
And then I just kind of add on more and more complexity.
while always making sure to preserve the underlying aspects.
So, and I guess that's also another way in which two-dimensional art helps,
because being able to focus on the clean, pure shapes and lines,
first and foremost, makes it so that when you do start to pay attention
and start to focus on adding all this little detail,
you're preserving what amounts to the fundamental...
visual power and thrust of whatever you've created.
So keeping it simple is is the best always.
Don't I appreciate your participation in the Give Serious Game Dev
Answers while watching horrible nightmares be rendered on screen in front of you.
That was that was I'm going to be dreaming about that tonight for sure.
Real quick, we're getting close to wrapping things up.
Here's what we're going to do.
There's one more question in chat that I want to grab
from Steve Kuhnhus.
We're going to make that the last question of this.
Want to give a shout out to folks like Michael Gibbs,
chemistry editor-in-chief Chris Graft in chat,
Sean McPherson, Tim Brangle, Jessica Mao.
Thank you all for watching.
We appreciate having you on for this weird experiment.
We haven't tried anything like this before.
We haven't tried a virtual GDC.
We haven't tried beaming in game developers
and speed runners.
and having the former watch the latter. This is new, and the fact that you have all joined us
here for this experiment is really wonderful. Normally, when we start these sessions, we say
turn off your cell phones and remember to do your session evaluations, but guess what?
You can keep your cell phones on because you're at home, but please do fill out your session
evaluations. If not for this, I don't know if there are session evaluations for this stream,
but for any other talks you do, please fill out.
uh... the evaluations for the end of the show the official survey all that helps
us make a better gpc for the future
uh... and we're gonna be back later this week with two more speed runs for
ukulele in the impossible air and star wars republic commando of those both
should be a lot of fun
uh... if you wanna find me i'm on twitter are brian twenty twelve jonah
and bubbles where can they find you
uh...
I can be found on twitch.tv slash bubblestuffuego, bubblestuffuego.com.
So it just redirects to Twitch and my Twitter is the same.
It's all just that word.
So Twitter, YouTube and Twitch.
I primarily stream on Twitch.
Lately I've been doing Halo 3 but, you know, I've had a bunch of stuff in a lot of games
so you never know what I'll do.
Roger that.
And Jonah, where can folks get in touch with you if they have more questions?
Sure, you can find me I do a live stream about once or twice a week on Twitch.
That's twitch.tv slash Jonah Loeb. You can find me on Twitter at Jonah Loeb. That's probably the
best place to answer me and to ask questions. My website is jonahloeb.com. You can also send
me messages there. And I'm on Instagram at I am Jonah Loeb.
So yeah.
So here's our last question for the day from Steve Kuhn.
How many LODs of the dragons are there?
I don't know if you're supposed to pronounce that LODs,
but how many LODs of the dragons?
We always call it LODs.
Gosh, I don't know.
I think there's only maybe like,
I think there's only one.
I think there's like the basic one,
and then there's like the LOD version.
architecture and landscape, it's a lot more levels.
But for the dragons, I think it was more basic.
Or maybe there was two, maybe there's two, yeah.
Yeah, that was always really fun,
taking my precious art and crunching it down
to something just awful in distance.
That was one of the things about working with Bethesda,
is I'm a stickler for all this detail, et cetera.
And I remember when we made Fallout 3,
and I made the radroach, and Todd Howard
was just basically telling me,
like, it looks great, but you need to,
you know, it's 6,000 polys,
you need to cut that number down a lot.
And I remember, you know, even as new character artist,
I was kind of arguing with Todd.
I was like, no, it's got wings, and it's got a shell,
and it's got six legs, and ta-da,
and I can't possibly do that.
But I remember when he, you know, I would often make a creature for the game,
give it this high-res texture and he would say, that looks great, you know, that looks, I love it.
Now cut the texture down, you know, quarter your texture. And I would just, and every time I would
just be like, damn you, Todd, like, why would you do this to me? Like, I don't want, no, why? And
then I would do it and then I would quarter the texture and I'd be like, oh, I made this and I
can't even tell the difference. And so I guess this is why you run the show.
I would I would say the second part.
I keep that second part to myself.
And I'd be like, oh, oh, oh, so we can't find Todd.
Oh, so we delete this part of the archive is what you're saying.
We can't let him find out.
No, no, no. I can't.
I can't let him know that I was giving him all the credit he deserves.
But ending on a Todd Howard anecdote feels like the right way to do this.
So with that, bye, everyone.
Make sure to wear a mask when you go outdoors.
We are going to go home now. Bye. Bye. Bye.