Good morning, my name is Brian Francis. I'm a community manager with GDC and a contributing editor at gamasutra.com.
If you need to refer to me in the third person, my pronouns are he him. I am joined today by EA Sports
Accessibility Lead Karen Stevens, who spent the last few years giving a number of great GDC talks about accessibility.
Karen, would you please introduce yourself?
Hi, I'm Karen Stevens.
It's kind of awkward because you just introduced me,
but I am the EA Sports Accessibility Lead.
I've been doing this for several years.
I've been at EA for seven and a half years.
I was at Microsoft for eight years before that.
Did some accessibility there as well.
And before that, I was actually in the medical industry.
My pronouns are she, her,
but I'm not super picky on pronouns.
So as long as I know you're referring to me,
it does not really strongly matter to me.
So yeah, rolling right in.
Just waiting for that.
We can keep it going.
Karen, how are you doing?
How's your GDC been?
Unfortunately, I've been having trouble
with captions in sessions,
so I haven't actually gone to any sessions yet.
I saw part of Cherry's session
because it was recorded after the fact,
but I haven't had a chance to, like, see anything else.
So I'm really hoping I'm able to participate
any more fully in the future.
I am deaf, so I am purely lip-reading you,
and will probably have to use typed-in questions, too.
Of course, yeah.
Okay, looks like everyone can hear us. So we're going to go ahead and get started.
Though that's interesting because we just talked about accessibility and now the folks who can
hear us will be okay, but everyone else will be having some issues. But we're going to get started
with some extra buffer time to get questions in. Okay.
I'm going to get started with a little monologue.
We're here to ask questions for Karen, so please go ahead and start typing those in chat.
Please use the questions feature in Swapcard, because what you do if you do that is that then everyone can upvote the questions.
And then from there, we need everyone to pick the questions they'd like to see answered by upvoting them.
I'll be pulling from that section and occasionally glancing into chat.
to make sure we didn't miss anything.
If you need some inspiration,
I'd like to point out that a big thing at GDC Summer
has been the topic of accessibility in video games.
Karen just mentioned Cherry's session from earlier in the week.
The GDC Live podcast had Greg from AbleGamers on.
We've seen developers like Naughty Dogs
build incredible tools to help players
with different disabilities play their game.
And the work Karen has been here at multiple GDCs
just kicking butt, showing off what can be done.
And it's been mind-blowing to see how the EA Sports titles have done all this work to be more and more accessible to players.
Accessibility can take different forms though.
Earlier this month Obsidian Entertainment built a feature to help players with arachnophobia
play their game grounded. If you have any questions about building these features for Karen,
we can get started on answering those because I see them coming in chat.
I'm gonna go ahead and
I'm sharing the first question we have with Karen.
This comes from Jade Summers.
What guidelines do you test against?
Microsoft XAGS, accessibility guidelines, et cetera.
So we use a combination of guides that come in
from all first party publishers,
because they all have, pretty much all have something,
and they're all different.
So, which means that if you combine those all together,
you have a relatively good cross section.
We also have our own.
So.
If you look and see our font guidelines I've had in some of my different presentations,
those are actually in EA as well.
We use those for certain critical path type things to try to push things forward.
Now you may notice a lot of things still aren't there.
A lot of policies we have is every year must be better than the last, and you should never move backwards.
And if you keep doing that, eventually you will reach those guidelines.
But we do have our own guidelines that are internal.
Certification does manage them.
And the accessibility team, because we do actually have a team,
goes in and works with those people.
And we try to come up with guidelines that we all follow.
So that's roughly what they come against.
Right on.
I just dropped our next question for Karen.
So I'm going to read it for the audience, which is...
Jason Doss would like to know, at EA Sports, have the dev teams on NHL, NFL, and FIFA shared
their accessibility suite of features? I assume they mean with each other.
Yes. And yes, it depends on which game as to what's shared. FIFA and Madden, for example,
share quite a bit. They both are using Flight for their menu narration, for example. All games at EA
Sports are all using the same libraries for text-to-speech, speech-to-text, which under the
hood is using IBM Watson.
And my talk I gave a couple days ago at GDC covers all of that.
So if you want more information and links as to how you can use those features,
then that's a good example.
In terms of code bases, the code bases of the game, like FIFA and Madden,
have some commonality.
Some games have more commonality than others.
So how much we use depends.
The Colorblind module for Madden is being used in a wide variety of games, even outside
of sports.
So, same thing with the text-to-speech, speech-to-text, it goes outside of sports, it's not just sports.
So a lot of things may incubate in one team and they get spread across the entire company.
Typing our next question in chat, so I'll read it for the audience.
Next question for Christopher Gomez, how do you playtest accessibility features?
Really, we play test them like we do anything else.
Honestly, we really need to do more in general.
We do ask types of questions with that usability in mind,
because really, usability and accessibility are related.
If usability is simply, accessibility
is usability that's considering a wider audience, more or less.
So we do cover things like that.
We do have like my team, for example, it acts as a filter because due to various legal like HIPAA type laws,
it's not possible for us to currently ask our employees to give feedback along those lines,
but it is legal to ask my team and I'm deaf, I have a co-worker that's totally blind,
multiple issues and so between my actual team, we just so happen to be a good crosscut.
And since our job is accessibility, it's okay to ask us.
So my team acts as a filter and guide for all that.
But really, we need to do more in this area.
Karen, I'm going to ask a follow-up question.
I'm typing it in chat for you.
Let's see.
I'm sorry for the brief silence.
I just need to type this myself.
And I can't copy and paste it.
Okay, so the question I just asked Karen for the audience is how should developers prep for the legal requirements around building accessibility features given that Karen just brought up the good point of employers often can't legally ask certain people about that in certain ways.
Talk to a lawyer. Seriously.
I am, I am not a lawyer I cannot give legal advice, I can't speak at the answer to, you know.
Relative things that have happened that I've noticed that there are legal issues to a degree,
but I literally cannot give legal advice and I have to ask you to speak to your local legal
counsel. And I recommend doing that immediately, honestly, because it does vary on region and
depends on where you are shipping things. What you can or can't ask also varies by region. So
what I said is very specific to certain regions. So please ask your local legal counsel for the
regions in which you're working in because it does wildly vary.
That is a great point, and I think just as valid an answer.
We are still waiting for more questions.
I would like to advise folks in chat
that if you are still getting the spinning
multicolored, inconsistently colored wheel,
please go ahead and refresh the page.
That will bring the video back online.
From there, I am going to pull from questions
that I prepared for Karen.
However, I was ill.
I was overconfident and did not move them to my other machine this morning, so I'm going to type them in right here.
Okay, and for the audience, what I just asked Karen is, what does your process for designing in-game communication look like at the start of development?
Okay, so I will say we should ask more generalized questions as opposed to these questions.
I will answer this, however.
So forget about in-game communication.
What does process for designing accessibility look like?
So it really needs to start from the requirements level and go all the way through.
You should be looking at this when you're first designing your game, even before you've
actually made any menus and things.
And that's in general good for all features.
It doesn't really matter what the feature is.
The later you do accessibility,
the more expensive it will be
because you'll be finding out that,
oh, wait, you don't meet file requirements.
Oh, look, you didn't think about menu narration.
Like it's really, really important
to try to think about this as early as possible
and design this in as early as possible
because then you're not going back
and having to fix things.
And that's more expensive than doing it in the first place.
The question that I prepared was that lots of games have been implementing ping systems
to allow for nonverbal communication.
Are there ways that these can...
Oh, okay.
Never mind.
That question has been nixed.
So to go over that, just in general,
when you're working on a paying system,
please make sure you're considering all your audiences,
including blind gamers, because they're often missed,
and they are just as important as everybody else.
Also make sure you're considering your deaf gamers,
so you're not making a paying system that's audio-based,
because that's a problem.
So largely, just try to consider a full audience
when working on any system.
Right on, we're gonna pull Ryan Lippert's question.
Ryan Lippert would like to know, I'm a law student in California.
I anticipate graduating in December,
and they're interested in this topic.
What, if anything, would you recommend
they do between now and then to get
some experience in this field and read new recommendations?
And for what it's worth, they have ADHD,
and they would like to know how the industry is when
it comes to employees with ADHD.
Sorry for repost.
My first attempt, accident.
Oh, OK, yeah, that's not part of the question.
All right, I'm reading the question right now.
Actually, I have ADD.
I've been diagnosed with ADD.
So I feel for you.
It can be, it really, you need to, what helps me is figuring out what my own accommodations
are and for me, I like, I try to streamline things as much as I can.
I have my own database that I use for tasking that's called currently JIRA or JAZ and I
actually have an internal email address that when I email, it creates tasks for me, which
is really helpful because people outside of my team can.
Give me these tasks and we can.
Go from there.
So like I can use that to just populate database, but I also use that for my own needs.
So every time somebody asks me something, even when I'm in a meeting, I can fire off
a one line email to this thing, even as soon as somebody asks, and it immediately gets
sent off.
Another thing I use is there's literally a whiteboard right behind me and the other side's
completely covered with scribbles.
And if somebody asks me something, I literally always have a pile of whiteboard markers on
my desk and I literally just write it immediately behind so I don't lose track.
So that's just my own ways of handling this, since like I said, I do have ADD.
And yeah, it takes figuring out what works for you, because every single person is different.
And even if we're all diagnosed with similar-ish type things,
I'm aware ADD and ADHD are slightly different.
that it's figuring out what works for us.
And I will say that this,
sometimes things can be more challenging
in a closed environment,
but honestly, I like working from home
and the fact that the total current work from home,
everybody doing thing.
because it's quiet and that really, really helps me.
So, plus I'm deaf, so actually when I'm sitting at my desk at work, I'm not wearing my hearing aids,
so I can just turn it off. Now, the opposite would be wearing a noise-canceling headset
if you're not deaf. For me, I just basically put my hearing aids in instead of taking a headset off.
But that's sort of just trying to stay closed helps.
When I am in an office environment, I have used really, really tall boards.
For example, foam boards, even though I'm at a cube,
and I actually have made extra walls around me,
so I can't see anything, and that's helped me too.
So it's a matter of figuring out ways to help yourself focus,
because I've had these challenges myself.
Our next question is coming up.
Did that go through?
Yes, it did.
Next question from Christopher Gomez.
How would you teach accessibility
to game designers?
Workshops can help having, I have a Confluence site that has information internally for this type of thing.
So I can, if someone asks me a question, I can leave them to a link to the answer, assuming it's something I've already answered.
If it's not, then I make a new webpage that covers it.
And I do have like an eight-hour masterclass I've done before.
that I've used, I've drawn information from.
And it's important to work with all game teams individually.
So like for EA, a good chunk of our teams
have accessibility like liaison type people.
So we have people who have been appointed
or have volunteered to be the accessibility contact
so I can give information to them to be passed along.
And that helps too.
I will also say that UXR is really important.
So if you have a UXR group.
Having UXR people work with your designers can help too.
And then have them be the ones to evangelize
different accessibility practices.
So, and also just sending them to things like GDC
and having them cover that sort of things really helps.
Our next question comes from Daniel Rupert.
They work for the Wounded Warrior Project.
Daniel, thank you for joining us.
And thank you for your service.
Some of our veterans have TBIs, lost limbs, et cetera.
What is a good resource for adaptable controllers?
Xbox's accessibility controller would be my first recommendation.
It works on most platforms at this point, and it allows attaching many, many different types of devices to it,
which gives you a wide variety of options.
Also on the Xbox, there is a concept of copilot.
So you can have multiple input devices
working at the same time.
This can help you if you want to use a regular controller
and also have your feet use some buttons.
You can set it up so you can use the accessibility controller
for some inputs and then your regular controller for others.
That works well, too.
So those are all options I highly recommend.
And if you go to Microsoft's website,
there is a
large amount of information available for all the different types of inputs that you can use with an accessibility controller.
Oh, sweet. I just want to thank chat real quick for bringing in more and more questions. They're coming in really quickly.
And they're upvoting really quickly. Thank you. From Jason Doss, with EA doing accessibility features built into games,
do you also test accessibility features in regards to hardware?
Specifically, do you test your game features for say,
Xbox Adaptive Controller or any third-party accessibility hardware. Thank you.
We do to some degree, not as much as standard controllers.
I will say that a lot of our play testing labs now are actually
gaining Xbox accessibility controllers and with a wide variety of adaptions.
So people are actually using those in our play testing sessions and things and we also are,
I have several controllers that
Especially pre-COVID, people would be continuously borrowing from different teams so they can use those with all the different attachments.
Like I have a gooseneck attachment. I have one-handed controller pieces. I have joysticks. I have all sorts of things. Buttons and switches and toggles.
So they are being tested.
They are not being as regularly tested as standard controllers, and I can see that being an improvement for the future.
I am sending our next question along from Olivia Tandowski.
How do you address accessibility for mental health concerns?
So this will be more of a general thing than game specific at this point in time.
One thing I have had come up because I've had, I do spend a lot of time speaking to
people with various types of issues and getting information from firsthand experience.
But I will say that I've noticed.
people with PTSD for various reasons have mentioned, especially veterans with PTSD,
things like it's important to have audio tracks that will be specifically for things that
could be contentious. For example, a gunfire could be an issue. A medic, someone shouting
out for a medic or yelling and bleeding out can be an issue. Now, the actual concept of
Gun warfare may not be the problem in itself, it could just be very specific things like that.
So, let's go back to things like Gears of War. They had an option for flower blood.
That was pretty awesome. That was a great way of handling it. Or, you know, option of no blood,
no gore. No gore is a great option too. So things like that makes a lot of sense,
and I highly recommend that. If you can think about the different types of audiences and
things people may be afraid of. I know a game recently came out with arachnophobia mode.
I can't remember the name of the game off the top of my head.
Grounded from Obsidian.
Thank you.
Things like that really help.
Now, it could also be that maybe it's stressful
and that causes issues for various things.
It's super timing.
So lack of hairline timing could be a good thing.
Different difficulty levels can help, too.
There's a lot of ways to address different types of mental health
issues in games.
While before the next question goes up, I will just say, wow, I never thought that some of the specific triggers might not be, you know, the gunfire or the violence itself, but specific realistic cues like someone shouting medic.
From Dom Harris, I'm making a fast-paced top-down shooter and would love to make it as accessible
as possible.
I've got sliders to control game speed for people with slower reaction speeds.
I've got made sure it's all color blindness friendly and works with a screen reader, that
sort of thing.
Is there anything else for this type of game, a top-down shooter, that you can suggest?
Wow, that's a difficult question.
It sounds like you covered a lot already.
Those are really good starts.
Make sure that when you're doing colorblind friendliness
that you're picking something that will work with most people
because human eyes vary a lot.
So if you're using filters, for example,
it may not cover everybody.
That's true of almost anything you pick.
So having brightness and contrast can help too.
Contrast in particular.
High contrast is great for people with low vision.
Low contrast is great for people with photosensitivity.
So both matter.
That's one thing to keep in mind. I do like the fact you have game speed in particular.
Alternate controls and reduced button modes can be helpful, too.
Real quick, I'm just gonna go ahead and catch up with chat for a second while we prep our next question.
Thank you all again for participating.
I will grab this question. One second.
Aerith Arzola would like to ask,
what has been your worst experience while testing a game?
I'm just going to answer this as which experience playing a game, something without captions.
And if it's something without captions or any indication of what things are going, what's
going on or what my goal is without only audio, I am deaf and lip reading and I can't lip
read a video game.
So if a game has like audio only and it's telling me what to do and it's very specific
as to what I need to do, I am probably not going to be able to play the game.
And there are several games I can think of, but I'm not going to name, I don't want to
call anybody out.
have been problems for me.
Our next question comes from Jade Summers. Jade would like to ask,
what is the hardest thing to try and implement at the last minute when making a game?
That is really hard to answer because games vary so very much. It could be that
Menu narration could be an issue for you, because maybe you don't have enough disk space, depending on how you chose to do it.
Or you're against the wall with performance, and that could be a problem.
It could be font size is too small, and there's literally not enough room on the screen to fit everything at a font size that's legible.
It really varies.
It really depends on your situation.
It's just important to try to consider it at the beginning, because pretty much anything can be expensive if added in too late.
While we're waiting, I will also say the custom controls can be difficult to cover at the last minute as well, so please also keep that in mind.
Roger that. Oh, that's a good point. Yeah, I'll read the question I just sent to Karen. What is a topic you didn't have time to cover in your talk that you would like developers to hear?
Um,
So for my talk, one thing I would like to overemphasize is that when you're doing
When you're considering what API to use to make a synthetic voice, keep in mind that most platforms have them already.
So, like, Apple has voiceover, Windows has narrator. It is possible to use that in your games.
Like, I was the tech lead for all the games that came with Windows 7 back from Microsoft,
and all those games had the ability to be menu narrated, even though they were all
DirectX-based. And it is possible to do that, and it's not as hard as you think.
So, keep that in mind that you can actually, like, make conceptual overlays.
Keep in mind that when you're working with blind accessibility that the way people navigate
things can be different than when you don't have the feature turned on.
You'll notice that Windows Narrator itself makes Windows behave differently because it's
assuming keyboard-based navigation, not mouse-based navigation.
And I really, really strongly recommend turning on narration on your own local platforms that
you're implementing on.
especially if it's Windows or a phone or a tablet,
to see how it's navigated and how it works.
Because I'll give you a lot more information right there
as to how to use your game,
or how to implement that in your game.
Our next question comes by way of both Pat Diemendahl
and with some clarification from Nicholas George.
Thank you both for asking this.
I just want to make sure I asked it as best as I could.
How do you get people, whether it's developers or gamers,
to buy in on accessibility mattering?
I will point out that there's such a thing as a vocal minority.
So keep that in mind when you're.
working on feedback because the vocal minority tends to drown out the majority sometimes.
So it may not be as negative as you may think. Generally speaking, especially each following
generation is more inclusive than the last. And Gen Z in particular just wants to know,
why can't I play with my friends? So keep that in mind that it does often come from the right place
and it's not as contentious as you may think. Now, when it comes to development,
But I will point out the fact that this is using US census numbers.
One in five people are disabled.
When it comes to 18 plus, it's one in four.
By the time you get to mid-70s, it's one in two.
And statistically speaking, most people will be permanently disabled before they die.
So.
It affects a very, very large number of people,
and gamers are aging.
Yes, we have new gamers coming in all the time,
but people, generally speaking, don't stop gaming.
So that's just things to keep in mind when doing this,
and that it is a large audience.
And those numbers don't even count the one in 12 men
who are colorblind.
So when you're talking about these features,
using the statistics can really help,
explaining how it helps people can do.
And I know that over half a million Madden users
are colorblind.
So when you come up with those numbers, and it's like, yeah,
half a million people can't play your game adequately,
and may not know that some of the UI is there,
it becomes a lot easier to try to push things through.
So I used a game jam to get started,
and that's how I put in these features into Madden.
And then I showed.
I got a lot of positive feedback and press and things and the things I did do and I used that
positive feedback to say look people actually like this it matters people care and that helped me be
able to do more. So that all keeps in mind. Use feedback from other games as if you go out there
and do search on accessibility into like news articles you'll find a ton. Use that information
to try to help make pitches to put features into your game that really does support.
A follow-up from Pat Diemendahl, what negotiation techniques can help convince stakeholders
that accessibility is needed?
So yeah, like I said again.
Showing that other game companies are doing things can help.
So that's why the news articles and feedback
and all that really do matter.
Statistics also helps with that.
Pitches, especially like executive level pitches
can be really helpful.
You might have to work up your chain for that.
So at that point, start with your producer level
and executive producer and work your way up
depending on how big your company is.
But yeah, it's challenging.
Like, and be aware that small steps matter.
So like when I originally put the features into Madden, I did almost everything within a month alone.
So it doesn't have to take a lot of people.
to start. And if you can show benefit with the little bit you started with,
that'll give you more attraction to do more. So,
baby steps do matter. And same thing with like how we're handling increasing font
size in games and things. If you if you can get one pixel larger
than the previous year, that's still an improvement.
And if you do that every year, you will get there. So,
it's important to try to do little steps and work incrementally.
Big steps would be awesome, but little steps matter too.
We are going to do a last call here. We have a couple extra minutes to account after our tech issues from the top of the hour.
So if you'd like to get your question in.
Get it in right now and we'll grab it.
While we're here, I will ask folks
to please fill out the session evaluation, which
in this case will come by way of a rating that
either pops up in your notifications
or will be visible in the session after it's done.
And feel free to fill out your session evaluation,
your feedback for the end of GDC that will come in your email.
That feedback will help us make the show better next year,
whether it's virtual or in person.
Our next question from Jason Doss,
after, could you please explain
how much planning goes into directional control patterns?
They have played UFC in the past,
and there are so many movement patterns on the analog sticks.
Some movements can put stress on the thumb
without needing to press a button.
I will say- With needing, sorry.
I will say this varies incredibly from game to game.
And the most important thing you can do is if you do run into issues,
just to make sure you give us feedback.
I have a Twitter account of EA underscore accessible.
I recommend tweeting this sort of thing.
There is also a forum of EA.com slash able, A-B-L-E.
And this is super important to give feedback on so we know that these are issues that need to be worked on.
Because all games are wildly different and we are going to miss things.
So, yes, feedback matters. Make sure you say things. Make sure if you say you like something too.
I know somebody who's using eye gaze technology to play The Sims with their eyes.
And it's really important to tell us that that's currently being used and appreciated
to make sure we don't accidentally break it.
Because we may not realize that something is super important to somebody and accidentally
turn it off and then cause problems and not mean to.
So it's important to say what you like and what you don't like so we can work towards
a more accessible future.
Real quick, I need to own up to a mistake from a couple of seconds ago.
Pat, who asked a couple of great questions, their last name is Dima Andal, not the way
I phrased it before.
Our final question will come from Chris Miglio.
Don't most text-to-speech solutions
need to be connected to the Internet?
What if you want the text-to-speech voice to be
on the device without having to be connected to the Internet?
So for both Madden and FIFA, you do not need to be connected to the internet for text to speech to work.
For menu narration, in particular. You still need to be connected to the internet to do multiplayer because it's multiplayer, you have to be connected to the internet to play multiplayer.
But for just menu narration, we're using a tool called Flight. I have a link to it in my GDC presentation that was presented on Tuesday. So I recommend going there and looking at the last slides and getting that link.
And basically it does menu narration on the fly.
So we just pass in text and it gives audio and that works relatively well.
NHL actually has pre-recorded menu narration, so we use voice actors to do the recordings.
And so that is also on disk.
Menu narration in general, I don't...
I think most of our games support it without the internet.
Roger that. This is it. Thank you all so much for asking your questions. They've been wonderful.
Thank you for folks who are participating from different parts of the game and game development community.
We appreciate you joining us today. Karen, if they have more questions for you, where can they ask them?
I recommend Twitter is probably the best place. So EA underscore accessible.
I am happy to answer any questions you have. Roger that.
Thank you all so much for joining us today, and I hope you have a wonderful day.
final day of GDC summer. Have a good day everyone. Thanks, bye.