So, the story of user research on Destiny is really a microcosm of the story of the development of Destiny as a whole.
And so, just so you can't really talk about Destiny without talking about Halo,
you really can't talk about user research on Destiny without also talking about user research on Halo.
So, for ten years, Bungie made this game called Halo.
and therefore that's what we did our research on.
And we got pretty good at it.
We made five games in that series.
And we pretty much thought we had this job down,
that we knew by the time we got to the fifth one,
we knew exactly how to test the Halo campaign.
We knew how to test competitive multiplayer.
We thought we were pretty good at this.
Unfortunately, it turns out that.
the move to Destiny sort of upped the difficulty quite a bit.
That there were a lot of built-in assumptions
into how we tested Halo,
into the Halo game that made user research easier for us.
Simple things like the fact that each game mode
was a distinct experience,
that you could test the story mode by itself
as an isolated experience
and not have people mixing and matching
in between activities.
The fact that all the missions were always played in the same order.
It turns out to have been a great luxury that we didn't know we had at the time.
Suddenly, we had to make every mission not only fun, but also the right difficulty level,
no matter when people got to it and what state they were in when they got to it.
The missions were more or less independent experiences.
For example, it's very common in game development that Mission 5 isn't working this week, and therefore, that's fine.
We have people play up to Mission 4, we have them read a little paragraph of what happened in the story in Mission 5,
and then we have them proceed on, skip through Mission 6 and let them proceed.
And that works pretty realistically.
In Destiny, suddenly, if you have to skip Mission 5, you haven't gotten any of the experience points.
from that mission. Your character is now under-leveled from mission 6. You don't have any of the gear or the talents that you needed to beat that mission. And suddenly, the entire rest of your testing experience is out of whack because that one piece wasn't there. And Destiny was this very integrated game where all the pieces had to function in order to get good data. A couple of our issues were also sort of metaphysical. On the Halo games, certainly by the time we got to the final ones, we very much knew what kind of game we were making. We knew that
what the modes were going to be, we generally knew what the general mechanics were going to be.
A lot of the big, sort of, hard decisions about game design were already made.
In Destiny, we were discovering a lot of that, and a lot of that was changing over the course of development.
And finally, we knew what kind of players we wanted to play the game.
I mean, the kind of people we wanted to play Halo Reach were pretty much the same kind of people who played Halo 3.
That that was a well-understood audience, that we really had...
had been in touch with for years, they'd played our games,
we had data on exactly how they played our games,
and we had this sort of very good understanding.
Suddenly with Destiny, we had RPG elements.
Okay, should we be recruiting RPG players?
Are we aiming for that?
Are we aiming for MMO players?
Are we aiming for people who play both?
Are these action adventure gamers?
There was a whole bunch of just fundamental assumptions
about our audience that were suddenly called into question.
At the same time, Destiny was just huge.
So we had four planets, all of which
were bigger than any of the Halo missions we'd ever done,
four enemy races, each as complex
as the Flood of the Covenant, three classes, hundreds
of weapons, story missions, strike missions,
and finally we had patrol and raid,
which were completely new experiences that really
had no analog in anything we'd ever made or tested before.
So this was pretty daunting.
At the same time, this is our first game
we were making outside of Microsoft.
So on previous titles, we'd had the benefit
of Microsoft's lovely user research infrastructure, which
is very elaborate and very well planned out.
And so we had to do this all ourselves.
And we were free of that infrastructure.
So we had to build our own tools at the same time
we were actually testing and building the game.
So building the lab is actually the easy part.
This is a picture of our lab.
It's pretty straightforward, pretty standard compared
to most of the industry.
But the hard part actually is putting people in the lab,
is actually recruiting the participants.
And I'm going to geek out a little bit here.
Please bear with me.
So I know that talking about recruiting participants
is not the sexiest topic in the world, but it really is.
OK, I have one enthusiast.
It really is what defines the limits of your user research
program, because if your recruiting methods don't
get you casual players, you can't run that kind of test.
If your recruiting methods take a few weeks
to get to your participants, suddenly you
have to be testing on a very well-planned, long-term time
scale.
And you can't do snap tests at short notice.
I'm going to talk a little bit about how we went about recruiting participants for Destiny
playtests.
Bear with me, this actually is important.
So first off, we created a sign-up forum on our website to let people volunteer.
We've had over 350,000 people sign up to be playtesters.
And they all give us demographic data, their age, gender, where they live, a bunch of their
attitudes towards games.
They tell us a lot about themselves, and we connect all that to their Halo gameplay data,
and now to their Destiny gameplay data, so we know who they were in their actual play
as well as who they said they were.
And this led us, when we wanted to run a study,
we could then pull exactly the profile participant we needed.
We could say, OK, we want people who've
beaten the campaign on Legendary.
We want people who played less than an hour of multiplayer,
people who played more than 100 hours of multiplayer.
We could use this survey data to say exactly where they were,
all their demographics, and their gameplay data to know
how they played our games.
We pull that sample of people and then send them an online survey to schedule them.
So this is unusual.
Most recruiting agencies call up all their participants on the phone and screen them
that way, which tends to be a very manpower-intensive process and take a lot of time, and ends up
costing something on the order of $200 a participant to recruit a participant this way.
Because we could send a survey that would screen them and schedule them and slot them into their time slots,
we could basically schedule a study with very little work, maybe a couple of hours of work total by the researcher.
and on very short notice.
So anywhere from a week to three days.
We did a couple of studies on two or one day notice.
We've never done a same day study
where we kicked off the scheduling in the morning
and had people show up in the evening.
The system certainly would support that.
But I don't want my designers thinking
they can drop things on me in the last minute.
Don't tell them.
I trust you guys.
And one other geek note I'll mention on this,
not all survey tools handle quotas the same way.
So not all survey tools are necessarily
suitable for this kind of scheduling setup.
So there's some fine technical details
in how they handle them that make them more or less suitable.
So we had all these systems.
working and they had them all connected together.
So we could have this one system that would let us pull participants that we wanted,
schedule them, screen them out, and have them show up in the lab.
And we had really good success with this.
We scheduled something like 1,400 participants over the course of four years for this game,
saving us on the order of $400,000
by doing all the scheduling in-house using an automated system.
Now, you may be right to be skeptical that...
our participants were probably a little biased,
that these were people who signed up on a Bungie website
to test a Bungie game in a Bungie building.
So yes, they were fans.
But we dealt with that bias in a couple of different ways.
First off, a lot of the questions we were asking them
weren't the kind of questions that would be affected by bias.
So if we asked them, do you like Destiny better than Call of Duty,
yes, their answers would be biased.
But if you asked them, do you like Mission 5 better than Mission 6?
there's no reason to believe that their bias would affect one mission more than another.
So it sort of cancelled out.
We also did some comparison studies where we actually did use outside recruiting agencies
and found that the internally recruited participants gave us essentially the same data.
Particularly directional data,
that if the internal people said a mission was too hard,
the external people said it was too hard, and so on.
And their rankings of what were their favorite missions and least favorite missions were all identical.
We also did some post-stratification work
to look at how our sample differed
from the real population.
So along the x-axis here are different player types,
and the y-axis is how common they were in our sample
and the general population.
And as you can see, type 1 players
were very common in our sample.
Those are the online engaged players.
But because we knew how common they
were in the general population, we could weight their answers
and give them the proper.
the proper impact on our ratings.
So the first thing we did with all this wonderful data
was to segment the Halo Reach player population,
say how many types of Halo players there are.
And there's a bunch of different ways to do this.
And the way we ended up settling on
was doing it by play habits, that we're
saying if you have a population of players,
are there subtypes of similar players
that play the game in the same way?
There's a bunch of different algorithms,
and we can segment them by things like demographics,
their ages, where they live, all that kind of things.
But what we ended up settling on and using mostly
is how they played the game, what proportion of time
they spent in the different game modes in Halo.
So some people spend lots of time one mode,
some people spend more balanced.
But we could use that to basically give
each player a behavioral fingerprint
and then group players by having who had similar fingerprints
to say there are a small set of specific subtypes of players.
And one thing I'll say about this process,
so in case you decide to do this yourself,
I'm not going to talk about the technical algorithms so much.
I found the process of segmenting the player base to be almost more interesting than the
final answers themselves.
I mean, it's very satisfying to say there are five types of players and here are the
mathematically the best five clusters of players.
But when you're, uh...
doing the analysis, you're trying a lot of different types.
You're saying, well what happens if I factor in age
or take out age?
What happens if I split up story mode
from just one bucket into two buckets?
Oh, sorry.
Into two buckets by difficulty level.
And the answers you get change as you change the question.
And how those answers change are almost more interesting
than the final answer themselves and tell you
a lot about the texture of your player base
in a way that just the there are only five players answer
doesn't tell you.
So one model might say, OK, there
are three types of players.
There's red, blue, and green players.
Let's say we add in a new factor into the clustering algorithm
to chew on, and suddenly that green population
splits into two subpopulations.
And now the algorithm says the best fit
is having four types of players.
The really interesting thing here isn't,
are there three kinds of players or four?
It's, why did that happen?
Why did that factor make that difference?
And why did those players group together or split apart?
And all those kinds of little texture moments to your data,
I found really important and interesting.
And I'll stop teasing you and talk about the actual type
we found.
So we found there were, depending
on how you counted, either 5, 10, or 3 types of players.
So there were three overarching categories,
that there were campaigners, there
were people who played Halo primarily for the campaign,
then played multiplayer for a little bit and dribbled off.
There were omnivores who played in a very balanced way,
spreading their time across multiple game modes.
And there were specialists.
There were people who loved one game mode
and just played it for like 90% of their playtime.
Some examples might be capture the flag specialists,
or people who played only custom games with friends.
And each individual subtype of specialist
was very rare, only a percentage or two of the population.
But taken together as a group, they
made up a substantial minority.
And so as we were analyzing this data and thinking about it
and incorporating it into our plan for Destiny,
the idea of the omnivores really struck home,
the idea that there were players who
were playing in this balanced way,
spreading their time across multiple game modes.
And it had always been the idea for Destiny
that there would be a variety of activities,
that one of the essential design pillars
was an activity for every mood, that we would have intense.
competitive activities, and very calm activities, story missions that you were guaranteed to
win if you spent enough time, and raids that were intended to be deliberately very hard.
But once we had the idea of the Omnivore, we started thinking that
We really want to encourage people to play not just the right activity for their mood,
but also to play a variety of activities and to not specialize too much.
This was connected in our heads to the idea of the buffet effect from psychology.
The idea that if you have one flavor of food, like a giant bowl of white rice,
you'll feel full and you'll get sick of it sooner than if you have five flavors or ten flavors out in front of you.
That's why when you go to a buffet you always end up eating too much.
because it takes longer to get bored of having so many different flavors and so many different tastes.
And talking about in terms of food, it feels a little negative and has some bad associations,
but if you think about it in terms of things like CrossFit,
where you go to the gym and there's a workout of the day up on the board,
and it's randomly determined and you won't get bored.
It's not like you're, okay, I'm going to the gym and I'm going to swim laps,
and I know I'm going to swim laps until my eyes bleed.
there's something different every time,
and you never get used to the routine.
And it makes for a more robust athlete.
And other games have done this sort of thing before.
They've deliberately set out to encourage omnivores.
So if you play Hearthstone, which I do too much,
they have their daily quest where they say,
OK, we're going to give you extra gold if you play this class
you don't normally play.
And so maybe you never play a priest deck,
but you have a daily quest for it, and OK, yeah,
I'll go look it up.
I'll go look up a priest deck and give it a shot.
And that way, if your other deck that you normally play
stops working, well, you had that priest deck
you played yesterday.
Maybe I'll play that instead.
that being a broader player, a more robust,
a more omnivorous player, actually
makes you a more robust player.
If you only play one game mode, in some ways
you're very fragile.
If that game mode stops working for you,
if it stops having rewards for you,
if it stops being possible for you,
if you only play cooperatively with your friend online
and your friend stops playing, you probably stop playing too.
But if that cooperative play is just
one segment of a wider array of activities you engage in.
you'll probably be more likely to keep playing even
after one segment of that stops working for you.
And therefore, if the decision was really
made to slope the floor towards helping all players play
like omnivores, and please note my phrasing on this,
we are not requiring players to be omnivores.
We are not forcing them to be omnivores.
We're just always making it a little bit easier
to play that way than to play as a focused specialist player.
And we're going to give little nudges to you to go play
as a.
to play in a more balanced way.
So for example, even if you're playing a warlock in Destiny,
we'll drop gear for other classes
to just give you a little nudge towards trying
another character.
So it's like, oh, I don't normally play a titan,
but hey, I got this really cool helmet.
Yeah, I'll give it a shot.
And we'll just encourage you to be playing
in a more balanced way.
Probably the extreme example of this
is the exotic bounties, where we, for example,
the thorn bounty.
where we require players to both do strikes and PvP to get this really good weapon.
I'm not the only person to blame for the Thorn Bounty, if you've had it and hate it,
but certainly this was one of the components that led to that idea.
So we did a lot of research on Destiny,
and we knew we wanted to start really early.
So this chart shows the research studies
we did per month on a number of our different games,
starting from launch at the far right side of the graph
and going backwards in time to the left.
And so we really wanted to start early on Destiny.
And we knew we wanted to get a lot.
We had these big open design questions,
and we knew we wanted to get the game in the lab early
and do a lot of early impact.
Unfortunately, there's some very real concerns about,
OK, you're testing the game four years before it comes out.
A leak is much worse than it's going to be later on.
Because we really didn't want the first information
out there about Destiny to be coming out of our labs.
So we upped our security quite a bit.
This is Jerry, our head of security.
This picture was actually voted one
of the eight manliest pictures on the internet.
And I fully agree.
But we upped our security quite a bit.
Our players go through metal detectors
to make sure they're not bringing any recording devices
into the lab.
We make them lock up their cell phones.
They are never left alone with the game.
And we do our testing platforms are very highly locked down
to make sure that no one could take a screenshot
and email it to themselves or anything.
Our security processes are probably overkill in a strictly
sort of practical sense, but they let the studio trust us
to put the game in the lab probably something like six
months earlier than they would have otherwise.
So we got six months more impact on the game
than we would have if we hadn't gone to such elaborate lengths
on security.
And one of the first things we found
was we were testing the game is that there
was a split between.
testing the game as a whole and testing it in specific parts.
And this is connected in my mind to the idea of the Heisenberg principle, not the
breaking bad Heisenberg, the real Heisenberg.
The idea that the more precisely you know the position of a particle, the less you
know about its velocity,
because measuring one interferes with the other.
And we really found if we...
we couldn't test both the game as a holistic unit
and any specific mission or part of the game at the same time.
Because if we wanted to test the game as a whole, we said,
OK, just sit down, go ahead and play.
Well, we couldn't guarantee that enough people would play
any part of the game to give us real statistical power
to say anything about it.
And even if they did, if half of them
went straight to that mission by just skipping straight there,
They're going to be underleveled and half of them go off and do something else for three hours and then come back.
They're overleveled.
How do you combine that information to get a real mathematical picture of how hard that mission is or how fun that mission is
when players are coming at it from such a variety of angles?
So we ended up basically testing every piece of content multiple times,
and pretty much in parallel.
The idea that we would test it very specifically,
and under controlled conditions,
so we had the statistical power to make strong claims about it,
about its difficulty, and so on.
And also test it as part of a larger, holistic, free-form test,
where people were allowed to progress naturally.
And so to give you an example of a free-form test...
the kind of results we got.
So this is, each column here is a mission
in our story mode.
And these are the Earth missions, Moon, Mars, Venus,
Mars.
The black lines represent the ideal level
for the characters going to that mission.
That's the level the enemies are.
So, and the blue dots represent the level
the players were when they got to that mission
in this particular play test.
And so as you can see, people start off on track,
missions one, two, three, pretty good.
Then they're under-leveled for mission four, five,
start to catch up on moon.
They're under-leveled on Venus.
And then by the time they get to Mars,
they're very under-leveled.
And in particular, that particular
level jump between Venus and Mars was a deliberate design decision.
And the idea was that people would get there, they'd look at the Mars missions and see that
they were higher level than they were, and they'd say, okay, well I can either go straight
into those missions and have them be a little challenging, or I can go do something else for a while and come back.
I'll go do a strike, I'll go do some PVP, and I'll come back and I'll be the appropriate level.
And as it turns out, players didn't even see
this as a choice. They just plowed straight from one story mission to the other.
The way people can...
and just said, oh, I guess the game gets really hard now.
And the way people ended up consuming the story missions
almost reminds me of the way people watch television
series on Netflix.
The new series of House of Cards opened, I guess,
this weekend, right?
And they drop all the episodes at once,
and people just sit down, watch it all in a weekend,
and just hate themselves afterwards.
And that's pretty much what seems to happen with story missions, is people, even when
we say, there's other stuff to do, go, go try something else and come back, it'll still
be here.
They still want to just plow through story mission after story mission.
And so we had to actually sort of correct our assumption and make it, Mars a little
more accessible than it actually ended up being, it was in this test.
So this is an example of our freeform testing.
the holistic testing.
And then, for example, of precision testing,
this is a difficulty for each of the story missions in Destiny.
So again, these are Earth, Moon, Venus, and Mars.
And each column is a mission, and the length of the bar
is how hard that mission was.
So if the bar is going up, it's too hard.
If the bar is going down, it's too easy.
And we did this kind of testing repeatedly
over the course of development, because things
would change all the time.
Even if nothing had changed in the mission itself,
There would be small changes to combatants, there would be changes to other mechanics.
If suddenly ammunition was dropping less frequently, a mission could get more difficult,
even if the mission designers hadn't changed anything.
So we did a lot of repeated testing to make sure that things were staying trued up all the way along.
And by and large, we were pretty successful in hammering down the difficulty spikes,
although there were still a few in the released game.
This is the Chamber of Night mission is one that stands out in my mind.
This is Telthor the Unborn. He's a cutie.
And so this is the final mission on the moon.
And this is actually, this mission is actually an example of a design pattern that we used
a couple of different times that ended up being very difficult for a lot of players,
where we basically lock the player in a round room, there's limited cover, and there's multiple
waves of enemies you have to beat with finally a boss Telthor at the end.
And if you die at any point in that process...
you have to start over from the beginning of the encounter
and do all the waves again.
There's no save points in between waves.
And this really ended up being a hard skill check
because there wasn't really a whole lot of options
for players to handle this encounter differently.
You couldn't, because you're locked in the room
with the enemies, you really couldn't hang back and snipe.
You couldn't sort of kill a few and then run away and come
back.
It was you're in there with them,
and you're either good enough to survive or not.
And this wasn't a huge blocker.
I mean, we didn't lose.
a majority of players or anything, but we lost a few percentage points of players in
the campaign when they just weren't good enough at that moment to come to beat that encounter
and didn't even come back after they were higher level.
So that's all I'm going to talk about is those two types of testing, the holistic and reductionist
testing.
I'm going to talk for the rest of this talk,
I'm going to talk about some special topics
and some particularly interesting research
findings about Destiny.
But please make no mistake, this kind of testing
that I'm showing here was the majority
of what we did on Destiny.
It was very straightforward user research,
where it's can people progress through the game overall,
and what does their progression curve look like,
and is each piece of content working the way
we think it should be working.
It's not, again, not particularly sexy,
but was the vast majority of what we did.
So to go into some special topics,
so Destiny is a class-based game.
And we really had an intent that players
would be able to recognize what class was coming at them
in PVP instantly.
That if something comes around the corner at you,
if it's a warlock, you have to react very differently
than if it's a titan.
So we really wanted players to be able to instantly recognize
what class.
And there was a lot of work that went into that.
on class silhouettes, class color schemes, and shapes.
And of course, once those assets are actually built,
they're very expensive to change.
So we wanted to test them early, back
when they're just concept art and they're very easy to change.
So these are some examples of Destiny concept art
we put in front of players.
And so if you look at concept A there,
essentially everybody said, yes, that's a hunter.
They looked at that.
They said, yep, earth tones, triangular silhouette, yep,
that's a hunter.
But character B, a lot of players misidentified as a warlock.
Something about the shape.
That was intended as a hunter concept,
but something about the color scheme and the clean outlines
tended to signal warlock to players.
Likewise, character C here, players correctly,
everybody correctly identified as a titan.
But character D.
a lot of people misidentified it as a hunter.
Again, because the color scheme is something
about the ragged cloth and the outline
made people misidentify what class.
So we were able to give a lot of feedback early
to help the artists tune their designs before they actually
built anything.
Another topic we did research on was class regret.
So like all RPGs, we asked players up front
to choose what class they want to play.
It's really stupid because we ask people to make that class choice at the moment where
they know the least about the game.
And we ask them to make a choice that's then going to affect the rest of their play for
the entire experience.
And we're pretty much setting them up for failure by asking them to do it that early,
but that's when you have to make the choice.
So early on we gave them class descriptions that were very lore-based, that talked about
the theme of the class and the feel of the class and the fantasy of the class.
But a lot of players ended up regretting
what class they were playing by the time they were done.
Because that lore didn't tell them
a lot about how the class would actually play in combat.
So we ended up moving to much more
gameplay-based descriptions, where
we were talking about the class's super abilities that
really defined how they would play in battle.
And players were much happier with this.
And by the end of the testing, we
had something like 85% of players
saying they were very satisfied with their class
by the end of development.
by the end of their play session.
So another topic we did research on was player recognition.
So Destiny is what we call a shared world shooter.
And it's a game where you run into other players
no matter what you're doing.
There really is no offline, single-player experience.
Even if you play a single-player story mission,
we're going to randomly matchmake you with people,
and you'll just come around a rock,
and there'll be other players.
And that's awesome, and that's part of the magic of Destiny.
And I'm actually going to play you
a quick clip from one of our earliest play tests
where that system was in action.
There's no sound in this clip, so don't panic.
So these are two players playing through in our lab.
Player 11 there is a little tired from his adventures,
and he's going to have a seat on the rock in Cosmodrome
and look out over the vista.
Yes, no.
Yes.
Let me try that again.
So player 11 is going to have a seat and take a little rest.
And player 6 is just going to happen to run into him.
These players are not in a party together, they just happen to be playing the same mission
at the same time.
And they run off to have adventures together.
So this is a great moment.
They can't talk.
We have no, we don't turn on voice chat by default.
They're not match made.
They don't know each other.
We just put them together and they have this great sort of human moment of contact.
As it turned out, and I think pretty much every employee at Bungie can tell you the
first moment when that system came online and we were testing an internal build and
you just happened to run into another employee, it's like, hey, cool.
You start following them around the environment because it's like, it works.
It's working.
But players were missing that moment in some of our testing,
because they didn't realize that what they were seeing
was another player.
They couldn't tell the difference
between a player and an AI.
And this is actually a video showing an example of that.
So what you're going to hear the moderator asking him
as he plays is, are the players you're looking at human
or computer-controlled?
Computer-controlled or controlled by people?
Computer-controlled, because this slayer just
threw a grenade that.
I don't know yet.
Hold on, just give me a little bit.
And let me make it clear.
I'm not making fun of this guy.
He is not stupid.
He's failing because we failed him.
We didn't show him, we didn't give him
the information he needed to know that those were
real people he was looking at.
And therefore, he didn't get that sort of magical moment
of, hey, it's a real person.
I'm really interacting in a living world,
because he couldn't recognize that those were people.
So we ended up improving the nameplates.
to make the players look, stand out a little bit
from the background.
So on the left is what you saw in that video,
and on the right is what we finally ended up with.
To make them much more distinct from AI,
and to make them clear that these were real players.
Let's see.
So we could guarantee they had that sort of magic moment.
Another topic we looked at was directional damage indicators.
So these were sort of, this is sort of a.
This was almost a religious debate on the design team
of how directional damage indicators should work.
And so in both these images, the player
is actually being shot from the same location.
He's being shot from above and behind.
And the top image is what we call
an absolute directional damage indicator, where
we're showing a little arrow pointing behind,
and we're showing a flash on the top of the screen.
The bottom image was what we called a relative directional damage indicator
that would sort of lead you towards the person who was shooting at you.
The idea was that you would turn towards that red flash and turn towards the arrow
and we adjusted on the fly to aim you towards your opponent.
And Destiny had a much faster time to kill than our previous titles.
So we really wanted people to be good at reading the directional damage and responding to it.
So again, this is one of those cases where the system is
expensive to build, and we didn't want to build it
and then decide we were wrong.
So we built these mock-ups and asked players
to click on a little picture of a character
and tell us where he was being shot from.
So for the top image, here was the heat map
of where players clicked.
They clicked above the character and behind him.
But for the bottom image, pretty much everybody
misread that and said, no, no, I'm
being shot from the right.
So of course, we finally ended up going with the absolute
damage indicators at the top.
This was almost a service we provided to the design team
in just breaking the religious debate.
And sort of like, OK, everyone can't agree.
Here, here's data.
We can all move forward now.
Destiny had a really complex UI.
So this was the first game where Bungie made extensive use
of eye tracking on our games.
And mostly we primarily used it in the moment to tell what player is looking at during usability
studies. And so I want to show you an example of that.
So I'll warn you in advance. So this character, this player is about to
accidentally delete a bunch of his gear while he thinks he's equipping it.
If you've played Destiny, this is extremely painful to watch.
I warned you.
I see some power, which might be helpful.
You can see the material he's getting from dismantling his armor popping up in the upper right hand corner.
Look at the green arrows.
He already worked those in there.
That was pretty impressive.
Quick turnaround.
I'm just going to try to load up.
Okay.
And as you can see from the eye tracking,
his eyes don't even flick to that upper right-hand corner.
They don't even see the materials pop up,
because that channel is just out of his field of view.
And you can tell he is reading the tool tip.
That just saying, pressing button X dismantles the gear,
clearly isn't enough to prevent him from doing it.
And so we actually ended up adding a safety mechanism
that you don't just have to tap a button
to dismantle your gear in Destiny.
You have to press and hold the button.
And the more valuable the piece of gear,
the longer you have to hold it to dismantle it.
So if you have an exotic and you want to dismantle it,
it actually takes a long time to fully destroy it.
And so just a personal anecdote on this,
like the first time I got in the Legendary in an internal build,
I did this.
I accidentally dismantled it because we
didn't have any safeguards.
And I was so angry.
I was ready to go over and punch somebody on the UI team.
And at the same time, though, it struck me
that this meant the game was working,
that that little pixel gun that I'd just gotten,
I was so happy to have it, and I was so
invested in that virtual gun that I was so angry that I
wanted to go over and hit somebody.
And so I had this great moment of, oh, we're screwing up,
but oh, that worked.
So.
We changed a lot.
So among the many changes from Halo to Destiny,
one of the minor ones was that we couldn't pause the game.
Because Destiny is a shared world game,
and we expect players to, it doesn't make sense
to pause in multiplayer like that.
And as it turns out, we used pausing
for a whole bunch of basic logistical things
in our research testing, from simple things
like being able to pause and go to the bathroom.
or telling everyone, hey, pause your game.
We have lunch for you outside.
And so suddenly, we couldn't do that,
because the game doesn't pause.
But one of things we also used pausing for
was giving feedback while people were playing.
As they were playing along in a campaign mission,
we'd pop up a little dialogue saying, how are you doing?
And they could say, I'm bored, I'm fine, I'm frustrated,
I'm lost, whatever, as they were playing.
And then we'd pause the game behind that menu as it came up.
And of course in Destiny, if we'd done that, players would die.
Because the game wouldn't pause behind the menu.
So we had to find a way to give feedback while they were still playing.
So we added a contextual feedback system.
So you basically press the touchpad and the face button and the data mining system would
log a moment of saying...
I'm frustrated here.
And we log it with all appropriate sort of XYZ coordinates.
We log who you were playing and where you were playing,
all that kind of stuff, so we can analyze it later.
And most importantly...
connected to our video.
So we could plot out maps of where people said they were frustrated, where they were
lost, and importantly, where they were having awesome moments.
We think of user research a lot of times as finding the problems in the game, but the
best moments in user research are when you find the awesome moments in the game and get
to tell the design team, we need more of this, this is working, that statue is awesome, how
do we make sure everyone sees it?
And so here's an example of an awesome moment of, OK,
you catch your teammate being heroic right in front of you.
And you can say, yes, OK, how do we give people more chances
to see that kind of thing?
We also imported our data into our world editor.
So the environment artists and designers in Destiny
work on a tool called Grognok, which is our world builder.
A lot of times when we were making this incredibly rich
data, but our designers had to come to us to get to the data.
They had to come use sort of strange visualization tools
that are really only well understood by user researchers.
So we wanted to be a little more accessible.
So we decided we were going to bring the data to them.
And we imported into their world builder tool
so they could look at it in the same tool they use every day,
the one that they use to make changes to the game.
And for me, this actually represented sort of how I believe fused research should work,
is that we brought the data to them, we made it accessible to them, and it's our responsibility
to put it in a format they can read and a place where they can easily access it.
We also streamed our playtest from the lab out into the studio.
Oh, yes.
Yes.
There we go.
We also streamed our playtests out into the studio
so everyone who didn't come down to the lab,
and we certainly wouldn't want them all
to come down to the lab at the same time,
could watch from their desks.
And this is the first game where we include face cams
in all the playtest video we recorded.
And I think that was really helpful
in really inhumanizing the data.
Because it's one thing to watch a player die,
respawn, and go and charge back into battle.
It's another thing to watch him die, see him bang his head on the desk,
respawn and go back into battle.
And just that moment of seeing what the human reaction was
to what's going on in the game, I think really helps.
Even if it's hard to quantify mathematically.
One of the challenges we had, one of the other challenges we had,
I'm sorry to be skipping around here so much, but a lot to get through.
One of the challenges we had in Destiny was how we were going to test the endgame.
So Destiny had this raid experience, where it launched, the first people to beat it took
I believe over 10 hours to beat it, even the best teams in the world.
And the problem is we had this endgame content that was designed for experts in a game that
didn't exist yet, and there were no Destiny experts to test the content.
So we end up breaking one of the cardinal rules of user
research, and we brought participants back
multiple times, which pretty much doesn't happen very often.
Most of the time, we bring in participants,
we get their initial reactions to the game, and we thank them.
We give them their gratuity and let them go.
But in this case, we were bringing back
people who would, say, come in for a story playtest.
One weekend, we'd bring them back a few weeks later
to do a late game strike playtest,
because we needed to have that expertise that they'd built up
in the early experience.
We also tested our raid by importing an entire shooter clan.
This is the Gunslingers clan who graciously used their vacation days to fly out to the
studio and play in our lab.
They were really good sports, playing a very hard and many places broken raid experience
early on.
They didn't beat Atheon.
They got them down to about 30 percent, I believe, which was pretty impressive for the
first weekend and gave a lot of really valuable raid feedback.
So now the game ships, we're collecting a lot of data
on how people actually play Destiny out in the wild.
And by and large, that data has been incredibly rewarding
and very encouraging.
So this is actually a graph of overall hours spent in Destiny
by game mode.
And people are generally playing in that sort of balanced way
we want them to.
And actually, this mix has been pretty consistent since launch,
about the same proportion of time spent in various activities.
However, there have been occasions where players have
wandered off the path that we thought they were going to take,
probably the most famous being the loot cave.
So you can sort of see in this picture.
Actually, just to check, how many people in this room
shot into the loot cave?
Yeah, that's what I figured.
So I'll do a quick explanation for those of you
who weren't there.
Where this player is aiming, there's a little tiny point,
there's a little tiny cave, and enemies would spawn out
of that cave at a steady clip.
Every few seconds, somebody would come out of the cave.
And the players would shoot them.
They'd die.
They'd respawn and run out of the cave.
And they were very weak enemies that
didn't drop very good loot.
But because players could stand at this great distance,
as you see in this picture, and just ping
into that cave for hours.
Once they finally did run over there,
even though there was a very low drop rate for loot,
there would be this lovely hoard of treasure
lying in the bottom of the cave.
And players literally did this for hours.
And the funny thing is we knew about this before launch.
We knew that this was a potentially exploitable
activity.
But we didn't care, because we said,
well, the actual drop rate per minute spent
is not any different than anything else.
So you actually will get less loot doing this per hour
than just playing the game.
But the players weren't actually doing the math that way.
They were doing the math of, they
weren't doing the loot per hour.
They were looking at loot per effort.
And this was so low effort that it felt like infinite free loot
to them.
And so, the interesting thing is this is actually pretty controversial in the player base itself,
that this was actually the time of the loot cave was the highest peak for player reporting
in Destiny, of players reporting each other for cheating.
is a lot of players were reporting each other,
people who didn't want to exploit the loot cave
were reporting the people who were in the loot cave,
who were shooting the loot cave.
And the people who,
and some people were even going so far
as to go into the loot cave themselves
and sit on the spawn point,
which would prevent the enemies from spawning.
And so the people who wanted to shoot into the loot cave
were then reporting those people
for being,
obstructing their chosen play style.
So this wasn't just a case where sort of,
Bungie hated it and didn't fix it.
There were a lot of players who didn't like this as well.
But we did patch the loot cave.
There actually is a memorial in the cave
if you haven't been back.
There is a memorial that's worth visiting and looking at.
And since then, we've also found a number of other loot caves.
So this is a top-down map of one of our destinations.
And those red spots over there on the right
are some minor loot caves that we discovered algorithmically
before they got on YouTube or Reddit or whatever.
and we were able to patch them before they became popular.
And so we're constantly doing this with, pretty much throughout the game,
of looking for moments where players are beating things very quickly,
taking too long, taking too short,
and looking for places where the experience isn't what we expected.
So we can then investigate and find out what's going on.
One of the great things about the modern age
is that everything is on YouTube and Twitch,
so if you can find some strange play style in the data,
somebody out there has put it online for you to watch.
That's a wonderful resource for you as researchers.
So a couple of lessons I learned over the course of this.
And I'm going to say we here.
I'm not speaking for Bungie in this case, in this slide.
I'm speaking for myself and my research team.
Or, OK, mostly for myself.
I won't get my research team in trouble.
So I absolutely underestimated our blessings on Halo.
That we didn't realize how good we had at the time.
as I spoke earlier.
We underestimated how rabid our fans would be.
So one of the first questions I got
was when I started at Bungie was,
so how much are people going to play the game?
And they wanted to say, OK, we want
to drop a certain amount of loot per week.
So how many hours per week are people going to play
so we can adjust drop rates to get people
about the right experience?
And I based it on Halo and underestimated by about 50%.
Our fans on Destiny are just way more enthusiastic than I think anybody anticipated they would be.
We really didn't correctly manage the transition to the Elder Games.
So Destiny has an early game where you're leveling up through experience points,
you're leveling up your character, then you get to level 20,
and you start leveling up through your gear.
And a lot of people missed that transition.
That's not intuitive for a lot of shooter players.
And when I say a lot of people, I mean something like 4%
of players got stuck at level 20.
They just never quite made that jump to the elder game
progression system.
We knew that there might be a problem there,
and we did some work on it, but we never fully
smoothed it out before release.
And I think probably the biggest screw up,
I thought players would hate power in PvP.
that every playtest we did on PvP and Destiny in the lab,
players hated the concept of level in PvP.
That the idea that they would get
killed by someone who was higher level than them,
and they would get really angry that they
were in this unfair match.
And they wouldn't even get angry at the other player.
They would get angry at us.
They would say, screw you, Bungie.
You put me in a game with that guy.
Your matchmaking system failed me
and put me in a situation where I couldn't win.
And they got really upset with us.
Even in a playtest where the power didn't matter,
and again, at all for stats,
but just we had the numbers over your head,
players got angry about power in PvP.
It was just a concept that players hated in the lab.
So of course, in our first Iron Banner,
we started out with a very minor, minor effect of power in PvP,
saying, okay, we're gonna let it matter a little bit
and see what happens.
And thinking players would hate it,
and actually the overwhelming response was
this should be worse.
I mean, a level 30 should totally destroy me in PvP.
And this was just startling to us.
And there was something funny happened in that transition
from the character I was, the throwaway character they
were playing in the lab, and the real character and gear
they'd earned out in the real world.
That once it was their real gear,
that they'd leveled their character up to 30 personally,
and they'd sweated blood to earn those guns.
they wanted those guns to matter.
So in subsequent versions, we've increased the effective power
in the Iron Banner.
And people seem to be happy with it.
I think they're masochists, but they seem to be happy with it.
So overall, in spite of the errors we made,
the game's doing OK.
Currently, we're at 17 million registered players,
playing a little over a billion hours
total in the first six months since the game's come out.
They've killed 200 billion aliens amongst them,
and enough other guardians in PVP to depopulate the Earth.
The average total playtime per player is over 77 hours.
That includes trial players, by the way.
If you look at just paying players,
it's actually, I think, something over 100 hours,
which is way more than we expected.
The average player who logs on today
will play for an average of three hours.
Our estimates pre-launch were something like 30 to 90 minutes
a day.
Three hours was not even on the scale.
And that's now, whatever, 175 days after launch.
And the average player has completed 230 activities so far.
So our user research effort certainly wasn't perfect,
but it seems to have contributed to something
that our players really love.
Thank you all very much, and do you have any questions for me?
questions, please come up to the mics. Thank you for the talk of course. I was wondering if you
can shed some insight into how you're assessing certain gameplay problems you're seeing when
you have incomplete UI because you're in production but you know the UI is actually critical
to people understanding the gameplay problem that people are experiencing.
and how often you take something to a certain level of user
testing so people can understand what you're trying to test.
Often you're waiting until the UI is complete,
but that happens at the end.
And what the strategies are.
Yes, it's hard.
Sorry.
Yes, it's very difficult to test early.
One of the great luxuries that we all had in Halo that I
actually didn't mention was the fact that the UI didn't
change much from game to game.
So for a lot of the Halo 3 development, we could just
leave the Halo 2 UI in place.
Because pretty much most of the mechanics were going to
be the same.
for Destiny we had to build a lot of that UI before we could
actually test the game. So a lot of our early testings were
things that didn't need UI and where they needed to be UI we
would do paper prototypes or mock ups or things like that.
But yes, it's really hard to do a game like this when the UI is
broken. Sorry, I forgot to repeat the question. Yes?
Sorry, I'm going to go to the other side.
Big fan. Thank you for the game.
How do you guys went from the lab to actual crossing data
from players on the live game?
How did that process happen?
So the question was how we went from collecting data in the lab
to collecting data in the live game.
And a lot of it is the same.
So we have very rich data mining in the lab.
And we actually collect that exact same set
of data mining for a very small slice of players
out in the real world.
And we collect a much less rich selection of data
for every player in the game.
So pretty much anything you see in your BungieNet profile
we have access to.
So we can look at gear.
We can look at activities.
There's a very rich data set.
We use a number of different technologies,
including Hadoop and high-based systems, too.
Can you please ask Zurg to stop selling the No Man's Land,
please?
He doesn't answer to me.
All right.
Hi.
I wanted to know a little bit more
about how you handled the long game.
You mentioned that you brought players back
from the earlier playtests.
But really, how often did you do that?
Because one of my games, I base a lot of my playtests
on your work on Halo, right?
But a problem that I had, I had anticipated,
is how players' relationships with that same content
changed after they went to 10 hours, 20, 30, 60, 90 hours.
So how did you guys learn about that?
A lot of guessing.
So there was only so long we could
have people play in the lab.
And we always had this dream that we would establish
fixed panels of players of like, OK, we're
going to say these 100 players are the Saturday afternoon
panel.
They can come in every Saturday afternoon for months.
And they can get really deep into the content
and replay the content.
And the game just was never quite.
And it just never actually made sense to do it.
Because by the time that they had gotten months
into the content, the developers were months along
in production.
And therefore, any feedback they had on that months old build
was just worthless.
And so we never quite settled down into being able to do that.
I really wish we could have.
And so we are exploring some different ways
to handle that in the future.
Thank you.
Oh, I was just wondering, have you formed any policies of using like Twits data as like a post-release user research?
I'm sorry, I can't even hear you.
Yeah, sorry. I had a question, if you have formed any strategies about using Twits and YouTube as like after-release user research?
So the question is how we're using Twitter and YouTube in post-release user research,
and mostly we're using it as evidence, that once we find interesting patterns in the data,
we're then going and finding evidence of them on YouTube, and finding videos to support
that position.
And we're also going vice versa.
We'll see somebody post a weird video on YouTube, and then we'll look in the data and say, okay,
how many people actually can do that?
Having played for 700 hours, I feel this is my destiny, anonymous bit.
What testing did you do into the RNG side that seems to get people so sort of
enervated about drop rates and stuff?
Were you surprised by how upset they got about not being able to find a particular thing they were looking for?
Upset? No. I mean, I certainly have a friend in WoW who ran the same dungeon
something like 300 times and never got his hat to drop.
I mean, we were familiar with the problem.
I think the thing that most surprised us was how focused people were on the RNG aspect.
I mean, the basic intent was always that most of the loot would come from fairly regular
sources through things like Vanguard marks, and then you buy the armor off the vendor.
And we expected that to be sort of the normal progression, and the random would be the sort
of very cool cream on top.
But that random just became so fixated in players' minds.
Even though it's a fairly small portion of the actual loot
they get, it just dominates the imagination in a way
I don't think we anticipated.
Finally dropped, so we're good.
OK, cool.
Thank you.
Thank you for the presentation. This is an RNG question as well.
I've been playing Destiny since September 9th, in like four hours every day at least.
So my question was, you spoke about reward and encouraging the players to play other characters.
Like for example, I'm a warlock and I get a Saint-14, so I want to try my hunter now.
So, I feel the game relies on RNG a lot.
Because you spoke about Vanguard, armor and all that, but the end game content is still the Yalahorn.
Why do I not have a Yalahorn yet?
I've been playing since a long time, and all my friends get it.
I, Sherpa, I Sword Bear, and still people get it, and I don't get it.
So the question is why he doesn't have a Yalahorn yet.
And the answer is somebody has to get that unlucky.
I mean, it is a random number generator,
and somebody has to get that unlucky.
But the thing that always strikes me
is how many stories come out of that,
and how much dialogue comes out of that,
and how many stories people tell about how
they get their gun in the end.
And that difficulty and the challenge in getting it
creates war stories and creates a great sort of community
feeling about the game.
So it does hurt when you personally
haven't gotten the gun you want.
I don't think I've ever gotten a random exotic weapon drop,
personally.
But I've bought all mine out of pity from Xur.
But it's one of those things that we expect everybody
to eventually get an exotic.
We don't expect everybody to eventually get all exotics.
But do you guys think you'll be working on this front
at any point in time?
Or are you just going to leave it at RNG at all points?
In upcoming expansions, upcoming weapons, or whatever?
So I'm not a designer, so I don't actually control this.
I suspect that RNG will always be a part of Destiny.
I think we will tune exactly how much of a part
it is as our understanding of the game improves over time.
But I think there will always be a certain RNG factor.
Yeah, I guess.
Thanks.
Yeah.
OK.
Hey, how's it going?
Awesome presentation.
I have a question.
So I work at a technology company,
and one of the things that we track pretty heavily
is user sentiment and how the new features that we implement
change how people perceive the company that's
creating the product, which is kind of interesting.
And it often leads to really interesting unexpected things,
either greatly improving or a.
negatively affecting user sentiment for the underlying company. So what are, in your experience,
some things that you've seen when you're testing that either made people say like,
oh wow, I really love Bungie for doing this, or surprising things that you saw people hate Bungie
for?
I mean, I think the number one, so the question was what things in our testing we found made
people like Bungie, like or hate Bungie in particular as opposed to the game.
I think the number one thing that actually stands out in my mind is matchmaking.
They don't see matchmaking and as you heard earlier RNG as being a product of the game.
They see it more as us being evil and messing with them is the number one thing.
Things that make them like us.
I'm not sure the game itself makes them like us.
I think our community managers and those efforts make them like the company and the brand.
But I don't think the game itself lends them to like Bungie.
Over here.
Hi.
Thank you for the talk, by the way.
You're welcome.
I'm really fascinated with the contextual feedback that you were talking about and how
it was integrated into the world builder.
Can you talk a little bit more about what that would look like for, say, a level designer
or an artist?
And now that the game is live, obviously we don't have this feedback functionality on
our controllers, but are you still collecting similar types of data and putting that into
the world builder with the live aspect of the game?
I'll switch.
So the question is, are we still collecting similar types
of data and putting it in the live version?
And what would that look like for a mobile game?
So even for a mobile game, what does
that look like for the actual people working
inside the editor?
Like a level designer or an artist, what would that?
what would they be seeing?
I saw the image that you showed.
Yes, it pretty much looks like this to them.
Okay.
So, I mean, this is a screenshot from the World Editor itself.
And those little red dots there are players getting killed.
The blue dots are players getting killed.
The red dots are what's killing them.
And so you can see there's a turret up there
in the middle of the screen that's
getting a lot of kills in that case.
This actually also, I'll toss in,
helped our QA department quite a bit,
because we found cases where people were being
shot through geometry this way.
Oh, they're turning off the lights on me.
So I think that is our last question.
I will hang around outside if anybody
has any more questions.
Thank you.