Thank you all very much for coming out on Monday,
or Wednesday morning, sorry, to see my talk.
I'm super, super excited to share this with you.
This is a project that I'm very, very passionate about.
And in particular, the journey that we've taken to get here
has been something that has had great successes
and great lessons learned along the way.
And I can't wait to share both with all of you.
Now the first thing I need to clarify is I only had so many words to fit the title of
the talk in, and the length of our, the name of our game is pretty long, and that took
up a lot of the words.
So the first thing I need to clarify is that there wasn't no specific game jam, you know,
this wasn't something that like we all went to TOjam and...
You know, spent the 48 hours and came up with a thing and then pitched it to Ubisoft and turned it into a game or something.
Rather, what we were trying to do was take inspiration from Game Jam techniques and Game Jam culture
and find a path to adapt that and scale that to AAA game development and the conception of a new AAA IP.
And a few months ago, I had the honor and privilege of announcing this IP to the world
at E3, where I got to go up and share the fruits of our labor with everyone.
And I couldn't be more proud of the work that the team has done to create this.
And I can't wait for, you know, we only gave a little snippet of what we're doing, and
I can't wait for everyone to see more.
This is an IP that has a lot of innovation throughout, and at the core of that is this
completely modular peripheral where you're able to add on wings and weapons and parts
and everything, and everything you add on is instantly recreated in the game, and it
totally changes the way that you play.
And so today I want to tell you about our journey and our story for how we got there.
How we tried to reinvent brainstorming and a typical conception process to come up with
the IP in the first place.
How we had some stumbles along the way as we tried to grow and expand that process.
And then how we had to regain our footing and re-find our balance to close out production and really bring everything back together.
But first I want to start with the fun and terrifying part of starting a new IP, which is the conception phase.
And in order to tell this story, I've got to go way, way, way back to the beginning of the story,
which is the ending of another story of Splinter Cell Blacklist.
Splinter Cell Blacklist was the first project from the Ubisoft Toronto studio, and at the
time everyone at the studio had been working together to ship it.
And I had joined Ubisoft Toronto during the production of Blacklist, and we worked through
that and brought that to a close.
And at the end of that project, as with many studios, people start splitting up and going
on to separate things.
And particularly at Toronto, we went from one project to lots of projects really quick.
And since then, Toronto has been, has done many very successful collaborations on Far Cry Primal, Far Cry 4, Far Cry 5, Watch Dogs 2, Assassin's Creed Unity, you know, many of Ubisoft's biggest brands.
But at the time, we also were given a chance to try something new and crazy.
And I'm still not sure exactly how I lucked out and got this opportunity, but I was given the opportunity to take a very small group of people.
And we were given this mandate, it looked like this,
to basically come up with something new.
And as far as mandates go, this one was really wide open.
You know, explore innovative gameplay and next-gen hardware,
which at the time meant Xbox One and PS4,
with the goal of creating a mainstream concept for development.
So...
This is really a blank slate, and this kind of freedom is incredibly liberating and incredibly
terrifying because it is super, super challenging to know where to go, especially with very
limited resources when you have just this wide open space ahead of you.
So we formed a little...
prototyping group that we called Tomcat, I don't know why.
And it was eight people to start.
Two artists, two programmers, two game designers, one animator, and a manager.
At this point I need to give a huge shout out. At the time we had two leads.
So it was myself, I was the manager, and we had a lead designer named James Everett. And he and I
really worked very closely together to come up with this process. So a huge shout out to him. He can't be here today, but
we worked really closely together on this process.
So we had this group of people, and these were a wonderful group of people who I thoroughly
enjoyed working with, but to be fair, we were kind of the island of misfit toys.
This was a group of people that...
You know, when all of the project selection and things came up,
and they were like, okay, do you want to work on, you know, the next big Far Cry thing,
or, you know, the next Assassin's Creed, or whatever it was.
These were the group of people that, you know, went dashing into the unknown,
and said, I want to do the thing that's called Tomcat, but otherwise we know nothing about.
And so, you know, it's a group of people that participated in a lot of game jams.
You know, we're really attracted by coming up with brand new things and iterating on that.
But it was also a group of people that really, you know, in many ways wanted to rebel
against the standard structure and process and way that we do things,
and way that things happen.
And so, you know, we wanted to just reinvent everything, tear up all the rules and do something crazy.
So we looked at how we would traditionally
go about coming up with a new IP as a starting point.
So we'd say, OK, well, we've got a bunch of people,
any people, so we'll all get in a room.
We'll brainstorm tons of ideas.
We'll put stuff up on the wall.
And then we'll all try to pick, or the leads will try to pick.
And we'll say, this is the best idea.
Let's do that.
We build a demo out of it.
And we polish that up and bring that to Paris and pitch it.
It'll be amazing.
It'll be awesome.
High five.
But when we looked at this process and the initial expectation,
we had four big problems that we saw,
that we didn't like about how this typical process works.
The first, we all kind of hated brainstorming.
In a traditional sense.
And one of the big problems that we have with brainstorming
is this effect of the loudest people in the room
and the loudest ideas resonating.
Not necessarily the best ideas.
Typically if you throw ten people in a room,
you say, okay, we're going to brainstorm this new thing.
Everyone gets talking and, you know,
You immediately start filtering down to three or four voices that are dominating this conversation,
and the ideas are mostly coming from them.
And there's a lot of people that have wonderful ideas that are going unheard because they're
being spoken over or they can't get the word in, or they're not comfortable jumping into
that fray.
The second problem...
It's biased selection.
I've got two young kids right now.
And with two young kids, there's always these events
and holidays and things that roll around.
And you get a lot of these best dad in the world things.
And I think I'm a pretty good dad.
But statistically, best dad in the world
is probably a stretch.
And we had similar worries with
Our, James and I, you know, in a leadership role, with our biases affecting this process,
where if we were going in and ideas are cropping up and people are throwing stuff on the wall,
you know, we come from a very, you know, James and I both had kind of similar perspectives
and similar interests, similar enough, you know, we came from similar backgrounds, and
You know, looking at that, we were really worried that this wasn't necessarily going to be the idea that resonated with a wider audience.
You know, the ideas that resonated to kind of two 30-something white guys who grew up in Canada would give us a fairly limited perspective and a limited selection.
The third problem.
Sounded good on paper.
Okay, big caveat, I do not want to insult any game designers out there.
I love game designers.
But I think the best game designers...
are kind of like the best batters in baseball, right?
And when you write a pitch on paper, you write a design down,
and you're like, okay, this is how this feature's gonna work,
it's gonna be amazing,
the best designers are probably batting at, you know,
a 40% success rate of that idea actually translating
into something that's really compelling and fun when you make it.
And more often than not, you know, once you take that design
that sounded great on paper and make it into...
A game, and you spend, you know, the months developing that feature,
you come back to it and you say, oh yeah, actually, we have to change that,
it was kind of flawed, or didn't work exactly as we expected.
And the fourth problem, which takes a little bit of explanation,
something called the secretary problem.
Quick show of hands, does anyone know what this...
Means, does anyone know what this is?
Navi knows.
So the secretary problem is a mathematical problem
with a kind of dated name.
And the secretary problem speaks to the challenge of
How to select the best sample from a data set
when you have to go through them linearly.
So the idea is, this kind of fictional scenario is,
you're trying to hire a secretary.
Secretaries are all different quality.
Some of them are great, some of them are bad.
And when you interview them,
you can assess the quality of that person.
But for whatever reason in this fictional scenario,
once you say no and reject that applicant,
they're gone forever and you can never call them back.
And so the challenge is, how many people do you interview before you take the next best one?
Right, if you interview two, three people, someone great comes along,
and you're like, oh, they seem good, let's just hire them.
How do you know that three people down the line, you wouldn't have someone much better?
And so we were really worried about this with our brainstorming and conception process.
We were brainstorming some ideas, some of them sounded cool,
you know, maybe we'd even make a prototype and that would be cool,
but how did we know that if we hadn't gone a couple more rounds,
we wouldn't have come up with something much more compelling?
So we had these four problems, and, you know, we looked at them and we said,
okay, let's, you know, how are we going to address these?
How are we going to change our process to try to mitigate this as best as we could?
So what we decided to do, one, we wanted to rethink the typical brainstorming process,
and I'll go through that in more detail in a second.
Second, we wanted to make it completely democratic and fair.
In order to use our tiny team, both as the idea generation and development,
but also as our smallest and easiest validation of the ideas,
we would have people vote on the best ideas,
and make it a completely fair and democratic process.
Third, we'd prototype as many things as possible.
In order to validate that what sounded fun on paper
actually was a compelling idea,
we would rapidly prototype as many things as possible
to validate their success.
And fourth, once we had those prototypes,
once we had that, no matter how compelling they were,
We would put it aside, success or failure, and completely restart from scratch with a
new batch of ideas.
And we would do that for a period of time that we kind of figured out based on our schedule.
And at the end of that, we'd look back over everything and say, OK, out of all this time,
what were the ideas, what were the best ideas that we came up with during that period?
So once we had those solutions, we split this into a plan.
We had a two-week schedule where we would brainstorm,
pitch, vote, plan, and then the second week we'd prototype.
And then rinse, repeat, go right back to the beginning.
And the first chunk of that is brainstorming.
So for us, we had this challenge.
Okay, how do we reinvent?
How do we do a better job with brainstorming?
The first problem we had was this wide-open mandate.
You know, how the heck are we going to ask people to brainstorm?
We're like, okay, group of people, go away.
Just come up with anything.
I don't know, like what are you into?
Are you into RPGs, MMOs?
You know, just throw some ideas out there,
because our mandate could be anything.
So, you know, we had to give some focus to that.
We had to get some clarity as to where people should focus their brainstorming.
What problem were they trying to solve?
And so, you know, we worked on this idea of a guiding question.
It had to be an open-ended question, we didn't want to force people into a corner,
but we wanted this kind of open-ended guiding question
that could help clarify and give them a direction to go in.
So some examples of these questions.
What game would you create where the primary mechanic is collaboration?
What E for Everyone game would you create with 10,000 simultaneous AI or human characters?
What exploration-based game could only be accomplished on a living room console with
a peripheral?
And there was a number of these different ideas and different questions that we put
out there.
One of my personal favorites that I didn't put up here was, what's a game that could
evoke a sense of discovery and wonder?
What would be a primary mechanic that could evoke a sense of discovery and wonder in players?
So, once we had these questions, we had to set about brainstorming those.
And the first thing that we did to combat this problem of the loudest person in the
room was we scaled the brainstorming way down to the smallest it could be with one person.
We'd start the first day of the week, this is Monday,
we've got the question out, first thing,
and everyone goes off alone to think about that question
and to brainstorm on their own.
And they could do a little bit of research, check things out,
but they had the whole morning of the first day,
and we tasked everyone with writing down 25
compelling game ideas based on that question.
And this doesn't sound too difficult, right?
25 is not that big of a number.
I assure you if you try to go through the exercise,
it's much more challenging than you would think.
You tend to get through 10, 15 ideas.
You're like, yeah, this is easy.
I am laughing.
This is awesome.
And then you get up to like 16, 17.
You're like, OK, these are a bit of a stretch.
And by the time you're at like 21, 22, 23, you hit 25,
and you are like, that is it.
This is the sum total of all possible human creativity about this subject.
There are no other ideas imaginable that could answer this question.
I've got them all.
I am tapped out.
And when people hit that point, we pair them up.
And all of a sudden, you meet someone else from your team who's also done the same exercise,
coming up with 25 ideas.
And lo and behold, somehow...
They've come up with a completely different set of 25 than you have.
Oh, they saw this problem from a totally different perspective.
They were coming at this from a different angle.
I didn't even think of interpreting it like that.
And so these two people would meet up, they'd share their ideas, they'd discuss their ideas,
and the remarkable thing is that now both people are invigorated,
they are suddenly seeing a different perspective that they never even thought of approaching this problem from.
And together as a pair, they're tasked with coming up with an additional 25 ideas,
riffing off inspiration from each other,
you know, suddenly opening up entire new avenues of thought that neither of them considered,
but, you know, once they saw the angle that each of them came from,
it would open up this possibility.
So by the end of the first day, each pair would have 75 ideas.
Day two, we do it again.
We take the pairs.
We pair them up.
So now we have groups of four.
They share the 150 ideas that they came up
with the previous day.
And they start riffing.
And as a group, now they're coming up with another 25.
Afternoon, now we bring everyone in.
And we literally have hundreds of ideas.
When any individual couldn't possibly think
of more than 25, now the whole team is empowered
with a set of hundreds of ideas
answering this open-ended question
from which they can draw from.
And then the last step is to scale all the way back down.
Right back down to single, solo work.
Where each individual had two full days to take those hundreds of ideas,
to take all of that huge possibility space,
and condense that down into three pitches.
Three slides each, five minutes each,
that were, you know, fleshing some of those ideas out
into something that they thought was a compelling and cohesive game pitch.
So they distill all of that info down.
And at the end of day Thursday, we'd get everyone
together in a room.
And it was very fun.
We had kind of a pitch day.
And everyone had their five minutes to go up, or five
minutes per, to go up and present their pitches, present
their ideas.
And it was amazing seeing even the ideas that you had seen in
very early stages.
At a brainstorming level, you know, once people had really put thought in and attached images
and kind of put some work in to put that into a cohesive and fleshed out pitch, it was absolutely
incredible seeing these just dozens and dozens of
Amazing game pitches come together and I still think there are a treasure trove, you know,
going back through our old files of so many games that I would love to make at some point in the
future. Incredibly creative and diverse ideas that, you know, we would never have gotten
through a traditional process.
Once we had these pitches, everyone voted.
We did this very simply.
We just gave everyone three little circle sticky things.
And everyone went up and voted.
As people were pitching, we'd write them down on the board.
And people could go up and vote on the ones that they wanted.
Now one improvement to this, this process is actually being taken and replicated over at Magic Leap in New Zealand,
where James Everett, who was the original designer, has gone to, the lead designer.
And...
One of the improvements that they made, one of the iterations that they made on this process
was to make the votes silent because you know you get some pattern of people looking at what
other people are voting on and and steering that. We didn't do that when we did it originally and
I think it worked well but you know it may have just been the way that our
that our group was structured and that we were going up. So everyone would vote and
After we'd voted, we'd have three top voted pitches.
Now, many times these three top voted pitches
actually came from four or five pitches.
It's really strange the way that kind of zeitgeist works.
People have the same set of raw ideas that they're drawing from
and sometimes you get pitches that, you know,
were going in a similar direction.
So rather than say like, oh, this one got slightly more votes,
we'd say those two pitches were pretty much along the same lines.
Let's merge them.
You know, let's combine the cool elements of both
and turn that into one thing.
But essentially we'd boil it down to three winning pitches each time.
And from there, everyone would submit their preferences of like,
hey, I'd love to work on prototyping.
This pitch or that pitch in order.
And we'd look and it was a very small team,
so we had to just make some decisions and break it up.
And each person would end up joining a small group
of two, three people, as we grew maybe three, four,
five people to work on a prototype.
And we made three prototypes in a week, every two weeks.
So we'd have one day, the Friday of that week, to break into those groups, sit down, start
talking, start talking about how the heck in a week can we possibly prototype.
These were big game ideas.
These were like...
Not a mini-game, these were pitches for something that could be a AAA game.
And so, you know, in a week, how do you get down, how do you boil down to the essence of that idea?
And how do you validate that in the most efficient manner possible?
And there is never any extra time.
Literally, there is only a week, that's it.
That's what you have to do.
So people would kind of come up with a plan, and then in the afternoon we'd run those plans by the other groups, get some feedback, get some validation.
Often you'd have suggestions for, hey, maybe you could use this technology, maybe there's this tool you could use, did you know that this was out there, that would be helpful.
And then we had a week to validate by any means necessary.
We used different engines.
We used different tech that was available.
We made paper prototypes or acted things out
or did anything we possibly could to prove this out.
And again, this was a wonderful process.
It was a mad dash.
It was very, uh...
Intense for a week making all of these games and this resulted in all sorts of wild and wacky
prototypes across all sorts of different technologies and genres and things and
lots of crazy stuff
AR and and mobile things and whatever. I don't even know what was going on here. This is
I'm sure it was a ton of fun.
And these photos were from something, I mostly put them in just to embarrass these people
that they were in my GDC presentation.
Yeah, these games were amazing, I'm sure.
Anyways, we came up with all sorts of crazy prototypes.
One of those prototypes was actually really cool, and I'll show you a quick video of it.
It was a game where you could, it was used to connect and you could kind of make these
silhouette paintings with your body.
and capture them, and it was kind of a Pictionary kind of thing, right, people would guess.
And, you know, this was something that we didn't think,
okay, maybe this isn't something we're going to turn into a big AAA game.
But we actually had a chance to show it to the world.
There's an all-night festival called Nuit Blanche in Toronto.
And so we went and projected it up on the side of a seven-story building
and had everyone come out and play it. It was super cool.
After we did all this prototyping, we'd all get together, big group, play all these games,
have a ton of fun, and give this really open and honest feedback on what worked, what didn't.
The power of this feeling of fairness, because it was this democratic process, you know,
everyone had been voting, there wasn't one idea selected because, you know, the lead
said this is the one we're going to go, this is the direction I want to go in.
Everyone felt like it was a fair playing field where each of them had contributed to that.
And that had an incredible effect on people's willingness to step up.
You know, give their honest thoughts on what was working, what they were excited about, what fell through.
And I think this is something that you actually see a lot in game jam culture as well.
You know, this incredibly open and transparent and honest feedback and assessment.
I think it's a really positive part of that community that oftentimes we miss out and we get a little bit wrapped up in politics and, you know, power politics in larger development.
After all that, we went for a while, we had dozens of prototypes,
and we reached that point where we were like,
okay, we really need to decide what we're going to do.
And so we took a step back and we looked through.
Keeping in mind that secretary problem, we had really given it a good run.
We had a bunch of stuff that we could select from.
And we looked back, and out of everything, one prototype really stood out.
It looked like this.
It had humble origins.
It was a Wiimote, kind of taped to a consumer electronics
board with building blocks and copper wire stuck to it.
But it worked.
And we made a demo.
You could fly around in space and grab asteroids and do neat things.
And it was a very rudimentary prototype.
You had to be careful not to make it fall apart as you were playing with it.
But we started to show it to some people.
And it was really, really cool.
They'd come and play it.
And people started filling in all of the missing parts.
I didn't play that video with audio.
But people started coming.
You know, adding in, they'd make their own sound effects and they'd come and, you know,
pshew, whoosh.
And, you know, everything that wasn't there from this prototype that we had built in a week,
people could imagine it and they could see the potential.
And we also started to meet a bunch of people from the studio who came up and said,
hey.
I could help make this a reality.
You know, I don't know if you know, but I have a background in X.
You know, people that had worked in industrial design.
There's one guy in particular that we met named Vlad.
And Vlad came up to me at the company barbecue.
And he has a very kind of blunt way of speaking many times.
And Vlad came up and basically said,
You're doing this all wrong.
This is horrible.
I can fix it.
And he said, I have to show you something.
And so we went to see.
And Vlad had scratch built this custom drone with head
tracked cameras and a crazy thing.
And this is scratch built down to his own chemically etched
circuit boards and things.
And he was like, I know how to do this.
I know how to do this stuff.
It's a shame the video that I had cut off there, this drone had like vertical take-off
and then would rotate and turn into an aerofoil and fly like a jet and it was just really cool.
So Vlad came on board and, you know, started...
redoing everything that we had stumbled our way through for this prototype.
And other people on the team started, you know, all of these skill sets started coming out.
People that worked with industrial design and...
And at the time we had this idea of building a custom game controller for the thing.
That's how we would interface with the toys and, you know, kind of a flight stick idea.
And so we started working and this was the next prototype that we had built.
So, you know, still pretty rudimentary.
It was heavy, it was big, it was clunky.
But it was a major step up from our kind of building block and copper wire thing.
It was much sturdier.
It used a...
micro USB connectors to connect everything, which, you know, USB-C just can't come fast
enough.
I absolutely despise those connectors.
But they worked, and they got the data across, the thing, you know, you could play it, and,
you know, we knew who we were making this game for, and I'll never forget the moment
that we brought in the first group of kids, and we gave them this thing.
to play with, and just, you know, the looks on their faces,
their eyes lit up, their jaws dropped.
And this was a rough, you know,
this was a very rudimentary prototype.
It was heavy, it was clunky,
but you could just see this magic
that it was something that they absolutely fell in love with.
And so we knew we were onto something special,
and we took this game.
And we brought it to Ubisoft's HQ in Paris
and we presented it.
And it went super well.
They were really happy, the pitch went well,
they were excited.
And we showed a little bit of all these crazy
prototypes and things we'd built.
We got a green light, and so that moves us
into the next phase of our story,
which is pre-production.
So coming back from our successful pitch,
we were feeling great.
We started to grow the team, expand the team, bring people on.
And we were feeling amazing, on top of the world.
We were like, this is it, we're kicking ass.
We threw out all of the old process.
We did this crazy new experiment.
It was super successful.
So we felt vindicated for trying to do things differently.
And we were incredibly overambitious, super audacious.
We were like, we're gonna do everything at this point,
just, you know.
Who thought we could do anything to do with hardware?
This'll be awesome, just throw more crazy stuff on the pile.
And, you know, but we still knew that we were a new team,
we were a small team, and we needed to prove ourselves.
So we set about making a vertical slice.
You know, we fully recognized that the little demo
that we showed to kids, you know,
that was never something that could have shipped.
It was, you know, a hacky kind of little demo
that made something work.
So we set out to prove that we could do this for real.
We could make a game and make a toy that looked and felt like something that could go to market.
And so, you know, filled with energy, filled with enthusiasm, we charged into this,
and it started going pretty well.
This is our next iteration.
Those are the connectors.
So we got rid of those horrible micro USB connectors,
and we made these really neat connectors that we'd click together and they'd work,
and, you know, have this really instantaneous connection to the game.
And, you know, we made our first real toys.
These are some of the early...
You know, the first version of real-looking toys that we made.
We started to bring on some people from the toy industry that knew what they were doing.
We started working with model shops and people that could, you know, really make...
Proper professional toy prototypes.
And we made these toys, they looked really cool.
You know, they had problems, there's certainly usability things.
I have gained an immense amount of respect for toy designers and toy industry and everything that they do.
And so, you know, you'd move these toys and the wings, you know, would kind of fall off because these connectors were great, but didn't really have anything that would latch or connect.
And we built a demo.
This was our first vertical slice demo.
And, you know, it was really coming together.
It was something that was a big step forward
from, you know, the little prototypes that we had made.
It was pretty neat.
You'd start out in space,
kind of take off from this mothership,
and, uh...
Eventually launch.
And then you'd arrive out in space,
and there was kind of these different levels
that you could select down on the planet's surface,
these different linear levels.
And you could look at one of these gates
and say, oh, I want to do that.
And then you transition down to the surface.
There was a loading sequence.
And you'd engage on whatever mission it was.
So in this example, it was a race.
And you'd go and start engaging that.
It was pretty cool, and everything you do on the toy would be instantly recreated,
and you could add all these weapons or boosters or things that could change the gameplay.
And so we made this demo, we're feeling great, we're like on top of the world, kicking ass.
We bring it back and we're like, okay, here's where we're at, this is our vertical slice, it's awesome.
And that's when we realized, OK, this is starting to get real.
We're playing in a bit of a different league.
There's real money on the table.
We're building a bigger team here.
The stakes are a lot higher, and the expectations
are a lot higher.
It's no longer good enough just to have something
that's a cool idea, a compelling demo.
And we start hearing all of this feedback of, really?
You guys making a custom controller?
Do you know how long Microsoft and Sony and Nintendo
spend on making a controller?
A pretty big endeavor.
And you know, the engine that you're working with,
I'm not sure you're going to ship with that.
And the game structure, and player engagement,
and play time, and world logic, and all these things
that you need to figure out for building a new IP.
You know, really real, valid things
that we were just kind of rushing through with vim
and vigor.
But in addition to all of these external things,
we started having these voices cropping up within our team,
saying, hey guys, I think maybe we should take a step back
and kind of plan this out properly
and figure out what our scope is.
This process is cool, but it's a bit chaotic.
This is a bit seat of our pants, right?
We should really document this, do all of this.
And at this point, we had two paths ahead of us.
We had a big choice.
We could thoroughly document, you know, scope it out,
rigorous process, analyze requests.
This is how, you know, Ubisoft has proven
these processes out.
This is how we make games.
You know, people have figured this out.
We've got Jira and Confluence,
and yeah, we can like really button this down.
You have to remember that this group of people
making this thing,
Kind of all pulled together specifically to rebel against this kind of process, right?
It was kind of a group of people that were specifically like,
ah, you know, to us this was the boring and slow, but you know, maybe sensible,
but boring and slow path that, you know, that we wanted to go away from.
And so to us, we saw another choice.
More innovation.
No matter what challenge came up, we could always solve it with more innovation.
And there's two guys that I wished I had paid more attention to, in retrospect.
Their names are Abraham Maslow and Vilfredo Pareto.
Does anyone know what Maslow is, what I'm referring to in this case?
Hierarchy of Needs.
No, not the Hierarchy of Needs. He is very famous for the Hierarchy of Needs.
But not that, thank you for playing into my GDC presentation thing.
Specifically, I am talking about Maslow's hammer,
or the expression that when you have a hammer,
everything looks like a nail.
And Vilfredo Pareto is famous for the Pareto Principle,
or the 80-20 rule.
The principle that 20% of the effort
will yield 80% of the results,
and that final 20% of the results that you need
actually comes from 80% of the effort.
Because we had a hammer.
And that hammer was more innovation.
The whole process that we had created
was effectively an innovation machine.
And so no matter what feedback came up,
no matter what challenge came up,
we could innovate our way out of that problem.
So too expensive and difficult to create a custom game
controller.
No problem. We'll make a controller mount that interfaces directly with the extension port
of all of the first-party controllers, allowing you to communicate instantly through their
hardware and leveraging all of that work in a way that no one's done before.
More powerful tech? No problem. We'll take Ubisoft's latest and greatest engine, Snowdrop,
and port everything over and leverage that work with an engine that is amazingly powerful,
but at the time hadn't really been fully proven out and was still being used on the Division.
More freedom and autonomy? No problem.
We'll create tech to allow you to seamlessly travel from space to planets, planets to space,
circumnavigate around worlds in a completely open and seamless manner.
More meaningful choices? No problem.
We'll simulate every single AI on every single planet simultaneously,
allowing the players to have real impact on the planets.
and allowing the enemy to fight back so that no two players will have the same story
and everyone's game will go in a different direction.
And, you know, we didn't stop there.
No matter what came up, there was something new.
We had crazy three-dimensional elemental propagation throughout the game.
We had second screen experiences and planet creation at some point, ill advise.
We wanted to build laser tag into the toy.
I still kind of miss this idea, it would have been really cool.
But we were really going out there, and we made all of this stuff, and we took a step
back, and we were like, OK, where are we at?
It worked.
These were cool prototypes.
They were amazing ideas.
And they worked.
We had this team that could make these crazy innovations functional and prove them out
quickly and...
Except for the other 80% of the work.
that it would have taken to actually make those features.
We had quickly gotten them to these 80% states of like,
yeah, yeah, yeah, that's cool, that works.
And when we started to take a step back and look at it,
we were like, oh no, we made a huge mistake.
And I'm not quite sure how all of these separate pieces were supposed to fit together.
You know, individually they were all really neat innovations, but they weren't adding up to create a sum that was greater than the...
a whole that was greater than the sum of its parts.
And so, you know, we started to realize, okay, you know, this process that was amazing for conception,
that was incredibly effective during the conception phase, I don't know if this is scaling in the way that we hoped it would.
And while there were some of these features that were really groundbreaking and revolutionary
and are still huge components of the game today, you know, this controller mount right
at your fingertips instantly swapping out and the seamless travel and this incredible
living world.
So many more of the features ended up having to be cut and cast aside,
and we wasted a lot of time and effort trying to innovate our way out of every problem,
which we could have solved in a much better manner.
And for me, this was really a moment, stepping back,
and it was kind of this shattering of the reality distortion field.
Engineers at Apple used to speak about
something they called the reality distortion field,
where the charisma of Steve Jobs
I could convince people that the impossible was possible and that no matter what problem
they faced, even when you couldn't push the silicon to do that, he could will it to happen
and they would pull a group of people together and make it so.
And, you know, honestly in the early phases of this project we felt like that.
We felt like, okay, you know, no matter what happens, we've got this process, it's working.
We will just will it to make it so, make it happen.
And, you know, it was when we stood back and looked at this and said,
okay, we're never going to ship this. It's not going to come together.
You know, for me this was really this kind of low point of reflection.
And that
Brought us right into the beginning of production.
With this question, how in the hell are we gonna ship this?
How are we gonna make this,
how are we gonna fix this process?
We had all of these incredibly powerful
and compelling parts.
How are we gonna pull them together into a whole?
A little voice.
We can solve it with more innovation.
We kind of realized, you know, maybe, maybe not.
Maybe that was, in fact, part of the problem
that had gotten us into this situation.
In Ed Catmull's excellent book, Creativity Inc.,
he talks about the importance of balance
and the importance of conflict
between all of the departments in a creative enterprise
to maintain that balance.
And when we took a step back and looked,
we realized that our development was horribly unbalanced.
And I want to clarify that this was not specific disciplines fighting against each other.
This was not game designers wanting innovation and programmers saying no.
You know, this was really guiding philosophies, and we had game designers pushing for, you
know, more scope control and bringing things down to a more elegant solution.
We had programmers pushing for more innovation.
You know, these were these kind of competing philosophies, but what we realized was that
the philosophy of innovation as solution was massively...
Unbalanced and overweighted.
And we had to take a step back and some of those voices that had been there within our team earlier,
we had to put things in place to empower those voices and listen to those voices.
You know, people in tech saying, OK, hey, it's great that we have these wonderful innovations,
but we need to balance that out with safer solutions, with proven solutions,
in order to protect the innovations and make them really sing.
People in production saying, hey, we can help.
make this scope more manageable, we can help address the timeline and adjust the timeline
to make this a realistic endeavor.
In business, saying, you know, we can help validate this offer, we can help validate
which parts of this are really resonating, really pinpoint the audience and their expectations.
Every GDC talk has to have some sort of cheesy analogy, so this is mine.
I think of this as...
trying to protect a spark, protect a flame, and grow it into a fire.
And early on, too much process and too much innovation and too much structure can snuff
that out, can, you know, really...
squander and kill ideas way too early.
And again, in Creativity Inc.,
he talks about protecting ugly babies.
That often these early prototypes
that you're making with a couple people in a couple days,
they're rough, they're rough around the edges.
And if people looked at them,
they'd be easy to dissect and they'd be easy to pick apart.
And you need to give that time and space
and freedom to survive.
But what we realized is as you grow, without the structure,
without the protection of that structure starting to come on board,
you're actually doing an immense disservice to these sparks.
New flames will spark up and consume all the oxygen.
Winds of change will come as things change in the industry
or things change with people's behavior
and start to snuff out things that were promising.
And you have to start putting these walls,
starting to put this structure in place,
bit by bit, leading up to protect the innovations that you have.
And that equilibrium point, that point of balance,
is not always the same.
It is not always that you want an even balance
between all of these different departments.
But that balance and that equilibrium point shifts
over the course of production.
And you need to carefully maintain that and nurture that
to help that spark grow into the kind of roaring flame
that you want it to be.
And really for me, looking back, that's my key takeaway.
In conception, we had a very unbalanced process massively weighted towards, you know, innovation
and protecting innovation and making that innovation as rapid and as effective as it
could be. And it was incredibly effective. And I can't stress that enough. This is a process I
would love to see other companies and other groups replicate because it was some of the most fulfilling.
game development experience I've ever had in my career,
and many people on the team, I think, would attest to that.
And we've already started to see some experiments
replicating that elsewhere,
and it's been incredibly effective.
But moving into pre-production,
we made the mistake of just trying to keep going,
trying to scale that process up.
And we should have still kept...
That balance on the side of innovation, it's still important to add that depth,
but we had to start to tip the scales.
We had to start to add some of that structure to make it work.
And then, you know, moving into production,
we had to find our new equilibrium point, our new balance point.
And that's going to look different for everyone, you know, the path to get there,
the path to adjust that new equilibrium. For us, it meant really creating the structure
of having regular venues for healthy conflict,
for...
You know, venues where people could challenge.
So, you know, we had creative briefs with a feature at an early level.
So kind of a high level presentation overview of the feature,
bringing in all the stakeholders who could say, OK, you know,
I want to raise a flag about this. This is a warning.
You know, then taking that into FSOs.
This is very Ubisoft specific thing, but essentially a much,
much more specific description of that feature.
Again, with a forum for challenge and debate discussion.
Our meetings became very much about making sure that anyone could add points for discussion.
They weren't just top-down, me saying, here's the agenda.
We built the agenda collaboratively, and we made sure that there were venues for everyone
to discuss and argue.
And we encouraged that healthy conflict.
On the production side, we really shifted focus to velocity
to better understand how we were tracking towards our scope.
We used playtest and external validation
to understand our audience and what's resonating.
And we really refocused in on our game pillars
in order to use those as the razor to help prioritize
and focus on what's important.
And we realized that only through focusing on these things
could we protect these things and actually make them
flourish in the game. For us, those pillars were of course this modular toy, you know,
this instant connection, this magical moment that makes kids' eyes light up and their jaws drop.
The creative combat that this instant swapping and connection empowers you to do in game,
this creative problem solving where you get into a challenge and there's no right or wrong
answer but you have to experiment and figure out how to adapt to take on that challenge.
And this incredible, living, dynamic world that makes it for no two players having the
same story, no two players having the same journey.
Now we're still active in development, and I need to give a huge shout out to our team
back in Toronto, who are still working very, very hard to bring everything to life.
completely together and wrap it up. I'm super, super excited about the game. I'm super excited
for you all to see more about it over the coming months. I can't wait. So far we've
only given a little glimpse at E3, and I can't wait for people to see what we've been up
to. And, you know, I'd really stress two things. One, I would love to see other people
Take advantage of the lessons that we learned in that incredibly effective conception process,
and you know, process that was inspired from game jam culture,
from game jam processes that we adapted,
and to keep an eye on that balance between structure and innovation
in order to help get through all of those phases of production.
Thank you very much.
That's the end of my presentation.
Now, I think we've got time for a couple questions.
First, I want to stress, please, please, please,
this is my first GDC presentation.
And I would really, really love it and appreciate it
if you would go, once you get the email,
if you'd go and fill in the feedback form,
because I would love the feedback.
Love your thoughts.
Any questions?
There are two microphones there and there.
Hi, so in the conception phase you had this two week period that ended with three pitches.
How many pitches did you actually end up making?
So the conception phase, you're asking me to do math.
Okay, so first of all, the first week ended in three pitches per person.
So that changed as our team scaled up.
So pitch wise, you know, initially I guess we were doing 24 pitches.
Every two weeks, but our team started growing as we were expanding.
So by the time we got to our actual green light pitch,
Many, over 100 fleshed out, more than that, I don't know, 150, tons and tons and tons
of game pitches.
There's really like a treasure trove there, I'd love to go back to that.
We built three prototypes every two weeks.
So that math should be a little bit easier, so again, doing math.
I think all in all, we probably had...
I don't know, 15, 16 different prototypes.
That's not divisible by three, so it's almost not the real number, but somewhere in that
ballpark.
Hi, thanks for the presentation.
You're welcome.
So I'm wondering if during the process where you were pairing people up or putting them
into the groups of four, did it really matter what disciplines you paired together or did
you mix that up every time?
So this is one of the areas where we actually, James and I actually put some design and thought into that.
We would make sure to rotate so that people weren't paired up with the same people.
Obviously we'd have a chance to go through.
But we would try to pair people up where...
One of the things we were most conscious of was one person steering or dominating that conversation too much.
So we would try to pair more introverted or quieter people together in some cases,
especially early on in the project, and, you know, more extroverted, loud people together who could play off each other's energies.
That changed over the course of our production because as everyone started prototyping together,
working very close in these intense things, building, pitching, everyone became much more
comfortable working with each other and you know towards the end we had to be far less concerned
about that and you know we were able to just rotate through people that hadn't worked together yet.
Thanks.
And also I noticed you had some AR pitches during the process.
Sure.
Was there ever an AR version of this game?
You know, you see the keyboard placement stuff.
That would be awesome.
No, but it would be awesome.
Just a small logistical question,
because I also make games that are designed for kids.
How did you find the kids for play testing?
I've Googled this repeatedly, and I
think the only result is I'm probably on some watch lists.
We work with a wonderful user research team at Ubisoft and at Ubisoft Toronto,
so I feel quite lucky to have a bunch of experts that can help guide us through that.
We've done a lot of playtesting with kids and we continue to do regular playtesting with kids.
I think it is wonderful to see really raw, unfiltered thoughts and reactions.
Sometimes we ask people for scores on playtests of like, what do you think of the game?
One to five.
And we found kids are useless at giving scores.
They are wonderful to learn usability lessons.
They're wonderful to, you know, actually watch their reactions and see.
But you know, we've had some...
Playtests where, you know, the build is broken and there's some horrible glitch
and you just see this kid banging their head against a problem and not understanding it.
And, like, they look like they're going to start crying.
And then we're like, what did you think of the game? And they're like, 5 out of 5! It was amazing!
And we're like, okay.
You're just excited because you're coming to test a video game.
So you have to be a little skeptical and take any scores with a grain of salt.
But I think there's immense value.
There's always immense value in watching people
from whatever target demo your game is targeting really play your game.
It's a very, very humbling experience.
Cool.
Thanks.
With the amount of ideas that you were asking your team to come up with during the brainstorming
phase, did you run into a lot of creative burnout?
And if so, how did you manage that?
It's a great question.
It is a really intense process.
You know, the mental drain...
that you get from, you know, you are really pushing yourself to go to the end of like
whatever the heck, you know, after a week of doing this and generating these pitches
and giving these pitches, you know, many people on our team, you know, was cross-disciplined,
many people weren't that comfortable going up and presenting and that was a draining process.
The key for us was that weekend.
You know, the key for us, and that's a big part of why we split it up like that,
was having that first week super intense, all these ideas are coming out.
You'd pitch on Thursday, which was good, because that gave you a bit more time.
You'd pitch on Thursday, come in on Friday, okay, pressure's off a little bit.
You're not generating ideas. Now you're sitting with a team,
and you're trying to figure out, how the heck can we prototype this?
But that's more about people leveraging their experience, their skill set,
saying, oh, I know how to do this, I could do that, I could, you know.
It's very fun, it's very engaging.
But then having that weekend to just go, let things simmer in your head for a bit.
Calm down, and then be ready to go the next week with intense brainstorming.
You know, it's kind of like participating in a game jam,
but you need those gaps, you need those breaks in between.
Thanks.
You're welcome.
Knowing how well your small prototyping group worked,
would you say there's still value in doing studio-wide game jams?
So we've also experimented with studio-wide game gems
at both at UbiToronto and other studios that I've been at.
I think they are very, very fun.
I think they're a great retention tool.
I think they're something very motivating for employees.
I think one of the challenges is
They don't necessarily have the right venue
to turn into something real,
to turn into something that you can really leverage.
There's companies that have done that really well.
I know Bethesda, you know, they tend to do game jams
of how could you add a feature onto our existing game?
But typically, the constraints of a game jam,
you know, where you're doing everything in a week
or you're doing everything in two days,
limits you to creating kind of little arcade-y mini games,
which are super fun, but isn't necessarily something
that Ubisoft is gonna be like.
Or big companies can be like,
yes, we're gonna take that and publish it.
So what we were attempting to do was scale that up
to something that it could be used really
in a major conception of a game.
I think that was really effective.
And personally, I love the idea of maybe,
often you have downtime as people are ramping down
from one project before they start another.
That's a wonderful time to try something like this
with the hope that it can actually turn
into a commercial product that the company could do.
Thank you.
Welcome.
So two questions.
The first one is about the 25 ideas.
How deep are always the ideas?
Is it just simple game play mechanics, or how do you
really define?
So typically people were trying to make ideas that a game could be built around,
so a little bit bigger.
You know, not just like, oh you could press A to do this,
but more like, oh you could build a game around this mechanic.
That having been said, the ideas themselves were just, you know,
a sentence or two short descriptions at that level and you're going through.
So the description was very, very short,
but the ideas were designed to be something that you could actually build a AAA game about.
Okay.
And just the second one was, who decided the idea of the brainstorm of the two weeks?
When you said, like, we will think about the game, I don't remember the example.
Yes, yes, the guided questions. Who decided?
Who decided on those questions?
So that's one of the areas where we were less democratic,
as well.
That was really just James and I, two leads on the project.
We'd sit together and try to come up with some ideas
and put that out to the group.
Thank you all so, so much for coming and listening to my talk.
Please rate it or give me the feedback
or whatever the email asks you to do.
Thank you.