Hi, everybody.
Thanks for being here.
My name is Floor Marti.
I'm the producer of the Deus Ex live team at Eidos Montreal.
And today I'll be talking to you about the process
we went through to create Breach,
which was originally a game mode for Deus Ex Mankind Divided
and has since become a standalone free-to-play game.
So I'm going to start with a quick question. How many of you here have played at least one
Deus Ex game? All right. Mankind Divided? All right. And how many of you here have given a
try to breach? Yeah. Less hands. All right. So for those of you who haven't, I'll start by
quickly explaining what a breach is.
So Breach is a game mode for Deus Ex Mankind Divided.
In Breach, you're not Adam Jensen,
the main protagonist of Mankind Divided.
You are a hacker who uses a VR device
to infiltrate the servers of mega-corporations.
Your goal is to steal their secrets.
And to do so, you need to find and download the data
that's hidden inside the levels.
The servers of those megacorporations are hosted
in a super secure facility that we call the Palisade Blade.
And the AI, which runs this facility,
is doing everything it can to stop you.
Breach is an asynchronous online experience.
It's an arcade twist on the Deus Ex gameplay peelers
with a leaderboard-based competitive aspect
and some light free-to-play mechanics.
So our launch trailer was actually more than five minutes
long, so I'm going to spare you that.
But to give you a better idea if you've never played it, I
will show you our latest trailer, which was actually
out two weeks ago, and sums up the major updates we've been
making to the game since it's launched.
So to tell you about how we created Breach, I need to start by telling you about the Life
Team and our initial mandate. The Deus Ex Life Team was created at Eidos, Montreal at
the beginning of 2014 with the mandate of taking care of all the additional content
for Mankind Divided.
In order to let the core team focus 100% of their energy
on crafting the main game.
That means that any bonus mission,
any additional content, item pack, narrative DLCs,
the post-launch contents and post-launch operations
were to be handled by the live team.
The mandate of the team was also to expand
the Deus Ex universe and experiment outside
of the traditional single-player story-driven experience.
And as part of that mandate,
we were supposed to deliver challenge maps,
which would be an additional bonus content
available day one for every player.
The pillars of those challenge maps were first
that they had to teach the gameplay mechanics
of Mankind Divided to the players.
and allow them to practice and master those mechanics
outside of the story-driven campaign.
Then we're supposed to bring added replay value to the game
while always delivering a true Deus Ex experience.
The constraints we had to work with were that we didn't have a lot of resources.
We were a very small team and we had a lot to do.
Because again, the challenge maps were only a portion of the additional content we were
making for Mankind Divided.
We also didn't have a lot of time.
We actually started conception one year
before the initially planned ship date of the game.
And we also didn't have a lot of money.
Our budget was pretty tight,
so we couldn't compensate neither the size of the team
or the tight schedule with, for instance,
outsourcing some part of the work.
The base idea for those challenge maps
was to reuse existing environments
from the VR tutorial mode of the main game
and implement new objectives for these maps.
So, for instance, there was a shooting range
in that VR tutorial,
and we could have implemented challenges
like shoot all the targets under 30 seconds,
destroy as many targets as possible
using only augmentations,
do as many headshots as possible, et cetera.
So, side note here, if you have played Mankind Divided
and are wondering where the hell were those VR tutorials,
well, they didn't make it to the final game.
So, how did we go from these VR challenges
to a full-on competitive mode with more than 100 levels?
Well, what gave birth to the bridge concept
is probably a combination of five factors.
So first of all, the team wasn't particularly excited by the idea.
Both on the actual implementation side of it, but most of all,
we didn't think it was going to be really fun for players.
Then there was also inside the studio a recurring topic
of wanting to make a hacking-focused game.
It had been around since the development
of Human Revolution, and several concepts
were pitched over the years,
but none made it past the initial concept stage.
And since part of the mandate of the life team
was to explore and expand the Deus Ex universe,
we wanted to use the incredibly rich lore at our disposal
and put more narrative meat around the bone.
We very much liked the fantasy
of being a super skilled hacker
and the idea of putting at the forefront
those corrupt mega corporations
that are always in the background of Deus Ex games.
Another factor which played a major role in the birth of Breach was that all our level
designers were new to Deus Ex.
So they were ramping up on the engine and on the level design rules of the franchise
by playing around in what we call gyms.
where they were building gameplay scenarios
using only gray blocks and messing around with them
and not paying any attention to the physical constraints
or the environmental credibility.
We realized that the very simple and modular environment
of the VR tutorials would allow them to keep that freedom,
even when they were going to build real levels for the game,
which is not the case when you create
a classical Deus Ex narrative mission,
where the credibility of the space and the,
sorry, or the credibility of the space
plays a major role,
puts a lot of constraints on the level design.
But we still wanted the visual to be carrying some of the narrative.
Everything in the art direction of Dosek's Human Revolution and
Mankind Divided is there on purpose.
Everything carries a very heavy symbolic and
we wanted that to be true of Breach too.
The added bonus was that actually in the first months of the existence of the team,
nobody was really looking at us.
All the energy and attention was focused on the main game,
and we were supposed to be progressively ramping up on the franchise,
and we were free to experiment on our own,
without anyone telling us that this was absolutely not what was expected of us.
I'll add to that my own background.
I come from mobile and indie, small-budget games.
Deus Ex was my very first AAA experience,
and I was used to making a lot with very little resources.
So my naivety at the time probably played a big role
in allowing the team and even encouraging them
to push the creative boundaries
and to go for something that really excited them,
even if it was way more than what we were supposed to deliver.
So when we came up with the idea for Breach, after a brainstorming session,
we had a little bit more than a month before the first green light meeting for the live team,
where we were supposed to present our whole creative and production plan
for all the contents tied to the Sex, Mankind, Divided.
By this date, we would need to have enough
to convince the higher-ups,
meaning the Square Enix management,
but first of all, the Deus Ex executive of the franchise,
and the studio head,
that Breach was a better concept
than the initially planned challenge maps,
even though it meant a lot more work
and most probably a bigger team
than the one originally planned.
So we did two things.
First, we crafted a 50 plus slide presentation of the concept.
Detailing our vision for all the gameplay mechanics, the scoring and
reward systems, the level design philosophy, the core loop, the online features,
the character building, the player fantasy, the back story, the ties to the main game,
the business model, the economic loop, all of it.
The presentation detailed the main production milestones for all this and already laid out
which features would be present at launch and which ones would be part of the post-launch
plan.
It also presented how we envisioned the post-launch lifecycle with promotion events, content patches,
and balancing updates.
The second thing we did was prototyping the core experience
of Breach, and especially the gameplay parts
that were unique to it compared to the main game.
So extracting data, escaping the map, applying modifiers,
computing the player score, et cetera.
Enough to be able to back up the PowerPoint presentation
with some concrete, hands-on gameplay,
and prove the base concept was solid and fun,
even if the deadline was way too tight
for us to have a full first playable.
So here's what the game looked like at that time.
And I must warn you, it might hurt your eyes a little bit.
This is very old.
And you know what? It worked!
Yeah, I'm not sure that deserves that much better.
But it worked.
We were allowed to go on with the development
of our first playable, which we actually delivered
a few weeks later after only three months had passed
since that very first brainstorm on the concept.
And I got the green light to add some very much needed
key resources to the team.
Which leads me to a short parenthesis about the team
before going back to the development of Breach itself.
So since the initial mandate of the live team
was essentially to create new content,
and we weren't supposed to be actually adding features,
or very few of them, to the game,
the vast majority of the initial roster
was composed of artists, level designers,
and narrative designers.
The theory was that all we had to do
would be to take the existing systems,
features, and tools developed by the core team,
and use them to create new content.
We would be in charge of creating our own assets
and storylines, of course, but that was mainly it.
But bringing Breach into the mix
created a big recruitment challenge.
It meant that we actually needed more game designers,
audio designers, UI designers,
as well as a bunch of programmers,
and not only for gameplay, but for all the online side,
and the massive amount of UI we're about to add.
Still, we couldn't go crazy and inflate the team too much
because, well, it wouldn't make sense budget-wise.
And one of the biggest challenge in building
the Breach team was to find generalists.
So we basically had to build a team of Swiss Army Knives.
And in the AAA industry, where people are pushed
to be hyper specialized, where they invest years
into developing very specific expertise,
this happens to be a very tough thing.
If you add to that, that at that time in the studio,
we were that weird new team labeled as the DLC team,
the B team, and that everybody just wanted to get
on the big AAA core team.
finding the right people proved to be very difficult. But you know what? Actually I firmly
believe that this all played a major role on making the team a success. With everybody
having a lot of ownership on the content and not only on breach but also all the DLCs and
the other stuff we made from My Kind Divided.
The people who joined us chose to do it.
And since there was not many of us,
everybody had a big role to play
and had the opportunity to be a real part
of the creative process.
And since we were a small team,
well, we could all fit in a single room together
to show our work to each other,
to play our game together,
and exchange feedback and ideas in a very fluid manner.
And this very quickly created a solid bond
and a sense of belonging.
And I truly believe that we made a better game for it.
The small size of the team also allowed us a lot,
to have a lot of interaction between the designers
and the programmers.
And that was a blessing because given the very tight schedule
we were on, we basically did the conception,
the pre-production and the production at the same time.
So some features were actually still being designed
at the same time as they were implemented by the progs.
And with a bigger team,
it could have been way more problematic.
Don't get me wrong, I'm not saying it's ideal
and that there wasn't any problem.
And no, this is not the ideal way to do it.
But for us, in a sense, it kind of worked.
So, back to our main subject.
Of course, there are things that sets
immediately breach apart from the core single experience.
First, we throw the player
in a completely different visual environment.
Then we introduced them to the concept of data extraction,
which is unique to Breach.
And of course, in Breach, you're not Adam Jensen,
but a ripper, a hacker from 2029.
Finally, the presence of leaderboards
introduces a competitive element
which doesn't exist at all in the single player.
But still, at its core, Breach respects
the fundamental pillars of Deus Ex.
Apart from a very few, very optional exceptions,
all the maps can be played using whatever play style
the player prefers.
From full on ghosting to blasting your way through the level
and everything in between, or even playing
without ever using a single augmentation,
Breach allows players to approach the challenges
any way they like.
And of course, there are always plenty of different paths
to get to your objective.
But very early during the development process,
we made the conscious choice to throw the players
out of their comfort zone,
to offer them the opportunity to try something new,
to discover that maybe they might actually enjoy things
that they had never tried in the main campaign.
And we used several different devices
to gently but firmly push them in that direction.
For starters, each of the corporations that you infiltrate
in Breach has its own gameplay personality.
So for instance, the Tarvos Corporation is your classic
Deus Ex type layout, filled with mixed defenses
of humanoids, cameras, and lasers,
and of course, a lot of air vents.
Steiner Beasley, on the other hand,
confronts the player to wide open areas,
swarming with guards and turrets.
while the VersaLife levels are all about verticality,
platforming puzzles, and hazards.
Of course, you could apply the same exact gameplay style
to all of these maps and still be able to beat them.
But if you are embracing the competitive aspect of Breach,
then you will have to be versatile
and adapt the way you play.
We also created and implemented the concept
of what we call AI evolutions.
Every action that the player performs is recorded
and taken into account to move one of the three AI meters,
damage, defense, and delay.
For instance, offensive actions against the defenses
of the map will increase the damage meter.
and the game will react to it
by making the enemies have better weapons,
deal more damages,
or gain some resistance to some type of damages.
Once this has happened enough times,
the player has two choices,
using pretty rare items that we call nuke viruses
to downgrade the AI evolution
because it's now pretty hardcore,
or simply opt for a less aggressive play style,
staying out of combat.
Of course, true to the Deus Ex philosophy, the same principle applies to actions oriented
towards stealth or hacking. The way we handle the equipment available for the player also
plays a big role into bringing them out of their comfort zone. Everybody starts Breach with
the same basic loadout, but one of the main differences with the single player is that
there is no loot inside the levels.
Enemies vanish once they have been eliminated.
So there is no corpse to loot from.
Instead, all the equipment needed by the player,
the weapons, the ammunitions, the healing items, et cetera,
are found in randomized booster packs
that players are either awarded
or that they can purchase with the credits
that they gain from extracting the data.
the randomness factor is very important because it means that there is a very good chance
you won't get your favorite weapon before a while. And even if you get it, the rarity
system, which is another feature unique to Breach, might cause you to get a very powerful,
say, sniper rifle when your favorite weapon that you've used in the single player campaign
is a shotgun.
But if you get a very rare class S sniper rifle,
super powerful, it might make you think twice
before you just stick on using your old class C
super weak shotgun.
But different enemies have different weaknesses
or resistances, and there again,
players also have to adapt and get out of their comfort zone
to try out new weapons and strategies.
The leaderboards are also a way for us to give an incentive
to players to try new things.
Each of the bridge level has two leaderboards,
score and time.
Obviously someone cheated there.
Aiming for the top of the time leaderboard
means trying to complete your main objective
and escape the map in the minimum amount of time possible.
Which means ignoring side objectives,
not losing any time getting into fights with the AIs,
not exploring for any hidden data,
and finding the best augmentation combination possible
to exploit every shortcut in the map.
Thus, being on top of the time leaderboard
has a very good chance to mean
that your score will totally suck.
Well, on the other end, if you take your time in the map,
if you chain XP, heavy actions, if you hack everything,
if you take down or kill everyone,
if you destroy every robotic defense
and find every single bit of data,
your score has a very good chance to be on the higher end,
putting you in a better position on the score leaderboard,
but make you fail down on the time leaderboard.
For the anecdote, the time leader wasn't really part
of the initial concept.
But when we started playing the game on the floor,
we realized that the speed running aspect
it was bringing to the Deus Ex gameplay
was probably one of the most exciting
and unique features of Breach.
It is also the one that has generated
the most emergent gameplay,
both in user testing and on the floor.
And there is nothing more satisfying
than the look on the level designers face
when they see your name on the leaderboard of a map
that they've designed next to a time lower
than they thought was possible to achieve.
We actually made.
one exception to the golden rule of freedom of play style.
And some of the maps in Breach require that the players
reach their data objective without being detected,
forcing them to play stealth.
These maps are always on optional path
in the overall progression, but completionists
will have to defeat them if they want to beat
100% of the levels.
And I admit this was completely arbitrary decision
because we are kind of biased towards stealth.
For some reason, we thought it would also be really cool
to have some heavy platforming navigation
in some of the levels, mainly in the VersoLife maps.
But since all the three C's were inherited
from the main game, which has next to no
platforming mechanics, solving all the ledge grab
and jumping related bugs was kind of super low priority
for the core team, which is totally understandable.
So for a very long time, while our user tests
suffered very badly from the frustration
this was causing to players.
who pretty much looked like this.
Yup, that's it.
But the bright side of this is that it actually pushed us
to develop one of the coolest bridge-specific augmentations
which is the multi-jump.
And it ended up solving a lot of our let's wrap issues.
Another area where we tried to bite off more than we could
chew was the AI and especially its behavior related to
data towers.
Originally the design was that downloading data would
attract the AI's attention and that the player would have
to stay near the tower while the data was downloaded
which meant that they would have to either fight the
incoming AIs or find a way to stay near but undetected
if they were going for stealth.
Unfortunately, that meant some heavy work on the AI side.
And since the team didn't have a dedicated AI programmer,
we never managed to get a satisfying result,
and not for lack of trying.
So after long debates, and with a lot of regrets,
we dropped this part of the design.
But the funny thing is that we discovered
it actually made the game way better.
It made it way more dynamic and fast-paced,
which was a really good thing.
And it played really well into our already established bias
towards speed running.
Another fundamental pillar of a Deus Ex game
is the choice and consequences.
And without the whole social aspect of the single player,
we had to transcribe this into gameplay features.
So for instance, we created modifiers that we call patches.
Patches are applied to a map and modify the rules,
making the map harder in exchange for a score bonus.
Some patches have a direct effect on the player or the AI.
Like for instance, draining the player's life every second
or giving a region to the enemies.
While other patches are conditional and can be failed.
Like for instance, if the player sustains any damage
during the level or uses any weapon other than a pistol.
Failing those patches won't make the player fail the level,
but they won't get the score bonus tied to it,
and since the patches are consumed on use,
players might want to be careful on when to use them.
And of course, the meaner the patch used by the player,
the bigger the bonus is.
And if you're feeling extra confident
about your skill on a particular level,
well, you can even stack patches for a bigger bonus.
We also made a major modification
to the augmentation tree system
by adding a memory space cost to each aug.
This means that even if the player
has gained enough praxis kits
to unlock all of the available augmentations,
the limited memory space available
prevents them from equipping all the augs at the same time.
And since once a level has started, the Aug tree is locked.
Players must make a conscious choice
before entering a level on which Augs
they want to take with them.
Of course, this choice should be different
depending on the actual map they're trying to beat
and if they're going for score or for time
and of course based on their play style.
I'm sorry.
Yes.
The inventory system, a big classic of Deus Ex,
was also revisited with the choice and consequences in mind.
In Breach, the players actually have two inventories.
The reserve, which is basically a stash with infinite space
where all the items found in booster packs go,
and the loadout, which contains everything the player
has access to while breaching a level.
The loadout reuses the main game's inventory system,
but with heavily limited available space.
So that, here again, players are faced
with a strategic choice about what to bring
with them inside the levels.
Depending on their play style,
or the type of defenses they can expect to face in there.
We also created items which give you bonuses
as long as they are present in your loadout.
This means that you have to trade space
in exchange for that bonus.
And that space would be otherwise used for weapons
or ammunitions or healing items.
And of course, the bigger the bonus,
the more space you have to sacrifice for it.
Now, let's talk visual.
So, at first glance, the art direction of Breach
can feel completely disconnected from the visual style
of both Human Revolution and Mankind Divided.
But it's actually far from being the case.
So first came the fuchsia.
So for those of you who haven't played
Human Revolution or Mankind Divided,
who have played them, sorry,
I don't know if you've noticed,
but there is no fuchsia or a pink or a purple in the game.
It is the forbidden color of the deus ex art bible,
with one exception.
It is worn by Eliza Kassan,
one of the major characters of the game,
who, it turns out, isn't real.
I'm sorry for any spoiler.
Eliza is an AI, so it made immediate sense to us
to make it the base color of Breach.
The color of data.
When we submitted this idea to Jonathan Jacques Beltet,
the executive art director of the franchise,
he immediately embraced it and gave us his benediction
to use the forbidden color.
So once we had the fuchsia, came the corporations.
So for various reasons, among which giving
as much freedom possible to the level designers
and working with modules to get production costs
under control, we wanted to keep the art style very simple,
but we needed it to convey the narrative,
and especially the real world backstory
of the various corporations that you infiltrate
in the VR world.
So while the base building blocks are the same
in every level with a white outer shell,
black inner blocks, and fuchsia magma,
we played with the shapes and the lighting
to give each server a very different mood.
And we created specific landmarks
which both help convey the narrative
and serve as orientation device for the player.
So for instance, in the Deus Ex universe,
the Steiner-Beasley Corporation is a German corporation
which manufactures weapons.
So in the VR world of Breach,
their servers are foundry-like rooms
with pixelated magma and orange fog in the air.
and in the ceiling of the Talonpike map,
a giant grinder rotates in an infinite loop,
breaking down the data magma into data shards.
Then, of course, once we had the corporations,
we had to populate the world.
And we started with the Reaper's Avatar.
And among our production constraints,
we had to work with Adam Jensen.
We had to reuse him as much as we could
in terms of gameplay, of course,
but also in terms of animation,
overall builds, down to his geometry,
and especially his arms,
because we didn't have any rigger,
any skinner, or any animator on the team.
So the challenge was to turn that constraint
into a design element,
which ended up with that dual material look,
the solid black arms, which are the original models,
and the more abstract-looking gold triangles,
which were both a way to have it stand out
against the mostly black and white environments,
and a nod to Human Revolution's
collector's edition key art.
And once the logic of the VR world had been laid out,
designing the enemies was only a matter of figuring out
how that world would generate them.
So, as for almost everything else,
we inherited most of the enemies
from Mankind Divided's casts.
So, drones, the sentry boats, the turrets, et cetera.
But the humanoids that we call the sentinels,
they stood out as they were the only human-like in breach
among the mostly mechanical other enemy types.
And in the context of being inside the machine,
it kind of felt out of place.
And that's a key notion in the Deus Ex franchise,
that everything has to feel logical,
that everything has to be credible
and to belong with the rest.
So we came up with the idea that while the rest of the defenses were logical defense
systems in the context of breach, which again is a machine using machine-like units to
defend itself, the Sentinels were a response to the presence of the Reaper. It's the AI
from the Palisade that is trying to come up with something to match the new threat that the
Reapers are.
So we tried to have a humanoid that felt like
an approximation, an average, and we got inspired
by the point clouds that you can see
in a Kinect's infrared feed.
In motion, you can tell it's human,
but in a static frame, it's only abstract data,
which felt like how the AI would perceive the reapers.
Once we had that down, all we had to do was making sure
that the Sentinel's building blocks
came from the same rule sets
that define all of the other elements of the world.
So the black cubes and the white triangular plating,
and voila.
So in the first iteration of the bridge concept,
the narrative layer was extremely thin.
There was the backstory of the bridge,
the references to the Deus Ex corporations,
and the symbolism of the art style.
And we had planned to hide pieces of information
inside the data downloaded in the level.
Players would stumble across those pieces
more or less randomly and get insights
on characters and factions from the main game.
But we realized fairly quickly that we couldn't be making a Deus Ex game,
even a game mode, without a stronger narrative layer.
Because Deus Ex is a story heavy franchise and, oops, sorry.
And the Breach was already weird enough in itself without taking the risk
to alienate our core story driven players from the beginning.
But we also didn't have the resources or the budget
to tell stories in the traditional way,
to make cut scenes, to record voiceovers,
to handle branching conversations.
Then we discovered that the core team had developed
a text messenger system for the main game.
And since having text-based interaction with people
totally made sense in the context of Reach,
which takes place inside a computer,
we decided to use it as a foundation for our storytelling.
So this is how we came up with the dark net files,
which are self-contained conspiracies
that you get to investigate by infiltrating
specific servers in search of data shards.
Along the way, contacts help you decrypt
or make sense of the data, ask you for help,
or send you to attack designated servers
to disrupt the real world security systems
of a corporation while they physically infiltrate it.
Each conversation with contacts has branching choices
and the system carries over your relationship status
with your contacts from one case to another.
So for instance, if you've been a dick
with a contact in the VersaLife case,
when you will need this contact's help
in the Steiner Bizet case, well,
they will ask you for a higher price
in exchange for their services.
At the end of each Darknet file,
when the player has solved the case,
a PyCast news broadcast is shown to them,
making the link between what they did in the VR world
and the impact it had on the real world.
Here's an example.
We now turn to Lyon, France, where earlier today, the Santo Group held a press conference debunking what they claim are unfounded rumors regarding their Grand Rapida project.
Santo felt the need to respond, after allegedly leaked documents on the internet began to cast doubt on the project's integrity.
A representative assures us that every home paid for is in fact being built,
and that their city of the future is well on track to accommodate the more than 100,000 augmented people projected to move there.
Any information to the contrary, they claim, is the product of doctored reports being uploaded by malicious hackers called Rippers,
in an effort to discredit the corporation.
I do not know about you folks, but I prefer to trust the people in suits over these mysterious rippers who will not even reveal their names, or just how they came across their information.
This is Eliza Kassan, reporting to you, live, from Pycus.
The Dark Knight files are a perfect example of a feature
built on top of something developed for the main game
that we repurposed for our own needs
and to which we added a few Brichonnet specifics.
All the writing was done inside the team
but in close collaboration with Marie de Marle,
the executive narrative director of the Deus Ex franchise
who's also the keeper of the lore.
The Darknet files turned out to be one of the most appreciated features of Breach in user testing
and one of the hooks that allowed us to get the story-driven players to give a chance to the mode
while they would probably have ignored it otherwise.
The newscasts at the end are also a very simple and efficient way to tie in the world of Breach and the Reapers
to the world of Mankind Divided and of Adam Jensen.
We actually managed to do quite a few of these tie-ins,
integrating references to the Breach
in the single-player experience.
This ad, for instance, seen in Mankind Divided,
shows the Palisade Blade, which is the physical facility
that's hosting the servers
that the Reapers infiltrate in Breach.
In the single-player campaign, also,
Jensen has to go inside the VR world
to steal some information,
and the environment that is used
is actually a modified map from Breach.
But our biggest tie-in was, logically,
one of the live team's productions.
System Rift, our first narrative DLC for Mankind Divided,
explains how the bridge came to be.
And of course, it's all Jensen's fault.
And it introduces players to Shadowchild,
a famous hacker who turns out to be the one
who's guiding you inside Bridge.
Now,
Let's talk about the more sensitive stuff, shall we?
So it's not uncommon today to have microtransactions
in the multiplayer live modes of games
on all platforms and in premium games.
As it is a completely different experience
that you add on top of the game,
it doesn't impact the main experience.
And being a life team, exploring alternative revenue,
revenue models, was part of our initial mandate.
But we were all very aware of the fact that players would already have spent $60,
or if you're based in Canada like us, $80, to buy Mankind Divided.
And that it would be extremely unfair to put up any kind of paywall.
It was also very clear to us that any real money spent had to be completely
optional and shouldn't be turning the game into a pay to win.
We also had one big disadvantage.
Deus Ex is mainly a first-person game,
even if the cover system and the takedown
switch the camera to third person.
And Breach is not a PvP real-time multiplayer,
so the interests of vanity items,
which are the most accepted form of microtransactions,
was vastly limited.
In the end, our monetized features
can be broken down into three categories.
First, we have accelerators, or using money
to obtain faster something you could have otherwise
obtained by simply playing the game a little longer.
Then we have the cool, weird stuff,
like our premium weapons,
which are not more powerful than other S or A grade weapons
that you can obtain in regular booster packs
that you can purchase with the in-game currency.
They just have a unique skin and unique gameplay features.
And believe me.
Some are really weirder than powerful.
Like our no scope rifle,
which is a very powerful sniper rifle,
except its scope is obstructed.
So you can't use it and you can only do hip fire
with the sniper rifle.
Finally, vanity items like our unique skins
for the Reaper avatar.
We still went for them, even considering
the previously mentioned factors of the first person game,
but we did bet on getting some interest in them
from streamers.
So when I say that we were careful with demonetization,
I'm really not joking.
We had pretty heated debates about what was crossing the line or not, and when in doubt,
we always defaulted to not going with something that could be perceived even a tiny bit
borderline. In the end, we probably wasted a lot of energy on this for nothing.
No matter how careful, how respectful we try to be
in our economic design, what we really didn't foresee
was that our player base was absolutely not ready for this.
And while the critical reception for breach
from the press was really good,
and we didn't hide the monetization from them,
The simple presence of real money transactions in the game created an unforeseen outrage among
our players. And it completely overshadowed everything else.
Things would probably have been different
if Breach had been released right away
as a standalone Deus Ex universe free-to-play game.
But as a game mode, offered as a bonus
alongside a full-price game,
the monetization was a deal breaker
for a big majority of the players of Mankind Divided.
And this, for me, is where the experimentation
found its limits.
I'm extremely proud of the work the team has done with Breach.
And I truly believe that we have proved we could take the core DNA of the franchise
and make something extremely innovative and different without betraying it.
The only issue is that the business model was not ready to be experimented with.
So to wrap up, here are a few takeaways
from the Breach experimentation
I would like to share with you.
First, I firmly believe it is absolutely possible
to innovate and experiment
within an already established franchise
without betraying it.
If you know exactly what your core pillars are,
especially in the mind of your players,
and you are able to think of new ways
to express those pillars.
then you don't have to reinvent the wheel
and rethink all your core mechanics.
By using them as building blocks
that you twist a little bit
and present in a different way to your players,
you can create a whole new experience.
But the way you deliver and communicate
about that new experience matters.
And know where are the limits of your fan base
and whether they are ready to accept or not.
Again, I think if Breach had been a stand-alone free-to-play
game from the beginning, the reception from our players
would have been very different.
So this concludes my presentation today.
Before taking questions, if you have any,
I would like to give a big shout out to my team,
part of which you can see
in this very cheesy heart-shaped picture.
I would like to thank them for the three
pretty awesome years that we spent together
making a pretty awesome game.
Thank you. If you have any questions, I think there are mics there. Just go and ask away.
Hi. I was wondering how did you manage the switch from being a game mode to a free-to-play?
There are many big challenges with the team or the system.
Absolutely not, because the free-to-play,
standalone version of Breach is actually
collection of everything we had made so far for the game.
And we released it on Steam only.
So it was really easy to do, and we didn't touch
at all the economic model or anything.
We just wanted to give the opportunity
to players who didn't buy Mankind Divided
to play it.
play breach. So with the community reception of the microtransactions not being very
positive, how do you see that carry over to some of the behaviors within it? Like do you see
certain noticeable groups of players still engaged with the microtransactions? But that
could be grouped separately somehow?
So we have the most active,
like we still have a community of players
who became very active and who have like
recorded tons of videos and how-tos
and post on the forums all the time.
A tiny community, I must say.
And they don't engage a lot with the microtransactions.
But it's not a surprise because, again,
we were so careful in the economic design.
I mean, you really want,
you need to want to give us your money to do it.
I mean, there is really no other thing.
Okay, thanks.
Hi there.
So I counted about 30 people inside of the LiveOps team.
Yeah.
I just wanted to ask exactly how many of those
were level designers and gameplay programmers
and sort of the guys that were making the content.
So I'm not gonna get into very specific numbers
because I don't think I have the right to.
But so what you have to understand is that that picture
is both the Breach team and the team
that was making the DLCs.
Some of those people were working on both,
like our programmers, for instance,
but the level designers and the artists
were separated into people working on Breach
and people working on DLCs.
And so on Breach we had two main level designers who made kind of all of the
majority of the levels with a bit more people chiming. And as far as gameplay
programmers, well the programming team for the whole life team was about eight
programmers.
I just had one more question as well based around, so I realize you've released the game
now as a standalone.
Yeah.
Originally it was kind of a menu option inside of the main game.
Yes.
And I wonder whether you had many metrics on people getting kind of lost about that
because I know some people were confused about what Breach was.
but the fact that it was kind of in that first section of the first splash screen that you have?
So, the thing is I don't have metrics about if the people were lost about it.
I know that about 30% of the players of Mankind Divided have played Breach.
That's the one thing I know.
The menu, when you're inside Minekind's menu, it says enter the bridge, I think, the sub
menu. I think if you go in there and you just watch the cinematic, then you kind of understand
what it's about. I don't know. Maybe not. In user testing, nobody ever told us that
they were lost about it. That's just  okay. Thanks. Very informative talk.
Thank you.
Hello, I have a question about the avatar vanity items. You said you had some doubts while introducing them
But I saw in the latest update you also introduced some new ones
So I would like to ask you from perspective how successful you say you would say they are or they were they were
Well, they are part of the things that sell the most because they're cool, I think, and
they're cool-looking and people like cool-looking stuff.
But still, again, the overall performance of the monetization of Breach is really low,
so it's not super significant to say that something is more successful than another
with tiny numbers like that.
Thank you.
Welcome.
Do we have another?
Yes, so you said that there's a DLC team and a breach team.
So is DLC a paid?
Yes.
Paid DLC, so is there a possibility
that you take all the bundles
and just make it a paid DLC on top of?
breach so that breach remains free and that everything that you want to add is just one or
two or three payments as DLC and then you don't have microtransactions and then you just
avoid the whole problem and you can totally monetize it as just three options.
That's probably something we should have considered honestly with now.
Seeing it, I would say that we have been very,
probably better for our players and better perceived.
We didn't do it like that.
And it's probably too late to change anything about this.
One of the things you guys couldn't have caught in process
if you need to get out of jail free card is that ESPN wrote a
scathing destruction piece about microtransaction economies on
steam that disseminated infinitely broadly and raised the
anger level about microtransactions to so much that
steam had to respond.
Yeah, there were timing issues.
We had very angry YouTubers come at us
with a very loud voice saying not so true stuff.
And we did a lot of concept testing and user research
and we really asked the questions to
fans of Deus Ex about the monetization and stuff
because we wanted to be careful about it.
And again, it wasn't foreseen.
The reaction at release was nothing
like we had anticipated.
We thought there would be a bit of backlash,
but not that amount.
Well, thank you everybody.
And don't forget to fill out your surveys.
I've been asked to remind that of you.
Fill out your surveys.