Welcome everyone to my talk in VRDC. I'm Chad Dawson. I'm a
project lead at Double Fine Productions. The title of my
talk is Reinventing Psychonauts for Virtual Reality. I'm
currently working on a Psychonauts game at Double Fine,
Psychonauts and the Rhombus of Ruin. It's for Sony's PlayStation
VR. It's an upcoming title coming out in the next few
months. First I'll give an overview of what we're talking
about today.
why Psychonauts in VR. We'll start with some inspiration on
kind of how we got the idea to take Psychonauts to VR and why
we picked that title to work on. Then we'll start talking about
adaptation, changes we made to gameplay, locomotion, controls.
Iteration, how we iterated on the controls and targeting, went
through a number of different prototypes, eventually settled
on the control configuration that we came up with. And then
finally innovation.
how we overcame design challenges. With any project you run into hurdles, you run into
things that don't work right and things that do. We'll give a few examples of what worked
for us and might work for you as well. It all started just over a year ago, summer of 2015. We
were all excited as most of you are about the new VR tech coming out.
I had done some research back in grad school in the 90s with the
old lawnmower man style giant helmets, some prototypes back
then. A number of our team had backed the Oculus Rift, we're
playing around with the DK2s. As a studio, Double Fine has always
kind of taken on new technology. We made games for the Microsoft
Connect, Happy Action Theater, Connect Party, and we also did
some for the Leap controller, one called Autonomous.
We had a lot of ideas but we weren't really sure which one
would be best. We were kind of all over the place but Double
Fine had something else in the works, something our fans had
been asking for a long time. Psychonauts 2. We planned on
crowdfunding Psychonauts 2 later that same year and we hit on an
idea. As Tim was starting to write the story for these, there
was a missing part and we thought, what if we made a
Psychonauts VR game?
It could tell the story between Psychonauts 1 and Psychonauts 2
and it would be in VR. It would come out earlier than Psychonauts
2 and accelerate our art and engine pipeline. We wanted to
get together some assets and stuff for starting the crowd
funding for it, but we didn't have much look development done
yet. But how would Psychonauts work in VR? Released in 2005,
Psychonauts was an action platformer. How many of you are
familiar with the original game? Show of hands. Okay, most of
you. Good.
It's an action platformer using third person follow cam. As you
can see here, your main character Raz, he's an acrobat.
Features double jumps, high speed rail slides, wild gravity
flips, dynamic motion combat.
We quickly learned that following this type of motion
with a camera in VR can be very disorienting and make players
physically uncomfortable and sick if you try to just latch a
camera to it. We started experimenting with fixed and
rail cams to try to reduce the camera motion a little bit when
we were trying stuff out, but it pulled us too far away from our
characters and was still making us a bit nauseous. But Psychonauts
had more going on than just dynamic third-person action.
Looking past the camera mechanics of the game, it also
received critical acclaim for its unique visual style,
stylized look, story, characters and the humor. A significant
part of the game was told through cinematic cut scenes and
vignettes like this one, featuring camera pans, close-ups
and handcrafted animation. When you ask many people about the
game, I think this is kind of what they remember getting to
know the characters as much as they do the third person action.
But cinematic camera movements like this are a bit jarring in
VR. It's hard to pan the camera in and do a close-up.
without the player feeling uncomfortable. And other
techniques like letter boxing to tell the player you're in
cinematic mode, none of your controls will work, didn't make
much sense. Our artists were starting on the visual
development. We were bringing our characters up to more modern
rendering technique. And we're using the Unreal 4 engine. You
can see the characters look a lot different than they did 10
years ago.
They did an amazing job getting the characters in lighting and
we really wanted to show off that expressiveness. We didn't
want to put you in a camera just behind the character where you
couldn't see the expressions on their face or have them be far
away where you couldn't tell what they were doing. So for
inspiration, we looked at story and development in the original
title. In Psychonauts, Raz, as shown here in this video, had
the ability to travel into other characters' minds.
but you never really got to see what it was like in Raz's mind.
You never really got to see things from his perspective. We
started to explore first person camera to see what would it look
like to be looking out the eyes and the famous goggles of Raz
himself. This is some footage of our new game. In this case we
show the first person mode.
This perspective feels more immersive. It finally feels like you're actually in the world of
psychonauts and not just seeing it from above running behind a character. This sense of scale
felt more personal. The familiar characters from the game took on new life. There's more of a
connection of a character like Lily here as she fails to meet your gaze, looks down or draws
your attention by looking over your shoulder.
The adult character here has to lean down to talk to you. That's
something you didn't see in the first game, that sense of scale.
That you're a kid, you're a 12-year-old boy and you're with
adults. They lean down to talk to you. That sense of them being
condescending to you or nice to you, you get a better feel for
it as soon as you get in first person.
This perspective worked well as we started to look at the
psychic abilities. In the first game Raz was at psychic summer
camp and he learned how to do all psychic powers. One of our
favorite was pyrokinesis. Lighting stuff on fire with your
mind is always kind of fun.
side blast is also fun. There's nothing like shooting a bolt of
lightning out of your head. This was particularly neat in VR. It
felt like it was coming from your mind. Use it to blow stuff
up and open doors. You can even use it to hit different things
in the level. Particularly fun. But we wanted something, slide
there.
There we go. Something a little bit more subtle. We added a
psychic poke, sort of our bread and butter interaction players
to touch the world a little less destructively. You don't always
want to blow stuff up. This goes to a little bit point and click
adventure style where you're just interacting with something
or just annoying your friends. My favorite adaptation was
telekinesis, moving an object around with your mind. It works
surprisingly well in our game as you can pick objects up, move
around by moving your head.
It worked well with our characters too. We added eye and head tracking. Characters would
follow what you're doing. They'd swat it away if it got too close. This added a sense of
immersion to our characters that we didn't really have with them just sitting there doing
idle animation loops. It made the characters feel more responsive, more alive. Many players
were surprised. Once they figured out that they could do this and the characters would react
to it, they would spend the whole rest of the demo just trying to stack pillows and hit the
other characters in the face.
The more you can add to your game to do character interaction
to have them respond to things and look at it, the more players
will connect with your characters. We now have a
pretty compelling experience from Raz's perspective, just
sitting there and looking around. But how would the player
move through the world? We know we wanted our levels to be
bigger than just one room where you're sitting in one spot. Our
next challenge was locomotion.
Two of our guiding design principles in making this game
were accessibility and comfort. The original game was
accessible to a lot of people, a wide range of audience and a
wide range of player styles. Some people went to the game
just for the story. Others went for it for the fun mechanics. We
wanted to include all of them. We recognize that for many
players, this could be their first VR experience. We didn't
want them taking off the headset after the first few minutes and
not coming back.
The game itself is a little bit longer than a few demos that are
only a few minutes. We're looking at around a two to three
hour experience that we're hoping the player, some players
might play start to finish from beginning to end, but we divide
it up into smaller chunks. We wanted to preserve a comfortable
seated experience. We wanted to avoid VR nausea of running
around, jumping players to the world that some people get with
more action-paced games. Again, we turned to the original
Psychonauts for inspiration.
In the original game, the player could walk up to another character and use the psychic
power of clairvoyance to briefly see things through another character's point of view. In
this demo, you see them going up to characters and they see Raz a little bit differently.
Sometimes their perspective on the world can be a little bit different. One of them sees them
as a hockey player, another sees them as a hockey player one there. It all depends on their
personality. It really lets you sort of develop the characters out.
So we thought rather than clairvoyance just giving the
player a temporary viewpoint, what if we use that as our
locomotion? What if we use that to be a persistent point of
view? The player could target another character across the
room and then jump into their mind. Now they'd see things from
that character's perspective. The player could stay in that
point of view as long as they wanted, looking around, using
their abilities. They could even clairvoyance into yet another
character, look around and use their abilities from there. With
this method of teleportation,
We can move the player around from character to character in
different points of the room. You can chain clairvoyance from
one character to another, going back to characters you've been
before and move between a number of points in the world. Your
main character, Raz, the character you're in, stays in
one place using his psychic ability.
This was also working with our story line. We wanted the characters to be captured. We
wanted them to figure out a way to escape. We were shifting more from the platforming stuff
in the original game to more of a puzzle based experience using your psychic abilities to solve
puzzles. Can you guys hear? I should have a little audio. Let's see if I can turn it up.
Are you getting any audio in the audio out? Let me try that again. Well, this video we're
showing here, not audio, but I can talk you through it a little bit. It shows an example of
using all your gameplay abilities. Here the player must use clairvoyance to go into a rat
in an overhead compartment. They must use poke to open up cabinets.
They see a character over the right sticking his hand out of
the bathroom door. They use telekinesis to grab toilet paper
and hand it to him. He shouts back at them that it's not
enough. He needs something a little bit more. What else can
you do? So in this case the player realizes they can use
their telekinesis ability and their pyro ability together to
give the coach in the background a little surprise.
It's a different type of game play, but it's something we're shifting to more with puzzles.
But an important consideration was also our controller scheme. We wanted to keep it simple
and accessible. All the different controllers coming out, we didn't want to limit our
audience to ones that just had hand controllers. We wanted it to be able to work with the
game pad as well.
Initially we considered looking at a pop-up menu to select
abilities like the original game did. In the original game you
could select from your different abilities and map that to one
of your buttons and have a couple of them going. But we
really wanted to focus on you combining your abilities. And we
wanted to limit the amount of UI. Having a UI pop up all the
time you wanted to use an ability in our game, which you
use pretty often, would be a little bit annoying to see it
come up in your face. And tricky as your world environment could
obscure the UI.
We ended up doing a controller mapping that mapped the
abilities to the different buttons. That way the player
could use multiple abilities at the same time. This had a number
of challenges using a game pad controller. The first was
unfamiliarity. When you're in a VR headset, most players can't
look down and see what their controller is doing. If they
don't know the controller very well, they're not going to know
what different buttons are no matter how much you tell them.
So to solve that, we showed the full controller diagram.
Rather than just showing a symbol of a button to press,
which someone might not remember, a triangle or an L2
button or an X, show a picture of the whole controller with
the button highlighted.
This technique worked particularly well, as players
can fumble around with the controller and try to get
their thumb or finger in the right position.
As long as you're forgiving with the controls, they'll
find the button.
But too much familiarity can also cause an issue.
people coming from using game pad controllers with other games typically like to use the
sticks. Initially we let the right stick move the camera. We quickly found that that was not a
good thing to do. Having people move the camera with their head and also right stick can
really make you sick fast.
but you shouldn't discount players using the controllers completely. By watching people's
hands when they're play testing, we're able to figure out which buttons they felt were
intuitive. Some of the combinations like holding down telekinesis and pyro, some players had
an intuition on kind of which trigger finger might be used for telekinesis and which ones
would be easier to combine with others. We also explored a motion track game pad
controller.
On the PlayStation, some of you may know the dual shot
controller has a sensor in the front and sensors inside which
let the camera which tracks your head also track the position of
the controller. For telekinesis we combined letting you move it
around with your head, moving it around with the controller and
moving it around with the sticks. We tried all
combinations of those to see what people found would work
well. We actually found that moving around your head worked
well with our game because it gave you more of a feeling that
you were psychic.
Once you started moving it around with your hands using a
controller, it started to feel like it was something in your
hand that you were reaching out. But to give you that sense of
presence that you were psychically moving it, moving
your head worked. We also had a wide variation of what players
would do when they would hold the controller. Many players
would just like to hold it in their lap. Not many would
intuitively lift it up and try to move it from a seated
experience.
In addition to using it for telekinesis, we had it work with rotation where players could flip
objects around. But flipping the controller over 180 puts it in a weird configuration for
people to hold and try to hit the other buttons. Eventually with our design we backed away
from rotating objects. We left it as an option on the right stick, but it's more for players
to just inspect something, and we didn't use it for any critical game play. Our targeting,
we used the headset rather than using a hand controller to point at things.
we look at stuff with your head. And as I was saying, we found
this had an unexpected but pretty desirable effect of the
player feeling more like a psychic. We found that if you
were using your mind to control something, if you were trying to
look at it with your head and move it, rather than a track
controller or wand in your hand, it felt less like a magic wand,
less like a laser pointer, less like a tool in your hand. You
felt more like a psychonaut in the game than a wizard or an
artist or a mechanic. But it ran into a set of issues as well.
With head track targeting, players are less precise. It's
rare for someone to hold their head and look at something with
a fixed gaze and hold it in the exact spot for very long. To
combat that, we did generous and sticky target selection. When
you look at something in our game, it would highlight. And we
had a number of different objects and players would try to
look at them. But as we started building up the worlds, the
density got pretty big.
We tried to reduce that and reduce the number of things you
could target but still players had trouble figuring out what
they were targeting and if they were targeting it correctly.
Sometimes they would see something and try to turn their
head to look at it but would have a hard time getting it
under a cursor or getting it under their view. To do that we
opened up our selection and made it more generous and sticky.
Generous meaning you didn't have to look exactly at something,
you just had to look near it and it would find the closest one.
And sticky meaning when you looked away it would still keep
your selection on it for a while.
We also didn't require accuracy. Initially our puzzles had the player being very accurate
with stuff. You had to pick up a bomb, move it to a hallway without it touching the walls or it
would explode, or insert a key into a lock and turn it. All of these were tricky to do and we
had some players on the team who were pretty good at it, but for most players it was hard to
do. Particularly if you started to get neck fatigue. Moving your head around a target and
particularly moving stuff around is one of the primary inputs. People's necks can get tired.
To combat that we tried to limit the required movement range.
We didn't want to have the players have to move something
from the far left side of their vision to the far right,
or up and down.
We didn't want you to have to do
repeated movements over and over.
We also removed time pressure.
As I said initially we had a ticking time bomb that you had
to get down the hallway without hitting the wall. People would
try to do that really fast. One of the tricks you could do to it
was to sling your neck really fast to throw the object down
the hall. Players would do that. Some would do it quite violently
and almost shake the headset off because they were running out of
time. So in our game design we started removing anything that
gave the player time pressure and tweaking the puzzles to be
more...
more solution finding on what to move and where to put it as opposed to how to do it in a quick
amount of time. Dialogue was also a challenge for us. Double fine games have always had
charming dialogue and quite a lot of it. But sometimes you need to give feedback on what the
player is doing, particularly if they're doing something wrong. Initially we had some generic
dialogue responses. Things like oop or bummer or nope if you tried to do something and the
player wasn't succeeding.
but as we started play testing it, players got confused. We
were watching them play and hearing the sounds and knowing
what they were doing wrong, but the players weren't getting the
feedback. We started changing the statements to be a little
bit more specific. Rather than just a generic thing, be more
particular and state the verb and object in what you're
saying. Say I can't burn that book or that crate is too heavy
to lift. Often when players are looking around,
they'll hit a button, hit the wrong button, think they're doing pyrokinesis on something to
burn it, but they're actually trying to pick it up. They're looking at an object just to the
right of the object they were trying to pick up, so getting a specific response back really
helps keep them on the right track and make sure they don't get confused or misdirected.
It's something that with a point and click adventure game and a
lot of other game styles, people tend to leave their cursor on
the object they're interacting with. They take their focus on
it. But if you're doing head based tracking, players will
look at something and then look away. So reminding them what
they were doing and what they were looking at can often be
helpful. We love the clairvoyance mechanic of
traveling through our levels from one character's mind to
another, but it also gave us a few problems.
When you teleport to a character, we would use the way that character is facing to give you a
hint at where you're going to be looking once you go into them. In this picture on the left,
you can see the character Mia staring at the monitor. If you go into her perspective,
that's what you're going to see. That worked out great. We put characters close to things. She
could watch a whole cartoon show on that monitor, switch the channels, solve a puzzle with
it. But then what would you do?
Because she was close to it and facing a wall,
she didn't have any other characters in her field of view.
In order to move to another character
using our locomotion system,
the player would have to look over their shoulder
or turn around 180 in their chair and get up.
And that's something we wanted to try to avoid.
This is the top view of the level we were looking at in the
jet. The roof is cut away and you can kind of see the shape of
it. Raz, your main character, is shown in the center and I've
highlighted his field of targeting in yellow. I use the
phrase field of targeting instead of field of view. Field
of view can often be pretty wide. In fact, you can look all
around you 360. But your field of targeting is more limited.
Field of targeting is kind of what you're going to turn your
head to look at as you use head-based targeting.
We found that a range of around 90 to 120 degree arc would work.
Sometimes we had to open it up a little bit more,
but that's what most players felt comfortable with.
Vertical up-down head movement, a pitch arc
of looking up and down to find another character,
is definitely less.
But most of our levels featured more
of a horizontal layout design than a vertical one.
In this level, we showed you going up
into the squirrel in an overhead bin.
That's about the level we'd go in vertical.
Here you can see overlapping fields of other characters
targeting each other.
Those are also shown in yellow.
If you look in the center, you can see the center three
characters have overlapping field of view.
All of them have another character within their arc.
But none of them have a good view of the character in the
upper right.
He's a hard character to get to unless we rotate one of the
character's seats.
And that sort of became our tuning game in the levels of
going through and saying, can you see somebody else from
this position or not?
You might also notice that we don't have very good coverage
in the back of the plane seen on the left hand side.
We had to come up with a creative solution so the player
could easily get back there and find the toilet paper to hand
the coach hanging out in the bathroom. So as shown on the
left here, we added a squirrel in an overhead bin who had a
good point of view of that area. Some level layouts work out
better than others. This is something we discovered probably
about halfway, three quarters of the way through the project. I
wish we would have known earlier. Long rectangular
levels don't work too well for this motion.
this type of locomotion. You have to have characters facing the front and also ones facing
the back so you can move from one end to the other. It turns out with no small coincidence
that our second level was a circle. And a lot of our other levels after that ended up being
this way. This is an example of our outpost level.
might be a little hard to see because of the yellow light in the center, but we positioned
a bunch of guards around the outside. In making a circular level, and I've seen a few other
games do this where they do an arena kind of style, with a bunch of characters on the
outside facing in, you always have a clear point of view of where you're going to go
and where you're going to go to. It also helps with the player's sense of...
sense of spatiality. Where am I in the level? Sometimes we found when you would go to a
character and they were facing a way you hadn't seen, players would lose their sense of
direction. They wouldn't quite know where they were or how to get back. Circular level
design worked pretty good because you can position them on the outside and they can
always see in with multiple targets to choose from. So to wrap things up a little bit and
to conclude what we're talking about, just don't add VR to your title.
It's just because your game can be played on a headset doesn't
mean it's the right title for VR or that it's the right platform
for it. Adapt your gameplay and controls to the strength of your
medium and your title. In looking at the original
Psychonauts game, we found a number of features that we felt
would work well. The psychic abilities, we extended some
features like the clairvoyance to not just give you a different
view but to let you get around the world and see characters
from a different perspective. Try to find the things in your
game.
particularly if you're adapting one that map well to VR. But
then also look at what in VR works well for your game. It
might be a first person perspective works better for
you. It might be you want to keep a third person's
perspective. It's great to be seeing all the things that
people are doing out there. And that kind of brings me to the
next point. It's still a new and fertile ground.
You'll hear people in some of their talks and some things say that they've solved locomotion,
or they've solved targeting, or they've solved shooting, but the more I've seen on the different
titles, the more I've seen people doing it different ways, and different ways that work
right for their game, for what they're trying to do. So feel free to explore. Just because
someone else is doing something a certain way, don't feel like you don't have to test it again
yourself. You might find that what didn't work for them, what didn't work for us even, with the
hand controllers and rotating objects, might be perfect for your game, depending on the context.
but also realize you're going to have unexpected challenges. Like I showed at the end, the
character facing, we thought our locomotion system was great, but then we realized you
couldn't get around many of the levels. We had to reposition characters, add new characters.
That can come, if that comes too late, it might be hard for you to correct that. Give
yourself time to explore them. Give yourself a chance to get your new ideas in, iterate
on them, and get them to a point where you can really shine.
That wraps things up. Do you guys have any questions? Yeah, if
you could state your name and the question, I'll repeat it
back for everybody.
Hi, Caitlin.
How do you deal with, when you have clairvoyance
to teleport into another character's presence or mind,
how do you deal with the fact that you're suddenly
occupying another character's body?
Like if you're moving your hand controllers,
do you see the avatars?
the other NPC's hand moving. Okay, sure. Let me restate it.
Caitlin was asking when you go into another character, how do
you deal with the player accepting that other character's
body? That's one thing I didn't mention in the talk but that we
looked at and many games look at is when you're in a character,
do you draw the character's body or not?
Because we weren't using hand controllers and we weren't
mapping your arm movements, it felt kind of weird for your
character to be sitting there not really mapping you. So when
we go into a character, we don't draw their body at all. We turn
off props and accessories they have like a pencil or notebook
so you don't see your character. We found that most players found
that more acceptable. We do do certain things like change your
eye distance to make you feel smaller or bigger.
in limited amount of scales if you go into a small character.
And we do, in certain characters, not shown,
they see the world differently.
They might see a sunny day instead of a rainy day.
Our characters a little bit differently
to try to give their personality.
But in general, we don't draw the body.
That's the choice we made.
Go ahead.
My name is Yost.
It seems like all the abilities you have in the game fit very nicely with the original
Psychonauts game. Was there anything you guys wanted to do in the game that you couldn't
make fit with the original game and you scrapped or just couldn't explain away?
Right. We looked at, so to ask this question, he was, Rose was it, was asking were there
any abilities in the original game that didn't work.
A lot of the original game was combat focus, so blowing stuff
up. Like I said, we shifted to a little bit more puzzle solving.
We added that one ability just to give something a light poke,
a little bit more of a point and click interaction. But there
were abilities in the original game that I thought would be
cool to put in that we didn't, such as invisibility. We tried
to figure out a way to do it, but since we weren't drawing
your character, you were kind of already invisible. We thought
we might tweak it to make other stuff invisible, but that's
something we might look at at DLC or an add-on. There's always
more to add.
Hopefully that answers your question. Thanks. Go ahead.
I have a question. You brought up something very interesting
with level design specifically. I was wondering if you found
that painting points of interest vertically things that were
above the player, if you had a challenge getting their
attention that way. So his question was with level design,
did we look at the challenges of moving vertically? We did a
little bit. Some of our initial puzzles you were in a prison
that was very vertical based with a lot of prison cells and
different levels that you would go up.
We do a few things.
We have a particular sort of boss battle in the game with a
giant character that's bigger than you that you look up and
you have to fight.
One thing we found is that we didn't really want to keep the
player looking up a lot, particularly our game where
you're moving stuff around.
If your neck is craned at an angle and you're having to
move stuff with your neck craned.
people got fatigued a lot sooner. For simple navigation or
drawing someone's attention, I think it works pretty well. It's
nice to hear a sound up there or see something and look up. That
really gives you a sense of scale and perspective,
particularly on levels with open skies and bigger spaces. But we
didn't really use it for navigation too much. Thank you.
Anybody else? One coming from the back.
So I'm assuming you didn't ever try to twist their head around
basically, right? You let them move and look at things. But did
you ever try experimenting with maybe gently moving their head?
We did a little bit. And how did that go? One thing we wanted to
focus on was you were going into a player's point of view and you
were in that view. I've seen some games, I think the recent
Batman Arkham one has where you can press a button and your view
suddenly switches 180.
We tried a technique like that, but it felt like you were more of a ghost hovering over their head.
It kind of lost that connection with you being in the character. As I said, if you see a way a character is facing,
that gave you a clue at what you might see. You might see that character kind of peeking around a wall,
and you go into them and see around that wall. That connection of kind of being in that character's head was something we wanted to preserve.
But sometimes we do cheat it. We have an eye locator on every character which is where your
eye is going to be when you go into him. Sometimes we'll cheat it up a little bit and
you'll be a foot over their head or a foot in front or left. Not too far. Usually between like
a foot to three feet distance from a character. And we found that since we don't draw the
player's body, most players don't notice. You can move it down a little bit or up a little
bit and that works pretty well. Cool. Thank you. Anyone else?
All right, well, thanks for coming to my talk.
Again, I'm.