Good afternoon.
We're going to get started.
Thank you very much for joining me during this session.
My name is Cyril.
I work for Rovio in Finland, in Helsinki.
And today we're going to talk about making games.
This is what we're going to talk about.
We're going to look back at what Rovio has done in the last two
years to modernize the production process, how
we look at game, and how we move forward with the production
process.
I'm going to start talking about myself, which is nice.
But it is relevant to this talk.
As you can see, I have been working
in the mechanical industry for 10 years
before I joined the game industry 11 years ago.
And this is quite relevant to what
we are doing today at Rovio.
There's a lot of DNA that I took over
from the mechanical industry to today to the game industry.
Let's think about it. I've got two points here.
The first point is about the type of product I used to do.
Aircraft, gas product, food packaging.
We can imagine that the level of quality of those products
is quite high.
And I'm not only talking about the amount of bugs
we can see or defects we can see in those products,
but also the usability of those products.
I'm sure we're all thinking about that now about games,
about the amount of bugs and usability of our games.
But I learned the hard way when I was a quality manager
that if one of my gas products was leaking,
I could injure people.
The other point is interesting.
Think about a factory.
Think about a high-speed production factory.
I was a quality manager.
I was an improvement manager.
And I was running continuous improvement.
I was running improvement with the process,
on the product, on the lines.
Imagine a very noisy environment with a very heavy machine,
50 tons press, spitting out 1,000 products a minute,
for example.
Like the can, the beer can, you can see.
1,000 cans a minute.
Every time I had to stop the line, I had to justify the loss of production of 1,000 cans
per minute.
Every time I wanted to change the process, I had, in some cases, to justify the movement,
the relocation of a 50-ton press.
There was a lot of thinking being done before all those happened.
There was a lot of soul-searching, being very honest.
What are we looking for?
What are we trying to achieve?
And I had to justify it out loud to a lot of people
before it will happen.
We can all take that to the game industry today.
How are we trying to define what does good look like whenever
we do an improvement, whenever we change a process?
Then I moved to Finland, and I moved to the game industry.
I worked for a company like Digital Chocolate.
Then I worked for a startup doing interactive images,
but with a software as a service mentality.
And I opened a Gameloft studio in Helsinki for a year.
And I've been working at Rovio for three years now.
About Rovio, just to get a little wrap up
about who we are, Rovio was founded in 2003
by three students.
In 2009, we had 51 games under our belt,
and the 52nd was Angry Birds.
I think we all know Angry Birds and the success that it has had.
A big milestone for us and for the industry, I think,
is 2016, when we launched the Angry Birds movie.
Went number one in more than 50 countries,
making $350 million revenue.
A big success for Rovio, a big success for the industry,
showing that we are providing entertainment.
Very recently, in 2017, Rovio went through IPO.
And the next milestone that we can see in the future,
for sure, is that in 2019, we are
going to have a movie sequel.
Hopefully, before that, we will create
all the milestones for the company
and for the game industry.
Rovio is around 400 people.
300 working on games and 100 on other activities.
The Angry Birds brand was downloaded more than 4 billion
times, which we are very, very proud of that.
The way we are organized in the game business unit
is we are divided in four studios in two locations.
One will be Helsinki, Finland.
The other one will be Stockholm in Sweden.
We are divided by specialty, by genre.
So a studio will focus on the slingshot mechanism
that we can see in Angry Birds, and with the Angry Birds
brand, mixing the two and trying to make a making
game for this genre.
Another one, Battle, we call Battle,
is located in Helsinki, Finland.
It's focusing on team versus team, real-time team
versus team battles.
The next studio is a puzzle doing match three,
tap to clear, bubble popper based in Helsinki.
And the last one, the RPG studio, is based in Stockholm.
So as you can see, we are divided by specialty
and by genre.
Doesn't mean that there's no crossover between the studios,
but this is how we are divided.
So let's talk about making games.
And I'm starting in 2015.
One reason is because I started at Rovio in 2015.
But the real reason I'm starting my presentation on that date
is this is the first time at Rovio
we started to ask us questions like,
how can we have a process that helps us to make great games?
How can we have a process that helps us to make great games
consistently?
And for me, that was a beginning of us thinking
of having a better process, having a process that
would be very modern, that will allow us to do great games.
If you think about it, process, great game,
in the same sentence.
Process is usually dull.
It's logistical.
It's operation.
It's not super creative.
It's a bit boring.
Great game, we are all here to make great games.
It's very creative, it's visual, it's fun, it's cool.
But we have those two opposite in the same sentence.
But for us, that was it.
We wanted a process that would help us to make
great games consistently.
So let's look at how Rovio was organized in 2015.
Well, we had a process.
We had a production process in 2015.
I mean, if we think about it, in terms of headcount,
Rovio was the biggest and is still the biggest
studio in Finland.
Biggest headcount studio in Finland.
We had and we still have around 15, 20 projects
going on at the same time.
And if we want to have any sort of strategy,
if you want to have any sort of management about where we're
going, we need a process.
So yes, in 2015, we had a process.
But I put the tick box here.
Because did we check that the prototype we were doing
were fun?
Yeah, we did.
We always do.
You do a game jam, they get a great prototype.
Is it fun?
Yes.
Should we go to production?
Yes, maybe.
There was a lot of mechanical things we were checking.
Do you have a date for launch?
Yes.
Done.
Now, did we talk about business case?
Did we talk about the market?
Did we talk about target audience?
Maybe not.
Maybe not the way we do today.
Did we talk about what are the motivations of our target audience?
No, we did not talk about that in 2015.
So yes, we had a process, but it was a very,
I'd say tick box is a good example.
It's a very tick box type of process.
So let's look at what kind of games were launched
following this process.
The one on the left is Angry Birds 2.
was launched in 2015.
Today, Angry Birds 2 is our biggest game by far.
A huge success.
Amazing KPIs.
When it was launched in 2015, it was the foundation
of this big success.
It was LiveOps compliant.
It was a full-fledged game.
It had depth, allowed campaigns, events, sales, et cetera.
A great game for free to play.
Now who knows about the other game?
Bats.
We launched Bats, soft launch, in 2015.
Great game, very, very fun, but impossible to monetize,
meaning premium game.
Give us $1, we'll give you the game.
So in them.
I mean, there was nothing else than just a fun game.
There was no possibility to make business with this game.
So in terms of deliveries, we could
see that there was a lot of variation
in the quality, in the overall quality of the game
that we were delivering using this process.
So we knew we had an issue with our process.
The process was not delivering a consistent great game,
or great game consistently.
So we started to work.
And we try to understand, is the process in place helping
us to make great games?
A good place to start is to go to the coffee machine
because you get a lot of people going in and out.
And we start to ask questions.
And we ask the central management a few questions.
And some of the feedback we had is, hey,
how is this game doing?
What does it mean if the central management asking me
how a game is doing?
They have no visibility of what is happening?
They have no visibility on the build that is available?
They have no visibility of what the team is trying to achieve?
Maybe yes.
We heard other things like, what is the target
audience for this game?
You have to understand that when we launched Angry Birds in 2009, it was such a success
that we took it.
We didn't question it.
The reality is the target, the audience that we got in 2009 was a very young audience,
you can imagine.
A very young audience that grew with Rovio.
But in 2015...
I'm not sure we were not sure that this audience was
the audience we wanted for our new games.
So we had to question ourselves, do we
want the same audience that we currently have?
Or do we need to target another audience?
So the question of which audience
are we making this game for is starting
to be very important for us.
And yet again, the central management
will ask the question, who are we making this game for?
No visibility.
The example of Angry Birds 2 and bats.
Will this game monetize as free to play?
Clearly, we got a scar from this release.
We want to make sure that every single game we're
going to launch from now is going
to be a great free to play game.
So how are we doing that?
How are we doing the design?
What kind of visibility do I have as a central manager
on that?
At the end of the day, you understand it.
It was really about the central management saying,
you know what, the process we have in place
is not really helping me to take the right decision
to drive the strategy and to build
a vision for the company.
So the process we had in place in 2015.
exist, which was great, but was not really helping the central management.
I stayed at the coffee machine and I carried on talking to people coming here.
And the next people coming were from the game development team.
And they started to tell me things, very scary, like...
You know what, I've got this game,
but I'm not going to show it to you or to anyone
because it's not ready.
And you know what's happening when you show a game that
is not ready.
I will receive email of, you should do this,
you should do that, long like that.
So I'm going to hide my work in progress.
We all know that this lack of transparency is not the answer.
But still, that was how the game were operating, in a way.
The other one, which is horrible, is like, hey,
I've got this meeting invitation in my calendar.
I have no idea what it is.
Are they going to kill my game?
No discussion, no visibility.
The fear of going to a meeting that is imposed by the process,
the fear of having your own game killed.
That was pretty bad.
And then coming to soft launch with no real idea
if the game was going to perform or not, really crossing finger
and just say, let's launch this game just in case of.
Maybe it will work, maybe it will not.
I have no idea from a real user before soft launch about,
is this game answering anybody's needs, anybody's motivation?
And at the end of the day, again,
the process we had in place didn't really
help the development team.
So we had a process in place, yes, but it didn't really help.
And at the end of the day, you understand
that what it meant is that the games team had some sort of fear
about the process, and that the central management didn't
really respect any of the process,
and try to intervene, try to micromanage the team.
That's what it was.
Of course, I'm painting a picture to make a case here.
It was not as bad as that, but you get the feeling.
So we looked, and we say, what do we do?
We saw three opportunities, three opportunities
that will allow us to make better games,
to have a process that will help us to make better games.
The first one is, what about us focusing
on the vision and the strategy for each game?
No exception.
Each game that we are making should have a clear vision
what we want to build.
and a clear strategy, how we're going to build,
why we're going to build it, when we're
going to build it, et cetera.
That will help us a lot.
That was a clear opportunity we saw.
The other one was.
Improved transparency.
It was clear from my example that the transparency
was not great.
And I'm not necessarily discussing
about the game team showing the central management what
they are doing.
I'm saying the central management giving
a clear visibility on the strategy on what
we're trying to achieve.
having the process so visible that it's very transparent
about how we're going to run the process in the future,
how we're going to run game production in the future.
So it's transparency all over the organization,
not just showing the build to the management.
And the third one is restore autonomy.
You know, the team that did Angry Birds 2 and Bats,
they were strong autonomous team, all of them,
the two of them.
But the autonomy they had was a fake economy.
Because at the end of the day, because of the lack of
transparency, a lot of people were telling them what to do.
Where, hey, I don't know what's happening, so show me
something, and when I see something, I'll
tell you what to do.
So it was not a true autonomy that we had in place back
then.
Out of the three opportunities, by far, and I mean by far,
we said if we focus on the last two,
on the improve the transparency and restore the autonomy,
we have the better chance to succeed.
And why?
Because the assumption, and we were convinced about that,
that by focusing on those two points, we will build trust.
We will build trust in the organization.
And again, it's not about one trusting the other.
It's about looking at the process,
the central management, and the development team
all trusting each other.
The central management and the development team
trusting that the process in place is good for them,
can help them.
Central management trusting the team,
and the team trusting that the central management will not
intervene or micromanage.
That was the assumption back then.
So we worked in 2016 in Flight Path.
This is a name we gave to our production process.
And I'm saying process here, and I'm writing guideline here.
We're going to see about that.
But Flypath is a guideline.
It's explaining what to do, but not how to do.
There's no secret recipe to how to make a great game.
So we acknowledge that.
It is a guideline.
It started in 2016, and I'm going to tell you,
it's still working today.
It's still called Flypath, and we're still working on it.
We still improve it.
How many of our project here started one day
and was canceled three months later?
This one is more than two years old.
and it's still alive and kicking.
And I'm very, very proud of that.
Every time we improve our process,
it's a continuation of FlyPath.
So when you hear me saying FlyPath,
this is what I mean, our production process.
And Flypass is a story of trust.
You have to understand that.
We have to understand that.
It's all about trust.
It's the trust that we build,
and where autonomy and transparency
are playing a leading role.
We build trust through transparency and autonomy.
And this is what I'm going to try to explain
during the next few slides.
So let's look at Flypath.
It's no rocket science.
I'm sorry to disappoint you.
There's no secret, amazing stuff.
It starts with concept like any other process,
and it will end up in global launch slash live operations.
Very simple.
We didn't reinvent the wheel.
There are a few principles.
I'm going to drink.
The first one.
is ownership.
So my title at Rovio today is VP of Operations.
I would say I'm a good candidate to be the owner of Flypath.
VP of Operations, operations, process, process Flypath.
I would be a very, very good candidate
to be the owner of Flypath.
But I'm not.
I am not the owner of Flypath.
At Rovio, we have a group called the Production Guild.
The Production Guild is a group of people, producers,
operation people, like user research, quality.
delivery, player support, and anybody who wants to opt in.
Anybody, product lead, management, finance,
anybody who wants to have a say in how we run operations,
how we run production in Rovio.
We meet every two weeks, and we discuss about production.
And whenever Flypass has to change, be evolved,
or be modified, we discuss about it,
and we take a decision together.
Making we're not coming with ideas that we will present to management
we take decision on how we're going to run the operations how we're going to run the production and
This is the production deal is the owner of flight path
So we are owning the way we operate and there's no VP telling anybody how to operate
The second one is flexibility.
Asset guideline is very important.
It is a guideline.
It's about what to focus on, not how to make great games.
There's a little bit of the idea of the battlefield.
Soldiers are very, very well trained.
They know all their gears.
They know all the procedure.
But when they're in the battlefield,
There's no book that describes how to win a battle.
It's the same for us.
We need to be highly skilled individuals and teams,
professionals.
But when it's about making games, there's no process.
There's no fly pass who will tell us how to make great games.
So we have to be flexible.
One of the reasons is not everybody
has got the same maturity.
So a young team or a young product lead
will need maybe a little bit more guidance
than somebody more mature.
The other one is if we're too flexible,
the process of today will be the process of tomorrow.
But if we are flexible, then maybe a more mature team
will decide not to follow FlyPath, which is absolutely
OK if we are transparent about it, if we are open about it,
if we are discussing about it.
Because today's experiment might become tomorrow's FlyPath.
We might drive improvement through not
following the process.
And this is a very interesting one.
But if we have a tick-box process,
then everybody does the same.
Everybody gets frustrated, and we're not running improvement.
Trust.
The third one is trust.
I said it, and I'm going to repeat it here,
because it is important.
It's about trust between the process,
the central management, and the teams.
We all acknowledge that Flypath exists,
and we are going to go through Flypath when we do production.
Central management acknowledges there's Flypath.
There's no need to do micro-management,
because I should get the visibility.
The team acknowledges there's Flypath.
I know what this meeting is coming in two weeks.
I know what I'm supposed to discuss
with the rest of the team.
Now, is it perfect?
Well, it's not bad.
Is there a tension here?
Is the team always wanting more autonomy?
And the central management always wanted to micromanage?
Yes, it exists.
But we acknowledge this tension.
And it's fine.
So we have trust also that this tension is healthy for us.
team asking for more autonomy, and central management
trying to put their nose into the project.
But that's fine.
So we acknowledge that.
We've done with the principle.
We can look at the different phases.
We'll go one by one in the next few slides.
Fly plus is the five phase.
And then we have a quarterly studio level review.
It means every three months, we know that the studio head,
remember I mentioned we have four studios,
so the studio heads and the product lead
will meet the central management.
And we will be discussing about the games.
We are going to discuss about the product, the game
we are making.
Flypast got three green lights, no more.
We had more.
It changed.
We have a production green light, a soft launch green
light, and a global launch green light.
That's it.
So FlyPath, the way we handle production at Rovio,
is five phases, one quarterly review, and five gates.
The first one, the first one of the phase,
is a mix of three things.
Concepting.
market research, and prototype.
It all starts with acknowledging the fact
that a fun prototype is not enough to justify 12, 18,
or 24 months of production.
We need more than that.
We need more than a fun prototype.
So concept is all about building a vision,
a team building together a vision,
and a product lead holding the vision forward,
taking the vision forward.
But we need time to build this vision.
Research.
We can't launch a game without understanding the competition,
without understanding what is going
to happen in 18 months or 24 months when we launch,
without understanding the users, the target audience
that we are making the game for.
And of course, we have a prototype.
So yes, we build a prototype.
And we have a lot of fun with it, absolutely.
But it's all together.
When we do research, we have one say in our head.
It's like, it's never too early to test.
It's never too early to have feedback from real users.
So as soon as we can put something,
it could be a sentence, it could be a graphic,
it can be a mock-up, it can be a prototype.
As soon as we can do that, we can
put that in front of a real user to get feedback, we do it.
It's a lot of effort, but we try to do it as soon as possible.
So we build this vision.
This is a concept phase.
Once we have this vision built, once we know where we're going,
once the team has built the vision together
and the product team owns this vision,
we are moving to pre-production.
And pre-production is not about building the vision
because it's already done.
Pre-production is about to figure out if we can deliver
this great vision.
Can we build it?
Yes, we can.
So it's all, of course, we're going to stay agile here.
I'm not saying we're going to.
freeze the vision and never change it for 24 months?
Of course not.
Of course we're going to iterate it as all the signals coming
from outside.
But at this point, it's not about building the vision
anymore.
It's about figuring out, do we have the right tools?
Do we have the right process?
Do we have the right people, knowledge, skills, et cetera?
Time, money, all this.
Do we have all this so we can deliver that game?
So we are going to look at what we know.
Maybe we don't need to test that.
What we don't know, what we have been in,
what is very innovative.
Usually, this is what we are going to test,
either to build or test in a prototype,
I mean in a final build.
And we look at the most risky aspect of our vision,
of our game we are trying to build,
and we try to leverage this risk during pre-production.
Remember my past in factories?
Before setting up a line that will spit out
1,000 cans per minute, trust me, we
were aligning all the machines.
We were running very slowly.
We were making sure we had all the machine we need,
and all the operator we need, and all the raw material
we need.
It's the same.
Different worlds, but it's the same spirit.
We run slowly.
We evaluate what it takes to be able to run fast.
We adjust, and then we go to production.
During all this time, we meet every three months.
We call it the quarterly review, quarterly studio-level review.
So it's one per studio, four studios.
And again, it's not all about everybody accepting that, yes,
we will meet every three months, and we
will talk about the games.
So there's no surprise.
So when we come to this meeting, we
know what the template of discussion we're going to have.
And it's a very open meeting.
I'm not saying that the visibility, the transparency,
is only built in this meeting.
There is a lot of discussion.
There's a lot of work in progress available,
so we can play the game.
But here is kind of the formal way when we all sit down.
And finance is also here, because we're
going to talk about money, about headcount, et cetera.
Marketing is here to figure out how
we're going to launch the game, et cetera, et cetera.
So a lot of different functions are in this meeting.
But it's a great way of giving transparency
within the organization.
Then comes the production green light.
And it's all about, well, we need
to figure out what the plan.
So there was a lot of things happening,
a lot of transparency.
We've built the vision.
And we saw during pre-production that, yes, we
can build the vision.
But let's sit all together one more time before we go and
invest 12 or 18 months of the company's time.
And we discussed very early about launch plan.
So we talk about marketing already at this point.
I took an example here on this slide about Angry Birds March.
It's an interesting one.
In 2016, the first production green light
that we run internally was for green lighting Angry Birds
March.
Are we going to production or not?
And we discussed about everything.
We discussed about Scrum.
We discussed about.
timeline about headcount, about tools and servers,
and how we're going to use AWS, et cetera.
It went well.
It went fine.
I was happy.
It was the first time we had it.
It was a bit of a test.
And yes, we have green light.
We agreed together that we're going to do it.
And then the product leads comes to me at the end and says,
what happened there?
What do you mean?
Well, you know what?
This Angry Birds Match is my fourth match three game
I'm doing with that team.
I've done three games that were all super successful,
each one more successful than the previous one.
Do you know what is my biggest asset
to make a great success out of Angry Birds Match?
I don't know, you tell me.
Well, my team.
We've been working together, same team, four times.
This is our fourth title.
If I'm going to succeed in this project, it's because of my
team, and at no point we reviewed the team.
And I say, well, that's a very good point.
So what do we do?
We are both part of the production guild.
We are responsible to make FlightPaths evolve.
And we change FlightPaths.
Today, and even though it's not perfect yet,
but today we are evaluating the team whenever
we are evaluating production.
That's very important.
Another point that is interesting
is that when the product leads come to this Greenlight
meeting, it doesn't come in front of the central management
to ask permission to move into production.
You've seen my build.
You've seen my strategy.
We met every three months.
We went through pre-production.
You got the result.
I've got a plan.
You know my plan.
And starting tomorrow, I'm going to start production.
I'm not asking you if I can.
But by the way, we have one hour.
So if you have any tricky question, maybe it's the time.
Because tomorrow, I'm moving into production.
So again, it's not about asking.
We already know that we're good.
And that gives a lot of responsibility
to the product lead to basically stop a game,
kill a game before this meeting.
We're not, product lead are not coming to this meeting
to hear anybody killing their game.
So we need to be true to ourselves and our understanding.
What is the strategy?
What we're trying to achieve?
And if we are all on the same page
whenever we come to this meeting.
Production.
We all know about production.
Last 12, 18, sometimes three years.
Oh, sorry, 12 months, 18 months, sometimes three years.
It's all about being agile.
I said it.
We don't want to be waterfall.
We have to adapt to the market, to all the external signals.
We will do a lot of user testing during this phase.
It means that we will receive a lot of feedback from real users.
We have to adapt.
But if we have to make 180 degree turn,
then maybe we should pause and think again.
But it's all about being agile, not being waterfall.
As I said, we do a lot of user testing.
This is something we're putting a lot of effort at Rovio
during the last 12 months to really understand
what are the tools, what tools are available for us
to test some aspect of the game.
Or whenever we have a question about the design,
depending on the question, how can we
get real user giving us hints about, yes,
your vision seems to be answering my needs,
or no, I'm going to put a bit of friction.
Are you sure this is what you want to deliver to target
audience like me?
And it's about the whole game.
What do I mean by the whole game?
We all understand the core loop and the meta,
and we all are individual.
This is given.
But we have legal compliances.
In US, we have COPPA.
In Europe, we have GDPR.
There are other compliances, legal compliances.
This is all defined before we move into production.
This is all put into the backlog before we
move into production.
And we need to make sure that during production, we build
all this, we integrate all this.
We can't come two days before soft launch and say, oh, what
is GDPR?
Or what is Child Protection COPA?
It can't be like this.
So we need to give a lot of visibility.
Then we have external compliance.
We all have partners, Apple, Google, Amazon, you name it.
So what do they want?
They forbid us to do this, and they want us to do that.
They would like us to do that to be featured, for example.
So we call it external compliance,
coming from our partner.
We are making sure that all the backlogs of our game
in production have all those tasks already listed.
So whenever we estimate a delivery time, or we estimate
the size of a game, we are as accurate as we can be.
And then we have internal compliance.
So that would be Rovio compliance.
So we can imagine that.
At Rovio, with a portfolio of 15, 20 games that we have live,
we always want to do cross-promotion.
And one game will promote the other game
whenever it's needed.
And I took the example of Angry Birds 2.
I said a lot of good things about Angry Birds 2 today.
I'm going to stop now.
I'm going to say something bad about Angry Birds 2.
They launched in July 2015, and I joined a few months before that.
My first project at Rovio was to make sure that all our catalogs, and when I mean all,
all our catalogs will have super-duper cross-promotion features that will cross-promote
Angry Birds 2 from every single one of our catalog.
I spent a lot of time with designers, product leads,
to convince them to prioritize their backlog,
to implement cross-promotion feature, to support the launch.
As a matter of fact, Angry Birds 2
was number one in the chart before featuring started,
because of cross-promotion.
The cross-promotion was so efficient
that it boosted Angry Birds 2 to the top of the chart,
just with cross-promotion.
No featuring.
Then featuring came.
Couple of months, when Angry Birds 2 is fixing all the bugs
and adding what they couldn't do before global launch.
And then we went to Stockholm and say, all right, now,
you're going to pay back.
Turn on your cross-promotion back and feed back some users
to our portfolio.
And the product league looking at me and say, cross-promote
what?
They didn't have a clue about what was cross-promotion.
So of course, they build the best game ever.
It's a great game.
But in terms of internal compliance,
they were not helping the whole portfolio.
It was a very singled out project.
Since then, they implemented cross-promotion,
and they're contributing a lot to the cross-promotion
of all the game.
But it was so surprising that after all the effort
that we've done, that they couldn't even pay back,
if I can use this word.
Then we go to soft launch green light.
And the question we are asking ourselves is,
what does good look like?
You remember when I said the example of the factory,
I had to justify a lot before moving a machine.
And this is a little bit the spirit.
So we asked the team to define what kind of KPI
would be good KPI.
What would be a success story?
We asked them that.
Once they answer, we asked them to put it on the PowerPoint.
We asked them to print the PowerPoint.
We're not stopping here.
We asked them to frame the PowerPoint that was printed
and to put it in the kitchen of the studio.
So everybody will see what this team is trying to achieve.
And this is simple.
This is silly.
But it is so powerful.
It is so powerful to let the team think
about what they want to achieve and to commit to it.
And of course.
You know, things will change, or things will not change.
There's always been discussion around those KPI.
But putting them in front of the whole company in the company
kitchen is very, very powerful, because you really
have to think about what you try to achieve.
By the way, we asked the same question
very early in the process.
But now we understand that the market has changed,
so we are trying to readjust that.
So across the whole production phases, we have an idea.
We have a clear idea about what we're trying to achieve.
And this is the soft launch green light.
Again, it's not about asking, can I move to soft launch?
It's more about, I'm moving to soft launch,
and this is my plan, and this is what I try to achieve.
Then we go to soft launch.
It's a KPI driven phase.
We're going to do paid user acquisition.
At Rovio, we do paid user acquisition.
And we also do paid user acquisition at scale
to make sure that all the CPI, cost per install,
and the lifetime value, LTV, are the same at low scale
and high scale.
And we have two things in mind.
Very hard, very hard to keep that in mind,
but they're here.
The first one is that.
Soft launch will not save our game.
There was a lot of talk in GDC this year
about improving retention.
And we all acknowledge the fact that beyond the obvious first
time user experience tweak, D1, D3 improvement,
it is very hard to improve retention.
One of the talk, I think yesterday,
said that retention is a factor of the genre, the art
style, and the game design.
None of those three is easy to change.
So what it means that if long-term retention is
bad at soft launch.
Then it's bad forever.
It's extremely hard to change it.
And we have to remind ourselves, if long-term retention is not
good, we should stop.
We can't save it.
There are exceptions, but in theory, we can't save it.
So we have to remind ourselves.
What it means?
It means that if we have a long soft launch,
it means it's a good game.
It means that we have a long-term retention that
is good, and we are tweaking the economy
to make better app DAO and average revenue per paying
users, et cetera.
But we have to remember ourselves all the time
that if it's not good in terms of long-term retention,
we better stop it.
And that's a soft launch.
So we do paid user acquisition.
We do paid user acquisition at scale.
And we're looking at retention very closely.
Battle Bay here spent 14 months in soft launch,
the longest for Rovio.
Quite long soft launch.
But it's worth it.
Very good game for us.
New genre, five versus five, real-time battle,
and very good KPIs.
We're very happy about it.
And we don't regret a single moment
to have spent 14 months in soft launch.
So we spend the time in soft launch.
We have KPI.
And again, we are going to launch it.
So it's going to be the whole company behind one game.
Marketing, operation, localization.
delivery, you name it.
Everybody's behind the game.
So again, we are stopping.
We're looking at the result of LTV and CPI at scale.
Can we boost download through paid user acquisition?
Do we have a launch plan?
What is it?
Who's doing what and when?
And then we talk about live operations.
The reality is live operation, we talk about it very often
during the design phase.
We talk a lot about it before production, green light,
during production.
But here, we're very honest with ourselves
that we need live operation, not only in soft launch,
because in soft launch, we also do live operation.
But we also need it right after launch,
so it feels fresh, straight off the bat.
I took the example of Angry Birds Blast
that was supposed to launch just very early 2017.
And early December 2016, so a few weeks
before the global launch, we met with our partner.
And one of our partners suggested that launching
on December 22, 2016 would be a good idea.
Oh, wow, three weeks before, like during Christmas holiday.
So what we did, we look at our backlog.
Luckily, we had a full game.
spec'd out on the backlog, prioritized.
And we said, to global launch, we need all this.
We don't need all that.
And we said, can we make it by December 22?
Yes, if we cancel our holiday.
So we cancel our holiday, and we launch.
It was a great launch.
But it was a good example of being well organized with a
proper backlog, including all the compliances and
understanding what our partner will want, what we will want,
what the legal will want.
being able to launch three weeks ahead was feasible.
It was a great launch for us, but it
was a very interesting Christmas in 2016.
Live operations is all about improving our game every week.
There's no magic bullet, but if we
manage to improve our game every week a little bit,
this is live operation.
It's about being the best at getting better.
And we're very lucky at Rovio.
We have the chance to work with amazing brands like NFL
and Iron Maiden.
I don't know if you saw those campaigns.
We're very, very lucky.
Not only we do live operations with campaigns and events
and sales, but we can do that with amazing brands.
It means that, of course, it puts even more pressure on us
to execute very, very well.
But all in all, I have to admit that our ability
to work with those brands is a great chance
that we do have at Rovio.
That's Flypath.
That's it.
We've seen the phases.
We've seen the green lights.
We've seen the principle.
Maybe there's one principle that is missing.
It's a life process.
In the last two years, we had four major updates of Flypath
that were dictated by our maturity, our culture,
but the reality that because Flypath is evolving
according to our culture and our maturity,
everybody's, I mean, all the three points
are feeding each other.
We removed green lights, we added green lights,
we merged phases, we did a lot of things.
But by no mean is a set process,
and if we meet again in a year,
it's not going to be the same Flypass that we're having.
It's going to evolve.
There is definitely a link between our maturity,
our culture, and Flypass itself.
So what's the outcome?
2015 was very clear about what kind of process we had
and what kind of game we were delivering.
What's the outcome?
Well, with Flypass, everyone knows
what to expect at every step of the production process.
This is a transparency that we are
giving across central management, the team,
and the process.
No surprises.
We all know what to expect.
The outcome is that we launch fewer games.
You have seen less games launched by Rovio recently
because we are more demanding.
But there are better games.
Angry Birds Evolution, Angry Birds Match,
great game for us, great launch last year.
And more importantly, all those games are fitting the strategy.
There's a great visibility at the Rovio level
about what is our strategy, what we're trying to achieve,
and what kind of game do we need to achieve that.
And every game that we are launching
are fitting the strategy.
There's no more rogue project that is happening just because.
They all have a review process through Flypass,
and we make sure that every one of our delivery
fits the strategy.
Autonomy and transparency created trust.
Rovio is a very nice company to work in at the moment.
There's a lot of trust happening in the company.
There's autonomy, we build it ourself,
and there's transparency.
It's hard, but it's happening, and we build it ourself.
We trust the process also.
We have a process that has a name.
We trust it exists, we acknowledge it exists,
and we trust it.
And the reality is that it enhanced the company culture
quite a lot.
I'm not saying it was a bad company in 2015,
but I'm saying that today it's a very, very nice company.
The company culture is really, really good.
So what are the next steps?
And we are coming to the end of the presentation here.
The next step are about ambitious continuous
improvement.
I used to be improvement manager.
I like the ambitious, because we want
to be leading the industry.
We want to.
set the world on fire again.
So what are we doing?
What are we looking at at the moment?
We're looking at need-based game design.
How do we define our target audience?
How do we understand our target audience?
What are their motivation?
What are their needs?
What are their frustration?
How do we build a relationship between the target audience
and the design.
This is something we're working very, very hard.
So very early in the process of making game,
we understand who we are making the game for
and what make them tick, and how we can create design
for those people.
Live Operations 2.0.
You've heard a lot about LiveOps.
LiveOps was in a lot of talks in GDC.
It's the buzzword.
It's very important.
It's very important for us too, very, very important.
There's a lot of live ops in the presentation I've just done,
but we know we need to get better.
When I said, if you remember, that we're
doing live operation in soft launch,
we are just starting to do live operations in soft launch.
Because we realize it is very important to understand
the LTV of our games while doing live operation.
It means that we need to work harder, faster, better
in having a real proper game before we self-launch
to be able to learn about this.
And this is what I mean by live operations 2.0,
being even better at doing live operations.
And the third one is fast cycle time.
Faster learning.
How do we accelerate the pace?
How can we learn faster from users?
It means how do we make release faster?
One of the points that we have in mind is about how do we
shift the quality ownership from a quality team to a
development team?
What kind of cultural change does it require to have the
development team being the owner of the quality?
And with that, we'll be able to go faster, have faster cycle
time, faster release, and learn faster from the users.
Coming to my last slide here, what's coming next is we have
a process we are happy about that is evolving with the
production guild on its own.
So now we need to look at the product.
We need to look at the product very closely.
One of the reasons is, if we don't have a process,
or if a process is broken, we might lose time,
we might lose money.
But those are small time and small money.
If we don't have good product, we're
talking about the life of the company.
We need good products.
So it means that the process is here to help us to make great game consistently.
It means we need to make great game.
It's not about focusing on the process.
It's about focusing on the product.
And that's when Flypath, the culture, and the maturity are coming to one.
The maturity is recorded in Flypath.
Our culture is dictated by Flypath, and they all one.
And now we are looking at the product.
This is it for the presentation.
Thank you very much for listening.
So I'm very happy to take any question if there is any.
Hi, I'm a producer on some mobile games right now, and I was just curious about
How you guys go about sun setting a product and making that decision because you just use you're saying in the green light
That's not for that
But along the way do you have some kind of formal process set up in flight path for if you do need to sunset something?
Early okay, so is the question about
killing a game during production,
or is it about sunsetting a game while it's
been live for many years?
Killing the game.
Killing, OK.
So killing is a good game.
It's good because it's painful.
And for the team, it's always painful to stop your baby,
stop developing your baby.
So we don't have a formal process.
I mean, we have the standard aftermath.
And we pop up the champagne, and we put the Wall of Fame photos,
and everything.
But it's
There are many things that we do and we don't do.
So we do the basics.
What we don't do is about considering the team.
So there are two points.
And I mentioned about the value of the team.
How do we see that?
There's one point about we take the same team and we try again.
It has a value because we all learn together.
Or the other one is acknowledging
that the team didn't work.
And it's very hard because they are colleagues and friends.
But acknowledging something didn't work
and then change the team.
And then you come to very personal decision.
And that we know we have to be better at.
So that is something that is coming.
But otherwise, I would say the usual suspect of the champagne
and parties and aftermath and these kind of things.
Post-mortem, sorry, is the proper word.
Yes.
Thank you.
I have a question.
Oh.
Sorry.
No, that's fine.
Of course.
I'd like you to go talk a little bit more about the decision to cancel holiday and make
the staff work leading up to Christmas because that's going to have a massive impact on company
culture.
Okay.
So I'd like you to talk a little more about that.
That's a finger in my...
in my ribs, so I lied.
We didn't cancel the holiday.
So what we did, though?
Because the launch was 22nd of December, technically, we
looked for volunteer.
That from 22nd of December to the 7th of January, whenever
we were coming back to the office, we will have the BI,
we will have the server operations, cloud
operation, et cetera.
available.
So we look for volunteers.
We didn't force anybody.
And then we just worked very hard for the few weeks
that was remaining.
So when I say we canceled our holiday,
maybe we canceled our holiday spirit
about ramping down toward the end of the year
when there's nothing much to do, because the apps are going
to close anyway, this kind of thing.
So I like to do it a bit just for the presentation.
No, that's fine.
But yes, we did work hard for it,
and then we looked for a volunteer.
But we'd never cancel any holiday in that sense.
Great.
Thank you.
Hi there, great talk, thank you.
Do you have a lot of old titles, right?
Do you apply Flypass process to maintainers?
To maintain those, because it's a tough process.
It's a good question.
It's a very, very good question.
A lot of observation here.
So if you notice that Flypass stop at live operation.
And we've been asking ourselves, what
about Flypass after that?
What about Flypass for a game that?
go beyond live operations, so maybe go to autopilot.
Autopilot, meaning it's on the store,
it's there to be downloaded and play,
but nobody's really maintaining it.
Sunset, you're there but you can't really pay any IEP, etc.
We've been asking ourselves this question.
The priority for us is really to focus on the game that we are making,
the new game we're going to launch,
because we are convinced that the game that we're going to launch
are going to be the next hit of tomorrow.
We're not going to...
We can maintain a lot of the game that is in live operation.
We can grow them.
But we know the next big hit that
is going to be hundreds and hundreds of millions
is going to come from a game that is in concept today.
So we're not applying FlyPath too much,
just because it's a low priority for us at the moment.
So anything that is coming live that is being developed
is going through FlyPath.
Thank you.
It was a very good talk from the concept on.
I was just curious about the process for generating ideas and filtering ideas that we will get
to preproduction.
A lot of good questions.
A lot of good, because it's really like all the plugs, all the holes that are in my presentation
are covered by good questions.
So this is also something that we are...
Searching we're searching our soul here. What is the what is the the good answer? So one studio has a 20% rule
so every in a sprint which is
Which is 10 days they will dedicate one day one day to do something something can be
Framed or something can be totally open. So they've tried different things
All the teams are thinking that you should be able to do your work with 80% of your time,
then you have 20% of your time to...
It's a bit the same principle.
Then we have very well organized game jam at the moment, a little bit at the studio
level, not at the Rovio level.
But for example, when the AR kit came, we made a game jam about the AR kit.
whenever we were thinking about,
would there be a next slingshot game?
Would there be one?
So what could it be?
Let's do a slingshot game jam.
So we have that.
But overall, we don't have a very strong organized way
of addition and of game jamming.
It's really ad hoc at the moment.
But we're looking at it to see how we
can be a bit more systematic.
Because we are convinced that feeding the beast, we say.
The more ideas we have, the better chance
we have to have good ideas and good business case.
Cool.
Thanks.
No more questions?
Well, thank you very much, everybody,
for coming to this session.
Thank you.