All right.
Thank you very much for choosing this session.
My name is Yut Saito.
I'm a game creator.
And I am from Tokyo.
And I am based in Tokyo.
So today, I would like to speak about how I create Seaman.
And with showing some other documentations,
I will mention about the kind of difficulty
in creating a brand new software.
So before starting everything, I would like to introduce myself.
I'm a, again, I was born in 1962, the year that the Beatles released their first record.
And I...
I'm a...
Started my career when I was 28 or 29, maybe.
So the first one did not sell well,
so you may never know the first title.
But second one, which is now here known as SimTower,
made a great score.
This is a kind of simulation game of building a skyscraper.
And
It's really released from Maxis as a sequel to SimCity,
so it really sold well.
I'm a little bit nervous today.
It's okay, we love you.
Thank you.
Woo!
So SimTower is a,
simulation that you have your own building and
oh this is a very good video on youtube so yeah this
so when you stretch your building to a higher level uh you your elevator shaft have to cover
more stories so there occurs a traffic jam so you have to be very careful otherwise
the tenant will be leaving your building and you will get less
profit. So you have to keep the customer satisfaction like a stress of waiting
elevator car in certain level and you have as the skyscraper grow bigger you
have to have it more urban functions and so you have to put a like hospitals and
schools some other urban functions in it and the key is how to make your elevator
very smart, setting the priority.
Like, whatever.
Anyway, I don't have so much time, so let's go to the next one.
I'm still a little bit nervous.
So, O-Dama is one of my favorite game I have made.
But it was not so much successful in sales,
because we took too long.
It was launched after Nintendo GameCube was almost vanishing in the market,
and a brand new one was almost coming up.
So, but this is a very, very unique game in the way that this is...
Oh, no.
I'm sorry.
This is a combination of pinball and I battled on the battlefield.
And I had the motivation as a game creator that I wanted to simulate the crowd of the people.
So...
With a voice command, you were...
controlling these troopers for certain directions as well as you hitting back
the ball like a pinball do not not trying not to damage your soldiers but
the enemy's soldier it's a tiny not easy
right it's a kind of crazy yeah
How many of you know this oldama?
Is it a race?
Oh, thank you.
It's kind of fair thing.
So, thank you.
All right.
And I
I would like to start talking about Seaman.
So if an executive guy of a computer game company
came to you and asked you if you can make guaranteed game
title to be a hit, which option would you
like to choose?
from all. Would you like to choose out of these three? One is it's a kind of dragons and dungeons
so that certain kind of market is guaranteed because it has a large share of the video game
and adding a little bit new feature on it or
Maybe another adventure game using famous licensed characters of Hollywood.
That's also kinda guaranteed to be a hit, I think, though it costs a lot.
Or a kinda rare beast of a game like nothing that came before it.
And I wound up going with option 3.
That's gonna be a Seaman.
And there are several reasons for this.
I think for a creator, it's better
to choose the option that seems to fit the best,
rather than the one you think is correct.
Option three differs from one and two,
because putting into the practice
requires inventiveness and courage.
I'm a game creator who's good at making new titles.
Because I am not very good at making sequels.
Even with my original title, that became hits.
And that's why I went with choice three,
although it looks as more difficult option anyway.
And that's what led to the release of Seaman.
Seaman, among the other titles, holds the record of sales
on the Dreamcast platform.
It succeeded in attracting the most new customers, people
who didn't own Dreamcast or Sega games up to the point.
The game also enjoyed the largest ratio of female fans.
It even became a kind of social phenomenon in Japan.
I will show you later about the TV program show introducing
the Seaman.
Back to the program.
Thank you.
See you later.
Bye.
This talk today is not about how to produce hit titles.
Then what the theme will be?
Well, when you're trying to create something completely new,
you're always going to find yourself lost
at some point in the process.
I want to talk about how you find a way firmly
out from indecision to accomplish your work.
So let's start about why I came up with this crazy game in the first place.
It all started with a lunchtime joke.
All it came down to was me having lunch with my staff
at the company I was running at the time.
At the time, my company was selling one game produced by me,
I mean, Sim Tower,
and another non-game entertainment software managed by another team.
This application worked on high-res Mac,
and it lets you raise tropical fish
with a beautiful screen of Macintosh.
We have this huge staff undergoing this huge amount
of research to make this app, the Phase 3 simulated,
the growth of living things.
We had actual aquariums in our office,
and there are staffers from agricultural colleges
to observe them and digitize them.
We were doing the kind of work research labs
at Zeus normally do,
instead of inside of an office
right in the middle of the Roppongi.
Roppongi is a kind of very pricey place in Tokyo,
so it's an area I like here.
So it was considered that they were calculating things more minutely than they actually needed to.
I was the manager of the company and I was jokingly complaining about this.
I am not making an app that costs that much time and effort to research for a normal aquarium.
Wouldn't people expect something that gives dramatic changes?
Creatures growing feet and hands, or going up on the land?
Isn't that more entertaining?
That's what I was saying to the staff around me.
and the staff responded by laughing heartily and asking me all sorts of questions about it.
I was on the roll at this point, so I kept saying more stuff.
Around the time there was a TV show on Saturday nights with a famous comedian.
At the very end of the show, he used to look right at the camera and say,
What are you looking at? You dump us?
I thought maybe the fish living in the aquarium, being stared at by a lot of people from outside,
may think like that way too.
He would say, what are you looking at?
Then I said, I wanted to have a voice recognition system on it to reply, shut down, just let
me sleep.
That's why I figured I'd need a human face.
And this reminded me of a sea monkey.
A sea monkey, you know the sea monkeys?
Yeah, it's a real creature.
I purchased this creature.
These eggs for, it's a hatches.
and starts swimming once it's put in the water.
The name of Sea Monkey and its package design
stuck around in my child's brain only
because it looked so creepy to me.
So I said, now.
If I'm gonna put a name to it, it would be Seaman,
not a sea monkey.
That's the first Seaman's name was decided.
After this joking lunch, my interest in this concept
kept still running in my head.
So I started sketching it out.
And one day,
I told my wife about those ideas.
She said, wow, I had this.
What a gross.
We dropped it all.
After some time had passed, one day my wife suddenly asked me, how is your concept going?
Why?
I answered, you've got to do that.
And I said, oh, but you said you hated that.
And she said, yes, I did.
But I didn't say I'm disinterested.
That was a very surprise to me because she really liked that.
I mean, she didn't say she liked that.
What I learned was the opposite of hate is not like, but indifferent.
That concept is a very, very big change in my life, and that leads to semen concept also.
There was another incident right around then. This became another trigger for me to build a
new theory, which turned out to be one of the most important elements of semen.
I heard from my old friend that a pair of coworkers had gotten married.
This couple pretty much constantly fought with each other all year.
It always put everyone around them on edge.
So hearing they got married was a big surprise to me.
My old friend, actually, he was a manager of those both people,
smiled and told me, hey, Saito-san,
he said the same thing.
The opposite of like isn't hate, right?
So right then and there, I made a huge discovery.
I decided to have this character's presence hated by most people,
instead of being trying to, you know, have it being loved.
If you succeed to make someone having a hate for something,
All it can take is a single flip of the switch for that to turn into a like.
In fact, the more you hate something, the more your mind becomes preoccupied with it.
It made me think, maybe this kind of creepy, creepy games I was thinking of could gather
interest from the people after all.
I figured I might as well go all the way with it.
Actually, I'm reading this.
So with two programmers,
I started a kind of prototyping of Seaman.
And with a very private reason,
I started here in Berkeley, in California, not in Japan.
And one day,
One executive guy of Sega came to me and he started talking about the new hardware.
And they had a severe competition with Sony and they're looking for a very strong and strange
title which will be called a killer title for the hardware. Now it's called Dreamcast.
So I opened up my laptop powerbook to the guy
and showed the prototype of Seaman.
And he again said, wow, it's creepy.
Yeah, I know.
And that was the starting that Seaman project really just
started forward.
So, for my directions, I settled on pursuing three opposites.
By opposite, I mean three major ways in which this game was different from the conventional
hit titles or your typical game in general.
maybe more to be hated than to be disinterested.
Yeah, the first one is non-cute characters,
as you may already know.
The second point that instead of having users project themselves
onto the game's characters,
We wanted to have them feel like someone's peeking at them
from within the TV sets.
No, actually, that was the third one.
I was talking about the third one.
I'm sorry.
The second one is talk about the reality around the user,
not a fancy world.
Which means they, um...
Games in general provide an alternate space, a fantasy world or whatever, spread out on
the screen.
Players' adventures around the space make new discoveries and so on.
However, I wanted to have this game confuse it by mixing reality and fantasy.
That leads to the reality fusing with the fantasy,
producing a strange, confusing feeling.
That's the second opposite.
The third one opposite is how the game works
from the user's perspective.
Normally, a game story proceeds with the game characters
not being aware of the players.
In movies, there's a
This iron rule that characters can't look into the camera.
That's because audience presence must never be a factor.
This game's character, however, looks right into the camera.
He talks like the user,
like he's looking right into their living room.
The game uses the aquarium metaphor
to make this easy to understand.
I worked to create a sort of a common link between users
and Siemens during the development.
At the time, I thought I was going wherever my creativity
and curiosity took me.
But I found myself realizing that I
needed some guiding theories to lead the project to the goal.
If it wasn't for these theories, I feel like I wouldn't have yielded to all the kinds of suggestions and requests.
And the resulting game would have been very different.
Creating something that's never existed before is a kind of battle against indecisions.
When you're at a fork in the road, you need a focal point to strive for.
And I concur this with these theories that served my boat.
About the word theory is here, I mean,
the theory is something it's not so much established.
So if this English word is really correct or not,
I'm not sure yet.
It's more like a hypothesis, hypothesis.
Yeah, it's not yet proven, it's not approved by the authority, it's something like more
unstable, insecure, that you built in your mind. So I made up my hypothesis
and trying to prove that through the development.
So to make this a hit, we needed a strong theme running through the conversation with the seaman.
That could capture anyone's interest. What is it?
And we decided the direction as the daily lives of the players themselves.
Talking to a pit doesn't have any thematic element to it.
It doesn't guarantee a hit.
If you have all these disparate themes flying around,
the players aren't going to spend their valuable time on it.
There needs to be a structure of understanding
that players are working towards something,
or else the players won't sit at the control seat.
So to achieve that, the conversations
had to be themed around something
that any player would be interested in.
What kind of theme would any player be interested in?
So our answer is that the daily lives of players.
I think there are people who aren't interested in fantasy
worlds, but my theory was that nobody's
uninterested in themselves.
Doesn't matter if they like it or dislike it.
So along with this theory, I started designing conversations.
To put it in another way, the user shares his own personality and relationship along
with the game's character.
And these conversations were structured along with lines of, you are raising a pet, only
to discover in the end that the pet was raising you all along.
Question 2.
How do we make people with even no interest in SEGA games purchase this?
This was also very important to me.
Alongside the thrill of dealing with this grotesque pet,
I made Seaman to be thoroughly dependent on the player.
I think that helped tickle the player's parental instinct, and I think that connected in a
big way to its success at the non-gamers market.
Siemens' incredibly self-centered behavior greatly reduces the player's freedom, but
people seem to like that part of it.
You have this situation where you have to go every day.
You go home every day at the same time.
But it seems that he's connected to players,
finding it worth doing.
I heard a lot of cases at bars and such, where players said they had to go home ASAP to feed
their seamen.
I also heard from many people about episodes where they'd go on vacation with their Dreamcast,
plug into the hotel's TV sets, and feed their pet.
It seems like being needed by someone else energizes people.
You also see a lot of cases where if they are no longer needed, that de-energizes people.
You often see this in the way people retire from work.
How do we appeal this game in ads?
So we decided to
not to sell our new tech.
In the ads, we simply use the term raising.
New technical jargon sounds cool
if you're lining up in the event like GDC.
Let's use this sentence for an example.
Wow, four-player real-time battle system
provides exciting team combat or something like that.
That really scares users, especially non-gamers.
Creators tend to boast about what we are proud of, right?
But any entertainment needs to have a structure of understanding.
because you're asking people to go through the entrance you've built. I think you need a trick
in replacing their fear of the unknown with something they have already in their minds.
When a person gains an understanding of something new,
they tend to think of it using an understanding of something older.
That's why successful new technologies have always entered our lives by masquerading as old things.
For example, cell phones.
These were very different from regular phones.
Rather closer to the radio transceivers.
Our doorbells don't have bells.
What you did see was raising, giving food, taking care of it, talking to it once a day.
These phrases are what we used in the ads.
Instead of voice recognition technologies equipped with the AI technology things,
we consider it to promotions with old-fashioned pet raising.
Actually, this is the graphic of the first ad of the seaman in the market.
And that was done not for a game magazine, but it was done for women's magazines.
And this is something we're about.
The question four is one of the most difficult questions to me.
Who should do the voice actor of the seaman?
Does he have to be a famous one?
Actually this question was one of the most difficult one of this project
Games like movies can create buzz by casting a famous actor
So this question has been the biggest headache
and
In the end we cast an actor who was almost completely unheard of for Seaman
me
I did that actor.
This was the ultimate decision, and the purpose of this was just to keep the quality of voice
and recording to its most.
And this voice actor guy didn't cost anything.
And could do retakes wherever they wanted.
I as a director didn't have to worry about maintaining a good rapport between an actor
and director.
When the work was over, I as a voice actor would have no further voice jobs, so we didn't
have to worry about rumors going around the industry like, oh, I did the Seaman's voice
and the director was a total pain to work with, something like that.
That's what allowed the identity of Seaman's voice to remain totally unknown.
It was an incredibly unique decision that we have made.
But in the end, projecting this mysterious air was really effective for promotion.
This is true even for the PlayStation version that was released two years later.
Question five.
Yeah, how about the voice actor?
How about the other voice actor?
Yeah, we needed someone else to support.
But just like the rookie, political candidates benefit from a big name.
And actually, we needed somebody very famous to support this unknown character.
And we picked Leonard Nimoy.
And that's my idea.
I don't know why I did it.
wanted to have him, but finally SEGA America agreed to make a contract with him.
I didn't think it was a very
easy job because he's really a star, but
you know, for the Japanese edition, we employed a famous actor with a long
career.
and have him use his real name within the games.
And Mr. Leonard Nimoy named his own name in the MC also.
The results of that were great.
I will show you.
Hmm.
Let's head over to the tank.
Of running out of food for Seaman later.
But if you manage the larvae well, you should have no problem keeping sea man well fed.
At the moment, the habitat contains two young men.
They appear to be...
I'm hungry. Give me something to eat. I'm starving. I'll bet if I
want.
Don't tell your mother.
It's fine.
And with Claim Rate Guard, they won't raise your rates just because of a claim.
That's why you're my favorite.
I know.
It's good to be in good hands.
I'm sorry.
Angry Atari Amiga, CD-i, Coleco, Vignax, Television, Sega, Neo Geo, TurboGrafx-16, Odyssey, 3DO, Commodore, Nintendo
This is one of the funniest YouTube videos ever.
But I heard it was once a porn about semen.
I just heard. That's all.
A Dreamcast game that sends you to porn.
More like wet Dreamcast.
Set the time? Since when did video game consoles start telling time?
I have a clock! A rolling rock clock! I don't need this shit! I can wear a wa-
Well, thank god for the instructions.
So you have to raise the heat up to a certain range, and then just wait for the egg to hatch.
All right, while the game does its thing, let's read up on a little history.
According to the manual, the species that we will be raising was originally discovered in Egypt in the 1930s by a French
anthro-bio-archaeologist, Jean-Paul Gasset.
His hypothesis suggests that the creature was responsible for transferring knowledge and language across the land during the Third Dynasty.
The creature is said to be the reincarnation...
I'm sorry.
You turn off the game, come back to it a day later...
Or five minutes later, like me.
You visit often.
If one didn't know better, one might assume you're quite obsessed.
Or you have nothing better to do.
Oh, I have better things to do!
No.
I think it's not working very well.
No way!
It's an official Fanacom disc game that...
That was the process we went through to produce the game. It was released in July 1999.
A lot of news and info programs on Japanese TV introduced it alongside the AIBO robot released
by Sony. And kind of a...
I think they are saying as if we are entering a new era where we lived alongside computers.
SEMA wound up selling a surprise number of copies, and we found out that the majority
of purchases were women and a lot of players bought the game with the Dreamcast hardware
system also.
To put it another way, it earned a lot of new users for us.
Things proceeded exactly as we theorized they would.
I was lucky.
To be frank, I don't think SEGA believed many of the theories
I put across to them.
They didn't think it would sell that much.
I agree with that.
I learned that when they don't make the full planned order to the voice mic that comes
with the game to the factory in Taiwan, we ran out of parts quick and thanks to that
we had a mounting of back orders.
Having the legacy, legendary games sell out in the market only further contributed to
the name.
mythological air around it.
It was really good news to Sega.
As I've shown, creating a new category of game isn't just
about completing the game program and graphics.
You need to...
You need enough consistency to answer the several thousand questions about it
from the people involved.
all the undefined things that need to be pinned down.
If these things lost their consistency during the development, it'll break apart mid-flight.
I have ever read a journal written by the wife of movie director Francis Ford Coppola.
And this was
the book about the middle of the production of the uh francis ford coppola and he was um
he was um in the middle of the um the status being lost
if the leader starts feeling lost developing falls into uh
um really really bad situations
And a game designer needs to start with the faith and conviction that's stronger than a rock.
It's not that you are prepared for everything.
So you need to build your own theories.
If you ask me what the most important thing is, though,
asked me if it's having those theories, this is not what I said.
The most important thing is that you execute it, not only to explore your theories in your
mind.
test your hypothesis in reality and prove it as correct by completing your titles.
There are probably several hundred people who come up with an idea almost as unique as yours,
but if there's a way to show off your inner strength, it's by bringing that theory to reality.
It takes one person out of several hundred to do that.
Hitting an idea of taking a talking fish is not an exploit.
If we are allowed to call semen as an achievement,
we think of it as dumb because we did manage
to accomplish this crazy idea as a commercial product
and put it into the market.
So please do not.
Be scared to be different from the conventional existing games?
I encourage you to swim against the stream.
Do not try to predict the future, but just make it.
Seaman was blessed by a development team,
including Mr. Endo, Aka Roy-san,
Suzuki-san, Ito Suzuki Hirose,
who believed in me enough that they even quit their job to participate in this project.
I also got to collaborate with a very generous publisher whose name is SEGA.
Those two parties are what allowed this to become a hit,
and I think it provides a precious case study to look at.
I'd like to thank Fukui-san who helped me
this trip,
Lopez-san who coordinated my trip also,
Josh-san,
Studio8-no-yon-san,
Kyoko-san,
for a great translation,
as well as Megan at GDC
who gave me such a great opportunity to be here.
And most of you, I would like to thank you for being here.
Thank you very much. Thanks for listening.
So we have another 15 minutes, so Kyokusan will be helping me to...
If you have any questions, please, please raise your hand.
Yeah, or if you don't mind, we're recording audio,
so there are two mics in the room.
If you could come up to either of those mics.
Thanks.
So bright.
Hi, can I go?
Yes.
Hi, I'd just like to know how you decided...
what things to put in it it understood because I got into a lot of trouble because it asked me if
I was having an affair. Getting personal. Would you speak slowly please? Okay yes so how did you
decide what scenarios or what situations that it would understand and respond to?
So...
Can I...
Do you want to rephrase that?
Actually, that was a very good question because I...
I wrote the script, I mean, I wrote the dialogues myself.
If we had two or three or more writers,
we couldn't have a kind of consistency.
I mean, it will be kind of a mixture
of several personality, and that will be kind of very danger
to entertain people, because sometimes the personality
of a scene changes day by day, and that
is a very risky thing.
So I did one person.
The key is one person does that and I did that from my experience.
So I'm not a professional writer.
I just express what I thought.
And so SEMA is something like a part of me actually.
And I did the voice actor too.
So it's a strange feeling.
But if you're running your own studio, right?
No.
Oh, no.
I wish I was.
OK.
But if you are too, then you have to be careful that,
The tiny sentence, tiny dialogues have a kind of personality in it.
And the user will be very aware of that if you have several personalities in one program.
That's very subtle, but they will know.
And that causes a kind of tiny contradiction.
The key is that one personality...
does everything at once, that's the key to have a deep personality in the computer program.
Was it a good answer?
Yeah.
Thank you.
Hello.
Oh, that was loud.
On my other side.
Yeah.
Yes.
Your friend.
Yeah.
Could you talk a little bit about the kind of the weird viral marketing stuff
like the strange websites and all of that were you involved with that and how
did it come to be?
What is that?
It's a promotion for various websites.
Shiman?
Are you talking about the kind of weird history things?
Yeah.
When I was 10 years old, my father took me to a kind of
strange exhibition.
That was...
Kyoko-san, would you translate for me?
Sure.
There was a strange fish called shirakansu,
and the body of that fish was displayed in Tokyo.
It was a strange fish that was called a fossil of Africa.
Is that okay?
I imitated that and, like a real dolphin,
I did a seaman exhibition at a museum when I released Seaman.
At a real museum.
I actually put a TV monitor there,
and made a white stone and a fossil.
What was it called in the bottle?
I put it in a formalin and put it there.
Creating that kind of world view,
I think of it now.
I wanted to create a world view, but...
You speak Japanese, right?
Does it make sense?
She's going to translate.
Please go ahead.
I also made a website.
I made a temporary website.
Temporary?
No, I don't know what that means.
So, the marketing team is the ones in charge of that?
Okay, so it sounds like...
I wasn't involved in the entirety of the whole entire viral marketing campaign,
but the one that was, I guess, stemmed from an idea that I...
or an experience that I had is that my dad took me to this very...
unique, interesting exhibit when I was 10 years old.
And it was basically kind of a,
I guess it's maybe a history museum
or an aquarium sort of slash historical museum.
And they had a creature from Africa called the sea buccaneer.
Shira-cans?
And it was...
How do you say shira-cans in English?
Silicans.
So it was an entire exhibit on that,
and it came in different shapes and forms.
They had a skeletal sort of writing or a...
you know, photos of it, exhibits of it.
And I thought that was pretty cool.
Like, it left a really strong impression on me.
So with Seaman, I kind of wanted to recreate that exact same experience that I had.
when I went to that exhibit.
And so we came up with ideas as if this really
existed in our world and basically
had this exhibit or installation where
we would talk about the history of semen,
give them a background, give them a story,
and even have these mock-ups of what semen looked like.
And so that was something that stemmed from my own experience
that I wanted to exploit and set really the background so
that people would really get into the story
and the history of semen.
great. All right. So in your talk, you mentioned that you
wanted the player to feel like C man was reaching out to them
and interacting with their life as opposed to the player
interacting with his world. Technology has changed a lot
since the original game was developed.
Now we have social media, webcams, and VR, etc.
If you were making a game like Seaman today, or if you had the technology that exists today, back then,
what kind of technologies would you integrate to create a more immersive experience?
Yeah, I'm very much interested in what's called the wearable,
so that I can collect the information all over the world about him.
Unfortunately, iOS has a lot of the guidelines between the applications.
One application cannot take the information from others, right?
Android is more easy to do that because once, let's say, the application of semen detects
that you got a mail from your girlfriend but you didn't respond to that.
Oh, why you didn't do that?
What happened between?
That kind of thing, very much you want to do,
but iOS is limiting that kind of activity
between the application.
So and these kind of things, like iWatch and Apple Watch
and some other devices.
Yeah, it's very much interesting.
But the first thing I just want to do
is the things I just mentioned, like your activity
in other applications.
Like you were calling somebody so many times,
but you couldn't get any call back.
And Steven's going to start mentioning
about the relationship between two of you,
something like that.
Is what, yeah.
And that is totally different from that kind of dissemination
in the way that this version has a scenarios, huge scenarios.
But to do that kind of data, smartphone games,
we just need a real AI, endlessly speaking.
And that's what I have been working on.
So it's not achieved, so I couldn't release a new version.
But that's one of the most things
I'm very much interested in.
OK, thank you.
Thank you.
Okay, question, do you especially like writing manuals?
I'm asking that, the manual that come with the game.
What is manual?
The manual, yeah.
Because we saw Seaman, it has an interesting history
at the beginning.
Sim Tower, I remember it was very interesting because midway through the manual you explained
how the game was working.
At the very end you said, I want these two put west and east in touch, and you actually
signed the manual, if I remember well.
And that I don't remember, not their case.
So is there, do you have a special interest in doing these kind of things?
Did you write all the manuals?
I mean, the first, second, and third volumes.
Yes.
You also wrote the autographs.
Did you write them because you were interested in writing them?
As well, as company make the presentation of the new game, but they don't spend so much
time on it.
They just spend half an hour before the presentation in the cafe and bring that.
Producers spend, you know...
a year or two on that, always thinking about that.
So basically, I think producer should,
like the theory, throw that kind of clue or hint
to the ads people, manual writers,
or the hook or maybe axis.
Because the best game is the game
that people don't need a manual.
Game itself, like the Nintendo game, speaks about its role first.
I think so, yeah.
But I did myself over writing because I love writing
and I didn't believe that kind of hired manual people.
temporary writing things is not always...
not going to... Finally, the developing team have to take care of that.
I knew that, so I start from the writing.
Even far before the game was completed.
So, the manual was kind of a spec sheet to the development team, almost.
Yeah, no, that's the interesting...
Manual, that adds to the game. It's not explaining it.
The controls is just, yeah, telling more. So, yeah.
Thank you.
A lot of things that today call themselves AI seem much, much, much dumber than C-Man
seemed then.
So I think you did an incredible job of simulating intelligence.
And to follow up on the very first question, which asked about how you created all of the
unique responses.
Could you give us some idea of how many total unique responses you created in order to simulate that intelligence?
Yeah, actually the first version of Simon is not AI at all. That was a massive
writing, you know, written materials did it and
the number of the folk
I was uncountable in...
Thousands?
I know much more.
Tens of thousands?
I don't know, at least the number of the jobs
is more than 200, so the combination of those kind of
things, I don't know, it's uncountable.
But the cement is one of the...
the job that only young guys can do.
So now I need AI, because I'm so much younger than them.
But the response is, actually, English version
is it was done by somebody else.
I mean, American people.
So I'm not so much familiar with the American version.
But in Japanese version, yeah, we
did put a lot of.
I wonder how to say it in Japanese.
I want you to translate it in a short term.
When you said something,
you were doing voice acting,
and you were able to do a lot of interesting things.
You were able to do a lot of interesting things.
You were doing voice acting, and you were doing writing,
so you were able to do a lot of pranks.
It was so much more, I guess, I had the pleasure and leisure to kind of like play around, play tricks, fool around.
So it was just basically like a banter with myself.
And that led to new discoveries in so many different scenarios.
Thank you.
Hi.
Hello.
Quick question.
Do you plan on creating more strange games like Seaman, or to bring back Seaman in some shape or form?
For these five years I've been out of the game industry for very private reasons.
And I think I'm coming back.
And for these years, what I have been doing was something to create a kind of AI.
It's not a game, it's a kind of R&D.
And so now I started thinking about a new game
and it's gonna be very strange.
I mean, it's...
Perfect.
It will be like very unexisting.
And I just started on that with a publisher in Japan.
I can't tell you that well, but...
Awesome.
It's a little bit related to Bitcoin.
Okay.
It's something like mining your own gold
and make your own...
money. Interesting. Yeah, we're using blockchain technologies. Yeah, that's almost everything.
Thank you. On that note, it's just at three o'clock right now, so I think that's going to
be it for us today. Thank you. Thank you very much. Thank you.