Hi, I'm Ed Zobrist.
I'm the head of publishing for Epic Games on Fortnite,
as well as Spy Jinks and Battle Royale.
Right off the bat, though, I'd like
to talk about what we're not going to talk about.
We're not going to talk that much about Battle Royale.
Some, but from a marketing standpoint, it's actually not as interesting intellectually
for what we did as what we did with Save the World.
So we're going to focus more on Save the World, which is our PVE game that preceded Battle
Royale that we launched this summer.
I'm also not really going to talk a lot about numbers or metrics.
First off, there are probably some analysts or competitors out there, and I'm not interested
in divulging more information than I have to, but really it's because this presentation
is more about principles and ideas that we use to launch Save the World and why we diverge
from what is really sort of conventional business practices for major publishers.
So to give you a feeling for my background,
I was basically classically trained as a marketer.
Coming out of Wharton, went to General Mills Consumer
Products, and eventually went to Mattel, the Walt Disney
Company, then to Universal Games,
then Sierra Entertainment, which became Activision Blizzard.
So I'm pretty well-grounded when it
comes to traditional marketing, as well as how major publishers
operate and launch games.
But in spite of that kind of background,
that's not at all what we did for Save the World.
And I want to give you a little insight into that.
And for you indie developers, which
is really what I'm here for, I used to also do indie
development, I'm trying to give you
a sense of how you could think about the world
and apply some principles to what you're
doing when you launch a game.
And you don't necessarily have to follow the same recipe
that the big publishers are following, or even that we
for that matter.
All right, so let's first set the stage for what was going on with Fortnite.
We started development in 2011.
That's right.
Seven years ago.
Survival game, action building,
had a cover for Game Informer in 2014.
And I just want to give you a flavor
of a video that was given to Game Informer back then in 2014
to give you a sense of where we were at that time.
Fortnite is an action building game that is heavily focused on exploration, discoverability, obviously building.
There's shooter aspects to it, there's RPG and progression aspects to it.
When players first get into the experience, the absolute raw thing is that they're going
to be masters of what we're considering the home base.
This represents sort of a group of heroes that have undertaken the task of saving the
world from the oncoming storm.
Our storm is our mysterious force in the world where the monsters come from.
They start out with their base and then they move into the sort of action aspect of the game,
which is they spawn into the world, they don't have any equipment,
they immediately have to get tools, they have to get weapons,
they have to get resources so they can build, and there are gates in the world that the players
will be closing because those are the things that tie the storms to the world.
And if they can shut the gates...
they can push back the storms and push back the monsters.
So they're basically taking terrain back one area at a time.
And then hopefully they interact with their friends and be like,
okay, we both have home bases, like, let's link them together
and the benefits from both our bases help us together as a group.
And that, to me, that cooperative nature of the primal building,
like, you know, I never built forts alone when I was in the woods as a kid.
That was something you did with your friends.
Same feeling in Fortnite. Like, let's get together.
We will work as a group to build these giant forts and fight the bad guys.
For us, the way we build is super new, the ease of use of the building system.
So I can't build Mordor or, you know, the Starship Enterprise. I can't.
So I think because people will feel like they're awesome and creative from the very beginning
without necessarily having a lot of artistic talent, Fortnite's gonna really feed to that.
There's a lot of really awesome building games that we love and that we play all the time,
and I feel like we're riffing kind of on that zeitgeist where we're like,
let's take it to the next level.
Although Helms Deep is a great fight to have, but it happens like what do I do in between that?
Well, the truth of the matter is you explore the world, you get resources to bring back to the structure that is the permanent one.
But since you can access building anywhere, you can use those tools however you wish.
And so making some quick strongholds that you can just hold up into for during the storm and just weather it, that's what you'll do.
But you know, the truly majestic version of it is back at home waiting for you.
People are going to get the experience of Fortnite this year. It's going to be free.
And I think, you know, that's awesome.
It's a great way to have a conversation with.
with players because they're not obligated to like it.
So we have to do our jobs.
We have to be awesome game creators to say,
it's worth your time to play this game.
And I think we've done that.
We looked at the people that were doing it really well
and we're saying, we could do it that way.
There are ways to have our game be free
and have it be fair.
Our game is definitely not pay to win.
It is just an experience to have fun.
We know that the more that people play
and the more people play, people will buy into it.
Like, I mean, if you like it, there'll be something about it that you'll want to spend some money on.
And if you don't, that's fine too.
Of course, you know, it's business, but it's also one of passion.
We're going to do things really smart and super fair.
We're going to start making a cool game that gamers want to play and then everything else will fall out of there.
We feel like Fortnite is a conversation with our players.
We want them to tell us what they want,
because we're gamers too,
and we recognize that, hey, we're just a few people.
We don't have all the right ideas,
and we know that a lot of players out there
have a lot of really cool ideas.
What we would love to see is a game
that lasts for years and years and years,
and ends up somewhere we don't even expect,
because that makes it interesting for us.
The team's really excited,
so the sooner we get it out there, the happier I'll be.
OK.
Pretty good marketing.
Game Informer supporting it.
Would have been great if we had launched in 2014.
But we didn't.
The issue then became, when we finally
did get around to launching, or start
thinking about the launch, we started
thinking about the launch planning in 2016, 2017,
knowing we were going to launch sometime that summer, mid 2017.
So, from a marking standpoint, we had a couple of issues that we had to deal with.
One was this sort of indifferent perception about the game.
It had gone through a long delay.
And we'd also described it all along as free to play,
and that's how it was designed as a game.
It's going to be a free to play game,
which led it to a certain sort of play system
associated with it.
It was also a somewhat unusual game.
It's sort of the mishmash of a bunch of different genres.
So it wasn't that easy to really grasp
or describe what it was in a short, pithy statement.
And finally, we were going off to launch in that summer of last year,
but we knew we weren't quite ready.
We knew it still needed tuning, it still had features that needed to go into it.
But we also wanted to start getting feedback,
because we needed some players, more players playing it in a live environment
to help us guide the...
the ongoing development to get us to that free-to-play state that we ultimately desired.
So we decided we were going to go a route that's very common on PC but very uncommon on console,
and that is we're going to call it free-to-play, or call it paid early access.
And everyone who knows Steam and PC knows what early access means,
but it's a little bit more of an alien concept when it comes to console.
The, but in our mind that was a way to signal to the players that it wasn't quite finished,
wasn't quite done and that what they were experiencing was going to ultimately change
and evolve on its route to becoming a free-to-play game. But we were paid. We were paid Early Access.
Partially we were paid because we wanted to make certain we had a really qualified
group that was coming in to give us feedback on the game.
And when we choose the price points, we probably, as a company, could have made a lot more money if we just started at $60.
The product itself looked like a AAA game.
But just ethics, just general stances, is just not the right thing to do for players.
If people wanted to come at a lower price point, we were going to let them come at a lower price point
because it wasn't really ready as far as we were concerned, therefore we'd offer the lower tier.
But if someone wanted to, you could go for one of the higher tiers.
and you would get even more loot and starting goodies.
And by the way, those prices, they were set around to deliver to the players
the equivalent plus a little more of what if in the free-to-play mode
you had spent that much money, the kind of things you would have acquired early on.
So it was our way of calibrating it
to get a sense of what the gameplay mechanics were going to be like when we started to tune it.
All right, now it starts getting a little more interesting.
A couple key milestones that a lot of big publishers
go through are they typically have a big cinematic trailer.
And you guys know who I'm talking about.
They have a gameplay trailer, and then they announce,
oh, here's the date we're going to launch.
Go to the stores, pick us up.
And I've come up with my sense of just a rough industry
standard of what most big publishers would
have done around the time frame, with the cinematic,
say, coming 12 to 18 months in advance.
And then gameplay trailers, I should use plural,
start coming out around four or six months in advance.
And then about two or three months
before the actual launch happens, they announce it.
They start a big pre-reg campaign.
And the machine kicks in leading up to the launch.
So here's what we did.
We actually didn't lead with the cinematic trailer.
We had one, I'm gonna show it to you in a little bit.
It's beautiful, but we didn't lead with it.
We started with the gameplay trailer,
and we announced the date of our ship
at exactly the same time, seven weeks in advance.
And then eventually the cinematic came along
about three weeks before the actual launch occurred.
So let's look a little more deeply at those.
We're seven weeks before launch.
We announced it at press release just before E3.
We're dodging the tornado of E3.
We know that we have got a lot of ground.
We've got to recover for the game because
of that indifferent perception.
And we have baggage.
So we want to launch or announce at a time
where we can get the max amount of attention
and not get overwhelmed by all the storm of E3 coverage.
We put out our website.
And then we put out a gameplay trailer.
Now remember I said the game is a little unusual.
It's a little bit not conventional and it requires you to
actually think a little bit more about how you play the game
because it doesn't fit a neat, tidy description.
So we did two gameplay trailers.
We did one real short one, 30, just because that's the norm
so people didn't have time to watch it.
But we also put out a really long one.
And I'm going to show you the long one
because it gives you a sense of
the things we thought were important that we had to start conveying to the players.
and also a sense of where the game had evolved
from that first trailer I showed you,
and the game did evolve,
not just in terms of gameplay and art,
but it frankly evolved as far as Epic's,
basically, its video services capabilities.
We put together a much more polished
and better trailer, in my mind,
on gameplay,
and the whole video,
the whole area of video within Epic
has just been a huge, huge progression over the years.
So let's take a look at that.
If you're out there, we need your help.
The storm came. The monsters followed.
They took everything. Our towns, our families.
The few of us left are in serious danger.
Now, it's time to fight back.
All we need is a leader.
And that's you.
Sure, it'll be dangerous. I mean, yeah, there's monsters. A lot of monsters.
But we've got massive forts.
Killer traps.
And piles of loot.
If we stick together, they don't stand a chance.
This is our world, and it's time to take it back.
The world of Fortnite is filled with places to explore and loot to scavenge.
Collect building and crafting materials while traveling across landscapes where no two are ever the same.
You never know what you'll find, or where you'll find it.
Make sure to go inside buildings. Searching can pay off.
Everything you collect can be used to protect yourself or help the survivors out there who need you.
For protection from the storm, you and your friends will need to build forts.
Use a variety of building pieces to keep enemies at bay and make a strong defense.
Edit mode lets you customize pieces to fit your needs.
Make doors or windows.
Or get more creative.
Stronger materials like stone or metal will give your fort more staying power.
Being able to build on the fly lets you respond to threats quickly and adapt when you need to.
You didn't make all this just to watch it get knocked down!
Defend your fort the way you want.
Build sniper towers if that's your style.
Or use all of the powerful traps you've crafted
to make a maze of death that'll do the dirty work for you.
When monsters do take a bite out of your defenses,
you can repair and reinforce them during the heat of battle.
Keep an eye out for weak spots, because the enemy sees them too.
Use your imagination.
Build the ultimate fort and use it to withstand all the bad things the storm will throw at you.
With what you've harvested, you can craft hundreds of weapons, from melee to heavy arms.
Make traps to set up the perfect surprise attack.
Or use gadgets that will help you and your team.
Manage your resources well and you can be fully prepared for whatever is headed your way.
Your friends will help you succeed. Each hero is a specialized version of one of the basic types.
Constructors, Soldiers, Outlanders, and Ninjas. Each hero you collect comes with individual
advantages that fulfill different roles on your team. Of course, constructors are skilled at
building forts, but they also provide valuable crowd control.
Primed for combat, soldiers bring grenades, as well as the big guns.
And sometimes, the biggest guns.
Outlanders are the best at harvesting, and have some unique tools at their disposal.
All that and a mean right hook.
Finally, there are ninjas.
Great for melee, and really into throwing stars.
They're good for getting into and out of trouble quickly.
Collect cards to get heroes with different skills.
More heroes equals more abilities at your disposal.
Get your friends together for a well-rounded team.
Cooperation can make all the difference.
The people need you.
Rescue survivors and give them a home.
Defend them with everything you've got.
Don't seek shelter.
Make it count.
Part of that video was also driven by research.
We wanted to confirm, it was no surprise, actually,
that there are certain things that gamers had to know
was inside the game before they would consider it.
For this style of gamer, things like we showed a skill tree,
because a lot of people wanted to make certain
that's how the game is played, or that we had classes.
So that's why we tended to dwell
on a lot of the different elements of the game,
to make certain people understood
the depth associated with it.
All right.
Two weeks go by, we've just done E3,
we've come out with the gameplay trailer,
and we start a program called Search for Survivors.
A lot of people talk about our influencer programs
that we run at Epic, but this is the first time
we've tried it on a major scale.
Our Search for Survivors program was essentially us
teaming up with a whole bunch of YouTubers,
and we would space them out, so a few every week
would come out with new videos, they're sponsored.
And the idea was that their viewers would watch these videos
and if they went and they clicked through to pre-register,
they would also get a banner that was unique to that influencer
that they could use in the game.
The game has banners inside of it.
They could use it in the game and they would end up getting special loot as well
if they had signed up through our Search for Survivors campaign.
Plus, this is all tying back to the website for the pre-register program,
as in almost compendium-like way, as more and more people signed up for pre-registration,
we had a higher and higher level of extra group of loot that was given out to anyone.
Anyone who pre-registered, as long as the numbers kept going up.
So let's take a peek at one of those influencer videos.
What's up everybody H2O Delirious here. We are playing a game called Fortnite. It's an awesome game. I've already played it
I played it with Ohm. I played it with Vanoss. I played with a bunch of people already
But this game is just me and Ohm goofing around making a massive base of our own. I hope you enjoy it
I'm gonna leave a link in the top of the description for you to click it if you are
Interested at all in the Fortnite game, so please click it for me
Anyone who signs up through the link will be granted custom banners which will be one of my own and it will be added on
The 21st of July if the game gathers enough survivors, which is you guys for pre registrations
There will be additional items a lot for you for pre registering on the game. That being said, I hope you enjoyed the game
Peace out everybody and goodbye
Welcome to fortnight. Um, welcome. Welcome
Part of this also was a very conventional device's trial.
We really would love to have had some sort of trial device
so people could play the game, do their own hands-on.
But remember, we're a co-op PVE game
which requires a lot of players.
So it's not very easy to do a trial device
prior to the launch of that kind of game.
Except just before, and we did have a Head Start program.
So by using YouTubers and Influencer, we're basically simulating what it feels like to play the game.
So we accomplished it in a different way than actually doing a trial device.
Alright, I've talked about the cinematic and how we didn't launch it until just before launch.
Three weeks before launch.
We debuted exclusively at the Rischi Teeth Convention in Austin.
Now, this was an ideal setting for us.
These are the folks that did the red versus blue videos.
And this is an audience that has a really high affinity for quality cinematics.
So they were naturally gonna be receptive to seeing what we had to offer.
And Rooster Teeth also has a decent network for getting out the word about what's going on
to their group of players, so we thought that was great.
And they're frankly just a blast to work with as well.
So here, let's look at the cinematic.
Alright people, let's search this dump and get out of here ASAP.
Dump? What's wrong with the Durr Burger?
Yeah, it's got everything. Garbage, rats, severe structural damage.
Some people just can't appreciate fine dining.
Did you hear that?
You got nothing to worry about.
Trust me.
I've got the heightened senses of a ninja.
I am so sorry.
Hey, hey.
It's okay.
We're gonna get you out of here.
Oh, thank you.
We thought you were more of those things.
Monsters are coming.
Looks like we're staying put.
Right.
All right.
You two stick with me.
Yes, ma'am.
Let's get to work.
We're here.
I guess meat is murder.
Ugh, you're killing me, man.
Okay.
Let's head to the roof for evac.
Aside from the part where we almost died,
that was amazing.
Hey, don't mention it.
It's all in a night's work.
All right, guys.
Who's up for pizza?
Oh, yeah! Pizza!
Reorder now and get a four day-
OK.
So you get the idea.
Pretty high quality video.
I mean, this is a further, yet another way for us
to just re-emphasize the quality of the products
that we were making and bringing.
And again, this is three weeks before launch.
So very, very soon thereafter, we would be selling the game.
July 25, we launch.
We had a minor, small Head Start program
where some people got in early.
We launched it mainly with digital advertising, so important to note.
We didn't use TV to do it.
Decided we didn't need it, actually.
We had a Twitch Viral Quest program.
And for those of you who don't know what this is,
it's when a streamer
completed a quest online to someone who had a Twitch account.
It was linked to our accounts. We knew through their Epic account that they had been watching someone who had completed it,
and they would get a special quest inside the game.
So we're actually tying you back to what was going on in the game.
That whole Searcher Survivor program activated, the banners went out,
the loot went out to people who had participated in the pre-reg program.
We also had retail support from Gearbox.
We didn't originally plan to do retail,
but late along the ways, we were talking with Gearbox
and decided to go for it, and I just had to give them props.
And at a really, really tight timetable,
Gearbox was able to get a retail program in place.
And then we had Sony and Microsoft Store Placements
to help us with the actual launch.
And everything depends on whether or not you do all this
for whether or not it works.
It frankly exceeded our expectations.
It laid the groundwork for the game to continue to grow
as it marched on to its free-to-play status, which we'll do this year.
I'm happy to say the retention is high and here we are
over six months later
and our audience is larger now than it's ever been for Save the World.
Not just for BR, this is for Save the World.
So for us it's worked out extremely well.
Okay, here's why you probably really came here a little bit about battle royale now talk a little
lot little on it.
About 2 months to develop it launched in September 26 so let's let's do some math.
Save the world the P game.
launched July 21.
This comes out September 26, so yeah.
We started working on this just about the time
Save the World was coming out.
And it was the Unreal Tournament team
that popped over to pick up the charge
for us to basically put, originally what we thought
would be a PvP version inside of our PvE game.
Then things changed as we got really close to launch
and we'd already started marketing it
as if this PVP mode, Battle Royale,
was gonna be inside of Save the World
and people, as far as we could tell,
we saw an uptick in sales, we're beginning to buy
Save the World and expectation of being able to play it.
we changed our mind.
We decided that this would work better
if it were a free to play game
and separated it out from Save the World,
even though it's just still one client.
You could just go directly in to play Battle Royale
and you wouldn't need to go through
the Save the World purchase gate in order to play it.
So if any of you are from a deal very much with first party
or console manufacturers,
you can imagine how difficult this was
in two weeks time to get through it.
The marketing staff at Epic probably worked
about 14 days straight, no weekends, no anything,
trying to make the transition points
and pivot into our ability to launch it as a separate game.
And ultimately we did.
That's another example of where I think we obviously have a little bit of an edge.
We are still a very nimble developer by mindset.
I think I doubt any major publisher really could have pulled off this kind of pivot in
the kind of time that we ended up doing it.
But there are a few interesting, I said the most interesting thing from marketing as far as I was concerned had more to do with Save the World,
but there are a few interesting things with BR and I want to show you a sequence of videos that gives you a flavor for
how we've evolved and how we think about Battle Royale over time.
So first we're going to take a quick look at the launch trailer.
And as you can see back then we're also still talking about the Save the World SKU.
What I want you to think about when you look at that video is it's a pretty action-packed
video.
It really has a feeling like it's geared towards players who may be more competitively oriented.
And originally, that's what we thought we needed.
We saw the landscape out there and we said,
OK, well, we need to be more hardcore.
About three weeks into the game,
we had started to get some traction.
It was going well.
We held a company meeting at Epic.
And as part of the company meeting,
we just put together a video
to help support the company meeting.
And that video,
which is showing influencers playing the game,
worked really well.
and was received so well we decided,
you know what, we're gonna use it when we announce our,
we hit a 20 million user mark,
and that was in the beginning of November.
But to me, this was the turning point actually
for how we started thinking about what was the tonality,
what was, this is where we really started to find our voice
for the Battle Royale brand.
So I'm gonna show you the 20 million video,
but remember it actually was created
about three or four weeks before this video
came out to the public as part of a company meeting.
Yeah, so the company meeting version just didn't have all those slates.
It was just the trail of the influencers on a reel.
So when I say turning point, this video is different.
It has this feeling, sense of just the sheer joy.
There's almost this sort of playful aspect
to what was going on and how much fun people
were having with the game as opposed to being
more focused on the sort of core
and the competitive side on it.
Immediately after this one we started to pivot and started to change the way we were thinking about it.
And we came out with a new video for
something called the bush in the game, this is something you hide inside of.
It's consumable, you pick up, you hide yourself as a bush.
So it started to shift the way we presented
the game to the players. So let's take a peek at that.
OK, really short, quick, it's because it's for one of these updates that we do.
We made that video, but you can tell it's starting to become different than the earlier
videos from before when we were more serious about it.
And so for the full evolution of feeling what the progression was like, let's look at what
the most recent video is like.
This is for C4.
So that pretty much sums up where the brand sort of evolved to as far as the way we were talking about it and presenting it to players and you know largely driven by the way that they were reacting to the game itself.
I have a couple more VR videos that I think are interesting.
The next one is 50 v 50.
What's interesting about this is that we launched it
at the VGA Awards.
I don't want to say launched it literally.
When Donald Muster went up on stage to talk at the VGA Awards,
the moment he went on stage, we threw a switch.
And this mode, he demoed the video you're about to see.
And the mode went live at the time,
because we have a little bit of a flair for the dramatic.
And the mode just was incredibly popular.
It did really well.
It's going down.
I should mention that if you're not familiar with the battle royale, typically it's played
100 players going down to either one single person or single squad.
This particular mode allowed the 100 players to be split into 2 groups.
50 v 50.
And the battle was whichever was the last man standing on one side of the 50.
And of course we've recently come out on mobile.
Sorry if you guys haven't been following that.
So here's the trailer we've been using for a mobile.
In this case, we were, it's funny,
the engine is so good at rendering,
and the mobile version looked really good on screen.
We had to be really careful that people,
when we were visually showing what was happening,
understood it was actually on a phone,
and they weren't just seeing yet another Fortnite video.
Oh, here we go.
By the way, if any of you are curious, we are doing this as an invite event on iOS only
because it's mainly about us wanting to throttle our CCO.
We're so popular, we're very careful about how many people inside the game so we don't
overstress the servers.
All right, let's talk back to this timeline and what I consider actually the real purpose
of today's talk.
So if you look at this, you start to think about, well, why?
Why would we scale this down to such a short time frame,
concentrate that marketing to happen in a very narrow window
versus other companies which will do it over a much,
much longer period of time?
And I'm not saying they're wrong.
It clearly works.
That's how all the big major publishers launch their games,
and they are clearly successful.
For us at Epic, though.
We're sort of an engineering driven culture,
and a lot of this comes down to just the basic logic
behind what's going on, and the basic theories
and principles being applied.
That's why I'm saying that for a lot of you indie developers,
if you think about a lot of the principles,
that's what you really ought to be thinking about
when you're trying to do marketing.
And you see those basics I have down there,
is just gain awareness, communicate key benefits,
have some call to action.
It's really all it ultimately boils down to.
It's not about time, it's not about scale,
it's not about how big your marketing programs are.
Yeah, a lot of you can't pull off, even we pulled off.
But as long as you're focusing on those elements,
you can do similar kinds of things tailored to yourself.
Now, for those long periods of time
that major publishers do it,
and I think they'll continue to do it,
A lot of it is driven by the fact, in my mind, that historically retail has been such a huge portion of their programs.
And it became a way for them to get a lot of retailer excitement and interest in the game in advance.
They could start planning their retail merchandising programs, they could have big orders for selling at launch,
they could have big signage, they could have lots of SKUs on the shelves when they launched.
But from a consumer standpoint, it doesn't really mean anything to know
something 12 or 18 months out in advance.
Do you think our cinematic came in three weeks before was any less effective
than somebody who saw a cinematic 12 or 18 months before?
because we weren't really retail focused other than the gearbox element of it,
and we're more digitally oriented in our sales,
it wasn't relevant to us about driving a lot of retailer interest.
So a lot of things that other companies would take into account,
we didn't, chose not to take into account,
because we thought from a user standpoint that really wasn't...
meaningful and we wanted to be as impactful with the resources we had in terms of the launch.
So that's part of the why we concentrated it down so tightly.
So you can see we had a lot of the same ingredients
that big publishers use.
We just baked it in kind of a different way,
tailored to our needs.
And in my mind, that's part of what
I would hope you guys look at when you're
thinking about your launches.
That if you can just bake it down
in a way that's really specifically designed
for what you're trying to accomplish.
you're going to have a lot more ability to have success within your world.
You don't have to have a huge, huge, huge boost like we did,
but you can still be successful if you just stick to these really core principles
and not be as obsessed with some of the templates or the recipes that,
that a lot of the other companies follow. All right. Well,
we're question and answer period. But before we do that,
I got a one other call out. Kylie, can you stand up?
This is Kylie.
Now, I just walked through a marketing presentation
for how we think about things at Epic.
If any of you out there are in marketing
or know folks in marketing that think
they might like this kind of approach, we are hiring.
So please reach out to Kylie after the presentation
and we'd be happy to entertain any application you have.
All right, who's got a question?
Hi, I'm a big fan of the Save the World game.
I thought the Twitch integration you guys did for Save the World was really interesting.
Just wondering if you could kind of talk more about that, what your goals for that were?
Do you feel like it was effective?
Yeah, for the Twitch integration?
Yeah, prior to that we hadn't done as much with Twitch.
We had been focusing primarily on YouTubers.
And, you know, frankly our videos on YouTube are astronomically high these days in particular.
But with Twitch...
It was... And if you guys have followed our own...
You know, like the... Even for Battle Royale,
we only broke into the top 10 in the last...
four months, or three or four months with any regularity.
We didn't start off that high, it just sort of built over time.
But for Twitch, it was really a way for us...
It was a neat trick, in a sense, being able to pull it off.
But for us, it was really more about building
that relationship with the streamers
and having something fun for them to do
and to work with them.
And that sort of partnership we try to have
with the influencers is a big component
of what we're trying to pull off.
It was a little bit gimmicky to actually to what we did.
So will we do it again?
Sure, if we would do it again as long as, you know,
the influencers wanted to get behind it and do it
and work with us on it, so we'd be happy to.
But this is sort of an example of where we consider this
more of a partnership.
And frankly, if it hadn't gotten a lot,
much traction from the influencers,
they don't want to, aren't as eager to participate,
of course we could pay for it,
we could buy for it if we wanted to.
We probably wouldn't have done it.
I was always curious if the monetization system in Fortnite was mainly created so that you
could market a soft launch in the Western audiences by having a paid-for game and then
going free-to-play for the Asian markets.
Was that a consideration at all in any of this?
No, not at all.
We are, by the way, should I be repeating these questions or is it okay?
It's okay?
Did they say to repeat them or not?
Yeah, repeat them.
All right.
Let me repeat it as best I can.
You tell me if I'm saying it wrong.
You're asking about the monetization system
and whether we were strategically
thinking long term about the Asian implications of us
doing it this way.
Well, first off, some of you may know that we are,
Tencent is a large equity owner, has a large equity
stake within Epic.
We consult with them regularly.
They're well aware of everything we're doing.
They give us plenty of advice.
We don't always take it.
But there's a lot of close collaboration with it.
I can unequivocally say no.
We were not considering the Asian implications
of anything we were doing as far as the monetization system
was going at the time.
When we do get to the point that we're extrapolating...
going free to play and making a bigger push into Asia.
We may have a separate approach for what happens in Asia.
Unlike Battle Royale, we might have unique clients around it,
but it wasn't part of our thinking at all.
Thank you.
Hello. So an important part for the strategy for Fortnite is to pay a lot of attention about the trailers.
If you have to share a little bit more details for us, when we should produce the trailer,
what kind of important points we have to pay attention to when we did the trailer?
What's the major point?
Okay.
Yeah, the question is about for the trailers we did,
about what we considered important for building it in,
and was there a question about timing too?
I wasn't certain.
Yeah, it's right.
Okay, so help me.
I showed you a lot of different trailers, quote-unquote.
For the launching, for example.
Go on, okay.
So, the two trailers, one was the cinematic
and one was the gameplay trailer, right?
Again, we did this, so we started seven weeks in advance for the gameplay and then three weeks for the cinematic.
Having gone through this experience once...
If we got, tried to do this again,
I might try to do it over four weeks.
I don't know if even seven weeks we needed necessarily.
It's really about trying to build as much of a bang
as you can in a short amount of time
while it's still top of mind to the people.
So that's about the awareness part, right?
So it's the awareness, it's communicate a key benefit,
and then this call to action.
I think that with,
It depends on what you're trying to accomplish.
You remember when we did that long form gameplay trailer?
We had specifically, we were trying to convey depth.
There were a lot of what was happening in the game,
and also that explaining some of the complexity of the game.
So we went out of our way to go deeper into it,
knowing that we could have made that more brief,
we could have made it tighter, we could have made it sexier, more entertaining,
but it really wasn't the point of that particular trailer.
And we did cut one that was 30 to do that part of it.
The cinematic trailer was solving it for a completely different issue.
The cinematic trailer was, yes, it's telling narrative and telling some of the backstory,
which we felt was important, particularly what was essentially an RPG, but it was also a...
clear feeling of quality.
There's something about that trailer that just says,
oh this is a quality game.
This is a very well crafted,
a lot of thoughts gone into this.
And look how much care and effort
they put into this trailer and that halo effect
would probably spill over to what we were doing
with the product.
So I can't give you a specific answer to your situation
other than to say,
just try to think of a tiny handful of things
that you think are really important
that someone needs to know.
and sort of boil it down into whatever you put in that trailer.
I can't tell you how many times that I've seen trailers from other companies or indies that come out
that to me are, they're overdone, they're trying to do too much.
Just pick a few simple things and make them important and big
because people just can't remember if you do a lot of stuff inside them.
So just stay simple, that's the other advice I would give.
Thank you.
Okay, sure.
Hey Ed, thanks a lot for sharing the insights.
My name is Gene, I'm with Starladder.
Well, I'm a little bit skewed since I see the world
and gaming through competition mainly,
but that's the question.
For me, it's a no brainer that in the marketing campaign
for this particular game,
there should have been some kind of an element of competitive play.
Hey, you've got a team, compete, there is a ladder.
There's all sorts of different things, you know, play one team versus another team.
And I'm just curious why you didn't use that thing,
eSports and competitive play for launching the game.
And is there on the books somewhere plans to include that thing in the Fortnite?
The question is, why didn't we use eSports as a marketing lever during the launch?
Specifically for Battle Royale, obviously Save the World, we couldn't have done that.
But for Battle Royale, and then what is the future for the game for eSports?
On the first topic, remember we built this thing in...
Two months I would say that it was it took everything we had
just to get a PV period component in.
On the topic of eSports, obviously it's very big, it's very topical,
but to us that's a major, major undertaking.
It requires a great deal of thought.
We could never possibly, for where we were at that moment in time,
been even a remote consideration for the actual launch.
We are doing things with, you know, we do have some custom servers going off.
At E3 we are going to effectively have a Pro-Am tournament.
But as far as the future on the eSports stuff,
it's something that's under discussion and we're not really ready to talk about it yet.
Okay.
Thanks.
So you had a lot of different videos and you had some for really small events like just releasing the C4 and stuff like that.
I'm wondering if there's any consideration for over saturation of videos
or is it just like as many as you can crank out that makes sense?
Yeah, that's a great question.
I mean you could ask a similar question about basically our content cadence because the videos are tied to the content.
The more recent ones, like the C4 are coming soon.
Whenever something new is coming into the game we make a video.
Now, they're relatively short.
So they don't take a lot up from that.
But I think the audience has begun to expect them and assume that there will be something.
It helps us shape the personality of the game somewhat by doing them.
Just actually putting something C4 inside of the game, that's...
If you think about it, that's such a dry idea.
It's just an explosive piece, so there's nothing really...
inherently entertaining about that.
So we build an entertaining little vignette around it
to just help with some of the more
the branding and personality.
You could find C4 in a lot of different games,
but I don't know if it would jump out at you the way
that we could really do it without one.
Again, as far as the Cadence goes, they're pretty short.
If they were really long, I think you'd be right,
but these are pretty short and meant to live for that week
that that new item's out.
I think that they don't have a long shelf life.
I don't think that weeks later,
and it really runs back, and we'll go back
and look at our bush video at the time.
So the nature of Epic is such that we can make videos pretty quickly,
like the C4 or the Bush video, things like that,
we can do in less than two weeks with our video team.
So it doesn't require a lot of effort on our part,
but we think we're pretty good at it,
so we just like to sort of exploit it since we consider it a competitive strength.
Hi, I'm Shiloh from China, from a game company.
Usually the marketing department always focuses on the...
They know the newest trend and information from the marketing.
And R&D department always focuses on the game.
So, which department first decided to change the gameplay of Fortnite?
The question is how basically,
where inside the company,
I'm guessing you're talking about Battle Royale.
Why you put it in.
Where inside the company the ideas for,
that led to us doing the PvP Battle Royale mode came from?
There's a third area in our company
beside the two you mentioned.
You're effectively in a Western parlance
would have been describing marketing,
publishing and development.
product development and an epic and that's a strategy team.
And so there are people that focus more on strategic issues
and they do spend a lot of time looking at trends
and a whole variety of factors that are considering.
The actual germ of the idea really came more from the strategy side.
But it was just immediately adopted by everyone.
We really badly wanted to have a PvP version inside of the game.
So it didn't take a lot of discussion for senior management to decide,
it's like, okay great, no brainer, you got a PvE game, you're a multiplayer,
let's go make a PvP component to it.
So everyone in your company just decided to change to PvP mode, right?
Well, change, add. We didn't change.
Oh, you mean add, yes.
We added it to the game, yes.
All right, thanks.
Hi, can I help you?
Hi, so my question is about...
how did you guys picture who your players were
back when you first started developing the game?
And then, who do you sort of see them as now,
and how did you go through that transition
of understanding your players, your player base,
from the beginning and who they are now?
And then also, is that different
for Save the World versus Battle Royale?
That's a great question. The question is about how we were gauging the essentially the characteristics or demographics of the user base for what was.
Save the world until we decided to launch the battle royale mode and then became battle royale as well.
We have a, basically we were doing a series of closed beta
slash closed alpha tests leading up to the launch.
And we were periodically either having focus groups
or sending out questionnaires and
And querying the user base basically about what they liked and what they didn't like.
And we had a series of these over time that happened.
So we got a very strong sense over time of how the game was evolving.
How the player base was adjusting to how we were evolving the game.
And it really was just a lot of time spent talking to them as we went through that.
When we know that, you know, we have a kind of a fanciful kind of cartoony look that's kind of fun,
but at the same time the game is kind of serious in terms of gameplay.
It's got a lot of very, very deep systems inside of it that harken back to, you know, just big, big RPGs.
So we knew that we were appealing to a blend of people who wanted RPGs,
as well as people who wanted something sort of mass-market,
you know, pick up and play to some degree.
And, you know, I mentioned that we're still early access.
We still don't consider it finished.
We still think we've got a lot of work to do on the game to get it to the proper state.
So that's evolving all the time.
Battle Royale as a free separate mode, I mean, it's obviously exploded and become huge.
Yeah, we have a certain percentage that will play Save the World and we're happy with that,
but a large percentage of them will probably never play Save the World,
because it's just not the kind of game they like to play.
They're really into playing competitive shooters and that's all they want to do, which is fine.
It's fine for them.
So for them, they do have a very different demographic characteristic as far as how they interact and how we think about them as well.
Right now they're so lopsided in terms of their size and it's so big that it's sort of dominant.
It's interesting, I didn't really talk about it.
too much in my presentation, but if you think about it,
we are in a very interesting branding position
because we have this, what is called Save the World.
And by the way, we didn't call it Save the World
until Battle Royale came out.
Until Battle Royale came out, it was just Fortnite.
There was no notion, the word Save the World didn't exist,
but we had to create it because of Battle Royale came out
so we could distinguish between the two.
So and we got to do some branding you know tidying up about the brand hierarchy because it's a little bit a walk because of
coming out with that rail.
But we effectively treat them as all part of this sort of fortnight family with with some adjustments for whether it's
dealing with the P.V.E. save the world or whether it's dealing with the battery.
I'm not certain I answer your questions as close as I can get to it.
I think there's one additional element there that I was more curious about, which is
what is that type of person who is interested in battle royale?
Is that the kind of person who's sitting down and playing 40 hours a week,
who's like, I want to be the best and be the most competitive type player?
I get what you're saying.
No, first of all, you can't get to the size we're at
if you're just too tightly focused as you describe.
We are kind of...
pop culture and mainstream at this point.
We know that we have a broad range of people playing
in terms of ages and also in terms of sexes.
There's lots of women that play Battle Royale.
So I'd say, it's funny, as a marketer,
I love to actually drill down to very specific demographics,
but it's pretty broad, it's pretty wide.
We are just so large, we have to,
it can only be explained by something that sort of
transcends a lot of what you're describing
as far as those segmentations.
Alright. Thank you.
Alright.
You're up.
It seems like there's an opportunity to leverage Battle Royale to get more players into Save
the World.
So for example, in Save the World you have three different tiers that you can purchase.
And the $150 tier has this really badass ninja that I can't use in Battle Royale.
And it seems like maybe to get people more embedded in the Save the World game you could
offer quests or things that you can unlock in Battle Royale for playing a certain amount
of...
I don't know.
save the world gameplay.
Right, right.
The question is about whether or not we will be
or should be doing more cross mode itemization or mechanics
or reasons for going back and forth between the two.
And we do do a little bit.
Some of the skins exist in both of them.
It's something we talk about periodically.
And I'm happy to bring it up again, by the way,
with the dev team.
The specific one you refer to is what's inside the high impact.
I don't think we've talked about that one quite some time, so we probably would.
We don't have a fundamental philosophy on this at this time.
We do worry a little bit about the confusion that happens between the two.
And sometimes when we have done things that they cross between the two, we've gotten feedback
that people got confused about what that meant or whether it was or wasn't.
So it's something I don't have a good answer for you because we haven't.
decided what a good answer is on that one.
And I was curious about, so last year I remember reading a story about Bluehole commenting
on your Battle Royale event, or game mode rather, launching, and I was curious if you
saw a huge increase of player numbers due to the free publicity?
I don't know if I should comment on that one directly,
but I think you guys are welcome to go pull up
something called Google Trends if you want to,
and go look and plug in a few key terms
around the time of what you describe,
and you can draw your own conclusions.
Fair enough, thanks.
Any more questions?
All right, we're running out of time,
so thank you very much.
Again, remember to come talk to Kylie
if you'd like to talk with us about marketing.