Are we good? Can you hear me? Am I on? Bueller? Bueller? Okay.
Good day. How do you do, fellow kids?
Thank you so much for coming to these Life is Strange, the Blue Age of Storytelling.
I feel like my voice is a little extra crispy loud, but that's just my paranoia and nervousness.
Thank you for coming to this panel on Life is Strange, what I call the Blue Age of Storytelling.
My name is Christian Devine. I was the head writer for the game Life is Strange
published by Square Enix and produced by the amazing Dontnod Entertainment.
I'm giving myself a few get out of UM jail free cards.
So that's just, if you hear an UM, it just means I passed off one of those cards.
Um...
So let's start, let's start from the beginning.
And, uh...
Because we're talking about a narrative and dramatic structure, the talk is going to be basically broken down into three acts.
Act one is the...
Intro where I'll talk about myself, background, how I came to work for Life is Strange.
Act two we're going to go into an actual anatomy of the scene.
We're going to take a major scene from Life is Strange and analyze it and show the levels
of writing and design and POV that went into it and maybe how all these different characters
choreographed creates a really strong emotional scene and a strong narrative scene.
And the final act is called the Feel Simulator.
And we'll talk a bit about the emotional response to Life is Strange.
And the unexpected to us emotional response, even though that's what we hoped for.
And how maybe we did that and maybe how we didn't do that.
And so, first off, my dad was, I'll start from the background.
This is G-Force, gotcha man.
No, I love these pants here because they're so 70s.
It's hilarious.
That's me on the far right.
My dad was in the military, so I'm what's known in America
as a military brat, meaning we moved around constantly
because my dad served in Vietnam.
And when he was in Vietnam, we were just at different bases.
I was born in New York, so we'd go from New York to Florida to South Carolina, Wyoming,
Columbus, all over Monterey.
I was born with one hand, what the doctors at the time called a congenital birth defect.
There's no real...
Reason or explanation, I don't ask for any sympathy or even barely empathy.
Because of course, everybody knows us, everybody's got their own shell on their back.
Either it's an exterior shell or it's an interior shell.
And we all carry the shell with us.
And mine just happens to be exterior.
And early on, I learned that I was different.
And I learned early on that I had to be smarter and better.
prepared to deal with society because they're always going to be like,
oh, oh, poor baby, oh, you can't do this, oh.
I can do everything but juggle.
And fortunately, it just does not come up.
And since Donald Trump is not going to become president,
I don't have to worry about juggling.
Just letting you know as an ambassador from America.
And one of the most important things I learned very early on,
my brother Scott was a big influence on me because he was a few years older
and I was always the, where you going, where you going, where you going,
which he loved.
But he was the cultural influence on me and so he exposed me to all the cool cultural
things that I needed to be exposed to as a kid.
And Bruce Lee was one of my early heroes and Bruce Lee's quote, one of my favorite quotes
is make your disadvantage your advantage.
And that's what I learned early on about my arm.
you know you you use whatever you have it if it's not
perfect take that and try to apply it
to in the system and make it work for example I will use Life is Strange an
example
Life is Strange obviously was not a triple-a game didn't have the big budget
but it's very lo-fi and so instead of trying to compete
with massive photo realism and incredible graphics
they use a totally different art style, a painterly, very beautiful, handcrafted art
style
and it's a lo-fi aesthetic but it works and it fits the aesthetic of the
game
and I think in
what's going on right now in gaming is that
you're gonna have all these new areas of aesthetic coming in
because it's a very young industry.
We're very, it's 30 years old when you look at it.
And if you compare that to the film industry
or literature, anything,
you can see what a very small timeline that is.
And so, but the acceleration is very rapid of technology.
And I think technologically we're there.
I mean, games, I mean, VR is the next thing,
but boy, graphically to go from Pong to WoW
is pretty incredible in only a 30 year period.
So this is a map of Rockland, California.
It's pure suburbia.
Oh, wait a minute.
That's actually the back cover of the Rush album, Signals.
Because the song Subdivisions was a defining album in my life
because one of the lines of the song Subdivisions is,
nowhere is the misfit or the dreamer more alone.
And that's a feeling that every artist has, or anybody who wants to go beyond feels.
So culturally, I consider myself a media baby.
And I sponged up everything as a kid.
I was a huge Godzilla fan, a huge monster movie fan.
When I was a kid, I wanted to be an animator.
Ray Harryhausen was one of my heroes, so I dreamed of being a stop-motion animator.
And I did a lot of stop motion, but I realized, boy, you really need a lot of discipline.
And it's not a field that there's a huge amount of people that I can succeed in.
And I moved on to drawing and art.
Jack Kirby is my new god in terms of artist.
And you can see Kirby's work today.
I mean, the Marvel Universe all came from Jack Kirby.
Stan Lee did write it, but Jack Kirby created everything.
And the power of that mythos and the power of that myth-making, you know, really influenced me.
Early on my brother gave me Martian Chronicles by Ray Bradbury that changed my life
I love Bradbury's writing because I was never into hard
I read the hard science fiction, but I was never I didn't really care about how the rocket ship worked and neither did Ray Bradbury
He was like they get in a rocket ship. They fly to Mars
That's it. That's the science of Ray Bradbury.
So there was a poetry to his fantasy, but his bent was more social issues and
how people deal with the future with their own morality.
Dandelion Wine, romantic, October country,
the darkness of the melancholy of October
that Bradbury is so beautiful at.
And growing up, Judy Blume was a huge influence on me.
She's a very, do you know who Judy Blume is out there?
She's the most famous young adult author in America
all up until recently.
She's still famous.
And she's the first young adult author
to actually present issues of bullying
and what you go through, puberty,
and in an honest way.
Her books are very controversial.
They're often banned.
Blubber was a very successful, very controversial book
about a.
a young girl who's picked on enormously because of her weight.
It's an incredibly cruel, mean book.
Not because she's cruel and mean,
because kids are cruel and mean.
And she just...
We love these books because these were our classmates.
And when I was 10 years old,
I saw this movie called Star Wars.
And Star Wars...
You know, I hate to say, yeah, it changed my life,
but yeah, Star Wars changed my life.
Because when I sat in that theater and the Star Destroyer went overhead, the entire audience cheered.
Now one thing we don't quite have anymore in movies is this communal feeling.
Yes, people applaud and they laugh and they cheer, but Star Wars brought back this immense audience involvement.
So the entire time people are cheering and laughing.
and literally almost standing on their seat.
And I don't think anybody today can quite imagine
that response.
And it was a very typical audience response.
So the moment that Luke Skywalker goes out
and looks out the binary sunset,
that is a brilliant myth-making moment.
Lucas didn't even really know what he was doing
in that moment, because that's the moment that he's saying
to every dreamer, every artist that's looking out there,
like, where is my place?
Where am I going?
And I at that point I said I'm going somewhere. I want to be an artist and I'm heading out towards that future
Now one of my other heroes is Jean Cocteau, who's a French artist, very famous French artist.
And he always said that art is a marriage of the unconscious and the conscious.
Meaning that when you're creating art, you need to be relying...
You can't be analytical because you just won't get far.
And that's why most people stop writing.
They're like, oh, well I was writing but I had to...
I keep editing, which is what I started doing.
But no, you have to let the shit out.
You cannot edit it.
You wait till afterwards to be analytical.
So you have to be really pure about that.
And my influences are so great.
And when I'm talking about the blue age of storytelling,
I'm kind of talking about a cultural change that we had.
I was a huge anime fan, obviously Gatchman, big influence, Captain Harlock.
And of course, satire, Mad Magazine.
For me, Mad Magazine taught me very early on not to trust anything I saw.
And I still don't. It's just how I am.
you know that there's a lot of manipulation going and I'm very
also as a writer I'm very aware of how things work a bit so I'm very like
I make sure that I'm I'm checking everything. Of course
you know I became a huge fan of Monster magazines
H.R. Giger
All these weird influences really created me.
Fantasy books, Conan and heavy metal when I started hitting puberty.
I'm like, oh, oh, there's some naked bodies in here and violence.
Cool.
And I also grew up with John Romero.
He was my best friend since 10 years old.
And we were.
a couple of really mean kids in terms of what we were doing artistically
because we start breaking the rules.
And National Lampoon Magazine broke all these scary rules.
And this is a page from a story called Boy's Wrath by John Hughes
who later created Breakfast Club and Sixteen Candles.
But before he was John Hughes, he was writing the most merciless,
terrifying stories about suburban youth.
And we kind of all intook that.
Ian Fleming, James Bond, huge influence on me.
And then, of course, games.
Monopoly, for some reason, I was obsessed with as a kid.
I don't know why.
I always wanted Baltic Avenue and Mediterranean.
I would get hotels on there and go bankrupt within, you know, two plays.
And Donkey Kong really changed my life.
A, I love the name Donkey Kong.
It's the two weirdest words put together ever and it fits perfectly.
And me and John would spend hours in the arcade.
I'd turn the Donkey Kong machine over
and I was instantly always huge in arcade games
and always attracted to the visual and even the narrative qualities.
Like, oh, come on, Mario, get up there, get up there.
And then, when I was about 12, I started reading about Dungeons & Dragons and fantasy magazines
and the back of counterculture magazines, and I didn't know, wow, this is like a board game,
but you get to have narrative, you get to talk and have dialogue and essay characters.
And so Dungeons & Dragons is the biggest storytelling influence on me, and it really taught me...
story in a way because when you're sitting at the table you have to
really come up with things because it's all built around
players decisions and you don't know what you may have a map you may have a guy
but you don't know what the players are going to do so
it really taught me to think about story and narrative and then I could a say all
the roles of the characters and
It was just a huge influence on me, and even games like Car Wars by Steve Jackson, which I totally adore.
This is not a picture of me and my friends, but it sure could be.
It's pretty much the archetypal picture of all the kids, you know, playing D&D in the day.
And as a writer, I started...
The first script I ever read was Alien.
And this is the scene right here.
This is the original description of the alien coming out of Kane's chest.
And I absolutely was fascinated by the writing style.
If you look at it, it's dot, dot, dot, dot.
And Walter Hill rewrote Dan O'Bannon's script.
And Walter Hill, who wrote The Warriors and Forty Hours and a lot of films,
he had a really amazing screenwriting style.
It's kind of like a haiku.
and just a red stain, then a smear of blood blossoms, the fabric of his shirt is ripped open, the crew shouts in panic.
You know, it's just, bop bop bop bop.
And Ridley Scott read the script in half an hour.
He wanted to do it immediately just because of the way the script was written, so that was a big influence.
And of course Stephen King, when I read The Shining...
blew me away and terrified me and I was a huge Stephen King fan
and I read everything.
Harlan Ellison taught me how to question and stand up for myself as a kid
because he's a very famous writer.
Harlan Ellison wrote the most famous episode of Star Trek,
the original Star Trek called The City on the Edge of Forever,
which is referenced in Life is Strange, of course.
Kirk has to go back in time and he falls in love.
In order to change time, he has to let the woman he loves die.
So it's the best episode of Star Trek and it's my favorite.
you
Ignore Ayn Rand's politics, but her writing to me was amazing and her writing style changed my life because she had a really beautiful way of
encapsulating ideas and emotion and
in a way that I never read anybody do before.
And I highly advise you, if you're interested in just dialogue,
just to read her dialogue.
Ignore her politics.
But just read what she's writing,
because it's truly amazing writing.
William Gibson, huge fan,
because he was the first person to predict the cyberspace,
where we're at now.
It's an amazing achievement.
My first published, the first time I was ever published in a magazine was Fangoria.
The first time the Evil Dead was ever mentioned in any media.
So I'm very proud that my, it was for a Draw the Thing contest from John Carpenter.
So I made it to one of the 100 finalists out of 4,000 entries.
And that also said, I said, huh, maybe I have something going on here.
Maybe I can, maybe there's a, maybe there's a way for me in this world.
I'm a big fan of Marshall McLuhan talking about the media because the media is somewhat of my subtext.
And I believe that a lot of my viewpoints are filtered through what goes on in the media.
And I also believe it's the most powerful force in the world outside of politics.
It does change and transforms people's lives and it hypnotizes them and inspires them.
And so all of these cultural influences, I always say nothing is wasted.
It doesn't hurt to have every arrow in your quiver.
Don't think anything that you do, like, oh, I'm interested in this, but I'm interested in that.
You never know where that one thing that you think is not going to mean anything is going to come up and actually mean something.
So let's get a bit to what I call the Blue Age.
Now the New Age, it was the term from the 60s and 70s, this holistic movement that was a response against Western kind of imperialism and capitalism,
and it led to this holistic spiritual movement in the 70s and 80s, and then strangely enough led to Yanni and record stores.
Next to Tangerine Dream, where does not Yanni and Tangerine Dream do not belong together, Brian Eno.
I'm a huge, huge ambient instrumental music fan, so...
But, to me, we're moving...
I realized quickly, early on...
I mean, blue is the color of cool.
It's the color of monitors.
It's the color of the screen.
The primary color in Blade Runner is blue.
and the first Apple ad, blue.
And I got the first Macintosh
and it transformed my writing life instantly
because I was writing on typewriters
and I could write on a typewriter but I did not want to.
It took forever and to correct something you had to go into it.
So when the computer came along, I was all over this.
It changed my writing life and I was like,
okay, I can instantly delete and correct
and I got the first screenwriting software
and I started writing.
I got the first Sony Handycam.
And the night that I actually came up with the phrase,
the Blue Age, I was looking through the lens,
I was having an epiphany,
maybe under controlled substances or not, I'm not saying,
but you don't question where epiphanies come from.
But I realized that the future
was gonna be through monitors.
And when you walk down the street,
what's the color you see from all the rooms?
Blue, blue, blue, light, blue, light, blue, light,
people looking down, blue, light, blue, light,
blue, light, blue, light.
So we're moving into this POV of screens and mirrors and reflection and refraction.
And by the way, this theory is just theory.
Theory is theory. It's not canon.
You can say this guy's full of shit and that's okay because it's just a theory.
I went to Berkeley, so I was saying this is full of shit about all sorts of theories.
But I love learning them because I do think it adds.
When I was 25, that was my 64th Cadillac.
I needed to change my life because I knew I wanted to be an artist, but I realized that I wasn't going forward.
I wasn't moving in the direction that I needed to move into.
And so I went back to school. I changed my life completely.
Moved down to Southern California, enrolled back in school.
You know, I thought I had some raw talent, but I had no discipline.
And I won, I entered it, but the first writing thing I ever entered was a national play contest.
And I ended up being one of the 100 finalists out of 5,000 people.
And that was literally the sign that I was looking for from the universe, like,
okay, I'm, I'm, maybe, maybe this will happen.
When I went back to school, it was wonderful. I had great teachers, they inspired me, and they taught me.
The best thing I learned about school is the platonic knowledge, is know when you don't know.
And I use that rule to this day. Just know when you don't know. It's okay to not know.
There's nothing wrong with that. You'll learn, or you'll figure it out, or you won't. It's okay.
And then, while I was at Berkeley...
John Romero, who had already of course become John Romero through Doom, called me up and
said the magic words, hey do you want to come write for my new game?
And I said, let me think about it, I'll think about it.
And then my apartment burned down and I was in Texas a week later.
So life worked out.
We can talk about die katana and ion storm on another lecture
That's a whole other story, but it was an amazing experience
I learned a lot about game development working with the team and also
it was a very early indicator because the online world was still very early in of how
Very toxic the online world could be when it didn't like something and I never forgot that moment
I still have not forgot that moment
And then at a certain point, Hollywood came a-calling for my scripts, and so I moved to Los Angeles
and started selling scripts and optioning scripts and writing for games
and writing for everybody who wanted me to write for them.
And it was wonderful because you're working through this entire system.
And this is one of my... Every screenwriter has the dream of being in a variety.
And when I optioned my script, 18 Will Butterfly...
Evan Rachel Wood signed on board to play the lead.
And Michael Polish, a director, who happened to go to my same high school in Rockland along with John,
ended up attaching himself as a director.
So, from there, I've been thinking, like, God, I really want to get back into games.
I've been missing... I kind of left the game world in a way because I thought, like,
it was a little bit stagnant and it needed new blood.
It also needed to go through growing pains. It was a little bit too...
it was just a little bit too boyish, let's put it that way.
And I was waiting for that changeover to come,
and then when my friend David Calbo, a French writer,
who is my... it's always good to have a French cheerleader,
he had heard they were looking for a writer for this new game,
and so he recommended me.
And I ended up connecting with Michelle, the co-director.
and they sent over the menu and some clips from the game.
And this is the first thing I saw from Life is Strange,
with the menu moving and that little piece of music.
And I knew immediately. I knew immediately.
I said, this is awesome. I get it. I get it.
I don't even know what the game's about.
I get what they're doing. I get the tone they're going for.
And Brenda Romero, who on the faculty invited me to speak here today,
she said, well you should, you know, for your test, because every game company
gives you a test usually, and the tests are not always
indicative of what you can do as a writer. It's like, describe the scepter.
Okay. There's only so many ways you can describe a scepter.
But for Twine, anybody using Twine at all?
I highly recommend it.
Just in terms of building story blocks.
And when I started using it, I was like, wow,
this is like narrative Legos.
What a great phrase, narrative Legos.
I was so proud of myself when I watched a GDC lecture
with Ken Levine talking about narrative Legos
from like two years earlier.
That's OK, great minds.
And so you can see, this is the branching dialogue
of the Twine.
and you can see the level, how detailed and how many it goes up.
And that's part of the problem with branching dialogue for people is
you have to think not only just one linear, you have to think of all the tangents
and that's a trick for some writers.
And that's why a lot of screenwriters don't really do well in games
because they don't quite understand the concept of branching dialogue and how to do it.
But you can see you just, you know, you can see you keep moving in
and it's, you're able to go to...
One here and one here and this is the very first mention of the word Hella.
This is for the test that I gave them.
And they were sold on the word Hella.
So I had a Skype interview.
They loved what I did for the test.
The test was totally not like a test.
It simply felt like it was made for me.
And then two weeks after I took it, I was in Paris.
And Paris was wonderful.
And what's even more amazing, to show you the curve of life,
how strange it is, is that this is Rue Emond,
say this for me please.
Merci.
Who happened to be Jean Cocteau's lover
and one of his mentors.
So the fact that I was actually working on this street,
I just felt like there's no accidents.
And this is just a glimpse of us doing some voice recording in the studio.
This is me letting me, I bugged them, I begged them to let me do a cameo voice
because even though I'm not an actor, I love to ham it up sometimes.
So they let me say the part of Trust Limbo, the radio talk show host.
Does everyone remember that fantastic scene with Trust Limbo?
Okay, yeah, I thought so.
It's right before Nathan has his amazing message.
But it was really, it's a great experience because you get to learn once again.
Everybody should learn how.
voice actors work if you're a writer you need to know you need to be writing for
actors and you need to think about actors and
you need to have respect for actors because it's it's an incredibly hard job
my very last day in paris after writing life is strange for tears i had to take
that famous one last shot in the rain it was sad i
was crying i was feeling i had the feels and the game the first episode had
already dropped and the first night the first episode dropped
Of course I sat down, I was visiting actually my hometown in Rockland where I grew up and I was by myself
and I realized like, oh shit, the entire world is about to judge me.
And it's kind of a scary feeling.
And then when I started watching it, I just was like, you know, you're watching the Twitches, the Twitch streams
and I was...
and I could tell by about 10 o'clock that night, I...
this is not ego by the way, this is just me saying, I just said,
I think it's...
And I just felt really good because I could see people responding to it.
Even the people, you know, and of course there are people that were responding to it negatively.
So the first night I'm watching the chat stream, one of the comments is,
I wish I could go back in time and give the writer's mom an abortion.
Now, you could say that is darkly funny, and I probably would.
It's... I can handle it.
But who does that? Who says that? Why do they do that?
And it made me think, because the point of Life is Strange
is also how the social media bullying affects young people.
And I... of course it would. It's terrible to have to deal with that.
And the scope that young people today have to deal with this,
you know, it's very powerful, and it's psychologically very damaging.
So I was really proud that the game was able to impress upon people,
and we were able to move forward in terms of storytelling,
and deal with these issues, you know, abortion and suicide,
and, you know, just making, busting your friend for weed,
these moral decisions that the game forced you to make.
It was just taking games in a direction that I was just always excited to go for,
and I was so happy and so humbled that...
the fandom and the critical acclaim came next and it was just a really you don't always get that you
don't get that very much and so you're happy if you if you get it at all and we were all overjoyed
to get it you know i said early on i really hope we're gonna get some BAFTAs we got uh five BAFTA
nominations and we won for story and just getting the awards is fantastic it's just it's just
approbation from the community and the fandom
responding to the game and sending us their cosplay and their messages and
people saying that
I was going to kill myself but I played Life is Strange and I decided not to.
It's powerful, it's powerful.
The fans always blame us for giving them the feels,
but I'm like, no, you give us the feels.
That's really what it's all about.
And GDC, earliest year we got the Audience Award,
which is really wonderful.
And for me, one of the great honors we got
was the Peabody Award.
The first Peabody Award for a video game.
The Peabody Award is basically
the electronic communication equivalent of the Pulitzer.
Which I kind of said, boy, I really think
we should get the Pulitzer.
Life is strange.
My ego was not in check at this point.
But we got the Peabody and I got to go to the ceremony and accept it.
And it was really wonderful because I got to tell Jon Stewart and Keegan Key about Life is Strange.
And they were both shh...
Everybody was like,
A video game?
What? Huh? A video game about a Peabody?
Like that's really... Huh? A video game?
Which shows you the mindset that people have about video games.
A couple months ago I got to meet John Carpenter, and he's a huge fan of Don't Nods Remember Me.
So I brought a copy of Life is Strange to have him sign for the team and take a photo,
and we talked about Remember Me, and he said he would play Life is Strange.
So it just shows you how far I came from this point as a child, just wanting to be involved in media,
to actually being involved.
And the best part of the story is when I went back to school later on,
and I was winning some awards for writing,
I ended up being a part of the team.
what meeting ray bradbury and for a contest i'd one and so they asked to
take a picture for us i said next to a bradbury
for some reason he reached out and grab my hand
and he squeeze it for the picture
and i really felt like he was blessing me he was saying i'm giving you some
energy and i i believe in you know you did it though i just felt so like
moved. So that's basically my background and how I came to write for Life is Strange.
Let's segue into the clinical part of the discussion, which is anatomy of a scene.
So we're gonna watch a scene here from Life is Strange. It's it's a
spoiler alert, by the way. Spoiler. This is not a major spoiler, but so you're okay.
But this is a pretty big pivotal scene in the in the third episode.
Hold on, make sure this is okay.
In the third episode, where David Madsen,
the overzealous security guard,
has come back to his house complaining
because two, some punks had broken into the school
the night before.
Those punks were his stepdaughter, Chloe,
and the lead character, Max,
who were looking for clues for the mystery.
So this is a scene where all the characters,
they've been very antagonistic,
and this is kind of the pivotal moment
where Max gets to finally confront David
for being an asshole.
And what I love about the game is that, yes, David's an asshole, but maybe he's not.
And people can decide for themselves how they feel about him or Chloe.
So let's watch the scene and we'll discuss the making of it afterwards.
Let's hope this works.
What happened?
Some little shit-ass punks broke into the swimming pool.
This is what happens at these PC bullshit colleges.
Entitled students taking over the campus.
Do you know for sure it was Blackwell students?
Who else would do it?
And I'm gonna bust them.
Figures you'd be here. Is that your Rachel Amber Halloween costume? You know more about her than me
No, you and Chloe think you know more than anybody like all teenagers
Leave Max alone David stop threatening students
He threatens them with surveillance cameras so he can spy on everybody like he spies on all of us here
Don't start Chloe not now
Yeah, I'm just always starting shit, right?
You're a total paranoid, David.
Not now, Chloe.
You used to call me a loser for getting kicked out of Blackwell.
So who's the loser now, David?
Who haven't you accused or harassed?
Between your investigations into Rachel and Kate,
what have you done besides get in trouble?
We're siding with, uh, Chloe in this one.
You're a bully, David! I saw you harass Kate Marsh when she was going through hell.
You could have totally helped her.
Everybody at Blackwell is a suspect to you, except for Nathan Prescott.
That's why the students and faculty don't like you. You even threatened me.
I do respect your service, but you don't respect anybody.
Uh, you were smoking pot in Chloe's room. That's illegal.
So is spying on people in your family and at your work.
Why do you have photos of Kate Marsh and Rachel Amber in your files anyway?
What? Is this true, Max?
Yes, David. Why do you have these files at all? I find this very disturbing.
I do not have to take this kind of interrogation. Not from you punks.
Maybe you should calm down.
Oh, you're turning on me now, huh? Of course. Women always stick together. Well, screw you.
David.
You better go to a hotel until we figure this out.
You can't kick me out of my own home!
It's my home, David. Paid for and in my name.
You know the law, right?
Oh, I thought I knew a lot of things.
Like when I'm outflanked.
Have a nice day.
Chloe, for once, just please shut up.
I hope Joyce doesn't hate me for tearing into David.
I don't want to see or hear you again, Max.
You've hurt me and my family enough.
Okay, so, what I love, this is actually my favorite scene in the game, and I have a lot of favorite scenes in the game, and the team is so amazing, I mean, what they put together is so incredible, and I was always, always amazed at the work they were doing, the artist, and the musicians, and the directors, and Michelle and Raul, and everybody just firing on all cylinders, and it's not often you get to work on a team where you really feel like,
you're all on the same page, but I really feel like we were all on the same page and
So what I loved about
that scene is
It's just the it's just that Joyce who I feel like is kind of like the most underrated character in the game in a way
And one of my favorite characters
She just doesn't she never really gets the good end of the stick, but she finally gets to tell David
What's what I really love that and I love Mac saying to David I respect your service
But you don't respect anybody because David served in the military
And so that's an important point to make that Chloe does understand that David went through hell
and he's seen horrors that she can't comprehend but
David doesn't mean it gives him the right to hold up his hand to his daughter or anybody.
And my favorite, probably my favorite article that anybody
wrote about Life is Strange was from a lieutenant in Afghanistan
and he said that David Mattson is the best veteran character in the history of video games.
Let's take that. I'll take that as a compliment.
So, as a writer, what I love doing is entering different POVs.
And one of my big writing epiphanies was when I wrote my first script called,
not my first script, but my fourth script called Little Girl Lost.
And it was the first time that I decided to not be Christian Divine.
I was always Christian Divine.
And I was like, God, I'm kind of bored of being Christian Divine.
I'm tired of hearing myself think and talk the same way.
So I thought, let's write from a different point of view.
It's two sisters, two females on the run.
And as a writer, you do write all sorts of different characters.
You know, somebody, you know, I met, I went for a meeting one time
and they said, well, what do you know about writing?
you know, female truck driver. I said, well, I probably know as much as J.K. Rowling does
about a boy wizard. You know, I know as much as Shakespeare knows about two lovers in eternal
love. You know, it's a kind of a silly question because when you're writing, you're, it's
up to the, I mean, you have to convince the viewer, the reader, the audience that you're
convincing them. So, you know, that's the trick. It doesn't mean you can, you can try it,
you can do it. But when you're writing different points of view.
you know I put myself in that character's mindset when I'm writing
David Madsen I'm like you PC entitled college punks and then on a max I'm like
you asshole you don't know anything about the world you know so you you have
to be I like to be fair to all the characters and that point of life is
strange is in fact this kind of empathy for people to look at what they're going
through it doesn't mean you have to say approve of them but you look at what
they're going through
So, that's just an example of how you kind of, you know, put these characters together
and have them, you know, kind of dance around.
Let's go on to this section, the Field Simulator.
So probably the most amazing thing about the game for all of us, I can probably say, is
just the level of emotional response that the players, you know, gave us.
And watching people on Let's Plays and Twitches crying.
I mean, we were writing, we were hoping to give them those emotions, but we, it was hard to believe that,
I don't think anybody knew that we would tap into this, and I'm not sure, I'm still not sure why,
but I think as part of this Blue Age, I think it's because, A, you're, you are involved in Max's
personality, you're playing Max, so you're within that world, so of course you, you, there's a
bonding there within that screen, there's a bonding going on, so I think that's what, what gives you
this kind of emotional connection to the characters.
And so, you know, just once again, just a small example of the outpouring of amazing fan art.
And once again, to me, the greatest tribute for Life is Strange for me is when somebody sends me a picture of them drawing a character in class,
ignoring the teacher, which is exactly what I did.
And John Romero's in front of me coding when I was 15 and I was drawing comics.
And they're drawing Helen, Chloe, so she's got a great future ahead of her, I can already see.
So for this section I want to quickly go through a couple, some clips just to show you maybe how we layer emotional weight within characters.
And they're tangents, they're not necessarily big pivotal emotional scenes, but they're like emotional building blocks and they build up to how you respond to the character.
So this is the introduction of Warren.
So you saw that he reached in for the hug there and he didn't get the hug.
He got the flash drive.
And originally the script just called for Warren to, you know, lean in and kiss
Max on the cheek, but culturally that's, we don't do that in America so common.
And so based on Warren's kind of cringy clinging character.
you know, I thought it's much funnier to do this go for the hug thing and they just nailed the style of it.
So great. But that really, that moment defines Warren for so many people because people are like friendzone.
Okay, now we know friendzone.
So, poor Warren.
And there is a lot of people that really don't like Warren.
And I tend to think some of it is they can certainly not like Warren because of the writing, that's fine.
Or in some ways I think Warren reminds some people too much of themselves, you know, a bit, including me.
But it's okay because, you know, Warren's a teenager and that's how teenagers are sometimes.
So this is what another section this is what they called it what michelle and raul called the z moments where max would sit down
And have these little contemplative moments to think about what's going on
The lighthouse looks so mysterious
I wish I could stay in this moment forever
I guess I actually can now
But then it wouldn't be a moment
I really like that line.
I mean, as a writer, you're your worst critic.
And trust me, I can read Criticism of Life is Strange.
We all do.
And so you're your own worst critic.
And you know what works and what doesn't work for you.
And there are moments that you're writing things that you should be happy for and proud of
because that's kind of what you're doing.
You should like what you're doing.
Hopefully you enjoy whatever you're designing.
writing or drawing. Hopefully you do love what you're doing and you and you pat
yourself on the back once in a while because the world is not going to that
often as an artist. That's just a that's the cautionary and I tell people that.
Get ready. You know you better develop a very thick skin if you're gonna be an
artist because the world doesn't care. They don't care if you write or draw or
paint or design. They just don't care. You have to make them care. That's your job.
And then hopefully they will care. This is another little moment that I really
like.
Why look! An otter in my water.
Dun dun dun dun dun dun dun dun.
You are so obvious.
And I still get freaked out by that movie, so stop.
I can't even watch any of those shark shows.
Now in the script, Michelle and Raul really wanted this.
This is the last moment between Max and Chloe that's really quiet and bonding.
And Michelle and Raul, the directors...
you know, they were very specific about the intent of the scene and what they,
and the emotional level they wanted to create.
And Michelle was like, you know, we want to have them splashing water, you know.
And it's what kids do, everybody does when they jump in the pool.
And I thought, you know, every, there's probably not anybody who doesn't jump
into a pool that doesn't start going dun dun dun dun dun dun.
I mean, it's just, it's, Jaws might be the most.
recognizable musical theme of all time.
There could be an argument made for that.
And it's just a little moment, and then she goes,
I'd only even like to watch those shark shows,
which is a reference to all these endless shark shows
they seem to have on TV in America and I'm sure around the world.
So it's just a cultural, you know, part of the layering of Life is Strange emotionally
is the cultural references.
And just to, it makes people identify.
It helps people like, oh, I know that.
I see that.
I get that.
And not to overdo it.
In a way, because Life is Strange is set in art college,
they are purposely overdone,
because I went to UC Berkeley,
and that's all you do.
You're dropping names all day long.
You're talking pop culture, everything.
So this clip is a moment in an alternate universe
when Chloe is actually in a wheelchair,
and she's talking with Max.
Max.
Thanks for coming out to see me.
You're doing awesome.
I don't think so.
My nose is getting cold.
Maybe we should get back to my place?
It is hella cold out here.
Hella?
I hate that word. No offense.
None taken.
Nobody says hella.
This is something that comes up in the game.
And part of what I was really excited about writing
Life is Strange for, I'm very familiar with
in Pacific Northwest.
I go up to Oregon, Portland, Seattle all the time,
and I'm there all the time.
And as a Northern California boy,
the word hella is probably one of the most
indigenous expressions you'll hear.
And it's been around forever and ever.
And around 2013, I noticed that young people around me
were saying it again.
It was so funny.
I was like, wow, people are saying hella again.
You know, I haven't heard that in a while.
And then when Life is Strange came along, I thought, well, this is perfect for Chloe,
because what you're trying to do when you're writing characters from a certain region,
you can do some research, or if you know, you can put that information in there
and develop and give a kind of realism to the characters, or verisimilitude of realism.
Little did I know that nobody says hella. I had no idea.
And I found the response interesting because I would see in comments say,
well, yes, nobody says hella.
And it's from somebody in London.
I would never assume to tell somebody in London, like, nobody says sus.
Nobody says that.
Nobody says brilliant.
You know, I wouldn't know.
I could research.
I could find out.
But I can't honestly say that I would know how somebody talks elsewhere in the world.
And I certainly don't think teenagers talk in one way.
I know they don't.
And part of what was fun for writing Life is Strange is to...
And, you know, I think the dialogue, whether you like it or you don't,
it's its own... it's different.
It's stylistically... it's true to what the game is.
And so I think in this new blue age of storytelling,
we're going to move towards more and more dialogue that's
more and more like films and literature, which has a whole...
Nobody talks like they do in Reservoir Dogs.
Nobody talks like a Quentin Tarantino character in real life.
Nobody.
But we love the dialogue because it seems true in some ways, and it's clever.
And that's why we go see movies, to see people talking better than we do, or talking in a wittier way than we do.
And if we want naturalism, which I love writing that too, then that depends.
It's the medium, it's the form follows function.
And so I felt very, very satisfied a year later when...
Somehow Merriam-Webster's dictionary added this word,
even though nobody says it.
But they do now.
And I love the fact that around the world,
people are saying hella because of Life is Strange.
That's the best revenge possible.
There's nothing better than that.
And I want to skip this one.
Yeah, I'm going to skip that other one because that's a major spoiler
and I actually don't want to give it away.
And we're coming down to the wire here and I do want to take some questions.
So I'm sorry I rushed through all this.
So it seemed like when Brenda asked me to speak and she said,
you have 45 minutes, I'm like, oh my god, how am I going to fill up that time?
And when I was doing it, I'm like, oh, wait a minute.
I need two hours just to do this.
But so hopefully I've given you just a little insight into what goes into the dialogue writing.
And please, you can contact me on Twitter, online, and talk to me.
I'm always available for questions, and I love answering questions, and I love talking too.
to people. So to sum up briefly, the best gift for me from Life is Strange is not only
the satisfaction of it responding with people around the world, it's just seeing people
trying to take the high road when they make these choices. They don't make fun of Victoria.
They try to get along with her.
they want to always take the high road.
And I was always shocked,
because I would often take the low road.
And so I was very impressed,
and I'm being very genuine here,
is that Life is Strange gives me hope for the future
of young people, it really does.
And people, because I just love seeing people
open up emotionally, as I'm trying not to do right now.
And many people have told me,
and the director of the Peabody said,
you know, Life is Strange is not a game.
You know?
It's it's a photo. That's not even me. It's another thing. I don't know what what's going on with that
Can I could I put that back up there?
Okay
I'm not clicking anything. I'm clicking but nothing's going on
That's fine, you know what it's actually fun because that's the last slide
But basically somebody wrote thank you for the game and the experience.
And of course it's a game.
But the idea that it's so emotionally involving with people
and it seems to take the interactivity of games to this whole other emotional level.
you know, always kind of blew my mind and that to me is the greatest gift of the game.
And when I say the Blue Age, once again, it's just a theory, you know, but I really feel
like we're moving towards this era of reflection, refraction, watching, watching, watching,
experiencing.
I don't know where it's all going.
I'm a writer, so I'm a cautionary writer too.
So I never say everything is all good.
I always say there's a flip side to everything and people should be aware of the flip side
to everything.
Because you have to be aware.
You have to really be aware.
But I'm very aware of the game's success and I'm very grateful for it and I'm really grateful for all you coming today.
So, thank you very much for listening and I love answering questions because then I can riff and not have to look down at all this bullshit.
So, any questions? Please.
I know everybody hates to be the first person. I love the first person to answer. Yeah.
I'm not afraid of that.
First of all, let me just put on that I love,
absolutely love the game.
It was a fantastic experience.
Thank you.
But I was getting into the right in the middle of the game.
So I think the first two or three episodes have been out
and I was still waiting for the next one, next one.
And I felt the fifth one was very different to the rest.
It felt more scripted, very slow work, and very little interactive.
At the end, it made sense, but did you feel the fifth one was kind of different than the rest?
Well, I mean, there's, you know, people talk about this.
Everything was scripted, I mean, nothing was changed.
I mean, everything, when I got the original episodes,
Jean-Luc Canot, by the way, wrote the original story for Life is Strange,
a brilliant writer, and that was built into the...
into the story and when Michelle and Raul and the team put it together
that fifth episode was that's what it was. It was always two choices, it was
always built around you know these things. Now of course you
always wish you had more time and more money to do more things but
what they wanted to do was what was in episode five so I can only speak for
and I and I and it's a it's a different episode because you're kind of wrapping
everything up and you've got to make these amazing decisions so
you know that's all I can say is that it's it's it's exactly what the team intended.
Thank you for asking that question.
Hello.
I wanted to know what was the design intention for the anting?
One was longer than the other.
Was there a preference for one?
No, no, I mean seriously, we all thought, you know, there's no canon.
It's the players, it's your choice.
You decide the canon.
And once again, if, you know, one ending is short because that's the way they wanted it.
You know, it's simply the way it worked out.
And I, you know, that's it.
That's the end.
All right, thank you.
Thank you.
Hi. So I love this game and actually I was really amazed by how I really felt that I made a
relationship with Chloe. Like I really felt that I had this strong friendship with her.
and I want to ask you if you have any advice of how to create this kind of emotional attachment
with the, I mean, for games in players.
Well, first have every character say hella.
That's the number one thing, just have them say hella.
Obviously.
I mean, like I said, you have to give credit to Jean-Luc Canut who wrote the original story
because their relationship was, you know, built in and
and then when the script was handed over to me, the story, to start, you know,
drawing it out and giving it more an American idiom.
You know, I always watched my sister's friends growing up,
and I thought they always had such, you know,
different relationships than my male friends,
who, you know, who we don't, you know,
men are expected in America to be a lot more, like,
emotionally secluded and not to be like,
not to share their emotions.
So I was always envious and jealous of my female friends,
my sister's friends, because they could kind of,
I don't know, they could hold hands,
they could goof around, and it didn't mean anything.
It wasn't a thing, but they seemed to have
this emotional connection.
I can't say how.
We do that and I can only speak...
I approach the characters honestly just as characters first.
Who are these people?
I try not to look at them as anything else but who is the character?
And then you start from there.
And you also treat the characters fairly and objectively,
which means if they do something that's wrong...
Let it you know work that into your story it max is not right to the game
There's tons of moments where max fucks up, and she doesn't always do the right thing, but that's very human
That's and I think that's why people respond to the game
And I was I was someone expecting people to say well, you know okay dude writing these female characters. You know but
As a writer, once again, your job is to go into all these different worlds and make people believe that.
But that's research. I believe strongly in research.
But that's what I'm talking about, this cultural layering.
Is all these things kind of add, you know, to the characters.
Their setting, the environment, the artist, the way they drew the characters tells you so much.
about the characters. I mean, immediately you look at Chloe, you know who Chloe is based on her look.
You know who Max is somewhat based on her look. So it's not just voice and dialogue, it's how they
look, it's in its perception, how they view the world, maybe the kind of music they listen to
tells you a lot about a character, their politics, you know, things like that.
I grew up with a military dad and he was not at all like David Matz, not brusque like that,
but had certain similarities.
But I was not going to write a character that was a typical military asshole.
That's an easy character to write.
I really try to make things not easy.
Don't write the easy character.
Don't write the glib character.
Write the complicated character.
Even if it's just one little line.
Every script I write, I give every minor character a name.
I never write Man 1, which you see in a lot of scripts.
Woman 2.
Child 3.
Child 4.
give him a name, give him one moment to have a little beat.
And there's, you know, Tarantino does that well.
I think Edgar Wright actually does that beautifully
in Shaun of the Dead.
That's a great example of a film
where it gives characters you might not like.
I was like, suddenly I was watching Shaun of the Dead,
I'm crying.
I'm like, what?
It's, you know, so, you know, things like that.
Just always looking for outside of the character
and what you can bring in to just give them more weight,
more spiritual weight, more, you know, aesthetic weight.
If that helps.
It's gonna be a technical question.
Was it difficult or very different from other games to work on Life is Strange because of the time mechanic?
Like going back in time to change your things.
Was it different from a writing point of view?
Well, I mean, in terms of... It means more writing.
I mean, there's 13,000 lines in Life is Strange about.
and only eight are hella, by the way.
So that's a massive amount of writing,
and so much of that is rewriting,
having to write all new dialogue when you go back.
And we were all doing this,
we're all learning on the same learning curve, the team,
because we'd never done this before,
and we'd never made a game like this before.
Although, Remember Me had this brilliant memory mix,
is what they pulled into Life is Strange.
So, I mean, it was easy in the sense of,
And once I got in the groove of it, I was like, oh yeah, okay, complete opposite, complete opposite,
complete opposite. That really helped because then I knew it, you know, and the team knew,
we all knew like, when we're going to veer off in these two choices, let's really veer off.
into these two choices, even if there's no right choice,
the more opposite you go,
the more interesting the writing became
and the more kind of narratively dramatic it became.
So yeah, it was difficult, but in the end,
it became really second nature to what we were doing.
Thanks for the question.
You have nothing to say?
Okay.
Hi, first I'd like to say that I'm just really glad to have experienced the game.
Thank you.
The first feeling I had about it is like, I'm just glad.
My question is...
Since, as I understood, you came into the project when a lot of things were already set, like the broad story and everything, did you ever feel limited?
Were there any moments where you felt like you want to do things that might not be possible? How did you deal with it? How did the team deal with your wishes?
Well I said I'm an American so we do what we want.
So they had to listen to me.
It was so...
It was the most freedom I've ever had writing.
And like I said, I've never been on a team where everybody was so much on the same page.
When I interviewed Michelle and Raul and Luke
and they said they wanted the game to be subtle, I was like,
what did you just say?
Did you just say the word subtle?
That is a word you will never hear in Hollywood.
you will never hear maybe... it's very... it's not a word that people like to use because it means
quiet and not obvious and not explosive. So when they said that we want this to be subtle
and then they were saying... they were thinking, well, you know, because this... because Max has got these
powers, the game has got to be like... and I said,
like magical realism? And they go, yes!
And I... that's actually when I knew I was going to get the game.
Because magical realism is in a way what the story is about and the experience is about.
But no, I always felt like...
I felt... and Michelle would always say,
Feel free to... feel free, feel free.
I heard that more than anything.
Feel free, feel free to do this, feel free to do this.
And they really trusted me.
Because, you know, I'm bringing a lot of America and they trusted me to do that.
So...
And there are times when, trust me, there are times when you have debates.
And as a writer, you're working for the designers.
I mean, that's your job.
They have the vision, and you share the vision,
and you're making sure that you're putting their vision into the game.
So I never felt limited because I believed in what they were doing,
and I was very happy to be part of that engine.
The only thing, the big fight we had is, I can't even tell you,
spoiler alert, but fortunately the French do like to debate,
which is fantastic, so do I, but they're not mad debates,
they're just like, da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da, like, okay.
And then it goes on. So no, I felt amazing freedom,
so much so that I'm scared for the future.
You mentioned the future. I don't know too much about your career. I haven't played Life is Strange, although it's on my to-do list.
I hope so.
Oh, I've got it.
Good.
Limited edition box set. Bought it brand new. First day, still sealed.
But that's not the point. The point is, you said it's how you want to get back into games.
Obviously, Life is Strange was one of your first projects.
What did you learn from your...
gaming, writing related experience that you can take on board with regards to your future projects?
And at the same time, what advice would you give to aspiring writers who also want to break into the gaming field?
Well, I guess what I learned from writing Life is Strange is I learned that you can write this kind of game.
I wanted to write this kind of game in the 90s.
I wanted to do this kind of... not necessarily exactly this game,
but I wanted to have characters have conversations that were more naturalistic and tangential,
and not have cartoony voices, which really bugs me to this day.
It's why I can't stand watching... I don't watch any anime dubs, because...
Americans always like, oh, and the Japanese are always like soft and they speak naturally
But Americans always have this car Saturday morning cartoon sense not so much anymore
Obviously, it's changed much but there's still this air of like actors have to always go over the top
So I just learned that you can actually put together
You know everything that you actually believe in and feel like you're skilled at into a game and have it work now
That's just my own that's my own story. And what I love about writing as far as advice for writers
The most amazing thing, and I lived in LA for 10 years and I wrote for non-fiction magazines for years,
and I still do because I love non-fiction. I teach about genres in film and I do film presentations.
And when I came to LA, my small writing group, which is a group of us,
And then within five years, ten years, my friend Kirker is a producer on The Family Guy.
My friend Matt, who started the group, creates the show Burn Notice.
My friend Jen writes a book called How to Be a Badass.
It's on the New York Times Best Seller list today.
My other friend Chris Rossi writes a movie called Meadowland.
My friend Anna Kaja is in Silicon Valley in TV shows.
So the most, the biggest advice that I have for writers is A, write.
You have to write.
You have to write. You have to put the work in. Don't half-ass it, because you're not going to get far.
Because there's ten other people that are going to be writing a lot more than you if you think you're going to just do it like...
I mean, you have to be passionate about it.
And I tell people all the time, like,
you know what? If you're going to be an artist,
you're not going to listen to me.
And that's going to make you an artist.
You're not going to listen to anybody tell you no.
You're going to believe in it.
And you can't be like,
oh, maybe I want to...
I just say, you know what?
If you have that feeling,
you better stop now.
Because you're going to give up at some point.
And the cruelty of the universe,
of this aesthetic universe,
is that you will be crushed.
you know, by a lot of rejection. You have to deal with rejection and you have to embrace it.
Because what I learned when I got the...
I'm glad you asked that because when I got Life is Strange,
I felt like, wow, this came at a time when I didn't think it was coming and I can't believe it came,
but I realized that my entire life built up to that moment.
all my acceptances, all my rejections, all my triumphs, all my tragedies,
everything led to me getting the game at that moment.
And I wouldn't change a thing.
If I could go back in time and be born with another hand, I wouldn't do it.
Because I may not be up here today.
That may be the thing that gives me a certain objectivity as a writer,
that I can look into other people's viewpoints and empathize.
So, you know, I think passion is the main thing to have.
Yeah.
Well, the game community is very open. They're changing too. They want these games too.
And I'm so happy with where games are going. I mean, look at her story in The Last of Us.
I mean, it's just... and No Man's Sky. That's my jam.
Like, 70's style science fiction looking paperback covers as a game. Yeah, sign me up. It's cool.
You know, I love the fact that all these new aesthetics are coming and that's really important.
Don't, like, make your disadvantage your advantage.
Don't worry about the big budget.
Focus on what you can do.
And every, I tell a writer, once again,
your point of view is your gift.
Nobody sees the world like you and that is your biggest gift.
And so don't worry about what they're doing.
Don't, and yes, you can copy people early on.
That's what you do.
You copy and you...
You intake it, and then you put it out, and then you start merging with your own personality, hopefully.
So, you know, always, you know, believe in your POV because that's really, you know,
you know, how you'll change things. In terms of the, you know, game community,
they embrace the game immediately. As far as, you know, other people play the game, you can go online and
find both points of view, so.
Anybody else? We're done. Thank you so much, and I'll talk to you out there.