Now that we got that out of the way, let's get going.
Hello everyone, I'm Grant Schonkweiler.
I'm your moderator and your first speaker today.
I'm a producer at Epic Games.
And, but before I start with my first chapter,
I wanted to talk a bit about what we're talking about today.
Production at the heart of the team
is the title of our talk.
panel. It's actually one talk with each of us sharing a
chapter. We're going to interweave and it will be a
little weird. You'll like it, I think. Each of us has our own
chapter written mostly in our own words. We are sharing stories
from each other and people who aren't on this stage. So when
one of us tells a story, it may or may not be something that
actually happened to one of us. The names and places have been
changed to protect the innocent, so to speak.
As you may have figured out or read in the guide, our talk is about the field portion of being a producer.
We believe in order to maintain the health of a project, producers must constantly be iterating on team dynamics.
Once processes are in place, the producer must have their finger firmly placed on the pulse of the team
and be able to diagnose, and that situations often call for drastically different solutions.
We're going to go over some of the situations and solutions today.
But we are producers, so we must have an agenda for everything
we do.
So let me go through the agenda for our meeting,
I mean session today.
I'll start out, and I'll talk about what is a team
and how to get one started.
And then Matt will go over what you do
when everything goes sideways.
Michelle will then talk about some
of the tools for surviving.
And Greg will end it up with how to get yourself
ready to thrive.
Then we'll do some Q&A if we don't talk way too long.
Alright, so time for my chapter. This is the part where I reintroduce myself. My name is Graham
Schonkweiler. I've been in the industry for about 8 years, 5 of that as a producer. I've worked on
small and big teams making small and big games. I've worked at MegaTouch, id Software and I'm
currently at Epic Games working on a game called Fortnite. Before I did games I ran
entertainment show production teams. So I have about 15 years experience running
entertainment teams. To start us off on our journey I felt like we should talk about that
word team. So what is a team? Is this a team?
Yeah. How about this? Is this a team? I'm in a bright yellow
shirt if you're looking for me.
Yeah, this is also a team, this is Media Molecule.
And this is ID Software, and they were a great team as well.
This is also a team, it's a little bit different
than what we're talking about today,
but I thought it was important to keep in mind.
The dictionary defines a work team as a group of people
with a full set of complementary skills
required to complete a task, job, or project.
All right, definition's done.
Now, it's time for a story.
Now imagine if you will, you're a producer
that was brought onto a new team.
What do you do?
Let me share one of our stories, which I'll tell from the producer's perspective.
I was asked to form a new strike team to take on an overwhelming task.
I was told who I could have and what the work was that needed to be accomplished.
During the first meeting on the team, some of whom had never worked together before,
I saw that camps were forming and there would be problems moving forward.
But I didn't head it off at the start.
As days went on, I tried to work with individuals to resolve the problems,
but it was clear that divisions had formed and it was hurting both the team and their output.
I knew something extra would be needed to bring them together.
Remember this slide from earlier?
The reason I love this definition of a team
is because it clearly shows how a team must work together.
If that big guy on the left stops walking or tries
to go to the right, then the other fellow
will go the wrong way or stop.
Just like the team in the story, without unity
they can't move forward.
So what did the producer do?
They got the team together and had everyone
do a presentation on themselves to get them
to connect on a human level.
and it worked. People on the team started to learn lots of
things they had in common. Like being born in another country,
having a father in the military, or a crazy raver past. I use
this with my teams as well. It's an idea I got from the amazing
Scott Crabtree. If you've never heard him speak I highly
recommend it. His website is there. He has some amazing
talks.
It is a take on the petra kucha talks but instead of 20 slides
20 seconds each we do 10 slides 10 seconds each and no talking
about your career other than what inspired you to get into
games. I'm going to go through mine a little bit quickly as an
example. I was born just outside of Cincinnati Ohio that's right
there. Yes I'm a Reds fan. It was in that area I applied my
trade as a child and youth. I was always an avid gamer and
sports fanatic but it wasn't until I messed up my buddy's
Pokemon Red that I thought about making games.
I was so infuriated by both my mistake and the lack of ability
to fix it in the game that I sat down with my friend
to write our own game, because we could do that.
We worked for hours on a design doc
that would eventually turn into Pokemon Killer, an arcade
shooter where you killed every Pokemon.
That's not our art.
We weren't that talented.
After working on it for a few weeks,
we sent the doc to Sony, because they're not Nintendo.
And they responded, which was amazing.
Thanks.
We don't want to be sued, so no thanks.
With our dream smashed we moved on to other things. I started
modding and making levels for Warcraft 2 and Tribes 2. And I
loved adding my own story. People liked my levels but what
they didn't like was in the loading screen I had to ramble
through my whole story and explain to them what was
happening.
Around that same time as well, I started working in the music industry.
Yes, if you're doing math, that's child labor.
I've worked with hundreds of bands you have never heard of,
and maybe two or three you have.
But I learned a lot in that profession and did a lot of random jobs.
During that time, I also played sports until I discovered my one true love.
oh, wrong way. Rugby. That's actually from my first game.
It's also a picture of Braveheart. Which has
dominated my life ever since. I realized at one point I
didn't want to do the music industry thing for a career.
And it is then I realized, hey, this game dev thing I've
been doing as a hobby, I guess that could be a career.
And I remembered reading about full sale for music while I was
doing that and they had a game program and I was like that
could be interesting. Turns out it was. Outside of work I spend
as much time as I can with this wild bunch. My nieces and
nephew. They are crazy. I also like to read, travel, bike and
watch films. If you're looking for me outside of work I'll
probably be doing one of those things.
Now, that was just an example for you all, but it also worked in my favor, right?
From that example, you found something to have in common with me, or we have in common,
and now we're relating on a more human level. It's obvious once you've studied the science
why this works so well. Hive hypothesis states, humans are conditional hive creatures. We have
the ability under special circumstances to transcend self-interest and lose ourselves
temporarily and ecstatically in something larger than ourselves, the hive switch.
We are all searching for a calling
that we can only find as part of a larger group.
The hive switch is a slider.
You increase the feeling of a family.
Don't bring focus on differences.
Focus on similarities, shared values, and common identity.
People are warmer to people more like them,
so do things that help them find similarities.
It's important for you and your team
to realize they are a group of human beings
with different backgrounds coming together
to accomplish something great, but also
that more than likely, they have something in common.
The most important thing you can do when building a new team is to help them build an emotional
connection and bond with you and each other.
So what other things have we done to help build these bonds?
A few years ago we took Fortnite on a roadshow.
We went to cities all over the world and showed off the game.
We had people play the game and give us feedback.
We would send the fewest amount of people to each show,
you know, to cut costs and also make sure that people were still making the game.
But we quickly realized something after the first event.
It's hard to stay on point and excited for eight plus hours straight.
So one of our programmers got the idea to do a sports-style pump-up.
I have a video of it here.
Yeah. Video games.
Okay, so that's not us, but we thought we were like that.
And it worked. We did it at the start of each day moving forward.
It brought the team together, built a bond, and got us excited.
This is actually us.
We weren't quite as in sync as we thought we were.
In his book, The Righteous Mind, Jonathan Haidt talks about the science behind this a bit
and has a great quote.
People who move together feel more together.
If you ask people to sing or tap out some beats together, it makes people more willing to help each other out.
If you've seen Wolf of Wall Street, you also understand what this means.
If you have ever been at a sporting event or church or sang together, it's kind of like that.
So what we're saying is have more dance parties,
do karaoke, synchronicity builds trust.
Another thing you can do is to create a healthy competition
between groups, but not between individuals.
As game development studios, this
may be the easiest one for us.
Play games.
Have your teams take breaks and play PVP games or board games
against each other, or even set up a competition
surrounding your own game.
But remember to frame these competitions around fun
and not around a bonus of some kind,
because then you change the incentives.
When we started doing company playtests of Paragon,
we saw that teams were forming a lot stronger together.
In fact, our animation team walks around as a gang now.
It's kind of terrifying.
One thing that will not only help to build the trust on a new team,
but will prepare you for a high-pressure situation,
is to put the team into a fabricated high-pressure situation.
Escape rooms are pretty much the 21st century version of the trust fall or the ropes course.
I don't know if any of you have ever done one of those, but they work really well.
They put you into a high-pressure situation where you're forced to work together as a team.
We've also used a variation on the game jam idea.
Basically, we worked really hard for a week
to bring our bug counts down.
And then we told the team, hey, you
have a week to add anything that you guys think
will make the game better in your area.
Both of these manufacture both external and then
internal pressures to be great as a team.
There are of course obvious team building ideas like throwing
parties, going out for drinks, going to shows, movies,
concerts, sporting events, playing sports together and of
course celebrating each other's successes in life. Hopefully
with wild abandon like my dear friend Kermit there. As well as
many more that you've tried and I would love to hear about.
Remember that you as a producer can be the single biggest change transformer on a team's
collective happiness and excitement.
You can lead the team to greatness.
Kaiser, Hogan, and Craig have this to say about leadership.
Transformational leadership changes the way followers see themselves, from isolated individuals
to members of a larger group.
Transformational leaders do this by modeling collective commitment through self-sacrifice
in the use of we instead of I, emphasizing the similarities of group members and reinforcing
collective goals, shared values, and common interest.
Because I love rugby, I must talk about this man.
The great coach, Eddie Jones, had an amazing year last year.
His team from Japan went into the Rugby World Cup ranked
16th, with only one top-tiered professional player
on their entire squad.
But they went on to have three major wins,
including the greatest upset in the history of the sport
against South Africa.
Basically, if you imagine the New York Yankees losing
to the UCLA baseball team, it was kind of like that.
After the World Cup was over, he said,
the team is the sum of the whole and not an individual.
And it was made a whole by the support staff.
To summarize, teams come in all shapes and sizes
and are made up of diverse groups of people.
Similarities build unity.
Synchronicity builds trust.
Competition builds strength.
External and internal pressures build cooperation,
and producers build teams.
Thank you.
Okay. So this being one talk, it also means that this is an
interactive talk because I like this. Now if you're willing and
able I would ask that you all stand up and turn to the nearest
person near you and take the next minute to talk about
takeaways that you could have from this talk.
All right everybody.
It's time. Stop talking. I know this is really exciting. Don't
worry. You'll get to do this again at the end of each of our
segments. Now you have a friend in the audience. Hopefully you
know each other a little bit. But Matt is going to go ahead
and go through his part now.
All right. Thank you very much, Grant.
This is so appropriate for my talk.
Yeah.
Right?
That's pretty great.
We planned that.
So hi, everyone.
My name is Matt Charles, and I'm here
to talk about what you can do when things fail because
something inevitably will.
So I'd like to share some tips on diagnosing
some common situations and some different solutions.
Grant, you broke it again.
There we go.
So, real quick, before I jump into that,
I'm a senior producer over at Gearbox Software.
I've been there for about eight years now,
ten in the industry, and I love everybody I've worked with a lot at Gearbox.
I've been a producer or a senior producer
on the Borderlands franchise for a while.
And I'm currently working on an unannounced title, and I promise it's not what you think, based on the titles up there.
I also was a soccer referee for quite a few years, which gave me great experience at being wrong all the time, and being told that.
So that was very useful.
So before I can talk about problems you might encounter on a team, we need to first understand what the ideal scenario actually is.
So the ideal scenario, of course, is one where, on the team, you have perfect communication,
everybody's best friends, cooler heads always prevail during disagreements,
and the team is in control of their own fate.
Well, as many of you know, the producer is the captain of the project,
and you're responsible for all of these things.
And a lot of what I'm about to say will be obvious to you,
especially if you've been doing this a long time.
But greatness takes discipline and constant reinforcement.
So there was a time looking back a couple of years ago where I...
thought that when I first started being a producer,
I was actually better than, you know,
four or five years in,
because I hadn't yet developed any bad habits.
So, I've tried to fix all those,
but that takes reinforcement and daily discipline.
Regardless, as a producer,
it's still better to be Captain Obvious
than Captain Hindsight.
So, when something goes wrong,
here are the three things you must do.
Well, okay, the first thing you might do
is panic a little bit.
And it's okay to panic a little bit, but if you're going to panic, try to do it internally.
Because remember that the team looks to you for emotional cues about how to react to a situation.
Regardless of if you panic, the next thing you have to do is figure out what actually happened.
Somebody may come into your room screaming about smoke, but is it a fire or just somebody using an e-cig?
With regards to diagnosis, I find this trick very important, very helpful.
Ask why, and then just keep asking why.
Be a curious five-year-old, essentially,
and then you'll get to the root of the problem pretty quickly.
Toyota actually developed a five-wise technique,
which is employed exactly like you'd expect.
And that's traditionally very effective at getting
to the root cause of the problem.
Last but not least.
Do take time to communicate to others about what is going on,
how you're handling it, and what you plan to do.
Get in front of the issue as much as possible.
Otherwise, the rumor mill is going
to do what it's going to do, and you
may end up with an even bigger problem on your hands.
So now I'll cover five pretty common issues
that I hear about, or I've seen, or hear about frequently.
And I'll suggest some responses and ways
you can deal with these things, keeping in mind the three
things I just mentioned.
So the first one, probably the most common,
is just simple miscommunications.
So these questions are telltale signs
that a miscommunication has occurred.
And you've probably heard something like this.
You've probably.
hear something like this weekly or at least monthly, right?
And the key in managing this type of problem
is actually embedded in the question that comes up here.
It's the phrase, I don't understand.
So when you hear somebody say, I don't understand,
listen for that and address that first.
Especially since you might be in the same position.
This might be the first time you're hearing
about something as a producer.
You might not also understand why somebody did something.
So then you can immediately empathize with that person.
So a good way to handle miscommunication, of course,
is with a response such as, you know, I don't know either.
Maybe he didn't know his change would affect you.
I can think of some other reasons
why this might have happened,
but why don't we go talk to him and find out?
If this happens consistently,
you might wanna skip to the abbreviated version
and just say, you know, I don't know, have you asked him?
So the person can, you know, take the hint
that they need to be proactive
in solving communication issues.
But the lesson here is that I don't know is a fine answer,
but do communicate what you're gonna do about it.
Another common issue is with personality conflicts.
Turns out not everybody just gets along naturally
to each other, with each other.
You don't need everybody to be best friends, of course,
but you should be aware of any signs
that things might be headed in a potentially bad direction.
So first diagnose what you're actually dealing with.
Some obvious signs are eye rolling
or people being curt to one another consistently.
And the response here is pretty straightforward.
First, remind people to be professional.
We're not in high school anymore.
Then the next thing you need to do after you've addressed that,
and hopefully that goes away, is still
understand that there could be some underlying cause.
That's a symptom, not the root of the problem
that you need to seek out and resolve.
Some subtle signs of personality conflicts
or people not getting along.
are ascribing negative motivations to somebody's behavior,
so-called like casting somebody as the devil,
assuming the worst about why somebody did something.
Constantly, somebody constantly disagreeing
with somebody else, maybe outside their typical roles
or responsibilities, and some subtle campaigning as well.
This unfortunately happens on some teams.
It's a real thing you have to deal with.
These are much harder to spot, unfortunately,
and oftentimes people aren't even aware
that they're doing these things,
so that makes it even more difficult.
You have to approach these with a bit of caution.
Because these can be more difficult to deal with,
usually, actually, counterintuitively,
the best fix is to get those people to spend more time
with each other so that they can better understand each other's
goals and motivations.
They might not come out of that agreeing
on a mutual direction to head, but at least then
you understand, OK, everything's out in the open.
we're not agreeing on this point.
Now we can solve for that, rather than people just
avoiding each other, or not making eye contact,
or any of the other personality conflict symptoms
I mentioned.
I've tried both paths.
And more often than not, putting people together more frequently
to resolve this resolves the root conflicts way more often
than separation, which tends to actually entrench people
and make things even worse.
So this one's fun.
Another issue I see is when a team loses control
of their own destiny, or their own fate,
or of some major aspect of the project.
It's when some outside force creates a change
in circumstance for the team, such as the dreaded mandate
from above.
So obviously, we won't name any products or any games.
But twice in the past couple of years,
I have seen in the industry significant changes
made to the product requirements.
For example, adding an entire gameplay mode,
like multiplayer, campaign, or whatever,
to the game with less than a year to ship.
So this is pretty, yeah, this is pretty,
I'm seeing some nods from everywhere.
So yeah, it happens, right?
So how do you respond with this? As the team lead, but not necessarily the company lead,
you're in a difficult position. Well, first, remind people that owning a company means that
as an owner, they do actually get to make calls about the nature of the product. So first of all,
that is entirely within their purview. Second, challenge people to come to a different solution
given the same information. These proposed big changes almost never happen on a whim.
They're probably, they're almost always necessary
in response to something that you or the team
just simply aren't aware of yet.
So when that information is laid out,
everybody can understand why a change
or a decision is being made,
and then you've resolved or helped to mitigate that conflict.
If it's an isolated incident,
things will probably blow over.
If a pattern is developing,
that's probably a sign that you should have a chat with
whoever's making these mandates from above
or whatever the case is.
and let them know that that can have a real impact on the team and the productivity of the team.
In the two cases I mentioned, one, hard to say, the other one actually worked out for the best.
So it's also not always the case that the mandates from above lead to negative results.
Just like any other change, you know, they have mixed results.
Now on to outbursts.
Yay.
An outburst is a sudden release of emotion,
perhaps caused by some of the issues I mentioned earlier.
These also usually don't happen for no reason whatsoever.
And the way you deal with this is to remind the person
that their emotion can come across
as bullying to other people.
And it'll shut them down.
So that person needs to work with others way more
constructively than they have been.
For example, you can say, you might be right,
but the way you're presenting your message
is really getting in the way of the message.
Try to get them to refocus on the issue at hand
and think about solutions rather than emotions
or emotional posturing.
A preventative measure that might be the most brilliant thing I've ever seen done in any
meeting to make sure a meeting and future meetings didn't get too heated was when an
art director brought a shake weight to the art critiques.
Yeah, that thing.
Turns out it's actually impossible for tensions to rise when somebody's using that in a room.
It's just impossible.
And the point was obvious.
It's actually okay to have a laugh during even serious and important discussions.
Sometimes, unfortunately, outbursts or other conflicts
can build into loathing, or somebody writing somebody off
completely.
This is very unfortunate, but it does happen.
And of course, as a producer, what you want
is to try to turn this into this.
So what's a dead to me situation?
What do I mean?
Well, they're kind of obvious.
It's when something like this is said, like, oh, F that guy,
right?
Hopefully nobody's had to deal with this situation,
but again, it does happen.
It's also important to understand.
how it happens, and this is the worst,
because it's the most damaging to the team,
and yet it can happen so, so easily.
At first, people are all on the same team,
and then something will happen that might prompt someone
to think that there are multiple teams,
or competing interests, or multiple silos, or groups.
And once anybody starts to believe the team is fractured,
bad stuff happens.
As an example of how easy it is to get into this state,
look at this.
It's so true.
Thanks to Zach at Extra Fabulous Comics for that.
That's so perfect.
So how you deal with this is to first recognize
where it's coming from.
Was there a single blow up that people harbor resentment over?
Has it been a series of miscommunication issues?
Is one or more people actually incompetent?
Remember the Steve Jobs quote, B players
discourage the A players.
And it's a real phenomenon that can
breed resentment in your team.
Communicate the stakes to those involved.
As I mentioned, the team can't function divided,
and everybody needs to be reminded of that.
So challenge the people involved to find some common ground
for the good of the project.
So to recap, quickly identify if you're
dealing with a small issue or a big issue.
Ask why.
Emulate a five-year-old.
Don't be afraid to communicate and respond appropriately.
And try to remain calm and be the best producer you can be.
That's me.
All right. It's time again for you all to stand up and talk to
each other about what you learned from Matt's brilliant
talk. I know this is really exciting and we learned a lot,
but sadly we do have to eat lunch at some point. So please
sit down. Stop talking. Thank you. Thank you. All right.
Michelle's up.
Hello.
Hi, I'm Michelle.
I'm a producer at Media Molecule.
And I'm going to talk you through three tools
that I use day to day, week to week,
that I feel kind of help me as my anchors, basically.
The things that I go to whenever I kind of come up
against any problem, I usually basically just
like revert back to one of these before I kind of feel
like I'm totally freaking out.
So, the first one is the overview tracker, the second one is creating a weekly rhythm,
and the third one is talking. I like talking. But first I'm going to give you a really quick
summary of my background. So, I've been working at the studio for eight years. I joined back
in March 2008, but before I joined MM, I studied literature, animation, I worked in the film
industry.
For six years as a casting associate with a casting director,
I did a bit of promo for new bands on small record labels.
And basically from there I kind of went into games.
But the skills I developed over the years working on projects here
and also my own projects transferred really well into
games production. But working in the
film industry didn't fully prepare me for working with creatives and programmers
in the games industry.
I felt like I had a lot to learn really, really fast, but I managed to adapt really well.
I was really hungry to learn and challenge myself and really push myself in areas that
I just wasn't familiar with.
There was a lot for me to figure out and I felt like I adapted really well and learnt
new terminology and processes pretty well too.
And our directors were amazing.
They basically trusted me and let me really run with things.
And I was given the room to kind of feel it all out,
make mistakes, and basically get better.
In all the years that I've been a producer,
I feel like I've been able to develop those skills
and understand, basically, the tools
that I feel that I'm going to talk to you about today.
But basically, I'm continuing to optimize my workflow
and use the tools that I've used on these projects.
and they work. They usually help me from, save me from spiralling out of control in
the sometimes chaotic environment that I work in. Not always, but sometimes.
So the first tool is the overview tracker, and basically what is that? That is the big
picture of the project. It's the project overview. So that basically has information like having
key milestone dates in there.
We have the high-level schedule in there, broken out person by person, area by area.
There's demos, milestone builds, team holidays, public holidays, basically all the information
that is important information that we just need to be aware of when we're looking at
what we're going to need to do to ship and what we need to manoeuvre around.
So I create a simple timeline in Excel.
I say it's simple, but to me it's really simple.
Basically, it helps me understand how much time
we have in the week.
I usually create a sheet that covers the whole year.
And that way I can look at it and I can freak out
by just the fact that we don't have a lot of time in a year.
And I note down all those key events.
It's all presented back in here.
And it's usually based around the beats and kind of like the flow of like what we're trying to aim to work towards as a team on the projects that we're working on.
Because there are only 52 weeks in the year, 52 cells, when I look at the work that people have to do and they've said that they need to do to ship, it basically looks terrifying.
All of that information is basically gathered, like the team information is gathered from
doing one-to-one catch-ups with people, and I'll go over how we do that in a moment, but
it's like gathering all that information and presenting it back in a really high-level
way.
There are also different ways that I present back that information in a more granular way.
Some people have completely different working styles and they want to see what their work looks like in different ways.
I use various different tools presented here to present that back to people, to the producers as well.
So in summary, basically this is what the project picture looks like.
As a producer, I need to be able to make big, broad decisions based off of what's going on.
I need to be able to discuss them.
Having the project view helps me do that.
It enables me to make strategic, broad decisions.
And it helps the producers and the team basically understand what the birds-eye view of the project is
and helps us analyze what's going on week to week.
So my other tool that I use is creating a weekly rhythm
and flow with the team.
So it's the picture of the week.
It's the realistic view of what is happening day
to day, week to week, or more like day to day.
So the structure of it is that we have from Monday to Friday,
we
basically have days where we go and we collect information from people, so we check in,
like we go and sit down with somebody and do one-to-one catch-ups between Monday and Wednesday.
Before we do that, though, we have a studio meeting, and basically we kind of set out, like,
what is the plan for the week, what are the goals, get everybody together and just run through that.
After that we kind of like break out, like we catch up with people, we do the big important
meetings that might need to happen, but basically we're just like, we're gathering information,
we're taking information from people, we're catching up with them, updating their schedules
one to one, and we're finding ways to kind of present that back, that all goes back into
the big overview tracker.
But basically having a weekly rhythm helps set an expectation for the team, they understand
what's going to happen day to day and there's like a little bit of structure there for them
to basically, for us to fall back on but also for them to fall back on as well.
So Monday to Wednesday is basically collecting information.
Thursday and Friday, this is just an example of how we work.
And those two days are basically set aside
for production days.
We take all that information, put it back into our reports.
Our reports are really useful because they're actually
presenting back everything that we've taken on
throughout the week and basically presenting that back
to our directors and to Sony, our publisher.
So having that weekly rhythm and flow, actually it can break down sometimes, like we're all
humans, something might crop up, something might kind of make that just not work out,
we might not be able to do a studio meeting at the beginning of the week, or we might
not be able to do those one-to-one catch-ups with people.
The weekly rhythm isn't rigid, but it's a really good backbone for us to have, and to
pull back on if things get a little bit messy.
Okay, it's like my third tool, which is talking.
I like talking.
I feel like I've got a really good rapport with people on the team.
I love talking to them.
I love helping them.
It's basically like one of the things that just helps me get through day to day.
So the first thing that I'm going to talk about is basically being the person that your team members can come to.
So letting them know that if they have a problem, if they have an issue, whether it's work-related or not, they can just come to me.
They can say, oh, I just need to kind of take your side and just basically air out concerns that they have or issues that they have.
So, making yourself available to be that person, or I make myself available to be that person,
so I say, okay, if I'm looking like I'm really busy, it's okay, just come over and say you
need some time, and then we can sit down and just talk through whatever problem that you
might be having.
So, during the week, basically, like, gather all that information, like, from people's
schedules, from what's going on day to day with them.
maybe it's work-related, maybe it's not, but basically we're just taking all of that in.
Whatever we take in will have to, in some way, or it will impact what is happening in the
overview tracker. So basically, it does all come back to what does the project look like,
what's the health of the team, but also of the project, because whatever comes out of that
must lead to change. There will be something that might impact it in some way.
Processing all of that information will have a price emotionally for me, for our other producers.
Finding the right people to go to, to help us zoom out and actually just kind of get a little bit of perspective on what's happening is really important.
It's really important not to go down the train if you've got like...
big things that you want to talk about that actually need maybe a little bit more experienced
people to kind of help you take that step back and zoom out. It's not cool to offload
on somebody who might take things the wrong way and basically overwhelm themselves and
get themselves in a bit of a spin because you've basically just pushed that emotion
and that...
back onto them and they might not be able to handle it, so don't do that.
I usually go to one of our directors for support, depending on what I need to talk through.
So if it's like a technical issue, I'll go to our technical director
if I'm freaking out a little bit about our code schedule
and I need to take a bit of a step back and figure out how to problem solve there.
But basically it just really helps to get perspective and zoom out.
So talking through issues with somebody who can help do that is really important.
Or just being able to find people that, and this is team members, that anybody in your
team that you've got like a really good relationship maybe, who you can just sit with, that can
just hear you out.
and so finding people to just sit and listen, someone that you can talk to, our programmers
call it rubber ducking, I've never heard of that before but that's their term, we're using
that. It's really handy to hear yourself say the words out loud, for me personally it helps
me problem solve if I'm actually just saying what the problem is and I'm trying to like
figure out like how I'm going to solve it but I usually
can get to the bottom of things just by saying those words.
And it helps me move forward, basically, if I'm stuck on something.
And that person might actually just say,
oh, hey, why don't you do this?
I'm like, yes, maybe I can do that.
But yes, saying things out loud is good.
I'm a really emotional person.
I have got feelings.
I hold all of this information of like project information,
but also team, like the team kind of coming up to me,
telling me what their problems are as well.
I love doing it, but it can be really overwhelming,
and sometimes I can feel really, really stretched,
and like I'm just gonna completely melt.
I find that I actually need to find ways
that I can offload as well, so breathing, hugs,
playing my ukulele, reading, going for a walk.
Things can feel really frustrating at times,
but it's really important as a producer
to kind of regain perspective,
so taking a break is good, just putting things down.
stepping away and maybe coming back to whatever the problem is later.
But sometimes, actually, like I just want to scream
and finding a room in the studio to scream
is really handy. And actually I recommend
audio rooms, they're soundproof, but just don't do it if
any of your audio team are in those rooms because you'll freak them out.
But I've totally done that and walked out
okay afterwards, but yeah, it's useful.
So basically, being the person that's just exposed to all of that information can be an emotional burden.
And so, actually, one of the most important things is if you need help, ask for it.
We're all human.
We will break down at some point, I'm sure.
So these tools are really useful for me.
It's going from basically the big picture to the granular and then coming back out to the big picture again.
They all work really well as a trio.
We use them all the time in our projects.
If any one of these tools is missing, it breaks down.
Basically, they're my anchors.
The process helps bind the team.
We're a very people-focused studio.
We care about what is happening with people in work,
out of work.
We're here to help.
We can accommodate for anything.
We're very flexible.
Everyone is really amazing at what they do at the studio.
We make amazing games together.
I really love the projects that we work on
and that we continue to work on together as a team.
These tools are really important because they
help with the choreography of the week,
with the expectation as well.
People know what they're doing.
People know what to expect.
Like when things are going to kind of,
if a random thing is thrown in, we basically
have something to fall back on.
The projects.
the projects that we work on can be really tough, but you know, we're problem solvers,
we're making amazing games, these tools really help us to basically ship them.
Here's some reference material, like these books are amazing, they're my production bibles,
I really recommend them, Siobhan recommended a couple to me as well, she's amazing.
I hope it was helpful, thank you very much for listening.
All right, now before we do this break,
everybody go ahead and stand up.
But before you start talking,
I wanna go through something that Michelle talked about.
So each of us has a burden that probably impacts us at work
and we're probably frustrated about.
So I want you to think about that thing.
And then on the count of three,
I want you all to scream, okay?
And we're just gonna get it out there
and then we're gonna talk about it.
Okay, ready?
One, two, three.
All right. I feel better. Okay. Now take 30 seconds each and
talk to your neighbor again about what you can take away
from Michelle. All right. All right. All right. All right.
All right. Or as Matthew McConaughey says, all right,
all right, all right. Sit down. Nate, stop talking. Sit down,
Nate. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. All right. Greg,
bring us home.
You're tall.
Thank you.
All right, well, hi, my name is Greg Stone.
I've been in game development for 14 years
and a producer for eight years.
I work at Backflip Studios as the senior producer
over Dragonvale World.
I live in beautiful Boulder, Colorado
with my beautiful daughter, Allison, and my wife, Benita.
As producers, we often talk about the best practices
for managing projects, but we seldom
talk about the preparation required
to manage the pressure of producing a game.
I want to share with you guys my story and attempt
to open up a dialogue on this subject.
When I was promoted to the position of production director
at a previous studio, I inherited
a number of problems.
We were trying to find a success that had been eluding us,
and pressure was mounting.
I spent most of my waking hours in the studio
listening to people's feedback and trying to react.
I took every comment to heart.
and cared deeply about solving the problems.
The more I listened, the more problems were dropped at my feet.
I internalized the stress in an attempt
to keep it from projecting onto the team.
As I became overwhelmed, I didn't
have the coping mechanisms in place
to properly handle the burden.
My anxiety continued to build up.
The stress manifested itself into a number of ailments.
I had panic attacks, hypertension,
heart palpitations, high blood pressure, shingles,
and weight gain.
Stubborn and a little dumb, I pushed forward.
One night when I was driving home from work,
I started losing control of my body.
The stress had built up to the point
where my body was attempting to shut down.
I pulled off to the side of the road
and slowly drifted out of consciousness.
That's the wrong way.
Sorry, unhealthy, overweight,
and stress beyond my body's capacity to handle it,
I decided drastic changes were necessary.
This became the catalyst for what has become
a fascination with self-optimization.
I began to modify my behaviors
to improve my reaction to stress.
I read everything I could on the subject of stress management.
Tried various workout routines.
Practiced intermittent fasting.
Dabbled in neurotropics to improve brain performance.
Put my body into ketosis.
For months, I experimented with eating only meat, beans,
and spinach at every meal.
I do not recommend this, just for the record.
I got really sick.
Played with caffeine intake and sources
to optimize mental alertness.
tried every major form of meditation,
and measured every body metric I could reasonably gain access to.
Three years later, I have drastically
improved my response to stress to the point
where it no longer plays a factor in my health and well-being.
More importantly, it has allowed me to thrive in the fast-paced,
high-pressure world of game development.
I want to share with you guys my practices
I found to make any producer better and more effective
underneath stress.
I call this HOPES.
HOPES is the acronym for a routine that is tailored
to bring a better version of ourselves in time of stress.
While this may sound like an infomercial,
I promise you guys this is entirely based in science.
First, a huge disclaimer.
I am not a doctor or psychologist.
I'm just a guy with obsessive tendencies
I've channeled into self-experimentation.
Please check with your physician
before doing anything that could impact
your mental or physical health.
Now let's dive down the rabbit hole.
So how do we prepare ourselves for the long hours,
constant demands, and mental challenges
that come with being a producer?
The first step is a healthy diet.
We literally are what we eat.
This rabbit hole goes so deep
that I could talk about this subject for hours.
What you really need to know is that
our diet's tied to our energy levels,
our outlook, cognitive ability,
and capacity to manage stress.
The abilities are critical to being an effective producer,
but we often sacrifice our diets
due to our busy lifestyles.
Don't fall victim to this trap.
Adopt a healthy diet,
and make your meals at the beginning of the week
to ensure you have enough when you need it.
I recommend the slow carb diet,
which is detailed in the 4-Hour Body and the 4-Hour Chef.
If you're more adventurous,
I would look into the ketogenic diet,
which is detailed in the Bulletproof Diet.
Exercise has been improved to increase energy,
reduce stress, improve sleep,
boost brain power, enhance immunity,
ramp up productivity, increase self-esteem, and more.
Like diet, it is a linchpin to our success
in maintaining control of ourselves when pressures mount.
To get the full benefits of exercise,
try to get at least three hours
of moderate physical activity every week.
Spread this across five days
and don't sacrifice the habit when we get busy.
The busier we are, the more critical exercise
becomes to helping us maintain our effectiveness.
Do whatever exercise you enjoy,
but if you're relatively new and looking for something,
I recommend looking into the book,
Bigger, Leaner, and Stronger for Men
and Thinner, Leaner, and Stronger for Women.
Have you ever been around someone with unshakable optimism?
Their attitude is infectious.
Optimistic people make great leaders
because everyone wants to follow someone
who believes that any obstacle can be overcome.
Cultivating optimism isn't just an innate ability
some people have.
Like any skill, it can be mastered
with the right techniques.
To make ourselves more optimistic,
we can employ the power of positive thinking.
Creating a positive mindset is as simple
as thinking positive thoughts.
A good practice is to think about three things
you are grateful for every morning.
Write them down in a journal and truly think about how grateful you are for those people,
places, and things.
Take the time to appreciate how amazing the world you live in is and how fortunate you
are.
Even now, in this room, most of us are alive, healthy, have access to the world's information
at our fingertips, are fed, sheltered, and clothed.
Life is good.
Keep this perspective and you will maintain your optimism.
Your team will come to depend on that optimism when they need someone to reassure them that
everything will be okay.
I use the five minute journal as a really quick way
to reinforce the habit of positive thinking.
It can be purchased online.
It was an app and it'll soon be an app again.
They're making a new one.
A patient producer is the rock that teams lean on.
They take the time to listen to their team members
when they need to talk and remain calm.
They know the pressures of today are temporary
and will eventually be a memory.
Keep a level head.
Keeping a level head rather and remaining patient is also a skill that can be cultivated.
To do this, we must train our minds to be less reactive and center on whatever needs
our attention now.
Meditation is the most effective way to train your brain to be patient and calm.
Meditating every day will train your brain to be less reactive, allowing you to stay
cool under pressure.
My recommendations for meditation would be the APCOM.
In the book, Creative Visualization
to start you on your mindfulness journey.
If you're rolling the splurge,
you can pair this with a Muse headset
to ensure you're getting to a really deep meditative state.
Try to meditate for at least 10 minutes every day.
All right, when pressures mount and stress rises,
our bodies release three chemicals
to respond to the perceived threat.
These chemicals are adrenaline, norepinephrine,
and cortisol.
Adrenaline and norepinephrine are released first.
These two chemicals narrow our decision-making ability
to get us to make one of two choices, fight or flight.
This limits our ability to think rationally.
Cortisol is even more dangerous.
Cortisol is the response the body produces
when the perceived threat lingers.
Lingering threats happen all the time in game development
because our problems take time to resolve.
And cortisol elevates blood pressure
and depletes blood sugar levels.
Over time, this leads to high blood pressure,
hypertension, and even weight gain.
As producers, we need to keep our wits about us to make effective decisions.
So our focus must be placed on returning ourselves to a state of calm.
To return to calm quickly, our brains need a set of operations during stressful situations.
When stress is triggered first...
Breathe deeply to regulate your anxiety, rather.
Seven seconds in through your nose,
seven seconds out through your nose.
Count the seconds in your head,
but if you're in front of other people,
don't make it weird.
You should be able to do this without other people noticing.
Next, take inventory of yourself.
Look inside.
Are all your primary needs being met?
If yes, you have everything you need to solve the problem.
There is nothing to run from.
This will help you stay calm
and lower the amount of cortisol and norepinephrine
that are being released in your body.
Gain perspective.
Five years from now,
you probably won't remember why you're stressed.
Maintaining perspective will help you stay focused.
Focus on problems you can only solve now.
Nothing spikes cortisol levels like dwelling on problems
that are too big to tackle all at once.
Only spend your time on the problems that you can solve.
You are in control of your own mind, nobody else.
Ignore items outside of your control
and don't get worked up about the what ifs.
If you run this set of operations
every time you are presented with a stressful situation,
you will significantly limit
your body's natural response to stress.
I recommend the book Crucial Conversations for advice on discussing difficult subjects
with difficult people.
The obstacle is the way for an intro into stoic philosophy and mindset for improving
your internal dialogue and governing beliefs.
To master all of these skills, practice and time is necessary, but how you implement is
just as important as what you implement.
My wife hates that I weigh myself every morning.
She thinks I'm obsessed with my weight.
The truth is I weigh myself as,
weighing myself is my keystone habit.
A keystone habit is one habit
that all other habits are built off of.
Weighing myself in the morning when I first wake up
gives me the motivation to stay on track
with my health goals.
I don't want to wake up tomorrow
and see my progress evaporate
and that motivates me to go to the gym and eat healthy.
Eating healthy and going to the gym keeps me disciplined,
and that discipline spreads through the rest of my day.
My weight is also a metric by which I can gauge progress.
When I first started working on improving my habits,
I eliminated soda from my diet.
When I succeeded at this, I got overly excited
and tried to implement multiple habits at once.
It was too much for me, and I failed miserably.
So I went back to trying to implement one habit at a time.
This allowed me to focus on making new habits stick.
I have noticed that there is no easy way to predict
how much time it takes to reinforce a habit.
Some habits will take hold immediately
and others will take a long time.
Give your new habit time to take hold in your life
before moving on to the next one.
Be aware of how you're reacting to a new habit.
If you dread performing that habit every day,
try something different to achieve the same effect.
Build your habits into routine by doing the habits every day.
When something becomes a routine,
it takes very little willpower to maintain.
This will come in handy during prolonged times of stress,
like crunch.
If you build a hopes routine, you
will come to rely on its power in your daily life.
While most days will be easy to maintain,
some days will be more trying than others.
Fight the urge to give up the routine,
because when it starts to erode, it's hard to get back on track.
Routines thrive on momentum, so don't let
anything disrupt your rhythm.
I recommend the book, The Power of Habits,
for more on how to make habits stick
and the app momentum to help you
build your habits into routines.
Thanks for listening.
I'm always looking for people to talk to you
in like-minded individuals.
Oops.
Feel free to contact me.
All right.
Thank you.
It's break time again.
All right, everybody stand up.
Talk to each other for a few minutes.
And then if you have a question,
we'll have a little bit of time for Q&A.
All right.
I hope from our talk,
you have realized that as a producer,
we work at the hearts of the team,
not just at the heart of the team.
Now we don't have a ton of time for questions.
We have about five minutes.
But we will take a few.
And then as soon as we're out of time,
we'll step out into the hallway.
So if you have any questions, feel
free to come up to the microphone and ask them.
If not, we'll all sit and stand here awkwardly
for the next few minutes.
There's a microphone back there and over there.
Go ahead.
Hey.
I'm wondering about the synchronized movement
you were talking about and what to do with team members that
are shy or not comfortable doing anything like that.
Yeah, most people are really uncomfortable doing it the first time, right?
So what I found is I'm just like really goofy about it and really kind of act like an idiot.
And I'm like, hey guys, check this out.
And then like you start doing it and then people kind of will get into it.
So it's more of kind of putting yourself out there and being like, hey, just try this once with me.
And then people will kind of start to get into it.
Karaoke is like really the most extreme case, right?
Especially for someone shy, that is like a nightmare as much as.
it was for the four of us to get up here and open ourselves up.
So I would start with just very simple movement things and stuff like that.
Okay, thank you.
Thank you.
I have a hypothetical for you. Are you ready?
Yeah.
Alright, everything you've just talked about, but your entire team is spread all over the planet
and very rarely gets to see each other in person. What do you do?
Anybody have any thoughts on that?
Basically he was asking how do you do this if you have a team all over the world.
So I've done this a bit. The first thing I did was I went to basically everybody.
So I flew out to other countries and got to know people.
I basically spent a week with the team and just sat in a room and they came and talked to me.
Kind of like what Michelle was talking about.
having synchronized meetings, one or two a week is really
good. And having that time be a sharing time, not just we're
going to talk about what work we're doing but we're going to
share a little bit about ourselves. When I originally
talked about the pedicure stuff, I've talked to a few studios
where every meeting, team meeting they have, they do one
or two people and go through that way. So that could be part
of how you do that.
Is this the microphone? Okay, cool.
So for Tearaway Unfolded, half of our team were based in Sweden, half were at MM, so we worked with another studio, all on the same code base.
So in order to keep our weekly rhythm, communication was the biggest thing, because there was only a one hour time difference,
but we tried to find tools that would actually help us get together and make it feel like we're all in the same room.
So we used Skype. Skype was actually awesome because we could do like screen sharing, group chats.
Basically, we just did things like we had like an iPad that was in the room with like one of our guys who's based in
Paris, like one of our level designers at MM is based in Paris, so we always have him like
connected in some way. And then for the team that were in Sweden, like we always had them on Skype in some way.
And it's really hard.
did break down at times, but it's basically really important to try and keep that moving and keep the visibility.
Email as well, but email can be really distracting when people just use it as a way to have conversations and go off on tangents.
So just bringing that back and as a producer, trying to make sure that everybody has the right information,
so presenting it back to them and keeping...
Well, I'm just going to use our weekly rhythm and flow because actually it really, really worked with...
making sure people knew what to expect and what was happening.
But yeah, it's just something to work out.
Cool.
All right, over here.
Hi, I'm Caroline.
Thanks all for all your talks.
They were really good.
Thank you.
Thanks again.
I've got a bit of a personal question for Greg
about what you just presented.
That must have been scary.
How did you deal with it to your team?
How did you communicate it to your colleagues?
Did you keep it for yourself?
Or were you just openly about it?
And how long did that take for you to get back on your feet?
Well, I guess Grant could probably
answer that as good as I could, because we were working
together at the time.
But I'm pretty sure I kept most of that to myself.
I don't think most of that was aware.
Most people were aware of that.
And it really came down to trying
to make sure that I wasn't panicking the team.
OK, thank you.
No problem.
Sorry the world isn't made for adults that are five feet tall.
I, so I have a question.
I think it may be mostly directed towards Michelle, just because you sort of spoke to it.
So I'm a huge, huge, huge advocate about
just really being in touch with your team
in terms of like how they're feeling and things like that because you have a way
better sense of what they'll be able to accomplish in the timeline that you have
based on.
like interpersonal and all that kind of stuff.
And like I am that person that they can come to.
So sort of a little bit of advice in terms of like
if they come to me and they have a problem
like it will personally affect me and all that kind of stuff.
But it's like working and then being sort of
interrupted to talk to them, which I'm fine to do.
But sometimes when I sit back down, I have a hard time
like getting back into what I was doing.
Do you guys have any advice for just getting right back into it?
Because often my thoughts will just linger a bit and sometimes it distracts me when I'm getting pulled away so often.
Do you mean breaking your flow?
Yeah.
Okay.
I, personally, I find writing a list for myself every single morning is really, really useful.
I basically used to keep notebooks that I would just keep writing everything down in
and then I've managed to kind of reduce that down to having a page a day diary
and it's just really handy.
Beginning of the day, as soon as I get in, get my coffee, I sit down,
I go through my list or I rewrite my list.
I'm constantly rewriting my list, crossing stuff out.
If anything kind of crops up, like I've always got that, that's like my one thing that I go to.
All right, so we're actually out of time. But we will be out in the hallway talking. First off I
want to thank all of you for coming. I want to thank a few people for the help they gave us.
Siobhan Reddy, Garth DeAngelis, Kim Swift and everyone else who listened and gave us feedback.
I also want to thank the awesome CAs who worked today's session, Cody, Josh, Renee and Keith.
And of course the amazing AV team. Thanks again and we'll be out in the hallway if you have any
questions.