Hi everyone, my name is Sammy. I'm here to give you a talk on how our game worked with our small tester community and Twitch streamers and other types of content creators to launch our game on Steam Early Access.
It is very nice to be here.
This is my second GDC.
In 2016, I came to San Francisco for my first GDC,
and I went to a lot of talks and learned a lot,
and I'm a huge fan of GDC Vault.
So it is very, you know, a kind of an emotional experience
to be here to talk about how we developed the game
and worked with our community
to launch our game successfully on Steam.
and other platforms.
So, okay, I'll jump right in.
So I go by the name Poopy Queen on Twitter and Twitch.
It's just a silly nickname that I have
because my friends used to tease me in college
that I poop on their strategy when I play games with them.
And I thought, you know, if I had this memorable nickname,
people will remember me.
And I think it's a tip for a lot of indie studio,
like community managers.
If you have a memorable nickname,
they will remember you because there were times in like during alpha or beta a lot of you know
streamers were like who's that girl like poopy something that works on player knows battlefield
whatever and they remembered my name so it was very like effective so I think that's a tip.
I used to do community management but now I'm focusing more on marketing but
For all the India teams out there, you can do it on your own in the beginning,
but don't forget to scale the team in the later phase,
because that's what we are going through right now.
Kind of, that's the pain point we're going through.
So moving on.
So these are the key takeaways for my talk.
There was an article on New York Magazine titled,
How an Unfinished Game with No Marketing
Came Out of Nowhere to Dominate the Internet,
which is kind of true and not true in a sense
because it wasn't out of nowhere.
We started with a small tester community in 2016,
and we were snowballing our tester community
until early access.
It was invisible to a lot of...
gaming media and the mainstream content creators, but we had this community that we worked really
closely with to really blow up and give more exposure to our game after the early access launch.
So I'm going to be talking about how we went through different phases to slowly grow the community
and give a lot of impact when there was this time where we had to create big momentum
without a big marketing budget. We had zero marketing budget in 2016. It was very humble.
We started as a small team, so I will go into details about that.
And yeah, the third point, how to market your indie game with a zero dollar budget.
I think this is some, you know, this is a topic that will be of interest for many people.
Okay, so a little bit about our team. We started with...
about 25 people, including a business manager and myself.
I started as an interpreter.
I had background in marketing and PR,
but my main job in the beginning of the project
was to translate and interpret for
Brandon Player Unknown Green and the rest of the devs,
so they can communicate and work together.
Part of the core team was the team that developed
DevVillain, which is an action MMORPG.
And the team had worked together for such a long time.
They had great teamwork and over 10 years of experience
in building an online game.
So they had the experience in providing an online service,
but didn't have experience in developing a shooter game.
So that's how we started.
Now I think we have about 200 people.
We are like continuously growing,
so I don't have the number, but yeah.
So, who has not played PUBG?
Show of hands.
Okay.
Who has played PUBG on mobile?
Ooh, yeah, you should definitely give it a try
if you haven't.
It's Valor Reality in a Pocket, yeah.
But, so how we started PUBG was that our producer and the team wanted to develop the first standalone
battle royale game.
I don't know if you're familiar with the entire battle royale, like, history of entire battle
royale genre.
But, um...
When we started our project, the only Battle Royale games that were available in the market was The Culling, H1Z1 King of the Kill, and Arma 3 Battle Royale, which is not an official mode.
Our team wanted to develop a standalone Battle Royale game, and we looked at the...
industry and there was so much potential that Valorant had and we wanted to use that opportunity and
launch our standalone Valorant game as soon as possible. So the goal was, you know, make a
realistic, serious Valorant game with an 8 by 8 kilometer open-world map.
And with that goal, we were just doing some research and thinking about how we should start the project.
And we found this guy who had been working on Battle Royale games for over four years,
and that player is known.
He had developed the first Battle Royale game mod on Arma 2,
and he had recently...
worked with Daybreak Games to help them create H1Z1's King of the Kill,
and we thought, you know, we want to make something authentic, and we...
had a different direction in the beginning,
but realized that we really need to go back to the basics
and create a Battle Royale game with the original feel.
So we reached out to,
our producer reached out to PlayerUnknown,
and it was just over a Skype call,
and then within a few weeks, he flew to Korea
and joined the dev team
and started developing PUBG together.
So that was a little bit about PUBG.
So at the core of our community management programs and strategies, there's community snowballing.
We started with this definition in mind and knew that this was going to help us grow because we
were a small team of 25 people and no one knew about us. Some people know about Terra, which is
MMO game developed by our mother company Bluehole, but we're a small team that had no, you know, marketing budget with the goal
very ambitious goal of launching this standalone Balearic game within a year on Steam Early Access.
So that was the goal and we thought, you know, PR and marketing efforts are not that necessary
if we build a good product.
And with a community snowballing strategy, we thought we could make this work.
and we wanted to tie this with open development.
For those of you who might not heard of snowballing,
you've seen in cartoon movies
where a Donald Duck picks up some snow
and then just rolls down the snowball down the slope
and then it picks up more snow
and grows larger and larger.
That's what we did with our tester community.
So this is just a general definition of community snowballing we had.
We wanted to develop a very close-knit, vibrant tester community.
So I will go through how we recruited people in the next few slides.
To build a community, you have to make them an insider.
We're not a AAA studio, no one is interested in our game.
Like, who cares? Who cares?
Like, Brandon had his Battle Royale community,
but it was a group of really hardcore fans that love Battle Royale.
And it's compared to other gaming communities, it wasn't that big.
So it was very important to us to really understand that core community.
and make them a potential fan of PUBG
in the very early phase of development.
And what's important in community snowballing
is that you have to strengthen relationships
and build loyalty.
This is important to any kind of community management,
but it's much easier to achieve
when you have such a small community.
Like right now, we have a player base of
40 million people just on PC and Xbox,
and it's very difficult to build relationships.
But it's much easier when there's just 500 people.
Like, you can't talk to every single one of them
if you spend like 12 hours a day.
And that was so easy back in 2016,
when I had the time just to give personal attention
to every single tester that was really active.
So.
That's really easy when you have a small community and it's also important to get them really involved in the development process
There are a lot of great talks and presentation on GDC vault about open development
I was a I was watching a lot of those
presentations last year and in
2016 to study what other games did to be transparent to their testers and what we did was
we had a discord server for
Alpha testers and we would share a lot of information in there
And luckily, they didn't care enough to share it on Reddit or anywhere,
so it was just in our Discord and there were like 500 people just checking out web screens
and talking to PlayerUnknown and myself.
And that's something you could use for your community.
So what was special about our snowballing was that Battle Royale games in general have higher viewability.
People love watching it on Twitch or YouTube because you can follow someone's journey from the beginning to end
until that person becomes the last man standing.
And this is something that we wanted to tap into.
So we thought, you know, we have to be...
at least mildly successful on Twitch to promote our game with zero dollar budget.
And we knew that this could be, you know, our go-to marketing strategy from the very beginning.
And the second thing we thought was that we are a small game, you know, and no one was like
expecting us to be a game, like there are people who didn't believe that we would finish the game.
and a lot of Battle Royale players were saying they're not going to finish the game.
H1Z1 was dominating the market at the time
and a lot of Battle Royale hardcore fans loved Arma 3 BR so much.
and although they were very supportive,
they thought, you know, like,
they've never heard of the studio
and they knew that these guys didn't have experience
in building a shooter game, so there was some doubt.
And we thought, you know.
it's very important to reach out to those who would support us because that would be, you know,
that would help us amplify and give more exposure to our game in the long run. And what was also
important was that content creators are always looking for new content and
especially the lower tier ones are looking for something that's unique to differentiate their channels.
A lot of bigger, like, top tier streamers will only play your game if it's mainstream
or if it will, like, grow their viewership as well
or if it's, like, a very, like, hot topic of that, like, week.
But we knew that we couldn't, we didn't have the money to pay the top tier streamers to play our game when we did our public alpha test.
And we knew that the streamers that are in the mid-tier would be interested because they want to differentiate their channel with low cost.
and they want to create something unique so they can stand out from the crowd.
And they don't have the resources or the connection to have access to exclusive content
of AAA studios. There was this opportunity for a mutually beneficial relationship.
And we knew that if we gave them exclusive content and a chance to create something unique,
they would support us.
So I've lined out a few points here, but I will.
go through all the details later.
So we did our first alpha
after developing the game for four months.
You will see that small screenshot.
That's just the key art we had created.
Brandon had tweeted out,
hey guys, I'm finally excited to announce
that I'm working on my own standalone Valorant game.
And you can see that it got like 2,000 likes.
And we were very stoked to have this
I'm just having this flashback while I talk about this.
And we had 1100 resistor testers.
That's a pretty small tester community.
And only 600 of them participated, and we had six hours of testing.
So this is, you know, I'll be uploading this presentation later on GDC.
You can check it out.
We had, you know, we were very scrappy.
This was our Google form.
We just posted this on Brandon's Twitter and our website
so people can click this Google form and sign up.
And we only looked at their PC specs and a few other things.
And on top of this, we invited the streamers that have been
long-time fans of Brandon's Battle Royale mods.
So this is just the content and marketing calendar
that I developed.
I wanted to establish a healthy cadence
for content to show to our community.
Brandon was very active, he was writing dev blog posts
and showing a lot of the stuff that was in development
on his Twitter and Discord.
Like, here are the samples,
like you can check them out on our dev blog,
and here are a lot of the WIP screens or videos we had.
So the question we had before we moved into our closed alpha was that,
do we really want to test this?
Like after four months of development,
our build didn't look like what we wanted to, you know, show to the world.
And there was like a lot of debate around it.
Like, should we really do a public test?
Although there was an NDA, we're very insecure about it.
But...
you know, this is what our game looked like after four months.
It looks, you know, definitely different from what, you know, you played these days.
The tone is different and there are a lot of bugs and the UI, you know, looks very interesting.
So we had this debate for weeks,
do we really want to show this to our small tester community
that are really passionate about this project?
And the answer is, you have to do it.
As an indie team.
There was no pre-launch hype. We distributed press release, no one really cared about. We got some
coverage, but it didn't give us a lot of exposure and we had no marketing resources. And this,
you know, closed alpha test was a great chance to really communicate to our tester community that we
are like committed to this and we have built something just in four months and we're excited
to show what we have in store in the next eight or
10 months. And we made it a privilege. We were very insecure about showing this build and thought
people are not going to be happy or they're not going to have confidence in us. But
it was a privilege because you had to be invited.
and you had to be a streamer,
you had to be Brandon's longtime fan,
or you had to have good PCs to be able to test
that alpha build because it was very heavy back then.
And giving them exclusivity worked out very well
because they had access to this exclusive content
on the private Discord server,
and we were giving them information
that no one had access to.
We didn't even share it.
with the media and we did a lot of communication to help every single player and tester understand
that this is a very early version of the build.
We communicated that on a daily basis and I don't think it hurts to really iterate that
so they truly understand that this is a product that's being worked on.
So then after a couple months, we moved to our first alpha.
That pubs, that's not a typo
because we used to call pub G like pubs.
And in our first pre-alpha, our game looked different and it also started different.
We would have 64 people running out of a starting building.
And a funny story I wanted to share with you guys is that our office in Seoul is close to
a military base and we would have C-130 flying over the building all the time.
and Brandon thought we have the plane like in other VR modes so maybe this is a sign so we
should put the plane like into the game so that's you know how we have the plane in the game if C-130
didn't fly over our office maybe it you know PUBG would start in a starting building 100 people
running out of the you know building that would be pretty hilarious but um
So for the first alpha, we lifted the NDA,
which means we allowed everyone to create videos,
share screenshots, and stream it on Twitch.
And our performance on Twitch during the test phase
was 44,000 viewers at peak, which is not bad,
but we're like in top 10,
and there were a lot of games that had the viewership
of 128,000,
and we still had a small viewer base and you know this was at peak and
average was much lower than that. So to lift or not to lift we had this debate
again before the alpha test because you know we were all insecure again like do
we want to show this to the public but this time it was even more scary because
If we lift the NDA, everyone will see the game on Twitch.
And we're not very confident that this was at a stage
where we can show it to millions and thousands of people.
But...
At the end of the day, we knew that we're just showing progress and we have to build, you know
some sort of hype towards beta and the next alpha and
Brandon and our producer had this long discussion for days and days and we thought this is going to you know
Work for us. We have to show what we have and
It will be
you know, great for them because they have access to this test build that no one else has
because they were invited or part of the tester community.
So it's really important to, you know, reinforce that sense of, you know,
exclusivity. Like we always communicated this and there were, you know, a small group of people who
were wondering how you get access to that test and, you know, we would tell them you have to sign up.
Maybe in our next alpha test you will be included, you should wait for that.
So that really, you know, drove some interest among people who saw our game on Twitch and got interested.
And if there was a Twitch streamer who wanted to participate, we gave them keys.
Like, we wanted to, you know, we wanted the streamers to stream it and give us feedback on their live streams.
So moving on to Alpha 2, we did our Alpha test for four weekends.
And you will see that, you know, our logo looked differently
for our Alpha and this time...
we had a bigger tester group.
We opened the applications for sign up again
and we also identified and invited more testers and streamers.
A lot of people asked me in 2016 or 2017
how I invited a lot of streamers to our test.
And it's very simple.
You just go to their YouTube and Twitter
and find their email address and send cold emails.
So you do that for two weeks, and then you
have this long list of 1,000 people.
And you just send out a Google form.
That's how it really works.
But sometimes it will just end up in their spam folder.
And then after six months, you'll hear back from them.
Hey, Sammy, I got your email.
It was in spam folder.
How can I get access to your alpha test?
like that happens sometimes but um you know when you send cold emails they don't really
read it or they get interested unless it's something they've heard of but what really
works is that if they watch their fellow streamers streaming the game on twitch
and they don't have access they want it
They want it and then they will you know somehow find you on Twitter
And ask for you know keys
So that's what started to happen in our alpha because we had it
You know we had the test for four weekends
and the group of streamers that have been with us from pre-alpha started streaming a lot
and they really loved what we had achieved, they saw improvements
and there was a lot of positive word of mouth going around
and that spread across Twitch
and other streamers who didn't have access were wondering, like, how do I get access?
and then they would ask their friends, fellow streamers
where do you get keys would sometimes you know give more keys to you know streamers so they can
share it with their community or friends or sometimes they would tell you know their fellow
streamers like go to Poopy Queen like she's on Twitter and then you know that's a very easy name
to remember so they would come to me on Twitter and then say like where are my keys like how come
I don't get them so I would spend like hours and hours um
sending out keys via Twitter and email.
And there was one time that during closed beta,
a lot of the streamers just wanted the keys
like at that moment that sometimes out hit
the limit of Twitter DMs.
So if you send more than like three or 500 DMs in a day,
like Twitter shuts you down.
So you can't send DMs anymore.
So there were times where I would post on Twitter,
hey guys, I've hit my limit again.
I can't send you keys anymore.
Like here's my email.
Or I would just post keys on Twitter.
So that's how you do it when you don't have money
and it does work.
So we had 800 streamers participated.
You can definitely see that the number has grown from 128.
It's because I was just running around,
giving away keys, inviting more streamers.
And for Alpha 2, we also had a couple of...
external teams helping me out to identify more streamers that have not played Arma 3BR, H1Z1,
The Culling, or other games. So the question we had was that if we scale this up by hiring a team
of influencer management experts to identify more streamers, maybe we could grow this bigger. Maybe
we could have a bigger streamer community.
And this is not a firm answer, but what I want to say by saying no to this question is that
they really want to talk to the developers.
Like, they really appreciate it when you approach them and give them information,
even if it's just a couple of Twitter DMs.
They want to talk to the developers or the community manager.
They don't want to talk to your PR rep.
And...
you know, the folks at the PR agency, they might be, you know, hardworking people,
but they're not as invested as you.
Like, they're not going to wake up at 2 a.m.
and see a Twitter tweet and a streamer is like, where's my key?
I want to play it now.
And then that streamer has like 20,000 viewers on Twitch.
You've got to give them the key now.
But the agency is not going to do that. Right.
And.
You're really desperate to get the keys to the hands of the streamers.
So it's really important that you have someone that's fully committed to driving this effort
while your test is publicly available and streamable on Twitch and YouTube.
And what really helps is that there are people on Twitch that still remember how I used to work with them.
And that really builds personal relationships.
And that pays back because they just want to help you.
And they know how you have been scrappy, like sleeping for six hours, you know.
And I was always responsive and they really appreciate that because...
I helped them grow their business at one point.
When we were small, we were not very helpful in giving them push or helping them grow viewership.
But when we made it, sort of, streaming our game was what they wanted to do and I was available.
and they really appreciate that because I gave them access.
It sounds very simple, but they remember that and they will help you.
They will help you distribute more keys and talk positively about your game.
And I said this in the beginning, they always look for new or better content to build their business on.
Some people still make fun of streamers saying,
like, how do you make money just playing games?
Like, they take it very seriously.
All these successful streamers think like an entrepreneur.
So it's a business for them.
And you have to think.
like a partner, how do I provide opportunities and unique content for them to, you know,
be differentiated, for them to be different and stand out from millions of other streamers.
So we moved to closed beta in early 2017 and
Then we still had a small community, but much bigger than what we had during our alpha phase.
And we wanted to reach a larger target market, so we looked at other games that are not Battle Royale or have Battle Royale game modes.
We looked at casual gamers and top tier streamers and variety streamers.
And I continued to send cold emails, you know, Twitter DMs, tweets,
and also asked our community members to...
talk to their friends about our game.
And one thing we did during closed beta
was that we developed this Discord bot
that was in our private server.
So you would type a command,
and then that Discord bot would send you
like five keys via DM.
Like it was a very effective strategy
to distribute keys to thousands of people that were.
in our Discord test server,
and that was the privilege
that was only given to alpha testers.
So they would type the command and get the keys,
and they could give it to their friends,
or they could do a Twitter promotion.
It's very easy to develop.
It's something that I highly recommend
if you don't have a flashy website to distribute keys.
And we started going to conventions like PAX West and we would have printed out like cars
with key codes and it would just you know hand them out like candies.
And our focus for closed beta was maximizing Twitch and YouTube coverage during closed beta.
My personal goal was, can we hit the number one streamed game on Twitch during this phase?
So that was my goal, and I had to distribute more keys to streamers
so they would stream the game during closed beta.
And this is the charts at the top right corner is a survey we did and it says,
have you participated in previous alphas?
And a large portion of closed beta testers hadn't participated in our previous tests,
which means our strategy of promoting this through Twitch streamers were effective.
You know, that was effective because...
People had not heard about us in the news, they just saw us on Twitch and found out that we were
you know running closed beta, got interested and came to us for keys.
So this is what we did during closed beta.
I will go into more detail in the next slide.
We had like a Twitch parachute
to celebrate the Twitch streamer community.
We had built from pre-alpha.
We had a small booth at PAX East.
And one of the interesting things we did
is that you'll see on the very...
writes that we had 64 graffitis of streamers like logos or artwork that were placed in the game.
So if you went into Erangel and played you would see those like graffitis and this was to celebrate
the top streamers that helped us you know promote our game during
of second alpha and closed beta and this worked out very well for us.
So we wanted to reward loyal testers and streamers,
and the graffiti event that I showed you
is one of the activities we did.
And to reward loyal testers,
you might have heard of this famous PlayerUnknown set,
where you get that PlayerUnknown coat and mask
that was given out to all the alpha testers.
And for the streamers who have been supporting us since like alpha and who started actively
supporting us during beta, we would give them extra keys. There were some streamers who got like
100 or 500 keys that they could share with their community and they could do like a
gleam giveaway or twitter giveaway to grow their following.
And that worked very well because we didn't give out keys ourselves.
And having those extra keys to share with whoever wanted them
helped them grow their following on Twitter,
or sometimes random people would stop by
and do like a chat giveaway to get keys from their Twitch chat.
And what we also did was that we were always watching Twitch a lot.
During closed beta, a lot of our devs had Twitch up on their screen while they were developing.
And there were a lot of interesting feedback from the streamers.
So sometimes we would actually acknowledge the feedback and act on it
and give credit to the streamer or player after implementing that change.
And then, you know, in a couple of days,
it will be our one year anniversary.
And so we, you know, launched our early access
on March 23rd.
And in 16 days, something happened.
Like we were, we got like the Guinness record
for selling 1 million units on Steam as an early access game
and then we got six other records
for selling too many copies in a very short time,
which was unexpected.
No one expected this in our team.
Brandon and I were the most optimistic people.
We were cheerleaders and our devs were like,
you guys are crazy, you guys just watch Twitch too much,
you guys hear good things from the streamers,
you guys are too optimistic, you gotta calm down.
But Brandon and I would be like,
we're gonna sell two million copies,
and they're like, you guys are being ridiculous.
But, you know, we hit the record and it's all history.
And then during early access, we launched our PUBG Partner Program.
And the PUBG Partner Program is...
something we were able to launch during early access because we became a bit successful during early access.
We are now in a position where we were able to reward streamers for streaming our game.
So we had a sign up page on our website where streamers would come and enter their information
and we would select streamers that had...
that could be a great part of our community,
and we would give them rewards.
Rewards like VIP access to our parties
and access to custom games.
Custom games is a feature in our game
where you can create custom games for your community
and then change the settings of Val Royale in our game.
And then there were other perks that comes with the program.
So the key points of early access, we continued to give benefits, but now we had the resources
and some money to give back. And we wanted to give them bigger exposure.
We launched a small advertising campaign and we were able to feature a lot of streamers there.
So we had a Facebook and YouTube campaign where we would grab clips of Twitch streamers enjoying the game.
it's available on our YouTube channel and you can see, you know, we tried to capture all the crazy
moments they had and it's so fun to watch because their reactions were crazy. This was a new game to
them and there were a lot of, you know, funny bugs and glitches and we just showed it all so that
people would think, oh, like, I want to play that game. What kind of, you know, game is that we...
had that ad campaign and it gives them exposure.
And all the streamers that participated in this
just did it for free.
And we later rewarded them.
So we also did the in-game graffiti event
that I showed you earlier
and it gave them access to custom games.
And...
The other thing we did was we created events to really celebrate the community that we built with them.
And one of the most successful events we ever did was the Twitch Charity Invitational.
You can find out more about the event if you Google it, but basically it was...
We invited 64 streamers from North America and another 64 from Europe.
And we had this huge group of streamers fighting with each other throughout a few games.
we got so much exposure through this and the viewers loved it because they always love when
there's rivalry going on among Twitch streamers and we were able to hit an all-time peak in terms
of viewership.
And we also had a streamer exclusive Pax East Mixer
where we would invite content creators and Twitch streamers
and really, you know, communicate with them.
We had, you know, Brandon come in
and he would talk about what's in store for PUBG,
how we plan to continue to develop the game
until we launch 1.0.
There were other programs and activities we did.
We had Dev Livestreams.
You can watch that on our official Twitch channel.
Yeah, we had, we, you know, arranged it ourselves.
There were a lot of audio and sound issues.
You should definitely watch it to learn what not to do in your dev livestreams
because there are so many issues and it shows how we are not prepared,
but kind of not afraid to give it a go and fail fast and learn quickly.
But you should definitely watch if you plan
to do like a dev livestream for the first time.
And we gave rewards to all the alpha testers, which was the player unknown set, which is not available anymore.
And we attended Twitch meetups. Twitch is a bit interesting because they have a lot of local meetups in different cities and states.
And we attended those meetups to talk to streamers and talk about our game.
So I was like a salesperson for our game.
any months and you have to understand what it's like to be a streamer so
I created my own Twitch channel and streamed for three months.
And I highly encourage that to all the community managers
who do not stream because it really helps you understand
what it feels like to get donations and grow your following.
And that really helped me understand how they think
when they want to grow their business and to viewers.
And it's also important to what it's like to be a viewer or a fan.
So what I did was I watched Twitch like all day long
during our alpha or beta phase and wanted to understand what kind
of relationship they build with their viewers.
At one point I was subscribed to 50 streamers and I was just paying that out
of my own pocket. I just wanted to support them for being
such a passionate part of our community.
But it really helps like.
because they know that you are from a small team and I'm just, you know, like a fangirl that want to support them
and it also helped me build like a special relationship.
So just to go over the key points,
these are the points that I wanted to really highlight
through today's talk.
Number one, you have to start with a small,
like exclusive community of hand-selected members first.
We had the privilege of starting with a small community
that Brandon already had built for many, many years,
and they were already big fans of Balrial Games.
And what's important is that to really strengthen that sense of exclusivity.
If it's open to anyone, they're not going to be really interested.
They want to be treated special, and they want to have something
that's just exclusive to a small group of people.
And if you take good care of them and start treating them differently
after a certain time, they just become like genuine ambassadors for your gang.
The second point would be that you have to, you know, especially for streamers,
you have to give them something exclusive, something they can consume.
Even if it's just a small nugget of information that's really important to
their business and you have to make them feel like an insider.
And that really.
helps them build their business and for testers, they feel like they belong to the community.
And you know, you allow them to shape your game by allowing them to give feedback and you act
on them and you have to communicate the changes you made based on their feedback. And it's also
important to communicate how, what they will gain from being part of this community. It's
they're in it for some reason, they want something back.
It's not that you have to pay them
or have to reward them in some way,
but it's always good to provide them
with all the perks or benefits you can.
And while it's difficult to do that as a small team
without a big budget,
there are a lot of things that you could try.
I've shared the examples, and if you go to our dev blog,
you will find a lot of evidence there.
The things that we could have done but didn't do because we didn't have time,
I still kind of feel like if we gave in-game badges for Alpha testers,
that would be really cool because you can brag about that.
And we wanted to launch an activity point program to reword testers
that were more active than the rest of the community,
but we didn't have time to.
So it's something that you could look into.
And, you know, it also, we wanted to have like a multi-tiered reward program for the streamers and testers.
But we're just busy, I was busy handing out keys and talking to all our testers.
So this is something you could, I would like to do if I could turn back time.
The third point, content creators, Twitch streamers,
they have to be part of your marketing plan
if you don't have the budget,
and they will help you if you build
the relationship the right way.
But they're not marketing tools.
A lot of publishers pay them to play the game.
You're not going to be able to build a relationship by doing that.
And it's just a one-off thing.
Like, they have to be emotionally invested.
And to do that, you have to commit to building
a mutually beneficial relationship with them.
You have to, you know, invest a lot of your time.
That's how I did it.
And to do that, you know, you have to understand their business.
You have to, you know, you highly recommend streaming yourself
and becoming their hardcore fans and also treat them as your business partners.
The last point I wanted to emphasize was that you have to directly talk to your players and streamers.
Having an agency or outside help is always good when you only have limited time,
but you should only do that when you want to scale things up,
or when you don't really have the time to reach out to someone who's not a hardcore fan or who is like a...
streamer that wants to support you, but not as someone, you know, as passionate as your key, like, tester.
Because you have to directly talk to them to build relationships, and that level of intimacy you build
like, grows and then helps you in the end.
If I could turn back time, I would rethink how I want to build a team out.
Because when we came out of early access, we didn't anticipate the kind of success we had.
And we only had a few people in the community.
I was the one who started talking to the streamers.
and there were community coordinators and assistant community managers that would interact with the testers.
And I really regret not scaling fast enough to be able to communicate to a community that would grow exponentially in the next few months.
And we also failed to maintain the level of transparency we had in 2016 and 2017,
because things grew so fast and we were not ready for that.
So I highly recommend growing the team before things take off so you're ready for that kind
of exposure and the need for interaction.
So that's it for my talk and thanks for your time.
And we're currently growing our team based in Amsterdam,
Seoul, Santa Monica, and other regions.
So if you're interested, hit me up on Twitter.
I'll be able to talk to you about TopG
and other positions that you might be interested.
Thank you.
So it looks like I have a few minutes for questions.
If you have any questions, you can come up,
and then I'll be happy to answer any questions you have.
Got a question.
Okay.
To what extent do you validate the identity of streamers?
I find this quite time-consuming.
Okay, so what it takes to validate the authenticity of streamers?
My answer would be that you have to spend a lot of time to watch them
and check their Twitter, you know, see what kind of content they've created in the past.
It's definitely time-consuming and it's something that...
is difficult to overcome, but one thing you could do is look at what other games have worked on.
We have a list of partners available on our Twitter. Maybe you could look into that,
because that means we've spent our time and that's the resource you could use,
because we validated them. There are a lot of other games that have a list of partners
available on their websites.
So that's something you could use.
Did you find Keymailer useful at all?
Who?
Keymailer.
It's a system of distributing keys to streamers.
Oh, and using what? I didn't get that.
Keymailer.
Basically, a YouTuber or a Twitch streamer would register with Keymailer.
Oh, Keymailer.
Oh, we used, like, we worked with some...
beta test focus media to distribute more keys and I don't believe we use Keymailer but it was a
platform that we had interest in and if we you know would have used them if we had time to work
with them. Okay thanks. Thank you.
I'll switch languages. .
. And I'm going to switch back to English now.
I'm the community manager for a mobile gaming company called Metamoki.
And I know we're rolling out a game and the devs are really keen to bring people in.
So some of these I'm going to try, although it's mobile, so it's a little different.
And my question is this.
Well, first, thank you for sharing your insights and your fails.
But that's something I'll probably be tasked with is kind of getting a feel for the key
times to kind of scale that team up, right?
You know, and to expand, and that's something...
Can you go a little bit deeper into, like, what those key moments were where you probably
should have?
So when did I realize that I should scale up my team?
I realized that...
few months ago because it has been a very overwhelming experience to have a game that
has like a 40 million player base on Xbox and PC.
But when I think we had this moment during closed beta when streamers were really enjoying
the game they couldn't get enough of the game so they would beg us to extend the testing
time and they were enjoying the whole experience so much they couldn't stop talking about it
on Twitter or Twitch.
And I feel like, oh, we have these like hundreds,
not dozens of people, hundreds of people talking
about our game on Twitch and Twitter.
That's when you should really scale things up
when they are really emotionally invested
and they want your game to succeed.
And they actually talk about it on live stream.
Like we had Shroud saying, I want to support these guys.
These guys just made a great game within like a year.
And I feel like that's when I should have hired
four people to start building like.
more relationships with content creators.
Thank you.
Hi, so you mentioned that having an initial nucleus
of a community which knew of Brendan's work helped,
but what would you suggest to people who are starting out
and have to build that community from scratch?
And the second question is that on mobile,
I know you haven't shared that part of your journey here,
but given the context that many similar games
were already there on mobile,
how did you choose to launch PUBG Mobile
and how do you plan to expand the community there?
Okay, so your first question is, what do you do when you don't have a player unknown, right?
Yeah.
So, you know, what we did was, Brandon had a community, but what you can do is look at
the fan base or community that already exists that are interested in the genre of the game that
you're going to develop. Because there will be a community that's interested in, you know,
your competitors, and you look at them and you can approach them and say, oh, we're going to develop
like a similar game.
but differently. That's how you can start building your community and that's what we kind of did
with people who are not really interested in our stand-alone game. And your second question was
how did we decide to launch PUBG Mobile and how we plan to grow the community there.
thought it would be cool to play Battle Royale on your mobile phone
and we worked with, co-developed the game with Tencent
and it was an easy decision, like we want our game to be on all platforms
so that people can enjoy Battle Royale wherever they go
and I got a lot of tweets from our players that it's so cool to play PUBG when they're, you know, pooping
so that's, you know, and it's cool, like
we had the resource and time and we knew that the players wanted that.
It's all about providing what they want.
For mobile, it's going to be a challenge,
but we definitely want to start implementing the same strategies
and introduce similar programs to mobile as well.
Thank you.
Hi.
I was just wondering within the grand scheme of things,
what role, if any, did early access play?
play. Yeah. Was it necessary? It was definitely, it was not necessary in terms of community
management. It was the, our dev team's goal to develop a standalone battle royale game
as an early access game within a year. And I think it was definitely necessary for development
because it helped us snowball the community as well, because we were pushing out patches
and fixing everything.
on a weekly, bi-weekly basis.
And that really got our community excited
because we were listening to their feedback,
we were fixing bugs as we go.
And it was an interesting time for our community
to see the game evolve and change on a weekly basis.
And that, alongside the snowballing strategy
for the community, helped our community grow further.
Thank you.
Thank you for the talk. I think you're the greatest community managers in the world.
And I thought you share your knowledge and your experience right now, and I think there
will be more people copying it. And if you had a next project, and I think at that time
you have a marketing budget more than this time.
What would you do to expand your community for that new title?
If I could turn back time and had more money to do community management for PUBG,
I would spend that money in building platforms for key distribution, which took up a lot of my time.
And I'd also spend a lot of time in building well-branded assets.
so that we could raise brand awareness and help the streamers,
help them with...
We want to give them content they can post on Twitter.
We had a very scrappy graphic assets,
and you want the streamers and YouTubers to use your assets
in their content.
So we can get exposure through their channels,
but we're not very good at that.
I would spend a lot of time in graphic design
and provide them with...
all the graphic assets that they can post on Twitter.
Yeah.
Okay, thank you.
Thank you.
I was wondering if you could provide a bit more insight
into how you channeled some of your community feedback,
especially as you went through alpha and into beta,
because as communities grow,
you get more and more different groups
pulling in different directions.
Did you, would you say you put more time
into that initial alpha group and gave them more weight,
or did you try and spread things out evenly?
Or do you have any insight you can provide around that?
So your question is how do we channel all the feedback we had?
Yeah, and did you give any weight to certain groups,
like that initial alpha core group,
or the streamers as you brought them on board,
or as things opened up to just everybody,
did any group hold more weight to what you brought forward?
Um, well it's not, I don't think it was about giving, you know, weight,
more weight to certain pieces of feedback.
It was more about testing something and then iterating.
So we would act on something we think that's going to work and we iterate.
If that works, you know, we implement that to the next build.
That's how, you know, things worked.
There were some feedback that we're not sure of, you know,
in early phase of alpha, we're not sure.
that whether we should have like first-person perspective,
which is something, you know, ridiculous to think about now
when like a large part of the community enjoys first-person perspective.
But there were a lot of streamers behind that idea and testers that supported that.
And we gave it a try and people just, you know, loved it.
And they said this is like the real like Battle Royale.
So I think it's something that you have to learn as you go and implement the changes.
And you just have to iterate.
You might fail, but you'd have to accept it.
Thank you.
Hi, thanks for the talk first.
And my question is that at a certain point,
when your community becomes so large,
I'm pretty sure players all over the world like PUBG.
There are players from Brazil, players from Japan, players from Spain.
They speak different languages.
How do you manage the streamers and YouTubers and make sure to give them the same personal
touch and to maximize the effort?
So how have we been communicating with a lot of content creators
from different countries that speak different languages?
Yeah.
We didn't have that luxury during early access.
We only had someone for Korea and China, as far as I remember.
But...
what we did was we had a lot of Miis for other languages.
So we had one person for Chinese, Japanese,
and then we had one person for French at one point.
So.
you could hire freelancers who would do the job to talk to the content creators
if you're not sure about whether your game is going to scale up and have a bigger community.
But it's something that you could definitely train other people to do
and do it on behalf of you if you have the core programs lined out.
Thank you.
Congratulations for PUBG's success.
And thanks for your sharing.
I'm curious about that.
We know PUBG's MS do the publishing work and the
reverb do the marketing work.
So you said at the beginning, PUBG is almost a zero budget
for marketing.
So why you say this way?
So you're saying we had some agencies that we worked with and then we had...
Yeah, well, we did the minimum.
We got to get the news out, distribute the press release.
So we had a PR agency that distributed the press release and arranged interviews for us.
But that's not really marketing.
It's like the minimum you have to do to give you some kind of exposure.
But by saying zero marketing budget, what I wanted to deliver was that those activities weren't effective.
It didn't do us a lot of favor and we didn't get a lot of exposure from that.
And all the results that we had came from the activities we did outside of that.
Of course, you have to have a PR agency.
You don't know if you're going to blow up and then have a lot of media requests coming in.
Thank you.
Hi. So you guys have a forum that's on your own site.
You have a forum and discussion boards on Steam and on Xbox
and all these different entry points and places for communities.
But I noticed that through your talk you're just saying engaging
with our community as one entity.
But in reality, it's actually very fractured and splintered.
On your own community, there's hundreds of thousands of posts on Steam, there's a factor
of 10 less.
How do you manage all of these different communities?
Is there a strategy to doing that?
Is there a desire to have a singular community for all of that?
What are some of your thoughts on that?
So your question is, we have a lot of channels, how do you be efficient and manage them?
Do we have a strategy to manage all different outlets?
Well, it's a bit of like a painful question to answer, because that's our pain point right now,
because we didn't have time to consolidate everything in like the last few months.
That's what we want to work on this year.
And in the beginning, we only had a few channels like Discord, our forum.
and that was it. But now we have a lot of different channels, different players that speak, you know,
different languages. So what we want to do is, we understand that it's going to be difficult to have
a singular community. We just want to find like the right platform or even build one that will,
you know, help our players interact with other community members and really enjoy having a
conversation around PUBG.
and that's something we want to explore in the next few months
since we've been so busy developing the game and growing the community.
Thank you.
Great talk, thank you for sharing.
During closed alpha, did you allow anyone exclusive access to share what they were doing,
either through a video or a writer or something along those lines,
or did you decide to keep everything closed?
For closed pre-alpha, there was an NDA.
So they're only allowed to talk about it,
but not post any screenshots or share a video.
And then when we started our first alpha,
we lifted the NDA and then allowed people
to share any video screenshots from the previous test.
OK, thank you.
Thank you.
Thanks for your time.