Thank you all for coming. My name is Jonathan Ackley and I work at Walt Disney Imagineering
Research and Development and I produce and I'm the creative director of various interactive
theme park attractions but I'm a very, very old game developer with games dating back to the 19
LucasArts adventure games including The Curse of Monkey Island.
Thank you all for coming.
Let me introduce you, my partner in this talk, Chris Purvis.
Hi, I'm Chris Purvis.
I also am with Walt Disney Imagineering.
I am very much like Jonathan in that I date back to the early 90s
from the game industry originally,
and we both somehow ended up at Disney together
and have partnered on a lot of the attractions we're going to talk to you about today.
So what we're going to talk today is we're going to talk about how we are using the storytelling
devices that have made Disney Imagineering the most popular theme park company for the
last 50 years and how we are taking the lessons learned from video games, applying it to the
development of those interactive theme park attractions and I apologize, when you fill
out your little surveys, totally forget this part.
So we're going to talk about storytelling in themed environments,
how we can apply the lessons learned in video games to gaming in the real world.
So we're going to start off talking about Mickey's Ten Commandments,
and you'll learn about what that is.
We'll talk about some of our projects moving forward,
and we'll talk about what lessons you can take from the video game industry
and bring into the physical world, and which ones are best left behind,
and what the differences are, and how to apply them.
So at Imagineering...
We're all about storytelling through new technology.
That is really how Walt founded his theme park group.
He wanted to take the worlds of his movies,
bring them into the real world,
and let our guests travel through those worlds.
And clearly, that turned out to be a very popular idea.
But what we are doing is we are taking that same Disney storytelling...
just like Walt had it, but we're turning on its head.
So now, our guests are becoming the main characters
in the Disney stories.
So I'd like to start off by some of the principles
which ground storytelling at Walt Disney Imagineering.
Tell you about a famous Imagineer named Marty Sklar.
Marty Sklar is a Disney legend.
He was with the company and he ran the creative
for Walt Disney Imagineering for many, many years.
He was also Walt's writer back in the 1950s and 60s,
ever since the Disneyland days.
And one day he was talking with Mickey Mouse.
And Mickey Mouse dictated to Marty some rules
behind storytelling in a dimensional world.
So I'll quickly go over them.
Obviously, you can probably read them faster than I can talk them.
But talk a little bit about them.
Give them some context.
Because these absolutely apply, I believe, to the products
that you guys make every day.
So know your audience.
Don't bore them.
Obviously, you want to know who you're making your art for.
You're going to tailor it to things that interest them, to the technologies that they use and
understand, to things that are going to intrigue them, little bits of magic that are going
to make them wonder.
You don't talk down to them.
You don't say, well, this is for kids, so I don't have to try as hard.
You try and make it as great as possible.
Wear your guest's shoes.
Anybody who's worked in testing knows this is very important.
You could create the most fabulous attraction,
but it requires you to walk a marathon.
That's not going to be very popular.
You need to understand who your guests are
and really design for them.
Organize the flow of good people and ideas.
This is just basic, good storytelling.
You want to be clear.
You want them to know your intention.
And you want to show them where they're going
and why they're going there.
Now create a weenie. A weenie is Walt's word.
A weenie is a large visual object that draws your focus, that really grounds and sets the
stage for an area. So at Disneyland, the castle is the first weenie that you see when you
enter the park. It draws you. You know you're there.
When you turn right towards Tomorrowland, what do you see?
You see the weenie down there. It's Space Mountain.
So these things give people focus, things to look at.
It's not a huge clutter.
Communicate with visual literacy.
So this is just good artwork.
Don't just throw it up there.
Think about it.
Plan it out.
Avoid overload.
If you fill everything with tremendous detail, people are
going to get tired.
You can't look at everything and focus on every detail.
Be sparing.
Choose important visuals.
This is a very important one. Tell one story at a time.
So, again as I said, at Imagineering it all begins with a story.
So everything in a land has to make sense.
You know, you wouldn't have Fantasyland and place NASCAR Days of Thunder racing simulator in it.
You'd be telling two different stories, the two stories don't match, the guests feel that.
and they know something's wrong.
So your storytelling needs to make sense.
Avoid contradiction.
It's very similar to the last point.
Now for every ounce of treatment, provide a ton of fun.
This is sweat the details.
This means it's not just good enough to tell a clear story.
You wanna give them as much value as possible.
And that really is baked into Imagineering,
back from the original Imagineers, as told by Walt Disney.
and keep it up.
Now this may be something that's less important
in a photonic world, but in a physical world,
as we're gonna be talking about, this is really important.
In the real world, you can't run at nine meters a second
for three hours straight.
You can't jump down 15 feet.
And things break, right?
In a video game, you can put 50 pounds of dynamite
against a wall, blow it up, and that wall still looks great.
Sun, rain, wind, five-year-olds,
they have more power than you think.
And so you have to focus on designing for maintainability
and also putting resources to keeping things up
and working well.
So I'll talk about Agent P's World Showcase Adventure.
And this was my first attraction
that I designed and produced at Walt Disney.
It wasn't really designed to be an attraction.
I was working in research and development
and had been working in a lot of mobile stuff.
And my boss came to me one day and said,
eh, you know, you used to make adventure games.
Why don't you make an adventure game
with Kim Possible in Epcot?
Because there was a perception at the time
that there wasn't much for kids to do in Epcot.
So maybe we could do a test.
And so I went into it thinking, all right,
I can translate some of what I did
back at the LucasArts Adventure Games.
bring it to the physical world, and maybe make WDI smart about how we might use cell
phones, mobile devices, which were really just emerging at the time, make us a little
smarter and maybe someday somebody will do an attraction about it.
So eventually Kim Possible became Agent P's World Showcase Adventure.
So forgive me if I get confused and use them interchangeably.
So the guest's role, which is very important, it all begins with a story, is a secret agent
EPCOT World Showcase, if you've never been there,
is designed like a world's fair,
with a whole bunch of different pavilions,
each pavilion representing a different country.
So for our story, as a secret agent,
the secret agent would go from country to country,
solving, foiling the crimes of the evil villains
from the Kim Possible TV show.
And because it was a high-tech story,
I could use mobile devices.
Secret agents would use mobile devices.
So it was a consistent story.
World Showcase, modern day world, secret agents,
electronic devices, the interface and the story
and the locations all work together holistically.
So this is the drawing of the UK Pavilion.
It celebrates a different culture of the world.
So our design goals.
We wanted to make our guests the main character
without disturbing the park experience
for non-participating guests.
So imagine if you were working on a massively multiplayer
RPG, maybe it was set in a fantasy world, and space men kept walking through it.
This would not be appropriate, this wouldn't be good storytelling, you wouldn't be telling
one story at a time.
And also, we have guests who would not be participating in the experience, they're just
enjoying the environment of World Showcase, which by the way, is my favorite theme park.
Great food, great adult beverages, you'd love it.
Story and interface.
Agent P is a classic, non-linear, puzzle-based adventure game.
Lucas, Sierra, it's just that, but brought to the real world.
So many of the design principles that, you know,
the people who predated me in that, Ron Gilbert and company,
just brought those forward.
They applied directly.
The secret agent story was great because, again,
we didn't want to spoil the existing feel of World Showcase
by adding a whole bunch of Ms. Pac-Man machines,
but spies hide their equipment.
And that made it possible for us to tell our story
without impacting the story of the rest of the guests
in World Showcase.
Now I'm going to show you a little video here.
This is just an example of how Agent P works.
Agent P works, the guests get a communicator, or now
a mobile phone, which I believe is
field operative notification equipment, or phone.
treasure hunt. And the phone tells you the plot, it tells you where to go, exactly where
to go. And when you reach a location, there is a story point that can only be solved by
you, the guest, and by pressing the communicator or the phone button, it triggers the secret
agent device and amazing things happen and you are the hero. So, I'm about to show you
a video. This is part of Agent P's World Showcase Adventure. In it, you've discovered the evil
lair of Dr. Heinz Doofenshmirtz.
And it has a secret underwater opening.
And so you need to trigger Perry the platypus.
Perry the platypus will come out in his boat.
He will set a depth charge,
which you will then trigger to blow open
Duffen Schmertz's secret lair.
So here's that video.
All right, he's set the depth charge.
Now for a kid, this is huge.
For a kid or a computer game professional, this is huge.
Because we all would love to blow things up in the real world, but laws and physics don't
allow it.
But it's particularly important for kids, because kids in this world don't have a lot
of power.
So giving them control over a physical environment is very important.
And when I first opened the Kim Possible playtest...
there was a little girl and she triggered one of the effects
and we were watching from the background.
And the effect came on and she turned to a perfect stranger
and jumped up and down and screamed,
I did it, I did it, I did it, and I swear I cried.
Because I had made that little girl just that happy.
So it's very rewarding, I have found, working in theme parks.
Because when I worked in video games,
the best you would get was you'd hang out
in an electronic boutique and fish for compliments.
No one does that anymore.
Or you'd force your parents to play and they'd say,
oh, it's wonderful beer.
But doing location-based entertainment,
you go out and you actually get to see real people
playing with the toy that you built for them.
It is so rewarding. It is fantastic.
I'll show you another couple of little videos. I won't show them all the way through because
they can be quite long-winded. But in this next one, you find Dr. Dufenshmirtz, who believes
that you are an informant working with him, and he's going to plot to give you a rigged
golf ball to win the evil scientists' open golf tournament. It makes sense if you do.
Alright, I'm going to skip ahead because the audio quality is bad.
In this next one, I'm not even going to describe why this is happening.
It's in the Germany pavilion.
One great thing about working at Walt Disney Imagineering is that there are people around
who can do anything.
You brainstorm these ideas and it's like,
oh, can we do that?
It's like, well, let's ask the laser guy.
Because, you know, we've got one of those.
And so you go talk to the laser guy
and he's like, oh, sure, yes, I can create you a death ray.
And then you don't build it,
but you're just happy to know that you could if you wanted.
So this next video, again, it makes complete lucid sense
when you're in the park, but in Norway,
Dr. Dukenschmerz is attempting to recover.
a stolen bicycle that was pilfered from his Viking neighbor as a child,
and it involves Viking reenactors, and, well, never mind, it doesn't make any sense.
So we have just a great toolbox of special effects animatronic robots.
lasers. It's just a very fun toolbox. And with that I will turn it over to Chris who
will talk about places.
Before we opened this attraction we mocked it up close to full scale in a couple of the
pavilions and ran a test for a few weeks to see how it worked with the audience because
we hadn't really tried anything like this before. Just to make sure that we weren't
being too confusing or making people march too far. And actually,
things we learned that was kind of surprising was how receptive
people were to walking long distances in the Florida sun in
the summer for extended periods of time and staying engaged with
the game and keeping their satisfaction levels up. We were
surprised at how sticky the experience was. The other thing
that was interesting was how
Well, the interactions with the human beings that we enrolled in the test, where we actually
had an interaction where one of the cast members, we have a tea shop in England, and one of
the quests, the guests go in and they ask,
somebody in the tea shop, they give them the secret password.
Danger is my cup of tea.
Right, the phrase.
And then they're handed a special tea bag that has a clue inside of it.
And that was actually one of the highest rated parts of the experience.
Where are we here?
Now, what we didn't know, because there have been very few examples
of location-based entertainment that lasted for...
you know, more than three to ten minutes.
And we proved out during this playtest, which was an exceedingly long
playtest that caused people to march at least a mile, probably over a mile,
in August in Florida.
And as Chris pointed out, the
the results of that playtest were such that we actually turned it into a
complete attraction.
But there are some other things that we worried about. We worried about griefing
in the park.
There was a lot of concern about that.
And it turns out, it's just not an issue.
Our guests to the theme parks are usually very well behaved.
And I also believe that griefing is often caused by a feeling of anonymity online.
You don't have that in a theme park.
No, it's really hard to be mean to the little girl who's waiting in line ahead of you
when she's actually right there.
And we also worried about guests running into each other.
There's a lot of concern about that.
Wouldn't spoil the experience.
Yeah, so Kim Possible, the effects, as you saw,
are mostly mechanical, show action equipment type effects.
They kind of do the same thing over and over and over.
And one of the things that we were afraid of
was that if you were sent to a location
and there's somebody else there and you're sort of waiting
around for your turn.
you'll see what's going to happen and it's going to be the same thing.
And that people would find that as dissatisfying, like,
oh, it's the same show that that guy just got, I already know what's going to happen.
As it turns out, that agency was more important than surprise.
The fact that they got to do it, even though they had already seen what was just about to happen,
even if it was the finale, guests didn't care.
They still wanted to do it themselves.
It was still just as satisfying for them.
And again, that was something that we were...
not expecting.
And it's always fun to talk about your brilliant game design ideas that totally failed, so
I'll tell you one of those right now.
I had a great idea which was going to solve this problem of people spoiling it before.
When two guests arrived at the same location, I can detect that with our location detection
system.
So if one pressed the button, I was going to tell them, oh, your communicator doesn't
have enough power.
Get the other agents around you to all push your button simultaneously.
I thought, ah, I'm a genius.
They refused to do it.
Refused to do it.
They queued up because I don't want to do it with somebody
else, I want to be the one who presses the button and makes
it happen.
So we didn't expect that.
So this attraction is effectively a large
multiplayer game.
We've got up to 700 to 900 people playing it
simultaneously at any given time.
So we had to write the quests such that they could be played
back in any order to allow us to load balance the
attraction.
So it's divided up into missions.
There's one mission per pavilion.
Each one of the missions has a number of steps, and those
steps are actually somewhat non-linear as well.
So we can really route people to any location that we want
based on the current distribution of players and
the current load in a particular land.
We have a disadvantage over you photonic folk in that you can
always put in another shard.
We can't just make another theme park.
So we have to be very careful with our use of the shared
space that is the theme park.
Right.
And really, the only thing that we found that was a big
dissatisfier was that people didn't like to backtrack.
So if we had you going.
World Showcase is a fairly large area.
It's about a mile from all the way around.
It's sort of the circular area around this lake.
And the circumference of it is about a mile.
So what people really hated was when we made them feel like
they're over here in Germany, and then they've
got to go over here to the energy pavilion,
and then back to Germany again.
That kind of drove them nuts, which in retrospect,
we should have realized ahead of time.
We don't do that now.
No, we don't do that.
We took that out.
So the next game I'd like to talk about is a game that Chris and I launched about a year
and a half ago called Sorcerers of the Magic Kingdom.
And the overall conceit behind Sorcerers of the Magic Kingdom is what if all those crazy
trading card games came to life and actually worked?
So what if you had a whole bunch of spell cards?
And when confronted by a villain, all you had to do was choose the spell you wanted to cast,
hold it out in front of you, and it would actually cast the spell.
And so I pitched the idea to Chris, and Chris said,
that's the stupidest thing I ever heard, that's not technically feasible, there's no way we'll do it.
And then he thought about it some more and said, oh yeah, we can do that.
You know programmers, they do it all the time.
So, it's in the Magic Kingdom.
So, the theme of magic was perfect for it.
The guests search out mystic portals scattered all over the entire theme park.
Once they open a mystic portal,
they may be confronted by a friend who will tell them a bit of the story.
They may be confronted by a villain.
If it's a villain, the villain will instantly attack, because villains are mean.
and then you choose the correct card or cards that you feel you need to play to defeat the
villain.
So if Agent P is a classic adventure game, we wanted a full-on role-playing game that
lasted hours and hours and hours and hours and was replayable.
Right. Coming out of the Agent Peek Impossible project, we had a few goals of things we'd like to do better.
One of which was to add some level of replayability, because, again, Agent Peek is the same effects over and over.
And once you've done it, you've seen them all. We wanted to try and fix that.
The other thing we wanted to try and do was come up with a way of doing a game where we didn't have to give you a handset that we needed to maintain an inventory of, because that's actually...
really expensive operationally to do.
Hence the paper cards which don't have any
technology in them at all.
But the main point to take away is
even though we weren't using expensive handsets,
those cards are valuable because those cards...
We put a lot of effort in them.
They're actually valuable works of art that people trade for.
So even though it was less expensive to operate, the
guests got to walk away with something.
And then it added a whole depth of trading within the
experience, which we learned was more important than maybe
we had initially thought.
Right.
So we wanted to make this.
You're going too fast, man.
Sorry.
We wanted to make this accessible to people that just
show up who've never been in the park before and have it be
a fun experience.
But particularly in Walt Disney World, there's a core
group of annual pass holders that are really kind of
frequent repeat visitors.
And we wanted to give them something as well, which would
not always be the same thing over and over again.
Again, that replayability angle.
How do we do that with an RPG without?
having an inventory or a series of stats or something
that's really intricate and hard to read
and difficult to communicate was something
that we had to think about as one of our
design considerations.
It's the whole know your audience thing.
When people are in a theme park,
they don't want to sit there and look at a stat screen.
Not to mention that thematically,
the art directors would have killed us
if we had tried to do that.
So.
What we've come up with for this was each one of the spell cards represents an individual spell.
The spells have, you know, n number of levels that they can increase in power with.
And we initially opened the thing with three different levels for each one.
So as you use your spell cards, they increase in power,
and the effect that is displayed when you hold it up gets more potent.
It evolves as you play the game.
Can I show them one of my favorites?
sure. This is an example. See it's funny because someone gets
hit in the face with a bat. That's actually my favorite
spell of all time. So we have 70 different spells in the
initial deck that we launched.
with a couple of additions for holiday special editions
that we've done over the last two years.
These are examples of the actual spell cards
that get handed out.
When you show up in the park,
you're given a deck of five of these
that are randomly selected out of using basic
tabletop playing card game.
rarity model that we hired a consultant to explain to us because we don't really know
anything about that.
Know your audience again.
We aren't experts in trading cards so we went and we sought help from people who really
knew the market and that turned out to be one of the wisest decisions we made.
We ended up doing 95 minutes of new, unique animation that is the main content that the
game plays back for you when you see the villains appear and when you do battle with them.
It's the equivalent of an interactive animated feature.
And this, because every installation could support any story point, my game designer
was able to write this attraction linearly.
which made him super happy,
because it's just a lot easier to write,
and also allowed some greater depth of storytelling,
because A can lead to B, which can lead to C,
which was something that just really wasn't possible
in the adventure game structure of Agent P.
So, I'll show you one of my favorite installations.
What's fun about the Mystic Portals
is they don't look like Mystic Portals.
So, this is an artist's rendering.
of a rock wall that becomes a mystic portal
and this is what the final installation looked like.
Well, the flower girl was wonderful to cast me.
But my medicine suffered no good back at the castle. You'd better see.
Unfortunately, the sorcerer and witch fairies have proven a bigger inconvenience than expected.
Then, prepare a trap to be turned against them first.
Phew!
So Maleficent has challenged the player here to a battle.
And that's them holding up their Prince Philip's Magic Sword card, which triggers a spell effect
blows the dragon up. So the interface is simply hold the car down in front of you. On agent
P, a cell phone, even if it is a very simplified interface, is a little hard for any kid under
seven years old. We had two-year-olds.
casting spells and defeating villains and having a fabulous time.
Just because the interface was that easy.
It took a lot of magic and technology to make the interface that easy.
But this game is appropriate for much, much younger kids.
I think the most important lesson that we learned doing this one is kind of captured on this slide
in that in Agent P when people are waiting to play the game and they're sort of lined up,
they kind of stay separated from each other and stay back and let each player kind of go through
the experience themselves. With Sorcerers, again,
we were afraid about what was going to happen when lines got
big. But as it turns out, the longer the lines are for a
portal, the higher the guest satisfaction rating would go up.
And that was because people would start trading cards with
each other. They would just start to turn into these
impromptu card trading parties and people would talk about
their tactics for what they were going to do next
and where they were in the story.
It was really very surprising to us
because it was so different from what happened
with the Kim Possible attraction.
Yeah, and so our guests, there's a large selection
of guests who come to Magic Kingdom now
who self-identify themselves as sorcerers.
And because the overall story is to protect
and enhance the kingdom.
They go out and commit what they call random acts of kindness,
where they take their extra cards
and they find small, adorable children
and they just give the cards away.
They also do things like hide them in places inside the park
and then put clues on Facebook for where they've hidden them
and create these sort of user-generated games
of hide and go seek in the park without any involvement
from us.
And talk a little bit about stupid programmer tricks,
as I like to call them.
Once we had this awesome game system,
Chris and I had an idea of just how to make it wacky.
Right, so we ended up making this line of t-shirts,
which if you purchase and wear,
because the game is based on a fairly powerful
image recognition package,
we can tell if you're wearing this t-shirt
that we sold you.
And so we use that as a shortcut.
This was a master sorcerer T-shirt, which turns you into
a master sorcerer, which automatically boosts any spell
you cast to the maximum power level, which actually helps
you if you're playing one of the more difficult levels of
the game, where it matters how strong your spells are in
terms of whether or not you're going to be able to
defeat the villain.
Which brings up a good point about
underestimating certain things.
So.
you know, I didn't necessarily buy into the fact that
our guests could only play a game for three to ten minutes, but I kinda thought,
you know, maybe a half hour, an hour at a time. That's probably how long people will
play the game.
And so the Easy Level was designed for that, for the person who,
you know, is going to come to Walt Disney World. They want to ride all the roller
coasters and
they want to spend maybe a half hour, maybe an hour playing this, and maybe
there'll be some people who play the whole game all the way through.
We should make it clear that easy is really more like a walking tour than an actual game.
If you hold a spell up, you win instantly.
But the summer before we opened, Chris and I were talking like,
Well, you know, it's just numbers. We can add a medium and a hard level. We'll do that really easy.
And so it takes about four, four and a half hours to complete the easy level, going through all the things.
maybe eight to ten hours to get through medium.
And if you didn't have the right cards on hard, you could not win.
It's not possible.
Yeah.
And so, but I figured, eh, big deal.
How many people are actually going to play hard?
Everybody played hard.
to the point that we had to turn it off and reengineer hard.
Because the fact that you couldn't complete it,
and really nobody could because this was early
in the game's opening and you needed a full deck,
really, to be able to complete hard.
Which is very difficult to get by randomly showing up
every day and getting your five spells.
So the people would go into the attraction
and never come out.
And they loved it.
But what that would mean.
They would not leave.
The lines, they never.
It was not designed for them.
The lines don't go down when they don't come out
the other side of the door.
So that became a problem.
Yeah, and so we actually just launched a new version
of hard which we sort of pulled back hard.
Now it's as hard as it ever was but slightly more fair,
a little more designed to.
to be a partner.
Well, we solved it by giving you an award for how well you did as opposed to how long
you got beat up.
How long you got beat up.
So that there's an incentive to keep playing and go back and do it better the next time.
So my takeaway as a game designer was if you design a location-based game with the same
long play game mechanics that you would use in a photonic game, people will play it like
they will play a photonic game.
If we designed a game that lasted 200 hours,
people would play it for 200 hours.
There's no difference between what you guys do
and what people do in the real environment.
And because it's a very social game, people took it online.
I think there are many different Facebook groups.
This one has over 1,600 now.
Story interface choice, again, tell one story.
The interface had to match the park, which also had to match the stories that we were telling.
Merlin was a great main character. He didn't ruin the storytelling because as a magic user,
he can travel through time, he can travel from place to place.
He was a great character to shepherd our sorcerers through the story.
And...
I'll just end with a few slides from the last game that we opened.
This opened at the beginning of the summer and it's a Pirates Adventure,
Treasures of the Seven Seas.
And this is just a great big pirate adventure game.
It all takes place in Adventureland.
And I'll just show you some of the moments within the experience.
Again, did I mention we have a laser guy?
This is a giant 13-foot-high stone idol that opens its mouth to reveal an evil, pulsing,
glowing golden skull.
In one of the story points, you trick an evil captain into hauling away some cursed treasure,
and later on he calls you to a parlay and rises from the deep to tell you that he's
really, really unhappy with you.
Designers realize that if you can have your players shoot a cannon, you've already won.
So, in conclusion, the design principles, the Mickey's Ten Commandments, good game design practices, just as you would in a photonic game,
can result in meaningful experiences for our guests that will keep them coming back over and over and over again.
and creating a strong, positively oriented community
among our players make the game experience
better for everyone.
So with that, I think we have some extra time in case
there are any questions.
We can go to questions and answers.
All right.
Thank you.
Do you guys have any papers on any of those?
The question is do we have white papers on the tech?
It's magic.
That is the official company line.
It's all magic.
Yes, sir.
The question is the Facebook site that we showed, was that created by Disney?
No, we didn't do any community building around it.
It all grew up organically from the people who come and trade the cards in the parks.
And that community expands out to people who just came and visited, loved the game, went
back to Texas or Illinois and they now trade the cards by mail and communicate through
this Facebook page.
So no.
I'd say there's seven or eight web pages dedicated to the attraction.
There's the Facebook page.
There's a couple of blogs.
There's the forums on Vinylmation.
There's a number of...
But again, yeah, we didn't have any part in setting any of that up.
So, way in the back.
How do you turn the ROI off?
Like, when you're sitting down and you're drawing,
you're making a pretty big, you spent X amount of dollars
and you think you're gonna make a wide amount of money.
But what if you're doing the right thing?
What happens to the revenue?
So the question is, theme park economics.
How do you justify building one of these things?
I can't really talk about that.
However...
We do have methods for judging the value of attractions,
but I really can't talk about it in this forum.
Sorry.
Yes, sir.
Pardon me?
The question is, how do you become an imagineer?
And in my case, probably random luck and persistence.
I became an Imagineer, I came right out of college,
and it was the first place I sent my resume,
and they said, thank you for your resume.
And so,
Wow, they said, they actually got back to you
with a thank you.
Well, yeah, with the little
It was the 90s, so they don't do that anymore.
No, no, no, no, it was, it was,
they sent me a postcard with Mickey on it,
and said, we got it.
And so something about me not having any marketable skills,
something like that.
And so then somehow I wound up in video games.
And after working in video games and then working in toy
robots when I worked at LEGO, eventually I just kept
sending in a resume.
And then somebody saw it and said, oh, OK, I have a use for
you.
And then before I worked in theme parks, I spent
maybe five or six years just doing corporate research
and development as a sort of technical consultant
within the greater Disney organization.
So it was just random luck that I eventually wound up
in theme parks.
So I think everybody has their own strange story
about any job they get, right?
Mine was easy.
You hired me.
Or just know me.
Yes, know him.
So there are Imagineers who are architects.
There are Imagineers who are landscape architects.
There are Imagineers who are computer programmers.
There are ride designers.
There are engineers.
There are art directors.
There are concept designers.
There are storyboard artists.
There are 1,500 different disciplines, actually.
So you're not going to name them all.
I was going to try.
Okay.
All right.
We won't name them all.
We kind of do a little of everything.
Yes, sir.
I have a question about game balance.
How did you solve the problem of making it deep or challenging enough that a hard core gamer in this room can have fun with it, but little five-year-old Susie plays her card and she loses.
That can't be a good experience for a five-year-old.
So the default when you go and you sign up is that you're
automatically put on the easiest difficulty level, which
as I said earlier, is really more like a walking tour.
Any spell cast will defeat any villain on a single cast.
You have to actually complete the entire game, go back and
say, OK, I want to do this again.
And they'll ask you, well, would you like to try playing
on medium?
and they explain to you that you can lose now.
So generally, the really young kids
don't have the ability to do that
because as Jonathan pointed out,
the fastest that we can get through the game
is about four hours if we're doing the whole thing on easy
just because there's so much walking around.
27 different encounters I think before you finish the whole thing?
Something like that?
No.
Actually no, it's 36.
So, um, so, most, most of the really casual players aren't going to come back and, you
know, sign up for another four plus hour.
block of time out of their day at a theme park.
Well, the kids will, but the parents will rebel.
Yeah, the parents will say, no, we're going to go do pirates now, because I didn't pay
for all this to play video games.
So very specifically, there is a game play style in location-based entertaining that
you actually, you find a little bit in games, but not much.
And you can't discount it.
Which is the treasure hunt in the real world game mechanics.
So say you're a heavy-duty grognard and you want super hard.
We can start you off on easy level because you're not familiar with the park.
So even if the combat is not particularly challenging on easy level,
you still have to find your way to all these locations marked on the map of the entire park.
Secondarily, we actually have some really wonderful storytelling.
The overarching story is that...
Hades, the evil god of the undead, wants to make the Magic Kingdom his summer home.
And to this end, he is sent, pain and panic, to steal Merlin's ultimate weapon, the Crystal
of the Magic Kingdom, because once that is out of Merlin's hands, Hades can invade.
There's a scuffle over the crystal.
The crystal is shattered and spread out across the entire theme park.
So you have to prevent Hades from getting the Crystal of the Magic Kingdom.
And Hades, being passive-aggressive, just recruits other Disney villains to try and get the shards for him.
So you go through a huge nine chapter saga.
So if you're an advanced player, even though the combat
is not difficult, there's the just treasure hunt mechanic,
which is fun, and the fact that you haven't seen any of
this before.
So you get all the storytelling and what's going
to happen next and what characters am I
going to run into.
So you entertain them on easy mode.
When they go back on hard mode, all bets are off and
we're going to hurt them real bad.
So that's how we handle the level load balancing.
No matter what.
We don't care, actually. You can go right ahead and do that. Our
fans have developed their own systems for making it more
convenient to carry the cards. A lot of people just have images
of them on their phone. People have made apps that have them
sorted where they can bring them up and hold them. This works
great. This actually works better than a real card because
it's more magical.
I gotta catch myself there.
But what we also found,
actually I think our consultant was telling us
that if you show up at a Magic of the Gathering tournament,
with a bunch of photocopied cards, you're kind of
embarrassed, right? Nobody wants to be seen with the knockoff
versions of these things. And so people really, really enjoy the
collecting aspect of it. And what they'll do is they'll
collect the cards, put them in mylar, lock them away and use
the image on their phone once they've got it because that way
they don't have to dog ear their mama Odie's voodoo.
Yeah, I mean, our business model, which again, I can't talk about, isn't based on selling
the cards.
So if they want to print out cards and have them all, and then they can keep their good
cards at home and not expose them to damage, we're all for it.
looking at ways to incorporate smart phones,
since everybody at the park where I go now
spends their time in queue staring at a screen
instead of looking at all the wonderful pre-show
that you guys do for all of your attractions.
Your next iteration of Sorcerer's or the Treasure Hunt,
will that incorporate smart phones?
So the question is, have we thought about
incorporating phones ourselves?
Take that.
Sure.
Imagineering is all about looking at new technologies and finding new ways to tell stories.
So the answer is yes, we've been looking at that because obviously it's very powerful.
If you look at the design of Agent P slash Kim Possible World Showcase Adventure,
you will see that it is designed not around the cell phone.
The cell phone really is just what I call a remote control for controlling the park.
So what the cell phone does is it causes you to look up and focus at areas of the park
that you otherwise wouldn't have visited.
When we ran the playtest, a lot of annual pass holders played it, and they wrote us letters,
and they said, I love this experience because I'm an annual pass holder,
I've been to that park maybe a couple hundred times, I never went there, ever.
Never went to this part of the park.
So we actually use the mobile phone experiences.
to direct them away from the one and a half by two inch screen
and back out into these wonderful worlds
that the Imagineers have created over the years.
But we don't have anything to announce specifically
about smartphones at this time.
The gentleman in the checked shirt.
So the question was how we considered multiplayer.
We did not touch on this source of the magic kingdom
actually can be played in a multiplayer fashion.
The system, it's fairly simplistic,
but if you have a family with a couple of kids,
and they want to all.
When he says the system, he means the magic.
The magic, right, the magical system.
tuned so that, you know, if you have a couple of kids or even
three or four people, they can all hold up spells and it will
detect all of them, cast them all, and that way you can have,
you know, two kids play with their parents without having to
split up and go in different directions because if they did
that, the game would physically separate them. There's no way
to pair two groups together in the  in the
in the attraction.
So as far as competitive multiplayer goes,
so it's something that we think about.
With the competition, we like the guests pairing up
together, uniting to defeat the villain.
We're not so much about, you know, Brenton and me
getting in a huge sorcery battle in the middle
of the Magic Kingdom and, you know, duking it out.
Because...
I think the game would have to match the story
that the park is telling.
Yes.
So if there was a park or a themed environment...
Better answer.
Which led to that and a technology that made sense
from a story point of view, we absolutely would consider it.
We just, you know, you design for location-based
entertainment.
the location you're putting it makes a big difference to the story that you're telling.
But every park has its own requirements, it has stories that are correct, it must function
as a living organism. You would not believe how complicated it is to run a theme park.
It's mind-boggling.
The answer is, I think we absolutely would look at something multiplayer, we just haven't found the right application for that yet.
Yeah.
Yes, there in the front.
I know you've probably touched on this a little bit before, but when it comes to game design, story design, and location design,
and then contrasting that between what you're doing in theme parks versus what's done in video games, what...
similarities have you found between those two mediums?
What differences have you found between those two mediums?
And also, are there any other any other surprises as far as like,
people queuing up and spotting games and trading cards, things like that?
Are there any other surprises you found that you didn't initially expect
when it came to either the way you design things or the way things kind of naturally work?
Okay, so the question is the differences,
what are some differences that we've found
between designing for regular video games and for locations?
And what things did we find that we did not expect?
It's a very good question.
One of the, we talked a little bit about
the theme park as a shared resource.
You can't double the ride capacity of Pirates of the Caribbean
by building another Pirates of the Caribbean right next to it.
So you have to be very efficient in your game play.
You have to, timing is very important.
You have to know how long things take,
how long it takes people to get from A to B on average,
how long they stand in a place.
You have to move them along.
You have to know that you're not going to be
in the parade route.
These are not things that you worry about in video games.
Now that's the five minute signal.
You also don't have to worry about maintenance.
And we have an army of people who are out there every night and every morning on all the attractions testing and fixing things.
Because mechanical things in games do not break generally.
From where in an aggressive environment like Tokyo or Hong Kong or Orlando, things break all the time.
I think the one thing to note that's a difference is the level of complexity, we don't want
to dumb the experiences down, but we do have to maintain a certain level of intuitiveness
I think that goes beyond, we have to be able to explain how to do this in like 30 seconds
to anyone and they have to be able to get it, right?
We can't spend five minutes.
telling each guest exactly how to play the game or hand them a
manual or anything like that. Or they'll just immediately
disconnect and stop playing. So you really have to try and make
the experience as really intuitive and quick to pick up
for anyone as possible, right?
And safety is also something you don't generally have to worry
about in a video game, particularly in video games
where so many people get shot.
When I had you know I had to oh gosh, I had these genius ideas for Kim Possible
They're just you know just brilliant
I had this idea with a golf club and the guests would come up and they hit a rigged golf ball and the golf ball
Would follow a bizarre path and would always land in the hole and I'm pitching this idea to the operations people and they're like so
Let me get this straight theme park
thousands of people around
You're gonna give a five-year-old child a big metal club
Thank you
Right.
Yeah.
So that's another thing that people don't generally
have to deal with regular video games.
Probably time for one more question.
Sorry.
Yeah.
Have you thought about actually letting
the player alter the course of the story?
We.
We have not implemented that in any of the attractions
that we've done, but there are definitely groups
within Disney and R&D in Disney
who are looking at things like that,
but we currently haven't rolled anything out.
I think we still have time for one more question.
Yes, in the back.
I was just curious about the difference between
Loda in Orlando versus Anaheim.
So the question was why Orlando and not Anaheim.
Because every property has its own needs and its own agendas.
As I mentioned when we put Kim Possible in World Showcase,
there was a perception that there was not enough for kids to do in World Showcase.
And so there was a need and we fill it.
It would be great to just think I could come up with any idea I want and put it in any park.
But those parks are living organisms and they have needs
and sometimes those needs come before an imagineer's desire
to just put something cool in the theme park.
And we'll probably hang out afterwards if anybody has any
more questions, but I think we're out of time.
I want to thank everybody for coming.
Yes, thank you very much for coming.
Thank you so much.