Today we're talking about Race for the Galaxy, where I don't want to spend a lot of time
on the game itself.
I want to talk about what went into the design and hopefully help you design your own games.
Just to help me calibrate things a little bit, how many of you have played Race for
the Galaxy?
Ooh, very nice.
Now how many of you haven't?
Feel free to get the hands up.
Helps me calibrate.
You won't hurt my feelings.
All right, we'll have a brief intro, then I'll do an overview of race to give you enough
structure to hang the design on, and then I'll get into the design stuff.
The takeaway that I hope you have is some ideas to help make your own games more strategic.
My name is Tom Lehman, I'm the designer of Race for the Galaxy.
My first game was published in 1992.
I've been a full-time freelance designer since 2008.
I've done various board, dice, card, and with Matt Leacock, he brought me on board to do
the pandemic expansions with him, and so I've done some co-ops as well.
The game we're talking about today, Race for the Galaxy, is a card game, a tabletop card
game.
It was published in 2007 by Rio Grande Games.
It's for two to four players and typically takes 20 to 40 minutes.
It's had five expansions so far, with another one that's been announced green-lit for next
year.
It's also had three spin-off games, Roll for the Galaxy, which is a dice version of Race,
and that itself has had two more expansions.
Rivalry will be out in June.
It's had Jump Drive, an even simpler introductory card game, and then New Frontiers, which is
a board game, which will be out late summer.
It's, you can play it online in a browser at Board Game Arena.
They have over 5 million games of it played on that site.
There is a free open source PC version that if you have any interest in AI and neural
networks, I recommend that you take a look at the source.
That began as an AI project by Keldin Jones.
Built on top of that.
is a mobile app by Temple Gates Games, which supports both AI and internet play.
There's a Steam version as well, and they added a really nice UI on top of it.
So about the game.
It's a card game, and the cards are two different types.
There are action cards that you use to select the phases, and there are game cards, which
are the cards you actually play to build your space empire.
You start with four cards in hand out of a choice of six,
and you have one start world on the table
as the start of your empire.
During the game, players select their actions
secretly and simultaneously.
There are five possible phases, but only the selected phases
will occur in each round.
When a phase occurs, everyone can do it.
So if I call develop, everyone can place a development.
and the player who selects a phase gets a bonus in it.
So for example, in a three-player game,
if players A and C both chose develop,
it'll only happen once.
Everyone can place a development,
but A and C will get the bonus.
Then everyone will have a chance to settle,
and B will get the bonus.
One of the consequences of this is that every round tends to be different.
So, we might have a game that starts out in the first round with develop and settle,
then in the second round explore and consume,
and then in the third round explore, settle and produce
when the three players all choose different actions.
You explore to find new cards.
You develop and settle to build your empire.
So develop is how we, the game cards are divided into developments and worlds,
and development is how we place the ones with the diamond.
Worlds with the circle are placed during the settle phase.
The gray worlds are essentially light developments in that they provide powers, but the colored
worlds, and there are four colors of worlds, are worlds that can have a good on them.
A good is just a face card, a face down card taken from the draw pile and placed on top
of the world, and in the computer implementations, you can see that they can color code those
according to the type of the world it's on, which determines what type of good it is.
Produce is what creates the goods on the production world,
and consume is how you convert goods
into VP chips and card draws.
So here we have two consume powers.
This one will take any type of good
and turn it into one victory point chip.
and turn it into a victory point chip and a card draw.
Obviously the second power is better, but you can only use one of these powers on one
goods.
So if you had two goods, you'd get two victory points and one card draw.
So that gives us two phases in which you're building out your empire,
two phases in which you're producing and consuming goods.
And this leads to two different ways that the game can end.
It can end when any player gets 12 or more cards in their empire,
or when the communal victory point pool is emptied.
In that case,
we add these 10-point chips to the pool
so that everyone gets all the chips that they're entitled to.
In both cases, we finish out the round and then we score it up.
There are three ways to score victory points.
There's the victory point chips that you earn during consume.
There's the value, the victory point value of the cards in your empire.
Cards in your hand do not score.
And finally there are the VP bonuses from the six cost developments.
Here we have a six cost development, Alien Tech Institute, and it pays off for all the
yellow worlds in your empire, plus any cards with the alien tag, such as Alien Tech Institute
itself.
And then whoever has the most victory points is the winner.
So that's Race for the Galaxy in a nutshell.
Hopefully that'll be enough to let you hang the design
discussion on it.
It's a game with simultaneous action selection.
You're finding cards that fit together to form strategies.
You're doing empire building.
You're building VP engines.
And you're trying to score those six cost bonuses.
So now we're going to dive into the actual design.
The first thing to notice is that unlike many Euro games,
this game does not have a set number of turns.
That instantly produces strategy along the lines of how fast
do you do something?
Do you do a quick tableau rush where
you're putting out lots of cheap worlds and developments?
to try to end the game quickly before someone else gets going?
Or do you try for more expensive but denser with more victory point worlds and developments?
Do you, on the produce-consume side, you could put down just a couple of production worlds
that have consumption, not all of them do, and run that
for victory points immediately, or you could put down production worlds and then nice consume
powers in order to get more victory points.
So simply by not forcing a set number of turns, you instantly get some strategy about the
pace.
But you get even more strategy out of the fact that you have two different end conditions.
This creates strategic tension in the game as to whether you invest in a victory point engine,
do you invest in order to get the discounts to develop and settle and build an empire,
or do you try some sort of hybrid strategy in between the two?
As a thought experiment, what if Hearthstone, a popular digital card game, or Magic the
Gathering, a popular tabletop card game, had two main victory conditions, ones that happened
all the time.
So imagine that the normal way you win in those games is you drive your opponent to
zero health.
However, imagine that they had a tower that they could build, and if they got it to level
then they instantly won the game.
Now suddenly you're going to think about, well, I could put minions that attack my opponent,
but I could also put out minions that build the tower.
Which do I want to do?
I can put out defenders for myself so that they defend my health, or I could try to defend
those minions who are building the tower.
And in particular, as the tower rose, if its height interacted with the various powers
of cards, right, if they start to interact, so if at, say, fifth level, archers fired
every turn instead of when they first entered the battlefield, and, you know, at eighth
level ballistas worked and dragons flew off the top of the tower and so on, you could
get a lot of interactions in the game.
I'm not saying that a game is better if it has two different winning conditions, but
if you have it, it's the easiest way I know to introduce strategic tension into a game.
So how do you pay for cards?
In race, you pay for cards by discarding other cards.
So here we have a hand of six cards.
We want to place this development terraforming robot out of our hand, and we have to pay
the cost in the diamond.
So we have to discard three cards out of our hand to pay for it.
There's no mana.
The cards themselves are the money.
If we'd called develop, then we'd have an extra card left in our hand
because it gives the bonus for development is that it gives us a discount of one.
So one way to think about the cards in your hand in race
is that they each represent an opportunity.
Something that you can put into play or not put into play.
And this gets us to what economists call opportunity cost.
Where the cost of something isn't just the resources spent,
but what you could have done instead.
So some examples from regular life, in college in most majors you have a limited number of electives.
When you take an elective, the cost isn't just the tuition and your time and your effort,
but it's also the fact that you could have taken some other elective
and what you might have gained from that elective instead.
If you're at a seminar session, the cost is, well, you could be, instead of listening to me right now,
you could be in some other room listening to someone else, and that's part of the cost
that you're paying. And similarly, job offers, investments, all these things have opportunity cost.
returning the games, if you have a system that gives you mana,
so that you're spending mana to place your cards instead of
spending the cards, then you have a much smaller opportunity
cost. Say I have four mana and I have two four-cost cards.
Well, I can place one or I can place the other, so there's
still an opportunity cost there.
but after I place it on the next turn I have four mana and I can place the other one.
So the opportunity cost in those sort of systems is much smaller
because you're merely postponing an opportunity
as opposed to giving it up when you discard a card.
Opportunity cost is often overlooked in games.
Richard Garfield talks about the fact that when he first
started designing Magic, he didn't think he could have
zero-cost cards in the game.
He thought it would break the game.
And he came to realize that there's an opportunity cost in magic
in that you want your deck to be as small as possible so that it's efficient and the combinations arise.
And that this cost is real and meant that he could have zero cost cards in the game.
Because when you draw an Ornithopter...
That's a card that you drew instead of some other card,
and that some other card might have been more useful for you.
So even though the cost is zero,
there's still the cost of the slot in your deck.
And we know that that cost is at least as much
as a zero-two flying artifact creature.
Returning to race, in a typical game of race, players draw about 30 to 50 cards per game,
but they're only building 8 to 12 of them.
This card sifting mechanism allows for a lot of varieties in strategy.
In the race base game, you have 114 cards, 91 of them are unique.
So you can have many different strategies,
because if you draw a card that doesn't fit your strategy,
you just throw it away, using it to pay for some other card.
Now, there are other approaches to variety in a game.
Deck construction, the problem there
is that you need a deck to play.
That's an investment of time in advance.
Drafting, if it breaks up the play,
if you do it over several rounds, like in Seven Wonders.
Then you have this, I play, then I draft,
then I play, then I draft,
and that can take people out of the game sometimes.
Or alternatively, it must be done before play.
In deck building, as a Dominion,
you have a large variety of kingdom cards
that's possible to be played,
but you're using only a subset in each game.
Debt sifting integrates variety into the gameplay.
And the other benefit of it is that it instantly adds a new
class of decisions, hand management.
You have a bunch of cards in your hand at the start of the
game, you can play them all to put down a big purchase.
But then you won't be able to do anything for several rounds
until you repunish those cards.
Furthermore, if you have cards that you want to save for the
end game, they have a cost.
They're like a boat anchor in your hand, because you can't
spend them to pay for something else.
There are some criticisms of deck sifting.
One is that some players find it too angsty.
The thought that they discard a card that two turns later
they realize, oh, I really wanted to keep that card, for
them is just a total turn off.
And the other one.
is that experienced players have a deck knowledge advantage.
They know what's in the deck, so they
know some of the combos they could wait for,
and that informs their discarding decisions.
Now, the experienced player issue
comes up in all games, whether it's a co-op,
whether it's a two-player competitive game,
or a many-player competitive game.
So I'm not that much worried about it, but I do note it.
So where does all this come from?
there is a Euro game called Puerto Rico by Andreas Seyfarth
and it was a very popular game.
And Stefan Bruch, the head of Olea,
the publisher of Puerto Rico,
felt he wanted a card game
and he had a very limited time to produce one
to capitalize on Puerto Rico's success.
And Andreas Seyfarth's prototype wasn't working.
So he contacted several designers, including myself,
and asked us to essentially become backup Andreas Seyfors
and to design games independently
that if Andreas couldn't get his prototype working,
that he would then publish instead.
So I designed the Puerto Rico card game.
I spent three months, I went through three major iterations.
I collapsed Puerto Rico's cost structure
from one to ten to one to six.
I figured out a bunch of things involving this card sifting.
And I presented it to Stefan at the gathering of friends.
We played it for a week, we made some small tweets,
and at the end of it he said,
Tom, if it was up to him, he'd offer me a contract.
But Andreas was involved, so he took it back to Andreas.
Andreas looked at it, said, ooh, this solves my problems,
but I still want to do my prototype.
And so Stefan Bruch combined Andreas Seyffardt's prototype,
my cost structure that I developed,
and his own ideas about market slips together
to form San Juan.
I get a royalty from San Juan, but it
was a bit disappointing not to see the game that I had designed
actually published.
Well, San Juan came out, it's a perfectly fine game,
but I felt it had not pushed the variety button
the way I thought you could push it.
In particular, San Juan has 29 unique cards
out of a deck of 110.
Furthermore, I had an unpublished collectible card game called Duel from the Stars
that I felt would be a very good setting,
and I had evolved some new action selection ideas over the year and a half intervening.
And those are the three things that I put together to form Race for the Galaxy
after getting permission from ALEA and offering them first right of refusal.
So the thing that had bothered me about Puerto Rico's action mechanism, it's a classic Euro
game.
The play goes clockwise, it's not simultaneous, and the interactions between the player are
very much this, you constrain the next player as you go around the table.
You limit their options, you block them.
In particular, when you pick a roll, which is their term for an action, you block it
for the rest of the round.
No one else can pick it.
You all get to do it, but you don't get the bonus.
This phenomena in which you are affecting the next player downstream the most,
J.C. Lawrence has termed left-right binding,
and it was beginning to bother me.
In particular, I played a number of five-player games at Puerto Rico
in which I had a player upstream of me
who would just hammer me
and make it so I could never win.
Now, if that player had won, I wouldn't be upset, but he never won either, right?
But his attitude was that was how you play the game.
You just squeeze the next player as hard as possible.
Furthermore, I had played some five-player games where we had four experienced players
and one novice player.
And in those games, the player downstream of the novice player always won.
And so I was really getting to the point where I was going,
I don't like this left-right binding.
And what if the actions were instead picked simultaneously?
Doing so gives a greater sense of player agency.
If there's an action you really want to do, you just pick it.
It eliminates the left-right binding problem.
And the game can now go in many more directions
because you're no longer forced to pick different roles.
You can have all the players pick the same role,
as I showed you in an earlier slide.
Once I made that decision, then I started going,
well, what if the build tempo per round?
was 0 to 2 instead of 0 to 1.
In Puerto Rico, you only have a single build action, so the buildings, which is one of
the ways the game can end, only grow at a certain rate.
What if we had both develop and settle so that you can potentially go 0 to 2 times?
Then I started wondering, well, if I'm going to improve the Empire building,
what am I going to do about the produce-consume stuff?
What if the consume bonus was double the victory points?
None of this namby-pamby, you know, just plus one extra VP in the captain role in Puerto Rico.
And from those ideas, I began to think about a game
where the players had much more control over how the game evolved.
The issue with doing simultaneous action selection
is that you want all the actions to be equally viable
to be called in the early, mid, and late game.
It's not very interesting if you have some action
that's only going to be called in the late game
because then there isn't a lot of bluffing or anything.
So I started looking at the five actions.
Explore was easy.
You're always looking for cards that fit together.
Sometimes, even on the final turn, you're doing a Hail Mary,
you know, I will explore and hope to draw the one card that
will save my position and pull out the win.
Develop was looking pretty good in that you often want to
build some technologies early, get some powers down on the
board, and you want to build those six devs in the late.
But what about the mid-game?
In both Puerto Rico and San Juan, the buildings that give you bonuses have no powers.
They're just for scoring points at the end of the game.
I said, what if I put powers on them so now I had a reason to build them before the end
of the game?
So here if I'm committed to doing a yellow strategy where I'm putting down lots of these alien worlds,
this minus two discount makes it a lot cheaper.
And if I have three or four yellow worlds, I'll actually pull a profit.
So now I have a reason to build this before the endgame.
And that sort of fits develop.
Settle, well, you often want to settle in the early game in order to get your card flow going,
in order to put down worlds and get some goods on them and sell them.
in order to get more cards.
There also obviously you want to build them in the mid-game in order to set up your VP
engines.
But why would anyone want to settle late?
From Duel from the Stars I always had this idea that there would be two ways to place
worlds that you could both settle them peacefully or you could settle them by military conquest.
So
I decided to take that from Deal From The Stars.
So here's how military works.
You hear I have a start world that gives me two military, I put down this development
that gives me three more, and that lets me overcome the defense of this card, which in
turn gives me another two military, which lets me put down this seven card, which is
worth a lot of victory points.
Now, when you do the big military strategy, you often don't want to be calling settle
in the middle of the game.
You don't want to help the people who are doing these VP engines build their engine.
So you'll save your worlds and then slam them down at the endgame because you don't have
to pay any cards to place the worlds that you do with a military.
The non-military worlds are essentially placed exactly the same as the developments.
You have to discard cards equal to their cost.
And the only difference is that the bonus is you draw a card after you place the world
instead of getting a discount.
So now I had Settle working.
Produce had the opposite problem.
In both San Juan and Puerto Rico, Produce looms too large.
It has a who bells the cat issue.
When you call produce, particularly in Puerto Rico,
then the players after you in the turn order,
they get first crack at selling for goods,
for shipping them for VPs,
and you don't get much for calling produce.
So everyone wants someone else to call produce.
So I decided to solve that and I did two things.
The first thing is I moved produce to the very end of the round.
So if you call produce, then next round you, like all the other players, can now call an
action that benefits from it.
The second was I introduced windfall worlds.
All the worlds I've been showing you up to now were solid circles.
This one has a halo, which is a windfall world.
The production worlds only get goods when produce is called.
The windfall worlds get a good upon being settled.
And so now you could settle a windfall world,
sell it this alien good for a large number of cards,
and don't call produce.
However, this is a sort of a two-sided, two-edged sword
because the Windfall worlds don't get goods during produce.
They need a power or the player has to call produce
for its bonus, which is to produce a good
on one of your Windfall worlds.
So I both gave away to avoid calling produce
and an incentive to call produce.
And with those two changes, now produce was being called.
It wasn't so dominant the way it is in Puerto Rico,
but it was still being called throughout the game.
For consumption, its double VP bonus works well in the late game,
but...
Why would you ever double your VPs in your early game?
We all know for engine building games that you want to build your engine, then score
the victory points from them.
So, consume trade is the bonus that we use to sell goods,
and it only sells the goods for that player.
Now, this may seem very inconsistent with the rest of the game, right?
When you call develop, everyone gets the place of develop.
When you call settle, everyone gets the place of world.
But when you call consume trade, only you get to sell the good for cards.
Why is this going on?
Two reasons.
One is the one I've already alluded to, so that consume is called early on.
But the other is to solve the rich gets richer problem.
And this is a problem in many games.
So, in Race, if you have an alien production world,
and it automatically produces on Produce,
automatically gets a good on Produce,
and then if you could automatically sell it,
when anyone called Trade,
then you would have this huge advantage over other players,
and the game would be all about getting the big world down first.
So to prevent Rich Gets Richer, I say trade is a bonus.
Now this Rich Gets Richer issue is an issue in all of these games.
And they all solve it, but in different ways.
Puerto Rico has a trading house, and your sales are often blocked.
So if someone sells coffee to the trading house in front of you,
you can't sell coffee, their high-valued good.
If there is coffee left in the trading house from an earlier trade phase, you can't sell it.
San Juan uses lower sales prices, those are those market slips I mentioned earlier,
and introduces compensation. They have buildings such as the poor house,
which if you have the poor house and not very many cards, you get extra cards.
And that's very much a sort of casual euro approach to this issue.
Roll uses lower returns when you factor in the cost of the producer and shipper dice.
And Waywa boosted its floor tremendously as an alternative to the point where some people
don't even bother trading goods to run their economy in Roll, they just use its floor.
Race gives you the largest return but requires player action.
So here we have one issue solved four different ways.
Each way is different.
in character with the game itself.
Explore also has two action cards with different bonuses,
allowing you to either get one extra card
or to go deep into the deck to try to find the card you
really want.
Simultaneous actions led to some very interesting player interactions.
First off, there's bluffing and gambling in the actual calling of the phases.
So for example, if I have an alien good and my hand is full with ten cards, and I look
around the table and I see someone who's likely to develop and another person who's likely
to settle, I might just call trade so that I refill my hand after I both place a development
and a world.
But those other two players might go, hmm.
Tom has an alien good and a handful of cards.
We'll just call it Splore.
He'll sell that good for a bunch of cards
and then have to discard them because he's
over the hand limit.
And so he screwed himself.
And so you get a lot of this double think
bluffing interactions.
You also get gambling interactions.
On the final turn, you might have, oh, I have the
development in the world that will let me win the game, but
I need both phases called.
And then you look around and you go, oh, that person's likely to call settle, so I'll call
develop and hope it works.
Then within the game, there's also leeching and blunting effects.
So develop is the second phase here,
and if I see a player who's set up to do lots of develop calls,
if I put down this bank,
I'll get my cut every time they call develop.
Similarly, if someone looks like they're going to call produce
to refill an alien windfall,
then I can put down this lost species world here.
It gives me a genes good,
which is almost as good as an alien one,
and it gives me two extra cards on produce.
And this, once I put this on the table,
the player who was thinking about calling produce
probably isn't going to call it in future turns.
So I have blunted their advantage.
There's also pressuring interactions in the build tempo.
If I'm low on cards and my opponents call both develop
and settle, do I put down two weak cards,
one strong card, one weak and save?
Every mis-build is potentially incurring
an opportunity cost, because if the game goes out
on tableau and I don't have all my cards on the table,
every slot that I didn't fill is lost victory points.
So here we were finding all these interesting player
interactions, yet one of the criticisms of race
is that it's multiplayer solitaire.
To some extent, this is a self-fulfilling prophecy.
If you play the game very heads down,
if you never look at what's going on.
in the other player's tableau, if you never make any predictions about what they're going
to call, it will feel like multiplayer solitaire.
There's no forced interaction.
But strategy games work when all players do their best to try to win, and the people who
do pay attention generally do a lot better in race.
In addition to simultaneous action selection,
Race also uses simultaneous play,
which can really speed up a multiplayer game.
So Race plays maybe five minutes longer
when it's a four-player game
as opposed to a two-player game.
When you introduce simultaneous play, that has a bunch of issues around it.
First off, there will be times when you have to serialize play in order, because you have
some situation where if someone does something, then the game may end and the other person
needs that information, because they may do something that could end the game and you
have to resolve that timing issue somehow.
But as a philosophy, you want to slow down play only when you need to.
and keep it going.
So two things that help you do that is one is to hide non-essential information.
So in race, the discards are face down that you use to pay for cards so that people can't
go, well, I don't want to decide what I'm doing until I see what you're discarding.
I just hide that information.
Similarly, you want to minimize your number of synchronization points.
If a race has one main synchronization point, which is during the action selection in Revelation,
then players who want to can go ahead with their turns while you might still be exploring,
and that's perfectly fine.
If you introduce too many synchronization points, you will not get benefit from simultaneous
play.
Turning to the actual design of cards,
I knew I wanted multiple powers on cards.
So here we have this terraforming robot,
and here in the settle phase it gets a card on settle,
and here there's a consume power as well.
And so this card could work
with either a produce-consume strategy
or an empire-building strategy.
And I knew I wanted these multi-power cards
in order to get the variety of strategy
that I wanted to pack into the game.
However, putting multiple powers at fire
at different times is tough.
It really increases the cognitive load of the game.
And you want to make that decision carefully.
The, you know, some people refer to race not having a learning curve, but a learning spike
that the players get impaled on.
And a lot of that cognitive load that's blamed on the icons is actually due to the multiple
powers.
This did influence the card graphics.
We added these little swooshes behind things so that players could easily look across the
cards in their empire and see the powers.
Another issue when you start thinking about designing a game, a card game, is, well, what
type of powers do you want to put in the game?
Do you want big effects, where the game is mostly about assembling a combo of cards?
Or do you want smaller, incremental powers, where it's mostly about gaining an edge and
slowly getting more powerful than your opponent?
And this is a spectrum.
Your game could fall anywhere between these things.
At the gain and edge thing, sort of the meta strategy
is making lots of small decisions well
in order to gradually produce a win.
In the combo thing, often the meta strategy becomes
stave off defeat until your combo arrives in your hand
and then play it and just take out your opponent.
So for example, in Hearthstone,
you often see someone defending themselves,
they have some defender in front of them with high defense.
And then when their combo arrives, it's like double their defense, double their defense,
make the attack equal to their defense, wham, take out their opponent.
And that's an example of a big combo.
I tend to like to make games with lots of tough decisions with good strategic tension,
so I'm more on this end of the spectrum here.
But it is a spectrum.
There's nothing about card sifting or anything that I've talked about so far that says it
has to be gain and edge.
Right?
Glory to Rome is an example of a game that uses big combos that lets people use the discard
pile to assemble their combos and is notorious for teetering on the edge of control before
suddenly someone puts in a combo and wins the game.
But I wanted to go with the smaller, simpler powers and one of my other reasons for doing
it was reduce the cognitive load.
As I'm sure the people here who haven't played race before have already noticed,
there's a fair amount that's going on in the game.
And so the powers in race are very simple.
They're like see an extra card in explore, or get a little extra military, or get a card
in the middle of the various phases, or add a new consume power.
They're all very small and incremental.
There are only three powers that really break the rules.
One of them is paying for military worlds in order to connect up the military game and the non-military game.
I felt that connection was important.
Another is to break that rule after having carefully built consume trade as a bonus,
is to have some powers that break that rule.
And the third is normally you can only make victory points through your empire.
But there are some powers that let you spend cards directly for victory point tips,
and that breaks that rule.
Those three I felt were important enough to put in the game,
but all the rest I went with very simple powers.
So with simple powers, you have the choice of do you put text on the cards or do you
just have icons.
And we went with having a mixture.
Here we have powers, no text on this card.
Here we have some powers with no text that are pretty simple.
And then we highlight this phase and we have text right here for the more complex power.
Something we didn't expect was that...
If you have some powers without text,
a lot of players then assume all the powers don't have text,
even when there's text right there on the card.
And so that was a bit of a learning experience.
Our model with the textless powers was to keep them,
you know, similar to road signs,
just a couple basic shapes and a number.
This is normally a big mistake.
Okay?
Normally you want to do everything you can in a game to make it accessible.
Because if people won't play your game, then, you know, who cares about the replay value?
But with Race, we had noted during playtesting that we had people playing the game hundreds
of times, even thousands of times before publication.
And so we backed off a little bit on the accessibility
to emphasize the ease of road play.
Most players who can handle the graphics,
I mean there's some people that it's just not the way their brain works,
but the people who can handle the graphics,
they find that the game clicks after a couple plays
and then it allows them to play much faster and easier.
For the spinoff games, these are geared to more casual audiences, and there we put both
complicated icons and the text right there.
Similarly, here this is from New Frontiers.
And then for Jump Drive, which has very simple powers, we just put a few helper words in
the middle of a power.
The icons paid dividends when Race was ported to a device,
because you can actually see it pretty well on your phone.
And then the implementer added an expanded mode,
and you can do some actions in this expanded mode,
and everything gets text.
Even the icons that in the base game didn't have text
have text in the mobile app.
The card design evolved through many iterations.
So here is one of the original prototype cards.
This is the finish card, this is all the same card on this slide.
These two are Waywa's designs before he and I started working together.
And these last two over here are after the art team gets involved,
and we're now testing their ideas on our players.
So you can see how it changed quite a bit.
So who's who on the race team?
Wei-Hua Huang, who I've mentioned several times, he did the prototype icons, the car
design, some development assistance, and he was the lead designer on Roll for the Galaxy.
Jay Tomelson is the publisher, the head of Rio Grande Games, and he's a huge science
fiction fan.
And in 2007, the German publishers were all convinced that science fiction games would
never sell.
And so he supported doing it and paid for a lot of artwork
from these three gentlemen.
He found the art team.
And Klaus and Martin do the covers, the card art, some of
the 3D modeling that we use, and the logos.
And Mirko Suzuki, our skateboarding graphic artist,
he does the rules layout, works on the card templates,
did all the icons, redoing all the icons, and does all the
production work.
We've been working together for 13 years now, which is a long time in any field,
and we work in a very collegiate way.
For Roll for the Galaxy, we talked to the art team and said,
you know, how we wanted to position it as the DICE version of Race for the Galaxy.
And they came back with this idea of floating DICE in space.
with the race symbols coming out in red light, which would help,
in yellow light, which would help pick
up the difference in the branding.
So, you know, they suggest ideas.
All the cards are actually designed from a thematic point
of view, but I don't tell the artist about it.
Okay? So, here we have Distant World, and my model for this world,
my internal model when I designed this card, was Iceland.
Iceland has a very isolated population.
They are the focus of numerous genetic studies going on in Iceland right now.
So that's why it produces a genes good.
And Iceland has one of the highest book readership, book ownership rates, cultural interest rates
in the entire world.
And that's why they have this huge bonus for novelty goods.
Do I expect any player to look at this card and go,
oh, this is obviously a science fiction analogue to Iceland?
No.
Did I explain this to the artist?
All I give the artist is the title,
and I let them do what they want to.
Occasionally, they'll ask me a question or two,
but mostly I do this so that they feel fresh
and they bring their own ideas to the project.
Race does have two thematic inspirations, both of which I credit in the rules.
Fred Pohl's Heechee saga contributed the idea of a long-vanished alien civilization where
the aliens, all we see are their artifacts.
And then David Brin has the idea of uplift where alien races are being brought to sentience
by other alien races.
I use nothing directly from these things, but they were inspirations.
Two ideas from optimization theory informed my card design.
To make a game more strategic, you want to mine the gap.
So here I have New Sparta.
They want to put down this military world here.
They have this card which gives them temporary military, one shot military.
It's cheap, but then they lose a tempo.
Or they have this one which is, I can do this, overkill.
It's more expensive than they want.
What they actually want is they would like to draw this card here,
but they have to make a decision when they're faced in this situation
as to whether they want to go into military as a serious strategy
or as a one-shot, get this world down, get going.
And if you provide all power-cost combinations in your game, then it's possible for very
tactical play, worrying just about what you need to do right away to dominate.
If you start putting in gaps, you force your players to make strategic choices.
Random draws reduce this issue for card games, because you may not draw the needed intermediate
card when you want to use it.
But CCGs, drafting, and board games need to be very careful in this area if you want
to produce a strategic game.
The other idea from optimization is the notion of switching costs and how to overcome them.
You don't want your players feeling trapped by their initial hands.
So this is a very abstract diagram where these are the strategy hills.
and you can think of them as your players trying to climb the hill up to the top.
And so this might be, symbolize the alien hill with the alien tech institute I've shown
you a couple times.
This might be big military.
This might be the novelty strategy.
And if your cards initially say,
Go the alien strategy and then you don't draw any more of those cards.
And your cards now say go military, you have a switching cost.
If you put down the six for this military, it will score less because you have fewer
of the military cards in your tableau.
So you need to come up with some way to compensate players for when they have to switch strategies
in the middle of a card game.
And the approach I used is the six cost devs having both powers and victory point bonuses
really helped.
In terms of their cost, they are under-costed when you consider both of these items.
But when you consider just their powers, I mean, we just saw that a development that
gives you two military is about two cost, right?
They're way over-costed.
And this provides you a way of putting in compensation without putting in cards that
are too powerful in terms of their in-game effects.
Finally, another consideration when designing cards is that you want cards to appeal to
various player types.
Mark Rosewater has a classic article describing magic player types, and so when it came time
to actually design cards, I sort of, I bore that in mind and I put in cards that were
very efficient.
for the spike players who really value efficiency and winning on a high percentage basis.
Pilgrimage world, which lets you win in a very creative way, it lets you take all those
goods if you had no other consume power and suddenly consume them in one big swoop.
And that appeals to the Johnny-type player who likes to win in very creative ways.
And then Timmy, big military, provides the big effects that the Timmy, the stereotypical
Timmy player likes.
So that's something to bear in mind.
So what didn't work?
The deck size, which was fine in the base game, became a problem when we got to about
beyond 180 cards as we added expansions.
This is what statisticians call the sample variance problem.
The deck variance remained the same, but the sample, those 30 to 50 cards that a player
saw, started to vary too much.
And this led us to break the expansions into separate arts, so that you play the base game
and you play with these three expansions, that's fine, and then you get rid of them,
play the base game with some other expansion.
That also lets me tell different stories, which as a designer I like.
A few cards were a little too specialized, and we turned out to have colorblind issues
in our browns and our greens.
And in JumpDrive, we introduced these dots to try to solve the issue.
We actually had a playtester who is extremely colorblind, but the problem was he was an
expert bridge player.
He just memorized the cards.
So we didn't realize that we had a problem.
We said, well, if Larry can play it, what's the big deal here?
So second edition race is coming out.
It's at the printer right now.
And we are adding these dots into the blue, green,
and brown worlds to help with the color blind.
It's not a complete solution, but it's like a 90% solution.
And that's one of the things we're doing.
And as long as we were in the game,
I made the rules completely gender neutral.
They were mostly gender neutral
because that tends to be the way I write,
but there were two he or she's and 12 hises
that are now they and their.
We added new samples of rounds of play for new players.
We added the six promo worlds from the app
that were designed for the app.
and added them as along with optional start world choice.
And then we adjusted five cards that were a little too weak
and we will make them available as separate promos
through the BGG store.
So some takeaways.
I'm not going to read this in detail,
but these are things to consider
when you're designing a strategy card game.
And good luck.
So we have about 10 minutes.
Questions are welcome.
And remember to fill out your evaluations.
Last.
Hey Tom.
So I really like what you were talking about, about multiple different winning strategies.
One of the things I really like about Magic is that it has that built into the deck building.
One of the things I really don't like though is the inevitability with certain strategies,
where you realize that there's no way you can win against that strategy because your deck isn't set up to do it.
So I'm interested to know kind of how you approach balancing different strategies for winning the game.
Okay, so the question is how to balance certain strategies,
particularly if one strategy starts to feel inevitable.
Yeah.
So part of that is magic, to some extent,
particularly at high levels when you're using lots of rares and so on,
is a game of big, big effects and combos.
By making a game of smaller effects,
the gain-the-edge thing, you...
get rid of a lot of that issue.
You don't completely solve it.
And in two-player experience in race,
in certain conditions you can see a very strong
develop-develop strategy that can sometimes produce problems.
The other thing is it really depends on the length of your game.
If you can whip through race in 10 minutes,
the problem's really not a huge problem.
Hi, Tim.
So I'm curious, since one of your major contributions
to San Juan was the cost crunch coming down,
and that's remained in place, I believe,
to some extent for race.
I'm curious about what led you to that decision
and how we can sort of approach holistically
to avoid that problem when we're starting from scratch.
So the question is, how did I come up
with the cost structure in San Juan?
What led you to realize that it needed to be crunched?
Yeah.
Well, one of the problems is simply physical, right?
If the cost goes from one to 10, and you have to pay nine
cards or 10 cards split down to 10, that's a big hand.
And if you want to save some cards in addition, now you're
talking about 15-card hands, right?
And so part of it was driven by ergonomics.
Part of it is driven by the entire deck size.
If all players can have 15 cards in hand and
cards in the tableau than we needed more than 110 cards. So a lot of it was driven by external
factors.
Okay, cool. Thank you.
Hello, my name is Steven. I really enjoy ROL and I also quite like RACE but ROL has an
aesthetic of accessibility that's much easier. The way that the tiles line up in different
phases.
Yes.
Yeah, so that's something that I feel that's really important to get people into the game,
whether new or old player.
I've played race over and over and I still can't quite wrap my head around each phase.
It's really annoying.
So this is, I don't know, is there something that you might want to...
I don't want to say fixed, but like, because they're intrinsically very different games,
role and race.
But the way the design and the presentation work makes role much friendlier to read.
Right.
So the question is, why is role easier to read compared to race, and is there anything
we could do to make race easier?
Yeah.
Largely, Roll avoids multi-phase powers.
In the few tiles that have it, it's the same power that happens to occur twice.
And that means that you can have the text right there because it applies to all of the
powers on the tile, and the vast majority of the tiles in Roll only have one power or
one power that happens twice.
That makes it a lot easier.
It's the multi-phase powers, I suspect, that are causing you,
I mean, everyone's different, but I suspect that's what's
causing it to make race harder to wrap your head around.
And I think it's just the nature of the game.
We are committed to the spin-offs in part
because we recognize that there's a variety of audiences.
And so race, we're sticking with the multi-phase powers,
but new frontiers in role largely avoid them.
Same with jump drive.
Thank you.
I'm interested in the balancing of all of the cards
that you used in race.
And because obviously you are drawing cards and then spending
them as a currency.
How did you come up with the numbers of 1-cost, 2-cost, 6-cost cards
in a kind of balancing way that made sense?
Because every time you playtest it,
people could get rid of the different cards each time, things like that.
It is tricky, but...
Part of it was the mind the gap thing.
You'll notice there's very few five cost developments
because I wanted there to be a big step up the sits
and that would be a strategic move.
Some of it was identifying what my strategies were.
I'm sorry, I didn't repeat the question.
The question is how did I balance all those cards?
Is that fair?
By defining some strategies early on,
like the novelty strategy, lots of cheap blue worlds,
then that gave me the anchor points
that then the other things could be interpolated to within.
I also tried to put in cards that were entire strategies in a card so that you would re-evaluate
when you drew a card and go, oh, I have consumer markets, maybe I should go the novelty path.
And then that was cost five because
Cost five is really tricky because for just one more you could have a six dev, right?
But so I made those very powerful.
So I had a sense of where in the cost spectrum various things would fit.
And once I developed my overall strategies, then it was just a matter of interpolating
and then testing and revising.
with the sixes, which seem like these really strong cards,
how did you come up with the total number?
If 30 to 50 are being drawn,
did you always want someone to get at least one
or two or three?
Like, just a little bit more on that sort of balancing how
Are you asking about the points on them,
or are you asking about the proportion of them in the deck?
Well, as a strategy led you to what card you wanted to design,
but the feeling for a player is to, when I draw that,
how often that happens to them and at which stages.
Right. So, some of...
How did I design the sixes so that...
and what led me to decide some of them would be a strategy in a box and some wouldn't.
If the strategies were well-defined in other cards, then the six could be a capstone and
mostly just scoring.
If the strategies weren't so well-defined in the sets, then its powers needed to be
stronger and its veeps needed to come down.
So, for example, the galactic economy in Rebel versus Imperium expansion works with all different
colors, and so that's a very powerful power, and we had to reduce the cost of the VP bonus
to compensate for that.
So it was an OP, basically.
Yeah.
Cool.
Thank you.
I also have a question about optimizing and specifically
balancing the cards.
When you're starting out, before you go through dozens
and dozens of initial play tests, how do you prefer to
visualize all of the cards in the deck and how they play
into each strategy?
Right.
So how do I visualize the cards?
How do I visualize the strategies before I start
playtesting, when I'm constructing the initial
prototype?
Well, every designer is different.
In my case, I sit in a tea shop and I write down potential
names of cards.
That's how I start.
And I sort of start grouping them into categories.
I get those names and I'm just working with the names first, and then I distribute them
among costs and so on from that.
But I start looking and go, this is one strategy, this is another strategy, and I start circling
strategies.
This is all before I've assigned numbers to the cards.
But by identifying strategies, then it's a lot easier to identify, and then I start thinking
about, well, what are the components of this strategy?
For example, novelty will be cheap worlds.
Alien will be density, because I know I want density as a strategy.
And by identifying the key ideas of the strategy, that guides me to putting out some numbers.
And in fact, I had all the experience from doing those three Puerto Rico card game iterations.
Race actually didn't change that much from the first prototype to the actual produced
version.
So it was three weeks in a tea shop.
That may not be how other people are going to do it,
but that's what it was for me.
Great.
Thank you.
Yeah.
OK, we are now, I believe, at the end of the session.
So I'm happy to have questions, but we'll
move across the hall to the wrap-up area, all right?
OK.
All right.
Thank you.