Thank you for joining me.
This is finding and engaging a great artist,
a non-artist primer covering tons of info today.
Getting your ducks in order before you even start searching
where to search, how to search, reaching out, paying.
giving feedback, all kinds of stuff.
A little quick info about me before I start
so you know where that info is coming from.
I am the co-founder and art director of Chickadee,
which is a visual design and art production studio
that I run with my wife, Sarah.
I'm also an artist at Spry Fox.
maker of triple town and alpha bear and other amazing happy
games that help you fill your joy quota.
And finally, I'm an educator at Maine College of Art, which
is a small fine arts school in Portland, Maine, which is the
original Portland, except for.
probably at least one in the UK.
So I have a lot of jobs,
but just so the About Me section isn't just
like the jobs I do,
that's sort of a shallow view of a human being,
here's like a little fun fact.
Last year, I gave a talk,
and I wore this exact same shirt.
They, oh my god, thank you so much, I feel the same way.
And it's, but there's a reason, it's not just like a shtick,
like, oh hey, that's black shirt guy.
It's because this is the only shirt I own
that doesn't make me look like a cartoon lumberjack.
And that is, all of my other shirts are plaid flannel,
which is like a super common look in Maine.
But in the Bay Area, you look like out of work L.L. Bean
model, or like guy who knows a lot about World War II.
So let's dive in now.
Woo-hoo!
Okay.
What you need to do before you start searching.
A prototype is just about the most valuable thing you can have.
Since I'm assuming you don't have an artist at this point,
don't worry about making it look pretty.
Just use Game Jam rules, grey box, asset store stuff,
royalty-free assets, that's all good.
You'll also need an idea about the work you want done,
because that's gonna dictate the type of artist
you need to look for.
You know, a concept artist to help shape the vision,
or a modeler to model characters and props,
or a painter, or an animator, art director, et cetera.
Now, this maybe seems like a, yeah, no shit kind of point,
but it's...
It's actually a pretty fine point.
When Chickadee started working with Spryfox,
it was because we answered a help wanted ad that said,
hey, we need a modeler for our next project
and bonus points if you can animate.
But what they actually needed.
was someone comfortable moving through the visual development process,
someone who could do concept art, who could plan pipelines, who could do VFX,
who could do a whole bunch of stuff.
It was their first 3D project, and they sort of yet didn't know what they didn't know.
And so if you're thinking like,
oh, I thought I knew what I wanted,
but maybe I don't now,
try searching for a generalist or just a game artist.
That's gonna be someone who's comfortable
wearing a lot of hats.
Reference of other work is also good to have.
Reference that hits close to the emotional mark
or kind of like the vibe you're going for.
It's useful to have something to show,
to get a potential artist in the same headspace as you.
So go ahead and make a Pinterest board,
just fill it up with stuff that,
even if it's like, oh, this isn't the style of character
we actually want.
This, it feels right, right?
It's okay to get emotional on that.
Other media, this, kind of related to the last point,
other media like music is sometimes really useful too,
because it's useful to kind of sometimes make a,
like a playlist and say,
hey, this sounds the way the art should look, right?
Get them in the same headspace as you.
If you have, obviously, soundtrack samples or something,
be ready to send those along.
That's all good stuff.
A list of verbs or adjectives is also good to have.
Stuff that describe what the player should be feeling
when they're playing the game or stuff,
or what they should be thinking
when they look at a screenshot.
You know, I think verbs and adjectives,
that's sort of like a common game design thing,
but it's also really good for visual design.
You know, and finally,
you're gonna need a sense of your budget,
and that is a big topic,
so let's dive down into compensation, cha-ching!
Come on, that was better.
Give a little more.
Okay, fine, I'll move on.
Thank you, thank you, thank you.
Okay, so the easiest, right, the most straightforward way
is like to pay an artist is just to have an art budget,
which is maybe not fair in an IGS talk.
But right, like, hey, I need art, and here is the money,
and then now I thank you for the art.
But again, IGS talk, let's talk about other stuff.
Royalties, profit sharing, that kind of stuff,
that's also an option.
Obviously that takes away the upfront burden of payment,
or at least eases it.
But it's something to consider.
If you're offering royalties without having proof
that you've successfully shipped a game,
that's sort of gonna make...
that in an appealing payment scheme because there's risk that that payment never comes.
There's a few points in this whole talk where your work history or your reputation in the
community, it's going to add a lot of weight.
This is one of those points.
uh... if people have good things to say about you or they have a positive
impression
of the past games you've made
uh... that's going to take some that risk out of the prospect of royalties
you know and and you shouldn't be afraid of
of using that that's a tool in your tool kit
Again though, if you're just maybe starting out,
you don't have that reputation yet,
you're still building up, still there's other options.
You know, if you don't mind going with someone
who has maybe less experience than you'd like,
depending on the laws in your area,
you might be able to get an intern for free
so long as they're doing it through their university,
they're getting credit.
You know, they get experience, you get art,
it probably will need to be touched up
because again, they're just starting out,
but you know, it gets the ball rolling, you have some art.
Beyond that though, this is such an important point.
Offering credit or experience or exposure
is like flagrantly shitty.
Just don't do it.
Don't be afraid to get creative with payment.
One option is working for trade.
Now the obvious thing is like, oh hey,
Maybe you both have side projects and like you trade code for art or something like that.
But I think you can get more creative than that.
I one time did, this is true, I one time did
not a ton of work, but a good amount of work
for a bunch of super delicious home-brewed beer.
And I personally think I got the better deal
because I got drunk for like many days and they just got some assets.
But we were both happy.
The point is that we were both happy
with the arrangement, right?
That's creative, we felt good.
Especially me.
So another option is to allow the artist to retain rights
to the work they make.
When I was starting out, I did a bunch of work
for different studios with me retaining the rights
to the assets I produced.
And then after the game shipped or after the contract
was over, I would package up some of that art
and I would sell it in asset stores.
And they got a lower cost or a lower price because of that.
because I was able to make up the difference
selling to third party markets, right?
So let's talk briefly about experience
as it relates to budget.
An experienced artist, someone with a bunch of ship titles,
they're gonna have a higher rate.
than someone who's more junior, I think obviously.
But their experience can ultimately save you money
because they're not gonna be hitting,
they'll be jumping over hurdles
that someone more junior might hit.
In that regard, they're sort of getting more done
in less time.
But going with someone more junior,
it actually might be the start
of a really long and fruitful relationship.
Junior people are gonna cost less,
they're gonna make more mistakes,
but.
Everybody gets better with time, right?
So if you're talking to someone, they don't quite
have the experience you wish they did, but you really get
along with them on a personal level, consider putting that
time in to help them grow.
OK, let's keep moving.
Where to search for your new artist?
So first and maybe most obvious, your own network.
People you've worked with in the past,
people you've met at local meetups or stuff like this.
These people are resources and you can mine that resource.
It's sort of the whole point of a network, right?
sort of related to that, recommendations, right,
they're sort of actually my favorite way of finding people.
You know, if a friend or a dev I respect
is singing the praises of someone,
they immediately get a million bonus de grande points
when I'm weighing them against other people.
This is another place where having good reputation,
it can really help you out.
If one of my favorite people is looking for someone,
I'll excitedly scan my own network
to see if I can find a matchup.
Just the thought of these two people working together,
it's like, oh, that's gonna be sweet.
So social media, another thing.
There's, you know, on Twitter, obviously,
there's a ton of, you know, creative hashtags,
hashtag game art, hashtag visible women.
You know, use that stuff to send out your own
help wanted ad. You know, chickadee, like I said.
We started working with Spryfox because of just a tweet.
And that was almost two years ago.
So it's a powerful tool.
And again, this is a place where good reputation,
it's super useful, right?
You know, just like with recommendations,
you know, if I see a friend's studio
is looking for people, signal boost.
You know, if I see a studio's looking for people
and I don't know a soul there,
I just am a huge fan of their work, signal boost.
And so finally, you can look through industry sites
for work you like the look of,
or maybe artist-seeking work ads.
Polycount, if you're looking for high-res.
High-fidelity 3D stuff, polycount,
you kinda can't be beat.
Cartridge is sort of like social media site
mixed with portfolios, sort of a weird one,
but you can look at stuff like that.
Forums, if you're using like Unity or Unreal,
you know, forums usually have,
hey, I'm looking for work, or hey, I need work.
It's a good place to look.
Okay, keep it moving.
What are some other things?
Just random extra stuff that needs to be considered.
So, hey, is this full-time or is this a contract?
And if it's a contract, for how long?
Personal connection is going to become way more important
the longer you're going to be working with someone.
you know if you're looking for you know just a handful of models
you can probably focus solely on skills
uh... you know if you're looking for something that's going to take months or
maybe years
uh... you're gonna wanna like this person on a personal level
Another thing, how specialized are your needs?
You know, if you're making a pixel art roguelike game
or something, at this point there's a lot of people
who can do that.
You know, but if you're making something
maybe more avant-garde, like hey,
this is a video-based narrative exploration game
or something like that, that's way more specialized.
You're gonna have a hard time finding someone to do that.
You will probably have to pay them more as well.
If your schedule is tight, you're gonna wanna find
someone with experience.
Again, you'll pay more, but the artist won't need
as much guidance, and as I stated before,
they're gonna avoid obstacles that someone more junior
might hit, which obviously is gonna help you
hit that deadline.
And then, how senior is the position?
A production artist with a couple years experience,
that's easier to find and pay for than,
hey, I need an art director.
So, if, sort of dive down into that, you know, if you're searching for someone like that,
someone with a lot of experience.
There's sort of no way to cut it.
You're going to have to be prepared for a long search.
There are just more boxes to check off.
You need to find someone you enjoy working with, who has
the experience you need, who you can compensate fairly, who
is willing to move to your area, or if they're not
already there, and someone, obviously, who's interested in
working on your game.
The rub here is that senior people like that.
you know, are often already spoken for or they have roots planted someplace and they
don't want to, you know, disrupt their family with a move, you know, or they're just more
expensive than you can pay for.
So long search, but a few suggestions, because that's the point of this.
First, use every search method you have available.
You should be doing all of the stuff that I already said.
Search your network and recommendations and put up ads
everywhere, social media, et cetera, et cetera.
Again, probably obvious.
But another thing to consider.
And, you know, I think this bears repeating,
I alluded to this before, you know,
if there's a person that you really like working with,
but they're more junior than you'd like,
you know, really consider giving them
a chance to prove themselves.
Progress on your game will be slower,
at least at the start, but you know, everybody gets better.
One important note on that though, if you go this route, be sure they have a firm grasp
of visual design topics like color theory or composition or wrestling with visual hierarchies.
These are all fundamental art issues.
I would say maybe additionally make sure they have a knack for problem solving and lateral
thinking and stuff like that.
And so I sort of just alluded to this.
I personally think really good art directors for games
are basically really good traditional artists
that have an understanding of technology.
And while interactivity is pretty unique to games,
there are other mediums that.
you know, have that mix of traditional art and technology.
You know, graphic design, animation, two examples.
Those fields require you to understand visual design.
You know, they're multi-step processes
that often involve, you know, various teams of specialists.
They require you to get X done and Y time for Z budget, right?
That stuff is all very similar to games.
So besides asking your dev peers for recommendations,
consider asking friends from other related industries,
if you have them, for recommendations.
There might be a graphic designer out there
that when paired with a lower-experienced generalist
or tech artist or something
to help explain what can and can't be done
in the realm of games,
that might be a really, really great combination for you.
So, last point in this section,
and this is sort of like the most important.
Whichever route you go, whoever you go with,
you generally, I think you want to shoot for rapport.
You'll need to critique this person's work,
and that is gonna be like way smoother,
you know, if you both respect each other
and you both enjoy each other's company.
Okay, let's keep going.
So let's say you have found a specific artist
you wanna work with, you know,
and you need to reach out, what do you do?
If you know someone that knows both of you,
consider asking for an introduction.
It's super, it's nice and easy, right?
There is sort of an instant level of trust
because of that shared connection.
Again, another benefit of having, you know,
like a wide network and a good reputation.
regardless if that introduction can be set up,
I would say just be professional,
but make sure your tone is still friendly.
The professional thing is maybe more a point
for younger professionals right now.
I personally have gotten emails
that have like LOL, OMG in them,
and it's like, that's cool, I hope your game does good,
but I don't think we're gonna work out.
So professional.
So, here is like a big list, and I'll be sharing my slides with this, so take a picture if
you want to, but you can also probably download this later.
So write two or three paragraphs that include, you know, what you need done, key dates, platform,
engine, if there's an existing art team or art director or just like a lone artist even,
because it's good to let a new person know who they'd be working with.
you know, if there is an absolutely non-negotiable budget, include that.
Obviously, info about your game.
This is a sales pitch, right?
Make that person interested.
And finally, it's good to let them know if there's a specific problem you're trying to
solve by bringing them on.
Like, oh, our characters need to feel more lifelike, or oh, we had a few interns and
they got the ball rolling, but we need someone now to kind of tie it together and form a
stronger thread that runs between everything.
If you have a press kit set up, send that.
That usually includes a lot of that kind of baseline information.
You know, and finally, I think it's good to end with something like, you know, if you're
interested, you know, I'd love to send you more info or screenshots or video, et cetera,
as well as answer any questions you may have.
It's inviting, but it's also maybe a little bit of a call to action.
Okay.
What if you don't have someone specific, you need to like blast the Internet with a help
wanted ad?
If you're casting that wide net, create a page on your website with a job listing that
includes all of that information that I just mentioned, even if you are using social media
to say, hey, we're looking for blah, more information here, link to this site.
It's all that information, what you need done, key dates, blah, blah, blah.
You can leave budget off this.
I know that that's maybe an uncomfortable thing
to broadcast, or maybe it even messes up
like a contract with a publisher or something like that.
But if that's not the case, it's still useful to include.
Also, include info about an art test
if you're requesting one.
This is sort of like, can be anyway, a sticky point.
Art tests are...
Our tests can be considered rude or even insulting if A, they're not paid or there's actually
not a B to that.
I just got sidetracked.
It can also sort of feel like being...
made to jump through hoops.
So I sort of think a good rule of thumb
is to really only request one
if it's like a uniquely technical gig
or the artist would have to use
like a special in-house toolkit or something like that.
Otherwise, I think it's appreciated
if you go just by portfolio
and work history and recommendations and stuff.
And, you know, finally this is like a small point, but it can save a ton of time.
Request that all inquiry emails have the same subject.
So like, animation position, or artist wanted, or something like that, because it's just
going to make sifting through, you know, when you have like a hundred replies, sifting through
that's going to be a lot easier.
Okay, boom, home stretch.
You found your artist, here are some tips
for giving them feedback.
So be clear and direct, polite and friendly.
You don't have to give two put ups for every put down,
just clear and direct, polite and friendly.
One thing we teach students when they're learning to critique
is that the feedback they're giving
is not about the person who made the work,
but the work itself.
You're not saying this work is bad
and therefore you're a bad artist.
You're saying this work doesn't yet accomplish
all that it needs to,
and so it just needs an iteration.
So don't be bashful, I think that's the point.
I think you can help yourself a little bit if you do a little research about art fundamentals.
So you know, visual design basics, the 12 principles of animation, these are things
that artists know, maybe you don't.
There are countless resources on the internet
that will quickly explain a lot of this stuff.
You can probably scale up in an afternoon.
For example, you know the 12 principles of animation
are, in case you don't know,
sort of the guiding principles that were formalized
in the early 20th century,
and now if you are an animation student,
these are like...
This is like, you know, geometry and calculus and blah, blah, blah.
This is all like that kind of core math that you would learn as a computer science major,
right?
That's what artists learn.
And you can, there's videos that explain all of this stuff in about 30 minutes.
So internet, do some research.
you know, even if you don't understand art,
don't be afraid of just trying to work through feedback.
Don't worry about looking stupid or sounding stupid.
Just sort of stumble through it
because an artist is not really gonna expect
that you understand all that formal stuff.
You go to college to learn that.
Very early in my career, I got a piece of feedback that a powerup I made didn't feel
pointy enough.
And I remember it made me so effing angry, because what does that mean?
After...
I was an asshole when I started my career.
So after I calmed down, I started a dialogue with this
particular programmer.
And we sort of figured out that what he was trying to
say was it didn't feel fast.
It was a speed powerup.
And didn't feel pointy enough was I don't get a sense of
speed from that.
So again, just stumble through it.
This shape or color or whatever reminds me of Doritos
and it's not good that that's the first thing I think of
when I look at this, right?
stumble through it, but I would say a really important point is try to avoid subjective language.
This isn't cool or this isn't edgy enough is not as
informative or helpful as this doesn't feel imposing, right?
Something to consider, and this is perhaps a little subjective,
but I feel the high-level purpose of all art in games
is to act as visual communication
about the design and goals and rewards and threats
and setting and all that kind of stuff.
So if art looks bad,
it's often that it's not saying the right thing.
This art says X to me when really it should say Y.
This shape looks slow, but it needs to look fast.
This posture looks threatening, but it needs to be more passive.
These colors remind me of the fall, which makes me feel cozy,
but we want the player to feel stressed here.
So it's worth asking yourself...
what the art in front of you is saying and then compare that to what the game's design
requires it to say.
And then finally, if you find an artist that you really enjoy working with, you know, let
them know.
Mention them in your weekly blog or Twitch stream or whatever.
Give them a shout out on Twitter because it's always nice to know that their work is hitting
the mark.
And that's it.
Thank you so much.
Questions?
Thanks Adam. If you have a question for Adam, please go to the mic.
So I'm from the AAA background, so I know approximately how much artists work salary-wise,
but how do you turn that into a budget for a contract?
That is an excellent question.
So, um...
What's the difference basically between an artist's salary and, hey, I'm contracting
someone, how much is all this stuff going to cost?
That's an excellent question and it's actually very big, with a potentially big answer.
What I...
There are a few different ways to do it.
So what I often do when I get an inquiry
is we try to build sort of,
first try and find out what exactly this client
is looking for, the total scope,
and then sort of see how far along
in the project already is.
You know, is this...
Do they already have an art style defined and I'm just doing an environment set or something
like that, or is this a total package?
If it is just assets, I usually try and find a flat rate that is based on an hourly rate,
but like, hey, for this...
snowy mountain art set, it's gonna cost blah.
And this happens like in a dialogue
between me and a client, right?
If it's visual design across a whole project,
I try to figure out
get a rough sense of schedule and stuff like that,
but in that regard, it's really,
there's a lot more just like back and forth,
and it's just a discussion, I think, at that point.
And if it's something really, really big,
I personally, that's when rev share royalties,
I think, really start to play in,
because otherwise, it's not sustainable.
I know that there are artists out there
that try to extract as much money as possible
right up front.
But I would prefer not to do that because I want the game to ship as much as anybody.
So it's really, I just try and work with a client to figure out something that's fair and sustainable.
One last question.
So I had a related question, and it's in a sense unfair.
I don't know how to put together a budget.
I don't know how much the work would be.
Yet I still want to know, well, what should I pay a junior
artist per hour or range?
What should I pay a senior just as information?
What is that kind of stuff going to cost as I try to put
together the budget for the whole thing?
I've never shipped a game, I'm just starting.
Okay.
You know, I don't know what,
I've been in indie games my whole career,
which I think is a little, you know,
salaries and stuff are a little different
in that space versus AAA.
I feel like last time I saw
the like,
game developer, you know, like, hey, here's the salary range of all these various disciplines.
In entry-level artists was maybe $40,000 or $50,000.
But again, that's like salary at like an established studio, and it goes up from there.
So just to do that into the, thank you so much,
just to do that in the microphone,
if you go to the Polycount wiki,
there is all of that information there.
I'm now forgetting, just broke into,
oh, freelance mounts.
So again, that's another resource, yeah.
Is that our time?
Thank you so much, everybody.