It's really an honor for me to be here today and to talk about the genesis of Another World.
This game was created 20 years ago and at the time I couldn't have imagined
that it would stay in the heart of many.
My objective today is to give you a clear view of the origins of a game,
how things were done and in what order.
how ideas appeared, and very importantly, in what context.
We also consider the periods of doubt
and the obstacles I met along the way.
As curious as it seems, I started
to create the game without knowing what it would be.
The creation of this game was an improvisation.
And that was not clear at the time, but in retrospect,
20 years later, I can see a parallel
with theater improvisation.
Because in theater improvisation,
the actors have to follow predefined rules.
And they must respect them and play along with them.
For another world, I set some very strong constraints,
like using polygons.
And also, in improvisation.
we develop the story layer by layer without knowing where it is going precisely.
That is what happened for Another World. That's why I'd like to present the creative process
chronologically, if that's okay with you.
So
The talk will be like a diary divided in four parts.
First, I will talk about the ignition, the desire that
sparked the development.
Then, we will look at the technology behind the game,
how it shaped the design, and give a solid foundation
to create it.
Then, I will talk about the creation of the game itself,
gameplay, graphics, animation, and story.
than the publishing aspects.
As far as possible, I will describe
the context of the creation and how the flourishing of ideas
is as important as ideas themselves.
First, let's brush on the context.
We are in July 1989.
It is.
the Amiga era.
I'm 22 years old, still living in my parents' house.
Okay, this photo was taken in 1991 at the end of the development, but in 1989, there
would be no less mess, unfortunately.
I had been creating various games since 1983 on various platforms like Oric-One, Amstrad,
and of course, Amiga.
The average time to create this game was from three weeks to six months.
None has been really successful.
And I had just finished creating all the graphics and animation for
Future Wars, which is a game designed by Paul Cuisset.
And Dragon Slayer was just released on Amiga, and its huge animations really impressed me.
I was wondering how to do this.
This game was purely beatmap. It was running on eight floppy disks.
But it inspired me, technically speaking,
to base a 2D game on a polygon drawing technology.
Why polygons?
Polygons mean low memory usage.
And therefore, it can cover a huge part of the screen
with very few data.
It seemed very advantageous.
And I felt it could open new horizons.
Also, a new thing that came with the Amiga was the ability to connect a Genlock.
What's a Genlock? A Genlock is a hardware that enables you to put a video behind the picture,
and the picture which is displayed on the screen, of course.
And I had seen a demo of this in a shop, and this led me to a conclusion that
If I could connect a video camcorder to the Amiga
with this hardware, I could create realistic animation
with polygons by using the classical technique
of rotoscoping.
Well, an idea is an idea, and it needed to become real
to have any value.
But there was.
One crucial question.
Was it possible to draw enough polygons at the right speed?
I hadn't coded for two years.
And my last experience with C language was a disaster.
Yes, I promise.
It was really depressing, almost.
So I chose to code in assembly language, which was familiar
to me.
And I prototyped a routine which drew a few polygons at 60 frames per second.
And I'm strengthening the system that reduced to 20 frames per second.
And that was good enough to go further.
So I decided that the graphics unit would be polygons and polygons only.
That was the constraint.
This was a major...
turning point in the creation of a game. It was like a dogma. I was sure that polygons
were the greatest thing in the world. I was obsessed by these polygons, how this car would
look in polygons, how would a potato look in polygons, and how a quad would look in
in polygon. Well, something's wrong. Where the hell is this? Aha, okay. Pixygon! What's
a pixygon? It's a polygon so small that it has the size of a pixel. I was used to doing
some pixel art, but dealing with flat surfaces.
was something new.
The first time I used polygons to create graphics,
I was spending hours and hours drawing pixels with polygons.
The clock was ticking.
And months later, I was still on the first level.
That was discouraging.
And after coding a third of a game,
I reverted to.
to using some bitmap when I needed details
for some backgrounds.
But finally, the whole game uses only 10 bitmaps.
As you see, this choice brought new obstacles, especially
for detailed backgrounds.
But it opened new horizons for animation.
Again, what I would create, I strictly didn't know.
I can tell you, I tried, and it was a nightmare because it was too difficult to design without
knowing precisely the technical limits.
I just knew that I wanted to create a game with a cinematic feeling on a science fiction
theme with the rhythm of a movie.
but not especially having a story. I mean a well-defined script.
I was thinking more in terms of mood, ambience, movie, but no story. Yes, because it was not the
story side that interested me the most, but the rhythm and the narrative tension which is connected
but different from a story. This is an important point.
I could have said, I want to create a game where a scientist is projected into an unknown
universe where he will meet a friend who will help him all along the game and sure, the
hero will have red hair.
And in the end, he will almost die.
But I had no idea of this at the time.
I was stuck.
It drove me to the conclusion that the only way to solve this situation was to produce.
But no specific tools for polygons existed.
And I had to create the whole game system from scratch, too.
Let's see the tools used to create the game.
There are two aspects.
One, a polygon editor to edit all graphics.
And the hover was a homemade editor for the homemade interpreted language.
This interpreted language was used to code all the game logic.
The tool was coded partly in GFA basic and in assembly language. Basic easy to learn was used
to create the user interface since I didn't need performance. The assembly language.
was used only for the core game engine. Let's see the graphic editor. On the bottom are
all the tools. It's possible to create an object, a polygon, add a point, move a point,
change its color.
The idea was to code a tool where every polygon can be grouped together so that it can be
easily manipulated and where each group of polygons can be grouped together again like
Russian dolls.
Here you can see that Lester is made of several polygons, but his head is another group of
polygons.
there was a special color which enabled transparency.
Indeed, that was a color palette trick,
and it is how I added some light effects.
So that's for the graphic side.
And then just by hitting a key, I
was able to switch from the graphic editor
to the code editor, which
which lead us to the specific language of the game.
I made the choice of an interpreted language because in 1985, I designed this for a game
called Infernal Runner.
This was, and this was really much easier to program than in assembly language.
The big advantage is that the game...
would be interpreted in real time,
so no compiling was necessary to run the game.
That was a key feature to be efficient during its creation.
What is more, the connection between the two editors
went even tighter.
What we see on the left is the visualization of a drawing code
on the right.
I could move the graphics and it would modify the code and vice versa.
Ok.
In the graphic editor, it was also possible to run step by step a part of the program.
The key feature is that the interpreted language has a special instruction to slice the code
into time blocks.
It is the break instruction.
You can see the break instruction here, and this instruction pauses the code until the
next game loop.
And the draw function just draws an object from the polygon editor.
This way, the interpreted code itself
became also an animation sequencer.
And it was possible to associate more complex code
to manage all the gameplay interaction.
The language has few instructions, very simple
and minimalism, like the assembly language,
but more readable.
The problem was that no comments were possible.
And the variable name was like V251.
And it carried just a number and no description.
So the solution I used was to note
that each variable was on paper.
And I have a full documentation.
I still have it today.
And it works.
So without entering into details,
the engine allowed to run small piece of interpreted code
sequentially on separate tracks.
A little bit like a clip in Flash, but without graphics.
So it was very easy.
to manage timing and sequence inside the code.
Hence, we have one track for character displacement,
one track to manage the pad control,
one track to manage the laser shot.
So I had my tools and the game engine.
I learned their limits, like frame rate, number of colors,
memory limits.
And regarding the improvisation process,
I accept these limits as a new constraint.
So now I was not lost, and I can build the game
with these limits in mind.
What's wrong again?
OK.
No common data between levels.
Each time.
I started a new level.
I copied the previous one to keep the basics,
like controls, characters, behavior, and graphics.
And indeed, it was a major failure in the game
development, since for every change
I was making on generic things, I had to do it on all files.
For example, each time Lester's behavior changed,
I had to change it for all five levels.
And later, when I did a lot of tuning,
this became a nightmare.
So let's go to the game creation.
The introduction was a landmark because it validated the use of polygons and the use
of the interpreted language.
And the whole thing took only 84 kilobytes.
It was a way, so this introduction was a way to explore the dynamic of pictures in a cinematic style,
and especially the transition between cuts.
And also, this was a way to immerse myself in the universe, which was not existing before.
And it was the first layer of the improvisation process.
Hence, the first layer of the improvisation.
I had the first stepping stone for the story.
I had too much belief in rotoscoping.
I created some great scenes with it, but in the end, there are only six scenes that use
the technique, this technique, in the introduction.
And the rest of the game...
I don't know.
In the rest of the game, only the gun sequence and the walk
and run of Lester was made with this technique.
I got the best result from unmade animation,
like the lightning sequence.
Anyway, this confirmed that polygon animation was great,
but rotoscoping itself was, well, a little bit too limited.
The main rule I followed during the creation of a game was to listen to my inner feeling.
What do I feel right now? What does it suggest to me?
That's why doing things in chronological order made things coherent.
At that moment, it was not clear.
But creating a game all alone brought a feeling of loneliness.
which you can also find in the game.
And I was always trying to consider myself
as a player of a game who knew nothing about it.
Each time, I was asking myself, what would I love to experience?
And then, as a creator, how can I surprise and break
my initial expectation?
Surprising the player was important.
Playing with the pacing was a top objective.
the hero just disappeared and from that point I just knew that he would be teleported into
another world. But where? I thought in VR, in Freefall first, but then I thought it would be
much more surprising and unearthly to make him appear underwater.
which gave another stunning moment when he emerged on the surface of a totally unknown place
that is clearly not Earth since there are two moons in the sky.
Is Jordan there?
Okay
The choice to do a 2D game came naturally. I was a big fan of Karateka on Apple 2,
and that was a kind of game I felt comfortable to create, so I went this way.
So, what's the player doing?
All gameplay activity is very traditional in many aspects.
You fight, you run, you jump, you flee, you die.
But the environment suggests a narrative and gives more meaning to these basic actions.
The color palette. Only 16 in total and it was very difficult to define.
A whole week was needed to define the first color palette.
full one week full time for 16 colors, a determining choice for the atmosphere of the game.
Some colors are sometimes used both for the landscape and for the character. For instance,
the hero's flesh color was also used to suggest the sunset reflected on the rock.
Having only 16 colors is very restrictive.
You could understand my need to optimize
the use of each color as each hue had multiple uses.
Giving Lester dark hair would have been an easy solution.
But I didn't want him to look too much like me.
Yes, because I was filming myself to create animation.
And the hero was physically nearly identical to me.
It was disturbing.
So I didn't want to see myself running on the screen,
being killed by a slug or whatever.
So I decided to choose a totally different color, red,
because I was sure that this color would be
very useful in many pictures.
And I also wanted Lester to stand out
from the background.
and I will never have red hair.
Only blue hair sometime.
So, during the creation of this part, I defined the vocabulary used through the whole game.
We will see this right now.
Creating a 2D game limits the gameplay to one plane,
but it gives the advantage of exploiting more freely
the depth at the front and the back of the scene
for something else.
This in order to build narrative without interrupting
player activity.
Here, the black beast can be seen from the beginning.
so the player can start to think about it.
So it's really a suggestion of a story.
And what happens in the background suddenly becomes real for the player.
This cutscene is very short.
And it gets, this cutscene is very short and can be seen as punctuating, as punctuating
to give emphasis to a major event, which is a turning point in the pacing.
So I played with the rhythm of the action.
We go from a slow rhythm before the creature arrives.
to a fast and very stressful situation,
with a moment of suspension, when you have to backtrack.
Then, to reach the climax, where another punctuation...
surprise again the player.
Here we've reached the end of part one, which ends on a cliffhanger for the player, but
also for myself.
And regarding the improvisation process, after that point,
I didn't know what would happen next.
I just knew that the next scene would be in a jail,
but the idea of giving lesser a friend hadn't come to me yet.
How this guy looked under his costume, I did not know.
So in the jail, the first thing I did was to remove his clothes
to know what he looked like.
And then I introduced the most important character
in the game, the friend.
He helps the player, but I was still not thinking about him being a focus of the game.
You will notice that this cut...
is the only moment where you can see the body in close-up.
And this picture is enough for the player
to project his face on the small-sized character.
As I say often, the real media is the player's memory
and imagination.
So seeing once is enough to complete the mental picture
of the game universe in his mind.
Okay, I always loved the way they render laser beams in Star Wars movies,
and they were very expressive visually with a lot of dynamism,
and I always wanted to see this in a game.
Okay, here is how a nice idea can arise from constraints.
I was thinking more...
about the core gameplay.
Something around fighting, but also a means for protection.
After the escape from jail, the initial idea
was to progress from one shelter to another
to avoid shots fired by the guard.
It was abundant.
because it was too complicated to manage the death.
In the end, the development of defense strategy
brought me the concept of protective fields,
which are shelters generated by the player himself.
This creates very interesting gameplay combinations.
which lead to a plasma ball, sorry, which lead to a plasma ball which is the third stage
of weaponry, like a Swiss knife.
And we have this.
In retrospect, this is one aspect I'm very proud of,
because the player has to choose from different strategies.
The player can use a small shot immediately,
but without protection, or risk his life creating a shield,
and ultimately, even taking more time
to create plasma to destroy enemy shields or doors.
So somehow, this became the building blocks
to different types of gameplay.
After designing my weaponry, I needed
to develop exploratory notions.
Everything up to this point was on a single level.
On a single level on the screen, I mean.
But I felt limited.
Having several stages.
in a game screen would bring more tactics and puzzles.
But the difficulty was to create character animation
and collision on stairs.
How could I do this with little effort?
I was thinking of a real elevator,
but another idea came.
Why not create a kind of teleporter
to switch from level to level just
by drawing a few vertical polygons?
in Lester's color, I realized that I could create a very nice impression of motion.
Something that was inspired by
by Japanese
manga animation, in which we get an impression of high-speed movement just by stretching lines.
This is the end of the jail level, where Buddy and Lester are separated.
At this point, I realized that I couldn't let him go without finding him again.
I felt attached to him.
Okay, I only did one third of the game.
And at this rhythm...
I would have two more years of work, which was really depressing.
From that point, I decided to work more and to not get lost in details.
Some backgrounds were more flattened.
So I got organized and created a set of graphic blocks I could reuse to create detailed
backgrounds fastened.
From that point, I focused more on puzzles, creating variations using the building blocks
I had at my disposal.
and each time I was trying to bring a new idea.
The friend became the center of the story
with a succession of twists
where Lester and his friend helped each other.
I never wanted at the beginning to create a game about the relationship between two strangers,
but the improvisation led me naturally to this.
Producing is a source of inspiration in itself.
Then I extended the use of parallel action to the foreground.
Here?
When the player leaves the jail, we can see the frame being chased by guards in the foreground.
This has the same effect as a close-up, but without breaking the player's activity.
On the first level, I discovered the pleasure of modulating the pacing.
But now, I was playing around with it.
For example, to modulate the pacing, I used laser beams to give different rhythms, enabling
me to modulate the tension, a little bit like music score.
MMMMMMMMMMMMMMMMMMMM
Here is an animation with five friends.
The laser beam comes from the foreground,
giving the impression of a raging battle.
Ha, ha, ha.
OK.
Publishing.
It was time to see if a publisher would be interested in the game.
I met Delphine Software, who were interested, but I wanted to meet another publisher, which
was in fact the French headquarter of Virgin Games.
Here was a major fork during the creation of the game, the moment where another world
could have changed drastically.
it could have become a point and click.
I love point and click.
And so the editorial director said,
if you want to make it a hit, make it less difficult
by transforming it to a point and click.
So it was the golden era of this kind of game.
And as always, being full of doubt,
he almost convinced me.
So.
Future Wars, the previous game I did, was a point-and-click.
I love point-and-click, as I said.
However, I don't like doing things twice.
And the effort to convert it would have been too huge.
Also, some friends who played the game really loved it.
So I maintained my direction.
And finally.
The game was published by Delphine Software, who were not an international publisher,
but were fully supportive of the creation.
They trusted their game creators and were not intrusive into the design process,
which was rare and extremely valuable.
time to think about the end. How would I conclude the game? I didn't know. And at this point,
I had an agreement for its release in November. I had done three quarters of the game. And
it was, yes, it was really the time to step back and review the game.
the overall passing, how I wanted it to evolve to the end.
So, the idea was to envision the finished game so as to balance the later stage with the rest.
I drew a curve of all major past events.
and activity for the player, and decided
to play with contrasting situations and change
of pace, which lead to the arena scene,
and which lead to an up and down rhythm.
So.
And yes, the cover illustration, I have tales to tell about this.
Throughout my career, cover illustration
has been a major issue and a huge source of disappointment.
I always consider the cover as the continuity of a game.
And it's the first, as it is, the first bond
between it and the player.
the publishers of my previous games had the habit to impose artwork on me.
Like this, or this, or even this.
Well, those games were particularly bad, by the way.
Over the years, I'd become passionate about illustration
to the point that...
I actually wanted to become an illustrator.
So for another world, I didn't want to miss the opportunity of doing it myself.
Being published by Delphine Software was fortunate.
They were fine for me to create the cover illustration.
But doing this...
while creating the game was really difficult as I was already under pressure to finish the game for Christmas.
It took me three weeks, but quite honestly, I didn't have.
One of the big issues...
for the first release in 1991 was the lack of playtest.
Delphine Software were not doing a lot of playtesting
at the time.
And we had only two test sessions.
And that was for the beginning of the game only.
I fixed some major issues, but the game was really unbalanced.
When Interplay became the US publisher, they did a lot of playtesting, and the game underwent
a second polishing.
I fixed a lot of bugs and removed some sources of frustration.
However, they asked me to make the game longer, and some parts became more difficult.
OK.
Interplay wanted to replace the original music used
on the Amiga version with new music for the Super Nintendo.
And I disagreed.
This was a serious source of conflict
as they were doing the porting for the game.
And the situation drove me totally crazy.
The music matched so well the visuals.
This.
led to a big transatlantic fight by fax,
lasting several weeks.
And after exchanging a number of faxes,
I decided I'd use a new strategy.
This consisted in sending an infinite fax.
What an infinite fax.
It's a long strip of paper where the beginning is stuck to the end using an adhesive strip,
such that it loops around the fax machine endlessly.
And of course, I sent it in the dead of night in Los Angeles.
So you could imagine their surprise when they arrived at work in the morning and found reams
of paper repeating the message, the message, keep the original intro music.
This didn't help.
They didn't change their mind until Delphine Software got involved and said that legally
they had no right to impose their choice of music.
And the discussion was closed.
Having a game on console had its own constraints.
One of these was censorship.
Another world could have ended up in a sex shop.
Yes, there is an extremely obscene feature in nudity.
So you get the drift.
The alien women were totally naked.
And here is the cause for concern.
The butt crack was too explicit.
So I considered using another infinite fax with the message,
keep the original crack on the alien ass.
However, the console manufacturer
gave me no choice.
I didn't send the fax.
So to limit the change, I had to remove only these three pixels to suggest a bathing suit.
At the end of the development, I was exhausted.
And this is probably the reason Lister was almost dying in the end.
Thank you very much.
Okay.
So...
Thank you.
And...
We have seen the whole process from the origins to a finished product.
How improvisation process was important in the creation of this game.
And I didn't talk about the music and the sound because the timing was too short.
Well, the game has a...
lived on longer than I originally thought,
and has been released on many platforms.
So I have a little surprise, as this is the 20th anniversary.
The game will be ported to iPad.
So.
Woo!
Thank you.
There is a little prototype here.
And now, if you have any question, well,
I really want to answer to your question if you have.
Thank you.
Mario is coming.
to help me to answer.
He will translate your question in French.
If needed.
Yeah.
OK.
Do you have any question?
I've got one.
Yes?
Right in front of you.
I'm Ryan from Untold Entertainment.
And this was a really inspirational game.
Your talk was awesome.
This is awesome.
So I understand you had no involvement in the sequel.
If it were up to you, would you have made a sequel?
And if so, what would you have done
with the story from that point?
So you're talking about Art of the Alien, right?
I had a very short involvement.
I was very little implied in this.
I only gave the initial concept, which was to play again with a friend
and look at the game under another viewpoint.
But beyond that, I wasn't...
I was creating Heart of Darkness at that time, so I was quite busy.
At that time, I was busy creating Heart of Darkness,
and I remained rather distant from this sequel.
Hi, I speak French, so it will go pretty quickly.
OK, I'll have to translate it into English afterwards.
I would like to know what you think of the remake that has been made recently.
It's on the web.
Yes, I have been involved in it, yes.
So I think I'm happy with this.
Hi.
So from what you said, it seems like the game
was kind of your diary you wrote at the time.
And how do you think the
game would change if you were to design the whole process from start to finish at the
beginning actually, you know, you kind of do it on the fly?
How do you think you will be?
The game will be different.
Really different.
I think that typically...
...not to enter quickly into creation.
wouldn't enter immediately in the creation.
That means we're using a lot of the energy in theory and in designing.
But I think that it's a good thing to look for ideas while experimenting.
And to want to freeze everything is dangerous.
Okay, thanks.
Hi, I was wondering what other sci-fi inspirations you had or fantasy?
novels or movies that you were interested in when you were making the game?
I've been influenced by comics
and especially by an artist called Richard Corbin
whose comics had an impact on me.
whose comics had really made an impression on me.
And more generally, all fantastic illustrations.
Michael Whelan.
Frank Frazetta, Don Makes.
Frazetta.
Bernie Wrightson.
Okay.
Yes.
The main expression.
Hello.
Oh, hello.
You want to go?
Could you please speak for just a moment about the sound effects creation?
Yes.
The whole sound part arrives rather late.
That all was done in the last six months.
It was easy enough and I approached it in a minimalist way.
I just wanted the essential noises.
The more complicated part was the music.
I had a clear vision of what I wanted in my head, but I couldn't translate it.
So Jean-François Freitas, the composer,
he iterated for six months.
He kept proposing different solutions regularly.
And then came a moment when everything fell into place, crystallized.
the introduction, for example, at the beginning of the game...
the people who knew the introduction without saying it...
Yes, it completely changed the perception.
That's it.
I answered...
At the fistrel?
Did I answer your question?
Or?
Yeah, make CS with the head.
Hello.
First, I just want to thank you for creating the game.
It is one of my favorite games of all time.
A question was asked of you earlier
about your inspirations.
I want to kind of reverse that a bit.
I know a number of games have been
made after Another World that seem
to have drawn clear inspiration from it.
Specifically, a lot of comparisons have been made between Another World and Flashback.
And I was wondering if you had any thoughts about these comparisons, or if there are any other games you could think of that seem to have drawn inspiration from yours.
Could you repeat your last sentence?
Oh, sure.
I was wondering if there were...
In addition to Flashback, if you want to talk about that,
if there were any other games that you feel have kind of drawn inspiration from Another World,
and any comments you might have about that.
Ok.
Do you know of any other games that were inspired by Another World?
What do you think about that?
I know that Iko was inspired by another one because Kumito... tell it.
Okay.
What I want to say is that...
All I wanted to say was that different games were influenced by it, but I haven't really looked and identified it or listed them.
It's more the creators of the games that told me.
And it was really a pleasure to see that this game could
influence other people.
I never have thought of it at the start.
Thank you.
Hello.
First of all, amazing talk.
Your game and just you as a person
is a great inspiration to myself and everyone in here, I'm sure.
I was wondering your thoughts.
on games as a form of artistic expression.
Another World comes up a lot as an example of this,
how games can transcend the traditional.
Oh, you can't hear me too well?
It gets really good.
Could you come closer to that mic?
I was just wondering your ideas on games
as a form of artistic expression.
Because Another World always comes up when
people talk about games as art.
So I was wondering what you thought about that.
So, what are your thoughts on the game as an inspiration in general?
Because every time, well, several times when we discuss the game,
another world comes to mind.
So, what are your thoughts?
I don't have that impression.
I don't have that impression that it's that important as an inspiration.
I'm more focused on creation.
I don't have that much to say about being an inspiration.
Hi, Eric.
Thanks for the great talk here.
Hi.
Can you tell us from your point of view
which version you feel it's the best?
And if it will be the iPad version, please tell us.
Well, the iPad version is not finished yet, so I don't know.
But the version that was released,
five years ago, it was possible to play it in low resolution or with more enhanced graphics.
So I think it is the best version that has been released because before
In the Amiga, a level was missing, and on the console, Super Nintendo, it was less...
well, less...
moins maniable...
less playable...
Yeah, it was less manageable.
So...
But, yes, the iPad version looks really, really nice.
We'll see.
So, okay.
Okay.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.