I'm going to tell you all about our project Immortality.
This was already going to be a loose and ramshackle presentation, and then the organizer of this conference decided to schedule my talk first thing in the morning, the day after the awards show.
I'm going to try and get through it, and we'll pull together.
I want to get to a nice, substantial Q&A, so I'm going to try and power through it.
Apologies, anyone that has to try and keep up with me.
So let's go.
I'll start my timer.
So I'm Sam Barlow.
I'm a game director, designer, writer.
Founded this company, Half Mermaid Productions, to go make interesting narrative games.
Why are we called Half Mermaid?
It's a fun story.
When we started my last project, Telling Lies, we had to set up an entity to go make things and do all the legal stuff, and the lawyer rang me up and was like, oh shit, we need a name for your company.
that has to be unique and interesting.
And on the spur of the moment, I thought of this dream project that I had, which was an idea for a movie about Alfred Hitchcock working with Esther Williams.
If you don't know who Esther Williams is, this is Esther Williams.
She was at the height of her fame, probably the most famous film star at the time, and she was known for
making movies in which she would swim.
She kind of invented the Olympic sport of synchronized swimming, and she would do these elaborate musical spectacles involving swimming.
Her story was fascinating because she had aspirations to be more significant as an actress, to take on work that didn't just involve swimming.
And so the idea for this movie was you'd kind of have Alfred Hitchcock at the end of his career and he's kind of fading and he comes together with Esther and they both want to make something special and the focus of this movie would be Hitchcock wanting to shoot the most elaborate drowning sequence that had ever been conceived.
And so the name of this movie was Drowning a Mermaid, which was nicely kind of ironic.
So that became the name of the company.
And then when we started Immortality, we decided we were going to self-publish.
We realized that without the context I've just given you, drowning a mermaid sounded kind of aggressive and scary as a company name, so we kind of morphed it into Half Mermaid, acknowledging that all of us, at least from the top up, are half a mermaid.
And this is significant because that dream project I had, this idea of exploring this combination of director and actress and the creative tensions, essentially found a new form in, ultimately, the project Immortality, which, if you haven't played Immortality, I am probably going to spoil everything.
So you have, I don't know, like three minutes if you can download it on your phones before it's all going to be ruined for you.
Immortality is a video game about exploring footage from three lost movies and answering, initially, the question, what happened to Marissa Marcel, the star of these three movies?
It was the first indie game ever to get a perfect score of 10 in Edge magazine.
And last night, we won two awards.
We clearly did something right, and if you follow all the steps I lay out here, you can recreate that success.
It's very reproducible.
This is a template you can just apply to your own projects.
So I'm going to zoom back out, and I'm going to kind of start from the higher level philosophies and goals that drive what we're doing.
And hopefully, if we have time, I'll get to the spreadsheets, which I know is the thing that everyone is here to hear about.
So what is the driving mission behind what we're doing at Half Mermaid and what is my mission in games in general?
And for me, it's kind of crystallized, especially over the last few games, to be about storytelling and the form of storytelling.
And for me, if I look back at the 20th century,
which, you know, I was born in the 20th century.
As my kids remind me, I was born in the late 20th century, which makes me sound like an antique.
The 20th century as a period of storytelling for me is defined by broadcast, right?
This is the big game changer.
You've gone from traditional storytelling techniques, kind of oral storytelling, in-person theatrical storytelling,
and you have the popularity of radio that then blossoms into network TV and cinema where a storyteller can create a beautiful piece of storytelling and then share it with a huge audience and that audience can then absorb and react and there is a sense of global community.
around it but it's so powerful and my go-to, this is like the best fact ever, my go-to kind of example of how powerful this moment was and this transformation to broadcast was in the 50s Orson Welles did a live TV version of King Lear
when this version of King Lear was broadcast, more people watched the live TV version of King Lear than had ever watched any performance of King Lear in the entire history of humanity prior to that day.
So you get this sense of like the seismic shift from like how stories were told and distributed and the scale at which they operated.
Once we hit broadcast, you know, the scale is obscene.
And that is such an interesting and powerful thing.
So now that we're in the 21st century, what is my sense of what is gonna define the forms of storytelling that we create?
And for me, it's all tied up in digital, right?
What does it mean to tell stories through digital media?
What does that enable?
And for me, the initial beautiful first step is what I call throwing away the container.
So if you look at, take movies as an example,
The structure of a movie, the fact that it's like 90 minutes to 2 hours roughly, the act structure is very specific.
Like the container of movies exists for very practical purposes, right?
If you want to distribute a movie, you need to print it on film, put it in a can, at least you used to.
drive it to the movie theater, play it.
If you're broadcasting a television show, naturally you have a single static version of the show that then gets blatted out to everybody, and again, there are restrictions there, right?
The 30-minute show or the 45-minute show, act structures based around commercial breaks, these very specific containers that, you know, exist for very practical reasons.
If I'm watching a movie, there is a limitation to the human bladder.
The movie theaters want to schedule multiple movies throughout the day for commercial reasons.
So we have all these kind of restrictions that come with this kind of 20th century version of broadcast.
But now that we're digital, we can throw those away entirely, right?
And I think up until now, the disruptive kind of digital storytelling media has tweaked the container, right?
Netflix might say, oh, we can have a 35, 36, 37-minute episode.
Or maybe Stranger Things can be two and a half hours long or an hour long.
Is it a movie?
Is it TV?
But these are all like very subtle shifts.
They're still writing these pieces of television in the same structure, with the same container, with the same usage of plot as this kind of guiding principle.
So for me, the real opportunity that we have in coming from games is to throw these containers away and what happens then?
What do you do in the absence of the container?
And for me, if you look at the core pillars of what video games do best and can do best, these are the means by which we can navigate this much more open, interesting space for storytelling.
So here are my four pillars.
In the background there, that's the pillars of Nosgoth, which is a little bit of foreshadowing, if you take note.
And the four pillars for me are challenge, right?
As human beings, if you put an obstacle in my path, if you give me a riddle or question,
I'm naturally inclined to want to overcome that obstacle, to solve the riddle, to answer the questions.
So challenge is this really interesting driver.
When you give people agency and control in a piece of storytelling, that's going to really drag them in and give them that sense of immersion.
Expression is, I think, like my favorite.
When I think of expression, I think of like Nintendo.
I think of playing Mario, which is a game in which Nintendo say, here is this game about running and jumping, but the mechanics of that game give you a richness and a fluidity to allow you to express yourself through how you run and jump, right?
Any two people playing Mario are going to navigate differently.
There's like a real kind of nice possibility space within that mechanic.
And I think what
differentiates my games often with some other narrative games is really paying attention to how can the player express themselves through how they interact with the story and finding mechanics and structures which open up to that expressivity.
The third pillar, exploration, is obviously a fundamental feature of a lot of video games.
As a hunter-gatherer species, we are predisposed to dig exploration, being led by a sense of curiosity, discovery.
These are key fundamental aspects to a lot of traditional video games.
And I think, again, what I've been doing is trying to
take a lot of those verbs around exploration and apply them directly to the story itself.
And that's been kind of a fascinating journey.
And then the fourth pillar is the one that we sometimes take for granted.
Video games are very good at simulating things.
We can simulate physics and vehicles and bullets and have AI that has an abstracted simulation of some kind of creature.
And so we kind of lean on that a lot because it's
for
would involve players, but I kind of questioned how useful it was for my, specifically my storytelling, and so starting with her story in 2015, I kind of explicitly gave myself the challenge of make a video game with no simulation, no state changes, no tracking of kind of structure, can I still create an experience which is enjoyable and immersive.
Given this kind of approach, the last few games I've made, I set out, so with her story, I was exploring a lot of these ideas for the first time.
The idea was to deconstruct a detective story, take a type of story that the audience is familiar with, knows all the tropes, take that knowledge and then use that to kind of fuel the experience by breaking it down into atomic elements, letting people freely navigate.
I followed this up with Telling Lies
And the use of video in her story was somewhat instinctive.
There wasn't a lot of conscious thinking about why I did that.
But looking back with Telling Lies, I started to think about what was interesting about this technique of using video.
And the kind of stated mission of Telling Lies was to make an anti-movie.
It was like all the things which make this distinct from the traditional forms of movies, the structure of it, the pacing of it, the way we shoot it, were kind of driving
the idea of telling lies.
And so both of these kind of culminate in Immortality where we kind of then revisited a cinematic aesthetic and said, well, what happens if we deconstruct movies themselves, right?
If we start to break apart how movies work, why movies work, how they're made, and kind of really dig into that.
And it unlocked some extremely ambitious and challenging questions.
So it's like a kind of fun thing to do.
So, also driving this, I have like my pillars of what is a video game, right?
And as I'm working on a game, I'll keep returning to those, right?
Is this expressive enough?
Is there a meaningful challenge?
You know, how does the exploration work?
Are we empowering the player with our exploration?
But the kind of other method I have, which is sort of fundamental to my process, is I have these three aspects of the game and
The logic is, if I have all three of these in place, this is going to be a good game.
And if I don't have a clear idea of all three of these, do not start making game.
This is the early sanity check of is there an actual solid core here, and as well it helps with
When the game's finished, is it going to be sellable?
Is it going to be explainable?
Is this something I can market?
The whole kind of concept gets tied up here.
So the method is to come up with a theme.
So the theme is, what is the question that we're exploring here?
And it might be a question I don't have an answer to.
and
And then there's the emotion.
And this is kind of key to me, is as a storyteller, I want to have a really specific emotion that I felt that I want to communicate.
And to communicate that needs an experience, right?
If I was to just put it into words, it would sound trite or unspecific.
So how do we create an experience, and through living that experience, have the player
feel this emotion.
So for example in Telling Lies the emotion was how does it feel to have been in a relationship that's failed
but still hold in your head the memories of the happy memories of when that relationship was working, right?
And it's a very complicated part of being a human is holding these conflicting emotions and still having the spark and the way that memory works.
Like there was this real gnarly little emotion there.
It was like, how do we get people to experience that and think about it?
Because if I express it like I just did, it's kind of lame.
And then a key thing is the metaphor.
I call it, I'm slightly breaking the use of the word metaphor.
The idea here is
what is what is the metaphor and kind of it becomes the mechanic that describes the game and this becomes really useful communication tool to the player so for example with her story the metaphor was that moment in a police show where the detective is sat at the computer and they've run out of leads they're at the you know it's
about
That's the core mechanic of her story, and that is this metaphor.
So then if you build the game around that, when you then show players the game, they get it because they recognize this thing.
And the question is, is this a useful metaphor for the story we're telling?
Is this going to be something that you can wrap these themes and emotions in?
And so yeah, the process is to really use this as just like a way of analyzing a piece of game design and going, do I have these three things?
And, you know, maybe it's easier to do this in the indie space, but also like throw out the crap that is extraneous to this, right?
If you can kind of focus on these three things, that gives you a tight and cohesive piece of game.
So doing this process on immortality, our theme, which was absurdly ambitious, was why do human beings tell stories?
And we're like, if we're going to do something that's about cinema and looking back at the 20th century, and cinema is the great storytelling form of the 20th century, this is an opportunity to ask these very deep questions.
And it was exciting.
to give myself permission to ask something as ambitious and silly as this.
Because sometimes you try and kind of scope things down and you feel like, oh, this is like overreaching or it could end up awkward if we try and answer these big questions.
And, you know, with this project, it really became tied up in
Like to what extent is our mortality part of this?
You know, oftentimes you look at people creating pieces of art, creating stories, and sometimes the objective is to use it as an immortality project, to create something that will live beyond them.
And is that a useful and healthy thing to do?
So this was like the theme that we set out to explore.
The emotion was, again, it always sounds trite when you try and express it, but
struggling with the impossibility of creating the perfect story.
And it was like, if storytelling is something we're driven to do, if there are kind of primal reasons for it, the most interesting way to explore that is a case of failure, right?
So this fella here is from the cancelled Legacy of Kane game that I spent three years of my life working on.
was the most challenging thing I worked on and the biggest failure, probably, of my career.
After that I went and did some stuff and I did her story.
So it's slowly being repressed and buried, all my feelings of this project.
And as we started to build this one, I'm like, oh shit, this is all
This is all about that Legacy of Kain game because there's such a commonality between movies and games in terms of the number of people you need, the expense, the technology, right?
These are very challenging places to try and tell a story and tell a true and pure story because there's just so much going on.
So, you know, I really wanted to try and tap into how that felt.
Why did I work so hard?
Why did I push myself so hard at the expense of my family and the rest of my life to try and make this legacy of Kengame, which was a constant struggle, and how did it feel when it failed?
And, you know, trying to put that into an experience for you all to enjoy.
Then the metaphor became the Moviola.
This was like the very first design doc for the project was this little picture of Pikachu with Moviola.
It's a slightly mixed metaphor.
We can kind of expand it and say it's the Moviola of the editing suite, right?
The metaphor became, imagine you're in an editing room and you have all this footage, right?
That process where in making a movie,
The editor sits down to do the assembly cut, and they have everything that's been filmed, this vast amount of footage.
And they start organizing it, and obsessing over it, and looking at it, and picking out the good takes, and going frame by frame, and just really immersing themselves in the beauty of the film, and slowly they assemble a movie.
And so that kind of was our sort of guiding principle and the mechanics of that and kind of wanting to explore the tactile nature of film as a medium versus the kind of more digital stuff we're familiar with.
But even at this point, the presence of Pikachu shows that we were aware that we were also making Pokemon Snap, essentially.
And this was another way that I justified, like, this project's going to work.
and we're doing some weird stuff and we have these ideas but I've played Pokemon Snap and that was fun and people liked Pokemon Snap so this is going to work.
So then the next thing that we do and this is going to be a huge difference for me going from the AAA space or the bigger project space
to being an indie and being able to kind of define how projects work.
And it is specificity.
And to be honest, like, all I ask of a game these days is to have some specificity.
Like, I want some real crunchy, little, special, unique details.
I want to feel like I'm engaging with something that's very authentic and specific.
Like, I just recently finished playing Pentament, right?
And I was like, oh, this is some, like,
This is like a deep, deep dive into a particular fetish for this period of history.
I'm feeling enriched by interacting with this.
It doesn't feel like a mishmash of generic stuff.
And the 100% reliable recipe I have for imbuing a game with specificity is research.
So on this project, we spent a year, year and a half of a two and a half year project
was researching and outlining and writing and thinking about this stuff.
And I have another cheesy tool that I call the list, which is I will basically go and read everything on a subject.
Just read hundreds of books, watch as much footage, read academic papers, just everything I can get my hands on.
And as I'm going, if I find a really interesting little detail,
I'll add it to a list and at the end of this process I just have this really long list just full of these little textures or details or moments that I've never seen before that feel fresh.
And it's kind of this little toolkit that I have as we then start to actually assemble the story and the process and the mechanics of like, oh, there's that little thing.
I've been looking for a way to use that and insert that.
But yeah, the research, reading, it's so easy now to just go online and convince yourself that you've researched something.
But if you sit down and read like three different autobiographies of someone, you just get like a volume of genuine like human detail.
That's interesting.
So to give you an idea, we're gonna watch a bunch of videos.
now.
Actually, I'm going to intro you first.
We started thinking about this idea of exploring movie making, answering these questions, trying to explore this idea of failure and the struggle.
For me, I have a particular love and interest in the idea of lost movies.
Here we've got a shot from a movie that Orson Welles
He shot like half of called The Deep, which was an adaptation of the book Dead Calm, which is one of my favorite thriller novels.
He never completed it.
He ran out of money.
In fact, Orson Welles ran out of money a lot later in his career.
Like he probably has the record for the greatest number of lost movies.
And it's like this perfect encapsulation of what we're talking about, because if the purpose of art is to create an immortality project, a lost movie is a failure.
You put all this effort in and it never comes out.
It's this radical example of failure.
But it still lives, right?
I get excited thinking about this movie that never happened and I see a couple of frames from it and a few clips from it and that's so evocative and interesting and my brain starts working and thinking about it.
So it's also got this nuance to it.
And then similarly, there are movies that have come out.
So Eyes Wide Shut was something of a North Star for this project.
of the movie.
From the very beginning, he was constantly trying to adapt this book that it was based on.
At various points, they almost made it with Woody Allen as the star, which is an alternate path that we have luckily developed.
There was a version with Steve Martin.
He had John Le Carre write the treatment.
He just kept trying to figure out how to make this movie.
and it ends up being his last movie, right?
And he literally died before finishing his movie.
In fact, this movie killed him.
So when Kubrick died, the version of Eyes Wide Shut that's out there was not a finished edit.
It was like, you know, 90%.
And Kubrick was also famous for continuing to edit the movie even after it had premiered.
And it's this idea of struggle and failure as well.
Like this at the time was the longest ever movie shoot
There was all this kind of intrigue and interest around what was going on, why this movie was running for so long, what was happening with Tom and Nicole.
And fascinating things like Harvey Keitel and Jennifer Jason Leigh were in this movie, shot out 90% of their scenes.
And then when it ran for so long, they had to recast them and reshoot it all.
So it's even a movie that came out, it's full of all these what ifs and potential versions that could have existed.
So the idea that the kind of finished,
ultimate version, like, is that the perfect version that Kubrick spent his whole life trying to make?
You know, and all those kind of unlived possibilities are kind of fascinating.
So this was, you know, we started to kind of hone in on this and this idea, well, how about we make our subject lost movies, right?
The idea that we're exploring and kind of unearthing and bringing back to life these lost movies felt like a really nice way to explore our themes.
And then we kind of
quickly
what goes on in the making of a movie and the history of making of movies and the power structures, this was like the absolute locus of like all of these forces.
So for example, the person on the left there is Margarita Cancino, and on the right is the person she became.
The movie studios picked her and decided to transform her.
She underwent painful plastic surgery, and this was like old school plastic surgery,
They changed her ethnicity, they changed her name, they kind of essentially rebuilt her from the ground up.
And she was their creation, right?
Under the studio system, they owned her.
Rita Hayworth was this new entity that they had created.
So it's like this real apex of like that sacrifice of self to essentially allow yourself to be rebuilt in service of the storytelling.
But at the same time,
There was this nuance as well of like thinking now from the 21st century, like Rita Hayworth has survived.
There is something of her soul that when we watch her movies, lives beyond the screen.
And we don't talk about the studio heads who created her, right?
And all the other people that were part of all these different power systems.
All these mechanisms, like there's something where she has kind of survived and she does still live on through this footage of her.
And so this idea of like a star, this idea of an actress who's brought in and kind of molded felt like a really useful kind of locus as our main character to explore some of these themes.
I also started to get really into hair, realized that hair was super important in our story.
So here on the right, this is Rita Hayworth in The Lady from Shanghai, a film that she filmed with Orson Welles, who at that point was her ex.
So like all of those complexities and different power dynamics were
extremely complicated
When he heard of this, he was absolutely furious.
He was like, we created Rita Hayworth, the hair is like 50% of who Rita Hayworth is.
And so you had these two guys, one was the guy who created her and owned her, the other was her ex who was also her director, both arguing about what she should be doing with her hair.
And it's like, it's kind of screwed up.
And the hair continues, right?
So we started to get really interested in Jane Fonda as well because she occupied this beautiful moment where film changed, right?
We went from the studio system into kind of new Hollywood and tracking her career, she was an actress who was able to actually assert herself and gain some agency and start taking on roles and sort of transform.
was
he was in love with the fantasy of them that he created on the camera and he was extremely controlling and so for him the idea of the beautiful blonde uh... woman was like his his archetype and at a point in her life where Jane Fonda was discovering feminism and was trying to assert herself and change her career she went out got a hairdresser and they cut the hair went back to a natural color and what became known as the clute haircut was born
There's a lot, there's so much hair, hair trivia that we were just like, oh, this is like such a big deal and it's so kind of interesting, the nuance that it brings.
Here we've got some videos.
So we were watching like so much video, I became obsessed with talk shows, right?
I watched like a hundred hours of Dick Cavett, which is, I recommend it.
And there's something really interesting about these actresses coming out, being interviewed, so they're playing a version of themselves.
And it was at points excruciating because all of the sexism and the power dynamics,
fully on display in a lot of this stuff so this was this is from like I guess the 80s is Phoebe Cates with Letterman I have a particular love of grungy video so clips like this I'm like I love this shit this is beautiful
There's a constant obsession with the age of actresses and their youth and their perfection and how moldable and controllable they are.
Thank you for being here.
It's quite an honor, I guess, huh?
Yeah, it's a real honor.
Yeah.
You look very young in person.
Yeah, everybody says that.
Yeah, you look like, I don't know, 15, 16, maybe?
Well, yeah, maybe.
Yeah.
And can we tell folks how... The rest of the interview gets worse.
He was completely...
Okay, we got next.
Okay, so this was another clip that kind of had pride of place on our mood board.
So this is Olivia Hussey with her co-star in the Romeo and Juliet movie at the end of the 60s.
They were both like 15, 16 when they filmed this movie.
And they're being interviewed by a very kind of BBC-ish British interviewer.
And there's this small little clip here which YouTube loves, like the YouTube commenters love this stuff because it's all about smoking.
personal question of the uh... and as you know you're at fifteen it's pretty young to be smoking cigarettes when did you start?
at about fourteen about fourteen while you were doing the prime of miss jean brody?
yes well just before then actually i mean that that is pretty young there aren't many girls at fifteen i know that smoke cigarettes publicly oh there are and uh... what are your
Yeah, she spent the whole interview smoking like a chimney.
But that little bit, the whole interview, this BBC guy is treating her like some slightly exotic, precocious creature, and he's very intrigued by her strength of character or whatever.
But the look she gave him, and she was like, you don't know shit about teenage girls and what they're up to.
That stuck with me, and I started watching a lot of these
clips
as an exaggeration and reflection of actually how much strength of character these actresses have to sit there and just kind of smile through this crap.
If actually inside of them there was something even more powerful that could just step up and rip the head off this interviewer or, you know, had a lived experience or a wisdom that was far in excess of what you're thinking.
And that kind of grew into the fantasy element of this game.
Another character that I kind of became obsessed with and
interestingly paralleled the story of Jane Fonda and where Jane Fonda was able to actually kind of emerge and gain control.
Jean Seberg, who you see here, did not.
She was an actress who was kind of cast from obscurity by Otto Preminger.
into a movie where he literally burned her alive on set and was a big failure.
She had this incredible moment where she essentially ushered in the new wave by starring in Goddard's Breathless, but subsequent to that, her career didn't work.
She was constantly trying to seek out meaningful work, and the system, the men around her consistently failed her, and then she kind of died tragically.
So kind of getting really deep into her story,
became a big part of the thought process of trying to create this character of Marissa Marcel.
This clip here is the first time she appeared on television ever.
This is a deep archival thing, so the quality is amazingly bad.
It's beautiful.
The generation loss is exquisite.
But check out some of the body language in here.
It's actually kind of excruciating.
exact moment.
You know, here are the two principals in the most exciting adventure in show business in the last 25 years.
The gentleman here, you probably recognize him, the distinguished producer and director from Hollywood, Otto Preminger.
So let's have a nice welcome to Otto.
Now before I introduce this youngster, I want to tell you the story that Otto Preminger conceived and carried out.
He has the rights to Shaw's St.
Joan for the movie.
He thought to himself that, wearying of the star system temporarily, that this time he was going to find a girl, an unknown, and so he scouted through all of the United States, and then in most of the countries of Europe and in Canada, and out of probably 18,000 girls, I believe, submitted their applications and their backgrounds,
And then Otto reduced this to 3,000.
He tested all of those.
And this youngster here, Jean Seberg, is the one who caught lightning in a bottle because of her talent and her beauty and the qualities that Otto was looking for.
So let's have a wonderful hand for this 17-year-old youngster.
And then we talked about Jane Fonda already.
We really kind of zoomed in on this moment in her life when she had this reinvention and she was living in 70s New York, hanging out with Warhol, who himself was doing some very interesting explorations.
Warhol's studio called The Factory is on Union Square.
He called there, no result.
He was at a farewell party for Jane Fonda on the SS France.
We're doing a picture together.
Building up all this research, we then kind of
zoomed on
responding to all this research, kind of orchestrate and pick where we put these in the history of film.
So we had our first movie at the tail end of the studio system, this idea of a director who is out of fashion, a kind of late period Hitchcock style director, who, you know, is coming from a studio system where everything is fake and owned.
And, you know, it's things that would have felt extremely cinematic and exciting, early in their career now feel more dated and theatrical.
And then we contrast that with this jump to the new Hollywood in the early 70s, particularly in New York, where filmmaking becomes more organic and authentic.
We have this idea of, like, 70s filmmaking being this kind of ideal of, like, grown-up cinema.
And we wanted to kind of interrogate that.
And then for our final movie, we give ourselves a little interesting time jump, and we're at the end of the millennium, where everyone's kind of looking back.
You have the invention and explosion of the indie movie.
There's all these young people who are looking back at the 70s and being like, this was the good shit, and we're going to try and replicate that.
And it was kind of the last hurrah before everything became digital.
So this gave us like this interesting arc to explore, right, and have this character live through these different moments.
and we were able to figure out different aspect ratios, so we'd have this kind of nice explorability of seeing footage from these different areas and being able to recognize where we were.
Okay, I'm going to get on to the mechanics.
I'm going to have to go fast, otherwise we won't get to the spreadsheets.
So whilst we're doing all this research and outlining and thinking, we're also in parallel, like prototyping the mechanics, so we kind of have the time to let those bed in and get the right game feel.
So the movie Ola, I talked about, you know, this idea of putting you in the editing room.
And we wanted to hit something, you know, I pitched someone early on about this and they were like, so is it like final cut?
Are you like gamifying final cut?
It was like, well, no, cause that's like the prosaic bit.
What we want more is like, you're in the editing suite with the editor, right?
You're looking over their shoulder and you're reaching into this bin and pulling out footage and putting it in the machine and then discovering what's on it, right?
We wanted to give you that, the excitement of that and the tactile nature of that.
without a lot of the prosaic stuff.
So the movie only became this focus.
We had like 15 hours of recordings of movie over sounds that we started trying to kind of use and concatenate.
And then there was this piece of research that I just kept going back to.
And this was Nick Rogue when he, so the film director, Nick Rogue, when he started out, he was like a T-boy at one of the studios.
And he talks about, and this part of his biography,
He talks about the moment where he first saw, this was an editola, which is the same thing as a movieola, first time he saw footage running and he could turn it backwards and he could play with the speed of it and he was just like mind blown like this was magical to him that he could manipulate time and it fundamentally changed his understanding of filmmaking and storytelling and
In the same biography, he then goes on to say, so the editola was like a PlayStation 3 for me.
So he was writing this a few years back.
And just like you read that when you're doing your research and you're like, holy shit, like he's telling us what to do, right?
We're gonna take the PlayStation 5 and make it into a movieola.
We're gonna flip that equation.
But he understood that there was something like playful and kind of tactile and exploratory about that experience for him.
I put this clip in as an indulgence, but I don't know if I can... I'll indulge myself.
So you see this in his work.
In the film Walkabout, he uses the manipulation of the footage to express some subjectivity.
So in this movie, some evil hunters shoot this buffalo.
We see the buffalo die.
And then Rogue starts screwing around to try and express something.
So he does this zoom right into the grain of the footage, right?
Breaking it down into its kind of atomic elements.
And then along comes this kid who, by the way, is Nick Rogue's son.
Movie making is always incestuous and complicated.
on
And he looks over, and because he's willing the buffalo to not be dead, we then see from his perspective the footage of the buffalo in reverse, coming back to life again.
This was like an obsession of Nick Rogue's.
And we really dug into that as well, this idea that playing the footage backwards was a way of resurrecting something, of bringing something back to life.
And if you
of play to mortality, you might see some moments or scenes in this where the idea of playing things backwards as a way of resurrecting, the idea that the existence of this footage and your manipulation of it as a way of bringing someone back to life is kind of a big core beat of that story.
And as a side note, using your marketing to foreshadow your big story beats and the endings of your stories is awesome, and you should do it.
So we just, yeah, every time we talk about immortality, early teaser trailers, we put out these images of this fire and these flaming posters.
So even before people were playing the game, we were preparing them and helping them build up the richness of where we were going in our story.
I think Pentamon did that as well.
not
Great.
They were terrified it might look like crap, and a lot of film grain in video games doesn't look very authentic.
So we set out to do the best film grain, and we came up with a system.
So the way film grain works is there's two grains.
When you first capture the image on the negative, there is an initial grain that's created by the little imperfections and holes between the actual material.
team.
look at the luminosity of the image, and then apply these different grains in varying amounts.
We had these fun little curves that we could set up in Unity for the different film.
Each different type of film, we had scans of actual film grain that we turned into tileable textures, and then we could apply and tweak the way the luminosity gradients worked so that we were applying the grain.
And you'll notice where you hit the really hot, burnt-out whites, there is no grain.
A lot of film grain shaders will just sort of multiply.
and you'll see the dots everywhere.
So this we just kept tweaking and going back and forth on to try and hit that authenticity and give us that beautiful kind of crisp grain when we were zooming in and out so it didn't feel like a kind of compressed digital version of this analog film that we were trying to celebrate.
So we continued to prototype and work on things.
And so we spent a year tweaking the feel of scrubbing the film.
And we had this prototype build.
So we hadn't shot anything.
We had a bunch of clips of different films.
And this was from the eyes of Laura Mars, a scene in which Tolly Lee Jones does take his shirt off.
And rewinding and tweaking film is
so much fun, right?
Me and Chris Nolan and Tennant are just like on the same wavelength of like, people take clothes off, you play that backwards, it looks amazing.
People shake their hair, play it backwards, see water, smoke, all these kind of things that just look beautiful and you start messing around with them.
So this was one of the scenes that I would just test and test and test.
And we tried so many different things of like, how are you scrubbing the film?
We started with this idea of like a movie, Ola is quite mechanical.
But we ended up kind of mixing our metaphor a little bit because we wanted it to have like a real tactile feel.
So we're like, well, imagining the film reels, if you're touching the reel and you can kind of move it, but then you can spin it and it'll have some inertia to it.
So we came up with these ideas of like flicking and what does it feel like to flick an analog stick?
Then we realized you lose control.
So we started like ratcheting it and locking you into certain speeds.
And there was like, yeah, it was like a year's worth of just like screwing around with the footage playback.
And as you can see there, I'm now technically married to Tom Lee Jones.
He's a lovely partner.
And then we got onto the grid, right?
This was exciting for me.
Like in the previous games, we'd always do a trailer.
And to show in the trailer just how much cool footage we had and the range and variety, we'd always end up on this visual of like a video wall.
Like, whoa, look at all the cool stuff here.
And on this one, I was like, what?
Couldn't that just be the game?
Wouldn't that be exciting?
I was also like, my teenage years were spent going to video installations in art galleries, I was obsessed with those things.
So just like big screens and walls of video is an aesthetic that I really appreciate.
And this is how we ended up with kind of our core interface of this grid that you can zoom in and out of and shuffle.
And the excitement for me here was this idea of the map is the territory, right?
It's like a Borges short story about the idea of a map that is actually to scale And that's video games, right?
Like we navigate these virtual worlds that have essentially an extent that is huge and here
This idea of an interface that does all these things I'm listing here like it's essentially your menu, it's your inventory of clips you've collected, it also serves as a kind of history because we have this symbol grid that every time you click on something we're capturing that image and the grid shows the place you parked the footage at as well so it becomes very personal and specific to you.
So the idea that it was doing all these things, and we wanted as well, like you never leave this screen really.
You zoom into the footage, and then you'll zoom out of the footage, and you can teleport between bits of footage, but like you're essentially in this consistent world, right?
Again, it's like an abstraction of the edit room.
You're surrounded by all the footage.
and we're just allowing you to feel overwhelmed by how much is there.
And it also recalls, like, if you're a hardcore cinephile, you're going to, you know, there's sites that do, like, a frame from every minute of, like, your favorite movie, and you can see how the color schemes shift across the movie and stuff, and it's, like, a really fun way to just kind of x-ray a movie.
A lot of this game was, like, what is all the cool shit I do as a cinephile?
How can we just trick the player into doing that without realizing it, right?
Because they just think it's a game mechanic.
The one thing we did, we were trying to be so authentic in everything we did, the one thing, and we were so torn about this because the aspect ratio of most gaming things is landscape, to sort all these clips
It made sense that the film strip would be on its side.
Movie film, however, is vertical.
So technically, if this was real footage, the strips and the little holes would run vertically down.
We did briefly try that, and it just didn't work aesthetically.
So we were like, yeah, well, we know that we're breaking a rule here and that this is not real, but it's going to help everything in the long run.
So we felt bad about it, but we pushed forward.
And then the core kind of marquee mechanic of this video game, the match cut.
Let's see if we've got time.
This is such a good match cut.
This is from Peeping Tom, a movie about people dying on camera and what that means.
Oh, look at that match cut.
Again, the match cut is something people are going to be able to grok.
It's this thing they'll understand.
It's exciting and fun.
Could that be the mechanic at the heart of our game?
Because we had been discussing how do we make a mechanic out of cutting in film, right?
How do we not have it be prosaic, like final cut?
How do you have that be interesting and expressive?
So we had this idea of what if I could click on anything in any frame and have that then cut to something else?
That's so expressive.
You can click on anything.
You're deciding what's interesting, what's aesthetically interesting.
And then we get really interested in this idea of, well, to preserve the magic of the cut, you don't know where it's going to go.
The game is going to decide where this cut takes you.
And that was fascinating to me because it was introducing randomness into a pure narrative game.
And we know that randomness works in Diablo loot drops, all these other game mechanics.
But usually in narrative, you're looking for this causality and this very simple causality and logic to it.
So I was like, oh, this...
feels interesting, right?
It's a big risk, but let's explore what it feels like to have randomness in a story mechanic.
And it felt like teleportation.
I'm obsessed with the idea of teleportation.
So many games are about moving faster, having superpowers, right?
And this idea of teleporting around a narrative feels like a superpower.
I'm going to skip showing you the video, because you know how it works.
So how did we do it?
And this was the big challenge.
I'm going to go really fast now, sorry.
And then I love in-game, sometimes the solution is just to do a huge amount of work.
And that's what we did.
We said, well, is it possible to actually just track every single thing that we think is worth clicking on?
And it was.
We had a team of people in After Effects, myself and Natalie, would mark up, these are all the things that are in focus that should be clickable.
And then we had a team of people using tracking technology to track all these objects.
We then had the complexity of having to compress that information, which was gigabytes per scene in VFX software, into these simpler, lower polygon animations so that every single object is constantly being tracked.
There were rules for how things overlapped and things that were interesting.
And then we had this big lookup table that would tell the code there is an equivalence.
An apple and an orange could cut together.
Marissa Marcel playing Franny can cut to Marissa Marcel playing Maria.
And there is a ranking to it.
which I'll get to in one second but also we kind of did a lot of iteration on well how do you click we had a version where you you could just click at any point and it would do the match cut and we're like it doesn't feel sexy enough so then we were like well let's make it a mode let's have to enter the mode and then it becomes like
at
I'm
We have all this information about thematically what's happening in scenes, what various elements mean, and it tries to choose a good point to jump to.
Maybe in the Q&A or outside we can talk more about the specifics of that.
But it tries to do clever things and it has this kind of heartbeat so it'll alternate between trying to connect things that are in proximity
and
of logic to it, but it's not exposed to the player.
It's kind of doing this meaningful little dance.
It's like playing a kind of two-player party game, right?
You play consequences.
I draw a funny little picture, and for it to be fun, you have to meaningfully respond to what I've done, but I also want you to surprise me.
So this was kind of this interesting balance
And then we have secrets in the game.
There are some big secrets.
We wanted this thing to feel alive and feel haunted.
So we talked about Orson Welles again, about the War of the Worlds, how he took radio, something people were so familiar with, and kind of took for granted, and then used that as a chance to actually surprise them and scare them and horrify them.
I keep mentioning Orson Welles.
The secret is we were trying to make the Citizen Kane of video games.
So we were explicitly like, let's just learn everything about Orson Welles and that will get us there.
We did lots of prototyping on this idea of hidden aspects to the footage.
This idea, like I said, of rewinding being a way of accessing and resurrecting and discovering things.
And we knew it was going to work because we did tests with footage of me during the pandemic, just at home.
And it still frightened me, like when stuff would appear and pop out or fade in when I wasn't expecting it.
And the few things we kind of iterated on in this mechanic that are interesting.
Originally, we had a lot more of these kind of invisible cuts where a character would walk off screen, and then seamlessly we would transition to a different version of this scene.
And those were really cool, and we used quite a lot of those in the game.
But then when we were actually implementing them, we discovered that there were places where if we actually created a jump cut, that should actually be kind of more scary and more horrific.
So we kind of started adding those in.
We have this concept of free-floating moments, so a lot of the supernatural and hidden scenes are linked to specific instances, right, and are very located in the moment.
But to facilitate keeping things spooky, there are a whole bunch of scenes that are free-floating that the code will attach to a clip.
If it feels like, oh, you haven't seen anything spooky for a while, here's a place we could insert something, it'll kind of fit those in.
So it's trying to keep things
Interesting and then we played around a lot with what people now call the immortality noise like how do we add these?
Audio layers to hint on the menu on the grid and also within the footage to let you know There's something creepy and usually people kind of start hearing that and paying attention to it And then 30 minutes later is when they really like hang on okay?
and discover things.
But thanks Metroid Prime because we talked a lot about how Metroid Prime hints its secrets with audio.
So now we've got two minutes to get into the spreadsheets which is why you're all here.
Everyone always asks me, like, how do you do this?
How do you create these things?
And the answer is, like, lots of spreadsheets, lots of outlining.
Like, we started here with early plans of, like, the meta story of Marissa Marcelle, figuring out the years, what was happening to Marissa Marcelle across the different time periods.
Then we came up with the three movies, and we outlined and scripted out the beats for all of these movies.
Then we got a producer to look at it and give us a shoot order of how would they actually have shot this movie, what order would it have been shot in, and transposed that onto Marissa Marcel's story so we could find synergies and beats of like, oh if this thing happens to Marissa it would be cool if it happened whilst they were shooting this thing.
We took these outlines, put them back into order, gave them to some of the great screenwriters in history, like Barry Gifford, Alan Scott, Amelia Gray, who I've worked with before.
They went and wrote us the movies based on these outlines.
Whole, full, finished screenplays of movies.
brought those back, moved them around again.
I sat down and then I injected the making of stuff.
I was like, well, if they're shooting this scene, what is Marissa saying?
What's happening?
What's the kind of behind the scenes drama?
So we started to kind of work into these screenplays and create the story of Marissa that kind of weaved into them.
And we get to a point where we have
Okay, I'm nearly there.
We had this sheet which was called the Organizing Monster, which is a giant, this is like a teeny slice of it, giant spreadsheet that is like everything in the game.
And then we used what I call a hologram method, which is how do these nonlinear things that you make sound make sense?
And the answer is like a hologram contains in every piece of it, like the information for the whole rest of the image, right?
So we look at every scene and we have all these columns and it's like every scene has to meaningfully answer a question about Marissa's story, tell us a piece of plot beat from the fictional movie, have a piece of craft from movie making, have some hint at the meta story, tell the story of what's going on with Arthur Fisher, what's happening with Robert Jones, have a piece of imagery that resonates with our themes, all three of our themes that we're tracking.
we just go through and make sure that every scene is doing everything so that then when the player starts combining them in different orders they can meaningfully make
progressions in theme or in story, if they're digging into a particular character or subset of the story, they can meaningfully put these things together.
And as well, like having seen this thing, seeing this other scene, now I put the two things together and I get some kind of greater insight.
So this is just like, it's all just about lots and lots of work and like just going over it again and again and again, iterating these outlines and these story beats.
talk.
Any object that was in the scene would be underlined in the script, and then the code would import the entire script in fountain format, which is like this kind of markup version of screenwriting, and it would extract all of the images, characters, and we had this looping scene from Eyes Wide Shut, and it basically generated the entire game of Immortality based on the screenplay.
So you could drop into a scene and it would just loop Tom Cruise taking his shoes off, and then it would beat out the dialogue, time out the dialogue based on the script, place all the action lines, and every time an object or a character came into the script, they'd get this little box that would appear on the screen.
So I could sit and play the whole game and click on these boxes and imagine
the finished game, right?
And this was never a useful prototype, but none of my prototypes are ever useful to give to normal human beings.
But there's enough there that I can answer questions around pacing, discoverability, feel, flow, and kind of get to the point where we feel good.
And we can also run like algorithmic tests that tell us how interlinked scenes are, how frequently certain things appear, and we can kind of tweak based on that.
So we basically just play this a lot,
We look at all the data we're extracting from the script and use that to balance the script and the format so that then we can go and shoot three entire movies and have a game that works at the end of it.
What next?
This is it.
It's my final slide.
We're slightly over.
Are there any takeaways?
If you want to make immortality, that's how we did it.
But I think genuinely this stuff that we're doing that I think is really interesting, like this idea of randomness and narrative, I think is a really interesting thing to explore.
You know, we're so tied to narratives that are on train tracks and the idea of causality and systems that actually injecting a little bit of spice, I think is really interesting.
Thinking about exploring
narrative content
they will have very different experiences in their heads, but also in what they're doing, what they're clicking on, the flow through the game.
Like it's meaningful to them, it's meaningfully personable and kind of expressive.
And then just fundamentally, if I have one takeaway, it's like this idea of losing the container plot.
People ask me like, how do your games still tell a story that makes sense if it's all out of order?
And it's like, well, plot isn't interesting or relevant.
Like plot is
a requirement of a movie because people are sat in a chair and they need the toilet and they're getting tired and they're looking for 90 minutes or three hours if it's a Marvel movie looking at the screen and so plot is this thing that's like keeps their attention right what happens next what's next what's next what's next
We don't need that because we have all these other things.
We have the challenge and the exploration and the expressivity.
So we have an engaged audience.
So these conventional ideas of plot and how you order and contain things are things that we can kind of move beyond.
That's something I would love to see more of.
Here we go, tail slates.
That's what you do when you have like a messed up shot and you can't actually get the clapperboard in shot to start with because it's all complicated.
So at the very end, camera assistant runs in and says, tail slates, and they have the thing upside down.
And it's really cool.
And it's never not cute to see the camera assistant run in excitedly and call tail slates.
It's the funnest thing.
I guess we can go outside if anyone has any questions.
Thank you for listening and putting up with me.