Okay, good afternoon, everyone. Let's get started. But before we do, and wow, I see a mask over there, too, in the audience.
So a few things. Please turn off your phones. So we're not distracted or interrupted by anyone's phones ringing.
And then we kindly ask you that you fill out a survey that you will get via email
under the email address that you, I think, registered.
And we do kindly ask that you refrain from taking photos of Yoko-san on stage.
You're more than welcome to take photos of the slides today.
And as you can see, we have two speakers and we're covering a lot.
So, the QA session may or may not happen.
It will all depend on how much time we have left, OK?
So, without further ado, I'm going to hand it over to the speakers.
All right.
Thank you.
Hello everyone, those sitting on the side, especially on this side, you might be able to see part of my face, but just pretend that you're not seeing it and that you can only see the mask.
We made a game called Nier Automata, and we'd like to talk about that game today.
In the first half, we'll talk about action, and in the second half, we'll talk about freedom.
So, without further ado, I'm going to hand it over to Taura-san.
Thank you.
Nice to meet you. I'm Takashi Sato, a game designer for PlatinumGames.
Hello, everyone.
My name is Takahisa Taura.
I am a game designer from Platinum Games.
We have been planning for the player character and enemies
with the titles that you can see on the screen.
When we are making a game,
we try to make it a game that you can enjoy
by just pressing a button.
I would like to talk about some of the reasons for this.
So my primary job and role, there are some titles on the slides here, but I'm primarily
responsible for player character and enemy planning and design.
On every game that we make, we strive to make sure that even the just act of pushing a button
is fun.
So I'm going to elaborate on that a little bit more using or talking about NieR Automata
as an example.
I have approached a number of things to make the action fun.
I will talk about three important things.
So we take a number of approaches to making the action fun
from the moment you first touch the game.
Today I'd like to talk about these three key topics in particular.
The first one, although it may seem pretty basic,
is to envision your ideal.
What I mean by that ideal is...
So from the get-go, from the very, very beginning,
you need to firmly decide for yourselves what you want and what you don't want.
It's a given, but the feeling of the game changes depending on the player's preferences and the content of the game.
So maybe it goes without saying, but the impression of a game
varies depending on the player's taste
and on the type of game you're trying to make.
To give an example of what I mean by that is,
if you're making a game like Dark Souls,
then putting in something like Bayonetta-like action
is definitely not going to work.
So what I'm about to talk about doesn't apply to all games.
So with that in mind, what I'm about to talk to you about today
doesn't apply to every single game.
And the second topic is,
are you able to make specific, precise, and sort of accurate criticism
on what needs to be changed?
When you imagine in your head what you want the ideal form to be, and then compare that to what you see on the screen in front of you, if you can't explain what's good and what's bad and point those things out, you're not going to be able to create that ideal.
There are many reasons why you feel good and bad.
And there are all sorts of factors that affect
whether a game feels good or not.
For example, if you increase the quality of the animation itself,
the connection to the animation,
the good things about the input,
and the effect SE, there are many possibilities,
but in any case, everything that appears on the screen
is the cause of it.
The range is quite wide, from the quality of the animations themselves,
to whether they connect each other, and how smoothly they connect each other,
to the responsiveness of the player input, to the visuals and the sound effects.
The list goes on, but every single thing that you see on the screen is a factor.
One of the things that we were particularly focused on in PlatinumGames' NieR Automata
was improving the response to input.
And amongst those, which is a very long list, like I said,
when it came to NieR Automata, we at Platinum Games
were especially concerned about making the response
to the player input feel really good.
And to elaborate a little bit,
if pressing a button doesn't cause an immediate action,
then the player will become frustrated while playing.
And if playing is frustrating,
then it's not going to feel good.
It's pretty simple.
And if playing is frustrating,
then it's not going to feel good.
It's pretty simple.
So if the button response is slow,
it's unlikely that the action will meet our goal of fun
from the moment you first touch it.
We kept that in mind as we created Near Automata.
What kind of approaches did we take to accomplish that?
We make it so that actions such as dodging and jumping, which feel good and are used very frequently during gameplay, can always be executed at any time, no matter what. You push the button and it delivers right away.
In games where dodging is important, like Bayonetta and NieR Automata,
we make sure that there's never a time when you can't dodge or you can't jump
from the very beginning of the work on the player character implementation side.
So in games where dodging is important, like Bayonetta and NieR Automata,
we make sure that there's never a time when you can't dodge or you can't jump
We actually brought a short clip here, so you can take a look at what I mean.
So as you can see here, whether you're standing still, jumping, attacking,
no matter what position you're in, if you press the dodge button, it will happen.
However, in the final game, in the final product,
there are certain situations in which you can't dodge,
such as when you're in the middle of taking a hit.
So what we do is we set a flag
to prevent dodging in those cases
so the dodge button won't respond at that time.
While we were working on the game, we thought that it would be more enjoyable to play without the game balance.
So we tried to make the game more enjoyable.
And there's a good reason for that.
We concluded that from both a visual and game balance perspective,
not being able to dodge in these specific circumstances actually felt better.
And the responsiveness to player input isn't just about how quickly the game reacts to the button press,
but we also placed importance on how quickly that action results in the desired effect.
So if the time between when you press the button and that action, you see the result of the action, またプレイしながらイライラしてしまい、
and this too results in frustration if it takes too long, 気持ちよくないと感じてしまう要因になることが多いです。
and it ends up being a frequent sort of factor in the action not feeling good. これに関してアプローチとして代表的なものが。
So, for a notable example of our approach to this topic, 基本的攻撃判定が出るまでの時間をできるだけ短くするというようなことをしています。
is that we make the time it takes for the basic attack to count as hitting the enemy as short as possible.
YOSHIMASA TANAKA, JAPANESE INTERPRETER
We place importance on both the responsiveness
of the attack button, you press it
and the attack animation immediately starts,
and on the result of the attack,
which happens right away, striking the enemy
without making the player wait.
In Nier Automata, when a player character, 2B,
presses the attack button while he's waiting,
And so in NieR Automata, if you press the attack button
while the player character 2B is not performing other actions,
the attack animation comes out and it happens immediately,
and the hitbox becomes active.
And the time it takes for this to happen
that you see on screen is
In 60 frames, which is approximately 0.16 seconds after pressing the button,
the enemy is hit.
I think this is pretty fast.
It's 10 frames out of 60 frames in one second.
In numbers, that would be approximately 0.16 seconds after pressing the button.
And I think that's pretty fast.
Of course, this doesn't apply to all attacks.
It's only a matter of time before you get a result,
such as a charge-required attack.
This will improve the balance of the game.
But I think it's important to feel good
when you touch a normal attack
and you get a result right away.
Now, of course, this is only an example,
so not all attacks in the game work this way.
But combining this with attacks that require charging
and those that take time to deliver the effect
or the result, the overall balance of the game
improves as it develops.
But with the aim of achieving a game that feels good the moment you first touch it,
we feel it's important that the very first normal, the standard attack that you can unleash
and unleash to respond to will be delivered quickly.
So to sum up the topic of responsiveness...
If you press the button and the action happens as quickly as possible,
you can feel the joy and happiness of the moment you touch it.
So if the game reacts as soon as you press the button,
and the desired result of that action also occurs as quickly as possible,
that leads to the game feeling really fun,
feeling good from the moment you first touch it.
And then, in other areas of the game design process as well, we refine our game's quality little by little through a repeated process of finding, calling out, pointing out, and then correcting parts that don't feel good.
And then the third important topic for creating action that's fun from the moment you first
touch is, again, pretty basic, but iteration over and over.
So fine tuning and adjusting.
And I have a few examples to show what I mean here.
First, there's flags.
Not only does the player characters and enemies have flags,
but every single individual animation in the game
has a set of flags associated with it.
KOSEI TOROIKAWA, JAPANESE INTERPRETER And the content of those flags are things
like what you see listed here, but a total of 64 flags were used.
KOSEI TOROIKAWA, JAPANESE INTERPRETER So here's an example. This is the tool for
setting animation flags.
So you first select a character and can play back the selected animation.
And the timeline appears right above the arrow there.
And you can set the flags from the flag list that you see in the black box onto the timeline.
The flag list itself looks like this.
YUSUKE USTUNOMIYA And I do apologize, we didn't have the resources
to bring an English translated version of this, but you're more than welcome to take
a picture and perhaps do your own translation for yourselves.
今この瞬間だけ写真撮ってOKです。
Yeah, even Yoko-san is saying,
please go ahead and take pictures right now. ただ適当な名前が付けられたりするものもあるので、 今僕が改めて見てもこれなんだろうというような 裏曲があったりするので、 翻訳してもらってもあまり意味ないかもしれません。
But surprisingly, even for me, it's like these names were kind of made up or labeled at that
time what made sense to us.
So now that I look back at all these labels, not every single one makes sense to me quite
well.
And so if you go ahead and translate, I might not even be able to say, you know, what that
meant at that time.
So how do we set these flags on animation?
So for example, we're going to take one that says follow, or that you can follow.
And we'll click on the box there, and then set the time frame to which the flag's effect will apply.
With this tool, we can set the flag to apply the animation starting from a certain frame and ending on a certain frame,
or to have it stay turned on permanently starting from a certain frame.
今設定方法でお伝えしたこの追尾可能というフラグも気持ちいいアクションを作る上で重要なものになるので少しだけ内容を説明させていただきます。 So there's a reason why I picked this flag because I want to use this as an example. It's an important one for making action that feels good and I want to talk a little bit about it. 追尾可能というフラグはその名の通りターゲットを追尾するかしないかを設定するフラグです。
So this one, I know exactly what it means,
and I'm not confused here.
Just like it sounds, it means that I can set the flag
to follow an enemy or a target.
When the enemy is within a certain range,
if this flag is on,
the player character will always be facing the direction of the enemy.
So what it does is, if animation plays with this flag turned on,
and an enemy is present within a certain range,
the player character will turn their body to face the enemy.
And as for how the flag is used,
So by turning it on for just a little bit at the very beginning
of an attack animation, the player character
will always turn to face the enemy when attacking.
In other words, even if you don't aim at the enemy accurately,
just by pressing a button appropriately,
it will be easier to hit the enemy.
This is a flag that improves the comfort of the play.
So in other words, even without perfectly aiming at the enemy,
you can still hit with your attack just by pressing the button.
The flag improves the feel of the gameplay,
and we find it important for achieving our goal of immediate fun.
This is also very important to make the player feel that it's fun to touch.
Yes, very important to achieving that goal
and to have that instant sort of gratification.
If the time the flag is on is too short, it's hard for the enemy to hit you.
And, oh, sorry, and then if, sorry about that,
if the flag on duration is too short,
it's hard to hit the enemy.
If the duration is too long,
it's hard to hit the enemy,
and if the duration is too long,
But on the opposite, if it's too long,
while it does make it easier to hit the enemy,
no matter how they're moving,
it makes your movement look unnatural, a little sluggish,
losing that feel-good feel.
In addition, each animation of the Baudai
does not automatically set the flag
so that the movement and the angle are different.
We find a way to set them up
by hand and set them up.
So this is not a small sort of chunk of work here.
There's a massive volume of animation in the game.
And each individual one has its own movement and length.
So we were unable to automate this whole process
of setting the flags.
I did it all manually, experimenting
to find what settings matched each of the animations.
SPEAKER 1 IN JAPANESE
It does take a very, very long time,
and it depends heavily on the sense of the person performing that work.
In addition to the flags,
the game designer also fine-tunes the animation speed.
Besides the flags and Nier Automata,
We are adjusting the animation by setting the number of frames and the ratio of speed.
So as with the flags, we use a tool function
to set frame count and playback speed
to fine tune the animation.
Even if the animation designer creates a cool animation,
when we actually move it in the game,
we often disagree with the game designer's wish
to make it a little faster or a little slower,
so we adjust it here
after confirming the finished animation.
So no matter how awesome the motion of the animation
designer has created for us, when we actually
see it in motion, we might find that it
needs to be adjusted a little bit,
or feel that the move is powerful,
so it should take longer to come out.
There are all these little fine-tuning adjustments
that we feel is needed.
It's very common for the animation
to not quite line up with my vision, the game designer's
vision.
So after an animation is created, we will go back in and check it and adjust it ourselves.
After we made the adjustments, the animation designer will make the adjustments to the animation.
And once we've made the adjustments on the designer side,
the animation designer will make those, implement it, and to match the speed that we set.
And that cycle just continues to repeat.
INTERPRETER 2 However, by making adjustments myself rather
than issuing or asking them to make these adjustments based on my verbal sort of requests,
the time required for fine tuning is actually shortened and the process is reduced and it's
a lot more effective that way.
So now I'd like to summarize my requests for adjustments.
So to sum up the fine-tuning process,
YUSUKE USTUNOMIYA, SPEAKING JAPANESE
we use our internal software tool to apply flags and speed settings to the animation
to make it feel good to play.
YUSUKE USTUNOMIYA, SPEAKING JAPANESE
and immediately test that within the game itself.
This cycle repeats for eternity.
And we repeat this cycle for what it seems like eternity, like it's not going to ever, ever end.
Even if you set it up once, you may feel that it's not pleasant to touch it after a while.
So we will continue to check it until it's completed.
And it's something that we thought we had gotten right,
may not feel good after some time has passed
or some days have passed.
So this process is truly a repeated cycle
of adjusting and testing nonstop
until the game is really locked and complete.
Speaking Japanese
And as I said earlier, because none of this can be automated,
it's a very tedious, challenging process.
But I share the opinion that whether or not
you can effectively perform this, so not so glamorous,
not so fun task, is what makes the difference on how
you can make the game feel good, resulting in the action
that you want to see in the game.
So to sum up, these are the things we consider very important to achieve our goal of action
that feels good from the moment you first touch it.
With the limited time we have today, I can only go into a very sort of general, broad
overview, but to reiterate.
Create a very clear plan for what feels good.
And precisely identify the good and the bad and perform a very careful fine-tuning cycle.
But it's also important to remember that there's no absolute correct answer to be found in the process of making this game.
And so that's exactly why it's important to have a very clear vision or plan from the very beginning.
That's all I have for today. Thank you for listening.
And that wraps it up for my section of the talk.
I'm going to hand it over to Yoko.
It's harder to talk than you think, so I'll have to sit down and talk.
It's actually not that easy for me to talk in this position, so I'd rather sit down if
that's okay with you guys.
I'll start.
Ms. Squeeny is sitting there,
and she's running out of time, so I'll speak really fast.
So I'm going to start my session now, or part of the session.
The Square Enix staff who's sitting in the front row
have told me that I need to talk at maybe 100 miles per hour to get through it, so here I go.
My name is Yoko Taro, or Taro Yoko, and here are some of the games I've worked on.
And this is the theme for today.
So, what is freedom?
In more detail, I'd like to talk about what freedom is in games,
which I've been thinking about while making the latest NINJA AUTOMATIC.
OK, maybe that's not fair.
So a little bit more about what I'm going to talk about today
is what is freedom as we thought of it
within the context of creating our title, Near Automata?
I'm sorry if I didn't meet your expectations
on how to create a scenario.
But I think I've mentioned it somewhere in the past in GDC,
so please do your best to search for it.
He's talking really fast, as you can tell.
There might be some people today in the audience who
came here expecting to hear about a scenario creation
sort of process.
I apologize that I may disappoint you today.
That said, I've done presentations here at GDC
in the past about that process.
So maybe you could search, look it up on YouTube,
and listen to that subject or topic later.
SPEAKER 1 IN JAPANESE
So I'd like to bring it back to the topic of freedom.
When you say freedom, you probably think of an open world game.
You might call it sandbox or free roaming.
But roughly speaking, you can do a lot of things on a large map.
I'm sure you all know what I'm talking about, but I'll explain it.
So when you think of games that offer a high degree of freedom,
the first thing that usually comes to mind
are open world games.
They can also be called sandbox games or free roaming games.
But to give a rough explanation of what that entails,
it means there's a large map and there's so much stuff to do.
Something like that, probably.
But regardless, I'm sure everyone listening to this
knows that already.
English is much better.
Thank you.
So if we were to look at the structure of NieR and NieR Automata, two games that I worked on,
it wouldn't be technically incorrect to refer to them as open world games.
Speaking in Japanese
So, well, I'm going to be honest here.
If we look at the structure for Nier's game map,
it's something that I basically stole from The Legend of Zelda,
Ocarina of Time.
I just said it.
It's built in the exact same way, with planes in the center
and distinct areas surrounding it.
Even if the size of the planes, it's
to the point where you might think I used a stopwatch
to time it, how long it took to cross the planes in Ocarina
of Time, and copied it down to the second.
Well, I suppose it wouldn't be incorrect to call Ocarina of Time...
an open world as well. But I think it's actually more of a perfectly straight sort of road and path
that you can go back and forth as much as you want. In that sense, and since Nier copied that,
it actually has extremely little freedom when compared to the kinds of open world games that we have now.
Speaking of which, there was a word in Japan recently that was used,
and that was the word, open world zukare.
I think that was a particularly prevalent trend in Western countries
after the release of the first game, Open World.
So a short while back, there was this term that people were discussing.
Even in Japan, it was open-world fatigue.
I think this phenomenon was especially prominent in the West,
where there was a sustained string of major open-world game releases,
one after another.
As a feature of the open-world strategy developed by the pioneer
of GTA, Skyrim, and Just Cause,
as you can see, there are vast maps, a lot of items,
and a lot of quests.
There are also a lot of other crafting and training elements.
There are a lot of games that don't have enough playtime even if you have 100 hours.
So, this genre that was carved out by all these pioneers, it felt so fresh and so new at first,
but as a result of putting out tons of these, one after another...
...those elements were said to be too much and too tiring.
And now people are starting to say that not only are they tired of elements like these,
but there are entirely too many of these elements to begin with.
So then why did this happen?
How do we end up in this very contradictory situation
where people have started to complain about having a high level of freedom,
even though a high level of freedom is supposed to be what they were expecting?
It's because we took the vastness of the map, a lot of items, a lot of quests for granted,
and started to think of them as work.
So I think our conclusion, at least in my opinion, is that because things like enormous maps and lots of items,
tons of things to do, once they became ordinary, people started to think of them as just simple chores.
Being free doesn't mean you feel free.
This is a phenomenon unique to games.
And I think it's fair to say that a state of high level of freedom,
not being directly connected, or does not equate to the actual sensation of feeling free,
and that is very unique to games.
I think the creators really want players to play freely,
so they have prepared a lot of content,
but in the end, for the players,
it feels like a duty to spend all the quests,
or else it will feel like a loss.
So game creators like ourselves, we work and work and prepare an enormous amount,
a number of quests and content because we think that that's what players want to play and freely
sort of play. But the end result of that is that the player feeling like they need to get through
every single quest because they feel like they're going to be missing out on something,
is transformed into kind of an obligation.
So how do we go about fixing this problem that's happening?
I took some hints from other games.
This is the Super Mario screen.
When I was playing the game, I happened to move to the top of the score.
This is the picture on the left.
So we're going to go way back in time here, as you can see.
So Super Mario Brothers is one example.
I was able to move my character all the way up to the top of the map
where the score is positioned, and that's what we see on the left here.
You can move to a different area like the one on the right.
The top of the score is a hidden passage.
And from there, I was able to warp to a different area,
as you see on the right screen.
The very top, the place where the score was,
was actually a hidden passageway.
I was very surprised when I saw this.
Because I learned that a vast world was embedded in this game
by breaking the framework of the world I had been thinking about.
I was absolutely shocked. I was like, what is going on here?
I was seeing that smash the entire idea about how the world was framed
and made me feel as though this game contained an enormous world.
So here's another example, a screenshot from GTA 4.
I was surprised by one thing while playing this game.
The people in the city couldn't talk to the NPCs.
In many Japanese RPGs, NPCs like this are usually able to have conversations,
but I couldn't imagine that a game with a big budget like GTA would miss out on such implementation.
So here's one thing that surprised me when I was playing this game.
You can't actually talk to the NPCs in the city.
NPCs like having dialogue on their own as a matter of course in most JRPGs.
And I can't think that a game with an enormous budget like the GTA series
would have shirked implementing something like that.
But
I had an aha moment, and maybe you guys did too.
If you stop to think about it, it actually does make sense.
Because in the real world, I don't know about you guys,
but I don't think we go around town just talking
to strangers all the time.
So in that sense, since GTA is imitating the real world,
not being able to talk to most NPCs
actually creates that sense of realism.
In the game, even if you could freely soar through the skies,
run out.
500, 600, 700 kilometers per hour, or pass through anything in the world at will,
that's not going to make you feel free.
What we know from Super Mario and Grand Theft Auto is that
being free is the key to feeling free.
So from just these two examples from Super Mario Brothers and GTA,
in order to make someone feel a sense of freedom,
we need a frame that inhibits freedom,
and that is key to making that world happen.
So let's say this is our world,
and you are free to go anywhere within this circle.
So at this point, what's important is not the size of the circle here, but rather the circumference, the circle, the frame, the gray frame that you see around it.
This frame is the limit of what the player thinks the world is. The moment you push the frame of your imagination, you feel free.
So this frame is what the player believes to be what the limit is, or the scope of the world,
and it's this moment that we expand what this frame has been perceived
to be that people feel a sense of freedom.
To perceive what freedom is, it's important to have this moment
when the frame of imagination expands.
So in order to foster this idea of freedom, what's important is the moment when, as you see here,
just two simple sort of circles, that your perceived framework of the world suddenly expands.
When you get in a car that you didn't expect to be able to drive,
or when you get into an object that you didn't expect to be able to break,
you feel the freedom of the player in that moment,
and that part of not expecting it is very important.
So in a game, let's say a player rides a vehicle that they didn't think they could,
or breaks an object that they think they didn't think they could break.
They say, I didn't think I could do that.
And that's what makes them feel the sense of freedom at that moment.
So the most important part here is, oh, I didn't think I could do that, but I could.
So freedom.
is in a future that you did not have in the past.
The reason why it's in bold and it's in large font is because I think that sentence actually sounds really, really cool.
I'm not sure if you can hear me.
But if you read it carefully, it's a sentence with no meaning.
What I want to say is that you can feel freedom when you broaden your awareness of what is free,
not when you are in a materialistic state.
But the more you think about it, it's actually kind of a hard to understand sort of sentence.
So what I'm trying to say here is to make people feel a sense of freedom,
what's important is not volume. Freedom is felt the moment that the perceptions held by the human mind are expanded.
I'm running out of time, but I'll try to speak as fast as I can.
Okay, so I'm going to go even faster because I need to cover a little bit more.
So to speak more on the idea of expanding that perception held in our mind,
I'd like to explain a case from Nier.
As I mentioned earlier, there is a limit to what you can do in the world.
It is important to create the outside of that limit.
So like I said before, the world has a framework that shows that indicates its limits.
What's important is creating what's outside of this world.
But Nier is not a AAA class title, so we can't just cost it to expand the world.
So this is how we came up with the idea.
That said, Nier is not a AAA class project.
We don't have that budget to go left and right and expand the world.
So this is the approach we took.
Went smaller.
YUSUKE USTUNOMIYA I'm thinking.
I went smaller.
So I created an additional framework
inside the limits of the world.
And by doing this, I wanted to have players experience
the moment the world's framework expands.
YUSUKE USTUNOMIYA And to make this happen,
I did a planning that looks like this.
I emphasize the inner framework, not the outer, preventing them from recognizing
that the world that would appear later on. It's necessary to make the player incorrectly
assume that this inner framework is where the edge of the world is.
And I'll use a specific example from the game so that it makes more sense.
So broadly speaking, the original Nier scenario is structured in this manner.
The premise is that Nier is a structure that allows you to collect the same map three times.
This is because we didn't have the budget to make a big map and had to use it three times.
So for starters, Nier is structured such that players will go around the same map three times.
The reason is simple. We did not have the budget to make a large map.
In the scenario, we first show the youth on the same map.
Then we watch the ending A.
So as far as the scenario is laid out, you first present the characters' life as a child,
and then you present them as a youth on the same map.
And when that's done, you watch ending A.
There may be some of you who know this, but the fact that you can play both the boy and the girl on the same map is a copy of the Legend of Zelda and the Ocarina of Time.
And of course, that's also a copy of Ocarina of Time.
After you see the end of the game, you can only play the boy's part again.
But here, you can hear the enemy's voice, which is a new element.
There's a reason why you can attack the enemy you thought was a bad guy.
This is a story that is like a back-end.
If you clear the back-end, you can see the B-end, which is a different ending.
So after watching ending A, it's then possible to replay just a section of the time when the character is older.
But that's when a new element comes into play. Now you can hear the enemies' voices.
There's a reason why you're being attacked by these enemies you had previously thought as very vicious.
It was as though we were telling a story with a flipside to it.
So completing this flipside of the story would then let you see a different ending, which is ending B.
In general, RPGs have one story, so the ending is one too.
In the previous game, Nier, by showing the A-end once,
we made the game end there, as if it was the limit of the world,
and then we showed the back route, so you could feel the world's expansion.
So your typical RPG usually has one route through the entire story
and then put broadly just one ending.
In Nier, by showing players ending A,
you give them a false impression that the game is over.
Or in other words, that they've seen the limits of what the world has to offer.
But then, by presenting them with the flip side through the story,
I was hoping to have them feel as though the world has expanded.
So then with that in mind, how should we go about structuring Nier Automata?
the sequel.
In the development of Automata,
Nier has been recognized as a game with a hidden story.
So, even if we do the same thing, we won't be surprised.
That's why we took the following structure in Automata.
So, by the time we were working on Automata,
there was already, everyone knew that Nier is a game that has these flip sides.
So, I decided to make Automata a game
with a story structured in the following manner.
First, it's the same as using the map three times.
One thing remains unchanged, we're still reusing the map.
Three times.
Unlike the previous game, we're showing the ending as soon as the girl's version is shown.
Next, we're playing the same route as the boy's version.
This is the same structure as the previous game's back route,
and has the ability to show the true form of the world.
However, unlike the first Nier, we presented the arc of the game,
where you play as a girl first and then show ending A right away.
Next, we go through the same route again,
but instead of having you play as a boy,
this serves as the same function as it did in the previous game,
being a flip side that shows the world for what it truly is.
And then we show ending B at the time when the boy's story is over.
And then after ending B, we then show an entirely new chapter that tells a story for leading up to ending C.
And the reason why we did that is...
At the end of B, the player gets the feeling that it's over.
To have, once players have reached ending B, we make them feel as though the game is over.
For the fans of the previous game, there is a perception that there is a hidden route,
so we play while imagining that the game will end on that hidden route.
To break that imagination, by presenting the feeling that there is a further hidden route,
we aim to make them feel the expansion of the new world.
So fans of the Prius game, they know that there's another route to the game.
So they will be playing the game with the assumption that it will end once they have
finished this alternate route.
We counter that assumption by presenting them with an experience where there is still more
waiting for them at the end of the alternate route when that's over, giving them that experience
of a new world opening up.
That was our goal.
I was going to go into another example, but seeing that we're running out of time, I'm going to have to skip that now.
One page, two pages, three pages, four pages.
We don't need to talk, I guess. You guys understand the content of this speech.
Let's move on to the last topic.
Okay, so this is the last topic I definitely wanted to talk about today.
This is the final part of the game.
We have a message of support from the world to players struggling in the final battle.
As you all probably know, this is a screenshot from the game's final section.
Messages of encouragement from across the world
for players who are struggling with the game's final battle.
This message of support can be entered by clearing the last battle.
In other words, it's a loop where the person who was supported
will support the next person.
So, as you know, you can leave these messages of encouragement
once you have finished the game yourself.
This creates a really cool loop where people who were encouraged by others
then go on to encourage others right back.
I've talked about this for a long time,
but I'd like to talk about what I want to tell you today.
Finally, I'm at a point where I can talk about what I've been wanting to talk about all day today.
I know it took a little while.
The truth is, this genius idea is not mine. I stole this one, too.
It's from a campaign called the Coca-Cola Small World Machines.
I mentioned this in my previous GDC talk, but Coca-Cola is a social experiment project
that was conducted in India and Pakistan.
So I don't know if any of you were at my previous GDC session,
but this is a campaign that Coca-Cola deployed between two countries that are on bad terms.
The project is about encouraging people in the bad countries to understand each other.
It's hard to explain, so if you're interested, please look it up on YouTube.
Right. It's a story between how can people still, human beings, still get along
even though they may have disagreements on their situation, the country's situation, and society.
But if I talk about it, it's a little too long, so please look it up on YouTube.
But because it is something that I was very deeply sort of inspired and influenced by.
I was very impressed by the project.
When I look at the real world, it is full of elephants.
People are able to hate each other.
The Coca-Cola project was a very innovative attempt to solve that.
That project left an extremely strong impression on me.
You don't have to look very hard in this today real world sort of society
to see that it's overflowing with hatred.
We are capable of just easily detesting people that we have never met or seen or heard of before.
And so I was really impressed by this project and what it was trying to do.
I saw it and the same way, in NINI and AUTOMATA, the last message,
that is, on this screen,
I wanted to use this final message in Near Automata, the screen you see here,
to communicate something. By having people share messages with people from other countries
that they have not so great relationships with, I wanted them to realize that the person
that they're directing hatred towards is also, just like themselves, a gamer.
So just like what Coca-Cola did, I wanted to use this final message in Near Automata,
the screen you see here, to communicate something. By having people share messages
that they're directing hatred towards is also, just like themselves, a gamer.
But I ended up giving up on that.
And the reason for that is because I felt like if I did that, that would be me imposing my own principles onto others, yourselves.
So I chose a country and a person randomly and displayed the message of support on the screen.
I think that video games should not be the creators' choice, but rather the players' choice.
I honestly don't know what kind of behavior the players will choose.
That is the freedom I see in this video game.
So what we did instead was make it
so that the screen display messages,
from words of encouragement, from people in countries
selected at random.
I believe video games should allow players the freedom
to make their own decisions and not
have the opinions of our creators,
myself, forced upon them.
I don't know what a player will think when they see this
or what you guys all thought when you saw this.
That's exactly the kind of video game freedom
I wanted to make this time.
But, well, if I can say something about my personal feelings,
I was impressed by the Coca-Cola vending machine.
If even a small number of players
could think of the people of a faraway country,
I would be very happy.
I pray for that to happen.
Having said that, if I were to have a personal wish or thought of my own,
just like I was influenced by the Coca-Cola campaign,
I hope that the people who played this game took the time to think about someone they don't know
in a faraway country, even if it's just for a little bit.
That would make me extremely happy, and secretly, that's really what all I hope for.
Thank you for listening, and thank you for coming today.
Thank you.
Thank you. ~~
~~ Normally we would have all you guys come up to the mic and ask some questions. ~~
And we don't have any time, five minutes left.
And there's a Q&A.
We're so selfish, we brought our own Q&A.
So, Tauro-san, what is it like to develop games at Platinum?
Okay, so yeah, now you can see I'm Yoko on the left,
and Tauro-san on the right.
Oh, sorry, yeah, we're standing opposite.
That's not... yeah, during rehearsals, we're standing on the right side.
So, Tauro-san, what is it like to develop games at Platinum?
The goal of everyone at Platinum Games is to actually become a game creator.
I'm sure there's all these different disciplines, art, programming, design and whatnot, and
we have teams of 10, 20, 30 people.
But it's very important to us that we foster an environment
where people aren't required to just stick to what they know
and that they can contribute their ideas and work together.
So, turning the question right back at you, Yoko-san.
It's hard to see you, so a little more.
Platinum is very young and passionate.
I thought it was amazing that young people are showing their creativity
when I thought that there was a Kamiya in Bayonetta.
I think you're a rare development artist in Japan.
I was appalled, you know, a very young and passionate group of people at Platinum Games.
It's a place that, you guys know, Kamiya-san, Kamiya Hideki of Bayonetta series is there.
So I figured it would be kind of a situation where you have one director, one person leading the pack.
But it wasn't really all about that.
There's a lot of young staffers doing a fine job of exhibiting their ideas and creativity, which I thought was amazing.
Not just probably in the West, but even more so in Japan.
That's kind of a rare sort of environment that we see.
So my next question to you, what were you particular about creating near Automata?
I was particular about a lot of things, but I'm going to skip ahead because of time.
Oh, okay. We are very particular about a lot of things, but we're running out of time, so I'm going to skip to the next question.
And throwing the question right back at you, Yoko-san.
So this is a near sequel, but I was really attentive to making sure that the people who were newcomers to the series could still ease in,
and it wasn't intimidating for them to get into the series.
When you talk about a long-standing IP or franchise,
there are so many of those that you feel like you can't get
the full enjoyment, the 100% satisfaction,
if you don't know the previous story
or the previous iterations of the series.
So I wanted to really avoid that,
and instead doing whatever I could to make sure
that you'd be able to enjoy the game equally,
whether you had previous knowledge of the series or not.
So, Tauro-san, what did you struggle with when creating this game?
RPG was a genre I had no experience with as a Platinum Games.
So, as Platinum Games, we have no experience in creating an RPG.
So, I think that was the most challenging for all of us as a team.
And yourself?
So everyone on staff was incredibly talented.
So as a director, I really didn't struggle at all.
But on the flip side, because everyone was so on top of things and so talented,
I was a little embarrassed that me delivering the scenario was delayed.
And, you know, it's a good thing to have talented people and staff around you,
but it's also not the best thing because then my sort of delays and, I guess,
challenges stand out a little bit more.
We still have a lot of Q&A, but we're running out of time,
so I'd like to answer each question one by one.
Taura, please choose one question you'd like to answer.
Which one?
Why did you include auto mode?
You can skip cutscenes, and we felt like, well, if you can skip cutscenes,
then you should be able to skip parts of the game as well.
So, it was pretty simple, but it was also proposed from Yoko-san.
So you are totally welcome if you want to skip the cutscenes and skip the game parts and just go for the trophies.
I'm all okay with that.
So I'm going to pick my last one.
Okay, so I'm going to pick my last one.
Yeah, that one? No?
Is alcohol necessary to write a scenario?
Interestingly, or maybe not so interestingly enough, the stuff that I write while I'm a
little tipsy and drunk is usually a lot more popular.
I think if you think too much and talk too much, it won't work, so I think it's better to drink and be a little stupid.
You know, I've concluded that when I'm like super proper and serious and thinking about work,
it doesn't really come into shape the way that I want it.
So it's alright to have a little bit of alcohol, get a little tipsy,
have a little fun, and make it easier for me to come up with my own ideas and put it in writing.
But if I write while I'm drinking, I end up falling asleep in about an hour.
The only drawback is that when I do that,
the productivity level is really low.
And so because I will pass out easily maybe in an hour.
So did you all have fun today?
Well, I hope you guys enjoyed our talk today.
Thank you.