Hello everybody, my name is Insane, or my internet name is InsaneTheRainMusic, my real
name is Carlos Ini.
I am very excited to be joining you tonight at a weird virtual GDC.
I am a musician on YouTube primarily.
I take video game soundtracks and I arrange them and perform them in the style of my favorite
jazz music.
Not just traditional jazz, stuff like contemporary jazz, fusion jazz, Latin jazz, all these kinds
of things.
And I play a lot of instruments.
One of the benefits of doing a livestream concert from home is that I have, let me see,
one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine different things I can play on with my
immediate disposal.
So without further ado, let's get started.
Oh, press the button.
This transcript was provided by Transcription Outsourcing, LLC.
Oh, this is on. Hello. Hey, everybody.
For just joining us, I'm Insanity Music.
I'm currently performing a song from the video game Deltarune.
The song is called Field of Hopes and Dreams, composed by Toby Fox.
He made the soundtrack for the game Undertale as well.
I love this part.
I can use a key change.
Woo!
Yeah.
Whoo!
There it is.
Woo!
All right, wow.
Uh, that was, as I said, as I said during the song, that was Field of Hopes and Dreams, uh,
from the video game Deltarune, composed by Toby Fox. I arranged that and for, um, the backing
track you heard was all me. I performed that as like a multi-track thing on my YouTube channel,
um, and I arranged it for like a big eight-minute epic arrangement because that song means a lot to
me. Um, one of the reasons I make video game music covers on YouTube is because, you know,
like, as we all know at GDC, game audio is just such a, such an, um,
A huge part of what makes a game great.
And I would love to be able to spread that.
You know, just recognize game music for what it is and the societal impact that it has,
which I think is tremendous.
And I am...
It's...
Coming from the background of a jazz musician, we have a jazz standard songbook that we all
know and learn over time.
And I think that's shifting, or something like a video game music songbook is emerging.
So I'm going to be playing quite a few classics from different games.
I don't think I have the same game that appears in the set twice.
So there's a good bit of variety in here.
This next tune is composed by David Wise, who I have met before.
He's a funny guy.
And this is from, I think it's Donkey Kong Country.
It's either one or two.
I'm not quite sure.
But this is Mining Melancholy, which is a beautiful, beautiful tune.
Here we go.
For more information, go to http://www.brainstorming.world
or go to www.brainstorming.com
Thank you for watching.
when i clicked plz
help
black
yes
NO
DUDE
MAKE A GAME
from Donkey Kong Country 2 or 1, not sure which one.
It's one of the Donkey Kong Country games.
They're both fantastic soundtracks.
So that featured me playing, at the beginning you heard a looping section
featuring the drums and all my percussion instruments.
Then I think I picked up playing piano and also Fender Rhodes using this keyboard.
Also the eewee, which is the electronic wind instrument.
A saxophone solo, and then drums to finish it off.
I really enjoy playing lots of different instruments.
I'm going to introduce one more in the next song, which is my upright bass back here, in a song I haven't performed live before.
This one is from an indie game that I really, really love. Amazing art style and soundtrack.
This is Green Path from the game Hollow Knight, which was composed by Christopher Larkin.
Thank you for watching.
Thank you so much.
Have a great day and have a wonderful day.
We hope you enjoyed reading these transcripts.
We do hope you check out our first two albums of this series.
You can find the links down below in the description.
And, until next time,
stay wild.
It's not.
So
This may not be entirely accurate, though.
Go to PDF content at https://donate.pdf
This transcript was provided by Transcription Outsourcing, LLC.
Whew, that was Greenpath from Hollow Knight.
What a beautiful, beautiful ballad
that I arranged into a jazz arrangement.
That featured, started with bass.
We had some piano.
We had some tenor saxophone.
Great piece of music.
There was also a bass clarinet in the background
of that recording, if you could hear that.
Cool.
This next song, actually, let me, I'm going to wipe this,
grab a little cloth.
Here I have.
Much better. I was feeling easier.
As fun as it is to play all these things myself and set up all this looping,
it is a lot more fun when you have a bunch of other musicians.
And that is such a wonderful experience, to have a bunch of other musicians there,
ready to do your bidding, as I say, as sometimes the crazy arranger that I am.
This next tune is from my favorite video game soundtrack of all time.
I had to put one in there.
I'm currently doing a project around this game,
where I am essentially taking most of the original soundtrack
and arranging it with my jazz vision,
turning it into what I like,
putting the music in the best way I possibly can.
And that soundtrack is Pokémon Diamond and Pearl.
I grew up as a... I remember getting Pokémon Red at like a Goodwill with my mom when I was a kid.
And, um, that music has become so important to me.
So, I only find it... I find it super fitting that I'm, you know, arranging it and performing it.
So this selection is, uh, Eterna Forest, which is one of my favorite songs of gaming in totality.
It's just such an amazing composition.
This was originally composed by Go Ichinose.
Here's Eterna Forest.
We're doing a bit of pressure here.
This transcript was provided by Transcription Outsourcing, LLC.
Oh man, that tune is so wonderful. That was A Turn of Forest from Pokemon David and Pearl, composed by Go Ichinose, arranged by me back in 2016, I think. I'm working on a new version of that right now.
That song was... I love the melody of that song.
So good. I love it.
I love it.
Oh, right. What is that?
We should be good for this.
This next tune is from a Sega franchise.
I know I had to get Sega in there somewhere.
Sonic music. I love Sonic.
I played Sonic Advance as a kid on my Game Boy.
I didn't really quite understand how it worked or how to beat the game, but I knew that it
was fun to play.
And sometimes I think that's forgotten, is that we have all these complex games that
have so many complex mechanics, but they're not fun.
Or they're not like...
There's something to be said about just visceral joy of just moving around the character.
When a game can nail having a character move around and have that be fun in and of itself,
that is something special.
I am presenting Studiopolis Zone from Sonic Mania.
I believe this is composed by T-Lopes. I know he did a lot of arrangements for this soundtrack.
He's a great dude. Happy to be playing his music.
This is Studiopolis Zone.
It's funky.
session.
Here we go.
This transcript was provided by Transcription Outsourcing, LLC.
The game is about to launch.
If you have any questions, please leave a comment.
Studiopolis Zone from Sonic Mania, featuring...
This is... I haven't introduced this instrument yet, I think.
This is the EWI. This is the Electronic Wind Instrument.
What a beautiful... a beautiful instrument it is.
It's so fun. It's like the electric guitar version of the saxophone.
There's so many different sounds I can make, and there's a lot of different...
It's so fun to play. So, I'm glad to be playing it for you tonight.
Oh, what is next on our wonderful list?
I had to move my keyboard off my keyboard, so I'll put my keyboard back on my keyboard.
Ah, yes. So, for this next tune,
um,
I want to do something a little different from the rest of the set.
This song is solo piano, which is completely different.
It is a beautiful song composed by Yasunori Mitsuda
from the video game Xenoblade Chronicles 2, which is one of my favorite games.
I played it last year, favorite games of all time.
It just has such a beautiful soundtrack.
And this is the opening theme from the game or like the title screen
called Where We Used to Be, also known as Elysium in the Blue Sky.
And this is a solo piano piece.
I took I'm also a classical pianist to some degree.
I can play notes on the piano.
So I'm going to tie my shoe.
Then I'm going to play that.
Sometimes you're just bopping, then you lose a shoe. It happens.
Xenoblade! I love Xenoblade. I just finished the first one.
And here is where we used to be from Xenoblade Chronicles 2.
By Yasunori Mitsuda.
Thank you everybody, that was Where We Used To Be from Xenoblade Chronicles 2.
God, such a... that melody of um...
It's one of my favorite melodies in all of video gaming.
Augh!
Woo, boy, it's so good.
Oh yes, because next we have the one non-video game song on the setlist.
This is an original song of mine, titled...
What's it called?
Oh, it's called Forward.
I wrote this after a bad period of my life, and I was at the airport leaving MagFest,
and I was like, huh, this is a good idea for a song.
So, I wrote a song.
It's in the style of a lot of Japanese jazz fusion, which is probably my favorite genre music ever.
So here is...
Forward.
There are various types of lenses, in which the dubbing of the sound styles found in the
game and an interactive orientation to the character of the character by looking at the
sources of the sound.
If you like this video, please subscribe to my channel.
And if you like my video, please like this video.
Thank you for watching it.
And if you like my video, please like it.
That was my original song, Forward, not from a video game, but probably could be in a video
game.
I'd be happy if it was in a video game.
That song was so much fun.
Jumping back and forth between the eewee and the saxophone is, uh...
They have pretty much the same fingering system, so it's easy, but the act of switching them
physically is hard.
Hope you guys enjoyed that.
My last selection is from a game called Animal Crossing, but it's probably not the cute Animal
Crossing type music you're thinking of.
Oh.
Oh, what is this?
Here we go.
Oh, that's it.
That's the first...
I thought...
Oh, wait.
Maybe I should do a...
Oh.
Okay, reverb time. Let me turn that off while I'm talking.
Uh-huh.
Talk off. Okay, great.
So this next tune, I was inspired by this tune by the wonderful dog, K.K. Slider,
who speaks in animalese, which is a wonderful, nuanced language.
I thought I would perform one of his songs. This is K.K. Cruisin'.
In the voice of TK Slater.
WAIT TILL THE TRANSCRIPT IS DONE
색ós Six rays.
dibidibidibidibidibidi
dibidibidibidibidi
omme
kwa
Yeah, there's your leg for you.
Oh yeah, oh.
Oh yeah, oh, oh, oh.
Oh yeah.
Having fun.
We have laugh a lot.
It's just all we can do.
It's fun.
Around when you're having fun, let your head down.
Oh, oh.
Oh, oh, oh, oh.
Oh yeah.
Alright guys, let's try something fun.
I'm gonna sing some lines, and at home,
I encourage you to sing along, call and response style.
Here we go.
Bop, bop, boop, bop.
Bop, bop, bop, bop.
KK messed up there.
So, let's get started.
Oh man.
I wonder if KK could actually sing using this thing.
Huh.
Alright folks, we're nearing the end of our show tonight.
I want to give a big thank you to all of you who tuned in for this precedent-setting, live-streamed GDC event.
Probably wasn't how most of us imagined it, but it means I get to be here playing music for you, which I very much enjoy.
So, thank you very much for the opportunity.
I'll play you guys out with the rest of this K.K. Kruisin arrangement, which is my favorite K.K. songs from Animal Crossing.
Here we go.
Do, do, do, do, do, do, do, do.
Do, do, do, do.
I love it!
Bye everyone!
Thank you so much for listening to me play!