So we all wear a lot of hats, right?
That's a thing that we say.
If you're an independent game developer,
I feel like you're contractually obligated
to say it at least once.
It is a truism in indie games, we have less,
so we need to do more, we wear a lot of hats.
I have worn a lot of hats, and they got heavy,
and they hurt quite a bit.
That's how I like to introduce myself.
My name is John Remedios.
I'm a game designer and developer from Toronto, Canada.
I've been working in video games for just over nine years.
I went independent in 2015 when I found in my studio
Actual Humans.
The first game from Actual Humans
is called Shoot Shoot Megapack.
It is a modular, minimalist party game
about rules, friendship, and shooting.
Like I said, it is the only commercial game
I've released independently, so surprise, surprise,
I goofed up a whole bunch.
It went way over schedule.
It did not hit its sales targets.
It's not on all the platforms it should be.
The name is a bit of a hard sell,
and it doesn't stand out.
However, it did have its fair share of successes.
It's a good animation.
It met its design goals,
like literally every single one that I set out to hit.
I built a number of
professional and personal relationships because of this game, and I think it looks and feels
quite nice.
But most importantly to me, it found its audience.
So these are teens.
In case you are unfamiliar.
When I showed SSMP for the first time publicly in the Megabooth at PAX Prime 2015, before
it was even PAX West, these three fine folks came and played the demo literally every single
day at least once.
And then they did it again when I showed in 2016.
And when the game was in the PAX 10 in 2017,
even though we had already released.
In 2018, I was just at PAX hanging out,
and so we became buds.
When I launched SSMP, they bought the game day one,
put it on a laptop, and brought it to school,
and played it with their friends over lunch.
throughout the school year.
They're all in college now.
I don't know if they're still gonna do this
with their fun college friends.
Hopefully they will, but in my mind,
this is what success looks like.
However, the way I made SMP is not a story of success.
The game was not built sustainably,
and by that I mean the mental and emotional costs
of its development would not have been worth it,
even if it had been some raging commercial success.
Realistically, I could.
make one, maybe two more games the way that I made
Choo Choo Mega Pack, and that is because
I struggle with my mental health.
This is left intentionally blank because I could not find
an image that felt appropriate.
I've struggled with my mental health
for the majority of my life.
I don't always like to admit it or accept it,
but it is something that I know.
It is in my family history.
I grew up in a household where it was prevalent,
to say the least.
It is part of who I am.
I understand this now, and I understood it then.
But when I started making Choo Choo Mega Pack,
I actively ignored it.
So today, I would like to talk to you
about why I ignored it, what that resulted in,
and how I'm trying to move past that.
But before I do that, I do have a couple disclaimers.
Number one, I am not a mental health professional.
I am a goof who makes video games.
I can listen and empathize, or at least.
try as hard as I can to do those things,
but I am not qualified to help anyone,
so please do not take anything I say
as an answer or a solution.
I only have my own experience.
And also, because we're in the failure workshop,
I was a little bit apprehensive about having this talk
as part of the failure workshop
because I wanna make something explicitly clear.
Struggling with your mental health is not a failure.
I am not saying that.
I would never say that.
I think that is gross.
I think that is harmful.
So hopefully.
We are all on the same page about that.
Thank you.
I do have a lot more slides though.
Okay, so let's dig into why.
So I started my first game job in 2009.
I cut my teeth making casual games for a variety of studios across Toronto.
I was launching games on things like
Big Fish and other casual digital download portals,
Facebook and a lot of app store work,
which is not surprising.
And I'm extremely grateful for this chunk of my career.
I learned a lot, helped me pay off my student debt,
which was huge, but that was not why
I got into the industry, right?
Ever since I started making games,
I wanted to do one thing.
I wanted to make games the way I wanted to make them.
I wanted to make them independently.
And the context of 2008, 2009
really only bolstered that desire.
This is definitely not news to most of you, I'm sure,
but in case it is, here's a little quick refresher history lesson.
Things like digital distribution on consoles and early App Store,
Flash game portals being a thing that existed,
and Steam actually developing a user base
created this weird, perfect storm
for a new generation of indie games to reach more people.
And as the audience grew, we developed a narrative.
We celebrated these games for being fresh, personal alternatives
to the increasingly cold, corporate, quote-unquote,
traditional game industry.
And part of that celebration involved highlighting individuals,
often white dudes, as the sole creative forces responsible
for these passion projects.
And for some of us, myself included, this was a nice story to hear.
I really latched onto it.
This isn't surprising.
We have a long history of idolizing lone geniuses, often
White dudes again.
We see it in our fiction, we see it in our businesses,
we see it in our video games.
So when I was lucky enough to start making games
independently, this is really what I was aspiring to,
whether or not I would admit it or not.
But by mythologizing this image of the lone game developer
and holding this ideal above everything else
is what I think is the core.
the core reason, or sorry, the core,
mm-mm, the root cause of making choices
that harmed not only myself, but others,
and this isn't as important as those other two things,
but also the game.
So that's a bit broad.
So let's get out of the heavens
and talk about what that looked like in practice.
So it looked a lot like this.
Unsurprisingly, me wanting to do everything myself
resulted in.
an unwillingness to accept guidance from others,
or the outright refusal of help when it was offered to me.
Which is ridiculous because a thing that I haven't mentioned
is I didn't build SSMP on my own.
I worked with a group of really incredible people
who contributed a great deal to the game.
And I knew this about myself, and I knew this about
the project when I was working on it.
I was technically collaborating, but I didn't ever feel
like I was collaborating with them,
because I was so entrenched in this idea
that it was my project, right?
I was the one working full-time, I was the only one
who could truly, fully understand the vision
for my triangle game.
And so over the course of development,
I went out of my way to reinforce this idea.
I isolated myself, I didn't leave my apartment
for long stretches of time.
I would organize the occasional workday here and there, but nothing really stuck.
It was hard to justify to myself.
I should be able to do this.
I should be able to work from home.
I also withdrew virtually.
I would quietly just work on things without telling anyone what I was doing or why it
needed to get done, and then I would pop up and say, hey, here's all this stuff I've done,
barfing out way more information than anyone needed, wanted, or could reasonably understand,
which only made me feel...
Like I could not be understood even more.
But this isolating behavior extended past just my interactions, or more specifically
my lack of interactions with other people.
It seeped into my process.
I became disdainful of production methods.
It felt like a waste of time.
I was making the game.
I knew what I needed to do.
I shouldn't need some arbitrary scheduler calendar to help me reach my goals.
It was a lie.
Obviously this is a ridiculous way to think about building video games.
but is what I expected from myself.
But it wasn't real, because in reality,
the combination of these behaviors left me feeling alone,
with no sense of direction, and I was ashamed,
which made me withdraw even more,
which made that feeling stronger,
until I didn't know where I was or what I was trying to do.
So this was a cycle of shame and depression
with moments of hyper-productivity that
started really early on in development,
way earlier than, as I was reflecting on it,
than I actually realized.
And it continued throughout the development of the game
and well past its launch.
Some of the cycles were fairly short.
They only lasted about a few days,
and some of them went much longer than that.
At its worst, I was not eating, or bathing,
or brushing my teeth, or shaving.
Some days, just getting from my bed to the couch was a good day.
I'd seen this in myself before, right?
I knew what this was.
But I thought, this should be different, right?
I should be different because I am doing the thing that I wanted to do.
I am doing the thing that I love.
And the fact that it wasn't loving me back made me feel weak,
and it made me feel lazy, and it made me feel worthless.
And I'm not saying that there's anything wrong
with aspiring to become something.
But when you're too focused on the things that you lack,
on the things that you are not,
it becomes really easy to lose track of everything else.
And that's what happened to me.
And yeah, I shipped the game, sure.
But what about the next one?
Or the one after that, or the one after that?
Like, how many times do I have to go through this
before I can't do it anymore,
before it severely hurts me?
I don't know.
And I don't really want to find out.
Which brings us to how I'm trying to move past this.
I am trying to improve my process and my relationship with my work into something that is a little
bit healthier.
This is not all-encompassing.
This is a very small slice of the things that I'm doing.
Obviously this takes place within a much broader treatment plan for myself.
Like I said, I'm not trying to give anyone advice,
and I wanted to keep this fairly work-centric,
so just please keep that in mind.
So I've tried making a habit of asking for
and accepting help from others.
It's not something that comes naturally to me,
but building it into my life
is something that I found quite beneficial.
For example, I help organize just a small,
peer group of game developers.
It's not mental health-focused, but we just get together,
and we talk about stuff, both good and bad.
And the point of it is, we're just trying to make space
for one another, trying to make time for each other.
I'm really just trying to say these things out loud.
I've also been really conscious of my physical environment
and its impact on me.
Keeping in line with asking others for help,
I reached out to an old boss of mine
who offered me a desk at a studio
and I go there a few days a week,
which is great if I need just a change of environment
or to be around other human beings.
I also brought on collaborators for my next project
extremely early because I do not want it to be mine,
I want it to be ours.
I'm still guiding the project,
but the process is a lot more conversational.
We give each other feedback constantly,
and who has final say is really dependent on the context.
Obviously, it's way too early to say whether or not
this is successful or will be successful,
but I already think that the game is,
at least the process is markedly better for it.
And finally, I've been trying to mend my relationship
with production methodologies.
I have found something that is manageable,
relatively lightweight, and works for me.
It's beyond the scope of this talk,
but I'm hopefully gonna write something about that soon.
The thing that's really important to keep in mind
if you are someone who is resentful of production,
like, I don't know that it's that uncommon
for smaller indies, is that it doesn't necessarily need
to just be a thing that you're using to...
make the game. It helps cut out ambiguity and anxiety and just give you a clearer picture
when you're in the middle of development and who knows how you're ever going to make this
goddamn thing. But I will say one of the things that my personal methodology does not have
is Gantt charts, because they're the bad thing. They suck.
So yeah, that's where I'm at today.
I'm still working at it, I am chipping away at ideals
that are doing me way more harm than good.
I'm a work in progress, right?
I'm not better, I don't know what that means.
This is something that I'm likely gonna have to deal with
for my entire life, and that is okay.
I don't have any answers about how to live like that,
but in my experience, regardless of whether or not
you're struggling with your mental health,
it's always worth reflecting on.
the things that you want, the things that you purport to want,
and seeing if it lines up with what you actually need.
Because sometimes it doesn't.
It didn't for me.
And I'm saying that because I do not think
that I am particularly unique.
I have...
I guess that doesn't really match the tone, huh?
I have no doubt in my mind that there are other people
either in this room or at this conference.
in this industry that have gone through, are going through,
or will go through something similar to what I described.
Not the same, but it doesn't really matter.
And if you are one of those people,
I just wanted to say that I hope you feel seen.
You are why I wanted to give this talk.
I don't think the world needs more games
about triangles and shooting,
but I do think the industry needs your voices
and your perspectives.
And the thought of us not being able to hear them
because you are trying to wear too many hats
or you're trying to shove yourself into one
that doesn't fit properly,
I think that's heartbreaking.
So I hope something I've said resonated with some of you
in some way.
But please do not listen to me for most things.
Here are some resources.
It's very GDC-centric again.
Both Checkpoint and Take This have
aggregated a lot of really great information
for people who are either struggling with mental health
or know other people who are struggling
with their mental health.
Also, there is an IGDA-led roundtable on Thursday
at 2 p.m. in the South Hall,
if that is something you feel comfortable going to.
I went to one last year and it was extremely cathartic.
It was hard, but I enjoyed it.
Enjoy is not the right word.
But that's not for everybody.
Yeah, so that's it.
Thank you so much for your time.
Thanks.
There's my contact information if you want.
Bye.
My name is Juan.
I'm 26 years old and I'm the co-founder,
creative director and business person
at a small indie studio based in Spain.
It's called Team Gotham.
First of all, I want to say thank you for having me here.
It's pretty much an honor for me.
And second, I want to apologize if I made mistakes
during my talk.
English is not my first language,
so I know I made mistakes.
So yeah, apologize for that.
This talk is going to be at postmortem
not only on our previous last game release,
but on the whole history of our company, Team Gotham.
And it's going to be a story about making loads of mistakes that led us to make desperate
decisions that led us to loads of anxiety and sleepless nights in the past few months.
As this is pretty raw, still is pretty recent, I expect this talk, like me being here, to
be kind of therapy to get some closure about all this.
recent events and also help, of course, others that may be in a similar situation, hopefully.
So the story begins when we founded the studio, Team Gotham, back in 2013.
We were starting at university and we were making mobile games, prototypes, and we quickly
jumped into PC development with a game called The Guest.
which is a first-person exploration game,
a really humble, classic thing,
somewhere between Gone Home and The Room,
if you may.
And yeah, so did we know what we were doing back then?
Kind of yes, because we knew how to do 3D modeling,
we knew how to do programming,
we knew basics on design,
so development was covered,
but hell no, like when we finished college,
We didn't know anything about the industry.
We didn't know how to get the game noticed,
and we were trying everything to make that happen.
We were trying to send out press releases,
going to events, pitch to publishers,
all those things that weren't working at all.
So we got into this sense of desperation,
and we collapsed.
So we say, oh hey, a publisher might help us, right?
people say a publisher can help, so that may be a good idea.
After all this process of desperation where we collapsed,
we traveled to many events back in Europe,
and we landed a publisher in a moment of huge desperation.
It was like the last resource we had.
Because we didn't have real resources.
We didn't have any money or savings.
We were just students.
So landing a publisher in this situation was a good thing and a bad thing.
So being desperate is the feeling of showing a hopeless sense that a situation is so bad that it's impossible to deal with.
And also a feeling of great need or desire for something.
I would say that we had...
mixed feeling between these two definitions of the word.
And yeah, this whole situation led us to this desperate decision number one,
which was signing a good deal in short term with this publisher,
but it was bad in the long run for us.
So again, we had no resources, we had nothing was working,
everything we were trying, and we were collapsed.
at that time, so when we were negotiating with this publisher,
we did a lot of things wrong.
We budgeted wrong, and we rejected
to have any revenue share in the short term, which
means they had 100% recoup policy, which
means publishers have to recoup the investment.
and only then you will see some profit of it.
It was good in the short term because it was going to allow us
to do things immediately and build a studio properly,
hire some people, stuff like that.
But this feeling of being anxious about getting money,
it wasn't greed, I would say, but we were students
and we wanted to build a thing properly.
So this anxious feeling...
didn't allow us to sit back and relax and take a lot of things
and ask people that were more experienced than us
and just stop thinking.
So we were anxious.
We ran into the deal, and we signed the deal.
So three years from that, from releasing the game
and 25,000 copies after launch, we've
seen no money from this game yet.
And it's not expecting to change any time soon.
I mean, it's not like the game.
is a hit and will be rich or something,
but paying bills is also nice.
But yeah, that's how we feel now,
but back then was like, hey, who cares?
Like a game didn't work out that well,
but we have plenty of money in the bank,
let's make a new game, whatever.
So we wanted to overlap the ending
of the production of The Guest with the...
with a new game, with a new pre-production of the game.
And we asked ourselves, like,
shouldn't we take a break before that?
I mean, we've been making this game for two years,
and it should be nice to have a break
and just stay away from things for some time.
But at that time, money blinded us badly,
and we were basically slaves of this money.
We were thinking time equals money.
and vacation equals nonsense, which is absolutely wrong.
And that had really bad consequences after that.
But we didn't allow ourselves to stop at this point
because money was running out.
So we started the production of our last game,
it's called Solo, which is an introspective puzzle
adventure about love relationships
and how love affects our everyday life.
And.
What happened six months into development?
We spent $45,000 into a vertical slice,
which was kind of like the half of the budget we have.
And the game was absolute shit.
Game was boring.
It's like doing homework.
So wow, why did this happen?
Because communication was inexistent.
It was really poor.
We were burned out. We never stopped to, as I say, sit back and think about things.
We were continuously doing things with this anxious feeling of money's running out, money's running out.
We have to do stuff.
So yeah, I remember one day I came to the studio and I asked people like,
how do you feel about the game? And no one was happy about it.
but we never talked about it before.
So yeah, it was too late.
We needed to shift directions now.
New design, a new business plan, but money was running out,
for real.
We spent half of what we had.
There was no time at all.
And we already pitched publishers,
and they, of course, rejected that.
trash game we had. So this situation again, this action, anxious, sorry, situation of
desperation of collapsing again, led us to the desperate decision number two, which was
making a crowdfunding campaign. We were super scared about a crowdfunding campaign, but
we had no other option to get money as AIP.
So we approached FIG, which is a crowdfunding, crowdinvestment platform,
and they shared the vision of the game.
We were excited about it, so that was great.
But we were still really, really afraid of doing a crowdfunding campaign,
so we budgeted the campaign way below what we needed,
because we were scared about not getting to the goal.
That would let us almost no money left for marketing and PR actions.
One thing also is that during the campaign, in the middle of it, we got stuck.
Like, money was not rising and the goal was approaching.
So Fick came out with a kind of a solution.
He bring an investor, and guess what?
Investor wanted 100% recoup policy again.
So, one year after launch, again.
We have seen no money from game sales,
and it's not expected to change anytime soon.
It's important to understand that we took these decisions
thinking that we're the best for the studio at that time,
and that was the only options we had all the time.
And well, it's not only that.
It's not only about these deals, but it's also the gap.
You never.
You know the industry's bad.
It's really hard to get your game on Steam, blah, blah, blah.
But you never expect your game to be that bad.
Press is talking great about your game,
but no one's buying it.
So that's also something that emotionally, it's on you.
So the thing is, the abusive 100% recoup deals
killed us in some way, and maybe killing
other people, all the studios.
We have no money in the bank left in the company account,
so all the expenses are out of our pockets,
like being here or going there.
And the games we made wasn't huge hits,
but still we'll be paying some bills, which is nice.
I often ask myself if we would be at the same point
if that first desperate deal hadn't been that desperate.
And honestly, I think yes, because this talk is not a rant on publishers or 100% recruit
deals, which I think they suck.
It's more a rant on us, talking out loud about all the stuff we made wrong, which is a bunch.
Like I said, we budget things wrong, we scope things wrong, we didn't communicate, which
is the most important thing that we...
we didn't do, I think a good producer is not only the one who is delivering the game on time,
it's also the one who has like a human approach to the people,
and a sensitive approach to the people who's working with,
and before asking how's work, asking how do you feel, how's life, are you okay, all that things.
And that's the lesson I learned and I'm trying to apply.
in my everyday life, not only in games,
but with friends and family.
So I think no, life would be the same,
because also we were making games
that maybe no one wanted to buy.
So it's good acknowledging that the desperate deals
are only like the turning points of the story,
but our mistakes is what led us to those points.
So right now,
We have made no money from game sales since 2013.
We have made huge mistakes out of huge desperation
that led us to sign bad deals for us.
We lost one partner and one employee in the last year.
Now I doubt constantly of my capacities
to be even talking here at GDC.
I've been like unhappy, suffering anxiety,
uncomfortable with myself since Solo came out last year.
I don't play games anymore.
I actually hate games right now.
I'm struggling with game dev a lot.
I'm trying to park game dev for a while in my life.
And we're trying to keep Team Gotham afloat, the company.
But I'm not really sure if it's even worth it anymore.
So I'm not sure if I'm surviving failure,
but I hope this talk might help you guys
if anyone is in a similar situation.
I hope not, but I really hope it helps.
So yeah, I love you and thank you.
My name is Charlie Price.
I'm the co-founder and creative director of Hidden Variable.
We're a small.
Independent studio based down in Los Angeles when we were first founded in 2010
We mostly made mobile puzzle games like baguette and tic tactics
We worked with servo on threes to bring to Android and Xbox among other things
But more recently we're most well known for the game skull girls mobile
trailer here
For those who aren't aware, the original Skullgirls game
was developed by Lab Zero.
It's a 2D hand-animated fighting game
that was released back in 2012.
We approached them about going through and bringing
Skullgirls to mobile.
And part of our goal there was to go through and make
fighting games more accessible for folks that otherwise find
them intimidating, but without compromising their depth
and a lot of the creativity that you ultimately
have when you're playing fighting games at a high level.
So as a result, while we were able to take over
a lot of the animations that they had already
built, these beautiful animations.
And some of the combat mechanics we had to make a lot of adjustments to go through and map it over to mobile native controls
So mostly taps and swipes no virtual thumb sticks or anything like that
In addition to all that stuff the mobile game unlike the console game was a free-to-play RPG
So there was a whole host of additional systems. We had to go through and build
progression systems, skill trees, signature abilities,
social features like chat, live events like daily events,
and prize fights and rift battles,
and all the bells and whistles you would normally expect
from a free to play game.
And it's a pretty ambitious thing for a small team,
and I'm incredibly proud of all the stuff
that we were able to accomplish.
However, this talk is not about all the things
that we're proud of.
Instead, this talk's about the time that we accidentally
went and deleted all of our users' data.
So, a brief history of how we got there.
So actually, Skullgirls started back in 2014 at GDC.
We decided to sign up with Autumn Games to go through and make this happen.
A year later we were approached by Line, who were interested in going through and publishing
the game, particularly to distribute it in Korea and Japan, which sounded awesome to
us because those are really notoriously difficult territories to crack.
And, you know, again, fast forwarding,
spring 2017, we were able to go through
and launch the game under the Lion label
in the US and mostly worldwide,
except for a planned launch in Korea and Japan
a little bit later on in the year.
When we launched, everything was going really well.
The game was really well received, good reviews.
We were getting a lot of organic downloads, which is awesome.
But there were some challenges.
Line was going through a little bit of corporate drama at the time.
They'd recently gone through and acquired a new game studio, and as a result they were
reshuffling some stuff, and so a lot of things were frozen, which included our marketing
budget.
So while we were getting good organic users, we knew we needed to be kind of figuring out
what our user acquisition plan was going to be in order to make sure that we were sustainable
moving forward.
So while we were hopeful that that would resolve itself, it became pretty evident that it wasn't.
So we made the tough decision to part ways with Line forever.
So that came with its own set of challenges across the board.
First off was a technical challenge.
We had basically originally planned to go through and like kind of pluck a back end off the shelf
and be able to use a lot of existing features.
But when we partnered with Line, they basically required us to build something from the ground up
to all of their exacting requirements.
And now that we were migrating, we had to somehow untangle all of that stuff
and migrate it over to AWS so that we could go through and manage it ourselves.
We were fortunate that we were able to find an expert back-end partner who knew all these things backwards and forwards
so we could kind of learn on the go with them and then we could focus on the client-side stuff.
The client-side stuff had its own challenges. In an ideal world, Line would just transfer the game over to us and players,
you know, one day the publisher would change from one company to another and players wouldn't be the wiser, they'd just be able to carry on.
Line was not comfortable doing that for data privacy reasons,
nor were they comfortable just transferring all of the user data over to us behind the scenes.
So instead, what we had to do was let them opt in,
which basically meant that, imagine logging into a game and saying,
hey, by the way, this game's going to shut down in two months,
but it's not going to go away. There's going to be a new game.
All we need is for you to put in your email address and your password,
and then later when this game shuts down,
in the new game you can log in with this stuff and everything's going to be fine.
So we did everything we could to try and make that a palatable thing.
We incentivized it, gave people rewards.
But when it was all said and done, when we finally did the migration, we went from 500,000
total users that we had before down to 50,000.
So that was a pretty big hit, but they were our most engaged users, we told ourselves.
So that's great.
And it's time to move on.
Time to move forward.
It's a new beginning.
We're going to be fine.
It's going to be fine.
So in January of 2018, right after we did this migration,
things were looking pretty good.
We had gone through and relaunched successfully,
the migration, which is complicated,
had turned out, it went okay.
We were doing some proper user acquisition,
we'd been saving up our marketing dollars,
and we invested and we were able to get
almost 200,000 users in our first month, which is awesome.
And our back-end partner was handling
all the different ups and downs that come
with running a live game, so that was really good.
And then we heard word through the grapevine
that we might have an app store feature that was coming up.
And so we're like, thank god, this is perfect.
So what we did, just to be safe, we
decided to go through and double our server bandwidth,
just to make sure that we could handle
the hopeful influx of all these new users
we're going to be dealing with.
So in general, things are going really, really well.
So 0800 Friday, February 2nd, 2018, mere days before this purported feature, I get a phone
call from one of our engineers who regretfully informs me that our back-end partner, instead
of provisioning a new shard, accidentally reprovisioned our live shard, effectively
reformatting it and wiping all of our user data.
So I took a moment.
And I said, okay, we're going to be down for a bit.
That's awful.
Oh!
What about the backups?
How long will it take for us to go through and restore from our backups?
And that was the kicker.
There were no backups.
Our partner had said they were doing backups, but we had never bothered to check.
And so as a result, we were left with no data at all.
It was a pretty rough day, as you might imagine.
We'd been through so much getting to this point.
We, you know, not only building the game, which seemingly was like a great game and
people dug it, and then we had to migrate and then we just rebuilt it and we're right
on the cusp of this great new moment for us and somehow we just torpedoed ourselves.
So you know, it's pretty disheartening for the team as a whole.
And there was a very real temptation for us to want to go through and basically absolve
ourselves of blame.
After all, we weren't the ones that pushed the button or pulled the plug or whatever
metaphor you want to use.
However, it was really important for us to go through and reflect on the fact that ultimately,
even though they're our partner, they're our responsibility.
This game is our responsibility.
We are responsible to our players, are responsible to our customers, to go through and maintain
the sanctity of their data.
I know a lot of these things can feel like an act of God in the moment, but reflecting
on it, there are always opportunities.
Maybe we couldn't have prevented the action itself, but there's definitely things we could
have done in order to go through and prevent the consequences from being as dire.
It was our responsibility to go through and make it right.
Assessing the damage.
So there was some good news.
We still had that 50,000 users worth of data.
It's a month old, but some data's better than no data, so that's something.
And then we had this activity log, which was basically a separate server, thank God, that
was used to track any time someone opened a mystery box or a character leveled up, major
progression events.
And we realized we could run a script on that server in order to basically go through and
roughly reconstruct most of the data for our players.
So it seemed like maybe this is all going to be okay.
We're just going to get through it.
It'll be great.
But there was some bad news.
Unfortunately, because it was from the activity log, we had zero authentication data.
So basically, we could reassemble 200,000 accounts, but we had no idea who it belonged
to.
So...
The only way we could ultimately remap it would be to do it manually.
And as you can imagine, that would be a pretty time-consuming process.
So in the meantime, we'd been down for three to four days.
All of our KPIs obviously had tanked.
We'd been kind of keeping people abreast, but being a little cagey just as we were figuring
out what actually happened and what our options were and what was going on.
But it was time for us to go through and deliver the news.
So I wrote this long forum post explaining everything.
And I won't go through the whole thing, but the main tenets were we wanted to take responsibility
for what happened.
let them know what was going on, give them kind of the full story of how we got to this point,
and reassure them that we were going to do everything in our power to go through and regain their trust,
and obviously apologizing profusely. That's kind of a given throughout this entire thing.
So we basically presented them with two options.
So one, we could go through and manually restore your data.
As I mentioned before, this is a pretty trying proposition.
It's kind of like looking for a needle in a haystack.
We could get clues from players like their account name, the last few things that they did, the state of their collection.
There's a number of clues that we could maybe triangulate and try and figure out who it was,
but we didn't want to give someone access to someone else's account in case they came and asked for it later.
So it was kind of a tricky proposition.
We also encountered a strange phenomenon where we'd find someone we're 100% confident this is that person,
and they'd say, oh actually, I'm pretty sure I had two or three gold characters that just don't happen to be part of my collection.
Which is really strange, we have no idea why that would be the case given everything else
as well.
Never the common characters, only the rare characters.
So I'll talk a little later about how we handled that.
But needless to say, this is a very time-consuming exercise.
So we presented an alternative option, which is basically a free starting over gift.
Why would you want your old data when you can get even better new data?
So basically, for 72 hours after we came back up, we basically had this bundle waiting for
people in their mailbox after they finished the tutorial, which would be any new players
or anybody who lost their data before.
And basically the idea was a lot of these players have been playing for a month and
change.
worth about $400 in in-game contents.
That was way more valuable than most people's progression
up until that point, unless they were super hardcore.
Because we knew we couldn't go through
and handle 200,000 users worth of data.
Hopefully a bunch of people would just go through
and take it and run.
The idea here is that we were comfortable
sacrificing revenue for retention.
We wanted to make sure that at least players
would stick around and maybe one day
they'll trust us enough again to spend money in our game.
So during this period, right after I made that post,
we almost overnight, we had over 2,000 requests that came in.
Normally we have one person that does customer service part time,
but this go around, everybody stopped what they were doing in the company,
across multiple projects, disciplines, everybody was doing customer service.
You're an artist, an engineer, producer, it doesn't matter.
You're either in Freshdesk talking to high-rate customers.
or you were going through and trying to find their data in the database.
And in a strange way, this was actually like a great bonding experience for us as a group.
Obviously, we just suffered this shared trauma, which brought us together in a strange way.
But for the first time, you know, we're an ambitious studio working on multiple things.
this was actually the first time that literally every single person at the studio was doing the exact same thing.
Being able to go through and see customers that were very upset,
and then hopefully by the end of the process, ultimately be satisfied.
When it was all said and done, we manually resolved over 3,500 requests from people,
which is good, that means a lot of people took the free bundle instead of going through and reaching out to us.
But ultimately, even though we tried to front-load it, it took us months to fully work through all of these requests.
So despite all of this stuff, there were still people who weren't happy.
You can't please everyone.
So lots of colorful comments on the forums and in mails and in reviews and whatnot.
And frankly, they had every right to be upset.
We kind of broke the fundamental covenant of we will take care of your data.
So while we were doing everything in our power to try and help folks, you can't make everybody
happy.
Thankfully, there were a lot of people that saw things another way.
The way we were handling it, the way that we were...
doing kind of one-on-one support for every single person, that we were very communicative.
People seemed to be very appreciative of that approach, and frankly, we had a very strong
relationship with our community beforehand, which I think helped set the table to make
sure that we would get the benefit of the doubt when some of this stuff ultimately happened.
So in terms of consequences...
As I mentioned before, all of our KPIs dropped to nothing.
We had no idea what to expect when the game went live again.
We were presuming that our revenue was going to go through and take a big hit.
Maybe some people would eventually go through and come back, but again, we didn't really
know what to expect.
Thankfully, when we relaunched, everything bounced back a lot better than we expected.
So we took a little bit of a hit, but when we did our next content update at the end
of the month...
Our numbers spiked again, like they always do with the content update, and we were able
to more or less, obviously we still had a lot of work to do behind the scenes to make
sure everyone was satisfied, but we were able to keep sailing.
It didn't sink us.
In addition, we migrated over from the back-end partner that will not be named to Mission,
who is an amazing back-end partner that we've been working with now.
I highly recommend it if you're looking for a game as a service.
They never delete your data.
So if you ever find yourself in a similar situation, I hope to God that you don't, here
are some general takeaways.
that you can bear in mind if and when that happens.
So first and foremost is obviously taking responsibility.
I did not mention the name of the other company that we worked with because ultimately it
was our responsibility to deal with this.
It was our responsibility to test their work.
Our customers don't care who ultimately did the actual action.
It's on us as developers to maintain the sanctity of our environment and their data and everything
else as well.
But it's also important to make sure that you keep your chin up.
Obviously, if you ever find yourself in a situation remotely close to this, it can be
pretty dark times.
It's easy to succumb to despair, to feel like you're a terrible person or a terrible game
developer, and really, at the end of the day, shit happens.
You're not going to be able to move forward if you're dwelling in the past.
So, you know, just try and be open and authentic and genuine with your fans and
hopefully they'll give you another shot at it moving forward.
I mentioned before that people would make some pretty strange requests of us that really
had no foundation in fact.
However, when push came to shove, people asked for those gold characters, we just gave it
to them.
This was for a number of reasons.
One, it was the fastest way to deal with the situation.
As I mentioned, we had thousands of requests that were coming in, and the longer it took
for us to go through and respond to one user and satisfy their needs, there were dozens
of other users that were still waiting for a response.
We needed to move through it quickly.
It was also because we trusted them, even if we didn't always trust them.
But they deserved it in part because we owed it to them.
We're the ones that have made the mistake.
We need to give them the benefit of the doubt.
And frankly, anything we do to go through and make them happy,
the better off we'll ultimately be.
A lot of this aligns with some of the exploitable customer service policies
with companies like Costco and Nordstrom, famously,
that we try to go through and adopt as well as part of this.
And even if you just look at it from a purely pragmatic perspective,
while it may seem like players are exploiting you for free stuff,
another way to look at it is this is a very low-cost investment
in retention of our highest-value users.
If they're going to be happy and they're going to go through and stick around,
Giving them a few free things that they clearly covet early on really isn't going to move
the needle that much in the long term.
It's much more valuable to have these people stick around for the long haul.
I mentioned that we have a really strong relationship with our community.
My in-game handle is MightyZug, and whenever I start typing Discord, someone invariably
posts this image.
We're always doing little AMAs and whatnot with our fans and the forums.
on Discord, in our in-game chat.
And so we're also, we all actively play the game.
We don't play the game with like God-level accounts.
Some of us are high-level, some of us are mid-level.
But as a result, people see us in prizefights and other in-game events.
And as a result, you know, the community really knows who we are as people.
They see us as accessible and relatable,
as opposed to just representatives of a faceless entity,
which I think really helped.
We're also very transparent about our gameplay and business decisions.
Whenever we need to go through and make changes, we always...
post our rationale on the forum if we need to go through
and change the way we're distributing content
in order to increase revenue
so we can reinvest it in the game.
We tell them, hey, we're doing this
so we can increase revenue so we can reinvest it in the game.
And generally, our fans are very receptive to that.
We also respond to every single user review
that we get, good or bad.
It's important to remember that your community
is not just your most hardcore players
that are in your Discord.
They're anyone who's ultimately reaching out to you
and your review board is a public-facing forum
where people can see who you are
and how you engage with your fans.
Last but not least.
Being open, honest and empathetic beyond just regular updates with folks, as I mentioned
before, when you have people reaching out to you with extremely irate, profanity laden
emails, it's important to remember that empathy begets empathy.
This is an example of some of the language that we would go through news when talking
with folks.
We understand that you're upset.
We would be too, putting ourselves in their shoes and showing that we're real people on
the other end.
And you'd be surprised at how many people that started with just completely dark, utter
vitriol by the time the entire process was over, they were apologizing for their past
behavior in the first email, even though they had every right to be upset.
Obviously, building your faction with your community in advance really goes a long way
before the crisis occurs to make sure that you can ultimately weather the storm.
So in conclusion, if you ever want to bring your team together and galvanize the support
of your player base, simply delete everybody's data.
It works every time.
Thank you.
Cool, so I think this is the time where I remind everyone
to go through and make sure that you fill out your surveys.
But I guess we're going to do Q&A. So either we'll
all come up here.
You guys are welcome to approach the various mics.
And either we'll approach the podium
or these mics will turn on.
Or we'll figure it out.
It'll be great.
Just make sure when you ask your question,
say the name of whomever it is you're asking it to,
John, Juan, and Charlie.
if anyone approaches the mic.
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Let me guess if there's not a...
Yeah, exactly.
Cool.
Hey, John.
Go for it.
I got a question for you, John.
For me?
Yeah.
So my name's Jack.
I'm not actually in the game industry,
just a third-party guy here.
Okay.
As somebody that's usually blind
to some of the things you described today,
what's advice you could give somebody like me
in the crowd to help somebody like that?
Hmm.
I feel like that is a good question.
Thank you.
So for anyone who didn't hear, for those
for people who do not, who are somewhat blind to mental health
issues, or I think this is probably even more broadly
applicable to just issues that you may not see,
what advice do I have to be understanding and comforting
for those people?
Yeah, I think that.
from my perspective, really has to do with the environment that you're cultivating, right?
And the things that you are asking, I mean, it depends on the relationship, right?
Like an employer to employee relationship is slightly different than an employee to
employee relationship, or I don't know, just people within the same industry.
Listening for people who are willing to talk about it is an extremely important thing,
and listening in a way that is not necessarily.
like you trying to give a solution to someone else
or you trying to, I don't know, help them in some way.
Sometimes you just need to sit back
and hear the things that people want you to say
or people want to say to you.
And I think just doing a little bit of research also,
like those resources that I pointed to are not,
there's way more, the internet is a good place.
Be careful, like vet your sources, obviously.
But I think there's just a little bit of information
can go a long way in order to, I don't know,
figure out what sort of signs you are looking for.
And lastly, just don't jump to conclusions,
I think, for a lot of people.
Like if something.
Even if you have a sneaking suspicion or something,
I don't know, it's very easy to hand wave
over certain behaviors and be like,
that person's just an asshole,
or this person, whatever, they're lazy.
Sometimes those things are true,
but having that as a default response, I think,
is just a little callous.
Without like a specific example, like I don't know that I could give you like a thing necessarily
to do, but broadly, hopefully that is somewhat helpful.
It is, yeah, thanks.
Hi, my name is Tote and I guess I have something of a comment that, you know, any of you might
like to elaborate on.
So I founded my first company in 97, and I'm horribly old,
so you can imagine how many mistakes I've made.
And for me, I never learned from them.
That's the problem.
But I've been able to handle them in one way.
It's trying to go for TTM, time to mistake,
as short as possible.
The mistake with the vertical slice was taking six months.
Why not six days?
You know, do one in six days and you'll learn two-thirds
of what you learned from doing it, you know, in six months.
So that's, I have a plaque.
Let's make spectacular mistakes, you know.
Make big ones and make them fast.
That would be, yeah, that's my comment.
Elaborate.
Thank you.
Yeah, bravo to that.
Hey, and by the way, this is a session like nothing I've been to at GDC, and I love it, guys. You're brave.
Thank you.
Oh, we have more.
I guess we should, yeah.
Basically, he was celebrating the importance
of going through and making mistakes
and talking through it to make sure that you can ultimately
move beyond that.
I'm kind of repeating the question,
even though it wasn't fully a question.
But yes, we're big proponents of make new mistakes.
So finding the time to retrospect on what went wrong
and not being afraid to ask enough whys to really get
to the core of it is super important to be
able to move beyond all that stuff.
Oh, yeah, go for it.
Hello, yeah, I actually don't really have a question. I just wanted to take the time to thank you guys for speaking it was
Clearly something that I don't think was easy to talk about so thank you so much for sharing your stories
I really do appreciate it. I really enjoyed hearing each of your stories. Thank you. Thank you so much appreciate it
Go for it
Hi. So, well, first off, again, thank you for sharing all of that with us.
I know it probably was not easy to have to relive that in front of a crowd of strangers.
But my question is for Juan.
You mentioned that you and your teammates were just coming out of university
and you hadn't really learned about what the industry was like in order to,
you know, be able to...
survive what came next better.
What would you suggest that maybe we can do
to learn about that stuff before going into a big venture?
Yeah, I think, I think I would do,
what I would do now is just go and email people
that I know that have some experience in the past.
I think in Spain, we don't have this huge industry.
We have a huge community, but it's basically people like,
not like me, maybe more successful.
But it's really starting to kick off now.
So back in 2013, 2014, reaching out to people
wasn't that easy as it is now.
But again, I think if I were a student today, I would go and just bother people that might
have some experience that I of course don't have yet.
Because in university I think it's not really possible to teach how the industry is in some
way.
So yeah, I would say just go and bother some people in the GDC or whatever.
Thank you.
Yeah, go for it.
Hey, this one's for Charlie.
Yeah.
Out of curiosity, how did the IP holders actually react,
if at all?
They were surprisingly, maybe not surprisingly,
they were very supportive of us during the entire process.
Obviously.
It's not something that you ever want to have happen.
But I mean, we've been working with them for years up until that point.
So, you know, we built up a lot of trust.
They understood they were abreast of every decision that we'd ultimately made.
The most important thing was for us to go through and try and recover
in the long haul as best we ultimately could.
There's obviously a big investment that we'd all gone through and made in the game.
So that was always our angle from the get go.
So we presented our plan to them and they supported it 100 percent.
So. All right. Thank you. No worries. Thank you.
Hi, this one's for John, I think.
So I have, I don't really suffer it from myself,
but I've got a lot of friends who kind of get
into the same game design habits or game development habits
where they kind of work from home and they won't leave
and they get really stuck in their own head
and every time something goes wrong
because they're really only working with themselves
and they're so isolated, you know,
they really struggle to get over that.
Do you have any tips on how I can help them
kind of get out of working from home all the time
you know, being more with people and kind of helping them
get out of such a loop, if that makes sense.
Yeah, that's hard.
Yeah.
I've had those people in my life too,
and I didn't listen to them.
I think it's a delicate balance, right?
Because it feels like a natural inclination.
It feels like a helpful natural inclination
to reach out when you see someone who's struggling
and be like, stop doing the things that you're doing.
They are hurting you.
But the tough potential problem with that is it can almost make that feeling more entrenched.
Obviously, it is dependent on anyone's personal struggle.
I think, I don't know, you can make suggestions, but I wouldn't necessarily push it and pose
things in a way like, hey, why don't you come join me here and we'll have a workday or something.
something a little bit more passive that allows them to still have some agency
without feeling like they're being pulled along or they are, I don't know.
I feel very apprehensive about actually giving you any concrete example because
again, I don't know, I'm not the guy to do that, but if it were me, I don't know
that I would want someone to say, get out of the house, you got to do it, it's bad
for you. I would want them to say, hey
if you feel like it, please come with me
and we will work together, or we will do something different
within this space and try and turn that
into a longer form habit that might result
in a behavioral change.
Aside from that, I don't know, just stick around and be
a good friend.
I know it's hard, but that, I think, means a lot.
It does not always.
feel like you were doing a lot when you were just like being with someone and listening
to them and accepting whatever they're going through as just a part of their life, but
I don't think I would have shipped the game if I didn't have people like that for me personally.
And I don't think shipping the game is the most important thing, but I wouldn't be right
here where I am right now if I hadn't done this and been able to reflect on it.
Sorry that's not super helpful.
That's good.
I hope it's good.
Well, thank you so much.
And yeah, the talks were fantastic.
So thanks so much for that.
Thank you.
I'm so sorry they just told us that we're out of time, but we're going to be here.
So by all means, if you guys have any other questions, feel free to come up.
Thank you all so much for taking the time.
Remember to fill out your surveys.