Hi, everybody.
My name is Anders Frank.
I'm sitting in a cool room with Zelda in the background.
And I'm going to spend the next 30 minutes
to talk about visual attention and getting good at eSports.
My talk has a key message, and that
is that visual attention matters.
It can support better game performances
as it provides opportunity to see the possibilities
of actions in a game environment.
And to establish that claim, I would like to introduce a theory from psychology that helps us understand the relationship between gameplay and visual attention.
But I also want to share some kind of work we do in the game League of Legends.
Before heading on on that topic, I would like to introduce, give a little bit background on myself.
I've been interested in use cases for
for quite a long time.
It started actually in the 90s when I was given the opportunity
to head a virtual reality laboratory.
Everybody was, of course, technical,
optimistic about technology at that time,
and I worked at the VR laboratory for the Swedish military
to try to find use cases
and how to use that sort of technology for the Swedish military.
Quite interesting head-mounted display, I would say.
In the end of the 90s, it was...
The technology was not, or VR was not that trend anymore.
And it became replaced by games and game technology and so on.
So I shifted to look at that one, which was quite nice for me because I love games.
And so we start using the commercial games engines and also
commercial games to adapt them to force release military.
try to figure out ways to use that technology for other purposes than just combat and violence.
So we did, for instance, a peacekeeping mission trainer called Foreign Ground for the ongoing
UN mission in Liberia.
And I became so interested in the training aspect of it, so you can actually train by
games and learn from games.
So I shift focus to do that in office training, trying to address that phenomena of wargaming.
Now, one has to imagine, remember that wargaming has been around in cadet and officer training for
centuries. But my sort of interest was not only the good side, but also the back side of it,
the bad sides, which actually became the thesis, the topic of my thesis.
where I just started to introduce a concept called
gaming mode, which is basically when you play the game
and not training for the real stuff.
It is the back side of the gaming
because it becomes so powerful that you actually
lose the concept why you play the game.
So that became the topic of my PhD.
But since 2017, I'm at Tobii working on other technology.
And in this sense, I'm working on eye tracking.
And I work as a position as a game experience researcher.
And once again, I'm trying to identify the user values.
But now with eye tracking.
And I've been working with many well-known games
to influence the games with eye tracking.
For instance, Shadow of the Tomb Raider or The Division,
where we're really trying to define aspects of the game
and influence the game with eye tracking, to move the camera,
to aim with your eyes, and also to create immersion effects
and lighting and so on.
But since a while back, we are more focused on eSports,
which is kind of another aspect of eye tracking
because it's analytical use.
To use the eye tracking technology to become better.
And a couple of years ago,
we did a study among professional Dota 2 players.
And we interviewed them to try to figure out
what kind of skills are needed to...
be good at the game due to two. And the arguments and the logic behind that was if we're going to
introduce eye tracking to support that skill level we need to first of all we need to understand
what kind of skills are needed to play the game to play the game good. So this is all these answers.
interviews was then analyzed and categorized into different groups of skill levels.
And we can see in this graph how the different categories are changing over as you move from
novices to expert. And the first category is mechanical skills, which is basically
learning how to play the game, the moving the camera control and the hitting and the creep control.
harass stuff in your bi-deabilities and very mechanical skills, which is a skill level that's
quite easily been learned in the beginning, but it's never ever learned, finally learned to the
extent that you don't learn anymore. So the graph of that one moving from novice to expert actually
goes from have a steep learning curve and then plateaus, but it doesn't, it still increases.
The second category of skills is what we can call awareness skills.
And awareness skills is when actually you would like to read the game.
If you survive and not being killed all constantly,
are you looking at the team positioning yourself
and also the opponents and the incoming threat.
You're being aware of what time it is,
the time awareness and cool down of your abilities,
but also what kind of level the opponents are.
And that is a skill that's quite not really introduced and learned when you're a novice.
It becomes aware of it, but it is being more associated to intermediate and expert players.
And the last category is what we can call higher cognitive skills.
For instance, be able to really, really understand the game in depth to predict what's happening.
What are the enemy intentions?
What are our current tactics, what to do?
But also on the meta level, what items and abilities
or heroes should I choose given the current situation?
And that skill is mostly associated
to those players who are really good at the game.
So having this graph in the end gave us a rough estimate
that having the eyes on the game really
changes.
depending on what kind of skills level you're trying to sort of enhance.
So the question is then how do players extract meaningful information from the
game? Because it sends it is different
meaningful information of tactics that is for actually creep control and
the clock and so on. So how does actually visual attention
and gaming relate? How can the player extract meaningful
information?
And one aspect of that one is to introduce the theory of ecological psychology.
One of the proponents of those is psychologist James J. Gibson.
He was, he spent his life interested in visual perception.
And in his work, he coined the term aphornesis.
Which I would spend some time to talk about.
A furnaces is the mutual relation between the organism, that is of course humans, and the environment.
One needs to keep in mind that the environment contains everything.
It is the background, it is the city, it is the forest, it is the objects in the city, it is the humans and the animals, so it's everything.
And all those things exist in relation to each other in a layer structure, which constantly changes as events occur.
Humans, an organism, are actively changing the environment, interacting with it.
And the phonosis is actually when the environment, how that offers to humans.
It is the relationship between an agent and the environment.
And I will give you a couple of examples here to really simplify what I mean.
If we take an object, as we usually call a chair,
it offers most humans a place to sit on.
But it doesn't offer that to a very small human, for instance, an infant,
who is not able to do that.
Or animals, for that matter, take, for instance, an extreme value as a fish.
Fish cannot sit on this one.
So we cannot say that this sort of object is something you sit on.
It applies to a certain kind of organism or humans.
And even if we design and create objects to offer actions to most humans,
one must remember this is always relative to an agent.
So this scene of the cockpit, as I am, and I'm two meters and four centimeters,
offers something else than a place to sit and rest and move around.
For me, it's more like it offers torture.
I cannot stand sitting in an airplane.
That's for sure.
Another example is that we have something,
an object we can call a hammer,
which has some certain, some kind of qualities to it.
It offers something to grasp.
It offers, you can hit with it, and you can also throw it.
But that's only relevant for those individuals
who can grasp the hammer.
And for instance, humans without arms.
That's not an object that offers the same qualities, properties, as for other humans.
And what about learning? Well, part of it is that it is constrained by the physical properties of
the agents of ourselves as interacting with the environment. But many of the things can
actually be learned. These abilities can be developed.
And one would need to keep in mind that the perceiving of affordances or the possibilities of actions are essential for survival.
It is what our perceptual systems have evolved to do.
So learning is about differentiating and making finer distinctions about the world to discover new affordances that was previously invisible.
By experience, training.
time and explorations. And it usually comes to that extreme when an organism is totally
compatible to an environment. We can call it attuned to the environment. And then in that
sense, the experts become a sea of furnaces that's more or less investable for novices.
For instance, if we take this beautiful part of the forest, for me, it's a place that offers
walking about and taking a rest and enjoying the smell and sound of it perhaps.
My stepmother looking at the same situation or same image will see other, will perceive
other affordances than I am. She will immediately respond to say that
this is something where I can pick mushrooms.
And she has done that, of course, to make a financial sense and of course,
and have experienced similar situations and cultivated her perception to see those furnaces.
And same goes for the sport situations where a good soccer player can see the opportunities,
when to pass, when to shoot. She or he are able to read the game. An interesting
for us as spectators of the sport is that it's enjoyable to see those really good soccer players in action.
If we can see those acting upon their furnaces.
Which is kind of interesting because it doesn't only apply to perceiving what to do, it's also performing what to do.
Which takes us to the difference between perceiving and acting on our furnaces.
And according to the theory, there is actually no difference.
Seeing and acting on a fornice is deeply intertwined.
We act to perceive and we perceive to act.
We move our heads to see better what's going on.
And we shuffle off objects to perceive newer fornices.
We move a wall to be able to see behind it.
We construct rows and level out the environment.
We do constant changes to the environment.
to pursue new affordances to make a roadway drivable and so on.
And the theory also describes two different kinds of actions to that one.
And the first action aspect is exploratory. And that is the part when you explore the sort of
perceived possibilities, gather all the information, what kind of affordances are
in the surroundings. And the other one is actually performing it.
As I said in the earlier example of the performatory soccer player,
he or she is able to see the opportunity but also act on it.
And to give another example for this one,
in the human activity of playfulness in the game world,
we have a game of chess. A game of chess is a game that's
more or less designed around exploratory function.
Performing the moves that is changing the chess pieces,
the rotation of the chess pieces,
is more or less trivial.
But what to change is on seed opportunities.
It's the hard stuff.
In the other end of the spectrum,
we have a tracking field, for instance,
100 meter dash relay, which is kind of a trivial way
to understand what to do.
You just run in a straight line for 100 meters.
But it's super hard to actually perform that in a good way.
And if we go through the video games.
For instance, Counter Strike, that's something that's always, usually falls in between.
You not only need to move around to see the opportunities of what to do and so on,
you also need to perform quite well.
So when you get an opportunity for a shot,
you need to really be fast enough and do it really quickly.
So most games have those kind of two aspects of actions already designed in them,
to play the game.
So now I'm going to show you a video from an influencer called VackyJacky
so when he explains how to play PUBG. We will see he's just night tracking in
this video so we can see the bubble moving around where he's looking at
and he will use show us how how a technique to spot the enemy.
And as you will see in the video, he will constantly move to be able to perceive the opponents,
but we also will see that he's quite effective at performing and realizing their forces when he gets the kills,
the opportunity for kills, I would say.
Let's see if I can get it off here.
Welcome guys!
I've said it before, being good at spotting enemies is the single most important skill to have in PUBG.
The reasons are obvious.
Spotting your enemies before they spot you, allow you to move in open areas with low risk.
Allow you to take the first shot in a gunfight, or let you decide if it's better to avoid confrontation when executing stealth tactics.
The art of spotting enemies lies mainly in the way you use your eyes,
where you focus and how you scan your surroundings.
I illustrated this manually in my old spotting video, but now thanks to my sponsor,
Tobii Gaming, I am able to show you this using Tobii eye tracking technology.
What you will see here is as real as it gets,
as I have been able to record exactly where I look during gameplay.
The content of this video is scan types,
focus resource management and detecting movement.
The first scan type is the horizontal scan.
The horizontal scan is by far the most important way to spot enemies when running in the open.
My most frequently used strategy is to stay completely away from vehicles and instead
simply move out directly in the open.
The reason I feel comfortable doing this is because of the effectiveness of horizontal
scanning.
Horizontal scanning is a method you want to use when you want to be able to consume as much visual information at the fastest possible rate,
which is also super useful when holding a position or trying to identify the location of an enemy while looking in the direction you just heard him fire a shot in.
Horizontal scanning should be used when an enemy would naturally stand out in relation to his surroundings by contrast alone.
Using the Tobii Eye Tracker 4C
I was able to record this heatmap of my focus which is really cool because you can clearly
see in which areas of the screen I look the most.
Take a moment to study this recording.
And as I said earlier, the horizontal scan that WackyJackie goes through, and there are
more examples in the video, I don't have time to show it, is a technique to really see the
affordances.
Horizontal scan is not the furnace itself. It's actually what's it's a technique to discover their furnaces
And since battle royale is more or less a game, but if you see an enemy if you see a moving
Avatar is is the enemy could be the team of course, but but it's mostly the case. It is
Survival game so it's mostly enemy. So there are certain techniques to really discover those furnaces when it comes in sight
hit the enemy
um, so
So horizontal scan is a technique to discover the affordances.
Which comes up to the summing up to the psychology in gaming.
And I borrowed this quote from Jonas Lindroth who wrote in his paper that
gameplay is to perceive and act on and transform the affordances that are
related to a game system or other players in the game.
And in this sense it's interesting because it's a definition of
gameplay and gaming with this theory in mind that doesn't actually care of what form it is being
played in. It could be board games, it could be video games, and it can even include sports,
which is funny because there's given the current debate about whether esports is a real sport or not.
So
What about visual attention and how to improve that skill?
Can we support the visual attention, the ability to
to attend to your visual perception? Yes we can and we have started this one
this journey. We can provide metrics, we can track
the visual attention in some aspect and by having metrics we can explain to
players
how the strengths and weaknesses of their ability to take advantage of the information richness of
the game environment. And TwoBear has together with Mobalytics created a visual attention
metrics in the sort of companion apps that's being developed by Mobalytics.
And that companion map, game performance index,
contains many, many aspects of playing League of Legends.
Now we are precisely, right now,
we are introducing visual attention to an eye tracking
to that sort of metric, existing metrics.
But the key challenge is to transform eye tracking data
into meaningful and game-specific metrics.
And last year we spent some serious time to create kind of an understanding of that field. So we
collect gaze data from a vast amount of different players from different ranks and analyze that
together to get some kind of a counter-factualizations of what's going on. So it became
meaningful and from that we obtained the five metrics. And those five metrics are first of all
the Meaning Map Awareness.
That's the frequency you look at the minimap and how much time you spend on that minimap.
The second one is tunnel vision.
Tunnel vision is a bad aspect of it because you're focused on a specific region and you're
sort of zoning out on something, you're neglecting other parts of the game.
So it's a metric that tells you how often you do that.
Information processing indicates how much rapidly you can process information.
which is kind of the average fixation as calculated,
because it is really associated to professional performance
if you are processing information quite rapidly.
And to those who is really aware about the theory,
he will say that, well, wait a minute,
information processing is not compatible to the theory
of ecological psychology.
Well, I can come to that.
I know, I know, I know.
The fourth aspect concerns fight preparation.
It is a measurement how aware you are with the surroundings before you enter a fight.
Look at the minimap, look at the surroundings, your abilities and so on before entering a fight.
And pick awareness is that you are...
When you're getting picked off, it's usually because of you don't pay attention to the surrounding so we can measure how if that happens and if you are paying attention to the game.
I would like to show you an example from a video.
I'm going to hide my screen over here.
And this is an image of, oh sorry, a video of a player who plays Twisted Fate and he plays mid lane.
and he's about to get his ultimate and before he gets an ultimate he
scans and see that opportunity in the bot lane
and we will see in the video how often he checks the bot lane what's going on
and so on and immediately he's got the ability for the ultimate he will go
there so he's and also looking if he's in the right
moment so let's see the video
it's without sound
And the red rectangle over there is actually the measurement of the fixations of the eyes.
So it's actually a way we can quite easily see when the eyes are on the minimap.
And we should perhaps take that again, because now it's over more or less.
So what's happening in the beginning here is that he is, he or she actually, is playing the game and
constantly looking at the bot lane over there, making a fixation, makes a fixation, and soon
he will get his ultimate. Bam, bam, check it out, there it goes, and decides where to go, bam.
So he constantly checks if it's the right, and preparing to do that before he actually enters
the fight.
What are the benefits for this kind of system?
Well, first of all, we have the ability to track how players gather information
and seek a furnaces with the eye tracker and storing of the gaze data.
And by that we can analyze that and provide feedback to the players
and tell how to improve their information gathering skills
and through the metrics.
and then we lay the foundation for players to make use of what they see to improve their decision making.
If James Gibson would be around, he would say that, well you know what,
players are supported in the quest to discover affordances.
He wouldn't use that kind of a thing of decision making.
He would say that players are supported in the quest to discover affordances.
Which is kind of neat.
However, the metrics support discovery of their affordances.
The metrics is not the affordances by themselves.
At the same time as the horizontal scan is not affordances by itself.
It's a technique to discover their affordances.
So the metrics tell us what part of the screens you're looking at,
not on what items specifically.
And to understand, to really understand what you're looking at,
you need to understand, you need to experience and training to,
as I said earlier, earlier.
For instance, if you have a situation on a minimap,
is that a threat or is that an opportunity?
That depends.
Depends on the skill level.
It also depends what was happening, of course.
To really unlock the potential for this one,
I encourage people to take on the journey
to develop future companion apps.
that will assist in perceiving and acting on more affordances, which is tailored on player skill
level. For instance, scanning. We can, if we have an affordances system live in the game app, we can
see, we can measure how often you were killed by an opponent that you didn't spot before.
And if that's live and that can be measured, we can have, we can introduce ideas that you need to change the ways you scan your horizon, actually scan the game.
Or we can make predictions of Fortis' encouragement. For instance, if things are building up to become a threat.
and to be able to detect if the players actually see those things
and or highlight that something's going on and so on
to really nurture and train the players to perceive those kind of
performances when the situation builds up. And the same goes for planning to
avoid taking risky actions for instance roaming around in League of Legends
when you are quite uncertain or unaware.
If that could be measured live, that could actually encourage you to change your behavior.
As having this instructor behind them saying, well, what are you doing? What are you doing?
But for you to realize that, of course, we need some kind of advanced systems. We need
machine learning and computer vision, or preferably we can integrate this kind of
a training matrix, analytical metrics, in the game itself. So it's encouraged that.
because then we can make use of the full API to really make sense of what's going on in the contextual situation of the game.
To sum this presentation up a little bit, I first introduced the Gibson ideas on affordances,
which provides quite valuable insights how visual attention relates to successful game performances.
The theory itself combines the exploration phase,
I mean, the ability to see what opportunities are
laid before us in the environment,
and acting on it, the performatory aspect of it,
in an interesting way.
And player discovery and acting upon those affordances
are essential to improve in the game performances,
not only seeing what to do, but also doing it.
And by tracking visual attention, we can support this discovery.
For instance, with eye tracking.
And the journey has just begun.
I encourage all of you to pick a game and let's get started because there's so much work to do.
And by that, I would like to say thanks for listening to this presentation.
Hope you learned something about that and adios, hej då.
and I hope to see you at the next GDC.
Bye!