I'm supposed to remind you that
you'll get an e-mail after this talk to rate me if you'd like
to. And please do take the time to do that. I would love to get
the feedback whether you like this kind of content, whether
you think this is useful. This is kind of a wacky, vaguely
personal subject to me. And I'm not really sure how much
interest there is in this sort of really to me special group of
players because we're not the biggest scene around. So the
feedback would really help me. So I'd appreciate it.
So without further ado, let's see. Like I said, I'm Tom. I've
been involved in competitive gaming, eSports, for over 25
years now. First as a player, as what amounted to a pro back in
the early 90s. I was a fanatic street fighter player, traveled
the country, going to tournaments. My mains were
Chun-Li and Dhalsim, just in case you're curious.
They're still my mains.
In 2011, I dove into the games industry as a developer,
co-founding a little startup called Radiant
with my twin brother and co-founder.
There we produced our own fighting game,
had a brief alpha for about six months.
That game was called Rising Thunder.
And we later sold that company to Riot Games.
But in the background for the past 15 years I've been sort of
developing this project called Evo with a couple of awesome
partners and that's really what I want to talk to you about
today.
And let's get to it.
So this is a really quick timeline.
I want to talk about a special group of players for me.
It's called the FGC, the fighting game community,
and talk about why I think they're
special in the world of esports.
I want to describe how they got that way
and describe most of my talk on that subject.
And then I'll contextualize it for how it matters
if you're building a game or if you want
to be involved in esports.
Okay, so, behold, this is the FGC.
How many people know what this is?
Show of hands.
Oh good, most of you.
Okay, so this can go fast.
So, the FGC, for maybe those of you
who are seeing this for the first time,
is a group of really passionate fighting game fans
who have organized themselves
into basically a global collection
of grassroots tournaments.
So, on any given weekend throughout the year,
tournaments for street fighter, all kinds of fighting games
happening all over the world. The US, EU, Japan. And the
largest of these events is EVO. And this is the event.
that I help run. It's kind of the de facto annual championship
of fighting games. We hold nine tournaments throughout a
weekend. And players really show up to this thing. Last year we
had over 10,000 players show up from over 70 countries.
And what's unique about this scene and Evo is that almost all of these tournaments are open.
They have open brackets.
Anyone who wants to come can play and compete against the best in the world,
regardless of your skill level.
Okay, so why is that important? Why does it matter?
Well, when we think about eSports events, we usually think about something like this.
And these are legitimately awesome.
I love going to these. I love watching them.
But the draw of this event is to watch the pros play at the very highest level.
It's that spectacle of seeing the best of the best of the best compete.
And most of the people in this stadium probably play this game.
Most of them are probably actually competitive players, right?
They play to win.
But in the context of this event, they're showing up as fans.
right, to watch the pros. So it's kind of like the NBA where
you may play basketball, you may be a diehard basketball fan, but
when you go to a Warriors game, you don't expect to like lace up
against Steph, right? That's just not why you're there. You
have to watch Steph do incredible things that you can't
do. Okay? But by contrast, this is the show floor at EVO and
this is what you see in all these fighting game community
events. What you're seeing are about 4 or 5,000 players all
competing at
30 or so playstations set up around the floor and it's so dense that you can't even see many of the playstations.
And this is about half of our show floor. Imagine like a whole monitor sort of next to this.
And that encompasses sort of what day one or day two of Evo looks like.
And so the draw of this event is not to sort of watch the pros, it's to compete against them.
It's to participate in an event which with a huge set of your peers and test yourself and see...
test your limits, see how far you can get into this event.
So it's a lot less like the NBA, and it's more like poker.
Where if you go to the World Series of Poker,
it doesn't matter if you're like a sponsored pro,
or if you're just sort of a casual player,
you go to this event with a winning mentality.
You're trying to get as far into the bracket as you can
to maybe make it money,
and then maybe if you're a long shot, even to win.
And so it's a different mentality.
So if you sum all that up, I think these are how our events
come together.
And it's a stadium setting in the end.
But all the people that you see in the stands
are basically kind of dead bodies, right?
Almost all of them were players who
got knocked out of this event.
And they stick around, and they watch the conclusion
because they love their sport.
and they're invested.
In fact, many of them probably got knocked out
by the two players who were left
playing for the ultimate championship.
Like they have skin in the game.
Like this is personal for them.
Okay, and so these are the three key values
that I attribute to the fighting game player, right?
There's competition and especially the spirit that.
competitors are all equal and every player deserves a shot at the best in the world.
There's the concept of hype. Fighting games are a 1v1 action genre. It's super emotional
and players love to see what happens to that dude when he's in that chair in the moment
up against the wall and he has to perform.
There's a whole lexicon of terms describing hype,
like there's salt, the pop-off, right?
Players really have almost like a WWE mentality
to seeing the action unfold on screen
and seeing the personal drama of human beings, right?
And then there's, this is related to competition,
there's the struggle, the idea that every single player
is always in a personal journey to get stronger,
and even if you're a bad player.
or a mediocre player, you earn respect for sort of putting your hand to the rig and testing yourself.
Okay, so, part one, over.
So, how did the scene get this way?
Why is the scene value those three values so highly?
And part of it is probably that this is a genre that embraces the warrior's fantasy.
So many of these games are tied up into martial arts themes and players are probably...
consciously or subconsciously sort of bind into that,
and so they tend to value these things.
And I think there's some truth to that,
but I don't think that's the major factor.
I think there's something much deeper
and fundamental at play,
which is that this is a genre that grew up in the arcades.
And that was a very specific moment in time
that probably won't happen again.
And that arcade had a very specific set of rules.
And that arena...
taught players what to value. It shaped their motivations.
And once those players had those motivations set,
they passed them down to future generations of players.
So then now you have younger players who have never
stepped foot in an arcade, never had that experience,
but they value the same things.
They learn that from sort of their ancestors.
And I guess I'm one of the ancestors,
which doesn't make me feel great.
But what was this experience?
What was so special about arcades?
Why was it different?
I want you to rewind your mental stack
all the way back to 1991,
which is the heyday of the arcades.
So this was a full 20 years before watching video games
of the internet was a thing, right,
with Twitch and with YouTube.
This was a long time before the birth of eSports,
at least for me personally, which was StarCraft.
And this was a full five years before multiplayer gaming
on PC was a thing with the original Doom.
So this was a lifetime ago in our industry.
This was a long time ago.
none of these things were around. But what was happening was a vibrant competitive scene
happening in arcades all over the world. Okay? Players were organizing into tournaments, the
companies themselves were sponsoring big tournaments. And if you were into competitive
gaming, if that was your thing, back then odds are you were playing a fighting game because it
was kind of the best game in town.
Okay, so this is a really old photo of Southern Hills Golf Land, which is a now dead arcade
that was in Orange County, California.
In the US at least, this was the place to play. This was kind of like the Mecca.
This was known to have the best players in the country.
They would hold regular tournaments, and if you were a street fighter player,
you would come to this place. People would travel from New York, from the Midwest,
to play against these players.
And when you did that...
Here's what the experience was.
First, obviously, this was a public place,
so you had to physically go there.
And then you show up with whoever happens to be
in the arcade at the time.
And when you wanted to play,
you'd walk up to one of these cabinets
and put your quarter up.
Literally put your quarter up on the sill of the machine.
And that reserved your spot in queue.
Reserved, I say, in giant air quotes.
But right now you can see there are four people
who are waiting to play.
This person is putting their turn up
and you'd wait in line.
it was your turn, you take your quarter, put it in the machine and you play. You play against
whoever happens to be there at the time next to you. It could be like the best dude in the
arcade or the country or it could be just a random person. And the key thing about this,
is that we didn't have things like matchmakers.
It was all sort of house rules
to determine how you got to play.
And so what is on the line for these players
when they're going through this experience?
Because that's really what shaped their values.
And I want to talk about this in terms of three stakes,
three primary stakes, right?
There's time, there's money, and there's face.
When I say face, I mean respect.
Respect and admiration of your peers, okay?
So let's talk about time and money.
And I want to tell you a story, real briefly, about how I got involved with fighting games
with the original Street Fighter 2 and a putt-putt golf arcade near my house.
I was in high school. I did not have a car. I did not have a driver's license. So merely
getting to the game was kind of an ordeal. I had to either persuade my mom or bribe like a kid
with a car to get me to that arcade. The game itself was a scarce resource. You couldn't just
sit down at your computer or whip out your phone and play this thing. It took effort to get
there. And once I was there...
I had maybe like six to eight hours a week
that I could devote to playing games in the arcade,
and I had probably $20, right?
Those dollars and those hours were my lifeblood.
They determined how much I would get to play
this game this week, and how much I got to play the game
determined how much better I would get.
That was my practice time, right?
So in a very real sense, I had limited lives.
and as I'm going through this experience I'm burning lives at
the same time. If I put in a quarter I lose a little money.
If I lose I go to the back of the line so I lose maybe a lot
of time. That time gap could be 20 or 30 minutes before you get
to play again. So it's super sharp.
And the final factor was that the only way that I could get better,
the only way to stretch out those lives, was to win.
That's the only way you're going to get to play for free.
That's the only way you're going to get to play even two times in a row, is win.
Beat that person who's next to you.
And what I learned going through this experience,
what everyone around me learned really quickly,
was that...
everyone is a competitor. It doesn't matter if you are playing
this game for the first time this week or if you've been
playing for years. When you step into this arcade and you step
up to a machine, you have to go in with a winning mindset. You
have to try to win. It's sort of a no excuses environment, right?
And winning like freaking matters, okay? There wasn't such
a thing as like a moral victory if you did your best and you
almost won and that guy is better than you anyway. So it
doesn't matter. You're still going to the back of the line.
right? So there's a premium on winning like every single time.
And so this was like illuminating and like crack for
me and I just really got into it and got involved with it and as
time went by.
I moved out of Albuquerque, New Mexico, where I was, and school brought me to California.
At the time I didn't know, but I was being dropped into one of the most hyper-competitive
hottest spots for fighting games in the US at the time.
I learned a ton about face and how you earn respect.
right? How you earn respect among your peers in this kind of an environment. So I want to
remind you that these arcades were public places. Which meant that anyone could go and the
geographical reality of this was that the usual players tended to congregate in the same
arcade. So people would go to the arcade in their neighborhood. So you were always fighting
with a group of familiar peers. And in this peer group,
everyone had a role to play. There was like the alpha, the dude who everyone knew was the best.
There were sort of the upper comers who were trying to like unseat the alpha. There were
the regulars who were neither good nor bad but they all just showed up because maybe they liked
it. And then there was kind of the fish. The person who had a bottomless supply of quarters
but they always lost but they always seemed to keep putting them up. And they were kind of like
the break where you're like, okay, I'm fighting the fish, I can take it easy for a bit and rest up.
unfortunately like local boy from Albuquerque moving up to
California full of killers I was like the fish initially. And so
I lost a lot trying to like razor up my skills to be able to
compete with these guys. And an interesting thing happens to you
when you're in the back of that queue. The first thing is
remember your quarter is up on the machine. You can't really go
anywhere because if you go off and like try to come back in ten
minutes, your quarter will be gone.
and no one will know what happened to it.
And the thing is, if you're smart,
you don't want to go anywhere.
You want to have laser eyes on that screen
so you can watch that dude who just beat you
and maybe learn something,
or at least study up on his pattern
so you'll have a better chance of beating him next time.
And so around this arcade cabinet,
you have a captive attentive audience.
They're captive because they can't go anywhere,
they'll lose their quarter.
And they're attentive because they want to learn this game
and the only way you can learn if you're not playing
is by watching and watching really closely
about the action that's happening on screen.
And this produced a quality of play as performance.
It wasn't just about winning,
it was about playing for the crowd
and being kind of a little celebrity
around that arcade cabinet.
Excellence in play was always respected,
but players who were
big personalities or could win with style were celebrated.
Those were the people that players really looked up to.
That's how you earned respect.
And there were a lot of players who would.
embrace this deeply. There are players who love being the hero. There are players who love
being the heel. That guy who you just could not stand and he knew you could not stand him.
There was one player in particular who he was strong but he wasn't the best. But he would
gain notoriety being the most annoying dude you have ever met. And when he played you in a
tournament and beat you.
business cards printed and he would hand it to you and the
business card said congratulations you've just been
beaten by Jeff Schaefer. Yeah. So I'm going to talk about
this builds a sense of hype. You have this familiar group of
players. You know these guys. Maybe you don't know them
personally, but you've seen them every week or every day in this
arcade. Everyone knows their spot in the social hierarchy.
And their little mini dramas and stories unfold day by day, week
by week on this cabinet. Like who's going to beat the alpha?
Hey, this dude was terrible a month ago. Now he's beating me.
What's going on? Am I a bad player too? And so, um,
the familiarity of this builds sort of a sense of drama and hype as you're playing.
And like I said, in this environment I started off at the very bottom of the
toting pole and I lost a lot. And losing in any competitive game kind of stings.
I still rage when I lose in Hearthstone.
But in this environment it was particularly nasty because your
losses were public. Everybody who was paying close attention
to what's going on just saw you lose. And you can't like rage
out, you can't steam or say that's cheap because you're
just going to lose everyone's respect. You just have to hold
that out. Keep it inside, put your quarter up and get to the
back of the line.
don't have that ability, you're just not gonna last long in the scene. You're gonna get kind of like
roasted out of the scene. And so what that taught me was that there's a continual struggle to get
stronger and you have to be able to absorb losses as like the way you win. The way you win is losing
and learning from losses and then gradually getting better.
And the thing is, eventually you see everyone lose. Even that
alpha eventually makes a mistake or the dude next to him gets
lucky and he loses. So it becomes very easy to understand
that everybody loses and you just have to learn to suck up
and level up from your losses.
So I learned a lot, I lost a lot, I gradually leveled up in
this hyper competitive group and there was for me a sweet, sweet
payoff when four years later work took me up to Seattle where
I was suddenly in a different environment with a bunch of
strong players but not the world class killers that I've been
competing against for the last four years. And so all of a
sudden I was the alpha. Which, let me tell you, was a pretty
awesome feeling.
and there's this thing where like you're in this arcade and
there may be five to eight to 15 people who are all at the same
cabinet. If you can potentially beat all of them, maybe not
consistently, but if you are good enough to beat every other
person in that arcade, you can potentially like go infinite.
Right? You can cycle the queue.
everyone puts their card up again. You can cycle it again and you can play for hours and
hours and hours off of one quarter. I actually did this a few times. My longest winning
streak ever was 73 wins and it lasted six hours. It was just a very, very different feeling.
from every other competitive experience I've had,
especially in the world we have now
of automated matchmakers with ELO ratings,
where the system's always trying to match you up
with a fair opponent, which means almost every player
kind of has roughly a 50% win rate.
Like, this was a very, very different feeling,
where even as like a good player,
not a pro, but a good player,
you could have like ridiculous win streaks.
You could be like the lord of this arcade, right?
it's the feeling of being the top dog in the moment.
Like, yeah, I'm not the best, but today, right here,
I actually am the best, and none of you can beat me,
and you all know it.
So that's super awesome and unique,
and I don't think it has happened since,
and I'm not sure if it'll ever happen again.
So if you sum all that up, you get a culture
that is hyper-competitive, but it's also really close-knit.
It's social, right?
There's trash talking and money matches,
but there's mutual respect between players as adversaries,
even for players who maybe are not nearly as good as you.
And the only way to earn respect in this peer group is to play.
It's to play and demonstrate excellence or it's to play and continue to play even though
maybe you're not the top dog.
But you're willing to put yourself into that cauldron.
So this lasted for like 10 years.
And it was growing gradually, but steady growth,
10 years of growth.
Tournaments were getting bigger.
We were starting to have international events.
And it was awesome, it was really awesome.
And then there was a problem,
which was the arcade started going down, right?
We were sort of a budding, growing, competitive community.
It was on a sinking ship.
when some of the very best, most popular arcades
for this scene started to go under,
like Southern Hills Golf Land in 2002,
the writing was on the wall that this was a genre
that was just gonna be dead if something didn't happen.
We had to jettison ourselves from the arcades.
We had to decide what to do.
And at this time, there was a resurgence on the PC
of eSports events like I talked about
in the beginning of the talk.
And I personally took a good hard look at these,
and they weren't really compelling for me personally
as a player.
Even though what they were doing is awesome,
they weren't for me.
And it goes back to the core value proposition
of these events.
Are you there?
Why are you there?
Are you there to watch the pros playing
at the very highest level,
or do you want an arena where you can struggle
and compete and test your limits
against the best players around?
And it was just way more of the right for me
and less of the left.
And so that was where the idea for Evo came along, right?
Evo for me was literally.
kind of the escape pod that we would use
to save ourselves from the dying planet of the arcades.
Our mission right from the beginning
was to preserve and grow the arcade competitive culture.
Can we take what's awesome about this arcade experience
and put it in a form that can outlive the actual arcades?
And our values were all competitors are equal,
support every player's personal journey to get stronger,
and showcase the drama of humans under pressure,
restated as competition, struggle, and hype.
So we tried, and it was a rocky road.
It's been like, gosh, 15 years now, trying to build Evo.
And we were faced with a lot of hard choices
when we were crafting this event.
From day one, we decided this was
going to be an open tournament.
No matter how big we got, we were always
going to let every player play.
And we're going to put them in the same pool.
And that was easy at first, because we were tiny.
But as we grew, how do you run an event
with 1,000 players?
How about 10,000?
We had to invest in new systems, new equipment,
new staffing solutions to make sure that every player
who wanted to play got to play.
And that came at a cost.
We chose to do that instead of doing other things.
When it comes to the dollars we spend,
we have to choose, are we going to invest
in more ways to play?
free-to-play areas, exhibition, things like that,
verse staging, lighting, things that make the event
more attractive and feel like more professional.
And we've chosen largely to invest
in widening the arena for play,
because that's what we value.
And then finally when it comes to our stream production.
This one is a really close case and I go back and forth on this,
but do we focus on as much content as we can?
Gameplay, show more matches, more matches,
verse context, showing players' backstories,
giving you the knowledge you need to sort of understand what's going on
and care about these players.
And we've biased a lot of our production towards content.
And the reason why is because these...
is the only opportunity where you get to see a wide variety of play styles from players from all over the world
and people really want to see that diversity of play.
And so when we ask players in our sort of audience online...
do you want to see more matches or do you want to see like,
you know, mini documentaries or Q&A after?
They consistently tell us, show us more matches, right?
And so we try to get creative and find ways
to tell that story and the natural downtime
between matches or over the course of the match.
Like I said, that one is a,
I go back and forth on that all the time,
but it's a tough choice that we constantly have to make.
And I think, you know, we've made some mistakes,
certainly we've made our share of mistakes,
but I do think we've largely been successful.
We have a scene now that genuinely captures
what was awesome about that arcade culture.
These players are hyper-invested,
there's just a ton of passion.
And the feelings that these guys have for their scene
and the competition has nothing to do
with the amount of prize money, right?
We're not the biggest scene around.
It's about the authenticity and the value
that these guys put on being able to come together
and compete and ultimately crown that winner.
So, why does this matter for your game?
I think it's clear that esports are here to stay, and this is actually me personally,
this is one of the first times where I'm willing to stand up in front of a crowd and say that.
Anyone who's been around esports for a while knows it's been kind of a rocky road, it's
been up and down, up and down.
But I really feel like...
the notion of competitive gaming as incredible content
and an incredible experience for gamers is here to stay.
And I think in five to 10 years,
we're gonna see a much wider variety of formats,
both in broadcast and in eSport than what we see today.
We're really at the very beginning of this journey.
If you're building a game or an e-sport or experimenting in
e-sports, I want to encourage you to choose a model for your
e-sport.
Don't inherit one.
blindly look at what's going on in another game
and sort of copy paste it.
If you're a game developer, try to spend
the same kind of effort in crafting your eSport
that you spend in crafting your game.
And when you do that,
think about what you want your players to value,
both from the competition
and how they should think about competition,
and what you want their players to value from each other.
Right, and that can help you decide
what kinds of, you know, rule sets and formats
and things like that you want for your eSport.
Okay, that's it. Thanks. Any questions? Hi, Dave Schwartz from RIT. We now have an e-sports
program there.
As we were building our program, one of the things that
we're concerned about is diversity.
And I know it was a phenomenal talk.
I loved your presentation.
But I was sitting there hitting Google Women in Evo,
and I was curious if you could respond to that.
Yeah, that's a great question.
Thanks.
So the FGC, I think, is one of the most diverse group of players in esports, except for when it comes to women.
And there are a lot of theories about how we got to be so diverse along some lines and not that particular line.
My personal feeling is that it comes to...
leadership and role models. For whatever reason, the leadership in the FGC, the tournament
organizers, the people who are out front sort of evangelizing the FGC, are pretty diverse.
There's a lot of black and brown people who are doing that. And there are no women. And
I think when other women see that, it makes it feel like this is not the right place for
me and they go and look at other games.
there's hope here. What's going on with Smash Sisters in particular is super awesome and I'm
really glad to see that they have some success there.
Yeah, they're cool.
Um, no, but what I want to say is like, if we want to solve this problem, then I really
want to solve it.
Not just for the FGC, but for all of esports.
I think we have to look at getting diverse leaders and diverse representatives from esport.
And once we solve that problem at the top, it'll become a more welcoming place for all
kinds of players.
Thank you.
Yep.
Hi.
So I'm curious, what do you think games of other genres can do to kind of encourage that
competitor mindset and not just the spectator mindset more?
Oh boy.
So the question was, what can other genres do to encourage the competitive mindset and
not just the fan mindset?
Right. So there's this paradox in eSports and the models that we're pursuing,
which is a lot of these games are pursuing sports-based models,
but they only look at the very top of the pyramid.
And if you look at a sport like basketball, okay,
yes, there's the NBA,
but there's a whole pyramid of engagement in competitive formats
to nurture a player up to the very highest level.
There's like the D League,
and then there's like all the way down to like YMCA and youth leagues.
And so you can have success as a competitor
when you were young and when you were bad
and when you were growing.
And that doesn't exist for eSports.
And so if you're a giant eSport
and you want to help support
the competitive mindset in players,
I would say add formats for young and budding players.
Collegiate formats are great.
Some of that is happening.
How about like, you know.
youth formats, just open tournaments where you maybe
explicitly carve off the pros, because we know they crush
everybody, but say, hey, if you want to get to know what it
feels like to be a competitive player, here's an event for
you.
So looking at the whole top to bottom solution, not just top.
Hi there.
It was a great presentation, by the way.
Thank you.
As an event organizer myself that runs a lot of tournaments, I'm always looking forward to
seeing where everything is going. And Evo has been one of those things, saying, what is Evo
doing? What games are they focused on? I'm curious on a twopart question, which is, first
off, how do you guys try to be thought leaders in the space? What do you do to try to be thought
leaders in the space, more specifically, to keep on the edge leading across all the other
tournament organizers in the country?
And secondarily, where do you see other events needing to be better in order to escalate the
major level to bring it up to better for the entire FGC community?
Thanks. So if I understand the question, it's what are we doing at EVO to try to stay ahead
of the game? And then what's my advice to other tournament organizers?
Basically.
Right. So we don't really try to stay ahead of the game in terms of competing with other
tournaments.
But what we do try to do is always push the envelope on pursuing risky projects that are in line with our values.
For instance, we've...
done things like the Evo Scholarship
to try to support the idea of indie game developer
and support our players' dreams
of ultimately entering the game industry.
We now have an indie showcase
where we show competitive games that aren't fighting games
to try to get, again, support for developers.
And so it's really, we're not trying to like,
make a million dollars, we're not trying to even be
the biggest tournament.
There's a lot of interesting stuff happening
on the more, I guess, professional, traditional
eSports side of fighting games,
with the Capcom Cup and with E-League.
Those are awesome, and I think there's a great space
for them, and we're just trying to focus on our area,
which is giant open tournament,
sort of like the World Series of Poker.
And I guess my advice to other fighting game tournaments is
to take the same approach. Find something that you can do better than anybody else
and then just go hard on that. I think Combo Breaker is a great example of an event that's doing that
where they have their own cool quirky feel in different emphasis than other fighting game tournaments.
Because when you do that, I think you have a great chance
of stumbling on something that is awesome and can explode.
Whereas if you're always following behind
someone else's footsteps, you're not gonna
really have that opportunity.
Okay, do I have time for one more question or no?
Nope, I'm done.
Okay, thanks everyone.