Today we are going to look at collaboration, first as a mindset and then as a practice
designed to help you get the most out of your recording sessions and foster relationships
to inspire creativity and engender productivity.
My name is Julie Nathanson.
I've been a voice actor for over 20 years,
doing games and animation and commercials
and whatever they tell me to say.
In terms of games, I started out doing games like Psychonauts.
I played Lampida.
In the Final Fantasy games, I'm Prish and Dissidia Duodesim.
In 13.2 and Lightning Returns, I am,
and I apologize in advance for this, ChocoBocalina.
Let's see, I play a wide range of roles.
Thank you, thank you.
I play a wide range of roles
from a soldier in Metal Gear Solid Peace Walker
to Samantha Maxis in Call of Duty Black Ops.
Chill in the Skylanders series and just black in Far Cry 5.
And as I stand here next to Eve, who is the voiceover lead at ArenaNet,
I can tell you that in the decade that I've been working on Guild Wars 2,
I have voiced over 30 characters.
I'm Eve Eschenbacher, I'm the voiceover lead at ArenaNet, as Julie just said.
I've had maybe as varied a career as Julie's, if not quite as prestigious.
I've been in games for about 14 years now.
I started as a localization editor at a translation company in Tokyo, Japan, working on a few
Metal Gear titles and varied other games.
I've been a freelance Japanese to English translator for a number of games and strategy
guides, and then I was a translator at the Pokemon company where I worked on Pokemon
Platinum, HeartGold, SoulSilver, and other titles.
I got my start at ArenaNet as a copy editor, and then I took over VO from one of the producers
and built the process and the team to what it is now, which enables us to put out large,
frequent content updates every two to three months.
Sorry, I'm balancing two computers.
collaboration.
Guild Wars 2 is a little unique in that we have our living world content updates that
we put out every couple months.
Since GW2 launched in August 2012, we've had four seasons of Living World and two expansions.
In six and a half years, we've released over 50,000 lines of VO from 70 actors across 38
episodes of Living World, in addition to two expansions involving another 50,000 plus lines
of VO from over 100 actors.
Some of our actors have been working with us for over a decade, even going back to the original Guild Wars.
And that level of commitment and consistency really necessitates a more personal approach, in my opinion,
because people are more likely to want to continue to work with you when you treat them well.
I can vouch for this.
So my experience working on Guild Wars 2 has been particularly collaborative, and I've
polled my voice actor friends and it seems to be a consensus.
We all look forward to these sessions.
And I think one of the reasons is this collaborative attitude and collaborative process that Guild
Wars has afforded us all as a luxury.
And this collaboration is not just because they almost delivered my baby, which is a
true story.
So years ago, I was ginormously pregnant and started to have some like, you know, early
labor stuff that wasn't ready for the kid to be knocking on the door.
So they just briefly put me in the hospital and I had to miss a Guild Wars 2 session,
which of course I apologized for profusely.
And when I got to session, still pregnant a few days later...
They all greeted me, these are directors and editors and developers,
going, okay, we know how to deliver your child.
Mark will get the hot water.
Eve and I was like, thanks guys.
Luckily, that form of collaboration was not needed,
and my child was born in a hospital.
Thank you for your concern.
He's nine now.
That's true.
It was a long time ago.
Why collaboration? I've had to study how to handle social situations because they don't come naturally to me because I'm autistic.
I'm constantly adjusting and fine-tuning my approach, and I learn from other people, I observe, I adapt.
And as I mentioned a moment ago, I work with a number of actors on a fairly regular cadence.
Every recording session, I'm bringing in 25 to 30 actors, and about two-thirds of them are people who have been playing named recurring characters for years.
So I've gotten to know everybody really well,
and I've found that a certain approach and mentality
work better to keep everybody happy and excited
to continue working with you.
Basically, my stance is that everybody in the room
is a professional.
We're all an artist of one kind or another.
And I'm talking about the sound engineer and the director
and the actors and the writers and myself.
We're all practicing our version of art.
And we all want to do our best.
Communication is the key to quality.
So you treat your actors like they're part of your team.
We like that part.
So in terms of defining collaboration, you can get a lot of definitions that have to
do with problem solving.
There's nothing wrong with that.
But I kind of like looking at it from a different angle.
Dr. Britt Andreatta, who wrote Wired to Connect, the neuroscience of team leadership.
I spoke about it in a podcast I listened to recently,
and she called collaboration
a mutual engagement of two or more people
trying to achieve some kind of common goal
that they both contribute to in new and unexpected ways.
So, it's really an act of creation.
She went on to say that when people are working together, whatever they're building is going
to get tweaked and changed because of the input of each member of that team.
So no one can predict how it's going to turn out because it's constantly evolving.
That's game dev, right?
So...
To explain, in addition to voiceover, which I love, I'm also a writer.
I've written for live-action TV. I've written some Disney mobile game scripts.
I've written and consulted on the upcoming Guildlings game for Servo.
And because I am from a family of shrinks with a great interest in psychology,
I also happen to have a master's in clinical psychology.
So I have three perspectives when it comes to collaboration.
From a psychological standpoint, I see so many benefits,
from social connectedness to neuro-synchrony,
which I promise I will get to.
It's the coolest.
As a writer, I know that the vacuum of the singular creator doesn't yield a lot of that
inspiration and innovation that comes from being in a room of other excited creative
minds.
And as a voice actor, I know that when I am brought into the process with renderings,
videos, storyline, and given access to the world of the game I'm being asked to inhabit,
I'm more likely to feel connected to the narrative, relationships, and life of the character,
and more dedicated to the experience of recording your game.
So in short, I feel included.
And inclusion matters.
Exclusion, by comparison, is measured in the brain
in the same way that the brain measures physical pain.
Exclusion is measured in the brain the same way that we measure physical pain.
So inclusion, by contrast, offers this openness, this connection and attunement.
And from there, real collaboration is possible.
So what happens when we have real inclusion and real collaboration and we really, really,
really work together?
Neural synchrony.
It's really group neural synchrony.
So neuroscientists have hooked up people's brains
with EEGs, with the thing that sounds like snuffalopagus
but isn't, the encephalophagram.
That's why I don't say it.
But it's, so you can hook up these people's brains
all working in a room together
and then view the electrical activity in the brain.
Check out the brainwaves, right?
The more people were connecting and truly working together,
their brainwaves start to look the same.
Not just a little bit, but they could be traced on top of each other.
So when they're really engaged and feeling really, really connected to each other and
having a higher degree of empathy, that neural synchrony is even more pronounced.
So that feeling of being on the same wavelength or being in sync when you're really getting
it when you're working with someone else, that's real brain science stuff.
So
That's why we feel like collaboration might be kind of a cool thing,
to add in all aspects of the creation of a game.
And why do this now?
I mean, coming together is more important than ever in today's world.
I mean, the old model was kind of more of an exclusionary mindset,
the sense that, you know, we pay you to be here for four hours,
you come in, you say and do whatever we want
because we gave you money and you leave.
And that's...
That's...
Great.
Well, at the end, we just feel like it's
possible to add a collaborative mindset.
So that just means, really, from the get-go,
looking at a we over a me stance,
valuing open-mindedness, and holding the belief
that other people have something to add
and that we're always learning.
So just starting from that mindset
might shift something, might shift a few things.
And we're also going to give you some more concrete tools that
might be helpful once you adopt.
A collaborative mindset.
Getting the most out of actors starts with getting the most out of their auditions.
Hey, fancy that. Look, we all want the same thing. You guys want us to nail your audition.
We want to nail your audition. We want to work for you. So,
when we get your audition material, it's all we get.
And most of us are going to be self-directed.
Most of us working actors at this point, we have home studios.
And even if we're not just directing ourselves at home,
if we go into the agency that represents us to audition,
the booth director there doesn't have any more information
than we do on the piece of paper.
So unless you have us go into a studio and work with a director in person who knows your
game, you've got to make sure that what's on that piece of paper is really crucial and
helpful for us to build what we can to make the character you're looking for.
And in the spirit of collaboration, if you don't hear exactly what you're looking for,
Listen beyond the voice print. Don't just listen to the sound of the voice. If it's rough, if it's resonant,
it's not just that, right? It's whether someone's connecting with the material.
Someone who makes you curious about whether or not she could maybe do something else with that character.
That's who you might want to bring in.
So...
Guild Wars 2 is a really big game.
It's a giant world with a lot of NPCs having conversations,
giving quests and whatnot.
And while we do work with Blind Light,
who's our external vendor, to run auditions
for our big new roles, I end up with a lot of little
small part NPCs around the world every episode.
So I work with the writers and the designers
to get a sense of what they're building
so I can make sure that there's enough voices
to go around for all these NPCs.
We also have a number of monsters and enemies that need to be voiced.
And I work closely with our audio team as we're working out the processing for new monsters.
For example, we had this large...
Did you see a monster?
You pointed to a monster.
I pointed to our audio director.
Okay, I feel so much better now.
I thought she was like, and the monsters.
Does anyone see something that I don't see?
He had this large creature that needed to be voiced.
The performance needed to be done in a certain way
so that when we overlaid the processing on the lines,
it didn't become unintelligible.
For that, we got one of the writers
to help us record some in-house scratch audio
to test with the processing.
And then we could take that into the studio for the actor to hear.
So we could demonstrate for him that this delivery plus this processing is going to equal this line.
And the actor was awesome. He took that cue and he made the performance his own.
So even just the act of sharing that information was an act of collaboration, right?
Some of this stuff seems so simple, but again, coming from a mindset, the rest of it will
start to be possible in other aspects of your experience working with or even considering
working with voice actors.
So casting sites for auditions.
If you can give us an image of the character, we get so much out of it.
And you can also give a vocal reference, right?
You can say, well, this really sounds like, you know,
maybe something like Hermione in Harry Potter.
So that might give us a sense.
But a picture does something to our brains.
Because our brains are natural problem solvers.
We are looking for clues.
We want, our brains are dying to fix and finish that puzzle that you're giving us.
So for a moment, I want you to imagine that I've given you a 1,000-piece puzzle.
No, let's make it worse, 5,000-piece puzzle.
And I'm going to dump it right in front of you and say, make a thing.
But I didn't put a picture on the box.
Your brain's going to get stuck.
You can put the corner pieces in.
We all know how to find the corner pieces.
And you can do the barriers, little boundaries.
After a while, you're just like,
ah, I'm going to shove this purple into the purple,
and that kind of looks like...
Your brain starts to distance from the experience
and maybe even shut down.
But once you put a picture on the box,
the brain starts firing toward completing the puzzle.
Our brains fire toward possibility.
And if you like that, read everything Dan Siegel has ever written.
It's amazing.
In the character backstory section,
you probably don't necessarily want to give away
exactly the plot or the who and the when of your IP,
especially if you're working on a fairly recognizable franchise.
On Guild Wars, we've been cautious in the past about noting that we were
recasting beloved characters from Guild Wars 1
who are going to make an appearance in Guild Wars 2.
But you still need to find a comparable event or experience that you can
reference to give your actor a sense of the journey that
the character will be undertaking without giving away the story.
You also want to hit the points of emotion.
So be sure to include the range of emotions
that this character will need throughout the game
to offer opportunities for your actors
to show you that they can go there.
So A, this will help you cast that particular character,
and B, give you a sense of whether or not
that actor can handle the emotional arc
of a similar character.
As you've said, sometimes you might be sending out
10 audition sides for 60 characters you're looking for.
If the character has any combat scenes, make sure to include a small amount of that in
the sides because that warns the actor that the role requires vocal stress and it also
gives you a sense of how they can do efforts and gutturals.
Auditions and protecting your confidential material.
Because casting sites for auditions are a bit public.
I mean, they're sent out widely to actors and agents that aren't necessarily under NDA.
You probably want to obscure, cut, and obfuscate your IP-specific terms.
You put war never changes in an audition site, and the games press goes, ooh, maybe there's
a new Fallout game coming.
You say you're recasting a British woman who plunders ancient burial places, and they're
probably going to guess that there's a new Tomb Raider game in the works.
There's a tendency to cut away so much from the casting sides to hide your IP that it
becomes over sanitized, leaving actors too little to work with.
You cut too much meat off the bone and all you're left with is scraps.
What we usually do is write the casting side as if we were writing it for an internal review
or an NDA to actor.
and then just disguise, find, and replace.
And yes, please do change the important details of the character,
but don't, just for fun, for example,
don't change your main prehistoric villainous dinosaur creature
to a member of the geek squad at Best Buy.
Make parallel changes and keep the emotional arcs.
So we want to give you some audition examples.
I'm going to pretend that I'm casting a game,
and this is the audition side that I would be sending Julie
through our vendor.
This first casting side has been scrubbed
of all sensitive information.
So let's see.
Let's pretend I've never seen this before.
So Emily is in her 20s.
That's all I get.
I have three lines from Emily.
Remember, bravery is not undone by injury, but by lack of faith.
Stop, no more.
I may not have been made for war, but I will fight with everything I have.
And now, attack.
So I am going to look for any clues I can
in this extremely sanitized audition piece.
I have bravery.
I have injury.
I have war and fight.
Okay, so she's in her 20s and I'm going to say she's a soldier, right?
And maybe at the beginning she's talking to herself, right?
Maybe she's got to remind herself that she can do it, you know, get her bravery back
because she's been injured.
And the now attack, well, okay, well, hold on, now maybe she's the commander.
So I want to make her really commanding and give her a lot of control.
So my stab in the dark with very little information would be...
Remember, bravery is not undone by injury, but by lack of faith.
Stop! No more!
I may not have been made for war, but I will fight with everything I have.
Now, attack!
So, we have no idea if that was any good.
Because we don't know anything about this character or the game.
This version is a little bit less over sanitized,
but it's still obfuscated, so I'm not giving away my IP.
I've changed a few terms,
gone with a few parallel sort of things,
but it's not giving away exactly what I'm working on.
Now look at all the clues I get.
Sci-fi fantasy?
Okay, so maybe not a first person shooter in a modern war.
I'm going to read it to you.
Age 20s, but immortal.
Ah, so maybe her voice and her appearance could be young.
But there's going to be a world weariness.
There's going to be an intelligence, a wisdom.
Her appearance?
Ha!
Look, it's so pretty.
Look, there's glowing lights.
That tells me there might be some magic.
There's power.
I can see her eyes are determined.
Her sword.
There's a lot of mysticism there and a lot of power
and a lot of contemplative emotion.
So there's a lot for me to play with just from that example.
That's a stock photo I pulled from Shutterstock.
You can too.
So she's a high priestess.
OK, great.
Probably some mysticism there, too.
Selfless, wise, empathic, and determined.
Backstory, high priestess Emelina, and you'll notice that we changed Emily to Emelina.
Why?
Because Emily feels so modern, right?
Young and cute and modern, or just, you know, modern, earthling.
Emelina spelled funny, well, I don't know, maybe it's a little bit more fantasy.
Just to bring us in.
She's the benevolent spiritual leader of the peaceful Palyx, an alien race of human-like
creatures with the ability to assume powers of nature.
When invaders began to siphon her planet's resources to fuel their biological weapons,
Emelina is forced to become a warrior, training her people to save themselves and their home.
So what do I have here?
Benevolent spiritual leader, so we have a leader with kindness and connection.
We have, we've got invaders.
So this beautiful planet is being taken from me
and it's my responsibility to now become
and forced to become a warrior.
This is an unwitting warrior who will now have to lead.
So now the line, the first line we had,
benevolent, spiritual, well now I know.
I'm not injured, someone else is injured.
Okay?
So I might benevolently say, remember.
Bravery is not undone by injury, but by lack of faith.
The next line, internal conflict then determined, so I'm going to say,
not that I wrote this or anything, but I'm going to say.
You know, work with me.
That stop and no more is she's looking and seeing something that's too painful for her
and then has to make a decision.
Maybe because I know this character is going to make a transition during this game because
it's in the sides, that there's a character arc for her that she has to become a warrior.
Maybe this is the minute that she makes the decision.
So stop, no more.
I may not have been made for war.
But I will fight with everything I have.
And then leading her people into battle.
Well, we've got the now attack.
That part's probably about where we went before.
But we have an attack effort at the end.
I almost want to cover the mic for it.
I don't want to hurt your ears.
All right.
But she's going to bring her people into battle.
Now!
Attack!
No!
Has a little more life to it.
I'm going to cast myself in that role.
You're hired.
To shift gears a little bit, casting actors for multiple roles,
SAG rules say that you can get three roles per four-hour session with SAG actors.
So, you know, sometimes I cast somebody for a named character
and also a generic NPC off to the side.
Um, sorry.
You want to know the actor's range and listen for ad libs and goofs in the session.
First of all, we're all goofs.
We like to listen to ourselves talk, and so when we get in the booth, you're going to
hear a lot of things.
Also, you listened for flexibility in our auditions, right?
Maybe you heard me slate Julie Nathanson, and then I went into my little kid character
and went, hey, who gave the jog all my peanut butter?
So...
From my slate, you went, oh, you know what?
She could probably play the kid's mom.
The mom just has a couple lines.
And then also the kid, right?
So you're listening for any clues you can from us
about how to enjoy our versatility
if we're lucky enough to have it.
I've been able to give a lot of our actors different roles with the confidence that they'd
nail them based on demos, credits, and just goofy voices they've done between takes.
I cast one of our actors as a Skrit Queen, which in our game Skrit are just these little
rat-like creatures, just based on the fact that she had worked as a Hanson puppeteer,
knowing that she would nail it.
Preparing for recording sessions.
What we do in preparing for the recording sessions,
there's a lot of table reads and script review.
You want to read it all out loud before you ever start sending anything out
because nail down the pronunciations,
the important words in your world.
If you're having a hard time saying it,
it probably needs a rewrite.
Gather image and video references to share with your actors of the game content.
Get your scripts in chronological order if you can.
This helps everybody keep track of where they are in the story.
It's confusing to jump around in story arcs and have to tell your actors, oh yeah, that
guy you just killed, now you're meeting him for the first time.
You can create an episode or chapter character art summary sheet if you can.
This is an example of one we put together for season four, episode two at ArenaNet.
It's the overall arc of the episode and summaries of each chapter.
And there were also a few sentences on each named character's backstory, motivation, and
arc for the episode.
It's a quick reference for actors, directors, and you.
For a long-running game like Guild Wars 2, this kind of helps our actors remember where
we left off.
Last time on Guild Wars 2.
So Excel-style scripts.
Sometimes you got to use them, right?
Sometimes we get into the studio and it's like,
we need you to do 400 lines in seven minutes.
So context goes away and we just do our thing.
Sometimes it's the only format that works for your content.
It's just a number of lines like an announcer.
But it's harder to follow the through line of the story.
And it often lacks context.
So as before, right, without context,
you know, just a generic human female,
I would say, no more breaks, we've got work to do.
And then, yeah, and the captain will have our hides
if she sees you loafing about.
Do what you like.
But if I'm going to die, I'll die on my feet.
I have no context.
I have no emotional quality.
I'm just going to say the words, and you'll get it in your game.
But it might not give you the feeling you need.
In contrast.
movie-style scripts.
These are what the actors are used to seeing.
Gives the context of the scene.
You can see the previous and following lines,
and it's easier to follow the through line.
So here we can see that you've got two Corsairs
near some wreckage.
The first speaker, that would be me at work gathering crates.
Oh, OK, cool.
So I'm moving while this is happening.
And the second speaker is sitting down.
Oh, now I get it.
I'm basically accusing the person next to me
of not working.
That really changes the context.
So I would say, no more breaks.
We've got work to do.
Work to do? Do you hear yourself right now?
Crocatoric's coming. The brand'll take us all.
Tia, then the captain will have our hides if she sees you loafing about.
I'm not spending the last moments of my short little life hauling crates.
Do what you like. But if I'm gonna die, I'll die on my feet.
Okay, so I still don't know if that was what they wanted,
but I sure got a lot more out of it.
Focal stress.
That's a fun topic, isn't it?
Look, it's a hot button issue, and we know it.
Professional voice actors, we know
we're going to have to scream and be electrocuted and die
by fire.
We know you're going to have to have us take damage,
and we're going to have to slice a lot of people.
We've got it.
The thing is that the body can only take so much.
So there are ways to structure and handle
vocal stress that, again, is more collaborative,
understanding that perhaps.
It may not always just be combat.
For example, one time I got some audition sides for a villain character
and I noticed that in the sides she wasn't yelling, right?
Didn't seem too intense.
So I made her a little darker and I gave her this rumbling, raspy voice.
I booked the job.
And then I got in there and it's not that she had to yell.
But everyone she talked to, she was very intense.
It killed.
So I had no clue.
And I had offered a voice print that I couldn't really
sustain for four straight hours in this character
at that intensity.
So that's why the clues are so helpful.
Help us help you.
Had to be in there somewhere, right?
It was my line.
There's a misconception that...
Oh yeah, there it is. That is your line.
Pretend I didn't say that.
There's a misconception that soldiers have to have a dark, gruff voice print,
and that's not necessarily true, because soldier's an attitude.
Anybody can be a soldier.
But help your actors help you.
You know, tell the agents roughly how much shouting
is going to be needed for the session.
Because actors can have multiple sessions in a day
and this helps them schedule and manage their performances
so they bring you their A game every time.
It can also be helpful for agents and actors
to have a sense of how many sessions
you're going to need them for.
There's SAG rules and guidelines regarding vocal stress,
about a two hour maximum.
If you need more, break it up across sessions.
Mix it up with content that's not vocally stressful.
Save your most extreme stuff for the end,
at the end of the session.
If you have us scream and die by fire
and electrocution at the beginning,
by the time you want us to do that really connected scene,
we sound like frogs.
Listen to your actors and notice when they're breaking.
Monitoring their vocal stress
and offering breaks and relief builds trust.
It's a marathon, not a sprint.
So one really great tactic is to map out the percentage of your game, or at least of that
session that will be vocally stressful, and give the actors a heads up.
Hey, you're going to have 30% of your work today is going to be combat oriented, 10%
is going to be the highest intensity and some death screams, 10% is going to be whispered
intensity, and then this other 10% is going to be efforts.
That lets us know how to plan.
And then partway through, you've got this amount left.
We've got this many more lines before break.
And what that does is it lets us plan, like again,
the way you would do in a marathon with mile breakers.
It lets you know where you are.
If you start out sprinting by mile 21,
you're going to face plant.
In the studio, hire a good director and follow their lead.
Let them speak to the actor.
Give context when necessary, but just don't give line reads.
Give the subtext of the line as a shorthand.
But your actors don't tell you how to design the game,
don't tell them how to do their job either.
Try offering intention, relationship, emotional context,
and be willing to accept a read that's not the one that you're hearing in your head,
if it works for the moment.
Sometimes, they shout and you're like,
sorry this is more of a one-on-one conversation.
Also in the studio, be energetic.
If you can, we know you get tired, it's true,
but remember neural synchrony, that really cool brain science thing?
You don't want us to synchronize with your boredom and your exhaustion
because it's catching.
And also, even after all this time I've been doing this work,
if on the other side of the glass I see that you're like this
and you're completely done, I think I've screwed up.
Even at this point in my career, I'm really lucky that I've been doing this a while, but
I'm really still hoping that you guys like what I'm doing.
And if I think you're disconnected, I disconnect.
I get in my head, did I do that right?
And then I start flubbing lines.
So your collaboration is part of affective resonance.
If you're enthusiastic, I stay enthusiastic.
And if you can, tell your actors who they're playing opposite in scenes.
It's not required, you know, actors are professionals, but it really helps because they're a tight-knit
group and it can help the performance if they know who they're acting to.
So I had given Julie this little ghost child,
young girl ghost to play.
She's half of a set of twins who were going to be voiced
by two different actors.
Here's the in-game models for those two twin ghost girls.
You know how twins can be super close and in sync.
Well, that day in the studio,
all I had to do was tell Julie that her twin
was being played by one of her best friends, Kari Wahlgren.
And she knew exactly what to do.
I got so excited.
I know how Kari is going to handle it.
I know how I'm going to handle it.
Maybe I won't get every moment of her performance,
but because I can see the lines before and after
and envision one of my best friends,
and I'm in a unicorn onesie there,
I can make it more real and more connected.
So, yeah, if you outsource your VO.
Yeah, if you outsource.
Put together an informational packet for your vendor.
You know, they've signed NDAs.
Put together scripts, reference materials,
summary documents, casting sides
with vocal performance notes for creature process voices
because they don't have that information.
It's in your head.
Give it to them so that they can do the job.
What are our takeaways?
So we've learned a lot.
Here's our summary of what we've learned.
Prep work is the key.
Putting in that extra effort before you even get to the studio raises the quality and saves you a lot of time.
Everyone's an artist.
We all want the game to sound great.
So, let's do this together.
Give enough information, but you don't have to give too much
So last thing I want to leave you with a tool. Is Sarah Elmaleh in the room somewhere?
She is.
Oh there she is. This is a lovely woman. She's my friend. That's Sarah Elmaleh.
For fun, you should also know that she's the player character in Anthem.
Voice actors like each other.
So
so I've just joined a team that's called SWOT and
specialized workshops and actor tactics.
And you can write down the website address,
because you might want it.
This is a group that was begun by Sarah Elmaleh, Jennifer
Hale, and Cissy Jones.
And the idea is to create a free service.
And I will say that again.
This is a free service.
to help give developers the opportunity to collaborate with professional voice actors
while your material is still at the pre-casting stage.
So we offer two-hour sessions for table reads or even performance capture, virtually or
in person.
So even if you're out of the country, we can do this virtually.
And we will help you workshop your game.
The idea here is to raise the level of content, community, and collaboration.
You can't record us while we're doing this, but you get union actors breathing a little
bit of life into your words before you're even casting.
And yes, if you need maybe just one more session for each project, you get another two-hour
session.
So I'm excited about this because it's sort of the embodiment of what we're talking about
today, the idea of wanting to collaborate together.
This group is ready to do that.
So if you have questions, Sarah is here.
I have some cards, some SWAT cards here.
You're welcome to approach me afterwards, and we'll be happy to talk to you about it.
And so will Sarah.
She's nodding and raising her hand.
Adorably, actually.
Thank you very much.
And if you have more questions, we'll be happy to answer them.
Please make sure to review this talk at the survey link in your email.
Yes, and as all Uber drivers, just say, you know,
you really like the music that we played and that we didn't crash the car.