Hi, I'm Henry Allen and at GDC 2017 I'll be your speaker for EA Presents Interact, Next
Generation Multi-Character Interactions.
I'll be sharing the tools we use at EA to allow content creators to author various types
of interactions that happen in our games.
Building a gang tackle interaction for Madden Football will show our data-driven tools for
defining interactions and their associated animations, controlling how and when the interactions
trigger in-game, and controlling how we align the characters involved.
We'll also discuss some details of how the system works and we'll share various features
and techniques that help us get the best quality and coverage we can from as few animations
as possible.
Thanks for watching and I hope to see you at EA Presents Interact, next generation multi-character
interactions.