Hello. Thank you for coming to my talk, Don't Make My Job Easy, Effectively Pitching to Publishers.
As mentioned in my intro, my name is August Brown, and I want to chat a little bit today about pitching.
So first things first, a little bit about me. I have been in the industry for about 12 years,
but the vast, vast, vast majority of that
has been working in indie publishing.
And most of that work has been in production,
but through my very start in publishing up to today,
I've been heavily involved in sourcing
and evaluating games and chatting with devs.
And through that work,
I have personally reviewed thousands and thousands
of pitches and chatted with hundreds and hundreds of devs
about mobile games, PC games,
basically any kind of game out there.
And my hope
is that using all that knowledge and knowing,
most importantly, like what gets me jazzed
and what gets me excited about pitches
can be useful information for you all.
And in this talk, I want to kind of recontextualize a little bit how we talk about pitching.
And that is in most blog posts and GDC talks and for Twitter threads and whatever,
there's always this focus on content. You got to have your pitch deck, you got to have your budget,
you got to have your et cetera, et cetera. And all that stuff is super important. Those pitching
materials, you won't get your game signed without them.
But I do think you will get your game rejected a lot of the time before those even come into play before anyone opens your budget they'll made a decision that they don't want to sign your game.
So I want to focus a little bit more on how we present information, rather than getting into the nitty gritty of what information to include in a pitch.
And to do this, I want to look at the pitch kind of as a whole as a sales funnel.
And if you don't know what that means, that's super cool.
We're going to chat about that in a couple of minutes.
And finally, I want to share some real-life examples.
I want to pull back the curtain a little bit.
show you a couple of games that got pitched to Armour Game Studios that we ended up signing,
kind of how they laid out information and most importantly I think is like what it looks like
on the other side when a publisher gets excited about a game and how we react to good pitches.
So kind of taking a little step back, I want to talk about that conventional wisdom I mentioned
a little bit ago and that is,
all the posts and everything about pitching for the most part comes from publishers.
And I know I'm super guilty of working for a publisher too, but I think it's super important
to realize that there are kind of inherent biases that come from that point of view when we talk
about pitches because the very natural thing for us to do is to give advice that makes our job easier.
We have business intelligence suites or spreadsheets or something where when we get your pitch,
we're going to plug in the budget.
We're going to plug in where you're from for tax purposes, and we're going to plug in when
you're going to launch.
And all these things go into some spreadsheet or something.
And so a lot of the information that people get from publishers tends to be like, what
can you do to make my job as efficient as possible at plugging all this information
in?
and other, our other advi
like, oh, it's really anno
do this, I'm going to adv
I want to steer a little
because while that is a v
to giving information and
you put together a fair like objective pitch,
you shouldn't be fair.
There are thousands of desk pitching games
and it's super competitive
and anything you can do to get your pitch
kind of resonating with a few more people,
you should try to do it.
So to talk about this, I want to conceptualize it through this lens of a sales funnel.
And to get everyone up to speed on what maybe a sales funnel is or isn't, I want to play a little
mind game for just a second and just pretend you no longer work in games.
And instead, you own a pet shop. And your goal in this pet shop is to sell puppies.
And in order to sell puppies, there are a few steps you need everyone to go through first.
First, someone needs to know your shop.
If they don't know your pet shop exists,
they can't buy anything from you.
They need to enter your shop physically.
They need to find a pet they want,
and finally, they need to purchase it.
If you look at this list,
there are a couple of really important things about it.
One is every step is dependent on the steps above it.
No one can purchase a pet if they never walk in the front door.
No one can find a pet that they really
want if they don't know your shop exists.
And at every step there are going to be a few people who like notice your shop and keep walking or someone who are like, oh, I really want this dog and then they see the price tag like, oh, I actually don't want this dog.
And this is where we get to the sales funnel. So this is just kind of a visual representation of this phenomena where at every step, some number of people check out, and there isn't anyone else coming in outside of this like at step three they have to go through all the steps.
And so to kind of conceptualize different ways that sales funnel might interact with different approaches, let's look at scenario A, where we have our pet shop and our approach is we're putting the biggest sign we can out there that says we're selling puppies for $7,500.
And scenario B, where we have the same pet shop, but instead we put the biggest window out we can with the cutest puppy out in front.
And this is where we get to the fact that not every sales funnel looks the same.
Some approaches you're going to have just as many people knowing that your business exists,
but then it's just going to shrink the hell up because I don't want to spend $7,000 on a puppy.
Conversely, you're going to have just as many people at the top know that your shop exists,
but they're like, oh, that's a cute dog. I'm going to go see what that dog's business is
all about. And they walk in your door and your funnel's a lot bigger. And this will come back
in a little bit. And all this is important because pitching, like everything in this
capitalist hellscape we're in, is some form of marketing. That's just a very, very specific form
of marketing, which is you are marketing yourselves and your potential game to publishers for funding.
And in doing that, it kind of follows the same steps
where the publisher will receive your pitch,
to play your demo, to distribute the game
to the team for evaluation.
They might take a few meetings internally or with you
as the dev to kind of see what your business is
and ask some questions.
They might run some projections on the game.
And finally, they might send you a publishing offer.
But it's actually incredibly more granular than that,
even if you look at just that first step of receiving
the pitch.
And in this example, I'm talking about email pitches
where you might email a pitch back to a publisher.
Just for simplicity, all of the examples will be assuming that.
But this applies to a meeting you might take,
or sending out a meeting invite, or anything in between.
All of this logic still applies.
So in receiving the pitch deck, the first thing they're going to do is look at the email subject
and make some snap decision of what they think about that game's description in that subject.
And then they're going to scan the email for visual elements, and then they might,
if they like what they see, click on a video and then scan to a random spot in that video and watch
for a few seconds to see if they like what they see. And they might look at some email text,
and then finally they might open your pitch deck.
and scan that to see if anything jumps out at them.
And then if you go through a thousand more
of these little micro steps,
someday you might get a publishing offer.
And so if this looks familiar, it's because it is.
It is the exact same thing as the pet shop.
This is a sales funnel and all the same rules apply.
you can't get someone to open your pitch deck if they archive the email at looking at your gifts,
which sucks. It happens. I think a lot of publishers try to give every game their fair shake,
and even if they don't archive your email, they might have made this internal decision of like,
oh, this game's not for me, and they might go on to open your pitch deck,
but essentially the game is already rejected at that point.
And there's no one who's going to jump in at step five. They have to get through all first
five steps before they get on to the later ones. And I think it's important to take one little
step back at this point and just talk about some unfortunate truths on just the fact of the matter
of what happens with publishers and how we evaluate games. And that is we get so many
pitches. We get thousands and thousands and thousands of pitches.
And we can't afford to spend hours and hours looking at every single pitch.
And what that means, and this sinks, most demos don't get downloaded, let alone played.
Decision will be made before we even look at the demo like, oh, this game isn't for us, we can pass on it.
And even beyond that.
a lot of decisions will be made whether or not we look at your pitch deck later.
Even before we open that pitch deck, we'll either be excited about your game or like,
this is probably a pass. And we might look through the pitch deck to see if there's anything in there
that might change our minds. But a lot of decisions have been made by that point.
And even if someone does watch a video, if you send a like 20 minute gameplay video,
I guarantee you almost no one is watching that. If you send a five hour gameplay video,
which we totally receive.
I guarantee you 0% of publishers watch those five hours.
And so you get 10 to 30 seconds of whatever you send that the publisher is going to realistically
watch. And those will be a random 10 to 30 seconds wherever they happen to scrub
through in the timeline on that video.
And this all just sucks.
It takes so much work to put together a pitch deck.
It takes so much work to put together a demo that's
ready to show to people.
It takes so much time to capture video and edit it.
And you don't get fairly rewarded with people's time
for doing all that work.
And that just sucks.
But if we were to watch every five-hour gameplay video or even every five-minute gameplay video
sent to us, that is literally all we would be doing and we couldn't effectively run a
publishing business. So while I admit this really sucks and it's not fair, it is just how things are.
And so I think we can go into this with that knowledge in mind
and kind of make some smart decisions on how we structure pitches.
And to do that, I think we have to talk about how decisions get made.
And this isn't talking about like how groups come together to form consensus.
This is just on a personal level.
Like, do I get excited about something?
Do I think something's a good idea or a bad idea?
Because at the end of the day, computers.
At least for now, don't process pitches.
Humans process pitches and humans have feelings and can be manipulated.
And I think that's super important to think about when we structure our pitches.
And to put context of this, I like to think about our thinky brains and our feely brains,
kind of these two different modes you might be in when you're making decisions.
And
it's important to know th
context, only one of thes
of your brain is really i
at a given time. If you a
analytical, logical mode
the numbers and like impa
are in thinking brain mod
is sitting in the passeng
And feeling brain conversely is a more emotional state
that we might be in when we're making decisions.
So to kind of talk about these different states,
let's first talk about thinky brain.
If I am in thinky brain mode and I receive a pitch
and I am going through and evaluating it,
My thinky brain is gonna be thinking about,
what is the potential audience size for this game?
Does this game team have the experience
needed to execute on it?
What are the marketing challenges?
Like, does the art look really like it would skew
to younger audiences,
but the game itself has some really heavy themes?
Is that gonna make a marketing heart?
Does the game fit within our budget
and does it fit within our launch calendar?
And are there other games launching in the same time period
that might pose kind of external risks to this game?
And if you, uh...
think about it as I go through this,
these are all very like logical approaches
to thinking about like what is the risk
versus reward on these things.
Conversely, feely brain,
feely brain just wants to have a good time.
Feely brain is only out there to get jazzed about stuff
or repulse, but we're mostly gonna be talking
about being jazzed about stuff
and really just doesn't care about anything else
other than like, hell yeah, this game rules.
So.
Thinking about the pet shop example earlier,
if your thinky brain is in the driver's seat,
typically speaking, that funnel is just gonna be
a lot more narrow because our thinky brain
is gonna be able to like, ah, that budget's a little high.
I don't think it's a fit.
Oh man, there are like two other games
that are kind of similar.
I don't think this one's a good match.
And it's very easy for thinki-brain
to disqualify a game.
Conversely, feeli-brain just gets excited.
And it's easy for feeli-brain kind of at that point
to let kind of your heart lead the decision-making process.
And like, oh, man, budget's a little high.
Doesn't matter.
This game rules.
I want to work on it.
So.
From those examples, you see, like, I feel very strongly that everything your pitch should be
optimized so that feely brain can just do its thing and get jazzed about your game.
And this starts from the very beginning of having an evocative email subject. We get so many pitches
that just are like, oh, pitch for Armor Game Studios or new game for pitching. And it's
accurate, but like, that's not going to get me jazzed. And.
An email subject will never be the end of it.
You'll never get your game effectively signed
from the subject.
But what it does do is it puts my brain
into kind of this curious mode.
If there's like, ooh, I don't know what that means,
I want to know more.
It kind of primes the pump for my feely brain to take over.
Right from the get-go, putting the absolute best gifts
you can right at the top of this email,
or your...
presentation if you're giving it live or whatever, just like hit them hard out of the gate.
There is no merit in burying the lead. The best looking thing you can do and put out there, put
it right at the top. And very short descriptions that get right at your unique selling point.
What makes your game unique in one or two sentences? A very important thing to know
about Feeling Brain is it doesn't like to read. And so if you throw too many words at it,
it's going to check out and Thinking Brain is going to take over.
And this applies to kind of burying links to important things because
feely brain still wants to check out your demo.
It still wants to check out your video, but
it needs to be able to find it. So if you have those links just like buried in a paragraph,
it's going to be kind of easy to check out. But if you just have it like super clear cut,
like this is where the video is, Feely Brain can keep doing its thing. And that's really it.
There are like obviously a ton of little bits of nuance to this, but at the end of the day,
just put the raddest shit at top and everything else will kind of go from there. And so
kind of as I mentioned be
way or reason why I think
about it this way is that
your deck and your demo and all your other materials don't have to do as much heavy lifting.
If think you bring were at the wheel, they would have to do all the lifting of like, yep,
this budget makes monetary sense. And this is a reasonable timeline for this game to be executed
on. But there's just a little more grace when you're feeling brain is driving. And finally,
and I think this is so important is your pitch.
The goal shouldn't be to get your game signed
because that doesn't happen.
No one just like sees a pitch and like sends you a check.
What happens is we need to go through
like different negotiations and different whatever.
And like it's way down the line.
What your pitch should do is get one person
at the publisher, super jazzed about your game
and want to champion it and be excited about it.
And so as I mentioned at the top, to kind of look over how this happens,
we're going to look at a couple of case studies of real games
that Armor Game Studios signed, how they organize their pitches
and a little bit of reactions from our private Slack.
So the first game I want to chat about is the charter ski.
It's a super rad game coming out later this summer.
Jumping right out of the gates.
Its email subject was nothing that is going to set the world on fire,
admittedly, but it did.
It wasn't.
This is a pitch for our game studios.
And there was a vocative.
I don't know what a horror mystery game really means.
That sounds kind of interesting.
PS1 style?
I've seen some games that kind of do that,
but that sounds kind of neat.
I'll check this out.
It puts me in that curious mode.
And then the body has this really short
and sweet literal description about the game.
And then they just hit us with this gif,
which is this room that's beautifully rendered
in this PS1 style with all these demonic runes everywhere
and blood splattered on the walls and floor.
and the main character talking about how fucked up it is.
And we'll chat about this in a second,
but it just came out of the gates like,
this is the game's identity and this is what we're about.
And secondly, just as I mentioned previously,
it just really clearly laid out like,
hey, you wanna check out the video
or you wanna check out the vertical slice,
here's a couple of links
so you don't have to worry about too much reading.
So at 1137 AM the day we received this email,
we got the email in,
within the same minute,
I pop into Slack in our eval channel and say,
hey, this game looks kind of interesting,
but it's not really my jam.
And I don't think it'll really be our jam,
but it looks kind of neat.
And immediately our director of games, Dora,
jumps in with yo and capital yo's
and just the excitement instantly goes from there.
and jump forward 25 minutes.
She's spamming all caps.
She's talking about how great the demo is.
The demo takes 20 minutes to play.
This happened 25 minutes after we received the email.
We had already played through the demo.
And my attitude towards the game went from like,
I'm not so sure about this, to being like, man,
I want to get on this train.
Dora's excited.
Now I'm excited.
And so things that the Charters Key did really well is it knew who it was and it knew that it
didn't have to hit with anyone. They could have just showed like a kind of generic hallway in
that graphic style and not worried about like all the blood and cursing, but like that's what the
game is. And so they would have seen that eventually if they played the demo anyway,
so they just hit us with that out of the game.
They front loaded all the really good feely brain stuff,
like the GIF and everything,
so that we didn't have to worry about thinking about budget
before we got excited about the game.
And then kind of harking back to before,
it just takes big swings.
It knows what the game's identity is,
and it knows that somewhere out there
will resonate with it, which it did.
And secondly, we're going to chat a little bit
about a game called Islands.
First off, here are a couple of quotes
I'd like to share with you.
First, metroidvanias are always gonna be a saturated market.
It feels like every metroidvania
is gonna be facing an uphill climb right now,
and I'm not sure what separates this one from the pack.
This is a very competent game,
but I have no idea what would make me excited
to sign a metroidvania.
These are all quotes by me.
These are all real things I said that are forever enshrined in our
kind of spreadsheet type stuff of where we chat about games that we're evaluating.
And these are all real opinions I had.
I was, I love Metroidvanias.
I play them all the time on my own time, but they're, it's kind of hard market.
And I didn't know what would make me excited about it.
And time after time again, I'm like,
I'll just never fall in love with a Metroidvania.
That's fine.
And then came Islands.
Uh, right from the beginning, the email subject.
Again, we're not running for a checkbook after seeing this, but
uh, what does surprisingly wholesome mean?
That's kind of weird. I want to know more about that.
Metroidvania, okay, I get that.
I'm like, what's a puzzle piece map?
How does a puzzle piece map work in a Metroidvania?
Again, I'm not going to sign the game right now, but I am curious as hell.
and then ignoring text or anything else.
the game jumps right or sorry,
the email jumped right out of the gates
with just two absolutely gorgeous gifts of this game
in this hand painted kind of Studio Ghibli style
with these super cute evocative characters
jumping around this bright colorful world.
And it took me five seconds to open this email
and see these gifts and be like, fuck yes, I love this.
I wanna love this game.
And then as I mentioned, like everything else was just like,
here's a cute little quote about the game.
And here's like really straightforward links if you want to know more.
So for this one at 1023, we received the email from the developer.
In the next minute, I am chatting a lot about this game
and talking about how gorgeous and wonderful it looks.
One minute later, people are trying to change the topic to some other games that we're evaluating,
and I won't let them, because all I want to do is talk about eyelets.
And 15 minutes later, we have the eyelets emoji in Armor Games Slack, and I will spam that emoji
to my co-workers consistently over the next week until they all agree to sign this game.
And so that's what building a champion looks like.
And I had not looked through the pitch deck all that much
at that point.
I already knew I loved this game,
and I was going to fight for it.
And so what did Islets do well?
It has absolutely gorgeous art.
Sorry.
And I knew it, and it put it right up front in the email.
It had that really evocative subject line that kind of hinted at little interesting questions
that I just wanted to be curious about. It had a 60 second trailer and every second of that trailer
was magic. There was no point where I could jump to and like, oh this looks a little boring or
something. No matter where I randomly scroll to in that trailer, that game looked rad as hell.
And it didn't try to do too much.
It included the budget.
It included the demo, which ruled,
and included all these things that
are necessary for us to eventually make our decision.
But it didn't front load those.
And honestly, if it didn't include a budget, there is no reality where I would have gotten
this excited and be like, oh, you didn't include a budget. I guess we're not going to sign this one.
I would have just emailed the dev immediately and demanded that budget
because I wanted to work on this game.
And enthusiasm is infectious.
And this is why it's all so important,
is I got so jazzed about this game,
and it took a very small amount of time for my co-workers
to similarly start spamming our eyelids emojis whenever
we're talking about games.
And it just spread, and then we eventually signed the game.
And so in conclusion, a couple of things
I want to wrap up with is front load your pitch.
Don't try to bury the lead.
Don't try to be cute.
Don't try to be like, ah, this is the final enemy.
I don't want to reveal it.
If that's the coolest thing in your game,
show it right out of the gates.
And this doesn't apply just to pitching to publishers.
This certainly doesn't apply just to email pitches.
This is if you're looking for grants,
if you're pitching to different funds,
if you're looking to build a Steam page,
any kind of marketing, I think this logic all applies.
Don't go too broad.
Don't say like, oh, I think this aspect of the game,
even though it's core to its identity,
might turn off some people, so we're gonna play it safe.
That might be how you get through
thinky brain a little further,
but that's not how you're gonna hook
feely brains with people.
You're gonna build your champions
by putting what your game is out there,
owning it, and hoping you find like-minded people.
And most publishers won't have your champion,
and that's fine, and that's just the reality of it.
There are hundreds and hundreds of publishers out there.
And chances are, if your game actually like,
you have kind of that heart in it and you put it out there,
there's a good chance there's someone at some publishers
just waiting to be your champion.
And when you think you have your pitch done,
go through point by point and say like,
nope, I don't need this sentence to be this long.
I don't need this thing to be this long.
Feely brain isn't gonna like that.
and put the stuff up a higher like no, this gives a little juicier.
We're going to put that up and we're going to put all these things below.
And whatever you can do just to make sure that feel
your brain can take the steering wheel from the get go.
And that's it. Thank you so much.
Hello. I really, really love this talk. A lot of the things you were mentioning was how important it is to get publishers even like into a state of like fast thinking rather than slow thinking.
Yeah.
Is there any, you know, is there any further reading that one could do to like start, you know, just learning sales or what anything you'd recommend to just, you know, be able to get a better salesman, I guess, is the main thing about this.
Yeah, I think
Nothing is jumping to mind too much for me. I don't know. I like paradox of choice kind of
gets into this is talking about like how people make decisions and how people make choices.
And that's been kind of fundamental in how I think about this stuff. But besides that,
I think you can just search out like.
marketing more generally rather than searching out specifically information on pitching.
Just any information out there and talks on marketing will apply to pitching correctly.
Thank you very much.
Hi, thanks so much for this talk. I think I speak for everyone when I say that it's just amazing to hear the other side of the table, to understand how these conversations can happen when you send something out there in the dark.
I was curious, actually, two questions. I'll try to make them brief. Question one, do you think that the way of thinking about this diverges greatly from an indie publisher to a larger publisher? And question number two,
if there's a developer out there looking for somewhat of a larger budget, have you seen more
kind of indie publishers carrying a title up to a certain level that then gets taken up by a larger
publisher? How do you think about that? So for your first question, I haven't worked at a AAA
publisher, so I can't tell you, but this applies. And there have been a lot of really good talks
from other folks. Nick, I'm blanking on his last name right now.
think from Xbox or something gave a talk a few years ago about finding champions and whatnot. And so whether you're pitching to
like a small publisher or a large publisher or you're pitching to Nintendo trying to get some co-marketing or Xbox or
whatever it is at the end of the day we're all humans and you're going to get people excited by finding those champions and
kind of hitting those emotional points. So I think it applies to basically anyone you're pitching anything to.
And for your second question, I don't think I totally follow.
I think typically, co-publishing in general
still is fairly rare, if that's what you're describing.
Yeah.
Often, there will be other funds or other things
that a publisher might be up to working.
I know like with.
you know, Canon Media Fund and like lots of other government funds.
But with other publishers, it just gets pretty muddy and I don't think it's super common.
I'll ask you about it on LinkedIn sometime.
Thanks so much.
Sounds great.
Hi, thank you very much for the talk.
It was very informative.
And you're absolutely right about everything you said,
that time is limited and so on, right?
But have you guys considered actually
like the other side of the coin?
And while we, as in the developers,
should be better at pitching,
What are your ways of getting better at your job?
Sorry for being cheeky, but you know, discarding games just by the fact that they don't have a screenshot.
You might be missing out on quite a lot.
Um, I think
There's a chance we're missing out on stuff, but honestly, I don't think so.
Because like, if a game doesn't show well to us, how are we going to market
that to a larger audience?
Because your indie developer doesn't have to be as good at marketing as you are.
And that's what he's looking for.
Yeah, that totally makes sense.
And I think like we look through at least at Armor Games.
I can't speak for everyone.
We look through every pitch and we look through.
We don't like just archive emails instantly and we respond
to every single pitch we receive.
And I think a lot of publishers are trying to do that.
So it's not that it's literally rejected.
It's just like you get those 20 seconds or whatever.
And it's just, I think a part of humanity
that like either this person is getting excited
about your game or they aren't.
And if they're not getting excited about their game
it's gonna be really hard to get signed.
Gotcha.
Yeah, thank you.