everybody. My name is Akash. Before we get into stuff we're
actually going to play a trailer of hyper light drifter just to
make sure everything is on the same page. One thing I want to
remind you of or a couple of things I want to remind you of
before we get started, turn off cell phones and noise makers and
all that sort of stuff especially for an audio talk
that would kind of ruin the audio.
point of this if we hear your sweet metal gear codec ring
tone during this. Keep that on quiet. Also fill out those
surveys that you'll get in your e-mail after the fact when the
CA scanned you in. You'll get a survey in your inbox about how
did you like this talk. And you're going to rate us the
highest possible because you're going to love this. It's going
to be the best. So let's play a trailer of Hyperlite and then
we'll get going. Looks good. Whoa. Whoa. Whoa. Whoa. Whoa.
Oh no. Hold up.
All right. Thank you. Goodbye. Yeah. That's Hyperlight Drifter.
So a little bit about us. My name is Rich Freeland. I make
sound and music for media under the name Disasterpiece. I've
been doing that for about 11 years. And...
I'm a sound designer working in games for about five or six or so like that.
Rich and I actually went to school together.
I met him by asking someone random in the hallway, like, where's the video game music
club at the school?
And it happened to be this guy.
So.
And Akash was a metal drummer, right?
I was a metal drummer.
He had hair down to like his feet.
Yeah, like super long hair and a giant beard.
And for the only straight edge person at a music school, I was always asked for drugs.
It was a treat. It was just a treat. So I got on to this
project literally just kind of in a funny way. So I already
knew Rich already when the kick starter had already begun. It
already got funded by the point I kind of got in touch with
Alex Preston, the creative director. And I e-mailed Alex
and Rich and said, like, do you need a sound designer? I'll do
good. I'll be good. And Rich thankfully vouched for me. And
you said, yeah, he'll be good.
who do you know i don't think it'll do a good job that's kind of right to be
he'll be alright okay okay
uh... so that was kind of at the end of the conversation it kind of blossomed
out of that just me sending a couple quick emails to rich and alex
thanks to you that all panned out but how did
and to get on
so i had a friend who uh... who does music as well for games and does game
development who is friend of alex the creative director and uh... i guess they
were talking about the project and uh... alex
knew that my friend knew me and so he wanted to get in touch with me through my friend. My
friend was happy to put us in touch but also a little sad I think that he didn't get to work on
the project. But this was like around the time of the kick starter. So that's kind of how it's
funny how just friends of friends of friends kind of. It's very meta.
So we're going to get into quite a bit in this talk.
We're going to talk about music, sound design, experimentation, and all sorts of little bits
of nitty gritty.
Of course we're going to leave plenty of time for questions at the end.
So please feel free to ask those at the very end and we will answer them to the best of
our ability.
But let's start with the music.
Yes, so I wanted to talk about some of the initial experiments with music.
So the first thing I wanted to show was the very first thing that I wrote for this game.
Kind of the thing that, you know, after kind of seeing footage of the game and kind of talking to Alex briefly about what the game was about.
Kind of the first, you know, initial sketch idea. So let's play that.
Outro
I guess Alex kinda like this one and it it pretty much ended up in the game and
a version that's pretty close to this
and it was a good just kind of initial step to kind of you know this is just
just seeing sting and thinking about the world like I wanted to do something that
was kind of
uh... deep and dark and and kinda had little uh...
i don't know kind of ambiguous details and uh... so that was a good place to
start
uh...
you know after that we kinda tried to do some experiments i had this idea where i
wanted to run the entire
soundtrack through uh...
through cassette
a cassette deck to give it like a more of an analog sound
but uh... doing that actually
it like makes the
speed of the recording fluctuate
And so if you're trying to do dynamic music in a game where you have multiple layers of music that are
moving through different
scenarios and are meant to stay in sync with each other, if you're using a cassette, if you're running music through a cassette deck,
you'll lose kind of the sync, the synchronization of the layers that all get like fall out of phase.
So I had to scratch that idea. It didn't really make sense.
Okay, and then, so in the beginning of the project, you know, I was writing,
something that I like to do is sit at the piano and come up with lots of different ideas
and just kind of try to let the project inspire me and see what comes out.
And it doesn't necessarily mean that the music that I write is going to be music that we use,
but it's a good place to start and kind of helps open the dialogue between me and Alex,
who's the creative director and had a, you know, had a pretty strong vision.
So.
I want to play for you kind of the original theme that I came up with for the game that
I was really excited about.
This is like a rough piano recording.
Thanks for watching!
you
You kind of get the idea.
That was, you know, even though we didn't end up using that piece,
because it didn't, it wasn't quite right for any particular moment
in the project, and that happens quite a lot actually for me.
I'll write this kind of sweeping piece of music
that maybe encapsulates a lot of the ideas that I have
about what I want the aesthetics to be,
what kind of emotional things I'm trying to capture.
But from like a practical standpoint, there's nothing
that I can like very directly.
assign that music to. So in this case it kind of helped, don't worry about that right now,
but in that case that piece helped with...
kind of establishing certain adjectives and ideas about the music.
You know, I wanted the music to be
very dark, but also cinematic and have this sort of impressionistic
style, kind of inspired by impressionist music, composers like
Ravel and Debussy and Satie
and things like that. So
it was a good kind of just to get into the headspace and figure out, you know,
what is this going to sound like.
And then so the last kind of initial experiment I wanted to talk about is
I like to kind of experiment with the creative process and see if I can come up
with new ways of coming up with material.
And so
very early on in the process
Alex really wanted to do an arena mode and of course if you play the
game you probably know that there is an arena mode in the final
version that's based on waves where you kind of have a bunch of
enemies and then you clear.
Clear room and then another another wave comes and so we were kind of planning to do this music system
And I had a friend who gave me these cue cards these flash cards with all the different notes
of you know the chromatic scale and
I kind of came up with this system
where the bottom the bottom row of notes is like the bass and then you kind of you kind of draw like a
This is kind of hard to explain
you kind of draw like a tetronimo, like starting at the bottom, going up and then over three,
and so the top four are like the right hand stuff, like uh...
like chords, and then the left, the one on the bottom on the left is the bass, and so
you have basically this idea of music that moves through every, basically moves through
every tonality, like every key, and then it kind of loops back around.
So this was kind of the starting point for this demo that I want to play, which is something
that I wrote for, it was a sketch for the arena mode very early on.
So this piece we didn't end up using, but it helped solidify
this idea of having up-tempo music in battle
sequences in the game.
So when you fight bosses, any sort of encounter
that feels like that.
this was in the game while we were developing it for a couple of months
and it was during kind of uh... convention season
where uh...
they were taking the game around the demo of the game to different conventions
and uh...
you know alex the creative director would be on the floor talking to people
showing the game and this music would be running in the background
and it was just like you know fifty second loop
and so he was hearing this music like probably six thousand times and uh...
he's just
he started he hated it
he really really hated it
And it's like, so I tried to stick it back in
towards the end of the game.
And he's like, what are you doing?
No, you can't, you can't do this.
I can, I have this extreme negative reaction to the song.
So it never, even though it's one of my favorite ideas,
we never used it.
That's funny.
All right. So let's talk a little bit about how the sound
design also worked as well. So I already gave a talk at GDC
Europe about some of this stuff. So I want to make sure not to
retread the same ground. But there's some stuff I'd like to
mention for those of you who are new. So for this game, we did a
lot of experimentation on both ends. But for sound design, I
decided to go with weird tech to get a lot of the sounds to sound
kind of distorted and crunchy and kind of nightmarish. Almost
like some sort of Evangelion ish.
awful neon nightmare sort of thing. So one of the first
things that I went to was a wire recorder which is a 1950s
recording device which I'll show you in just a second. It
records on to this thin metal filament. It looks almost like
fishing wire. It's before tape, before vinyl, all that sort of
stuff. It creates this really crazy distorted sound when you
record directly on to this metal wire.
and when I got this thing it came with a whole bunch of recordings from the 1950s when this
thing was built. So you could hear recordings of people playing the piano.
little girl learning a song for the first time, people listening
to the radio, people talking about their experiences during
World War II. I digitized all of it. So it's like a lot of cool
historical sounds on this thing. So best $250 eBay purchase I've
ever had. I also made a microphone out of a stethoscope,
which is the most normal thing I'm sure all of you have heard
of. So now that no one is confused, let's move on. No, in
all seriousness, I basically used that to record a whole
bunch of sounds I couldn't get otherwise. So things like quiet
machines, like fridges and freezers and
my own blood, which I'm going to show you worked out as kind of an ambience near the
end of the game.
And I eventually ended up deciding to use samples over synthesizers.
Not entirely.
There were plenty of synths, like Massive and stuff, built into a lot of the layers
of the sounds I ended up using.
but the reason I decided to sample and record stuff using this wire recorder or my stethoscope
microphone or just field recorder or whatever mics I had handy was because it allowed me
to have the sounds grounded a little bit in reality and then stylize out from there as
opposed to kind of grabbing things from the ether with a whole bunch of just pure synthesizers.
So that allowed me to make things sound really, really stylish, but a shotgun could still
sound like an otherworldly shotgun, for example.
I think that's cool too because the music is kind of like very sort of ambiguous. Yeah, and everything's trying to be like
kind of
otherworldly in some level even though some of the ideas are rooted in reality
but I think it's a good counterbalance to have the sound effects be more.
Everything kind of stuck out more as a result and
separated itself in a good way and also most every sound was created from scratch.
I barely used any library stuff. I maybe used a couple gunshots here and there as a
base
or a couple explosions here and there as a base but most everything I record from
scratch in my
one-bedroom apartment and just like had a carpet covered in sand
just doing footsteps and all that sort of stuff.
So that's kind of how the process went.
But I want to show you this wire recorder thing that I
mentioned earlier.
So this thing built in the 1950s.
And what I want to show you real quick is just a quick
video of what this thing actually sounds like.
So I'm going to play you a quick video of just a
recording of some piano music that came onto this thing.
So that song was probably like brand new at the time.
Which is crazy.
All the distortion and artifacts and stuff you heard
of like it slowing down and speeding up,
that wasn't like the microphone freaking out or anything.
That's what it sounds like when you record onto metal wire.
The craziest part is that it can snap in half.
That wire snaps all the time.
And the instruction manual even goes like,
it's gonna break.
It tells you that it's going to break.
And when it snaps, like if you're close,
it'll cut you, it'll cut you good.
And I'm serious.
You have any scars?
I don't have scars, but I've been cut on my hands a good amount.
And you have to physically take it and tie the metal filament back together.
I don't know if any of you have tried to tie metal back together like a shoelace.
It's really hard.
I'm glad this thing is deprecated and obsolete, but man, it gave a cool sound.
So I'm going to show you some examples later.
But next up is this everyday normal looking device.
Is that a stethoscope attached to a regular microphone?
Absolutely it is, sir.
Okay.
ingenuity. So what I did was buy a cheap stethoscope off of Amazon for like five bucks. I think
this was actually, yeah, five bucks-ish. I cut off the little ear hole thingy, so it's
just a straight tube basically. And then looped that through a garden hose spigot, because
why not, and then taped it, taped the hell out of it.
to a very cheap small diaphragm condenser microphone. So then the signal of the stethoscope
goes direct into that microphone. And I can record regular everyday things like blood
or the conversations on the other sides of windows. You know, just regular everyday stuff.
Whatever I felt like that day. So what I'm about to play you is a recording of my own
blood basically. So what I did was just hold it up to my wrist.
and just let to get really personal. It's gonna get real.
And all I did was take that blood recording, pitch it down and add
distortion to it and this ended up being a part of the ambience that was
in the last boss battle. This kind of low rumble.
For those who've played it and beaten it, you've all listened to my blood.
I'll never look at you the same way.
I may have some health issues that I need to get checked out.
But the cool thing is that a stethoscope has two sides to it,
which I didn't know before I bought one.
So the larger flat side is a low frequency capturing ability.
It has the ability to capture lower frequencies.
And you can turn it around to the bell, which you're seeing
facing upwards there.
And that captures higher frequencies.
So you can choose getting your breath or your heartbeat
and just turn it around that way.
So it's like a contact mic that you can play around with.
It's great.
it's pretty neat i'm i'm a big fan of it
okay so we're gonna talk about establishing style and getting
creative direction
So how we use creative direction on this project,
you know, we kind of had to feel out the dynamics of,
I feel like you have to feel out the dynamics
of a relationship when you go into a project,
figure out, you know, who's kind of the go-to person
or is it more democratic when it comes to, you know,
the creative direction of a project.
And so in my experience, everyone tends to fall
on some sort of scale when it comes to how they like to,
uh... you know
uh... direct a project kind of ranging from hey you can do whatever you want
or to like you know uber control freak uh...
uh... like an uber-auteur. An auteur is kind of a phrase that
I think fits well. An auteur is like someone, you know, usually a filmmaker
who has a very singular vision about what they want and everyone's ideas kind
of get funneled into them.
And so uh... Alex, the creative director,
in this case I would call him a friendly auteur
because he has a very singular vision but he's also malleable to external
ideas and so he was he was really uh... pleasant to work with.
Yeah, and he was the first artist director I've ever worked with, which is a treat, honestly.
So he could use a lot of emotional words and give a lot of good feedback, kind of from
his background, and it worked really, really freaking well.
I liked it a lot.
There was no micromanaging happening, which was much appreciated, but he had opinions
ready to kind of help both of us when either of us were stuck or maybe not hitting it as
much as we could.
I hit like version 40 on some of those sound effects, so.
there were times where his opinion was extremely helpful to
get things all kind of settled away. So we kind of crossed the
streams a little bit throughout this whole project. There are
some musical sound design elements and some sound designy
musical elements that came across all throughout the
project. And they just kind of popped up naturally. We never
really discussed, like, oh, I'm going to do a musical sound
design thing here or you're going to do some sound designy
musical thing there.
It's very natural, whatever kind of came up that we saw needed some work.
So basically what I'd like to play for you is if you've played it, there's a sound that
happens whenever you pick up a module, and I decided to make it kind of a fun musical
fanfare that isn't too positive, because this game is kind of dark.
Nothing could sound too happy.
Initially, though, it was kind of a, oh, let's make this sound kind of Zelda-ish.
But if I went that far, then things did not work out well.
We didn't want too much happiness.
in this game.
So...
It's like, you did it, but it's still a pretty dark world.
So don't get too happy.
Here's a moment of happiness for you, and back to it.
Yeah, and then on the music front, you know in my in my process of making music
especially early on you know we were kind of concepting ideas for areas of the game that maybe didn't have any sound design yet or
You know maybe Kosh put kind of a placeholder ambience there, and maybe it wasn't exactly what I wanted to explore so we kind of
we kind of set out to explore things separately on some occasions.
And so, I wanted to play some sounds. This first sound is for
the birds that live in the northern region of the game.
They're kind of like cultish and I wanted to create this kind of like
menacing
sound of birds swarming and use that as like a texture in the
music.
So this is what that sounds like.
It's so cool.
Is it menacing?
Very.
So yeah, I mean, we use that in the music.
And down the line, we actually ended up
kind of isolating some of these and using them
as like straight ambience as well.
The next thing I wanted to play was two versions of a track.
and the end of a track.
Just to show that like a lot of the music in the game,
I'm kind of thinking about like the,
kind of the surroundings that the music is being used for
and like, you know, are there,
would there be animals in this environment?
You know, what is the air sound like there?
You're kind of thinking of music as sound design
and thinking of, you know, what are sort of the,
what are some of the things that I can achieve with the music that will help to establish the ambience.
And so this piece that I'm going to play is for a section of in the eastern region of the world
where it's kind of this like, it's like a water, outdoor water temple.
It's, there's like running water everywhere.
Yeah, so I'll play like the music, the end of the song with everything
and then I'll play kind of the isolated.
So there's like wind in there and hoots, like hooting sounds, like ambiguous animal sounds.
So I'll play the isolated version now so you can hear them better.
So just in general, I was trying to think of music as mimicking the reality of the world.
And that wasn't just for animal sounds and wind or whatever.
It was also for creating kind of depth of atmosphere in some of the deeper regions.
So when you go underground, a lot of times you hear this drum that's really big and kind
of far away.
It sounds like this.
So I use that same sound like almost everywhere.
I tried to play that out of my laptop speakers
and nothing came out, it's so deep.
Yeah, and it actually, I found that it worked really well
in just kind of establishing like,
there's something like really far away
from where you are right now that's happening,
or just something to create this sense
of like really big, deep space.
And I feel like that helped a lot.
And then there are other sounds kind of of that ilk
that do similar things, like I had this kind of like,
this very far away like kind of electrical sound that I would use
from time to time to kind of give the same impression and that sounds like
this
it's a it's kinda subtle
But in right moments, it kind of comes out of the mix a little bit and just helps to
establish the environment there.
And this other thing that I would do a lot is I would build these synth patches to use
to play chords and melodies and things like that.
But then I would like experiment with the sound because I have all these effects on
the sounds.
If I go up like six octaves and try to play it, you get all these weird like aliasing
effects and stuff that I wasn't expecting.
And so I use that a lot to kind of create kind of just weird, weird sounds.
So this is a little shrill, so prepare yourselves.
That wasn't too bad.
Yeah.
So there are some kind of more iconic sounds in this game so we're gonna talk
about some of those and Rich, your stinger is probably the most
well-known. I can't take all the credit for this because Alex and I
had this process where
at some point I was struggling a little bit to find the sound of this game
and so we just started a Dropbox folder where I just threw like
tons and tons of piano sketches into it.
There are probably like 100, 150 sketches in there.
And him and I would just listen to them and talk about it and take notes.
And he found this like,
he found this like three chord thing in one of the sketches.
And he's like, this should be the theme.
And I was like, you're right, this is perfect.
So this is what it was.
This is the piano version.
So we felt like it kind of did a lot.
It was very evocative in a very short period of time.
So that was something that we could probably latch onto.
And so, you know, that turned into,
the first time that we got to use it
was when we did the second trailer.
So this is that in the context of the trailer.
Press it again.
So it kind of worked, I think.
Yeah, a little bit, yeah.
And it's funny because talking about trailers,
you know, the kind of the aesthetic and timbre of the theme
kind of came out of working on the trailer.
And I have a lot of mixed feelings
about working on trailers.
I kind of prefer to work on the thing itself
as opposed to getting caught up.
in trailers, because sometimes it can take weeks to get the trailer right and it's very meticulous.
But in this case, for this game, it was so important.
Like this trailer and the final trailer, which has piano in it,
those were really important in kind of helping us to understand
what it is, sonically, that we're trying to achieve with this game.
All right. So next up is some of the weapon sounds. And I spent probably the most amount
of time on making the weapon sound as cool as humanly possible. So to do that, I did
a technique that basically all sound design uses, and that's called layering. So every
time you hear any sort of sound effect in most any game or movie or any piece of media,
every single sound is made up of multiple things playing at the same time. And the sound
I'm about to play for you here is the diamond shotgun.
And what that is is made up of nine different layers
for each and every shot that you pull.
And there's two different versions of this,
but I'm just gonna isolate one version for you.
So in this video, this is just a video of me in Logic Pro,
which is the software I used
for all the sound design in this game.
And basically I just walk you through each layer
to see what they sound like individually.
And then at the very end,
you'll hear how they all come together.
And you might be wondering how I recorded all of this stuff.
A lot of it is the result of that wire recorder,
and that's how I could get kind of such strange,
artifact-y, kind of distorted sounds.
So this will walk you through every layer,
and then all together at the end.
It's a little bassier in here.
It's like a flutter echo, wow.
Yeah, that delay is not actually a part of the effect.
So if you're like, boom, boom, boom, boom, boom,
that's not a part of it.
That's just the script.
So that's how I approached basically every single sound
effect from the footsteps all the way to the weapon sounds
to the monsters and everything in between is made up of
sometimes as much as 20 different layers of sound.
So every single weapon you hear,
and that's kind of the trick in a way
to make things sound unique or iconic
or special to that world,
is building it up of different elements
that on their own can sound like they fit
within that world, in this case like Hyper Light,
but all together sound like its own cool, unique thing.
And next up is the kind of monster effects.
So I've talked about this a little before, but this is Hal.
He's the final boss of the game.
This is an older animation, but it's a cool gif, so I
thought I'd throw it in here.
So for all the monster sounds, except for the wolves, you're
hearing my angelic voice being super processed.
So all of the monster deaths and roars and all that sort of
stuff, all them screaming is.
What sad soul did you ask to do the wolf voice?
I just had her wolf recording.
I have a pack of my own anyway.
I just recorded them.
They're my friends.
Just curious.
Yeah, yeah.
You know, normal things.
So for this HAL character here, I needed this to sound completely different.
from every other monster in the game.
It needed to sound horrific.
Alex Preston, the director, kept saying,
it could sound really terrifying.
I wanna sound scared when I hear this.
So what I did was squeal like a pig into a microphone
and then process the hell out of it.
What?
So what I'm gonna play for you is my raw voice,
which will sound awful,
screaming like a pig into a microphone,
and then the processed version.
You're gonna do it live?
No.
Oh, come on.
I actually thought I would.
I was like, oh, maybe I should,
and then I realized how much it hurts to do this.
It's so painful.
I'm not a voice actor by any means,
but it was good for monster effect.
So here's the raw version of me screaming like a pig.
Raw!
So that's me.
This is pro stuff right here.
This is the real art.
So now next up what I did was record that directly into my wire recorder,
then put it back into Logic Pro and to do that there's no output on that thing.
They didn't have those back then.
So what I did was just shove a microphone up against the speaker
and then record it directly back into Logic Pro like it's an amp.
and then what I did was take that sound that you just heard
and time stretch it, reverb it, bit crush the hell out of it
and add some reverb and this is the result.
Yeah.
So yes, all the monsters start from this seed,
but thanks to the magic of old and new technology,
it starts to sound a lot more unique
and a part of this world.
They all started from that one sound?
Every single one.
I'm just kidding.
So have you guys noticed these things
and what they sound like?
Anybody?
Okay, so this, so the sound of Hyperlite
was something that Alex and I started talking about.
I think it was just a random idea that I had,
and he's like, yeah, that's cool, we should try that.
So this is what those things sound like.
Oh.
Oh, man.
Go back?
Mission Conquered!
So this is just like a subtle thing that we decided to do to kind of like, you know,
what is the sound of hyperlight? Does it have a sound?
And you know, there are these like, there are these little modules and stuff
and pink stuff like in corners of like most of the rooms in the world.
And so, you know, we made the sound and the sound is singular.
So no matter how many of those objects that you have in a room,
you just hear the one sound, which I thought was kind of like a cool thing.
I'm assuming almost nobody notices, but that's okay.
It's a nice touch.
Oh, this is me.
So, ambiences.
This is a funny thing.
We kind of...
Akash set off in the sound design world
and had his hands pretty full with figuring out these sounds.
And I kind of set off in the music world doing music.
And I was doing a little bit of ambience, like,
as part of the music at times, but not always.
And at some point, towards the end of development,
we kind of realized, like,
we should probably have some ambiences in this game. That would probably help a lot.
And it made a huge difference. And so basically,
I was like, hey, gosh, is it cool if I just like start making
ambiences? Because I didn't want to step on your feet.
He was like, cool, go for it. So I just started making ambiences for the game
and I actually hired an intern whose name is Curtis Mitchell
who helped me.
And he just kind of did a lot of foundational work for me and then I would come in and we'd kind of do the right effects to the sounds.
We'd do like spotting sessions where we'd play and be like, oh this needs a sound, this needs a sound.
And we did not use bitcrushers.
Actually there's no bitcrushing in the music or the ambience.
And there's a ton of bitcrushing in the sound effects.
Which is something that we, I think, just...
kind of happened out of luck and helped to create, I think, a good contrast between the
sounds and the music.
It helps with the communication level of the sounds.
So we did a lot of iteration on this whole sort of process in this game.
They're basically, for me at least, nothing was really right on the first try.
I think only one sound, which was the rail gun, is still at version 1 and I wish I took
a screenshot of this, but Alex said, I want to marry this sound.
It's like, yes!
Yes. But everything else hit version 2 and above. Again, some...
I can hear that sound in my head.
Yeah, yes, awesome.
So, yeah, so a lot of things took a good amount of time
and a good amount of iteration to really get right.
Sorry.
I don't know what you're saying.
Yeah, so the West music was something
that went through a lot of iteration.
There were multiple versions of things.
It kind of reached this point in the project
where I thought, you know, maybe I should like,
maybe I should write everything at the piano
and like figure out the entire,
these long like five, six minute songs
and then notate them.
And maybe that will help me.
And that was like, that was the wrong,
totally the wrong decision.
That didn't help at all.
It was a total waste of time.
But we kind of over time figured out that oh, yeah
The music should probably be like these shorter pieces
But have a lot of different variations of it so that the music can react
Very quickly and we were also somewhat limited technically by the software that we used which we'll talk about a little bit later
And so, you know, that was a really important thing.
And then another really important thing was this idea of kind of reappropriating my own ideas from the past.
And this is something that I always bring to projects.
I have a huge database of just musical ideas from the very beginning that I started writing music.
And so, you know, I'll often like go back and find an idea from like six years ago that's like,
oh yeah, this might work for this particular thing.
And then I'll dress it up so that it fits the project.
And a lot of times when I'm stuck or just looking to mix
it up, that helps a lot.
And did, oh, I think we forgot to use that.
No, that's all right.
OK, so let me just skip over that.
Actually, no, I'll just mention it real quick.
There's this funny thing.
It's called Teddy Dieffenbach, who's a
programmer on HyperLite.
He put this secret sound effect in the
game called Shack Jack.
Which confused the hell out of me when I found it.
So when you're editing, when you're using the game editor,
it was kind of like, maybe there's a 1% chance that when you hit the save button,
you'd hear Teddy going,
Shackjack!
when I discovered SND underscore shack jack and the game maker
thing I was like what is this? I didn't put this here. I can't
believe I forgot to put this in the talk but basically the I
just messing around with the sound one day and I was like
wow if you pitch this down and start to mess with it like
granular effects and stuff it kind of sounds like the boss.
So actually when you in the boss room when you first open the
door you hear Teddy going.
Jack. It works really well. I think it works pretty well. So
we stuck that in there. Thanks, Teddy, wherever you are. Okay.
All right, so what I did, well, kind of how we kind of
started to get better and better at working on stuff
is just through trying and trying again.
Again, like not for me at least,
nothing was really right on the first try
except for that one railgun sound.
So Alex was really, really good at using
super descriptive emotional words,
which for sound designers is super freaking rad.
I really, really like using that.
If someone says make this sound lonely
or make this sound desolate or whatever it may be,
I'm a huge, huge fan of that.
So, for example, one of the sounds that we created was this kind of frog enemy dying.
So I'm going to play you version one.
So that's a frog dying, being stabbed.
Ouch. Ouch.
But not ouch enough, Rich.
So what Alex said was something along the lines of like,
I want this to sound like agonizing.
I want us to feel kind of sad
or just kind of disgusted a little bit when this thing dies.
So again, using my beautiful angelic voice,
this is what ended up being the end frog death sound.
So just.
that thing didn't want to die but it did
uh...
that's gnarly uh...
And then on the music side of getting better, Alex and I had many, many very long philosophical
discussions about the music and kind of what he was looking for and what my agenda was.
And that was something that was really nice about Alex is that he had a very strong vision
for what he wanted, but he was also willing for us to have these discussions about kind
of how I saw the project and what I was bringing to the table.
And we often found the right solution to things by just having these really long conversations
and talking it out and kind of finding our common ground and reaching.
Like the better I understood what his vision was, the more it informed my vision and I
kind of allowed him to influence me and I think it was kind of, you know, a two-way
street in that regard.
And so, you know, one thing that we kind of figured out, you know, Alex wanted a lot of
melody in the game and I didn't really want any melody.
I wanted it to be really subtle because...
For me as an artist, I'm very cognizant of not wanting to do the same thing over.
And so, you know, coming from like, to me this was in some ways a spiritual successor for me to the work I did on Fez.
But Fez is very like melodic, and so I wanted to do something that was much more kind of understated in that regard.
But we kind of reached this compromise where you know for and it's not really a compromise because I agree with it now
But basically for like bosses and vistas which are these moments where you know you might see
Titan like a big big dead robot way in the distance
We'd have the music kind of sweep sweep up and kind of get kind of cinematic and have some kind of melody
And everything else is kind of more subtle, so I think it helps to build kind of this contrast and this kind of dynamism in the music.
And then also in that same regard, you know, one of the things I took from Fez was that we used ambience a lot to create space
and to give the player a chance to breathe between areas and things like that.
So there are a lot of moments in the game where there's no music, it's just ambience, just to kind of like...
give the player a beat, give the player a moment to kind of catch their breath
and things like that. Kind of play the game, kind of get a feel for what the
the momentum of the game is, the rhythm of the game basically
and kind of see, you know, where can I kind of push
the emotions, where can I help the player like relax a little bit, especially in a
game like this that's so demanding and can get really kind of
frustrating. It was important to have, to try to
inject some moments where the player could maybe feel a little bit more relaxed.
So we worked remotely, Rich and I.
You were in Berkeley at the moment?
I was in Berkeley at the time.
And I was in Seattle.
So we were remote while everyone else was at Glitch City in LA.
And Slack was the best.
Slack was everything.
It was literally everything.
It was such a huge help.
We used Asana as well to kind of track bugs,
but it was not the best.
Everyone used Asana, really.
I don't really like Asana, but we did use it to track bugs.
Yeah, I use it to track a few assets here and there, but
really I just made a Google spreadsheet, and that's kind of
the best way to do it.
And at least on my end, Alex and I had weekly calls to work
stuff out, even if we had nothing to update one another
on, we made sure to get on Skype or on the phone.
hey, how are you doing? Good? Cool. Anything this week? Nah.
All right. See ya. Even if it was that, that was really
helpful to make sure as working remotely that I wasn't forgotten
or that I didn't forget them to keep working on whatever was
needed. And it was really helpful in case an enemy got
caught or a huge feature got caught or something got added. I
was made sure to stay in the loop because in the early days
of this project we didn't have that set up and that kind of
led to some stuff like, oh, I'm finished this sound for this
thing. Doesn't exist anymore.
Oh.
It was similar for me for a long time, just having periodic calls, which were really helpful.
But towards, at some point I, you know, the game was made in Los Angeles and that's not
that far, so I was like, you know, I should just go there more often and hang out and
get to know the team.
And...
It'll be, you know, I think it'll be good. So I started doing that. I started going for weeks at a time
and staying at Alex's house, sleeping on his couch.
And, you know, I got to go to meetings with the team and, you know, hang out with the team
and kind of get to know them. But I still kind of isolated myself so that I could focus
because it's hard to write music in like a co-working space.
It can be tough when there's no like designated area for you.
But it was good for morale, I think, and it was good for being on the same page.
And I think having closer relationships with the people that you work with just kind of
it boosts accountability for me personally.
And it makes me want to do a good job even more.
Yeah.
So a lot of people asked me and probably you as well, like, how did we kind of work together
to get things done?
And we didn't.
So in all honesty.
So we didn't.
We didn't do this intentionally, we're not like,
oh, I hate you, Rich, let's never talk again.
What kind of happened is that we talked
at the very beginning of the project
when I was brought on on a Skype call,
laid some things out here and there
that I don't even remember,
and then throughout the rest of the three-year project,
we maybe chatted three or four times.
Yeah, very infrequently.
If it wasn't for Alex, it was kind of like a triangle,
like he was kind of, you know, he was funneling both of us.
If it wasn't for him, I mean,
we might have ended up with totally.
Totally different. Yeah, unrelated work. Yeah, and looking back. We should have
More would have been good. I think I think there was something where the maybe the
Whatever our connection was just wasn't quite gelling or something because yeah
Yeah, but I don't know
So we used GameMaker for getting all of our sounds and music into the game, which was a little bit of a challenge.
Yeah, we didn't intentionally use GameMaker, but GameMaker is the software that was used for the game.
And, you know, they were really helpful actually, and kind of...
iterating on GameMaker itself to give us the tools that we needed to do a good job.
And so they helped us with things like adding Ogvorbis support and doing things with like
adding more memory support for like streaming multiple streams of music and things like
that.
And, you know, we also had two programmers who were super helpful, extremely helpful
and wanted to, you know, do good by us.
And so...
Yeah, so we did a lot of mixing and things where music changes over time by using...
a script editor. This is a screenshot, an early screenshot of the editor.
It's kind of nuts. It's not ideal but you know it does the job and
it helped in the long run for everybody. So basically we had this visual
scripting language where you know we would place sounds, we would place
music in the world, there were little boom boxes which was kind of fun.
And you could attach them to different things like regions where...
the character, if the character walks into this region, you know, you do a thing with
the music, you fade it in, you fade it out, whatever. And also we had this, we had group,
a group system for the music, so, you know, you could have a bunch of different versions
of the same track that kind of crossfade between each other. And then we had things like, um,
Oh yeah, we did a lot of conditional music triggering.
So, based on the position of the player,
camera events, like special camera events,
like when you see the jackal,
if you know the jackal character.
Hands over.
Spoiler.
Enemy events, like if all the enemies are dead, do this,
or if one of the enemies is dead, do this.
Special events, et cetera.
You know, no middleware, it was all directly
in the editor with everybody else.
We were all kind of working in the same tool, which was.
interesting is interested in bad uh... and uh... we we actually want one last
thing that i want to say is that i had to rebuild the system uh... for
positional ambiences
so you know we were doing and uses for the game but the ambience is really
general and uses like winds that you hear everywhere
at some point i realize you know there are a lot of like these little sounds
like
like uh... torches like uh... lamps uh...
things that are like but the hyper light stuff that that that is all
positional so you know
he helped build this system where you could have sounds in the environment that you could
walk past and it would get louder, get quieter. It's not rocket science. It's been in games
for a long time. But it wasn't something that, I don't think it was something that GameMaker
really did. So we had to build it.
So this question I'm sure we'll get a lot just so we can cover it now.
For me on my end for software and sound design and all that sort of good stuff I use Logic
Pro.
Nowadays I use Nuendo and Reaper for all that sort of stuff.
But Logic Pro is great.
All the built in plugins are fantastic.
Lots of bit crushers, the built in bit crusher in Logic is what I used a lot of, and that
helped a ton, it was actually quite good.
And for synths and a lot of things like Massive and Complete, or AppSynth and all that sort
of stuff, I used Native Instruments Complete, it's a great sort of all in one package for
music and sound design software, I really, really liked it.
I also used Reverb a lot, that was my favorite effect and still is to this day, it's like
the fairy dust of the music and sound design world, just put more on and it'll be better.
But I use Audio Damage EOS, which is like the darkest, most beautiful sounding reverb
with an infinite setting, so I really like that.
Cool.
I use a lot of, I use Massive almost exclusively for the music.
It's just a synth that I'm really comfortable with.
And I wanted to do something different than what we did with Fez, so I very early on decided
I don't want to use any Bitcrushers at all.
So we kind of went for a more tape analog kind of sound.
And so I kind of played a lot, tried to play a lot with saturation and distortion.
And also baking things into the signal chain to kind of like...
You know, you can put reverb at the end of the signal chain on a sound and then it sounds like it's in a room.
But if you use it really early in the signal chain and you mess with the stereo imaging, like you can...
you can put a mono reverb on a sound and then you can bake things on top of that
and then it becomes a texture.
And so I try to use reverb a lot as a texture,
as a tool to kind of paint and create different textures for sounds.
And... Oh, we already said that.
I think me not using Bitcrushers and you using Bitcrushers
kind of helped the sound stand out.
So lastly before we finish up, we just have a few take aways
for you, just kind of lessons we learned on how to work with
us audio folk.
So the first thing is hire early, as early as you can.
And that's always a nice thing to have.
It is a little bit typical to see audio kind of brought in
at the very last moment.
And that's no good.
Having the ability to kind of fail upwards
with the rest of the team is always really appreciated
for all disciplines.
I always like to say that game development
is nothing but a whole bunch of people failing
until something happens.
So make sure that your audio people
also have that ability to fail and grow upwards
with the rest of the team.
I mean, this one I'm not sure I agree with, but it's okay.
It's all right, go for it.
I mean, have opinions ready, but don't micromanage.
I think that's nice if you're someone
who has strong opinions, but it's also okay
to be someone who, you know,
Zakay, I really like what you do,
and I want to see what your vision is for this project.
To bring someone in and have them self-direct is also okay.
But I think in general, micromanaging is something
that nobody really likes.
Yeah, agreed.
So like we mentioned, allow a lot of time for experimentation,
that failure and all that stuff, because you can get a lot of
weird results of letting that kind of time really cook and
bake and all that sort of stuff.
Especially if you're like, hey, Akash, here's a week where you
can just record some stuff.
I'm like, I'm going to build a stethoscope microphone.
So if you give enough time, that sort of
nonsense starts to happen.
And it can be for the better of the game.
And don't let don't let us work together. It's bad. It's a bit. No, just kidding. Oh, we should have talked more for sure
So that's it. Thank you so much for coming. We'll have some time for questions now
Yeah, we have time for a few questions if you have a question come to the mic in the center aisle, please
Come up to the mic
Hey, how's it going?
Hello.
So this is generally more towards the music side of
things, but it can definitely be used for both.
During your creative processes, I was curious if
you find yourself getting into any patterns, and you're
finding anything similar that you do in your ideas, and how
you work around that.
That's an interesting question. I think it's important to
acknowledge patterns and kind of lean into the ones that you
like and kind of try to work your way out of the ones that
you don't like. One of the things that I've always tried to
do is to iterate on the creative process itself. So if I find
that what I'm doing is stale, I'll try to go back to the
drawing board and be like, you know, maybe I should change the
actual way I'm writing. So.
if I'm writing at the piano, maybe I'll write at the guitar.
If I'm writing at the guitar, maybe I'll use flash cards like
I did or I'll use, I like to build generative music tools. I
try to have a lot of different options so that I can keep it
fresh. Cool. All right. Thanks. Yeah, sure. Yeah. Hi. I was
wondering, so with the shotgun you had nine separate sounds.
What was your process? They were all different.
I doubt you just randomly said hey here's nine sounds how does
that sound. How did you make that? Why did you decide that?
Good question. Basically how I decided for all the weapons
basically. Let's say it's a shotgun. I made sure to know
that okay my seat is a shotgun so I'm going to have some sort
of gun shot sort of layer in here at the very least. That's a
good starting point.
Then from there I know, okay, this is the diamond shotgun.
I should make this sound really crystalline.
What sorts of crystalline sounds can I get?
Cool, okay, so I'm gonna start recording like me.
I bought a belly dancer scarf for like a dollar
off of Amazon, Amazon's the best, for a dollar
and just shook it around and pitched it up.
So okay, there's a crystalline sound.
Now I want something that sounds kind of bassy and thuddy so it has some impact to it. What
sort of bassy thud could I get? And then I kind of go from high, middle and low frequencies
from there to see what I can fill out. That's usually how I approach this. Sometimes it
is like I'm going to put a tiger growl in here and see if it sounds good. There's a
lot of experimentation, especially when I'm stuck. But in general, I break things out
into frequency spectrum, kind of a seed that I'm starting with and then go from there.
Okay, thanks.
Yeah.
I have two questions now. With the shotgun you mentioned you
want to use all the frequency. Is that mainly because it's a
weapon or do you?
Do you want certain sounds to not occupy the whole range?
Yeah, so for example, I don't want the footsteps to occupy the whole range,
because that would drown out music.
Unless it's like a giant monster.
It's a huge monster or something very important.
Right.
So when it's something that I need to just sound like,
oh, that's cool or that's impactful, I feel powerful,
that's when I want to occupy not necessarily all,
but a good chunk of them, especially bass.
that's how I play with it. My question is in the project I'm
working on I'm fighting music with my room tones or ambience
like they kind of either don't go together like the music might
be happy but you're in a cave and maybe that's just a bad way
to do it.
you guys use effects like stereoization to keep things
separate? You have the bit crusher. For music and ambience
I think part of the reason I pushed for doing ambience is I
knew it would be easier for us. It would take less time if I did
both. When you're trying to make music and ambience fit together
I think it's important to treat ambience like an element in the mix of your music.
And so, you know, a thing that I tended to do with ambience is, like you said, you know,
do stereo stuff where you push the ambience really wide.
And also use, pretty much always would use high pass filter.
Okay.
Great.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Thanks.
Hey, thanks. I wanted to start by, Rich, you had said earlier
that you, I don't know if this was true of all of the
soundtrack, but you were talking about creating a music system
that would cycle through all of the different key signatures. So
my question is for Akash, in that case, when you're doing
musical sound effects, how do you make those not clash with a
constantly changing key signature?
remember asking you what keys to send. I don't know. Most of
the music is all over the place. Because it was all over the
place it never  I think we decided why don't you do what
you're going to do and we'll listen and if it works it works.
I think ultimately that's the most important thing is using
your ears. If it did clash when we put it in I would have
changed it. But when it came in it sounded totally fine so we
just left it. That's how it works.
you so much for coming. I'll be wandering around. Same chat and
all that.