Okay, good morning.
Hey.
I have two pieces of housekeeping to start with.
First, I need to remind you all to please
fill out your evaluations after the talk,
not 15 minutes before the end,
but you'll receive them then,
and yeah, then fill them out and do that thing.
And the second is to turn off your phones or put them on silence.
I've been told to say that, I would say that anyway because you should.
And right now I'm praying my phone is off or on silence.
I'm pretty sure it is. Pretty sure it is.
First, thank you all, so many of you, for coming this morning.
I know it is early and there are lots and lots of other brilliant talks you could be at.
It means, it genuinely means a lot to see you here.
I had a bet last night that there would be 13 people in the room and there's more than that.
Maybe there's 13 at Sid Meier's talk, I don't know.
Thanks also to GDC for inviting me. It is genuinely an honour to be here, it's an honour to be part of the conference.
It's an honour to be part of the advocacy track, which is always special and feels particularly important this year.
My name is Steve Curran, I'm a game designer. I do other things apart from games as well, but also I talk and that's why I'm here.
I don't know how many people in this room have seen me talk before.
I always feel like before I start I should kind of warn people a bit.
I don't want to disappoint anyone because life is short and the worst thing you can
do is waste time.
Double Tap is a story.
I mean, it's a bunch of stories, really.
It's arranged around thoughts on life and game design.
I write something like this every year,
present them around the world, these things,
at conferences, colleges, wherever I get invited.
This is actually my seventh piece.
It's about an hour long.
There is no downloadable PowerPoint.
There is no succinct, tweetable takeaway
on workflow pipelines.
You will not get any advice about shader techniques today.
Sorry.
There's no easy headline at the end of the talk to report back to your studio.
And there will not be a Q&A at the end either, though you can talk to me.
I'd love you to find me here or online.
I'd love to talk to you either Twitter, email, whatever.
One of the reasons, one of the main reasons I do these talks is to meet new people.
So please do that.
Double Tap was written in 2016.
Preparing for today meant revisiting words
that I had not seen in nearly a year.
And so much has changed since then.
And so much of that has changed for the worse.
The rise of the populist right feels like a nightmare.
I want to stop this tumbling dissent,
this asphyxiation of empathy.
And I don't feel like I can.
I am just one person.
And that's how I feel as a straight white male privilege incarnate.
I'm sure the way the world has changed has affected some of you out there
far more directly than it's affected me.
So I wanted to say at the start that I stand with all of you, my friends,
who fight as they have their rights stripped away,
with Muslims, people of colour, the LGBTQ community, with women.
I stand with anyone who feels targeted by power.
I love you.
and I will fight for you and I will look after you as much as I can.
That feels like a dumb, pointless thing to say.
Like, what does it actually mean?
It's just words.
What can I do?
Privileged or not, I am just one voice.
Not rich, not clever, not anything.
Just, you know, a snowflake.
But it is not pointless.
Words do matter.
Taking a stand matters.
At the very least, taking a stand means other people
feel like they can stand too.
Stand with you.
So I wanted to say this before we started.
I wrote Double Tap a year ago
as a collection of fragments around a theme.
And please, I want you to take whatever you want
from those fragments.
My intention at the start was to make you ask questions
about the games that we choose to make
and the games that we choose to play.
But there are other threads in the piece too,
and some of those feel more relevant now than ever.
Our lives are short, often much shorter than we expect or deserve.
And when we die, all of us, whoever we are,
rich, powerful, poor, privileged or not,
get to leave two things behind.
The first is our work, whatever that is,
and the second is the impact we have on other people.
That is how we are remembered and measured.
That is how future generations will remember and measure those in power
making spiteful, selfish decisions today.
And that is how you will be remembered and measured too.
So leave a positive effect on the world in everything you have,
everything you make, every conversation you have,
in every person you touch.
That is all we can do.
We can stand up.
That's what Double Tap means for me now,
and I hope you find some meaning in it too.
So
You
The most human I've ever felt inside a video game
was while I was lying face down in a bush doing nothing.
Tom Clancy's Ghost Recon was published 16 years ago, in 2001.
A third-person shooter developed by Clancy's own Red Storm Entertainment,
the player takes the role of the leader of a squad of ghosts.
This is a video game, but these are not fun, bright Pac-Man ghosts.
This is a Tom Clancy video game, and the ghosts here are gruff American soldiers,
so called because they are skilled enough to ghost through combat situations unseen.
Like all of Clancy's work, Ghost Recon is lead heavy with power fantasy and military
pornography, though its rhythm is more cautious, more thoughtful than arcade shooters like
Call of Duty.
This is the sort of game that requires patience, that takes guns seriously and demands that
you do the same.
This is the sort of game that feels like it belongs on a PC,
controlled by players whose hallow skin
seems permanently illuminated by centuries of monitor glow,
spines curved to accommodate keyboard and mouse gameplay,
dank caves echoing to military barks
issued over air traffic control headsets.
But 15 years ago, I was a console gamer,
and so I played the game with my friends on Xbox Live,
not long after Microsoft's service launched.
And it was an awkward fit, as ports often are.
Ghost Recon's keyboard controls,
digital inputs that let you issue binary pulses
to your character's nervous system
and communicate simple commands to your squad
are mapped across more than a dozen different buttons.
And, as fans of dumb internet arguments doubtless know,
controlling even the simplest shooter on a console
is very different to controlling one on a PC.
Aiming and firing with a mouse is so simple, as effortless as finding and double-clicking
on the Microsoft Excel icon after your first cup of coffee on a Monday morning.
But to aim a gun on a console, that's more challenging.
You push the crosshairs, you correct course, and you lock on.
Firing the gun, though, that's basically the same on both formats.
With a mouse, you press a button.
With a joypad, a trigger.
It's just a gentle squeeze.
or two, if you want to be absolutely sure.
Games are about cause and effect, input and output, call and response.
While most media does its best to entertain through instruction alone, tireless preachers
deliver in calculated, manipulative monologues just like this one.
Games are, or at the very least pretend to be, dialogues.
That is what makes us different.
That is our strength.
That's what game design is.
When designing a game, you are considering two things,
consciously or otherwise.
What are the questions that I want to ask the player?
And how will they answer those questions?
The questions that we ask, those are the shape of the game.
Can you save the princess?
Can you make that headshot?
But the player's experience is defined
by the limited answers they can give,
defined by the actions that we let them perform
inside our world.
We put words in their mouth,
so we have to choose those words so carefully,
and that is game design.
What are the answers we create for the player?
Which of those answers do we think they'll choose?
Which do we want them to choose?
And so on.
Those responses must be delivered by the player
to the game via an interface,
and that interface inevitably forms part of the answer too.
A first-person shooter controlled with a joypad
is one thing.
The same game controlled with a keyboard and mouse
is very, very different.
Neither is a perfect simulation.
The latter is more instinctive.
The former more interesting, I think.
Both give the impression of aiming,
but are not the same as aiming.
The way you fire on each format is a better match.
Just a gentle flex of the index finger.
So the player's experience is this.
Our answers to our questions,
and the manner in which they deliver those answers.
As designers, there aren't many ways we can solicit a response,
and so our choice often comes down to two things, analog or digital.
Analog or digital.
Analog systems measure the degree of input, the pressure, the direction,
the weight applied by the player.
Digital systems, they simply register a change of state.
A button can be on or off.
Analog systems offer nuance.
They let the player express caution in their answer.
They can edge towards a blind corner,
then change their mind.
Digital systems, they're useful for decisions.
When you play a video game, you are the captain of a vessel.
The system turns to you and says,
Captain, the button gives the yes or the no.
The button tells the system to fire.
There is no maybe.
If you want to feel something, demonstrate humanity,
which is often rooted in doubt and uncertainty.
Analog systems matter.
If you only want to do something,
you can think digitally.
You tap a button.
And in some systems, to show you are absolutely certain,
you double tap.
M02 Farm is a multiplayer map in Tom Clancy's Ghost Recon.
As the name suggests, the map is centered around a ruined farmhouse in clearing, surrounded
by what I remember to be dense jungle.
I might be misremembering.
The map takes place at night, and I never saw the jungle close up.
I didn't see much beyond the dirty white texture of a farmhouse wall
and a jagged pixel plane of some billboard bushes intersecting my soldiers' feet.
There were four of us on my team.
There was me, my friend Simon, my colleague Mark, and my boss, Xiao.
This was our first match together.
We sat in a 4v4 team deathmatch lobby
and we waited for the opposition slots to fill.
We made in-joke small talk, war movie cliches.
Mark, Mark would be the brains.
Simon, Simon would be the maverick.
João, he would be the tough love leader.
Cool under pressure, ready to take the heat.
I, I would be the first to die.
With a soft chime, the four empty slots for the other team filled up all at once.
Each new player's name had square brackets at the front.
What does that mean? I asked.
Nothing good, muttered Joe.
And we all chuckled, pleased with the Hollywood dialogue.
This was going to be great! Ha ha ha.
Yeah, but what does it mean though? asked Simon.
Mark the Brain spoke up.
They're from the same clan. It means they do this a lot.
It means they know what they're doing.
Oh dear, I said. Ha ha ha.
I remember the night that Xbox Live launched in the UK.
The only people were journalists like I was in 2001, or Microsoft employees, or players
who had applied to beta test, who'd understood what a beta test is.
We call those players the hardcore, an adjective that implies obsessive dedication and often
anti-social behaviour.
But the atmosphere that night was not aggressive or even competitive.
It was singing with joy and curiosity and friendship.
A thousand strangers on their first night on an internet cruise ship,
marvelling at the vessel, fumbling for the right etiquette.
Deathmatch is the first-person shooter term for a simple kill-or-be-killed multiplayer fight,
where death, as so often in video games, is an inconvenience.
It's a quick restart and on with the show.
Like lots of video game neologisms, we don't think about the etymology.
It's so universal that it's its own thing now, like the word video game itself.
From Masters of Doom, David Kushner's 2004 History of Id Software,
John Romero comments on the word's origin.
Sure, it was fun to shoot monsters, but ultimately they're soulless creatures controlled by a computer.
Now gamers could play against spontaneous human beings,
opponents who could think and strategize and scream.
We can kill each other!
If we can get this done, this is going to be the fucking coolest game
that the planet Earth has ever fucking seen in its entire history.
And he was right, I guess.
In a death match game of Unreal Championship
on the very first night of Xbox Live
inside a science fiction warehouse on an empty server,
I hopped and skipped and bounced around
until I stumbled upon a second player,
a low-poly space marine,
spinning and staring at the ceiling.
It seemed poor form to just, you know, shoot him.
So I called down from my position, high up on the scaffolded gantry.
Hello?
I offered cautiously.
Oh, hey there,
he said, turning his spacesuit, his body, his head, and his gun to face me.
He performed this kind of double hop.
and I read it as delight.
And then he ran off to another corner of the room,
and then he ran back again.
Sorry, he said.
I'm just trying to see the sun.
If it's there, I haven't found it yet.
I took a look at the roof above me,
nothing more than dull rivets and gunmetal panels,
and then I climbed down the ladder to join my new friend.
Hello again, I said.
I thought about offering my hand,
but it was attached to my gun, so I hopped instead.
What's the weather like up there, he asked,
twisting his whole body towards the gantry.
No sun either, I'm afraid, I said.
I love a good skybox, he said.
I love the feeling there's more in the world to explore,
even when there probably isn't.
I double-hopped in agreement and we both fell silent.
This is weird, isn't it? I said.
It is a bit, he replied. More silence, headset static.
It is a bit weird, he added.
We began to explore the level together.
In another room, god rays cut through precisely engineered rips
in a rusting metal ceiling,
cast our darting shadows as ballroom dancers
on the dirt texture floor.
But we still couldn't see the sun.
Eventually, we were back where we started.
The gentle conversation drifted to silence,
and we both knew that we had to bring this relationship to a close somehow.
So, he ventured, slowly twisting to face me, eyes dead as a mannequin, ugly heavy weapon
pointed squarely at my gut.
Should I, er, shoot you now?
The phrase double tap predates video games
and has an established meaning outside our weird parochial language.
It is not just a second press of X.
Developed by British police chiefs in Shanghai in the 30s,
the double tap is the practice of firing two shots
in quick succession into the same location.
It is an exercise in pragmatism,
the purpose being to ensure a target is functionally disabled.
For example, a person may, rolling the dice, survive a single shot to the head.
But to survive two is vanishingly unlikely.
So force those odds. Pull the trigger twice. Double tap.
In an online essay for NRA magazine, American Rifleman, entitled,
The Art of the Double Tap.
Writer Matt Lindler describes the practical difficulties of executing what in theory sounds
like a simple maneuver.
It takes time and ammunition to learn to rebound from recoil quickly enough to conduct a second
tap, writes Lindler.
Begin by quickly firing two aimed shots at a target with a safe background.
Continue until you can consistently put two shots within five inches of one another in
one to two seconds.
Under a subheading, why not a triple tap?
Lindler argues that a case can be made
for putting as many bullets as it takes into a bad guy.
The NRA often refer to their targets as bad guys.
Before arriving at the conclusion
that really, two shots should probably be enough.
These days, he laments,
you have to defend your actions to the world.
Language changes as we change, and Double Tap has taken on an even more sinister meaning in the last few years.
It describes the practice adopted by terrorists of a secondary attack in the same location as the first, designed to target first responders.
Abdelhamid Aboud, one of the ringleaders of the Paris attacks, returned to the Bataclan.
He stood outside as the emergency services struggled to deal with the unthinkable.
And then he ran.
Inside the theater, gunmen moved from body to body,
checking to see if their targets were still alive.
Double tap.
Games highlighted by Google in a search for Game of the Year 2015.
The Witcher, Bloodborne, Metal Gear Solid V, Until Dawn, Fallout 4, Rise of the Tomb Raider,
Arkham Knight, Halo 5, Splatoon, Call of Duty Black Ops 3, and Rocket League.
Downwell, a short, playful indie game from that same year, is described as delightful
and charming, and I do not disagree with that. It is kinetic, responsive, instinctive, stylish
and fun. But it is a game where your objective is to destroy everything you can, firing guns
from your feet as you fall down a well.
Blackroom, Romero's first-person shooter pitch,
describes itself on its abandoned Kickstarter page
as a return to vast, violent, and masterful play.
It promises that each weapon has a specific use
and does the damage that makes you feel good.
Gunsport is a bright, beautiful, smart take on volleyball
that is intelligently designed and so fun to play,
where you use sleek, expensive, sports-styled weaponry
to shoot a ball over a net and into a goal.
20 million people have played
the cartoon-style Team Fortress 2 on Steam,
collectively spending 1.4 billion hours
killing each other for fun.
A patch for GTA V still riding high in the sales charts nearly four years after release.
The fastest selling game of all time allows you to play it in VR and it looks like this.
Of the 50 best-selling video games in the UK in 2015,
41 of them involve some kind of shooting mechanic.
And of those 9 that are left, 8 of them are sports games.
The other one is Mortal Kombat.
It's a running joke in video games that lovable rogue Nathan Drake
is actually a mass murderer.
Your first action in Uncharted 2 is to kill some minimum wage security guards
who are trying to protect a national museum.
You will have triggered the death animations of around 800 more simulated people
by the time the credits roll.
Ha ha ha.
The night of the Paris shootings felt grimly familiar, viewed through the telescopic lens of the internet.
Like a bad dream, unreal, inescapable, closing your eyes and knowing what's about to happen
and praying that it's not.
A cold news ticker reads gunfire reported.
The absence of information is slowly shaded in with gruesome detail and there is nothing
you can do as your stomach drops, just gawk at the live blogs as the horror unfolds and
the numbers rise.
Keep watching as the body count climbs. You know that you're being ghoulish,
but you can hardly return to the game you were playing. Not now.
Many of my friends who make video games, the people who read when I write,
who listen when I talk, who come to events like this,
people like you, a young, empathic, anti-gun, outspoken.
And whenever there's another mass shooting in the US every other fucking day,
I see the ones who live there speak out.
Fuck the NRA.
The Second Amendment has to change.
America has a problem.
What will it take before we are compelled to do something about that?
The Europeans, they offer sympathy and words of advice.
They are horrified and relieved.
It's not our problem.
Just like when we hear gunfire televised from the Ukraine,
from Syria, from Palestine, from Iraq.
The day after Paris, I watched the same people
struggle to deal with bloodshed much closer to home.
There was so much sadness and anger and above all, a lack of comprehension.
How could anyone do this? How could anyone do this here?
That phrase thrown into the void with no expectation of an answer
because the question is drowning in thousands of years of politics and religion and history and hate.
But still, how could anyone do this?
How could anyone, anyone do this?
How could anyone switch off another human like a light?
How can you look at a gun and not feel revulsion
at a tool designed to do just that?
And then, slowly, the red mist of other people's blood fades.
and we drift back to our lives,
where we play and we write about and we promote and we create games,
so many of which fixate on and profit from those same tools.
The game began and our team spawned outside the farmhouse.
It was a nighttime map, pitch black.
Put on your night sights, commanded Xiao, you'll see better.
The grey and black world became a green and black world,
but that felt fancy and military.
Sure.
I scanned the jungle in the distance.
Can't see much, but they're out there.
I paused for dramatic effect.
Somewhere.
Then, from nowhere, gunfire.
move, get inside, shouted Joao,
and our group made a dash for the farmhouse entrance.
But there was no entrance,
or we couldn't find it at least,
perhaps because we had our night sights on
and everything was green and confusing.
So we kept running and we ended up
on the other side of the house,
crouching in different bushes.
Okay, said Simon, what now?
Joao changed his stance from prone to crouch walk.
I've got this, he said with comforting confidence.
The entrance is over here somewhere.
His words were abbreviated by two precise shots
from somewhere in the darkness.
And I watched his bright green body slump
into the shadows on the floor.
I don't know how this is going, right?
I have no idea how this is going.
I do not know what you're thinking.
I don't get to control that.
I do not have complete control over this situation.
I have some.
Here is a theory.
Life is a terrifying collision of a billion events
that are all out of your control.
From beginning to end, we are offered choices, decisions, questions, and the answers we give
have little to no bearing on the result.
You take the dream job and it makes you miserable.
You find the right guy, but you're the wrong girl.
You live a cautious life, and then you get hit by a stray bullet.
That unpredictability, that lack of foresight is important,
because if this thing was a movie, if we knew what was going to happen,
then we would sleep our way through it.
The question marks, they keep us awake.
The unknown is terrifying and confusing, but it is also thrilling.
We cannot see the future.
Except sometimes, sometimes, for a moment, we can.
There are brief, tiny moments in life where things feel wholly under our control,
where we get to decide what happens, and they are relief.
When I hit the light switch and I know that the light is going to turn on,
and then the light turns on,
for a microsecond, I am a prophet.
And the more complex and skillful that action,
the more weight and satisfaction the action carries.
The right key goes in the right lock, and it turns first time.
I change the batteries in the remote, and it works again.
If I can throw this ball of paper in that bin,
I will find true love.
Next time.
In each case, we imagine what happens, we make it happen,
and that makes us momentarily happy.
That we have managed not just to predict the future,
but engineer it.
We are gods, tiny gods who operate light switches.
Video games are that level of control, inconsequential satisfaction offered in a completely safe
environment.
We are asked a question, we supply an answer from the choices that were offered, we think
we know what's going to happen next, and then usually it does, over and over again.
Each action we perform has some kind of predictable consequence, and shooting is a perfect example
of that.
You aim, you see the future, you fire, and the enemy falls down.
But it's not the only example.
So why are we so fixated on firearms?
I mean, history plays a part, of course.
We've been killing things since space war
and every game prepares you for the next.
The performance side of firing a weapon matters too.
Players are actors, guns are the perfect prop,
the sound and the fury, the glamor, the forbidden cool.
Those things play the part, but I think the main reason is that shooting is such an easy,
understandable solution to challenge for us as designers.
It's a discrete action with a binary result that can be layered to alter difficulty.
You make a digital choice, touch a trigger, and after that you lose control.
The bullet continues towards a future that you can no longer alter, but one that you
have anticipated.
You're a tiny god.
Now, can you shoot two things?
What about four, but they're further away?
Don't worry, they're bad guys.
Fine, but the game designer's portrayal is, by necessity,
an idealized, sanitized sketch of a gun.
When we point and click,
when we respond to the violent, leading question
asked by the developer
with the only answer that they let us give,
yes and yes again.
The result is unemotional. A one or a zero.
As quick and effective as turning out a light.
There is no recoil beyond the spinning whir of our haptic feedback.
It is clean and it is satisfying.
A headshot is always an instant kill.
If the consequences of shooting a real gun were that kind, clinical, binary,
the double tap would not exist.
A bullet is not fictional, but physical.
A piece of metal, maybe the size of the tip of your little finger.
At the rear of the bullet is a primer, which when struck,
creates a small explosion.
That explosion ignites the propellant in the middle section of the bullet.
The propellant produces gas, which accelerates the bullet down the gun barrel.
As it leaves, it's traveling around 300 meters a second,
a speed so fast we can't register it as movement.
The result of firing a gun is effectively instantaneous to us.
Point, click, done.
We avoid detail.
We do not think about what actually happens
when a bullet strikes skin and bone.
We know this is not really an off switch, but it feels like one,
partly because of its treatment in media, Hollywood and our own,
and partly because of the speed at which it happens.
We want to feel the challenge.
We don't want to feel the horror.
So, slow it down. Slow it all the way down.
The bullet, which has no mind of its own and simply follows our instructions,
leaves the barrel of the gun and moves forward until it reaches something
that will provide resistance.
Perhaps that is a wall or perhaps that is the floor.
In this instance, it is a person.
On contact, the bullet punches through the skin in slow motion, millisecond by millisecond,
a tiny metal fist.
The skin gives way to tissue and the bullet continues pushing.
It strikes bone and only slows it down a fraction.
The bone, tough but brittle, cracks first and then it splinters.
The bullet pushes the shattered bone to the side and continues forward, cuts through more
tissue, tears through another layer of skin, out the other side.
Blood rushes into the hole and spills to the floor.
Someone cries out, or perhaps they can't speak
because their throat is full of blood and they are choking.
A producer at a major games publisher
shows me their World War II first-person shooter,
which begins with an epic opening
based on the Normandy landings.
Yeah, we wanted it to be as realistic as possible, they say.
We wanted you to feel what it was like to be there, the fear, the confusion, the chaos.
I notice there's no blood in your game, I say.
Yeah, that's a certification issue, they reply.
After Paris, I decided that, for a while at least, I would stop playing games about shooting.
I settled on this definition, games where any core mechanic sees the player firing a
projectile intended to cause damage.
That usually means guns, but is a wide enough definition to include missiles, arrows, lightning
bolts, fireball spells, tiny clusters of 2D pixels in side-scrollers and red shells loosed
from the front of your cart.
Most games are about shooting, it turns out.
It was a restrictive rule.
What did I discover apart from that?
Right from the start, it made me ask questions all of the time,
of the material and myself.
Was it guns I was objecting to or violence?
What about knives?
What about gun-laden stealth games that give you the option,
even encourage you, to finish them without ever shooting?
Would I play Mirror's Edge?
What about The Last of Us?
Would I still play Downwell?
And I found these answers as I went.
Knives are real.
So is knife violence.
But as my exploration was specifically about gun violence
and how that dominates the form,
I would not play Metal Gear Solid.
I would not play Metal Gear
because its questions are framed around guns,
even if a valid answer is to avoid them.
And I wouldn't play Mirror's Edge either,
though I completed the first one without firing a shot.
I stopped playing Danwell.
Those answers, and my frustration at trying to find games I could play, made me more sure
how I feel.
I am uncomfortable with games' part in how we perceive guns as a clean, clinical, digital
solution to a problem, and their fetishisation as shiny, beautiful collectibles or fast,
fun solutions.
My silent, or not so silent right now, protest was initially against that.
I don't want to be part of a system that I believe is playing a very real part in sanitising gun violence.
But I also started to wonder how our preoccupation with guns
affects the questions that game designers are asking.
Because again, that is what makes us different.
That is what games are, a story framed
by a series of questions then answered by the player.
And the only question we are asking time and time and time
again is this.
Can you predict where the object will
be in a fraction of a second?
Can you stop the bad guy who's in the way?
It will be clean, simple, I promise.
Point and click, maybe a splash of red,
maybe not even that.
The player, human and predictable,
optimistic and violent to the last,
returns the only answer we give them.
Yes.
Red Eye, Edge 129, November 2003.
On the evening of June 25, Aaron Hamill, a 45-year-old nurse from Knoxville, Tennessee,
was driving on the I-40 highway through nearby Newport.
His cousin Denise was in the passenger seat.
The pair were on their way back from a day out in the mountains.
We were driving down the interstate back from a great trip,
Denise later told ABC News.
My cousin said,
Hey, look at these flowers.
And then all of a sudden, through the window came a bullet.
The heat was so much I could feel it.
On my lap, I saw lots of glass and lots of blood.
I thought that I'd been shot.
But she hadn't.
The blood belonged to Aaron, her cousin,
the driver of a car now out of control,
traveling at 70 miles per hour against traffic.
Imagine that, covered in blood and glass and God knows what else,
in a speeding vehicle you have no way of stopping.
And when the car finally, fortunately, grinds to a stop against a guardrail,
imagine looking to the driver's seat
and seeing blood gushing from a wound in your cousin's temple.
Headshot. Instant kill.
On August 28th, 13-year-old Joshua Buckner
and his 16-year-old stepbrother William pled guilty
to the reckless homicide of Aaron Hamill.
Joshua had stolen two .22 caliber rifles
from his parents' closet the week before the shootings
and hidden them in the nearby woods.
On the evening of June 25th, the pair headed to a small hill
with a line of sight to the I-40.
Their intention was to shoot at the sides of passing trucks.
They were bored.
They'd been inspired by Grand Theft Auto.
Red Eye was a column that I wrote at Edge for four years,
the magazine's only voice under a style guide
that was pointedly poker-faced and anonymous.
The editorial staff were very close,
Mark, David, my editor Joao and I,
and I did my best to voice the thoughts
that I felt we couldn't express elsewhere in the magazine,
in theory.
Truthfully though, Redeye was my opportunity to show off and say things that might make people cross.
A little like today.
So, it was the early 2000s and games were under attack, as always.
It seemed to me that the industry's defence back then was largely to refer to the treatment
of heavy metal music or horror films from decades past.
I watched Friday the 13th as a kid, it didn't turn me into a serial killer,
it's just hysteria from old folk who don't understand our medium.
Dismiss it.
I didn't think this was right.
I believe in games because they are different from other forms.
I believe they can change people for better and for worse.
Those questions that they pose, the answers they suggest, force the player to change the
way they think.
And that is our medium's strength.
But that power works without conscience.
Anecdotal evidence.
I know games affect me.
I play Tetris all day.
If I play Tetris all day, I see blocks when I close my eyes.
And I know I'm not alone there.
That's like a phenomenon, right?
The Tetris effect, that's a known thing.
And when I play Grand Theft Auto all day,
if I spend eight hours stealing cars like it's nothing,
and then I go out into the real world,
and I walk past a car parked on my street in real life,
I can feel a tiny part of me, tiny part of me, want to try the lock.
And I'm not alone in that.
I hope I'm not alone in that.
So I wrote this piece for Edge, right?
The first part was a plea for the games industry to take the consequences of their actions
seriously and adopt a defence less digital than,
no, nothing we make can ever influence anyone, shut up.
Because why would I care about games if I thought that was true?
But there was a second target as well.
The kids who shot Aaron Hamill were not trying to kill him.
They weren't even trying to shoot people.
They were being reckless with a gun they'd stolen,
messing around on a hill, attempting
to hit the back of trucks as they sped down the freeway.
That was what they'd done in GTA.
And some part of them should have been screaming,
this is a terrible idea, had been worn away
by hours of pixel-perfect gunplay in a digital world.
It turns out that aiming in real life is more difficult than push correct on an analog stick,
and actions have more serious consequences.
I was tired, and I still am tired, of the way we position guns, tools explicitly designed
to switch off humans like light switches, as glamorous, cool, fun toys.
The way we smooth over the violence just enough to sell it.
And even more tired of the way we sell those games to children.
We know that high schoolers form a huge part of gaming's audience.
We knew it back then.
We know how seriously their parents took 18 ratings.
And we know that today, too.
And we didn't, and we still don't, fully understand
how games affect people.
But we choose to look the other way.
So Red Eye went to work.
Magazine covers are full-color adverts for an 18-rated product aimed directly at under-18s.
I wrote, Red Eye would be interested to hear Take-Two's defense against accusations
that it's been selling an adult experience to minors.
He wouldn't mind hearing UK magazine publishers doing the same thing,
since from where Red Eye is sitting,
there are an awful lot of people covered in Aaron Hamill's blood.
On page 22 of Edge 129,
I accused my employer of acting as an accessory to murder.
It was not a great career move.
Worse, apparently, was that I'd said the same of Take Two,
who were one of the company's main advertisers.
They called the magazine the same day, furious,
demanding an explanation.
Our publisher, who signed off the pages,
perhaps without reading them,
called our editor into the office.
And Joao, my boss, took responsibility for my words.
In the end, the whole magazine was collectively disciplined,
placed under the oversight of a new senior editor.
And within six months, we'd all left Edge.
Actions have consequences.
João's lifeless, khaki-mapped body fell to the floor,
and our team was without a leader.
The question the game was asking of us was clear.
What now?
But there was no one ready to answer.
Someone had to take control,
and it was the brain's mark who moved first.
Clear-spoken and assertive with faultless logic,
he made a decision.
Our enemy must be on the left side of the farmhouse,
so he would lead us to cover on the right.
He stood up.
Wait here, he said, edging around the building.
I'm going to check.
which left Simon and I alone.
Which left Simon and I alone, completely alone.
Last men standing, except not standing,
lying face down in some bushes.
I know there are people in this room
who are working on games that involve shooting.
I am not telling you to stop.
I've started shooting again now.
I can tell you about that later if we have time.
I know people like clear lessons from talks.
That's the way, right?
That's why I gave that warning at the start.
40 slides and then a summary telling you how to feel.
I like experiences that ask questions and let you answer them in your own way.
That's why I like video games.
But some questions are more complex than a trigger can answer.
So, I know and I believe.
I know games are obsessed with guns and the act of killing, specifically shooting.
You could claim that other parts of pop culture are as much at fault for glamorising firearms,
or at least argue that they have more history. But our form is different.
Only games let you fire the gun, feel the impact, the power, the pleasure.
Only games give you control, let you answer a leading question yourself.
And this is the hard bit. I believe that only games erode a little bit.
of the human part of us that should recoil in absolute horror at the idea of shooting
someone.
I know gaming can change people.
I have felt it change me.
I want to make games that change people for the better.
And I believe that you do too.
I believe gaming's obsession with guns is making the world worse, by inches or feet
or miles.
I don't know.
But even if I'm wrong...
I am certain, I know that the default recourse to firing projectiles is limiting games as
a form, limiting our audience and the stories that we tell.
I know that shooting is a fundamentally satisfying mechanic, but most of that comes from the
controller.
It comes from the way that maps to those singular moments of control, prophecy and execution.
And I believe that there are other mechanics out there as well.
Mechanics that can provide the same feedback, offer the same feedback to the player.
More interesting answers.
And I know that finding those answers is not easy.
Finding those mechanics is not easy either.
And it will limit your commercial opportunity.
I believe that Uncharted 4 would have been
a much better experience without shooting.
I know I'm not alone in that.
But the shooting sells, that's why it's there.
And shooting sells because we haven't taught
enough people yet that there are more to games than shooting.
And I know that earning money is important.
We all have to do that and sometimes that does come
at the cost of making the world a tiny bit worse.
What's another bullet in the infinite rain of digital gunfire?
Probably doesn't matter.
But I believe you can make a difference, all of you.
I believe it's worth taking a stand because then others stand with you.
So if you want to,
look at what you're doing.
Look at what you're playing, look at what you're making, look at the impact of your creative
choices, think about the questions you ask and the words you force players to repeat over and
over and over again. Think about how you produce analogue systems from digital inputs,
moments that don't just destroy humanity but amplify it.
Because I believe we can do better.
And I know that because I have seen glimpses of humanity in games.
And the most human I ever felt in a video game
was when I was lying face down in a bush,
holding a gun that I would never use,
searching for the right answer to an impossible question.
Simon and I are face down in the bushes and Hollywood, brave, beautiful, gun-happy Hollywood
writes the script from here.
This is a buddy picture, comedy and tragedy, the maverick and the rookie fighting near
blind against the odds, against a team of teenagers who know exactly what they're doing.
Likely the rest of the story runs like this.
Adrenaline kicks in.
We surprise ourselves with fast reactions,
animal instinct honed over a lifetime of shooting.
We fight back to a situation where maybe we might,
just might, beat the odds and win.
The gunfire is loud.
The body count is high.
It is still nothing like Uncharted's.
Near the end, one of us, almost certainly me,
gets shot, pop, pop.
delivers an inspirational monologue as we're dying, I'm dying.
The other one, almost certainly Simon, is the hero in a one-on-one fight against the
team's leader.
There is some bullet ballet, the boss drops, and we win.
For Joao, whispers Simon.
Credits roll.
But here's what actually happened.
Simon and I stayed exactly where we were,
face down in the bushes,
where we knew we were safe and we couldn't be seen.
And twice, I glimpsed someone from the other team
duck out of the jungle and then retreat.
I tracked them in my crosshairs, but I couldn't be sure I would make the shot, or even if
a single shot would be enough, because death is not always digital.
And besides, I knew the gunfire would attract attention, so why bother?
I took my finger off the trigger, and I didn't put it back.
And in those moments, Simon and I were human,
freed from a script that we'd been given,
vulnerable, blind to the future, aware death would come,
but enjoying the world while we could.
We made jokes, we talked about the game, the world,
considered plans we knew we would never execute.
We didn't know how to answer the game's questions.
We barely even knew how to stand up.
We lay there and we giggled under a bush for seven minutes,
and it was glorious.
I looked around and everything was beautiful.
I looked up, but I couldn't see the sun,
not even through my night sight.
Seven and a half minutes after the game started,
about seven minutes after Mark and Joao's deaths,
I heard footsteps.
Simon's prone form slowly span on the spot
as a luminous green ghost ran towards him.
he didn't have time to make any kind of speech.
And then the bad guy turned to face me.
Hello?
I said, hopefully.
Half a question, only one answer.
Double tap.
That's the end of it.
So...
I have...
I don't know how long do we have left?
Three minutes.
Okay.
Okay, I have an epilogue but I can tell you the epilogue in the wrap-up room, which is 2022, I think.
That's where I'll be going anyway.
Thank you all so much for coming and thank you for your patience.
Sorry about my voice, which went a little bit, but you all did very well.
Now we can all nap, I think.
See you later.