Hello everybody. I'm Chris Martins and this is Rogelio Cardona Rivera. We are both at
North Carolina State University and we're both really excited to be here to tell you
about some of the things that we've learned about as researchers.
We are both researchers at NC State.
I just started there as faculty in the fall,
and Rogelio is finishing up his PhD.
I do work on tools for rapid prototyping
of interactive stories,
and Rogelio does work on computational models
of how players think about interactive stories.
So this is our first GDC talk.
We are really excited.
We're kind of motivated by this idea that in,
academia, we have a whole lot of techniques that people have
explored and debated over the years.
And when I come to conferences like GDC, I talk to a lot of
people who are saying, I really want to create a
procedural story, and I have no idea how to get started.
So we're hoping that we can share with you some
interesting ideas and techniques that you may be
able to use in your designs.
A lot of academic work as well as a lot of early game
development work started by sort of being inspired by this idea
of the holodeck from Star Trek.
In other words, a simulated reality that affords not only
the experience, an immersive experience of a story that you
can enter and
take part in as a reader of sort of a script,
but also a reality in which you can take improvised actions
and have the system respond in a meaningful way
to those reactions.
In the early days, this was kind of realized
through some of the early adventure games
like the Hobbit DOS game from Beam Software in 1983.
And on the surface, adventure games like this
sort of seem to offer the promise of the holodeck,
sort of showing you these first person images
of spaces that you could inhabit
and narrating story around you
and allowing you to make some kind of choices.
And ultimately, these experiences centered a particular
kind of plot and progression.
They really wanted you to, in some sense,
follow the script of what the designer had in mind,
but they're not very permissive of the kind of spontaneity
and improvisation that people initially
sort of fantasy designed in the Star Trek holodeck.
More recently, people have been very excited about the idea
of emergent gameplay realized by games like Dwarf Fortress,
in which there's a rich simulation underlying
this game system and players can,
players and the artificial agents within the system
can very much improvise and have the system respond.
And then people perceive that there are narratives
that get overlaid on top of these experiences.
For example, many people like to post on Reddit
detailed descriptions of their narrative experiences
within Dwarf Fortress that they think are really compelling.
So this is sort of representative of the other end
of the spectrum in a sense.
These experiences are very permissive of player
and procedural spontaneity, but on the other hand,
there is no enforcement of sort of authored narrative arcs.
So just as a working definition for those of you
who may not have encountered the term procedural narrative
generation before, I'm including both of these things
under this umbrella term, and basically considering
any kind of automatic process
that creates a narrative over time.
where that narrative is not determined at the outset
before the process begins to be procedural narrative
generation.
So I've given a couple of examples,
and I'm listing a few more here, including
some that I think are a bit lesser known that I'm really
excited about as examples in procedural narrative
generation.
And I kind of have these loosely following a spectrum
of prioritizing agent spontaneity
to prioritizing authorial structure.
And largely what this talk is about is the challenge
in first of all introducing agent spontaneity
in the first place, this kind of improvisation
and simulation, but also how to balance it
with author structure.
So going forward, I'm going to show you just a simple example
that we can use to walk through a lot of the
terminology and ideas.
And then we're going to go through in detail a couple of
approaches, the simulation-centric approach and
the plot-centric approach that have been really thoroughly
explored in academic research.
And then Rogelio will talk about the plot-centric
approach, and he'll also conclude with some of the
ongoing challenges in procedural narrative
generation.
So the example that we're going to start with is an Aesop
fable, largely because Aesop fables tend to be relatively
simple and small and they can fit in a talk slide. So this is
the ant and the dove. So a dove saw an ant fall into a brook.
The ant struggled in vain to reach the bank and in pity the
dove dropped a blade of straw close beside it. Clinging to the
straw like a shipwrecked sailor to a broken spar, the ant
floated safely to shore.
Soon after, the ant saw a man getting ready to kill the dove with a stone.
But just as he cast the stone, the ant stung him in the heel so that the pain made him miss his aim,
and the startled dove flew to safety in a distant wood.
The moral is at the bottom, a kindness is never wasted.
When we start to think about how to introduce some kind of
generativity into the story, or interactivity, which ideas
are closely interrelated, one technique that underlies a lot
of, that opens up a lot of possibilities for
procedurality, is logical modeling.
So some kind of formal representation of who the
characters are, and what situations they're in, and how
those situations change across story events.
So if we first think about discretizing this story
into kind of a comic book form,
where we show different narrative situations in each panel,
we can start describing each situation
in a sort of formal, logical form.
So we can represent this first panel
where the ant is near the stream,
getting ready to fall into the stream,
as the ant being thirsty
and the ant being at the left shore.
The next panel.
as where the ant falls into the stream. We can represent that as at ant stream. And the dove is
above the stream and so on for the rest of the panels in kind of the first half of this story.
So that's our formal representation of a little example story. And now I'm going to go through
the simulation centric approach. So the basic idea with this is that you're going to design,
the author is going to design a bunch of characters and sort of world elements and
identities.
in terms of their personalities, desires and relationships to one another. Then give a
whole bunch of rules describing how these entities can interact with one another and
potentially change those properties. Then you kind of throw them into a world and press play
and see what they do. So you have your designer who is going to feed these interaction
rules and initial state into a story generator and then that whole thing kind of gets
packaged up and becomes an interactive narrative which then the player can interact with
in the usual way by.
submitting actions and receiving responses.
So we're gonna zoom into specifically
what the authoring process looks like
for this kind of approach.
And we're gonna look at what interaction,
what it means to design interaction rules.
So an interaction rule is basically
a transition between story situations.
basically going from the ant is beside the stream and thirsty to the ant being in the water. We
can label this transition with a story event like the ant falls into the stream. And to make
this formal we simply have to think about our logical representation of each of these
situations and then give a formal label to this transition event.
The next thing that we do in order to start introducing generativity into the story is
to make the rule more general.
So I'm using a particular kind of quirky syntax with this question mark which designates a
variable, which is an argument to the rule, that can range over any character.
Basically any character can be substituted into this rule to have it apply to them.
So we could say if someone is thirsty...
someone is at a location somewhere and that somewhere happens to be near a stream, then one
way their situation might transform is that they could fall into the stream and become in the
stream. It's important to know that when we're representing things formally like this, we also
have to make sure we're preserving information that doesn't change. So if our situation
doesn't change the fact that this location is near the stream, we have to repeat it on the
other side.
So that's enough dense syntax for now.
We're going to go back to pictures.
So we'll represent this kind of rule with a variable in it
with this outline of a person to say if the person is
thirsty and the person is near a stream, then the person
can fall into the stream.
So that's one way of introducing generativity is
sort of generalizing these interaction rules into things
that can be instantiated with multiple
characters and entities.
Another way is to introduce choices into the world,
to sort of say that, well, if a person is near a stream
and thirsty, then they might fall into the stream.
We can label that rule drink fall.
On the other hand, we could have a rule called drink succeed
in which they don't fall into the stream
and simply stop being thirsty.
Other kinds of interaction rules we can represent with this rule-based style include movement
to locations.
So if a character wants to move to a particular location that they happen to be near, then
they can simply transition to being in that new location.
More interestingly, perhaps, we can also represent
social interaction rules.
So we can say something like, if two characters,
X and Y, are in a shared location,
and X doesn't like Y, then they can transition
into a situation where they don't like each other.
And we can call this story event insulting.
X insulting Y.
We can also represent social interactions like helping.
So if somebody has a cure for,
if somebody named X has a cure for an ailment
that somebody named Y has, and X happens to like Y,
then perhaps they spend the cure to get rid of the ailment
and now Y is grateful to X.
So those were just a few examples
of the kinds of interaction rules
that you can create in a simulation.
And then I mentioned before
that you also have to feed in an initial state.
So what does that look like?
Initial state is simply a sequence of logical operators
representing the situation that the story is in
before the simulation begins.
So for example, the dove being on the shore,
or sorry, the dove being above the shore at the treetops,
the ant being at the shore,
and other properties of the world
that will be manipulated by these rules.
then when this is actually executed at run time,
what happens?
Okay, so the algorithmic concept is that
our system is going to randomly explore the state space.
And more concretely, as an example,
what that might mean is that
we start with some initial state, including the.
locations and relationships between the world entities.
And then we take a random movement in a particular
direction, like say, the ant moves to the stream.
And note that the other part of the situation, wherever
the dove is and which locations are near each other and so
on, doesn't change across this transition.
And then we can follow that with another part of the
sequence where the dove moves to the stream.
Now both of the characters are in the same location and
some interaction might take place between them.
On the other hand, we might start from the initial state
and first move the dove, and then move the ant,
which takes us back to the same situation
as doing so the other way around.
So in doing this, we are creating not
what you may be more familiar with,
sort of like a branching story tree,
but rather a branching story graph
where things might connect to the same node.
So.
A concept that we could consider for generating stories
includes randomly exploring the state space,
but a perhaps more useful way to think about it
as sort of interactive experience designers
is that we can also include the player in the loop
and allow them to control some of the steps
through the state space.
whether it's a player or an automated decision maker taking
these steps, we can consider each traversal through the state
space to be approximately a story. So sometimes these things
may not be very interesting stories but some of them might
be. So if the ant moves towards the stream and the dove moves
towards the stream, the ant can insult the dove and the dove
might eat the ant.
In terms of interacting with simulations,
there are, of course, a lot of design questions
to ask for using this technique.
So one of the biggest ones is, where is the locus of control?
How can the player intervene in the narrative?
Are they playing as one character?
Are they able to manipulate all of the characters in the story
and completely control what takes place in the simulation?
Or are they perhaps able only to subtly manipulate
the world around the characters as they
go about their daily activities using these interaction rules?
and try to subtly manipulate their behavior in that way.
There's a couple of examples I wanted to highlight,
one of which is the game Prom Week,
which came out of research from UC Santa Cruz,
in which the player does get to control all characters,
but kind of one at a time.
So they select one character who's the actor,
and then another character that
that first character will act upon,
and they get to decide what kind of interaction
will be started, but how that second character responds.
is automated. Another example is Blood and Laurels, which uses the Versu storytelling engine.
In that case, it actually plays a lot like a traditional choice-based narrative, but all of
the choices that are presented to you are generated by the simulation possibilities underlying the
world. With that, I am going to pass this off to Rogelio, who's going to tell you how to actually
introduce some kind of control over your dramatic arcs that unfold.
Hi everybody, I'm super excited to be here.
So, in order to set up a specific narrative progression,
which you won't have in the simulation-centric approach
because you kind of get to decide
where the narrative is going on the fly,
you need a way of specifying and enforcing goals,
which is, again, achieved through the techniques
that I'm gonna outline.
However, the plot-centric approach does build upon the simulation-centric approach.
So you need to describe what is the initial state of the narrative universe,
as well as what are the interaction rules that allow the states of the universe to change.
Additionally, you require a narrative agenda.
So the agenda represents the desired plot
that you as a narrative designer want to have happen
in terms of the trajectory through the state space
that Chris was describing.
So to give you a kind of diagrammatic representation
of what's going on, this is the diagram
that Chris finished upon.
And we're gonna just shift the story generator to the left.
And in addition to specifying, like I said,
the initial state and the interaction rules,
you also have the narrative agenda.
Now, the story generator in creating this story
actually needs an additional agent, storytelling agent.
And one will generate the partial story structure,
which is the generator,
and the other will try to enforce that story structure.
So there's this idea that you have the narrative agenda
that you want as a designer to have happen
in the interactive narrative experience.
You now need an additional agent
that will monitor what the player is doing
and try to get the player directed
on that narrative trajectory.
So the partial story is created.
passes to this agent called a story mediator agent
and the player once again takes actions
that the mediator interprets.
It then requests story content from the story generator
which in turn in response to the player's actions
creates this partial story
and then delivers those responses to the player.
So you can think of it as an iterative process
that takes place between the player and the story system.
Essentially they're taking turns advancing the chronology.
So the player takes a turn in the interactive environment
and then the system responds in turn.
Thank you.
So like I said earlier, you have to describe
the initial state as well as the interaction rules
that can evolve states.
The way that we approach authorship
in this plot-centric approach is,
again, I have an idea as a designer
which of the states in that space are desirable,
and that is the narrative agenda.
So say for example, that at the end,
I want the ant to be at the shore right,
then what that does in terms of the simulated world
is distinguish a state as desirable,
which I've highlighted there.
in that alternative color.
So as we specify more conditions in the state space,
we get a more specific trajectory
of the interactive narrative.
So the more that we specify,
the more we have in terms of constraints
of things that we as designers would like to have hit
during the progression of the player.
And this sets up nicely the first technique
in the plot-centric approach,
which is this notion of beats.
So the idea that you have some state,
you have the states of the state space
and a subset of those states, which are the desired ones.
And in the literature,
you'll find these referred to as beats.
The second technique in the plot-centric approach
is this notion of turn-taking, which I kind of alluded to.
And you can think of it through an analogy
through Dungeons and Dragons,
when you roll for initiative, right?
You, the DM, have players roll for initiative,
establish the turn order of players,
then the players go and the DM responds in kind.
So the DM and the players take turns
advancing the narrative arc.
So the same principle applies here.
From the initial state, the player is allotted
or afforded the opportunity to take action
in the state space.
And then the system is allowed to respond in kind.
And so this continues throughout the progression
of the plot structure.
And the third technique is that idea of mediation,
which I talked about earlier,
the notion that there are some actions in that state space
which essentially take us away
from the desired plot points.
So we have the beats that we have specified
in the narrative trajectory,
and any action that takes us away from those beats
from the system's perspective constitutes an exception.
We want to avoid those
because we want to hit those plot points
during the progression of the player's experience.
So those dotted arrows that I'm highlighting in the diagram
represent those exceptional actions.
And so if we consider these beats to be hard constraints,
so we don't want the player to deviate from these beats,
then the system must fail the user's action
when the player tries to take that,
or never present the action in the first place.
And otherwise, the system will accept
the player's action during the experience.
There's actually a third option here, replanning.
But this requires a story generator.
In essence, if the player tries to deviate
from the beat path and you have access
to a story generation system,
then you can request additional story content
to try to replan the experience
around the player's interaction.
And find a story that gets us back on track.
During runtime, the plot-centric technique
is all about deciding how to evolve the story
in response to the player's actions.
So like I said earlier, the player in the initial state
will decide what action to pursue for the narrative plot.
Then when the system's turn is up,
it will suggest, or the story manager will suggest
which action will get us closer to a narrative beat.
And so this interaction, like I said,
it's a turn-taking mechanism,
and every time the system is afforded
the opportunity to interact.
it will choose an action that will get us closer
to the narrative beats.
So some plot-centric examples,
and I have to call out facade
because it is an unstated rule in academic talks
that reference interactive narrative
that facade must appear at some point.
part of the PhD manual.
So facade is an example where you have the player
afforded the opportunity to interact in the environment,
but invariably you will hit some specific plot points.
Of course, the trajectory that you take
to get to those beats will affect the way
that the experience culminates.
Another example is a game that was developed
at North Carolina State by Justice Robertson
called Base Case, which in essence,
the interactive environment is procedurally generated
in response to the player's actions.
But it's also with this notion of turn-taking.
So every time the player acts, the system responds in kind
and actually can manipulate things behind the scenes
to try to make sure that the player's plot progression
is as intended.
So that concludes the plot-centric approach,
and I want to shift over to talking about
some challenges in New Frontiers.
So one big challenge that we're currently facing
as an academic research community
is going from this plot-centric approach
to a more discourse-centric approach.
So this is in service of what Emily Short
has called out before, which is there's no need
to simulate part of the environment
that ultimately will not be told to players
because it's not relevant.
If it doesn't in some way advance
the interactive narrative experience,
there's no point in talking about it
at the simulation level.
So traditionally, systems have gone from this simulation approach where you generate
the simulation of the story world through its state space, and then you pick and choose and
present over that state space and lay a discourse above it. And that's ultimately what is presented
to players.
Ideally, we like to go the other way around.
So the simulation of an un-narrated part of the story
is unnecessary.
Chris and I actually have been investigating new models
of communication, understanding what is it that we have
to communicate to a player, and then figuring out
the simulation in service of that.
And I hope to continue that.
That's really exciting work, I think.
Another challenge is this idea of scaling.
So, NanoGenMo, the National Novel Generation Month,
where you have one month to create an AI system
that generates a 50,000 word novel, that's correct.
Clearly we are not in a state as a community
where we can do this automatically.
And ideally we would want to scale
our interactive narrative generation systems
to encompass a wider story experience.
There's an interesting problem in that
in trying to write a small amount of interaction rules
that generate a large body of text.
So what is, I guess, the minimal amount of authoring
that we have to do in terms of input to these systems
to get a wide array of output?
So some parting thoughts.
One thing that we feel procedural narrative generation
will get us toward is opening up the possibility
in terms of interactive story experiences.
So Jesper Juul talks about this idea
of progression versus emergence
in terms of the kinds of games that exist.
And the basic idea is that you have games in narrative
about progression where you have a very linear
structured plot, something like what you would find
in The Secret of Monkey Island,
where you have some space to explore interactions,
but the main plot kind of progresses like checkpoints.
You do some actions in the environment,
you progress to the next plot point,
and the progression is very tied
to your interactive experience.
Contrast that with a game of Emergence.
where, like for example in Civilization,
where you can think of games of emergence
as games that are simple to learn and difficult to master.
And so the narrative or the narrativization
of your experience happens through the interactions
that you have in that game.
Chris and I feel that procedural narrative generation
can help move story games,
which have traditionally been games of progression,
to explore games of emergence.
And this is not to say that these story systems,
one is better than the other,
but we feel that developing these tools and techniques
allow us to explore narrative games
that exist beyond their traditional mold.
And lastly, we're both very excited about this,
we have a new resource to share with y'all,
the storygen.org website, which should be live,
and hopefully you won't give it a hug of death
and then knock it out.
But, so we've compiled a list of procedural narrative
generators that represent systems that you can download
and play with, and we recognize, of course,
that this is, some of it is still research software,
but hopefully that you can actually play with and use
to explore these interesting narrative designs
going forward.
So as a recap, so we've covered the simulation-centric
approach and plot-centric approaches,
and like I said just now, what we have presented
is not normative.
Designers still have to decide what the experience will be,
and hopefully the technology that we've developed
in our community can help enable those experiences.
We've talked very briefly about some challenges
in New Frontiers, and we really encourage you
to visit storygen.org.
Hopefully you will be able to suggest.
new systems, we'd love to have that array of procedural
narrative generators expanded.
And that's it.
I'm Rogelio Cardona-Rivera, this was Chris Martens.
Thank you very much.