I hope it's a useful talk. That would be nice. My name is Chris.
I'm the creative director and artist at Red Hook Studios and
worked on Darkest Dungeon. I wanted to start really quick by
just saying it's a very humbling experience to be able to stand
up here. I've learned a lot from GDC and especially from a lot
of people that I see in the audience that are people that I
look up to. So hopefully I can give something back. Okay. So
enough of kissing ass.
So after three years working on darkest dungeon from Tyler
Sigmund and I and a bottle of scotch in my living room
through all the way to early access and to finishing, this
idea kind of took hold in my mind. Essentially that
development is a lot like being in a dungeon crawl. You form a
party of skilled adventurers. You equip yourself with the
best gear. For us like
workflow, methodology, competencies, great ideas,
and then you basically plunge headlong
into this sprawling abyss of uncertainty
for the next couple years of your life,
running out of money, ruining your relationships,
and all the rest of it.
It's a, what's that?
Yeah, too soon.
No, it's going better, it is.
development, for all of you guys, you guys know this, it
can be paralyzing because you're faced with making like constant
choices with consequences you don't never fully really
understand until it's too late. And the landscape is always
changing and you're always operating with imperfect
information essentially. And I have come to believe that based
on my experience on this game, if you go into this development
dungeon without a strong creative vision for your game,
you're essentially going in torchless.
So what is creative direction? I think it's a lot of things to a
lot of people. You could call it like the thematic and conceptual
framework of the game. You could call it the DNA that runs
through all the sort of soft sciences, you know, narrative
game design, art, music, audio. It's a very nebulous and
amorphous concept. And I think a lot of times it gets ignored for
that reason or not talked about in practical terms.
I think on big projects, you know, when you get face to face
with sort of the realities of development, the pillars and the
vision documents, they just live on the drive somewhere and
because there's no time to go back to that stuff. It doesn't,
it's not relevant anymore. And on a smaller project, you're
like, well, maybe I don't need it because our game's about
jumping. So let's just make the jumping really good. But I, I
respectfully disagree. I think that the misconception that it's
a nebulous and intangible notion.
is a missed opportunity for indie developers.
For us, it was a practical tool.
It was something that we consulted and referred to
constantly throughout our development,
and it served us really well.
we're small teams. We don't have a lot of money when we get
started. We can't afford to just arbitrarily bloat scope or add
parkour on Sunday morning to the game. It doesn't work for us. I
think that we have to be more focused and
deliver tighter experiences by necessity. And in order to do
that successfully, we need to make sure that we align all the
elements in our game to deliver on those thematic beats or we
risk losing our way in development. For us on this
game, what am I, 38, 39? Pushing 40.
The opportunity cost was extremely high.
So actually before Tyler and I kicked off the game,
both of us had had job interviews
and there were offers on the table.
I have a wife and children and a mortgage and an iPad now.
That's cool.
And you know, it costs a lot and it's a huge risk
when you're at that sort of stage in your life.
So for me, it was really important to clearly understand
the game we were going to make
so that I didn't wake up one morning,
like eight months later.
completely depleted of my career's worth of savings
and wonder like, wait a second,
what is this game actually about?
And so we invested early and intensely
in clearly understanding the game's creative direction.
And we looked back on it at every sort of decision point.
We've gotten a lot of great feedback on Darkest Dungeon,
a lot of really positive comments, which are awesome,
about how the atmosphere and the thematics
all sort of like, all the features funnel in together
to deliver this sort of singular experience.
And that's great, but it wasn't by accident.
It was basically a function of how we approached
looking at the game.
So consider this like horrible looking tree.
In the soil you put all your ideas and your inspirations and your influences.
So like classic CRPGs and comic books and sad music and HP Lovecraft and just the earth
that the game is going to kind of grow out of.
And through a process of debate and discussion, you arrive at the trunk of the game.
I'm going to skip ahead here.
the clearly defined vision that's going to create a
framework for you to move forward.
And from that trunk, the branches grow out,
all the different disciplines.
So design can head off in its area
and face its own challenges.
Art can do the same, audio, writing.
But if you trace them back far enough,
they all share an ancestry.
Which I think, looking at the project this way,
gave us a really great place to start.
And no matter what challenges we face later,
we can always come back to this trunk that we built.
sort of a clearly defined and articulated vision statement for the game.
We did this a couple of different ways.
The old collect a bunch of reference art,
put it on an image, classic, classic move.
But putting, like annotating it with what about those images
is really important, I think, because it's not enough just
to stick a picture somewhere.
We had a lot of conversation and debate.
We stress tested what we felt like the game would be about
and how the game would handle certain problems
as they popped up.
And we ended up with this.
uncompromising, gothic rogue-like, low fantasy,
Lovecraftian adventure that challenges players to make the
best of a bad situation and make decisions with permanent
consequences with imperfect information. And that really
became the sort of core vision for the game and everything was
routed through that.
And I wanted to point out I think the love child metaphor.
Thanks Jeff for clarifying what that actually is.
You know when you're like,
oh my game is X meets Y.
For us it became like XCOM meets Dark Souls.
I think that's nice to arrive at at the end of the day
after you've gone through a more exhaustive process
of understanding what it is you're trying to make.
But if you start from there, I think it's really reductive.
And I think that you risk,
like if that's your internal mantra
is XCOM meets Dark Souls.
It's not specific enough because you're not saying what about XCOM you're taking and leaving
and what about Dark Souls you're taking and leaving.
It's just up to personal interpretation.
And I guess that's what I'm really driving at is that when you settle on a creative direction
for your game, it cannot be subject to a personal interpretation.
It needs to be strong enough to exist on its own.
So I did this drawing of Batman.
I think what worked really well for us
by defining this vision for the game,
repeatedly articulating it, and actively looking
for ways to involve it in our development process,
it kind of became its own.
entity. We externalized it. Darkest Dungeon became a team
member. It wasn't what I thought was cool or what Tyler thought
would work. The game was a part of our team. And it had its own
likes and dislikes and things that it wanted to be and things
that it didn't need. Like parkour.
So it's a lot like Batman and Bruce Wayne.
The creative director is a man, or a woman, obviously.
You can be sort of swayed by shifting trends.
You can wake up one morning after you play a great round
of Fallout 4, and now you want to have power armor in your
racing game.
You're vulnerable to these things as a person, just by
the nature of, especially a creative person, right?
We're very easily attracted to neat ideas.
But the creative direction for a game has to be a symbol.
It has to be immutable and powerful
and outside of yourself.
And Batman's really cool.
I could have chosen a different superhero,
but it wouldn't have been a great creative choice given
the talk, subject matter.
So yeah, essentially, the thing has
to be strong enough to live on its own and fight crime.
So being, you know, moving into production with the confidence
of what we knew what we wanted to make led to some really
interesting choices. So what I thought I would do is
demonstrate the practical application of creative
direction by just sort of selecting a few sort of key
examples. Like I said, it was literally something we talked
about all the time. But
the art style, the overall presentation of the game, the
writing style and the lore, some marketing, some game design
stuff. All of these things were really like big sort of home
runs I think for our creative direction. Excuse me.
When we first started, pixel art was hot,
and it was only getting hotter,
and you could get a lot of attention
by virtue of simply being a pixel art game.
And I think there's a case to be made
for the irony of cute pixel characters
suffering horrible depression and syphilis in a dungeon.
Like, that's kind of funny, right?
There's something there.
It, ultimately we looked at it,
but it communicated the wrong things.
It led out with this idea of retro and charming.
And even though we were sort of a retro inspired
kind of RPG, we couldn't lead out with that
rose colored nostalgia and cuteness.
It actually, it flew in the face
of what we were trying to accomplish.
We needed something like really awful and depressing
to really just hammer that horrible stuff home.
So heavy blacks came into play.
We started looking at a lot of comic books
and how to deliver on that vibe.
And the looseness of the art really reinforced
this idea of imperfection.
Your heroes are imperfect.
The information you're getting for your decision-making
is imperfect.
Imperfection is a huge theme in our game.
and it was great to give that like a visual personification
so that it's literally there.
Even if you're not consciously aware of it
when you're playing, it's one of those things
that it creeps up on you and you understand it
without necessarily knowing it consciously.
So I think that was a good choice.
And the big win for me is that if I can be loose and sloppy
and people still think it's cool,
then I can get more done faster, which is great.
Because there's only one of me.
The other sort of assumption when you go in to make like an
RPG especially a turn based one is that the top down ISO Diablo
or classic Final Fantasy grid cam is usually the default
assumption when you describe a game like this to someone. But
we ended up with this weird side scrolling thing. You're always
moving left to right. And the reason was because as you can
see we did some exploration. Even after sort of getting some
real solid wins on the art style you can see it's starting to
creep in over there.
we tried to make it work with this sort of,
operating under the assumption that we had to do this.
But the more we got into it,
we realized that the wide angles
and the sort of godlike overview
robbed the game of that claustrophobic tension
that we felt like was so important.
We wanted you down in the dungeon with your characters.
We don't want you standing up above like,
you know, the Lord, kind of looking down
with this wide panoramic view.
It lost its sense of intimacy and a lot of the intensity.
And also, our game is about the psychological ramifications
of adventuring, and that's the characters.
It's not the environment.
So it's less about dungeon layout
and more about who's in the dungeon.
So again, that was an argument to be made
for getting nice, close in on those characters.
And it's also really hard to relate
to the top of someone's head.
So, you know, having nice side view characters
gives you something that's a little bit more interesting
to look at, and you can kind of attach yourself
to the look and feel of the character.
And again, another big win is that it's the same set
of assets as combat.
So we didn't have to JRPG to a battle cam and, again,
imply bigger spaces.
And as a result, the game feels very,
you're very wrapped up in it as you're playing it.
The writing, a big assumption I think too
that we sort of wrestled with is that
when you make an RPG, usually there's gotta be
dwarves and elves that thought 10,000 years ago
and then there's a chosen one thrown in there at some point.
Maybe there's a life tree, I don't know.
Collect a few elements.
But it's always very exhaustively spelled out
and quite frankly, it kinda bores me to tears sometimes
and I kinda skip through a lot of the quests.
I'm like, do you want the wolf pelts?
Yes or no?
I just wanna get another sword, man.
So we felt like for our game though, um...
imperfect information. We don't want to spell out the story. We
want to suggest it's there and create this fog around the
player to deliver on this twilight zone uncertainty that I
think is really important and it features in a lot of love craft
stuff. You only get a keyhole glimpse into these awful
horrors and if they were to be described exactly it does them a
disservice. So we went a different direction. We tried to
tell the story.
as much in the panels as in the gutters.
Like, I'm sure a lot of you guys read comics,
and your brain interpolates what's
happening between the panels in the white space in between.
And so that gives you a point of contact
as the consumer of the product to get invested,
to use your own imagination to fill in those gaps.
And we felt like that would be, it
would pair nicely with the comic book style art,
and it would allow people to sort of integrate themselves
into the fiction.
And it means that we don't have to write a novel, which
is a huge win.
The writing style was a big risk for us as well,
because the game uses a lot of really antiquated verbiage,
if you will.
And it was really a way of us honoring the source material.
We felt like we couldn't decouple
the Lovecraftian overwrought tonality from the actual.
thematic influences. I felt like they were really enmeshed.
And so to try and tell a Lovecraft style story without
that terminology, that phrasing, that turn of phrase, would rob
it of something inherently that it needed. But it was a risk as
far as localization goes. And we were worried that people just
wouldn't like it or wouldn't get it. But that was a risk we were
willing to take because we felt like it honored the creative
direction of the game much more.
And again, yeah, horror thrives in the absence of certainty.
So the dark places of your imagination,
that's where kind of fear and concern settle in.
And anytime you can pay that out in a horror game,
I think you're doing well.
So we've looked at a few of these soft science areas
where the creative direction was important.
That's kind of low-hanging fruit,
because I think when people talk about creative direction,
they immediately associate it with art
and that kind of thing.
But we used it actually as a razor
when it came to features as well.
We really tried to ask the game essentially what it wanted,
what it needed to be able to pay off its identity.
So for instance, a gear system is a popular thing
to have in an RPG.
It's usually what drives the player experience.
They want to upgrade their stuff and get new loot.
But it's extremely, extremely costly.
And we have a small team, obviously, and limited resources.
And we had to really ask ourselves,
is this something, is this a road we want to go down?
Does this actually serve the creative direction of the game?
And the answer was no.
Our game is about the sword arm, not the sword.
It's about the person who's wearing the armor,
not a number of upgrade gems on the armor.
Those games are great.
I love those games.
But that's not this game.
And I think understanding what game we were making
really helped us make these decisions
and really never look back.
So we used it as a razor to measure
the relative value and importance of many, many features.
You'll notice there's no crafting system.
we reduced it down to like two inventory slots,
but then we blew out the number of items that were there
because we recognized the value
in having collectible loot.
It's great, it's part and parcel of the experience,
but it shouldn't play lead guitar in this game.
It's the bass or even just the little dude
with the shaker in the back, you know?
It applies to marketing too. Trailers, when we were first
getting started I did a lot of research into sort of how game
trailers should be constructed and the conventional wisdom was
that they need to be fast, punchy, there needs to be flying
text. I think you're supposed to announce a new game mechanic
every five seconds. It's all, you can find it on Google. We
didn't do any of that. Just because it didn't align with the
mood and tone of the game. So our trailers are...
are too long, they're too slow,
and they deliver feeling over function.
But ultimately, they were really successful
precisely for those reasons.
They stood out from a lot of other marketing materials
because of their commitment to the game's identity.
They felt like they were an extension of the game
as opposed to something that was slapped together
after the fact.
And I think that's really important
because what's a marketing material but like an on-ramp,
right, you're trying to pull people in,
and if you're pulling them in in a slapdash way
that doesn't feel genuinely connected to the product itself,
I think you're on ramping them on to a gravel road somewhere.
So the last example I want to bring up is related to game
design. Generally this is a sound principle. Don't just
take away shit from people who worked really hard in your game
to earn it. That's kind of a no brainer. You can kind of see
what we did here. Oh, yeah. Come on to your maker.
What? Oh, my God, I have to choose a hero.
No. Oh, no way.
Oh, it's the cauldron all over again.
No wonder you bring that up.
Oh, wow. Yes.
Shit. Oh, man, we've got the whole boy.
I don't know who to pick.
I feel like we need our healer for the rest of this, but.
Alright, well, we're getting a spare of the others I am ready from our lepers, so I guess
we're gonna send him in.
God damn, that's cold, dude.
Son of a bitch.
Oh my god, come on.
You just, you go through all this and then you just have to give him up.
So that was the final boss for the game.
We violated pretty much every UI, UX rule and game design
rule with that fight precisely to pay off
cosmic horror, incomprehensible cosmic horror,
and the futility of trying to swing a two-handed sword
at the heart of the world.
You can't beat this, right?
How can you beat a Lovecraftian monster?
It's absurd.
So the final boss fight is like a thematic compression
of the entire play experience.
There's all the mechanics feature into that fight.
It's the entire mission.
And death and loss are an important part of our game.
And so we have to kill you in this fight.
Even if you're the best player in the world,
you must die in this fight.
But the first time you play it,
you don't understand what's happening.
We broke the move flow, and you can see,
this is from a streamer called Bitterbit.
You can see he pauses, he's like, I don't understand.
Because the game completely stops doing
what they're used to seeing it do.
And we did that specifically to create
this sense of like, dawning horror.
It's uncertain.
What's going on?
Suddenly now the player is in the position of the heroes
who are in the game.
I mean, it's not as bad for the guy in his computer, right?
But it aligns their expectations,
and suddenly the play field is wide open,
and you're just wracked with uncertainty.
How many more times is he gonna do this?
Is this a death race?
Am I on a timer?
All of these questions kind of swim around,
and it elevates the intensity of the fight,
especially in the final minutes.
Truth be told.
We built it so you could beat this end fight.
We want you to go through this experience,
but we want you to go through it off balance and unsure.
And because that's really what our game has been about.
And we wanted to make that final encounter everything
that we'd been building up to.
So those are some examples of how
we use creative direction practically
throughout the project.
What we do is not easy.
I mean, you guys know this.
There's the hours, there's the pressure,
the desire to do great work as creative people,
not to mention the crushing self-doubt
and financial insecurity,
and all the other sort of horrors
that lurk around in the dark.
But having the confidence that comes from investing early
in a strong creative direction for our game
and understanding it, articulating it,
and referencing it in every discussion
that we possibly could.
It gave us a lot of confidence and made our journey a lot easier, I think, than it could have been otherwise.
So we got to know our game.
We externalized its creative core.
We invited it to the meetings.
We leveraged its creative vision to vet features,
to inform decision making.
And the result was, thankfully, a high degree
of creative consistency.
Thematics meshed with art, meshed with sound and audio.
And Stuart Chatwood and Wayne June and Power Up Audio
did a fantastic job on the audio stuff.
everything is in there for a reason. Everything has a
purpose in our game and it can be clearly pointed to. I think
that's really important as an indie game. You can't do
everything but what you do do you have to do it really, really
well to stand out. So... Thanks. I asked him to do like a
Brazilian macaw thing to let me know when I was running out of
time. It was good. It was good. Yeah.
So we spent a long time in early access. We were faced with an
onslaught of fantastic but often times diametrically opposed
feedback. We had our own ideas. We had deadlines. So for a while
there we were mired in the darkest dungeon of development.
But we used our creative direction to illuminate our
decision space a little bit and keep our party focused on what
was important and ultimately we got out intact. Having said
that, I still need a few nights at the tavern. Anyway.
That's my talk. Thank you very much.
I think I timed it okay. I think we have a few minutes for Q&A
if anybody wants to say anything. I have a question.
Yeah, okay, so when you're making a game you sometimes have to pivot your design because you realize it didn't work as well
You did when you separate yourself from your creative direction as its own thing
Is it still able to pivot or you like this is where we have to build now?
I think you want to get to the point where you feel confident
in it before you jump into development so you save
yourself a pivot later.
Obviously, practically sometimes you've got to make
adjustments and changes.
But I think that when you're talking about creative
direction, it can be implemented a number of
different ways.
And usually when you pivot, you're pivoting on specific
features or the way it's expressed.
So I think you can make strides on articulating a
creative direction and still make adjustments to your
implementation.
I don't think they're mutually exclusive.
Thanks.
With regards to the kind of metagame in Darkest Dungeon with the characters being disposable,
was that something that was intentionally designed with the same theme of horror and
uncertainty and all that kind of stuff?
Yeah, of course, because we kind of wanted to subvert this idea
that when you start an RPG, like, they're all little
precious snowflakes that you're going to carry through to the
end. And pay off that sort of pulp horror view of humanity as
being inconsequential. So we layer that in right from the
beginning, although you don't actually know that's what we're
doing until it's kind of too late and you're getting heart
attacked just relentlessly. So the disposability of human life
is part and parcel of the whole cosmic horror thing.
and it's also just sort of a really neat exploration
in terms of how people play the game.
They start out very attached
and then they start to lose their heroes
and then they get resentful at the game
so they say, well fine, I'm not gonna name anybody.
And then they start making way more money
and then they realize they're the villain.
And we didn't do that, it's on you.
Thanks.
Hi. I was wondering, you had mentioned you had that fear of
the financial issues and stuff. So I was wondering exactly how
did you guys choose where to allocate funds for when you were
in development?
Well, you know, the first part of our project was all bootstrapped, so we each had our own sort of like personal runways
that we used up, you know, for a while. And Kickstarter was a huge, huge help to us.
But really it just went towards cost of living and just keeping us fed and keeping the lights on.
Where we broke down our man hours, or our focus,
was driven a lot by what we felt were the most salient
and important things.
Sometimes it's not, like you can't always work on your
top line feature, the other stuff has to get attention too.
But certainly the early access release that we brought
to market a year ago was sort of our best effort
in making sure that we put our time and energy
on the things that were most important.
And then throughout the year we were able to circle back
and kind of like raise the quality level
and everything else.
Thank you.
I was just curious how much of the game's mechanics had you
prototype before you felt like your direction was totally
solid?
It's a bit weird and I can't say this is going to be entirely
transferable but Tyler and I would sit down and we talked
through and storyboarded most of the game prior to even starting
development.
It was just the two of us.
So when we started, I'm not saying we had every problem
solved but we certainly had a lot of the
the vision and the core idea of how the game would play out and
what the mechanics looked like. Obviously there were changes and
nuances. We added corpses. That was really fun. So things
evolved over time as they should. But, yeah, it's we knew a
lot before we started. Sorry, I think he was up.
So most games focus on giving power to the players and make
them have a lot of fun and feel good about playing the game.
Were you prepared for making a game where you were pretty much
doing the opposite and maybe making people really upset?
Like, just out of curiosity.
Yes.
Okay.
We knew that we were sort of like walking a bit of a tight
rope.
To be totally honest with you guys, and I guess the internet
because it's going to be recorded,
we maybe weren't prepared for some of the vitriolic responses
once you've experienced the party wipe and the level of like.
lemon juice that goes along with some of those comments.
But we always felt like we managed to straddle the line
and make sure that you were empowered enough to make
progress, but that your progress was never guaranteed.
And so I grew to sort of disregard feedback that said,
you know, I have my level two guys with level two armor
fighting a level two monster.
I should win.
Fundamentally, you should not in our game.
That's not a promise that we ever made you.
That's just your condition for it, right?
But yeah, I think that in some ways
we weren't necessarily prepared for some
of the more colorful responses to that.
Thank you for being so uncompromising.
So obviously you highlighted the importance of creative direction when it comes to unifying all of the game elements such as art, design, narrative and so on in order to create a cohesive whole because otherwise if you had one element that kind of stood out of the pack and was an outlier then obviously it would have been all the more noticeable and that would have kind of thrown the player off.
Regarding, you know, maintaining that creative direction,
can you name me, like, any particular roadblocks
and disagreements you and your teammates had
during the development of Darkest Dungeon?
The irony of making games is that you don't often times get a
lot of time to play them. But I can say that like Crypt of the
Necrodancer, for instance, I felt like really had the same
sort of tight vision, the way the dungeon floor turns into a
disco and, you know, little nods like that just to keep looping
it back around and the beating heart, it was a great, yeah,
they wove like sort of this dark fantasy story around this like
crazy dance game. And I thought they did that really, really
masterfully. So that was a standout for me as well.
interesting. Thank you very much. Appreciate your time.