Just a little bit of background,
Situational Game Design is a book that I wrote.
I'm going to talk a little bit about what's in it
and why you might be interested in using it
in an academic setting.
Myself, I've been in the industry for over 20 years.
I'm currently the chief creative officer
at a little startup called Croquet Studios.
If you've tried to reach me to do consulting work
when I was freelancing, I'm very sorry
that I haven't responded because we're starting
a new studio and it's been crazy.
So in order to explain why situational game design exists,
I first have to explain a bit about my first book,
The Aesthetic of Play.
I wrote The Aesthetic of Play because I was troubled
that my own thoughts about how game design worked
weren't really reflected in what I was seeing
in the existing literature.
and the existing way people were talking about things,
and I wanted to basically lay out my own philosophy
for how to design games and what the meaning of play is.
As a book, it's an argument.
It's an argument for a particular stance
with relationship to play and towards game design,
but it's not really a teaching text.
It was designed more as a polemic
to convince people to think about play in certain ways.
So this was a problem because then I was approached a couple years ago by Brenda Romero,
who said, essentially, I want to use your book to teach my undergrad class on game design.
And I was very flattered, but my response was...
I don't think that's a very good idea.
The reason why is because it really wasn't geared
toward an undergrad audience.
It was a whole bunch of really weird esoteric theory
about why I think I'm right,
and not really anything about a practical methodology
for how to actually make games
using the techniques I was laying out.
So as a result, being a good friend,
I decided to write a book for her.
And that wasn't the only reason,
but I wanted to take the ideas that I'd put forth
in The Aesthetic of Play and try to turn it into something
that could actually be used both by undergrads
and also by working designers.
So it's not like, you're not,
this is not something where you're trying to be convinced.
This is like, here is a methodology that you can use
to analyze games and to design games.
And so that's basically what I'm gonna talk about.
One of the things that prompted me to do this talk is because I gave a smaller talk on this subject at USC last fall as part of their Play Think series,
and I discovered that they had actually adopted situational game design as one of their texts.
And I thought, well, if USC likes it, then maybe other people would like it as well,
and so maybe I could talk a little about it, and people could see if they were interested, and it would be useful for their own game design programs.
So in order to describe what situational game design is,
I should first start with what we normally think of
as game design, what I call transactional game design.
And in transactional game design,
we tend to focus on what the game does.
We focus on the affordances that the game offers
to the player, and we focus on the interactions
that can occur.
We think of play in transactional terms
as being something that happens on the interface
between player and game.
So the game lets you do certain things
and in doing them you are playing.
It's focused on getting good interactivity,
having good feedback loops,
making sure that interface that exists
between the player and the game
is really crunchy and chewy and satisfying and wonderful
because that's where all the play lives.
So as a result, it's focused on how do we design the game.
It's very game-centric, but it's also player agnostic.
It kind of assumes that a good game is a good game for everybody and that games sort
of exist as platonic ideals rather than something that is actually played
by specific players with their own specific agendas.
In contrast, situational design is extremely player-centric.
In thinking about how I approach my own game designs,
I don't think of the game as being something
that stands apart from the player.
I think of the game as actually being something
that exists as a fusion of an external rule set,
an external set of constraints.
and the internal set of predispositions and attitudes and strategies that the player brings
to the table.
Play, in that case, is not centered on the interface between game and player, but play
is centered in the mind of the player themselves.
And so as a result, it allows you to analyze certain things
that are a little hard if you think about everything
being about interactivity.
So for example, you can think about what happens
when the player is holding very still
and not actually interacting with the game,
but is still enjoying themselves.
You can think about in a turn-based game,
what's going on in the off-turn experience
where you're waiting for somebody else to move,
but you're still actively engaged in gameplay.
you can think about the ways that it can be playful to experience a narrative
or to experience an emotional moment in the game.
And so as a result, whereas transactional game design is useful
for certain sorts of very interactive heavy games,
situational game design gives you a set of tools that you can use
to analyze these other sorts of experiences
that we don't often think of as gameplay, but are still very, very playful.
And so it's player-centric and also,
as I'm gonna explain it a little bit,
what I call a constraint agnostic.
And I'm gonna explain that on the very next slide.
So what is a constraint?
Constraints are central to the notion
of situational game design.
Constraints are anything that limits
player action from moment to moment.
So in most games, a rule is obviously a constraint.
But things like the layout of a play field are constraints.
So the bounciness of a soccer ball
is a constraint on how soccer is played.
The layout of a level on a first-person shooter is a constraint on how it's played.
And even things that we don't usually think of as being in-game are also constraints.
So the physicality of a controller that you hold in your hands
is also a constraint on the sorts of ways you can play,
which is why you have a very different play experience if you're playing with mouse and keyboard
or if you're playing with a console controller.
But there's some other things beyond this that also count as constraints.
And these are things that exist in the mind of the player.
These are things like genre expectations.
So if you're playing a first-person shooter,
you have certain assumptions that you bring to the game
that stand outside of the system of constraints
that the game itself imposes on you.
You may have strategies that you adopt.
You may know that doing certain things is a bad idea,
and so you don't do them.
That counts as a constraint.
Certain games are more fun if you know a lot
about how to play them.
So if you have a very steep learning curve,
it might be like, well, this is really boring
and frustrating, oh, but once you know everything about it,
then it's interesting,
because you have the right strategic constraints
in order to make something interesting to play.
And things like narrative flow or your sense of characterization, who it is you're playing.
If you're playing somebody who is a hero, you may actually choose different actions while you're playing
than if you're playing somebody who you think of as a villain.
And finally...
There are all sorts of what I call perversions or misunderstandings.
Because the game you play is often not the game that is imposed upon you, the game that
has been designed, but the game that you think you're playing.
If you don't know certain things,
or certain features exist within the game,
then you won't actually use those features.
They won't become part of the constraint space
that describes how it plays.
Or you may willfully decide to ignore them.
So for example, you may play in perverse ways.
Years ago when I was playing a lot of Doom,
a group of us got together and tried to see
how big of a human pyramid we can build in Doom.
It was a complete perversity of how Doom was supposed to be played, but by imposing our
own unusual and very strange constraints, we actually had a really good time with it.
And so, there are maybe all sorts of ways that you can play within a game's play space
that are not constrained by the actual rules or built-in constraints of the game.
So constraints are what define what I call a situation.
A situation is a relatively stable set of constraints.
It is a place you find yourself in playing the game
where the constraints around you are not changing very much.
Now, by relatively stable, I mean, you know, within the, within the, um, stable within
the, um, the context of like a fraction of a second when you're actually making your gameplay decisions.
So, if it's turn, if it's a turn-based game, your constraints might be, you know, stable for...
several minutes, but it's a fast-paced action game,
your constraints may be relatively stable
for a few milliseconds.
But in any case, it gives you a way
to get at the moment-to-moment experience
and form a model of something that's stable
that you can analyze.
So a situation is composed of constraints.
And then within a situation, you have moves.
Moves are things that you can do in a situation.
They are things that are allowed to you by the constraints.
And then finally, what makes a move a move
is that a move is something that changes your constraints.
So that every gameplay experience or every play experience
can be understood as a continual motion through this cycle
where you have a set of constraints
that structure a situation.
Within that situation, you have a set of moves.
You pick one of those moves
that changes the set of constraints
and now you're in a new situation.
And this gives us a way to have a theoretical model
of what is happening moment to moment
in the mind of the player
as they're moving forward through a game.
So anything that changes the constraints is a move.
Pressing a button on a controller obviously is a move.
But many moves can happen entirely
inside the player's head.
So if you're playing a game like Portal
and you're standing staring at a puzzle room
that has a bunch of different possible solutions,
You're actively engaged, you're actively working through a set of moves,
but the moves that you're working through are not ones that you're making in the game,
in the external game,
they're moves that you're making entirely in your head.
You're moving from one situation to another,
one internal situation to another within your own mind.
And what makes a puzzle game like this interesting is the way these internal situations are structured.
So that is, you're moving from one, considering one possibility to another.
You have the right number of possible permutations of moves that you can select in order to move forward.
So what this gives us, the notion of the situation,
gives us a way to conceptualize the moment-to-moment
experience of playing a game.
And it gives us a way to analyze this experience,
so that if you have a student who's designing a game
and they're not sure why something isn't working properly,
or you're trying to do a critique of a game,
you're like, you know, I'm playing this
and it's just not fun, what's wrong here?
Breaking things down into situations and trying to understand the situations
it's structuring can often give you these answers.
So in any moment you can say, okay, what constraints is the player actually operating under here?
What are the limitations in the player's behavior?
And what assumptions might I be making about limitations in the player's behavior
that I am not taking into account?
Is this game boring because the players have discovered master strategies that have eliminated all their choices?
Is it frustrating because they don't know the things they need to know?
Trying to identify the constraints that exist in a situation can often give you a way to analyze
whether it is working or not as a play experience.
And then knowing what moves you can make as a result.
So recognizing in a situation the tensions that exist between moves and constraints
can help answer game design questions.
So once you look at a situation,
what I also provide is a set of heuristics rules
for determining whether a situation
should theoretically be playable or not,
or playful or not.
This is a set of general principles
for what makes situations interesting for us to be in.
And it's broken down into six different heuristics.
If you want to know more detail,
I don't have time to really go into them in a lot of detail,
but I can explain briefly what the theory behind it is.
We like situations where we have a handful of moves,
where we have three to seven different possibilities
that are meaningful to choose between.
If we don't have enough, a game feels boring.
And if we have too many, a game feels confusing.
And so when you're looking at situations,
you think, what are the meaningful moves
that a player can make here?
And do I give them too many or too few?
Situations also can't repeat.
You need to have situations that,
you need to be continually encountering new situations.
The reason for this is because your memory
of your previous, of a previous move
you make within a situation affects your,
becomes a constraint upon your new moves.
So if you encounter the same situation over and over again
and you've already picked a move that you like,
and you're happy with it,
you will automatically pick that move.
And now this new constraint,
your knowledge of what you've done before,
reduces the number of moves
from what might have been an interesting number
the first time you encountered it
into just a single move,
and the situation becomes boring.
The moves need to have consequences.
This is kind of baked into the definition for moves.
Moves need to change the constraints.
If a move does not take you to a new situation,
if it feels empty or pointless,
then you're sort of by default
are repeating the same situation over and over again.
That makes it less interesting.
They need to be predictable.
When we choose moves, we need to have a reason to choose one move over another.
We need to feel like we are accomplishing something when we choose moves in a situation.
And in order for that to happen, the move has to be predictable.
We have to be able to run through a chain of possible moves in our head and see that
it might probably arrive at a future situation that we find desirable.
Whether because it leads us towards winning, or because it answers some question we have about the game,
or because it allows us to perform some role within the make-believe that we have of the game,
we want to feel like our moves have consequences and that we can determine what those consequences are.
But at the same time, they can't be too predictable.
We can't be absolutely sure that the moves we make in a situation will give us the result
we want because otherwise we could run through future situations in our head.
This is the mirror of having situations that get played out because we encounter the same
situation over and over again.
If I'm able to run through a long chain of situations by imagining all the moves that
I'm going to make,
then it becomes boring when I actually get around
to making those moves.
I've already made the choices in advance
and I've already taken,
I've already used up all the fun.
This is an example where, in a chess game,
where the end of a game is a foregone conclusion,
someone may say something like mate in three.
Well, there's no point in actually playing
because everybody knows how it's going to go
and at that point, there is no more play left
in the situations that you'll be encountering.
And finally is satisfaction.
It's not enough to know where you're going,
but you want to be able to pick moves
that lead you at least in,
that offer the possibility of success.
So you want to be able to choose moves
that you think will help you win
or that will give you some other reward
as either personal or internal as you're playing the game.
So in order for all this to work,
you really need to come into this
thinking about who's your player,
and not who's your player in the very vague sort of,
Oh, we're targeting the action adventure demographic,
or we're intending this to be about fans of fighting games.
You need to try to get yourself into the mind of the player
and think through what sort of constraints
they might be bringing to the table.
So that different people from different backgrounds, from different ages, different ethnicities, different genders,
people will bring different pre-existing constraints to the game.
And so when you're thinking about assembling a set of constraints that will offer interesting situations,
a lot of times what you need to do is be thinking,
okay,
What assumptions am I making about the player?
No game exists entirely with,
that is entirely self-contained.
We all make assumptions when we're designing games
that players will bring certain pre-existing constraints.
Sometimes these constraints are drawn entirely
from the real world.
So if you make a driving game,
you kind of assume that even if people
don't know how to drive,
they know in general what driving is
and what the rules of the road are.
And so simulation games rely heavily on people having a sense of what they're supposed to be doing before they start to play.
And so when you think about how to design games using situational game design,
a big part of it is thinking about who is going to be playing it and how are they going to change as they're playing.
So this is kind of reiterating what I just said,
but play is the intersection between a well-designed game
and a suitable player.
We create sets of rules, we create the game as designed,
and then the player brings their own internal constraints,
both that they had previously
and their understanding of the game,
and it is the intersection of those two
that produces the play space where play emerges.
But more importantly, this is not a static system.
Games will change us as we play them.
So as you are playing a game,
you are constantly developing new constraints
based upon what you're learning from playing the game.
You have new ways of understanding the game,
you have new strategies you're developing,
you try something out and it fails,
you're like, oh, that was wrong, I shouldn't do that.
And so, when we're thinking about designing
these constraints, we're not just designing
for one assumed player, we're designing
for an assumed player who's going to be evolving
through time in response to the problems
that we were posing for them.
So in many ways we can think about that if somebody is really into a game,
and if you don't just abandon a game because you're not interested in it,
then what happens is that you are becoming the player that you need to be
in order to play through a game.
And that gives us a very powerful tool for thinking about
how games can actually affect and influence people.
So when we talk, this is another advantage of situational game design,
is it gives us a really concrete way to get at what games mean.
Meaning is not what a game tells us.
It is not a didactic exercise in a game instructing us.
Meaning is the residue of the experience that we have while we play the game.
Meaning is what we have learned to be in order to successfully play the game.
And so that games that are very, very meaningful to us are games that reinforce particular
patterns of behavior that then linger with us afterwards.
They give us ways of being.
in a playful world where we were rewarded for adopting certain attitudes and certain strategies.
And then those attitudes and strategies persist after they've gone.
They are the residue of the play experience.
So really quickly, because I only have half an hour and I want to have a little time for questions.
So you can think about how we put this all together in order to
have a coherent model for designing games within this.
And this is how I approach it.
I start off with an intended experience.
There is something I want players to feel, some way I want them to be
within the games that I am creating.
And then.
that way of being within the world will lead to a set of performative moves,
because since meaning is the residue of experience,
the experience I want to deliver is composed of performative actions
that they will perform in the context of the game.
These performative actions will merge out of situations,
so that if I want to create particular actions that give a particular feeling to a game,
I need to design situations that are going to make those actions emerge naturally and
fluidly where I wanted those actions.
I'm not doing it because I'm told to, but because that's what it seems natural to do.
And then the design of those situations is constrained by the heuristics of play, so
that in order to keep people engaged in making these performative moves, we need to structure
situations that from moment to moment will keep them continually engaged.
The need to have these situations gives us an idea
of what sort of constraints we need to have,
what are the limitations that we put on the player,
and in particular, what assumptions do we make
about what the player already has as constraints,
and what is the minimal amount of constraints
that we can add to what they already have
to structure these sort of playful situations?
And finally, the need to generate these constraints
gives us a way to get at the game system.
So that the system we are creating is step by step produced from the experiences we are
intending to evoke in the player.
We are creating a system that will contain constraints, that will interact with constraints
that the player already has, that will structure the situations we want, that will be playful
in a way.
that will keep the player engaged.
And as a result of that, they'll have a set of performative moves
that will reinforce certain either understandings or strategies
within the player that will linger with them after the game is over
and gives us a way to actually convey something meaningful, hopefully,
to players who are part of receptive audiences.
Thank you very much. That's it in a nutshell.
Thank you.
It's kind of hard to summarize an entire book in 25 minutes.
But there's a whole lot more in the book
about designing goals and anticipation
and how this all ties into narrative.
But this at least gives you a background
and gives you a sense of whether this might be something
that you're at all interested in.
And so now if there are questions,
there is a microphone and these lights are in my eyes
and I have no idea if anybody actually goes to it or not.
So.
Hello?
Yes, I can kind of see you.
Okay, cool.
So where I teach,
Breda University of Applied Sciences in the Netherlands.
We're very much focused on what you described as the transactional model at the start there,
and then after a couple of projects we jump straight to, we're very focused on like the
Ubisoft rational game design, really deep dive, like what are your parameters, what are your
variables kind of approach. Do you have any experience with that Ubisoft kind of model or
that kind of level of...
Not really, because I've kind of been designing this way
for my entire professional career.
Okay.
So, yeah.
It sounds very much like this sits between those two concepts,
and we have noticed we have a gap there,
so this is really interesting.
Cool. Yeah, actually, I'm supposed to repeat the questions.
The question was whether this ties in at all
with Ubisoft's model of rational game design.
Okay. Yep. Thank you.
Sure.
Is there anybody else?
I think that may be it then.
Thank you very much and enjoy the rest of the session,
or the rest of the show.