First off, I want to thank all of you for coming.
It is the first session of the day,
and if you're like me, you are super tired.
So I appreciate that you took the time to be here,
because if it weren't my talk,
it'd be hard-pressed to get me
somewhere at 9.30 in the morning.
So, hello everyone.
I am Tara and today we're going to be talking about Evolve and Adventure in Accessibility
Retrofitting.
So basically, I always say, and I tell people this over and over, you should always consider
accessibility from the very beginning of a project.
But what happens when you don't?
And that's what this session is about.
So if you want, you can also follow me on the Twitter.
It's right down there at the bottom.
In case you have a question we don't get to and you want to ask me later.
But fair warning, my Twitter account is mostly pictures of cats and beer.
All right, so about me. I have worked on some stuff.
I always think these slides are kind of silly,
because it is like, why you should listen to me on this subject?
But basically, I have been in the video game industry for about nine years.
Mostly working at AAA studios on stuff like Saints Row 2,
Evolve, obviously, Bioshock Infinite, Red Faction Guerrilla.
But I have also been in game accessibility for eight years,
starting with AbleGamers, later becoming the chairperson
of the IGDA Game Accessibility SIG,
where I championed some.
cool stuff, and then just last Monday there was the first ever
game accessibility conference, hashtag GAConf, and I was the co-chair
or co-director, whatever you want to call it, of that conference.
I guess I've done work in this field, just trust me. I promise I'm not lying to you.
So in this presentation, what are we going to be talking about today?
So step one was how did we evaluate our accessibility after the fact?
What did we eventually do to make our game more accessible?
What did we learn during this process?
And how can you just take what we did, use that knowledge to make your projects better,
and not make the same mistakes we did?
So obviously the first question was, how well did we do?
And something interesting about asking that question is
you have to have a benchmark to grade yourself against.
And we didn't actually have one.
So although there are plenty of guidelines out there on
how you should develop an accessible game, there isn't
really a scorecard to check your game against.
So that's where we started.
We made one.
We took the guidelines that were published at GameAccessibilityGuidelines.com,
the includification guidelines by AbleGamers,
the special effect wish list, and then all of the recommendations
by the IGDA Game Accessibility SIG,
and we combined them into a giant feature list,
of course moving duplicates because there were some,
and kind of starting off that.
In the end, we had about 150 unique accessibility action items
that we could check against to see if we had done it or not.
So once we basically had this giant list of features,
we know not all features are created equal,
so we evaluated each feature for a few different things.
So number one was its reach,
or the number of people it would benefit.
The next one was the impact,
so the difference it would make to the people it reached.
And then the cost.
Now when we considered the cost,
we did that in the amount of effort
that would have been needed.
if we had done it originally, not what the cost of retrofitting it was, but if
we had planned for it from the beginning, how hard would this to have been
implemented?
It was really convenient to get this list together and organize in that fashion.
Because most of the lists, particularly the Game Accessibility Guidelines and Includification,
are already bucketed in the same way.
Based on this information, we placed each of the different features into a tier and
we assigned it a point value.
Something basic would be like subtitles.
Just having subtitles, really basic feature, really easy to do.
3 points, but having subtitles that have optional letterboxing, multiple size value, repositioning
options, a lot more work but make the subtitles a lot better, 10 points.
So it was kind of how much work did you put in for this?
So we went through item by item and we awarded points for fully met goals.
Partial goals for partial implementation or subpar implementations, like technically we meet this requirement, but it's not a good user experience.
Zero points for just not having anything or marking it as not applicable.
if it didn't work for us.
So for example, if there was a guideline on how to do voice activation, we didn't have
that, so we weren't going to ding us for not having something related to that.
So what was our overall score?
We ended up having like 64%.
That's a D. Not exactly a great score.
Some would say it's near failing, actually.
So obviously we had a lot of room for improvement.
So we needed to figure out where to start,
and so we started going through the report card
and looking for those basic items first
to see where to start and what could be an easy win.
And the key points were looking to see, like I said, if there were any of those basic features
that were missed.
And then we went through and started collecting player feedback.
So one of the areas we really looked for was in our forums and seeing what players were
already saying that they wanted and kind of cross-checking those two things to see if
there was something that, oh, this would be easy and it's already something that players
are requesting a lot.
So, once we identified the list of features, we started scoping out the work and set our
plan into motion.
So what was the first thing we did?
Actually, one of the most requested features
for game accessibility was amazingly simple,
and it had next to no cost.
Gamers with disabilities often do not know
if they can play a game until they buy it
and bring it home, open it.
And this is due to the lack of information
about the accessibility features contained within the title.
This information normally isn't made public, so again, it puts these gamers with disabilities
in the situation that they've bought something that now they're stuck with because they can't
return it.
I guess you could trade it into GameStop for like $5, but that's not exactly a great value
proposition.
So all of the references, every list we looked at, just asked for this.
So we grabbed the game accessibility icon,
this little controller wheelchair guy,
which is available from One Switch for just, you know,
creative commons use, as long as you're denoting
game accessibility information.
And we made a simple online post,
and we also posted this in our forums,
that was just a factual list.
We had to state what features we had, the options associated with those features, and
we were honest about what our title didn't have.
Pretty early on, we decided that we would rather be open about our game's features,
and if we did not have something, be honest about it,
and hope that in the future we could be better.
Maybe even deter someone from buying our title in some cases,
rather than having them buy it and go through that experience
where they just spent their money on something they cannot use.
I was talking to one of the co-founders, Phil,
and kind of advocating on why we should do this.
He was like, yes, we need to put that information out there.
Not doing it would just be shitty.
So it was very nice to get that kind of buy-in
Because I don't know if you guys have ever been at a studio like that where you don't say
You don't say anything that could stop someone from buying your title. So it was very
refreshing to be someplace that that was honest and
Didn't want to have a gamer buy something they couldn't use
So, the next feature we actually got as one of the number one requested things out of
the forums, and it also fell into the basic category on our list, was being colorblind
friendly.
So one of the things we quickly realized was we had a lot of UI elements that were using color only to identify the state of things.
So one example was our ping system, which used red or green circles based on what you were pinging or marking.
And the fix was really simple and it actually inspired us to make the ping system much more useful.
So we ended up using a series of symbols to denote what wildlife was what.
So you can see on the example on the left, the monster instead of a red circle now has a paw
print icon. This plant that's going to eat you now has an exclamation mark. I don't know,
I don't remember what I was pinging on the far right, but that was something friendly. So it
just has the less scary paw print icon. So we were able to make things more recognizable and
give people more information. And all of a sudden, you know, this section was now colorblind friendly.
Something else that we noticed was in our game,
if you were looking at player names,
that was how you could identify what class
someone was in if you just didn't know the characters.
We realized that the names were just colors.
So if you can't tell the difference between the colors,
you don't know what class that person is in,
unless you're super knowledgeable about the game.
So with that one, we ended up doing something really simple.
We ended up just placing all of the icons above the name.
So that if you had colorblind mode turned on, these icons
would appear and you could tell the difference.
But we actually had some larger problems.
Now I know the screenshot is probably a little blurry, but
I liked it because it.
showed one of our larger problems.
We had several in-game visual effects
that would either display the state on color,
which was one problem,
but it was compounded with this problem,
and it was some visual effects
were just getting lost in-game completely.
So here, for someone who is red-green colorblind,
this red icon in the green swamp would just get lost.
We knew early on that adding a color filter was not the right answer.
Colorblind issues, number one, only applied to certain visual effects,
not everything, not the entire game.
Furthermore, adding a colorblind filter could fix the problem,
but it would also make the game really, really ugly,
and it could potentially shift other colors that weren't a problem.
into a problem state. So we knew that was not going to be what we wanted to do,
but we still had to deal with this in some way. This was obviously still a problem.
What we ended up doing was making an additional three version
of that visual effects that the player would select
before loading into the game.
Let that sink in, that is right.
For the features we found causing issues with color blindness,
we ended up with four separate versions of that effect.
The one we shipped with, and then three additional ones
for the most common types of color blindness.
Obviously, the cost of retrofitting colorblind mode for us was extraordinarily high.
It literally quadrupled the work of some of the visual effects.
But we knew this was something that we needed to be aware of going forward, and we kind
of made it our internal goal to not introduce anything new because we were still releasing
hunters, monsters.
We didn't want to introduce a new character that would need to be hooked up into the system.
In my screenshot here, I really like this screenshot because you can see that, like
I said, when we turned on Colorblind Mode, it is not changing everything in-game.
It is only changing these problem visual effects.
The only thing that is different are the footprints on the left and the targeting reticule in
the middle.
This is really important.
There are people who do Colorblind Mode wrong.
all the time.
So I really, it's like, just let this soak in,
absorb it.
If you learn something about colorblind mode today,
it's that please don't do a filter,
just address the problem areas.
Now, like I said, we ended up being smart
and basically starting at the concept phase.
we would tell if a visual effect was gonna be a problem
in colorblind mode.
So if a gun had two different states,
like charging and ready to fire,
but the concept art looked like the picture on the left,
we knew that wasn't gonna fly,
and we'd just send that straight back.
But if it had a other visual difference, something other than color, a second way of displaying
that information, like the one on the right, we knew that that was going to work, that
was good, we could use that one, and then we'd actually go about building the visual
effect.
In the end, we did have several additional updates to Colorblind Mode
after the initial patch that contained it.
We updated even more UI elements,
and we caught things such as in-game outlines
to make them also part of the system.
The class icon fix that I mentioned previously,
that ended up being so popular, we had non-Colorblind players
using Colorblind Mode so that they could see that icon.
In the end, we actually pulled that out of Colorblind Mode,
made it its own toggle that was on by default.
That just goes to show accessibility features will be used beyond your core player base
and makes games better for everyone.
The next one we decided to tackle was remappable controls.
Although we had remappable keyboard controls on PC,
we did not have anything for the controller,
meaning that console players were left
completely without the ability to remap.
This was a highly requested feature and
incredibly helpful for gamers with various impairments,
or if they were using a specialty controller
that did not work with our out-of-the-box control schemes.
What was interesting for me personally
while I was digging into this feature,
I mean, kind of pushing it to get made,
was I learned at one time.
This feature had actually been in development, but it ended up being cut.
Although there was a couple people who had championed it previously, they had kind of
attempted to simply duplicate the system that was on PC onto console, and it led to a kind
of buggy design.
And the result was a system that really wasn't worth the effort, and so it got cut.
Now, once we decided that, no, we're going back,
we're going to do this right, is something we need to tackle,
we actually took inspiration straight
from a previous GDC talk of mine,
which I'm sure you all saw, No More Excuses, Your Guide
to Accessible Design, and we implemented the button swap
method.
Now, although I'm sure you all saw it,
let me go ahead and refresh your memory on what that was.
We offer the player different preset control schemes.
Evolve actually shipped with five different control schemes for Hunters
and four for Monsters that the player could choose from.
The next part of this process is making sure the control schemes group different actions together.
If you look at this one, you can see that Action Reload is grouped together on the left.
Then on the right, Action Use Cover is grouped together.
That is what I am talking about when grouping things together differently.
This mixture of actions, not just rearranging the buttons,
allows the player more customization when they are trying to remap their controls.
Once a player decides on what control scheme they want,
the player is simply given the option to switch what is mapped between two buttons.
Everything that is with that button goes with it.
It is not like, I want useCover to move with action but reload stays there.
No, you would have to find another control scheme that offered that pairing.
I know a lot of people get, like, Tara, my button Y does six things.
just have everything that goes with Y move in this method.
So for getting this in and getting this tested on Evolve,
it was actually really easy.
We avoided a lot of the pitfalls of remappable controls
because we already had a remapping system on PC.
So our UI was already set up to be able to update.
We already had the UI elements for all of these icons
already available.
We had like one small thing where like a monster scheme and hunter scheme had
something that was shared on controller but we just had to split that and that
was pretty much all we had to do. The largest loss of work was the first time
someone tried to do it and it actually got cut. Now so this is a system for us
that had very little overhead in terms of getting it implemented.
But as I was saying previously, if we didn't already
have a PC remapping available and we didn't already
have all that art ready with UI, this
could have been something that would
have been way more expensive to add in after the fact.
So these two features were the first accessibility patch
that we actually got launched.
Sorry, excuse me.
We decided that we were just going to roll out
the accessibility features in chunks as they were ready,
rather than waiting for the game to be 100 percent accessible,
because that will never happen anyway.
In our weekly livestream,
we took time to educate our audience on, number one,
the idea of what game accessibility is
and why it was important.
Not why just it was important to us as developers,
but to us as gamers.
and we showed off all the features and told players how they could provide additional feedback,
requests, and we really opened the door for accessibility conversations with our players.
We wanted it to be a dialogue.
So the accessibility portion of our live stream lasted over 30 minutes of Evolve's weekly
live stream on the Twitch channel, which has over 23,000 followers.
And it was also hosted by the Turtle Rock Twitch channel.
So I got to be on there.
I was really excited.
I didn't, you know, there aren't many live streams that highlight accessibility.
So for me personally, it was a big day.
But obviously, we didn't just stop at two separate features.
Around this time, we were actually
getting ready for the launch of Evolve Stage 2, which
was the free-to-play relaunch of the game.
And we wanted to make the game even more accessible.
We ended up having a big update on our visual effects.
One of the things that became very apparent was there was a lot,
like a literal shit ton of things happening in our game.
There were four different guns that could be fired,
there were area attacks, monster attacks, there were wildlife,
and some of it was very, very obtrusive and often happening simultaneously.
To be honest, a lot of these visual effects were not only making it difficult for players
with visual impairments, it was just hard for players in general.
We took this approach at overhauling the visual effects and we updated almost half of them
with the goal of clarity, less noise, and defined borders.
If you look at this example, this is Hyde firing his flamethrower in a toxic grenade
cloud.
And the before and after is drastic.
In the left, like, you don't even know what he's firing at.
So obviously, like, these were big changes.
These changes were across the board.
If you look at this screenshot, you can see the before and after of Kratkin's Aftershock.
Before, it was a completely fuzzy vortex.
But after the redesign, it had a well-defined and high contrast edge that allowed players
to know where the end of this was.
What was the hit zone.
This actually helped to relieve a major problem that we had been experiencing.
Only players who played against Kraken all the time, who were really experienced,
knew how far you had to dodge to avoid getting hit.
You just had to know before these changes went in.
Now that I had a defined border and a clear outline,
it was easy to see all players, even new players,
knew where they needed to go to get out of the way.
As I mentioned previously, we often had multiple complex visual effects happening simultaneously.
Sometimes they would stack and stick.
Another thing we did to help this was develop a unified language for all of our visual effects
to make them similar so you had a better idea of what was happening, where it was going
to happen, so we didn't have too much happening in one place.
Much like with the concept art in dealing with colorblindness, we had a very similar
approach on making sure we weren't.
doing things that were going to be too busy or might cause new conflicts
become a problem going forward.
One thing that also became clear to us
was although our tutorials allowed for a safe space for the player to learn
the controls without dying, it wasn't a good representation
of seeing if the player actually understood the game, the cues around them,
or even just how to play.
Originally, we only offered Goliath and Markov tutorials.
Later, we expanded them to include these Hunt tutorials,
which were basically advanced tutorials.
Each one catered to a specific character in that class,
who we determined was sort of the best starter character
for that group, the one that was normally the easiest to use.
And these tutorials allowed for everyone
to get a better grasp of the basics before moving on.
And it was a space that the player could take their time
and adjust to any class without pressure
and helpful guidance.
So in our original tutorials,
let's say we had a gamer with a specialty controller
who was trying to see if they could, you know,
use their controller to play.
They couldn't learn that from our original tutorials because it wasn't really playing.
It was, you are here, press A to jetpack there.
Not a very good representation.
So with these advanced tutorials, it was much better for someone trying to understand if
they could play or trying to learn to play.
These tutorials were actually one of the most complex things we ended up retrofitting.
It was a great experience for us as devs, though.
Not only, number one, did we have to see if we actually understood how to play our game,
we had to teach how to play it to others.
We ended up actually having to develop a new audio queuing system to ensure the most important
VO, which was the voiceover from Abe and Kyra, who were leading you through this tutorial.
make sure they were heard above other noises.
We also had to develop a priority system for the subtitles
because we also didn't want them to get stomped out
by less important systemic lines.
Like if Kyra was telling you something important
about how to fight this monster,
we didn't want Hank saying reloading
to push her subtitle off screen.
So, and this also was, you know, heavily scripted and just required a lot of man work to get
done.
So, this was something that doing it after the fact and trying to teach players, you
know, how to do this afterwards was pretty high.
Another one of our largest efforts was actually updating our in-game UI and having it match
the existing visual effects.
There could be a disparity.
A UI element could be a blue bar on a health thing, but a green cross in the world.
You may not realize that was telling you the same information twice.
And we also found out that we had a ton of in-game occurrences that were either sound-based
and sometimes so subtle that players, even without hearing impairments, just didn't know
that they existed, or the UI was so subtle or lacking contrast that they were overlooked
and frequently just unused.
So we took efforts to double down on communicating a lot of this information, and this included
being poisoned, healing. The Defense Matrix is shown here.
Previously, if someone was being shielded, they would have a little bar on top of their health bar.
But here, as you can see, the visual effects, boom, it is right on top of the character.
It is a lot easier to see. Also, if you had a Defense Matrix on you,
I should have got a better screenshot now that I think of it, but on the left you can see you
have that same icon showing up for you.
It looks the same, the visuals are the same, they're bolder, they're a lot easier to see.
We also did this for shielding fire damage.
Beyond this, we also took steps to make a lot of other things visually clear.
Visual tells dead carcasses, so if a monster killed a wildlife and went on its way,
that carcass would be there to let you know that the monster had gone this way.
But if you couldn't notice the carcass, obviously that's not helpful.
We ended up putting outlines on them so you could see them more clearly.
We also did the same thing for elite wildlife.
If they had like a...
tower of light. They offered you buffs if you kill them, so you want to kill them,
but if you can't find them, it doesn't do you any good.
We also added new UI for major gameplay events, such as teammates dying, being revived, that kind of thing.
Of course, you cannot add UI elements for everything.
That would be terrible.
We also decided to put an in-game announcer
who was capturing a lot of these events.
If something was there visually, but maybe not strong,
or it was not something we thought should have a UI element,
the VO of the announcer could help reinforce that
and display that information in a second way.
Like I said, we just kind of went crazy.
We got all sorts of new UI things.
We had the ping that changed, and now all of a sudden,
if you are harpooned, you get an icon for that.
Stuff that, again, we had a lot of things
that we just kind of expected players to figure out.
At one point, we updated how Behemoth's armor worked,
and no one knew what was happening.
We ended up adding information for that.
We are telling you when your dropship is coming.
Really, there was a lot of information we realized
that if you just didn't know it.
then you are not going to get it from in-game anywhere.
That was a lot of what we were doing.
One of the other things we realized,
and I think that goes in tandem,
is that Evolve had a difficulty problem.
We found that our gameplay was frequently inaccessible.
You know, if one player were underperforming, as it were,
it could ruin the experience for the entire team
and put them in a situation where they couldn't recover.
It was creating this extraordinarily toxic
get good kind of community,
which obviously wasn't what we wanted.
So one of the things we did was change our gameplay to more evenly distribute these gameplay tasks.
Make it so that more people could take a chance at doing some of this stuff.
It meant that if there was a struggle for a certain player with a particular class,
the team could balance it out and still have a chance at winning.
We wanted to create gameplay that was inclusive, where a whole team could work together
rather than punish new or inexperienced players,
or a player who was struggling because they weren't good at a particular class.
We ended up changing a lot.
We reworked three of the major class abilities, which are kind of like, you know...
staples in the game. For me, the best example of this is the mobile arena, or
as players just called it, the dome. It originally could only be thrown by the
trapper, and the trapper would have to throw it to where they thought the
monster was going to be.
For some players, such as myself, being a trapper was legitimately stressful.
I personally lacked both the skill and reflexes to capture the monster.
I was known for throwing domes and catching absolutely nothing in them.
It had a significant recharge time, so once I threw that dome,
missed the monster, we'd all have to hang out for another two minutes until I get to try again,
at which point I'd probably still miss the monster.
We changed it for stage two so that all classes could throw the dome.
Even better, when you went to throw the dome, it came down automatically over the monster.
Now anyone could throw it, and you were guaranteed to capture the monster.
We had to make some changes to how the dome worked once you captured the monster because of that,
but it was still so much better.
For myself and a lot of other people, the class went from something we literally dreaded
to something that was new and exciting to explore.
Some of the characters even got more than one class change.
With Behemoth, we actually took time to not only redo his abilities,
we fixed tons of long-standing bugs.
He basically got a full refactor.
But we did some other stuff, like tinkering with how our Aim Assist worked,
changing our controls on our...
What's the right word? The sensitivities on our controller to make it better.
I mean, we just went ham.
I've never worked on another project that basically took so many core tenets of gameplay
and we're like, fuck it, doing it live.
Again, patching every week. We're crazy people.
But it was all better, and it made a lot of improvements.
Now, as I mentioned earlier, in many cases,
gamers with disabilities don't know if they can play a game
until after they buy it, at which point,
they'll find out it doesn't work.
And that's why it was so important for us
to publish that list of game accessibility
features that we had.
But in-game, after we went free to play,
we had a similar problem.
So now,
Anyone could download the game, anyone could play for free,
but you could still spend either real money or in-game currency
to unlock new characters, unlock new perks.
And again, we really had no way for any particular player
to know if they liked that character
or if they could even use that character or that perk
without that initial investment.
Again, we wanted to give the players this information.
For us, we figured the best way to do this was to remove the problem
by implementing a try-before-you-buy system for all characters and perks.
The player is actually able to go into single player and play anything,
any of the characters, any of the perks, as much as they wanted,
for no cost to them.
They could go in and see if they liked it before they spent their money.
Obviously, playing in single player isn't quite the same.
as playing in multiplayer.
We also offer free characters on rotation every week
so that players could try these new characters
that they didn't own in multiplayer as well as single player.
Something else that was really fun was for Global Accessibility Awareness Day,
which is in May every year,
we saw Uncharted 4's awesome video
that they released about their game accessibility features
as part of Global Accessibility Awareness Day.
Basically, I got super jealous because I was like,
we've done accessibility work, this isn't fair.
Why does Naughty Dog get an awesome video?
So I was like, we should do something.
We should do something right now.
So literally right right then we're like, well, what we can do we can do a stream and so we
Didn't even like go to our we have a
Like a streaming area with like a proper green screen and all that stuff. We didn't even do that
We like rocked a whiteboard up behind my desk and erased it put a camera on my desk
We're like we're doing it here. We're doing it right now
So yeah, we just did a global accessibility awareness day stream about Evolve just straight from my desk in the office.
So on the stream we talked about some of the changes that were due to be released in our next big update,
which were some of the things that I've kind of talked about up to this point.
And
we talked about some other changes.
that were going to be coming up as well.
And what was really great was the amount of people
who showed up to the stream,
and very few of them are actually gamers with impairments.
They were just gamers who were excited to learn.
The stream was also a great opportunity for us.
Our, again, low-budget, at-my-desk stream with a whiteboard as the background got picked
up by a few blogs who were rounding up the news for the day, for Global Accessibility
Awareness Day.
And so we got exposure through accessibility that we wouldn't have otherwise gotten.
And we also announced two other features that, at the time, didn't have a cemented ship date
that were still in the works.
Now, one of these features were closed captions.
This was a feature we actually started developing way back at the same time as remappable controls
and colorblind mode, but it didn't get done in time for the first patch.
Although hooking up the system to give the options of subtitles and closed captions was done really quickly without many issues,
the major stumbling block was actually what sounds should be triggering a cue.
You know, what sounds do we have in game that are actually really important to gameplay?
So along with the engineer who built the system,
I took a stab at making a first draft of lists of
what sounds I thought were important and should be triggered with the system.
So once I had the list, I brought it over to our balance group.
So our balance group was comprised mostly of QA
that we had hired out of the competitive community that
would make sure that when we made changes we weren't breaking our game at
a super high level.
They knew how to properly utilize every cue in game, so I brought it to them.
Here is an accurate rendition of how our conversation went.
Hey guys, look, I have this list of awesome game accessibility things that should trigger
sound.
Can you give it a once over?
I am sure it is perfect.
Tara, you left spotters off the list.
I have no idea what you are talking about.
Tara, don't you know spotters make a noise when they hear the monster?
No, I didn't know that.
So, although I will admit I don't have the best hearing,
I had no idea that that sound was even in-game.
And that was just one of the many sounds I learned in-game
that meant something that I had no clue about.
This coupled with UI changes I mentioned earlier,
were just another way we had information
that was not getting to not just our core players,
but especially those who had impairments.
What ended up happening with this was,
at the same time we were trying to identify the sounds,
we had started making a lot of
these crazy gameplay adjustments.
We ended up holding off until after the adjustments were made and seeing what new UI we were adding
before we went to put sounds on the closed caption system, so we could wrap our head
around what wasn't being reinforced in some way.
Unfortunately, this was a feature that never shipped.
It was still in progress when Turtle Rock's contract ended with 2K for Evolve.
It was something that I was personally really excited about, so I was pretty bummed when
it didn't get out.
The other one was the comm wheel.
One of the things that had become very apparent
was if you weren't using a mic or couldn't use a mic,
our game was nearly impossible to play.
Communicating with your teammates and other players was key.
So sure, on PC, you had in-game text chat,
but number one, that wasn't always fast enough.
If you're in the middle of a fight,
like hitting enter type stuff,
not very efficient.
There wasn't actually any way to do that on console at all.
If you are on console, there was no way for you to talk to your other players
if you didn't have a mic.
We started developing a Commwheel.
This is the original concept art.
Unfortunately, I wasn't able to get an in-game screenshot of
what it ended up looking like.
It was fairly true to this.
Basically, our goal was
Identify the most important things you need to tell your teammates.
I am down, we should group up, that kind of stuff, like heal me, blah, blah, blah.
Once you triggered it, it would have some sort of in-game visual effects.
For example, if you wanted to group up here,
a little visual effect popped up in the world
to show you where you wanted to group up.
Honestly, the largest problem we encountered was trying to have a comm wheel that nicely
integrated with both platforms in terms of controlling it.
Since we'd used so much real estate on the controller, particularly already, for everything
that you could do.
And we had play tested it.
We're still kind of tweaking it to make it
a truly great usable experience.
And also around that time was when our contract ended
with Evolve.
So this was another thing that was in progress that
didn't get to ship, but we were pretty excited about it.
So what should you learn about Total Rock and Evolve's
adventure and accessibility retrofitting?
So some of the things we implemented weren't that much work to add them in after the fact,
but some things that should have been stupid simple, like colorblind mode,
ended up being huge endeavors.
But none of the stuff would have been that difficult or hard if we had just thought about it early in development.
If one person had mentioned it or kept track of it,
maybe we wouldn't have made so many mistakes to begin with.
So I know this doesn't sound like an actual lesson, but apparently it is worth repeating.
Pre-production is the time to think about accessibility.
Doing accessibility from the beginning is not expensive.
Retrofitting accessibility can be incredibly costly.
Please don't do it.
The other thing we learned is, you know your game.
You know how your game works.
But to really understand how players engage your game,
you need playtests with people who
do not work on your project.
At minimum, they should be on a different project, friends
or family.
people from outside your studio who don't know your game like you do.
get some user research up in there, up in that business.
So we knew how to play our game,
but we needed to see if other people did.
One of the things that I was also really jealous of,
I mean, this talk should be subtitled
Tara Jealous of Naughty Dog.
We didn't have the resources to do it,
but one of the things that Naughty Dog did
when they were putting in their game accessibility features
was they actually had gamers
with different physical impairments come in and test it.
that was something that I would have loved for us to have the time and
resources to do.
So if you get that chance, do it.
Another thing was a lot of the changes that were massively beneficial to gamers with disabilities
weren't always even proposed for accessibility reasons.
They just happened to have a huge impact for these gamers while improving the experience of the core audience.
Most accessibility features fell into this category.
We didn't implement a single accessibility feature that hurt the core audience.
And that's something that I have to fight all the time.
I get told, oh, but no one will use this.
This only, the core gamers won't like it.
That's just absolutely not true.
So don't think that that's bad.
And lastly, our accessibility efforts
wouldn't have been nearly as successful
if we hadn't told people about them
and got buy-in from our community.
So we shared this information on our live streams, our forum, our social media accounts,
and we created a dialogue with our players and we created an avenue to get feedback from them.
We became more connected with our player base.
And really the coolest thing about this was
we created our own little army of accessibility advocates
out of our players.
So users in our forum,
they were helping other players find what they need.
The forum members were tagging devs and being like,
hey, did you see so-and-so's request?
I think this falls under accessibility.
Or in some cases, they would want a feature and ask us,
hey, I was interested in this.
Would this also help someone with an impairment?
And that's awesome.
They were...
getting empathy for these other gamers. I mean even today they still
tweet at me cool accessibility stories or if they see it in the news and they share it with me and they're excited about
helping more gamers game and
like I actually have something to to back this up. So one of the coolest things that happened was Shara
which is Shane and Tara, really official,
sponsoring Hashtag GA Conf,
or the Game Accessibility Conference
that happened for the first time last Monday.
At Total Rock, the now Community Marketing Manager and I, Shane,
we would just stream us playing video games
and making mixed drinks after work on Tuesdays.
Collectively, we became known as Shara.
Shane and I were both working at the Game Accessibility Conference.
At the time, we were still doing fundraising for the conference,
and we decided it would be awesome to try and raise money
to become a Bronze-level sponsor on our goofy-ass Tuesday Twitch stream.
So we brought it up one day, and within an hour, we had raised the funds.
So these names on the right, they are just Twitch users,
with the exception of Mommy Au Pair, who is my mom,
who decided that they loved games, and they want everyone to be able to play
games, and they put their money towards the cause.
So by talking about accessibility with your community,
they'll grow as people,
they'll get empathy and it comes down to gamers want to play games,
gamers want other people to be able to play games.
For us, like I said,
they literally put their money behind us to help us teach
other game developers how to become more accessible and help everyone.
So.
You may be interested at this point on doing your own accessibility adventure.
So I was going to go ahead and go over in a little bit more detail what we use to make
our report card.
So the first one is in Cluedification, which is done by a really popular charity for disabled
gamers here in the US called Able Gamers.
And they have, you can download it as a PDF or they just have their website.
For me, what's really nice about this is it gives you...
empathetic stories. They'll be like, hey here's a feature, but then they'll also
either give you a real-life scenario of like, oh I see that you are trying to ban
this type of third-party feature in your game. Well let me tell you a
story of how because of another studio doing that, this girl with
cerebral palsy was no longer able to play her game because it was flagged as
cheating software.
It gives you lots of heartfelt examples on why some of these features matter.
It also has some great letters from the community and other game developers.
If you need emotional validation on why the work you're doing is good, this is a great list.
So the other one we used was the Game Accessibility Guidelines.
This is actually the one I prefer,
because I don't need that stuff.
I just want a straight list of, do you have this?
Who did it best?
Who did it wrong?
Let me learn.
So this is just gameaccessibilityguidelines.com.
It was put together by tons of different accessibility
advocates.
Like I said, they work together.
It is a living document.
They updated it fairly regularly with either new examples,
new cases, new best case examples.
Like I said, this is one that I reference all the time.
The other one was the IGDA, Game Accessibility Special Interest Group.
They have a set of guidelines.
This one is a little bit more...
The other ones have been more recently updated, but it is still really good.
What is really awesome about the IGDA Game Accessibility website is they have an awesome
resource page that links out to tons of places to get additional information.
You can also just email...
They have an email list and if you have a question,
I want to do this, I'm not sure how, you will within two days get like 10
responses from other accessibility people who will either point you in the
right path, give you the resources you need, tell you
how to do it. It's a great tool to find
people who can help you.
Now the other thing I did is if you go to this terrible long
URL. Sorry, this is what Google did when I published the document. You can actually go and download the scorecard that we used, if you want to have your own scorecard.
So it's pretty easy. On the left, we have the item, if I could link easily to one page I did, the available points, what type of implementation you had, and then the awarded points.
You know, it does some formulas and spits out a number at the end.
So I'll leave this up for another second so you can take a screenshot because that URL is terrible.
You know, that's really it.
So I'm gonna take some questions.
I'm also gonna remind you right now
to please fill out your surveys
and tell everyone how great I was.
And so yeah, there is a microphone right here.
So if anyone has questions, you can come up and ask it.
And yeah, so let's take some questions.
What do we got?
Come on.
Here we go.
I guess so. Oh, what feature did you most want to put in that
for whatever reason at a time budget, whatever you just
couldn't
I think for me personally it really was the closed captions, especially since with the,
you know, Turtle Rock did the original Left 4 Dead and it had closed captions and it was
one of the first games that was kind of recognized by the accessibility community as having closed
captions so that was one that I was always really sad didn't go out because, you know,
Turtle Rock had kind of set this benchmark of, hey, we have closed captions.
And then unfortunately, Evolve didn't.
So it was both needed and I had an emotional investment
of wanting to get it out.
So I was sad that it didn't.
Hi, first time caller, long time fan.
What can platforms be doing and what can middleware
be doing to help make this process of adding accessibility
to your titles easier?
So I was actually just talking with some of my friends
at Ready at Dawn at the Oculus party last night,
and they came up to me and they were like,
Tara, I really, really love that there's the backup
of platform level remapping, but they want an easy way,
so if a player does want to remap their controls,
they would love to have a way to basically read,
I don't know, maybe some sort of API or something
that's like,
This player wants their controls remap to be like this,
and the game to just be able to look at that file
and load it up and do it that way.
So I think there is a craving for a, hey,
if they're using these accessibility features
on the console level, let me as a game look at that stuff
or look at that stuff more easily
so that I can mirror those same choices they're making
at a platform level in my game.
Yes, what do we got?
So in terms of convincing your studio to make good choices about accessibility, did you have like a really compelling source of stats or anything about player accessibility needs or disabilities?
Yes, so I did and it was actually really funny. So with Total Rock
When I went to convince them that we should be doing it I did I had a whole presentation together
So 22 percent of Americans have an impairment that could affect the way they game and I I did I had all these stats
Right, you know, it's like yeah, you know a low-balling estimate is, you know
9% of colors are players are colorblind and I did I put together like a 20 page
deck and I was like we got this and I was on like slide two and you know Chris and Phil were like
we just want to be good people and have people play our game and I was just like no but I worked
really hard like I got I've got transitions like can we just go through it like I have this star
wipe in here I'm really proud of. Use the star wipe that um you're you're so lucky I've got to
say like because you know sometimes you need to like convince them. Yeah well every um other time
that I'd gone to have that battle um.
I mean, I think the fact that I called it a battle shows how it went, which was why
I prepped this whole talk before I even went to talk to them, because I assumed I would
have to go in like, here's the business case, here's why it makes sense, here's how we can
reach a broader audience and improve our core players' experience.
And Turtle Rock were just like, no, we're good people, let's not be shitty.
What?
Yeah, that's great.
Any source that you would use if they were harder to convince?
Where would you go to find good player disability stats from now on platforms?
Ian Hamilton's Twitter account.
Hey, Ian.
Hey, Matt.
I've been looking for him, actually.
We used to work together.
Yeah, we worked together.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, no, just ask Ian.
Yeah.
No, I'm too intimidated by him.
All right, cool.
Thanks for...
Yeah.
Yeah, but I think you can also get a lot of that information in the guidelines that I
mentioned earlier. They're kind of peppered throughout. The IGDA website does have some
of that basis information, or like I said, Ian Hamilton underscore on Twitter. He just
posts relevant articles all the time. So there you go. Follow Ian on Twitter.
Hi. I was wondering how did you balance making, like, you have all these UI elements for
accessibility, but how do you balance having an intimidating UI versus an accessible one?
Yeah, that was something that it was hard for us because it wasn't so much intimidating
for us as cluttered because we had a lot of things happening.
For us, it was...
The big question really became, does this need to be UI?
Or is there another way that we can reinforce this?
So sometimes, instead of a UI element,
it became a visual effect.
Sometimes it became something we would add a sound for,
but ensure that it was captured in subtitles.
So we did kind of go about the process of identifying key
things that were being missed and then adding them first.
And then sort of stuff more on the periphery.
We really looked to see, does this need to be UI?
Or can we give this information in a different way?
And just play testing.
Like, is this too much?
Is this too intrusive?
Do players understand it?
That kind of thing.
Thank you.
Hi, did you make any changes based on players with epilepsy, by chance?
We did, actually. We cut the intro trailer.
So, we found out after we had shipped,
and this was only for Evolve Stage 2, since it didn't get brought over to consoles,
we actually got contacted by...
I am blanking on her name, but a woman in the UK who...
I don't know how it happened, but she had run parts of Evolve through the test that
shows if you have patterns that could trigger epilepsy. And we found out in the very
beginning sequence that Markov with his lightning gun, it actually hit that pattern. And
so we just cut it. Which worked out great anyway because we were like, oh, we need a
lower install. And so we were like, great, yeah, let's get rid of this video anyway.
You know, it could cause seizures.
And after that, it was definitely something that we were more aware of.
Like, I'm going to be honest, even as an accessibility person,
I frequently forget to consider epilepsy.
Um, but yeah, that was the main change that we made.
Um, for some reason, the in-game version wasn't hitting it.
It was like something about this pre-rendered cutscene
specifically that could cause problems with epilepsy.
Thank you.
Thanks for that talk. So my question is beyond subtitles and UI, were there any other
common feature requests from deaf gamers? The comm wheel was the other big one. The fact
that there wasn't a way to communicate with other players if you couldn't hear them on
console like I said. On PC it wasn't so bad because you know there was the text chat but
you know in the event of like quick action.
You know, it's not like, oh my god, there's a monster.
Let me hit enter and start typing.
That's not as good, which was why we wanted to get the comm wheel out so bad
that so we could allow for quick communication for people who couldn't
hear it or, you know, even talk with other players.
So really the comm wheel.
Okay.
So there wasn't much feedback in terms of flashes or, uh, base sounds.
No, but I think it was mostly because, like I said, there was so much information that
even core gamers didn't realize were being transmitted by sound, that people didn't know
that they didn't have the information.
So obviously, like, deaf gamers weren't hearing about things they didn't know because the
core gamers didn't know, which is a problem in and of itself.
I think if more players had realized...
how much more information we've been given by audio alone,
I think there would have been an increase.
you know, oh, the, like, you could hear the monster sniff,
like if the, you know, monster was looking for the hunters,
and you were a hunter, you could hear that,
and it was so quiet that, like, that was another thing
that I was like, oh, that's an audio cue we have in game?
I had no idea.
So I, like I said, I think if more core gamers
had knew the kinds of sounds that gave information,
I think the deaf gamers would have been more aware
that they were also missing it,
but we were so bad at just letting people know
to begin with that there wasn't a lot of requests.
All right, great, cheers.
Hi, thanks for your talk. I'm interested in the conflict between engaging your high skill cap players and the introduction of accessibility features, which could potentially be called dumbing down the game.
How do you resolve that? A good example that you spoke about would be the mobile arena. How does that balance come into play and how do you resolve that desire to provide a high skill cap for certain players?
Yeah, so what we ended up doing,
so I worked a lot with the balance team directly,
and we started thinking about how
the range of our skilled players,
and
Basically, our goal was to like, so if you think about like,
this is your range of skill available to players.
For us, step one was bringing up this bottom bubble.
So you can still play up here if you want.
You still have to know or be faster,
you know, that kind of stuff in these players down here.
But, you know, we wanted the base level.
to be a little bit higher up.
So that was really when we started thinking,
it was like, how can we bring this bottom level up
while keeping people with super fast reactions
or super great planning, allowing
them to climb up to the top.
So, for example, when we changed the mobile arena so that anyone could capture the monster,
like, that was when we were like, okay, well, now we have, like, a different meta game that's
happening within the dome, and, like, we needed to provide an opportunity for the monster
to be able to get out of it now, because he would always get domed before he could dodge.
So, like, if you were a good fighter, you could...
get out of the dome quickly. You know, just kind of, like I said, it really for us was about
bringing up the bottom players while letting the top players stay up there without taking
away, if we took something away from them that would boost them up higher, giving them
something to replace it essentially.
Okay, thanks. Just as a kind of follow-up, because no one's waiting.
Is there like a communication aspect to that to out to your community?
Like, did you, when you made those changes, did you receive any negative feedback
from people who perceived this as a negative change?
Oh, yeah, yeah.
How did you address that?
We ruined our game.
Exactly. We hate gamers. We hate our game. We're ruining it. We know nothing about our game. We know nothing how to play.
No, we it was really interesting. So there were like two camps. There was like the first camp that was like, oh my god
This is great
Like now I can play with this other set of friends and you know all this other stuff and then there were people there are
Still people today who are like I'm loading up the vault beta branch because classic evolve is better like that uh
There are always going to be people like that, but for us, we worked really hard to communicate
the changes and why we were doing them.
And we were able to win over a lot of people by just having a dialogue.
I think if we had just been silent, be like, we're making these changes, we're not talking
to you about it, it would have gone over super, super poorly.
Especially because a lot of the times we would try to explain things to them before they actually saw it
So like we would warn them and we're like, hey guys, I'm gonna make this change
That's why we're gonna make this change. Oh my god. I hate you. Stop ruining evolve. We're like no we swear
It's making it better
and then we would do stuff to back that up. We were public with our telemetry. So we were
like, hey guys, so we're changing this monster because this monster is just not very good
right now. That monster is the best monster. That monster always wins. Okay, well looking at
the telemetry, that monster only wins 16% of the time, so maybe you're just really bad.
And just putting that information out there so that they could see it.
And like I said, explaining why we were doing things.
And most of the time we got buy-in.
Of course there were some grumpy guesses, but they're always going to be vocal anyway.
Okay, thank you very much.
Hi.
What were you doing about accessibility for players that don't really have a disability
but are really bad with observation and awareness?
So I think a lot of the changes we were making, like,
so for example, the announcer was something like that.
So I know I got really self-involved when I would play as Bucket,
and I would frequently not pay attention to, like, if my teammates were dying
because I was too busy having fun shooting rockets.
So, you know, being able to, like, have the announcer there that's like,
your teammate has died, and you're like,
oh, shit, I should have been paying attention.
You know, we also, like I said, we increased different cues
and more prominent UI elements to really put the stuff
that you should pay attention to in your face.
Because we found, oh, trying to put it subtly over here
on the right, like, oh, hey, someone's down.
There's a little arrow over here that's
like pointing that someone's down.
No, no one saw that.
Like a giant thing in the middle of screen that's like,
someone so died.
It's like, oh, OK, I can't miss that because it's right here.
So for us, it was really identifying,
what should people not miss?
What do they have to know?
OK, yeah, just put it in their face.
They have to see it.
Thank you.
So I think I have time for one more question,
if there are any more questions.
All right.
Just a simple one.
So you mentioned that there was a colorblind mode.
Where did you put that in terms of selecting it,
and why did you put it there?
I think we ended up putting it under.
Thank you.
I would love for Evolve just to have had an accessibility menu.
Again, this talk should be subtitled
Terra Jealous of Uncharted.
So for example, the latest Uncharted just
has an accessibility menu where all of these accessibility
features are in there.
So you can go and look and find them in one place.
because you frequently do need to use them together.
So if you're low vision and you need to up contrast,
you're probably also going to want to
have your aim assist cranked up a little bit.
So putting those all in one menu
would make it really easy to get to in your one-stop shop.
So if I had to go back,
I would love for an accessibility menu.
So that's it, I am out of time.
I will be drinking a tea for like 10 minutes
over in the wrap-up area.
If you have any questions you were dying to ask me.
Otherwise, you can follow me on Twitter, and please, please, please fill out your speaker
surveys and let everyone know that I was awesome.
Thank you!