everyone's having a wonderful GDC so far. Yeah, yeah, that's right.
So, I'm happy to be here. I hope all of you are happy to be here. Not only am I happy to be here
just because it's GDC, it's the first GDC in a couple years. So that's cool. I'm also very happy
that we have a video game releasing this week. It's called Tiny Tina's Wonderlands. So that's
pretty cool. Before we get started, I've been told to ask the crowd a few questions.
Uh, if everybody can like move to the center, uh, it looks like everybody's fine.
Is everybody fine?
Everybody looks good.
Okay.
Uh, turn off your phones and any noise making devices that you might have.
Uh, remember to not record any of this cause, uh, that's illegal.
Uh, yeah.
Sweet.
All right.
So, uh, this is gonna be a talk all about, um, Wonderlands, but don't worry, I'm not gonna spoil
anything. There's mainly gonna be talk about the audio systems in the game and stuff like that,
um, and mostly we're gonna cover loot is the main topic and how in audio we kind of, like,
make the loot special in our own, uh, specific way.
Um, so yeah, shout out to everybody at Gearbox.
I wouldn't be here, you know, there are so many incredible, uh, talented
people on our team and I wouldn't be here if it weren't for all the
amazingly, uh, smart, talented and hardworking people that pour their
hearts and souls into everything we do.
Um, so yeah, big shout out to them.
So who am I? I am Joshua Davidson. I'm lead sound designer at Gearbox Software.
I was born and raised in Macon, Georgia. I graduated full sail in 2007 with an
associate's degree in recording arts. I started my career in video games back in 2007 at Volition Inc.
I worked on Saints Row 2 and Red Faction Guerrilla while I was there.
I did a little bit of music composition on Red Faction Guerrilla.
Not a whole lot, but it was a fun experience.
I started working at Gearbox in 2009, exactly two years after I started my job at Volition.
And the sound design team at that time in 2009 was just Mark Petty, Rayson Varner,
and myself.
I spent about a month or two helping them finish Borderlands 1.
I mainly finished off some bugs and stuff like that on Borderlands 1
and went straight into work on the DLCs.
So Borderlands is kind of known for the long-winded DLCs
and that was a really cool experience to just have that quick turnaround cycle
of working on a project for a month or two and then pushing it out.
We were working very, very fast back then.
So yeah, between 2009 and 2010, this is what the audio team was.
It was Mark Petty as an audio director,
Raisin Varner, audio lead and composer, Andrew Chaney
was an audio lead too, and I was the young sound designer.
We were in this old building in Plano.
This is the old building that we were in between 2009 to 2015.
Those audio offices were kind of makeshift audio offices.
They weren't really designed to be audio offices,
because it was like in a bank.
So we just put audio panels all around the rooms
and tried to make our best with it.
But in 2015, we had an opportunity.
We had this opportunity to build an actual game development
studio from the ground up.
And that was really cool, because it means
we can make.
an audio facility from the ground up,
and actually really, really think about how we want
our audio facility to operate.
So this is just a little diagram.
That little sloppily drawn circle that I did right there
is where all the audio offices are.
There are six control rooms right there.
And we have a live room, and we also have a VO room as well.
So the construction of it began in like middle of 2015 or so for the audio offices.
And these are kind of like what those preliminary shots of them were looking like before we finished construction on them.
And as we go through, you'll start to see the shape of the offices start to come together.
This is one of the control rooms.
And now we got the desk in there.
We got the monitor mounted on the wall.
You can see on the sides there, there's
the acoustic foam batting that goes inside the walls.
So if you actually touch the walls,
you'll feel like this kind of foam inside of it.
And then we have this other layer of cloth
that we put over the top of that.
And then that just kind of helps with the sound more
and also makes it aesthetic.
Yeah, and this is when we started to get more of the equipment in.
And this is the final look of the office, basically.
So, like I said before, we have six control rooms.
One is a Dolby Atmos room now.
It eventually evolved into that around 2019.
As we were kind of finishing up Borderlands 3,
we got pretty hardcore about making sure
that we are a game supported Atmos.
The control rooms themselves are powered by Yamaha Nuage,
which runs on the Dante network.
I don't know if y'all are familiar with that.
But basically, the Dante network allows us to be able to have every room networked from one to another.
So you can set up a microphone in one room and then record in any room you want, really.
You can record from control room one to control room six, and vice versa.
So it's a really flexible facility that we have.
And from 2015 to 2020, we all came to this facility to work every work day.
And then the pandemic happened.
So yeah, we were all there when the pandemic changed everything.
And Gearbox went fully remote, as did a lot of game developers,
and as a lot of different jobs in the world became fully remote.
And, you know, things changed very quickly.
Luckily for us, we had shipped Borderlands 3 already.
We'd already got that out the door.
So that was about six months prior.
We were making good progress on the DLCs,
but still, this was a drastic change,
and a lot of people had to make adjustments.
And while we were also adjusting...
Gearbox was looking to grow in size.
And, and, and, uh, despite that pandemic, excuse me, uh, despite the pandemic
happening, we did a lot of hiring and, uh, we did a lot of really interesting
things between the start of the pandemic.
And now, in fact, that's what I'm about to show you today.
Um, so, um.
So yeah, we started hiring quite a bit.
So this is the audio crew in 2022 in Frisco, Texas.
Frisco, Texas is headquarters for Gearbox right now.
So we have Mark Betty.
He's our head of audio.
And now we have a sound design branch.
And so the sound designers are basically
the sole content creators for the sound design in our games.
And so we have staff that are just completely dedicated
towards that now.
We also now have tech sound designers.
So our tech sound design team is basically,
they're in charge of creating audio systems
and spearheading implementation.
They work on things like occlusion
and in-game DSP systems,
such as in-world convolution reverb.
They also help the sound designers
get temporary audio hooked up
to the various gameplay systems in our games.
So yeah, they have a pretty big task.
And we also have audio code that helps us create the tools
that we all end up utilizing.
We also have VO design now.
We have a, you know, there's a lot of voice in our games.
And it's got to get recorded, edited, organized,
and processed.
We also have an in-house composer, Joshua Caro,
and we have a producer, Nate Randall,
that basically helps us keep everything organized
and stay on task and everything like that.
And we also have Audio QA, an Audio QA lead
that helps us track down issues and bugs,
and he's very knowledgeable
about all these borderland systems.
He's been on our team for over a decade, too,
so he kind of can speak our language and so forth.
He's a very valuable member of the team.
But that's not it.
We have a sister studio.
We have Gearbox Studio Quebec.
And we have staff there.
And they've been working on certain different aspects
of Tiny Tina's Wonderlands.
Like, we pretty much let them kind of operate autonomously.
But we have check-ins, and we talk with them a lot
to make sure that we're all on the same page.
So that's 21 audio staff.
And remember, a few slides ago, there were only four.
So we've come a long way since 2009, 2010.
So yeah, let's get to the fun stuff now.
So now, a couple years back, my colleague Brian Fieser
was going to come to this GDC and do
a talk on the modular weapon system for Borderlands 3.
It's a system that he really pushed for after we
hired him in 2016.
And while it took a ton of effort
to work within this modular system, it greatly paid off,
and we are extremely proud of it.
And over the next few slides, I'll
give you a slight overview of the benefits we
got out of that system.
So in previous Borderlands games,
we were limited by memory and scope
with how many weapons we could design and use
with our weapon system.
Like on Borderlands 2, it was a lot more rudimentary.
On Borderlands 3, we had more memory, we had more staff,
and we had a bigger overall scope for the project.
So we decided to build a system that
would allow for placing sounds on individual gun parts.
in-house tool, it's known as the Gestalt system basically.
And it basically creates a modular approach
that could strengthen variety
in Sonic character considerably.
The catch though is it requires a lot of content to be made.
And for example, the total asset count
for all of the gunshots in Borderlands 3
ended up about 5,500 individual gunshot sounds.
And for a comparison, we shipped about
250 individual gun sounds in Borderlands 2.
So it was quite a huge leap in scope and content creation
that had to fall onto the team.
And I think we did a pretty cool job.
So yeah, this is actually like a...
This is what the Gestalt system looks like.
Just from the editor perspective, as you can see, there's...
This is a Hyperion shotgun, and
you can select all these different types of parts, and
make all sorts of different kind of configurations for
just this one manufacturer-specific weapon.
And every weapon in the game basically
has a system attached to it.
Now, this is the debug menu in game
that we can access as developers.
This allows us to basically build any configuration we want.
Like in this example, I'm selecting parts
for an uncommon Maliwan sniper rifle.
I can make a very specific configuration
if I want in this menu,
or I could just select from a wide variety of parts
and let the system create a bunch
of random Maliwan sniper rifles
within the part selections that I've chosen, basically.
So on the next slide, I'm gonna show
examples of two Jacobs pistols and two Jacobs assault rifles. They're the same gun,
but listen to how the two pistols sound different from one another and the two assault rifles sound different from one another.
If it will work.
And here comes the assault rifle.
So yeah, sometimes with this system
you can get very drastically different sounding
configurations between the same types of guns.
And sometimes they'll feel a little more subtly different
depending on the weapon.
But either way, we achieved something we hadn't
in our games before, and that was something
we were very proud of.
If you play our games, like maybe a certain one
coming out this week, maybe check out
two of the same weapons in your inventory
and notice how they might sound different from one another.
Oh, oops, I skipped that.
So if you wanted a deeper dive on just the Borderlands 3
weapon system, you can take a picture of this slide.
I did about a 10-minute video breaking down
how I made the sounds for the Maliwan sniper rifles
and also how it basically worked within the framework
of the Borderlands 3 weapon system, essentially.
So.
Now we're jumping forward to today.
Over the next few slides, I'll show you
how we approached moving from the sound of Borderlands 3
to Wonderlands, into the world of fantasy, essentially.
So the Borderlands aesthetic we were used to
has normally been wildly varied between the organic
and the synthetic, combining themes of Western sci-fi.
And there's always been a little bit
of a dash of a fantasy element in Borderlands.
I always say to people that Borderlands never really gets old to work on,
because as a sound designer, the world is so very interesting and varied.
It doesn't feel like you're ever doing the same thing at all on a day-to-day basis.
So Wonderlands actually presented us with a new aesthetic challenge
to dive deep into the high fantasy aspect
and really focus on cultivating a Borderlands-y take on magic systems and melee weapons.
There were also some noticeable design changes
that influenced our aesthetic choices.
We had quite a few new systems being added to the game,
in addition to some overhauls of the previous systems
we were working with.
And a lot of these big design overhauls
influenced the aesthetic we were aiming for.
So to amp up the fantasy theme,
we did sort of a remix of the Borderlands 3 weapon system
by adding crossbow barrels and behaviors
to familiar Borderlands franchises
and weapons manufacturers.
Grenades were also replaced by spells, and they have some really cool behaviors, and I'll cover those in a little bit more depth later, because there's a lot to those.
We also deepened our melee mechanics by adding melee weapons as a form of loot in the game.
So the melee weapon system kind of piggybacks on the modular gun system, essentially.
So as Wonderlands was spinning up on pre-production,
we were still in the midst of Borderlands 3 DLC production.
So at the time, we were a bit short on resources
to kind of get the jumpstart on Wonderlands that we needed.
Our associate director of sound design, Brian Fieser,
had worked with Paul Stoughton in the past,
and we contacted him to see if he would
want to do some contract work with us.
Stoughton, I don't know if you know Paul Stoughton, but he is an industry veteran with amazing
talent and a reputation for creating and releasing his own very high quality professional sound
libraries under his company, Penguin Grenade.
We tasked them with helping us basically create our own personal sound libraries
for our team to use once everyone rolled off the DLC and straight into production of Mordorlands.
We requested a highly organic library of raw, processed, and designed content.
Having this content for our designers to work with would help ensure that our designers were
utilizing the same palette of material in their work,
so we could all have a really nice cohesion to our magic audio.
So the raw source material mainly consisted of recordings of organic material that had been cleaned up for us to use and put into SoundMiner.
So in the next slide I'll play various examples of what that raw source material is using a few different elemental types.
Oops.
So once we had that raw source, we would move on and process that source.
So the process source basically takes the raw source that was recorded and
adds some heavier processing to it.
So this stuff was intended to be designed and used as a magic layer for our
designers, but you know, it gave, it basically allows the designers to have a
lot of wiggle room to have their own forms of creative expression with it.
And finally, there's design source.
We didn't do a whole lot of pre-design source
because pretty much all of this work
happened before a lot of the art and design
had been created in the game.
So it was kind of like more audio concept art
is what I kind of think of it as.
Either way, it became pretty useful stuff in the end anyway,
and it really kind of got everyone inspired
in thinking about what the real sound
of Wonderland's magic was gonna be.
So here's some examples of that.
So now that we've covered the aesthetic aspects
of Wonderlands, over the next few slides,
we'll talk about how we expanded our modular systems
from Borderlands 3.
So on Tiny Tina's Wonderlands, we
wanted to take that modularity a step further.
We kept our existing modular system for the guns,
but then we also added modular functionality
to other aspects of the games.
Most notably, that was the spell casting and the melee weapons.
The cool thing about the Borderlands 3 system is when it came to our new magic guns and our crossbow weapons,
we had a system we knew already would mostly just work.
Outside of that, we just had some new RTC PCs that we needed in Wwise,
and after that, the biggest challenge really was nailing down how we wanted the things to sound.
So for the crossbow barrels, we had a challenge.
We wanted them to sound punchy and pretty satisfying
to shoot, kind of like any other Borderlands weapon
in the game, but we needed it to also have this
kind of like old school, kind of medieval crossbow
sounding aesthetic.
It took a decent amount of experimentation with the content, but we figured out if we replaced sounds
from certain parts on the other guns from Borderlands 3, but kept some key choice layers,
we could keep the familiar signature brand identity for our weapons, but also make them feel, you know, fresh and unique.
So yeah, a good example would be the TORG weapons.
We kept some of those mechanical bombastic thumpy sounds
that you would typically notice in a TORG weapon,
but we added some more of that medieval ballista kind of
aspect to the aesthetic of that sound.
So snappy releases, satisfying projectile whooshes,
and here's a video medley of some of those crossbow weapons
to kind of give you an idea of what we ended up going with.
We also had magic weapons in the game.
So for magic weapons, we also removed a lot of those
like native Borderlands 3 layers
and kept some choice layers for supplementation.
So for example, like a doll assault rifle
might keep some of those mechanical Call of Duty
kind of sounding elements and the reload sounds
so they could stay uniquely to doll.
But we added new layers,
it's added to represent like the new magical content.
We kept focus primarily on the weapons elemental magic properties
and crafted those transients and tails around those elements.
We also kept that design language just kind of familiar with those weapon manufacturers.
This next slide will show you some of the cool magic weapons we worked on.
I love those poison reloads so much.
So yeah, melee weapons presented an entirely new challenge,
and we didn't have a system for anything like this yet,
so we kind of got to dreaming up one.
I knew that we would want to continue our philosophy
of adding audio to specific types of parts,
but I wasn't exactly sure how going into it.
There are basically four main types
of melee weapons in the game,
and each of those four categories
has three subtypes underneath those.
And this is what those look like.
So this is blade type one.
It's a one-handed sword, and those are examples of the three different types of subtypes that go underneath that.
This is Blade Type 2. It's a two-handed sword, and this is a pre-textured version of those subtypes.
I promise they look a lot better now.
And then there's Blade Type 3. These are blunts, so very handed to two-handed weapons.
And those are the three subtypes for those.
And the last one is the one-handed axe and the three subtypes in that family.
So we thought that these could require a lot of content,
and we're always cautious about these kind of things
because more content means more audio,
and more audio usually means more things
get loaded into memory.
And Wonderlands is also releasing on last-gen consoles,
so we have to be very.
mindful and about that delicate of balance to the approach there.
We played around with a procedural whoosh and loop system first,
and the video on the next slide is a very interesting prototype of that
using the tone generator in Wwise. . .
Woo!
So yeah, that file name is we, weu.mp4.
Very appropriately named.
So there were successes and some drawbacks to that loop system, and I think we could
have gotten there with more time and extra code support, but those resources were kind
of limited at the time, so we decided to instead just create a one-shot system for the swings.
And on the next slide I'll show you an example
of how that all comes together basically
with a blunt weapon.
So yeah, they're all broken out
into different types of categories
and those whooshes.
are very dull for the main subtype, but it gets more interesting when we add things like the
shing layer or the spice layer. So the shing layer is basically the layer that a subtype inherits,
and each subtype has its own unique shing layer.
And each subtype also sometimes has its own,
I don't know why we called it this, but the spice layer.
We realized that sometimes just the main woosh
and the shing layer sounded just too literal.
Like, yeah, it sounded like a melee weapon swinging,
but it wasn't very cinematic or interesting.
So we would add another layer on top of that
just to kind of make it feel bigger
and more impactful as you swung it.
So here's an example of
all those layers combined and some of them, you know,
soloed and then combined rather, excuse me.
So now we'll add the unique shing layer for that subtype there.
And that's just the shing layer soloed.
And this is the spice layer just soloed.
And this is all the layers including a cryo elemental loop layer.
So these all come together just to make this one unique Pacific variations sonic identity.
So we basically utilized Melee impacts in a similar way.
Each parent category had an impact sound associated with it.
So if you're using a blunt weapon,
a blunt weapon's gonna have a unique impact
just for the blunt weapon.
And we kind of, we didn't wanna add too many,
too much unique file names or anything to the system
because memory's a very delicate thing.
So we just kind of, instead of making an impact sound
for each type of, you know.
material like grass or concrete or, you know, glass or something like that.
We basically just created hard and soft generic impact sounds.
And then we layered on top of those our existing generic bucket of sounds that we use for material impacts essentially.
So yeah, that's what we did for those.
And this next slide will show off some of the gameplay
utilizing the systems mentioned previously
with just the one-handed axe weapon, essentially.
Those skeletons are fun to kill.
So spells, these are actually my favorite.
I like them a ton.
I don't really miss grenades at all,
and I think if you play Wonderlands,
you'll probably feel the same way.
But the spells are also extremely modular,
but their core component can be kind of broken down
into a few main high-level categories.
That would be casting, projectiles, and spell mods.
And casting is very varied.
This is all the different types of casting
that can occur.
So without going into too much detail, absent from this list are a bunch of the uniques,
which are like the legendaries and stuff like that. But I don't want to spoil those.
So there are different types of buildups, loops, and casts
that can be performed.
For example, you may have a spell
that casts a magical elemental missile via a wand,
or you may see a spell that casts fireballs
from the player's hands.
Some types of spells can instantly cast,
while some can just cast.
like be held down and then let go and then you can cast it that way.
The casting times can also change based on the timing of the
they can change timing based on the players like skill or the rarity of the of the spell itself.
All these variables come together in the system to create a lot of variety and interesting dynamics
that can change basically the moment to moment gameplay
and play styles up quite a lot.
A lot of these projectiles also that come from these spells,
basically we're able to reuse the main spell,
magic missiles audio,
because the magic missiles were basically utilizing
all the different types of elemental sounds
from all the other aspects of the game.
So every now and then we would need something bespoke,
like there's a meteor spell,
so we would need a meteor sound for that,
we or like an elemental hawk or dragon fly out so we need to put some
some bespoke creature sounds on those and stuff.
Yeah, and then the last pillar of all the spells are basically the spell mods.
And that's basically like a small way in which a spell can have its behavior changed.
So sometimes they would spawn additional projectiles, and those projectiles could share the same audio.
But more often you would get new projectiles, like a whole new giant meteor falling from the sky,
or a gravity well, which is kind of like a singularity.
So the next slide will show off a lot of those spells that we...
have in the game.
Yeah, that meteor one's my favorite for sure.
But yeah, so some final thoughts here.
So as you can see, we've done a lot to expand
the modularity in the Borderlands universe in Wonderlands.
And it's a game based on loot,
and these modular systems add, in our opinion,
a great deal of value to the fundamental core gameplay loop
basically by increasing sonic variety
while also being very practical
because we're simply piggybacking on the variable nature
of the gameplay design in our games.
We added a lot of interesting new ideas and content to Wonderlands,
and I'm excited to see where things get taken in the future.
And I hope you all pick it up at some point
and enjoy the amazing hard work our entire team did
making all this come together.
So a big shout-out to everyone on the audio team back at Gearbox.
They are incredible people,
and they have so much collective and extraordinary talent.
You just heard a lot of the work that they did,
and I'm super proud of them.
And thank you all for coming.
I guess we can do Q&A, because we've got still a little bit of time.
If anybody wants to ask any questions or anything.
Carson.
Yes.
How much changing, so the audio concept art that you made, the visual for an area, do
you find that some of those, like, really...
Um, actually the, we didn't do a whole, uh, the question was how, how, how
useful was the audio concept?
Oh, by the way, there's a microphone over there.
I just realized.
I'm new to this.
Yeah, the question was how much did the audio concept art
change, and how much did it actually work out?
It actually worked out pretty well.
The only thing that we mainly just prototyped casting sounds,
because we knew that we were going to need those.
And really, all that was needed was just
like a little bit of timing adjustments here and there.
But that was about it.
But we didn't do a whole lot of that,
because it would have been a huge investment just
to work it out.
not know if it was going to pan out, but most of it did, yeah.
There's a microphone there and a line there,
so if you want to ask a question, yeah.
What's up?
Thanks for the talk.
I was wondering, with the modular system, I'm guessing it means that some weapons can have a ton of voices playing every time they do their thing.
Did you have any constraints related to that and what are techniques you maybe used to reduce the voice impact of having this modular system?
Yeah, that's a good question.
So the modular system, it's not like, you know,
we have a lot of parts to choose from to put sounds on,
but we didn't use all the parts, you know.
We, like, for example, on Borderlands 3,
each gun type has three different types of barrels.
and each barrel has three subtypes called barrel mods,
just kind of like how the melee weapons
had three subtypes.
So we would basically kind of piggyback on that
and we would also put sounds on like the muzzle
and like the grip and a few other parts.
So generally at one time what's usually happening
is like you're hearing about.
five to six different sounds playing on top of each other at the same time, but it rarely goes
more than that unless there's some specific like edge case, which there probably is because there's
so many different types of guns, so. But we test it all the time and so we usually don't find too
many crazy edge cases like that, but yeah, it can happen for sure. That's a good question.
Thanks.
Hello, my name's Owen.
Um, I would let you kind of like, if you can go more into like the modular
philosophy and more about that, like, cause I understand, I mean, with sound
designing, you want to, you know, add more layers that you were doing to kind
of create more distinction between different sounds, but what is that modular
philosophy that you were talking about?
If you can go more into detail about that.
Um, just like the sound design philosophy for them, like, like what
sound do we put on what part?
Like that kind of thing.
So yeah, like, uh, typically like, um, for.
You know, each sound designer kind of approaches it a little bit differently.
But like a lot of us put like, for example, on the muzzle,
that's where we kind of choose what tail sound plays.
Yeah. And like for the grip, like we'll have a different type of transient crack
for that. And so we'll give each one of those parts like its own family of sounds.
And we kind of, you know, we approach it differently for every type of weapon.
I did a lot of the work on the Maliwan sniper rifles, for example.
And I would just kind of find families of sounds that felt good for certain parts and kind of go from there.
And, you know, like when I first started working on this modular system,
it was Brian Feaser who kind of spearheaded the whole development of it.
And I got to admit, I started working on the Maliwan SMGs and they just sounded like trash for like an entire month.
And it really took me taking a break from the Maliwan SMGs,
and then I started working on the Maliwan sniper rifles.
And I just kind of had that fresh perspective, you know,
and like, I would make like some pretty cool, like,
synth punch layers and stuff like that, like laser pews,
you know, and stuff, and I would put them on,
I would give a certain part a family of pews,
and then some...
Some parts would get more of a body, like a bottom low end layer and stuff like that.
So the philosophy is more like exploring the feeling of the sound and allowing yourself the time to kind of like create that
similar to my family's sounds that we're probably married again.
Yeah, yeah, totally.
Okay, cool. Thank you so much.
Yeah, yeah, absolutely.
Hi, I was just curious about the procedural exploration that you did with the Wise Tone Generator,
and what eventually led you to abandon using that on this project,
and whether you think it's feasible that you might use it for this purpose on future projects.
Yeah, that's a good question.
So the looping system, it was mainly,
we just didn't have, like, we didn't at the time,
our code staff were kind of ramping up
on kind of some other engine side work stuff.
So we didn't really have the code support
that we needed to get that done at that time.
So that was kind of why we ended up abandoning it.
We were like,
I'm not exactly sure.
We were kind of, we were really in the thick of development at that time.
So adding like really, really brand new features was like risky.
So we just kind of had to, and it kind of, that's why we kind of stuck with what we
knew, you know, and just kind of stuck with like the one shot method, you know, and.
That ended up working out well, but yeah,
and I think in the future, something like much more,
you know, because like what's cool about like
a looping system is you can get away with like
doing a very little amount of content
and get a lot of mileage out of it.
You know, like I've seen some really cool systems
from some games, you know, that can utilize fully that way,
essentially, you know, like just with a few loops,
like you can have, you know, with like one six second loop,
essentially you could probably like.
do a whole game's worth of audio with that, you know, but that's, that's like a whole,
whole nother, hopefully we'll, we'll have like a GDC talk on something like that in the future.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Hi. Jumping back to the whole modular approach of weapons,
how do you make sure that things aren't clashing in a weird way?
For instance, like you have some transients on something
and there's some body or spice or the tails.
How do you make sure that it all kind of amalgamates
into a good sounding thing rather than like random stuff going?
Yeah, the trick there is to not put,
just be very choiceful in your decisions
on what parts you use.
Try not to use every part for a family of guns.
Like I kind of mentioned before,
just use barrels, barrel mods.
And the same thing happened with the melee stuff.
We really, when you're swinging a melee weapon,
there's usually not gonna be more than three or four sounds
and they're all whooshes, you know,
so they kind of naturally blend together
and it just takes a little bit of experimentation
just to make sure like they're, you know.
you know, in the frequency spectrum sense of things,
that they all kind of like fit their own,
fit in their own frequency space essentially.
Like that's why the shings are kind of just like
a very resonant,
that are kind of like a resonant spike essentially.
And you know, the whooshes are more dull and more low mid,
you know, and then like the spicy layers are kind of like,
you know, a little bit,
you hear a little bit more higher frequencies with those,
that kind of sells more of the wind whooshes
and like the passage of air going through the weapon
essentially I think.
Okay.
So you're kind of assigning more throughout the frequency spectrum to the different modular parts of the gun to make sure that there's no...
Yeah, and I kind of showed that debug window that we have in our game, and that allows us to really, really, really test it thoroughly.
And it also allows us to kind of really see how random things can get.
And so you can just like spawn a...
a thousand variations of that particular type of weapon.
And that can enable you to just really pick them all up
and play with them and see if you're going to get any weird things.
But after a while, we, you know, at first,
I was, like I was saying with the Malinois SMGs on Borderlands 3,
I was, everything sounded like a mess
because I didn't know what I was doing with this system for a while.
But really, I think just having the right amount of layers
and just knowing...
how to design them, it just takes time working with the system and like, um,
everybody who, everybody who's worked with the system, all of our sound
designers that have come up, the new, the new guys and stuff, like they're
extremely intimidated by the system and it, you know, but it, and that's very
understandable, but once you've, it really, it really takes a little bit of
lead time work, like to really get used to working in it and like, it takes a
couple of months sometimes to just to really get a good feel for it because
it's pretty complex for sure.
Thank you.
Mm-hmm.
Hello. Well, first of all, I'm sorry, I have a couple of questions, but I'll try to keep them really quick.
So, in creating of a gun sound, do you start with natural guns sometimes, or you prefer to start everything synthetic?
In terms of taking a real gun and recording it just because it might be more natural,
and maybe there are some sounds that would keep it more as a better clue.
However, maybe over-exaggerating would be better in general.
So, what is your approach to creating this type of sound?
Yeah, my experience mainly working in the system for the guns specifically is like,
I mainly worked on Maliwan weapons and I'm a big synth nerd,
so that's kind of where I feel most comfortable, you know, naturally.
So I kind of, on Borderlands 3, we had a lot of pre-production time where...
Like my colleague, Rason Varner, and I,
we were using Serum like crazy
and just constantly making patches with it.
And I was making a lot of synth patches with Serum
and learning to design my own laser sounds,
like laser pews and things like that.
And so I started personally with the synthetic stuff,
but you can't just use that, you know,
because like using just the synthesizer
or raw synthesizer sound
is gonna sound completely awkward in the game
because...
That's not how a real gun would sound in real life.
I always like to layer in real weapons
and kind of dirty it up with saturation and stuff
to kind of pull back that really clean sound
that a synth can have, especially a software synth
like CRM, it's very, very clean.
So you kind of have to find unique ways
to dirty it up a little bit and make it feel more fresh.
So do you put sometimes the real sound
into the sampler in the CRM itself
and then start using some of the algorithms there?
The wavetables?
Yeah, in the wavetables. Do you use it or you just do it separately?
I have used my own custom wavetables, but I've done them more as like just an experiment.
I didn't do that with gun sounds though, but that's a cool idea for sure.
Okay, well, another quick question.
So about the recording processes,
I assume that in the beginning when you started,
it was probably more difficult because you needed to,
in both cases, you needed to have a studio
and a good environment.
What was the regular problem with recording
and did you have to, I mean, you probably have to fix
some of the sounds and clean them up.
What were you doing with this?
For example, if you recorded a sound,
but there's some background noise
or some frequencies picking up
that are not natural to the sound.
Yeah, so like when it came to...
Refer to re-record it.
Yeah, we actually enlisted some outsourcing partners
to help us get like recordings of guns.
We also recorded guns ourselves
and got those files cleaned up.
So yeah, that's pretty much what we did with that.
We also, this is actually a pretty funny story,
and this is a very Texas story
if you've ever heard a Texas story,
but we sent out an email to the team
asking, hey, who wants to record some guns and gun foley and stuff like that?
And so, um, this was probably like in 2017 or something like that.
And it was just a blast to the whole company.
And I think we got like 50 emails back or something like that.
Yeah, I got a gun.
Let's record it.
You know?
And so we, we invited people to our Foley room and basically we created this giant
like library of Foley sounds, uh, for the reloads and things like that, just.
simply based on all the people at Gearbox that seem to have guns.
Some of them have quite an arsenal, which is impressive.
Yeah, it brought them to the office. Yeah, probably shouldn't tell people that.
Yeah, but yeah.
Another question, the deadlines in a company, how long and do they change through the time?
Because you started with a smaller team and probably when the company grows,
the deadlines and it becomes more strict.
However, the more there are layers in the processes, the more something could go wrong.
How often do you deal with situations when you need to produce the sound or
deliver the sound in a really short time?
Do you prefer to...
be more creative or go with a more safer approach if we're using most of the sounds and just adding something to that to make it more unique?
I mean, that's different depending on what... It's different depending on what phase of the project you're in.
Like, if you're in pre-production, you have time to do...
Like, we're getting more disciplined with this over time, like you were saying, like...
Gearbox is getting bigger. We have to kind of like process orient things a little bit more so like
doing pre-production now is like
We will work on design documents. We'll work on prototypes. We'll work on mock-ups and things like that for us for a particular
type of design feature that's coming down the pipe. We'll get as much of like high level stuff done
very early on, but we can't, we'll have to revisit that later whenever the design actually gets
implemented into the game. So there's like a stagger process now, but, and that's always
changing for sure. Okay, and what's the most common problem you have to face with everything?
All right, this will be the last question because you got a big line behind you, buddy. Sorry,
then never mind. Okay, you're good. Thank you very much. Yeah, you're good.
Hi, yeah I was curious about the, you mentioned there were some new real-time parameter controls you used,
I was wondering if any of that you would consider played a part in your modular system.
I know you scrapped the procedural tone generator,
but I was curious if there was any procedural kind of real-time parameter control or if all that was baked in.
Yeah, like the RDPCs that we created for these are basically like things that helped change the timing of the weapon,
depending on the variable rate of speed that it's being swung at, which can happen with the loot basically.
So our tech sound designer, Jesse Lemons, was pretty much primarily the guy that set that up.
But so I'm not exactly sure what the exact parameters were, but they basically could change the rate of time and pitch to kind of like affect the parameter based on how
you know, what the loot swings at,
what time it swings at, because, you know,
in Borderlands, you can level up your character,
and sometimes that'll change the way you swing things,
or how, you know, how fast it goes and things like that.
So we have RTPCs that kind of like
piggyback on that, basically.
Okay, yeah, so did that affect the layering?
Because it seems like a lot of the modularity
was about the layering.
It did on the guns. So the guns, like, typically whenever we're working with guns, sometimes you'll want to change the volume of a layer
based on some parameter that you want to control.
So like if you have a higher rate of speed or like if you have, here's a good one, like whenever
you're getting low on ammo, for example, we have an RTPC that kind of like starts to duck certain
layers and bring more mechanical layers up. So like you'll hear that and then you'll hear that,
you know, it cues the player in essentially to, oh, I'm running low on ammo. So we have like a
lot of little RTPCs that do those kind of small little detailed kind of things. Great. Thank you
so much. Yeah.
Just a quick question about the raw processing stage that you mentioned that you did with your library.
How much manual work was involved with that? Did you do much editing between the different types or was it more just batch processing?
So we, pretty much for that whole library setup, Paul Stoughton, he's the guy that was behind that,
he recorded a lot of that stuff himself and then also spent the time like, you know, doing the RX treatment on it and basically cleaning it up.
And we would divide all those things out into folders by elemental type.
Each elemental type folder had a raw...
a folder full of just random things like that, like the bedsheets tearing or, you know, ice
crackling and things like that. And then they would each have that process folder as well with
the more, the more, uh, interesting, like, you know, effects added to those, to the raw source
and stuff. And then the design folder usually didn't have that much stuff on it, because like
I was saying earlier, it's pretty much just, it was kind of more used as a concept kind of phase.
Did I, did that answer your question at all?
I think so, so the processed stage was that mostly just effects, it wasn't sort of any
sort of like actual editing together of different...
No, not really. It would be mostly just cool editing. I know Stoughton likes to use Traveler.
So for a lot of those whooshes that he makes, he would actually take the... He showed me how
he did it, but he basically would take the raw source and then just kind of... He can make really
cool transients out of the raw source. And sometimes, yeah, he would layer things just
to kind of beef them up a little bit because, yeah, you've probably heard some of those probably
have a little bit more... A lot more body.
you know, than the raw source did. So he would use Traveler to kind of get those really dynamic
whooshes. I know he uses actually by the same company, you know, it's called Woosh.
Tarnstrom Woosh. I think it's, I don't know how you say, is it Tarnstrom? I don't know.
But yeah, he would use that a lot. And so he would take that raw source and then make some cool,
interesting things out of it that could be useful for our other sound designers to kind of like
pick through and layer and things like that.
Yeah, great, thank you.
Hey, I was wondering, with a team of 21 sound designers
and all making modular layers that have different purposes
for different guns, and you're all using the same
like source library that is custom made,
Was there some kind of agreed upon signal chain or mixing mastering chain at the end
of the process for individual layers, like certain DB that you're like aiming for, or
was there like certain plugins or like everyone were using this compressor at the
end of the chain or I don't know?
Uh, no, no, not at all.
Actually.
We don't, we don't really, uh.
mandate that our sound designers do anything.
We're not that process oriented.
We definitely have certain like pillars and style guides
that we want them to reference,
but whatever tools our sound designers want to use,
we let them do it.
And we don't really have any specific like set requirements
because we kind of feel like that kind of limits
the creativity a little bit too much.
And we also don't have...
We don't have that many people actually working on the modular stuff, you know,
it's usually like four or five people at most, you know, so it's a little bit easier to kind of like
see where everybody is. It's not like everybody's just throwing stuff at the system. It's only like
a few of us pretty much doing it at one time and we're all reviewing each other's work and stuff.
So all right, perfect. That's the answer I wanted to get. Yeah, thanks.
Hi, going off of that question, once all the audio is implemented, when you are mixing and mastering, is this only in Wwise or are there iterative sessions where your sound designers start mixing in the DAW, they do it in Wwise, and then there's one?
Yeah, all the content is created in the DAW and then all the in-game aspects are mixed in Wwise.
So we hook Wwise up live to the game and we do the mixing there.
And we also, like when it comes to the actual mix down of the game, we go to the office.
So we actually spent a lot of December at the office mixing the game and we all sit in the room together.
a few of us sit in a room together and kind of participate.
And we're in the Dolby Atmos room at our studio essentially.
And yeah, so we all kind of like sit there,
we mix it, we find what levels we like it to sit at
and just kind of all vibe together
and kind of come to a consensus on something, yeah.
Okay, and is it separate for stereo mixes
and surround sound mixes?
Or is there like mix down that can naturally be?
Sorry, could you say that again? I just couldn't hear it.
For people who have those surround sound speakers at home versus stereo,
are those two separate mixes you send out?
Oh, no.
Basically, most of the files in our game are going to be mono,
but for weapons, we typically do stereo.
And whenever it comes to mixing in Dolby Atmos,
we do very, very choice scenes
to really highlight the Dolby Atmos experience.
I can't, I don't want to spoil anything, but there are some in the game that we purposely
mixed to make pretty big sounding in Dolby Atmos.
We work with Dolby and they kind of help us out a little bit with that.
But really the game itself, most of the assets in our game are either mono or stereo.
And like, if you have a surround sound setup at your house,
basically the game engine kind of gives you a lot of stuff for free
because it's all 3D audio and like, you know,
the 3D audio just kind of gets baked into what we're doing already in the game
with setting attenuation values and things like that.
There's usually, whenever we want to really, really accentuate,
like the surround sound, we do it very, very deliberately
for a very particular type of asset
that we think will get noticed,
but it's a little bit less common for sure.
Okay, thank you.
We have about three minutes.
Hello, thank you for coming here and talking.
Does the modular system change the approach
that you take when sort of designing
the more synthetic sounds and...
How so?
Yeah, it totally does because usually, you know, it, you know, be like,
whenever I was working on the modular system, it just, I hated it at first
because I, I missed just being able to just make the sound in my DAW and hope
and just make it sound good in the DAW and then put it in the game and make
tweaks from there, but, um.
Yeah, it was really tough. You have to kind of make things that don't sound as great in the DAW.
When you're working in the system, you have to kind of make something that sounds
like a layer of something that you would make, and then you have to put it in Wwise and then
put it in the engine.
and then you would have to test it against all the other layers that you're doing.
So the approach basically, you start to make things a lot more piecemeal that way.
So you'll make like a transient layer, or you'll make mechanical layers,
or like you'll have layers that are like with the Malaywan sniper rifles that are just more synthetic,
or a layer that might be more meant to be more like your low-end thump or something like that.
And then it takes a lot of experimentation, but...
It's extremely rewarding when you get it working right finally.
But yeah, every sound designer kind of approaches it in their own unique way.
For sure. Thank you.
So I think you may have actually answered this question already when you said that all the content was created in a DAW.
But I was wondering if any of the synthesis, like the shock synth source and the sweetener layer for the crits
came from Unreal's built-in synthesis rather than from a plugin?
No, we have not been using Unreal's built-in synthesis at all.
Oh, okay.
Yeah.
But pretty much a lot of the stuff that we do is either, if it's like a tool that we
use that's playing live in the background, it's usually like...
Like convolution reverb is a big example of that.
Like we use that, we have a whole,
I can do a whole nother talk on Triton,
which is our occlusion and reverb system in the game.
And we have compressors and limiters
and things like that that run in the background via Wwise.
In these games, a lot of the synthesis that you're hearing
was created in a DAW, printed,
and then made into a WAV file essentially.
Oh, perfect, thank you, thank you.
Hey, thank you all so much for coming.
It is 1149.
We did it, we did it.
We're having, if you'll have additional questions,
we're having a lunchtime surgeries thing,
and I forgot what room it's in.
It's a few rooms down.
Yeah, well.
The 3014?
Yeah, at 3014, it's gonna be myself,
some other sound designers, or sound people in the industry.
We're gonna be chillin' at tables,
having one-on-one conversations with people.
So if y'all wanna come to that,
that's just right down there, the 3014.