very last slide of my presentation,
I have some contact information on there for you,
so my email address and my Twitter account.
So feel free to reach out to me after the talk
if you wish to follow up on any of the subjects
that I covered today.
How many of you are familiar with the Londar?
Oh gosh, okay.
I guess I better be careful what I say then.
Okay, how many of you have actually played it though?
Okay, all right, good.
My favorite new thing is when you ask people,
like in job interviews, if they've played your game,
and they all say no, but I've watched a lot of streams
of it, which is.
Not exactly the same thing.
So, I'm just gonna, for the sake of kind of
setting the stage for this presentation,
I spent a lot of time talking about,
like making comparisons between sandbox mode in our game
and story mode in the game.
So I thought a good way to kind of refresh that
would be I'll play, I'm gonna play
our launch trailers for both,
just to kind of highlight maybe the differences
in how we present the two modes.
And then I'll segue into the presentation.
The reason I'm doing that is because
I made the critical mistake of a game developer, which is I'm using new software in a live
operation.
So I'm not good enough with Keynote to do a proper swap between video and...
and my keynote.
So I'm gonna start by playing the Sandbox trailer
that we launched.
It's almost two years old now,
so since you're all really familiar with the game,
you'll probably see some things
that you know are outdated by now,
but this is, I think, a good way to establish
how we think about, how we talk about,
and how we present the Sandbox mode.
Excuse me.
Oh, shoot.
This is what I was talking about, sorry.
One second, one second.
I'm very sorry.
Maybe I won't do that.
All right, let's try that again, shall we?
Thank you.
Copyright 2018 atellani.com
♪♪
Alright, so that's Sandbox.
And you know, sort of the emphasis on the atmosphere,
the ambient experience, that's really the focus
of the sandbox experience for us.
And then by comparison, I'm gonna play for you
the trailer that we launched on August 1st
when we launched the first two episodes
of our story mode last year.
I didn't come here to fight about the past.
I need a pilot to take me somewhere remote.
Someone who won't ask too many questions.
Someone I can trust.
Wait, questions?
Astrid, are you in trouble?
Are you gonna help me or not?
The power went out.
Who knows the reason?
People started to get cold.
started to talk crazy.
Others walked here from the highway.
Some belonged here.
Others were outsiders, like you.
Yeah, see, I was part of that world.
It's a world of closed doors and things being off limits.
But that world's over.
This has all happened before.
Soon, we'll all be tested.
We'll have to choose how far we'll go to survive.
You don't have to get it, Mackenzie.
You just have to do it.
What I did, the choice I made.
I did it for us.
He'll be back soon enough.
I know when he is.
I'll be ready.
Holy shit, wait!
They left her, didn't they?
She needed help, and they let her go.
This is how you make it right.
Alright, so thanks for coming.
I hope you learned a lot today.
by the lone dark.
All right, let's see if we can do this correctly.
Does this look great to you?
Yes, okay, great.
So, hi.
My name's Raphael Van Lierp.
I'm the founder and creative director at Hinterland
and the creator of the lone dark.
I'm here to share with you my thoughts and experiences
around the challenges of blending two types of narrative.
the authored story, and the playered story,
a problem that's fairly unique to the interactive space,
and in a genre not well-known for its narrative potential,
the sandbox survival game.
But before I get into that,
I'd like to thank the GDC Selection Committee
and the Advisory Board, and in particular, Clint Hawking,
for inviting me to speak here at the main conference.
This is my third time presenting at GDC,
and it's always an honor to stand amongst
and in front of such distinguished creators
and survivors of game development.
I'd also like to thank my team at Hinterland,
some of who are sitting in the audience today, back there.
So, if there's things you don't like about the game.
And without whom I wouldn't have much
to stand up here and talk about.
I'm gonna start with the standard GDC caveats.
I'm not a lawyer and forgive me if this sounds like
disclaimers against litigation,
but really this is about creating a safe space
within which to share information and ideas.
This caveat allows me to feel comfortable
in sharing my experiences with you today
without the pressure of feeling like
I'm trying to teach you or influence you in some way.
I'm merely here to share the benefit
of some lessons hard won.
It's up to you then to decide if this information
is of any use to you.
If you wish to embrace it, great.
And I hope it helps guide you to success
in your own projects.
If you wish to run away from it, also great.
Perhaps I helped you to avoid some very painful experiences
or inspired you to blaze a much better path forward
for your own project.
We can't really talk about player versus author story
without first agreeing on what we mean by story.
For the purposes of this discussion,
I mean story as an architectural construct.
It's a set of consecutive moments
that are imbued with meaning due to their context.
While game mechanics are the building blocks
of the gameplay experience,
that is what the player does in the game,
story is what emerges when you give
these moment-to-moment experiences meaning
by how you think about them, how you feel about them,
and how you talk about them with other people.
But how you feel about your experience
can be heavily determined
by your sense of authorship over it.
If I present to you a well-crafted story
that you happily submit to,
you'll come along for the ride
and feel a strong sense of connection
to what you have experienced.
We've all played linear games that were extremely well done
to the extent that we didn't notice,
or at least if we noticed, we didn't resent
the hand of the author guiding us along.
If on the other hand, you feel that the story
is reducing your sense of authorship over the experience,
the mechanics of the game are at odds
with what the authored experience is trying to convey.
Well, you end up with a dissonance
that can ruin any sense of immersion
you might have otherwise experienced.
And even though you may not be able
to articulate exactly why,
the game just won't feel right.
The challenge in providing authored story
as a framework over a game that is heavily biased
towards player experimentation of the gameplay space,
which is the definition of a sandbox survival game,
is in striking the balance
between the different types of story
the player will experience.
In The Long Dark, players experience story
across a variety of layers.
Each of these layers is supported
by a kind of narrative scaffolding
that is comprised of all the things you see, hear, do,
and feel as you go through the game.
This is just an opinion, but I feel that players,
I believe that players who feel good
about their experiences in the long dark
enjoy the interplay between these layers.
I hear snow and wind wherever I go.
Always.
Between these layers and find them additive
to the foundational gameplay experience,
which for our game is really 90% about walking around
and strategizing around your rapidly depleting resources.
I also believe that some of our approach
to isolating these layers into discrete experiences,
our sandbox survival mode on one side
and our story mode on another,
resulted for some players in a narrative experience
that felt at odds with their expectations.
To really understand that,
we have to talk about the various layers
of content and systems that generate
what we talk about as the story of the game.
And we also have to talk about our specific approach
in the long dark to presenting these layers
to the player over time.
I wanna talk about the layers of story
as I see them in the long dark.
Maybe you can see these layers in your games too.
There's the world story layer,
which is comprised of what the player sees around them
as they explore the playable space.
This is supported by the game's art direction,
environment design, props,
and the remnants of the game world's prior life
before the player arrived to witness it.
So details like signage,
narrative collectibles left behind, or mise-en-scene,
this is the story that emerges
from interacting with the physicality of the world.
World story is heavily implied.
It's a mostly ambient experience that players take in
and mostly without thinking about it.
And as implied story, it doesn't present itself as such.
It's more about look and feel.
And in some cases, it will be described
as the world's personality.
An example of the world story would be our portrayal
of the town of Milton in episode one of our story mode.
You can tell just by looking at it that not all is well.
You can tell the world is desolate, rundown, isolated,
and decidedly not modern.
Although you can also tell that you aren't in the 18th
or 19th century due to details like power lines,
solar panels, and cars.
For anyone paying attention, these details combine
to create a sense of the game world's prior life.
They serve to draw you into the world and its mysteries.
There's also a system story layer,
which is the story that emerges from the things
the player is doing in the game.
This is mostly about stimuli that force decisions,
the player's manipulation of mechanics,
user interface or controls in trying to execute on decisions
and then the outcomes of those decisions,
always forced by the interminable march
of the game's underlying systems and tuning,
which conspire to create a kind of experiential heartbeat.
By my definition, the system's layer of story
is about memorable moments that exist
at the intersection of the game's interactivity.
Everyone who's played The Long Dark
has a story about getting lost in a blizzard.
I'm sure it's happened to most of you at some point.
Nearly dying and then, upon the brink of death,
miraculously encountering a cabin
that seemingly emerged from out of nowhere.
Or a church.
Contrary to popular belief, there is nothing scripted
or intentional about these moments
except that we want them to happen.
These stories emerge from players recounting a moment
in time that at its heart is a purely mechanical process.
The game systems conspire to create this moment,
much like a printing press conspiring
to produce a page of a novel.
But it's the context the player brings
to this mechanical process that turns it
into something dramatic, giving it meaning.
Oh, geez.
Sit back, there we are.
So here we come to a definition of player story.
Player story is what you get at the intersection
of world and system story layers.
The player can use their intuition and senses
to generate a mental model of what the game world is,
what it might have been before they arrived in it,
and then can use that information
to orient themselves on a visceral level.
Once they engage with systems,
through controls and user interface,
they can start to establish their own presence in the world.
They start to feel some influence over how the world works,
how systems react to their choices.
It's a stimulus and response operation
that increases the player's connection to the game world
with each interaction.
Through this process,
the player begins to feel a strong sense of ownership
over the game world and their interactions with it.
They feel that they are shaping the game
and creating their own story along the way.
For some players, their player's story
is the most important expression of narrative.
And it's a much more powerful story for them
than anything we can create.
Cute bunny, eh?
Authored story is different from player's story
in that it is a narrative structure
that is imposed upon the game systems and world
by external forces, namely the creator of the game.
This tends to follow more traditional narrative lines
such as those we're familiar with from movies or films,
sorry, or novels, movies or novels,
but its primary characteristic is that it is something
that is brought in from the outside,
not something that emerges naturally
through the confluence of world and systems.
It's also something that can, for some players,
interfere with the sense of the player story,
because in terms of hierarchy,
the authored story rules overall.
This can be mitigated in games that have extensive systems
supporting player choice, and then allowing these choices
to modify authored story in a meaningful way.
Some RPGs are able to do this.
for example, or in games where players can more or less
opt out of the authored story and continue to experience
the game primarily along the system and world story layers.
A lot of open world games like Skyrim or Red Dead Redemption
for example, allow you to do this.
That said, most open world games still impose
an authored narrative structure that even the most
free roaming mechanics focused players
will eventually bump up against.
Minecraft is one of the few open-world games
that comes to mind that exists primarily
on the systems and world layer
and eschews authored story entirely.
But I think it's generally true
that for any game that has an intentional authored narrative
this authored narrative supersedes the player story
in the sense that even if you want to ignore it,
you'll likely need to engage with it at some point
if you want to progress.
So why bother with authored narrative at all?
When done poorly, it can conflict with your system story,
and frankly, it's a lot easier and more cost-effective
to create experiences primarily through systems
than through authored narrative content.
Well, I think the truth is that traditional stories
work for a reason.
We're hardwired to understand them,
and the context they provide is an important way
of adding meaning to events which can otherwise feel
kind of pointless.
And while there's certainly a type of player
who prefers their own story
to the one a development team might come up with,
a constituency that's grown a lot
over the last 10 years or so,
this is essentially the Minecraft generation.
A lot of players just can't be bothered.
They feel lost without the benefit
of some overarching storyline.
And they take comfort in knowing
that someone has put some thought
into why they are there, what they are doing,
and how it's all going to come together in the end.
Any X-Files fans here, Lost fans here?
Remember when X-Files first came out,
not the garbage that they're putting out now,
but the first, let's say, five seasons
that were really good, okay?
Or Lost, anyone ever got into Lost, big way, yeah?
Do you remember the moment you realized
that the creators didn't really have a clue
where they were going with the story?
The moment you realized that we were just
kind of making shit up as they went along, right?
That was the moment you probably, like me,
threw your hands up in the air and said, screw this.
Why was that moment upsetting to us?
Because an authored story is taking us along for a ride,
and it's a ride we're willingly submitting to
because we think we're being taken somewhere interesting.
So you know, it better be going somewhere interesting.
And if you stop believing in the tour conductors,
well, it's done.
The illusion is broken.
The magic is lost.
You see behind the curtain,
and there's no point going any further.
I love that GDC is happening
in the middle of all this awesome construction.
To be clear, in this talk,
I'm talking about player story and authored story
in a solo survival game, okay?
Multiplayer is a completely different beast.
Multiplayer games are almost entirely, in my opinion,
about system story, with the added context
of playing against other humans rather than AI
being the thing that provides meaning to the system story.
I think of multiplayer story more like
participating in a sport.
Your story there is about your performance,
close calls, near misses, dramatic goals or saves, and so on.
I don't play a lot of multiplayer games,
but I recall a lot of rounds of Co-op Halo or Left 4 Dead
that were tremendously memorable experiences
because of the reaction from the other humans
I was playing with.
But that gets into a whole other realm of motivations
and psychology around player story
that we don't really have time to get into right now.
Suffice it to say that for the purposes of this talk today,
we're focusing on solo games.
And speaking of solo games,
it's time to talk more about the most solo game of all,
The Long Dark.
You're sitting in a lecture hall listening to a talk
with the subject, Blending Player and Authored Story
in a Sandbox Survival Game.
So you might start by asking yourself,
what does this guy know about it?
See all this gray hair?
It's actually coming out.
That's mostly come in the last five years or so.
Coincidentally, since I founded Hinterland,
it started working on the game
that would become The Long Dark.
If you'll allow me to stroll down memory lane,
and I promise you this is a journey
with an intentional ending,
I'd like to recount for you some of the history of the Long Dark's development and how certain
choices along the way had a dramatic impact on our approach to player versus authored
narrative.
And I might just spare you some gray hairs in the process.
My first concept of the Long Dark was a tablet game called Survival Story.
We built a prototype on iPad,
which let you navigate a simple top-down map
and select points of interest or locations to explore,
at which point the game would transition
to a small 3D scene the player could move around in.
It didn't take long to realize
that this form of presentation would be too limiting
for an experience that was meant to be 90%
about immersive exploration,
so we quickly shifted our focus
to creating something for PC and Steam.
This was back in 2013, and you have to remember
that Steam, while impressive
as a digital distribution platform,
didn't feel quite as omnipresent as it does today.
Everyone, it seemed at that time, however,
was developing games for iOS.
It was a new gold rush.
So to step away from the platform that seemed to be ascendant
for the more pokey-feeling PC felt like a big risk.
Don't forget, this was still the era
when analysts brazenly predicted the death of the PC.
Still hasn't happened, by the way.
In any case, PC felt right for the kind of experience
we wanted to deliver, and Steam meant we could find
an audience without a publisher,
and satisfying these two needs was enough
to merit this way forward.
Most of the team at Hinterland, back then as today,
came to Hinterland after long stints making games
in the AAA side of the industry,
which meant we didn't really know anything
about social media.
Streaming wasn't really a thing,
and our primary experience of community
was the occasional piece of fan mail,
like literal mail, like physical stuff
they send in the mail, that would get sent in
and posted on a bulletin board for all of us to see.
The point here is, we were building along dark
in an environment where community was becoming a thing.
Nobody really knew what it meant or what one was,
but we knew that we needed one.
And a lot of studios kickstarted the creation
of their communities using, well, Kickstarter.
And we did too.
We launched a Kickstarter campaign,
experienced 30 days of terrible anxiety,
and in the end we raised $250,000
and gained a community of nearly 7,000 backers.
And this was amazing for us
and our first wonderful experience
of being front and center with our community
as opposed to interacting from behind the shield
of the marketing and PR departments
that we were accustomed to from our AAA days.
And I think we got a bit excited.
maybe even a bit addicted to the idea of having fans
and feedback for the things we were doing.
Our Kickstarter was for a heavily story-driven
survival experience about a bush pilot
named Will McKenzie who'd crash in the Canadian wilderness
in the aftermath of a mysterious geomagnetic disaster.
Sound familiar?
And that disaster would render all of our technology inert,
thrusting us into a new dark age.
And in the throes of a harsh Canadian winter,
Mackenzie would have to struggle to survive
while managing relationships with other survivors
who were upset at starving and pissed off wolves
and not being able to check Facebook and stuff.
So with our fresh community in tow,
we embarked on work to take our Kickstarter prototype
and flush it out with more mechanics and content,
with the emphasis being on these intriguing,
post-apocalyptic story moments we'd be delivering
in these amazing 2D animated scenes.
What we quickly realized, however,
was that the core of our game, the systems layer,
really needed more feedback.
We'd released an early version of our gameplay systems
and world layer, which we refer to as our sandbox,
hinting at its non-narrative roots,
to some of our backers and received
our first playtesting feedback.
And much like the outcome of our successful
Kickstarter campaign, we were heady
with having direct access to our players.
We wanted more feedback.
We also noticed a trend with some of our Kickstarter backers.
Despite giving them an early build to play,
many of them came back to us saying they wanted to wait.
They didn't want to experience the game
before it was finished.
Specifically, they didn't want to experience the game
before the story was complete.
So we asked ourselves.
How can we get more players more feedback,
but in such a way that we wouldn't spoil their first time
with The Long Dark, by making them go through
the clumsy first draft of a story experience?
I then landed on a solution that would forever
sunder our world and systems layers from our authored layer.
I said, let's separate the mechanics from the story,
release only the mechanics in one region of the game world,
leave just enough info to provide context
for where the player is and why they're there.
but keep all the rest of the real story until it's done.
The intention was to generate more player feedback
on systems while holding back the story
for maximum future impact.
We launched our non-narrative sandbox mode
on Steam Early Access on September 22nd, 2014,
and it kind of took off for us.
In our first three months, we had 250,000 players.
In our first year, we had half a million.
By the time we launched our first episodes
of Story Mode last August,
nearly three years after launching our sandbox
on early access, we had over one and a half million players
across Steam and Xbox One.
Today, we have over two million players
across all platforms, and we still have
three remaining episodes of our Story Mode to go.
I won't lie, we didn't anticipate
how big our sandbox experience would become.
We didn't understand how the growth
of the sandbox player community
would essentially dilute our focus
from the game's story mode
to that of trying to support the games,
the needs and requests of our rapidly growing community.
And while our original Kickstarter backers
may have fallen in love with the game's premise
and narrative aspirations,
our early access backers were buying
into a non-narrative survival sandbox.
Sure, we promised all our backers they'd get all five episodes of our story mode for free,
with their purchase of the game on Early Access or for backing it on Kickstarter,
and some percentage of our Early Access players were certainly anticipating the game's story content,
but the truth is that the majority of players who fell in love with The Long Dark
fell in love with the game's sandbox mode.
They fell in love with the game's world and systems layers.
They fell in love with their own player stories.
And thus began the struggle, the light side, dark side conflict
that continues to influence and govern the thoughts in many corners of our
community today.
What is the Long Dark really about?
Is it about your stories?
Or is it about my story?
The author's story?
The story I wanted to tell in the game?
Well the good news is it's about both.
But as the sandbox experience continued to gain momentum,
I became increasingly frustrated
by how much narrative ownership we were needing to sacrifice
to keep the sandbox engine fueled and functioning.
While the early sandbox regions were intentionally generic,
we started hitting against constraints.
The more world and systems we built to sustain the sandbox,
the harder it became to hold on to content
that would be fundamental to making the game's story mode
stand apart from the sandbox.
Why was this important?
Because we wanted to be able to launch twice.
Once with our sandbox and once with our story mode.
We didn't want to lose out on the chance
to do a big reveal of our story content
and we wanted to ensure that by the time
we launched our first episodes,
people would still give a shit.
In order to accomplish this, we needed our story launch
to essentially be a whole different experience.
And the more we built up the sandbox,
the longer it took to build up the story mode
to the corresponding degree.
Because, well, story was our idea.
It was the reason we'd made the game to begin with.
It was, I wanted to present the story of Will McKenzie
and his estranged wife, Dr. Astrid Greenwood,
and share their complicated relationship with players
against the backdrop of a harsh wilderness survival
in this post-apocalyptic,
aurora-illuminated Canadian landscape.
I wanted to create an epic survival story
with a decidedly Canadian context
and a new kind of disaster, a quiet apocalypse,
that would be thoughtful and beautiful.
But many of our players were happy
to simply avoid freezing to death
while they tried not to get eaten by wolves.
Many, many times we heard the refrain
and we still hear it today.
I don't care if they spend any more time on story,
I just want more sandbox updates.
Maybe some of you write that.
It's okay.
In order to maximize the impact of our story mode launch,
we kept the game world intentionally generic,
almost as if we wanted it to stand as a placeholder
for what the game would become at full launch.
Regions took on totemic names like Pleasant Valley
and Mystery Lake.
Items had simple names and iconic labels
that left as much as possible to the player's imagination.
There was no readable text in the world,
including on signage.
We kept our world story vague and almost impressionistic
to allow maximum mileage in player story.
We do as much as possible to influence
the player's experience of the world and its history
as little as possible.
But in this was my fatal flaw.
Well, not fatal, because clearly I'm still here,
but if I was a character in a novel,
it would be my fatal flaw.
Despite this intentional genericism of world story designed to support as much player freedom and ownership of the game experience as possible,
I didn't really revise my internal definition for what the authored story of The Long Dark would or should be.
Well, that's not entirely true. I'd actually made it way harder on myself and my team.
I decided that it wasn't enough to just tell Mackenzie's story. We should also tell Astrid's story.
And we shouldn't tell the story in such a way
that the plot remained the same
whether you select McKenzie or Astrid,
a gender-based selection that would have no real impact
on the story the player would experience.
The mass effect approach,
we would go all the way
and create two entirely different stories.
Yikes.
Back when the game was called Survival Story,
the narrative would be delivered primarily
in these motion graphic styled cinematic scenes.
You can see remnants of the style in our first episode,
actually, in those flashback sequences
in the hangar and then plane crash.
With basic dialogue trees allowing
some fairly simplistic player choice logic.
And while the world would feel relatively open,
the narrative structure would be pretty linear.
Much more linear than a truly open world game.
Because back then, Survival Story wasn't really
an open world game like The Long Dark would become.
The point here is, I was still thinking
about the structure of the story being more linear
as it was in its initial iterations
of the project's early days.
And that failure to update the narrative structure
to suit an increasingly open
and free-form player experience
created a tension and conflict
in our player experience that persists today.
We were also faced with the fact that our game world,
in the pursuit of supporting the thriving sandbox mode,
had become far too big for us to support
with one holistic chunk of mission and narrative content.
Although I liked the episodic structure
for how it mapped to television-style writing
that felt like a great fit for our game,
we ultimately had to find a way to break up our story
into smaller pieces,
because our game had just become too big.
So when we launched the first two episodes of Wintermute,
our story mode, players discovered an experience
that was, well, much more linear
than they had become accustomed to having
in their sandbox mode play.
And not at all following the same general
main quest, side quest, directionless wandering paradigm
that games like Fallout and Skyrim had trained them to expect.
Add to that, they'd had three years of player story,
knowing that the authored story would come along someday.
Three years to think up all the ways
in which the story could go.
Three years in which to create their own ideas
of what the story of The Long Dark should be.
And while that wasn't something we could really live up to
in some cases, and even for the people
who may not have had such stratospheric expectations
about the game's narrative mode,
imposing a strictly linear mission and narrative structure
on what for many of them
was a vastly open world survival sandbox.
Well, this just didn't work.
It wasn't what they were expecting.
It wasn't how other open world games blended
their player's story and author's story.
Essentially, we had gone against the true nature
of what the game had become
and forced an adventure game narrative structure
onto what had become a very open,
very free form sandbox experience.
Now, not all was lost, of course.
While some people were frustrated with the new constraints,
others embraced the goals and context
provided by the game's narrative mode.
While some players found that the game could never live up
to the stories they had made up in their own heads,
others found it a pleasant diversion
from the game's sandbox mode,
something to jump into as a kind of palate cleanser
before moving back into a challenging
100-day interloper game.
Still others found the story mode provided the game
with the necessary narrative momentum
that the sandbox mode was sorely lacking for them.
The story gave them a reason to play.
One thing we've realized since we launched our episodes
last August is that this dissonance between expectations
set up by the game's sandbox experience
and what we delivered in our story mode
were largely a function of our lengthy
early access campaign.
We found that players who've jumped into the game
since we launched our 1.0 with Wintermute
actually play the story episodes as a kind of tutorial
in preparation for the game's more challenging
sandbox survival mode.
This works as intended since the story mode
not only introduces mechanics in a safer context,
thus softening the hard entry
into our permadeath survival mode,
but also allows players to take all the world layer context
from story mode with them into survival mode.
Issues with mission linearity aside,
I suspect that if we'd launched our story
and survival mode simultaneously,
rather than with a three year interval between them,
this perceived disconnect
wouldn't have really been an issue.
The other benefit of launching the first two episodes
of our story mode is that it allowed us the opportunity
to reset expectations about the world layer of the game
by adding more specific information about what happened
before the player arrived,
essentially the world's prior life.
As if to reinforce this, the first region in episode one
was the town of Milton, the first major region
in the Long Dark to have a non-generic name.
we poured a lot of energy into making Milton
feel like a real place.
And it set a new standard for us
in the level of realization and verisimilitude
we'd achieve with our locations.
We also took the opportunity to add some life
to the world layer by leaving narrative collectibles behind.
Notes that would, again, fill in some of the blanks
regarding what had happened to the world
of Great Bear Island before you crashed your plane
in the aurora-filled night sky.
One way in which we attempted to unify the system story
and authored story layers in The Long Dark
was through the inclusion of our trust system.
The idea here was that various predetermined narrative
and knowledge breadcrumbs would be unlocked
based on your gaining trust with survivors in the world.
These breadcrumbs could be background on world events,
map locations to supply caches, crafting blueprints,
or even skill knowledge that would improve
your capabilities as a survivor.
These gameplay elements were contextualized
with story moments, typically dressed up with lore
or backstory to provide at least a thin veneer of meaning
outside of their value to the system's layer.
In order to gain trust, however,
the player has to provide the NPC survivor with supplies,
resources they can't get on their own.
And gathering these resources requires the player engage
with the game's core exploration survival systems loops.
It's similar to the relationship mission progression has
to narrative content in most games with a story.
In a mission, you are provided with narrative context,
a reason for why an NPC needs something from you.
You then engage with game systems
in order to achieve the stated goals,
and your reward is typically some gameplay benefit,
loot, progression, et cetera.
And then also the unlocking
of the next beat of narrative context.
That's not unique to The Long Dark,
that's just a general structure.
Trust plays with the same structure
but streamlines it to its very essence.
The context is simple.
The goal is often something that the player needs,
and in the process of trying to satisfy the objectives
outlined by the narrative context,
the player engages in the core systems loop,
which then produces new opportunities for player story
via the systems interactions.
Unfortunately, in our current implementation,
many players found the trust content
to feel very fetch-quest-y.
In the context of a survival experience, it makes sense that NPCs are often weaker than you,
which are to get you to take risks on their behalf.
And in a world of resource scarcity, the challenge of obtaining food, fuel, and other supplies
to help ensure someone else's survival, potentially at the cost of your own success,
creates an interesting tension, and is thematically very relevant to our world.
It's relevant to our game world,
but I guess it's relevant to the real world too.
It was also a way for us to differentiate
between the survival mode, an ultra egocentric experience
where you only have to worry about your own needs,
to the challenges of having to consider the balancing
of your needs against the needs of other people
you encounter in the world, many who need your help.
How far will you go to survive?
It's probably a testament to how systems-focused Trust felt
and the fact that we treated it individually
from the rest of our dialogue, narrative,
and mission content, that it presented
as a thinly-veiled progression system.
In future iterations, we're making Trust more integrated
into the core experience of interacting with NPCs,
and I still believe that as an experiment
in blending player story, system story,
and authored story into a single system,
Trust netted some pretty interesting results.
While the decision to split the game into sandbox
and story modes allowed us to confidently launch
our early access campaign without fear of spoiling
the story content for our players,
and to be clear I think that was the right call
given that I don't think heavily narrative games
generally do well in the early access model.
I think we ended up breaking with open world conventions
in doing so.
We created a split between our more heavily
narrative focused experience and our more heavily
systems focused sandbox experience.
Whereas most open world games allow
the two approaches to coexist.
leaving it up to the player to choose for themselves
what type of content they prefer to engage with.
There have been some sandbox survival experiences
who have managed to introduce their narrative mode
while still in early access.
The Forest and Subnautica come to mind as examples
where this has been done well.
And both those games have been able to integrate
their narrative modes directly
into their core open world sandbox.
For our game, however, we found that by the time
we had a strong handle on what an episode
for The Long Dark would look and play like,
the game had already essentially become, well, two games.
The strongest expression of this difference
is in the way we handle player failure and saves.
In story mode, you can save anywhere,
and failure can more or less be remedied
by reloading from an earlier save point.
But survival mode is permadeath.
If you die, we delete your save.
And the risk of the game's permadeath nature
is frankly one of its core strengths.
The danger of loss is what lends meaning
to the system's story in survival mode.
Combining story and survival modes
into one open world survival experience
would have unified the two approaches,
but removing permadeath from survival mode
or adding it to story mode
would destroy the spirit of each experience
and frankly, result in a worse game for everyone.
So this reunification is just not possible for us,
given how our game has evolved over time.
So while I think that our approach has taken us
outside the standard conventions of open world games,
we're committed to making it work
for the remainder of our five episode story mode.
That said, this doesn't mean we're happily standing still.
One of the things you quickly learn
about making sandbox survival games in an open development
and community-focused environment is,
you're only as good as your last update.
And after over four years of highly iterative
open development on The Long Dark,
the team at Hinterland is now heavily optimized
for this particular development methodology.
In other words, we can't leave well enough alone.
So we're working on several things
to strengthen the relationship between player story
and authored story in the long dark.
Some of these are a bit spoilery, but hey, it's GDC.
You have to get something for your money, right?
We have an episodic story structure
which does introduce some useful constraints for us.
We can present a series of narrative nodes
within a specific physical area,
keeping in mind that the survival mode version of Great Bear
has eight major regions, four transition regions,
adding up to over 50 square kilometers
of terrain to explore, which makes it bigger than Skyrim.
Episodes one and two combined
only cover about 20% of this world,
and the world is still growing.
A lot of our narrative and mission structure
for the episodes was actually designed by necessity
to work around the design goal of constraining the player
to specific areas before letting them move on.
This is a common technique used in open world games,
but in general, the constraints are softer
and the boundaries are a bit less binary
than in our episodes.
Our goal was also to make our story delivery
feel more like a television series than like a film.
So we have hard openings and cliffhanger endings in the episodes to hopefully draw people back in
after they complete each self-contained episode, which to be clear are not telltale sized.
Our episodes are between five and ten hours long.
In any case, one of the things we're doing
to unify player and author story a bit more moving forward
is making our mission structure less linear.
We've actually gone back into our episode one
and two mission scripting and opened things up significantly
so that you can now complete most of the major objectives
in whatever order you like.
And in some cases, you can completely opt out of mission
threads that were previously mandatory.
We're also redoing the bear hunt for anyone
who might wanna know that.
In order to support this increased openness,
we also had to move away from our previous
cinematic presentation style,
where we bookended dialogue sequences
with non-interactive cinematics
towards something that can support enhanced player choice.
We've been working on a new kind of dialogue mode
for The Long Dark,
something that does a better job
of integrating the system layer of the game.
this thing, and it's contextualization within story moments
into interactions with NPCs, and also an interface style
that itself represents the nuance around what it's like
to interact with a character who might be scared
or mistrustful of you.
As you can see from this example,
topics sort of float around NPCs like dust moats,
and their position relative to you, their size,
color, and behavior, all indicate something
about their context.
Larger fonts mean these are subjects the NPC really wants to talk to you about.
Locked items suggest topics that are available if only you first satisfy a gameplay requirement.
We use question marks to indicate that this NPC has more to say to you in the future.
And the speed at which some topics move, or the fact that they may fade in and out,
making them hard to select during a conversation,
reflects on an NPC who might be trying to be evasive about something.
This approach not only blends the systems layer
and authored layer much more organically,
but it's also scalable and dynamic enough
to be reactive to player choices,
which supports our goal of opening up the mission
and therefore the narrative structure.
Well, I certainly don't recommend that you go back
and spend a lot of time and money redoing content
that you already spent a lot of time and money on,
content that a lot of your players have already experienced
and may not want to experience again,
but we see these improvements as important work
for strengthening the foundation of our game
so that we can build a future story episode content
such that the player story and authored story
coexist more cohesively.
So after all this, what comes next?
Well, as far as this presentation goes,
I'd like to leave you with a few high-level takeaways,
things for you to consider in your own projects,
and then with whatever time we have left,
open the floor to your questions.
For a lot of players, and this is particularly true
if you have an open-world-ish or sandbox-ish game,
their story is a lot more important to them
than anything you might come up with.
Make sure that you create tools
that allow them to influence the game world
in a way that gives them a sense of ownership.
In the long dark, we often have players
post lengthy survival diaries that narrate
the moment-to-moment mechanics of their sandbox experiences.
To a lesser degree, players share their experiences
of the story mode, but there's just less for them
to own there that other players aren't also experiencing.
Our survival sandbox has become an engine
for memorable moments, which makes it appealing
for streaming, itself a kind of player storytelling.
And we have an in-game diary that encourages players
to keep notes of what they've done each day,
or remark on where they may have stashed supplies
or encountered obstacles they'd like to come back to
when they're in better shape.
We also think about how to create interesting choices
within our mechanics.
Things like our rabbit harvesting interaction,
where you have to make a choice
about snapping a cute bunny's neck,
or releasing it and going hungry yourself.
These are relatively small investments
from an implementation standpoint,
but they can create tons of animated discussion
amongst your community.
A lot of it in public places
where other people's curiosity might drive them
to check out your game.
In this case, the rabbit harvesting
also becomes core to the player's story,
and the choice to harvest or release, as in Bioshock,
is something players will reflect deeply on,
strengthening their bond with the game.
The point here is, sometimes small tools
dedicated to player sharing can go a long way.
when they are in support of a game with a high index
of player-generated story moments.
A lot of your players won't be satisfied
with only having player story.
Authored story still has a very important role to play
in setting up overall context
and providing necessary momentum
and motivation for player activities.
If you give players the opportunity to opt out
of the authored story from time to time
in ways that feel meaningful,
then the two approaches to story
can complement one another nicely.
This is in fact the true strength of the open world genre.
And if you don't have the budget for cinematics,
VO, facial animation, et cetera,
find a more cost effective way
to present your narrative moments.
There are many great examples of how to do this
across the spectrum of independent games.
So don't abandon authored narrative
because you're afraid it will be too expensive.
Consistency is more important
than hitting a particular presentation style.
This is less of a note on narrative approach
and more about general community engagement
or setting expectations.
If you're making a sandbox survival game
in an open development environment
like early access or game preview,
be very clear about the kind of game you are making
when you talk about it with your community.
We spent nearly four years publicly making
a super open freeform survival sandbox game
and at the same time made a narrative mode for it
that we kept very much in secret.
Even though we tried to explain that our story mode
would be different from Sandbox,
for fear of spoiling stuff, we never really articulated
exactly how our story mode would differ from Sandbox.
It might be better to give up some of the surprise factor
and just be more forthcoming about the exact nature
of your game structure,
assuming you were holding major stuff back
from your community.
I think in general, you can get a community on board
with pretty major changes to a game,
provided you ease them into it,
which in the case of our story mode, we did not do.
I would never suggest that anyone design a game
specifically to make it more streamable,
but if your game naturally lends itself
to this type of player storytelling,
then do whatever you can to make the most of it.
That said, for offline games like The Long Dark,
the most important storytelling tends to happen
outside the game, in the community itself.
So try to provide some in-game tools
to facilitate players recording their own experiences.
A journal-type system is a good place to start.
And outside the game, make sure you dedicate
some safe community space for the sharing
of fan fiction and player diaries.
Not only will this serve as a stage for your players' creativity,
but their excitement about their own stories will be infectious
and encourage others to explore your game.
Well, I don't think we've necessarily solved the problem
of better blending of player and authored story
with the long dark, at least not yet,
and I don't pretend that I've provided the solution
to this talk, the balancing act between the imposition
of authored story on player story is one
that many open world games are still struggling to solve.
My theory is that it's not really possible
to find a balance between these elements
that satisfies all player types,
so that providing as much freedom as possible
is probably the safest path forward.
In this way, our solution of creating two different modes,
one specifically targeted at systemic anecdote creation
and one specifically targeted at a more traditional narrative
might be a viable alternative to the vast,
blended open-world experiences that are the purview
of the Skyrims and Grand Theft Autos of the world.
Because ultimately, whether your game has discrete systems
designed to support player or authored story,
or it doesn't, the player's experience of your game
and how they talk about it with other people,
whether it's in streams, in forums, blogs,
or in social media, will be the most powerful story
they experience.
Thank you.
So we have seven minutes for questions.
Anyone who knows me knows that I'm a terrible rambler,
which is why I had to read off my slides.
By those, I would have run out of time a long time ago.
Go ahead.
Hi.
This was a really insightful talk.
Thank you very much.
Thank you very much, too.
If it would have gone the other way around,
and you'd had authored story first.
Thanks to everyone who came, sorry.
For however long, a couple of years or something,
how do you imagine the challenges would have been different?
So the question is, if we had done it the other way around,
so started with authored narrative and then done sandbox,
how would the challenges have been different?
I mean, I think that's sort of what I was trying to get at
with the layers idea is that I don't know that in a
open world or sandbox game, you can't have
an authored narrative layer without a systems layer,
a world layer, et cetera, et cetera.
I can't off the top of my head think of an example of a game that does that.
Maybe you can.
If you say if you've gone like you can only allow the player to experience it through
the altered story.
Mm hmm.
So we more like an adventure game.
Yeah.
Right.
And then like it would feel like a.
really linear story, okay, I finished the story,
and now you start to tell the players,
oh, we've got this other sandbox mode.
Right, yeah, I think what would have happened
in that case is then sort of the differences
would be even more stark, like,
because you literally would have a very linear game,
and then this other open world game
kind of bolted onto the side.
So even though we do sort of differentiate
between the two things, even our story mode,
for a lot of players,
It's not actually as linear as I portrayed it here, I don't think anyways.
I think there's still a lot of freedom within the constraints of each episode.
And a good example of that is I remember when we launched,
we had a piece of feedback in our community from a player who said,
You know, I find episode one so boring.
I spent 90 hours wandering around Milton
and there's just like nothing to do, right?
And we're like, yeah, but it was only designed
for you to be there for like five or six hours.
And it just highlighted that I assume that this player
was someone who had come to us from the sandbox mode
where they would maximize their time in a space
and optimize their resource use as much as possible.
ignoring the fact that there was a whole story going on in episode one that was trying to kind of give the momentum forward.
So to answer your question directly, I'm not sure we would have ever done that,
but I think if we had, we would have ended up with two very different games, even more different than they are currently.
Great. Thank you very much. Thank you very much. Hi.
Thank you so much for the talk. That was super interesting.
Thank you.
I have a question. It seemed to me one of the things you were pointing towards in player story is the importance of novelty.
Is the idea that you as a player can always generate new content for yourself, a new story content for yourself.
And I was wondering if you think that may be the key hook in making players so enamored of player story and how you think...
What ways do you think you can best push that into the author's story and get the same sort of novelty hook,
even if it's a story with which the player is somewhat more familiar?
That's a great question. I'm going to try to rephrase it, but you might have to help me out.
work with me here. So the novelty of the player's story
is what makes that experience interesting and you're asking how we can...
Yes, that's my question. It seemed like part of your argument for why it makes it
interesting is the novelty.
If that's the case, how can you best push that into the authored story?
Yeah, I'm not sure if I would have used the word novelty myself.
I think of it more from the perspective of ownership.
So I think there's just a natural feeling,
and that's kind of why I tried to make the note about,
you know, if a story's done really well,
you kind of go along for the ride and you don't mind,
and you sort of, that's why I use words like submit.
You submit to it because you're giving up some freedom to do that.
In the sandbox mode, where it's more about player story,
there are no constraints other than the mechanical constraints
of freezing to death, et cetera, et cetera.
So I think in those cases the players that really align themselves with that style of game
derive much more enjoyment out of those little moments that happen
kind of along the way as they're experiencing the game systems.
So I think what we tried to do with our story mode was exactly what you're suggesting,
which was we tried to...
use the mechanics layer of the game, the system story,
you know, as the, I won't say filler, that's the wrong,
but basically the narrative or the story layer,
if I approach it the other way,
the story layer was really providing the context
and kind of that momentum and the heartbeat
of what was going on in the world,
and the systems layer was what was providing the moments
for those, you know, moment to moment experiences
that would hopefully be memorable for players.
And so that was really our intention
with that survival mode.
Sort of echoing what I said over here.
I think where we ran into problems was just that,
you know, when you have a 50 square kilometer world
and you can wander aimlessly forever,
and we have players that play for 1,500, 2,000 hours
kind of in the sandbox world,
even putting them in an area that's 10 square kilometers
suddenly feels very restrictive to them.
But anyways, to your question,
I think we tried to do that with our story mode.
And I actually think that that's,
if you think about any open world game that's successful,
I think they all are doing that.
They're providing that overarching narrative
to give the player reason to continue,
but then really it's the moment to moment experience
of the game, which is what kind of brings them back.
And those are the things that people tend to talk about.
They don't tend to talk about like,
oh my God, remember that awesome cinematic that happened
where that character said that thing
to that other character?
It's really more about like, holy cow,
do you remember that moment that that thing happened
in the game that I did in the game, right?
Does that answer your question?
Yeah.
Not really?
Feel free to get in touch with me afterwards.
It's pretty nuanced stuff.
Yeah, yeah, absolutely.
But thank you, yeah.
Thank you for the question.
I'll take up everybody.
Okay, thank you.
Anyone else?
All right, you guys let me off easy.
All right, thank you very much for coming.
Oh, we've got one more here, I'm sorry.
I shouldn't have spoke too soon.
Hi, how similar is the story mode as it launched
to how you envisioned it at the time
of the Kickstarter pitch?
I mean, in terms of realization, we were able to achieve much more than what we'd expected
to achieve in our Kickstarter pitch.
We had a fairly small budget when we did that campaign, fairly modest ambitions for what
we would do with the game.
And so what we ended up delivering is, I feel...
at a much higher level of quality,
a much more impressive level of realization
in terms of facial animation and character realization
and the music and the VO and everything
that's going on there.
So certainly in our original intention,
things were gonna be much more modest
in terms of presentation.
So we were able to not only provide a much bigger world
that had a much richer set of systems to play with,
but also the actual narrative content itself
was at a higher level of realization.
But the actual underlying story or the intention of the game pretty much didn't change at all from the Kickstarter to launch
with the exception of adding the Astrid story.
So in the original sort of idea for the Lone Dark,
you would just play Mackenzie's story kind of all the way through and Astrid was there as a character to kind of help
provide motivation for doing certain things.
But when we launch our third episode,
you're actually gonna be playing as Asterix.
You're gonna see the sort of the experience
of the long dart from a completely different perspective.
She's a doctor, she's in a different part
of the world than you are.
So sort of we'll show her part of the story as well
and kind of go back and forth between the two characters.
So that was something that we would never have been able
to do in our Kickstarter,
like in the pitch that we had for the Kickstarter campaign
and would have been far outside of our reach.
I think it's not outside of our reach right now.
Does that answer your question?
Okay, great.
Anyways, it seems like we're out of time,
so thank you so much for coming,
and feel free to get in touch with me afterwards
if you like.
Thank you.