still somewhat hungover from last night. I know this is the
first talk of the day and I appreciate all of you taking the
time to come out and see my presentation.
So my name is John Jones and I have spent the majority of my career working remotely and I've
learned a lot of things through trial and error and mistakes I've made, successes I've seen in
others and I've been writing and speaking for years on the subject of how to be a really
effective remote worker, contractor, freelancer, and essentially just helping
I learn as I go and I'm very honest about what I've learned, my mistakes, my successes,
and I like relaying that to other people so they can get to the same point where I feel
I am in my career, where I have more choice and control over what I do, how I do it, and
get to, most importantly, live where I want instead of not having to move everywhere.
So hopefully this presentation will give all of you an idea of some of the tips and
techniques you can use to start working remotely, whether you're working full time,
working full time doing so and want to keep doing that for your existing employer or if you
want to make a complete break and go into the exciting world and stressful world of
freelancing. So first off,
I have 16 years in game development, nine of them remote,
I've worked on over 50 titles.
My specialization is as an outsourcing manager,
as a freelancer, which to my knowledge, nobody else does.
And I've been doing that since 2009.
And I've been building and managing remote teams
of anywhere from five to 75 people
for a variety of clients and employers,
including Epic Games, Avalanche Studios, 2K Games,
NC Soft, Sony Online Entertainment, et cetera.
So I've had a lot of experience at studios, both large and small, all kinds of tool sets.
And all that began because in 2008 and 2009, I was laid off twice in one year and I was at the
point of forget this. And I decided, okay, I'm going to take more control over this. I'm not
going to be beholden to one boss anymore.
didn't, it bothered me a little bit that technically there's no such thing as a freelance
outsourcing manager, but I lived in Austin, it was cheap enough to live off unemployment and
severance, so I figured I'd make a go of it. Eight years later, I'm living in Brooklyn and
doing the same thing.
So, cutting the tether. Much has been written about the tools, the philosophy, the home
set-ups, what hardware to buy, what attitudes to have, blah, blah, blah. I'm not going to
do that. I'm not here to repeat those. And frankly, I've done several talks on them as
well. On my website I've had other talk presentations and articles on specifically what
hardware to buy if you want to be an independent content developer on like the Unity
asset store, the Unreal Engine marketplace, which I used to run, I have an article on
that.
I don't want to retread that, I want to go into the nitty gritty details that I haven't
heard other people talk about before in hopes that some of this will stick.
So ask yourself, what do you really want to do? Do you want to do the same job as now, only
doing it from home, just transition into being someone that works full time from home with
your current employer? Do you want to freelance from contract to contract? Or is your
ultimate dream to develop your own game and just pay the bills by freelancing until you're
in a position where your game is released and that can be your full time thing?
So scenario one is doing the same job from home.
When in your heart of hearts,
you really just want to spend more time
with your cats and wearing shorts.
So, but the sad truth of this is,
sometimes organizations simply will not allow remote work
and there's only so much you can do
like within those parameters.
Sometimes it may be a non-starter,
but it's still worth feeling out.
And I'm going to go into some tips and techniques
for how to negotiate that and earn your way into doing so.
typically speaking, management by walking around is the norm,
seeing people at their desks, speaking from the management
producer level on down, okay, all these desks are full, looks
like they're working the applications I expect. So
scenario one, the same job from home. So management by walking
around is the norm. It's essentially producer or manager
walking around saying, okay, this person is at their desk,
this person isn't.
the appropriate applications are open. I can sit down and have a quick casual conversation if I
need to. It's a lot easier to just casually encounter someone walking around in the
workplace and get a general sense of what's going on and to be able to have a specific
request.
for them doing so.
Some managers prefer being able to see people
physically face to face.
Others prefer doing all of it digitally,
either through Hangouts or Slack or even SMS.
I've had some bosses, which is strange.
So for people that, managers that prefer walking around,
their ability to control their environment
and feel confident in what they're doing
involves being able to see people,
being able to speak to them,
and being able to serve them physically.
So in the worst possible case, for them, remote work is a loss of their control.
So you have to go out of your way to increase your presence remotely
and make it easier for them to feel comfortable knowing what you're doing
and to have you be a predictable component of development.
This is a way to alleviate anxiety in a boss,
which is, generally speaking, a really good thing.
So fortunately, a lot of these techniques
for increasing your productivity,
increasing your reliability and presence
can be practiced on site.
For example, projecting yourself remotely
is the biggest thing you can do as a remote worker
to be able to increase confidence,
not only in your bosses, but also in your team,
so they can know that you're someone reliable,
they can be assigned work,
and they know what you're gonna do and where to expect it.
So your job is to be where they look first. What are their basic expectations in the day-to-day
workflow? Some people use slack, some people have internal messaging systems, some people
have like an internal forum or like base camp shotgun, something like that.
Just find out where that expectation is and focus your efforts on being visible there,
because you have to actively participate and actively make your presence known far above
average than you would if you were working in house.
And that's a really, that's a large hump to get over.
So while you're still working at a studio, you can try and increase your presence digitally
to find out how to get people's attention when you can't simply walk over to their desk.
You have to always actively compensate for being out of sight.
So there are a lot of ways you can challenge yourself to be able to get answers if you're not
physically there, even though you still are. For example, which co-workers ignore email and
instant messaging? Who's always texting? That could be one way to reach people. If source
control is down, where else is the information you need to live? Is it somewhere on the
server? Is it...
like back up on Dropbox somewhere, do you have access to that and can you get it? These are
things you have to seek out and think about when you work remotely because if you're 30
minutes to an hour away from the office and you have no other way to access it except
physically, you should have planned better.
And another situation, if it's late and you need help,
and you know from being in the office who always stays late,
that person's a potential resource.
You have to constantly challenge yourself
to try and find out how would I seek these things out
if I didn't have physical access to the facility,
and what do I need to have access to at this studio
for me to be productive?
even if no one else is around. You have to learn to be extremely self‑sufficient and no one
will really teach you that. In a way this is like a build‑up to being able to ask if you can
work remotely, which I will get to, but always challenge yourself and pose interesting
problems to yourself to try to solve. You also have to accept greater
responsibility. So when you're working remotely, you're responsible for your own
hardware, storage, connectivity, a high rate of responsiveness and consistent productivity.
So I bring up productivity in particular because it's the best
thing you can do if you're working off-site to maintain
confidence in your team and in your bosses is to be a
consistent, reliable resource. I think of it as a marathon
instead of a sprint. I'd rather someone that was about 90%
productive every day consistently so I know what to
expect of them instead of one day they're an incredible
performer, the next day they're barely there, and then the next
day they're an incredible performer again.
the more you can be a component they don't have to actively have to think about,
the more valuable you are to the company.
And a lot of that is how you're able to project yourself remotely
and be where they look first in what they expect of you.
So I see this, so if you're working for someone full time,
I see earning your way up to being able to work remotely
as the end point of a campaign,
you have to start in the beginning.
So you have to lay the groundwork
to increase your perceived value internally and externally.
So step it up at work and perform better than ever and show that you can sustain that over
time. Like I said before, if you can be a solid 90 percent productivity every day instead of
fluctuating quite a bit, that will build a lot of trust in that environment. You have to
increase your mastery of the tools and technology and understand what you need to be able to
get the job done either on site or off site and showing that kind of technical mastery very
much unlike what I did in trying to get this up on the screen.
that can be a huge confidence builder
and help build a case for you being able to work remotely.
Also, write about what you do, write about your craft.
Blog, publish, get involved in online forums.
Like, work on creating a credible name for yourself
and help other people in doing so.
Basically, the more you write or talk about a thing,
the firmer that gets in your mind,
the easier it is to explain,
the better it is, the more of a subject matter expert
you seem, and generally speaking,
employers like and promote and encourage that.
And a lot of people won't do it.
So if you can make that kind of,
if you can distinguish yourself.
in that kind of way that will also help build the case for you being able to be allowed to work
remotely. Also speak at conferences, both local and national. Find local user groups like the
IGDA that Ian and I have spoken at several times before. That's an excellent resource. Just
building up that kind of portfolio as a public facing subject matter expert is yet another
reason to be able to be granted the privilege to work off-site.
and as I said earlier, practice your telepresence while you're on site and find out how to be a
visible contributor, not just walking around, not just in meetings, but also like inside your
actual tool set. Like inside whatever tools you use where other developers are going to be able
to see your contributions. You need to learn to communicate that openly and clearly. So it's
obvious that whether or not you're physically on site, they know where to look to see that you're
getting things done and that is concretely provable.
And this will make your request to work from home
a much easier thing to say yes to.
And this is something that should begin realistically
three to six months before you really want
to target doing that.
Again, consistency and predictability is key here.
So how to ask.
First off, just ask your employer about their work from
home policy and how flexible they are on that.
This varies wildly.
Some places are really open to it.
Some places are very resistant to it.
The campaign for proving yourself to be more reliable,
practicing your telepresence, all those things will get you
a little bit closer to a yes in environments where they're
not necessarily going to be amenable to letting you just
go off and work from home.
It's an extended buttering up period, essentially.
So if you're pitching, here's how I could work from home,
it's incredibly important to clearly define
what performing to expectations means.
So you have to have goal posts that are concrete,
provable, that you can prove that you have crossed
in order to map out progress over time.
So let's say I'd like to work from home
one day per week to start.
Here is how much productivity is expected of me,
like this amount of work or this amount of output.
whatever, some sort of concrete metric that you can point to and refer back to historically.
So at the end of let's say a three month review period of working one day from home, you can
say, look, I kept my promise, I maintained this consistent level of production over this
amount of time based on these agreed upon parameters that we negotiated in advance. If
you feel this is going well based on this, like based on this review,
could I do two days per week? And at that point the negotiations move forward, it will be a
little bit easier to ask for more. And again, everyone's case is unique, but this is at the
very least a starting point for finding out whether or not you can do that in your
organization and you can plan accordingly. And again, always be consistent, predictable,
and dependable. As a manager you don't want to have to worry is this going to be a productive
day for them working from home or is it going to be a nothing day?
have they done nothing but post cat pictures on Twitter all day or am I getting 150
emails of all the change lists I checked in this afternoon. Never make them wonder. The
less they have to actively think about you the better because they know what you can
produce, they know where to look for it. It's a part of their day to day already and you're
not something they have to actively follow up with or be concerned with because you're
everywhere they're looking.
and also don't be sneaky. Anything except for full honesty will ruin this opportunity and it
will ruin the working relationship. I was in a situation once where one of my developers was
secretly trying to work from home because he moved too far away to commute.
So, a piecemeal, he would borrow equipment and work from home and say,
oh, I have a doctor's appointment, can I just work for the rest of the day from home?
To the point where he just thought that he could stop coming in one day
and say, oh, well, I've already borrowed all this equipment, I don't really need to come in ever again, do I?
No, that was not the case, and that permanently ended his opportunity of working from home
pretty much ever again, because he was not open and honest about it.
Although I admit it was kind of comical the way he went about it.
So scenario two, the freelancer life.
I'm not looking to be tied down right now.
So the sad truth is, freelancing is really hard.
You'll spend at least 50% of your time
doing business development.
You, like, in your heart of hearts,
you're thinking you're gonna be sitting at home
with your Cintiq or with your laptop.
kicking your feet up in your favorite chair,
and just rocking out, doing really cool stuff all the time.
No, a lot of this is gonna be emailing people,
asking for work, following up,
trying to collect on payments,
filling out tons and tons of paperwork,
having a legal contact sometimes,
having to do your own taxes
or pay a tax professional to do them.
It is really, really annoying.
It's only half of it is what you think.
It is absolutely not for everybody. Because there are a
lot of ‑‑ so if you're working in a studio, all of
these things are taken care of for you. So you'll begin to
immediately appreciate what admin, legal, finance and
business dev departments really do for you. They
They oil the gears that keep the engine running. When you go out and freelance on your own, all of
that is up to you. And you become painfully aware of, oh, wow, this is literally everything but my
direct job was taken care of for me. This is a lot more. And a lot of people don't really last
beyond the first six months to one year of freelancing because it's a splash of cold water.
and it can be really fun when it's at its best,
but just know there's, 50% of it's gonna be
fairly unpleasant unless you just love signing NDAs
and forms and chasing people down for payments.
So where do I start? So first, if you're going the freelance route, find out what kind of
side work your employer permits, if any. If they don't, don't freelance. Don't find yourself in a
situation where your current employer could technically legally own the content you're
creating for whatever client you have on the side. That is ugly, that's messy, that will
blacklist you as a freelancer and always stay on the right side of whatever contracts you
have signed and abide by. Do not mess around with that.
So if they do not allow side work,
you can start yet another campaign
to break out on your own and start gathering clients.
So be prolific, publish, broadcast your work,
start months before you want to go full-time remote.
Think of it as a marketing campaign.
So if you're an artist, be on Art Station, be on CG Talk,
be on Poly Count, enter every contest.
Whenever other people are entering contests,
comment on their work.
It doesn't have to be 100% self-promotion,
but if you can make yourself a part of the communities
in which...
active freelancers and other subject matter experts
alongside you, see you as a regular fixture.
That is, and you can be a normal part of that consistently
over time and consistently produce good work,
and it's not 100% self-promotion.
That will make it much easier for people to come to you,
especially if you publish tutorials, if you give talks,
and if you write about the craft
and you get really involved with other professionals.
I just signed my 50th project recently and literally every
single gig I have ever had on every title has been a result of
a referral because I had been socially active in various
Internet forums and like a poly count in particular.
and because I write and publish.
At a certain point, people start coming to you
because you are there consistently and presently enough,
and I cannot emphasize how important that aspect of it is.
You would be surprised once you really get
that inertia going.
And most importantly, never stop doing it once you start.
If you only show up when people,
like when you need something from other people,
it's easy to write you off.
Just be a part of the community
because you want to be a part of the community,
not solely because you're trying to extract value from it.
People can tell.
So, where to find clients?
If at all possible, never burn bridges
and stay in touch with former employers.
They are the greatest source of either continuing work
or references to other studio heads
or other studios that are looking for work.
And just every, anywhere, like two, three, six months,
just checking in with them,
seeing if they have any needs,
or if they have, or if they know of anybody that's looking,
that can be an extremely valuable source
of potential revenue, like in perpetuity.
And if they if they say no always always always ask for a recommendation or lead somewhere else
Every single no can be turned into an introduction. I've gotten incredible results from that and
Also along with rejection you'll get used to a lot of rejection and getting anything signed will take a minimum from the first email
the first introduction email
to actually getting signed on, officially starting work.
On average, 30 days is the fastest I've ever seen happen.
Normally it's about 45 days.
So you'll have to be patient, you'll have to be,
I get used to hearing no a hell of a lot,
and you have to get used to sending a lot of emails
and following up constantly.
Again, that's the less fun part of it,
but when it works, it feels terrific.
and alongside sending emails, create an email template saying,
hello, I'm offering my services, blah, blah, blah.
Try and customize it for each person you send it to,
because it's really obvious that it's a template.
Always include a portfolio link.
Don't ask too much of them.
But just try and get on a regular and respectful cycle
of how often you send that and who, and keep track of that.
Because if you have to custom write it every time,
you'll learn to hate it much more than is necessary.
So try and save time and find ways
to streamline and optimize that.
So, cutting the tether in five acts. Preparation, discipline, security, marketing and
tenacity. So preparation. Decide. Are you going to be mobile or are you going to work from
home? By mobile I mean if you're traveling everywhere, if you're working out of coffee
shops or co‑working spaces. That is a very different hardware set up than you would have if
you were working from home.
You also need to buy all of your own equipment and you need to have a broad software proficiency.
So if you're deciding whether to be mobile or work from home, mobile is good for producers,
project managers and directors and for people that do work that involves travel. And if you
live in cool cities with lots of cafes and co‑working spaces. If you can do most of your
work off of a laptop or a phone, and if you're traveling around a lot, you're not going to want
to carry around 150 pounds worth of everything all the time. So be realistic about the power
of your spine.
Work at home is good for artists or developers with serious hardware needs,
for people developing for VR, and for parents that can work with minimal interruption.
So the importance of buying your own equipment.
So you're responsible ultimately for all of your hardware.
It's expensive but it's worth it for many reasons.
So first off, if you are contracting with a company,
so if you're introducing yourself to a company
that is not a former employer,
if you have your own equipment,
that is less of an equipment cost on them.
That's an immediate, basically an immediate savings
as soon as you start talking to them.
But in addition to that, if that contract ends
either expectedly or unexpectedly,
you don't have to give that hardware back because you provided everything for
yourself.
Find suddenly finding you've grown relied upon this like a massively beef
tacular PC that whatever client gave you and realizing, oh,
I have to give this back. Now I need to,
now I'm back to my old crappy PC that I didn't invest that much money into.
It's not a very good feeling.
So it's really deeply worthwhile to make sure that you have a consistent set of
hardware that you can use for anything that is 100% yours and no one has any
claim on but you.
and really don't go cheap. But also don't think of this as the perfect time to massively
overspend on every weird little gadget you ever thought you would need. Because I've
done that. I have a lot of things that do and do not go into my go bag. And over the
course of time you realize I actually did not need that $750 whatever. Buy things you
need as you need them.
don't skimp necessarily, but just be realistic about what you
really think you will be using on a day-to-day basis,
otherwise you'll waste a lot of money. And if you're a mobile
dev on the go, you're going to be really destroying your back
carrying around extra crud that you don't need. And you can also
deduct all these things on your taxes, which is really, really
nice.
and having a dedicated work machine is ideal. I'm very particular about partitioning off
personal things, personal projects and just like my average day to day use PC with my work PC.
The less commingling the better because when I'm at work I'm at work, when I'm at home I'm at
home and mixing the two is the fast track to insanity.
So broad software proficiency. You use whatever tools your clients use and never, ever,
ever mix work and personal accounts. Always have your own unique accounts on Google, Slack,
Trello, Skype, Dropbox, Box, OneDrive. Any professional tool that you use, create your own
special dedicated work only account for that. Ideally with a work related email address, a
personal email address that you own that is only for business matters.
because I've been in many situations where my clients have
given me an email address and say Trello for example. I had
not used that before I had a particular client and then when
that contract ended my log in credentials were tied to that
email address so I lost that account even though I had many
other personal Trello boards running off of that. That caught
me off guard and I realized that was a really stupid thing to do.
This is an account that I will use for a lot of different
things and all that should be run through my domain, through
my email address, through my unique account.
So whenever conceivably possible, have your own account for that and maintain control of it.
It's the same principle as owning all of your own hardware.
You know what you have to use, you know what your capabilities are,
and you know what you have access to at any given point,
and no external force can take that away from you.
And that builds a sense of confidence and reliability.
And just not having to worry about, you know,
this contract ends, so I'm not going to have access to this tool anymore.
It's unnecessary mental overhead.
Own all your own stuff, all your own accounts.
and pay for and license all of your own software. A lot of the common tools they use are
remote worker, perforce, Gera, base camp, Trello, hand soft, SVN. Gain at least a
passive familiarity with these even if it's just signing up for a trial account. Just do
whatever you can to know enough about it to be able to jump in really quickly if you're
asked because
different company has a completely different set of tools that they use and the more
familiar you are with each of those, the better selling point that is. So if you're the
person that has at least a little bit of knowledge about absolutely everything, it's a lot
easier to work your way toward a yes, we'll sign you on, let's have you start working
remotely. Discipline. So ubiquity, work space, responsiveness and disaster readiness.
So ubiquity. Use the services your clients use. As I said
before, oh, you use this app? I'm already on it. Here's my
work account info. Here invite me into your GitHub repo.
Integrate with the team and the tools where they work and never
ever ask a client to sign up for anything. You have to adapt to
them in whatever they are using and it is up to you to be a
tools expert and to be extremely adaptable to whatever they
happen to throw at you. Because you will see everything and you
never want to be caught out of your depth.
Inevitably, you will be, but if you act confident about it and you've done at least a bit of
preparation working with these tools, it's much more likely you'll present yourself as
confident to the client, or prospective client, and you're that much closer to a yes and that
much closer to retaining them as a client.
So you have to establish a powerful, reliable remote presence to build their trust in you.
And the best possible place to do that is inside the tools where they already exist and
already work. Slack has been a boon in the past couple of years for me because it's IRC for
work. People chat in all the day. They have the random channels, but they have the
discipline-specific channels for our production, for AI, for programming, for level design.
for general discussion. That's where if organizations that use Slack well and
correctly
are really easy to like to work your way into because you can be physically
present,
well virtually present in all the chats that they have and in that particular
interface
you are no different from anybody that's working inside the four
walls of that studio.
That is the most even ground you're possible to have with them and
you need to take maximum advantage of that.
don't goof off all the time, but just make sure that you're there and present and that your
name, actually this is a little trick I learned recently. Make sure that your user name in
slack follows the same naming conventions as everybody else in slack for if they're tagging
their name. So if it's first initial last name or just first name, make your name that so they
can tag you just as easily as anybody else at the studio and you're that much easier to
contact and tag in the conversations.
and you're just a little bit more integrated with everything they do.
The less friction there is with dealing with you and talking to you externally,
the easier you are to work with, the more likely you are to retain them as a client.
Any tiny advantage you can find, you should take it.
So your work space, set aside a dedicated work space and do not
work and play in the same area. Ultimately that's purgatory.
You're never completely at work, you're never completely at play.
If you're trying to relax, you're going to feel obligated
to log in, like, sync down to the latest Perforce build or
catch up on e-mails or see what else you can do.
and you'll feel a little bit guilty for not catching up on this or that.
And conversely, if you're working in a place where you play,
you're going to be tempted to go on Reddit, to dink around on Twitter,
to play a game.
So you're never completely at work because you're always tempted to play.
And it's a very strange place to be,
so that's why I recommend having a completely physically distinct,
separate place in which you work and you only work.
When I started my company I was renting a 650 square foot apartment and the entire bedroom was my office
I had a bed in my living room
That gave me you can you can write off the amount of square footage on your taxes
For the space you work in with at your home, which was you know really convenient, but more than anything
I only worked in that space, and I worked primarily off a laptop when I'm at work
I'm on the laptop in the room where I work and I'm focused on that. When I'm off work, I unplug
the laptop, I go into the living room and that is where I play. Never co-mingle. So having that
physically different environment is really important. And that can also apply to a cafe, for
example, or a co-working space.
And having your physical surroundings encouraging you to work and focus on whatever you need to do is really important.
And if you start out doing that, you will avoid a lot of the issues that a lot of first-time remote workers and freelancers would have otherwise.
and remove attention distracting items from your work space. Like those little physics
balls where you pull it back and it clacks back and forth. Just any kind of weird tactile
little distracting thing like a Nintendo DS on your desk. Remove anything distracting and
have it be a dedicated focused place for work. Because you're already having to compensate so
much for your remote presence and force projecting yourself and practicing your
telepresence that anything that can detract from that should just go away.
and establish work time boundaries with family.
This is a big one I've seen a lot.
You can't work remotely with constant distraction
and mismanaging this weakens both work
and family relationships.
Like if your kids are always running into the room
and you're always playing with them
and you're getting distracted every five to 10 minutes,
how...
you're not going to be producing your most high-quality work, and you have to find a way to
partition out your time so you're respecting your client, but also being the parent that you
need to be. And this is unique for every person in the situation, but the work at home
parents, this is a very common thing that I hear. You need to learn to put up those
boundaries, because it's really, really convenient to go, like, oh, yeah, let's go play
out in the backyard. It's something worth paying attention to.
And also, if you say yes to every single contract
and opportunity that comes your way,
you'll quickly hate your life
because you have no time for your family,
you feel like you're always at work,
and you'll begin to resent the entire institution
of working remotely.
And ultimately, everyone I know has made this mistake,
they've overcommitted themselves,
and they've had to learn from that, sometimes painfully.
But at a certain point, after about maybe a year or two,
you know what you're capable of,
you know how to manage your time between work and family,
and you're not afraid to say no.
Because it's natural if you're sending out 100 emails a week trying to get somebody to say yes to you,
saying no back can be a little bit daunting because you know the very, very low yield of yeses to noes that you get.
But at a certain point for mental health and time management and family, you really have to.
Responsiveness, always respond quickly and follow up
when you say you will.
Being able to make a commitment and then keep it,
even if it's just saying, hey, I will call you at 2.15.
If you can do that consistently,
that is a massive confidence builder in your client.
and just being able to say that you're going to do something and then not following up on it,
they may not tell you that they were disappointed or they noticed.
That's entirely possible. They may not even notice at all.
But over a long enough period of time, your word is your bond. And if you're not able to
meet even minimally consistent things like that, it's going to be a much more difficult
relationship working remotely. And they're not going to be able to trust you to do what
you're going to say you do for large things if you can't do it for small things.
and always communicate in the channels they expect like in slack or perforce or whatever
systems your particular client uses. And show up early and dress well for remote meetings. I
learned a fairly embarrassing lesson when I was working ‑‑ so I worked with Epic Games for a
year running the Unreal Engine marketplace and I worked on site in North Carolina for one week a
month but the rest of the time was in Brooklyn.
and the very first meeting, video conference I had with Tim Sweeney from my home in Brooklyn,
I was unfortunately wearing a tan shirt, so it looked like I showed up shirtless for a meeting
with Tim Sweeney, the CEO of Epic. That was a very humbling and instructive moment, so be
aware of how things look on camera and try to dress it up a little bit. Oh, that still stings.
And remote work on an ongoing basis is earned.
When you're working on-site, attendance means
I see that seat is full.
When you're working off-site, attendance means
they consistently respond to us quickly.
In consistency and reliability,
I keep pushing that as much as possible.
The expectations are so different of on-site versus off-site and this is one of the better
examples I can think of it.
Just always be responding quickly, even if you're not giving them necessarily the answer
they want.
Just being able to say, hey, I hear you, I'm in the middle of something else, I'll respond
at this time.
That is better than not saying anything and then responding two hours later with what
they need.
Just acknowledgement rather than fulfillment or delivery is key.
disaster readiness. So realistic scenarios to plan for are power outages, internet self‑
service outages, hard drive crashes, stolen hard drive or laptop, hospital or family
emergency or nonspecific hardware failure.
find out, just plan out what you do in each of these cases. At
home do you have universal power supply? If you're working off of
a laptop and you work on a mobile basis, where is the
nearest internet cafe where you can get back online if your
connectivity drops? If you are working from home, your internet
goes down and there is a critical delivery,
do you have a cellular modem. Verizon has what's called the jet pack which is a pay as you go
cellular modem which is extremely convenient. It's 4G LTE speeds. It's fairly expensive on a
pay as you go basis but if you absolutely need internet access and you have to make a delivery,
that's a convenient thing to have in your back pocket. Literally, they're very small.
You can get one for anywhere from $125 to $175, no contract, and then just pay as you go as
you use the data. I have found that it's...
So my clients know that I have that. I've only had to use it in a handful of cases, but it's
always been kind of a nice bullet point to say, hey, here's my backup. Rarely used, but
it's here if you need it. So sometimes a sale is made not on ‑‑ you can sell somebody on
like a service or a feature like that that is never really used. That's what leads to a yes,
even if it's never actually exercised in practice. And that's just a nice thing to have
around.
for a hard drive crash, since you're responsible for your hardware, do you do regular
backups? Do you have web-based backups? Where are those files if things fail
catastrophically on your side? Again, in your studio's IT, this is the kind of thing that's
taken care of for you. This is now something that you're responsible for and have to plan for in
advance. If your hard drive or laptop are stolen, were they encrypted? Were they
passworded? Can you track them remotely? Can you disable them?
these are things you have to plan for. If there's a hospital or family emergency, it might
help to have an e-mail template set up in advance, like in a draft folder to your bosses or
whoever would need to know if you're out. So as you're on your way to the hospital or
something, you can pull out your phone, hit send on that draft and then have that be
essentially taken care of instead of people wondering where you are. Ultimately they'll be
understanding, but if emergencies like that happen, it's a convenient thing to have.
to have in place so they can know and plan for it. So security. I did another talk on this
called tools and tech of the globe trotting freelancer. I go into a lot of detail on this
and I will not do that today. But ultimately encrypt your hard drives like in windows use
bit locker for Mac, use file vault for USB drives, use Vera crypt, it's a fork of true crypt.
essentially creates encrypted passworded container so if you
lose a thumb drive or someone steals it from you, they'll see
just a big lump of file they cannot open without the
password. Never leave any client data up to chance. Treat it as
though it's more valuable than your own.
use a password manager. I like last pass, one pass and key pass
are also very good. If you're using the internet today and
you're not using a password manager with unique passwords
for every website, you are using the internet wrong. And just
very bluntly, you're using it wrong. And if you have your
logins to your various client sites, you're not using unique
passwords with them and you're not taking care of all that
inside a password manager, you're putting your client's
data at risk and you're being irresponsible.
If for nothing else, use a password manager for your
client's data. It's very little extra effort to do it for
yourself. But think of your clients. Two-factor
authentication on everything. It's the same basis. So
essentially two-factor authentication is a way, let's
say you're logging into Google. It wants you to prove you are
who you say you are. And the easiest way to prove that is to
send a message to your phone.
So we'll do it either via SMS or by constantly rotating code.
Say, OK, enter these six digits to prove that you are you and
you're in physical possession of your phone before granting
access to your account.
Dozens and dozens of websites, especially business focused
tools, offer two-factor authentication.
And you should enable that for every single one of them,
especially for your client.
any log in that you can find on 2TWOfactoroff.org. It's a
comprehensive list of every service that offers two factor
authentication. Sign up for every single one, especially your
client sites. Because, frankly,
My clients have never pressed me particularly hard on security, but it's one of the things
that I push forward showing I care about your data, I care about your project, and I take
great, I take extreme measures to make sure that your data is protected no matter what
happens, whether it's a data breach, whether it's a big password dump, whether my hardware
is physically stolen, your data is safe and these are the precautions that I take. Again,
It's never really been something that a particular client
has exercised, but it's a part of my sales pitch
and it's appealing and generally it's just good
computer hygiene and you should do it.
and also use a virtual private network any time you connect to a Wi‑Fi hotspot that you do not
own. So any non‑HTTPS connection on a Wi‑Fi hotspot like here at GDC 17, that's visible in
plain text. You can collect passwords, you can collect user names, you can collect every site
the person has visited.
on my phone I'm able to map out all the different devices that are connected to this WiFi
hotspot for GDC and there are over 2500 of them and dozens of your computers have your
full names on them or your user names. I was able to very easily find people online who
are at GDC based on what they named their mobile devices or laptops.
and it would be trivial to snoop on their traffic.
Using a virtual private network
that encrypts all of your traffic
when you're connected to a public Wi-Fi hotspot
and that also protects you and protects your client
and anytime your connection is not encrypted with HTTPS
and you're not connected to a Wi-Fi hotspot
that you own or trust,
you're putting all of that at risk.
I recommend Air VPN.
private Internet access or Weetopia for VPN. It's anywhere from $2.99 to $4.99 a month.
It's very cheap, very easy, works on mobile devices and again this is just decent data
hygiene. So, marketing. You need a professional website, a LinkedIn, and you need to be
networking and you need to be constantly engaged in publicity for yourself.
So your professional website, if at all possible use your real
name or a new company name. It should be short, easy to
remember, professional and able to be spoken aloud in a way
that people are able to easily understand. Get the dot com or
the dot net. Avoid weird top level domains like dot biz, dot
radio, dot triple X unless you're a very different kind of
contractor.
Summarize your services using 3 to 5 bullet points. Ask friends for input. Wordpress is
notoriously insecure but if you're just having a very simple public facing website, they're
very simple, easy to use, easy to set up, free professional looking themes to present
yourself professionally. And if you're providing professional services, you absolutely should
have at least a website with your name on it that can prove you are who you say you
are.
I'll also list prominent projects and employers, but only
list roles where you did what you were selling. So LinkedIn,
part one. Being on LinkedIn is not optional. It's a top
business networking site in the world. It's the first place
people with money will look you up. And if you don't have a
LinkedIn presence, you look risky and unprofessional.
Generally speaking, it's a good idea to be in the first place
people with money to give to you will look to find out if you
are qualified to give money to.
And that is essentially the beginning and the end
of the argument for LinkedIn.
Like, be there, be professional,
maintain it every few months.
It takes very little effort,
but it's absolutely important that you're on there.
and polish up your presence.
Update your roles and descriptions, spell check,
use the proper tense, present tense, past tense,
give and request recommendations.
And this is an important one that I've not really seen
other people touch on before.
Add projects and link to your coworkers on those projects.
So let's say a game is shipped or there's a layoff.
If you add those projects on LinkedIn and add your coworkers on LinkedIn,
you're much easier to discover for potential work or being hired as a team or for
freelancing if you're associated with that. So if you're connected to, you know,
five coworkers away, it's like, Oh, this coworker is an engineer. Uh,
who else are you working that with? Oh,
I'm actually looking for artists and they're able to find you through that path
of discovery because you're associated with that project or with that event.
It makes it a lot easier for good things to come to you.
And if you were not already on LinkedIn and you weren't connected to their
projects, they would never have found you otherwise.
This is a very simple way to establish a passive presence.
Part two, connect to your coworkers. Not during a layoff.
That's when everybody realizes oh, crap, I haven't updated
LinkedIn since I got this job. That's actually a really easy
way to spot layoffs. When everybody from one company is
connecting to each other all at once and flooding your LinkedIn
feed with it.
I've discovered layoffs that way. Add them before you need it. As you meet someone and
work them out, at work or for a client, add them whenever, like at the earliest possible
point. Just before it seems like you're just trying to get something out of them.
Also, connect to recruiters because this expands your network reach.
It's easier for people to find you through recruiters who are naturally going to be connected
to everybody on LinkedIn.
This also passively increases your discoverability.
Join relevant LinkedIn user groups.
You can use a group affiliation as one of the reasons to connect to someone on LinkedIn
when you send them a connection request.
The more of those you have in common, the easier it is for you to reach people that
may otherwise be unreachable.
Get in the habit of cold emailing and introducing yourself.
Do not be shy, rip off the band aid.
You must be constantly communicating and networking.
Don't stop doing it just because you secured a client
in the near term.
Always, always, always be networking,
be reaching out and be practicing.
And just follow general industry goings on with LinkedIn.
Networking, attend trade shows constantly.
GDC is the highest value in my experience, wink.
Also, XDS, E3, gamescom, packs, steam dev days, look up and join local game dev user
groups, attend meetups, game jams, workshops, game nights, beer nights, drink ups, job fairs,
anywhere there are developers in your area. If you're working remotely,
can get really, really lonely just for one thing. But being
able to go out and hang out with other developers is not just for
networking and potentially finding work locally. It's just
good to be around other devs to remember what it's like and be
able to share war stories and be able to feel part of the
community. It's important for sanity. And always have business
cards ready. I recommend Zazzle and Moo. They have great
quality cards, very good designs.
I should put a referral code up there. Man, opportunity missed. So publicity. Publish
articles in your area of focus. Publish on your site and cross publish to LinkedIn.
LinkedIn is desperate to be a publishing platform and they promote the hell out of
anybody that will publish something on their site. They'll promote that to the top of
your feed to anybody you're connected to, which is yet another good reason to connect
to people before you need them. Also, apply to speak at industry events. And local IGDA
chapters are a great place to start.
Publish original content frequently on your blog or on
Gamasutra or LinkedIn. Do Reddit AMA, do Twitter Q&A's, be part
of Screenshot Saturday if you're working on cool stuff. Twitter
is an amazing way to reach out to people. Request guest spots
on industry podcasts, get involved in that community. The
more broadly present you are in these communities, the easier it
is to find you. The more likely it is you'll be able to find
paying work.
Tenacity, constant biz dev, taxes and expenses and cabin fever. This is the fun part. So
constant biz dev, at least 40 to 50 percent of your time will be doing biz dev. That's just
the sad truth of it. And the sooner you can get used to that and automate it or try to make it
fun, the better. But that's just going to be a part of your life from now on. Always be
networking, always be selling, but don't be a dweeb about it. Just be like, hi, it's nice to
meet you. My name is such and such. Do you have a job for me?
Don't be that person.
Be the person that's cool, that attends events,
that people like hanging out with,
and don't try and find a way to bring
the conversation around to yourself.
Be that presence and don't push for a result.
Ultimately good things will come to you,
but also don't be too shy.
It's a balance, but it's worth trying to find.
always remember, you work to secure next month's income, not
this month's. So if you're getting paid this month, that's
fantastic. Where's next month's coming from? Always be doing
business, always be pushing, always be trying. And when
you're employed, all this is invisible to you. Respect your
company's founders, admin, finance, legal and IT.
So you're in customer service now.
Retaining clients means ongoing customer service.
And understand what doing a good job means
on a per-client basis.
They may define it differently.
Be explicit because only their opinion matters.
You may think you're knocking it absolutely out of the park
but their expectations are completely different.
and they may perceive you as being underperforming.
That's why you have to go out of your way
to reach out above and beyond what you would do
if you were working on site.
Find out if you actually are meeting their expectations
and find out if they actually are
communicating those back to you.
It is your responsibility to reach out and pull
and get that information.
and how to retain clients. Be responsive, aware, present and
always check in. Always be where they look first. Keep in touch
with old clients. Manage your time wisely. Don't get greedy.
Like your shiny new gig is tempting but serve your existing
client well. Just be realistic about what you're realistically
able to accomplish and don't take on too much too soon.
People find this out over time. Everybody makes the mistake.
Taxes and expenses, hooray, best slide.
Work with an accountant from day one.
Do everything they say.
Remember, taxes are no longer withheld.
You need to be saving at least half of whatever you bring in.
Start a tax savings account for paying taxes
and immediately deposit half of every check in that
and do everything your tax professional says from day one.
This will lead to pain.
Be smart, get a tax pro, pay them to do the thing
that you will undoubtedly hate doing.
Also, be frugal and focus on savings.
Plan for lean times, budget for disasters.
Target six months of savings in the bank
in case anything goes wrong.
Not many people I know actually have that
and have all that saved up
when they're starting out working remotely,
but this is something worth moving toward
and that is something to aspire toward.
And finally cabin fever. A dedicated work space as I
mentioned before helps you focus. Get plenty of exercise
in sunlight. If all you do is stay inside all the time,
eventually it will turn into a pale sickly little thing that is
practically transparent. I had a two or three month stretch where
I realized I was starting to resemble like a mole rat that
doesn't see the sun. My eyes were, yeah.
It's an unpleasant place to be and I have an extraordinarily patient wife that would sponge me off.
So, create healthy... Oh man, I said that.
Create healthy daily rituals. Do yoga, walk your dog, cook for yourself, take language lessons, develop a new hobby.
Do something that is not your job to expand yourself, expand your horizons
and to be able to mentally switch focus to something completely different.
it's really important to maintain a well-rounded,
well-balanced life, because otherwise,
work can become your life,
and you have to force yourself away from it
to be able to remember to be a human again,
to have a third dimension to you,
instead of just that sweaty, pale thing
that's at the computer all the time.
and maintain a strict separation of work and life.
If you let it, it can absolutely consume you
all hours of the day and night.
You really need to clamp down on that
and just be realistic about, you know,
what do you value most in your life?
Like yourself, your health, your family,
your relationships, your career.
Like there's, you know, that famous example.
Has anyone on their deathbed ever said,
I wish I spent more time at work?
just realistically, just be good to yourself,
be honest with what you really want
and maintain that separation of work and life
because it really can consume you if you're not careful.
And that's all, thank you very much for listening.
Does anyone have any questions?