I'm Vesa Paakkonen.
I work as a senior tools programmer at Remedy.
Today I'm going to talk about how we improved the overall
design of our internal tools framework during
the past few years.
So a few words about Remedy first.
You might know us from games such as Max Payne, Alan Wake,
and Quantum Break.
We're based in Espoo, Finland, and we currently have about
150 employees.
We're working on two games, P7, which is our own IP, and
on our first FPS, the single player
campaign for Crossfire 2.
So it's always important to know the reasons behind decisions
leading up to a design.
So I'm going to start with a bit of background
of the problems we faced.
After that, I'm going to dive into what I actually
mean by workflow-driven design and how
we build our current tools framework around that concept.
So let's start by looking at what
we had when the production of Quantum Break started.
Here's our world editor, or WET, as we call it,
in all of its MFC glory.
It is a monolithic application originally built for Alan Wake,
and it has been our most important tool ever since.
But the tool has become quite outdated, not only due
to its UI, but also due to the technical depth, which has
caused several big problems.
One of the biggest problems is probably something
that is familiar to most of you, changing the simple things
regarding opening a level, as well as exporting it,
making the iteration speed unbearable.
Due to the monolithic design, the code
had become so tangled that it was virtually impossible
to determine what kind of effects even seemingly
small changes would have.
It heavily uses singletons, so modifying the state in one
panel could cause undecided side effects in all of them,
possibly causing a lot of regression.
And because all the code was so tightly coupled,
it meant that even the most basic test would
have required initializing the whole application, which
makes any kind of test difficult to write and slow to run.
So we did not want to continue using MFC, just imagine that.
So we decided we're going to build the new tools with
something more modern, and ultimately
ended up with WPF.
As a lesson learned from WET, we wanted the new tools to be
completely plugin-based to prevent the new code from
becoming a similar monolithic mess.
And because we were building tools from scratch, we wanted
to reuse existing functionality as much as
possible by hooking the new tools, both
for the engine and WET.
So this is the high level architectures
we came up with for our .NET tools and the plugin system.
There are shared C Sharp libraries
that can be used in different applications.
There are different plugins providing
different panels and background services.
And finally, there is a simple bootstrapper executable
that loads plugins for a given workflow based
on a configuration file.
For example, for machine editing workflow,
we loaded asset browser, property editor,
and live editing functionality.
For timelines, we also needed curve editor and timeline
editor.
And for Screenplaylay workflow, we
had completely different plugins.
So let's have a look at the probably simplest workflow
we had during quantum break, editing mesh properties.
Here we have the asset browser and a property editor
to edit the current selection.
You can see that the contents of the panel
change when the user selects an asset.
And if the user wants to view multiple meshes simultaneously,
he can open another property editor panel, which by default
follow the same selection.
So the user must use the lock feature
to lock one of the panels while having the other panel
to continue the follow selection.
Simple stuff.
And for comparison, here is a quick look
of what the timeline editing looked
like during quantum break.
It required a few more panels.
And the thing to note here is that the asset browser panel is
actually the only one that's common for the mesh
editing workflow.
The property panels are completely
specific to timelines as well as the hierarchy and the timeline
panel.
I'll get back to that soon.
So all in all, the approach to use .NET tools
was a success for Quantum.
The development speed improved, and thus we
could ship better tools with better UX.
It also made it easier to make them look significantly better.
And the plugin framework allowed easy unit testing
of individual systems.
So naturally, we wanted to continue
building new functionality on top of our WPF tools,
and ultimately enable us to replace WED.
But there was major design flaw with this plug-in-based loosely
coupled design due to how the panels communicated.
When the selection changed in the asset browser panel,
it sent a message through a multicast system
called a mediator to avoid tight coupling between the panels.
The mediator forwarded the message to any panels
that were listening to a given message,
and those panels were responsible for determining
how to handle it.
In the case of the property editor,
it was responsible for deciding if it
should change the selection, keep it, or clear it.
And you could have any number of panels in different states
handling the same messages.
So let's have a look at a concrete example of the problem
that occurred when we added new panels for mesh editing
workflow to allow users to edit physics definitions.
First of all, you can see that it's
very cumbersome to open new panels individually
if they don't happen to be open yet.
And when the user opens the panels,
they are empty because they haven't received any selection
changed messages.
And now user has to manually reselect the mesh
to get some content to the new panels.
And now the user can finally select the node in the FBX.
So let's take this even a bit further.
Now the user wants to edit the materials as well.
Let's see how that goes.
So there's yet another panel.
Let's drag it there.
We change the color.
And now we want to check out the texture as well.
Yay, we got another panel.
And as last step, now the user wants
to check out some other material using the asset browser.
So he searches for a specific material.
Selects it, and boom, the mesh selection is gone
because he forgot to use the lock.
So just looking at fumbling with the panels.
Just looking at the video is painful enough,
so you can probably imagine our users going something
like that.
So that's just the tip of the iceberg.
There are plenty of other problems as well.
The loosely coupled design and the subsequently growing
number of panels caused a mental load that was simply
too big to manage.
It was simply too easy to make mistakes.
You could argue that the design also gave the users quite a
lot of flexibility in terms of how they
set up their workflows.
But that would essentially mean that you need a team of
super users and not mere mortals.
It was also very difficult to read information on the screen
when the number of panels increased.
Here you can see that it's not immediately obvious that
there are three separate assets here.
Mesh, material, and a texture.
Also in this version, some panels did have locks and
source control statuses, while the others did not.
It didn't feel right that we would
duplicate the same information for all the panels
involving the same mesh.
If we introduced locks to all of them,
the users could really suit themselves in the foot
by mixing locked states on different panels representing
different parts of the same asset.
All the panels had business logic inside them
because they had to work individually
due to the loosely coupled design.
Here are three examples of panels that resemble each other
but is having different business logic,
causing us having to maintain three different versions.
The property editor followed asset selection
and handled writing to disk, as well as source control
operations.
Physics definition editor followed the selection
of an FBX hierarchy and also handled saving and source
control operations.
And then there were quite a few editors
that simply followed some other selection,
like timeline events or nodes in a node graph.
This got several general problems.
One of the first, for example, was
that if there were two panels editing the same data
with only one of them writing data to the disk,
closing the one writing the data would essentially
mean that your data never got saved,
and user could just keep on editing
and never realize that his changes are not there.
We had around 10 different variations of property
editor at one point, and it was very confusing to the users
because they didn't behave similar to each other.
This also meant that the development cost got higher
after adding new variations, because in the worst case
scenario, some changes had to be made in each of them, and
each of them had to be tested.
It also virtually prevented any reuse of the business
logic, because it was tied to the UI.
And adding more panels just added more complexity.
Here's an example of us adding a behavior tree editor.
If we just start with one panel for editing the graph
and one for editing and selection,
everything works relatively fine.
But one of the first requirements
we got from the users was that they
want to be able to edit multiple graphs simultaneously.
So how would we make that work technically?
In case of two graphs, should the node property panel
listen to both of them?
What about if we have two node properties?
Should the user's manually hook them up with a specific graph?
And the situation would get even worse
if the users would want to have some completely different
asset types open simultaneously as the number of panels
would just keep on increasing.
So something had to be done.
The problems and successes during quantum
gave us the basis for creating design goals
for reworking the architecture.
Most importantly, we need a better structure
for the application, so we're not solving the same problems
in multiple similar use cases.
Context sensitivity.
We wanted our users to be able to use the tools right away,
just like an asset, and they'll say relevant things.
This was also a technical goal.
It should be easy to determine in the code
what the current state is, what has been changed, and so on.
We wanted to keep the flexibility of the plugin
system so we could easily modify the set of the panels
and services that we show the users.
We're easily able to unit test them.
And in addition, we wanted to be able to have game-specific
plugins.
And finally, we should be able to reuse the UI controllers as
much as possible to provide consistent look and feel.
So.
It was very clear that the main observation was that the
biggest mistake was writing the business logic inside the
panels that apply rules to specific workflows.
We clearly needed something to glue together different parts
of the workflow.
And this is from where the term workflow-driven design
comes from.
The application should model the workflows in some way,
and that should be responsible for setting up
all the relevant things for the users
by configuring the panels, enabling the background
services, and exposing the workflow-specific commands.
By reusing the same panels in multiple workflows
by injecting any custom behavior to them,
we can significantly improve the code reusability as well
as the user experience.
And most importantly, this design
allows the domain experts, like AI or animation programmers,
with intimate knowledge of the specific workflows
to concentrate on modeling the behavior of the workflow.
This improves things significantly
as the tools team can concentrate
on building the framework and the UI controls,
while the domain experts who work closely with the users
write the actual business logic.
It also means that experts rarely have to dive into any WPF details,
as those are handled in the panels and controls provided by the framework,
lowering the learning curve to build new tools.
So, with these points in mind, we started concepting the UI
to get a clearer picture of how we could design the architecture of the new system.
Let's look at a video of a recent build of our tools,
which is quite close to the original UI design we had.
Here you can see three different node editors built by AI,
rendering, and animation teams.
You can see that the tools are now context aware.
Selecting an asset opens a new tab with relevant panels
inside them.
And you can see that the source control status
is now shown clearly in the top right corner.
Now we're using the same property editor everywhere.
Let's go back to the mesh example one more time.
Now you get all the relevant panels open when the mesh is opened.
You can open a material.
You can easily browse through the different materials.
And if you go to the texture, you can browse through those as well.
So let's move to the high level technical design.
From the previous video, we can easily
identify the following concepts.
The panels, the document hosting the panels,
and the data that is being read and written.
A naive implementation would look something like this.
Panels are assigned to some document,
and then the document handles reading and writing the data.
However, there are two major problems.
Now, because the panels need to know about.
The specific documents they are going to be used in,
we would not be able to reuse them
on other workflows which is against our design goals.
Also, we're mixing low-level concepts
like reading and writing data with the document, which
is clearly a UI concept, making it difficult for us
to use that code in other systems that
might not even have a UI.
The solution for the first problem is relatively simple.
We use dependency inversion to abstract out the document
with an interface to prevent coupling
with a specific implementation.
As for the second problem, we need
to create a new concept to abstract out
the details about the data.
We decided to call that a context.
It handles all the details about the data,
like where it's coming from, how it is saved,
as well as tracking any changes.
To summarize the concepts on a very high level, the document
is the UI layer describing how things are edited.
It works as a clue between the panels, commands, and the data.
The context, on the other hand, handles all the details
of what is being edited.
It abstracts out the details from the UI, allowing us to
reuse UI components with all kinds of different data.
Let's look at the two main cases, how all of this is put
together.
The simpler one is to configure panel
to always show the same piece of data in the same panel.
For example, in the case of meshes,
both the mesh properties and mesh viewer
are configured to always show the same data
of the same asset.
Properties panel always shows the full contents
of a metadata file, while the viewer panel shows
the mesh itself.
The FBX is read-only, while the metadata is editable.
Let's look at how the panel is configured to behave this way.
First, we need to configure the context to load the data.
We use some string ID to identify the piece of content,
and then we pass in a method that loads it.
Loading happens lazily, so if there's
no panel requesting that data, it's never read from the disk.
And now that the context knows how to read the file,
we can configure the document to host the property editor panel.
We use the same ID that we used to register content
to let the panel know which piece of data it should request
and show when it's opened.
The second case is a bit more involved.
Now the document will contain a panel
that changes its content based on user interaction.
Let's have yet another look at the mesh editing
and especially the physics definition properties panel.
When the user changes the selection inside the document
using either the FBX Heuric panel or MeshView panel,
the physics definition panel reacts to it.
Also note that the selection is synchronized
between all three panels.
So we start again with the context, knowing how to load
the data.
This is configured exactly the same way as in the previous
example.
But now there is a small problem.
We need to have an internal selection.
We cannot add a property to the mesh document, because
that would cause a tight coupling between the panels
and the mesh document implementation.
It would also make it more cumbersome to extend if the
number of internal selections would increase.
So the solution in this case was to introduce a concept
of components, which is very similar to components
in an entity component system.
We register a component responsible for requesting
the data and maintaining the selection.
Now, instead of depending on a specific document,
the panels can depend on a generic selection provider
component.
Now, the only thing we need to do
is to hook up the panels again.
Because the selection provider is such a commonly used
component, we made it simple to use.
We can just tell a panel to follow a selection with a
string ID, and it automatically starts to listen
to the selection provider.
And we tell the FBX hierarchy to load the FBX data and use
the given selection provider to set the selection.
The last problem we had to solve was tracking down the
changes from multiple sources, like from several different
files or from database.
It ended up being really simple, because with the
context, we already have a single point of entry.
to all the data, and we can easily
track all the changes without having
to know any details about the data itself
by using the observer pattern.
By aggregating a single stream of all the changes happening
in each different piece of content that
have been registered to it, we can easily hook up
not only panels that track the changes,
but additional systems as well.
For example, we can catch each change
to undo stack or live edit system
just by listening to that single stream.
So let's review the concepts once more.
The document is used to configure
the UI part of the workflow, while the context
is used to read, write, and track
the data used in the workflow.
So let's have a look at the final example, our screenplay
workflow that we created quite recently
and which really starts to show the benefits of this design.
Here we have the screenplay hierarchy and the screenplay
editor.
The really cool thing here is that the data is actually
stored in the database instead of on disk.
And the document context system abstracts it out
so we can reuse the panels, like the property panels,
as well as other systems like undo, redo.
Here the user wants to use the dialog lines on a cinematic.
So he uses an asset browser to open a timeline on disk.
And then he just tracks the dialog unit on it.
And that automatically creates tracks for each character
and new events for each dialogue line.
The user also wants to make some modifications
to the screenplay.
And this causes the corresponding event
in the timeline editor to be highlighted
because the duration changed.
User can now export the latest screenplay data
and then retime the event to match the source dialogue.
And I think this really validates this design
because there are two different workflows,
screenplay writing and building cinematics,
working almost seamlessly together
and within the same UI with the same controls,
even though the data is stored
and handled completely differently.
So, here are the biggest benefits we've seen so far.
Our productivity significantly increased.
It allowed other teams to work on their specific workflows
and thus we've managed to add more new workflows
to our .NET tools during the past two years
than we did during Quantum Break.
Context sensitive significantly reduced the fumbling
with the panels.
Now that the panels are grouped inside the documents,
the state is clear.
And reusing the same panels allows
to have better and more consistent UX.
As for the takeaway, start thinking the whole,
have a high level goal for your workflow, high level design,
before diving into details and solving problems one by one.
Clearly separate different layers of the application so
you can reuse and test the code.
And last, and most importantly, promote
reusability and empower other teams.
I strongly believe that as a tools programmer, the first
and foremost responsibility should be to empower other
people, may that be either end users or other programmers.
Thank you.
So, questions?
Thank you for your talk, really interesting stuff.
I was wondering how long did you, did your team work on the refactoring or just cutting
out the MFC and just switching and how did you sell it to the management?
We are still using the MFC application, but this is just
replacing the framework of the .NET tools, the loosely
coupled one.
And it took about half a year, about two people working full
time, to get all the bits and pieces of the
framework up and running.
And basically, we just solved it by saying that we're
spending now half a year, and then we're going to save like
three years later on.
Hi, great talk.
You mentioned the selection provider.
I was curious, can you elaborate more
on how things connect to these sorts of providers,
like how they know which provider they want to listen
to or how they publish to one?
So like I said, it's not really just the selection provider.
It's kind of this.
component system, that you can have any kind of component
there.
But in the case of SelectionProvider,
we just made it work with the same string ID.
So you give a panel the string ID,
and then you say that it should follow a selection.
And it just looks up a SelectionProvider component
from the document using that string ID
and automatically uses that.
Thank you.
I guess nothing else. Thank you.