Good morning. How's everybody doing?
Woo!
Okay, it's great that you're here in the very first session of the day.
Welcome, everybody.
Okay.
Oh, I'm Matthew Weiss, and this is Clara Fernandez-Vara,
and we're here to present the Narrative Innovation Showcase.
So we are game writers, game designers.
We've been doing this for a long time now.
And basically, we wanted to talk about experimentation in
narrative, because when we talk about game
experimentation, people think about mechanics.
And at times, the storytelling, the narrative is set aside.
And we wanted to actually focus on the kind of work
that people are already doing.
We want to explore new forms of storytelling in games
that also happen alongside design.
There are people who are already doing it, and we want to highlight this kind of work.
All the games that our creators are going to talk about today come from a variety of
backgrounds, from academic experiments to experimental narratives to commercial games.
So we have a nice range that we wanted to showcase and show that this is already taking place.
So one of the reasons we wanted to do this is because game
narrative has been around for a really long time.
It's been around since the beginning of games.
And there's talks all the time at GDC and other events where
people are always trying to say, we learned this thing,
we just discovered this new thing.
And it's true, new innovations happen all the time.
But we also really need to build a strong understanding
of where we've been so we can understand where we're going.
So we really want to use this as the beginning of
You know, the building of a real shared knowledge on this
topic. So the format is going to be we have selected five
speakers for you. They're going to give five talks, ten minutes
each, focusing on challenges in narrative design and the focus
is going to be on process. How they tackle that challenge. And
there's not going to be Q&A. We're going to go to the wrap-up
room so that we have plenty of time to cover the topics that we
want to cover.
And our first speaker is Samantha Gorman talking about
Prime.
Hello, everyone.
Hello, so I'm Samantha.
I'm one half of the collaborative duo, Tender Claws.
We've been working together for 10 years.
And we write design, code, film, basically do a lot of
different hats on our projects.
All our projects argue that the way a story is told and
interacted with is actually part of the story itself.
So today I'm going to be talking about Pry. Pry is part book, part film, and part game. It was a finalist for IGF, Excellence in Narrative, last year. And Apple nominated it as one of the top 25 apps of 2015.
And I'm going to be talking about Pry.
Sometimes she looks back at me.
Then nothing.
A wet red pain, a spade slicing like a knife, a hand reaching.
So Pry is a character study. It's an internal character study that's set during a specific time, mainly the first skull four.
The player is a guest inside James' mind and through the use of the iconic pinch gesture, Pry's apart his memories and thoughts.
So, coming from an art background, we're like, okay, as directors, video is more consumed
on a timeline by directors' authors, where text is often consumed on the reader's pace.
So how do we integrate the passive and active and text and video in a meaningful and compelling
way?
How can we merge text elements and gameplay that feels integrated, that keeps player agency
and moves away from the cut scene or DVD extra?
And what we saw, we're familiar with the background of full
motion video for games.
But this project was actually inspired by the e-book.
Originally, e-books were like future of the book.
But then they were adapting print conventions, such as the
page turn.
And a lot of media was very segmented
rather than integrated.
And we really pay attention to the medium of the platform we're working with.
So tablets are excellent devices for video consumption.
However, a lot of early projects were simple branching narratives,
where the branches weren't necessarily weighted in a satisfying way.
They didn't go to a conclusion that felt satisfying for me as a reader.
And Pry's story was actually going against branching
because it was really a process of someone coming to terms with their memories
and the idea of the reader drilling deeper instead of branching outward.
So how do we integrate text and video?
We usually do a two-pronged approach.
First, we think about the story.
OK, what does the story suggest?
It's a character that's losing its sight.
It's forcing open.
It's coming to terms with something.
There's an exchange of control.
Then we think about the medium, the iPad.
What are the basic gestures, the vocabulary, the ways of
interacting that can be used for storytelling?
So combining those, as well as bringing different knowledge from different disciplines like theater, film, and installation,
we came up with different models to integrate text and video in ways that we felt were more meaningful.
One of the first ideas, we kind of had this idea of the sympathetic gesture,
where the player is a privileged guest inside the mind, and the player's actions and character's thinking are intertwined.
So the character gets a Braille Bible inherited from his mother.
If the reader, our player...
She's got indeed twins in her womb.
moves their finger smoothly over the text, the associations that the character has with
their family is more static. It comes up. If the reader moves their finger slower, then
they get separate associations with their family during the war. In this way, we're
able to remix the character's memories of his family according to this text that's relevant
to the story.
At a certain point in the climax of the narrative, he actually gets a...
He's trying to tell himself a story of what happened in the past, but he's an unreliable narrator.
At any point, the reader can pinch open different lines and they'll get information.
He'll go back on what he said or give alternative versions.
If it gets to a point where he can't conceptualize the text anymore,
he'll get fragmented thoughts or a kind of frantic pace of thoughts.
Or, images of video will open up that are associative with the text he's encountered.
There's about 45 minutes of video in this chapter alone.
And finally, we wanted something that unlocked throughout as the reader went through the project.
And here, there's an album that James encounters that's destroyed during the war.
It holds the memories of his mother and one of his friends, Jesse, in the pages.
But what remains are only obsessive thoughts of what the objects once were on the page.
If the reader scrolls fast, the objects become whole again.
Otherwise, on the large level, it's a description of literally what was on the page,
or on the smaller level, memories or associations with the objects.
So these are some ways we tried to combine text and video and have a system where we had very authored, controlled aspects where I'm controlling what the lines say, I'm controlling the order, but at any point the player can dig in and get more information. It's very exploratory.
So these are the principles that guided us through Pry, and I can actually highlight it in some of these mechanics.
One of the central mechanics of the story is this eye-open chapter, where the violence
of the pinch gesture forces the eyes open, but at any point in the timeline, the player
can do this.
Closing the eyes will return to a default space where the thoughts update on what was
just seen.
But however, there is a third layer to this where there's three spaces where an inverse pinch will crunch down
and it'll get more subconscious memories and thoughts.
And these three spaces work together.
However, we as authors have used a timeline to plan out.
Everything that happens according to time code.
Where we can take the time code and without the player
necessarily realizing it, manipulate it to make sure
they see certain story beats while leaving other moments
exploratory.
For instance, if we want them to see something that happens
further on and they close the eyes, we can make sure that the
external world video pauses but the sound continues so they
feel like they're in a continuous world.
So that when they open the eyes next, immediately that
story beat hits.
There's a very complicated system in how we actually author the underlying structure
to make sure that we're creating a cohesive narrative while still leaving open the exploratory
mechanic.
One of the things we're also interested in is there's times when we invert the idea of
text at a player's pace and video at an author's pace.
What happens to text when it becomes video?
What is watching and what is reading?
So the last slide is changing game narrative is not necessarily
the goal here.
It's the evolution of game narrative is not one
conclusion, but a rich variety of approaches.
Instead, we argue for deeper attention to how interactions
and story itself resonate.
That story doesn't exist in a vacuum.
It originates from player and author effect and a
combination of passive and active viewing.
Thank you.
Our next speaker is Aaron Reid talking about Icebound.
All right.
Hello everybody.
So, yeah, yeah, I'm Aaron A. Reid.
I'm a Ph.D. student at the University of California Santa Cruz and also an independent designer,
but I am graduating soon, so this second part becomes more important.
So I've been making indie story games for more than 10 years
now. You might recognize one or two of these things. I've
always been trying to push at the boundaries of what
interactive stories can do. I'm going to talk about my latest
game, the icebound concordance. So we had this on the festival
circuit last year. It was here IGF and we actually won indicated
story award last year which was a huge honor. And I wanted to
say that this is really a true collaboration made equally by
myself and Jacob Garby who I think is not here today but is
going to be around GDC. So if you see him, say hi.
So the narrative premise we set out to explore with this game
was this. What if exploring an interactive story could feel
like sculpting with clay? Because the choice structures
we're used to in game stories tend to fall into one of two
imperfect categories.
So branching paths can feel like being lost in a maze. You
can't see the structure or where you're positioned in it. And
that makes choices feel stressful because you can't see
the consequences of them. What decisions will lead to the best
story? You usually don't know. And you can't usually try again
without starting over from the beginning.
Mazes are also static. You'll never do something that surprises the designer of the maze. Mazes
are also hard to build for the designer because you might waste your time building paths no one
ever sees. But in practice this usually isn't a problem because most mazes are fake in games as
we all know. There's usually only one real path through the story. And collapsing branches is
fine. I do this all the time in my work. So do all of us. But it's a trick. And so with this
project we really wanted to think about alternatives to that.
So another technique we often see in interactive stories is
sort of like customizing options in your new car. So
you're offering decisions to the player that might have a
cosmetic effect or might get aggregated into stats that the
game refers to later on.
But these kind of decisions don't usually change the shape
of the overall experience very much. So this works too. And
again, I do this all the time in my games. But sometimes not
even the new car smell can hide the fact that maybe this isn't
the car you would have picked out for yourself. You're kind of
stuck with it. And maybe it's even more of a railroad car than
one that you can actually drive around to explore in on your
own.
So the sense of exploring is really what Jacob and I wanted
to try with this game. What's a different model that really
puts exploring as a mechanic as the thing you're doing front
and center? Genuinely exploring a story space. And the story
part of that is important too because we're both writers so we
didn't want something that felt so procedural or generative that
it stopped working as fiction.
So our challenge was to find a new narrative mechanic and build
a game around it that allowed low cost reversible decisions
and the ability to make surprising things. So that's
kind of what we mean by feeling like sculpture.
So for extra fun we had some constraints. We initially did
this project for an art grant called future of the book that
wanted a digital game that worked with a physical printed
book which is right here. Which we also designed along with the
game. As writers without a budget it needed to be mostly
driven by text and also this.
So we had some interesting constraints that might be
different than the constraints many of you work with on your
games. So let me talk a little bit about the game we ended up
with and then I'll go back and say how we sort of tackled these
challenges. So in the ice bound concordance you explore a
series of connected stories set at a place called Carina
station, a polar research base slowly sinking into ice. Each
level of the game is a deeper level of Carina station and a
story further back in time of people who lived at this remote
outpost.
As you reach each new story you see a map for that level of the
station. The map is filled with objects and areas that might
become significant to the story if you choose to shine one of
your virtual spotlights on them. And we kind of like to call this
idea Chekhov's doll house. So if you know the theater convention
that if there's a gun over the mantelpiece someone's going to
shoot it before the end of the play. In our game you're sort of
choosing what narrative element has that significance. What
set ups will lead to dramatic payoffs in your version of the
story.
And I should say that the set of possibilities on each map isn't static. It's in part procedural
chosen from a library of content and winnowed down in part by the player's earlier choices.
So certain combinations activate more story fragments, which you're seeing on the left
side here. Events and endings. These are second and third act style plot points implied by
the setup you've created. So for example, loneliness plus romantic thoughts might lead
to a love story, but then if you add an element of danger, it might give it a tragic ending.
All three kinds of story fragments can also be examined as longer texts which are altered
based on the current state of the story.
Such as other active fragments, recurring themes and so on.
There's also shimmering text that can be cycled through different alternatives.
And sometimes a single word can really profoundly change the meaning of an entire fragment.
So while this is happening, you carry on a running conversation with a sort of digital
ghost, the original author of all these stories who has been resurrected as a virtual agent.
To resolve a story, you need to convince the author that your version makes sense.
You do this by showing him pages from the companion physical book, the Icebound Compendium.
Filled with more layers of narrative, the book acts as a kind of thematic controller
for the story.
Augmented reality recognizes which page of the book you're
looking at and hidden tags determine whether a given page
and your chosen story have any overlapping thematic ideas. If
they do, those themes become strengthened and the next level
you visit will have more objects and text connecting to those
strengthened themes. As you go deeper, you're slowly bringing
the narrative more and more in line with your own thematic
preferences, making the story feel more and more like
something you contributed to.
Thank you.
That was a lot to take in. But the core gameplay loop is
really kind of just this. You're building stories using a set of
available fragments. You're resolving stories by finding a
page in the book with a thematic match. And then that set of
fragments gets winnowed down based on those decisions so that
the next story you build has more fragments that connect to
the themes you're interested in.
So how did we get to here? What was the solution to our initial
challenge of wanting something that felt more sculptural? Well
it turns out we took a couple of significant ideas. So rather
than invent one giant system that could create the aesthetic
we wanted, we realized we needed to make the story dynamic in a
lot of different subtle ways. So on the highest level choosing
themes by showing the book pages helps shape the story in a big
sense, what's it about, what's the big picture.
The mechanic of moving the lights around controls the sort of
major details, which characters you're going to focus on, what
plot events are important. And then that zoomed in view of the
individual text gives you the player control over really small
aspects, words and phrases. And at the same time, this cycle is
going on, there's also things like the conversation with the
central character who has a state that can change and how
the player chooses to interact with the printed book. Do they
read it all at once at the beginning? Do they dip back into
it as they're playing?
So together all these things worked better than any one
system for creating a dynamic that made the player feel like
an author. One of the things we've been happiest about is to
see this come out in reviews of the game. So we got a few weeks
ago this really nice piece from rock, paper, shotgun where they
said I'd feel some small but significant change ripple
through the game from a choice I made. The icebound concordance
is a game that more than anything else captures this
feeling of editing. So that's been really cool to see people
pick up on that.
We did a lot of prototyping of narrative mechanics. We did a
lot of experimenting with ways we could break story up into
pieces, move those pieces around, combine them and
importantly restrict those combinations so they stayed
narratively valid without restricting the player's
creativity so much they felt railroaded.
Another insight when exploring a new space you need a map. So
we built a lot of visualization and authoring tools to help us
understand the kind of huge combinatorial space representing
the different ways our story fragments can be combined. And
this is actually a doubly exponential space because each
level has thousands of possible sets of fragments based on what
themes are active but each of those sets has hundreds of
permutations based on how the player has currently configured
their lights.
So the tools we built really helped us discover how much
content we needed to cover that possibility space and to find
any holes or edge cases that might have taken weeks of play
testing to emerge more organically. And another
interesting insight, we actually needed less content than we
originally thought we did. So Icebound has about 50,000 words
of story and that's smaller than other projects I've done by a
significant amount. But we've seen in reviews and in play
testing and stuff that players feel more like they're actually
shaping the story and having a big impact on it.
Which is a huge win for two overworked writers. So how does
this change game narrative as we know it. Sorry Clara that makes
me think of this.
So I think I have less grandiose conclusions than a Star Trek
episode. But I think Jacob and I actually kind of succeeded at
what we set out to do. We genuinely didn't know if we
could make this work. But we went out exploring strange new
mechanics and seeking out new models of interactive story and
we hit on something really special I think. So if you're
lucky enough to be in a space where you can explore an indie
space, an academic space, a personal project space, even a
studio willing to take some risks, you should be boldly
going.
The rewards might be fame or possibly even fortune as illustrated by this photograph
of Jacob and I holding literally fives of dollars.
So finally, I really believe that players are more engaged if
they can build story not just choose story. I've seen this in
a lot of my own projects and I'd love to see more people building
story engines that let players truly collaborate with us. Let
them use the story telling skills that we all have as
writers and narrative designers to help them tell their own
surprising life changing meaningful stories that they
truly had a hand in crafting.
So you can find out more about our game at ice-bound.com. The
book is actually here at the GDC bookstore, which is awesome.
And if you're interested in getting a hold of me, that's my
website. Thank you very much.
And next up, we have Katie Chironis talking about Elsinore.
Hi, so I am a game designer at Oculus by day and by night.
Some friends and I work on Elsinore.
Here's our trailer.
So what is Elsinore?
Elsinore is a time looping Shakespearean adventure game set in the world of Shakespeare's Hamlet.
It's really weird and we're still honestly not sure how to elevator pitch it ourselves
so we're still working on that.
It's kind of like if you took Hamlet and mashed it up with the time looping mechanics of Majora's
Mask and a little bit of performance location based theater like Sleep No More.
As Ophelia, for those of you who slept through high school English, is Hamlet's ex and jolted lover,
one of the side characters in the original play, you are attempting to stop the tragedy of Hamlet
over the course of four days. There are two catches with this.
Number one, Ophelia is stuck in a time loop and she knows it.
So all the information that she learns between loops is retained.
And number two,
The information that you do acquire goes into this inventory of information that you have at
your disposal and you can then present it at any given point in the timeline. So obviously
talking to characters about what your dad thinks has a very different impact on day one
versus if he just got murdered by Hamlet.
Working with that has been really interesting.
In many ways, Elsinore is sort of born of what if.
Most of us on the team work in game development for our day jobs.
And we wanted to sort of explore this concept of tragic gameplay.
And you know, you think of tragedy as sort of this concept of a group of characters or a tragic protagonist
doing everything in their power to try and create a good outcome,
but because of some innate flaw or some vice they have, everything goes to shit.
And so we really wanted to take the concept of the traditional game which is structured
around this power fantasy.
You're always supposed to be excelling and learning and gaining clarity and getting better
and how can we turn that on its head and create something that really feels like playing a
Shakespearean tragedy.
Accounting for player agency makes this really hard.
We tend to try and turn things against players and so I'm going to talk a little bit about
how we managed to make that happen.
Number one is that giving players this arsenal of information at their disposal
allows them to do completely reasonable things that Shakespeare didn't account for
when he was writing Hamlet in the 17th century.
So, you know, for example, players go up to Hamlet and they're like, hey, Hamlet, I noticed
that you're feeling really stabby today, what if you didn't kill anyone?
Or conversely, you know, go ‑‑ they go right up to Hamlet and they say, hey, Hamlet,
I know for a fact that your uncle totally murdered your dad, so here's all the evidence
you need.
Go get him, tiger!
And so, you know ‑‑
When you sort of allow players to attempt to solve the tragedy for themselves, the puzzle
becomes can they actually do it?
It seems so straightforward, right?
You look at Romeo and Juliet and you're like, what if they had a cell phone?
Oh my God, this would have just cleared itself right up.
And so writing to this and writing around this required digging really deeply into the
source material.
And doing a lot of reading about the original play, what do scholars think of it, what do
scholars think of the characters, and creating large bodies of new information and new characterization
that did not exist in the original play.
So taking the example of Gertrude.
Again, for those of you who don't know Hamlet, she's the queen of Denmark.
For most of the play, she's kind of a background character.
She sits at her husband's side.
She rules the throne.
In Act 5, she gets poisoned and dies.
That's a large amount of her contribution to the play.
She is still a queen, and she's still on the throne.
What happens if the player goes and tells her on day one, hey, I have proof that your
husband is a murderer and murdered your last husband?
How would she react?
It really required going back and reading through the play and creating new avenues
of content that move around that.
Not to mention, because it's a time looping game, we can see Gertrude in so many different
situations.
We can see her at her peak and at her lowest point.
We can see her when she's ruling on the throne of Denmark as a solo queen after having disposed
of her husband.
And when she's about to commit suicide because she learned something that she shouldn't have
long before she was supposed to know it.
And so really, the secondary struggle, once we had sort of created all this content around characters,
was, okay, how do we bring it all to a nice close? How do we take everything that we know and create
a tragic ending out of all this? Because, you know, if you sort of go with the scheme of tragic
gameplay, we're trying to force players into scenarios where all of their best intentions
are thwarted, and the things that they thought would work out don't in the end.
So a large amount of this comes back to sort of writing around each character's tragic
flaw.
We wanted to basically, like, you know, the player will present information and characters
will seem to move in rational ways according to that information until inevitably it starts
to break down towards the end of day three and day four.
So a lot of day three and day four, they start to go crazy, they start to kill each other.
And...
Um...
In a way, it feels a little bit dirty as a game designer and a writer because I will
see players come in and play the game and they're like, hey, everything was going really
well and then it totally veered off the rails and went out of control.
And that's sort of the exact opposite of everything that you're taught to do in commercial game
development, which has kind of been really fun.
Watching the gameplay sort of feels like a back and forth
between myself and Connor, our designer, and the players as
they're attempting every possible avenue that they think
will lead to success.
And at every step of the way, the game is saying, no.
No, you can't do that.
So, in the end, we've sort of seen players come to an interesting conclusion, which is
that, you know, when you're reading a tragedy, the characters within the tragedy normally
come to death or failure.
But when you're watching players engage with a tragic game, they come to catharsis.
They sort of realize, oh, like, you know, it's not about solving.
It's not about winning.
It's...
It's about understanding who these people are and who these characters are and empathizing
with them and trying to befriend them in the face of the end of the world.
How does Elsinore change game narrative?
I think that's a large question.
To some extent, I don't know.
As the writer and as the designer,
it's not really my job to expound upon that.
What I will say is that I think Elsinore
works best as an outlier.
I think it works best as, you know,
in a world where there are games that empower the player
and lift her up and allow her to, you know,
excel and to gain new heights,
Elsinore says, fuck you.
And...
Maybe there's some power in that. We are demoing the game at the Indie Mega booth every day this week if you would like to come and play for yourself as writers and designers and tell us how we're doing. Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Next we have Nina Freeman talking about Sybil.
Hello.
So hi, my name is Nina Freeman.
I'm a level designer at Fulbright right now,
working on Tacoma.
My last project was Sybil, which I worked on
with StarMade Games.
And today I'll talk to you about vignette games,
which is what Sybil is.
Okay, so what's a vignette?
I really like this definition of vignettes from Ian Bogost.
I think it encompasses vignettes in the broadest sense, which is useful.
Some examples of vignettes in other mediums that are not games are Mrs. Dalloway, if you've
read that.
Much of William Carlos Williams' work, who's a poet, or the movie Lost in Translation.
In games, some pieces that I consider vignettes are Dysphoria, The Last of Us Left Behind,
or The Beginner's Guide.
So just to give you some context about the kind of vignette that I'm talking about.
So here's a short vignette style poem, just to give you a concrete example, by Frank O'Hara,
which you can read.
Much of my work is inspired by this kind of work in poetry, and particularly by this poet
and the other poets that are considered part of the New York School of Poetry.
In my work particularly, I've used vignettes as a guide to developing mechanics that enable
the kind of intimacy that help players examine the wrinkles in individual human experiences.
So the vignette games I designed are character focused and focus
on the specificity of human lives or moments in human lives.
They don't often try to make a statement or have a theme,
although they can. They're exploratory or descriptive of a
single, concise experience or character.
So I used this vignette approach when designing Sybil, a game that I worked on, like I said,
with StarMadeGames.
I was the designer and writer.
It's a game about a relationship between two young people, Nina and Blake, sort of in their
late 19s, early 20s.
And they're two people who met in an MMORPG, like a World of Warcraft style thing, that
want to meet up in real life to have sex.
You play as Nina and experience this situation from her
perspective.
So it's a concise vignette game about this one particular
moment in a larger relationship.
And here's the trailer just to give you a sense of what the
game is like and how it plays.
Modem device.
Morning.
Not much.
Want to do it right together?
Yeah.
I kind of wish we lived closer.
Being on opposite coasts isn't the best for hanging out.
Want to meet up with me? Like, in real life.
That's how you spell Sybil. People always ask me that, so that's how you spell it.
It's already out. You can go to SybilGame.com if you want to check it out later.
Oh, and it's in IGF, we'll be showing it on the expo floor later this week.
So the challenge in making Sybil for me was that, you know, it's about this romantic relationship.
And romantic relationships are full of complexity and nuance, as I'm sure most of us know.
So how do I tell the story of a relationship without overwhelming the player with information
about like all these experiences that these people have had together?
That's like a lot of stuff.
So the, the, um, wait, I'm going to go back to the slide and stay on it for a bit.
So, um, when I started working on the game, I wanted to tell the story of this relationship,
and it's based on a personal experience. So I had this whole deep, complicated memory,
um, that spanned over a few years, and that's a lot of story to tell, and I didn't necessarily
want to tell all of it. Uh, the entire relationship between these two people has many aspects.
How did they meet? What was that like? What have they bonded over? What have they fought over? Etc.
Making a story that addresses all of these things with depth and nuance would probably lead to a project of a larger scope than my team had the capacity for.
Four of us worked on it while I was in grad school and we all had other jobs.
So even more importantly, is every aspect of this relationship interesting to me as
a writer?
Potentially not.
So I asked myself how I could focus on the aspect of the relationship that I found the
most interesting to write about and sort of like cut the scope down to that specific part
of it.
In a vignette way.
So, in my effort to focus in on one aspect of the relationship, I developed the story
within the constraints of a vignette.
The vignette of Sybil focuses on the in-person meeting for sex between the two main characters.
Given this constraint, each piece of the game needed to support and contextualize how and
why the couple decide to meet up.
Each act of the game consists of one conversation between the pair that contextualizes their
meeting and ephemera to support the player's understanding of that single moment in their
relationship.
So of course, because it's a vignette about this one
particular moment, the game does not start at the beginning
of their relationship.
It doesn't start when they met.
It starts sort of in the middle.
So it doesn't depict that part of their relationship at all.
It really just focuses in on this moment.
Despite that, the players still need some context to understand that the relationship has already begun to develop, just for context.
So, throughout the first act, the players presented with ephemera that refer to their interactions sort of prior to this moment.
For example, Nina's friend comments on how much she likes Blake in this email that the player can find.
It's just enough information to show the player that Nina and Blake have already started down the path to becoming close,
without spelling it out explicitly or exceeding the scope of the vignette.
So it's really like sort of context building so they can understand where this relationship
is coming from.
So Act 1 continues to build on this basic level of information and begins to explore
the physical side of Nina and Blake's relationship.
The player finds pictures the two have been sending back and forth to each other while
they overhear this flirtatious conversation in which Blake asks Nina for more pictures
of herself.
This act shows that the pair have become close enough to send real pictures of themselves
to each other.
And these photos and what they imply about how Nina and Blake are feeling are a really
important wrinkle in this vignette of their oncoming sexual encounter.
These photo exchanges show the player that the two are becoming intimate in a sexually
charged way.
So finally the act ends with a short film of Nina taking a sexy selfie to send to Blake.
This is meant to emphasize how important intimacy and the physical body are to this moment
in Nina and Blake's relationship.
So like I said before, each act is sort of meant to contextualize one sort of wrinkle in this moment.
So this first one sets up sort of the sexual part of it.
So of course all this is conveyed to the player through emails and pictures and dialogue. It's
almost like sort of a gone home style thing where you're like going through a space and looking at
stuff and learning about the characters that way instead of having them like tell it to you
explicitly. So it's all pretty minimal.
I leave it up to the player to fill in the blanks.
I give them just enough information in order to paint a picture of where this couple is
at in their relationship without exceeding the constraints of the vignette by getting
too much into sort of the history of it and the nitty gritty of the stuff that came before
this moment.
So I think this is an important example of how the vignette as a constraint helped inform
the mechanics and storytelling in Sybil.
Vignettes are all about evocative detail, details that tell a story in between the lines.
Details that do not need to explain themselves or be spelled out.
The player plays Sybil listening to the brief conversations between the characters and understanding
the context of those conversations by finding ephemera that relate to them within the game's
computer interface.
So you're sort of listening to these conversations and understanding the context of them by clicking
around Nina's computer and exploring all of this ephemera.
So in Act 2, Nina and Blake are further breaking down the barriers between their digital and
physical relationship as they come closer to having sex, because they are becoming emotionally
intimate for the first time in this moment in their relationship.
So in this act, the two are doing a lot more than sending pics to each other.
It's no longer just about the physical sex aspect of the relationship.
They're sharing intimate details about their lives.
So in this conversation, for example, Nina tells Blake a story about how her mom and dad first met.
And Blake tells Nina that he thinks she'd really get along with his real life friends.
So these are just, you know, the sort of things that you tell to someone when you're
becoming intimate with them. These like personal stories.
So finally at the end of the act it's clear that they're intimate enough to be thinking about what
it'd be like to meet and to talk on the phone and to be sharing these more personal stories with
each other rather than like kind of just flirting and like sending sexy selfies to each other.
Sort of another layer on top of that. So all of these little details that add depth to the
vignette contextualize their awkward conversation in act two that ends with them on the phone with
each other and when they're talking on the phone they're sort of professing their love and desire
for sex.
Not because of the sexy pics, but because they feel like they understand each other in a way
and are growing closer to one another at this moment in their relationship.
So this act further contextualizes the vignette and gives the player a better understanding
of how the meeting for sex came to be and how it developed to that point
and the details of their relationship that support that understanding.
Okay, so finally, in Act 3, the player experiences the conversation between the couple that really
ties up the vignette.
Nina and Blake decide to actually meet.
So Blake will fly to New York City to see Nina in person.
But the act is about that, and how the two feel about it.
So it introduces some uncertainty, illustrating Blake's particular uncertainty about this
meeting and Nina's enthusiasm.
As you can see, her enthusiasm is sort of expressed by this list of potential plans
on her desktop.
That's sort of one of the first things you see in the act.
So you can kind of see, like, oh, Nina is off on her own, like, kind of planning this
out and she's getting, like, pretty hyped up about it.
And then that kind of contextualizes later in the act when she is really like, hey, we
should meet, like, let's talk about this.
I'm kind of already making plans.
And you know that because you see her plans.
So each act consists of one detail about their relationship that ultimately contextualizes
the final short film which closes this act.
Nina and Blake meet up in person and have sex in this final short film that closes the
final act of the game.
The player's experience of that final scene is understood through the lens provided by
the details of their relationship as evoked by the previous three acts.
The sexy pics in act one, the phone calls in act two, and finally the uncertainty in
the plane tickets in act three.
So, by the way, I would like to emphasize that all of this, I'm sort of explaining it
in terms of the ephemera you find, because so much of that is there to really contextualize
what's happening.
It's really not just about the conversations.
The conversations are so dependent on the player clicking around this computer and understanding
what's going on in the background so that they can kind of feel like they know where
Nina's coming from on a different level beyond just what she says.
So, yeah, it's really about those details rather than a plot.
There's not really much of a plot to this game.
It's really just these three conversations and then they meet.
It's as simple as that.
It's about the characters and the nuance of the situation.
It's about the snippets of conversations in the ephemera that contextualize them.
This is what makes Sybil a vignette game.
It's not told through an elegant beginning, middle, and end.
It's one moment explored through the details that contextualize it.
It's an ordinary life story told through ordinary life things.
So the game does not explain the exact circumstances
of this relationship that are not specifically relevant
to helping the player's understanding
of the focus of the vignette,
which culminates sort of in that final short film
where they meet up.
The game begins in the midst of their relationship, like I said earlier.
It explores how they came to meet up for sex and ends abruptly after this sort of sex meet
up happens.
I wasn't interested in exploring how the characters were impacted by what happened.
That would be outside of the scope of the vignette.
This vignette is constrained to the circumstances and nuances of exactly how it happened and
nothing more.
So the ending may feel unsatisfying because it ends at what many may consider the climax.
However, the choice was deliberate in order to maintain the scope of the vignette and
to evoke the character's feeling of a sudden end to a sexual encounter.
The abrupt ending itself is necessary in order to express the ephemeral nature of this meeting
between Nina and Blake.
So I would like to emphasize that tying up your story neatly may not always be necessary.
If abruptness evokes a feeling, use it.
If the climax is the ending or the beginning, then make that decision purposeful and use
it.
If you're feeling overwhelmed by the complexity of a story, consider whether or not you're
really just trying to explore one concise part of it.
A vignette.
And try to focus on that.
Explore your story through its details, no matter how mundane.
Don't be afraid to cut the cruft, even if it makes the story arc unusual.
Every story has its own shape.
Embrace it.
Thanks.
And, finally, we have Richard Rouse talking about the church in the darkness.
I want to thank Matt and Clara for inviting me to do this and also thanks to all the other
amazing talks we've had here today. I'm sort of intimidated by this lineup.
But as the other speakers have talked about, when Matt and Clara proposed this session,
they said, well, first state what your challenge was with the project.
And I thought that was a really good thing to think of a project in those terms. And not enough
projects made me think about, like, what is the big challenge we're taking on?
I think a lot of really good directors do that sort of thing, but maybe they don't articulate it to
themselves or write it down or anything like that. And I certainly didn't when I was starting this
project. When I thought back about when I started on this, on working on the church in the
darkness, there were actually two challenges that I was taking on. And the first one was I
really wanted to make an action game with a changing narrative.
The reason I got into games was wanting to tell stories that would react to players and
that would allow them to express themselves and to see what would happen.
And I've had some success with that with games I worked on in the past, like the first game
I made, Odyssey, was an Ultima-style RPG, to the suffering horror games where the choices
you were making in the present not only affected the future but also the past.
Or most recently working a bit on state of decay where an
ongoing simulation produces a lot of tricky narrative choices
you kind of have to make under time pressure. But I was
interested in some other games that I remembered back from way
way back in the 80s. There were several murder mystery type
games that actually randomized who was murdered in the game and
who did the murdering. And it was a game that was sort of
This was an interesting approach to adapting one of these things that made these games
highly replayable.
Or a more recent, but still 20 years ago, example.
It comes from the Blade Runner game that Westwood did in the 90s, where it randomized whether
each character was a replicant or not.
And obviously the choices you would have to make is the player would change dramatically
based on that.
So the second thing I really wanted to do was explore the
nature of cults. And I've been sort of fascinated by cults for
a long time. And specifically how cults often start off with
these very noble intentions of really wanting to change the
world or do something positive.
And then things sort of drift off and maybe go wrong.
But maybe sometimes they don't.
And why does it happen sometimes?
And why does it not happen other times?
And how can you tell?
So the solution, of course, I realized was to combine these
two things.
And that's what I'm trying to do in The Church in the
Darkness, which is the game we just announced.
And I'm going to show the trailer.
We came to the jungle looking for peace.
America is corrupt.
It sends our children to die in Vietnam.
It's system keeps you poor, keeps you segregated, keeps you powerless.
We told you our way was better.
Living in socialism is God-intended.
And because we preach the truth, they call us a cult.
So they hate us. They want to kill us.
That is why we had to leave their sick country.
So we came here, to South America, to the jungle,
to isolate ourselves, to purify our community.
But still they hate us, because our success proves that their society is wrong, that their system is cruel, that their way is doomed.
So they are coming for us.
They will infiltrate us.
They will sabotage us.
They will try to kidnap our people.
But we are ready.
We take up arms, and we will have no mercy for anyone that violates our home.
Attacking us will just show the world how corrupt they are.
So let them call us a cult, because we stand firm for what we believe.
We have God on our side, and we will not let them take a single one of us alive.
So if I had to give you the one liner, the church in the
darkness is a top down action infiltration game set inside a
religious cult in the 1970s where the story changes every
time you play. The player is infiltrating this group, the
collective justice mission to check on a relative. But the
thing is you don't know the true nature of this group. You don't
know are they a bunch of happy socialists just living their
alternate life in the jungle or is there something more
apocalyptic going on. And the player has choice about how they
interact with these people and what they do there.
You can be completely snealthy in your infiltration looking for the person you're trying to find.
You can use non-lethal methods to take down opponents or you can kill anyone who gets
in your way.
So how did I come up with this, how did I get to this point and
come up with this design? I really started with a lot of
research and when I was prepping I told Matt, well, maybe I don't
need to talk about the research. He was like, no, no, you should
talk about the research. People need to do more research. So I
love doing research, you know, really going beyond just what
you find in the Wikipedia article or that cool movie you
saw once with Denzel Washington in it. If you're on a budget
like me, I recommend the library. They're still around.
They're still awesome. Go find that dusty book in the corner
that no one has read and read it and put that stuff in your
game.
So when I was reading up on this I found that the 70s were
really the ideal time for this sort of radical progressive
group. In case the American education system has failed
you, the 70s were a time of great sort of distrust of the
government and uncertainty like if our society was going to
collapse at any time. We had the ongoing struggles in Vietnam
and illegal bombings in Cambodia. You had ongoing fear
of nuclear annihilation.
And people were really not sure if society was going to make it.
And they started thinking, well, you know, the peaceful protest movements of the 60s
have kind of failed us.
And some people started actually going about things differently and threatening violence
and some actually carrying it out.
And so in this time period, this very fertile period for these groups that were presenting a new way of life, a new way to approach having society that would work better.
And the interesting thing in reading up on all these groups that I found was that you don't join a cult because you're weak, you join it because you're really strong, because you're really strong-willed that you want to do something different.
And these groups generally offer really great benefits to the
people who are in them like help them with their personal issues
or help them find a community if they're outcasts. And they also
then tend to start to involve this us versus them mentality
that we're right and everyone else is wrong and you need to be
with us. And the darker groups take that even farther saying
well if you ever leave us we're never going to talk to you
again. Your children are never going to talk to you again.
We may hunt you down and persecute you.
And the leaders of these groups tend to take the power that comes with leading this movement
and the absolute power corrupting absolutely happens.
And sometimes bad outcomes happen.
But sometimes they don't.
Interestingly, reading about so many of these groups, they don't all end badly.
Sometimes they just try something for a while and then it peters out.
Or sometimes some of these groups are still going today, but they don't get the headlines
because no crimes were committed and everyone didn't die.
So looking, it wasn't intended to be funny.
Looking at how to put this into game form, I thought, well, the
player needs to be an outsider. He needs to look at this group
from the outside in order to try to figure out which type of
group is this. Is it one that is just trying to do their own
thing or is something bad going to happen? You can think of it
like one of those murder mysteries except the murder has
not taken place yet if the murder is going to happen at
all.
So I thought an infiltration game was something that fits. I
wanted to build on a bedrock of sort of known game play
mechanics and things that I've worked with in the past. Unlike
some of these other talks when I'm innovating I like to keep
some stuff that I'm familiar with and innovate in a few ways.
I wanted something that felt like a good immersive sim that we've played many versions of that
infiltration game before but that everything was completely grounded in reality that stripped
away the sci-fi trappings or the fantasy trappings we've seen in other games in the genre.
And where the player's choices in that world really have an impact on what happens.
And I wanted you to soak up the narrative while you were playing.
You're listening to the cult leaders talk over the PA system the entire time you're
infiltrating their movement.
And what they say changes subtly based on which type of group this is.
And you're finding documents and reading them and trying to put together which type of group
is this.
Because the interesting thing about all these different groups is I researched them.
There is a great commonality to them.
There is a lot of the dogma they say is the same.
So a lot of the base of the game is the same, and then these little bits along the edges change.
And it's your job as the player to seek those out and try to figure out what they are.
So I thought, you know, we've, and then obviously you have a
choice about what to do with the information as you get it.
And you know, you can think of it like this, we've all played
choice based games before where you have a baseline narrative
and then players make some choices and then you have a
number of possible stories that can result from that.
But if you think of the game as having several starting
narrative states that are changed every time you play the
game, you then put your choices on that and then you have a
much bigger possibility space for all the player stories that
can be created.
And that was something that excited me
about working on this game.
So the final question they posed to all of us was how does this involve game narrative,
and that was a very highfalutin question, particularly for a game that is the farthest
from shipping of any of these.
But since they asked, you know, I like to think that each storytelling medium that we
all know and love, you know, they each do something really well.
So for example, books are really good, you know, novels are really good at putting you
inside the head of a given character.
putting you in with that one person and their innermost
thoughts. Comics take the written word and add an
illustrative level that makes everything much more have a
specific style and tone to it that's unique.
Theater is great because I think it's the most human because the people are right there
acting in front of you, going through this whole scene, and you're right there living
it with them.
And film is obviously in complete control of the experience, the framing, the lighting,
the music, everything can be exactly what the director wants it to be.
So I think games can be a lot of different things but the thing
that excites me about them the most is I think that we can ask
the question what if, right? What if the situation was like
this? What would you do then? How would your choices change?
How would that impact everyone else in the game? What if your
family member was in a religious cult but you didn't know whether
that cult was really bad or not? What if you found out the group
was apocalyptic? Would you save your own family member or would
you risk it all and try to save the whole group?
What if the group had no bad intentions but you still thought
they were creepy? Would you let your relatives stay there?
And I think, you know, with subject matter like this, I
think it's really valuable to explore it in games because we
can see more sides of the story. Because looking at the story
of all these cults, you know, there's not just one. And I read
so many stories of survivors and people who have left who say,
you know, it's just not as simple as everyone thinks. You
know, we wanted to change the world. We weren't brainwashed.
You know, there was good along with the bad. What if things
had gone a different way? And I think those are the interesting
different sides to the story. And telling a linear story of
this, you can only tell one version of that.
But telling it in game form, you can look at multiple sides of
it and show some more of the complexity.
And the player can make choices about how they deal with it
and see just how many sides there are to any one story.
So that's the game.
If you want to follow along with development as we
continue to work on it, I've got a mailing list up at the
website there, or get on Twitter, or
something like that.
If you come by after, I have some cool postcards you can
take with you.
And I'm doing another talk about dynamic narratives
tomorrow at 210.
If you want to hear that more broadly about a whole bunch of
different games.
All right.
Thanks very much.
All right, so I hope that you were all taking notes, because that was a lot of information
and there's been a lot of insights, but we wanted to give you a bit of a summary
of the things that we've learned today from listening to them,
but also from our conversations while we were preparing this.
So the first thing that we realized is that all of the talks here deal with games that
go beyond genre fiction.
And I mean by genre fiction things like science fiction, fantasy, mystery, and I love those.
But I think that going beyond genre fiction, looking at histories of real people, going
to Shakespeare, culture, you know, the 70s.
They're going to challenges in the ways that we have to tell those stories, that we have
to create those stories.
So just by shifting to something that is not genre, we're already innovating and finding
new ways to tell those stories.
Also fragmented modular narratives, the vignettes that we were talking about before, are a great
way to tell a story. We tend to think of plot as being that's what a story is. But really
there's many kinds of stories that are just little bits of information that you can arrange
in any way or come across in any way. And this is actually not a strange way of telling
a story. This is a very normal way of telling a story when you think about poetry and other
forms. And it fits in games very well.
We often don't take advantage of it and it's a pretty simple thing to do in a lot of ways.
I mean, in a way, you're going to see, actually,
in the narrative summit, there's a couple of talks
about branching narratives.
And in a way, we have to think beyond branching.
We're looking at combinatorics.
We're looking at ways in which we can create new stories,
which links to the next point that we want to make, which is
leaving gaps.
And at times, leaving gaps are ways to encourage players to
interpret the game, to explore, to find out what else
is there.
to figure out the story for themselves.
And in a way, what we do is less storytelling and more story building.
We are building the story from those modules that we were just talking about.
But also we invite players to build their own stories by exploring the gaps that we're leaving for them.
Excuse me, for them.
And surprise, video's not terrible. We just did it wrong 20 years ago.
You can use video or in a broader sense static media and
still have rich interactive experience. It's just a matter
of approaching it in the right way.
So that's it from us.
You'll get emails from the GDC organization asking you to
fill out the e-vowels.
Please tell us nice things about us.
If you want to see more of this next year, we'll be
happy to come back and find more experimental narrative
games for you.
There's no Q&A, but we'll be happy to meet you at the wrap
up room on this floor.
All right?
Thank you, everybody, and a round of applause for all the
tech.