All right, so to kind of dig into it,
this talk is about the character balance
that we did in Skylanders Swamp Force.
A little bit more about me.
I actually originally had an animation background,
it was about 15 years ago,
but that's kind of how I started in the industry.
Skylanders was my 26th ship title,
and included in those were all kinds of crazy genres
from Tony Hawk's to Guitar Heroes,
you know, sandbox style games of Spider-Man,
2D, 3D platformers.
But really my focus for at least half of that and up to now has been on combat design.
So for those of you who don't know what Skylanders is, I just wanted to do a little bit.
Hopefully a lot of you know what it is, but it was released in 2011
as a reinvention of the Spyro franchise.
It was a dungeon crawler for kids pretty much
and it really started the whole toys to life kind of genre of which we have lots of nowadays.
Over the course of the titles...
They added a bunch of characters. So the first one had 32 characters, Giants added 16, and then Swapforce we had 32 characters on top of that.
That brings it to 80 wholly unique characters, and when I mean unique I mean very unique characters.
On top of that, in Swapforce, we, you know, didn't want to do anything easy, so we said 16 of those new characters could be broken in half.
reassembled and made into 256 possible combinations.
So we kind of had to say, well, how are we going to attempt
to balance all of these things into one game?
So I just want to tell you guys a little bit
of what we're going to cover today.
This way, if you're, you know, getting hungry,
you can know how close you are to the end,
but also just a way to track how we're moving along.
So starting with kind of balance priorities.
different players have different balance priorities with Skylanders they have a
certain set
for example League of Legends is a pretty different set
uh... if you take a look at who a Skylander fan is
it's usually boys to girls ages six to ten
as well as some of their parents
now
Skylanders is a game for everybody, but when you try to start balancing something for everybody,
you're going to have a whole lot of, oh well what about this individual.
So we really had to target. So we targeted the 6 to 10 age range.
The types of balance that I'm going to talk about today, because there is lots of types of balance,
all of which is relevant to most games, but in the case of today I'm going to talk about
player versus player. Now player versus player is the actual human being
I'm sure a really talented Pat
versus another human being and so this is me playing against you and we would
kinda like a fair fight so games like checkers chess where they're completely
symmetrical those games are obviously very balanced
with the exception of who goes first
so that's what I'm talking about with player versus player
Character versus character, even though characters are typically used in a PvP situation,
it is why would I choose this character over another character.
Now in the case of Team Fortress, there are roles in the game,
and so you have more reasons to pick one particular character over another.
Even in League of Legends you have certain characters that will take certain paths based on their role.
Skylanders doesn't have roles, but there is a very strong reason why we want you to play multiple characters.
The next one is player versus environment.
So this is PVE, as many people call it.
It's just any of the monsters, hazards, traps,
other things that the computer is doing
to try to make the levels more interesting, difficult,
and other things like that.
So anything that's not another player, that's what this is.
And then the last one is the character within itself.
Now this is why would I use one ability
instead of another ability.
A character who has one ability that is the best ability and no reason to ever use any other ability again
is a character that has very poor balance within itself.
A character that has lots of reasons to kind of mix and match and play all of its moves has good balance.
So if we kind of look at whose priorities fall where, we'll start with League of Legends.
Now League of Legends in a very small nutshell is a game that
you play, there's lots of characters, you try to kill the
other team with your players. There are many more rules and
I'm sure many of you know them.
But in this case, PVE is the least important factor in this
game.
Doesn't mean it's not there.
There are little minions and there are enemies that hide in
the map that aren't players.
But it's not important.
It's not what needs to be gotten right.
For example, if one of the monsters on one of the maps
just had way too many hit points, it's not really going
to break that match because what matters is the fairness
or balance between players, which is why the PVP section
is the really big wedge.
Character versus character and character within itself are also very important.
League of Legends makes a lot of its money by selling more characters.
It's very similar to Skylanders.
So, that's a big deal for them.
And then the character within itself, because there's some depth in it that you don't,
you want interesting characters using one ability at the right time versus another ability is important to it.
Now to contrast, if you look at Skylanders, PVP is the least
important thing to our audience.
I am going to spend a little bit of time on a little bit
more as to why it is.
But the big purple wedge is the PVE.
This is story mode.
This is the kid sits down and wants to play through the game
and get to the end and beat Chaos at his.
new scheme. Very important to them. Character versus character is almost exactly as important.
We want kids to want to buy more toys. And we want them to enjoy it. We don't want to
feel like they're ripped off or they got a toy and it was kind of lame and it didn't
really meet their expectations. We also want kids to argue on the playground which Skylander
is cooler than another Skylander. And then the character within itself is actually pretty
much the same importance as League of Legends is why would I pick this ability instead of
this ability.
characters start to get boring when they're not.
So that's really what I'm talking about with balance,
the priorities of what is important to your player base.
So start with what your players like,
and kind of scope and balance accordingly there.
So to get into the meat, so much meat
that I had to break it up into four smaller sections,
these are the types of balance.
Now player versus player is kind of the first one
I'm going to talk about.
I'm going to talk about it for a very short period of time.
This was the lowest priority for our demographic because they
just didn't play it as much. We did have to make some special
changes to it and there was some really big things that we
learned that even made us prioritize it less.
So one of the big things that we changed was anything that would remove player control from another player was actually removed from that mode.
So we have lots of abilities where you can put people in bubbles, or you can freeze them, or you can make them dance.
Those victim events, or victim states as we called them, didn't happen.
to another player. Now they would still do all the damage and you could still hurt the other person
but you could never be put in a bubble, you could never be frozen in a block of ice because that was very frustrating
especially to a kid. You don't want to lose control of your character.
Some of the other under the hood balancing stuff we did was kind of health
for example if you were playing a character that's very low level and it has very very low health we would kind of up the health a little bit for you just kind of under the hood as a handicap, make it a little bit more fair.
But all of this paled in comparison to the living room balancing that occurred naturally with kids
we would put kids down on the same couch or chair or whatever I would set up that day and
We would have them play and what we would see is that they would make up their own rules a kid would put down a giant
No, you can't put down a giant. We're not playing with giants in this match. All right fine
We're both gonna play as Giants or oh you're playing as a swap first character. I want to play as a swap first character
We're only gonna play as girl characters today like that
overshadowed any amount of balancing that we would do on top of it because they had their own
priorities. They had already ranked these characters and they were doing self-balancing.
And so that made our jobs a little bit easier. We still had to do a lot of work to once again
remove certain things. But that's really all I need to talk about with that one.
We made this decision pretty early on because of the balance priorities. So to go again back to my
first point, we obviously couldn't do this amount of work on many of the other points.
So the next thing is PVE or player versus environment.
So there's gonna be a little bit of boring math
at the beginning, I'll try to tear through it
and then we'll get to some of the more.
interesting and or controversial topics. So the simple ones, these I'm just going to run through.
Hazard damage versus players. We pretty much had kind of a optimal level for a Skylander to be at
when they were on that particular story level. Now in Skylanders, as you know, your lives are
your toys. And so if a character dies, you have to put a new toy on the portal.
So we have no idea what toy is going to be put down at what level.
And in fact, later on in the game, you are more likely to replace a toy with a very low level toy
because you've been playing the game with your favorite character, he's awesome, and then suddenly it dies.
And you're like, oh, well, dig around.
Oh, I haven't played as this character in a while and I'll stick it down.
And now you really kind of have to learn that character again.
So we kind of couldn't account for it fully, but we had to make some assumptions that,
oh, well, you're at the end of the game, you probably have a high level character.
and we would just balance the damage accordingly so at the end of the level
it was flat damage
same exact amount of damage to every single character
pretty simple
health pickups was a percentage of total health it wasn't a flat amount
this is because when it
kids were playing in co-op
one of them would get pizza we made it so one pickup goes to both players
if I had a max hit point level of ten thousand say and my friend has a max
hit point of
two thousand
and he gets 2000 life back and his bar goes to full and my bar goes up a fifth. It feels like I got screwed.
And so we just made it a percentage, which means characters with more health got more health.
It was just kind of part of the character and even though it was contrary to a lot of the kind of balanced things that we thought,
that's what kids wanted, that's what kids expected.
XP games and gold pickup, once again more math.
We try pretty hard to make it such that you can
beat the game completely.
from start to finish without doing any extra content with
what was given to you in the starter pack.
So Swap Horse came with three characters, two swappers, and
the repose Stealth Elf.
We figured out, oh, it takes this much money to max them
all out, and it takes this much XP to max them all out.
We then just took the levels we had on the main path,
divided how many levels, and divided how many enemies were
in it, and that's what we got.
So if you played through the whole main story, you would
have enough money and enough XP to max out all those
characters.
Those are the kind of the boring ones.
Now, some of the trickier ones is where we started getting
into things like, what about the AI?
Now, once again, we wanted all characters to be balanced.
But we said, what's the purpose of AI?
Well, AI are there as a challenge.
Really want to make that player feel powerful.
We also want a player to feel like they're advancing
and they're getting stronger as they move along.
We want every character to feel viable. Even though there are
kind of types of attacks that are stronger in certain areas,
which we're going to get to more later, you never want to feel
like you put a character down that was just utterly useless.
And then lastly, winning can't be boring. Kids have no patience
and they will tell you if they are bored and they will walk
away from a controller no matter how many chips or soda you give
them. So winning can't be boring. So there was kind of
this interesting thing that caused more problems than we
thought it would originally.
and that was damage numbers. Now damage numbers was something that was kind of established
with the franchise already, and they weren't really going away, but I feel it's pretty
important to talk about the problems that they caused. So what are the good things of
damage numbers? Well, it's a literal reference point. You say I just punched that guy or
I blew up that barrel or I sunk that ship, I did 50 points of damage because see, look,
it says 50.
It's also really good for incremental progress.
If I put on a hat that gives me 0.3% strength
and I see my damage number go up by one,
yay, I can see the change.
And once again, it was established for the genre.
The cons, however,
were that nobody read them.
Now, you could ask someone,
hey, how much damage do you do?
Or what does that damage number say?
And they will then read it.
But subconsciously, while playing the game,
they didn't actually read.
If we took the number 10 and made it really big and red with an exclamation point,
it actually was perceived as more damage than the number 88 that was written small.
Because when you're just churning through it, you're seeing big things flash up.
And we even were like, well, can't we just do big hit reacts and hit effects?
Once again, there are a lot of pros to having them, and they weren't going anywhere.
But it was important to note.
Once again, we're not like World of Warcraft.
We don't have people running Omen or Recount or other things to maximize their damage per character.
There were also a very distracting reference point, as you'll see in a little bit.
When a player would try to figure out how powerful a character was,
they would look at the damage number.
Which sounds like, oh yeah, of course that makes sense.
But let's say you have a character that can kill everything on screen in one attack.
and when I say kill everything it just does a lot of damage. So
we would balance that move to say do 40 points of damage to
everything on screen. Well let's say you put that character down
and you execute that attack and there was one guy on screen. It
does 40 points of damage to the kid.
and you might put another character down that has a pretty strong single target attack
and that single target attack does 60 points of damage
to one thing
the kids like well the 60 is bigger than 40 of course that character is more powerful so it's not very
reflective of the actual value of a move so it was distracting
and once again it wasn't reflective, well not once again
it wasn't reflective of the players action count. Now what do I mean by the players action count?
With action counts, it's how many buttons you're pressing and things like that.
So let's say an enemy has 100 hit points,
and you have an attack that does 25 points of damage.
Okay, math whizzes out there.
Four attacks.
That's how many times it's going to take for me to hit that guy to kill it.
Now let's say you get an ability boost or a hat or you upgrade your character and now you're doing 20% more damage.
20% is a pretty big jump. There's a lot of raids that I would grind to get a sword that gave me 20% more damage output.
However, it still takes me four buttons to kill the same thing.
So even though the numbers are a little bit bigger, I don't feel any stronger. I don't feel any powerful.
It's just as much work to kill the same darn thing.
this concept of wasted damage is just not really received at
least for our target demographic. Once again if you
hit an area and the strength of that move is it can kill ten
things at once or attack ten things at once and they're not
using it right, it's just problematic. So how do we kind
of balance for this? Well, we actually started with our
enemies. So we actually started with our enemies. So we actually
Our basic melee guys were 6 hits. 2 combos. Our average combo was like a 3 hit combo.
Our basic ranged was half of this. This is because the challenge of a ranged enemy is closing the gap.
Popcorn is always 1 hit.
If you find a chompy who is super chompy at the end of the level,
he will still take one hit to kill.
It's a couple special things in some of our arenas, but for the most part that was the popcorn.
The heavies were the same as the melee guys,
however they would usually have a little rule or a little special thing.
For example, you have to get behind them or you have to wait for them to sneeze
other things like that.
One very important thing when you do this, do not do chance.
Do not do an enemy that has a 30% chance to block what you're doing.
Or, oh, maybe it'll do that or 50% on hit.
Doesn't go over well.
That just means that you have to button mash 50% more of the time.
A rule is a rule
and when a kid learns it, you want to reward them for figuring it out
and they will do it over and over again and they're going to feel great.
But if it's like, well, I have a chance to learn.
chance to kill them it just kind of gets lost it gets confusing
and usually they just end up button mashing it. The super
heavy the last one really these were just give them as many hit
points as is not boring. Traditionally we would mix in
super heavies with a lot of other things that were going
around them so you didn't just run up to a wall and beat on it
for forever. Usually they would kind of stay around while other
waves of enemies would kind of jump in. The big thing with all
of this AI hit point is that the difference in health from the
very first level.
to the very last level or the easiest difficulty to the very hardest difficulty was only two hundred percent
we did this because once again if you go to the last level
and you put down a fresh Skylander who's level one
we didn't want you to feel useless we didn't want you to feel like you had to hit that enemy five hundred times just to whittle away at it
so then it's like well how did you make the harder levels harder well that's where we were we really leaned into how much damage these enemies output
So we ramped the damage enemies output very significantly.
So much so that if you play the game on Nightmare, most
enemies in the first half of the game had the ability to
one shot you.
However, they couldn't actually.
We put a rule in that says, if you take enough damage to kill
you in one blow, we give you 20% of your health back and
make you immune for about a second.
It prevented people from being completely ganged up upon.
You can still totally get beat if you stand still for that
one second.
But what it meant was that.
to be good at the game you had to get out of the way. Dodging
and blocking is a technique that is very, very tactical for a 6
to 10 year old. The best offense is the only way to play. And so
what we found was that once kids started getting good at getting
out of the way, getting out of the way, then they were like,
okay. And they could take on nightmare. But it meant that if
you could play the game on easy and never get hit, you could
beat the game on nightmare.
So we're done with PVE.
So moving on to character versus character, this is why
I would choose one character over another.
Now this one, we got a lot of awesome data.
We did tons and tons of kit testing.
If you are even more interested in how we did our
kit testing, Gareth is giving a talk about how we did all
that Friday, I think.
You can look it up.
So the character versus character. We found that there was some pretty core reasons why people would pick
and that these things would change over time.
Aesthetics, what the character looked like was huge.
The surprise or fun. I'll tell a little bit more about that in a little bit.
Ease of use, pretty self-explanatory.
The utility, how actually useful the character was in given situations.
And the actual power. Actual power was the least important to everyone.
which made it even more difficult, but I'll get more on that later.
So over time, so if you look at the first red line,
it's the only thing that matters on that first site,
because they're looking at the character on a shelf,
they're looking at it on a commercial.
So they're instantly making expectations of what that character's going to do,
and how awesome that character is going to be when they get them home.
So none of those other things matter.
They can't play the character yet, they're just seeing it.
And so that's why all those other things are at zero.
The aesthetics kind of continues to be important, but once they've kind of built a rapport with the character and they know what they look like, it kind of fades off a little bit.
If we ever make the character start to be ugly, or we change them so much during an upgrade, it does have a negative impact, but it does slowly taper off.
The blue line, now the blue line, next one is ease of use.
You'll see it spike and then taper off.
This one's pretty self-explanatory.
They don't know how to use the character.
They put it down right on the portal.
And the first time, if they're frustrated, it's a really big
deal for them.
However, very quickly they'll learn how the character works
and it kind of tapers off down.
Now, that yellow line, my favorite line, the fun, this is something that keeps being important
to them and actually continues to grow.
You can't have a character get boring.
A kid has no tolerance for that and will walk away.
And so fun spikes up and continues to be,
in the end, is really the most important thing
at the end of the day.
The green one, now this is one where those
annoying little damage numbers pop up
because you'll see that it spikes,
goes down, and comes back up again.
The reason for that is, once again,
the first time they put that character down the portal,
they run up to a thing, they hit it,
how much damage did it do?
Oh, that's how powerful it is.
It's usually fairly inaccurate, and so they kind of forget
about it.
And then once they really start playing the character a lot
more and understand the depth of the character,
it kind of slowly goes back up.
The brown one, it has a slow grow.
This is utility.
This is because the character needs to,
or player needs to kind of take in all
the different encounters we're going to throw at them
over the course of the game and find out,
oh, this character is good here.
This character is good here.
So you really can't appreciate the utility character
played a pretty large amount of the game.
So let's dig into this a little bit with some examples.
So aesthetics.
What does a character look like?
Skylanders go through an awful lot of iteration to get where
we really want them to be.
For example, this is Trap Shadow.
He was awful scary when he first came out.
He lost his Bowie knife and a couple other things.
And we actually ended up making his little trap all ghost and
shadow, because bear traps are pretty nasty things.
And so we go through a lot of these changes.
The moment a kid, actually the moment anyone sees this character, they make an assumption of what that thing is going to do.
Once again, most important, slowly tapering off.
Now you'll notice that the line stays flat from first to thirty seconds of play.
And that's the moment where the design team was really put to the test.
We had to cash the check that the concept artist wrote.
So I'll show you an example. Stink Bomb, who is a little kung fu skunk, he's very ninja-esque.
Now in his toy he has these throwing stars. They're in his hand, he's getting ready to throw
them, he looks really cool. So what happened was we made him a ranged character. Now,
Arranged character having kung fu moves kind of starts to mix
up his kit. He's now pretty good at too many situations. So
what we ended up doing is we gave him a little one inch
punch, little Bruce Lee stink palm. And it worked great
because it delivered on the
kind of kung fu fantasy the kids wanted, but it kept him very
safely in the type of character we wanted him to be because the
one inch punch doesn't really do that much damage and it knocks
enemies away making them more susceptible to using your
ranged attack. Originally he had a little blow dart and would
shoot these little poison darts on one attack and then he would
throw the stars on the other attack.
We kept the little poison acorn he throws as kind of a Hadouken fireball as an upgrade, but
they, kids didn't see the value of having two very quick ranged attacks, even though one was
a damage over time. We kept the damage over time, we just put it on the punch.
Now the fun and surprise, this is not about a talk of what is fun.
There's probably a billion books you could go buy,
and I hope that most of you have read at least one of them.
This is really more about that one memorable, fun thing about the character.
When you ask a kid,
hey, what was it about that character you really liked?
This is that thing.
So once again.
Very important and continues to stay important.
Frieno's bike is a really good example of this.
So Frieno is a fire character.
He hasn't come out yet.
and we didn't want to do just another character that breathed
fire. We used flame attacks and a lot of things. So the whole
thing with him is what he actually does is he heats up
metal, kind of like a blacksmith does. So you'll see he gets a
little tantrum, he starts to get angry, but instead of charging
when he's hot, he summons a molten motorcycle. And this was
just meant to kind of be a fun one off. Hey, wouldn't it be
cool? Yeah, we'll change the charge of a rhino. So what we
actually ended up doing, because it was so well received,
is we cut a pretty substantial number of his other moves and we made one of his base abilities that motorcycle.
And even after that, if you look towards the end, he's got an entire path devoted to the motorcycle.
If you look on his model very carefully in the ship game, you'll actually notice that where his fist meets his wrist,
there's a little chain inside of it.
He used to be able to punch his fists off and grab things and pull them to him.
an awful lot of time spent doing that, but it wasn't really relevant to his kit and it
was not what he was remembered for. So we cut it and just put in a motorcycle. Now easy
use, this is how learnable the character is. With our game, since you could put down any
character at any time, we can expect you to go through a tutorial.
But we still have to teach you these characters and these characters have lots of moves.
So we actually hide our tutorials within the way that you buy the abilities.
Because we know that once you get some money you're going to want to buy an ability.
And while you're in the ability shop we can at least have your attention for maybe four
seconds before you push the buy button and go back to playing.
So this is something we have to be very mindful of the persona and how the character gets played and who it's being played by.
So once again, spikes up, then kind of peters off.
So Popthorn, he's this little teeny puffer dragon.
He can inflate himself and he can deflate himself.
He's awful adorable.
He would have been more adorable if we got the sneakers on him that we wanted to, but we never got that to work.
But we found that because he has such big goofy eyes and was really awful cute, he was very, very well received by our younger demographic.
So even out of the 6-10 on the 5 scale.
What he is, is he's what we call a modal character.
Meaning he can go from one mode to another.
Pop Fizz is another character, if you know the franchise,
he can drink his soda and turn into a little monster.
So what Popcorn does is he's little,
and then he poofs, and then he's big.
So what we did was we made it such that
you could actually play this character as a button masher.
He has one button that inflates him and he has one button that deflates him.
If you're already inflated when you try to inflate, he shoots little spikes.
If you're already deflated when you press the deflap button, he breathes little air.
Now what this means is you could just blindly button mash back and forth
or any one button and you'll actually be having fun. You'll be doing stuff.
He's not very effective though when he's played that way.
He's actually balanced such that if you
go back and forth frequently and at the right time,
that's where he starts putting a lot of his damage out.
So what it did was it meant that if you were a very young player
and you really didn't have the skill to know that you were going between modes,
he looked fun, he was doing cool things, and you were actually being effective.
However, if you kind of wanted to get into the depth of him,
you would really focus on how he upgraded,
know when you would expand.
For example, if you run into a crowd of guys as you're small,
and then you inflate, you'll knock them all away.
There are upgrades where he gets like fresh breath.
So when he goes small immediately,
his breath is minty fresh and does more damage.
Or when he just inflates, his spikes are spikier.
So this was a time where we kind of balanced the whole character
for how easy he needed to be to use.
Now utility is the next one. Now if you're familiar with Skylanders, there are little gates around the game that say,
oh you need an earth character to go in here or in Swap Force you need someone with the rocket legs.
This is not the type of utility I'm talking about.
What I'm talking about is, this is a melee character, this is a lobbying character, this is a crowd controlling ability.
So we call these archetypes.
this is something that once again you have a very slow
appreciation for and you really can't because you're going to
have to experience multiple encounters and be like oh this
is one of those encounters where I need one of those
characters. So the type of utilities was kind of big. I'm
not expecting you to read this eye chart. In fact I'll go away
right now.
But the first category is melee or close. Now melee is common, we have characters with weapons that swing them or they punch things, but we have lots of things that just do close attacks.
So this is really, I hit something in front of me or right immediately next to me. This is one of the most common ability archetypes that we have.
And that's what melee close is.
The next one is kind of this straight ahead category.
Now you'll notice that I'm using a ranged character here.
Our ranged characters actually tend to fall in the straight ahead.
Most of our straight ahead characters are ranged characters.
However, really anything that attacks in a hall,
if you could imagine a hallway in front of you,
is a straight ahead character.
So in this case we have characters that shoot snakes,
or characters that shoot throwing stars, other things like that.
The next category we have is the lobber.
And the lobber does just that.
It's kind of an arc.
Now, this is the lowest archetype
represented in the game.
But it's the one that has the most kind of odd ability in
that it can hit enemies that other abilities can't.
And so you'll notice in here, Countdown's throwing his head.
Another character would have to jump up onto that ledge.
Or even it could be on a ledge that you can't get to with
another character, at least by going the long way.
The next one is kind of the miscellaneous category.
If I was making a harder core game, I would call this crowd control.
So in the case of Stink Bomb, he can go invisible, no one knows where he is,
or he can kind of stink them. In the case of Magna Charge, he can pick people up,
carry them around, throw them. Doesn't really do that much damage.
It's all about kind of controlling the battlefield.
Special is something we try to have most of our characters have something in,
because it allows us to do a lot more wacky things.
The new category we added for Swapforce was the movement category.
The video will load. There we go.
Now movement is an ability that does just that.
Moves the character in some form.
So in the case of Hootloop, he has a portal ring that he throws down.
He can fall down it and he kind of comes up the other side.
That moves him forward. It kind of teleports him.
Firecracker will turn into a giant parade, move him forward.
I love that move. It's so cool.
This was very important to us because swappers,
we wanted to have the top half be how you fight and the bottom half be how you move.
So we tried to kind of keep that. As you can see here, Freeze Blade has a skate attack where he'll kind of skate forward.
He's actually the fastest character in the game, by the way, but we make you work for it because you've got to keep pumping your ice skates.
So this is a little bit easier to read.
So the global spread...
kind of felt like that with the new categories.
You'll notice that the numbers are not the same,
and that's totally fine.
What was important was that if you look at the lobber
and you see, okay, well 12 out of all the characters use.
that type of archetype.
We go and we work with the level designers and say,
hey, this is about how many characters are going to utilize this.
You should probably make this many encounters have that as kind of a cool thing to be able to do.
You don't have to make it even across the board,
because some people like certain types of categories more.
You just have to be aware of it of how much you're going to use it.
For example, if every encounter in the game had lobbers,
it would actually create a really high demand for a character that we don't have a whole lot of.
So you kind of want to gel, talk with your level designers.
Now swappers of course were special, they had some extra rules.
Most of which are not as complicated as we thought they were going to have to be.
So the first one is synergy with the matching half.
Now you may not always play the stink part of stink bomb.
when you buy a stink bomb, but you bought one of them and they come together in the same box.
So we at least know that you're putting them together.
We also know that there was two type of kids. Kids that loved to mix up everything
and then the slightly more OCD crowd that was like, no, everything must match perfectly.
So we had pretty good chance that there was a large group of people playing the swappers as a normal character.
So we tried to keep synergy.
We also limited each parts archetype to two, almost always.
This means that because there was five archetypes total in the game
and each swapped half could only be in two, you could never have a swapped
combination that filled all archetypes.
We had about two characters that could do it.
I think Trap Browser is one of them.
But it ended up being okay because he's not strong in all of them. He's kind of a jack-of-all-trades, pretty good at everything.
Once again, the legs were themed with the swap abilities, so characters with the rocket boots probably needed to have a rocket dash.
That was just kind of more of a design theme thing.
But we balance the characters like you were just playing 2 weaker characters at the same time.
I know that sounds really easy,
but it was just kind of a nice little mantra we had and it ended up working out really well.
The last one, and the most important one, and the biggest revelation for us,
because we had some fear,
was if anyone played Marvel Ultimate Alliance, we had a concept called Fusion,
where if you had...
Spider-Man and Wolverine and you put them together you get a
brand new Spider-Man Wolverine combo move. We did not want to
do that at all because it creates a ridiculous amount of
work. It's exponential work in fact. And exponential is a
terrifying word. And so what we had instead was move synergy.
Meaning if I had a character that had a fire top and an ice
bottom he did not get a new water attack.
We would have the things that get created and placed in the world have rules with how they interact with each other.
For example, Punkshock shoots electric bolts and she throws water balloons.
So you throw the water balloon, you shoot electricity at it, the electricity electrifies the water.
But we also had Zap, and Zap would leave a trail of water down.
So if you play as Punkshock and you shoot the electric at his trail, it electrocutes it.
They would just have a lot more kind of these happy, more emergent gameplay modes that we did not go and make that move.
We just had these rules of things in the world.
We even did this with characters. For example, Night Shift has an upgrade where every time he uppercuts someone, money comes out of them.
And Scratch has an upgrade where every time she collects money, she gets healed.
And so it actually made a very interesting vampire-cat-cleric-warrior combo.
that we totally did not account for and it just worked and we
didn't have to do any extra work. So to talk a little bit
about the utility, one example I'm going to use is Gorilla
Drilla. Gorilla Drilla has the straight ahead archetype, he
punches and he uses these little drills. He becomes stationary
when he does so, you hold it down and the drill stays out
there. Because he becomes stationary when he punches we
wanted to give him a kind of attack that could go much
further out ahead. So when I was designing him I was like, oh
hey, what's kind of a jungle-y thing? Oh I know, Jumanji,
wasn't that an awesome movie?
kind of was. But either way, the idea was that I was going to have these little, like
a bunch of animals kind of stampede forward in a straight line. Well, when I was just
kind of proxying it up, we had this monkey statue on one of the levels and I swiped the
monkey statue and I was just like, oh, we'll just make the monkeys run out.
And monkeys running around with just a canned monkey chimp sound playing was so hysterical
that I was like, screw it, I'm just going to have a bunch of crazy monkeys running around.
And so at first we started doing just crazy monkeys everywhere
and it started breaking him out of this archetype he was supposed to be in.
So we kept the aesthetic, but if you notice, when enemies are a
little bit closer, they'll all run to the same target and then
they kind of scatter around.
And that means that they still fall into that hallway
archetype, but it kind of gives you this sense of, oh, a bunch
of crazy freaking monkeys running around.
Actual power. This is probably the hardest one to communicate
to people. But this was how much damage is an enemy or a hero
actually outputting. Once again, we don't have recount. We don't
have some damage numbers running in the background. But we had a
very large perception problem. And not in the bad way. We had
characters being perceived as too powerful. This is where you
got that weird little spike from the damage numbers.
I talked enough about that.
So here's an example.
So here is FreeRanger.
Sorry, I use dev terms.
He's FreeRanger.
And we had a kid.
The kid played through the whole level.
He was actually in for level testing.
And he said, MagnaCharge is so OP.
He's totally OP.
I think he said that he was beast.
I guess beast is a thing kids say now.
But he had gotten to this encounter and now if you'll notice that little icon that's kind of flashing at the bottom.
In Skylanders if you have a certain element sometimes you're stronger in that area.
So this is Free Ranger. He's a melee character.
And he was very strong in this area.
He's an air character. He was of the right element.
It took the kid 20 seconds to beat this encounter.
We then said, okay, you think you can do it better with Magna Charge?
He's like, yeah, Magna Charge. It's OP. He's OP.
He did it with MagnaCharge in 36 seconds.
We didn't tell him how long it took,
we just asked him how awesome MagnaCharge was.
And even after doing this,
he still felt MagnaCharge was more powerful.
Managers took a lot longer. He even had to go and pick a guy up and run off the counter or find a cliff.
And I know that these things aren't totally controlled experiments.
He did one after he had done the other one.
He had already played this encounter though beforehand.
But it just showed that the perception of how powerful a move could be.
And in fact, the case of managers, the kid thought they were breaking the game with this ability.
it was a really hard challenge, because now I have a whole bunch of people saying,
you gotta totally get rid of Magneturge's ability,
and it's like, dude, he's not really breaking the game at all,
it's all in perception.
So that proved to be very difficult,
and I'm gonna go into a little bit more of that when I get to the communication section.
So that, once again, be mindful of why people are choosing
to play a certain character, because those reasons will change over time.
Moving on to the last one, the character within itself.
This is why you want to choose one ability over another ability.
So I just want to talk a little bit about how Skylanders upgrade, if you guys don't know already.
So with a Skylander, they start with two basic attacks, a primary and a secondary,
and then they can purchase up to four abilities in any order they want usually.
After they've bought all four of those, they then get to choose a path.
They either go, you know, path A or path B,
and then the soul gem is something that's kind of upgraded.
tangentially because they collected in the level.
So, Swapper's a little bit different, a little bit the same,
basically a slightly shorter list, but they have it twice,
one for the top and one for the bottom.
So, what we found that was really important is when we started
prototyping these characters, we would go crazy.
We'd be like, oh, we could have this upgraded,
you know, this upgraded, and we'd start prototyping
all the way up the upgrade path.
And it created kind of a lot of tangential moves that nobody
ever really played.
This is Starstrike.
Starstrike is one of my favorite characters.
She has two basic moves.
She shoots these little stars, and then she has a spin attack.
Now the spin attack will reflect projectiles.
And just as a whim, the designer said, oh, wouldn't it
be cool if she could project her own projectile back?
And it kind of created this whole final boss of every
Zelda game you've ever played type mechanic.
And
uh...
we just started making a whole new game out of it like hey can could you keep
that ball bouncing the entire level how how well can you do it
and it was
ridiculously fun
uh... so much fun in fact that we said we're just gonna make the whole darn
character all about this
uh... and so the first ability is to shoot the stars the second ability is to
spin
now the third ability
uh... the starfall one right here
uh... used to just kind of be a screen attack
it would just she'd she'd throw her her fan up in the air and you'd see all these stars kind of fall around her
um which had really nothing to do with her core kit and so what ended up happening was we changed
it so that when you do it it just creates a little turret and that turret basically provides even more
things that you can bounce she actually gets an upgrade where she makes like kind of the you know
the fourth uh not fourth of july new year's eve ball drop and that's a giant one that kind of
slowly comes down you can spike it away
And we found that the more and more we could make all the upgrades kind of keep reinforcing that base mechanic,
it made tutorials less important because every time you go into the store,
you're being reminded of how that character kind of plays,
and it makes every move useful because you're learning how their basic moves work.
So now when we design characters, we say,
get that core set right, I don't care about any upgrades,
make it fun just to do that first thing.
And then we move on from there.
So that brings me to the next big bullet, the validation and communication.
So we learned a lot of these things, we make a lot of changes,
but there's a lot of stakeholders in Skylanders,
and you all probably have a lot of stakeholders in your game,
and so you have to communicate how and why you're making these changes.
Kid testing, surveys and data is huge.
We collected as much data as we possibly can.
I actually ended up tricking the team to play the game
because we are in the toy business, we have a 3D printer
and we print a lot of bad toys
because we're trying to figure out something.
What I do is I also kind of paint Warhammer minis.
And so I was like, I'll just take these junk toys
and I'll paint them up.
And I said, hey, if you fill out a survey,
your name gets entered into a raffle.
And so in the end, we ended up getting almost 1,000 surveys
with a total of a little over 10,000 lines of actual feedback
from the team alone.
We sorted it all.
We prioritized it all.
We went through it all.
On top of that, we also had all the feedback from kids,
as well as all of our executive meetings.
And that gave us a really clear picture
of what types of people liked what types of characters.
Once again, we didn't want to make any character
that people were kind of okay with.
We would rather make a character that people loved or hated
because we wanted those kids arguing on the playground.
The big thing was we wanted to follow up with those stakeholders.
Even if we said, hey, we took your feedback
and it was absolute crap and we threw it away,
If you can say why you did that and here's the thing, getting
back to someone when they give you feedback makes them feel
like you actually listened to them.
It was tremendously helpful.
It's a little bit of work, but it actually ended up saving us
a bunch of work in the end.
When you're sitting in these meetings with a lot of people,
you really want to rely on those facts.
Remove yourself.
Because even myself, I am biased.
There's some characters I really like to play because
they match my style, and some characters I don't.
But when I know that, OK, we just got 50 kids in there,
and 45 of them all love this character,
that's pretty good in my book.
Avoid anecdotal stuff.
Use good data.
And create as many opportunities to get the
feedback as possible.
The more and more you ask feedback from someone, the
less they're going to feel like they need to swing by
your desk at 6 o'clock on a Friday to tell you about it.
Because they know that you're listening.
They know that you're going to come back to them.
And really track that character's history.
So Rollerball is a really good example of this.
We love her because we love roller derby.
But originally she was very badly received because when we first showed her
she didn't really have a whole bunch of VFX on her.
And there was a particular control scheme that she used to follow.
So once again she was kind of like a modal character.
You would tap a button to put her into this dash move.
Well the only way to get out of the dash move was to tap the button again.
The reason why we made you enter the mode in the first place was because
a younger kid has smaller hands and trying to hold multiple buttons at the same time.
it's kind of tricky, especially for a character's core move.
And so what would happen is they would push this mode, and they'd be like,
ah, I'm dashing forward, I want to get out of it, and they would let go of the stick.
And they've now let go of the controller,
and the character is still moving around without their control,
and they felt like they were completely disconnected from the character,
and it was just so uncontrollable.
The fix was ridiculously elegant and easy.
The designer just said,
oh, well if you let go of the stick you stop 2.
Fixed it.
The very next round of kid testing loved it.
Problem is that the damage had already been done on the executive level.
And so she had a huge amount of negative baggage
when we would go into these meetings.
What helped it was I went back, gathered all the feedback and said,
look, here's how the kids received it here.
We made this change and see how now all the kids are receiving it.
And even just starting the meeting with that and saying not,
hey, we fixed it, but saying this is what kids think now.
It immediately cleared a lot of people's expectations and the meeting moved much, much, much better.
And so it helped us a lot. It helped me stress out a lot less.
So that kind of ends this last part. I just have a little bit of a wrap up and then we can do some questions.
So the first thing is prioritize the balance for your audience.
You want to balance the priorities of your target audience. If you're making a PvP game, please make the PvP most important.
When it comes to balancing, start with your data, even the boring ones, and then use that feedback, and iterate, and iterate, and look at how, if you're seeing trends in your feedback, and make that to fun.
You really can't be all numbers like the title of the talk says, you really just gotta get it to where it feels right.
Especially when it comes to taking into consideration perception. If a move is perceived as being very powerful, it is powerful.
If a move is being perceived as very unpowerful, go add some big VFX and maybe an awesome sound
effect or even a screen shake.
It goes a long way.
And then lastly, communicate that feedback.
in a very non-biased removing yourself method.
Say, hey, look it, here's all the data,
here's how we got here.
If you understand why all those changes are made
and record them, it's gonna be so much easier.
And it makes making the next character even easier
because you're like, oh, we've seen this problem before.
Let's not do it again.
And that's gonna help you a lot.
So I think that wraps it up.
Does anyone have any questions?
Thank you.
Oh yeah, if you have questions, go to the mic.
If you ask a good question, you can just keep walking from the mic and grab a toy.
Hi there.
You went into a great detail about how you developed the player characters.
I'm actually curious, did you use a similar process when developing
the enemies for encounters?
Like, you only really touched on how much health they had at the start.
So, with the enemies,
we actually went through a lot of changes with the AI.
The big thing was we kept trying to make more and more variety.
Originally we had very few AI types and we just kind of copied them all over.
We also, all of our enemies had way too many hit points.
When we first started doing this we wanted a lot more tactical style combat system
where it's like, oh well I'm going to stun this guy and then I'm going to stun this guy
and while those two guys are stunned I'm going to go run over and punch this guy.
And that just wasn't, it wasn't being played that way, and it made everything seem very boring.
And so we ended up giving the enemies far less health,
and when you shorten the lifespan of your enemies, it changes your combat significantly.
And so we had to move all of the choices,
not to be, how am I going to kind of juggle all these things,
but when it came to AI placement and where they were at.
We originally started our AI being like,
oh, well they could all have victim events
and you need to use this AI and everything.
But because we literally make characters up to the last minute,
we very quickly realized that we need to set a benchmark for what the AI are
and then balance all the characters to it.
So the AI actually got nailed down pretty quickly.
So yeah.
Did that answer the question?
Are there any archetypes in particular that you had to drop because they just
they were too hard or they didn't work with it?
Or was it more that you just made the enemies too hard to begin with?
Um...
We definitely ended up cutting... Oh, the question... I'm supposed to repeat these questions.
The question was did we end up cutting any AI because they
just ended up being too hard. And the answer is not the AI
entirely. We ended up cutting particular functionality to
them. Blocking AI was a huge thing that we fought with for a
very long time. We also had lots of AI that kind of
uh... would summon minions or they would just be too hard and when we made them
simpler it kinda they lost the uniqueness in the first place so we're
like okay we're just gonna scrap that functionality
we ended up reusing the assets and repurposed but yeah
awesome thanks
So now that there's multiple Skyliner games and you have your large backlog of characters,
how do you go about ensuring that those older characters are still relevant, especially
with the introduction of swap force and the ability to change your characters?
So the question was how are the old characters still relevant?
In Swamp Horse, we did want to make the swappers a little bit
more important because, hey, their name is on the box.
But one thing that we did was any new functionality that all
the characters got, we had to go and add back to all of them.
For example, jump.
None of the characters could jump before.
We had to go back and make them all jump.
They all need to know how to rail slide, other
things like that.
We changed some of how their attack windows worked.
We used jump in our game as an escape.
We didn't want to make a hardcore platformer.
We put a couple little platforming puzzles off to the side.
But the big thing with Jump was
it would cancel whatever you were doing.
Because if I'm in mid-punch
and a bullet's coming at me,
the fact that the kid even decided to get out of the way
is a huge win for them.
And so we actually make them invulnerable
for a very couple frames.
And kids are like, oh, I narrowly missed that.
It's like, actually you didn't.
We made you invincible for a second.
But we had to go and do that for all the old characters to make them feel as responsive and everything like that.
And so whatever the new things will be in the future of Skylanders, it's very important that we...
We would, I think, as a parent who also has kids that play Skylanders,
I think that kids would feel really betrayed if the old ones just started becoming useless.
Thank you.
Could you go into a little bit of detail about the fair fight toggle that's in the PvP menu and...
given the weight that you guys had placed on balancing for PvP, why you even chose to expose that to the players?
The question was, there's a fair fight toggle in the PvP mode and why we even let people choose to do that.
Originally it wasn't exposed and what happened was, we did see some of our, you know...
vocal minority, I guess you could call them, who started to notice that we were tweaking
the dials underneath the hood. And so, because that was starting to be perceived as us cheating
to them or lying to them, we wanted to kind of expose it to them and say, all right, look,
if you really want to turn it off, you can go ahead and play with these settings. So,
it was one of those things where we observed that kids felt that they were getting a worse
experience because we were doing something for them.
Could you go into a little bit of detail about what was modified by the Fair Fight?
Uh, the question is what's modified? It's the health.
It's the health and damage resistance, so we actually kind of play with your health and your armor.
So if you're a character that is lower level and has less hit points,
we kind of give you a little bit more. It's like a golf handicap of like,
okay, well you're starting with really low health, you could be two-shot by this guy.
And once again, it's like that whole talk about we balance a super heavy such that they don't become super boring.
And it became kind of not fun when a character has just really stacked their health stat
and they have a huge amount of health and they go against a character who's very young.
Once again, the kids kind of took care of it themselves, but that was our effort under the hood to make it a little bit more fair.
Could I get a Skylander?
All right. How are we doing on time? Oh, we still got like, how much time we got?
Seven minutes. All right, we got time.
So, say you have a character that you're working on, and you have really opposite opinions from your feedback.
What do you usually do to try to satisfy as much as you can?
So the question was, what happens when two different...
points of feedback come against each other. One is we try to
get more feedback. It's very rare that if you ask ten people,
five of them are going to say one thing and five of them are
going to say the other. The other thing is it really
depends on the issue. So for example, Gorilla Drilla, he has
this ability to call down monkeys. Now the monkeys are
not very useful. They're a little bit chaotic.
And if you play tactically, you really want to go his other upgrade.
His other upgrade gives him a bigger range and it does more damage to his drills.
So if you're playing him, quote-unquote, the way that his base level is played,
it's more useful to go the drill route.
So we would have people who were kind of the number crunchers,
who would be like, why in the hell would you ever buy the monkeys?
They're just so unreliable and everything.
And the counter was always, because they're goddamn monkeys.
And so...
It was one of those things where it wasn't really a problem.
But then in other cases, we would have stuff where, for
example, RollerBall has the Soul Gem.
The Soul Gem allows her to headbutt a target, and it
draws a beam between her and her target.
And it works like a maypole.
If you skate around and you have the beam, it then does
damage to anything that touches the beam.
Now, the fact that it already took me almost a minute to
explain how that rule worked.
kind of created a lot of red flags for people.
And people were like, it's gonna be too hard,
it's gonna be too complicated.
And so we were like, okay.
And so that was starting to get negative.
And in that case, we just focus tested that.
And every kid just was like, oh, it's like a maypole.
And I'm like, oh, I guess that's common knowledge for kids.
I thought maypole was like knitting.
Like no one got it, but every kid got it.
And we were like, okay, I guess the kids decided it.
So in that case, once again, we went to more data,
more people, or people closer to the thing
and it ended up working.
You can get a toy if you want.
I'm not trying to hoard them. If you ask a question, you can take a toy.
Alright, we'll take two more questions. I think that'll be good, right?
Two, one.
It sounds like kids can be a bit more irrational and predictable, and then
older players can be a bit more elegant and complex in, I guess, their play styles.
Could you go into some
pros and cons for testing with children and testing with adults, and uh...
do you think that any game could be useful by having children test it?
So the question was the pros and cons of kid testing and their usefulness in any game.
So absolutely any game can be benefit from kids.
So with kids, the pros are that they're brutally honest,
they have no qualms about your feelings at all.
And additionally...
A kid is not afraid to fail like an adult is. Amazingly we've had kids who, there was
a bug, a free ranger had a lightning attack. Now the lightning attack was meant to stun
enemies and it would put them in this kind of electrocuted state, you can see their skeleton,
and it would arc to targets and the more enemies that it arced to, the more damage it would
do.
Well, what it meant is if you just hit an enemy, like a giant golem who couldn't be electrocuted,
it did one point of damage. Now, a golem has 350 hit points. Sorry, spoiler everyone.
This kid beat the golem using the lightning bolt.
He played for 15 minutes using the lightning attack over and over and over again.
And we're like, oh my god, I can't even watch this kid.
But he saw a number popping up.
He knew he was making things.
And he was not afraid to just do it the hard way.
Same thing with people who kept missing a jump.
They would die and die and die and die and die.
And they were like, oh yeah, it's fine.
We would ask them, was the game too hard?
And they're like, no, it was just fine.
Because the whole concept of dying or failure hadn't been ingrained in them by society that you're a stupid idiot if you fail all time
Whereas parents are even a even an even even worse than parents. God forbid you test a teenager
they feel that they're playing a kids game and if they're seen not being able to completely
trounce the kids game, that they are horrible. And so they are less likely to even try things.
And so it was pretty terrifying how afraid of failure some adults are when they wouldn't
want to try something or something like that. So yeah, I mean really kids are almost all
pros other than
A lot of sugar is kind of difficult to maintain when it comes to kids.
We do a lot of testing and you got to get good people to run your kid testing sessions.
And also you can't always listen to what they're saying.
You have to watch what they're doing.
So, when we do our kid testing, we have three cameras, one on their face,
one on the portal and one on the game.
And we watch what they're doing.
And so, if a kid is...
his face is getting frustrated or he's not ever pushing a
button, it tells us a million things that they may not come
out and openly say.
We'll take one more.
First of all, thanks a lot for the presentation.
I thought it was great in terms of content flow,
the little examples and illustrations.
My question was related to the five play reasons
which change over time.
How did you measure them and compare them?
OK, so the first thing he said was I was awesome.
What was the next part again?
The question was about how do we balance the difficulty as it progressed throughout the game?
No, how were the five play reasons measured or compared?
which change over time? The five reasons you showed?
Oh, oh, how we measure that. So that was done by a lot of the
survey data that we got from kids. We would also have a lot
of kids be repeats. And so we would start to see that kids
would start to get really good with particular characters. And
so we would be like, oh, we want to put this character into
testing again. Make sure that we bring this one person back
because they're
they're the slobber-toothed player, they're going to give us different feedback than something else.
So we could then use it as a data point to be like,
okay, here's what a kid who's played this character for several hours
and is at the end of the game thinks of it
versus someone who's never played this character before.
So it was lots and lots of kids.
We actually didn't really include our adult data
because most of our adult data we couldn't track the overtime.
It was all kid testing that we got that from.
So how could you compare that?
Let's say appearance mattered the most in the first 30
seconds, how could you come up with that metric, or that
number, or that data point?
So the number for the very first one.
The number was really just done by a lot of us and our gut of how important it was to them.
For example, if something got them to walk away or put the controller down or they were clearly disengaged
and they were like, hey can I, like they would literally come out and be like, can I play another game?
Or they'd be like, I already played this game for a couple minutes, can I have my 70 bucks or whatever?
that was like, okay, this is ridiculously important to them.
If they would then say, oh, okay, well, no, I'm kind of,
like, I'm liking this, and they'll tell you they're liking it,
but you could see on their face that was kind of,
and then if, once again, you know when a kid is excited,
you know when they're engrossed, when they're like,
I just want to keep playing, you know,
when it's like, hey, do you want more soda?
And they don't even hear you,
because they're just engrossed.
We use that as kind of a way to do the ratings.
Thanks.
All right, I think we're good.
So thank you guys very much.