Welcome everyone to the Gaming for Good Philanthropy as a Business Strategy session.
We appreciate you taking the time to join us today.
Before we jump into the topic, we thought it would be helpful for Derek and I to introduce
ourselves.
My name is Dan Widner and I'm the Vice President for the West Region of the American Cancer
Society and co-creator of our Gamers vs. Cancer program.
I lead the execution of our enterprise-wide vision, direction, and strategy through major
gifts, corporate accounts, distinguished events, and innovative solutions, where each of our
departments have revenue-targeted goals that we set and work to achieve to actually help
support our mission efforts.
I'm very excited to be here to talk to you today about the work that a team and I are
doing in helping to lead.
the fight against cancer within the gaming industry,
because I myself have been an avid gamer
from a very young age.
I've known, I've now been able to blend a lifelong passion
with the ability to support a mission and a cause
that is very personal to me,
given that my family has been significantly impacted
by cancer.
And now I'll turn it over to Derek.
Thanks, Daniel. Hi, I'm Derek Morton. I'm CEO of Flowplay.
Flowplay is a group of 60 people in Seattle. We make casual MMO games.
Our most successful games are Vegas World, Casino World, and Our World.
These are virtual worlds where people from all over the world get together.
They have an avatar, they run around, they have parties, they go to restaurants,
they play games together. We have about half a million monthly active users.
So during today's presentation, we're going to cover the following.
You're going to hear from Derek on how Flowplay has approached working with charity partners in the past,
and the process that he took as a company in finding the right nonprofit to work with.
I'm going to talk a little bit about the mission of ACS and give you some insight on why and how we ended up creating the Gamers vs. Cancer program.
Derek is going to cover the creation of the partnership between Flowplay and the American
Cancer Society, talking about how it is that our teams collaborated on the project itself.
I'm going to then go into the impact that the gaming industry has had on social good and give
some insight on why others might want to support nonprofits across the world if you haven't already
done so. Derek is then going to go into detail.
on the specifics of what the activation actually is
and what the teams ended up creating together.
We will also cover how you can get involved,
talking about some action items and some next steps
that you can take to immediately drive social good
through your line of work.
As this presentation is going on,
Derek and I are going to be monitoring the chat,
answering any questions that you have.
We also dedicated some time at the end.
To allow us the ability to go through and answer any questions that we might have missed. And with that, we're going to go ahead and jump right in.
Hi. Well, I'll tell you about how Flowplay started getting me into charitable giving. It started with a couple world events where there was an earthquake and tsunami in Japan. It was an earthquake and
And so, there was an interest in the company to sort of like do what we could to sort of send money to support those causes.
And to do that, we reached out to our players, we created elements in the game that would help them contribute to that fundraiser.
And then we wrote a check and sent it off to the different relief organizations in Japan and Nepal.
We got so much interest in that from our players and from our employees as well.
We decided we would make this more structured.
We started budgeting for it in our yearly planning,
setting aside what portion of our revenue and profits
we would apply towards charitable giving throughout the year.
So we started setting aside this money
and started looking for nonprofits to fundraise for.
found a great organization called Girl Start, a group called Home for our Troops, which
builds houses for wounded vets, people that were working with human trafficking rescue.
We built makers labs for underprivileged schools, all kinds of stuff, but we were kind of, it
was kind of random.
We would hear about a charity and say, Oh, yeah, let's pick those guys.
And we would go write them a check and, you know, maybe go volunteer some hours as well.
So things were still a bit ad hoc.
But in 2018, we decided to take a much more structured approach.
Not only did we set aside money in our budget, but we thought that we would really hone in
on what do our customers and what do our employees support?
What would they like to see as support?
How could we really get everyone involved and excited about being part of doing fundraisings
for charities?
So we started with some community surveys.
We started surveying our players.
Asking them, you know, what's touched your life?
Who do you contribute money to?
What's of interest to you when it comes to philanthropy?
And we did the same thing with our employees as a group.
We met together and just talked about, you know,
what would you love to get behind as a fundraising event
and for Flowplay to be part of?
And we really run into research,
like what would really have the greatest impact on our community?
So after talking to our community members,
talking to our employees,
cancer kept coming up again and again and again.
Our players are primarily women,
and primarily women over 50.
And for them, either through friends, family,
or them personally, cancer had touched many of their lives,
and it was a recurring theme throughout some of the surveys
and some of the conversations I had with the players.
So, knowing that cancer was an important issue for our players, we started doing research on, you know, who is making the biggest impact, who is a really great organization to work with, and has, you know, the majority of their fundraising going towards actually helping people.
Through all this research, going to Charity Navigator, looking through what cancer charities were doing their mess work, we came across American Cancer Society, and it's been great for us.
Thank you.
Very well recognized, both in the research area and the amount of money that goes to the actual work of curing cancer and helping people that have cancer.
So we were very excited to find them and begin to form a partnership with them.
So, to expand on what Derek was just talking about,
so the American Cancer Society is a national nonprofit with the sole mission of saving lives, celebrating lives.
and leading the fight into a world without cancer.
I've provided a few key statistics on the slide
that you can see to showcase the impact
that cancer has had on so many individuals.
As you can see, one in three people within the United States
will be diagnosed with cancer in their lifetime.
Globally, in 2018, there are more than 17 million
cancer cases and 9.5 million cancer deaths worldwide.
By 2040, the global burden is expected to grow to 27.5 million new cases and 16.3 million cancer deaths,
simply due to growth and aging of the general population.
In the past few months, with the COVID-19 crisis, our mission
and services have become even more vital for cancer patients,
many of whom already have a compromised immune system.
and are more vulnerable more than ever.
To combat this, we have had to shift our needs
for cancer patients and communities facing the pandemic.
We've added video conferencing to our 24-7 cancer helpline
and provided valuable information and guidance on cancer.org
in order to help keep patients safe and well-informed.
We've also continued our efforts to fund critical research,
as Derek had mentioned.
Unfortunately...
COVID-19 has had a tremendous impact on the ability for labs
not only to remain open so that they can continue the research,
but also in the ability for organizations
to actually be able to fund them.
Like many nonprofits, we are doing everything that we can
to continue our efforts to fund researchers
during this challenging time.
And if we don't, the long-term effects could be significant.
Lastly, we are working to promote health equity and ensure equal access to cancer research,
education, screenings, and treatment for all individuals. The American Cancer Society and
American Cancer Society Cancer Action Network, or as we call them ACS-CAN, are committed to
addressing the unequal burden of cancer by reaching individuals in underserved communities
in collaboration with community partners through our advocacy work.
This, the reason I'm bringing this up is because anytime that you work with a nonprofit,
their central core mission is going to be what it is that they are driving from a social good perspective.
Whenever you communicate with them, their mission is always going to be top priority.
It's the main reason that they create partnerships.
We're looking to expand not only from a fundraising perspective, but also drive awareness in anything that we do.
And so I wanted to give you some context in terms of why we are here, why we are helping drive social good.
That is our mission is our core value.
And so all of these are reasons why opportunities like the engagement through our Gamers vs. Cancer program are so vital in us allowing to support that critical mission.
Last year, myself and Maya Al-Sazh were able to create the Gamers vs. Cancer program.
We have been having success through partnerships within the gaming industry, which is how the program actually got started.
Organizationally, we strategize on how it is that we can maximize our partnerships through a more unified approach versus kind of a segmented one based off of just individual partnerships.
The ultimate goal of our program was to be able to help partners achieve their own goals and to
It supports our mission, not only as I mentioned before,
through fundraising, but also in driving awareness
within the gaming industry.
The program itself focuses in on engaging the industry
within the five areas that you see on the slide.
The first is partnerships.
So looking at how it is that we can engage software,
hardware, and e-sports corporations.
Our partnership with Flowplay is actually a great example
of how it is that we've partnered with a game developer
to work on an activation to address both what I mentioned,
helping to raise funds and drive awareness.
Second is streaming.
We've had great success in live stream fundraising
with content creators to support our mission
through charity streams that they host.
Creators like Little Simsie and Greg Miller,
aka Game Over Greggie.
We've been able to raise hundreds of thousands of dollars.
From kind of funny games have collectively helped us raise hundreds of thousands of dollars.
Which leads to events. We've hosted our own and partnered with other nonprofits to host in person and digital.
Nowadays, much more digital gaming events and have also been chosen as the charity of choice through e sports tournaments like the recent PUBG charity showdown event.
We have been featured as a beneficiary on multiple bundles through Humble Bundles platform in partnership with developers like EA and Bandai Namco.
These platforms alone have helped raise millions of dollars over the last five years to support our mission.
We've expanded opportunities through merchandise collaboration.
You know, we looked at how it is that we could create specific merchandise with a partner,
maybe aligning it with a awareness Cancer Month or even in alignment through an event
or a digital activation that we create.
We are by no means the only nonprofit partner.
And we have a number of
people who have been working within the gaming community to support their mission.
Some of which have been doing it much longer than us.
While others, I can tell you, are just now starting to create strategies and are looking to see how it is that they can not only engage their existing constituents, but even the community as a whole.
And so we're going to have to expand on what the community is currently engaging with through game developers.
In addition to content streamers, establishing a presence at gaming events, creating an ambassador program, and securing hardware and software donations to expand our reach and give potential.
This multi-pronged approach allows the gaming community to truly take ownership in the fight against cancer.
We are tapping into opportunities to incorporate cost marketing as a major strategy for free-to-play games.
And as I mentioned before, our partnership with Flowplay is a great example of this, which Derek is going to cover in greater detail now.
So once you've found a charity that you really are passionate for, your community is passionate for,
it'd be easy to start getting a fundraiser going in your game and just write a check to them.
What I really recommend is that you partner closely with the charity that you've chosen.
You'd be surprised how eager charities are to work with you and to work closely with you
to create a really great event. They know where their money is going and what the issues are
and can help you identify very targeted fundraisers. It's my belief that, you know,
just raising money for cancer or some other great charity
If you can narrow it down to help people understand exactly an issue that you're going to be dealing with and exactly where the money is going, it's a much more successful campaign because people really get a better sense of the help that they're going to be creating through this program.
Our two PR teams work really closely together, so we're creating social media events, we're creating
PR releases both before and after the fundraiser.
So it's great for you to get visibility,
both from the efforts of the charity you're working with
and both from the PR that your own team is doing
to announce what the event was
and what the result of the event was.
So four things to be sure to do.
Make sure you're highlighting a very specific cause.
And also get your creative team involved so that they can bring some of what you as the game company can do to really make this successful.
You know, we're the creative people. Most of the time the charity people are not super creative.
They have a mission, they have things that they're working on, but it's really up to you to come up with something super fun and super creative to engage the community.
We also encourage you to integrate a lot of this stuff into your live ops.
and your game promotion calendar,
so that you're announcing what's going on
and keeping people informed all along the way
and allowing people in your game
to actually spread the word themselves.
We keep these charity promotions live for about four weeks
because we're on a two-week sprint
and that seems to be about enough time
to have a really successful promotion.
Excuse me.
The keys to a successful fundraiser, I believe, as I said, make it specific.
People want to know where's the money going to and how is it going to help people.
Our most recent campaign was to provide hotel rooms for frontline workers
so that these frontline workers that are working in COVID wards don't have to go home
to infect their family or have a place to rest in between their shifts.
So this really was much better than just saying, hey, we're raising money for frontline workers.
It's like.
We are raising money for frontline workers because they need a place to stay in between their shifts.
So that really brings it home.
Make it easy in the game.
You know, buy this thing and all the money you spend will go towards this charity.
Also, make it a benefit for the player.
If you buy this thing, make something in the game happen.
that benefits them so that they get a little something back out of it as well.
It's also really good if it's socially engaging, if there's a way for them to actually buy one for someone else,
to share that, so that if you're spreading the word and allowing them to, you know,
share their philanthropy with other players in the game.
And also make it, it's really optimal if you're, make it easy,
either through chat or other mechanisms you have in terms of
And so, we're going to talk about the game development transcript.
And we're going to talk about chat boards and things where people can
announce, hey, I'm part of this fundraiser,
and I want to get everybody else involved in it as well.
Next slide.
So Derek shared how to create a successful fundraiser.
So I want to dive deeper into the why.
We have an unparalleled opportunity to cultivate gaming as a platform
The goal of the game development
transcript is to help players
frequently connect and help with one another. By combining
gameplay, emerging technologies,
inspired talent, the commercial gaming industry can extend
these communities to invoke monumental social change.
Although not all nonprofits are the same, we create
partnerships by looking at how we can help solve problems
and to help strengthen the brand.
As the middle of the slide deck shows,
we are looking at the
game development transcript.
The goal of the game development transcript is to help players
frequently connect and help with one another. By combining
gameplay, emerging technologies, inspired talent, the commercial gaming industry can extend these communities to invoke monumental social change.
Although not all nonprofits are the same, we create partnerships by looking at how we can help solve problems and to help solve problems.
Although not all nonprofits are the same, we create partnerships by looking at the game development transcript.
By partnering with nonprofits, you can create value that actually aligns with your own priorities.
Research suggests that 85% of Americans will switch to a product if the company supports a cause they believe in.
And that figure jumps to 90% for millennials.
The gaming industry's reach has the potential to address the world's most pressing issues.
For us.
Partners allow us to help save more lives from cancer than ever before.
With a 26% drop in cancer death rates in the United States since 1991,
this steady decline makes us even more determined to accelerate this progress.
And it's important to note that while all of the overall cancer mortality rates are dropping,
populations who are marginalized are bearing a disproportionate burden.
A preventable death and disease.
Meaning there is still more work to be done.
Meaning there is huge opportunity, right,
for us to be driving social good within the gaming industry.
Partnerships within our organization
through the industry itself demonstrate just one way
at which the gaming industry has had a tremendous impact
on driving social good globally.
And now Derek is going to dig into
exactly how our partnership has been implemented.
Thanks, Daniel.
I wanted to give you an example of what we did
so I could sort of help you come up with some ideas
for your own games and how you might integrate
this kind of charity fundraising inside your products.
In our game, this is our game called Vegas World.
One of the major ways we make money
is we sell people good luck charms.
These charms, if you purchase them...
Next slide.
So, we're going to go through a couple of different ways
that we can increase the odds of winning in the game.
So, if you're playing slots, if you're playing blackjack,
any of our social casino games, you will win more coins back
if you're using these lucky charms.
So, they're very popular.
They drive about 85% of our revenue.
So, it's a major, major thing in our products.
Next slide.
We also, through our party system, allow people to group together and have parties in their hotel room in the game.
And through this party board, they're able to create these events around the charity
so that everyone in the community knows these events are going on
and can easily click a link and go to the party and be part of this charity fundraiser.
This is what it looks like to be in a party in Vegas World.
You see the avatars of all the players.
There's chat, there's people buying these charms.
And you see that people are actually in this room buying charms as we go.
At a charity fundraiser party, people would be buying, in the case of ACS,
American Cancer Society charms that are distributed to everybody in the room.
They buy one for themselves, but everybody else in the room gets one as well.
And later when they go play our games, our slots games and blackjack games,
that gives them a benefit in the game, so it's super social.
And this is just an example of where the American Cancer Society charm was placed in our purchase
merchandising.
It was 25 gems.
You want to keep the price point fairly low so it's really easy for people to buy a lot
of them and share them.
If you set the price point too high, you won't have a lot of activity.
But what you want to create is like this sense of a lot of activity, a lot of charms being
purchased or a lot of whatever you're building in your own game.
I feel like it's really exciting and really interesting for everybody.
So we just finished our most recent successful campaign.
As I mentioned, we were working with,
the American Cancer Society has what's called the Hope Lodge.
And while the Hope Lodge is a place
for cancer patients to stay while they're traveling
to go for therapy and treatments,
during COVID-19 situations,
it was temporarily switched to be used
to allow frontline hospital workers to rest.
remain separated from their families so they didn't spread the disease to their family.
So we did a specific fundraiser around this.
So the reason I believe this is successful is it's super timely.
COVID-19, this was run during May, so it was obviously very timely during May.
The players got bonuses for being part of this, for buying the charm for the Hope Lodge.
They got benefits for their friends when they buy one for themselves, they get benefits for everybody else.
And it was easy to share because everybody could create these parties where everybody could come and have a good time and support a great cause.
The result of this was that we raised $55,000 just for this one campaign.
32% of our MAU went to one of these parties, so about a third of all players were engaged
somehow in this fundraising effort.
And literally 28% of our monthly active users actually made a monetary contribution toward
buying these charms.
So this is one of many that we've done for the American Cancer Society.
We've raised, I believe,
I think it's over $300,000 for ACS so far.
So we are super excited about continuing to do this.
We're going to do another one with a different fundraising
angle this October.
Great, thanks, Eric.
Again, I think that it shows just
how you're able to connect an engagement activation
for your own constituents and tying it directly
to a mission effort.
That's where I think there is huge synergy in terms
of being able.
with the nonprofit.
And so now we want to showcase how you can get more involved and what are some next steps.
So first off, you can reach out to nonprofit partners.
You can connect with, if you already know that there is a cause that organizationally
you hold dear, near and dear, reach out to a nonprofit to see if there is the ability
to create an activation.
If you don't have a nonprofit, you can reach out to us.
You can do a number of things, right?
And then secondly, what you could do
is you can also connect with your community,
like what Derek was saying and how they approached it.
Finding out what is near and dear to your community
and aligning that cause through an activation for them.
Secondly, and Derek mentioned this previously,
you know, incorporate the creative and innovative
way that you have built out your own business and company and bring that to the nonprofit.
If, as Derek has mentioned, the nonprofit isn't necessarily going to have answers and how it is
that they can engage the community, especially nowadays with a lot of nonprofits in the early
stage of just looking to see how they can incorporate the community into their mission.
And so a lot of times you're going to need to be that subject matter expert.
Secondly, you're going to want to discuss goals early on.
What are your priorities?
How does it align with the priorities of the nonprofit
that you're going to be connecting with?
I think it's important to also note
that nonprofits are also held by specific laws
in terms of what they can and can't do within partnerships.
And understand that, you know,
if you can't equate it to how you might have worked
with a vendor in the past,
or how you might have worked with another business partner.
It's slightly different, though not as much as you might think.
But just wanted to preface that there might be differences
in the two approaches
when you initially start to have communication.
And then last but not least, share the impact.
You have created an activation.
You've engaged your constituents.
You've really been able to build out something
and build it behind a cause, right,
that's either important to you or important
to your own constituents.
And share what that impact is after the activation has taken place.
Derek, is there anything that you might want to add to this?
I think the main thing I would add is that, you know,
there's probably many people out there.
They're saying, you know, this sounds like a great idea.
We'd love to give to charity and, you know, get something going
with our community around it.
But you'll be you'll be shocked and you'll be surprised that
what the real impact later is for you.
It's one thing to just carry out a fundraiser and donate money.
It's another when you start to see the feedback from your players,
the appreciation that they have for the fact that you're doing good
and that you're helping the community and the same thing with your employees.
The feedback that you'll get from your employees is amazing as well.
So we've provided additional time for us to go through and look to see if there are any questions in the chat that we haven't been able to address just yet.
I did have two questions for Derek to kind of build upon what it is that he's discussed earlier. So, Derek, you talked about
how it is that you went out and you connected with your community to find out what cause was near and dear to their hearts.
You know, what are some best practices that you've seen over the course of the last couple of years in doing an activation like this?
that others could possibly take.
Well, the surveys and emails and having people respond
by electronic communication are great.
But I was uniquely lucky in that we have a virtual world.
So I walk around in it.
Most people know who I am.
I have a, my name in the game is Dignania.
So people say hi to me.
They know I'm the CEO of the company.
And so I'm kind of a popular guy.
But my advantage there is that I get to actually talk
to people in the game one-on-one
and talk to them about their stories.
You know, if somebody sends me a message saying,
hey, you know, cancer is very important to me.
It's a charity that I support and would like to see you guys support.
I can actually go in the game and talk to them about that and find out, you know, how
has cancer touched your life and how can we, you know, create a campaign that's meaningful
for you.
Great.
So my last question would be, how has the impact of driving a social good campaign through
your business impacted you as an individual?
Well, probably the biggest thing that's happened is I was asked a couple of years ago to join a group called the CEOs against cancer, part of the Washington group.
And later this year in February, I actually became the chairman. So today I'm the chairman of the Washington CEOs against cancer.
It was an organization that takes, you know, leaders around the state to come together and do big events and fundraisers to try and make a contribution for this important research.
And supporting the community of people that are the patients and the people that are dealing with the cancer issue.
Great. All right, so with that, we have concluded our session.
We want to thank you so much for joining in the dialogue through the chat and just being a part of the session as a whole.
We would love to hear, you know, in future state, if you ever do connect with a nonprofit.
and end up creating an activation. We'd love to hear from you. You can reach out to
myself and Derek individually, or you could reach out to us at gamersversuscancer at cancer.org.
Again, thank you so much for being a part.