Hello, are you all exhausted? No? Okay. Then it's your job to
keep me awake because, oh boy, I'm exhausted. I'm also somewhat
losing my voice. So I need you to be the loud ones this time.
Well, you know, how many of you have been to my talks before? A
few of you.
I'm known for giving these incredibly dense brain blast
talks with 150 slides and tons of references and facts and
whatever. This is not that talk. Not only because I'm losing my
voice, but just because this topic, I agonized over how to
give this talk, to be honest. I've rewritten it more than
almost any talk I've ever given. And guys, I've been doing this a
long time.
It's something that I feel really deeply and passionately
about and it's something that I take very, very seriously. This
is co-listed with the advocacy track and not just the design
track. And it's for a reason. The other thing about this talk
though is it isn't entirely going to be about games. Right?
Social is in the title of this talk.
And as soon as we're dealing with people,
we aren't necessarily entirely in the realm
of just entertaining.
So, here's the thing.
I'm just gonna say it bluntly.
Social spaces aren't just games.
Like from the get-go.
There are a few of you with whom I remember
sitting and having discussions.
You're here in the room, it's so good to see you.
Literally now, gosh.
almost 20 years ago having arguments about whether or not we were even making games when we
were making the early virtual worlds and the MMOs. You know, when I was making Ultima Online, I
would have arguments with people like Eric Zimmerman about this.
I told them bluntly, I'm not sure that's what I do. I'm not sure I make games. I think I design
places and worlds and societies and not just games. They just happen to have a lot of games in
them. Things that you can stumble across and play. But really, a huge amount of the work was
going into simulating things like tailoring and rabbit hunting and running a shop. Not
necessarily what we think of as games. I used to say I was making worlds.
virtual worlds. And I really do believe that when you start
working in the arena of online social spaces, that's what
you're doing. Even though those days are long gone and you know,
MMOs are not the new hotness anymore. They have not been in
quite a while. But if you are making a social VR space, a
social AR space, a lot of people are trying to do, you aren't
just making a game, you're designing a society.
When you choose to take up those tools, connectivity,
persistence, identity, you are going to design that society
either on purpose or by accident.
And sorry to say, I'm seeing a lot of people
doing it by accident.
So I'm here to try to persuade you to do it on purpose.
We'll start with the obvious thing. This should be a
terrifying responsibility. The problem is we're all blinded by
snow crash. There's still people out there. I know we have some
folks from Oculus in the audience. There are people in
leadership at Oculus saying yes, I dream of building snow crash.
No, snow crash is bullshit.
It's not where we are really headed.
And it's a great book and a really compelling vision, but
we need to be aware of what we're actually working with.
The very first time I met Bruce Sterling, a different
cyberpunk science fiction writer, I had already been
working in online worlds.
I asked him point blank, how did you get virtual reality?
So wrong.
Wasn't really a fair question.
I want to tell you an anecdote that happened while speaking
with an extremely powerful and famous executive at a very
large blue company whose last name starts with Z and ends
with Uckerberg. I was interviewing for a job there.
And I had talked with people all day long and last
interviews with him. And
He says to me, well, I've heard good things
from everybody all day, and everybody's been asking
you questions for eight solid hours,
so what questions do you have for me?
And I said, well, I'd like to know your opinion.
What do you think are the social and ethical implications
of social virtual reality and connected augmented reality?
This was his answer.
I may have ranted at him for a little while and then not gotten the job. But I also would
not have taken it at that point. And probably will never work for them again now that I've
said that. But that's okay. Let's get real for a minute. We are talking about companies
that are trying to create world spanning social VR and AR structures and haven't done basic
work on what online communities are. I often say I'm not entirely sure Facebook understands
right? Adding you willy nilly to groups. Is anybody a fan of that one? Features like that.
So the idea that people are out there building constructs like this without doing some basic
lesson learning is a little bit terrifying to me given the way that society has developed and
the amount of power that has ended up in the hands of large internet companies. And it should
be a little bit terrifying to you too.
So I promised some lessons. How many of you here are actually working on building social
virtual reality experiences? Awesome. How about, how many people are working on like trying to
cash in on Pokemon Go and build social AR experiences? A few. Okay, good. So let's get
real and look at some specific lessons here before I go all lofty on you.
is, I'm going to call out actually a particular company, but I think their response to this
incident was actually really good. So I want to preface that. Do all of you recall the case of
the virtual groping in quiver, quiver, VR, whichever? Okay. Good. So a woman logged into this
game, which apparently is about doing VR archery, and a stranger named, I think it was
big bro some number, walked up and started virtually groping her.
response of the company, they were not logged on at the time.
They did not know about the incident until an article was
written.
when they found out, to their credit, they immediately put in a bunch of features so that
gropers, bodies could not see one another anymore when they came into close proximity. They
expanded what they called the personal bubble. And they added a new gesture that they would
like to add to the vocabulary of social VR. One where you can do and create like this
exploding blue force field that turns the harasser invisible and prevents them from
interacting with you.
And they were very up front, immediately posted a post mortem
about what had happened and encouraged everybody,
hey, we need to take this stuff seriously.
And major props to them.
But let's be straight about what should have happened.
What should have happened is that the people
who were logged on 24-7 monitoring behavior
were called by a harassment call,
appeared with the wrath of God,
turned the asshole into a toad and banned him for life.
Right?
This is actually best practice in online community spaces.
Now, I understand that we have a lot of small companies
that don't have the resources to maintain
customer support on call 24-7,
that don't have all of the tools and the background
and the technology to be able to do this.
And I don't care.
Because if you host an online community where people can cause harm to another person, you are on the hook.
And if you can't afford to be on the hook, don't host an online community.
I wish there were a different answer. I don't think there is.
Now, you're the government of that space. You're hosting real people.
You should want to be doing this.
You should understand the idea that...
You may not quite know how.
That's fine.
Let's talk about ways you can do it.
The first thing people need to understand is that you
actually need to build all of your moderation structure, all
of this, on a due process.
You actually need to institute a rule of law.
That means starting from the very beginning, actually having
such a code of law, a code of conduct. You need some kind of
code of conduct, end user license agreement, terms of
service written in plain English that every player
affirmatively signs up to the first time they log in and they
swear an oath, I will abide by this. And it needs to be posted
everywhere and you need to be reinforcing this as a cultural
thing. Every day. Right?
This is kind of what we do in the real world.
And we're not even entirely satisfied
with how well it works here, right?
But you don't get to abdicate doing it.
It has enormous benefits,
just not only as a cultural thing,
but also for clearing up edge cases.
Because you're going to be fighting
an awful lot of edge cases.
The most concrete practical thing is a tool that has been in use for, oh gosh, I went
asking and the earliest virtual world I could find that was doing it were games on America
online and genie.
Anybody who here doesn't know what those are because they're too old.
And that's a concept called the circular buffer.
And this is a very simple thing that if you weren't using voice chat you could all go
and implement right now.
unfortunately using voice chat so you're screwed. But simply
recording, keeping track of the last minute to five minutes of
every single interaction each client sees and storing it.
Discarding the stuff that's five minutes old and always entering
the most recent stuff so that when something like this
happens and no admin is online.
When they hit the report button, it is attached as impartial
evidence that can be adjudicated.
The Quiver story, how do you pronounce that anyway?
Quiver, quiver, anyway.
That story, I absolutely believe the woman.
I absolutely believe that story happened.
There's corroboration and all the rest.
At the same time, believe me, you will have cases where it
will turn into.
One says, the other says. If you don't have tools like this, you are literally going to spend your
entire monthly profit on the first call. Standing there mediating between two people who are
yelling at one another. It is actually cheaper to ban every single user who calls for help. I
know, this sounds horrendous. Banning every person who calls for help is cheaper.
than helping them, right? Because they cost so much money to support. So you need to have
incontrovertible evidence. I have no idea how small shops are going to do this with voice
logs. Worse, I think you need to do more than just voice logs. I think you need to record
every single gesture so that when somebody does this, the CS person can replay it back and
verify who started the fight.
It's not going to be cheap. But you need to do it. The gesture was a great touch, but banning
wasn't mentioned in the article. A key lesson from all kinds of social spaces and virtual
worlds is that offenders repeat. The number one player killer in Ultima Online was
personally responsible for murdering over 4,000 people.
The people who engage in this behavior do it over and over again. And if your social VR or AR
system does not have a persistent account system with persistent identity that players invest
into, you're effectively making every player get away scott free. Because all they need to do is
create a brand new account every single time they log in.
Actions like this matter more in VR, precisely because VR embodies us and makes us feel like
we're really there. Okay? There's a lot of talk about, oh, well, we'll just block, we'll just
mute, we'll do a personal bubble. It's wholly inadequate. Okay? Let's take a simple thought
experiment. One avatar interpenetrates another avatar in some way that somebody finds
uncomfortable. They, you know, they, you know, they, you know, they, you know, they, you know,
do something nasty and start dry humping the other avatar. Great. So the personal bubble kicks
in and the other avatar can't be seen. In theory that person is now okay, right? It's the same
logic as well, I'll just block them on Twitter and everything will be fine. What about the
third party who is still watching? You're going to be still just as angry about this incident
when you get told about it by the third party, right?
Block and mute have never been adequate enough tools for
managing these sorts of problems in online settings.
How many of you have read the original rape in cyberspace
article? I should ask that more precisely. How many of you
working in social VR and AR have read, have not read the
original cyberspace article? Okay. Homework item number one.
This was an article that came out in the village voice in 1993 regarding the first major
documented case, because I'm positive there were many, many more. Instance of one avatar
raping another one. And actually he raped two in public in the living room in the main house at
the main entrance of the entire virtual space. With a knife. As in raped with a knife.
But here's the interesting thing.
He didn't even do it to their actual bodies.
He did it using this technological tool
that was available in this game called a puppet.
And the puppet, all it did, this was a text world,
all it did was make it look like
somebody else was doing something.
The victims were actually just standing there.
And they could mute and block him all they wanted.
but it didn't matter because it looked to everyone else in the room like Mr. Bungle was getting
these two poor people to do horrendous things to themselves. In 1993, this became a bit of a
cause celebre because people started arguing about whether or not that was really rape. I
mean, it's online. That can't be real, can it? We know better now, I hope. Although...
have to see, I think there's plenty of Twitter trolls who
probably still think, what's the big deal? Right? But I'm pretty
sure that right now somebody is going, you know, it will be
awfully cool to do user generated content in social VR
and somebody is probably inventing the VR version of that
puppet right now. Right?
another fellow virtual world guy going way back has this absolutely wonderful phrase, TTP. We
use it as an index with which to measure the success of virtual worlds social design. It
stands for time to penis. How long until you find the UGC penis that some player has
managed to stick in your game?
Ultima Online, the first one I saw was drawn by dropping fish on the road. It happened on the
first day. And of course the most famous incident, I encourage you, go look up the video on
YouTube. It's astonishing in a surreal kind of way. This poor woman, Angie Chung, was
literally attacked by a flying swarm of thousands of penises that swirled around her in a
tornado.
So that isn't entirely on the troll, right? If you run that world, that's on you. It's on you.
Every feature you make should be looked at first as a weapon. And it's a dark way to look at
humanity, I know. I've grown so cynical. How will a player abuse someone else with this?
Odds are excellent that you aren't actually evil enough
when you playtest.
Otherwise, something like groping somebody,
God, that would have come up in the first 15 seconds, right?
You know, it's almost an obvious scenario.
I mean, what could they do with the actual bows and arrows?
We haven't even gotten to that part.
It wasn't long ago that we saw an experienced triple A team
miss one of these kind of basic things.
How many of you played The Division?
Right. So here's this MMO shooter on the console with a
triple A team and they made all the players collide with all the
other players. And then they had a single quest giver sitting in
the central lobby. So there were lines running out the door and
people would barricade the door to prevent other people from
getting quests. Right?
My personal experience with making that mistake was in the
alpha for Ultima Online sometime around February to May
of 1996, where we allowed people to spawn in the inn.
And then they would walk outside.
And they were collidable, of course.
And people would gladly let them out the door.
But then they would sand in the door and not let anyone
in, and in the pursuit of realism, we had made it so you
could shoot arrows through the windows.
of the inn. So they would let you out and rush to the windows and shoot you in the back as you
walked away. And of course you couldn't get back in to defend yourself. You couldn't see who was
in the building. We basically proved all of the fundamental premises of medieval defensive
architecture. That was 1996 and a game in 2016 can still make the same mistake because we're
not necessarily very good about sharing the history.
Or reading it, rather, because the stories have been told.
We laugh about them.
They're fun, until you're pincushioned with 100 arrows
in your back.
This brings us to another issue. Those of you who are building social VR, you are here
listening to this talk. Excellent. You are good people. You are not going to do these
things. But if you are successful, the people you hire will hire other people who will in
fact do things like consider it a perk.
to go over to people's private chat spaces and watch them as they engage in, you know, very
private things. The very first guy that I banned and fired as an admin on a text mod was
somebody who thought it was the perk of a God to be able to spy on same sex couples who were
having cyber sex in their private rooms. You have to hard code in the same sex couples
limitations into the architecture of your world. Permission bits, absolute logging of every kind
of extra normal command, the ability to grant or revoke any kind of capability granularly per
individual and only grant the powers that are specific to the scope of that individual's job.
And you have to do this because in the early days of MMOs we had
issues where game masters in Ultima Online were having hot
tub parties with players and trading sexual favors for in
game items. They needed the ability to spawn those items for
their job. Unfortunately we didn't have logging in the hot
tubs. Probably fortunately actually. So it was hard to
prove that these situations were happening.
thing is odds are near certainty. If your virtual world is successful, your digital objects
are going to have real money value. There's no escaping it at this point. It is absolutely
hopeless to try. Just assume that anything you create as a digital object has real world
value and people will be doing things like sleeping for it, paying for it and stealing it.
Just go in the door assuming that that is part of this field.
Fundamentally, you should not be opening a virtual world
unless you think in terms of this kind
of legal infrastructure.
The easiest way to think of this is you are the gods
of this space, but you're the government of this space.
We have drifted away over time from having in-game admins
have even visible avatars in the space.
And the reason is in order to minimize the possibility
of personal relationships forming between customer service
and individual players.
I miss the days when you could hang out with the players
and you were the God and they weren't and all of it
and you could hang out and do things for them.
But the reason why we've gone and anonymized everybody
is because corruption happens.
You also need to be aware, and this is also just a home truth,
the people who use virtual spaces are very often using them for therapeutic purposes.
That means a higher incidence of individuals inside your space who are dealing with psychological
stress of various sorts. It's just how the numbers work out.
You just need to be aware of it. There is not a single large scale commercial virtual world
that does not have the FBI and suicide hotlines on speed dial. The number of runaways that we
tracked down for the FBI and the police while at Sony online was easily in the triple digits.
And I would add to this, by the way,
Be prepared to deal with manifestations of mental illness.
Those folks will frequently be calling for assistance
within this virtual setting.
And you have gone and built their home away from home,
the place that they use to cope,
the place that they are using as their support system.
Often the friends that they've made in your space
are the ones that literally keep them alive.
You are holding
their lives in your hands.
So you have to take it seriously.
You shape this society in really fundamental ways.
Have I scared the shit out of you yet?
I hope so, right?
I hope so.
Don't worry, it won't all be a downer.
I promise.
But the flip side of this power
is that you can shape this environment
in ways that are amazing.
The original Mudd, Richard Bartle actually designed it
as a blow against the British class system.
That is why you can level up and be anyone and anything.
Because he felt like he'd grown up
in a very restrictive world where,
oh no, you have the wrong accent.
You'll never get a doctorate, right?
That's amazing, that's super cool.
And in fact, a lot of the earliest virtual spaces
were safe spaces for
safe spaces for queers, safe spaces for the asexuals, safe
spaces for people who prefer the idea of having hundreds of
little tentacles for genitalia. They were all colors and shapes
and sizes and ages. All of those ideas. One of the huge, huge
mistakes of social VR is that they're forgetting that the
promise is be someone you aren't. Right?
That has always been a fundamental premise of engaging in a virtual world.
Even in the normative modern MMO worlds, cross-gender roleplay is still incredibly common, right?
We all know this.
Identity exploration is one of the fundamental things that alternate realities let us do.
And when you choose a class or a race or whatever in one of
these online worlds, like wow, you're effectively almost
engaging in a personality test.
People tend to choose archetypes that resonate and
relate to how they visualize themselves.
This is why I hate voice chat, because it's one of the many
things that is taking these tools away from people.
It extends beyond voice chat, though.
How many of you are short, like me?
All right, short people.
You guys know that you have lower lifetime earnings
than tall people, right?
You get less promotions and lower salaries?
Yeah.
So it turns out that halflings and gnomes
in fantasy role-playing games are in less XP per hour
and level slower.
because we import real world biases into these worlds. Not intentionally, just the fact that
we made halflings short results in them earning less XP because people have biases. So as we
chase realistic avatars, we should consider whether realism is really a good idea. If those
are behaviors and beliefs that we actually want to reinforce or not.
You know, one of the beauties of the early internet and of
virtual worlds in particular is that nobody could tell you
were a dog.
Only now we can hear you barking on discord, right?
And we know.
So that's an issue.
most obvious of these are tend to be related to gender presentation but race presentation is
another one that's really frequently overlooked. I have lost count of the number of social spaces
that don't have race as a customization option. That is embarrassing. From the get go you
should be thinking about it. It was controversial in star wars galaxies for us to have a breast
size slider. Fortunately female players pitched a fit.
when they found out it was controversial. Because it's
important. People need to feel like they can be what they want
to be. And be who they are. We had to rename it the torso
slider though because LucasArts was very touchy about the
terminology. Probably the biggest bias that is present in
social VR is around empathy, frankly. Um, I don't know if
The challenge here is, well there's multiple challenges,
but as people enter a space,
if they don't have a stake in the space,
if they don't have persistent identity in it already,
they, it's very easy to behave as a virtual sociopath.
They don't have any community ties whatsoever.
So you have to start creating investment
into an identity really early on.
So those of you who are making systems that are drop-in,
don't, you have to start doing persistent identity. If you can
abandon identity, that's basically a license to do
whatever you want and not get stopped. You can't use things
like credit cards to block, for example. Average U.S. household
I think has 13 credit card numbers. That's an awful lot of
shots at harassing somebody without getting caught.
So the real way you have to do it is by causing personal investment in the identity they are creating so that they don't want to lose it.
They don't want to lose the investment they've made.
But the other big thing that you need to do is increase channels for conveying emotional content.
between the avatars, between the players.
And again, this is a place where voice
kind of cuts both ways, right?
I mean, there are two classic ways of doing this.
Very simple.
One is gameplay that involves teamwork.
The other one is an emote system.
Simply put, an emote system.
Best practice emote systems.
involve automatically parsing text chat and pulling out the
emotional cues that people are already sticking in there, like
smileys. You know this because Facebook messenger does it, chat
does it, Twitter does it, everything does this now. That's
best practice. Giving people manual puppeteering structures
like, oh, I have to hit this combination of buttons to smile,
results in people not smiling, I'm afraid. Right?
Yes, there's a subset of people who are good at puppeteering. Most people are not. Having
the system puppeteer for them off of cues has been shown to be dramatically more
effective. Dramatically more effective. I don't know how you're going to do this with
voice. Maybe it can be a really cool research project for somebody to start developing
technology to do natural language processing and analysis of voice stressors. But I'm not
expecting it any time soon.
So good luck, those of you working in that field, because
wild voice does convey a significant amount of
emotional content.
particularly once you get into fictional social VR spaces of any sort, you can't expect people
to be trained actors in knowing how to convey emotion. It's going to be challenging. And if
what they need to do is convey real emotion, they will prefer to use Skype where they get all
the cues rather than settling for an inferior system. So my actual advice to social VR people
bluntly is to sidestep as many of these problems as possible.
don't have large scale worlds with a bunch of strangers interacting with one another in an
unsupervised fashion. Because I don't think you have solutions at the current level of
technology for some of these problems. You know, maybe Facebook or Google will be solving
these for you at some point, but right now they just don't. Stick to small groups, people who
mostly already know each other. Make the avatars relatively unrealistic so nobody cares about
the fact that the emotional cues are wrong. Play to the strengths.
The strengths of VR today are that VR is clumsy.
Play with that.
I think that is part of why something like Job Simulator is
one of the most successful VR experiences we have.
It embraces the limitation.
Here's the thing, for those of you now who, how many of you
played Pokemon Go?
I want to say in advance, Pokemon Go is an amazing
achievement.
It's phenomenal and brought joy to millions of people.
So I'm now going to shred it to pieces.
All of these issues get dramatically worse once we're
talking about social AR.
You know, from the technology side, people are starting to
figure out that a lot of people made this mistake.
They thought that the technology of VR headsets
would naturally lead into the technology for AR headsets.
And they're wrong.
It's kind of a speed of light thing.
It's just not happening.
They are, if you are talking about social things, they are the same technology in this very
particular way.
I want to take you back in time to 2006 when a whole bunch of us got invited to Stanford
for an exercise of the Institute for the Future where we engaged in a futurist envisioning
project called the metaverse road map.
This was in those days when people thought it was a good idea to have Twitter feeds behind
speakers.
I'd love to see the one for this talk right now.
This is what we said virtual worlds would become.
We said there are four kinds. And at that time, almost all of them were virtual worlds.
Which is to say, fictional environments that you connect to through a client of maps of places
that aren't real. Where you go run around and do stuff. That box holds Eve and a second life,
Habbo Hotel and World of Warcraft. Right?
But we said, you know, if all you do is swap out the data set
of those maps, you instead get virtual worlds that are built
using the real world.
And you can log into those instead.
And those are called mirror worlds.
And it's a term that's been around for quite a while.
This is also the time when there are a lot of people who
are mounting backpacks on their back with computers and
then putting a webcam on their head and filming everything
that they were doing and having to swap out hard drives
about every 20 minutes.
This is called life logging.
And yes, we saw that as being part
of virtual world structure as well.
This is the identity piece, the identity component.
And then lastly, and chronologically last as well,
is what we called augmented reality,
where these things would start to come together.
Where you might have a virtual world or a mirror world
both overlaid on top of the real world,
and you engage in life logging
as one of the ways to interact with it.
Well, all of these are now here.
All of these are now in fact here. And the thing is, even
though the operators of all of these different services don't
know this really, they are all running against what I would
call virtual world servers. Virtual world back ends. It's
just that Twitter only bothered to build the chat part. And
Waze only bothered to build the moving around part. And Yelp
only bothered to build like region markers.
Right? One of the key lessons of virtual worlds, and it's one
that actually a lot of virtual players just refuse to accept.
And I think a lot of people who work primarily with headsets
refuse to accept. Rendering is by far the least important part
of this entire field. Sorry if you're a graphics programmer.
It is easily the part that matters the least. Every single graphical world I have ever seen
has offered a plain text client. Why? Because the admins need it to go look at logs. Right? The
worlds are on the server, the representation independent. We might have a canonical
client, but the representation is not the part that really, really matters.
What matters is the action that's going on on the server,
which is where you actually track things like
the avatar profiles, their histories,
the location of objects, how they interact with one another
and what their behaviors are.
So all of those things are actually virtual worlds.
I call this the goggles fallacy
because it is distressing, perhaps inevitable,
that the current boom in virtual reality
is being driven by the hardware.
If you actually go look at what is going on in these various
settings, they're all about clients moving on servers.
Interacting with objects on servers.
Sometimes we drive around on those servers by driving
around in the real world.
You know, that's Waze and Google Maps.
It's actually every Android phone.
You guys know that, right?
Android phones are, that's part of how Google detects
where there's traffic jams.
Your phone's not moving, tells them.
But Yelp and Zillow are all about teleporting around on
the virtual side, but not the real side.
But it doesn't matter.
Either way, there's an avatar moving on the virtual side.
So it's the same technology.
You can literally run down the kinds of technological elements required to build a virtual
world server. Does it simulate a space? Yes. Check, check, check. Where is the data from? Is it
real or fictional? Doesn't matter. Who cares? Could be half and half. Does it track clients?
Are they connected? Doesn't need to be constant on connection. It could be some of the time.
Check, check, check. Are our clients positioned relative to one another spatially? The main
difference is that in WoW and Pokemon we actually bother to spawn bots in there.
right? And let you like interact with them in some fashion. That's about it. Of course these
days we kind of allow people to spawn geotag markers into Google maps so we're kind of
letting people spawn bots there too. I'll say it bluntly, an old school text mud from 1992 is
closer to Snow Crash than anything that has been built with goggles. By quite a lot.
A lot of defenders of VR start talking here about how the sense of presence that exists inside
of VR is what makes the difference and they're wrong. They're wrong. Telepresence was defined
back in the days before we had pictures.
People reported those sensations in pure text environments.
In factually, if I had to rank the level of presence,
I would probably put VR first, then the text games,
then all the ones that are on monitors.
Because text games actually embody you
almost as powerfully as VR does.
And in fact, if you are looking for more specific concrete
lessons about how to deal with avatar intersection issues and
all the rest, I would be looking at how text mods
handled things.
For example, consent systems for paired emotes was a very,
very common design trope in text mods.
One that also appears in modern day LARPing.
where you can't just hug somebody or grope somebody,
but there is almost a two-factor authentication process
that players must go through in order to engage with others.
That stuff popped up in the text worlds first,
because in the text worlds,
there was no distinction of distance.
Everybody was standing on a pin
in each individual text room.
So all it took was one word for them
to be interpenetrating with your avatar.
The takeaway from this is, I mean, how many of you have heard crazy stories about Eve
or the plague in WoW or any of these things?
You all heard crazy shit like that?
Awesome!
In a post-Pokemon Go world, expect that to start happening in the real world.
right? All of those things will happen in the real world. Because all of these
technologies are really just virtual world servers. It is not going to be very long
until there is a template ID associated with your washing machine so that when you look at it,
you'll be able to pull up the manual. You can do that crudely right now with Google, of
course. But we're not very far away from it actually having an individual instance ID.
Like your washing machine.
and it will have its own character sheet that will have its repair history. Because all it
needs to do is be an object in that database. In the run time database of our world. That's not
far fetched. That's not science fictional. The problem is we never trust the client. What
happens when you are the client? Because you are going to be the client. Your phone is
anyway. And this is most relevant because of Pokemon Go. Okay?
I'm going to pick on it, I can't help it. I already did a very detailed mathematical
breakdown of why it's advancement system was utterly broken. But I did that back in Austin,
you can find that on my website, it's called systems designed for retention, if you like
graphs, it's full of it. The real question for us in this room is around things like there are
no player killer switches in meat space. Right? So if you start designing your social
structures in a way that incentivizes players to commit virtual violence against one another,
they're probably going to start doing it for real.
All of these things can be quite unintentional. Pokemon Go, I'm sure, absolutely did not
intend for its map of spawns to be racist and classist. And yet, it's really, really hard to
find Pokemon in poor black neighborhoods and in rural areas. Because its UGC map happened to
be built out of kids who were going to Stanford and Berkeley. Right? Technologically
advantaged college students.
further. What starts happening, you all heard, oh, Pokemon spawn in the Holocaust museum.
Pokemon spawn in Arlington cemetery. Sure. Right? None of this happened on purpose. I don't
ascribe any malicious intent.
But nobody ever means to do this stuff. Nobody ever means to damage somebody's actual equity in
their home by accidentally putting Pokmon spawn points or gyms in their privately owned
backyard, thereby causing an endless stream of trespassing. And yet, it happened. Right? So we
do have to think about these issues.
It might be that someday legislation will appear that goes right alongside
well there's water rights and mining rights and air traffic rights
and virtual layer annotation rights.
That might actually be the only solution to something like Pokemon spawning in your backyard.
And of course then somebody will license Pokemon rights to a company for money, right?
I struck oil, I struck Pokemon.
But it starts raising questions like can or should a company
like Niantic strike a deal with coffee shop A as opposed to
coffee shop B, thereby tilting the level of the business
balance in that area? There's no rules or regulations around
stuff like that. They could direct traffic somewhere it
isn't wanted. What if somebody happens to create a really cool
social AR game and says, wow, it would be really fun, you know,
I'm actually a secret gamer gator, I'm going to start
spawning Pokemon on top of a Black Lives Matter rally.
It is trivially easy for an operator of a virtual world to pull a stunt like that.
We've seen the early harbingers of things like that. Anonymous got its start by holding a flash
mob in front of a Scientology facility in New York City. We kind of trained people to do this.
All those anonymous kids, we kind of built them, right? We've been training them how to do this
stuff.
Phrases like geo tagging mistakenly give us the
impression that, oh, we're sticking a little bit of
virtual on the real, when what is happening is actually the
exact opposite.
We're actually sticking a little bit of real stuff into
what is already a primarily virtual environment.
The Harbingers here get real.
We used to say, oh, I even said it earlier, a character
choice in an MMO is effectively a personality test.
But so is a collection of your likes on Facebook,
because Facebook is really just an extended character sheet.
And sure enough, that's why there's a company called
Cambridge Analytica that data-mined that data on 220
million Americans and used it for targeted micro-advertising
in order to both suppress votes and encourage people to
come out and vote and get us Brexit and Trump.
Because if you run a virtual world, that is the kind of
panopticon power you have.
Fake news. Fake news is an instant dungeon. It's an instant dungeon personalized tailored just
for you. You get your own spawns and there's Alex Jones is the boss at the bottom of the
dungeon. And you get to play lizard people. Right? Because that's the power you have when
you're running a virtual space. You all saw the mobs for Pikachu. I have no idea whether it
was a conscious decision in that game.
to make it so that each spawn of a Pokemon was instanced.
But if they had not been, if it had been zero-sum,
there that day in Central Park
around that Santa Monica pier,
and there was only one Pikachu to have,
I think we would have seen Pika murders by now.
It's human nature. And this sounds like it's crazy, but it is not. I know it because it
already happened. In Ultima Online, when we launched first in Hong Kong, the triads joined
the game. And they would go and do their player killer war in the game, and then they would
take it to the streets. Because by designing our game in such a way that it encouraged
tribalism, encouraged othering other players, and then encouraged violence between the
groups, we encouraged them to do it everywhere. What happens when the real world is the
playing field?
My local gym is a locked church. They've had a lot of problems with people parking in the
parking lot at 3 a.m. and getting as close as possible to the stained glass windows to try to
catch a signal so they can zap a Pokemon inside. How long until they break in, I don't know. The
phones have all of this stuff built in. They do. It's built into the phones, but the phones
at least have privacy chips.
The phones have private store houses that even Apple can't
break into its own phone. But just yesterday a cloud stuffed
toy, I don't even remember the name of it, turned out that they
were storing the voice chat logs of all of the kids that ever
talked to their plushie on AWS instance on a database that was
not passworded. We don't even need the actual user. We don't
It's enough to just get enough users to see the perturbations
of what's around them. Are we prepared to community manage
downtown San Francisco when we have better history tracking of
what each individual does than the police or the government do?
You want to manage community for downtown San Francisco? We
couldn't even handle a bunch of kids angry about supposed ethics
and video game journalism. We're supposed to deal with San
Francisco? But those are the tools we're taking up.
It doesn't take away from the achievement of Pokemon Go. It's possible to achieve great
things and still open Pandora's box. But we do have these lessons. We do know that these are
the things that we can be thinking about. And I realize I'm here at GDC and I'm talking to you
about stuff that does not seem very game like at all. But I'm talking with you about it
because you're my peeps. You're the ones who will listen. I can't get a, you know,
I can't get a Google or anybody to listen to this. If there's anybody from Apple here, call me.
We're going to be playing logged in whether we signed up for it or not is kind of the
message I'm trying to give. That's your take away. That's really what this is about. And we
usually call entities like that governments. It's not an accident that we talked about
governance clear back in the text mods. So yeah, monopolistic giant governments.
There's a little bit more awareness of that since I
submitted this talk months ago.
Zak has actually said, oh, maybe this news thing's an
issue.
And we do have our first gold farmer in the White House.
Steve Bannon used to run IGE, the gold farming company, and
then he turned around and built a gaming website network.
That was his training wheels for running Breitbart.
So some people are paying attention.
When a time comes that new modes and venues exist for communities, and said modes are
different enough from the existing ones, that question arises as to the applicability of
past custom and law, and when said venues have become a forum for interaction in society
for the general public.
regardless of the intent of the creators of said venue.
And at a time when said communities and spaces are rising in popularity and widely exploited for commercial gain,
it behooves those involved in said communities and venues to affirm and declare the inalienable rights of the members of said communities.
August 27, 2000.
To my knowledge, exactly three virtual worlds in history
have bothered to adopt that Declaration
of the Rights of Players.
But the need for it is now greater than ever,
and I really wish Pokemon had adopted it.
And I sure hope that those of you
who are going back to your companies
will seriously consider, oh, please, update it, revise it.
But start thinking in terms of the rights that players should be having in these spaces.
Because soon enough, Internet of Things is going to hit.
This is also not fiction.
I had this conversation with Zuckerberg too.
This is why he bought Oculus.
To turn the world into a unified database of objects.
I'm probably not getting any more consulting gigs there.
Oh well.
We're actively collaborating in this process.
All that's missing is unifying the data.
Facebook owning identity and chat, Amazon the object template database, Google the runtime
template database, Apple the client, you know.
We're collaborating in this process and what comes, I don't know.
I honestly don't know.
That's why I'm here.
I need your help.
We need each other's help if we're going to deal with this because this is not hypothetical.
Do not let our world be designed by the people who prefer the lobby of the W to the IGF.
You guys don't go to the lobby of the W, I hope. Right?
Technologists in this room, you guys know how much of this we
can build right now. Bluetooth LE beacons, some simple mesh
networking. We could build this now. So I wish HoloLens and
Magic Leap had that emblazoned on the eyeballs instead of
demos because the chip that matters is the networking chip.
Not the graphics chip.
That is what keeps me up at night. I'm sorry, GDC is not supposed to be a downer. If we had all
gone to the EGW, I'm sure we would all be leaving here inspired and psyched up. But this is
the advocacy track. But I'll say this. This room is the one that gives me hope. How many of you
have played a game in the last 24 hours? With a stranger? How many of you feel games, hey,
they're for connecting, right?
How many of you feel games, about fairness, supposed to be
fair, right?
How many of you think games are for being smart, right?
And that games are for everyone?
Yeah?
Good.
That's what gives me the hope.
Because entertainment has always led the way on this
stuff, and that is a pretty good ethos with which to start.
And this is a group that is willing to read giant strategy
guides.
So please, go read the work of, you know, read Julian DeBelle,
read Nick Yee, read T.L. Taylor, read Thomas Malaby.
Go read all of the endless stuff that has been written about
this, because I got to tell you, by the way, virtual worlds
are the best documented part of all of video games and the
most studied, probably by an order of magnitude.
The stuff is out there.
So, you know, frankly, I'm leaving our collective fate in
your hands here.
These are your tools. Now you know what you're actually doing.
Right? It is not what you were not making cute archery
simulators. It is not what this was ever about. Now you know
better. And that's good. So it shouldn't be too much of a
downer. You're the best qualified people on earth to
actually build this future. So go out there. Let's have some
fun.
Right? Seriously. Let's explore. Have some fun. Just get your
homework done first. Thank you. We probably have like some
seconds for questions. Five minutes for questions says the
glowing yellow sign.
There are microphones here if anybody has any, but you don't
because I've persuaded you completely.
That's awesome.
Now, there we go.
Hi, I thought it was really interesting what you said
about, essentially, you have the responsibility, and you
have some legal responsibility.
You can't go, even if someone wants to open up a taco stand, you have to deal with the health
department and all those things. If you run a bed and breakfast, you have to do that. So all
these things are not unreasonable.
for people to, you know, devs to take into account. And I guess,
you know, dealing with human nature, a turbine, we had to
take out the point up emote because, you know, it's a Nazi
thing. And, yeah, you don't always expect that at the
beginning, but it's, yeah, it's bad stuff. Yeah, so if the
questions all turn out to just be MMO veterans coming up and
saying, yeah, that, that's fine. Thanks.
By the way, the inventor of TTP. Actually it was Freeman. Oh,
really? Jeff Freeman.
There's one thing that I wanted to say just to pile on top of this, which is that over the course
of WoW we saw something that's really remarkable, which is something that makes me really sad
that people aren't making MMOs anymore, which is that MMOs started as the wild west of gaming
and ended up being the single safest genre for women to play in gaming.
because everything else is unmoderated voice chat,
whereas MMOs have persistent identity,
have persistent community, have the logging,
all of the stuff that you talked about,
and that's something that we fought.
And Blizzard led the way and made it real.
And you can actually see the gender split of that audience
of wow, just go from 2080 to 5050
over the course of a decade.
And I think that's important for us to realize
it took a lot of work.
And I have a question, I just wanted to be sure
that we all acknowledge that.
Yeah, I think we should.
And it's even more depressing when you realize
that the starting point of 2080
was actually already way the hell ahead.
right, because at the time that virtual worlds were starting,
the gender split for typical mainstream gaming
was more like 95-5.
So virtual worlds were already dramatically more inclusive
spaces than gaming was in general.
And now we've made a lot of progress.
And along comes Xbox Live, oh my god, right?
So yeah, there's definitely a lot to learn there,
a lot of lessons to take on.
Let's go over to this side.
I think you said for the ideal virtual space, the avatars would be non-realistic and not moving.
Can you elaborate on the not moving, because not moving in VR seems...
Especially with hand controllers, it seems kind of bad.
Not moving very much. I actually mean locomotion, physical locomotion.
So, yeah, VR is really good at...
clumsily moving arms. It's really good at that. It's pretty
bad at moving your legs. As we know, right? Most of the
locomotion methods involve short hop teleporting and whatnot
because of the nausea issues, vestibular, blah, blah, blah.
But the other side of that issue is that, you know, allowing one
avatar to move on to another is one of the starting points for
these problems. If I were making a social VR thing that I wanted
to be a commercial success, I would go clone IMVU.
You sit at opposite sides of a table. You're sitting. You can
wave your hands and head all you want. You can build crazy ass
avatars, right, because it's all about personal expression and
getting to know the other person. It's limited to two
people at a time, so if you bail or block, you'll never have to
deal with that person again. It just sidesteps all the issues,
right? Whereas if you say, no, what I really want to build is
wow, only in a VR headset, I go, then you're going to have to
build all of the infrastructure that Damien just talked about.
and you can't, frankly.
I'm not sure anybody can, right?
Like I don't, literally do not know a way
for people to solve some of those issues
with voice chat at current levels of technology.
Will we get there?
Sure, but not today.
So that's really what I meant.
Thanks.
Sure.
I am aged enough to have played MUDs and traditional MMOs for decades.
People tend not to take it very well when they get banned, even in text mods.
So what happens when the form we are projecting into a virtual world is our form?
Are people going to get more addicted to that experience such that we could expect severe
reactions from people who would be banned from those worlds?
No, because most people who want to project their real forms aren't going to bother to use virtual worlds to do it.
Virtual worlds convey real forms really, really badly.
Right?
That's not what I mean.
I know what you mean. I think I do.
People will take it more...
You're basically asking will people take banning and punishment more seriously when what they projected is their real self, right?
They put more of themselves physically into it. We're playing a bunch of MMOs. It's a lot of text. Maybe there's chat.
But in virtual reality, you are there.
Yeah, Avatar might not be, you know, might not look like you, but to you, you are in that space.
So what happens when somebody kicks you out of that space?
Yeah, I think there's probably a physical reaction,
but in practice, I actually literally do not buy
that you are more there in the VR case
than you are in the others, right?
The building up of identity is the thing
that actually stings, and so it's the loss of that identity
is what ends up being really painful.
And CAs are signaling me that we have to go
to the overflow questions room.
So really fast, on that, to add to your list,
live on the screen.
Yes, Sherry Turkle. If I started listing books and academics we would be here all day. I'll
head to, just follow me. We'll find a spot out there. We'll find a spot out there. We'll find