What can meditation teach us about game design?
Can we design digital games to alter a player's experience of their universe as dramatically as a dose of LSD?
In this talk, I offer that understanding trance is a key to using good old-fashioned game design to alter a player's experience of consciousness itself.
We'll be going over different kinds of trances, what those trances do, and how to induce them.
And in order to ground these ideas firmly in a practice of game design,
I'll be relating my own experience designing Soundcell through this frame,
through this lens of trance design.
So, let's start now with just a very short mindfulness meditation.
But we're going to look at this not as a yogi, but as a systems designer.
So, close your eyes. This will just take a minute.
Take a deep, luxurious breath in. Really enjoy it.
Breathe out all the way and focus your attention on the
sensation of breath. You can release yourself of controlling
the breath and just observe. Now your mind will come in and
distract you and take your attention away from breath.
When that happens, just bring your attention back to the
breath. And this is natural, it's natural to get distracted.
Just bring your attention back to breath. Now what you're doing
right now is playing a game.
And the rules of this game shape your attention and your experience.
And as soon as you begin following those rules automatically,
you've entered a trance state.
The function of a meditation trance is very specific though.
It's to reveal and to help forgive other more unconscious trances.
You can open your eyes now.
In this talk, we're going to learn to leverage this and many other kinds of trances.
So, even if our goals are just simply to create a more fun game, a more immersive game, and give a player more joy,
these tools of trance, having a deeper understanding of trance, gives us a really powerful tool to helping shape a player's journey.
But I think we can use these tools to create fundamentally different kinds of experiences as well.
Experiences that were totally unreachable to us without this frame of looking at game design as trans design.