to bringing fantasy to life in Final Fantasy 15. If you're looking for bringing hell to life,
you're in the wrong room. That's in 2002. I'm not even making that up. That's going on right
now. So, uh, my name is Dan Inouye.
I'll give you a quick background on me.
I was born and raised in New York,
and I bounced back and forth to Japan for a while
before landing at Square Enix about 12 years ago.
And for the last couple years,
I've been leading the team responsible
for the English language content in Final Fantasy XV
and its companion projects.
I'll warn you up front that there are spoilers ahead,
but there's also a section on why the spoilers
don't really spoil anything, so I hope you'll stick with me.
And we'll start with Final Fantasy.
So I'm guessing everyone here kind of has an idea
and has heard of Final Fantasy, but what is it?
For 30 years, Final Fantasy has reinvented itself
and rebuilt itself anew with each iteration.
So every time it's new characters, new worlds, new gameplay.
new combat, often fabulous hair, but it's never the same game. So what defines a Final Fantasy
game? Well, one answer is it's lore. More precisely, the way the lore of each entry kind of
co-ops monsters and magic and mythos from different traditions. You have the Babylonian next
to the Celtic, next to the Chinese, next to Greek mythology, without any regard for the dogmatic
baggage that comes with it. So Final Fantasy kind of draws on these for inspiration without
any limitations.
And so many, many years ago when this project began,
it was built on a simple premise,
a fantasy based on reality,
which is a significant proposition
because reality has never really been the series' focus.
So of course, all fiction is to some extent based on reality.
On the surface, the intent here was a modern take,
sort of a real-world setting with touches of high fantasy.
But in time, with the companion projects and promotion,
it added an extra dimension of reality
and
the project kind of developed a life of its own.
So at the core of everything is the game,
which follows Prince Noctis and his three close friends
as they leave home on a journey.
It begins with an open-world exploration of the continent
and then gradually assumes a linear format
as the story progresses.
The film, Kingsglaive, recounts the events
that unfold in the crowned city as the prince is away,
centering around his father, the king, his paramour, Luna,
and the titular Kingsglaive, the defenders of the city.
So the film was released about a month, sorry,
a couple months ahead of the game's release in theaters,
and the events of the film occur parallel
to the first chapter of the game.
The anime, Brotherhood, references the bond
between the prince and his friends.
So as hinted at in the panels here,
the story opens with the gang on the road
and then tells the story through flashbacks
from their boyhood.
So the series began streaming on YouTube
roughly a half year before the game's release
with one episode each month in five installments.
So these weren't kind of thinly related spin-offs
or throwaway side stories.
These were threads of a simultaneous narrative
woven together across media.
We couldn't assume everyone in our audience
had seen all the companion projects
or even any for that matter.
So this represented a big challenge,
building integrated yet independent narratives
and forming a coherent and cohesive reality.
So that's the intro, and with that in mind,
here's the breakdown of this talk, as told in three acts.
First, I'll start off by introducing some of the tactics
and techniques we use to bring realism into our work,
and in the second act, I'll discuss how realities
of development and promotion got in the way of these plans,
and finally, we'll wrap it up with some observation
about what it all means.
So, Act 1 is the best laid plans.
So on any project, our first task is to anchor our reality in our static material, our setting,
our characters, and our lore.
Final Fantasy is a Japanese-developed franchise, but the reality basis meant it was more important
than ever that we ask ourselves, how would this be done in the West when making our linguistic
choices?
One thing that made this Final Fantasy different from others
also was the fact that it was set to launch simultaneously
in 12 languages.
As there would be no lead time to perform
the usual localization tweaks,
it meant that the game had to be global from the ground up.
So just as the ecology and nature of the game
borrowed from real world sources, so would the cultures.
So the world of Eos features four distinct civilizations
with their own architecture, lifestyles,
and written languages.
Pictured here is Altissia, the walls of water.
It's sort of a reimagined Venice,
and in line with that flavor,
our Italian translation team was called on
to help in naming the locales and helping with the signage.
Here we see a scene from The Continent which uses English as a base with sort of French
and Gaelic leaning spellings.
Now normally localizing art assets is unwise and a headache and most fantasy games rightly
opt to use iconography or illegible text.
But one of the kind of benefits and luxuries of having a multicultural, multilingual in-house
translation staff is that it let us review things early on so that we could globalize
them and incorporating this sort of semi-real world languages into the world helped build
that road trip aesthetic and make the trip familiarly foreign for all audiences.
And so I have just a quick aside here,
which is that I want to stress the importance
of consulting native speakers
when working with foreign cultures,
especially when in real world
or real world based fictional settings,
because especially when shows or games...
kind of, they do the Japanese season
and they use the Japanese setting.
It's usually laughably inauthentic
and I realize that stories cater more
to people's perceptions than they do necessarily realities
but it's 2017 and the internet will call you out.
You will be exposed.
So be sure to ask a native speaker
when you're working in another culture.
So next up, this also goes to that point
on the divide between perception and reality.
While we added plenty of uniform local color to the continent of Lucis, the English-speaking
continent, this wouldn't fit with the kind of modern metropolis of its capital, the crown
city.
So we have some cool concept art here.
And the Crown City is a cultural amalgam.
Our art team consciously intended
to show it as street scenes from the world over.
So you can see bits of London, New York, Paris, and Tokyo,
kind of depending on the angle you look at it from,
to make it feel both familiar and foreign
to a worldwide audience.
And to give it that same kind of diversity linguistically,
we employed accents according to social circle
more than geographic origin, which
gave it a more modern feel than the classic all dwarves
are Scottish fantasy trope.
So ultimately, I can't say definitively
whether this enhanced or diminished
the reality for the audience at large,
but it did give us the freedom to assemble a really
great transatlantic cast.
So that was one plus of this decision as well.
And so the next aspect might strike you as a little too real.
The astute viewer may have noticed a fair amount of product placement in these shots.
So yeah, some of you will find this jarring.
The lines between reality and fantasy
become very blurry here.
And the specter of commercialism looms kind
of large over artistic merit.
So these imports from beyond the fourth wall
may be hard to explain away in canon,
but they do make the world more kind of recognizable
and familiar and more real to a good segment of the audience.
And so that's what I tell myself at night.
When it came to hawking cup noodles in the game,
we did it kind of tongue in cheek
because we definitely wanted to respect
our audience's intelligence.
And we thought it was a playful tap on the fourth wall.
So hopefully they enjoyed that.
And moving on to characters.
So relatable characters can make or break your reality.
And so, yeah, I joked about it earlier,
but identifying with spectacularly quaffed JRPG heroes
can be a real barrier to entry for a lot of players.
And the fancy schmancy names don't always help.
So we rely on touchstones to kind of turn foreign tropes
into more relatable people for our audience.
And here's the core four for our main story.
On the far left is Ignis.
He's the suave brains of the operation,
sort of James Bond in The Great Outdoors.
Next to him is Prompto, the funny fast talker,
kind of a zanier Ferris Bueller.
On the far right is Gladio,
who's a younger John McClane from Die Hard.
And I'll get to the rock star in the middle in a second,
but who wouldn't want to take a road trip
with James Bond, Ferris Bueller, and John McClane?
So writing with established reference character voices in mind isn't exactly a cutting edge
technique necessarily, but it's especially critical in a localization.
Obviously you tinker with the archetype, but it provides a compass that keeps your character
directed for your audience through all the cultural clutter.
And another key point here is that the analogs aren't sidekicks.
Each one has his own brand of cool.
Each can carry his own story.
Each is the normal one in his own mind.
And so it really keeps the give and take fresh,
because they all feel they're right.
And so here's a little side story about Noctis's character.
I always use scripted characters for my references,
and I avoid using real people, because real people.
You don't know them as well as you think you do necessarily.
And so I just always prefer to use characters.
So I knew who he wasn't.
He wasn't going to be the whiny emoji RPG character.
But whose voice was it?
And I was actually talking to the Japanese voice actor for Noctis, who one night told
me that his inspiration was sort of Kurt Cobain.
who's kind of sweet at heart, but always on edge,
and this rock star who scorns the spotlight.
And it really clicked for me.
It was kind of an epiphany.
And so this is my one exception
to my only using scripted character roles.
And so if you have the opportunity
to talk to your Japanese voice cast,
it's a great place for ideas.
Failing that, your English voice cast
can give you a lot of input into the characters.
And so, yeah, if you do have voice actors,
definitely use them.
They know their characters kind of as well as we writers do.
Next up, so one bonus of having these independent backstories and flashbacks is that it added persistence to the universe and to the characters.
And so each story had its self-contained arc, but when you put them together, they form these life arcs for the characters.
And this really added psychological depth to the characters.
So if you go into the game alone,
Noctis starts off as kind of a disenchanted youth
who embarks on a journey to overcome sort of self-doubt.
But when we see him as a kid,
he's actually a really happy kid.
And we see the events that kind of cause him
to become the disenchanted youth we meet later.
But together, when you take his childhood story
and the story we see in game,
it forms this story of...
recovering lost innocence, which is kind of beautiful.
And similarly, with Prompto, there's
some stories of his insecurity and brotherhood,
and that gets reprised in sort of a heart-to-heart conversation
he has later.
And so this is kind of that independent yet integrated
at best.
Both stories stand on their own, but it
gives you kind of a deeper appreciation when they connect.
And the last point is a little more technical.
So Final Fantasy XV is a road trip
where you spend a lot of time hanging out with your friends
and that feeling really needed to be immersive.
So we devoted a lot of our energy
to creating this conversational chemistry.
Making the friendship feel real
was kind of the heart of the player experience
and these are some of the formula we applied.
This is very early, but early on we defined the interpersonal dynamics and kind of personalized them by equipping each with his fair share of
nicknames for the others.
We also kept little background speech ticks and idiosyncrasies for them, like generally avoids contractions,
never says he's sorry, and that sort of thing.
Establishing these kind of behind-the-scenes rules
was really invaluable given that we had multiple writers working on the project and it was across media.
So it was good to have these background rules that we could refer to.
We also used linguistic techniques to flesh them out.
To bring home the kind of casual and comfortable feel
of the characters, we tended to drop subjects
whenever possible, and we also leaned on our voice actors
for organic non-verbals, those little mumbles and clicks
and squeaks that can be tricky to script.
So along with breathing life into the characters,
these tricks helped us hit our line timings
because every line in the game had to match
the Japanese timing.
precisely. So that was really invaluable for keeping it sounding natural. And then the
last thing I have here is another technique we use to mimic real world speech that I call
Sorkinization, where each line picks up on or directly ties into the words of the line
before where you borrow a word to start a line or spit it back with a little twist or
expound on a metaphor or kind of mimic the delivery.
So picking up recently heard words is something natural
to language that we all do kind of unconsciously
and done in moderation, it can add a natural feel
to the dialogue.
Of course, if you overdo it,
you get a little too much Sorkin in it,
but yeah, use in moderation would be my advice.
And lastly for our plans, I wanted to talk about our plans for lore.
So Final Fantasy developed an unfortunate reputation for kind of delving into the esoteric
with its cosmology and for inundating players with unpronounceable proper nouns.
So we wanted to keep the lore rich, we wanted rich lore but needed to make it accessible.
So we built an on-ramp here.
And so we focused on the layman's kind of understanding of lore and made sure that we
could couch it in easy to digest terminology.
So we used terms like gods, demons, messengers, oracles, things that the average person on
the street had heard of.
Our summoned characters, which every Final Fantasy names differently, were called astrals.
We basically made sure that everybody could be clear on the basic ground rules for lore.
And then to prevent it from becoming too flat, we added in some flair in the forms of cryptonyms
and kennings.
So pictured here is the astral titan, who's also known as the god of earth, and that's
how most of the people of the world refer to him.
But every now and then you'll hear him called the Archean or land forger for a more kind
of eloquent style, depending on the context and who's talking.
So that was one way we kind of dolled up our lore.
And one other mode I personally enjoyed working on
was our Surreality.
And this is one example of some things we did
to kind of bring home a surreal feel.
So here we see Gentiana, a messenger who is in fact,
spoilers, the avatar of the ice goddess Shiva.
I'm sorry if that spoiled it for you.
Sorry.
To keep her shrouded in mystery,
we wrote her dialogue to not use you or I,
and it really created that sort of
otherworldly, detached feeling.
We kind of stole a page from Song of Ice and Fire,
Game of Thrones' Jaqen H'ghar.
That's kind of how he talks.
But we did it in a little different way, and it worked really well for her.
So we kind of stretched it out to all our gods, that they wouldn't use those direct
subjects and would give them kind of a detachment from humanity, which worked really well in
monologues, but it made writing dialogue really, really difficult because obviously the person
they're interacting with has to understand it as well.
And it took a lot of polishing to get right, but it was fun to do.
So yeah, beyond the structure, the diction we used was also chosen to convey that eerie
feeling that something beyond our understanding is happening.
So using interpretive language in our god scenes and our dream sequences gave more weight
to the words.
So for instance, the Japanese might literally state that the astral gods have granted you
their power.
which we rendered as the stars shine for you now,
which accomplishes the goal of the point
and allows for deeper interpretations and also
kind of adds depth to our cosmology as well. So we really enjoyed
using that sort of interpretive dialogue as a tool.
So those are some pages on our playbook
for establishing reality and surreality,
and I realize that nothing I've described so far
is particularly revolutionary or game-changing.
Many of you have probably employed similar techniques
in your own work.
What inspired me to give this talk, however,
was observing how some of these traditional
tried-and-true tactics proceeded to backfire
as the project progressed.
So this act is in two parts,
covering the wacky adventures of production
and the zany mishaps of promotion.
So, remember that bit I did on character chemistry
and Sorkinization?
That worked out fine for our cut scenes and set pieces,
but as it turned out, some of our pieces weren't so set.
And after we completed our recording
for the episode Dusk Eye demo,
we observed something interesting.
Part of our AI team's plan to maximize our voice assets
had been to concatenate the lines.
On the left here is the conversation metrics that they used
and on the right was a snippet
of the original linear studio script that we had submitted.
And this wasn't a branching dialogue tree, but also not entirely random.
The patterns were defined, but the same voice line could appear in very different mini-conversations,
with different lines preceding or following, and sometimes no lines.
So after all the effort we'd put into making our characters sound as humanly possible,
as human as humanly possible, the conversation started to kind of sound like robocalls.
So making an interchangeable dialogue system work in text is hard enough.
Set aside our lofty intentions of having the characters pick up on each other's lines.
And simply making the subjects and predicates agree
grammatically was going to be difficult.
So to pass the Turing test, we established,
we worked with our AI team,
and we established a couple ground rules.
The first was to separate the lines
that would launch a conversation for tonal difference.
Secondly, we worked on mapping out the specs linguistically,
because Japanese doesn't use plurals
and treat subjects differently.
And lastly, we needed to be able to stretch
any permutations that weren't working,
because you always need a safety clause.
And our AI team was great about helping us with it.
And it turned out really well. It was pretty organic. It was better than I expected. Our
banter was actually really well received and some of it was scripted and some of it was
this sort of organic concatenation. It really sounded like when you're on the road with
your friends for too long and you just kind of, your mind's in the distance. So it came
across really authentic in that way.
So, as stated earlier, the Final Fantasy XV universe didn't feature spin-offs with only
a few touch points.
Everything was interwoven.
So with three separate production teams for game, film, and anime, you run into some continuity
issues.
So I'm not going to rip any of our minor stitches into plot holes right here, but we did make
sure to cover all our logistics and details in the background at least, hopefully.
So while we managed to reconcile those details, there were kind of larger continuity concerns
that grew as the universe was expanding.
Namely, how does this all fit together?
So here you see dudes around a campfire, a tense confrontation with royalty, an illustrated
boy petting a dog, and a transforming flying car.
How do these people talk to each other?
It simply wasn't practical to have one overarching style that would apply to everything.
So if we couldn't have that, at least we needed to have contiguity, which is to say maintaining
suspension of belief at the seams where Technobabble met the arcane or where high fantasy met casual
banter.
And we actually encounter one of these in the very first scene of our game as Regis,
a character with a high fantasy tone, is established in the film.
is sending off Noctis, aka Kurt Cobain.
We found this, so we, I'm sorry,
we found the key to connecting their speech
was to build off the emotional father and son dynamic
and let the emotional content
kind of supersede the stylistic.
We found this with other characters as well.
When you draw on the relationship,
it kind of overwrote whatever stylistic conventions you were
trying to build beyond that.
So it kept the characters in the same scene
and indirectly in the same world.
And the last production test of time I have
is pretty straightforward.
For Authenticity, we cast kids for our child roles
and they turned in amazing performances.
But as our production schedule lagged on,
we did get a little nervous.
Just remember that your in-game kids will be young forever,
but your voice actors will grow up
and plan accordingly when you schedule.
So this was the intricate space-time tapestry of our rollout, and you'll notice I've included
trailers in here.
Most of us would not consider PR as part of our story.
Traditionally, the story is the part that is permanent, the thing that will be left
decades after the dust is cleared.
Promotion is an ephemeral phenomenon.
It happens, and then it dies.
But now more than ever, games are also phenomena.
They are experiences to which context is integral.
And they may have metas, they'll probably be patched,
and they'll definitely be memed.
So nowadays, games happen, and that's true
even for single-player games.
So we'll start at the beginning.
In the writing of any book, film, or game,
there looms a specter of those critical early questions
we have to ask ourselves.
So what, who cares, and why does any of this matter?
And more and more, audiences attempt to
kind of answer these questions by overanalyzing trailers.
So prior to the release of the previous slide,
before our regional marketing was really up and running,
the majority of news and promotion for the game
was coming out of Japan in the name of global promotion.
where English content was being plugged
into Japanese trailers.
So as I mentioned earlier,
we tend to rethink things from the ground up
in our localizations,
but we'd always done this on the assumption
that the information would be conveyed in the classic style,
i.e. when the player starts playing the game.
So while our character naming and accenting decisions
were being made with a larger background exposition in mind,
the audience wasn't seeing this,
and the global promotion and English exposition
were out of sync.
So we needed to prevent the misunderstandings
from melting down the internet.
Communicating with our regional marketing teams,
once we got them up and running,
and knowing their promotional schedules and messaging,
let us better kind of contextualize our content
for our audience, and tell a more cohesive story.
And they also helped cover for us,
like in the demo where we had the term Archean,
but we didn't have the term Astrals yet.
and people thought that the Archeans were the Summons when they're really the Astrals.
I know it's a minor detail, but it's a huge deal.
And our marketing was really good about contacting the community
and getting the fans to get on board with the correct terminology.
So, we owe them one for that.
So we worked on a lot of things for them also.
We were looking at their figurine box descriptions
and Latin American launch events
and commercial newspapers that would probably
get screen capped and soundtrack titles.
And we really ended up looking at a lot of stuff,
but that's kind of all part of maintaining the universe.
So one danger, however, of being steeped in your game's promotion so much is that you
lose sight of the players who come in blind, those who haven't been following the news
or watching the companion projects.
So how do you bring that audience up to speed without alienating or boring your avid fans?
So there's no easy answer for this.
I'm not sure we found the solution.
There's just so many permutations of the story,
storytelling and having an open world format
it only adds to the chaos.
So, first and foremost, the game's tale needs to stand on its own legs, and you write for
the uninitiated audience.
But that said, you don't want to kind of spoon-feed people what they already know.
And so one of the keys for us was to be nonchalant about our surprises and things, so that the
people who already saw it coming wouldn't feel too kind of taken there.
It also helps to be conscious of things like making sure you name drop in dialogue more
than you would normally, and making sure any key plot points from other media would at
least be available in ancillary text or interactive objects.
So yeah, in Final Fantasy XV we actually ended up with some kind of heavy-handed measures
like announcing characters' names on screen and a montage from the film.
But your mileage may vary.
We also had to be mindful of...
not overselling our reveals, uh, because you don't want to rub in the dissonance that the
player knows something that the character doesn't. Which brings me to my next point.
So one of the earlier trailers for the game back in 2014
showed the invasion of insomnia pretty much giving away
the ending of the film, like I just did right now.
But somehow it didn't spoil the story.
A trailer at Tokyo Game Show two months before our release
unveiled the main villain, which the player character realizes
only halfway through the game.
But this also didn't ruin things like I feared it might.
And so I think this owes to the story's reliance
on suspense over surprise.
I imagine a lot of you are familiar with the Hitchcock parable about the bomb in a restaurant.
You know, if the bomb goes off without warning, you surprise the audience for 10 seconds,
whereas if you let the audience know there's a bomb under the table, it'll go off at 3,
and you put a clock on the back that says 2.45, you get 15 minutes of suspense.
So spoilers really only spoil stories when they, when the stories intentionally hide
things or mislead the audience to hit them with a twist.
I mean you know that Caesar is going to die in the end, but you stay tuned to Julius Caesar
to find out how.
So in the age of internet crowdsource theories where kind of every outcome can be anticipated
by someone, leaning on big twists is becoming less and less kind of tenable.
Unless you can completely fence your game experience off.
So naturally you need some surprises in your work.
You don't want it to be too boring.
But if you're relying on the big twist in 2017,
it's not a good idea.
Okay, so the meaning of life.
Hold on, I skipped ahead one.
So life is short, which is to say fleeting or finite.
So Final Fantasy XV wasn't really built for eternity.
It's not gonna be brought out of cobwebs
and 100 years from now be ported to PlayStation 42.
The language and reality present
is very much a product of our time
and the experience is constantly kind of evolving
to survive.
My second point is that life is messy.
I'm sorry, I didn't set this up good enough.
So by meaning of life, what I mean by this is...
When I said bringing fantasy to life as the topic for the talk, life is a very vague thing
and I realize a lot of people cop to it, so I wanted to talk about what life meant to
me in the scope of Final Fantasy XV.
So first being life is short, where obviously it's a product of its time, and then life
is messy being all the unpredictable things that happen on Final Fantasy XV.
It doesn't really have emergent narrative, but it's also far from authorial because there's
so many hands in it, both development side and promotional side.
And so I'm not sure what it's gonna look like
a year from now, which is both frightening
and exhilarating, a lot like life.
And then my last point is that life is fun.
So, so many cool things have happened
that we didn't expect.
Our voice actors play the game on Twitch.
These forum debates and these hilarious memes
and our team is always taking it
and finding ways to tuck it into the game.
There was someone...
on our marketing team kind of dialed a tweet once
and it was this random string of letters
that got like a million likes, it was ridiculous.
So we just took that and made it one of like,
in the mobile game, it's one of the random names
it generates.
So just being able to kind of tie those things together,
it's been a lot of fun.
So all the missteps and successes along the way
have made for an amazing ride.
And so making the game was a lot of fun,
I hope playing the game was a lot of fun.
And talking here has been a lot of fun.
So thank you.