So my name is Dan Somali.
I'm a tools programmer at Guerrilla Games.
And together with my colleague, Sander van der Steen,
I'm going to talk about how we rebuilt our tools
pipeline during the development of Horizon Zero Dawn.
So for those of you who might be unfamiliar with the game,
let's take a quick look at a trailer.
All right, so now everybody knows exactly what the game is about.
Let's continue.
So prior to creating Horizon, we worked on Killzone,
which is a series of first-person shooters.
And when we were going to make the jump from building shooters
to creating the vast open world of Horizon,
it was going to be a big challenge for all disciplines
within our company, and the tools team was no exception.
So we'll cover a few different areas of interest,
but I guess the main takeaways of this talk
are that you'll get...
bit of insight into why we decided to rebuild our tools
and learn a little bit about how we approached this
while we were already in production.
And we'll show a few ways in which we think that it paid off.
So if you're somebody who is responsible
for maintaining a legacy toolset,
or you're just somebody who uses one on a daily basis,
this will hopefully inspire you
to do something about that situation.
So yeah, to begin with, I'll talk a little bit about the tools
that we use on Killzone Shadowfall,
followed by a bit of background on the process
of actually rebuilding our toolchain.
And then we'll go into some detail about our level editor,
our 3D editor, and how actual data editing works.
And if there's time, I'll cover a few other tools
that we have and finally share a couple of learnings
from our project and a bit about our future plans.
So at the start of Horizon,
we had a pretty fragmented tool set.
It was built upon a mixture
of different languages and frameworks.
We had very long iteration times.
I mean, in a really bad case, it could be like,
between a designer making a change
and actually being able to see it in-game
was like 20 or 30 minutes.
And to be frank, we had a lot of pretty unhappy users.
I mean, at this time, Unity and Unreal
were becoming much more popular and visible.
So we had some pretty strong dissatisfaction with our users
when they were comparing their workflows and features
in Guerrilla Tools and comparing it to Unreal and Unity.
So just a quick technical detail.
At Gorilla we use an intermediate storage format which is called Cortext
and we use that for all of our game data.
Almost everything except for textures and audio.
And before the data is loaded in the game, we transform it
through a... into an optimized binary representation
through a process that we call conversion.
So the primary editor that we had for Cortext was the Cortext editor.
Here's an image of the thing in all of its glory.
It's pretty old school.
Cortext editor displays the contents of a Cortext file as a 2D graph.
So...
just within follow resources with the file represented as notes on the on the
cameras and references between those objects are represented as wires.
So uses to create and figure a lot of our game data but in terms of actual
data editing it's pretty low level it's it's basically one step removed from
just editing your cortex files directly in a text editor which incidentally is
how a lot of the configuration for earlier kills and game was actually done.
So much of the user's energy was spent on the busy work
of kind of creating and understanding
these complicated resource structures
instead of just being free to focus
on the actual creative process.
This tool was written in C Sharp and WinForms
and a Sony framework called ATF,
which was recently open sourced.
And additionally, the code base for this tool
was fantastically complicated.
There was, it required really a lot of effort
to make even trivial changes in this tool.
So there was only a handful of programmers in the company
who could actually even work on it,
and there was basically nobody
who enjoyed working on it at all.
And the next major piece of a pipeline was Maya,
specifically our in-house Maya plugin.
So the plugin allows us to edit our game environments
inside of Maya and then export them into core text.
And the plugin uses Decima's renderer in the viewport,
so you get an accurate representation
of how your assets are going to look in the game.
However, it doesn't run the entire game loop,
so and also it leaves a lot of the game systems
in an uninitialized state, which means that you miss
a lot of the things that actually bring life to the game world.
This was built in C++ and Python
and also uses the Maya API very heavily.
And much like the Cortex editor,
there was only a handful of people
who actually were able to work on it
and also willing to work on it.
So the last piece was a state machine editor called SMED.
And SMED is a tool that generates Lua script,
which is then executed in game.
And this was used by designers
for much of the level scripting logic within Killzone.
So SMED began life as a prototype actually. It was created by a technical designer
to see if it would be possible to produce a visual script editor for our game.
The deal was that if the prototype worked out and was proven to be okay,
then the tools team would take ownership of this thing and make it into a real tool and then...
Yeah, we would go forward.
But even though the prototype was successful,
that transfer of ownership thing never really happened.
And so at some point, this tool gained critical mass
and the technical designer that made the original prototype
was now responsible for maintaining
an important part of the tool chain.
And this tool was written in Python.
So with the set up a designer who's aiming to accomplish a
simple task is is forced to navigate between the sort of
like Bermuda Triangle of lost productivity which involves
like flipping between these 3 different applications manually
copying string identifiers file names and values between them
and the tools also didn't talk to each other so it meant
that mistakes are only indicated way after the fact and usually
by some kind of impenetrable error message when you try to
look at the game just not not ideal.
There were also many other tools and utilities that were part of the daily guerrilla workflow,
but there isn't really time to go into them here.
So one kind of tangential thing is that during shadow fall
possibly out of just sheer frustration with the way that the tools pipeline was set up,
the debug UI was created.
And debug UI was an in-game user interface framework.
It's a pretty feature-rich framework,
but most importantly for what I'm talking about right now,
it was something that programmers found very easy to use.
And because of that, we ended up with a large number of very useful in-game tools.
So I'm going to show one of those quickly, just so you can get an idea of what I'm talking about.
So this is our in-game GPU profiler
and you can see it displaying timing values
for various draw calls during a frame
and it allows you to jump to different points in the frame
to examine the render targets or the back buffer.
You can also see the inputs for the different samplers and so on.
And it has an X-ray view which you can move over the scene
and get an idea of which intermediate buffers
are contributing to the final frame
and what they actually look like.
Yeah.
So that was a little bit about the tools and some of the technology,
but what about the game itself.
So when starting out, we knew that Horizon was going to be very,
very different to Killzone.
We hadn't made an RPG before.
We hadn't made an open-world game before.
And aside from that, this game was going to include new types of content
which we just hadn't built before,
like quests and interactive conversations.
And additionally, the tools team at Guerrilla is relatively small.
So depending on how you count it, we had like four or six
full-time tools programmers for a team size of about 220 people.
So we had to be really efficient about how we used our time
and our resources.
All things considered, it was pretty clear
that our extant tools pipeline would not easily
scale to meet the demands of Horizon,
so we decided to start again.
So at this point, we were ready to define some initial goals
for the new toolchain.
And we decided to start by building a tools framework,
which was going to act as the basis of all
of our future tools development.
And this was intended mainly to mitigate the
arbitrary linguistic and technological differences
between the tools and just enforce some consistency
between all of them.
Decima, which I'll cover a little bit later on,
is our in-house engine, and we wanted to leverage
as much of it as possible while building the new tools.
And lastly, the debug UI had shown us that
if it's easy to do so, then programmers will happily
make tools for their game systems.
So by using the engine libraries
and keeping the others code simple,
we would increase the chances of getting buy-in
from other teams and, most importantly,
help from other teams.
And, yeah.
So just because for an editing environment.
We want to make sure that we build tools that would fit our
content creators needs so that and we decided to build like
specific editors for each discipline and we call these
editing context and we built from usable components that we
could then create new ones for other teams as they needed them
and so these editing
context would sit inside of it a single application where the
content creator would be able to do all the work and this would
become the integrated game development environment which we
now call the decimator.
So before continuing, I want to provide a little bit of background on Decima itself.
Decima is, as I said, our in-house game engine,
and most recently it was used for Killzone Shadowfall,
RIGS, Mechanized Combat League, Horizon Zero Dawn,
and is being used for the upcoming Kojima productions
titled Death Stranding.
And like most engines, it's separated into layers.
So at the base, we have platform-independent game systems
just above the OS, and this insulates the layers above from the operating system,
which makes it just easier to port between different platforms.
It's also important to note that our engine has always had a full PC build
for development purposes.
Next is core.
This adds rendering and mesh primitives,
lights, particles, and so on.
And then game code on top of that,
which adds more specific game features
such as entities and crowds and cinematics.
So we wanted to put the tools framework on top of that stack
so that we would have access to everything below.
Decima is a very mature code base,
and it contained many libraries
that would be useful for tools development.
So here you can see the kind of things
that we were interested in taking advantage of.
One of the most important features
was the engine's super optimized RTTI system,
or runtime type introspection system.
which is exactly what we need to be able to manipulate data
in an Editor. So aside from getting a lot of well-written
code for free, using the Decima Engine libraries
would also mean that the Editor's code would present
a lower barrier to entry for the other programmers in the company
when compared to the Cortex Editor and SMED
and the Maya plugin.
So to fast forward a little bit, here's the Decima Editor
as it exists today.
And this is our level Editor context,
which is a 3D viewport onto the game
and an Asset Browser at the bottom,
a hierarchical outliner on the left,
and an Attributed Editor on the right.
Pretty standard stuff that you would expect to see.
This is a shot of our visual script editor,
which is used for almost all of our in-game designer-driven logic.
It has a 2D diagram renderer,
which displays the logic graph of the script.
On the right, you can see it uses the same attribute editor
as the previous slide.
And finally, here's a shot of our conversation editor
or dialogue editor.
So it uses the same diagram render as the last view,
but to show the logic graph of the conversation.
And this time, there's two new components.
So on the bottom left, there is a timeline
for positioning stuff inside of a sequencer
and a screenplay editor for writers
who work on the in-game dialogue,
which is on the bottom right.
So we...
We'd established some initial goals,
and we actually needed to start moving at this point.
But the thing is, Killzone was already finished,
and aside from a few people who were remaining on the project
to support multiplayer and DLC,
everybody was moving onto Horizon.
So production was already starting.
And despite the fact there was many issues
with the Killzone toolchain, it did work.
You could make a game with it,
and the content creators were familiar with those tools,
so they didn't necessarily even want anything to change,
which seems illogical, but that's just how it was.
And we also had no way to gauge how successful we'd be in this endeavor.
So we were going to have to start really small, minimize risks.
We couldn't disrupt the production of the game,
and therefore we would need to continue supporting the old tools
while we did this drive for new stuff.
So with that in mind, we decided to focus on a single team,
which was our audio team.
And it represents a pretty small group of users.
At this time, it was around four people,
and they have a very specific set of needs
for their workflow.
So by essentially porting this workflow
from the core text editor
into the fledgling Decima editor,
we would have an isolated test case
for the viability of the framework as a whole.
So our audio team works primarily with NodeGraphs,
and NodeGraph is a high-performance visual scripting
language that we developed in-house.
And this is a technology that we,
it generates C++ by the way,
which runs natively on the target.
And this was something we used very heavily in Shadowfall,
and it was being proposed as a replacement for SMED and Lua.
So this meant that if we were successful
in porting this audio team's workflow,
then later it would have benefits
for other teams in production.
If you're interested in learning more about this technology,
there's actually a talk from GDC 2014
by Andreas Varga and Anton Waltek,
and they go into some detail
about how our audio system works.
So as a reminder, this is the thing
that we were trying to replace.
And this is our first prototype,
which we built in C++ and Qt.
It used Qt's QPainter class for the diagram,
displayed the nodes in a similar visual style
to the old editor.
At this point, it wasn't very usable.
It was basically just like a read-only display
for node graphs that already existed.
We also had some performance issues with Qt,
so we decided that now we had access to Decima's renderer,
we could just rewrite the diagram rendering using that.
So that allowed us to write the diagram renderer
as a single, it draws a single quad
and then it has some pixel shader magic
to draw the entire thing.
It was super fast.
It can handle huge amounts of data.
Wasn't very useful though,
because you still couldn't edit or save or anything,
but it looked pretty good.
And this is what we have today, kind of skipping forward a few steps.
So once we added an attribute editor and a way to browse for files
and save them and edit them and so on,
we managed to convince one or two members of the audio team to just try it out.
And this was a really, really painful process, actually.
It required many iterations, and every time they came up against something
that wasn't possible in the new editor,
they would just immediately go back to using the old tools.
But we focused a lot of our energy on implementing features
that they were missing and eventually achieve feature parity
with the old editor, and these guys started working
in the Decima editor every day.
So it was our initial test case and it worked pretty well.
We reached feature parity with the old editor
much more quickly than we anticipated.
And because we shed this like onerous complexity
of the old editor, it meant that we could implement
new features very easily.
And most importantly, programmers from other teams
were comfortable enough with the code
that they were able to contribute
some pretty awesome features.
But I'll come back to that later.
For now, I'll hand over to Sandra.
OK, thank you, Dan.
So the Node Graph editor gave the tools team the necessary
confidence to pick up the next larger project.
And that would be creating a level editor, or 3D editor, as
we call it.
So in the next section, I'll explain some of the early
design decisions that led to this new editor.
So why create a 3D editor at this stage, you might wonder.
As Dan mentioned, we were already in production, and so
this is fairly ambitious.
Why did we not just simply invest more
into our Maya plugin?
So first of all, the first reason
was that Horizon Zero Dawn needed a lot of Quest content,
which is a somewhat new content type coming from the Killzone
series.
So the game design workflow that we had in place in Maya
was really the worst part of our Maya plug-in
in terms of usability.
Maya is simply not designed to do any level editing.
So secondly.
the 3D editor, a 3D editor like Unreal Unity
would eventually benefit other workflows as well.
It is a formidable task, and if we hadn't started it back then,
it would have never been able to finish it in time
for Horizon in the first place.
And finally, the game design team
offered a very achievable starting point
for us to work on a 3D editor.
If we could facilitate only object placement in the game,
we would already provide a huge workflow improvement
for the game design team.
So now that we've established why we wanted this 3D editor,
let's have a look at how we can actually achieve this.
Looking at what we have available,
a tools framework in its infancy,
and a game executable, we are immediately
presented with the first choice.
Do we integrate the desired game subsystems into our editor,
as illustrated on the left?
Or do we actually merge the full game
into our editor environment?
So let's zoom into using only game subsystems.
So this is the advantage of being able to tailor make your
game loop based specifically on your editor needs.
This leads to a very controllable viewport,
skipping unwanted game subsystems.
However, doing this will introduce a second code path
where these systems will be used, leading to code
complexity and potentially disparity between what you'll
see in your editor versus what you see in the final game.
Because more code is required, it will also
take longer to develop.
So the alternative then is integrating the full game in
the editor.
Game systems would truly function as they would in
game, and as an added bonus, we can use the earlier
discussed debug UI for free to give us a head start.
We would also be able to play in the editor just like we
would be able to do in game.
As a disadvantage, though, it does introduce more overhead,
as a lot of game subsystems are usually not required for
certain editing operations.
An example of this would be a weather system.
It's typically not very useful for the game
to be raining when you're actually
just placing an object.
It's both a hindrance for performance and usability.
So given the time considerations that we had at
hand, remember that we were already in production, we
really felt that integrating the full game would be our
best option.
So now that we want the full game running in the editor,
how do we actually achieve that?
We're faced with another decision.
Do we run the game in the same process as the editor,
or as we depict on the left here?
Or do we attach the editor to the game executable
and use an out-of-process solution?
Again, we examined our options.
An in-process game is faster to set up and easier to debug
because all data changes are direct and synchronous.
A crash in the game is problematic, though,
as it will inevitably take down the editor, which
will cause loss of work and loss of frustration.
It also makes it easy to modify in-game data directly,
as you can access game objects via pointers.
Over time, you could end up with a situation
where many different systems in the editor
would access different systems in the game.
We felt that this would lead to an unmanageable situation,
but enforcing this separation, we
figured that would be hard, because due to time constraints,
it's ever so tempting to just directly access a game system.
An out-of-process solution, on the other hand,
offers more stability, primarily because you
would be able to recover from a crashing game.
Because the game is a separate process,
coders are forced to work in a cleaner way.
as the editor cannot directly modify game objects via pointers.
Finally, UI updates are not tied to the frame updates in the game and so your UI will be
more responsive, even though the game might not be.
So the downside of this is that you have to write a communication layer, resulting in
a longer initial development time.
This communication layer would also be asynchronous, which make it quite tricky for debugging.
So similar to the decision on integrating the full game, we
went for an in-process solution because of the time
constraints and pressure from production.
We did decide that an out-of-process solution should
always remain an option later on, and so wanted to ensure
code separation.
To enforce this code separation, we developed the
3D editor as if the game was running in a separate process.
No data was to be shared between the
editor and the game.
Because of this separation that we quite strictly enforced,
I'll continue to use the word process to describe,
like editor process, meaning code executing in the editor,
and game process for code executed in the game.
Anyway.
Luckily for us, making these early quick gains
paid off quite well.
So I have a video I'm about to show you here from roughly a
year after starting in 3D Editor.
And it demonstrates how a game designer uses the ability to
play in the editor for his workflow.
So to start off, the designer explores some section of the
world in play mode, decides this is a nice spot for an
encounter, and so goes into edit mode.
Now there are some trees in the middle here.
So what we're going to do is we're going to paint them out
to clear the area a bit.
And we also want to paint some more trees in the surroundings.
So we're just going to do that.
And then in the center of the screen
where you want to place this encounter,
you want to flatten the terrain out a bit.
So we use some terrain sculpting magic for that.
And so this looks like now we can actually place our encounter.
So we use the content hierarchy on the left to create an encounter, give it a name,
create it in the middle, use the asset browser also on the left to create some robots.
So now we have two robots and we want to add a rock in the middle,
provide some player cover perhaps.
I'm not a game designer, so I wouldn't really know.
But yeah, so we just use the tools to drag drop the rock in, place it.
Save it, going to try it out.
So now we're immediately back into edit mode.
And yeah, Aloy can shoot some robots and see if this
actually works out well.
Pretty sweet.
So with our high-level design now discussed, let's look into
some subsystems that we required for this 3D editor to
actually work.
So in this section, we'll also see how we deal with the
separation between editor code and game code.
So a problem that you encounter quite early on when
then diving into this solution is that the data that is in
the game is not necessarily the same as the
data that is on disk.
This is caused by the process called conversion that Dan
explained earlier.
Examples of what can happen in conversion are shader
compilation, and mesh optimization, et cetera.
So having this optimized game data is a fairly common
situation in games, but it provides a problem for editing
as information is lost.
Saving out cortex based objects that are read by the editor is
not always possible once you're in the binary game data.
So luckily, we already stated that we did not want the
editor to operate directly on the data in the game.
As a result, the editor works on the cortex counterpart, if
you will, from the loaded binary data in the game.
Each process, therefore, has its own copy of the data, and
it cannot access the copy of the other process.
So data in the editor is not identical nor shared between
editor and game.
A central concept in dealing with this problem is something
that we call the editor node.
So editor nodes provide all editing functionality for an
object in the game.
An editor node knows about a game object, but this is a
one-directional relationship.
So this is a convenient way of keeping the game code clean.
The editor node lives in a separate project and code file
from the game, and so the game code stays very clean.
There's no hash ifdef editor in our code base.
Second problem caused by the game operating on the
converted data is hierarchy.
For performance reasons, the game has little hierarchy of
objects left remaining, resulting in a long, flat list
of objects that are all in world space.
This is very fast and efficient for rendering in the game,
but not very good for editing, as often we
want to edit in local space.
So in order to restore some hierarchy of objects
for editing in game, we built a hierarchical tree structure
of these editor nodes.
So this is done once the game is loaded
and the user enters the edit mode.
The tree is constructed top down,
starting at the content root, and reflects the content that
is currently loaded in the game.
So having a single editor node tree, as shown on the image
here, would violate our earlier stated goal that the editor
cannot directly modify game data.
The tree structure is built up in game, and so it should only
be used by the code living in the game.
So in order to facilitate editing hierarchical data, we
actually have two editor node trees.
So this allows both the editor and the game to reason about
content hierarchy and do world or local space
conversions, et cetera.
So these two trees are structurally identical,
but reference different data.
Changes made in the editor are mapped onto the node tree
and communicated to the game.
So what we actually communicate in our editor
is the next part of this presentation,
and for which I'll hand over back to Dan.
All right, so making changes to objects.
When defining goals or requirements,
it's sometimes important to list things
that you know you don't want.
And in our case, after working with the Quotext editor
and to a lesser extent the other legacy tools,
we had a pretty good idea of what we didn't want.
So we didn't want to have any kind of proxy representations
for game objects or string-based accessors
or editor-specific boilerplate in the code
or any kind of code generation steps in the build pipeline
that would make the editor work.
And that helped us to define some goals
when it came to how we wanted to actually write the editor code.
So...
In the editor code, we wanted to just work directly
with the concrete objects that the C++ classes
and structs that were defined in the engine.
And data modification by the code should just be performed
with direct member access or via accessor functions.
And mostly as a corollary of these two goals,
we should be able to reuse any kind of existing
data transformation utilities that already existed
within the engine code and within our conversion pipeline.
So doing these things would mean that our game
and engine programmers would also understand the editor code
and would find it easy to work with.
So being able to make changes is good, but what is best in life?
In any kind of data editing environment, it's critical to be able to undo changes that have been made,
and this allows users to experiment, to recover from their mistakes,
and generally feel like they're in control over what's actually going on.
So, looking at this slide, like the first goal seems almost redundant to state,
but it is actually important.
The code for the undo system had to be as simple and reliable as possible,
and in the interest of accomplishing these goals,
we decided to avoid the kind of common...
uh, command pattern which involves a virtual do and undo function.
Um, because, well, there's two reasons for this.
Like, the first is we didn't think the undo system or anything related to it should need to change
in order to support new editor features.
And we wanted to remove the
possibility of having asymmetric data transformations.
That is to say, an undo implementation that isn't the exact inverse of its do implementation.
So given that we're approaching this whole thing from a completely clean slate,
we may as well consider a totally ideal scenario.
And in our case, that would be a system that just sees all the changes that are being made in the editor,
knows how to undo those changes automatically.
So we investigated this a little bit,
but quickly found that such a system involved way too much overhead.
And it was also pretty difficult to delineate
when complicated changes were starting and ending.
So the compromise that we settled for is that before modifying data,
a programmer will provide some hints to the undo system
about which objects are going to be modified,
and then perform some modifications,
and later indicate when those modifications are complete.
So it's actually described changes in the editor.
We use a transaction system, and the transactions
consist of commands.
And you can see a pretty simplistic example
of such a thing here.
But each command describes a simple individual change,
such as the addition or removal of an object
or an individual change to an attribute value.
And these changes are annotated with RTTI
so that we have enough information
to actually use these transactions to transform
the editor data.
And the transaction system also has a subscriber mechanism,
which allows you to receive notifications for all data
changes that are happening in the editor.
And this system is mostly used to update the user interface
inside of the tool, have the visual representation
of the data remain in sync with the backing data.
So when a transaction is created or applied against the data,
It is sent around to all the registered listeners in the editor.
So in this case, that would be the individual components
that have subscribed for notifications.
And each listener is free to respond to the data change however it likes.
But typically, a controller will inspect the transaction
to see if any of the data which is being changed
is represented in the view,
and then it will just update its visual representation.
For our views, we follow the Model-View-Controller pattern quite strictly,
which has a few advantages in such a system.
Mostly, code separation in that our components
don't need to know about each other or even...
communicate with each other.
They're only interested in representing data,
modifying data, and responding to modifications in data.
It also means that the components support changes
from anywhere, so they can be representing a change
that's made by themselves or by other components,
or even framework-level operations
such as reloading of files and what have you.
And it also means that because of this,
there's no notion of directionality
in any of the editor code, so views aren't concerned
if this operation is a do or an undo or a redo.
They just respond to the data changes.
So one of the things we tried in the early days
when we were playing around with the system
is to actually build these transactions by hand
and then apply them against the data
in order to effect the change.
And this is possible, but it actually proved very quickly
to be way too cumbersome to be viable
and it didn't fit with our ease of use goals
in coding terms.
So instead, we built a utility class
which would just analyze changes
after they'd already happened
and generate a transaction that described
all the changes that it had observed.
So, before making a change, the programmer will use this diffutil to take a snapshot of the object state.
And a snapshot is just a shallow, attribute-wise copy of the original object.
And after that, the code is free to make any kind of modification to that object.
And once those changes are complete, the programmer will tell the diffutil that he or she is finished with the changes,
and the diffutil will compare the original snapshot against the current state.
And...
This works by using our RTTI system,
so it reads the attribute values,
and therefore we only see changes
on data that is actually exposed to the RTTI system.
So it's more fine-grained
than just doing direct memory comparisons.
Yeah, so how does this actually look in code?
As you can see here, we have a super handy function
that's gonna give us a pointer to a spotlight
that we intend to modify.
So we call that function,
and then we create a diffutil on the stack,
and we use it to take a snapshot
of the spotlight's current state.
So then we just perform some kind of modification.
In this case, we use an accessor function
to set the cone angle to 30 degrees.
And then afterwards, we tell the diffutil that we're done
by calling commitChanges.
And we also supply a human-readable description
of what we just did, which can be shown to the user
in the user interface, for example.
And then the diffutil will compare the snapshot
against the current state, and it will produce a transaction
that describes that change.
And that's the only interaction that a programmer
who's writing editor code actually has to do with the undo...
has to perform to work with the undo system.
So once we have a system that describes changes in this super granular fashion,
it means that writing code to undo those changes is actually trivial.
So to revert a change, we take our original transaction
and we reverse the order of the commands
and then we replace each command with its inverse.
So, for example, an add object command becomes a remove object command,
a set value command will use the old value instead of the new value,
and once we have this transaction, we just apply it against the data
and the data is now back in its original state.
Easy.
So in the same way as before, when we have an undo transaction,
we just send a notification about that transaction
to all the subscribed listeners,
and the whole system just works without any kind of code changes.
So what went well with the system?
Well, it was very, very reliable,
and it's a transparent system,
at least to the programmers who are using it,
and it can represent any kind of complicated changes.
Because our in-editor views are only ever responding to transactions,
there is no distinction between do and undo
in any of our editor view code.
And I guess what's most telling about this code is the fact that it hasn't really changed all that much in the last couple of years.
I mean, we wrote it. Of course, there were some things that we didn't figure out in the beginning,
so we had to tweak it a little bit.
But at some point, it worked, and it just has continued working for, like, two and a half years or three years or something.
That said, there are a couple of things that are not super great.
So...
The system relies very heavily on having transactions which describe all data changes that are occurring.
However, as a programmer, it's pretty easy to forget to surround your changes in a diffutil
before you actually start directly modifying the object.
And this can lead to some very subtle irregularities in the timeline of the history stack.
We perform some validation on transactions and debug bills to try and check the changes
and make sure that everything makes sense, but of course we can't catch everything.
And lastly the system doesn't support any file system changes
which means that if a user moves files around using our refactoring tools
the system doesn't support undoing those changes.
But this is something that we're actually looking into fixing right now
and we'll try and get it working for our next title.
But actually now I'm going to hand back to Sander
who will describe how this works with the 3D editor.
So let's map this on to everything I explained about
the 3D editor before.
So when we make a data change in the editor, it results in
the transaction being broadcast.
So the editor node tree living in the editor listens for
these changes and picks up this change.
It determines which node in the tree is affected by the
change and sends this information to the game along
with the data change itself.
So the corresponding editor node in the game then receives
the change and modifies the game object, and thereby
completing the edit.
So with the information I've given before about having 2
editor node trees in our process and the data
differences between the editor and the game, the previous
diagram is obviously a bit of a simplification.
For starters, data in the editor is in local space, and
objects in the game are in world space.
Let's have a look at how the node trees allow us to deal
with these changes.
So let's say we modified the local space of the spotlight
object, my spotlight, in this little hierarchy you see here.
The spotlight has a parent object, myPrefab, which for
this example will be the root of the tree.
Each node in the tree can act as an adapter for transactions
flowing through it.
To facilitate this, all transactions are applied at
the root of the tree.
In this case, when the local space changes passes through
the prefab, it appends its own local matrix to the transaction.
So the transaction then being passed to the next object,
which is the final object in the spotlight.
It can do its modification.
And because the data has flown through its parent, the
data transaction will now be in real space.
So because these steps are recursive, we return back to
the prefab after successful application of the change in
the spotlight.
Should an ancestor node need to respond to changes of its
children, this is the place where you could do it.
More advanced objects might trigger updates to vegetation
placement or terrain, as we'll see in the following video.
So in this video that I borrowed from my colleague,
we're actually moving a road node.
And road nodes are part of the content hierarchy.
And its parent node is a road system.
And that actually knows how to modify the terrain.
So moving these roads, as you see, actually updates the
vegetation and the terrain systems in the game.
This is a good example of how the EditorNodeTree actually
facilitates this.
So to the observer viewer, there is a piece of
information missing here.
Tools like the ones we've just shown actually draw a gizmo in
the game and allow the user to interactively operate on it.
Plenty of tools work this way, such as, for example, moving,
but also painting, et cetera.
So how did we implement this in the framework?
Because we already know how to describe a data change using
transactions and a diffutil, in an Eve implementation, we
would simply reverse the order of the transaction and support
the following data flow as well.
So reading the diagram from right to left, the tool sends
a transaction to the node tree in the game, which then
transmits its change back to the editor, where we do the
same modification on the cortex data that we have just
done in game.
So we did not do this, because this is problematic for
various reasons.
First of all, it becomes unclear which process has
authority over the data.
Secondly, because of data loss in conversion, it might be
impossible to have this code path in the first place.
And thirdly, and lastly, you would need some system to
prevent a transaction being generated in the editor to
flow back to the game again and then create a cycle.
So because of these problems, we implemented tool support or
gizmo support somewhat differently.
The key here is that the tools do not actually modify the
data.
They simply broadcast an intention to the editor,
telling the editor what they'd like to change.
It's up to the editor to actually make the data
modification itself.
This data modification is then processed in exactly the same
way as any other transaction.
And that way, the editor keeps authority over
the data at all times.
So it also automatically works with undo, as the input for
the editor data modification on the left is then the undo
system instead of the tool.
It is still the editor node in the game that modifies the
game object as a result of a transaction in the editor.
The game itself has no notion of the undo system at all.
So there's one part in updating a running game that
we have not looked at at all.
And that is structural changes to the node tree itself,
adding and removing objects.
So this is done by a separate system that we call GameSync.
So GameSync is a continuation of a system that we had in place
before we started working on the 3D editor
and was written for hot-loading particles into a running game.
The system has been heavily expanded
during the development of Horizon,
and it works by tracking all changes in the editor,
creating a patch file, and then inserting that into the game.
Since we like working with spotlights,
let's copy the spotlight in this hierarchy
and see how GameSync works.
So first, the incoming change is analyzed.
The analysis phase determines which objects are modified and
what other dependencies are required for successful
application of the patch.
So these dependencies are extra objects that are
required for the conversion process or extra objects that
might be required for the targeted game subsystem.
The analysis phase writes out a single cortex file containing
all required objects.
So in this example, it contains the prefab as it will
contain a reference to this new spotlight.
And obviously, the file will contain
a new spotlight itself.
So this cortex file is then converted into a binary file
and saved to disk, ready to be loaded and
inserted into the game.
The game is then paused at a sync point, meaning no
streaming is happening and all threads are
paused effectively.
So applying the patch means copying the objects in the
patch file to the affected game systems.
The target objects in the game are overwritten, meaning that
any cached pointers in the game actually
will remain valid.
Finally, after applying the patch, the game and all of its
subsystems are resumed.
Recapping on how GameSync worked, from a tools team we
have mixed feelings.
On the one hand, we have a solution
that accepts all changes throughout the editor,
and even changes on disk can be tracked
by monitoring the file system.
It can also sync patch files to a dev kit,
allowing a user to see edits on the target
without having to restart the game.
On the other hand, getting GameSync fully reliable
proved impossible throughout the project.
Because game systems predate game sync,
game sync tried to respect these systems as much as possible
and thereby avoiding work for other code teams.
This led to special case code creeping into these systems
and very complex analysis code.
These complexities further then complicated
or generated performance problems
where worst case applying a relatively simple change
could take as much as five to 10 seconds,
breaking a user's workflow.
All of these complexities also led to inconsistencies
in the results as well.
Game sync could crash or produce incorrect results,
such as objects being not placed incorrectly placed
in the world.
And this then led to a very low level of confidence
from the users, making it high on our wish list
to rewrite for a next project.
But let's not end here.
For the final part of this presentation,
I would like to give the word back to Dan
so he can give an overview of other tools
that we have developed.
Those out.
Okay as I mentioned earlier we managed to get some help from
another team while working working on the note graph editor
and the most significant contribution came in the form
of a fully featured debugger which was able to show debug
information in real time from active instances of a graph
which was running within the editor or just within a
connected instance of the game running on target.
And so the debugger had all the kind of usual features you'd
expect to see such as variable inspection execution
visualization and.
It was also gathering this information over time,
so this meant that the editor could then facilitate historical debugging
and it would highlight previous executions on a timeline
where the execution flow had changed.
So it meant that it was very easy for users to kind of scrub back in time
and figure out when some particular condition was met
or some condition had changed.
So this debug functionality turned out to be super useful
during the development of Horizon Zero Dawn,
and it spawned some similar debuggers for other systems,
and all of those debuggers and visualizations
were made with very minimal involvement
from the tools team, which for us was a pretty good indicator
that we were successful in making the tools framework
something that could be used by the rest
of the programmers in the company.
So here's a video of the note graph debugger I was talking about.
You can see how the graph is currently executing.
This is actually the graph sound for the main character's breathing.
You can hover over inputs on the graph and see what is actually going on, how the value
is changing over time.
and you can see the execution path being visualized,
but you can also pause the execution of the graph in game,
and then start to look at previous executions,
and you can see how long they were taking
in microseconds and so on,
and you can actually then step through those executions
and see when the control flow changed
and flip back and forth and see how the values
are actually working in this graph.
Something else that was completely new for Horizon
was interactive conversations,
and
With this feature, we were not beholden to any kind of existing workflow.
So it meant that we were free to just build a new editing context from scratch
to meet the specialized needs of the teams that were going to be using this tool.
So that would be the writers and the quest designers and cinematic artists
who would actually make the conversations within Horizon.
So here's an overview of the editor itself.
It's kind of hard to read, to be honest,
but we have a graph that just controls
the flow of the conversation.
So the main character is speaking to somebody
and they are presented with dialogue choices
and the graph can also check for conditions
like have you accomplished a particular quest objective
and so on.
Let's take a quick look at a conversation in Horizon.
You gave them the best work you'd ever do.
And look at it now.
They defaced it because they hated what it stood for.
They defaced a thing slaves like him lived and died for.
Slaves they've already forgotten.
Short-sighted bastards, the lot.
If they thought their son set off this bridge, they'd jump after it.
Ah...
I thank you for honoring my wish.
I hope you can find peace.
Okay, so that was actually from quite a while ago in production.
But what's interesting about this conversation is that it's completely auto-generated.
So, I mean aside from the audio, all of the animations and camera cuts and gesture beats
and so on were selected by a data-driven rule-based system.
And the...
Auto generation system will also generate a robo voice
and facial animations where required.
So basically it means that a designer
could just produce game ready content by typing
in a few sentences for a conversation
and then immediately see it in the game
or even just game sync it into an active instance of the game
and get quick feedback on how their actual flow
of the conversation is actually going to be.
The system was pretty heavily inspired by the work of CD
Project Red and BioWare who've both delivered talks
in the last several years about how their conversation systems
work.
If you have any interest in the subject,
I highly recommend you check out the talk from last year's GDC,
which is shown here about the Witcher 3's dialogue systems.
But this is something that we were only able to do
because we'd built this new framework
that meant it was easy for us to experiment
and just try out new ideas.
So something else is the profiler framework.
So at the beginning of the talk,
I showed a video of our GPU profiler,
and this is a video of our global profiler,
which is for profiling on larger segments of time,
more along the lines of milliseconds.
But we had this profile framework already running in-game
and we were able to expose it to the editors
that we were able to start getting profile data back from any tools basically.
So we can see like how much time is being spent in certain areas,
we can drill in really quite to quite small time scales
and get an overview on what's actually being done in the editor or the game.
So we expose this profiler framework to the editor
and this allowed us to build a front end for the profiler,
which can show profile data in real time from any tool.
And this of course includes the game,
but it also applies to the executables
that we use to run our conversion process
and any of our kind of demons that are running
to facilitate our other tools, framework stuff.
And it's interesting to note that the editor
also runs the profiler framework,
which means that it can profile itself.
in real time which is super handy for being able to investigate performance
issues quickly or just figure out why the editors running slowly on like one
guys machine.
Something else we worked on you is a world map and one of things about
working on an open world game is it can be pretty hard to get an overview over
where things are happening so to that and we started working on a 2 dimensional
map representation of our game data.
displaying game data on the world map it's used in game is a pretty logical progression
and thanks to a plugable overlay system. It's possible to create visualizations for whatever we want basically so
right now we use it for showing stuff like the locations of quests or the location of Jira bugs
and it's pretty handy to get a quick quick eye on what's actually happening in the game.
But unfortunately it came on pretty online very late in the project
and it wasn't really widely used but it's something we'll probably continue to work on pretty heavily for the next project.
There's a quick video of that.
This is just a view that shows some world encounters.
So you're able to kind of filter and see
where you might run into particular types of robots
within the world.
And again, there's filtering, so you
can get a quick overview of what you actually want to see.
There's another overlay that we have
which shows our performance stats for each tile, which
is gathered on a daily basis.
And this shows whether our tiles are in memory
and within CPU budgets and GPU budgets and so on.
It shows tiles that are in budget as green and tiles that are out of budget as red.
And unfortunately, this screenshot is from very late in production,
I think right before Gold Master, so everything is green because we were in budget.
But we can drill into that tile and then get an overview on the different parts of performance stats
that have been happening over time, over very long periods of time,
because we gather these stats always.
So the last thing that actually came up was...
Now that all of our tools are written in C++, it meant that a few of the programs at Guerrilla
had the idea of creating a C API for the tools framework, so we could use this to expose
certain areas of the tools framework's functionality to other languages.
And so, with that in mind, we exposed stuff like file loading and saving and object manipulations,
and then we wrote a wrapper in Python.
for the decimal API which allows tech artists and designers and anybody who
knows most Python basically to create scripts that will like create game
content or modify existing game content and they use these the same tools
framework functionality that we actually used to build the editor.
So revisiting the C++ code example from earlier we can look at the same code
which is written in Python.
And yeah, we retrieve the spotlight to edit.
And in Python, we create a transaction
so that we can actually start modifying data.
And then we just use some accessors
to modify the cone angle once again.
And then we just commit the transaction.
And this is how somebody would do the same things
that we do in the editor with Python.
There's also a lot of other really cool stuff
that I would like to show today, but there just isn't enough time.
So I'll move on to conclusions.
So now that the game is finished,
we have some time to kind of tick stock.
And we realized that we were much more successful
in this whole endeavor than we anticipated,
but there's still a lot of work left to do.
We'd like to bring more of our team's workflows
into the new editor.
A lot of our environment, our set dressing
is still being done in Maya.
Some of our VFX work involving particles
is still performed in a standalone particle editor tool.
And so...
We'll start building you at a contest for these different workflows and continue to move
everybody in the company into our editor.
And it's under mentioned we'd like to rewrite the game sync system.
So it's a source of a lot of mind boggling debugging problems throughout the project
and.
we want to 3 is out of process that we can stabilize the editor because even
though we we had a really quick start with the 3 editor and a lot of progress
it meant that when we came towards the end of the game and and the project
story in the game was being optimized very heavily that had a really big
impact on the stability of the editor. So we'd like to separate this process so
that we don't lose start this use his work from crashes in the in the game.
And although we made a lot of progress on this project for the tools user
and space building was done in like let's say an organic fashion which means
that a lot of tools and concepts of the editor as user interface are kind of
confusing or irritating and users find it pretty hard to discover new features
and so we want to work on the stuff quite a lot in the future.
Let's say thanks to everyone at the gorilla who helped out with the stuff
and some special thanks to the people whose work you've you've seen here
today.
And.
Also, we are we're hiring so if you're interested in working with
What is frankly just a bunch of really awesome people with a lot of talent?
Then please click that link and send us your resume and we'll take a look
But yeah, that's it. So does anybody have any questions?
Thank you.
So after seeing some video content,
like just mass market content,
on how they were changing the workflow
of Decima Engine in previous titles
to fit the new Death Stranding title,
I was wondering, is there anything in particular
that you learned from that experience
or that was integrated as a result of that experience
with the Kojima Productions team once they came on?
Yeah, I mean, those guys were working for many years
on their engine, and Fox Engine had a lot of
cool capabilities.
So we learned a lot of technical stuff from those guys,
but in terms of workflow changes,
they're much more focused on cinematics than we were.
So our cinematics pipeline was something
that we analyzed quite heavily to understand
how we could improve it to fit their workflows
where they wanted to have very long sequences
of a lot of complicated interaction
between many characters.
So that was a pretty big part of it.
But yeah, that's about it.
So a couple of questions.
One would be.
How did you get buy-in from production and management,
or were there any problems with it?
And also, in the early days when you were working on stuff
that wasn't yet usable,
were you having to support two systems
for people editing the game?
Yes.
So, the question is, like, how do we get buy-in
from other teams, and how do we actually, like,
approach the process of dealing with two separate parts
of editing?
So getting buy-in from management wasn't that difficult
because we had the backing of our technical director
to just push forward with this that we thought,
in a way that we thought made sense.
Getting buy-in from our users was much harder
because the tools were really kind of crappy
for like a very long time.
And that meant that nobody wanted to use them.
So we had to invest a lot of energy
in just making sure that we met all the demands
of like reaching feature parity for that stuff.
In terms of editing,
having two different systems of editing,
that was kind of a pretty.
tricky tricky thing is very hard to summarize shortly because
there's like many different angles that was always different systems and we have in the game and
moving on to new data formats in the new editor would make anything
much easier. But I can give you some specific examples in more detail
but it's it's very very hard thing to to summarize.
mainly like all the old tools pretty much had a feature stop
once this got rolling.
So we did support them.
I mean, as Dan ended his presentation,
not all teams have moved over to the new editor.
But yeah, the new features for the old tools
is zero or very little since we've started this.
Hey.
Thanks for the talk.
do you have any um like uh data messaging uh steps like you know like a pipeline step or
something like that and how does that work with the like you know the diff patch file that you
do or is that actually what you mean in the uh the game sync stuff where it's actually done on
the game side where you know the the the the editor data has to be kind of messaged like you
know strings need to be hashed and.
all the things need to be generated for the run time to work.
Okay, so you're talking specifically about how the
editor data is actually transferred into the game
and how that transformation process works?
Yes.
Yeah.
Okay.
So we have a conversion pipeline that is basically just
lazily converting the graph of content
that is going to be loaded into the game.
And that conversion process can involve basically anything.
I mean, in the simplest form, it's just that we take
some
pre-converted data and write it to a binary stream in accordance with the RTTI schema.
But in complicated cases, it can be things like where we do a lot of baking operations and then write out
Stream in a certain way or whatever, but this is something which
Game systems and game objects are free to implement. However, they want so there's a lot of different things happening there basically, but so that
Runs in the game process, right? It technically does but not not inside the game instance
So we use the same executable
But it's it's a different instance like we rename the executable file and then we run the conversion process so that will basically just eat
up the core text files and spit out core binary files.
And those core binary files are then
actually loaded by the game.
So this is essentially an offline process,
but it's done on demand.
So as you're working in the editor or whatever,
and you load up the game, the game
will make a request to a convert worker for this operation.
It will convert the data, and then that
will get loaded into the game.
Cool.
Thanks.
I had a question about a little less technical, I guess, logistics of making this happen.
And so you guys started out with one prototype.
Was that pushed from like engineers to higher levels?
Like did you pitch it or was it like an order from up there somewhere?
Like how did you guys go about that?
We don't really have like a sort of...
strong hierarchy or something and the real so it was nobody
saying like hey you need to make this or something it was more
like as a tool seen we discussed it quite quite extensively
and we look to the options we're faced with and it was kind of
like the new game was so big and complicated that
while it would be technically possible to make it with all
tools it would just require so much effort that we decided
we should at least explore making a new editor and trying
that out so that was something that we just sort of did and
it was something we a conclusion that we reached as consensus
as a team basically.
I had a quick question about the basic stuff like the menus and the docking panels and the trees. They were all rewritten using this
That's the framework that that was started. There was nothing reused from OS code or you know I'm trying to say
Well for all of the kind of like lower level stuff like
File handles and what have you that was already present inside of the decimal engine
For the user interface, we have sort of two different parts.
We have our own custom control framework,
we call it, which is just simple things like buttons or any kind
of two-dimensional rendering.
And then for the most of the bread and butter controls
of the user interface, such as buttons and menus and whatever,
we use a framework called Qt, or Q-T,
depending on how you want to pronounce it.
But yeah, that's it.
All right.
OK.
One more.
Quick question.
So at what point of the process did you
decide to create the Decima API?
And how much of an undertaking was
it to create the Python wrappers for your tech artists?
That was something that happened very recently, actually.
I don't recall the exact date, but I
think it was within the last two or three months or something.
And in terms of getting it online,
it was a very easy thing to make, in a way.
It took much more time to really drill down and understand
exactly what this thing was going to do
and how each API call was going to look and whatever.
And then one guy just sat and wrote it,
and it took him, I think, a couple of weeks
to make the thing.
Cool.
Thanks.
All right, well, I think there's no more questions, so.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.