This is the Digestive Talk.
I hope you'll stay with me.
If you fall asleep, please don't snore.
If you can turn off your sound on your mobile phone
and other noisy devices, that would be very much appreciated
and we'll jump right in into
crowdfunding your video game in 2019.
My name is Thomas, Thomas Bideau. I'm French. I've been in the game industry for a while.
I'm a video game consultant. I consult on a variety of topics related usually to video
game publishing. I work a lot on free-to-play, PC, and console games, these sort of things.
But I also have crowdfunding addiction. I really like crowdfunding. I'm back.
To this date, 279 projects on Kickstarter and a few others
on other platforms.
But also, being in the game industry,
trying to make my addiction something useful,
I also work with people with a crowdfunding campaign.
I started with looking at data, because people were not
looking at data for crowdfunding.
They were looking at the big projects.
So I started to do data mining on Kickstarter,
able to provide a 10,000 feet view on the crowdfunding
state for video games.
And by providing data, I started to look at best practices.
People brought me on their project.
I've advised about 40 campaigns, most of them video games.
And I've worked directly into five campaigns, four of them
on Kickstarter, one of them on Hulu.
And I've been running workshops helping developers and creators
to basically try to make their crowdfunding campaign as
successful as possible.
This talk has four parts.
There's the first one is going to be the state of play.
How is crowdfunding right now?
There's then a part on what kind of projects are right
for crowdfunding and try to help you,
you know, establish whether or not a crowdfunding project
is what a crowdfunding campaign is right for your project.
I'll talk about choosing your platform.
Should be relatively brief.
And then I'll talk about best practices.
And before we go into the state of play,
so I love numbers, I try to spend not too much time
on numbers, I try to show like snapshots
and give you a sense of where we're at.
Sorry.
And I'm not going to see much of your hands,
but if you can try to raise your hands,
who has run a Kickstarter campaign before,
a crowdfunding campaign before,
who wants to do something on crowdfunding?
Yeah, that's why you're here, good.
Who's not sure, is coming here to get an answer
whether or not they should do it?
Okay, a few people, excellent, excellent.
Who has never backed,
who has never backed a Kickstarter campaign
or any crowdfunding of any sort?
Good, shame on you.
So numbers.
I said numbers, yeah.
So this data is us crawling Kickstarter every day,
trying to see which products work.
This is all about video games.
Kickstarter is very useful to understand
the state of play for crowdfunding,
because this is the biggest crowdfunding platform.
This is not the only one,
we'll talk about a couple of those later.
But it's a very much...
There's so many of the crowdfunding for video games
that happens on Kickstarter that it might as well
be all of it here.
It gives you a sense of the numbers.
So last year, there was about $15 million
that was going through projects that were successfully
funded on Kickstarter.
It's a little bit less than the year before,
and a little bit less than the year before again.
It's a significant less than 2015.
these numbers are what they are.
There's 15 million, it's 15 million.
It's a good amount of money,
but it's not comparable to the vast amount of money like
big publishers or the industry is putting into video games.
But this is still money that comes with a few strings attached,
comes with the community and tend to have lots of added value to them.
What's more interesting as well is to look at the number of projects that get funded every year.
And if you look at, you know, back to 2011, before Double Fine Adventure kind of like rocked the crowdfunding boat,
there's been about, you know, between 350 to 400 projects a year that got funded on Kickstarter.
And what's interesting is that that number has not dropped significantly.
We see now about like, you know, a project a day, a video game project a day gets funded on Kickstarter.
What's also very interesting is to look at the number of total projects that are submitted
on the platform. The number of projects that fail is actually going down. Quick anecdote,
2014, there's a project called Potato Salad that launched on Kickstarter, and that's the
reason there's a big spike in low-quality projects that went there. So that's this Potato
Salad effect you're seeing it play here with the...
huge increase of projects that don't get funded.
Now we are back about the same ratio we were in 2013
before Potato Salad.
So we are probably in more like the natural state that
crowdfunding should be for that.
So a project a day, you probably don't know most of
them, that means that there's a lot of projects that are
below the radar that actually get funded on
Kickstarter every year.
And last slide on Kickstarter purely, this is about the size of the project that got
funded last year and the year before.
So there were about like five projects last year that raised more than half a million
dollars.
There was like 25 projects that raised between $100,000 and $500,000.
And like 179 projects raised less than $10,000.
Again, this is, I think, useful for anyone who, kind of like,
try to understand, oh, Kickstarter, you will do a million easy,
or, you know, or you can't do more than $10,000 on Kickstarter.
These are the numbers.
This is the number of projects every year,
video games that get funded, and how much money they raise.
So, depending on what's your expectation,
this might be, like, very distressing,
it might be very good, I don't know.
But this is a tool for you to use to understand
where you sit in terms of expectation on how much money you can raise.
I want to talk very briefly about FIG as a crowdfunding platform that's dedicated to video games.
I think it's interesting to see how much they've performed in the past few years.
The first two years of FIG, they raised a significant amount of money, north of 5 million both years.
Last year was a low year for FIG. There was less than half a million total across six projects that got funded.
So Fig is still a small platform in comparison to Kickstarter for what video games are.
Enough numbers.
Let's talk about the serious stuff. Is your game good for crowdfunding?
And there's something you need to understand about crowdfunding is that it's all about love.
And it's such an important notion.
You need love to be successful in crowdfunding.
You need people to love your project.
Before I go a bit more into that,
there's also a few projects that,
even with all the love in the world,
you probably won't be able to crowdfund them.
So these are my red flags of any project
that I immediately will say,
you're probably not going to make it.
So, so, and if you get the answer you wanted
in those like three slides and want to leave,
I won't take it personally, it's all good.
So, games for kids.
People don't back games for kids
because the time you get between getting the money
and delivering the product, the kid has grown,
changes taste, so people don't back games for kids.
Free-to-play games, people don't buy free-to-play games.
Free-to-play is the antithesis of crowdfunding.
You play the game first,
and then you decide if you spend money on it
because you played when it was free.
Trying to get people to spend money on a free-to-play game
before it's even out is very, very counterintuitive.
And the last category is mobile games.
This is a bit more complex.
I could go into more details about that,
but mobile games are very difficult to crowdfund.
The average pledge per backer is very low on mobile,
makes it more difficult to raise the amount required.
The distribution is very complicated.
And just the psychology of people,
they tend to back things that they feel is important
and something that on a small screen,
people feel like is less important,
so it's more difficult to commit them to back a mobile project.
So it's kind of like the three categories of games
that you probably should not do on crowdfunding
and can cause circus.
There's a last thing.
If there's no love in your game,
and by that, it's not bad.
You can have a game that's very good, but nobody loves.
Nobody has a passion for it.
Nobody's kind of like driven by.
game is good, I want it to happen. If you don't have love, you will fail. You need people
who actually have an emotional connection to your game that they want to see exist for
a crowdfunding campaign to succeed. So there's lots of different ways to look at your game.
Is it loveless? But more important is, like, do you have people who know about your game
and the people who know about your game, how they feel about it?
Feel keen, interested, curious, or really excited.
You want that last category.
And that's all kind of like the green flags,
the things that you want to have.
An existing community that's incredibly
attached to your property.
How many people in the room know about Critical Role?
Okay, good, good, good.
You should all check out Critical Role.
It's a D&D show.
They've done a Kickstarter campaign.
They have like a month left.
They've already raised $7.6 million.
They have 56,000 backers.
And the rewards, if you look at the details,
there's not much in the rewards.
and people have backed the hell out of it.
The average pledge per backer is $130,
and there's pledges that do $25,000,
and every pledge that's limited,
that's more than $1,000, they're all sold out.
They've all been taken.
They have a lot of love.
People are passionate about it.
There's lots of Tumblr about it as well, which is good.
It's also easier if your project has come like a...
a drive behind it.
Like, I want that to happen.
Whether it's because it's so stupid it needs to happen,
or it's missing.
I want like a point and click in the old style
of, you know, Dare of the Tentacle and Magnet Mansion.
I want that game, because nobody else is going to do.
It's kind of like a drive.
So if this is present, you tick another box.
Like, you're probably going to be
in the right side of crowdfunding friendly campaign.
And then you need something that's communicable.
You need something that's easy to understand
and people to share, understand
why there's a passion about it.
So yes, you have an existing community,
people love your project,
but for them to be able to recruit,
they need to be able to bring people to you.
I like Superhot.
Superhot is a category of game
that should not work on Kickstarter.
It's a first-person shooter.
First-person shooters, there's tons of them.
Why would I back a Kickstarter about a first-person shooter
when I can go to any store and buy the latest
iteration of one of the big franchises?
But Superhot has a unique style and a unique concept of,
the time moves when you move and nobody's done that and that's so easy to explain. I'll just
explain it in a sentence. It's easy to demonstrate just a couple of gifs and then suddenly you
understand the action. On top of that when Superhot launched their Kickstarter they had their
prototype from the game jam where the game was initially conceived.
And they just share that, and just like, if you don't get it, just play it.
You're like, oh my God, I understand it immediately.
That makes it very strong for crowdfunding campaign.
It makes it more easy to be viral, more easy for people to recruit their friends
to support you because they love it and they want more people to support it.
So if you're all into the categories,
or if you think you can get into this categories, good.
I want to talk about a few projects from last year as well
and to explain a bit more what is a good project
for crowdfunding.
So the Good Life is a project I worked on
and that raised a bit more than $700,000.
and it has a unique art style,
and it's trying to do something innovative
into the RPG genre.
There's no combat, it's all about taking pictures
and solving quests by spying on people, maybe,
but at least you don't shed blood,
and there's murder mystery,
and then you turn into a cat at night.
Like, it's a bit bonkers, it's a bit unique.
People also have an emotional relationship
with the games made by Swery, the creator,
as kind of like a unique style,
he has a fan base, people care about that.
But for the campaign to be successful, we had to show the game.
Midway through the campaign, we were at GDC a year ago,
and things had slowed down, which always happens on a Kickstarter campaign.
And we are like, okay, what can we do to basically give it a bit more life?
And it was very difficult to convince the studio to share the demo they had.
They had a little demo with like three quests they were using for press demos.
And we're like, no, it's very, very bad.
It's ugly. It's buggy.
We don't want to share it with anyone.
And so after long discussions, like,
if we want the campaign to succeed,
we need to share the game.
We need to give it to people into their hands.
And so we did it.
And then nobody complained about the quality.
Everybody's like, it's exactly what I expected.
It's quirky.
It's funny.
I understand the gameplay about taking the pictures
and all that.
And people streamed it.
People shared it.
And it was a second life into that campaign.
It really made it work.
And so that was very important component to actually...
Sometime you let it out and share what it is you are building because otherwise people will not be able to
follow you through a campaign that promises.
Another campaign I want to talk about is Iron Harvest.
Iron Harvest did
1.3 million dollars last year. It's one of the big campaigns from last year and
It's a niche game.
It's a real-time strategy.
We're talking about the drive of people
to support the campaign.
There's not that many real-time strategy games
around at the moment.
So actually doing an RTS is immediately going
to attract the attention of RTS fans.
And then they also choose to partner with a Polish concept artist that's very popular,
that did the art direction for Scythe, a board game that was also very popular.
Unique style, unique visuals, unique universe.
It kind of like increases, they multiply that attraction that you have for the project.
Not only it's RTS, and I wanted to do RTS for a long time,
but on top of that it's kind of like it's on universe, it has its own like world that's very attractive.
Good, that works.
Top of that, don't ignore that.
They did 1.3 million.
It's their fourth Kickstarter campaign.
They understood really well the environment.
They understood really well their base.
But it's also mean that you can do repeat Kickstarters
and be successful.
You don't have to choose to do one
and then never do it again.
Actually, it's a tool they can repeat and get better at.
Omno is a campaign from last year as well.
They did almost 100,000 euros.
Omno's success is very much the success of the single developer behind it.
It's a solo dev and he is a former animator and he's very good at animation.
He did a lot of prep work on the campaign where he shared his GIF of the game on Twitter,
showing people all the things you can do into the game and the animation was really sleek,
so the GIF was really sleek and people were really intrigued.
But there's also a story.
People know that.
the developers alone so likely truly alone making that game with you know
couple of finances for music or a few things
he told the story you didn't say like i'm a studio making a game he says
i'm a person alone trying to make that game and i try to make it good and
any money i get and will make more time and you know get some help from
after parties and to get me to get better and stories important because you
create an emotional connection
the love on the home those as much as love for the project and
the kind of like support, like the crush you have
on that developer that kind of trying to tackle
making a game on its own, and we all know how hard it is.
So, I want to talk about a little intermission on timing.
2012, Kickstarter explodes, everybody does like
a Kickstarter campaign, and they all work very well.
But we're in 2019.
And over time, for the past seven years,
people's expectations on Kickstarter campaigns
have changed.
The excitement you have of, oh, we
can bypass the publishers and give power to the devs
and make them very creative is also like, OK, well, maybe we
want to see more of your game to understand
what you are backing.
And so we've seen when a game is ready for a crowdfunding
campaign move towards closer and closer
production and of production.
And 2019 we are very much like you need to be able
to show a vertical slice of the game.
You need to show the art direction,
you need to show something that looks like the final game.
You can fake it, but the closer you are
to what is your real vision,
the further away you are in your production,
the easier it will be.
Also means that Kickstarter is not really good
for the start of a project anymore.
But it's still, you know, an excellent tool to leverage
an existing fan base, get more funding into your project.
But it also means that the biggest competitor
for Kickstarter on crowdfunding
is not the other platforms, it's early access.
And we're talking about what kind of type of projects
are good for crowdfunding.
And what happens is that if you have a game that,
by the time you have a vertical slice,
and maybe you have a short gameplay loop
because it's a very mechanic-driven game.
maybe you are ready for early access.
And a lot of people, rather than go to crowdfunding,
go to early access and like,
why would I spend so much time into building rewards
and presenting the campaign
and recruit people to back my game
and I've got 30 days of anxiety
when I'm trying to run the Kickstarter.
Let's launch on Steam on early access.
And that's fine.
I think that if you have a project that's of that kind,
maybe go to early access.
It also means that a certain project
are not good for all the access,
are the one that also go back to Kickstarter.
Anything that you can spoil
will more likely go to a crowdfunding campaign.
Like you have a story and you don't want to do any access
because then you spoil the story.
Well, maybe you present that story,
the concept of it on Kickstarter,
and that's where you raise the money
you need to finish the project.
Good.
Where do we launch our crowdfunding campaign?
I was going to be quick because there's not that many platforms,
but I'll review quickly what I recommend to people in terms of platform
where to launch their crowdfunding campaign.
So if you care about, if you think that the idea of asking money from people
for something that doesn't exist yet and them not getting any money back,
Fig is for you because, you know, revenue share.
They get something back from their investment, some of them.
Some just do like, you know, pre-order the game.
That's one reason to go on Fig, I think.
If you have a huge audience in France,
you should go to Uludaí.
You're laughing, you're laughing,
but there's some people who made $1.4 million
on that platform for a video game,
and you've never heard of it.
So some platform is really good for your very ultra-local
campaign.
Most of you are not concerned by that.
If Kickstart is not available in your country,
Indiegogo is not a bad platform to go to.
It's more accessible than Kickstarter.
That's limited to certain countries.
But if you can, Kickstarter.
And it's not about,
Kickstarter is never going to do anything for you
in terms of making you successful.
I'm not talking the individual behind Kickstarter,
like Luke and Anya from the game team.
They will love you.
They will help you as much as they can.
But the platform itself, the nature of it,
there's no discoverability.
This is the discoverability track.
There's no discrepancy in crowdfunding.
The people you bring, you bring by yourself.
They can help, maybe put you in the newsletter,
products we love, maybe you get some organic traffic,
but 90% of the backers, they are your backers
you bring to the platform.
And in that sense, you could bring them to any platform.
But the strength of Kickstarter is there's less friction.
People know the name.
The number of people who tell me,
Thomas, we want to do a Kickstarter campaign on Indiegogo.
because in their head, Kickstarter campaign means crowdfunding campaign.
It becomes like, you know, it's like googling something on Bing.
There's less friction. People already have accounts. People already have credit cards.
It's just easier. People understand the code.
So that makes, that's what makes Kickstarter the best platform for crowdfunding.
If you can get more support, excellent, but don't be naive in thinking that...
I'll launch it on Kickstarter and then magic happens.
People find my game and we get funded.
That never happens.
I'm very optimistic and nice, right?
Killer of dreams.
Best practices.
So that's the last bit.
This is where I give you advice on what makes
your practical advice to make your company successful.
It's not about likes, it's about love.
Anything you can do to induce love
on your specific project, do it.
So that kind of like a spectrum.
On one end you have like iron harvest,
super hardcore military RTS.
On the other end of my spectrum, I have a boyfriend dungeon.
Like quirky, dating sim, mixing Diablo,
dungeon crawling, wacky things.
you don't do the same thing to induce love into two different audiences
boyfriend dungeon you show like oh here's a body pillow here's like the new weapon
and you know here's the personality of the people you're going to date and here's the wacky thing we want to do
on
iron harvest end of the spectrum you say
oh we're going to do multiplayer and this is the kind of units we want to have
and this is the different factions we have and go more into like a nerdy geeky stuff
and to paramilitary
fantasy
armies and all that kind of stuff
But that's the kind of stuff you need to push to your audience.
Like, what is it going to tell them
that make them love your product?
And it's not like a USB thing.
It's going to be like images, going to be like lore,
it's going to be like little details
like that you can put into that
that make them care more about your project.
It could be also you. It could be your team.
Hey, we are 5, 10, 20.
Here's the people behind.
Maybe that makes them love you more
because it's more human.
The momentum is incredibly important.
incredibly important. If you don't have good momentum at the beginning of your campaign,
it's so hard to recover. You need 20 percent in the first 48 hours. So if you think you're
going to be clever and like, oh, we're going to have like, you know, announcements throughout
the whole months of the campaign and we're going to talk about, you know, different elements
we put into the game, over time, don't.
use as many ammunition as you can at the very beginning.
Maybe keep a couple, because it's always good
to have a few things up to your sleeve,
but don't use any of the big bullets.
Don't keep them for you.
Just use everything so that you have the best start possible
because a good start will make the campaign
overall more successful.
There's a corollary to that, you know,
20% in 48 hours is like halfway through
you have 50% of your funding.
Sounds like stupid, but because the pace of a campaign is like a lot of money at the beginning
and then very slow and then not many at the end, it's not that actually clear.
But we've seen that campaigns that do like 50% midway through were successful in most
of the cases.
So if you have like a bit of a slow start, but you manage to get to like 50% of the way through
You're on the you're on a good way. You are beyond track to be successful
It doesn't mean that you need to stop and to keep pushing and keep talking about it
You need to ask your fans to keep you know, asking nagging their friends about supporting you, but it's important that you
You know that that you are on track and it will it should work
Game needs gameplay and demos.
Talk about that a lot.
This is very important.
You can't get funded without showing your project.
Like John Romero tried, he didn't succeed.
So do you think you are more successful
in terms of having fans than John Romero?
Good luck.
Next one, super important.
I will just leave it there for like two seconds.
This is my number one pet peeve on campaigns
and the number one mistake people make
when they do crowdfunding campaigns.
did not announce the stretch goals.
It serves no purposes.
It changed the people's view about the campaign.
If you ask for 10,000 and the stretch goal is 20,000,
the 20% psychological effect doesn't happen at 10,
it happens at 20.
so it's very important you get nothing and lots of people do it because what
they do is research all the companies and say
all of that's result as a special as well and then they announced it from the
beginning
actually the company you've seen is finished maybe the announced a special
the beginning this and that's them as they were acting
much better do not announced a special if you have a friend's doing a quick
side company the one thing you don't need to not announce a special
you know luncheon begin of the months finish at the beginning of the months
People have payroll, that's good.
It's easier to make the decision
to support something you love,
and it's a bit like an emotional decision
when you are not like struggling to feed yourself,
so it's always a bit better.
I recommend to launch between Monday from Thursday,
because you want the first 48 hours
to be during the weekdays,
and you want to end between Tuesday through Friday,
because you want last 48 hours to be during weekdays.
It's good to do 30 to 35 days campaign.
I think less than 30, you miss one of those payroll cycle.
It also doesn't give the time for a campaign
to kind of like spread.
Longer, it's very taxing.
30 days is very long when you are managing the campaign.
I understand that.
But I think it's also important to let, you know,
the time to go, to get people to talk about your project
and share it and care about it.
and let the work happen.
And sometime midway through, like, nothing happens.
It's very frustrating.
But you have a number of people
who actually follow your campaign,
who push a little button on Kickstarter,
and get an email in the last 48 hours
that tell them that the campaign's about to end.
They're like, oh, my shit, oh, I need to back it now,
and they support you at the very end.
So actually all that time when nothing happens,
there's stuff in the background you can keep an eye on
that actually helps you for your campaign overall.
Nowadays, like 2019, I think Discord is a very good tool before the campaign,
because you can recruit your future backers, your fans, you can engage with them,
and then when the day comes, you can align them on Discord and say,
now is the day, back us!
It's good during the campaign to coordinate, like...
discussion for them to, oh, how are we going to recruit more backers, you know, where can we talk about the project and have them,
you know, be your little army, kind of like talking about you. It's good after the campaign as well to
reward them, give them a little like, you know, role into Discord that makes them look unique and also,
you know, inform them about, you know, the progress of the game and these sort of things.
I recommend to stream during campaigns,
just like sometimes just you talking about the project,
doing AMA, showing the game,
maybe showing some developments,
like, hey, I'm going to do animation,
I'll show you my rig and I'll show you how it all works.
So it's good stuff to show that you're actually
real people working on the real game.
It's a good tool.
Kickstarter have their own Kickstarter live tool to stream.
It's horrible, but it's useful.
So I say try it and see how it goes for you.
I recommend you learn the ecosystem.
I recommend people to actually be backers themselves.
So anyone who tried to be, to launch a Kickstarter campaign
who never backed a Kickstarter is a little bit counterintuitive.
I think you should try to try that by yourself.
Understand what it is to be in the shoes of a backer
and understand how it feels.
I've met people who actually don't like crowdfunding
after they realize that being a backer
was a horrible thing for them
and that make them like realize
they don't want to do that kind of stuff.
They were not right in terms of, they couldn't have done a good campaign because they would
have the wrong tone or anything like that.
So that's important.
You also need to understand the lingo, the number of tools that exist.
That graph I have here is from BiggerCake, biggercake.com.
It's a very good website that have lots of stats on past campaigns.
It's a good tool to understand, oh, I like that campaign.
I think they did a very good job.
Try to understand how much money they raised in the beginning and what was the pacing of
it.
This is a critical role.
Because I like critical work.
It's good to spend money.
Do advertising.
You know, Facebook, Google Ads, maybe.
Don't spend too much money.
Kickstarter gives you tools to actually track referral links
and see if the money you spend actually
bring money to your campaign.
Ask for help.
There's no such thing as competition on Kickstarter.
All the other Kickstarter campaigns
are in the same situation as you.
People who back one campaign are more likely to back two campaigns.
They're not going to say, oh, the other thing is better.
I'm going to take my money out of yours and put it over there.
There's a lot of goodwill.
People who are into crowdfunding and the concept of crowdfunding
tend to be very benevolent and very open to look at other things
and support other creators.
So don't hesitate to ask for help.
Those two updates are from two projects that support each other,
Lunark and Chaindeco's.
I just like to say, hey, I'll scratch your back, you scratch mine.
And then there's the last slide.
I want to talk about failing.
If you fail a Kickstarter campaign,
it's not the worst thing that could happen to you.
You could have failed launching your game.
There's a lot of lessons to learn from failing there.
And you should embrace failure.
Forest of Liars is a project of a friend of mine.
It's beautiful.
He's a concept artist.
He has 40,000 followers on Twitter.
And then he get funded.
And we had a talk and say,
is it bad?
It's like, no, no.
You have a very bad start of your campaign.
Don't cancel it.
Try to understand why you didn't get funded.
Comes up, it didn't show enough of the gameplay.
Game is beautiful,
but the game was not ready to be shown in terms of gameplay.
And so, there are like lots of fans being disappointed.
They were disappointed.
But they also created like bonds to that community.
They felt together.
And now the game is still in development.
They're looking at, you know,
maybe doing Kickstarter again,
maybe doing other ways to get funded.
But the project is probably better now
because they failed at Kickstarter
than if they had not done the Kickstarter.
And that's my closing words.
I think I have no question, no time for questions.
I'm so sorry.
But you can see me afterward.