Hi, I'm Scott Peterson, Visual Effects Director at Zynga.
At the GDC 2017, I'll be presenting a talk,
Creating Effects Shaders Optimized for Mobile.
As a veteran effects supervisor from animation,
I found that the constraints of mobile hardware,
understanding those constraints has helped me
transition skills from the animation industry into mobile.
This talk focuses on both visual and technical choices that we made on FarmVille, Tropic Escape, to create water and clouds.
The techniques discussed apply to a wide variety of effects, including a blend mode that is both bright and maintains color saturation.
Also using erosion in conjunction with transparency to make more graphic splashes.
using particles to enhance specular highlights,
understanding the role of draw calls
and precision in performance.
If you work with shaders or visual effects on mobile,
please come to my talk.