Hello. Oh, God. You could hear that. Hello.
Hello.
Hi.
Thank you very much for coming.
I'm really tired, so you're going to have to put up with that.
So, yeah.
I'm surprised there's this many people here on a Friday afternoon.
I would be in my hotel room asleep by now.
So, good on you.
So, yeah.
I'm surprised there's this many people here on a Friday afternoon.
I would be in my hotel room asleep by now.
So, good on you.
My name is Mike Rose. I have been around for too long.
I used to write about video games many moons
ago, and then I moved to a publisher called
TinyBuild, and we did a whole bunch of stuff,
and then I decided I could do this myself.
Like an egotistical bastard. And so I did. Last
year I started my own publishing label called NoMoreRobots.
And the idea is, for anybody who has been following me for a while, you know that I
love numbers.
And I love trying to apply numbers and maths and all that kind of malarkey to making games
sell.
So that's what I tried to do.
And our first game's called Descenders.
It was released last month.
And thank God for me, it has done well.
Which means that, you know, I don't look like an absolute lemon.
And I'm announcing a second game next week,
which is massively exciting and tiring.
So this talk is a version of a talk I gave earlier this year.
Sorry, earlier this week.
Well, technically it was earlier this year.
And this talk is focused around the fact that basically on Descenders a big part of my plan
was to spend as little money as possible.
Because I think there's this perception you've got to spend a whole bunch of money on marketing
now.
And if you don't do that, then no one's going to care about your game.
And I've seen people plow like tens of thousands of dollars into marketing their game and honestly
not get a great amount of payoff.
I was trying to work out how much money, because we didn't spend zero, just to be clear.
That was a flippant title, but we spent close to zero.
I think I basically paid...
a monthly subscription to MailChimp, which sends out email addresses.
It's probably about $50 a month or something for the last seven months.
Outside of that, we've not really spent anything.
Everything that I have done to make Descenders sell
has just been me just hard grafting, basically,
and screaming at people until they finally listen.
which is a thing you can do as well.
But maybe not with this accent.
So,
so things I'm not going to be
talking about today are
these kind of things. Now the reason
I'm not, and sorry if that's what you came
for, you can leave.
If you would like, and I won't cry too much,
I will.
But things like writing a press release,
getting in touch with YouTubers, all that kind of stuff,
it's been done absolutely to death.
If you go on the GDC vault,
you'll find plenty of talks on this stuff.
Even from me, I have done talks on this.
So you can see me talk about this
if you want on the GDC vault.
There's, there's plenty of stuff that I think is
honestly more important than this that, that I ended
up focusing on for Descenders. And I think that,
hopefully, you lot are going to be able to
apply it yourselves as well.
Here are the six things we're going to talk
about today.
Everything here I'm going to explain in horrible, excruciating detail.
But a lot of this stuff might sound quite simple,
but when I actually say it out loud, you'll be like,
I hadn't thought to do that.
So let's just get cracking, because I've got lots of words.
The first step before you even start doing anything is actually working out what is exciting
about the game.
Because as I tell so many people, the thing that you think is exciting about your game,
you are wrong.
It is not the thing that is exciting about your game.
Well it nearly is, alright.
The problem is you're focusing on the wrong thing most likely.
I keep saying you, as if you're wrong, but I mean that most people I talk to who are
making games, they are focusing on the wrong thing when it comes to actually talking about
their game publicly, from a marketing perspective, I guess.
A lot of the time, you're focusing on this thing because you think, oh God, people are
going to care about this.
And it turns out that, yeah, that's pretty interesting, but it's not actually the thing
you should open with.
So, so I've been calling it, like in my head I was calling it this, and then I started
saying it publicly and it sounded really dumb, but I've stuck, I'm doubling down.
I call this like the hook and the kicker.
So the thing that I think you are probably focusing on is the kicker.
You are probably focusing on this thing about your game, which yeah, sounds pretty cool,
but actually if you open with it and say, hey this is what my game's about, a person
might be like, okay.
Sounds alright, but then maybe they'll drift off and find another game.
What you need first is the thing that's actually exciting about your game that is then going
to link with this other thing.
Let me give you an example.
So with Descenders, from the very beginning, we were talking a lot about the procedural
generation stuff in it.
and for us that seemed like it was going to be really exciting.
People were going to care about this.
But here's the thing, loads of games do procedural generation now.
You know, like it's cool.
Procedural generation is cool.
But it's not like a publicly facing thing
that whole marketing campaigns are sold on.
So we needed like the thing that procedural generation
could actually follow on from.
It turned out that I was literally just telling people
from, you know, kind of trying to describe the game to people in many different ways.
It turned out when we actually just told people that it was a downhill mountain biking game,
that was enough to just grab them initially
because no one's really doing downhill mountain biking games.
When we then followed up with, oh yeah, and it has procedurally generated worlds in it,
that's the bit where they'd be like, what?
How does a mountain bike game have procedural worlds?
That's not right.
So you can see how, like...
taking procedural world, which is, eh,
and then actually making it sound like,
I wanna know more about this.
You take this one part, and it elevates the second part,
but the second part by itself possibly
isn't as exciting as you think.
Trying to work out your own line
for your game like this one at the bottom
is really important.
you can do that by just trying to describe your game to different types of people over
and over again in different ways until you finally start getting the reaction that you
deserve.
It's a really important thing to do because it will...
it will kind of, you can take it into a lot of other things as well,
especially even when you're just designing the game.
If you've worked out exactly what it is that people find exciting,
it might start to sort of show you
what direction to take your game in as well.
So I, this is another thing that I think a lot of people don't realize is so important.
I see people all the time, they'll, someone will put out a trailer for a game, or they'll
put out a website, or they'll put something on Twitter and they'll get a ton of retweets,
and that's great, but then...
then they go off and they make the game and the people, those 100,000 people you got on
your trailer or whatever, they go off and they play other games and then by the time
your game's coming out, they've basically forgotten about your game and all that work
you did in the first place was kind of for nothing because, you know, we know how fast
games are moving now in like six months.
They probably don't remember your game anymore.
So a big question is...
if someone is showing interest, if somebody, if you're announcing your game and you're putting
out a trailer or anything like that, and someone like thinks, hey, this is kind of cool, I'd like
to be more involved, what exactly is it that they can get involved with where you can kind of hook
them and keep them until the game is available and hope that they will buy it? For us, and I
think this will work for a lot of people, it's Discord.
I started fiddling with Discord a couple of years ago,
and at first I didn't get it.
It seemed like it was just another Skype, but it was purple.
It seemed very strange.
I mean, you know, like, everyone's used every chat-based thing under the sun.
But...
But the cool thing about Discord is that, I mean, it's a slick system, but also they've
just got kind of lucky, really, and they've managed to just get shedloads of people joining.
And they're all people who actually buy video games.
So what we did was we started a Discord for Descenders.
Now when people ask me how you start a Discord,
you don't just make a cool place where people can chill about your game.
Because no one wants to do that.
No one wants to just come and chill in your Discord until the game's out.
That's not a reason.
You've got to actually have a reason why they're going to come and hang out
in this little chat room.
And the main way that we managed to do that was that we ran the closed beta for Descenders through Discord.
So when we announced the game, we said, hey, if you want to be involved in the closed beta for this game,
you are going to have to join our Discord.
and thousands of people did that.
When we announced the game, they'd watch the trailer
and then the link would be right there under the trailer
or when a press place talked about it,
they always say, oh hey, if you want to be involved
in the beta, here's a link to the Discord.
And we got thousands and thousands of people coming through there.
And at that point then, once we had them,
we then started giving them things to do.
So I set up the Discord using a variety of bots.
I made it so that when someone first joined the Descenders Discord,
they only had access to one channel that was called Pick Aside.
And in the game there's three different kind of teams,
factions that you can join.
And we made it so that they had to pick one of these three
teams before they were allowed any access to the Discord.
And this essentially caused like a tribe mentality,
where then like on a weekly basis
we gave them tasks to do against each other.
You've got to come up with the best one of these
or the best one of that.
And then we started giving them things to actually design
for in the game.
Let's design some kits and let's design some banners
and all this kind of stuff.
it meant that by the time the game came, eventually came out,
we were pretty damn certain that we had at least x amount of people who were going to
buy this game within the first 24 hours because they were all just like feverish for it.
In fact, when we launched the game, we were going to launch the game at sort of 4 o'clock
and at 20 minutes to 4, we were just like, hey, let's do this.
Let's just launch it 20 minutes early and we'll only tell Discord just to say thanks
to these guys.
And then we'll officially announce the launch at 4 o'clock.
So we launched it, but what I didn't realize was that the launch discount of 10% wouldn't
kick in until 4 o'clock.
So I run into the Discord, I'm like, oh God, I'm really sorry everyone, like, the, the,
you know, just wait, just hold off, I know it's available, just hold off 20 minutes.
We sold like a thousand copies in 20 minutes from all the people in Discord, because they
didn't give a crap that it was, that there was no Discord.
They needed it now.
They needed the game right now.
And it's been incredible.
It's been absolutely incredible for the game,
because it's the kind of longevity of the tale of sales
as well has been amazing.
People who kind of see the game and think,
oh, I might be interested in this,
they join the Discord just to see what the community's like.
We've got this super active community.
They join and immediately are greeted by a bunch of people.
And within a very small amount of time,
they decide, yeah, all right, cool,
and then I want to be involved in this as well.
So, I honestly, I can't stress enough,
like, doing this Discord stuff,
I have plans to do Discord for every game that I do now.
It's probably going to become a logistical nightmare.
But it's honestly something you should 100% look into.
So, this one is an interesting one because I think probably a lot of people don't think
about this.
When I say the right vibe, I mean when people are seeing your game, what is it that they
are perceiving it to be in terms of those horrible things we don't like to think about.
What value are they perceiving?
The, the way that you present your game,
I think right now, especially with so many games
coming out, is incredibly important.
Your game needs to be perceived that it is
more interesting than all the ones around it.
Your game, when it comes out that day,
is gonna be in the middle of 40 other games,
right, when it, when it drops.
Why are people picking your game out?
Again, with Descenders, when we announced that,
we'd been originally talking that,
oh, maybe people would pay, you know, sort of $15 for this.
We honestly had no great idea
about how much people would be into a mountain biking game.
But we wanted to just try and give off this perception that it was sort of this AA game,
you know, somewhere in between like a traditional indie title and AAA.
And so we worked incredibly hard on trying to make this image.
The trailer we tried to make,
we made like over two dozen drafts of this trailer for the game
over and over and over again for about three weeks
just to try and make it look as AAA as possible.
All of the assets we were doing,
all the ways we were talking about the game,
the way we were presenting the game.
We spent an incredible amount of time on this.
And when it did come out, a lot of people...
accidentally thought that it was like this this massive game made by this
massive team there was comments on the YouTube video that were like well I'd
only pay $40 for this which was incredible for us because there's three
guys making it so
So, the fact of the matter is that different games have different images, right?
The next game I'm announcing next week is definitely more towards the more traditional
indie scale, so we're working out then what image we're building around that.
But the value that is perceived,
I know we hate talking about like,
well how much is my game worth?
What should I price it and all that?
You can really help those kind of conversations
by deciding how do I want my game to be perceived?
What value do I want my game to be perceived in?
And then just starting from there.
And if it turns out that maybe people
don't buy into the image so much,
you can go down from there, right?
But you can't, if you start off with,
it's not worth as much.
And then it turns out that maybe, you know,
people would have been more interested in,
in, you know, sort of looking at it in a,
in a higher perspective.
It's more difficult to come back from that.
Um, all right.
With a lot of the stuff that I'm talking about,
and a lot of the stuff that we did,
um, it's, uh,
it's about not relying on luck.
Um,
I think that with the vast majority of the games that come out now,
and it's been like this for a long time,
but I think a lot of developers rely on luck,
rely on, you know, sort of saying,
alright, I've done everything,
I've tried to put press releases in these places,
I've done some tweets,
hopefully the day that my game comes out,
people are just going to buy it.
And you can't do that. You absolutely cannot do that.
You need to make sure that on the day your game comes out,
you're pretty certain you've put enough stuff in place
that it's going to at least do a baseline well.
there's plenty of stuff you can do to do that.
The Discord stuff I was talking about earlier, for example,
is a great example of that, right?
Like I told you, we had thousands of people in the Discord.
We could see how much they wanted the game.
They were asking for it on a daily basis
before we launched it.
So we were pretty confident we were at least getting
X amount of sales from that.
There was other stuff we were putting in place as well.
You know, we were talking to different platforms,
different communities.
We'd been talking to Steam a lot.
and just hounding them about what is it we can do
to make sure that on the day our game sort of does as well as possible.
There's plenty of ways to actually...
not guarantee success, I'm not going to tell anybody in here that I can guarantee success,
but there's a lot of ways to at least guarantee a baseline of success in that you're not just
like sat there like scared out of your mind on launch day with your fingers crossed.
There's plenty of stuff you can put in place.
Unfortunately, to put a lot of this stuff in place,
you have to do some horrible things
that I found the vast majority of people don't like doing.
You can probably tell just from the way I talk
and from my general demeanor that I don't mind doing this stuff at all.
I am very much a person who will just sort of ask for everything
and will just go in and just fit.
It's not that I believe, you know, like, that I deserve any of this.
It's more that...
I know that if I ask, I have a chance of maybe getting help from people and from platforms.
And if I don't ask, I definitely don't.
That's the absolute bottom line on it.
So asking for stuff.
is honestly just one of, it's, I've been saying it for years,
and I know there'll be loads of people in here who'll be like,
I can't do that. I can't email people or get in touch with people just asking for stuff.
every single thing that I have put in place for Descenders,
I asked for, no one came to me.
Xbox didn't come to me and say,
hey, we've seen Descenders, can we work out all this stuff?
I went to them and I shoved Descenders in their face
and said, what can we do together?
not a, can we do something, what can we do together?
Can we do this, can we do that?
And now I've put deals in place with them.
With Discord, I started setting up the Discord stuff
and then I shoved myself in Discord's faces
saying I found a contact, I just worked out,
oh, who can I talk to here?
Finally found a person to talk to
and now I'm sort of working out a bunch of stuff
with Discord that we can do with them.
Another platform, Mixer.
So, if you're not aware, Mixer is essentially Microsoft's version of Twitch that also is
on the Xbox dashboard.
I started streaming on Mixer just because I like to always just try and be ahead of
the curve, so I try everything that's new, and then just stick with the things that actually
work.
And with Mixer, I started streaming a lot on Mixer.
And then I emailed them just saying, hey, is there any
fact I can get involved with?
And they got back to me saying, oh yeah, actually, we
do developer accounts on Mixer.
Do you want one of those?
I was like, yeah, OK.
And a couple of days later, they'd verified my account.
And the next time I streamed, I was front page of Mixer.
And now I'll randomly be front page of Mixer whenever I
stream, because that's apparently a thing they do.
But I only found out by asking.
It's, it's this kind of thing where if you're not
just absolutely just asking and talking to everybody,
nothing's ever going to happen.
The worst thing that's going to happen is you're going to ask someone for something
and they're not going to respond to you.
And then you'll feel a bit crap inside.
But, but who cares?
Because at least you asked.
Asking for stuff is, is just incredibly important.
And when I was, when I was saying this earlier this week,
I was talking to a guy who, who just said to me,
I just can't do that.
I can't, I just can't ask.
It feels so, like, reckless and horrible.
And I, I, I just said to him, just try it for a month.
Just try asking for stuff for a month.
And if at the end of the month you're like,
oh, that was so horrible, and now I feel dead inside,
then all right, fine.
Get someone else to do it for you instead.
But really, honestly, you'd be surprised at the times when I have just out of the blue
asked someone for something and they've gone,
alright, yeah, cool, let's work something out.
It's easier than you think.
You've just got to get over that little voice in your head that's saying,
this is horrible.
The final thing is that out of everything that's happening,
you just gotta be realistic, all right?
And when I say that, I mean you need to
have a plan in your head for if your game
ends up making sort of the average
or less than the average of what a game is making
on Steam right now, is that gonna be okay
for you and your situation?
or are you going to have problems?
And if you are going to have problems, what are you going to do about it?
You need to be able to take those numbers
and actually have plans in your head for what's going to happen.
I mean, when we were doing Descender stuff...
We did this.
We all sat down and we were like, OK, so what
if Descenders tanks?
Because you've got to ask yourself that question.
I was optimistic it was going to do well,
but this is video games.
So we had to be really realistic and say, all right,
if it tanks, what are we going to do?
We had plans for, all right, if it only
makes this amount of money, then we're
going to have to scale back scope.
We're going to have to aim for roundabout this day.
and then we'll work out what happens then.
If it does well, then yeah, we can kind of stick
to these more longer term plans.
You got to ask yourself these questions as well, because
for anybody who has launched a video game knows that
no matter whether it's done well or badly,
you still feel depressed and awful after it.
So the situation you don't want to be in is that you launch a game
and it does badly, and then you don't have a plan,
and then you're just like...
a husk of a person.
At least having that plan in place means that
it becomes ever slightly more bearable.
I know this is kind of a slightly
lower note to end on, but that's just the
way that I structured this talk, so I apologize for that.
So anyway, yeah, kind of just to wrap up,
really, really think about what it is
that's actually interesting about your game.
Talk to other people.
See what they think is interesting about your game.
Try and work out that exact thing.
Work out ways to keep people interested
once you have started talking about your game.
Things like Discord, things like Mixer.
There's bound to be other platforms
that are popping up as well.
Anything that's new, just try it out.
you never know it might actually do the works for you.
And like I said, just try to start just gritting your teeth
and asking for stuff and trying to hunt anything down
that you can.
It might be, there'll be people who are sitting here
and thinking like, oh well, this platform holder
and that platform holder and this company,
they're not gonna care about the thing I'm making.
They very well might do.
You just gotta ask them and see,
because you might surprise yourself.
Right, said a bunch of words.
Thank you very much.
I have no idea if we've got time for,
do we have time for questions?
Three minutes, I get one question.
Whoever gets to one of the microphone,
actually I shouldn't say that.
All right, hello.
Hello.
I'm actually one who asked about the Discord
because I know about Discord
and I'm almost like searching for it
and I see it's things that is most suitable
for those like strategy games
and all that call up games,
there's like lots and lots of discussion.
But for us, we have like a very narrative to run game.
And then we don't think about doing a beta or a demo.
So I don't know how I can work with Discord to promote our game.
I'm, so I'm, like I said, I'm announcing another game next week, and the game I'm announcing
next week is a very niche, single player experience.
And so I, for a while, was struggling to like think, well, Descendants made more sense for
Discord.
If I, I feel like if I'm going to do Discord with this next game, I'm just going to be
just kind of ramming a circle into a square.
But then the thing was, when I started to really think,
okay, well, what actually is possible with this thing?
I started to realize that there's,
when you really have an explore of what is possible
with all the kind of bots and stuff
that are available on Discord,
there's some crazy things you can do.
I'm setting up this Discord server,
I'm kind of putting the finishing touches on it right now,
that is way weirder than the Descenders Discord,
where people...
join the discord and they essentially are given a channel where they live and that's
like where they start off and it's like a base channel and then they have to work in
the discord to earn money to then be able to buy their way into better property in the
discord.
and they have to go to work.
When they go to work, home disappears.
The home channels disappear,
and all the work channels appear.
And they have to then go there and work in these places
and do this loop.
And then every week, the top 10 people
who have the most money and the most standing in the server
then become these gold players in the server
and are eventually gonna have their names in the game.
This is just the stupid stuff that happens in my brain.
But you can see how essentially creating.
this kind of miniature meta game in Discord.
I haven't launched it yet, so maybe no one will care,
but I'm hoping that it will at least give
a small subset of people a reason to stick around,
even if it has no real, them playing this thing
has no standing on what the game
that eventually comes out is.
So I think there's plenty of possibilities even when it seems like there's not.
But yeah, I guess I'll have to keep trying it for more and more games.
I do know that something Discord are doing is they are
they're kind of revamping how bots work in Discord right now
and trying to support a lot more people making these things.
So I reckon in the next year, there's going to be.
a whole lot of additional kind of interactivity stuff that's going to come to Discord.
So I imagine in a year's time the Discord servers we're going to be seeing are going
to be just ridiculous.
So you might as well start exploring it now so you can be one of those ridiculous people.
Thank you.
No worries.
All right.
Cool.
Bye, everyone.