One, two.
Good morning, everybody.
Everybody's sober from last night.
I see some tired faces, that's good.
So let me put you a little bit to sleep.
Listen to this relaxing music.
In your nightmares.
Hi, my name is Inan Zur.
Welcome to my talk.
I have written here that I need to do an icebreaker.
So here's my Donald Trump latest implementation.
This is a great and tremendous industry.
Yeah, it's, and nobody, nobody is better than me
and this thing, and you guys are all fake composers.
But the rest of it is history.
So anyways, a little bit about myself.
I was born in Israel and raised in Israel.
Really liked music.
When I was 19, I recruited to the Israeli army
and I told them that I am a musician,
I am a composer.
Please, anywhere you put me, no loud noises and no dust and other things that could really
disrupt me.
Show the Israeli army with their famous sense of humor put me in the elite tank unit.
So basically, since then, four years later, I cannot hear a pitch higher than a cello.
And it's really interesting because, you know, like these people that are playing these silver sticks,
it's like, it's really great minds. I don't know what they're playing, but it's wonderful.
So I'm writing a lot of these things. I don't, you know, but anyways.
It's kind of like very interesting year for me this year
because I'm celebrating 20 years
of writing music for computer games.
My first computer games I wrote on 1997.
It was Klingon Academy.
And I'm really managed to survive, I think,
this harsh industry.
First, because I'm really good looking.
But other than this,
the competitive edge.
Like, I'm looking at each one of you.
I always look at them, it's like this guy probably, this guy
has to be much better than me. What can he come up with that I can't?
And this is basically what drives me. I love competition
and I always try to find something that will be
interesting and different. And first and foremost
you gotta love.
what you're doing. If you're not in love with what you're doing and if you're not in love
with the whole notion of writing music, then forget about it. It'll suck because this world
is full of disappointments and turn downs and
criticism, and a lot of harsh things.
And you know, every once in a while,
you get like, oh, that sounds great.
Oh, this is good.
But, Fallout main theme,
what you hear here is version 29.
So you could understand, I mean, this thing.
So let's start talking about it.
Originality and signature factor.
When we're basically talking about this thing,
we gotta really understand what is originality.
And I always would say to you one thing.
If you wanna be original, start with something
that is the less original thing you think about it, okay?
It has to be something that convey,
something that people know, that they recognize.
And only after that, insert just a little thing
that is different, okay?
After you did it and it's cool, repeat it.
Just repeat it a few times so it'll become the hook.
If you manage to do this, your first layer will be something pretty known, pretty solid.
And on top of it, you did something that is a little different, then you got something
definitely going.
And I'll give you a little example.
All right.
Actually, I'm going to play you a cue now.
Nobody, seriously, except of myself and Mark Lampert,
the legendary Bethesda audio director, ever heard.
And this is the first cue ever to be written
for Fallout 4.
Never ended up on the game.
Nevertheless, it set up the tone
for the whole more action for the game.
You
And anyways, when I played this to Mark,
he said, what the hell is that?
And I said to him, well, this is me
playing, hitting my piano, scratching my guitar,
hitting, scratching, scratching, hitting,
taking some vase, bowing it, and doing all this stuff.
And he said, why?
And I said, because Fallout is all about alternate.
If you know Fallout, if this is reality,
This is another reality.
So basically, they probably think the same
but use different means to pronounce themselves
or to talk about or to do things
because it's a different reality.
So instead of drums, let's use piano.
Instead of whatever, I mean, any other,
like shaker, percussion, let's just hit on guitars.
Let's just throw in a junkyard.
And the way I did it is basically.
totally experimenting with my little Zoom instrument, like probably each one of you
have it and if you don't, please get it, because this is amazing, it's a $100 thing that it's
a lifesaver, because you're going about and then you could record anything and then you
turn it into your own sound machine.
And that basically brings me to this signature thing, okay?
And there you have it.
Thanks for watching.
I'm Chris.
I'll talk to you soon.
Bye.
the combination between something that you know and expect, in this case, rhythm and
rhythmical patterns, and then weird sounds that basically are not so common to hear.
This combination is a great start to create a signature touch.
Here's another little example.
I love cello.
I told you, I mean, this is the highest instrument I could hear.
So I really love cello.
But Fallout is such a lonely game.
You're wandering in the wilderness.
Okay, what could be better than play a cello with a fog horn?
I'll be back.
Thank you for watching!
And it's so cool because instead of using synth as my bottom pad, I use this fog horn.
And a little secret about it, Bethesda's not gonna be happy, but anyways, it's not only the fog horn.
I actually record myself also singing with my ugly voice with the fog horn.
So basically what you get, you create your own pad.
We all know what pad is.
If you're a composer, you put a pad.
Okay.
But what about if this pad could be something that somebody could recognize as something
that has nothing to do almost with music.
Okay.
It's a freaking fog horn.
Okay? But you use it as a musical pad.
With this you play the cello, there you go.
Okay, another thing is, it's a more musical term,
is actually introducing some rhythmical... ♪♪
Um, I'd say, uh, things that are not really clear.
Where is one here?
Where the hell is one here?
really great asset to have when you ship.
because a player and I'm sure most of you are playing games and you listen to
the music to me if you start doing this when you play a game it's not a good
thing at all because then you will start to recognize when the cue starts to loop
and after the third time you'll shut it down
Okay? But if you could just create something that is there, it's creating the tension,
but you don't really do this, or you don't know where it is.
One, two, three, four. One, two, three, four.
You made something because it will keep you engaged, it will keep you interested in what you're doing.
Okay? Alright.
Just forget about everything I said so far.
You don't really need all this shit.
Sorry, I cannot swear.
All this thing.
Just look at Hollywood.
I think 80% or 70% of the music that is being written in Hollywood today
just bound, because of many considerations, to be what we call mainstream.
And mainstream is something that we'll expect and it will be there. It will do the job
But if you listen to it, it's not what we called
original because we heard it in some kind of versions before
but in games and
I must tell you and I'm really pride on our industry now jokes aside
People in games will always look for something different. They have more courage
And I am encouraging you and to encourage the audio director to go places.
All right. Just venture a little bit.
It will really make, you know, the whole thing stand out.
And we are pioneering today in many ways a lot in the music industry at large.
I'm serious about it. We are.
really doing a lot of pioneering and discovering,
sometimes more than movies,
because they have so many considerations,
and we could just open our wings and fly.
But, first we need to understand
that if we will do something more than 20% original,
forget it.
Nobody will listen to it,
because it will be just plain weird.
If we are able to get 80% something,
like let's take whatever, the cues that I played before.
Think about it, about 70 to 80% of the elements there
were not original.
It had rhythm, it had harmony, it had melody,
but it had a fog horn, it had a scratching chair.
It had something that was a little different.
Just this little thing is what's important.
And if you could find this thing and insert it
inside something that will be communicative,
then you got it.
By the way, it's a smaller room
and I really love conversation.
So if you really feel compelled to ask any question
during it, I'm not waiting for.
you know, the question session.
Just raise your hand and ask.
It's really important for me because I'm here to share a thing with you guys.
Okay, so let's go to work.
I got the gig.
I need to write the music for Fallout.
I need to learn and most importantly,
what do we want to say in the game.
What is the game all about?
Forget about originality, forget about all this music, forget about everything.
What is the actual game wants from me?
What do I want to tell the player?
That's the most important thing.
The rest of it, OK, I will deal with this.
But now I need really to learn.
And for that, I encourage each one of you, when you get a gig,
you go to the studio.
You really sit with the artist, you sit with the game designer, and you learn this thing.
I have a few people that I worked here before.
Andrew, for example, from Amazon.
He knows how many times I went down there and we worked together.
And other people here.
It's just so important to learn about the game.
And only then you start.
Okay.
Fallout is a different animal altogether.
It's not that it's a post-apocalyptic world.
This is not what's important.
What's really important for me as a composer,
that it is a parallel reality.
It's a reality that basically got conjured somehow
in the 50s, but right now we are in 2150.
So it had, whatever, 200 years to evolve.
So it's a parallel thing.
So everything I'm doing will be a little twisted,
a little out there.
It's going parallel to our reality,
but in a different way.
And it's all about choices.
The musical choice that you make should be based
on this premise that this is a parallel reality.
Okay?
So, let's hear some, you know, example.
Here, at Brightness Calling...
This is my vase in my living room.
And I'm basically...
playing it and bowing it
and record it and then layer some other stuff with it.
And basically you hear harmony
and you hear other elements
but you really can't tell
Is that a sin? Is that organic? Is that organic sin?
What the hell is it?
And this is sort of like the secret of the Fallout score.
That you create something that you definitely could connect with.
because it talks to you, but the way it's being created is just a little quirky, just a little different.
The elements are different.
I'm not using set libraries. I usually try to create my own libraries.
There are some companies like Umloud, for example, that helps you out.
manage the shit you're recording.
So, this is really helpful.
Now, in this one for example, using the orchestra.
I got the French horn Jews just to scream into their horns.
literally scream
and be banged on chairs.
So I did use traditional instruments
but in a little less traditional way
because when you play the horn
you have to also shout into it
and create some kind of like a different thing.
Let's try that again.
It's not about how you do it.
It's about your musical choices.
Today, everybody's doing crazy things,
but the choices you're making of how to use these things
is basically what create the special signature.
Or you could use untraditional instrument
in a traditional way.
And this is solo piano.
What you hear right now is only one instrument.
Everything I could take out of the piano,
basically, that is not playing the actual piano.
And it doesn't matter.
how creative you get or how crazy. I don't care if you go to a cave in the Alps and play on a goat.
It, you know, it doesn't matter. What matters is that for the specific place in Fallout,
this piano craziness things really worked because the place there was some sort of like dilapidated
village with lots of metallic things.
So this is what worked for that.
I just didn't have it, so I created it.
And this is the thing, never just set back some time.
I don't have this sound.
You don't have this sound?
Create it.
Work.
For God's sake.
Okay, so, and here's another example.
Here, for example, I did the other way around.
This actually are tons of things.
If before we heard only one instrument,
this is about 20 instruments,
all played together and tried to do the same thing.
Again, in a non-traditional way.
So we have a guitar, we have a piano, we have a cello, we have an oil jack, we have a soundboard,
and other things, but they all try to basically mimic each other and really basically give you
the same element but each one in a different way. And this is what you get.
Again. Wow.
That's because...
Ah, because I thought it's really clever.
No, because I thought that this specific place in the game, it was really needed.
If I thought that a solo flute that I can't hear, well, is a good thing there,
then I would write a solo flute.
Again, it's about what the game wants to do.
All right, so basically, when we're choosing the palette,
and this is actually a really interesting thing,
we want to go and not listen to music at all.
And that's actually a really interesting thing
that I found really beneficial.
I sat with the audio director and told him,
what do you hear as far as the ambient?
Blame me the wind you hear.
It'll be a little different than a regular wind.
Blame me the thunders.
Blame me the animal calls.
Blame me everything.
Blame me the people.
How do you envision them?
All right?
Only then, oops.
I think I crushed.
I'm good.
Only then we could get going.
After that, I started to try to mimic what he played me.
And this is the first cue ever that actually found itself
inside Fallout.
I tried to mimic.
A animal calls that he played me
With some wind and thunders
And this is only me trying to imitate a sound, pure sound design and sound effect that the
audio director gave me.
I didn't really try to create music.
I was thinking if we would kill all the sound effects.
and we'll play only that that could serve as some kind of your sound effect element
and this is another way and it's very unique for Fallout
by the way
This thing that he played that was basically some of the wolves that he played me
is a string quartet that I recorded in my studio, slowed them down about half tempo
and lowered them in one octave. And this is how it sounds. It sounded a little bit like a wolf to me.
It was really, really, really inspirational for me.
Let's talk harmony a little bit.
Here I decided, okay, let's take piano.
Even when I'm using piano here, in its own sound,
I made sure that all the instruments behind the piano
are detuned, everything except of the piano.
And that's what created this mo-mo-mo-mo-mo-mo-mo-mo
kind of a thing, that you, you hear that?
Everything is detuned.
So when the piano plays its own regular harmony and everything is detuned, then you get this effect.
And here's another example of using only blowing instruments.
Didgeridoo and voice.
Do you see how many things you actually basically?
and how many tools but they're so simple you don't need to work hours and hours and hours of thinking
but this is the singer Mimi Page singing along with myself blowing into a weird dj redo
um it doesn't really matter this is technical
But this music gives a certain feel that is so, so, so iconic to Fallout.
Because this combination between these instruments is what creates what we called the Fallout signature.
By the way, for this kind of weirdness I really recommend Valhalla.
You know, Valhalla is...
great plugin, gives you this huge reverb and I'm using it a lot when it comes to
these kind of things, so just a little technical thing. If you've noticed I
didn't get too much into technical
descriptions. I'm more into the content but even more
I'm more into the concept.
Each one of you has his or her own voice.
And the way you're gonna get it,
I'm sure that there is a way.
But remember, as long as you're not being captured
and be pressured by, oh, I need to be clever.
I need to find some kind of a thing that nobody ever found.
No, it's not about that.
It's about what you hear.
As far as what works best for the game and then try to bring it to life
These things works great for fallout. So I did it
If I had to do a live orchestra for it, I would do live orchestra
It's not about
How sophisticated we are?
Is about how?
Committed we are to create what we believe can be the ultimate
signature sound for the game.
Now let's get funny a little bit.
And I'll give you some secrets.
Not real secrets, but it's so primitive.
Really is.
Okay.
I give you the Fallout Ensemble.
Yeah, no joking.
And not only that, I prepared for you a little treat.
Again, nobody ever, I was not allowed up until today
to play it because Bethesda and rightfully so
are very, very protective on what we're allowed to say
and what we're not allowed to say.
So this is just the tip of the iceberg of things.
Alright. Raw material. Here is me playing bowed guitar.
If you didn't go to the dentist yesterday, then maybe tomorrow.
Here's another one.
Even I can hear that.
But here is this in a queue.
Here it is.
This is the bow guitar.
And here is the other one.
And here's the thing, it's ugly, it's raw, but it's freaking fitting to what I want to say.
The rawness, the stupidness, the primitiveness of it is exactly what I wanted to say and thought.
And I didn't want to take a professional player.
If I wanted, I would take.
Okay, but it's not what I wanted to say.
Here's another example.
Yes, this is me.
Singing into a ditch.
These sounds never heard before for live audience.
Monday morning.
In a queue.
Remember what I told you?
Element
like harp.
Everybody knows.
get we get like synth pad we all know about it
and here's our friend
Spirit?
It's just sitting there and you don't know what exactly it is.
Because it's stupid.
But it works!
Sorry.
Here's my famous...
You see this...
Thing?
I call her Uka.
in queue.
And again, the reason is this Ocarina was what I thought about when he played me the
Howling Wind.
It's not because I had a new career.
Well, actually, yeah, also because this is what I have.
But also, it was holy enough for me.
So what the hell, let's stick it in there.
And it just worked.
Harmony is so simple. Nothing, no, doesn't get any clever. Remember, always keep the 80% premise of
known and acceptable and touchable concept that you could relate to and then give it to them.
How about percussions?
Somebody pissed me off.
But...
In cue.
Again, nothing sophisticated about the actual rhythmical pattern, nothing sophisticated
about the tempo, nothing sophisticated at all.
Still, you're using different elements for that.
And why? Not because we really want to outsmart somebody.
This is not the purpose.
The purpose is, well, that a parallel reality,
these guys probably didn't have drums, didn't have anything like these things.
They had junkyard.
So probably that's what their, whatever, ensemble sounded like.
Here's another little secret.
The low, we don't have, I think,
maybe we have a subwoofer here.
Okay, so really, really cool from time to time
to have like a really low sub bass thing, okay?
And I tried to create it out of things
that I have in my studio rather than really go
and make like a synthetic sound or using whatever.
808 drum machine thing. Okay. The first thing is actually interesting. I don't think even if you could hear it, but
This is
Knocking with your finger on a bass trap
if you do it and then you amplify it and
This shit has so many loads you cannot even imagine.
It's crazy.
Some of it you just feel in your stomach.
And you don't really need to hit it hard.
Just do this.
After sampling it and putting it as your oomph bass drum,
believe me, it's really effective.
But it's different.
Found oil jug that really.
amazing has so many things in it. Listen to this.
That's a half full oil,
jag plastic that you hit with your finger
and it has so, so many lows, really. I mean,
and again in your soundscape, sometimes,
especially in the battles and stuff,
you really want to find something to support the whole thing.
Same thing.
If we're talking alternate reality,
we want to find an alternative instrument.
And basically, that's the whole thing, you know?
So here's basically, to sum it up a little bit,
because I want to give as much time as I can for questions.
I'm sure that there are a few.
The most important thing to remember, and I know I'm repeating myself here, but it's
so important, and I feel that this is why I'm here to tell you, and I believe also
that this is what really helped me also survive these 20 years, is understand that you are
a part of a team.
You're not a composer.
You're a team player.
Okay?
I know that you have a lot of aspiration.
I know that you have a lot of great musical ideas.
Forget about it.
Come to the project as a blank page.
Soak in the project and let it basically inspire you before you try to inspire the project
with your ideas.
Only then...
you could actually sort of like get the most immersive sound design and music into a project.
If you don't force yourself into the project, if you don't really feel committed to say
what the project wants to say, you know, then just forget it.
You could create a masterpiece musical, but it really will never...
be as immersive as it could be.
Music in games doesn't really need to be heard.
You don't hear a music in game,
you feel the music in the game.
You don't need to notice the music in the game,
you need to live the music in the game.
The music is basically something that drives you
without you really know what drives you.
It's there, but it's in your imagination.
And if you remember that,
then it's really gonna help you
to create successful scores.
I remember I just created a soundtrack,
my first VR game for Eagle Flight for Ubisoft.
And I was talking to Marty O'Donnell, you probably know who Marty is, he's like the famous Halo composer.
And I asked him like, so Marty, what do you think, you're really into VR,
what do you think, how the music should sound in a VR, because like it's everything, it's all around.
And then he told me something that, and I was like, yeah, baby, this is it.
It's like.
All right, the sound effects, the foley, the dialogue, yes, everything is around it.
But music actually doesn't really exist.
Music is the emotional layer.
So it's right here in your bald, ugly head.
Why?
In between those ears that can't hear anything because of the amount of shells that they
saw and heard.
So it's here.
So you mix your VR score in stereo.
So simple.
Okay?
And we did it.
So all the sound effects is in 5.1, 7.1, 11.20.
I don't care.
Music was mixed in hard stereo.
And it worked like a charm.
Because once everything else moved around and crazy and you're flying and everything,
music was just there.
And it stood out, but it was not in your way.
You heard it extremely well, but it didn't really interfere with the action.
And this is almost summing up what I was telling you about today.
the way. You call it original, you call it signature, but more than anything, it's really
thinking what could be the one special thing that can give your project what it needs to be,
you know, what it really calls for from an emotional point of view.
All right, great. Let's hear you guys.
Hello.
Hi.
I was curious for a game as big as Fallout, you know,
hundreds of hours of gameplay, do you end up writing more music
than you need or is there, do you feel, was there any restriction
on the amount of material that you're putting out?
Is there something that ends up being cut?
Was there anything that you created that you wish was in the game?
that didn't make it or is everything included?
Okay, so here's my answer.
Yes.
Great.
Yes to everything you said.
Do we need more music?
Definitely.
Did you create a lot of music
and some of it is not ending up in the game?
Totally.
All right.
I mean, did you do stuff that you think you need to do
and you didn't do?
Always, you know?
I mean, and basically you nailed it.
This is the secret that specifically
for these kind of expansive games like Fallout,
the amount of material that can be put in is immense.
But then also the choices,
and that's what I'm telling you all the time.
choices. It's all about the choice you make.
Your artistic choice and what you really want to do.
This is the most important thing. So, as I said, yes.
Thank you. In addition to Valhalla Reverb,
are there any software tools that you particularly like for processing the
household sounds you've recorded?
Oh, great question. So, um...
I found that Soundtoys actually really works for me,
if you guys are familiar.
It has a lot of things, of course,
power plugins and everything.
But the real secret, to me at least,
is never use one plugin, A.
B, never use the same plugin again and again in the same queue.
Actually layering the plugins, and it almost doesn't matter.
Everybody's doing a great job.
Wave's doing a great job.
I mean, I mean, I mean, everybody's doing a great job.
But actually creating a layer,
it's like layers of instruments.
I never use the same, like, string patch.
I always layer at least three string patches
on top of each other,
and I'm playing each one of them separately,
so it'll have different dynamics, okay?
Only then.
this is kind of great. So I'm not like a big on one instrument, I'm really big on
the enhancement of layering of elements and this is usually what creates what
I'm looking for. Awesome, thanks.
Hey.
Second time I hear you speak, last time was at MIGS.
Always inspiring as usual, thanks a lot.
Thank you.
The type of music that you're creating
is seems to me like it's very well suited
for semi-generative applications
like live reassembling of textures and music
using middleware.
Is this something you're doing
or you always prefer to have hard-bounced loops
that are already...
assembled. Oh no, no, no, no, no. Let me stop you right here. And especially for Fallout,
every note is played. And if not in a real time, it was played, recorded, and then only then
recorded and looped. I am very, very much hands-on when I'm composing. I never use sort of like
prepared loops or prepared... Oh no, that's not what I mean. I mean...
for example, recording a bunch of piano cues
and then recording a bunch of bowed guitar cues,
but having all of those randomly reassembled
in a wise, for example, software.
Oh yeah, yeah, yeah, no, no, of course.
I mean, oh yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Is this something you're doing?
Yeah, everything, actually, it's a good question
and I hope I'm answering it correctly.
One thing that, I'm not really great at the technical thing,
but one of the things to being a successful composer
is really work with the right people.
and I happen to have the right person
that is creating a lot of my contact instruments.
First I use, as I said, Umlaut
to help me create great loops,
but also my assistant, Alex Ruger,
is basically notoriously taking everything
I'm recording and playing
and make it into a contact library on my own.
And it is so freaking great.
All right, thanks a lot.
Hi Anon, really big fan.
I just wanted to ask you kind of about your approach
to coming up with these cues.
Do you kind of get the inspiration
from the interesting sounds that you're creating
and then create the composition around those sounds
or do you have like a bed first?
Or so what, basically what's your process?
Great question.
And basically,
It's a great question and it's so hard to tell
because the way I'm working is so intuitive.
I could sit and before even play one note,
I want to hear something.
It all starting from me wanting to hear something.
And then I'll start to experiment.
And this something could be melody.
This something could be, it doesn't have like a rules of,
oh, I lay out the chords, I lay out the melody,
I lay out this, and then, no, no, no,
it doesn't work this way, at least for me.
I will try to listen to.
this thing before even starting and then if I got like an idea of
Okay, so it should be this kind of sound I'll play the sound or I'll look for this sound once I found the sound
Usually it will have inside of it already some kind of a melodic
gesture and
With all the anharmonics and stuff many many cases
It's also starting to create the harmonic texture
So you first listen to something, you know, before playing, and then you start sort of
like the creative process.
So it's no, I mean, it's not like, oh, melody, oh no, rhythm, oh no, harmony, no, no, no.
It's not like this.
So it's more organic than that?
Exactly.
On that note, if you aren't finding good inspiration from that, do you have a process that you
like to go through that you can derive something from?
Well, yes.
And again, I recommend each one of you to listen to other people.
I got a lot of inspiration from other composers.
hate them because they're so good.
But nevertheless, I mean, hate your competition, but respect them also.
So listen to them, listen to what they do.
And I will listen, okay?
If I really want to hear stuff that is interesting me, you know,
like in games and stuff.
plenty of great guys Austin Jason Graves Tom Salt I mean lots of people
okay if I want to listen in movies I probably listen to Johan Jansson
that really creates interesting texture
and for me I get a lot of inspiration from this or Thomas Newman
okay so yes do recommend listen to other stuff
thank you very much of course any more questions
if no well then
Thank you very much.
It's time.
Thank you.