Hi everyone, welcome to the GDC Twitch channel. My name is Brian Francis. I am here today with our wonderful guest in the lower left hand corner of the screen.
Our wonderful guest is Matthew Burns of Zachtronics.
Matthew, I believe it would be accurate to describe you as the lead developer on this game we're playing today, right?
Yeah, it's kind of unlike every other Zachtronics game. This is sort of like my game, I guess, in a way.
And the game in question is, I believe it's called Solitaire?
Yeah, you guys just made a whole Solitaire game this time?
Simple and startling?
Yeah, it's called Kabufuda Solitaire.
Oh, Kabufuda, wait, so this is a different kind of Solitaire from...
It's a Solitaire based on Kabufuda cards, which are kind of a, you know, a kind of Japanese playing card that you can still buy today.
Nintendo actually still makes them.
So, you can buy Nintendo brands.
physical Kabufuda cards if you want.
That is absolutely correct. It is a visual novel in almost every sense of the term.
Yeah, we'll dig into that a little more, but yeah.
Eliza is a visual novel set in the far off land of Seattle.
In fact, I got a really eerie look when I went on the light rail in this game, and I was like, wait, I've been here?
Uh-huh.
So, like I said, it's a light novel, which means it's a narrative story about an app developed for treating mental health, which is something that is happening in our real world.
It's a little weird, a little prescient, you might say.
It's different than a lot of the other games we've streamed, which have been...
Kind of delving through all kinds of systems.
This one shows off some of the fine writing that has showed up in interesting characters and settings
that have been part of other Zachtronics games, but usually are sort of helping make the interesting puzzles take shape.
But, Eliza has been nominated.
For a couple of IGF awards, and I'm pretty sure that those awards are the IGF Award for Excellence in Narrative and the Seamus McNally Grand Prize.
That's right, right?
Mm-hmm. Yeah.
Yeah.
With that in mind, we are here today with Matthew to take your questions and my questions, and
everyone's questions, whoever's questions.
We are here today, as we play the game, check it out, sort of dive through the ins and outs
of the way Eliza tells its pretty unique story.
We are only going through, I've played about 30 minutes of the story, so if you're concerned
about spoilers, we're going to go through what I call the first 90 minutes or so, unless
I get stuck on something, or I don't think there's anything I get stuck on, or if I get
distracted.
Yeah, you won't get.
stuck.
I don't think, unless you want to try to beat Solitarium hard or something like that, but
other than that.
This is X-A-Punks.
No, it's not any X-Actronics game in that sense, right?
Like you can...
It's a visual novel.
I'll get things rolling here with the game.
Matthew, would you mind...
Actually, I'm going to turn the music down real quick.
Would you mind just explaining to us the origins of this game
and what sort of got you and the folks at Zachtronics started on a visual novel
as opposed to the normal puzzlers that we see from you all?
Sure, yeah.
So, before I worked at Zachtronics full-time...
I worked at the University of Washington here.
This was sort of in between working on AAA games and the other stuff that I was doing.
As part of that academic job, I saw a bunch of different technologies that were in development,
having to do with trying to apply game technologies to health and education and things like that.
So while I was there, one of the demos that I saw was this like kind of virtual therapist
application thing that people were working on, where there was like an avatar, like a
second life looking avatar that would like interview you about your day or whatever.
And this was in 2014.
And I remember seeing that demo and just being like, that's such a wild thing.
It just struck me in a certain way.
It seemed kind of dystopian.
It seemed just like an interesting story.
I had this idea for the scene of someone talking about some very, very deep topics about themselves.
When you go to therapy, sometimes you access some really deep things.
And then it's just like this Amazon Alexa on the other side of it.
The contrast between those things is so great.
So I was thinking about telling a story about this.
And so on my own time, I always do my own writing.
I have some Twine games that I've made.
So I thought, well, maybe I'll do a Twine game about this, where you are talking to
a virtual therapist, or where someone is talking to a virtual therapist.
And maybe you can
maybe you work at the office and you are like...
applying AI therapy to people, like you don't actually do therapy on your own, but you are
the vector for this AI to do therapy to people. So I kind of worked out that basic premise in
twine form. I still have some of the twine prototypes that I made, there are like two or
three of them. And the basic format of the game was actually all just done in twine, so there's
There's a very early one where it's just like you're sitting in your office and then you have a couple options of like,
look out the window, do another therapy session, go into the kitchen and see if there's cookies, things like that.
And so I was working on this, again in my own time.
And then around the time after we shipped Opus Magnum, I think in like 2016, at Zachtronics,
I was talking to Zach and I've been...
We were just chatting about stuff and I was like, well I'm working on this story about
this virtual therapist and it would be cool to do it as like a visual novel with some
art and if we could get some actors in and things like that.
And Zach was just kind of like, yeah, let's do it.
Let's give it a try.
So because I had this kind of fully formed idea already that, I mean it wasn't fully
formed but it was pretty well formed.
and I had a lot of the script done already.
So it wasn't hugely risky because to him, for his part of it, Visual Novels is very simple.
He doesn't really have to think about the design space of it too much.
There was some user interface work, obviously, but there wasn't this big design space.
that he needed to explore, anything like that.
Like, by saying it's going to be a visual novel,
kind of grounds it in an established genre,
you know, an established style.
So, it was pretty easy to think about doing at that point.
Yeah, let's talk about the visual novel-ness of it and how there's still kind of a sense of interaction with this game that means you're not just sort of clicking through dialogue and you're not making a lot of choices, like there's some light branching that I've encountered so far.
But I want to talk about what we're looking at here on screen, which is the dialogue that's playing as, you know, the character here is explaining their problems to you.
You, the character, you're not just, you're playing as Evelyn, who is using the Eliza interface to interact with this person.
So, right now things feel very on rails, but early on there's a lot of talk about something that feels like it will be a choice.
which is the idea of you're supposed to be reading off the script here that I'm mousing over
and then down here obviously the text is popping up
and in the very first conversation the character here trying to help begs you to go off script
and the software prompts you to go off script by staying on script
by saying things that seem off script
so it's kind of this loop that even though it is nothing has changed in the
In the scripting, in the formatting, in the string of pearls that you're constructing,
there's an illusion.
The player is suddenly conscious of control and what they have choice over in a way that
a lot of other games like to make big statements about, but this one sort of does just by railroading
right through the conversation.
How did you sort of come to that?
So there is design space, right?
Like even though there's not a lot of...
even though this isn't Choose Your Own Adventure,
there's still... the player's brain is being wrapped around
the idea of what choices they have the ability to make
and how that affects these characters.
I'm speaking broadly. Totally.
It's easier to go into specifics, but...
Yeah. What were your thoughts about that when you were making it?
I think...
You know, I didn't have this term when I was doing it,
but I feel like if...
if interaction...
if interactive design is like giving people...
choices or is about giving people choices, then taking choices away is kind of like a
it's kind of like the negative space of game design in a way. And that can be very powerful
to say that, you know, in this instance you don't have any choices. And so there actually was, I
played around with a couple different ideas of like how these therapy sessions would actually work.
And in some early versions, it's like, oh, well, you should pick between these three
things to say.
And then maybe the client feels better if you pick this thing versus that other thing.
And the more I thought about that and making therapy like a mechanic, the less I liked
that because you'd be making the argument that like...
all someone needs to do is hear the right thing and then they feel better.
You know, it's kind of, there's a lot of, um,
but it, it, there's a lot of issues around, around trying to like,
the make,
make something interactive that actually has to do with real human beings and,
and like what you say to them and how they feel.
Like I didn't want to reduce people to like these little mechanical objects
that are just like, Oh, you did a great job.
There are no specific guidelines for this.
I just want to say that I'm not a therapist.
I'm not a therapist.
But...
So eventually, yeah, eventually it was just like, you know what, I think the therapy sessions are going to be completely linear.
You're going to be railroaded on them.
And then hilariously you get that sort of completion screen with like little metrics and how they rated you and stuff like that.
It's like you have no agency over that.
Right, yeah, those are completely canned, right?
And it's funny because some people understand this, but like other people...
Play the entire therapy session, click through it, and then they're like,
oh, but how do I get a better rating?
Oh my god.
And yeah, and it's funny because it's so ingrained in us that like, you know,
you do something and then you get your little Overwatch badges at the end,
and it's just like, you got this, this, this.
And so those, you know, that completion screen being completely fake is,
you know, my way of like...
Having a little bit of commentary on that, because you had absolutely no choice, there's
nothing you could have done, but you still get these fun little instrumentalized badges
and XP and stuff like that at the end.
It made me feel bad about my Apex Legends badges.
We are looking at it right now. I wanted to talk about the interface too.
You said Zack had a lot less to do this time, but he did some UI work on this.
This UI is really simple. This is sort of a little standard.
Although I like the nice pagey kind of feeling here along the top of the UI.
But when you're in there, there's a couple of really cool things happening,
which is on the left, there's kind of some prompts that are firing off.
On the left side of the screen, which is what we have here, there's the prompts that are firing off that are like positive or negative responses to the dialogue.
Over here, there's kind of like this thing, you know, like their audio inflection.
I was really surprised that the waveforms on this seem to be lining up, and I was surprised at how there were all these little things firing over here, positive, negative, on the dialogue.
And it wasn't just generic flow, like it felt really immersive for even though this was in such an intimate moment.
How much work did that take?
It was a fair amount of work to hook that all up.
All of those, you know, all of those metrics and things like that are pretty fake.
They're kind of like fluttering around and just there to make you feel like it's doing something.
That even comes up in the story that like, if all you really have to do is say exactly what the AI tells you to,
you don't actually really need all of those metrics, right?
Like if this job really existed.
You wouldn't need to actually have all of that information.
But the headset, the fictional headset that you put on, shows all that stuff just to kind of like make you think that it's doing something.
It's sort of like when you...
You know, when you go to your bank's website or something and it like...
It'll have animations and stuff for things when it's not...
You know that it's not doing anything, but it'll play that animation for you anyway,
just to make you feel better about how it can't contact the server or whatever.
So that stuff is kind of a little bit of a UX commentary on how...
We like to see that it's like...
So that it looks fancy, that it looks like it's doing something.
And you can imagine that Skanda, the tech company in this...
built all that out so that it demos really well, so that people think that it's doing so.
Right on, we're gonna shift gears a little bit here in conversation, get back on talking about the game's narrative.
If you folks have questions for Matthew in chat, feel free to drop them. I'll grab them and ask him myself.
The main character of the story, Evelyn, takes the job as a Eliza proxy, in part it seems because she seems to also be dealing with a kind of emotional or mental, I wouldn't call it a crisis, but definitely a hard time sort of fits the bill.
I was sort of struck by playing the first 5-10 minutes of this game how super emotionally
intense it is, especially when all there is to focus on is the text and not any shiny
doodads, Overwatch badges, gunplay, whatever.
I was wondering about what your experience was.
I can sort of conceive of the writing and understanding a character and letting it
flow out, but I was curious about how you wanted players to understand the story.
How did you understand Evelyn in this way?
And how you could help them understand her position when all you sort of have are dialogue trees to work with?
Yeah, I mean I think there were a lot of cues at the beginning of the game that this was going to be a more introspective kind of experience, right?
Like at the start, the key image of the game is her sitting on the bench and it's this very, very...
blue-gray Seattle day and there's a big focus on the clouds in the sky and things like that.
Evelyn at the start of the story I think is sort of recovering from a depressive episode.
And so there's a lot of like people saying, wow I haven't seen you in a while, you know,
where have you been, how have you been, sorry I didn't ever contacted you and things like that,
because she's been kind of just more or less...
moping around in her apartment for close to three years, which is a pretty long time.
Part of that is, it's really like, there's a lot of reasons why that's the case.
One is that it's kind of, it's nice to start a story that way because she's like reconnecting
with people that she used to talk to but don't quite know.
It's, you know, they...
It gives you a little bit of an excuse to fill people in on what has happened in the past.
It's sort of like a gentler version of starting a story where someone has amnesia or something like that.
The hero washes up on the beach and has amnesia, and then everyone you meet is new because everyone in the story is new to you as well.
So mechanically, that's a useful thing.
Emotionally, I think it's really important to show her getting her bearings again and making a very large decision about what she needs to do next in her life.
That's where this game is basically going, as it's building to Evelyn needs to make a decision about what she's going to do for the rest of her life or for her career.
What is she going to dedicate her time and energy to? What's important to her?
And having that depressive episode where she didn't have anything that she cared about,
you know, this story is about coming into the process of discovering that again, and
figuring that out, and making a big, maybe a career change, or moving away, or something
like that.
Just a very large decision that affects your life quite a bit.
And then, you know, there's another aspect to it, too.
She's really burnt out.
I kind of wanted to tell a story about people in their 30s.
And so Evelyn is in her 30s, you know, Evelyn and Ray and Nora are all in their 30s.
And at least, you know, my personal experience of like kind of like getting into my 30s,
I had this moment where I was just like, wow, I don't.
I worked really hard throughout my 20s, and I don't even know why I did that.
I look back and it was just like, wow, I worked very hard, and now I don't...
What do I have? What have I accomplished by doing that?
And so there's this moment of looking back and feeling burnt out,
and asking myself why I did that.
And I think that that is definitely part of Evelyn's character as well.
I was still there for some reason.
The choice dialogue driven games, players are often aligning different choices.
Sometimes there's a moral system, sometimes there's a character system.
Some really interesting games are kind of using an information system,
like you want to make different dialogue choices because you're motivated
to get certain information.
In a game without those tangible rewards, I'm still sensing kind of a reason to pick.
I'm going to be doing a lot of different dialogue choices here as I play.
It's kind of like how people don't say what's on their mind,
they sort of translate what's on their mind into dialogue, if that makes sense.
That's true in real life, and that's true of really good screenplays,
is when you're talking about one thing, you're talking about something else.
I'm curious how you approach that as a writer in this story,
and maybe other stories you work on too,
because you've had to transition from objective-based dialogue
to open dialogue as well.
I think that it was important to me to be honest, in a way.
I don't really like the idea of fooling the player into thinking that there's more agency than there really is.
I would much rather say, here's this thing that you have to be on board with and go along with.
As opposed to saying, here's this mysterious system where you pick dialogue options and then stuff happens,
but you're not, you don't quite understand why stuff happened.
You know, like maybe it's tallying points in the background or maybe it's like you did this, you did, you picked the wrong kind of like
cookie to eat so somebody doesn't like you or something like that. Like that kind of stuff feels
arbitrary to me and it feels kind of
you know,
Not necessarily that true to life, even.
So, like, to me, I think it's... I just want to lay it out there and say,
hey, yeah, these are the things that you can choose.
They won't matter in the long run.
And these particular choices that you get throughout most of the game
are kind of these flavor choices, you know?
You can make Evelyn a little bit more defiant or a little bit more agreeable.
And these things are...
The reward for picking them is just hearing that, hearing the conversation go in that direction for a little while before it kind of wraps back around to what the conversation was going to be anyway.
So...
Yeah, you know, it wasn't like a...
It definitely wasn't going to be, ever going to be a story where it was like, you know, there are lots of different routes and like lots of different outcomes and...
So and so will remember that and you know things like that because
I don't think
I don't know. It just wasn't it just wasn't where this story was going, right? You know, it wasn't like a
Which person's life should you save or any anything like that? And that that kind of stuff like can be very
um gut-wrenching if you build it up properly, which person's life do you save but it's also like
That doesn't come up a lot in in real life and I kind of wanted to like
ground this very much in real life.
I mean, unless you're like a medical professional or something like that, but it was really
about like, yeah, choosing what you do as a tech worker, I guess, in this instance.
Man, this is not a question, this is not a question but an observation.
I sort of think it's interesting how in this dialogue with Nora,
she's talking about, you know, giving up the tech life and moving over to the artist and rocker life.
But there's, and she talks about the tech business being a business causing as many problems as it solves.
And she got tired of trying to get rich, trying to get famous, trying to change the world.
But there's still kind of a want to change the world in her personality that comes through.
Right in hand even as she sort of knocks down the job she used to have.
That's such an interesting and good psychoanalysis for a character.
To still be fixated on something even while they're tired of it.
Like I said, observation not question.
My actual question is, I think it's time to talk about text in games like this.
I was watching an interview with one of the lead devs on Disco Elysium,
and they talked about how they were using the right side of the screen and the lower right-hand corner in particular to be this place where
to create this kind of Twitter-esque addiction quality to text.
This game doesn't have that, although your choices over here do show up in the same corner of the screen that he was referring to.
How did you and Zach think about this kind of process?
Obviously there's sort of a conventional visual novel style which brings dialogue into the space of where subtitles usually go.
That was something that the Disco Elysium guy brought up too, was that most games put text here because it's where subtitles go.
Text can go anywhere. Text couldn't be across the screen. Text can be floating over people's heads.
In this scene right now, the dialogue could be popping up in comic bubbles right over their heads if we wanted it to.
Well, if you wanted it to. I have no say in the matter.
But did you think about that at all? What was your approach for making interactive dialogue?
Interactive text? Excuse me.
I definitely just started with the standard visual novel stuff.
The way I thought about it was...
Here's this story that I want to tell, and here are these themes that I want to explore, and stuff like that.
And then, the cool thing is that visual novels actually are a pretty well-developed and storied genre of game, you know?
And there's a grammar that visual novels have developed over the past 15, even 20 years of...
You have character portraits, you have backgrounds that they exist on, and then you have this
sort of text window at the bottom of the screen.
So using established visual novel stuff was very useful for us because it was this way
to just say, some of these problems have already been solved.
Not necessarily solved like this is absolutely the best way to do them,
but solved in terms of like, this is a language that we can use,
an established language that we can use to express the ideas in this particular story.
So we started there and I think it works out pretty well.
The dialogue looks pretty nice.
The display of the character's name on the far left there
kind of comes from
plays. If you've ever read the script to a play, it has that kind of look to it. This
was as opposed to putting another small character portrait there, or putting it in another box
on the screen, stuff like that. And then, because this game is pretty much just a series
of conversations between Evelyn and one other person.
There are some exceptions, but most of the game is a conversation between Evelyn and another person.
So it kind of just worked that Evelyn would always be on the right side,
and her choices would be represented on the right side,
and then whoever she was talking to would be on the left side, which is kind of the...
In Western culture, the left side is kind of the stronger side, because you read from left to right.
Sorry, I'm just falling a little bit in love with Meredith M. Mercer,
dramaturge and game designer extraordinaire,
because that's an excellent title, and his excellent manifesto about...
No, her excellent manifesto about how to play Solitaire.
Right, yeah. I'm glad you like my bit characters too.
Oh man, I just love that even in this, you know, even in, like I said, I genuinely, when I was playing, especially Obismahagnam, was falling in love with the little bits of story that were creeping in there, and I'm just loving the way you guys handle devices, and I love this little phone you built in, I love the little hand buttons things, there's just like, look, this little scroll bar works, oh my god.
These, and it looks like she's doing it on the phone.
These are little details that, um, every time I pick up when you,
one of Zach, a Zach Tronick's game, um, your whole team manages to impress me with these.
Um, sorry, now that I'm done, uh, kissing up, kissing up to y'all.
Um...
Okay, we're at the bottom of the hour right now, which means we have about 30 minutes left in our chat or so.
Go a little shorter, maybe go a little longer, we'll see.
I can see we've got a few folks hanging out. If you've got questions for Matt or you just want to say hi, go ahead and chat. We will grab them.
Right on schedule, TFK365 would like to say, as a software engineer in his early 20s, Erland's story really resonated with them.
They just wanted to say thanks for making this game.
Awesome, thank you for playing it. That's really nice to hear.
I'm going to move on with the narrative in that case and also move on with my questions.
Matt, thank you so much for putting an auto-advanced text in this game.
Text games are so hard to stream for the most part and the auto-advanced is making it so easy.
Again, that's another visual novel thing.
That was like, you know, over the decades they've just developed this standard set of features that...
are created based on need and stuff like that so it was really nice to use
to use things like that.
Let's talk about the art direction for a second. I didn't put this in the notes I gave you, but I know
you aren't doing the visual art for this game,
but I'd love to know more about what your thoughts were as someone who had this idea for the story.
You could have gone really wild with the setting, you brought it in more to a more familiar setting.
I'm curious how you then worked with an artist to go,
okay, we still want things to look eye-catching
and appealing and to let the visuals tell a story too,
which thankfully they have been in the background here,
the coffee shop, the room that's behind
this text message stuff.
Oh my God, there's so many cookie options.
Give me a second here, but yeah,
would you mind talking about the art
and how your process interacted with your art team?
Yeah, well, you think about what your favorite
type of cookie is.
I can say that it was,
we did take a.
a bit of time at the beginning to really think about the best way to approach the style of
this.
Because we knew we didn't want to do super anime art or anything like that for the story.
It wasn't supposed to be super stylized or anything.
This is a story that takes place in Seattle in modern day, so it's a pretty grounded story.
At the same time...
We didn't necessarily want this photorealistic treatment either, whatever that even means.
So we kind of settled, it took a little while, but we kind of settled on this sort of painterly,
mostly realistic but also somewhat stylized approach to both the characters and the backgrounds.
Taking reality and then painting it with a little bit of a stylized eye.
But other than that, going for a naturalist look.
I think it ended up working out pretty well.
I think you can get where this game is coming from by looking at the art and character portraits, which is a testament to the...
to the artists who did a fantastic, fantastic job.
Moving over to my question pile, what I will ask next is, oh yeah, here's one of my favorite questions to talk to writers and narrative designers about.
I have a weird, big, stump speech about how the incredible stories we get to experience in video games, and elsewhere, outside of video games, in movies and books,
How the narratives and the themes and the characters that we get to encounter are often shaped and informed by the medium and not just by the medium but by the tools that are used to make the medium.
So there's a lot of things that the average player sort of doesn't get to see about the process, if you will, that totally shapes the kind of story that comes out.
You mentioned using Twine at the top. I don't know quite how you translate Twine into whatever tools you guys use at Zachtronics.
Excuse me, y'all use at Zachtronics.
Have you thought about that at all?
Oh, definitely.
Do you have anything you want to contribute to that thought?
For sure.
Yeah, yeah.
Well, so Twine, when I was using Twine, it was definitely, it was super, super early
in what this was.
So it didn't go directly from Twine into this.
Yeah.
When I decided, like, okay, this is going to be a visual novel, then I, like,
wrote it for real, basically keeping that in mind that it was going to be a visual novel.
I think that having that set form again really does inform a lot of things.
For example, most of the conversations are one-on-one. That's not necessarily a limitation
of visual novels. Some of them have three people, some of them have scenes of up to
four or five people sometimes. I don't...
think that it always works as well.
The basic visual novel conversation style is usually between two people.
And so that form informs what I wrote, right?
And how I take advantage of the strengths and weaknesses of the medium in some way.
The idea of like...
Having your phone, for example. Not all games give you a little in-game phone.
But because you have an in-game phone, I wanted to play around with having some of the conversations happening over IM versus happening in so-called real life.
And then also just all these emails that you get. You're looking at one right now.
Someone forwards you an article that they saw in the newspaper and that kind of adds another dimension to the story.
So thinking about the technology that you use...
It absolutely affects how the story is told and then from there, the content of it.
I just want to say thank you for being one of the...
There's a lot of fake newspaper articles that show up in video games.
Almost none of them use the inverted pyramid that we have to use in Gala Sutra.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. I'm proud of actually following...
Newspaper-y guidelines for writing the newspaper article.
Thank you, thank you, thank you.
My partner works in news too, so I'll let her know that you guys did that, now that I found,
that y'all did that, now that I found that here.
Yeah, that, that, that's, that's, um, that makes a lot of sense.
Okay.
I'm going to, as we advance, oh my god, like, folks, I don't know if you know, we are the
Game Developers Conference, so right now we're on the Game Developers Conference Twitch channel
watching a keynote at an in-game conference, and I think we're about to say we're a little
far down the rabbit hole right now.
There might be a little bit of GDC in this scene.
That's fine, that's fine.
It's art.
Art's the point about things.
Simon doesn't...
doesn't kill me, but there's a little bit of GDC in this.
I love it. Yeah, GDC I'll do I'll do a quick plug for if you
want to check out our show this year, the dates are up in the
top left corner of the screen and we hope to see you there.
The award show that Eliza will be is nominated for is on
Wednesday night, Wednesday the 18th. There, there's it. There's
my plug. That's how I counter you're putting GDC in the game.
Okay, well this is also kind of a TED Talk as well, so it's not, I mean, you can see the very dramatic presentation here is kind of meant to evoke the feeling of like his sort of TED Talk like pageantry and pompousness.
I would goof on... I would keep goofing on that, but I might get in trouble.
You called them pompous, I didn't. I don't know if they get mad at us.
So, I mean, this character is Pompous, so I'm making a fu- uh, you know.
Yeah.
Um, this was fun-
Pompous people give talks.
That's- that's a thing.
Yes, it's true.
Um, I'm including myself in that.
Um, this was fun because I designed- like, I authored these, like, fake slides for him to have,
and then we kind of- the artist did a pass on, like, making them look especially, like, tech- techie and kind of, um-
Look at the triangles, man. Like-
Yeah.
Look at all these triangles your artist did.
That's what really makes it picky.
And like the green glow.
Right. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I can keep riffing on that.
Let's talk about planning and producing this kind of game.
Obviously you're the lead, you're the writer, you get to say like, you get to have a lot
of creative control over this thing and you sort of get to say what's possible and what's
not.
Obviously with a script that you were working from, that sort of makes it different than
how other narrative games get written.
But there is still a factor when you're making a game like this.
Okay, we're producing this much content, it takes this much time,
we can budget for this much, we have to scale for it going over by game much,
if something's not working, if we get stuck somewhere.
How do producing challenges sort of intersect with your creative vision?
That's what I'd like to know.
I think for this it was just a matter of like really keeping a lid on
on the number of assets that we made.
And I tried to be really careful of that and keep that in mind when I was writing the script.
Characters and locations, everything is pretty stripped down to what absolutely has to be there,
because the only way we would have made this is as frugally as possible.
So when I introduced a background or a character, it was always with
There's always a very specific purpose that that exists for.
And the stuff that we did that was a little bit bonus or extra was the Solitaire game,
the little meditation app that you have with the pixel art on your phone.
Those were little bonus things that we might have cut if we had run overboard on some of this other stuff.
But luckily, we went in, the script was basically done, the entire script for the game was kind
of at a rough draft point when we started bringing on the artists and actually putting
the game into production.
So when we started, it was like, okay, we know we'll need exactly this amount of stuff.
Because the script was not open-ended, like, I don't know how I'm going to end this.
And oh, wait, I need new assets in order to do this.
So...
It was actually, from a production standpoint, it was actually quite under control the whole
time.
But that's not always possible.
I think we really benefited from having basically a finished script and having this saying right
off the bat that it's going to be a visual novel and not necessarily...
mechanically innovating in any particular way.
Right.
Like I wouldn't say that this game is mechanically innovative.
It's not really doing any like things that any other given game hasn't done before.
If it innovates in any way, it's in its content.
Yeah, that's so interesting. That's such a tough...
I feel for game developers because part of the push for any game is
you're trying to make something that can find appeal, that can find an audience.
One very quick way is to say we're innovating your gameplay,
you're going to play something you haven't played before.
And that's still true. And when you say you're going to play something you haven't played before with Eliza,
that's still true in that...
This unique story hasn't existed before, especially not in mainstream games.
But sometimes it's a harder sell for an audience, especially when unfortunately discourse or dialogue about narrative in games can sometimes go,
Oh, well this could have just been a book. I don't think it lies it could have been a book.
I don't think so either, although definitely some people have criticized it for not being mechanically innovative.
It's it doesn't.
It doesn't give you any fancy new reverbs to play with.
And so I can see that if your interest is in narrative games for the purpose of creating this cool new way of interacting and stuff like that,
then this Eliza might not seem very impressive.
But my hope is that people can focus on the content and think about the themes of the story and think about the characters.
and enjoy it on that level.
Mouse over the text or mouse over things in the scene, interesting things will happen.
That may, that one may even go back to the classic adventure game format where, like,
if this scene was sort of presented without the text scrolling by, you could mouse over
and then maybe one of these, like, heads would pop up and do a weird thing or something.
Right, right.
But that's like, man, an educational game in the day, in the day you see that.
Right.
The, but, um...
You've got the folks who were working on Tyranny, you've got Disco Elysium, like making it so that when you mouse over things, other interesting things happen.
And the thing is, I know you know how to do that, because I played The Writer Will Do Something, which was you and Tom Bissell.
And that was such a cool, like...
Interactive experiment that is also the kind of work that has been done by a lot of great works authors entwined
Shout out to friends of the show like Chris Legman who get to do stuff like that in their work. Totally
So what was your thought process about like it's weird to say why is this feature not in the game when we just talked about
not innovating on features
right, but
I might as well ask like what are your thoughts about like that kind of those kind of mechanics? Sure
I think you know, I mean, I love those kinds of mechanics and I would say that like
If it's not in Eliza, it just didn't feel right for the type of story that it is.
The limited amount of looking around an environment that you can do in Eliza, every so often you
get the scene where you can look at your apartment or you can look at the office and Evelyn has
a little line about the coffee maker in the office and things like that.
Those are these little...
very, you know, extremely light exploration moments with no stakes and completely optional.
I think my answer is just that, like, that's just, it's just not the type of game that I think
really supports that. I think the delight of, like, those edutainment games, you remember the
word edutainment that people used back then? That was my first book for Gama Sutra was about
edutainment. Oh my god. So, you know, like that.
like when you click on something and a fun little animation plays or something like that
it's just not that, it's not really that type of game
it's not going to reward you just clicking around on stuff
because it's, you know, when you're
when you are attending a conference about mental health
applications and watching someone's keynote speech and then running into your old boss
in the lobby as you are now
That kind of fun exploration stuff isn't really on your mind, right?
So I would say it just comes from the story and being embodied in that place.
um, let me see here, just clicking around my email, my work email, man this contractor parking is so...
I worked, the job I worked at before I worked at this job we didn't, I didn't get parking when I first got there
so it's like, yeah, you're just gonna need to find street parking and in Los Angeles it's like, you know it's a challenge
It's a challenge
It's all, it's not the worst
Not New York
No, but you know, it's all, a lot of that like
It's funny because, as you have learned in the story by now, Avalyn used to be a full-time employee of Skanda.
And so coming back as a contractor, she's like, kind of encountering all of this stuff that contractors actually face.
And it's a contrast from her previous, you know, experience at Skanda.
And I kind of wanted to do that whole, like, blue badge versus orange badge thing.
Which is a thing, I mean that's not even just a tech industry thing, that's a game industry thing too.
It is, yeah.
I hope I don't get you in trouble right now because I stumbled on, geez it,
I stumbled on something when I was looking at screenshots for this game that made me pause and ask.
So our friend here is wearing the logo of a popular football team, American football.
I assume you had to get clearances for that or is this artistic interpretation?
This is an artistic interpretation.
Artistic interpretation, there we go. I was curious if that was a...
Like, making things real life in games is sometimes hard because it's so hard to recreate the branded worlds we live in.
This is... I'll just say it, that is absolutely a calculated risk that we decided to take.
We thought about it, and usually game makers are very, very skittish about this.
They don't want anything at all in any kind of capacity to possibly show up.
But, you know, I thought that by setting things in Seattle and making it realistic, you know,
why not have some real stuff in there?
And we thought, we were just like, you know, it makes sense.
And I think that there is a case to be made that this is allowable, right?
So it's like kind of making a stand a little bit.
making a statement and saying we think that games are...
you know, the defense for artistic interpretation is games are like art, right?
So they should be able to do things like this.
Yeah.
And I know, obviously, like a lot of TV show would go ahead and get clearances on this thing.
Certainly independent art, a lot of times also skirts the risk of... skirts the lines on this kind of thing.
Often for the same reason, for naturalism, for...
These are the clothes people wear. These are things that people...
This is how people look. You can't just hide that behind legal stuff.
Right, right. So yeah, this is kind of like our small, you know, our small flag that we're planting and saying that we think that this should be allowable.
Yeah, I admire it.
We have come to the end of our time here with Matthew. If you folks have questions, feel free to toss them in chat.
It's been a little quieter today, but I don't mind. I've really enjoyed just getting to talk and I've enjoyed having you folks listen.
For my part, I will go ahead and ask Matthew...
Oh yeah, here's one. Visual novels are...
The visual novel style is actually a little more familiar than folks may know.
If they play games like Fire Emblem, if you play other Zachtronics games,
its elements pop up there, you know, the talking head and the scrolling text.
And depending on how high the budget for the game is, you may have different animations that accompany those,
like either fully animated or just jumping from pose to pose.
Obviously, having now played more of Eliza, I realize this is sort of one face per conversation,
which seems quite economical.
What were your thoughts about that?
What were your thoughts on making the most of a limited asset palette,
which is something that visual novels do so well?
Yeah, so I was hoping that it would work this way. I think it does work. I think that the
actual still expressions that the artists drew and painted are actually very, very expressive,
like Gabriel's face right here that you're looking at right now. I think it's actually a
very expressive face and has a lot of emotion to it already. And if he was switching between faces
a lot as you spoke to him, I think...
Combined with this semi-realistic art style, it would bring more attention to the fact
that it's not animated, and then he's switching faces and things like that.
This was another aesthetic decision, as well as a production decision, that went hand-in-hand,
which is that I think that these very nice, expressive...
Portraits are enough on their own, you know, and combined with the amazing voice acting
that the actors provided, I think makes these characters very rich without needing to give
them facial expressions that actually change.
That's a nice transition for us to talk about the voice acting.
I'm really curious what kind of approach you brought as the person in charge of the story to go into the recording booth and hear your dialogue.
What was your process for working with the actors here?
So the biggest thing that I told every actor was that naturalism was the most important thing.
That all of these people that we're speaking to are real people.
And that it's just important for, like, if they read something and it doesn't feel right,
that they can try to, like, say what comes to mind.
Like, you know, contract things or run two sentences together that are listed as separate
lines in the script.
Or throw in pauses, throw in you knows, things like that, to try to make the dialogue just
feel like people actually talking.
It turns out video game voice actors don't get to do that as much as maybe other types
of actors because a lot of video game voice acting is you must say the exact line and
you have to stop between each line.
There's a lot of parameters and that's not to say that that's bad, it's just because
of the way the game works.
They have to stick to a very regimented way of saying things.
Being given the freedom to open up a little bit, I think they really responded to it and gave some
really amazing performances. And if they said something that was different from the script,
or if they ad-libbed a little bit, or added things, or whatever, it was fine. I could just
go back and change what the text says to match that. So it was a great process because you feel
like you're creating the character with the actor.
and not just having an actor come in and say words and then leave.
And that, I think, if the voice acting ended up working well, I think it's partially because
of that.
It's like including them in the process of creating that character and giving them, you
know, making them feel like they have the space to really go places and really explore
things.
Okay, with that, we're coming to the end of our hour here, and I think Matthew's got to go back to...
You know, Eliza's done. There's other games that got to get made out there in the world.
We're gonna quietly wind things down here on the GDC Twitch channel.
Thank you all for watching today, thank you for playing Eliza with us.
This game is nominated for the 2020 IGF Awards.
You will be able to watch the awards ceremony here on the GDC Twitch channel.
Again, that is on Wednesday the 18th.
Next month, which is coming up real soon.
You keep saying next month in February and suddenly it's a few days away.
Because even though it's leap year, it's still, you know, like,
there's a couple of less days you get to work with.
If you are attending GDC, you will be able to watch the awards yourself.
If you just drop by West Hall Lower Level, you will see all the signage to get in there.
Just sit there and watch and hopefully Eliza wins something.
But if it doesn't, another great game is going to win because all the nominees are great.
And on top of that, I would like to recommend that if you're going to the show, you can check out Eliza at the IGF Pavilion.
I don't remember exactly where that will be on the show floor this year because things move around a little.
But if you wander the show floor, you will find it. You'll be able to check out the game for yourself.
And hey, maybe you'll decide to pick it up and play it.
With that, Matthew, I think we ask this question every time we wrap up, but just in case, where
can they find you if they have more questions about Eliza?
You can find me on Twitter at Matthew Seiji, Matthew S-E-I-J-I, and my website is also
MatthewSeiji.com, and you can go there and see my other work, my short stories, and you
can contact me either way.
His profile picture is of a wonderful cat.
It's your cat, right?
Yes, yeah. My Twitter profile is a picture of my cat.
You get really nervous when you're live, like saying things that are definitive,
because you feel like you're going to be held accountable for that later,
and that must be really onerous as a guest.
But let me tell you, as I'm trying to host these things,
making definitive statements just feels like,
oh, is someone going to come back and sue me?
I don't know why I'm Scottish all of a sudden.
I don't know why.
They're going to sue you for saying that their profile was their cat?
They're going to go, excuse me, that was not my cat, it was my friend's cat.
Oh, I see.
He got a little bit of a last year.
Oh, I see, I see.
It's my cat.
I don't know if that's just a normal hosting problem or if that's just my own anxiety,
but you know what I won't do if I have anxiety?
I'm not going to use the therapy app for myself.
Alright, that's wandering into territory I should say for Off's channel.
But, have a good day everyone.
Bye!
Bye.