Hello, everybody.
Welcome to the most boring talk here at GDC.
You've all made a mistake coming here.
But seriously, thank you for coming.
There's a lot of good talks going on right now, so thank
you for choosing this one.
So what is this presentation about?
It's about Atreus, a companion AI in God of War.
For those who don't know,
God of War is a third-person action melee game
with light RPG elements.
And this talk will focus mostly
on the combat aspects of Atreus,
go over the hows and whys,
and take you through the journey of creating Atreus.
So before we start, who am I?
My name is Hayato.
I'm a senior combat tech designer.
I've been working at Santa Monica Studios for over eight years.
And these are the titles I've worked on in the past.
And before I start, let me tell you how I ended up
working on Atreus.
It's a little bit of story time.
So one day, I was tasked to implement and design
Atreus from scratch.
I was like, what?
Why?
I have no desire or experience making companion AI.
So since I wanted to keep my job,
I went on the internet and searched
how to make good companion AI.
I know.
Yeah.
I like...
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Please.
Oh, God.
I like to copy and paste a lot of code, so that's my workflow usually.
So anyways, what I found was, I saw a talk by Max Dyckhoff.
He did a talk about Ellie in The Last of Us, and he said he treated Ellie like his own
child.
So I was like, okay, if that's what it takes to make a good companion AI, so be it.
So next day, I got a picture frame of Atreus.
Yeah, yeah.
But the problem here is that I don't want kids, or even have kids.
I'm like, what am I doing with my life right now?
So fortunately, though, I treated Trace like a friend that plays games with you,
a friend that knows what you're going to do and vice versa.
You can just play games, and you know what you're going to do,
and he knows what, or they know what you're going to do.
So it was like some kind of teamwork.
And that change in perception ultimately influenced some of the decision made
when building on Trace.
So, enough about me.
Who is Atreus?
He's the son of Kratos, a small child,
born in a harsh Norse mythological setting,
uses a bow primarily, and has no formal training.
And this clip I'm going to show you
is just showcasing what Atreus does in combat.
Ah!
Uh!
Don't get up!
Yeah, he's like dodging attacks, attacking stuff.
I'm not gonna go into too much detail right now, bye.
He's doing a mixture of both autonomous behaviors and directed actions.
And the main thing here is that you don't even know, if you look at this and you don't
know what the game is all about or whatever, but you can see Atreus helping you like a
teammate and you're like, yeah, he looks pretty useful I guess.
That's what we were going for.
So as long as you get that, that's all that matters.
Yeah, and that's it.
Unfortunately, it wasn't always like that.
And this is how it all started.
So like any respectable designer, I guess,
I started with core pillars.
The first pillar being supporting the player.
Kratos is the main actor in the game,
so Atreus needed to be supporting Kratos.
Second pillar is he should not hinder the player.
He should never get in the way of the player.
That's just a big no-no.
Third thing is, if he ever does something,
it should always be helpful.
It should never make the player feel bad
whenever it's a performance in action.
And lastly, and maybe most importantly,
you should not have to babysit him.
And if any of the last three points actually just goes bad,
the game will immediately feel like a bad escort mission,
and we tried really hard not breaking any of these rules.
So, these core pillars are pretty good,
but the real question is, who are we supporting, right?
We're supporting Kratos, a one-man army.
He's killed titans, gods, he's went to hell and back,
killed more gods, and then he killed a lot of guys.
And nobody was saying, oh, you know what?
You know what Kravis needs?
A child to fight with him in battle.
I'm a genius, right?
Nobody was saying that, maybe except for one director.
But that, yeah.
So the real question is, how do we support a literal god of war,
a child?
How is he going to support him?
So it's all about the framing, like how
do we approach this problem?
You know, when you look at movies like Marvel, you know,
the Marvel movies, you see Thor,
he's just destroying enemies left and right,
kind of like Kratos, right?
And then you see guys like Hawkeye,
maybe not as, you know, impressive as Thor,
but he's doing work.
But the main thing here is that they're working as a cohesive unit.
They're a team, right?
And then whenever they work as a team, they can finish their goal quicker.
And this framing was a good step in approaching Atreus' role.
So knowing this framing, what were the next steps?
To prototype.
Prototype a bunch of things.
And we drew a lot of inspiration from a lot of single-player games with good companion AIs.
And also we looked at multiplayer games where your teammates will help you out.
So cooperative and also team-based games.
So looking at all these archetypes, we're like, what's the first thing we want to try out?
So we tried Atreus being an initiator.
An initiator is a character who will start a team fight
and will give you or give their teammates a huge advantage
when the fight starts, or usually.
And that's what we did.
So in the next clip I'm going to show you,
Atreus does exactly that.
Find your angle, boy.
Yes, sir.
So he does a couple of things.
First, this first clip, he's gonna just
hail down some arrows.
Maybe that's too much, but that's what he did.
Other things, removing enemy weapons, kind of useful, not bad.
Or even rooting enemies using the tree, that's kind of useful, I guess.
And then, you know, summoning crows.
I wonder where we got that inspiration from, you know?
Like, well, yeah.
So all these look good on paper, but there were
two main issues with this.
Number one, the players exhibited a play pattern
that we did not want to promote.
The players were kind of like sneaking around
in the battlefield.
They were like, oh, what can Atreus use?
And it almost felt like a stealth game,
and that's not something we want to promote.
So already, that was a big problem.
Number two was when players actually use Atreus,
it was really mindless because you would just say,
oh, just interact with that, and then you're done.
So the first point I made, you know,
making the game feel like a stealth game,
that was a problem, so we didn't address that.
But we were like, okay, if he's kind of mindless to use,
what if he was more involved in combat, you know?
What if he...
you know, what if we can change his behavior
to be offensive or defensive?
So in the next clip I'm going to show you,
the first half, Atreus is kind of offensive.
He's going to be, you know,
distracting guys in front of you.
In the latter half, he's going to be
helping you out when you get hit.
And sorry for a debug, I'm so sorry, I'm so sorry.
Yeah, so right here, he's gonna distract the guy on the right,
he's gonna shoot him.
Oh!
Ah!
Don't let them buy it!
And then he's gonna distract the guy kinda in the outskirts.
And he does this every interval,
so he kinda keeps a healthy,
like he's cycling through all the enemies,
who he thinks is the best target
to kinda throw their attention away.
This was kinda useful, it was interesting.
Next thing we tried is, this is a defensive move.
You see here, Kratos got hit,
and Atreus will try to help you.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's interesting, yeah.
So note that Atreus is going behind the player.
He can only help out when he's actually behind you.
You know, this action is kind of helpful, I guess.
You can do all these interesting things.
But, there was a couple of problems with this, too.
You had too much control over Atreus.
Like in the heat of the battle,
people didn't even try to like change his behavior.
Like, oh, I'm attacking this guy.
I have no time to think about
what the behavior of Atreus should be.
So that's problem number one.
Number two was during this time,
enemies were dying like three hits, you know.
We were fighting humanoid, like human bandits.
So as a god, you should be able to kill them relatively easily
so they were dying in three hits.
So Atreus couldn't even shine in this kind of environment.
But the silver lining was, when he was actually
distracting enemies in front of him,
it was actually pretty useful.
So I'll talk about that a little bit later.
But first, I want to point out that around this time,
we actually took Atreus and we split him
into two core traits.
One defining his autonomous behavior,
and the other defining his directed actions.
Directed actions is when the player tells Atreus what to do.
So when we actually split these apart,
it was actually easier to work in isolation,
and that was the right call.
So back to what I was saying,
where when he was distracting enemies on his own,
like autonomously, that was really useful.
So I want to kind of dig deeper into this autonomous behavior.
So the next thing we tried was, okay, you know,
what if he actually behaved like a real player?
When you're playing like an FPS game,
your teammates will hopefully try to like,
handle a threat from the other side of the map
and you'll handle another side of the fight or map.
You're kind of essentially splitting up the battlefield
and Atreus did exactly that.
So in the next video I'm going to show you,
Atreus is dividing the field in his own way.
Sorry for debug again, but all the circles around the enemy, that's who Atreus is focusing on.
And in this RTS-esque camera, you can see what's happening.
Great. Atreus is kind of, you know, dividing the battlefield. Great.
And in, you know, this view, in the actual game view, if you're just looking at Atreus passively,
like, yeah, you can see a couple of enemies going after Atreus.
I guess that's kind of helpful.
But...
You know, people don't play a game like this.
They play like this.
They translate a lot, move the camera like crazy,
change their focus, you know,
and you briefly maybe see a trace,
like what is he doing there?
I have no idea, what was he doing?
Who knows?
I'm just gonna go back to fighting this troll,
I mean ogre.
So that was a huge issue.
And honestly, at this point, I was like,
oh man, I suck.
I should probably update my resume.
I'm gonna, you know, like honestly.
But, you know, there was key nuggets of goodness
when I was doing all these things.
So I was like, you know what?
I'm gonna do a little deep dive
and kind of list out all the core issues
that I'm seeing right now.
And yeah, when I actually did that,
I actually identified three issues.
First one being presence.
People didn't even see where he was.
Number two was perceived impact.
Even if he did something,
you don't know what the impact that is for combat.
Number three was weak enemies.
Not necessarily Atreus' problem,
but it was adding to a problem.
So, let's address these three issues.
Presence.
This is a reality.
Can any of you guys see where Atreus is?
I'll give you guys a second, I guess.
Yeah, nobody, right? Probably. Yeah, because he's not in the picture.
I'm just kidding, he's actually right there.
He's laying on the ground like that. And this was a reality.
Even if he's on screen, you can't even see him.
And the fact that we can't have, you know, the camera cuts and stuff, so, you know, we had to adapt to that.
And, you know, that exasperated the issue.
But, there were three things that actually helped his presence.
Now, first thing was, make him use a bow as a melee weapon.
Number two is dynamic poses.
Number three is changing his position behavior.
So first thing, him using a bow as a melee weapon,
completely un-intuit, why would an archer use
a bow as a melee weapon?
Well it turns out, when archers are shooting,
they're doing this still pose, right?
And so when you're scanning the battlefield,
you'll see, oh yeah, Atreus has that pose,
but the arrow went somewhere,
I can't make the connection who he shot.
But the moment he uses a bow as a melee weapon,
he's using a more fluid animation,
and then he's next to an enemy,
so you can make the, you can add one and one together.
just by scanning the battlefield,
and that helped his presence immensely.
You saw a lot more interesting things
happening in the battlefield.
And number two was, my favorite, dynamic poses.
And people, you guys might be thinking,
duh, why didn't you guys do that at the beginning?
Do you even design, bro?
Like, I know, you guys might be thinking that,
but there's a thing called us wanting to be grounded.
The game was grounded at the beginning.
We couldn't do these jumping moves and stuff like that,
but.
we had a great tonal shift,
and that restriction kind of came off a bit,
so we were able to have a trace jump up in the air.
We essentially kind of dialed up the anime knob
by like 30%, we're like, all right,
this is the right amount.
So you can see this pose in combat.
You can see here, he's like occupying like the second half
or just the top of the screen, that's fantastic.
There's a lot more noise and you see what's happening.
When he's trying to stab enemies,
he'll kind of arc his back and kind of hold his pose.
It's fantastic.
And even his profile, he would actually go sideways.
And when you actually see a small child
become sideways in battle,
you actually notice that really immediately.
And when he's grabbing enemies,
he would tower over enemies.
He's a small child, so he's trying to look
bigger than who he is.
So he would hold that pose, grab enemies.
And it worked out pretty well.
And again, when he's doing melee attacks,
he's putting his entire weight into it.
And when he does that kind of motion,
you really notice it.
So even if you're doing all these interesting combos
or whatnot, you notice Atreus kind of coming in with you,
and it's fantastic.
And my favorite pose of all is this one.
Him kind of kneeling down-ish to do like a dash attack.
And whenever he did that,
you knew he was gonna go into position
like as fast as possible.
And speaking of position, that's my next topic.
Intuitive does not mean it's going to be interesting.
So initially we wanted Treyus to be safe.
He's a small boy after all,
and he's using the bow as a ranged weapon,
so he's kind of moving away from threats.
We even gave him a strafe set
so he can actually change his position really quickly.
But what ended up happening was he looked really erratic
because he was trying to find a safe spot.
And not only that, since he's evading all the enemies,
nothing interesting will happen on its own.
He's just carefully avoiding enemies.
So we were like, OK, let's make it slightly more interesting.
Let's make him stand his ground a bit.
Let enemies actually bump into him and see what can happen.
So when that happens, we decided that if Atreus swings his bow
or does some offensive action that
leads to some kind of positive outcome, it felt great.
Now, with this, when we tell Atreus to go somewhere,
he's gonna actually stand his ground,
and with that, we're like,
well, what's the best place to put him?
And it's behind the player's target.
You know, when the player's focusing on the enemy,
like, he has a field of view,
and right behind the enemy is also somewhere
where players can actually notice him.
So, when we actually moved,
or tried to position Atreus behind the enemy target,
or the player's target,
that's where the magic happened, actually.
His movement actually now had intentionality.
He was moving there for a purpose,
the purpose being double team the target
you're fighting against.
And when he did that, it didn't look contrived.
He came on screen with a reason.
When he was actually dividing the battlefield earlier,
like when he actually came on screen,
you're like, what is he doing?
He's just charging into battle.
I have no idea what he's doing.
So when he did this, it was fantastic.
And like proper teammates.
when they go into position to set up an alley-oop or a bump-set spike.
In Atreus' case, it's just being a crap out of your target.
They all had a good reason to move to a position.
So that's fantastic.
So this is a small clip of Atreus posting up to the player's target.
I gave myself a 3-4 second rule where it takes around that time for Atreus to come up on
screen and try to post up next to your target.
Yeah. So all this was possible because of my favorite tool in game development.
Warping.
Thanks, John.
I am not above using warping.
I use it everywhere.
Like the moment I can warp, I just do it.
Like I even have a script that allows me to like,
you know, just copy-paste something, you know,
the warp will just happen.
And the main thing was, you know,
I want to make sure Atreus was a reliable teammate,
not a realistic teammate.
And that was the most important aspect I focused on
because whenever Atreus needs to come in
and help the hero,
I want to make sure it happens at a timely manner.
So the logic of teleporting is pretty straightforward.
If he wants to go to a target, he takes the edge of the
fresnum of the camera, and then he picks a point closest to
the target.
I'm kind of overly simplifying it, but that's how he
teleports when he's off screen.
And I'm going to show you a video clip of him just
teleporting everywhere.
And he just popped in there and just, yeah, he's going to
attack that guy.
And obviously when he teleports, you usually cannot, I mean, you can, but most of them
you cannot see him teleporting.
And what's funny about this teleporting behavior is that he's actually a lot more reliable
when he's off screen, because he's teleporting constantly.
If he's actually far away, he needs to run towards your target.
So that was an interesting thing.
So, with all this fantastic teleporting,
all these things we did,
we felt that his presence was actually improving.
And we're like, okay, let's focus on the other things now.
So, perceived impact.
When he was actually dividing a battlefield,
people might have seen it, but they're like,
what am I gonna do after this?
After he divided a field, what am I supposed to do?
They didn't know what to do.
Atreus focusing on the macro aspects of the battlefield,
we were like, what if he actually focuses
on the micro aspects of the battlefield?
What I mean by that is he's going to be now,
oops, sorry, focusing on the player's target.
So whenever the player does something to the target,
Atreus will be extremely reactive.
He's constantly looking at what the player is doing.
So, knowing that, what kind of actions did Atreus take?
These are some of them.
So if you launch an enemy, Atreus will keep him juggled.
And if you ground an enemy, trip an enemy, he'll keep him grounded.
If you kick an enemy into a wall, Atreus will keep him pinned to the wall.
If you're hitting an enemy, Atreus will just grab him so he can't move.
and if the enemy is just constantly blocking your attacks,
you'll just break his block by tripping him.
And these are just a couple of them, there's a lot more.
The main thing here was that he extends
the enemy's vulnerable state and allows players
to attack the enemy and kill the enemy quickly.
And every time Atreus did this, this was when the intentionality of the player and Atreus
kind of aligned.
The player just wanted to kill the guy quicker, and then Atreus just helped him out.
So when he did that, Atreus felt like a better teammate as a whole.
So, perceived impact, people are now feeling his impact,
and they're like, all right, he's kind of useful now.
But the weak enemies, not Atreus' problem,
but we resolved it by increasing
the health of enemies, obviously.
But if the enemy actually gets stronger,
it doesn't mean Atreus should do more damage
so he helps the player out.
The main thing he should be focusing on
is creating more shortcuts for players to dispatch the enemy.
This was really important because you don't want Atreus to take the spotlight of the player.
So the next video I'm going to show you, I'll show you a clip of a player killing a Draugr
without Atreus's help.
In the latter half, he's going to kill Draugrs with the help of Atreus.
So all this is taking about 14 seconds, which is pretty bad, I guess.
But if you use Atreus, he gives you shortcuts,
you can kill them pretty quickly.
The main thing here is, not only does he provide shortcuts,
he actually provides you other options in combat as well.
So if he's grabbing an enemy and you decide to launch him,
Atreus will kind of slam the enemy down
and create a huge concussion.
That was how he actually helped the player.
Even though the enemy got beefier,
Atreus constantly provided these shortcuts,
so it was actually fantastic.
And while we were working on these mechanics,
there were some key findings that weren't very obvious.
Timing is everything.
Not every time is a good time to follow up.
So if the player is aiming with his axe on a reticle and Atreus happens to knock the
guy away, that's terrible.
So you have to be mindful when he can attack.
Other times, when the player is actually wailing on a guy, it's okay for Atreus to actually
come in and help you out.
And the key thing here is that, you know, the best, actually the best time for Atreus
to help the player is when the player actually does like a really strong move or whatever
where there is a long recovery time because during the recovery time usually the players
can't like move and stuff like that.
And that small beat, that window, they can actually register what Atreus is doing so
when Atreus is jumping off the player's back, that's when people really notice.
And so just because you found a great time to attack,
doesn't mean the actions are going to be helpful.
Not all support actions are useful actions.
If the attacks are extremely disruptive,
we have to be mindful when we're gonna do it.
For example, if players are knocking enemies off the ledge
and stuff like that, and Atreus happens to kind of
interrupt it by hitting them out of the air,
that's disruptive, that's really bad.
And also, conversely, like if, not conversely,
if the player is causing a stumble reaction on the enemy,
and Atreus comes in and just causes a basic reaction,
he effectively negated the recovery time of the enemy.
So, he needs to.
we need to respect their reaction hierarchy of the game.
This is a really simplified reaction hierarchy.
There's a lot more reactions, but I just simplified it.
But that's the idea.
And the main thing here is that we
have to predict the player's intentions, essentially.
So if the player is doing some kind of actions,
make sure whatever Atreus does is
going to enhance what the player wants to do.
And that's kind of how we design his attacks.
And this is kind of seeing everything in action.
This is kind of early, but this is when I was like,
all right, maybe I get to keep my job.
Maybe I'm doing something smart.
He's actually doing, helping you out autonomously.
Yeah, I mean, there was more tuning that needed to happen,
but this had all elements of Atreus kind of helping you out.
This is just purely autonomous.
You're not telling Atreus to do anything.
So, this all looked good, and we were like, okay, maybe the playtesters can now play with
Atreus.
But, it looked good, but...
It was only helpful when players were actually offensive.
Remember I said Atreus is going to be reactive to your actions?
So it turns out when players are low on health,
they start to become very defensive.
And since you're defensive, Atreus
can't do anything after that.
So we're like, OK, we need to come up
with a couple of helpful behaviors
to allow players to become more offensive.
So some of the helpful behaviors were.
Calling out threats, especially attacks for coming out of offscreen,
you can't look behind you, so it was a perfect way for Trace to call them out.
Another thing is he sometimes protects you from offscreen attacks.
Most people didn't notice this, but it actually happens quite often.
Other thing is reviving the player.
This is not really a behavior per se, but it's another resource mechanic
that allows players to become more offensive when they're kind of low on health.
And finally, my favorite, detecting danger.
Thank you, Sam.
So there's this danger meter where
Atreus is just detecting if the player's in danger or not.
And if this meter hits a certain threshold,
Atreus does a spread shot and pulls enemies away.
So here's a video of that.
So he's going to do right about now,
and he just pulls a bunch of enemies towards him,
and you can just only fight one enemy.
And the danger meter was based off
of the number of enemies around the player, his health,
and also the types of actions Kratos was doing.
Like if he's blocking or defending or dodging,
that meter went up.
And the moment you actually perform an offensive action,
the meter actually just reset
and just continue on your merry way.
And honestly, this thing wasn't to promote defensive play style.
We were just making sure that there's some brief moments where
players can actually take on the offense when they're in trouble.
And this extended the intense fights a lot longer, which was good.
So with all the autonomous behavior kind of in place,
you know, it was pretty much done and we were at a good place.
So now I want to talk about the directed actions.
So the directed actions, a.k.a. the sun button.
We always wanted a dedicated sun button,
and we examined these on-demand actions, actually.
And before we actually dove into those ideas,
we had to ensure a couple of things.
Number one, they have to be reliable.
And when I say reliable, it doesn't mean it needs
to like destroy the enemy.
What I mean by reliable is, if you press that button,
whatever action Trace is gonna do, it needs to happen.
What if, you know, Trace like jumping up in the air
or whatever, we have to author all the actions
in a way where it can be interrupted.
And that also meant that his update loop
can't be round robin because all the actions
will be delayed.
Other thing is, it shouldn't disrupt the player.
You know, when Atreus is gonna perform an action,
he can come from all sides of the battlefield,
so you don't know where he's gonna be shooting at.
So whatever he does, it should not cause
any grief to the player.
And if Atreus does something, you have to make sure
that players will know what's gonna happen to the enemy.
The player is actually, sorry.
The players are actually operating on a moment-to-moment basis,
so if something random happens, it's going to throw off their game.
And lastly, the actions need to be super helpful.
If you use the action and it causes some harm to the player or whatever,
nobody will be interested in using it.
So knowing all these, we're like, OK, these are pretty solid.
Let's try making ice arrows, focused on crowd control.
So when this went int, I was like, alright, this is pretty good.
What can go wrong?
Ice arrows.
You know, he's slowing down enemies.
Nobody's slowing down enemies right now.
But obviously, as you guys may know, you know, Kratos has a Leviathan Axe.
It used to be the Blood Axe, but it turned into the Leviathan Axe, so the moment I put
in the ice arrow, I had to just remove it because I was competing with the Leviathan
Axe.
Yeah.
figuring out what Kratos is going to do was first and foremost the most important thing,
so I had to concede.
So the next thing I did was, alright, maybe crowd control isn't the right answer.
What if we just try out damage?
Let's just try it out.
And that's exactly what we did.
His arrows actually did damage.
He can use his knife to regenerate his arrows.
We also added some kind of risk factor to see if it's interesting to use it.
And this video is Atreus just using his knife as a melee weapon.
And it's not showing his arrows being regenerated,
but the arrows and the knife kind of operate the same way.
You shoot or you stab somebody, and then something will happen.
So you see right there, he actually killed the guy on the ground there.
And then when he does an action, he just knocked the guy on the right.
But then he killed the guy on the left.
So we're like, what? What's going on?
So the issue at hand were, you know, the results were very random looking, you know.
If the enemy had like, you know, full HP and then you use a Trace, he'll probably knock
him down.
But if the enemy's low on health and you use a Trace, he'll immediately kill him.
So it looked very random.
Second of all, when you're actually trying to use Atreus,
that risk layer we added was just not engaging at all.
When you're fighting multiple enemies
and your focus is constantly changing,
if you happen to press the sun button
and he actually gets knocked down or something like that,
you no longer want to use the sun.
So that risk layer was already a bad idea.
And lastly, there was no synergy.
These two systems, like the regenerating of the arrows
and killing enemies and the hero actually doing damage,
they kind of live separately on their own.
So they weren't even talking to each other.
So that was all bad.
So the first two points of it being looking random
and the risk layer being bad,
we're like, okay, we can't do anything with that,
but let's remove that.
But let's try to focus on maybe promoting
some kind of teamwork with this mechanic.
So we came up with a tagging mechanic
where you shoot an arrow at an enemy,
they get tagged, and then you could detonate it
using your shield.
And to do that, you have to press L2 twice, or L1 twice,
to actually detonate the charge.
And when you detonate it, the enemies actually fly back.
It's no longer going to do a lot of damage.
It causes a really good reaction.
So it looks good, but the mechanic
was hidden behind the L1 button.
And most people didn't even engage in it.
So we're like, OK, so what if any hit causes this explosion?
Let it detonate, right?
Well, if you do that, like in this clip right now,
he throws the axe and the enemy gets thrown back.
That's really disruptive.
You know, if you tag an enemy
and you wanna launch an enemy in the air,
you know, what's gonna happen?
Is he gonna go up in the air
or if he's gonna fly back, who knows?
Like now we're like destroying the hierarchy
of the reaction, it's just all bad news.
Plus, this also discouraged me from using Atreus
when comboing enemies.
So if I'm like hitting guys
and I wanna keep arrows being pelted on the enemy,
the next hit's gonna send him flying.
So this was a terrible idea.
So it was really back to a drawing board.
And honestly, at this point, I was like,
I don't know what I'm doing.
I'm just gonna just keep the thing how it is
and let the system kind of stew for a bit.
And we just kind of waited it out and see what happened.
And key things happened that made me want to work
on the directed actions.
And they are, player mechanics were finalized.
The player didn't change as much.
There were a lot more constants to work with.
So it was a lot easier to frame how to support Kratos.
Second, UI came on board about one year before ship.
So finally saw health, we finally saw status meters.
Our creators can now feed into those meters,
which was great.
and we got the stun system on board.
This was like the best thing ever
because now Atreus can apply stun
and allow players to just rip enemies in half.
He wasn't really competing with Kratos
because the stun system just allows players
to live Kratos' power fantasy.
So just because Atreus can apply more stun was okay.
And finally, while we were working on autonomous behaviors,
we found out that distracting enemies
wasn't really...
It was really helpful.
So, you know, I got all the ideas
and just kind of like mashed it together
and I kind of created the Runic Arrows.
So the first reason why you want to use Runic Arrows
is because it applies stun and it pulls enemies aggro away,
which was very helpful.
The secondary reason is to apply damage and also apply status effects.
So if you want to shock enemies and hold them in place, you would do that.
And the more nuanced reason why you would want to use it is so that you can extend your
combo.
So if you launch an enemy, you can kind of keep shooting at them, extending them, the
combo and whatever.
And also, when you actually did that,
the enemy's backside will be turned
because remember how Trace will now be behind your target?
If you actually pull the enemy's attention,
their backside will be turned against you.
So now, hitting them in their back
was very, very beneficial.
So these mechanics were actually very good,
and then we had to also make sure
that using this was really intuitive.
So when you actually pulled aim using the L2,
the arrows needed to hit the reticle.
We ensure that it goes through environments,
make sure that the arrows actually hit the reticle.
And if you aren't using the reticle,
we just guess who we think the best target is.
Some targets have higher priority
because enemies like the revenants or the nightmares,
most people tend to use the arrows to defeat them,
so we prioritize them higher.
And this was good, but balancing these arrows
was actually a big issue.
People didn't realize that you can actually
be performing an action, and Atreus can also
be performing an action together with you.
So you can be attacking, just mash your square button,
and Atreus can also attack.
Even when you're getting hit, you can also mash that button.
It'd interrupt the enemy.
And not only that, these arrows would constantly
interrupt enemies.
And top it off, Corey, our director,
wanted to spam Trader's Arrows as fast as possible.
So that just exasperated the issue.
So how we dealt with that?
We limited the rate of fire of the arrows
and limited the ammo count, which is pretty easy, I guess.
But the other thing I also did was
I actually slowed down the rate of fire
like one frame every week without it getting noticed.
Yeah, yeah, I know, I know.
I'm a jerk, what can I say?
Yeah, and Corey would ask me,
did you slow down the rate of fire?
I'll just chalk it up to a bad frame rate,
who knows, like I can't tell.
So he probably knew, but whatever.
But the main thing was that,
you know, it was about adding
these key invulnerabilities to enemies.
So if the enemy is about to do
like a really, you know, signature attack,
we made sure that can't be interrupted.
Otherwise, we would just
completely trivialize the enemies.
and my favorite thing, the runic summons.
And just like Kratos, Trades can perform
these special runic attacks.
And this was actually added probably towards
the end of alpha and beginning of beta
when we were feature complete.
So me and a couple of people that didn't care
about job security, we were like,
all right, let's just check this in
because it's really cool.
And it turned out pretty good.
It actually fit into
Tracer's fantasy, summoning animals, talking to animals, and it was great.
It was a production problem after that.
So putting it all together, the main thing is player commands, the square button, it
needs to just interrupt everything.
That is the main thing we have to keep in mind.
Number two is making sure his autonomous behavior, like when you trip an enemy or you launch
an enemy, he can follow up reliably.
That makes him feel like a good teammate.
And lastly, this behavior where he's actually just doing
something on his own, like bumping into enemies.
He will apply, you know, he'll swing his bow,
apply some stun, he'll cause some happy accidents.
Those were actually important because every fight
will now no longer feel like the same.
So that was actually very useful.
And I wanted to just kind of dive a little bit
into some of the additional systems
Atreus kind of dealt with.
So death.
no death. We wanted to follow the core pillars of Atreus. We didn't want to babysit Atreus
so we made sure he can't die. And if you were a bad parent, I mean if you were a bad player,
you might just leave Atreus on the ground. You're like, okay, I don't care. I don't care
if he's incapacitated. That was okay. If you didn't want to help Atreus, that was fine.
So we were okay with that.
Second thing was player customization.
Early concept, people wanted to teach Atreus
through actions, like, oh, I'm gonna teach my boy
not to attack, or be, whatever, right?
That was a really bad concept, but we just made sure
that you're allowed to customize Atreus
through gear and skill tree.
So if you wanted Atreus to become a heal bot,
or if you wanted to be a nice sharpshooter,
or he's good at applying stun,
you can all do that through gear.
And the skill tree, we, or I worked backwards on that.
So after Trace was done, I just took what was cool
about Trace and just shoved it into the skill tree.
I'm like, ah, this looks kind of good.
That was how I worked.
And honestly,
The resources used to upgrade the skill tree and the gear, I made sure that there's an
aspect of sacrificing your own improvement for your child, you know?
So your resources, you have to sacrifice to see your child grow up, you know?
It's like a reoccurring theme in parenthood or something.
I don't know.
That's...
That's what I heard.
So we actually put that in.
And then the last thing is, you know,
these behavior nodes that were really strong,
so all the autonomous behavior he did,
we made it so that it's easy unlocked.
So the moment you spend a little bit of points
or some points into a trace, you saw a massive gain.
And we have to make sure that the moment, you know,
you invest in a trace, you feel like it was worth it.
So there are a couple of key takeaways here.
Number one, Atreus is really like an AI mechanic,
and we had to make sure that using him
was really easy to perform.
You just mash the square button, and he does the shots.
And also, for people that are advanced,
I talked about earlier where you can combo your attacks in,
stuff like that, we had to make sure
that was actually in there.
But the true skill is teamwork.
If you actually pay attention to Atreus,
you know, Atreus is always paying attention
to your actions, but if you actually pay attention
to Atreus, what he's doing, and you become
a better teammate for Atreus,
that's when the true teamwork happens.
So, if Atreus is running towards an enemy,
and you know he's gonna trip him,
you can land a cleave with the greatest of ease.
You're like, oh, that was so easy.
When both you and Atreus kind of play off of each other,
that's when.
the true teamwork shines, and that's when I get to cry
because it's so beautiful.
And the main thing is the intentionality
of both players are aligned.
And this was interesting, narrative.
So this was kind of hard for me to do something
because at the beginning of the game,
Atreus can't be this crazy killer, right?
He needs to be kind of a little bit weaker.
So all of his autonomous behaviors were kind of,
it was kind of stopped.
So the only useful thing about Trace
was using the square button.
So at the risk of making a trace feel kind of weak
and kind of useless, we have to do that to fit narratively.
And towards the end of the game,
we have to make sure that Trace kind of just becomes a jerk
and he doesn't follow your directions anymore.
So if you press square button, he doesn't do it.
It feels like a really bad companion AI.
But narratively, it all made sense.
And this was a really big takeaway for me.
I like to go on YouTube and watch reaction videos
of things happening, because I'm like that.
And then I would see people fight the last fight
with the stranger.
And you would see Atreus do all these crazy things.
He's doing these backflips.
He's shooting arrows in the air.
And he's summoning snakes and stuff like that.
And people were like, yes, that's
my boy doing all that stuff.
And the people were actually proud of Atreus.
You know?
So like, all the investments they made, it culminated into this cinematic moment where
they're like, oh yeah, that's so cool, I invested so much into him, he's doing all these things.
And when people saw...
when people saw the growth narratively
and in actual gameplay.
And when Atreus did all those things in the cinematic,
people weren't like, oh, what is he doing?
Why is he doing that?
People were actually like, yes, he's doing that
because I taught him to do all those things.
And when he did that, the game actually felt
more cohesive, and it was really good.
And obviously, we were reimagining the game,
combat changed frequently, so we have to be pretty agile.
Old ideas became relevant really often, and vice versa.
And we had to make sure that all the scripts and all the
ideas were very modular.
You can actually copy and paste and just remove all
these ideas so that you can actually
iterate a lot quicker.
And final thing, combating doubt,
the pretty much the final boss of every game development,
I think.
It's getting the right people to believe in your systems
really, really crucial.
Because during development, a lot of people
ask me, so when is Atreus going to be cut?
Ha, ha, ha.
I'm like, oh, that's really funny.
And that's like a constant, constant thing
I have to deal with.
And I even had some people in higher positions say,
oh, if Atreus gets kind of cut, here's the exit plan
and stuff like that.
I'm like, okay, thanks.
So much confidence in me, thanks.
But honestly, rallying the right people to garner support
is the most important thing.
Because when you do that, people start to stay late with me
and play tests and give me feedback.
They will create assets for me to prove out an idea.
And this is true for all game systems, obviously.
But when there's so much doubt in the future,
having these key people to help you out
was really, really helpful.
So doing all that, how well did Atreus do?
IGN said, yeah, Atreus's impact cannot be understated.
He's both an asset to the story and in battle, thanks.
GQ was like, yeah, my biggest takeaway
from the New God Award is that a developer
has finally cracked how an AI companion
can be the best part of a video game.
It only took 20 odd years to do it.
Thanks GQ, thanks.
But my, oh no, stop, no, no, no, no, no, wait, wait.
No, that's not the punchline, no.
Now, the best quote is from Rice, Bean, and Cheese from a Reddit thread.
And he says, the boy is one of the better AI companions in video games.
Thanks, Rice, Bean, and Cheese.
And really, this was a team effort.
Everything from cinematics and behaviors outside of combat
helped realize who Atreus is.
And, you know, that was it.
So thank you. That's it.
Thank you for coming to this talk.
No, no, please.
Ah, yeah, yeah.
Thank you, thank you, thank you.
Sorry, yeah, yeah, sorry.
Sorry, there's a little bit more, sorry.
The slides are terrible, I'm sorry.
So tomorrow, you can check out Mihir's talk about evolving God of War combat.
If you want to take a closer look at what we did in combat, go check that out.
And now I will distract you guys with this video as I take a Q&A session,
so no questions will be asked.
All right.
Please.
I can't see him.
No one's going to ask me a question?
Sweet.
These are all prototype videos.
Yes.
So you mentioned that Atreus responds to what hit reaction you cause on an opponent.
I was just wondering under the hood if Atreus looks at which attack the player uses or if
it looks at the targeted opponent, which state they're in.
Sorry, sorry.
Can you repeat that again?
So I was curious, you mentioned that Atreus looks at, behaves differently based on which hit reaction the targeted opponent's using.
Yes.
I was wondering if it looks at which attack the player's currently using, and whether or not it hit, or if it takes a look at the opponent's state.
Right, so the question is, when Atreus decides to attack, does Atreus look at the enemy's state or what the player's doing?
We actually look at the enemy's state, because depending on what the player does...
His power level and whatever could be completely different.
So calculating that we couldn't do.
So we based it off of the reactions.
So if an enemy were to play a reaction
that might be, you know, we don't want to disrupt it,
Atreus will still perform an attack,
but it wouldn't cause any reaction.
So we would preserve that reaction.
Oh, okay, okay, thanks.
Yeah.
Hey, you mentioned a few times how important it was for you guys to have that feeling that whenever you press square something happens and your companion is doing things.
How did you deal with all the aspects where it was impossible for the gameplay reasons?
So either he was out of ammo or he was visibly occluded towards the target so he couldn't take a shot.
Did you have situations like that and how did you feedback that to the player that he knows that something is going on but it's wrong?
Right, so the question is, we wanted to retain the square button to be very reactive, but
sometimes it's not reactive because Atreus is in trouble and stuff like that.
How do we deal with that?
Yeah, that's a very good question.
So when he can't shoot the arrows, there were actually very limited reasons why he couldn't.
Number one is if he's actually incapacitated, that was actually the player's fault for making
that happen, so we were okay with the arrows not responding to that.
With the arrows, him actually running out of arrows, he just says,
I'm out of arrows constantly. Maybe it's not the best way, but he just vocally tells you that he's out of arrows.
Yeah, aside from that it wasn't really...
Yeah, I think that's about it actually.
So you didn't run into trouble of him not seeing the target that you're pressing the square if?
Because I can easily imagine him being behind a tree visibly and being able to reach the target that you're trying to attack.
Yeah, so the question is, you know, what if Atreus can't physically shoot at the target?
We just allowed it.
Yeah, we just made sure the arrows actually goes through everything and hits the target.
Makes total sense.
Yep.
I can't see, I'm so sorry.
That's fine.
So thank you again for doing this.
And I just had a quick question that I obviously know game
development is a very fluid process.
But you mentioned a couple of times that you sort of started
out knowing that you wanted Atreus in the game.
And you mentioned a couple of times of people joking about
taking him out or things like that.
But that would have affected both the
storyline and the combat.
So sort of, it sort of.
Maybe this is the wrong question, but what was,
how did Atreus fit into the initial vision of the game,
and how much, can you tell us how much
it sort of evolved over time?
Well, I'm here to talk about the combat aspects.
You can talk to Corey about that, but yeah,
I mean, from the onset of the game,
we always wanted Atreus to kind of grow with his father
and kind of help you in a fight,
so there was always an aspect of that.
But like you said, oh sorry, the question was,
What was the vision of Atreus?
And we were always talking about cutting Atreus,
so how do we deal with that?
Yeah, so the vision, we always want Atreus
to kind of grow with you and stuff,
so that was always there, but the combat aspect,
we were like, okay, maybe it's okay
to actually remove the combat aspect
and let Atreus kind of be like a set narrative piece
to fulfill the father and son relationship.
So we had a backup plan, which I never wanted to do,
but we had backup plans, yeah.
Thank you.
Guess me. Uh, hey, so when you were dealing with the warping of
The child around did you ever have to worry about the time it took for him to warp?
Like oh, I saw him really far to my right
I'm gonna fight enemy left and then he just all sudden appeared instantly and you wanted did more to take like yeah
I think or two instead of instant. Yeah. So the question is do we care about the realism of teleporting from far away to close?
Yeah, I didn't care
Like I was like, I'm just gonna, I'm teleporting immediately.
Because first and foremost,
if a trace becomes really unreliable,
you kind of don't want to use a trace as much.
So make sure the reliability is key
and realism is kind of just down there.
Okay.
Yeah.
Thanks.
Hello, yeah, so thank you for the chat, it was pretty good.
So I was wondering, how was the,
how did you use a scripting language
or something to do all this, or?
Yes, the question is, do we use a scripting language?
Interesting enough, we actually got a real scripting
language, Lua, probably, hmm, maybe a year and a half
into development, yeah.
So before that, we didn't have anything like that.
Cool.
Thanks. Yeah.
Hi. My question's about how in a lot of the cinematic moments,
particularly near the end, the camera plays over and swaps
between Kratos and Atreus as they're swapping through,
particularly fighting the stranger on,
I can't pronounce it, the big snake at the end.
But were there thoughts as it was developing through combat
of having the camera emphasize Atreus' actions and kind
of moving over the shoulder with him?
Or was it always locked behind in this third-person perspective?
Well speaking of camera, I mean here we'll talk all about camera stuff, but
you know, if you're actually playing the game and the camera just takes over
like without kind of like you knowing, it's very disruptive as well. So
yeah, we never, I mean we entertained the idea early on but we were like, no this is
terrible idea, we don't want to, you know, focus on what Atreus is doing during combat because
you know, if we did that, you know, player can be hit out of it and stuff like that. So there's a
lot of issues with that, so we didn't go with it. Okay, thank you. Yep.
Hi, my question is I'm curious about the design process
of individual resolution.
Since I've noticed that most of your design pillars,
core pillars are more like constraints,
like no death and no babysitting.
So how do you find a idea to start a prototype
and play test?
Right, so the question was, how do we prototype things when the core pillars seem like more
like restrictions?
I mean, there are like guidelines of how we want...
So honestly, when we're prototyping, we had restrictions of, you know, Atreus can't do
these crazy things, right?
But the main thing was, when we're prototyping, we wanted to make sure Atreus is a good teammate.
And as long as he's a good teammate and follows core pillars, we were okay with any type of
prototype.
So that was kind of like the basis of how we went with...
you know, all the testing and stuff.
So I'm not sure if that answers your question.
Is the picture still on your desk?
Yes.
I don't even have a picture of my wife.
Yeah.
I suck.
All right, so how do you make sure that Atreus is helpful
at the beginning of the game before you get all the upgrades
versus towards the end?
Yeah, so the question is, how do we make sure Trace is useful at the beginning of the game
without getting all the upgrades?
So you know how at the hierarchy I listed initially about him, the commanded actions
being very useful?
We just did that.
So even as a base level, if you just spam square, there's a level of use that's actually
helpful.
So he applied stuns, you can now grab the enemy, pulls the enemy away.
So yeah.
you know, we just pretty much banked on that mechanic and it worked out pretty well.
Hi, so this video reminds me of one thing which used to be talked about among Chinese players.
Do you know the game actually among our players have another name as the god of war and his old father?
So the reason why is when, for as a player,
when they play the game, they will feel,
okay, so archers will die and they can,
and he can cause high damage.
So my question is, have you considered about
keep the, to balance the damage caused
between the critters and the archers?
So you're saying, sorry, the question is,
how we considered balance and damage
based off of what, sorry?
Yeah, so the balance, the damage caused
between these two characters.
Oh yeah, so the question is how do we balance the damage of induced characters?
Yeah, Atreus actually doesn't do much damage.
His arrows actually do very little damage.
The only time he actually does damage is if you actually gear him to actually do that.
Atreus never should have taken away the player's spotlight, the power fantasy.
We just ensure that Atreus will always support the player in killing the enemy quicker.
So that was it.
Oh, yeah. So in the boss fighting, so when I was playing the boss fight with Valkyries,
and I will keep pressing the sound button until the boss died, to maximize the damage of that.
So what you see is just to limit the sounds, limit the actual damage into the lower than the
creatures, right?
Yeah, so I guess the question is, do we lower the damage of Atreus' damage?
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean, yeah.
Atreus, like, you know, even if you upgrade him a lot, he'll never surpass Kratos' damage.
That's like the rule we set.
So, you know, when we're balancing these things and you're fighting these Valkyries, we're
like, okay, Atreus can do, you know, maybe six shots within this kind of time frame and
we know what his damage per second is, and we kind of balance his health and the toughness
and stuff like that.
So that's kind of like the process we took.
So...
I don't know if that answers your question.
I'm sorry.
All right.
I guess that's it.
Thank you all for coming.