It's an honor to have everyone here to listen to us.
And you guys are here for the nine takeaways from Duelist, from tabletop to digital game.
And we want to share a lot of our experiences from prototyping it all the way to all the
obstacles and challenges that we personally faced, Eric and I.
on developing this game from a tabletop prototype all the way to a digital game on Steam.
So just to kick things off, have any of you guys played Duelist?
Okay, wow.
And how many people here have a tabletop prototype that they're planning to convert or to start
to port over to digital?
Okay, great.
So I'm going to just start off with a little bit of background
about ourselves.
Eric can start off.
I'm Eric, I'm the lead game designer of Duelist and I'm primarily from the tabletop space.
I've designed board games and card games for the last 15 to 17 years.
I'm mostly known for living card games, for Fantasy Flight, I did a little work for Wizards
of the Coast on Magic and Duel Masters.
Most people know me for big box board games by this point, games like Blood Rage and XCOM.
Chaos in the Old World. I'm a huge fan of both magic and games like Fire Emblem
and Final Fantasy Tactics which makes our meeting very serendipitous because
it was really exciting to work on the game.
And I'm Keith Lee, I'm the CEO and Creative Director of Counterplay Games.
I was the former lead producer of Diablo 3 at Blizzard Entertainment,
and also the former lead game programmer for the Ratchet & Clank series at Insomniac Games.
But more importantly, what's Duelists?
So you guys already know a little bit about Duelists,
but for those who haven't heard about it or played it,
it's essentially a collectible tactics game.
And it's a way for you to assemble a small army
or deck of cards that are actually playable on a nine by five.
grid and it's online. You play 1v1 head-to-head and it has turn-based battles on there.
Currently we're only on the PC, Mac and it's playable also on the web and we have about 250,000 matches that are played per day.
The inspiration for this game is the fact that we love Final Fantasy Tactics, we're
huge fans of Fire Emblem, but those are primarily single player experiences where they gate
you at a boss or a certain level cap before you can progress.
And our curiosity and the question that we wanted to ask was...
can we build a competitive tactics style game but still be able to make it in a very short,
to play a match in a very short reasonable time.
So our goal was to build a game that lasted 10 minutes per session or less and to still
keep the breadth of being able to still make it relatively competitive, to have a lot of
archetypes and options from aggressive to control or mid-range.
And we...
felt that using a CCG sort of model for us worked really well because it's very
hard to build a competitive game if every character that you have have sort
of different power levels or things like that so those are really great way for
us to combine CCG elements that people are familiar with but to also have
positioning and to introduce like a lot of new concepts around that.
And so this game itself is a 9x5 grid.
There's a bunch of minions that you can play on the board.
There's also artifacts and spells
that create effects on your units,
and the object of the game is for you to defeat
the enemy general.
And we kept the winning objective
and the condition really simple.
Doesn't require a lot of math or calculations
and things like that.
And essentially, you have a hand at the bottom,
which we call an action bar,
and you can also replace a unit every single turn.
And these are some of the cards that you can collect.
And we have 400 plus different minions
that you can play on the battlefield,
each with their own animations and things like that.
The game's actually been out also.
The game's been out for a year in past open beta.
And we're working on our third expansion right now,
which will release soon.
So how did we get started, more importantly?
This was basically what Duelists looked
like when we first started.
And we would be testing and prototyping our units.
And we wanted to be able to iterate
on visualization of the board state,
as well as how we can prototype as quickly as possible.
And we had a lot of iterations.
And one of the important things is that we tested not only
with people who love tabletop games,
but people who only play digital games.
And we also played with folks that are in the industry
and also people that are outside of it.
So in the bottom left, these are some folks from Riot Games,
Paul Sadasanti and Steven Lim.
And these guys are guys from Riot
that play a lot of tabletop.
And then there's other folks that have never played tabletop
and only played games on Steam.
Now, we wanted to also have a very cheap DIY way
to be able to prototype.
So for the game that we wanted to build,
it was relatively simple.
We just bought a Chess X vinyl mat
that you just get off of Amazon for probably less than $30.
And the nice thing about those is they have a hex side
as well as a...
square tiles. So depending on the type of game you want to make, it's really easy to prototype.
We just get a bunch of polyhedral dice and typically if you already know what type of attack
ranges that you're going to have or hit points or HP that you're going to have for your units,
we did like a 20 D20 dice for the hit points as a tracker and a counter
and then we did like a D8 for like attack or anything that you want to do for defense and things like that.
We then also started to print out all the effects and spells and cards that we're going to have in the game.
And then we cut them up every day when we iterated and put them into card sleeve protectors
so that we can always put it on top of the square for the type of effects and buffs that are occurring for your units.
And then we love to get like Pathfinder miniatures because they have a lot of unique heroes.
There's a, you can actually add a little bit of flavor into the prototype if it's a flying unit or a knight
and to kind of create a little bit of a sense or if you have a unique hero, then at least they would sort of stand out.
But then of course just to keep things relatively cheap.
We also got like a bag of like generic fantasy miniatures that are like a bunch
of knights and things like that.
So they're viewed as like the pawns of like chess
and you can just get them really cheaply.
So there's a lot of repetition here.
So there's a really important design point also why I want to prototype
like this as simply and stripped down like this is that there's a bit
of a misconception in tabletop and digital that just
because.
You're designing a digital game because in the digital space you can make the game really,
really complicated and have a lot of hidden information.
We found that isn't true.
We wanted the game, we wanted to make sure that the game is comprehensive even on tabletops,
that people can really, really quickly grok what the board state is without having to
rely on figuring out what is going on in the back end of the game because a lot of players
assume that that's cheating.
Yeah, and a little side tip too, we like to do a 2x6 on the square tiles because they actually fit the cards that you want to place easily.
So if you're moving your characters and units, it's easy for people to remember what tile they're on for your cards and it's really simple.
The other important point too is that...
Although we have a lot of different types of players, you can actually have a pretty
small sample size to be able to test your prototype.
And the key thing is just making sure you can observe what they're doing and not trying
to bias the opinions for how they're playing.
just getting a sense of what areas that they might be confused around,
or they might be doing a certain strategy that you've never considered.
And we usually just have a logbook, so every single time we play,
we just track what units they've been using and how they've won.
And we don't really spend too much time on asking them if they have fun or not,
because if for them, if they start to look a little distracted
and they're starting to lose interest,
we know that it's not capturing them anyway.
And that's usually like our first sort of gut test for how things are going.
Absolutely and also the because one of the keys to a digital game is how
smoothly it plays. One of the reasons we gave ourselves limitations of this
medium is of course we knew that we could we could fake a lot of the we
figure a lot of the user input in on the digital side. We want to make sure that
even if we get this prototype playing fairly smoothly and fairly easily that
putting the extra polish on the digital side would be absolutely top-notch.
Mm-hmm.
Now, before just even starting with tabletop and moving
to digital, we took a step back and started
to think about what the strengths are of digital.
And I would say 20% of the time before we even
started implementation, because it's really easy to roll up
your sleeves, get excited to start to code a couple things,
and try a couple ideas on digital,
because it's still a really fast prototype.
But we took a step back and we said, hey, what are the strengths on the tabletop side and the weaknesses?
And what are the areas on digital that we know that we need to bolster and to continue to support that's very different from tabletop?
So the biggest salient thing on the tabletop side, of course, is that you have a very, very custom, highly social experience with friends.
And it's very easy to have games where you have secondary expressions and ways that you can bluff and to read signals because people are interacting you face to face.
And of course the challenge and the weaknesses of tabletop is the fact that it does take time to schedule. You usually need to have a champion or a leader to kind of organize things.
generally is a larger time commitment to make sure that things work out for that week.
Now you don't have any of those problems on the strengths of digital.
You can play randos anytime, anywhere, players across the world.
So that's a huge strength from our perspective.
But it's also a subtle weakness as well because
you lack that level of personal interaction with the players that you're the people that you're
playing with and of course it hides a lot of massive number crunching on the digital side so
there's for the type of game that we built on tabletop we knew that it's going to work even
better on digital because we have lots of interactions and secondary effects that all
interact with all of the keywords that we have that
Actually, if we had now ported it back to tabletop, it would actually be very hard to have this exact duos game
Because there's so much number crunching that actually occurs on the board state, especially introducing movement and things like that
now on the digital side the area that we wanted to focus on and to bolster is
we knew that there was going to be a lack of deeper person-to-person interaction
and there's this sort of mindset that you're looking at a screen
you have the web that you can get onto, there's movies, there's like more distractions for you
as you are on digital. So as a result
anything that you can do where the player is
ultra engaged, never has this feeling that
they have to wait.
is utmost critical important versus being on a tabletop,
you know, night situation.
Right, and also a key corollary to that is that
in digital you lose the social contract of the table, right?
So, I mean, we've all played digital games.
We know what the difference in politeness
between a tabletop game and in digital.
So we had to make sure when we were designing the game
to make...
In a tabletop game, you're not going to rope out every turn.
You're not going to make people, you're not going to grieve people for no reason.
You're going to play efficiently and there's a lot of unsaid communication between players,
you know, when to end the turn, etc.
In this, we had to design the game around that to make sure,
around the worst possible type of griefing player
and every possible way to make the experience bad for their opponent,
we had to assume that the player would.
So I would say that this is a very common graph for anyone that's going to move anything
from tabletop to digital and something just for you to consider.
But then it opens up another question.
Is a tabletop player similar and what's the overlap to a digital persona?
Does a player that loved tabletop, will they even play Duelist if it's on digital?
So that's a hypothesis, that was a big question.
We didn't know that.
So we had to just make a couple assumptions
and to kind of test out our hypotheses.
So our initial first most important assumption
is people don't want to play 40 minute games
and then lose and feel bad on digital.
So we wanted to ensure that our play sessions
were less than 10 minutes.
And then the other difference is that the velocity and the frequency and the volume of games that you're going to play on digital is astronomically exponentially higher than playing a tabletop game where you might just have one game that night.
And most of the variety may not even come from the board or the game itself, but from the interactions that you have that night with the players that are playing with you.
So, from that perspective, we had to make sure that we increased the priority around
creating match variety in every single game.
So, the goal is that for every new match, you might encounter a different general, or
you might have a, you might encounter a different deck, or a different set of minions when you
play against other players, so that things don't feel as samey.
And this is, of course, the number one challenge for building a game like ours, is to avoid,
how to make the people who grind through 50 games a day.
to still have them enjoy themselves and for the folks who might only play a few games in a day.
And again, the hypothesis for us is that we had to make sure that you're playing with anonymous players
and how we can alleviate any of the negatives around that.
So on the data side, we also track.
Peter Drucker has always said that what's
measured is improved.
And so we took that hypothesis, and then we started to test it
out on the web first.
So we actually didn't push out our game on the PC at first.
We wrote our entire engine in JavaScript, and then kind of
put it out on the web.
And the main reason why, and why people always ask us this
question, is like, why did you guys do that?
It's because it's very easy for us to deploy a new build,
to change the balance of things, to push it out.
And it's very easy for a user, a new player,
to get into the game without going through a lot of hoops
and to log in and do all these type of things.
And we started a track.
very early on what the average playtime was for the players,
what the actual match times were.
And so when we started to tune our cards,
when we started to tune all of our systems,
our number one goal was to make sure
that the match time didn't increase over 10 minutes.
And so originally it started at around 15.
That's right, yeah.
So once again, we haven't even started talking about the
takeaways yet, but just really wanted to set the design
pillars that we had started with at the prototype stage.
Again, to enforce a match time, upper
bound to 10 minutes.
And that's already, we feel, at the highest for the type of
game that we have, especially if you want to potentially
move your game onto mobile as well.
And then number two, we wanted to offer a wide variety of deck archetypes.
And then third, we wanted to find ways that we can build player confidence in the game
and also to allow them to see that they're improving in terms of their skill level.
And then lastly, we also started to predict and started to think about how we also wanted
to build our ranked player distribution.
So early on, we knew that it wasn't going to be a Gaussian normal distribution bell
curve.
We instead knew that we wanted to skew the curve towards time served and the amount of
time that you were playing and skew it slightly towards like a lower level.
So this is actually the results of where our ladder stands in the last few months.
And you'll notice that the distribution of these five different divisions,
and just to give you guys a little background if you guys haven't played Ranked,
is that every month it resets, and as you continue to play,
you will progress up the ladder if you win,
but at the lower levels you just have to play to be able to go up.
And then we actually have a floor on every single division.
So what this does is alleviate sort of laddering stress.
because once you hit a certain division you can start to experiment a bit
and play around with different decks that you do
try out without losing rank. So this is the distribution we share this with our
community because a lot of times people think,
hey I'm not doing well in this game because I'm not
silver or or gold or
or even Diamond or S-Rank, but being able to show this to the community also helps people
realize that it's not just about being in bronze because a lot of people spend literally hundreds
of hours playing our game and playing like 100 matches a day to get to S-Rank.
All right, so we're going to start with the first takeaway
that we learned with Dualist.
And the first one that is different from tabletop is we
focused a lot on real-time interactivity.
So what we mean by that is.
Everything that we did in the game, when it's your opponent's turn,
everything from mouse movements to what they hover over, to what they're looking at,
to them dragging a card to display what they're doing, is all done in real time.
So we have a real-time system to track everything and you can actually see what your opponent is
doing. So that way you still have this feeling that you're playing against a real human opponent,
that they're looking at things and doing stuff, rather than, you know, waiting for like...
a minute or 90 seconds and there's like nothing happening on the screen and
you're just off to get a coffee or something. So we want people to still feel like
they're engaged
on the opposite end's turn. And on a deeper level actually,
this is one of the, I'm a hardcore CCG player and
one of the things I wanted to make sure that we did here was that...
In tabletop games, you can read cues,
especially when you're bluffing any game
with hidden information like we have.
You can read cues from players from body language,
watching what they're looking at,
and you can also double bluff people
by giving off false tells.
In this game, if you're high level
and you're familiar with the cards,
you can actually watch what people,
you can watch what people are looking at,
you can watch how long it takes somebody
to play a card at a particular time,
you can watch what they're,
what they're pointing out, what they're not, to see and start to formulate some
hypothesis. And it gives you, it's inches, gives you a tiny little incremental
advantage, but that's important in games like this where you're improving tiny
tiny percentages at a time.
So the high level idea for anything outside of even the real time inactivity to some reason just to think about ways that you can gauge your player when they're not actively doing something in the game and they're just like waiting or pausing so here's actually a video just to show you of the enemy's turn here so on the left side would be me let's say and your opponent now is actually hovering looking over some units hot looking at
at these two units that you have and they're going to deploy things.
So this is all done in real time, a real time system in the back end
to better track this and to track all your mouse movements and everything like that.
And he's animated right now, which means he's in the middle of,
he was clicking on a card in his hand and looking at and thinking about playing it.
Yeah, and of course, this is an example also of,
besides just doing mouse interactions,
you can also do emotes and other like soft ways
to communicate with each other,
so that you feel that there is another person
that you're playing with,
but still in a kind of controlled way.
So just to kind of dig a little deeper, we also offer a restricted level of player-to-player interaction.
So as you've seen, emotes.
And the cool thing is that once you start playing a lot of Duelist, it becomes like an expressive language.
There's like a language in itself for how people start to communicate with each other in the game
based on the dozens and dozens of emotes that we sort of have.
and that's like kind of a cool language that people start to learn.
We have a buddy list where if you add and mutually agree to add with each other
you can now start to chat
and we also have replay sharing within the buddy list.
So I can actually share a replay that I've just done to show off
like a really cool lethal that I did.
And we also, outside of the game itself, we have on our main menu a watch section.
So the idea here is that if you're not playing a game, you can actually go into any division ladder
and start to see some of the more interesting, popular games.
And we have an algorithm for pushing out kind of unique sort of a...
games that are happening, you can watch on any side and then you can sort of see what people
are doing. So this is a fun way for players to just relax, kind of watch what people are doing,
learn some new strategies, or kind of see like what other people are doing in a very safe kind
of environment, especially if people are just starting to learn to ladder and jump into the
game. And of course we also have a spectate mode, so you can hop into any sort of a Twitch featured
person that we have.
And one of the things that we did, we actually integrated Twitch into our PC game.
So we highlight Twitch streamers that are playing Duelist and it's a benefit for them
because they get players that are just hopping in and we also let them to jump right into
Twitch and watch it.
And of course you can actually spectate your friends and this is actually really important
anyway.
because it's a requirement if you plan to do competitive tournaments
and to be able to have a spectating sort of system
so that tournament organizers can start to display
different sides and things like that.
So this is a real-time interactivity.
These are some of the emotes.
We spent a long time on these, by the way.
I think we must have spent at least a week in just design
to figure out, because we didn't have infinite emotes.
And I remember the key discussion we had.
We wanted to make sure that the language was 100% emergent.
So we wanted to pick some of the most common expressions
that people would use that didn't necessarily
point to an exact word or an exact adjective.
and allow people to use them individually or in strings in succession to communicate with each other.
And the meaning behind it, like, as you...
It created a really cool secondary talking point across the Internet,
across our forums and Reddit and stuff. It was pretty cool.
I am still on takeaway number one.
So, the other thing, too, is...
It's really important is, again, people are impatient,
people don't want to wait.
So anything you can do to shorten the matchmaking queue
times, ultimately if you can do it in less than 20 seconds,
especially on the lower ranks, is pretty critical.
So I played a lot of Warcraft III.
Shows kind of like my age on this,
but tons of Warcraft III and you have the Roving Eye.
and you have like a sort of a timer that displays like how long you've been waiting,
those all help because anything where it looks like the screen just froze
and you don't have anything to show will concern people.
So we always have like a timer that displays and there's some level of interaction.
People really, like you know that you're in a matchmaking queue
and we really try to make sure that we can get below 20 seconds.
And sometimes that means that early on.
when you're first like pushing out your game on digital you may not have a lot
of players jumping in right away and so it's it's very like all your fans
again I always ask to add like all these different modes that they want and we
all want to do that that's like the things that we love doing we want to
have rainbow mode we want to have casual and all these other things but to have
that you need to have.
literally 200,000, 300,000 matches happening a day before you can even get close to hitting
like a less than 20 second interval time. So for us we started very simply with a ranked ladder
and then also we had a draft mode which we called the gauntlet. So we didn't release casual mode at
the start.
And I can talk a little bit more about casual later and only now for the next
expansion that's coming in a few weeks are we adding this rainbow mode system
where you can actually mix and match every single card from every faction for
the first time so that's going to be a lot of fun for people we hope those you
guys who play it's going to it's even more fun than you think it is.
So, starting with take away number two.
So, one thing we learned is that you're really only as good as your matchmaking systems.
So, on a high level, how we kind of built our algorithm was we thought of a bunch of different metrics that we wanted to track.
and then we put a weighted parameter
on each of these metrics.
And then later on, once we did that,
we reduced it into a normalized range
and created a rating score.
And then that way, it was very easy for us to compare
in real time how to match make different people.
So some of the metrics that we used
or the most salient ones is rank radius.
So what we mean by that is we would start out
matching people that are both rank 24, let's say.
And if that didn't coincide,
then we would actually expand the radius on that.
So you would start to match someone that's 23 and 24,
and we would start to expand that out.
And that would actually have its own metric
that would get normalized into a weighted system.
We also have a time serve.
So what we mean by that is that we look at
every player's profile, and we look at how much time
they've actually invested into Duelist.
And we also track as a proxy, it's a high correlation.
We also look at their win counts.
and how well they've sort of performed internally.
And then we give priority to people who've been waiting
for longer amount of time.
So then we start to actually expand that,
put a higher weight on this, and that's the Q wait time.
So we feel like people have been waiting
for more than 20 seconds.
We'll actually give in and.
make sure that they can jump onto a game, even if it's not the ideal match.
And the number one thing that we wanted to avoid at all costs,
and people have different opinions on this, so other people are totally fine not putting this into the system,
but for us, we felt that it never felt good to be able to fight another,
to play the same player again on the next matchmaking, when you're matched,
because...
the loser is going to feel super frustrated, because
they're going to ask, why am I getting matched up with the
same guy that just beat me?
So I think that we view as a bad thing.
And then more recently, we started to think about, once
you get to over 200,000 to 300,000 matches a day, you can
start to do this thing called cohort-based matchmaking.
So what we can now do is take.
a tranche of players that came in in a certain season as a cohort and then match them all
together.
So what this helps us do is it actually is a way to alleviate, it actually solves all
of these sort of problems because it's almost like everyone's in the same generation or
wave or class and they're all starting to learn and kind of grow their decks and it
solves a lot of the kind of issues for us.
So a core base thing is something new that we started to implement that has worked nicely
for us.
It's also a really good problem also with the we're talking about with the
deck size and collection right one of the invisible issues with a lot of
matchmaking games is especially with people with asymmetric
power levels is the new player power doesn't necessarily equal
rarity in this game but it can feel like that to some players somebody doesn't
want to come up against somebody at the same rank that has like 50
legendary cards in their deck so this helps
almost by itself alleviate that
Now, again, Peter Drucker said, what gets measured
gets improved.
So specifically around matchmaking, we also built a
system where we actually graded ourselves at any moment
in time as a snapshot throughout the day.
And we had a rating system based on those parameters.
A 1.0 perfect, 0.75, 0.5, and 0 would be, for example, the
same player played twice in a row.
And the important thing with this metric is that we did
a system for every single division. So you need to have a granular enough matchmaking system
to be able to track your performance across every division because in some cases
your bronze matchmaking might be at close to 1.0 but then something's happening on silver and gold
and those matches aren't really working. So here's an example. So we actually have a real-time
graph that all of us have on the screen.
at our office to be able to track matchmaking quality.
So at any moment in time during the day, we can see.
how things are performing, if things are above,
at what division these numbers are hitting a good number.
So if it's over 0.5, I think we're relatively happy.
And the nice thing with this too is that
if we put in a balance change or we tune something,
we can already, or we change like how our algorithm does
stuff for the matchmaking, this helps a lot.
This doesn't ever explain why.
your matchmaking is going down, but at least it's a good early indicator
that something is wrong and that you can actually think about how to solve it.
So we don't have this.
You're just guessing at that point if matchmaking is good,
because hearing stuff from the community is always helpful.
But at the same time, you're going to get so much noise
coming in from the community.
People always complain that your matchmaking sucks.
So you need to have your own system to be able to at least have a way to measure.
that yourself and internally understand how you can improve that.
Sometimes people actually wonder when we're doing balance changes and tweaks,
why we'll address a particular issue that wasn't necessarily called out by the community.
It's usually because we have, this is one of our starting points,
and if it does hurt matchmaking at some level,
we've considered that as important as any other balance metric.
So the third takeaway that we thought about was realizing how
can we extract fun and progression for people that
are still losing matches.
So no matter what, it's a zero-sum game.
Someone's going to lose.
And we offer the most fun for people that
continue to lose matches.
One of the differences with tabletop is you can walk away
finishing that night, ending a session.
And even if you lose, you still had some fun in some way
because you're interacting with your friends.
You had some sort of social capital.
So what we did on the quest side is to think about how we
can offer play quests that you can complete and get.
rewards for that, and also win-based quests.
So there's a delicate balance, because again,
if you only do play-style quests
to accomplish your quest in the game,
you're gonna have a lot of people starting to concede
in your matches for PvP,
and so you'll have to always develop a system for penalties
and an algorithm for detecting when a player is conceding.
And that's one of the things that you have to...
twist a lot and change a lot because you can't ever let anyone know
how you're detecting that people are conceding.
One week we might track how many turns that they're playing before they start to exit.
So we always change how we detect the conceding algorithm.
And it's a lot of work, but if you do want to avoid
the exploit of players constantly conceding,
that's something that has to get built,
and a lot of people don't think about that.
And it's just one factor to think about
as you develop your game for digital
that isn't something that's common on tabletop.
And then faction progression.
So the idea for us is for every faction,
we don't just give you a big starter bundle
with like 30 to 50 cards,
and you get overwhelmed with like.
how to even start. So we always have a couple marquee cards so that you continue to play
your faction, you start to get introduced to new cards and we make them really clear
with a single ability, very few words on the card text and typically it's very obvious
to the player that this card has a win condition, that this is something I can use to start
playing and to win.
So that's, from our perspective, what we kind of built.
And this progression allows people to feel that they're learning the game,
that they can sort of win in the lower ranks, that they can play well on practice,
and also have this feeling of getting more cool new cards
and getting excited about how they can change different cards
and start to develop and master their deck or their faction.
And what we also do, too, is that if you start to lose a lot of games,
we actually have achievements and things like that where...
at certain specific points of play behavior,
we'll give you orbs because we want to make sure that
the people who aren't succeeding in the game can still have ways for them to
find, get new cards and still feel like they can progress
even if they're losing a certain number of games. So that's a really
good way to kind of bolster
that format. Just to be clear for those who don't play, orbs are the
packs that contain new cards.
I remember we tuned that a couple times, and how many games it would take
to lose to get to pick one up. Yeah, because again, people will concede and try to get those orbs
and that's a natural thing, but that's okay. That's a natural thing, so
it's a balance on what you're going to do.
So here are just some examples where we front load a lot of the rewards for players that may not be winning or they're not grinding 50 games a day.
So we'll have win a practice game which is relatively easy because you're playing against an AI.
So that's a win condition game.
But then we have a welcome back quest where people feel like they can still play a few games and get some gold.
early on and kind of warm up if they haven't played Duelist in a while.
We also have a first win of the day to motivate people to just keep playing
until they can win their first game and to build that sort of confidence and
still front load some gold. And then we also still have like you
know typical play quests.
I was just going to talk about that for a real quick sec.
There was a real delicate balance between how we chose
what quests were win quests and what quests were play quests.
For the most part, we wanted people,
when you log into the game, especially if you're
a new player, you log in.
And this is inviting.
This tells you, oh, you just need to play x number of games.
The first one of the day was actually hidden.
We didn't show that.
We showed in anywhere on the hud but of course the first time you win a game
you're like oh I win first one of the day which does motivate you to win. We
didn't only want players to just fit to make it feel like a Facebook game you
just log in and play we want them to feel driven to win so you can you will
get something even if you lose over and over again but the first time
you win you'll feel you will get that you'll get that adrenaline rush and get
your cool packs.
Yeah and you can talk a little bit more about in match stuff to write so that we're talking about before the extracting fun from losses was in the other was in the the the metagame right in the game itself.
We want to make sure it does is this very it's a high skill game that ties the higher skill than some of our competitors are but.
which is daunting, right?
Sometimes people are going to lose by not know why.
So we put a lot of subtle elements to the design,
which is taken from my trading card game background.
So in a match, we put, we built the game around milestones.
So even though there's one clear winner, one clear loser,
we wanted to make sure that there were.
There were things that people could accomplish inside a match, whether or not they won or lost.
So most of the game, for those of you who play, of course, many of the cards are very combo-oriented.
They're simple, but there's some clear synergies in cards, and there's some subtle synergies in other cards.
The game is highly consistent, so if you're playing the Vitruvian faction,
you want to build the deck that lets you build lots of obelisks and generate tons of little guys,
you might lose, but at least you've got the cool feeling of having built that board state.
the and learning moments of course the game is relatively high skill and highly
interactive there a lot of the positioning on the board means the
cards have different value based on where they are in relation to your
opponents pieces so even if you you the take away you'll get from a game very
often is the very clear like off I only a plates only play by minion behind my
general instead of in front of the general I actually would have won
because you would have been able to talk by X.
So that was, none of these are explicitly out there,
but people do get, they will get the feeling,
they will learn quickly from game to game.
We also push really hard for being able to have replays very early on in our game cycle.
So as a player, you can just hop into your profile and look at an entire history of the last set of games that you've played.
And you can start to watch and kind of see like what you potentially did and observe how you've performed and see if there's potentially like a few mistakes that you had made and how.
For example, you might have lost lethal or things like that.
So I feel that it's a evergreen learning platform
to have replays in the game.
And although it took a lot of time for us to build,
because you want to fast forward and scrub
and do a lot of different things like that,
it's worthwhile because people will go back into the game
and be able to learn from their mistakes, which.
For a game like ours, it's challenging because sometimes you just don't know why you lost.
And that's the hardest part of trying to explain things in our game is
you may not know because something you could have done might have been even like two turns before.
So this is like a thing to kind of alleviate that too.
So, takeaway number four is to...
We focus on a lot of systems, too,
that can encourage positive behavior.
So we had this idea of player gifting.
So, of course, that's more standard
with a lot of other games.
But we really wanted to make sure
that the rewards that you're giving to your friend...
was pretty significant and very high.
And you can still rate limit that.
So if that's an issue, you can always rate limit it in some way,
but you really feel like the recipient is getting a really good reward from that.
And I think that's really important.
And also we had a kind of an interesting system that we haven't seen in other games really,
where the winners can also tip.
their opponent after the game.
And the idea for us of doing that was we felt that let's try to distribute
gold and currency as far across the ecosystem
and people actually really like tipping.
and kind of as a way to kind of help another person that may not have some of the cards or things like that.
We also had a top 50 tipping leaderboard so that people had an alternative vector to progress in the game
just by tipping some of their other opponents rather than trying to gruel through necessary like S rank and things like that.
And then we would display that on Twitter or like our Facebook and things like that.
And we also send them custom physical rewards that are unique.
from in-game rewards, so we actually mail them.
to some of the winners and things like that as a cool little prize.
It was actually, besides the tipping leaderboard being super cool,
it was also important that we made sure that we never made any explicit reason for tipping.
It was entirely up to the players why you would tip,
so that they would make their decisions based on social norms rather than anything else,
rather than something they would try to exploit.
That's very important. It actually dates back, that's a tabletop style mechanic.
If any of you guys...
played old games, workshop games back in the day,
Warhammer and stuff, they had a sportsmanship award
that was awarded by the group,
by the players of the tournament,
to the player who made the game most fun for their opponent.
So from a design and systems perspective,
when we're building Duelist, it's
really easy to start to look at achievement systems, and then
faction progression systems, and the first time user experience,
and think about, OK, we're starting
to see an issue with how our players' behavior is operating.
So let's try to add this quest in here to fix things,
and stuff like that.
And that's going to be.
a problem because you're going to start to have these kitchen sink sort of systems that
don't really solve anything at all and they're trying to plug like little holes that are
starting to appear.
And then the problem later too is that some of your later designers or people that started
to join your team have no understanding like why you built this particular system and what
problem it was even trying to solve in the first place.
So for all of the system that we develop.
we very clearly delineate what the goal of that particular system is trying to achieve on the game design side.
And if it does not fit that goal for anything we want to plug in,
we decide whether to remove a system or to develop another system that accomplishes that goal,
rather than trying to mix too much stuff into a single system.
So for example, achievements were very different from...
other systems like quests because the purpose of achievements was to give you a ding and like an
achievement at a very specific point that we're tracking to reinforce a particular play pattern.
So for example if you're losing a lot in a row we actually give you
a particular reward the first time you ever disenchant a card.
You get an achievement and also it gives you enough spirit to be able to then craft a new card.
So we're reinforcing that you can now actually build something from something you disenchanted
rather than just getting all the spirit and not knowing what to do with it.
The first time user experience, the FTUE, we made sure that we didn't really focus too much on the meta systems and how those work, but the goal of the first time user experience was just to focus on the in-match gameplay and the sort of dynamics of how you're playing day to day, like in practice.
And then faction progression, again, is to solve the issue that we want to do around starter bundles and packs
and how we can slowly teach the player new concepts in a way that we felt like was the best possible path for them to learn a faction as quickly as possible.
Because, again...
Like an LCG model, other things that do work on tabletop,
it's not a necessity for doing something on digital.
And I think a lot of our community folks say,
hey, why don't you do a LCG thing?
Well, we don't really have to do that.
I think that's actually a...
almost a result of like the practicality of having to print stuff on tabletop.
From our perspective, giving someone a starter bundle is challenging because we don't know how
to value that, the players don't know how to value a starter bundle yet, they're super overwhelmed.
So being able to actually show new cards in a nice sort of progressive way has worked better for us,
even though I think most people do want to do starter bundles.
I think that's a very common decision.
So it's just something to consider.
I think every game is different, but that's the sort of philosophy and the thinking that we took.
Absolutely. When we were doing design and tech work very closely together, when we were working on systems design, one of the litmus tests we would always give ourselves is we would run a simulation of first-time user experience, like virtually write it down on paper or figure it out on the graph.
plug that system in and make sure that it is as seamless as possible for the first-time user.
It's one of the biggest traps of feature-based design like this is it is really easy to lose sight of what the first-time user experience is.
Once all of us have our own accounts, it is time-consuming to keep starting new accounts and run through that experience again.
But we have to keep cognizant of it because these games live or die by acquisition.
OK, I'm going to zoom through a little bit faster.
So even besides doing some of the stuff around systems, like
our progression vector, even around our goals for how we
design cards, I had the same idea.
It had to fit one goal.
So everything from our goal for text was avoid hyper
literal text.
So we started out as the premise.
And we said, hey, we just got to lower our word card count
because our stuff's getting way too wordy.
and we try to aim for like a budget of 30 characters per line, a hard max of like four lines,
single card abilities, especially early on, and just kind of move discoverables into a different area
so people can kind of start to discover cards.
So here's like an example of...
a very typical day-to-day card for the original idea for the Kera,
which is a general Bloodborne spell.
And we started with whenever you summon a minion from anywhere this turn,
give it plus one, plus one.
It's very technical, it's very accurate,
it also represents how tokens work in the game.
But now you have to spend all this time to read it,
and most people won't really know the difference.
And the bottom version is cut almost in half,
and it's just generally more clear.
and accomplishes 80% of the objective of what we wanted to say.
I know, some players do complain that our text isn't as precise enough,
but aggregate complexity is a real thing.
You can never judge a card in a vacuum,
you have to judge it as part of a six-card hand.
So every time you add a word onto a card,
you have to multiply that by six, theoretically,
and that aggregate complexity can turn off new players so fast that...
Like again, kills are actually-
We still challenge with this all the time.
Oh yeah.
It's a very tough one.
So for takeaway number six, again, not everyone
can catch up to hardcore players.
They may spend more time playing the game.
Some people just are better with positioning.
They might have a better collection through time.
And originally, we offered a discrete number of wins.
And you get certain like, why gold?
But again, this makes people stronger, richer, and it makes,
you can create, like, essentially a death spiral,
where the bottom 10% of your community just quits
just because they don't think they're good at the game,
or they're losing a lot, and then now the next 10th,
10th percentile will leave, and then all you get
are these super hardcore, high-skill, super elite players
that can play, like, 50 games a day.
So what we did was think a lot about how to do catch-up mechanics on digital.
So we had welcome back quests, which we talked about.
And this one is a very interesting example.
So the first original idea for doing a catch-up mechanic was,
hey, we're going to offer you 10 gold for every four ranked plays.
So, and we have a cap of 50 gold.
But we started to see people progressively starting to concede 20 games on ladder.
This is like what they did. They log in, just lose 20 games.
And they figured out how long they had to play and just estimate and optimize their gold time.
So what we ended up doing is then switching it to five gold per two wins.
And
What that means is that per completion, you get plus 10 extra gold for completion.
So that means that in the first 14 wins per day, you're essentially getting 15 gold per
two wins, and it tapers off at 14.
So the nice thing is that
It allows players to start to mentally think that I'm kind of losing extra gold if I don't play more,
but in a way that reinforces them to play and to win.
And it's a positive. It's almost like the original like WoW rest XP system,
where it started punishing you. It just said, hey, you got some extra XP
that you can get just by like playing a bit more.
or killing a few more mobs that day.
So that's actually a very similar psychological system
than we did.
It's all positive reinforcement.
But then what this also solved too
is that for people who wanted to grind
and continue to play and play 100 games a day,
they can still continue to earn gold
because in the previous version,
we capped it at like a max of 50.
So this pleases both sides of the player base.
Absolutely.
So in the catch a mechanic that's what for out of game systems inside the game we use again a lot of standard ccg designs here so the man around some of the returns of the amount of stuff you can do it. The power level of your place increase every turn so people get an early advantage are could be defeated by somebody with who has.
waits on more powerful stuff that's pretty standard.
The stakes elevate from turn to turn so we have in the game we have
mana springs that allow people to get temporary mana for running into the
middle of the board and interacting with their opponent.
They could, even somebody who gets it that first will burn through more cards
which the other player may decide to hold on and get card advantage by
killing more of their stuff.
And we have something called strong board clears.
Players who, games like this often ramp,
boil down to how much tempo can I get,
how many threats can I put on the board
as quickly as possible that my opponent cannot react to.
We decided to increase the strength of the cards
that can wipe out multiple, multiple threats at once.
So again, to give an advantage to somebody
who is laying behind or allow people to play defensively
in a control style.
wait for your opponent to over commit and just stabilize, don't die, and then finish them off.
play a board clear and then win the game
with your more powerful stuff.
And be aware, of course, every design decision
has trade-offs, so philosophically,
we decided to do that, and we stuck with that decision.
There's obvious negatives for having strong board clears
and having a lot of options for removal,
and that's an issue that community will talk about as well,
but it's something that we stuck to on a top-down level
to kind of maintain fidelity of the game and the board.
Now, number seven, what's different from tabletop compared to digital is also consistency in
being able to release patches and having sort of like this military unit basically on your
team that can continue to push out content.
So as mentioned before, we originally launched on the web.
And one of the huge benefits for doing stuff on the web is that we can deploy things very
quickly without people having to get updates.
and very quickly just started to tune things
behind the scenes, especially like early on.
Then once we knew that we had a pretty consistent game,
we had like the amount of time that we wanted,
then we can like push out onto PC.
But our cadence is pretty much close to
two patches a month, and we did 55 patches in one year.
So we're very focused on having a plan
for what we want to push out, and we think about...
The type of content that we want to do in terms of live events is split into three areas daily, as well as weekly, and then also for monthly.
So the monthly stuff would be like ranked ladder, and we have an inverse reward system.
So for example, we front load the best rewards actually at a lower rank, and as you continue to go up, the rewards are actually a little bit less.
awesome than the ones at the bottom. So the bulk of people will get the coolest cards like that month and
rather than the richer getting stronger by being more skilled and getting better stuff.
We have boss battles that we introduced that you can play against the AI every week with completely different types of decks.
We have daily challenges and you know, our game is like primarily PvP
but we spend a lot of time also thinking about training challenges and
single-player challenges that people can start to experiment with so that they can build confidence before you you jump into into ladder
And so these are some of the cards that we release every month that are different and kind of change things up in terms of meta.
Now, takeaway number eight is creating a social community atmosphere, which on tabletop everyone does too.
But especially on digital, there's a lot of different cool ways that we did things.
We split it into like three distinct areas.
We use Discord for like real time interaction that is like short lived, ephemeral.
And then Reddit was something that people might check daily.
and the content there are the folks that would check once a day and things like that.
There's like some good content that you can kind of see there that was happening.
And then we also have, we run our own forums and those are designed
for long form where people are going to spend time to write long articles and essays
and like deck types and you know all that sort of thing. We have a custom support
system where we actually have a 24 hour grading system so we look
at how fast and how quickly and what the quality is for all the
different.
requests that we get and
tickets that we get and we our goal is to always get like zero tickets like every day and that's one of the key
things that we strive to do and
So just to give you kind of a benchmark our Twitter number of Twitter follows about 18 K
Facebook is like 35,000 likes and
Our our view right now at this point in time is that Twitter is still a very is a very powerful
mechanism to communicate like
patches and ideas and new cards and things like that because the challenge right now on Facebook is that
1% of your Facebook posts reach your audience even less than that
Even if they like your product or like your page anything you post up there just doesn't get to anyone anymore
Okay
And again, we integrated featured streamers directly in-game so that people can also start to,
if they're not sure how to play the game, they can click, immediately jump onto, watch a game that's on Twitch,
and also to find someone that's there, and also perhaps even interact with the player and kind of learn some things.
And we also run a lot of dev talks where different parts of
our community can talk about an upcoming boss or how we
sort of designed it or things that you can think about.
Number nine is, unfortunately, you just can't make everyone
happy in digital.
And it's really tough.
And a lot of the decisions that we make isn't a majority
sort of thing where all the players, like 80%, will make a
decision.
Generally, it will polarize very evenly.
on a certain decision. So if you query a large group of players, it would always polarize
into like two different areas for like what they believe is a good design. And they're
both all valid. I think that a lot of these decisions are feedback that we get. So we
just stick true to our original philosophy. We try to have some pillars that we do in
terms of our planning for the next expansions.
And our goal is just to bolster the strengths that we have.
Rather than trying to plug all the weaknesses
necessarily in our game, we just move forward,
try to build the things that we know that we're strong at,
like having a game that lasts for less than 10 minutes,
building, like, a really cool set of archetypes
and exciting win conditions and things like that to do it.
And there's just no way you can build,
quote, unquote, like, a perfect game.
And I'll give you a couple examples.
Is that...
We had originally like two card draw where you can draw like two cards and we change it to a single draw that that really polarized and in some ways pissed off the community.
But there were a lot of reasons why we needed to do that.
A lot of times we might have the keyword random in our card,
and a lot of that stuff is to fix variety,
and also to smooth out parts of the skill curve.
But again, the folks that are playing a lot and they love
deterministic highly skilled games are going to get frustrated.
So there's a balance and we just decided,
hey, we're not going to be.
We're going to have a little bit more RNG than chess or Go,
but we're going to have less RNG than another typical CCG
that's out there or any of our competitors.
And we just kind of stuck with that position.
We might do questions. Yeah, so this again the summary. He said that the bottom right quadrant is the area to start thinking about in terms of how to improve those areas. I think this will always benefit for high frequency for the game and that's that's pretty much it from so thanks so much and.
I think we have a couple of minutes for questions if.
Yeah, we'd love to answer any questions you guys have.
Here they come.
Hi, thanks for a great talk.
I've been wondering recently, with board games being so huge,
we've seen some successful ports of board games into digital.
But it seems like, aside from CCGs,
there haven't been a lot of natively digital games
that borrow board game mechanics or feel like board games.
We haven't seen a lot of digital deck builders or worker
placement games, for instance.
Is that something you guys think there is potential for,
or is it just like...
nature of the medium that it doesn't work.
Well, if you mean why we think there aren't any more
natively digital board game-esque type games
is because of the strengths of the medium.
Once you build a digital game natively digital,
then you are clearly going to be playing
to the strengths of the medium.
And the more, there's always going to be a point,
there's always where you have to choose.
We have to choose is this a digital game with all the with the strengths that
Keith was talking about or are we going to try to make it a little bit more
real-time kitchen table style game. So I mean
there will at best will probably be more hybrid style games
or games that are adapted from board games in order to teach
board games a little bit easier.
Thank you.
Given the process that you guys, or given the amount of time you spent invested in going from
the prototype to digital, and now you guys I know are thinking about mobile, or at least tablet,
or phone, I don't know, how is that, how are you kind of looking at those challenges?
So going from like desktop to mobile?
What are the biggest challenges from desktop to mobile?
The biggest challenge from desktop to mobile is screen space, screen size, and text size.
So text size is the hardest thing for us to adjust for.
That's really actually the biggest one was text size.
And also the UI and how to frame some things.
So if you guys have already tried out our like beta
for the mobile, it's going to be,
there's a certain things that we had to remove
out of the game on mobile
so that we can accommodate that sort of space.
Hi, I wanted to actually ask two questions if I could.
So the first one is just for your matchmaking.
As a player progresses and starts playing and they get better,
they also start playing better players.
Do you feel that they're still getting a rewarding experience
even though their win rate might not be increasing, but they're getting better?
Well, I mean, every player is going to cap out at one particular division based on their ranking.
That's one of the main reasons why we have floors in our ranking system.
What we generally find the behavior is, once a player hits their skill cap and starts going down to the floor of their rank,
That's where, because you can't go down, generally speaking,
more players tend to experiment more with decks.
And they play more fun decks or more experimental stuff.
And the chances of that player winning against those decks
goes up quite substantially.
So they will end up with a bit of a roller coaster.
But our seasons being one month and resetting
tends to solve a lot of that.
Can I actually ask one more quick question
related to that same issue?
How much do you value skill, sorry not skill, quality of decks in matchmaking or does that just over time become a component of their skill if they keep playing the same deck long enough?
If you mean, do you mean quality of decks by how good?
How well it's put together, how consistent it is.
We don't track, for example, what number of legendaries
or the rarity of the cards when you hop into a match.
Where we, I think what the cohort-based matchmaking does
is it helps us solve a lot of those sort of issues.
Okay, thank you.
Thank you.
Hi, so you went through lessons learned.
I'm wondering if you actually had any of these design pillars
in the beginning, or are there lessons learned?
And how late in the process did you learn them?
I'm sorry, I didn't.
So the design pillars were pretty early on.
So when we were already developing the prototype
and thinking about transitioning to digital,
those were the first thoughts,
making the game less than 10 minutes.
That was definitely at the start,
how we built the first set of 60 cards to test out.
So the first 60 cards helped to accomplish
that the matches would last less than 10 minutes.
Although at that time, of course,
you had very clear hard counters and things like that
because of the limited card size.
and then the other goal is how we can accommodate players that we're losing.
I think those were all things that we planned pretty early on in the game.
One other thing that's like a little bit more on the technical side is that
we knew that we might move to the mobile or to have the opportunity to expand there
and that's why we did pixel art, why we did like 2D style art, because we knew that...
Potentially we would have limited bandwidth, texture space, things like that.
We wanted to have an app that you could download, have a small binary, and things like that.
So those were more technical things that we planned out very early on.
Because a lot of people ask, why isn't your game all in 3D?
But the reality is having 400 units all 3D animated on a board is pretty challenging
and it could actually be pretty high effort for doing that.
And they look so cool on your iPhone.
It does look pretty good, the pixel art now.
Thank you.
You talked a little bit about the challenge of making sure
that people have a really good experience with
matchmaking online.
And I'm curious about doing that when you have a premium
game and you're trying to build out the community, how
you might approach something like that.
Making sure you have enough players there when you first
launch so that all your new players aren't coming on and
then finding they can't play online because no one's there.
A premium game is a paid game?
Yeah, like a paid online multiplayer game.
That's a tough one.
A lot of the digital board games are paid online multiplayer.
It's true.
I mean, with a premium game, you've got a hard gate already of how many players you're
going to get.
Our game was, because it's a free-to-play, we knew we were going to have a huge cohort
of players to start with, I mean, compared to a tabletop game.
So we made our rank ladder very granular.
The best way I could think of to start with, you would have to make a very non-granular
ranking ladder.
And just...
allow for a little bit more,
a little more give in actual,
like in the fidelity of matchmaking for sake of time.
Because I think time, the time between matchmaking
is your number one consideration
because that's what makes your game feel active and alive.
And also one thing is that casual queue
seems like just another thing to do,
but it's, in our opinion,
really hard to build a casual matchmaking system because the mindset is oh, it's casual, but
everyone still wants to win in that queue.
So as a result even if you lose it feels bad and then also you have people with insane skill level that can jump in
there, and then you also have players that want to experiment with decks.
It's really hard to find a quality match for everyone because everyone's goals are so different on
casual. So, although people say, hey I want to practice on that and not have like
ladder stress, actually they don't feel that great going on a casual unless you
spend a lot of time building that system. So, if you're thinking of maybe building
a lot of modes, I still think that having a very simple ranked progression system
that can reset, that's PvP, have a single queue, is probably better because casual
is like very hard to build.
Hey, my question is primarily for Eric.
How do you go about balancing your responsibilities on Duelist with whatever responsibilities
you may have on your more traditional tabletop games you're working on simultaneously?
Oh, I mean I've I've got an amazing team so it's I'm not like the only designer we have a team we have a full team of 5 designers that work as a group so my role at to do this is the I mean it was the design of the core game and the and the full alphabet is that but during that time we've been training our team of really really talented people to
like to, in the dualist design style, and they all have the,
they've all got separate talents and perspective as well.
So, my job is more of a, at this point, is as a vision keeper.
So, I'm the one who will lay out the foundation for the set,
why this set is fun, what cool mechanics are we going
to explore, but this is a point where it's so collaborative
that there's four of us in one given set.
So, even as my.
exact participation rise and falls in the exact card design,
you probably won't even notice a difference, I don't think.
And there'd be some cards in our previous expansion
where designers can learn best from the mistakes.
So there's some cards that some of our other designers
had pushed out that didn't work out very well.
And then also, we have a very specific top level,
S-rank competitive balancer that's really top ranked
and is always like rank zero every month,
really understands what's happening.
in the game. Yeah, exactly. I'm like the worst player on our team.
Hey, thanks guys. Really appreciate it. Thank you so much for your time.