All right, well, I guess it's go time.
Thank you all for coming.
I am truly delighted to be here.
I am not exaggerating when I say that presenting to rooms
full of smart, creative people like you
is what I enjoy doing most.
Presenting at GDCs in the past has been
a career highlight for me, and hopefully this year
I won't trip and fall down, hurt myself,
and have a career low light.
But anyway, thank you for coming.
For those who don't know me, I'm Scott Crabtree.
My life story in about 30 seconds goes like this.
I was born and raised in Massachusetts, born in Western Mass, raised mostly around the
town of Andover.
I went from there to Vassar College in upstate New York where I got a degree in cognitive
science.
This is where I really fell in love with the mind and thinking and what makes brains tick
and not tick so well.
From there I moved, long story short, to Oregon.
This is lovely Oregon, which I love not only for its
beautiful nature, but the awesome city of Portland,
Oregon, where I am from.
And I decided to stay in Portland, even though it's
been absolutely terrible for my video game
development career.
As you may know, there's very little game development going on in Portland, but there's
some games coming out of Portland and New Zealand where I spent a year.
And these are some of the games that I have shipped in my career, most recently the iPhone
game Middle Top.
And of course, probably like you, I've worked on some games that haven't shipped as well.
Enough about me.
I want to learn some things about you, and I want to start with a little experiment.
So, please do the following with me. When I say go, I want you silently in your head
to say the alphabet as fast as you can from A to Z, and then count from 1 to 26 as fast
as you can, and then stand up. Silently in your head, alphabet, 1 to 26, then stand up.
Ready? Mark, get set, go.
Okay, awesome.
And yes, my friend back there with the broken leg,
you don't need to stand up
and I'm not gonna force anyone to stand up,
but I'm encouraging you all to stand up.
Why?
Because solid neuroscience shows
that when your body gets in motion,
your brain produces what's called BDNF.
brain-derived neurotropic factor, which you can essentially think of as fertilizer for brains.
I want you to not just hear me but actually learn something today.
And so that means getting you in motion occasionally. Thank you. You can sit down.
Now we're going to do it again, only I want you to alternate. So A1, B2, C3, D4.
Fast as you can, then stand up. On your mark, get set, go.
Okay, I'll spare you all the suffering. We're now at about 10 seconds
when the vast majority of you were standing up previously.
That is what multitasking does to your brain.
And we live in a multitasking society, so we feel like we're being more productive,
and the science is abundantly clear on this.
When you're talking about paying attention with your prefrontal cortex, multitasking is impossible.
All you can really do is rapidly switch your attention between tasks,
which is expensive not just for computers, but also for brains.
And in particular, this valuable brain real estate you have up here
called your prefrontal cortex, which is responsible for your executive function.
So that is why I want you to eliminate or at least minimize multitasking as we go through this talk.
Okay, on with learning more about who's here. Please stand up if you're a programmer.
Awesome, thank you. Many of you. Sit down.
QA people of any kind, managing QA, testing, etc.
Thank you. Sit down.
Artists, musicians, sound people, any kind of artist, animator, modeler, etc.
cool thank you and production people business people of any kind you're
managing production you're running a studio
you're suing people for a living whatever it is
thank you
now i want you to think about what you know about the brain
None of us know that much. It's one of the most complex things there is in the universe.
You all have 100 billion neurons in your head with average of many thousand connections
to other neurons. And the fact that that two to three pound blob of jelly can make any
sense out of my voice and this complex visual scene in front of you is nothing short of
miraculous. So none of us know everything about the brain, but there's been an explosion
of information coming out of neuroscience recently.
So stand up if you've read one or two books, watched one or two videos, read an article
or two about the brain, you know some stuff about the brain.
Awesome.
Thank you.
And stand up if you've read many more than that or more than that.
So this is the challenge. I have some people who know very little about the brain and some people who know a lot about the brain.
So, I'll do my best to strike the middle ground as we go.
The rest of this talk, basically my deal with you, is if you pay attention and focus and
participate for the next hour, I will teach some of you, hopefully all of you, some stuff
about the brain and how it works, and in particular about neuroplasticity.
And you will leave with some information and some tools that will help you rewire your
brain for the better.
The story of this talk is basically the story of your brain.
You are the lead character in this story, and if you went to school any time around
when I went to school, you were told roughly this about the brain.
You're born with a gazillion brain cells, they die throughout your lifetime, the brain
cells set like concrete when you're an adult, so suck it up, right?
You're getting stupider and you lose your ability to really grow and change throughout
your life.
That's a problem.
Part of the problem that results and the main problem that I'm here to focus on is that
I suggest you all spend a lot of time making your games better and very little time making
your brains better.
At least that's been true at the game companies where I have worked.
And if this conference is any indication, that's true, right?
There are lots and lots of sessions on how to make your game better.
And as far as I know, this is the only session on how to make your brain better.
but your brain is not only making your current game, it will make every game in
the future, which means investing in your own brain
pays enormous dividends as you go through your life.
So the solution is neuroplasticity.
Science is telling us a much better story of your brain now.
The story coming from science in recent years,
there was some controversy about this for a while,
and now there's virtually no controversy left.
The science about your brain is very clear
and telling an awesome story.
That story goes like this.
Yes, you learn more easily as a child,
but you continue to learn throughout your lifetime.
You don't just lose neurons throughout your lifetime,
you also add neurons throughout your lifetime
and make and break connections in your brain
throughout your life.
We're talking about real, physical, observable changes
to your brain.
Size changes, structure changes that you
can see in your brain if you do things right.
which means that you get to write how the story of your brain ends.
And that's what I want to ask you to do towards the end of this talk.
Those who got a handout, there's a space where you're going to fill in a little neuroplasticity
plan before we're done.
So as we're going, I encourage you to think about how do you want to apply this?
How do you want to use the fact that you can rewire your brain to be a different brain?
This is fantastic news.
It's nothing short of miraculous to me.
Your brain
produces your mind.
Your mind arises out of your brain, right?
With your mind, you can think new thoughts
that rewire your brain.
That is nothing short of miraculous to me. This is some of the biggest news we've
had about the brain
in four hundred years.
because for most of that time again we thought you're basically fixed once you're an adult
and we now know that's not true.
So it means that we all need
what Stanford professor Carol Dweck calls a growth mindset.
She divides people into two categories. Those who have a fixed mindset say
things like
you can't teach an old dog new tricks.
I am the way I am.
he's just the way he is, she's just the way she is.
If you have a fixed mindset, you believe that we're basically all just set.
Now there is some truth to that. I don't want to overstate any of this.
I give separate talks on strengths and how to apply strengths, and that's largely because,
hey, guess what?
Everything you've done so far until this moment in your life has rewired your brain.
So some of you are really good at some things and not so good at other things, and you're
not going to think your way into a completely new skill overnight.
I, for example, play a lot of music and do a lot of programming.
If I work on growing as a musician or a programmer, I'm going to grow really well.
I am an absolutely fucking terrible artist.
I mean, I could not draw you a picture to save my life unless it was a stick figure.
If I invested a lot of time and energy in growing as an artist, I would go from absolutely
freaking terrible to just a little bit less terrible.
So growth does not mean, hey, just pick whatever you want to be.
You can grow like crazy.
I can be a master artist in a matter of weeks if I turn my attention to it.
No.
Many of us take the philosophy that we can grow the most in our areas of weakness,
and science suggests, no, you can grow more in your areas of strength.
So try this data on for size from the Gallup organization.
If you send a random group of people into a speed reading class,
you give them a pre-test and a post-test.
The slow readers who go in, they all learn the same material in the same class.
The slow readers improve about 50%.
The fast readers improved 600%.
So growth doesn't mean pick where you know nothing and have no brain circuits and focus
there.
It means you can grow strongest where you already have some good circuits, where your
brain is already wired up to do some things.
But regardless, it means that we all should adopt what Carol Dweck calls a growth mindset.
which means the opposite of the fixed mindset.
You can learn and change in significant ways throughout your lifetime.
This turns out to be extremely important.
Virtually every great person in history, if you think of a person in history who you admire,
according to Dweck, that person had a growth mindset.
It's a consistent attribute of people who achieve greatness in their lives.
So I want you all to stand up if you as of this moment have a growth mindset.
And don't feel pressured to stand up if you don't. Awesome! Everybody's on board. Yay!
So, now that you believe and understand that you can substantially change your brain over time, how do you do it?
Step one, you've got to feel safe and relax.
When you're stressed out, you can learn facts like,
don't go there, there's a tiger over there,
but you are not in a space to learn and grow
and build new connections.
Now, I want to make clear about stress.
Stress is not a bad thing necessarily.
Most of us, I in the past, think stress, bad,
must avoid stress.
If you have zero stress,
you do not get out of bed in the morning.
We're talking about too much stress, excess stress, stress you can't control, and chronic stress.
That's the kind of stress that makes your brain work really poorly, and in fact, kills neurons.
The opposite of what we're focused on here today.
The problem here is that your fight or flight response is a really effective part of your
brain, historically speaking.
If there is a tiger in your midst, your limbic system, which is the older part of your brain
that looks very much like brains of cats and all other mammals, that emotional part of
your brain is wired for the fight or flight response.
So that if you feel any threat.
In fact, if there's a mix of things in your environment,
two good, one bad, you get stressed out, you go into fight or flight mode
to one degree or another. This is not a switch, this is a continuum.
When you go into fight or flight mode, your limbic system says,
I'm in charge now, because there are three ways to get out of this stressful situation.
Run, fight, or freeze. You hear about that less because
it doesn't rhyme, but in fact it's your number one option under stress.
Freeze, don't move, don't say anything because maybe Tiger hasn't seen you and you've shut up
and don't move, you stay alive. So you freeze and if that doesn't work you try to fight it off and
if that doesn't work you run and we see these in the office all the time and the problem is they're
absolutely terrible for coping with stress. Really terrible for coping with stress. Really
good for keeping you alive at Tigers and really terrible for helping you make games.
So the problem is that there seems to be a three to one ratio.
This is called the Losada line, if you want to look it up later.
And by the way, sources for my material are at the, in addition to the books I showed,
are in the tiny print you can't read at the bottom of the slides.
It's in tiny print you can't read because I don't want to distract you with it,
as I already told you multitasking sucks.
But I want you to be able to look into the studies later.
So if you don't have a handout, I can email you one or there are some at the back of the room.
And I'm happy to email you slides as well so that you can dig into sources.
I'm trying to give you as little of my opinion as possible, basically,
and as much scientific information as possible.
So what the science says is that when you go into fight or flight mode,
you suck.
oxygen and glucose and dopamine and all the stuff your brain needs to work
into your limbic system so that you can focus on fight or flight
and that is not a good way to use or learn
in your cortex, your uniquely human layers of brain
immediately under your scalp. So if you really want to learn and you want to
rewire your brain you have to relax
first. So I want to do a little stress poll. Stand up
if in the past six months
over half of those months, I'm going to give you three choices.
Not very stressful, moderately stressful, very stressful.
Okay? So stand up if the past six months for you on average have been not very stressful.
Awesome. Your peers want to work where you work. Okay, sit down.
Thank you. Stand up if the past six months on average have been moderately stressful.
Okay, thank you. Sit down and stand up if they have been very stressful.
Yes, you people should talk to the first group that stood up. Anyway, thank you.
Okay, so I want to teach you some quick relaxation techniques that you can use in the office.
Why? To get your brain working more, your brain working more better, I was starting to say, which I'm very proud of.
I want your brain to work more better in the moment and I want you to set the stage for
neuroplasticity and long-term learning and growth in your brain.
So here are a few things you can do and I want you to try them with me as we go.
The first one is visualization.
Roll your eyes now, have the gag reflex, because I know some of you are like, oh my God, spare
me the woo-woo, Oprah, BS, whatever.
But the science is clear, visualization works.
in part because visualization is not a healthy response to stress.
If you have a tiger in your midst,
picturing a beach in Hawaii, you're dead.
So when you visualize, when you picture something, it's a signal to your brain
that everything must be okay.
So I want you to try this right now.
Just take about 10 seconds and shut your eyes and in detail
picture a happy or safe place for you.
Home, beach in Hawaii, a hike, you want to,
whatever it is, just picture it in detail if you can.
Okay, I just went back to Mount Jefferson in Oregon.
I hope your spot was good for you.
If you're anything like me, you feel just a little bit more relaxed.
Now, I don't want to overstate this.
If somebody's screaming at you a string of George Carlin curses
and calling you an idiot and you're trying to visualize,
it's not going to help you enormously.
But if you've just come out of a stressful meeting
or you're even in a stressful meeting
and you can take a few seconds and visualize something,
again, it's a signal to your brain to relax.
Breathing also works really well.
Hopefully, most of you are breathing most of the time.
But deep breaths, again, your breathing corresponds to your stress really well.
When you're stressed out, you tend to breathe quickly and shallowly.
When you're calm, you tend to breathe more slowly and deeply.
So I want you all to try a breath with me now, but not your usual breath.
We're going to do a funky weird breath, which is.
We're going to count in for four and you're going to breathe in for four as much as you possibly can,
hold it for four, and then out for eight.
And while you're doing this, you're going to think thoughts like,
wow, this Crabtree guy is even weirder than people said,
or he's distracting me with his counting, or his counting is faster or slower.
Try to just put all those thoughts aside and focus on the sensation of your breath.
You have two circuits in your brain primarily that you're using in any moment.
One is the default or narrative circuit.
This one tells stories.
I'm at GDC.
I'm going to this talk.
This guy's really weird, whatever.
And your direct sensory experience is just feeling your sensations.
Turns out that direct sensory experience, although we're in it less,
is a more relaxing circuit to be in.
So in addition to focusing on breathing, I want you to get into that direct sensory circuit
that is the alternative to your default narrative circuit.
So we're going to go in for four, hold for four, out for eight.
Here we go.
In for four.
One, two, three, four.
Hold it.
Out for eight.
And then as you go back to breathing normally, again, if you're anything like me, you feel
a little bit more relaxed than you did before.
Now you've got to watch your deep breathing in the office or people think you're a total
freak.
But, again, I'm trying to give you techniques that you can use in the middle of a stressful
situation.
If you just think to breathe into your belly
and just feel it for a second or two,
it refreshes your brain, helps you relax,
which puts you in a state of thinking better
and using some of your better brain real estate
and also setting the stage
for learning and growth in your brain.
Of course, there's a lot of relaxation techniques you should do whatever works with you, but
I want to share one more with you, which is touching your lips.
Now this is weird, right?
Touching your lips.
Why would this work?
Now the science is that it does work.
The following is Scott's speculation about why it works.
My speculation is that your lips don't get touched normally unless something good is
about to happen.
If your lips get touched, you're usually about to get something to drink.
Beer.
Or some food.
Or somebody's going to make out with you.
In any case, it's going to be good.
Right?
So again, somebody asks you a really difficult question, you feel yourself stressing out,
you go, let me think about that for a second.
And nobody's going to be like, what a freak, he's touching his lips.
You can touch your lips subtly, you can even lick your lips the way Kobe Bryant does.
Stand up if you're a basketball fan.
Wow! For a minute I thought we're only going to have one. Okay, thank you, you can sit down.
Okay, so as much as it pains me to show you Kobe Bryant because I'm a Celtics fan and he's about to score on my Celtics here.
Kobe, virtually every time he shoots a foul shot, he licks his lips first.
And I don't think it's because he knows the science of relaxation. I think it's because he's just developed the habit.
He even does it when he's getting interviewed.
Which the people who made...
NBA2K11 know and they have very good attention to detail. Watch this
giant lick lip after he gets fouled and is heading to the foul line.
So again, just try it right now, just touch your lips a little bit.
and you may not feel a dramatic difference. Again, this isn't going to suddenly make tigers
go away or suddenly make your unbelievably difficult boss go away, but it can help get
you further along the continuum towards relaxation, which is good brain function, which sets the
stage for neuroplasticity. Another thing that works really well is exercise.
I'm sorry to be the hundredth person to tell you you should get some exercise, but you
know it's good for your body.
You may have heard it's good for your brain.
It's very good for your brain.
If you go on a walk before a test, you score higher on the test.
Exercise adds gray matter to your brain.
Exercise produces BDNF, as I mentioned, brain-derived neurotropic, which you can think of as fertilizer
for brain, and we're here to talk about growing brains.
Social connections are also really good for brains.
If you're worried about your parents' cognitive decline, or your own, because you're getting
on in years, social connections is one of the best things you can do to keep your brain
thriving.
You can do this in the office with a walking one-on-one.
Many of us have one-on-one meetings.
Few of us go on a walk for those meetings, and it's a fantastic technique for getting
your blood pumping, building some social connection, and learning the meeting better.
So I want you all to try this right now.
pair up if a few of you end up in a group of three that's fine if you have a broken leg you don't
need to stand up but generally speaking i want you to pair up and then stand up and at least
fidget i can't have you all go on walking one-on-ones or it'll be total chaos for the next
20 minutes but stand up walk in place fidget whatever and talk with your partner what have
you heard so far and how do you want to apply this you have about one minute for this walking one-on-one
go
I'm just listening.
I'm sorry, no, no, no, it's all good.
Okay, a few more seconds.
If you're walking, make your way back to your seats, please.
Find your seats, take your seats please.
Thank you, you are a very cooperative audience and I appreciate it
and I hope it helps burn in some of these
new circuits of what you're learning.
Now that you're relaxed, you're ready to rewire and to rewire
I want you to reach.
This is the acronym I've come up with to summarize some of the key requisites, prerequisites
for rewiring your brain.
Not everything you do as an adult rewires your brain.
Essentially everything you do up until your early mid-twenties does rewire your brain.
So this is why for a while we thought neuroplasticity, significant brain changes only happen in children.
And some things do happen more easily for children. Many things, many brain rewiring things,
happen more easily for children. Many of you have probably heard it's much easier to learn a new
language as a child than as an adult, and that's true. There are limits to neuroplasticity.
Essentially, your neuroplasticity machinery, if you will, the parts of your brain that
are responsible for neuroplasticity, those parts of your brain are always on as a kid.
They are not always on as an adult.
These are the things you need to do to turn on your neuroplasticity machinery in your
brain so that you can rewire your brain and develop new skills and even personality attributes.
So reach, R is for repetition.
R is for repetition. R is for repetition. I will stop now. And really that's enough said.
When you do something repeatedly, it's a signal to your brain that you're going to do it again,
and your brain adds clusters of neurons as opposed to a neuron here or a neuron there.
R is for repetition. E is for effort. If you're doing something that is essentially effortless,
you don't have to try very hard, you're not rewiring your brain.
Many of you have probably heard crosswords are really good for your brain and preventing
cognitive decline as you age, right?
Not if you're really good at crosswords.
If you're just going through crosswords and like...
Honey, this is awesome, I'm totally nailing this crossword.
You're not rewiring your brain.
You are not building the cognitive reserve, the rich networks that protect against cognitive
decline as we age.
The way that works is something like this.
All of us, unfortunately, unless the science changes again, all of us will develop problem
spots in our brains as we age that are called plaques.
You can think of these essentially as dead spots.
So if you have a very sparse network, you can picture a few trails through the woods,
and there's a problem on one of those trails, you're screwed.
You can't get to that part of the woods anymore.
The woods being your brain, obviously, here.
If you have a rich network of neural pathways, like a rich network of paths in the forest,
if there's a problem shows up in one spot, I'll just take this other path.
So, we all tend to experience cognitive decline as we age.
Those with rich cognitive reserves are affected less by those problems because they have other
ways to get where they're going, which is why I think neuroplasticity is so important
to all of us.
You may live a very, very long time.
Stand up if you heard Ray Kurzweil give a keynote speech here a couple of years ago.
Thank you. Okay, so the rest of you, I'll very quickly tell you, for those who don't know, Ray Kurzweil is basically a genius, invented the flatbed scanner, the synthesizer, 16 honorary doctorates.
Now, he's a bit of a freak and a bit controversial, in particular in how he's applied this to humans and health.
But he is a fantastic predictor of technology trends.
And he ended his talk a couple years ago by saying something like the following.
We are just a few years from adding more than a year of life expectancy for every calendar
year that goes by, which means if you can live a little while longer, you will live
forever.
And he walked off the stage.
Now that's quite a statement, right?
You're going to live forever.
And I talk to my smartest friends who are doctors and they say, I don't buy it.
You can't apply technology.
I don't buy it.
Whether you believe or not you're going to live forever,
I am convinced by Kurzweil's talk and the science that we are going to live a
long time.
If you don't get hit by a bus during GDC or next year,
you could all easily
live to be well over a hundred.
I'm not guaranteeing that. I know that sounds far-fetched to some of you,
but I think we are all going to live longer than we expect to live.
which means you want your brain to live and work at least as long as well as your body does,
which means building cognitive reserve is important,
which means you want to do things that require effort.
If you play Tony Hawk...
or World of Warcraft for the thousandth time, it is not going to rewire your brain unless
it's more difficult. It's a new level. It's a new challenge. Novelty helps. Effort helps.
E is for effort. You want to be putting some effort into activities if you want them to
rewire your brain. So R is for repetition. E is for effort. And A is for attention. Stand
up if you went to the talk last night on attention.
A few of you, yes, excellent talk.
Okay.
So, for the rest of you, you might want to check it out on the Vault, the GDC Vault.
Attention turns out to be extremely important for neuroplasticity.
And not just a little attention, but the intense, rapt attention that new challenging activities
require.
Attention is extremely powerful, more powerful than many of you may realize.
It's also difficult.
So here's a little attention test for you.
If you know the answer, please don't give it away to your
neighbors.
Some of you have seen this video before.
You are about to see a video of two basketball teams, one
dressed all in white, one dressed all in black.
Your job is to count the passes on the team dressed
all in white.
He said, reaching for the audio.
Never mind.
You don't need the audio.
The audio says, count the passes on the team dressed
all in white.
Here we go.
Ready?
Stand up if you got 13.
Sit down. Stand up if you saw a moonwalking bear.
Awesome. Here it comes.
You can all sit down. It's going to come in from the right hand edge.
Right there. A guy in a bear suit.
Right in the middle.
And moonwalking out the other side.
Stand up if you missed the moonwalking bear.
And this is consistently what happens in studies.
About half of the participants, when told to count the passes on the team dressed all
in white, miss the moonwalking bear.
Because attention is intensely powerful, it doesn't just focus you on something, it starts
blocking out other things.
Your attention is required for neuroplasticity.
And not just a little attention, a lot of attention, and strong attention.
And if you multitask a lot, you're going to have issues with attention.
Stand up if you are a frequent multitasker.
Don't be shy.
I know I've already made you feel bad or tried to for multitasking.
Okay, sit down. Right. This is the problem.
I think multitasking is a cultural disease.
You feel like you're getting more done, but you're not.
Why do you feel like you're getting more done? Because you're getting challenged.
And when you're getting challenged, because it's impossible, by the way.
Remember, all you can do is rapidly task switching,
and you felt at the beginning how difficult it is to rapidly task switch.
So when you multitask, your IQ essentially drops, you make more mistakes, and you become
what Clifford Nass at Stanford calls a sucker for irrelevancy.
You lose your ability to filter out the important from the unimportant.
You lose your ability to focus and sustain attention.
That attention ability is required to rewire your brain.
So how do you develop your ability to pay attention?
One way is with mindfulness and or meditation. You can think of them
largely as the same thing.
Stand up if you've ever meditated.
Okay, many of you. Good. So you won't think I'm a freak.
Stand up if you've never meditated. I know it's the other half of you. I'm just
trying to get your brains
producing BDNF. Thank you. Okay, those of you who were just standing
may think this sounds really weird and freaky. Don't get your spiritual crap on
me, Crabtree.
whatever it is, you may have associations, whether it's martial arts
or a particular kind of spirituality. I want you to try to put all those
associations aside, because meditation comes in many forms, and essentially the
kind I'm talking about is simply
focusing your attention.
Excellent meditators aren't better at sustaining their attention
as much as they're better at noticing when they've lost their attention.
It's kind of like balance.
People with great balance, you can't see me but I'm standing on one leg now.
people with great balance, it's not that they're just always right perfectly in line,
it's that they notice sooner that they're getting offline and a little to the left,
and they shift back right, and they notice sooner that a little bit of right,
and go back left, and that's what people with good attention skills do as well.
They notice sooner that their attention is drifted,
and they more quickly return their attention to the object of focus.
If you practice doing that, you will rewire your brain
to add neurons to your prefrontal cortex and improve your ability to sustain attention.
which is why I want you to try just 30 seconds of meditation with me.
Just sit comfortably, put your hands on your knees, in your lap, wherever is comfortable
for you.
Shut your eyes if you're comfortable doing so.
If you're not, you can just look at the chair or the floor in front of you.
I'm going to guide you through this a little bit, which means I'm going to talk, which
is going to drive some of you crazy.
All you want to do is focus your attention on the sensation of your breath.
Again, I want you to get into your direct sensory circuit.
Feel the breath wherever you feel it, in your nose, in your belly, wherever you feel the
breath.
Just focus on your breath, notice when you're not paying attention, and without judgment,
which is important, return your attention to your breath.
About 30 seconds of this.
If you're thinking thoughts, don't judge them, just return to the sensation of your breath.
Again, just return attention to your breath.
Okay, whenever you're ready, you can return your attention to everything around you and open your eyes.
And again, if you're anything like me, you feel a little refreshed, a little more relaxed,
and you also just started the process of strengthening your inner CEO.
Your prefrontal cortex is sometimes called your inner CEO, your prefrontal cortex is
this part of your brain right behind the middle of your forehead and it is fantastic brain
real estate, responsible for executive function like planning, decision making, initiation
of action, inhibition of action.
Wow, I really want to punch Paul in the face right now, he's such an asshole.
When you don't punch Paul in the face in the office, that's your prefrontal cortex helping
you out, helping you keep your job.
So your prefrontal cortex is awesome brain real estate and in addition to all that other
inner CEO stuff, it helps you focus attention and return attention.
And when you practice being mindful or meditating, you add neurons to your prefrontal cortex
and you even, studies suggest, remove neurons from your amygdala and your limbic system
that gets you upset and irritated with people.
I encourage moments of mindfulness or meditation. If meditation feels weird for you,
try just being mindful moment to moment, which goes like something like this.
As you walk to your meeting,
don't think anything, just try to feel how your feet feel as they hit the ground as you're walking.
Or when you're driving, turn off the music and just focus completely on driving.
How does the steering wheel feel in your hands?
Or when your phone rings, instead of immediately, God damn it, I can't take that now, or, ah,
I've got to talk to Jim, listen to the sound of your phone ringing all the way until the
sound is gone, and then answer.
Little moments of mindfulness like that reinforce, refresh your brain with that direct sensory
circuit, and again, improve your ability to pay attention.
So A is for attention in reach, and attention is awesome and an important prerequisite for
rewiring your brain.
C is for complexity. Why complexity? Because the more complex the activity you're doing,
the more you're going to rewire your brain, the more benefits you're going to get,
which is why neuroplasticity experts recommend if you want to empower this neuroplasticity
machinery in your brain, you want to do something very complex that uses as much of your brain
as possible. If you're going to play a game, a game that uses your body as a controller is
better than a game that doesn't.
You hear neuroplasticity experts often talk about things like learning a language or even
better playing a musical instrument.
Why?
Because when you play a musical instrument, you're activating so much of your brain.
Visual systems are going to read the chords or the notes or pay it or visually see what
the other musicians you're playing with are doing.
Your auditory cortex is obviously heavily involved when you're playing music.
Your cerebellum is involved with timing and keeping the beat for you.
and your muscular cortex controlling your fingers as you play guitar or drums or whatever it is.
When you're learning a musical instrument, you're activating a lot of different parts of your brain
which brings you richer cognitive reserve which helps you prevent against cognitive decline
and strengthens your neuroplasticity machinery as neuroplasticity pioneer Mike Mersnick calls it.
So C is for complexity.
If you can rewire your brain with something simple, but you'll get more benefits if you
rewire your brain with something complex.
So R is for repetition, E is for effort, A is for attention, C is for complexity, and
H is for health.
I'm going to let you in on a shocking revelation from the world of science.
Your brain is in your body.
I know, it's weird, isn't it?
Not only that, but it's a huge part of your body resource speaking.
Speaking resource-wise.
Your brain is about two or three pounds.
But it takes 20 to 25% of the nutrients, blood sugar, and everything else that you consume.
Because it is an intense machine, as I described earlier.
So I'm sorry to tell you to be healthy at a conference like GDC, where many of us are not so healthy.
But, this starts with eating right. Basically, any healthy food is good for your brain.
In particular, things with vitamin B, C, D, or E.
And antioxidants like omega-3 acids are good for your brain,
which means you should eat things like fish, drink things like tea,
eat berries, walnuts, and perhaps the best news of the whole talk, chocolate.
I've already mentioned exercise.
I don't mean to dwell on this, but again, exercise is fantastic for your brain.
And as disappointing and problematic as it may be to hear at GDC when there's so many
good parties going on, you need to sleep well to learn well and think well.
So in studies, if you teach a rat a maze during the day, and during the day it learns left,
left, right, right, left to find the cheese.
When you watch that rat brain sleep, at certain stages of sleep, it is running that maze back
and forth way faster than it could in reality, learning that pathway.
During the night as it sleeps, that rat brain is going left, left, right, right, left, left,
left, right, right, left, left, left, right, right, left, left, left, right, right, left.
Your brain will do the same thing when you sleep.
So if you want to learn more and add more circuits to your brain, sleep well.
So H is for health.
Reach to rewire.
With repetition, effort, attention, complexity, and health.
Again, because circuits get burned in when you talk out loud about something, and circuits
get burned in when you physically move, I want you to do one more walking one-on-one
with your partner or partners.
Just for one minute, stand up, talk about what have you heard so far, how can you apply
this to your brain and your games.
Go!
Okay, make your way back to your seats, please.
Walk back to your seats if you went on a walk, which I appreciate.
Take a seat again.
Thank you.
I'm sorry I'm not giving you more time.
I would if I had it, but I want to encourage you to continue this stuff after the talk.
Talk about this stuff over lunch, and you'll learn it and burn it better.
So reach to rewire.
Once you've rewired your brain, this is a use it or lose it situation.
Circuits in your brain that you don't lose gradually wither away.
I like the phrasing work it or waste it a little better, again, because it goes back
to that effort.
If you're putting effort into something, it's a signal to your brain, you need this.
Let's build this up.
Video games can help.
which is great news.
I'm sure you all don't need to be convinced this, but
video games don't just rewire your brains in evil ways the way that some of
the general population thinks, and the media certainly seems to think. More and
more studies are showing that when you play video games, you build beneficial
circuits in your brains.
A recent article in the Wall Street Journal, I think just a few days ago,
describes some of these studies.
Any game will rewire your brain. These games, or these sites, are designed in particular
to rewire your brain for the better. I do not claim to have done an industry-wide, thorough
survey of all braining training software out there, but these are some of the options available
to you. And basically, the higher on the screen, the more the activities seem to be research-based.
So, resources for you to consider using to rewire your brain include the games you're
already playing and maybe some of these.
We're going to go towards making plans in just a minute, but I have a couple of minutes
here for Q&A, which I want to do before you all make your neuroplasticity plans.
So for the sake of the recording, hi everybody watching on GDC Vault.
Please walk up to a microphone if you have a question and I will do my best to answer.
Yes, sir.
Actually it wasn't a question. I just wanted to reinforce two things that you said that I knew intuitively, but I didn't understand the reason for it.
Number one, my wife, who like a lot of people, is under a lot of stress. We have two teenage sons.
She uses a lot of lip balm.
It never occurred to me that maybe there's like a self-medicating relaxation thing that's going on there.
The second thing is, I don't know how many of you watched, I used to watch a show called
The West Wing.
I'm a politics junkie, I loved it.
If there's one thing they do in that show, it's walk and talk.
And they worked in a high-stress environment in the White House, so maybe there was intuitively
something going on there.
Awesome comments, and thank you. I think a lot of us know some of this stuff intuitively,
and part of what I want to do is give you scientific backing to ground and instill
more motivation into some of the things you're probably already doing. Yes, sir.
So I've been very aware of the multitasking problem for a while now because I've noticed that as a
programmer some of the changes that I make sometimes take 5, 10 minutes to compile, run,
implement, stuff like that. And I find myself going off and responding to messages, writing
emails and stuff like that. And it's a problem I've been trying to address but I can't find a
good solution because I have to come back to the original problem. I can't do anything while
that's happening.
Are you looking for a suggestion? I'm looking for a suggestion, yes.
So I feel your pain, first of all. I come from a programming background and
despite all my former colleagues at Intel making processors faster and
faster, compiles still take a while because we keep writing more and more code.
What comes to mind is the concept of flow. Stand up if you're familiar with flow.
Mike Csikszentmihalyi's concept of flow.
Okay, many of you. Very quickly for the rest of you,
if you sustain attention on something that is challenging,
high level of challenge, and you have a high level of skill to do it,
and you stay focused for about twenty minutes, you get into what is called a flow channel.
speaking, all the right gates are open and closed in your brain.
you get in the zone, everything is clicking. If you've ever looked up at your watch and been like,
well, is it that time already? I got to go. I had no idea. Then you've been in flow. Flow is an
awesome, productive and happy state to be in. Peak experience is what Csikszentmihalyi wanted
to study and he came up with this concept of flow. So the difficulty about flow is that it
takes about 20 minutes to get into it. And guess how long to get out of it?
maybe not as bad as you think, it's one or two minutes
to get out of it.
Which means a five minute compile takes you out of it.
So if you ever have a disruption of more than two
minutes and you go back to what you were doing, where you were
in flow, what do you think and feel?
Where was I?
right? Where was I is the loss of flow and it's killing your productivity and your happiness.
So the suggestion is this, not easily done, but the suggestion is this, you're writing code,
you hit compile, stay mentally on the code.
look at object design, do some inspecting, think about which assertions you're going
to put into which functions next, think about how you're going to test the code you've just
written.
If you can stay on the same subject during that interruption, then when your compile
is done, you're right back in the flow.
Not easily done, but I hope that helps.
Few more minutes.
I may not get to all of you.
I'm just going to warn you now.
Next, please.
This all sounds great and I'd love to try it, but when I get home, I have a husband and two small children and I'm the CEO of a company.
And when I get back home, it becomes, I need to get the kids out the door because they have to go to kindergarten and she needs her backpack and she needs her shoes.
And this one has a tummy ache and my mom is on the phone and she needs to find out what day she's coming.
And you know, you get caught up with your life and what can you do?
Can you do this in small doses?
What suggestions do you have?
you can do this in small doses. In fact, I would recommend, you're about to write
neuroplasticity plans for yourself.
In your plan, I suggest you write down, at most, one thing you want to work on.
Because what many of us ambitious people do is write down eight things we want to work
on and we fail at all eight, we get frustrated and we give up.
If you pick one thing and you focus on it repeatedly for a month, you will rewire your
brain.
Studies have shown physical changes in brain in as short as two weeks.
So, the other thing to try to do is to pick a goal that is intrinsically valued.
It's important to you, not your family or your kids or your husband or anyone else.
and an approach goal. Something you want to do as opposed to
I want to stop doing this. All of that helps you succeed
with your goals. Then try to lower the hurdles to doing it and integrate it
into your life. So here's an example.
As some people may know who saw me talk last year or the year before, I'm very into the
science of happiness.
Gratitude is extremely important for happiness.
Easy to do.
If you make a habit of feeling and expressing gratitude, you end up being a more happy person.
So I got into the rhythm of with my wife and three-year-old child, every time we sit down
at home at dinner, we hold hands.
I know, cheesy, whatever.
We hold hands and we say, what's one thing we're each grateful for before we eat dinner?
As we have done that for more than a month, it is now a habit.
Habit equals brain circuit, essentially.
Habit equals brain circuit that you don't have to decide to do with your prefrontal cortex.
Your basal ganglia deep in the middle of your brain says,
time to do this, I'm habituated to do this.
Which means that even when my wife and I are running around stressed out and like,
oh my god.
Crap, gee, you just quit Intel. What are we going to do about health insurance? We're massively stressed out.
Are you really going to be able to make people happy for a living? This is insane.
We're going to be pouring on the street in no time. Let's eat.
My three-year-old says, hey, we didn't say what we were grateful for.
Oh, man, awesome.
So if you can wire those habits in just one small change at a time,
it's less effort and it integrates with your life.
Again, more easily said than done, but does that help?
I apologize, this is going to be the last question, and I'm happy to stick around for
the rest of you, but next please.
So one, thank you for at least trying to bring this to this audience.
Culturally speaking, you know, working in game development, everybody wants to collaborate all the time and multitask and da-da-da.
So, you know, I work on a team for myself, you know, trying to get into that flow state.
I'm an artist, is important, but I am interrupted about every 15 minutes to discuss something or deal with something.
You know, is there, do you have any ideas about that?
Again, easier said than done, seems to be the theme here on how do you apply this, which
is really, again, why I'm asking all of you in a minute, how are you going to apply this?
But what I've suggested to people, and some have applied, is to communicate about Flow
and getting into Flow.
I presented this material for years, not this exact material, but related material, including
Flow at Intel for years, which led to me sitting in my OpenCube environment and people walking
up and I swear to God, first words out of their mouth, are you in Flow?
Awesome.
Because I could say, yeah, I'm really, can it wait or is it less than a minute?
And if it is less than a minute, you can do it and write back where you were.
And if it's longer, most people say, ah, I can send an email, it's fine.
A group I presented to a couple of weeks ago, a person sent me a picture a few days later
of their flow flag.
They took a little dowel and cut out just a piece of paper,
and in small writing it said, can it wait?
I'm in giant letters flow.
And they stick it up on their cubicle when they're in flow.
Now, you're not always going to be in flow.
And for many of you, it's your job to get interrupted, right?
So you can't just say, don't talk to me.
But you can give signals to people.
And if nothing else, turn off your automatic interruption
machines.
The little Outlook thing that pops up and says,
you got an email?
You want to be distracted with this?
I'll show you the first few words just to suck you in.
Right?
Turn it off.
Turn off IM.
Put yourself on do not disturb.
Go to a coffee shop.
Work from home.
Whatever it is, try to block out times
where you don't get interrupted.
And then allow times when it's like, yeah, green flag is up.
Interrupt me all you want.
Again, easier said than done, but I hope that helps.
OK.
Time for you to make a plan.
This is a plan about who you want to be.
This is nothing short of miraculous to me. You can think or even just imagine things
and rewire your brain. Because for your brain, the difference between doing something and
imagining something is very slight. If I had half of you practice shooting foul shots on
a basketball court and the other half just imagine doing so, the imaginers would improve
almost as much as those who practiced. So you can literally think your way into being
a new person.
If you do something repeatedly and reach to rewire over the next month, you will rewire
your brain.
So now the question is to you.
Who do you want to be?
What do you want to do?
Take a minute or two, write down a plan, then I'm going to have you talk about it and I'm
going to summarize and we'll end.
So about a minute and a half or so, who do you want to be?
What one thing do you want to do repeatedly
over the next month?
Hopefully your goal is something where you can notice small progress. Don't be over-ambitious
with this. Don't necessarily focus on something you're terrible at. Think about something you
can make progress on pretty quickly which reinforces the progress you're making.
Okay, now, because studies show that when you publicly share a plan, you are much more
likely to follow through on that plan, I want you all to publicly share your plans with
your walking one-on-one partner, and later, I encourage you to post this on Facebook,
Twitter, wherever you want.
If you publicly share your intention, you're much more likely to follow through.
So one last walking one-on-one for about 30 seconds.
Stand up, talk to your partner.
What are you going to do?
All right, about 10 seconds left.
Make your way back to your seats if you can, please.
All right, wrap up and sit down, please.
I'm sorry I'm not giving you more time.
But again, I encourage you to continue these conversations later.
But I have to get you out of here on time by wrapping up as follows.
You have every bit of potential for growth that this little baby has.
If you make your plan and follow through on your plan for the next month,
you will physically rewire your brain for the better.
So the problem I came here to address is that I think you all focus so much on improving
your games that you don't put enough focus on improving your brains.
Science gives us a truly miraculous solution.
Neuroplasticity.
The ability to rewire your brain in ways that you want to.
And neuroplasticity can rewire your brain in ways that you don't want to, so you have
to be careful about what you're doing and thinking and rewiring your brain, which is
why I want you to be intentional about rewiring your brain.
Who do you want to be?
Remember that neuroplasticity requires reach, repetition, effort, attention, complexity,
and health.
Reach to Rewire.
I would love to hear from you all about how this works or
doesn't work.
Questions I can help with.
Here are various ways to get in touch with me.
And some of my business cards are up here on the corners of
the stage and by that video camera in the back.
I would love to hear from you how all this works.
Reach to Rewire.
Thank you so much for coming.