Yeah, are we good?
Cool.
OK, so I thought I'd prepare for this talk as much as possible.
So I got it all done a few days early,
and I left my power cord at home.
So I borrowed a laptop so things might go wrong.
Let's just see.
So yes, my name is Tameem Mansoonyadis.
I'm the creative director at Ninja Theory.
And one year ago in Cologne.
I did a talk called the Independent AAA Proposition, which was a theory of a new model of development
that we wanted to try out.
I don't know if any of you guys were here for that talk.
We have a quick show of hands.
Okay, quite a few.
Great.
So now we're a year in, and so I want to give you an update of how it's gone.
We're about to enter the full production phase of the project.
So the jury is still out as to whether the independent AAA model will work or not, but
you could say I'm quietly confident at this stage.
Just for those who don't know us very well.
We're what I would call a mid-sized development, a console developer.
We're based in Cambridge, England, and we're working on several projects.
And some of them are large projects, and Hellblade, in this instance, is a very small one.
So over the past 15 years or so, we've created about five console titles, and we've collaborated
with Avalanche Studios and Disney on Disney Infinity 2 and 3.
So we are effectively in the AAA console space.
Myself, I've been making games for 20 years,
15 years of which is at Ninja Theory as a programmer, designer,
and now creative director.
So I've seen a few shifts in the industry that are quite big,
and I feel like this one, the digital transition,
is going to be the biggest one yet.
So for many people, digital means alternative models.
So it might mean free to play, or indie, or mobile,
or new genres like MOBAs.
But I'm here to really promote a model that I think
has been largely absent, which we call independent AAA,
for lack of a better term.
It means doing what we're good at, what we're used to,
what we're experienced at, high production values,
but with the independence and ethos of indie development.
And our new game, Hellblade, is going to be released sometime in 2016,
and it represents our first attempt at this model.
So, to summarize why we're wanting to explore different models,
I'll very briefly cover what the model is and move on.
I mean...
I think the AAA retail model, there's nothing wrong with it per se.
You get fantastic games that come out, but effectively every game is a blockbuster.
It's like if there was a movie industry where every movie was an Avengers movie or a spin-off.
It's not good for developers that are smaller in scale.
Largely these are games that are done by internal studios that scale up to 100, 200, 300 people.
And one of the questions I always had is, why is this the case?
And the best answer I can come up with is that it comes down to the price point of games.
Like the retail model is like, I think of it like a grumpy old grandpa that doesn't want to change his ways.
It's got to cost 60 euros or 60 dollars or however much it is.
And that's that. And it's got to be that way because it's always been that way.
And so games have to compete on size.
They compete on features.
And they have blow-by-blow features
in each subsequent game.
And this has resulted in what I think is an enormous checklist.
I think this is what you have to do these days
to pitch a AAA game.
You have to cover all these bases
before you can even think about what is unique about the game.
It's a strategy I call the Go Big, Go Home, which someone from, I think, EA once told me.
So it's no coincidence that we are seeing fewer and bigger games succeed,
many of which actually do seem quite similar to each other.
So.
This is a little bit of a sad slide.
This is from 2006 to 2012, so it's not even current.
But it's hundreds of developers have disappeared
over the last few years.
Very good developers as well.
Not all of them because they made bad games.
And in some cases, that's true.
But in other cases, they just don't fit into this model.
And if I was to highlight some of my favorite games
of a few years ago, I don't think any one of these games
would be published these days under the retail model.
They just simply don't have enough to them
to compete with the big franchises that
are out there today.
And I feel like you can call it survival of the fittest,
but I really think there's.
Evolution never really was survival of the fittest, it was survival of the most adaptable.
And when the model is not adapting, then these studios, they die because they don't fit into a particular model.
of the industry.
So I do think that digital gives us an opportunity
to reverse this trend somewhat, to revive games
that have been off our radar for a long time.
A lot of teams that have gone away,
there were teams that were functioning well together,
really experienced people that knew how to work together
and knew how to craft amazing experience.
And those teams have been split up.
And in most cases, they're not going to get back together.
So I think there is a loss there, but I also think that there is a lot of promise still to come.
So this is where I see the independent AAA model, for us at least.
On the one hand you've got indie games which are...
I'd say most of the innovations are coming from these days.
Most of the interesting concepts are coming through from the indie scene.
And on the other hand, you've got the big franchises, the AAA in quality.
I'd like to try and find a space in between this.
We want to make games that look stunning, that are, you know, we're known for our storytelling
and production values and we want to keep that.
But simply put, we do want to make games that are
smaller and more focused. So hence the phrase
half the size, half the cost. And size can be length of game or it could be
the feature set that you have in the game. It's kind of...
open to interpretation. But the idea is, you know, we're used to buying stuff for about
25, 30, 40 euros, you know, t-shirts and DVDs and Blu-rays and things, so I don't really
understand why we impose such a big financial commitment of our players.
I think the idea perpetuated that you must go big or go home, I think of it as a fallacy.
And I think that fallacy has been proved wrong when the indie scene started to blossom.
Of course some of these games were amazing, of course they sold, and of course they found
an audience.
Now the story goes that you can either be indie, super low budget, or AAA, and there's
nothing in the middle.
That's a perpetuated statement or fact by a lot of people, a lot of publishers, and
I simply do not believe it.
So we want to chuck out as much of the baggage that really comes with AAA retail and focus
on the areas that we love as a studio.
An affecting character journey, stunning art,
and some great action.
Which brings us to Hellblade.
So given that independent AAA is about creating diverse games,
you should consider this as simply one case study.
It's the only one I know.
Although a lot of what I talk about is specific to Hellblade,
I think you should take the ethos forward to whatever games
you may be making or considering.
And right now, we've just finished a vertical slice
demo of the game.
And from that, we made a trailer.
So I'd like to show you the trailer
so you know what we're talking about.
Darkness is a disease, a rot that takes hold and spreads to every part of me.
And I fear I will follow in your footsteps.
I am alone and scared. I beg for your guidance.
Before the darkness takes me.
Few would brave such a desperate journey into darkness.
But it isn't bravery that drives Senua.
Senua...
Only those afraid of death would use such terms.
Senua's fear runs far deeper.
They know you're weak.
Get up and fight.
You're pathetic.
Control the fear.
Let it pass through.
Remember his words.
I'm going to save you.
Run!
Okay.
Thank you.
So I want to cover a little bit about the model itself and how we're going about doing it
and how we came to this conclusion.
So this chart has various budgets for AAA retail games that are not uncommon.
Usually independent developers are at the bottom of the food chain.
developers in general are at the bottom of the food chain when it comes to the royalties and upside.
Retailers come first, distributors, platform holders, publishers, they all take their cut.
And then once they've all taken their cut, then the developer has to repay the development fees plus a percentage.
It's... so that's why it's very difficult.
It's a very difficult business for an independent developer
to make royalties on.
In effect, we're like the post-industry in films.
We survive project to project,
and there's a chance of a breakout hit,
but it's very unlikely.
I mean, it's...
I've heard it's less than 5% of games
make royalties for the developer.
I don't even know if it's that high,
to be perfectly frank.
So in order to make a go of it, we want to compete by undercutting AAA price points by half.
For a small fry developer like us, that means digital distribution, where we can cut out as many of the middlemen as possible.
But the digital market is just not as big as the retail market.
There's not as many people on there, at least on the console side.
And it's very difficult to get figures of how many people are out there.
People generally don't seem to share those figures.
So what we did was we thought, OK, what's a reasonable best estimate of a break-even,
like in terms of sales?
Say we do it at half the price of AAA.
What's a good estimate?
And so we came up with 300, 300,000 units across multiple platforms.
It's tough, but it's achievable.
It feels like it's a good, ambitious number to go for.
So the price with the break-even suggests a very low budget,
probably comparable to a high-end indie budget,
and nowhere near a AAA standard.
But there is an advantage to digital,
which means you have a longer tail.
So I think that there is some other things
that we can play to our advantage.
So a budget of about 15 people for two years is what it equates to.
This is far lower than the kind of development team size we have been used to, and it's incomparable
to the team sizes you are seeing in this current generation.
It didn't seem possible or feasible to try and hit AAA quality with 15 people,
but there was reason for optimism.
I mean, tools have been getting a lot better.
I mean, Unity, UE4, productivity, the experience of the team.
Like, we seem to be getting a lot faster.
Heavenly Sword took nearly five years to make.
When we did DMC, we did it with half the people in half the time.
And so I think, so we simply don't know what a small,
well, we simply didn't know what a smaller team
was capable of achieving.
So I would say take this slide a little bit
with a pinch of salt.
It might be optimistic thinking.
It's not very scientific.
But let's start with the assumption
that you need about 100 people
to make a current AAA game.
Let's say you reduce the scope of the game by half.
Let's say that that reduces your development size by 30%.
I mean, not 50% because there's always fixed costs.
So you've got 70 people left.
And when you're working with a publisher,
there's always changes in feedback.
And I estimate that it's probably about 15%
of development time is spent.
rearranging the project to suit the publisher's needs.
I'm not being mean or nasty.
I think the publisher has to respond to what their audience wants,
and you have to respond to the publisher.
So that figure comes down.
Now, let's say you use middleware like Unity or UE4,
and you say to your team,
don't change anything.
All right, change one thing, but don't change anything else.
And you stick to it.
I think it is possible to save, like there's an enormous saving to be made there.
It's pretty much the approach we're taking on Hellblade.
There's three programmers on the team, and for the first six months or so there were
no programmers on the team.
Management overheads, this includes things like managers, producers, communication in general.
There's a lot of inefficiencies that can be saved there.
So you see where I'm going with this.
Eventually, it's not that unreasonable to arrive.
at a number like 15. Obviously, I've massaged the figures to reach at 15 because isn't that
convenient, but the point is made. At the bigger the team sizes, you start to come up
against resistance, air resistance, and the more you put in, the less you get out.
So what does a team look like? Now, things we found. So in a 15-man team, it's sort of
meaningless to have the concept of hierarchy, leads and bosses.
I mean, when you've got one guy making the art for the whole of the world,
what's the point of calling him a lead?
Or rather, actually, we call everyone a lead,
because everyone's in charge of their area.
So in our team, there was a little bit of an epiphany partway through that.
Everyone's a lead. No one has managerial authority over each other.
Everyone has different responsibilities, so I have a creative direction responsibility as an art director.
But that doesn't make me, or I'd like to think, it doesn't necessarily mean that I'm everyone, the people's boss,
and I have to tell them off when they come in late.
I don't really care how people arrange and do their work,
as long as we're all stepping together and we do it out of a place of mutual respect.
and trust.
So we do rely on experience, ambition, and resourceful inventiveness of every member
of the team to come up with solutions to old development problems.
And it really did take a while.
It took nine months maybe, nine months to a year for people to kind of settle into this
kind of way of thinking.
that you really do have to take responsibility and you really do have to do things off your own back and
there has been
shuffling of the team. There have been people that have joined the team that didn't, that left the team,
that it didn't suit them.
And one of the reasons is that everyone on the team
has to effectively do a couple of different jobs,
two or three different jobs.
So you need polymaths.
And the industry has been specializing people.
We've been focused on specializing people
into very narrow disciplines.
And it's tough to then ask that person,
we also need you to do this and the other,
when they don't have much experience
or knowledge in that area.
So we have wound up with 15 people that are very experienced.
It's turned out that way.
Okay.
So I want to give you a good example of how limits can drive innovation and solutions.
And our approach to...
building environment art in this case.
So there's one environment artist, Dan,
and he's in charge of creating the whole of the world
of Helheim, which is the setting of the game.
And it's a large world, that's a mere section of it.
So he started to research ways of building the world
with kit parts, which isn't new,
building worlds with kit parts,
but strangely, something we've never really done before.
Looking at things like decals and different methods of using the same decals across large areas.
Finding ways of creating procedurally generated content, or in this case, blueprints.
Writing blueprints. That's very technical.
So that makes the job of populating the world a lot easier.
Finding new ways of creating texture maps that may involve some procedural texture map,
some of it's modeled, some of it's hand drawn, and combining them in ways that look rich
and don't look like the world's full of repeated patterns.
We've just got a 3D scanner, a handheld 3D scanner, that we're using to also scan real
world objects.
So the first year of development, the first, well, maybe nine months, has been spent prototyping
across the whole of the game.
Because when you do this, you have to, you come to the realization that you can't just
design a game and then ask 15 people to make it.
You have to work out what those 15 people are capable of.
And this is another example, more of a team effort.
This is, how do you do performance capture?
Performance capture is something that we're known for.
We did it, our first game was Heavenly Sword.
We shot it in Weta, at Weta in New Zealand.
And it's the capturing of face, body, voice.
and cameras all at the same time.
So the idea is that if a scene feels good on set,
you've already got all the data you need
to turn it into the final form.
And it's something that even AAA studios these days
don't use, don't do, because it's seen as complex or costly.
So when we buy, you know, we've cobbled together,
we've prototyped a lot, and we've failed a lot
with a lot of our prototypes.
And we've bought, a lot of our setup
is stuff we've bought from Maplin Electronics, IKEA.
Amazon. And we've tackled every stage of the kind of process from body capture phase, voice, cameras, 3D scanning,
created our own little prototype devices like this. So this is a plant pot with some LED lights and with it you can capture skin details like surface, like wrinkles and things.
So it actually turns out that it's quite fun when you start doing this stuff.
And half of it didn't work, but half of it did.
And we're using that.
So the cut scenes I'm going to show you in a bit is shot in our main meeting room with
that equipment.
Right.
So...
So, like, it's all well and good to say, yes, you can do it with 15 people for two years,
but that's still expensive, that's still a few million dollars, or euros.
How do you get the money to do that?
So last, well, a year and a half ago or so, when we were showing Hellblade around, there
really isn't much, there really isn't many, much in the way of...
a model to fund this. We went to publishers, but publishers, their policy is generally
to own IP. So that straight away, that's the first question we would ask. Is your policy
to own IP? Yes. Okay.
So there's also Kickstarter. About this time, Kickstarter started to get some negative press.
We didn't want to go down that road because we feel like the only thing that we own, that we carry from our previous games,
is the following that we have from our fans and gamers.
So we didn't want to try and prove an unproven model and kind of risk the goodwill of the only really tangible thing we do have.
So we made a choice to not go down the Kickstarter route.
It might be something that we do in future, but I want to feel confident that we can actually
pull this off.
Early access is another thing that came up, and it wasn't for us.
Not in a story game.
We can't put out a broken story.
We don't want to give away any spoilers.
It's not for us.
So where did we get the money?
Some of it was savings, like a good chunk of it was just savings that we've had in the bank.
We took out a good sizeable loan, which we'll have to pay back.
We've managed to get some grant money, which has been very useful.
More on that in a sec.
In the UK, there's a 20% tax break, and that certainly helps.
But another thing you can do is, when you're going to service providers,
maybe it's art outsourced houses or localization or whatever,
a lot of these studios actually would prefer to get a back-end deal,
a percentage of your royalties, rather than a front-end payment.
It's something publishers don't generally do for service providers,
but for us it helps, it helps enormously.
And in terms of additional SKUs and DLC and expansion,
with this long tail of digital, I
think it's more reasonable to put off those costs
and bootstrap them as the game comes out.
So hence, we're targeting two platforms initially,
PlayStation 4 and PC.
But we will hope to take it on to more platforms.
And then lastly, there's a shop.
We're putting our finishing touches to a shop.
We've never sold anything directly.
So that's going online, and we'll see how that goes.
We're going to sell t-shirts and all the usual stuff
you might get on a Kickstarter program.
And we will consider that bonus money.
So any money we make there, we'll
stick it back into the game.
So for us, doing something like this is risky.
So part of what we want to do is to stick to what we know,
know who our audience is, do the things that people like in us.
And
But having said that, I also don't think that if you're going to do something like this,
a smaller cut-down game, it's not enough to say,
remember those games that we did?
Well, we're just going to...
Well, here's a little cut-down version of it.
You know, that's not a selling point.
You have to find something better to offer.
And you think, well, how do you make something better for...
Much less. And I think this draws analogies with movies, independent movies.
I mean, you wouldn't say that something like Drive or Black Swan or whatever,
Memento, whatever your favorite indie movie is, is any better than...
You wouldn't say that those movies are worse than Avengers, Age of Ultron, would you?
It's different experiences, and you could argue that they're better.
They are better.
But that's not to say that big budget movies can't be great as well.
It's just, in gaming, there sort of isn't that equivalent.
A game that looks like a AAA game, but it's got that indie kind of feel.
It's got that independent movie kind of thematic gravitas.
So as you saw in the trailer, I mean, we touched on the idea of mental health, mental illness.
And so why did we pick that?
I mean, I think gaming is unlike any other medium in the sense that you can engage an
individual's undivided attention for hours at a time.
And players can embody the main character,
making choices, taking action.
I mean, this is what makes gaming such a powerful medium.
And it's a tool through which you
can see the world through another person's eyes.
And we don't often really exploit that.
So the mental health theme came because I was interested in the subject.
I have a personal interest in the subject.
I've got a personal interest in the mind, creativity.
It's stuff I do outside of games. I like reading up on that stuff.
And it led me to reading about psychosis and schizophrenia.
And I wondered, like maybe a lot of people might do,
what that would look like.
When that person is talking to nothing, do they actually see someone?
So I went to find out, I read about it, I saw videos that represent what it's like
and it's truly, truly shocking, but also amazing that our brains can create
such fantastical concepts, imagery and belief systems
that make someone believe that there's a demon in their room and see them.
that's staring at them at night, or that you can hear someone shouting at you, speaking
to you, a voice, 24 hours a day, and you can't stop it and control it.
So I wanted to...
find out more, and I thought games is a good medium to do this.
And I felt like it's a taboo subject, and it doesn't need to be.
A lot of people get help, a lot of people recover, a lot of people deal with it.
It shouldn't be a taboo when I would pretty much bet that
everyone in this room has been touched by it,
either directly or indirectly, at some point in their lives.
So one way to get over a taboo is to make it public, to talk about it.
Obviously incredibly nervous about putting out that trailer and kind of announcing that
the theme is serious mental health conditions.
The response has been as good as we possibly could have wanted or imagined.
It feels like there's a lot of gamers that
are familiar with mental health issues, and they saw this as a game that acknowledges
what it's like, or acknowledges their struggles, if you like.
And where some... it's not all been positive, some people have been negative, they felt
offended, really offended by the fact that we're taking a subject like that and making
a game out of it.
Many times when people have expressed that on comments, YouTube comments or whatever,
others have jumped in and said, well actually...
I'm in this camp and I think that it's a good thing to try and tackle.
People have got in touch with us directly about it and we've responded directly to them.
We've engaged with them.
We want to know what they're worried about.
We want to know if they'll tell us what their experience is and we're being very open and
sincere about our communication on this front.
So I'd say for now, we've been given the benefits of the doubt, and it's something that we have to
understand that this isn't a free pass to do whatever we want.
Early on in development, we contacted a psychiatrist.
His name is Paul Fletcher.
He's a psychiatrist and professor of health neuroscience at Cambridge University.
He was fascinated by the potential of games.
He came to the studio, talked to us.
He presented the latest...
scientific or neurological model of the mind.
He related what people's experiences are like.
He produced research papers and condensed them down in a way we could understand.
And he's been involved for a few months, coming into the office,
looking at what we're doing, giving us advice.
And Senua is largely, the main protagonist Senua,
is largely a character that's formed because of his input.
And so I'd like to show the cutscene that we,
the test shoot, the test cutscene that we shoot
to try and represent some of that.
I'm not turning back.
It took months to get here.
Well, maybe, but I made my promise.
We'll all die someday.
It's getting dark.
I'll continue tomorrow.
You're afraid of the dark.
I'm being patient.
Getting closer to him.
I hope so.
You're sure it's safe here?
Yes.
Nobody followed us.
Be careful.
I know.
I just wish I could rest a little.
shit
someone's here
This makes things quickly understandable.
Thank you for watching!
So, there's one charity that has helped us enormously.
It's a charity called the Welcome Trust, which possibly you've not heard of,
but it's the second biggest charity in the world after Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation.
I think they give out something like a hundred, no, a billion dollars a year for research,
but also a portion of that is given to...
movies, arts, and games for projects that try to further the understanding and science of it.
So they gave us a very small grant at the beginning and that allowed us to work
deeper with Professor Paul Fletcher and create, get that far, create that cutscene.
Since then we've received a larger award and
This was, this helped us enormously and what they offer is like, what they want us to do
is to make an entertaining, compelling experience, a game.
And what they want and what they think they can help us with is to try and represent
the experiences of peoples and the scientific theories behind it in a truthful way.
So for us it's a win-win. It's good research.
It means we can make a more believable character and a more believable experience in the world.
And because of their backing, we now have...
It's easier for us to approach mental health organizations and charities.
So one of the things we've done recently is we met with a group of service users
who have had very serious psychotic experiences in the past or currently.
And we showed them our vertical slice and played through.
through it with them. And they gave us feedback on how their experiences relate to it or how
it doesn't relate to it. And they gave us a lot of encouragement to continue forward.
And they were very excited. It was a really nice experience. They were very excited and
thrilled to be involved. And we're going to continue to be involved with them intimately
for the next year.
So, really, Wellcome has introduced, has opened up
doors to us that we otherwise wouldn't have had open.
And Ian Dog, I'm sorry, I can't, I don't know,
I can't pronounce his surname.
Ian Dog-dog-dog-dog-dog-don, I think it is,
is the Creative Partnerships Manager,
and they're on the lookout for games that try
and further the understanding of science or health.
So, it's worth looking into,
if that's an area you're working in.
OK, so one thing we did after our meeting with the service users
is to try and put some of their...
thoughts and experiences into the game,
like rapid prototyping, try and figure out
if we can represent what they see and hear better.
So what we have here is a video that shows some quotes,
some statements made from some of the group,
but also from a wider range of feedback
that Professor Paul gave us, and where we're at.
I mean, we've only been doing this for a couple weeks now,
so it's something where we want to.
We're very excited about it. We want to push forward as far as we can.
As we all know my heart is so, I'll be so far away
Don't you know I want to feel deeper
I could never know how you grow, all these days are killing me
Now I see deep in me insanity does unfold
I just wanna feel, I just wanna feel deeper, deeper
As you know my heart is so, I feel so far away
Don't you know how I wanna feel deeper?
I could never know how you grow, all these days are killing me
Feel like this, read like this, I just wanna live, that's all
I just wanna feel, I just wanna feel deeper
I just might feel, I just might feel deeper, deeper.
So I personally can't wait to keep doing this and showing it back to the group and getting
people's points of view and getting their feedback.
And what came out of some of those meetings is the flip side to the more horrific side
of things that we're used to seeing.
The idea that sometimes it can be stunningly beautiful.
For some service users, they wouldn't change a thing.
So the final part of our strategy is open development.
So even if we're able to make a compelling game
and complete it under the independent AAA model,
there really still is a high chance of commercial failure
if we can't raise awareness.
And like most Indies, we don't have.
marketing and PR budget.
And so this is partly why we're being open about our development.
And the way we're doing this is we've released 13 video diaries so far,
one per month, each around seven to nine minutes long,
to show people how we're making Hellblade.
And we do these in-house.
It's not expensive. It's someone with a Canon camera and a microphone and a copy of Vegas.
It's each episode covering a different topic and it's got a loyal following now.
It's something we hope to build over the months.
And as well as that, we're doing Q&A and social media.
With the press, we're letting them just come and visit us.
So there's very little that we are hiding from the press.
In fact, the only thing we're hiding from the press is the actual story itself.
They have access to the full team.
They can talk to anyone, unsupervised,
whoever they want on the team.
And we're confident that they come away feeling impressed.
But also, they come away with something different each time,
because they each come at different points
in development.
And it's resulted in a few game covers.
I think that's quite.
That's been quite remarkable for a game, for us anyway,
for a game so early in development.
So, I mean, what we want to achieve with this whole thing
is, first and foremost, we want to make a great game.
I mean, we're in it for that.
And we want to offer a new experience, something
that we haven't created before and gamers haven't experienced
before.
So, really, this does mean striving for financial independence so that we can strive for creative independence.
And we hope that being open will inspire other developers like us, or students, or whoever's out there,
to help make gaming a more diverse and exciting space.
We have nothing to gain by being secretive about it,
oh sorry, nothing to lose by being secretive about it,
and so far we've gained a lot from being open about it, in terms of support.
People like Sony, Epic, Vicon.
NVIDIA, all of them feel sorry for us in some ways, I guess you could say, and have
supported us in various manners.
And I think actually, you know, part of the reason they're helping us is because they
want to see a bigger ecosystem.
Vicon want to see their low-end motion capture equipment used by more developers, not just
the high-end things.
You know, everyone's got an interest in there being more games, more exciting games made
by more people.
We're not taking away anything from AAA publishing.
We're not taking anything away from the indie scene.
We just want to create a full, rich landscape of gaming.
And we do that by being open about it.
Because it's no good us just saying, yeah,
for a few million dollars and 13 or 15 people,
you can make games.
We want to show also how we're doing it.
And it might not work, and if it doesn't work,
there'll be someone out there that looks at us and goes,
well, that's where you went wrong.
We'll do it better.
And that's fine.
There's a high risk of embarrassment and failure
of being open, but I think there's an even bigger
risk of being closed.
With that, I mean, if you do want to follow Hellblade
and what's going on, it's easy to find out.
But thank you very much for your time
and this being the last session of the day.
We probably have time for a few questions
if anyone would like to ask them.
But thank you very much.
Thank you.
Hi, it's the first time I heard of the game.
Can you describe a little bit more the sort of mental illnesses the protagonist is suffering?
So, yes, okay, so what kind of mental illnesses does she have?
So what's important to say is that this is a journey not about mental illness, it's a
journey about Senua with her particular...
because it's different for everyone. So with that, we've modeled it on cases of psychosis.
So you could say there's symptoms like hallucinations, visual and aural hallucinations, anxiety,
And there's a term like schizophrenia, I'd hesitate myself to say she has schizophrenia
because it's a diagnostic term that actually it means a collection of symptoms and it can
include hallucinations, anxiety, depression, it can include a whole series of things.
Yep, another question over there?
I was wondering, you mentioned you were a middling studio of like 115 people, but you
only have 15 people working on Hellblade right now.
So once you succeed, because let's say that you will succeed, because we want you to,
do you see transitioning into like seven parallel teams all doing this sort of smaller scale
projects?
I don't know.
When you're working in the big AAA space,
you have a lot of people dedicated to that.
And that's great, because you've got secure employment
for a lot of people.
But you're only one green light away from losing that.
And I want to make sure that we have a backup.
Like, I want to make sure that we create
some projects that we own.
I'd like to repeat it, is the short answer.
And I think probably the best strategy
is to have a balance of the two.
Any other questions? Let's see, there's one hand up right at the back and another one in between.
Hi, the art style that you've chosen, is that a conscious decision in terms of one person being able to create that world, you know, rather than the kind of...
setting. Was that something that's conscious because of the constraints of the project
or is it more just to do with the narrative itself?
Yeah, so I would say the art style is more influenced from our past games. Games like
Heavenly Sword and Enslave. I wanted to create a fantasy setting. It's kind of our heritage.
But I didn't want to go down the tropes of, you know, Lord of the Rings and things like that.
And I see the mind as the ultimate creator of fantasies. So, in essence, the game feels real,
like it feels like a historical piece. It's a Celtic warrior going to Norway,
fighting a war. But the fantastical elements come from her own mind.
So everything is pretty dark and grim and real in that sense.
If you mean, if by real you mean present day reality,
I prefer fantasy because I think with fantasy you can get away with
dropping people's prejudices in a way.
You can approach subjects that, in our environment,
we immediately put up barriers and say,
well, we've already got our barriers up.
And I think fantasy can do that,
like George Orwell's 1984
and George Romero's Dawn and Day of the Dead.
These are fantasies that let you see the world differently,
and I like that.
It's one step removed.
Okay, we've got one more, we've got another question there.
Hello, thanks for the presentation. I actually wanted to ask you the question regarding the
management that there is, the team management question.
So in every team there are sometimes, you know, like, argues in a good way on something.
So how do you come to a conclusion in the team where, you know, like, everybody is responsible for his part and...
So you have a team that...
No, like you showed the scheme of your team of 15 people, everybody is responsible for his own part.
But if sometimes, well, in every team sometimes there are argues on something, like a project, how do you resolve that?
If they are arguing against it or something like that.
So if in a small team someone doesn't want to play ball or there's arguments and stuff.
I don't have a solution. I think when people argue, and people do argue sometimes, and I speak to them, it's never...
I don't sit them in a room together and tell them what's what.
Everyone's a responsible adult and they've got to work out a way to work together.
As long as everyone has a good intention, it works.
If somebody fights against a model that says, I don't believe this can work, there's no
way.
I haven't found a solution to that.
And inevitably, it leads to them not being on the project.
I'm not a producer.
I'm not a particularly good manager, I would say, as well.
Like, I don't know if there's a better way to deal with it.
But I haven't found a better way, is the honest answer.
OK, let's take one more, and then we're done.
We can go for some beers.
You mentioned that your system should be a role model for upcoming projects and other publishers.
But your team has got huge experience in making video games and you've got specialists working on the game.
How could this kind of a system work with indie gamers who don't have that much experience or...
I think what makes independent projects interesting is the subject, is the theme, is the hook.
In our case, there's a very clear story-based, character-based differentiator, you could
say.
In other games, it's more mechanics-based.
I think with projects like, with platforms like UE4.
You can make absolutely stunning, beautiful art
without having to go for realism.
I think the aesthetic is important,
but it doesn't have to be an aesthetic that demands that level of...
detail and work in it. We're doing that because it's one of our advantages of being experienced,
so we're throwing every advantage we have out there. But I don't think this game could be said,
for example, you couldn't say that this game is more beautiful than Journey. So there's a
difference between the aesthetic and the production values that are needed to go,
the production that needs to go into it. But make the idea special is the cool thing.
All right, well, thank you very much.
It's been a pleasure.