I work at a place called Mount Sinai.
It's a hospital.
For those of you who haven't come across it before,
it's a hospital system in New York City.
There are eight hospitals, several hundred clinics,
tens of thousands of clinicians, and millions of patients
that go through Mount Sinai every single year.
And my role at Mount Sinai is to run a place
that we call the Abilities Research Center.
And we really built the Abilities Research Center
because of a couple of horrifying statistics,
and I'm gonna run those by you in rapid fire
just to give you a sense of where we come from.
The first one.
It came out in Forbes magazine in 2016 and it was about health technology companies.
They said that 98% of digital health start-ups are zombies.
What they meant by zombies was that 98% of digital health start-ups were failing before
they got to touch a human being.
You know, on average, these companies were raising a few million dollars a piece,
and then 98% of them would die before they actually got to help someone.
When you think about the fact that...
The health technology industry right now is around $85 billion a year, and I think
the NIH budget is around $35 billion a year.
That's a tremendous waste of money on technology that could actually be helping people.
So that was the first thing that really got our attention.
The second thing that got our attention was that in the pharmaceutical industry we've heard of this concept of the valley of death.
This idea that to take an idea in healthcare from the moment that you conceive of it,
the moment that you're like, I've got something and I want to develop it further.
all the way over to the point where it's actually in common clinical usage,
that period of time is 17 years in the United States.
And this is not, we're not talking about medicine here.
We're talking about an app. We're talking about, you know,
We're talking about very, very common technology,
and it takes this long to cross the valley of death.
Obviously there are a lot of issues with this.
First and foremost, who is still using the same phone
that they were using 17 years ago?
In fact, who had a phone 17 years ago?
Let's start there.
This is the problem with integrating technology into healthcare.
So, the mission of our lab and our space is to take technologies and rush them through
clinical trial protocols, get them in front of the FDA, have the right conversations,
and get them into the hands of clinicians as quickly as is humanly possible and is responsible to do so.
And ever since we started the lab,
we've had a lot of clinical trials starting up,
coming out of the lab,
and they range from everything from
the simplest of mobile app technologies.
Just gonna give you a quick example.
This is a technology that has been,
the name has been changed, it's now called WellPath,
but it is a app for suicide prevention,
where what we have shown is that
when people who are at risk of suicide use this app,
They can experience a 35% reduction in negative emotions
that bring on suicidal thoughts
within two minutes of interacting with the app.
So we're talking about point of care emotion regulation.
So we're rushing this through clinical trials as we speak
and working with, pardon me?
It's called WellPath, yep.
And it follows the PATH technique,
problem adaptation therapy by,
a psychologist called Dimitris Chiosas.
So this would be an indication of a low-tech technology that we're working with.
Right on the other end of the spectrum, this is a technology called a stentrode.
This is developed by a neurosurgeon at Mount Sinai.
And what we're looking at right now is an endovascular stent,
something that ordinarily goes into your blood vessels and holds them open,
but it has electrodes built into it.
So this technology will go into the superior sagittal sinus,
which is the blood vessel you're seeing it go into now.
And as it is withdrawn,
It will heal into the blood vessel.
So you're about to see what happens
over a period of a few days.
Once it's healed into the blood vessel, it can actually record brain activity.
Very, very similar to something like EEG, but internally, so there's no sort of sensors
getting knocked off or external noise affecting the recordings.
Once you're recording EEG, we can implant it into someone with, say, ALS, who can only
communicate with eye movements.
And rather than having them communicate at a rate of two words per minute,
because they need to look at the letter that they want,
hover over that letter, and then wait for the hover to initiate a click.
They can look at the letter that they want, think, click, and the system will click for them,
accelerating their communication rate to about 10 words per minute. So that's the goal of a project
that we'll be starting at the end of this year in our first in-human trials with this technology.
So that's kind of the scope of the projects that we work on, all the way from, you know,
Mobile apps all the way out to implantables, injectables, and really fun technology.
I really think we got a cool job because we just get to play all day long with fun tech.
But...
Today's talk is about pain.
So one of the projects that I'm really proud of and excited
about is some of the work that we're doing with pain.
Unless you've not been paying too much attention
to the global conversation recently,
pain is a big problem, especially
in Western countries, especially as it
pertains to the opioid crisis and the way
that we manage pain currently, especially chronic pain.
And I wanted to take a real big step back, because typically when I'm talking about the
role of virtual reality and pain, you know, I sort of have to sort of run through it.
But I figured today we could take a little bit more time just to talk about how virtual
reality might help someone's pain. And we can start with the Neuroanatomy 101.
So, we have areas of the brain that are focused on
producing movement and sensing things that are coming in from the outside world.
And what we've known about the brain for a little while is that the sensory and motor areas of the
brain are actually really well organized. You can get quite a nice map of the body from the amount
of brain tissue that is assigned to each body part. And what we tend to notice is if you happen
to use a certain body part more, more brain tissue will be assigned to that particular body part.
And so in most people, what you end up with is a funny little guy like this, which is
your motor homunculus, where what you see is how many bits of brain tissue is assigned
to each body part, and they're represented by being larger in the picture if you have
more brain tissue assigned to it.
Up until around the 70s or 80s, maybe even the 90s
in some of the slower moving hospitals,
this map was thought to be static.
It never changed throughout your life.
This is you for the rest of your life.
But what we started to see was actually it did change.
So it had the potential to get better,
it had the potential to get worse,
it had the potential to always be dynamically changing
depending on what sort of trauma you were exposed to
or what sort of skills you were learning and practicing.
So, when we think about this in the context of pain, what starts to happen is, let's say,
for instance, you have an injury to your hand.
And you have chronic hand pain as a result of that injury.
What starts to happen with your motor and sensory representations is not only do they
start to...
react to the hand pain in a way that you start avoiding movements, you start using the hand
less, you start to learn to use the other hand, for instance, because you know that
using this hand will hurt.
But as well as that, you also start to fear using the hand.
So a really great researcher by the name of David Butler actually showed that, and his
colleague Laura Mimosly showed that.
When they put a whole bunch of chronic pain patients into an MRI scanner and asked them
to imagine using the painful hand, and then they had a whole bunch of blinded radiologists
reading the brain scan and trying to diagnose the patient, all of the radiologists said,
oh, you brought me phobia patients, because what they were seeing were the fear centers
lighting up.
Not only do they start to see fear, but they start to see loss of that hand representation.
They actually described it in their research as blurring.
The hand representation starts to get very sort of confused.
Neurons from other representations, like your leg or your arm, start to take over your hand
representation.
What that results in is this weird dysmorphia where you don't really know where your hand
is.
What we know about chronic pain patients now is if they have chronic hand pain, even the
task of looking at a magazine and telling you if they're looking at a left or a right
hand is harder than it is for an average individual without hand pain.
So their whole relationship with their painful limb gets thrown out of whack.
And so
Once we started to think about what we could do to fix this problem, a whole bunch of clever
people started to realize that the nervous system can be tricked in lots of ways to rebuild
a relationship with the hand.
We have this whole network of neurons that are affectionately called mirror neurons.
Some people like that name, some people hate that name, but effectively what these mirror
neurons are, are a network of neurons that will fire and get excited.
whether you're performing a task or just watching someone perform a task.
So what that means is just the act of observation or just the act of imagination,
imagining you're observing something, can actually trigger a whole network
that is similar to the network that is triggered when you're moving,
which to some seem like a really clever way, a really clever backdoor
into the nervous system of someone who was in so much pain
that they couldn't even think.
about moving. And so a really brilliant scientist by the name of V.S. Ramachandran came up with this
idea of mirror box therapy. And so his idea was for people who were missing a limb.
So they had what was called phantom limb pain
in their missing limb.
This sensation that the missing limb was still there,
maybe it was itchy, maybe it was cold,
maybe it was in a cramp,
but the point was it was there,
it was hurting or being very, very annoying,
and there was nothing that they could do about it.
And so what V.S. Ramachandran did was he said,
okay, well, I'm gonna put your missing limb into a box.
And I'm also going to put your intact limb over here.
And on the side of the box, there's going to be a mirror.
And when you look in the mirror, what you're going to
see is the mirror image of your intact limb.
And I want you to start scratching at it.
I want you to start stretching it,
whatever it does to give you relief.
And it was elegant, it was wonderful, it was simple.
And it really, really,
in a thousand studies out there now showing
it really, really does help a lot of people
who have phantom limb pain
and other forms of chronic pain.
But, you know, we like to be difficult, so.
It doesn't help everybody.
And we still had a problem because at Mount Sinai,
we treat a lot of people with chronic spinal cord injury.
And people with spinal cord injury have this condition.
Around 80% of people with chronic spinal cord injury
also have a condition called chronic neuropathic pain.
This is a very,
a very upsetting, intractable form of pain that is basically your injured nervous system
telling you that there is something wrong with one or many of your limbs, but there's
actually nothing physically wrong.
So what these people go through on a daily basis, and we see thousands of individuals
with this issue, is at all times, 24-7.
Their brain is telling them that their leg is in a block of ice, or is on fire, or is
unbelievably itchy, or there's bugs crawling on it, or just throbbing, and there's nothing
they can do about it.
It doesn't respond to pain management, so opioids don't work.
They have other sorts of drugs like gabapentin.
They have a varying rate of response,
and less than 30% of people respond
to medications for neuropathic pain.
And Mirabox, as much as it would be great
if we could help these people with Miraboxes,
unfortunately, they lack the basic requisite
for Mirabox therapy to work,
which is the ability to move another limb
that looks like the limb that is hurting.
So that was when we actually started thinking about maybe we could use virtual reality for this.
And it was a pretty simple idea. It seemed logical, right?
So we started playing around with virtual reality and we started creating a bunch of
hand environments and leg environments for people with chronic neuropathic pain.
And I've got to say, humble beginnings.
I'm going to show you guys some pretty embarrassing virtual reality environments here.
But, you know, these were just real simple things that people told us that they missed doing.
Playing silly games with a sibling or a friend, playing cards, driving a car.
And we used the cheapest 360 degree camera that money could possibly buy.
And we started recording all of these experiences for people so that they could throw on a headset, look down,
and after years and years of not having arms or legs moving,
actually have this experience of their arms and legs moving.
And what we've seen has been really staggering.
So what we've seen in a cohort that keeps growing,
so now we're at about 35 or so individuals
who have worked with us on this protocol.
These are all individuals who have had
spinal cord injury for at least five years.
They've been diagnosed with chronic neuropathic pain
this entire time.
They haven't changed anything about their medications for at least six months,
so we know that their symptoms are stable.
What we're seeing is that there is on average a 40 percent reduction in
their symptoms within 10 minutes of exposure to the virtual reality environment.
So this has been a really impactful intervention for them just off the bat.
And so we're really excited about this because even with a crappy environment,
we can do something. And I'm allowed to call it crappy.
You guys aren't allowed to call it crappy, but I am.
And, you know, so one of the things that we see as a really strong potential here is
this is Woody. He's one of our serial volunteers for every single project that we've ever run.
And one of the ideas is...
Well, any smartphone, Google Cardboard, and let's get this
content on YouTube, and off you go.
So with that in mind.
I want everyone to take this down.
We've got a whole bunch more crappy virtual reality
environments on YouTube right now on the Petrino Lab channel.
We're running clinical trials on the East Coast.
So if you know anyone on the East Coast who
has a spinal cord injury, who has chronic neuropathic pain,
send them our way.
And I'll put all of our contact details at the end of the talk.
If you know anyone else who is not on the East Coast,
who wants to try something out that is non-invasive,
not a medicine, and pretty easy to try out.
just direct them to this YouTube channel, get them a Google Cardboard, and the internet
will do the rest, and fingers crossed.
So what we're doing right now is, now that we've seen some really powerful initial responses
to the virtual reality, we're trying to delve into why the virtual reality works.
how we could make better with virtual reality environments,
how we can collaborate with people to make really high quality virtual reality environments,
and how to keep it sustainable, and all of those things.
One of the main open questions that we have right now
about virtual reality, which we are currently testing out
in the next clinical trial that we begin in May, is why is it working?
So I gave you a whole bunch of theory about why I think it works.
And I hope I haven't biased you because there's another reason why it might work.
So the first theory is, of course, maybe we're rebuilding.
So we've got our homunculus with a blurred hand representation.
And maybe over time, as you're watching the virtual reality environments
and you're starting to take it all in,
maybe over time that homunculus is being completely repaired.
And that person has regained a healthy relationship with their limb.
And...
They're going to be okay.
But there's also another reason that it might be working,
and it could just be distraction.
So it could just be that we're creating
a home away from home for our viewers
where they just get to think about something
other than their pain,
and it's a very novel experience,
and therefore they feel this relief.
In our initial pilot trials,
what we did was in a repeated,
in a crossover design study,
we actually exposed people both to
the distractive VR and the somatic VR.
So the VR where they were actually watching hands do things,
as well as what we called distractive,
where they couldn't look down and see a body at all,
but they were kind of like a floating eye
going through an aquarium and things like that.
What we saw in our initial data was that
Both of them caused significant pain-relieving effects.
The somatic environment caused more
of a pain-relieving effect, but it wasn't significant yet.
So the next study is to actually expand that
and see if we can see how things piece out over time.
The other thing that we hypothesize is that
The distraction virtual reality might just be kind of like a band-aid,
and it might stop working over time.
So if you just keep showing someone distractive content,
maybe after a while they're like,
oh yeah, well, virtual reality is kind of old hat to me now,
so I need something even more immersive or more extreme or something like that.
Whereas with the somatic environment,
maybe you actually really are rebuilding a relationship with their hand or their leg
or their painful body part.
The other thing that we're looking into in a lot of detail
is trying to understand how certain psychometric properties
of the people who are viewing the VR
actually impact their response to the VR.
So again, in the pilot study that we've done,
what we saw was that individuals who rated high
on a scale called the immersive tendency scale,
has anyone ever heard of this scale, by the way?
Couple of people, yeah?
It's really interesting.
It's this scale that actually tries to delve into
how likely you are as a person
to be drawn into a virtual reality environment.
It asks hilarious questions like,
you know, if you're walking through a room and a TV is on,
how likely are you to stop and get drawn into the TV?
You know, how scared do you get after scary movies?
Do you need to sleep with the light on
or you just forget about it immediately?
And from that, it tries to get this sort of measure
of how easy it is to immerse you.
What we saw was that people who scored high on the immersive tendency questionnaire overall
had better responses to the VR.
But we also saw on a separate questionnaire, which was the presence questionnaire, this
is a questionnaire that says regardless of all that immersive tendency stuff, just how
in the moment were you in the virtual reality environment we showed you.
In that case, and this effect was stronger than the last effect,
people who scored high on the presence questionnaire
had much stronger effects to the virtual reality environment.
So again, what we're trying to do is understand
A, how realistic do we need to get to hook everyone in?
Or how unrealistic do we need to get?
Because actually, one of the things we've been playing around with is like
Rather than trying to perfectly match skin tone and masculinity or femininity of a hand and hairiness and all of these sorts of things,
maybe we just give everyone a blue alien hand.
And so, you know, everyone is at a sort of similar level.
So these are things that we're playing around with to see what matters, what doesn't,
and how quickly we can scale this experience to sort of draw everybody in.
And it's been a really interesting experience
trying to understand how to explore agency
within a virtual reality environment.
And we really hope that this is something
that we will be able to scale out
to lots of people who are in pain.
And I can't stress it enough,
lots of people who are in pain at the lowest possible cost
because the populations that we're dealing with
in this case don't have a lot of money to spend
on solutions like this.
So that's why.
Even sometimes we get pushback when we're talking about a Google Cardboard.
That's the sort of demographic that we're dealing with.
So we're really trying to push into ultra low-cost solutions for this
because we really need it right now.
So thanks everyone for listening.
All of the work that I've been doing is supported by a lot of amazing people.
It's not just me doing all the work.
And all of those...
Things are where you can find us.
We're best at Instagram.
We're okay at Twitter.
We're not so good at Facebook.
I think we're too cool for Facebook now,
but you know, don't tell them.
But thanks a lot.
And I think we've got some time for questions.
Yes, I have a question.
Yeah.
I know everybody probably has their pet condition that they would now like you to address, so
I have pretty severe scoliosis.
And of course everybody says, nobody knows what causes it, can't possibly be cured.
All you can do is adapt to it.
Can you think of a way this could be adapted to scoliosis because it affects millions and
millions of people and it's one of those absolute dead ends in terms of the medical profession?
Yeah, so the question was about clever ways that we can treat scoliosis.
My experience with scoliosis, I don't think it's a dead end so much as it is one of those things that
Education and advocacy for real hard work doesn't get enough of a look in.
There's a lot of different causes of scoliosis, and when we're particularly remiss we call
it idiopathic because we don't know why it's happening.
It doesn't actually mean that it has no cause, it just means that we don't really understand
what's going on.
Currently, the best thing that we have for it is to do very targeted, very personalized
exercise therapy for scoliosis to strengthen the muscles that are going to, you know, sort
of push the spine in the other direction, to work on posture, to create environments
where people are constantly being reminded to draw themselves up and do all the right
things for their body.
But the problem is people lose interest in...
interventions like that very, very quickly because it's not a silver bullet.
And when I say people, I often mean physicians and clinicians,
because what they really want is to be able to say, here it is, here's the pill,
now go away and get better. But that's not the case with scoliosis.
It's a lifelong journey and it needs to be addressed consistently over time.
But so can you see, can you even imagine a VR solution,
something that would help people do that?
I think more than VR,
I don't even think we need to go as far as VR.
I think we just need, you know, RIP Connect,
but we need like motion capture systems
that give people continuous feedback
about how they're moving, walk them through exercises.
This is a perfect example of a,
A condition that would benefit from having daily exercises in front of a motion capture
camera that tells you exactly if you're doing the exercise correctly and if you're maintaining
good posture and good form.
And how cheap are those cameras right now?
Well, they just got discontinued.
So they used to be about $250.
But now they're on eBay, like $800 or $1,000 if you're lucky.
But Kinect said they are coming out with a Kinect 3.
So we'll cross our fingers.
And if the Microsoft gods are listening, we'll see how we go.
Thank you.
No worries.
This is sort of amazing, because I'm currently developing
a real-time motion capture.
virtual, somatic visualization system.
But we're deliberately taking an approach
that does not use VR headsets,
partially for inclusivity, partially,
well there are many reasons,
but I personally don't like to sweat in a VR goggle,
but we're deliberately rendering the body
that you see in an abstracted impressionistic way
so that we don't generate negative
So, you know, idealizing ourselves in ways that are not really healthy.
But I wondered, would you comment, do you think all of this sort of research is equally
applicable to a non-VR but still somewhat immersive system?
I absolutely do.
And one of our control conditions is actually viewing...
just in a 2D screen.
Because if we can do this in 2D, let's do this in 2D.
I totally agree.
I would love to talk to you about possibly being a consultant.
Yeah, for sure.
Thank you so much.
On your website, do you have information about patients?
Like, what are the requirements to be a patient?
Yes, so on the website you can link to all of the clinical trials.
The VR clinical trial is already up on clinicaltrials.gov, which will tell you exactly how to, you know,
who uh what our recruitment criteria are and who can be a who can be a patient. So you can be
functioning like I have a spinal injury I take medicine every day all the tingling burning but
I'm not in a wheelchair. I can still that's fine that's fine any anyone with a diagnosed
spinal cord injury who experiences neuropathic pain welcome in the trial thanks. Hey I was just
curious if like player interaction has been like an accelerator something that you've uh
experimented with or seen. Say that again sorry.
Player interaction has been like an accelerator for rehabilitation. Have you noticed any differences?
Player interaction as in like...
Oh, I see what you're saying. Yes, sorry. So all of the trials we've done thus far have been passive.
visualization, simply because we wanted to create the most inclusive experience for
everyone with spinal cord injury, and we have a lot of people with spinal cord injury who
can't move.
But we have done a lot of work with gamified environments in the past, and we've seen really
positive results in improving motor function and things of that nature.
In fact, we've seen them outperform conventional care.
Thank you.
So these have all been a lot better questions than mine,
but mine's more on FDA regulation
and moving forward with FDA regulation.
I know that eventually, if you're planning to get this
into a patient market in the hospital,
how would you move forward with the FDA regulation
if you haven't already and if you have?
Yeah, so I think it's a great question.
I think we've always got to be mindful
of these sorts of things.
You know, when it comes to regulation of technologies like this, it really does just come down to
A, what are you charging for it?
So in a case where we're not charging anything for it, you know, and it's not particularly
a high risk intervention, it's just watching videos.
Take care.
Give good instruction.
and don't do anything foolish.
When it comes to actually charging for something like this,
so let's say we wanted to start a business,
I think that just by creating content...
I think, you know, if there's anyone out there listening who wants to create a business out
of this, do VR Netflix and don't make any claims about it.
Don't tell people it's going to, you know...
revolutionize their pain management.
But do put it out there.
If you have 100 people sending you in videos
saying it's completely changed their life,
put those on your website
and don't make any claims yourself.
And off you go.
Again, it's not a very...
a high-risk thing that we're talking about here,
and there should be no reason for the FDA
to try and block you creating a repository
of content of limbs doing things.
That can be viewed from a third-person point of view,
so long as you're not assigning
any sort of therapeutic intent to it.
Once you get enough pilot data to actually show that you're making a difference,
different story. Go to the FDA, get an indication, because then insurance can cover it.
Then you can actually start to get doctors prescribing it and all those sorts of things.
And that's where you can start to scale more rapidly.
But in the early stages, it's just content. You're just making content.
If you have time afterwards, I'd also love to talk to you a little bit more about that.
Sure. Thank you.
Hi.
Kind of made me nervous.
So I'm from the FDA.
I'm part of a new initiative for going
towards medical mixed reality.
And so actually we have a collaboration
with MedStar Rehabilitation.
We actually last week just talked to.
The PT's working with patients with spinal cord injuries.
And one thing that they mentioned
is for the patients who are younger,
it's so easy to get them in VR.
But for the, they said they had a 56-year-old woman who
they put her in VR.
And in five minutes, she came out and she says,
that was great.
I loved it.
But that was her VR experience.
They offered to put her in some different kinds of games,
but she was like, no, that was good.
That was my VR experience.
So what would you recommend?
How can we get more patients in VR?
Yeah.
Cool.
So first of all, I just want to say
that for the last 10 minutes,
I've just totally blacked out.
So I don't know anything that I just said.
Can't be held responsible for it.
But secondly, I think it's a great question,
and I think there's no silver bullet for any condition,
least of all pain.
I was having a conversation with a VC
the other day about another pain intervention that.
We're running through clinical trials in my lab and the VC said,
I only want to invest if it's definitely going to work on at least 80% of pain patients.
And I said, well, then don't invest in anything in pain because that's just not a reasonable thing to experience.
And we have the same in all aspects of rehabilitation, whether it be robotic rehabilitation.
or gamified rehabilitation with motion capture,
or just regular old conventional OTPT.
Some people respond, other people don't.
Some people have preferences, go with their preferences.
The way that we really like to compare it
is athletic performance.
In our lab, we work with a lot of high-performance athletes.
When I have a world champion athlete that doesn't want to do a certain exercise, I find a different exercise for them.
I don't say, oh, well, stick with it because I'm the coach. That doesn't fly.
And we should keep that frame with all of our patients because when they're telling you this isn't doing much for me,
well, what that is telling me is I know I need thousands of hours of intentional work to get a satisfactory outcome.
And.
If they're not feeling it from the first session, I've got to do something else with them,
because I know right there and then it's not going to work.
Okay, we're out of time.
Okay, we'll go gather in the hall. Thank you everyone. Thanks for listening.