Hi, I'm Joan. And I'm Tom.
We are documentary filmmakers and VR creators.
We've been working on a VR documentary that's about a very personal, emotional, and non-easy subject.
Part of it is shooting interviews with people.
We chose for it initially this technique, volumetric capture,
but pretty quickly we discovered that it's not enough for us.
What we found is that it wasn't lifelike enough.
So we've had to develop a...
technique to combine 3D cinematography with volumetric video and we'll be talking about it as a part of our presentation.
Our presentation is part of the VR Entertainment track at GDC and it will be on Monday 440 p.m.
Rome Tow to South Hall.
We also have time at the Canada booth on Wednesday at 2 p.m.
So you'll be able to see a demo there. So please come to our talk. We would love to see you all. See you at GDC!