Well, so welcome.
I'm Matt Baum.
Welcome to Playing With Pride.
So this is a several years long project
to answer the question of what happens
when queer culture and game culture collide,
and particularly what that collision means
for game developers.
For the last three years, I've been gathering video interviews
with LGBT gamers, along with my partner James.
And we're going to share some stories
that we've collected today.
So, just a quick introduction about me.
I'm a writer and multimedia producer in Seattle.
I cover LGBT issues for Rolling Stone and Vice Magazine and Slate and a whole bunch
of others.
I have a podcast called The Sewers of Paris where I interview queer people about entertainment
that's changed their lives.
And along with James, my partner, we do a live show and podcast called Queens of Adventure
featuring drag queens playing Dungeons and Dragons.
So the intersection of queer and game is a big part of our lives.
So a couple of years ago, we noticed that there was this rising interest in gaming events geared towards LGBT people,
and we were curious about that. What do games have to do with sexuality?
This is a question that a lot of people were asking, not always in good faith.
So we wanted to answer that, particularly when it comes to the games industry.
James is a long-time game designer.
I worked at Capcom and LeapFrog and LucasArts and we noticed that there might be a need for
games culture and queer culture to overlap in a way that wasn't currently being met.
So we decided to ask people about that. We recorded interviews with over 100 people in their homes,
occasionally at work, asking them how games have helped them to come out, fall in love,
explore their sexuality, feel less alone. We also talked to developers about how they've
incorporated queer themes into their work.
A lot of the people that we spoke to were queer,
some were straight, some were trans, some were non-binary.
We heard a lot of deeply personal stories
about navigating between those queer worlds
and gamer worlds, particularly when it comes
to love, romance, and dating.
We also heard from gamers about needs and wants
that the industry isn't currently meeting.
And we talked to game developers about what they're doing
to meet those needs, what they're changing on their end
and changing about their practices.
So what we're going to look at today, what I'm sharing with you, is some short video clips from those conversations,
highlighting some themes that came up again and again and again.
A couple of quick notes.
These are the stories from people that we talked to. It's not the complete queer gamer experience.
There are a lot of topics that we touched on in these interviews that we just are not going to have time to talk about today.
And also, some of the folks that we talked to spoke about their experience being harassed.
They used some slurs to talk about what they experienced.
just to prepare you in case that's something that you don't want to hear.
So something that we heard from almost everybody is that when
the people we spoke to were young, gaming was considered safe. It was fun.
It was something that brought people together.
And then for a lot of people that changed when they wanted to share their
love of games with queer friends,
or when they wanted to talk about sexuality or sexual orientation or gender
identity with gaming friends.
And these two worlds just seemed incompatible.
You know, I thought I was...
an outcast, there was some kind of freak, because I didn't know any gay people and there was nothing on the telly.
So it was like, what's wrong with me?
When I was a kid, all my friends were like the nerdy boys.
And the very fact that I was also into the same nerdy stuff that they were into
made them assume that I wasn't gay.
And if you talked about gay stuff, it was not okay.
I'm sitting there like I have all these likes and loves and it's like I didn't really have a place to really express and even in like the anime groups and whatnot, it was kind of like,
you don't like it the way I like it. You guys are staring at like all the big, all the girls with big boobs in the anime and I'm just like, who's that hottie guy over there?
I mean, before I was even attracted to anyone, I was being called faggot.
I just knew that it was bad. And it was something that I should feel guilty about and I tried to not be. So I guess I kind of closed myself off from my parents.
and closed myself off from my peers.
So it made me, you know, my parents copped and commented
that I was a hermit,
because I would just be up in my room all the time
playing my video games.
But that was, that was the way I coped,
although I didn't think of it as coping at the time.
My friend had completely abandoned role-playing games.
He no longer wanted anything to do with me.
And so I was completely, completely baffled.
And I would be asking, so what happened between you and your friend?
And I don't know.
He just doesn't want to talk with me.
Because, like, you kind of feel like an outsider in both worlds,
because it's like, oh, well, I'm not straight,
but like, I'm not completely gay, so like I'm not gay enough.
I have this like gaming aspect of my life.
And in a way, I like I have the queer.
you know, aspect of my life and like, you know, never the twain shall meet sort of thing.
I can either be black, I could be gay, or I could be a nerd.
And I did for a really long time feel like that I kind of had to like hide parts of myself.
Games kind of started being a lot more about like bang bang and like macho chess beating
and for like reasons that I can look back at now and understand, right, but at the time
I couldn't.
I started just kind of being like, well, maybe I'm just not into games.
You know, like, we have PAX East here in Boston that when you go, you sometimes are concerned
about, you know, being out and, you know, sometimes some people are being very immature,
some people being homophobic.
Other times if you just go, you know, to do other events, like, for example, going to
Gay Pride, folks are mainly more focused on kind of either kind of the more body conscious
aspects of pride, looking good, or...
Um, you know, or we don't necessarily get to really talk about people's interests beyond just being gay.
Yeah, the two never overlapped.
In the gay community, there's just other things going on, and so they don't necessarily...
Not always the best time to pull out a board game and be like,
Hey, guys, want to play Risk?
My biggest gamer friends were all straight men.
Which, I mean, not a bad thing. Straight men are people too, and we should give them all the love they deserve.
But, like, there was definitely, like...
we could only talk about video games,
like, talk about relationship stuff with little, like,
uh, you're into girls, I'm into dudes, like, mm.
I think I still feel like that
Tara Brantford character from Final Fantasy,
where that, I don't feel like,
when I'm at a gay bar, that I fit in there,
because everybody's excited about
a Britney Spears video being on the monitor,
and I don't really care about that.
And if I talk about a game that had just come out that I'm excited about,
they don't care about that.
So I never really feel like I fit in anywhere.
Meow!
That's why I have animal friends.
So we, by the way, we could do like a super cut of all the times that interviews have been interrupted by cats in this project.
Turns out that queer people have a lot of cats.
So the feeling that a lot of those people talked about there, of being unwelcome, closed
a lot of LGBTQ people that we spoke to.
It just closed them off to games in general.
It made them feel as though gaming simply wasn't for them.
That was even my, like personally, that was my own experience.
For most of my 20s and the 2000s, I just didn't see queer people in games, and I felt like
I was intruding whenever I talked to what I thought of as real gamers.
And, you know, something that we heard from a lot of these folks that it would alienate
queer people to talk about games.
And those feelings extended into dating as well.
We heard from a lot of the folks that we visited who felt as though they couldn't bring up
games on dates for fear of alienating a potential partner.
Gaming was seen as a liability, a source of embarrassment, like you're not a real queer
if you play games, you're not a real gamer if you're queer.
And then worse, that didn't stop with rejection.
It also included harassment from other gamers.
Because sometimes with gamers, it's a little, they don't really care for drag queens.
When I started playing World of Warcraft, I was in a raiding guild, right?
Like I was in a serious, hardcore, 40-man, three days a week, spending time raiding guild, right?
And I left them because they kept using the word faggot in guild chat.
And I was like, you know, I'm done.
I was in a guild on my son's server and...
That was, anytime we didn't win, it was, that's okay, or you dumb faggot.
And I was just done.
I played World of Warcraft for a short period of time.
This was a long time before my transition.
So, identifying as female at the time,
there's plenty of bullying when it comes to female gamers.
At the time, I couldn't even fight that.
I just stopped playing.
I think I only played World of Warcraft for
maybe a week before I just completely stopped.
We also heard a lot of first-hand accounts from people working in the game industry.
A common thread was a perception that their input wasn't valued, or that bringing up LGBT
topics relating to games could negatively impact their career.
And so this next video features all people who work in games, and we asked them if they
perceived obstacles to just doing their work, and here's what they said.
If you go to GDC, or you go to any convention that is gaming or tech-focused, you don't
see people like you.
It can be very discouraging.
Growing up, video games were always for children.
And homosexuality was not proper to be exposed to children.
I just never, I just, even being in the industry, I just assumed that those were two things that were never going to be, come into connection to each other.
You know, I thought, alright, well the queer world is pride parades and all the bars and clubs and that sort of thing.
And then there's the game world where I have to be...
super serious, you know, get ready, let's make this shit.
I didn't realize there was any overlap.
So I worked at Electronic Arts,
global rookie of the year,
and I designed a game called Madden Football.
So there was,
and before that I had been like a sports reporter in school
and there was no intersection of gay life
and sports, professional sports life in that time,
like in the early 90s.
There was no, there just wasn't a thing.
Like I wouldn't bring any personal
to it. I just would just shut that down if anything got super close to personal or what
are you doing this weekend or whatever. I'm like sports. Going to PAX for the first time
really opened my eyes to this is the community where I feel most at home. But then after I
started, you know, participating in that community more, I also then started to see how I wasn't
fully at home there. That the media in that community wasn't being made.
for me? So we spoke to a lot of people about the problems that they've experienced as players or as
makers, and we also found a lot of optimism as well. So despite all those problems, a lot of
people spoke about how games could provide some measure of relief. Even though most games, even
to this day, aren't made with queer players specifically in mind,
Many of the folks that we interviewed either sought out titles that intentionally included queer people,
or they used their imagination to insert themselves into their favorite stories.
And in creating and playing as characters who reflected their interests,
queer gamers were able to find a place where those two sides of their personalities could both coexist.
And for a lot of these players, they spoke particularly intensely about the importance of character creators,
particularly about having a...
avatar that represents them in ways that they might not be ready to express in real life.
So that allowed, for example, transgender gamers to experiment with gender and sexuality
before expressing themselves, before basically affirming themselves in the real world.
There's a chance to really get into the story, get into why characters are doing things,
hopefully their motivations, and figure out kind of who I am along with these characters.
We feel like our characters in Final Fantasy really represent what we would be in a fantasy world.
They complement each other, because you're white magic, I'm black magic, you're healing and destruction.
Yeah, so I have to clean up his mess, wow.
Video games were actually kind of the first way that I kind of became comfortable with expressing other genders.
My first kind of...
gender change happened when I was someone had bought me a bootleg copy of Pokemon crystal for my birthday because it was bootleg
halfway through the game crashed and then when I rebooted my save I
Was a girl that was kind of an epiphany moment because I'm like, oh I
Like this more than I should
Peach is a big one growing up because back then she was just the princess
I was it kind of identified with her and I was just like picking the girl characters when I could
It's nice seeing yourself on the game screen and that's your avatar out there.
It's not actually you, but it's nice to kind of think it is you a little bit.
Seeing Samus and knowing that was a girl going into that, I'm like, this is really cool.
And she kicked ass.
I was actually really aware of what I was doing.
Like I'm picking her because I actually identify that way.
Favorite characters?
Um, probably Wheatley from Portal.
I tend to kind of lean toward characters that aren't really, uh,
specifically human because it's easier for me to relate to somebody who's not
specifically set into a certain gender. Like robots, they're robots. Wheatley has a male voice, but that doesn't mean he's technically male.
Myself being a female-to-male transgender, it's easier for me to kind of relate to characters like that.
Growing up, I had always chosen
my character's creation had always been male. Like it was just, oh, click!
I mean, it was really, they really were, character creators were like such a safe place where
I could just, gender could be whatever, like the character creator would allow me to make
it.
And I would always explore.
Oh, and small boobs.
Short hair.
Women, no boobs, short hair.
Big boobs.
I don't know.
I have a lot of favorite game characters.
One of them is totally cheating.
which is Fem Shep from Mass Effect.
That's cheating because a lot of what you make
that character is your choices.
You know, she starts as a relatively blank slate.
There's definitely some information filled in.
But she is very much what you make of her.
But she's so well done and she's so nuanced.
The writing and the presentation is so wonderfully done.
Easily one of my favorite characters.
Well I guess, you know, Shepard from Mass Effect.
He was a good character, he was the hero, and then just the fact on top of it that the
game allowed you to play a gay character.
So he could be the gay hero that I wanted to be.
I think I probably took a lot of my inspiration from myself when I was coming out, from characters
like Bayonetta, who are stronger and sexy.
The first time I went out as a woman and as my true self, I was...
I think I remember shaking because I was just so nervous that people were going to be so mean to me.
I think that's why avatars are so important, especially for young trans kids,
because they can create that identity in the game and live as that identity,
especially if they're not ready to do it in their actual reality.
So many of the people that we spoke to gravitated towards games that allowed them to explore
objects of their affection and to role-play romance stories.
In contrast to real-life situations where talking about gaming might cause a date's
eyes to glaze over, which is something that a lot of people spoke about, a lot of the
gamers that we spoke to found games that let them safely explore sex and attraction and
relationships.
in ways that might not have been available to them,
or that they might not have been comfortable exploring
in real life.
And for those players, the games were about much more
than just having fun.
Those games were providing a safe haven
that folks might not otherwise have,
particularly for people who live outside of a major city,
or who live in a country that might be more conservative when
it comes to dating, and might pose safety hazards
to being openly queer.
Or just to people who didn't have online support networks.
I definitely give in to the sort of like typical male power fantasy except queer.
So like with Dragon Age and Mass Effect I build sort of you know like it's like you
know build a boyfriend.
I think my Fallout character was pretty hot.
We like to make big muscle guys with beards and no hugs.
When we play Saints Row, we run around with our characters naked.
So it's all about the beards and the muscles, really.
And for me, it's inspiring because I do want to have that superhero body.
So I work hard to look like my characters.
I really love the Shepard, Kate, and Elenco romance option that was there,
but I wish y'all got to fuck more than once.
And I also wish Elenco had a beard.
And I want to see Shepard and Elenco.
on the rooftop looking at the stars in Vancouver, where he's from.
He is such a sweetie.
In Fable, you can flirt with male or female.
The storyline's amazing, too, but to have that option
until you actually have it and do it, you don't realize how much you missed
not having that.
I mentioned Fable because I think that was the first game I played
where you could actually play a gay character.
It was common. It was, you know, it was.
something I can identify with.
Like say, in Skyrim, you could totally marry a guy.
And, you know, being a gay man,
like if you had the choice to marry a girl or a guy,
of course you're gonna marry the guy.
You know, I'm playing Fallout 4 still, right now,
and right now I am in a relationship
with a feisty Irish lady.
rugged, roguish, ghoul man, a synthetic woman, and I'm currently working on impressing a certain
George Clooney-looking paladin. And that really is my idea of a perfect lifestyle.
That was a revelation because I was so, I guess, just shocked that something
that is part of my life was suddenly in this video game.
having a lot of fun with Irish rogues and ghouls and paladins and robot women.
So I think that that's the closest the video game's going to get to me, I think.
So just as a kind of a measure of how much has changed in the last few years,
when we started this project probably about four, four years ago-ish, you know, when we would have
a conversation about queer characters and games, people would be like, oh, isn't this amazing that
it was right before Inquisition came out.
And people were like, oh, there's this game coming out
that's gonna have queer relationships.
Isn't that amazing?
And then just last night, I was having a conversation
with a developer about a dating sim involving monsters,
and I asked, are there going to be,
can you have relationships with characters of any gender?
And he gave me this look like, of course.
And he was like, yeah, of course, why wouldn't you?
So just to have that be the response,
instead of like, isn't this amazing?
We're doing this for the first time.
Just in the last few years, a lot has changed.
So as the people that we interviewed felt more comfortable expressing those two sides of their personality,
the queer side and the gamer aspect, something big changed in their life.
Going from virtual relationships into real life, they found that this is something that affected their dating and romance and relationships in real life.
When they talked about games on dates, instead of being met with skepticism, they were met with enthusiasm.
And so games really changed how people were able to...
form bonds with other people.
I met my boyfriend through Baldur's Gate.
It's run this weird thread through my life.
She was in a friend's dorm room
fitting for her Padme costume from episode 2.
We met, we actually met online,
which we don't usually tell people.
Usually we say we met at a comic book shop
because there's still a lot of stigma
around people who meet online.
We met on Grindr.
Yeah, I mean, we...
didn't know we were like kind of geeks in that way at first.
Like over text, it was just like, what are you doing?
Oh, I'm, you know, playing some Final Fantasy.
Oh yeah, what's your favorite character?
And so we got into it that way and it was kind of cool.
Right now he's still underleveled so I'm helping him, you know,
gain his bearings and whatnot.
The guy I'm seeing now is very Canadian
and I met him at a board game convention a couple years ago.
So he's got, it's really funny, the first time we went to his house,
I flipped out because I saw an NES like right by his TV and I got really happy.
Like even if he doesn't play it, just knowing that it's there,
it tells me something about him, something that we already have in common.
I think finding somebody who was also a gamer was really important to me because
having that agreement and just being like, our space is not going to be conventional.
And people are going to look at us and they're going to scream, my God,
they're terrible nerds.
And
were going to laugh in their face about it.
And I needed that in my life.
We're both playing through Fire Emblem Fates right now.
So we're each playing that on our own.
And we're talking about like, oh,
who are we pairing together to make their kid
and like to have like the best stats and all that stuff.
Like he's made like a full on like Excel sheet
of like all the pairings that he's going to make
for the game.
Like he's super into it.
Yeah, and I'm like, you're a nerd.
And I'm like, I love it.
Like you, are we getting married tomorrow?
Where's my ring?
So it's actually been a while since I showed that particular clip and I just realized like a nice little
Coda to that story is that DJ is now engaged to his boyfriend. So so he got his ring. Yay
And that was actually like an experience that I had as well I met my partner James 15 years ago
through Final Fantasy
it was in college and my suite had the nice TV and he had the PlayStation and so
We kind of combined forces and that was like how we got talking to each other
because we're both shy nerds and we wouldn't have been able to talk to each
other otherwise. And so you know it's just this common thing that like games
bring couples together in a way that really it's a recent development. It's
something that we've heard from people in just the last couple years that was
much rarer maybe like a decade or two ago. And so that's not the only personal
change that people experienced through that blending of queer culture and game
culture. A lot of players experienced...
significant personal changes when they encountered queer content in games or queer characters or just games that lent themselves to queer headcanon
So I mean for me Mario Kart like I queer every character in Mario Kart and I have this like whole backstory about like Bowser
Competing with Donkey Kong. I mean, it's just my story
but you know, we hear the power of people kind of taking command of the
Of the content that they that is presented to them and saying okay. Thank you for making this Nintendo now
I'm gonna take it from here
So among those personal changes that people experience,
they're seeing that acknowledgment of their existence.
That invites queer players into games
where they might have felt unwelcome.
It gives them an opportunity to identify as gamers,
where previously they would have been,
we heard this common thing, oh, it's just not for me.
This is still something that I personally deal with.
I produce a show right now where I'm DMing a D&D game.
And just even a year ago, when I thought about Dungeons and Dragons, I was like,
oh, that's not for me. It turns out D&D is super queer.
Also, like having games as a practice space to express that you are queer
can allow players to build confidence in other aspects of their lives.
So a lot of people that we talked to talked about how gameplay helped them
assert themselves authentically, even after they stepped away from the screen.
Right after my sister passed away, I got a key for Gone Home.
And I went through Gone Home, and there was this moment of, I don't know, you could call it an
epiphany or an aha moment. I was reading one of the letters in the game, and the characters,
you know, was doing the voiceover, and I kind of had a little bit of disconnect because
what the character was voicing about her sister, it really echoed some of the feelings and emotions.
and just experiences that I had with my sister and her sexuality.
And I remember I even like blurted it out on stream, like, whoa,
like I'm in my feelings right now.
I might need to take a minute because this is really reminding me of the
relationship that I had with my sister.
I guess you could say revealed to me some of how she might've been feeling.
It, it put, it put me in her shoes in a way.
It was kind of like.
This might sound odd, but it was kind of a way for me to get closure, too.
Like, this is kind of reflecting me in my sister's life.
It really actually gave me some peace, honestly.
Gone Home as a game that was explicitly queer was extremely powerful.
It was a game that I didn't realize I'd been waiting for my whole life until I played it.
Why is this so rare?
Why is it so unusual that a narrative that centers, you know, queer women?
is practically unheard of.
Confirmation that you exist is an amazingly powerful thing.
I think at some fundamental level that's a need that everybody comes to media and entertainment for.
So it's nice to see in something that's so mainstream that...
you know, it's okay to be gay because that means that everything else in real life
that is also mainstream makes it okay.
And seeing the character in Undertale,
you know, portrayed with they, it's validation.
It's realizing that somebody out there is willing to sing part of your song.
People said, I, you, you helped me,
they literally said, you helped me realize I was gay.
You gay, your characters gave me the courage to come out as bisexual.
your playing your game got me through a time where otherwise I was considering killing myself.
Solidarity is a big important thing, knowing that you're not alone.
It's like, it sounds so cliche, right? If you say like, oh, how do you feel when you see someone
that's queer in a game or someone that you can relate to? It's just like, it makes me feel like
I'm not such a, like I'm not so outside of the norm. I know that we're a minority, but
It's great to feel like, yes, you're a minority, but you're accepted, you are allowed to be a human.
Any light at the end of the tunnel, even if it's far away, that is so reassuring to me,
and to my friends and people I know.
So we found in our interviews that games give players a cultural touchstone around which they
can build some community. Particularly in the last decade, we've seen a huge increase in
offline social groups built around queer gaming.
It's grown to the point now where a lot of cities
have multiple organizations all building
queer community and support through games.
In my hometown of Seattle, we've got two groups.
There's Queer Gamers, which has been around
for a couple of years.
There's Gamers with a Y, which is fairly new.
Queer, no, Queer Geek.
Queer Geek has been around for a while,
and it tends to be a slightly older demographic
and a little more focused on board games.
Gamers with a Y is a little bit younger
and tends to focus more on nightlife sort of events,
so gamer parties.
In LA, there's a newish group
that's more focused on community service.
So we're seeing not only are people organizing
to meet each other in physical space,
but there's enough demand in large cities
that they're doing it in multiple different organizations.
And for several years, one of the largest queer gaming
events was the annual convention Gamer X.
It was based here in the Bay Area for a long time.
We heard from people all over the country that they attended that convention, learned
organizing techniques at GamerX from other people who were facilitating meetups, and
then returned to their own hometowns to start new local gaming organizations wherever they
happen to live.
The only part of the gaming room I'm in is the Phoenix Gamers because I've spent so many
years of my life just sitting in this house, playing video games by myself.
Finally, I've figured out the experience that you can go out and do anything and be with like, meet new people.
It's such a great experience and I wish I had more places like to do that.
Uh, being gamers, uh, we're a social group.
Uh, a lot of the times, uh, people in our group say they don't quite fit in into like the main stream game community.
And also, I was just wondering what the...
They don't quite fit into the nerd community.
So we kind of like have that middle ground
where they have to create that space where we can come together.
It's so great to like know people and also be bringing people together.
Every other month or so we open up the house on a Saturday from like 3 until 11.
And we have board games and card games.
I'll be able to set up Dance Central or...
Raving Rabbits down the basement.
And then we just have a big daylong party.
I host a monthly queer female, queer women's board game group at Riga Lounge.
And I do a bi-weekly queer women's board game night at Phoenix Conference Games.
I'm actually the event coordinator for the Minneapolis Gamers Group.
It's kind of a way for all of us gay youth to kind of meet up and, you know, interact and meet people that we may not normally meet up with.
So I'm just going to pause it for a second.
That's like, sounds like it has like a ton of reverb on it.
Does that sound weird to everybody?
Yeah.
Let me just double check, because I have a feeling
I might actually have that slide.
Yeah, OK, that's why.
Sorry, I have the video on the slide twice.
So that's why it was doing that.
So I'm just going to resume that right there we go.
Sorry about that.
that you get to actually have the nerdy effect of liking, getting satisfaction playing games
around people who are just like you and, you know, it's great.
It's a great social outlet.
So something like Gamer X is a place where people can go and realize that they're not
alone, that there are people like them out there.
So when I found a place that, or like a con where a bunch of people were gathering to
kind of celebrate both aspects and bond as one community.
I had to be there.
I don't know, it just felt like a really big family.
And I'm not even gonna lie, I'm really looking forward to seeing some storm drag queens so
I can be like, yes bitch, walk!
I'm hoping that people who are straight go to the event just to see for themselves that
as long as you're not a jerk, you're gonna belong there.
So most of those folks were talking about GamerX,
which really was a transformative experience
for a lot of people.
Just a show of hands, who's been to one of the GamerX events?
Yeah, it's actually, so not a ton of people here.
They're really lovely, and MidBoss,
the company that did it, still exists,
and they're making games now rather than doing events.
But it really, it was the first time
that there was an event like that,
where people could come from all over
and meet at a specifically queer-focused gaming convention.
There was, I think at the first one, there was a proposal that was done with musical
accompaniment by Elle McLean, who's the voice of GLaDOS.
There was, I think, a proposal at the second one as well.
It was a really supportive, positive, and pretty unique space.
And they haven't done it for the last year or two, in part, I think, because we've just
seen this huge rise in people organizing both online and offline.
But it's really changed.
The community in physical small towns, maybe not small towns, but in more cities has really
expanded since where we were about five years ago.
And one of the byproducts of that is that we're seeing queer gamers organizing in ways
that they didn't used to.
We heard a lot of people who are becoming basically self-taught at articulating.
what they want from games.
And so this presents a really beneficial opportunity
for game developers.
Now that queer gamers are becoming increasingly prominent,
they can express what they want in more public spaces,
whether it's streaming or in physical spaces.
And it's easier for devs to listen
and to learn about how their games can appeal
to that broader audience
and incorporate more queer content.
So here's some people, this next video
is gonna be some people talking about
basically how they found an audience and a community for expressing what is still missing from games.
Seeing someone out there in the world, be it gaming or anything, that's like person came out and is
doing all right, they transition like wow that's really cool. Or just seeing a woman in a prominent
position, like I identified as a woman anyway, so I'm like seeing someone out there in a position
of power, it's like yeah that's really cool. I want to...
Like there's more people like me.
Now I know I can be that person as well.
The whole reason I started my Twitch channel in the first place
was because of all the homophobia
and the homophobic stuff that I was seeing
from different gaming channels and different streamers.
And I was like,
I really need to get into this.
And there needs to be much more vocal LGBT identities
on the Twitch sphere.
I was hearing all these stories from LGBT youth, hearing their coming out stories, or people that hadn't come out,
and it's now my job to help create a safe space on that place for them to share those stories with each other.
Now when you look at Twitch, some of the biggest streamers on their platform are LGBT or LGBT allies, which is amazing.
But a lot of trans and gay people, younger people, they will come and ask me a lot of questions when I'm streaming.
because they don't have any outlets.
And I love that about Twitch.
That it's not just me sitting down to play a game.
It's more like, let all of us sit down
and enjoy this title together.
So I think it's great because it opens up
line of communication with people you might not
have ever met before.
Earlier this year, I was looking for private funding
to undergo some surgery stuff that was going on.
And
where years ago I'd have been afraid to even talk about the fact that I was trans.
In this example, like, lots and lots and lots of people online came to my support and I think it
took maybe 10 days to bring together this huge amount of money I was trying to for surgery.
And it was just this moment of not only am I not having to hide that I'm trans but that there are...
people out there who are willing to step up and support me when I need it.
If you can talk to people about video games and get them interested in what you're saying
because of games, then introduce, hey, here's some of the struggles of being a queer person
who's a content creator. It certainly makes it easier to get people who otherwise might
not listen to conversations about queer identity to say, oh, I will stop and listen because I
care about you as a creator and want to see you happy.
And this last couple of years I've had a lot of people come and say to me,
I didn't know anything about these issues that the LGBT plus community face.
I know about them now because I listen to you talk about them
in amongst silly discussions of gaming butts.
And sometimes that's all you need to get people to listen,
is sandwich it inside a conversation that they're already looking for.
I had a recent experience when I had my first panel at PAX East.
I went in there kind of thinking like, what am I doing here?
I'm surrounded by these amazing people.
And my turn came up.
And I've been out for years.
It's no secret, but I just don't talk about it much.
So I went up there and said just,
my problem is how open to be about it.
I didn't realize how much I had bottled up inside.
I had to take a moment and kind of catch myself.
I was like starting to have tears well up
and I just stopped and my friend patted my shoulder
and like, it's okay, just give me a hug.
And in that moment, the entire crowd, like hundreds of people, started cheering and clapping and applauding.
I'm like, oh my god, this is...
Like, wow, thank you so much.
And, um, that felt amazing.
That was my contribution, is kind of like re-outing myself as a trans person.
Because afterwards, if you go to panels, a number of times afterwards, people start kind of rushing to the stage.
They want to talk to the panelists, ask them their questions.
I look up and like, there's people standing in front of me.
Like, what? What?
and I will never forget this person and I really wish I would have been able to catch their name.
And they looked up and it was me, they had their spiky hair and this red vinyl shirt,
had the biggest smile on their face and they just said,
thank you, thank you so much for being open and just being out there.
And I almost lost it right there again.
And they walked off and I never got to learn who they were. I really wish I could.
And a number of other people came up and said the exact same thing.
And I was, each time I almost started falling in happiness.
Wow, I never thought of myself as...
being that person for people. But growing up, I always liked seeing someone who kind of represented me.
And now all of a sudden, I was put into that situation where I'm that representation for someone else.
So now it's easier than ever for queer, for game developers to include queer gamers in the product
that they're making. There's no shortage of voices on streams, at conferences, and conventions.
People who are doing diversity consulting.
And what we're seeing now is a lot of companies are changing their practices to listen to those voices and incorporate the feedback into their production process.
So as part of this project, we sought out some developers who are doing basically good work in that area, who people are putting queer content into their games.
And so we asked them how they're doing that and how it's affected their work.
I own a video game studio now, and that was actually my literal childhood dream when I was six.
So, I mean, like one of the key things about Indivisible is that it's about people from
different viewpoints coming together and being better than like this monolithic thing.
And so, I mean, just diversity is kind of like built into that storyline.
It initially started out with like racial, but then it's like, okay,
let's expand this and see what we can do with it.
So we've got neurodiversity, we've got sexual diversity.
Video games are what I really love to make, and they also pay my bills.
When I started my company, it was like, I either need to drop drag because it's too expensive,
or I need to make it work for me.
So I wanted to go against the grain, made a game about love, put Kitty Powers in it.
There was another box I wanted to tick, was to make it very inclusive, the game,
and to have a drag queen in it as well.
I mean, there's a lot of queer in the game.
But queers are included, and they're very visible.
Having suffered so much when I was a kid, I thought, well, if all these young kids are
going to be watching this video, this game being played, then at least they're getting
some kind of exposure that I didn't get.
If kids can see that and see it being treated as if it's normal, then that's a good thing.
And we decided, you know, my producer pulled me aside and said, hey, I think I want to
put a girl.
as an option in this game, and I looked at him and I was like,
you picked the right person to be on your team, buddy.
Um, but it was, oh, it was so nerve-wracking.
There were all these people around me who had years of experience,
some of which who would have loved to have a lesbian route,
but were too nervous to try.
Um, and I was ungrateful that I had the backing of two other senior producers
behind me to say, like, no, let's do this, we can do this.
Um, and then let me take control.
of that content because they respected that I was a queer woman wanting to write this
queer woman.
Our queer fans, obviously, are overjoyed.
I've never...
I get teary-eyed when I look at some of their posts and their responses because they're
so heartfelt and genuine in saying, you know, thank you.
We've never had this sort of representation before.
Thank you so much.
And it feels...
amazing to give them that. I just want to give people content where they see themselves and content where they get a happy ending.
Those are kind of my two big goals.
So people aren't being quiet about it anymore, and that's a great thing, but it can't just be the smaller indie studios.
It can't just be, you know, the person making a twine game on their own time.
It needs to be, it needs to trickle up to the AAA space. I'm here and I
get our, you know, I get our audience, but I get that our audience is also people like me and
I'm fortunate to work with a bunch of people who understand that.
And we do try and look out beyond what is stereotypically thought of as the target audience
and with Twitter and getting to go to conventions and talking to people.
We can just have a lot more conversations a lot more easily than we used to.
And we can say, okay, we're going to make this kind of character.
I'm not a trans person.
How do we make a character that
is respectful of you that makes you feel like this is a good thing. And then when it does
okay that makes it sort of less scary for the next game. Okay, maybe. And it because
it rarely comes, change rarely comes in giant leaps and bounds and it's okay, this time
we'll do this, this time we'll do that. So the character of Krem in Dragon Age Inquisition
actually came pretty much out of a, uh,
sort of a panel. It ended up being more of a discussion that we did at a BioWare base
in PAX Prime, and it was specifically geared towards the LGBTQ community, and it was just
what do you want to see more of? What are we doing right? What are we doing wrong? And
that opportunity for feedback, and a trans gentleman got up to the microphone and said,
I would just love to see someone in a game like me who's not a monster. And we all just
went, okay.
this is something we can do something about, you know, and
and that, you know, we went straight to
somewhere and got drinks and started talking about, you know, okay, how can, this is
important, this is,
this
needs to happen and we are in a place where if we do it right we could maybe
make it happen.
And it was, it was not.
It's an easy, there's a lot of discussion.
There's a lot of frank discussion and some hits
and some misses and a lot of trial and a lot of error
and a lot of talking to people.
But we, Patrick and I got to go to Dragon Con last year
and met some people rocking some cram cosplay
who just came up to us and gave us hugs.
And there's,
I don't know, it's hard to put.
in two words that it's humbling and it still feels like it's not enough.
You know, that a moment like that is so profound for someone is wonderful and also sad that
it's rare and that it's something that stood out for them and is wonderful to have happen
and makes it really obvious we need to keep doing it.
We need to see a trans character in games, and let's be honest, it's not going to happen until Bioware does it."
And we went, okay, well...
I'm not sure I'm comfortable with this, and I'm really, really worried about messing it up.
But...
If there are people who are telling us,
you know, you saved our lives about gay stuff,
if we can do something that has some minor effect on the same way for trans people, for non-binary people,
We owe it to them and to ourselves to try to make that attempt.
And again, we make entertainment. We make...
You know, we're not...
We're not curing cancer, but if something like that,
if that was someone who did not have that in their lives,
and if our entertainment product helped someone hit that
and made their lives a little bit easier or gave them...
let them realize there were paths available to their lives that they saw only as dead ends until
that point, then it's worth us having uncomfortable conversations and making mistakes and messing
stuff up. So it's not a secret that the game industry has had a problem with potential gamers
feeling excluded or feeling unsafe either as consumers or as people working on the games
themselves.
And for a long time, when queer identity collided with gamer identity,
it left people feeling left out of both worlds.
But a lot of the people that we interviewed
found that those worlds don't have to collide so much as overlap.
And that overlap can form the basis of strong relationships,
provide shared meaning with partners.
Feeling attraction, falling in love, and forming relationships
are all fundamental aspects of queer identity.
And games that incorporate those themes...
can help queer people understand their own sexuality,
can improve the romantic bonds that they form with others,
it can turn people from being game avoidant
into game obsessed.
And so rather than being in conflict,
what we found is that queer culture and game culture
are a highly compatible pairing.
This presentation is just a small segment
of the stories that we've gathered.
We've spoken to 125 people in 19 states,
four countries at this point.
We've got over 100 hours of footage and lots more topics to explore.
We're still gathering first-hand accounts and sharing our findings.
So what's next for this particular project is you can sign up for updates.
You can see more of what we're doing at playingwithpride.com.
We're still gathering more interviews and footage, and we'd love to get feedback.
There's some feedback form on what we're doing at playingwithpride.com.
And we're also incorporating some of the things
that we've discovered in doing these interviews
into our D&D show, Queens of Adventure.
That's a live show and a podcast
that features drag queens playing D&D.
And we've been very intentional with that show
about crafting something that's responsive
to what we learned in this project,
something that builds community
and makes people feel incorporated, feel included,
and helps people feel connected to, you know,
a big, wide world of LGBTQ heroes out there.
So you can find that at queensofadventure.com.
And so we've got I think about 10 minutes left,
so we could do a Q&A if there's any questions.
Well, thank you.
Thank you.
Thank you, thank you.
So if there are questions, there's the mic right there.
Otherwise a question that I have just in general
for the audience is.
if there are games that have included queer content
or games that you kind of head-cannoned queer content into.
Like, what are games that you found are doing it right?
One game I was really surprised about was The Last of Us.
Oh yeah, The Last of Us, fantastic.
It's my all-time favorite game.
Something that really surprised me about that game was
as I, when I got to know,
sorry, this is whether it's funny or not,
But as I got to know Ellie's character, there was something about her that just made her kind of feel like me.
And I couldn't, like, the flag in my head, excuse the term, but I guess gaydar, was going off in my head.
And I was just like, no, I'm just thinking this because of me, like, I'm just putting this in my own head.
It's not real.
And then when we got to that part where something actually did happen, like, that was the first time I ever experienced that again.
My heart absolutely just blew up.
Sorry, sorry.
But it was really amazing.
Also, Life is Strange.
Oh yeah, Life is Strange, my goodness.
You know, and that's something really frequent
that we've heard from other people is like,
oh, it's just me, I'm just making this up.
It's all my own baggage that I'm bringing to the game.
And I think it's something that we're still like,
as queer gamers, kind of dealing with,
of like this sort of internalized homophobia,
or maybe not homophobia, but sort of like
our own queer erasure of saying like,
oh no, no, no, there's no queer game,
there's no queer characters in games.
I just have to make it up.
And then when a game is like, no, no, it's real, you exist, it's okay, you're real, it's
kind of the reverse of Emperor's New Clothes of being like, no, no, this thing that you
thought was pretend is actually a real thing.
Yeah, and if I may say one more thing, one thing that really surprised me also about
Life is Strange is I started noticing early on, when I was playing the game and making
all these different choices, I honestly thought it was going to be one of those joking things,
there's a lot of like...
I thought it was going to be like, oh, ha ha, this isn't real.
This is just me thinking it.
And I'm a high school teacher.
So I actually spoke to one of my students
about this who is bisexual.
And I was telling him, I thought it was just a troll thing.
So I started making all these different choices
to give myself a laugh.
And I'm just like, oh, I'll just do this.
Ha ha, this isn't really going to happen.
And then it did.
And I was shocked.
And again, my heart exploded.
And I mentioned this to my student and his response was,
well, maybe they're doing that because they want people
to realize that it's normal.
This is a normal thing and it's normalized.
And when he said that, my heart just dropped
and I was like, that's absolutely, he's right.
It was absolutely true.
I'm a little bit shook because that whole thing was amazing and I was kind of tearing up for most of it,
especially with the creme stuff, because that helped me with my own coming to terms with myself.
I just want to say with the social mobile gaming scene, I work with a thinking ape,
and we have a pretty strong queer, LGBT community in there that we've been really supportive of.
And it's been kind of fun working over time
to just build more and more content that just is there
and we're just up front about it.
And it's been really amazing to have that opportunity
as a content creator.
So it's been pretty cool.
And yeah, I mostly just shook.
Thank you for sharing.
Well, thanks for coming.
And there's a couple people at the microphone too.
Hi there.
So I went to a Muslim, how to represent Muslims talk yesterday.
And one of the things he said was, you know, include us.
It doesn't, you don't have to really talk about our religion, but you can include the way we dress.
And people are still going to identify with it.
And we need that too.
So my question for you is, are we at a place or are we moving in a direction
where having someone who is
gay, queer, how do I put this?
That it's at the forefront of the character
and are we moving to a place
where it's part of the character and that's acceptable too
but it's not something that's played forward?
Does that make sense?
I don't know if I'm, I don't know
that I'm saying it correctly,
but are both of them equally important?
Is there one that's more important right now
we're moving towards something else like?
That is a great question and you know.
I've been looking at games, I've been a games journalist and sort of making this documentary
project for a long time.
And so I have to say it seems like games as a medium are maybe lagging ten-ish years behind
TV and film.
And if I'm understanding your question, it sounds like the question is like there's two
ways that queer can be represented.
One is this is a story about queer.
And also this is a story about something else and queer is just an element of it.
And is one more important or where are we at with that?
And I have to say, my impression from speaking to people
is that there's kind of an equal need
for both of those still.
It certainly reminds me of going back even further
where we were in the 1980s with TV and film
where every show or movie that had a queer character
was it was this huge crisis of like,
mom I'm gay and it's tearing the family apart.
And so there was a need then for a lot of stories that were very much about, like, what is the queer experience?
Because it was something that hadn't been spoken about.
And I think my perception of the games, of games media, is that we are not entirely at a place where it's no big deal.
And I think there's a lot of value to explicitly addressing what is queer, what does it mean to be queer?
Let's talk about it. Let's foreground that.
That having been said.
there is a huge relief when you can just play a game and have a gay character there, and it's no big deal,
and it's not even a part of the game, and it's just life.
Because I think that's how a lot of people want to live, and not always be like, you know, I'm kind of...
As a reporter and a producer, and all the different hats I wear, I'm sort of a professional gay.
And there are times when I'm like,
oh man, I just want to like, you know, go on a hike, or like, I just want to pet a cat, or something like that.
And like, it doesn't always have to be about queer all the time.
So it's a real relief, for example, when I play Stardew Valley and I'm like, okay, I'm
going to be in a queer couple in this playthrough and that's just how I'm going to play it.
And you know, Stardew Valley is certainly not about the queer experience.
So I would love for us to get to the point where it's just no big deal and you've got
a gay character there and it's nothing.
That having been said, it feels to me as though games media is still sort of in a state that
is kind of pre-Glee, if that makes sense.
Glee was kind of a catalog.
The TV show was kind of a catalog of all the different ways
somebody could come out of the closet.
And I don't know that games have had their Glee moment
where it's like, gay, gay, gay, gay, gay,
and now we're done.
Are we done?
We're done?
Okay, good, and now let's move on.
So I'm waiting for that point,
that we could just move on and just have gay characters.
And I don't know, the next Dragon,
actually, it's interesting that that's the first one
I thought of, because Dragon Age is a game
where you've got.
Gay?
Like, same-sex relationships.
And nobody comments on it, it's no big deal.
And that's something that we've been very deliberate about
with Queens of Adventure, is we've got queer characters
in there, and at no point are they like,
oh, and I had this difficult coming out,
or oh, and I had this, you know,
my family rejected, da da da da.
Because, you know, there comes a point where you're like,
I just, I don't want any more, like,
the angst of being queer stories.
I just want to go on an adventure.
And now that I think about it, there is a,
in Dragon Age Inquisition, a whole storyline
about the angst of being queer with,
spoilers, sorry, with Dorian.
I mean, he's got a whole storyline
about his relationship with his family.
So, I guess Dragon Age kind of straddles the line
in a way that is very nice.
Because a lot of people talk about,
we don't have the clips in here,
but a lot of people talked about Dragon Age
as an important game.
And I think that one splits that balance
in a way that's really nice.
Great, thank you so much for.
expressing all that. Absolutely, yeah. Thanks for coming.
Hi, my name is Daryl. From what I've mostly observed, it seems like it takes that mature
rating for these issues to be really tackled so transparently in a game. So I don't know
if anybody has any example where there is something that's more targeted at a younger
audience that still is unapologetic about it.
So in this presentation we have some clips from Kitty Powers,
who's a drag queen. She's based in the UK.
When we interviewed her initially I thought,
oh, this is great, this game company hired a drag queen
to be the face of, you know, the mascot of their game.
No, it turns out Kitty Powers is the CEO of the company,
is a drag queen who started her own company.
Which, awesome.
And her game is extremely family-friendly.
It's very kid-friendly.
So she's got two games, Kitty Powers Love Life
and Kitty Powers Matchmaker.
And it's a dating sim and sort of a life sim.
And they're just super, like, pure and lovely and adorable.
And so there's, like, you know, I don't actually know what the games are rated, but I can't
imagine anybody having an objection to any of the content, other than, like, if somebody
wanted to make trouble about there being same-sex couplings in the game.
So I don't think it's necessary that games have that mature rating.
I do think that there is still a lingering stigma.
you know, that there's sort of people are put on red alert when they see like same-sex couples or
we're talking about trans identity, sort of a stigma of like, oh well this is inappropriate
for children. But I think that's fading very fast. Faster I think in games than it took to
fade in TV and film. Thank you. Yeah, absolutely. I just wanted to contribute to the list of games
that I think handle it really well. Night in the Woods. Oh yeah.
couple, Greg and Angus, they're like... there's obviously like a storyline with
them or sort of a backstory involving their situation, but they're not really
the ones that I'm talking about. It's actually at some at a point in the game,
Mae, the player character, hits on a girl, and you don't even really realize until
like afterwards that that's what it was, and it was just like, oh sweet, like it's
so not an issue, and so you've got your like... this is the...
like this sort of focal relationship where Greg and Angus are dealing with the town's
idea of them, but then you get that extra identification in the player character also.
Yeah, and it's very similar to what Laura was bringing up in her interview. She was the
person who had blue hair, about how you can kind of sneak some queer content into games sometimes
and catch people by surprise and say, oh, here's just something fun.
She made reference to a podcast that I actually don't know if she's doing anymore called Gaming
Butts where she just talked about butts in games.
Because it's so much of what you see in your character sometimes.
And so, you know, it's just a goofy little podcast that she was doing.
And then, you know, she's trans and she has a lot of colleagues that are trans.
And so they would incorporate that, you know, you're already friends with these people through
the podcast as much as you can be friends with someone through a podcast.
And then you throw in some inclusive content and people like, oh, oh, yeah, yeah, that's
actually okay.
I don't have a problem with that after all.
like have sex once. You can have a lot of sex in Robert Yang's games, which I think
is like really important when we're talking about sort of reaching this
point that you're talking about. I mean it's a lot of like cis male gay stuff,
but from that perspective I think he's really doing incredible things and also
confronting a lot of those like censorship and rating.
things head on. I mean like one of the interesting things he did with the tea room is like they
wouldn't let him have penises on Steam so he replaced all of them with guns which is
allowed. So just like really clever. But yeah I just wanted to shout out to what he's doing
because I think it's really amazing and also how he handles consent in one of his games
actually.
if you, it's like a kind of a BDSM sim, and if you go too far with the NPC, you literally are
locked out of the game. So really exploring a lot of issues, like I think within our own community,
in a way that like doesn't feel like, oh I'm just checking some sort of like token box, or yay,
I get to like hit on or like make out with this cute dude, but like actually experiencing, you know,
an element of life and queer history that a lot of other games don't do.
Yeah, I love all of Robert's games. They're fantastic. Robert Yang, I highly recommend
checking those out. They're really challenging games. And we're running up on time, but I just
want to get one more question from the microphone. Hi, my name is Carter. I'm actually a student
a little while south of here. For one thing, this was a great talk.
I'm actually working on creating my own VR experience right now, and I was wondering
if you would have any advice to...
I want my main character, the player character, to be non-binary, and I was wondering how
I would be able to explore that in a setting where it's a first-person game.
That's a really interesting question, and I think that's something...
I don't know that I have great advice for that just off the top of my head, but I bet
like, I know there's an overflow room where we can do Q&A after the panel, and I bet if
folks have thoughts on that, that would be a great place to pick that up.
Do we just, GDC folks, where's that room?
Do you know where the overflow room is?
Okay.
Because I'd love to give that two or three more minutes of thought before I answer that.
Just off the top of my head, I think just having those moments where you look in a mirror
or you...
see your hands or something like that as an opportunity to, you know, inhabit a body that
is not the body you're used to seeing or maybe reflects the body or affirms the body that
is more natural for you. That's, I guess, where I'd start. And just, like, making people aware
from the beginning this is an option. I think Dream Daddy did a really interesting thing in
their character creator where binders were an option, like, right from the start, like,
when you're creating your character, which, like, I've never seen that in a game before.
It was really profound.
So just like being clear, you can be non-binary,
you can be any gender, you can be any orientation.
But let me think about that for a few more minutes.
And then where?
Wrap up the room, so straight back to 2022. 2022?
Yeah, 2022.
Yeah, so back that way, 2222.
That's where we'll do some wrap up conversation.
Thank you again, everybody, for coming.
Please leave feedback.
Great.