We should begin.
That means it's time for me to ask you all,
are you ready to log in?
Yes?
Yes.
All right, let's go.
Welcome to the classic game postmortem for Ultima Online,
20 years going strong.
In alphabetical order, Richard Garriott, Lord British.
What did you do on this game?
I was there.
Star Long.
Original Game Director.
Me.
Original Lead Designer.
Rich Vogel.
What did you do on this game?
I was the Live Producer.
All right, we need to travel back in time.
To 1995.
So just a reminder of what technology was like.
So the height of technology was a 28 8 modem and a so this is you know,
your network currently is 20 2500 times faster.
Okay, the state-of-the-art CPU is a 33 megahertz, you know, so.
you know a four core PC is a thousand times faster than what we were working
with back then okay. 16 megabytes of RAM you probably have a thousand times the
amount of RAM that we were working with. One megabyte 16-bit video card okay so
you probably have 8,000 times the amount of video RAM right now and 260 megabyte
hard drive okay your phone
The thing in your pocket has 10 times the amount of storage that we were working with.
So that's just the kind of limitations we were working with.
And then we've got like, so what was happening in the space of the kind of games that we were?
So the other games in the space were things like Air Warrior, Neverwinter Nights,
and of course, The Realm.
So these, and Dragonspires, and if Dr. Cat was here, we would go, Dr. Cat, Dragonspires.
Tell him later that we gave him a shout out.
Yes.
And then of course, really the thing that I give the most credit is Mudds and Moos,
and that's where of course Mr. Raff here came from. And so that's kind of the general environment
that we were working in at the time. Things have changed. Yes, things have changed quite a bit.
And then, so what was the start of all this? It was what we affectionately call Multima.
But if you look back at Origins history,
when we first started making,
or when I really first started making Ultima
back in the late 70s and early 80s,
they were always simulations of a party-based
live-action Dungeons and Dragons campaign.
And so doing a multiplayer Ultima
is something we talked about year after year after year.
But Star just went through the games that were out
kind of ahead of Ultima Online,
and most of those were games that you had to pay per minute.
or at least per hour, to a dial-up bulletin board service.
And so they were very expensive to use.
And the total user numbers were pretty small.
And so years would go by.
We would sit down and we'd talk about it.
We'd even go talk to the people who made the games
that you just saw flash by.
We'd debate whether we could justify
spending an Ultima scale budget on an online game.
And year after year, the answer was no.
The time was not right.
Until.
So I was in QA at the time, actually.
And the inspiration, actually, for UO,
I affectionately call it the rocket to the face.
And we were playing.
During lunchtime, Doom had come out,
and we would have these multiplayer sessions of Doom.
And I came around a corner and we would race for the rocket launcher.
And the guy, somebody beat me to the rocket launcher and I raced around the corner and
I got a rocket to the face.
And it was this inspiration of like, oh my god, players are really fun to play with and
more fun than AI.
And it was these conversations about a multiplayer Ultima and recreating that feeling of playing Dungeons and Dragons and having that social experience of playing multiplayer RPGs on paper, and looking at the other things that were happening with mods and moves.
And so going to Richard and saying, really? And then looking at what was happening with the internet and looking at what was happening with the World Wide Web had just happened. I mean, this is literally just happened.
Websites were just becoming a thing and it was like now is the time we really should
Do this and we should convince our parent company electronic arts to give us money to make this happen
And so that we came up with this pitch for Ultima online
It was still called multiple at the time multiplayer Ultima and then we started pitching it to yeah
And and and as with many big companies the pitch process is you put together a design document
Which is mostly going to be thrown away if you start working on the game, you're probably familiar with this
You put together the technology plan,
which also probably won't survive any form of utilization,
and you hand that over to the marketing team,
and the marketing team does sales projections based on that,
and then they do a cost return on investment
based upon those sales and decide
if they're gonna green light you or shoot you down.
But at this point in time, don't forget,
there had never been any product released
that was referred to as a massively multiplayer game.
And so we went to go pitch this massively multiplayer game,
the sales department would look at that and go like,
hey, it's an Ultima, that's cool,
there's at least some audience.
But then they would look at the entire class
of games that existed in the online space
that were dial-up bulletin board service games
with a maximum of five, 10, 15,000 users peak,
and they would look at this,
and this was back when games,
a top-selling game would probably sell a million copies,
and so they'd look at that and go,
okay, 15,000 units, a million units,
you know, this is a no-brainer, the answer's no.
And so despite us arguing that the times are a changing,
the World Wide Web is going to be this great equalizer,
and everyone's going to be connected,
and the pricing model is going to change, we were told no.
So we went back and licked our wounds.
Six months later, we came back to give the same pitch.
But we thought this time they're going
to go for it because it's even more obvious that the World
Wide Web is going to be real.
And we made our case again.
Got the same sales projections back again.
By the way, they gave us a lifetime sales projection
of 30,000 units, twice the success
of the best-selling online game in their mind previously.
And so we were told no a second time.
Then we go back literally the third time.
So the third time, which is now a year later
from the first time we gave the pitch.
We give the pitch the third time,
get the same results the third time,
and we literally just refused to give up the floor.
So we're in this pitch meeting, and they say, no, get out.
And we literally do the stomp our feet and hold our breath.
We are not leaving until you guys get a clue here
and at least let us, and they said,
our budget as a developer, we go over budget
and under budget by, well, usually over,
by 25 to 50% every year.
We're only asking for, we asked for, I think, $250,000
to build the prototype.
And I'd already had a piece of paper prepared for just sign
here and you approve of us going over budget to prove
that this can work.
And finally, after it was heated yelling and screaming,
they finally signed the piece of paper and basically kicked
us on the ass as we left the room.
So great, we have money.
And then it was like, well, now what do we do?
Because nobody in the company had built a multiplayer game.
And I was like, great, I made the pitch.
And oh, god, I have to build this thing.
And so we got the idea of, well, let's go to MUDs.
People who have built MUDs know how to build multiplayer games.
And so I assembled this scrappy little team.
And there's a picture of them.
And we were having breakfast.
And Raph had this really great point of,
if you look at that team, it's a pretty amazingly diverse team
for the time.
We have a woman on the core team.
It was Raph's wife.
We have the really young team, you know, so the average age of that team was about 22
You know, we we actually have a older
First artist on the team was this guy Michael priest who was actually one of the very first artists at origin
One of the first artists in the computer gaming industry. Yeah, so
and
And that team of about eight, actually,
was the same team all the way up until the beta.
So we had a really small Agile team.
That team actually built 90% of the game,
all the way through the lifecycle of the game.
And so there's a power of small Agile teams.
But actually, at the very beginning,
it was just me and one programmer,
a guy named Rick Delishmite, who built a prototype using
the Ultima VI engine.
And all you could do with the prototype was you could run around, pick up an object,
and then if you bumped into another character, that object would drop on the ground.
That was it?
That was it.
But you could get about 100 people in the game at the same time.
And so we did a test with the whole company,
and everybody got on a big conference call because we didn't have any chat or anything like that.
And everyone was like, oh my god, what is this?
This is interesting.
And all of a sudden, we had people who were like, oh,
I'd like to be on that team.
We're like, well, I don't have any money,
so you can't be on the team.
And we built this prototype.
And all of a sudden, we got interest,
and we built the prototype.
And then we ended up using most of that foundational prototype
tech to build the whole project.
And moving on from there.
But then.
We were kind of the bastard stepchild because no one got it and no one was really interested
because everybody wanted to build the next Ultima or the next Wing Commander because
those were the big sexy projects and still no one got it.
And I would also say that the corporation was still actively trying to kill it.
I mean this really was, no one in the corporation believed in this game, nobody wanted this
game to continue.
Is that why you put us on the fifth floor?
Because we were on a fifth floor that was under construction.
that literally they had knocked out all the walls and the windows.
So the elevator surfaced to bare concrete.
And if you turned right at the sign,
you went to see our team that was still in a converted hallway.
That was the only part left standing.
If you turned left, you fell off the building five floors to your death.
Yeah, that's true. That's true.
It was a test. Yeah.
And there were actually sheets of plastic
hanging down in this converted hallway.
to keep the dust from the construction out of their computers.
Yep.
But the noise of course came right through anyway.
As did the cold, by the way.
Yeah.
Everything about this team was given the least possible support you can imagine by a company.
There was one point where we couldn't figure out why it was always cold and the heat never came on
and we finally figured out that our server was sitting underneath the thermostat.
Yep.
And that's why...
And that's why the heat never came on,
and why we were all sitting with gloves on all the time,
trying to program with a microphone.
Trying to type.
That's right.
So my wife and I had been working in text mods, right?
And these guys hire us, and they hire Rick.
Actually, all three of us had came from the same text mod,
one called LegendMod.
And we'd actually, on the drives back and forth
from the interviews and whatnot, we
were designing online game systems.
So you can actually see here.
This is mostly my wife's handwriting.
She's actually the uncredited key other designer.
There were two key designers, and Kristen
is absolutely the other one.
And this was the only game she made,
and she got out of the industry.
You can see here the birth of things
like abstract properties that underlie every object,
the birth of ideas that today are Minecraft.
She had an economics degree.
So here you see things like modeling overall economics
flows.
We actually submitted the idea of a full world simulation
with abstract properties and player run economy
and crafting based on abstract properties
in our job application, which was probably weird.
It was awesome.
So we submitted that.
And it had all of these crazy ideas,
like what if we have a resource system that's
based on Maslow's hierarchy of needs?
so that AIs want food and shelter and desire in that order
and we can define everything, like the branches, the logs,
the sheep, the rabbits, the walls, the swords,
in terms of these abstract properties and this AI
so that everything can move along
in all these different ways.
This didn't ship.
It broke badly.
Closed economy, real disaster.
From the outset, we were thinking
in terms of this really vast simulation.
Even today, a four kilometer by four kilometer world
at one meter resolution, where every entity is
running abstract properties as a cellular automata simulation.
Those of you who are programmers are going, cool.
But it barely ran back then.
We thought we could actually build four times that,
and then Star told us we were wrong.
So that all went away.
And simulated all the way down to individual one meter
granularity, which meant that people could build anything
they wanted, dress any way they wanted.
They could craft anything they wanted.
Just about everything in the game
was going to be something that was dynamically created.
NPCs would set all the prices.
There wouldn't be much static data.
Everything could be customized and colorized.
I mean, we didn't know what was impossible.
So we built it anyway.
And that was kind of our whole team's attitude,
was we would just do the impossible,
or just do what needed to be done.
And in fact, so we built our own website because, and again,
you have to remember, this was at a time
where the web had just happened.
Electronic Arts, our parent company,
didn't even have a public-facing website at the time.
And so.
We built our own website.
And we didn't tell anyone we had built a website.
We just did it.
And our lead programmer, the guy Rick, who basically built all
of the foundational tech, amazing guy, he loved llamas.
And so our whole website had llamas all over it.
And since there were only ten of us.
Yeah. And we, that's the original logo for Ultima Online
that pretty much no one ever saw unless they saw
that original website.
It's still my favorite logo for the game.
I wish we had used it.
And by the way, this website had this FAQ on it.
By the way, we think one of the very first FAQs ever.
No, there were tons on Usenet.
But for a commercial game.
Commercial game, maybe.
And it promised a huge list of features.
Yeah, I mean, come on.
We promised the moon, right?
And everything.
I mean.
Think about what Yua was even compared to what there is today.
We were saying, let us make a true alternate fantasy world
where everything is alive, where everything is simulated,
where every single dynamic object in the game persisted.
Remember when you could drop shit on the ground?
Right?
I mean, you can't do that anymore.
A world with true consequence.
Part of the point was live the virtues for real,
like the training wheels are off now.
Right?
We're not going to give you little quests necessarily
so that you know how to act.
We were saying, no, you have to actually know.
You've had, come on, you've had eight games and nine games,
10 games at that point with all the spin-offs, right?
You should know by now what the virtues are.
Start behaving.
And a game where combat and crafting and role-playing
were all equally important instead of killing
being the only thing.
So we promised the moon, and it turned out
people liked the promise.
Well, and.
What's interesting also about when we put up
that first website, or something we announced
on that website, is by the time we got around
to being willing to let people come in and test the game,
we'd now already spent our $250,000
that we had barely managed to eke out.
And we suddenly came to this point where we're going like,
well, now that we have this game,
it's much larger than these slow modems could download.
People couldn't download the whole game practically.
And so we needed to send people a CD with the game on it
for them to really be able to help us test it.
And that, of course, would cost us money.
And so we thought, well, we don't have any money left.
We could have people sign up.
We wouldn't be able to afford to send them the discs,
since we're now broke.
Or even manufacture the discs.
Yeah.
And so we said, OK, well, we will now
charge people for the privilege of being testers.
So there is a first early access right there.
Yeah.
And so we weren't sure people would go for that,
but we put that up on our website.
Hey, we're the Multima guys making this Ultima Online thing.
And don't forget, our sales projections for the game
were 30,000 units lifetime.
And as soon as we put up this marker that said,
pay us $5 to be a beta tester, within a few days,
50,000 people had signed up to pay to be beta testers.
And that was the day EA got it.
OK.
Yeah.
And so they sort of woke up.
So we had all these people sign up.
We started our beta, and we started manufacturing
these CDs, which, by the way, those things are collectors
items now on eBay.
And EA woke up.
And so the other project that was happening at Origin
was Ultima 9.
And what's funny, up until this point,
electronic arts had been like, Ultima 9
is the most important thing.
You know, it's the next sequel to the big franchise.
And you know, that's the thing, you know, let's do the,
you know, each franchise has its sequel
and you do that every year.
It's like the next Madden, et cetera, et cetera.
And you know, you're the bastard stepchild
who we put on the terrible fifth floor.
You know, you don't matter, blah, blah.
You have the little scrappy team of whoever's.
And all of a sudden, everything flipped.
They were like, the slumbering giant woke up
and like the eye of Sauron switched over to us.
And it was like.
Oh, you are the most important thing.
And it's like, all of a sudden, U9 got iced,
and the entire Ultima 9 team got reassigned to us.
And it was like, we're here to help.
And it's like, well, wait, what?
And don't forget all the EA middle management
that came over to help.
Oh, yeah, and then we got a bunch of experts
got flown in to help us as well.
So we all of a sudden went from this scrappy little team
of, you know,
12 people up until this point.
Who understood online games.
Yeah, who knew how to make multiplayer games
and all the gives and takes that that took
to, you know, all of a sudden we became a team of like 50
who, and a team that did not want to be there,
who just had had their project canceled,
you know, who were super excited, right?
And so a big takeaway there is, you know,
don't, don't,
take a bunch of people who were just off a canceled project
and assign them to another team,
especially something they don't know anything about.
Because I, yeah, okay.
So one of the big things that when I came on board
I realized is they had no, they had a game
but not the infrastructure to launch it.
So they had nothing, no service component on it at all.
And I go, oh my God, how are we gonna do this
in the time that EA gave us to do this in?
And so I had to reach out.
We did develop a very unique system.
We had key codes.
Now, key codes are used everywhere today
to register your product.
Well, we actually had to come up with that methodology
to make that happen, because no one else has done that before.
So we came up with a way to develop unique codes.
And what it was was a system where
I moved a mouse on a mouse pad, and it would generate
radium codes for us.
And that's the way that worked.
And that's what someone would sit down and do to generate all these codes, is just sit there and do that.
Which was me.
And then I had to come up, oh my God, we have no billing process and neither did EA.
So they had nothing, they didn't understand what digital products were or anything else like that.
So I had to reach out to mPlayer to help us because they did have a registration system that we could use.
and then a billing system that we can attach to
until we got our own up and running,
because I had no time to build that.
That takes a lot of time.
And then we realized, well, Europe
doesn't have credit cards for a subscription.
I said, what are we going to do here?
And I said, oh, crap.
OK, we'll put a game time in a box
so the retailers can sell it, but we can't take that big cut
out of it, so we've got to figure out a way to do this
where we can at least get some profitability out of it.
So we sold game time.
on 60 and 90 day gain time cards,
which no one's ever done before in a retail box
so that people can prepay to pay.
So a lot of cool things came out of that,
but it was very rushed and we were like sitting there
figuring out what do we do here for,
because again, credit cards at that time in Europe
weren't widely used.
So that helped that.
Well, and to add to that too,
I mean, at an even more fundamental level,
one thing to realize, the whole idea of
customer having an account, a username and account, didn't even exist.
Like, there was no registration, like create a username, create a password.
Not for single player games.
Not for, because it existed in the online service stuff.
Right, but not for.
Not packaged goods at all.
Yeah, we didn't have anything like that.
No. So we actually, all those systems that you see today, actually were born out of this.
That everyone adopted.
One of the big things we did before launch, which I heard about, is we used to have just
servers that could hold up to 170 people, but then when we sold 50,000 beta periods,
we said, oh my god, we want to put thousands of people on the server.
How are we going to do that?
And everyone looked around, and of course Rick Dellisman is an amazing person, and he
comes up with this seamless server idea, so we actually were distributing the load of
a map between multiple servers in real time, which no one's ever done before.
In fact, I don't think any other game has done that to date.
No, we've got a lot to have now.
To seamless.
Yeah, seamless.
We did in Galaxies.
But anyway, so we had to figure out
that was done pretty close to when we were launching.
And then we had to figure out, OK, all the details of that
were never debugged very well, as we all know in launch.
There were a lot of bugs.
Dupe bugs.
Ton of bugs with that duping was one of them.
Because who's authoritative over what as you transfer between the servers was a big deal there.
And then one of the big things we learned is because we had to get this done very quickly,
designers were doing a lot of the heavy lifting on game code.
That's not good.
Designers being programmers lead to a lot of bad things.
And we realized that as we were going through and testing the game, there was a lot of bugs
because there were just things that.
designers don't understand as programmers would, and we had to figure out how to deal
with all those bugs as we were going to launch.
And then when we created this game, we had to have log-in servers.
So we had a centralized log-in server that would take people all over the world logging
into the game.
It was in one source at that time.
And then we would distribute the people to the appropriate shards that are going out
to the different parts of the United States.
And in fact, I want to make a comment about shards.
Even that term, shards, was born out
of a unfortunate crisis of our success.
We planned for everyone who was playing the game
to live in one world.
We thought we'd built this world 10 times bigger
than our own estimates were 10 times as big as EA's.
We thought, oh, you know, 30,000,
we'll make at least 300,000 sales.
And of course, as soon as they're selling,
it pretty quickly in the first month or two
sold over a million units.
And so as we saw that coming, we realized we couldn't fit everybody into one world.
And for me, that was sort of a tragedy.
That actually meant that we were going to have to separate people who, from that moment
forward, would have different experiences than each other.
And so I thought, you know, how can we fictionally make that okay and make that these, this multiverse
feel like a single world?
And so
If you've watched the introduction to Ultima Online,
we made up this fiction where Mondain,
the evil wizard out of Ultima I,
who survived because of his gem of immortality,
and you in Ultima I go and break it into shards,
that at that moment, copies of the state of reality
were copied into each of those shards,
and so you would go play in one or the other
of those shards, but in theory,
they could be unified again.
We actually had this big plot we'd put together
about players being able to collect these shards.
and be able to reforge it and reunify these separated worlds.
And that at least made me feel fictionally comfortable
that we were splitting people up.
And of course we never did that recombination point.
But what I think is really ironic is I go to talks where people will be talking about
servers that have nothing to do with games,
where they'll keep a server up to date in the US and Europe and Japan,
and they keep them identical.
but they call them separated as shards.
And so other industries have picked up this piece of fiction
about Mondain's gym.
Ha.
Yep.
And the neat thing about the shards
is each one grew up differently.
So the role-playing shards were in the central US.
The PK shards were in the Northeast of the country,
as well as in the Pacific became where.
those were PK shards.
And it's amazing how each one evolved differently,
which was kind of cool.
But also when we were tracking bugs,
sometimes we realized things would happen over here
way before things would happen in the central
because the PKers are doing something
that the role-playing shards weren't doing.
And it was interesting to keep up with all that.
Yep.
Moving on.
So one of the things that we did when we launched
was you only get one launch.
Now we say, don't launch until you're ready.
And because we have now early access and things like that,
you really have to be very careful about when to launch.
And I think that has been a lesson we've
been trying to preach ever since you all launched,
that don't launch until you're ready.
And you see all the different catastrophes
that happen when people are launching
because of other reasons.
Basically, I look at that as making short-term decisions
on a long-term bet.
You have to balance out.
What's more important? This thing is a living, breathing organism, so to speak, when you launch,
and you're just beginning. So it's really important to get whatever you're going to
reveal out the public test to be at a certain level of quality that you can get people to
continue playing the game. That's really, really important. One of the other things we learned
because we broke up in shards was the whole...
population control.
So, we had to have mechanisms to backfill our shards because
what we didn't want to do is open up too many shards where
you have a dispersed population problem where suddenly you have
low population on servers and high population on other servers
and what that does is you really can't close down a shard easily.
You just can't because especially a persistent
world shard, that's really, really hard to do and collapse.
So, basically what we had to do in order to do that.
is make sure that if you had people coming in,
we'd backfill to the lower shards.
And other thing is escalation plans are really important.
So one of the things we did,
we had no escalation plan at all
for whether anything happened.
So we had to develop a whole escalation plan
or a runbook on the service.
And one of the biggest things about,
one of the things I always talk about is,
there's a lot of hidden work to do on a Games as a Service
that we learned in Ultima Online.
30% is a game and 70% is a service layer underneath it.
And so it's really important to understand that.
And one of the things we went on the services side
that was important is understanding
how to manage community.
Because of what happened on UO, if everyone remembers
the lawsuit and things like that,
we got kind of silenced for a while, which hurt our
we started to see, we actually had analytics on the game.
We actually could see DAU, MAU, WAU.
We had all that.
We actually could see the population starting to drop
and churns starting to happen because we couldn't communicate
well because of the lawsuit.
And once I said, you know what, we're not doing that.
We're not listening to the lawyer.
We have to start communicating to our audience.
And we could not act like a PR piece.
So there was this friction between PR,
because everything we said, because we're connected,
gets broadcast everywhere.
And so what we learned is.
we went back in and started talking to the community again,
we started climbing again in growth.
It was amazing to watch.
So that's how important it is.
And again, another thing that's really hard
is we had a whole bunch of people playing in beta
that never told us about the exploits that were happening.
They waited before we go live.
Then they had these sites developed
because it was really important
because people could actually sell items on eBay.
And so they wanted to exploit things in the game
so they can make a lot of money.
Dr. Twister was one of our favorite sites
that would have a whole bunch of area people talk
about the exploits in the game.
Yeah.
Basically, because we designed a game
for a tenth of the audience in a world,
a whole bunch of solutions that we knew pretty well, actually,
from previous online games, from text mods,
broke under the pressure of the quantity of players.
One of those, most critically, and actually the single largest,
most damaging design choice.
was that we had open player killing.
It easily cost us well over half the users, right?
We tried so many things.
I think there were, how many did you say yesterday?
Seven?
Seven complete redesigns of flagging systems,
notoriety systems, karma systems, bounty systems.
The bounty system turned into a high score table.
for player killers.
Because the emergent behavior problem of people working
around what was going on, right?
We'd lost track of the power of a small community to control
through peer pressure fell apart, right?
And that was kind of a key lesson.
But it's interesting to point out here though too,
it's interesting, you know, when we talk about,
when people come up to me and tell me their favorite stories
from the UO era, it almost always.
almost invariably includes bad behavior of one kind or another.
Yes. People cheating, exploiting, PKing, or you know, in some other way,
you know, taking advantage of others. About once a week I hear somebody say,
oh, Fortnite, H1Z1, PUBG, yeah, those are just spiritual successors to UO player killing.
Yeah. I hear that about once a week from somebody. We hear stories like Phil gave a,
from Sony, he runs Sony, he gave a speech of how he got in games, and he gave a speech about UO.
and about the PKing he did and how much fun it was.
And that's how he got into games.
He loved it.
Of course, there was this other emergent thing.
So all of our objects were dynamic,
so they were streamed down, except the ones
that shipped on the CD, and those were static.
But we forgot to lock down a bunch of stuff as static,
and that meant that it respawned every time the server booted.
And that meant people grabbed all of this stuff.
They looted the candelabras off the dining room tables.
They stole trees, patches of water,
would put the patches of water in their backpack,
and they could fish out of them because the simulation was
that real.
These then became called rares.
And pretty soon, people started transacting them on eBay.
And then people said, well, let's
hunt for these on purpose on eBay in order to make money.
And then they said, wait, why do you intermediate the rarest?
Let's just gather gold.
And so gold farming was born.
First, they started contracting to Mexico, then eventually
to China, in order to swarm in and get all of the gold
as quickly as possible.
And then a bunch of companies said, wait a minute,
why don't we just sell the gold directly?
And gradually, microtransactions were born, and eventually
all of free-to-play, because we forgot to lock down
the fricking candelabra.
So free-to-play is our fault.
Yeah.
Sorry.
GMs.
One of the biggest lessons I learned,
and this came from MUDs that I was involved in previously,
is we had people in the game, literally,
as GMs and counselors.
And there were huge challenges for that.
We should never have done that.
It was something that we should have done a lot differently.
To have GMs in the game, there were problems.
GMs could be bribed.
GMs could do things for players or make money themselves
through eBay.
And that actually did happen.
One of the good things is we did have logging turned on,
so we can log everything that's happened.
But we didn't know about it until players reported it.
And we actually went in and investigated.
So we had a lot of issues of abuse because of that.
And we had a very powerful God client
that we gave the game masters and counselors in the game
to use.
And so we learned how to lock things down.
And one of the biggest things is, you can see the games today versus games then,
is we started pulling away from GMs present in the game 24 by 7.
That's a huge cost, by the way.
Someone coming in the game, responding to your things within 24 by 7,
it's just crazy from a cost wise.
We definitely, it was one of the biggest mistakes we learned.
And you can definitely see as games progressed, they didn't do that anymore.
Yeah, gradually what we realized is that we had founded.
a community that actually at the time was approximately the size of San Antonio.
Yeah.
Right?
We were running a city.
And so I actually started reading about politics and government stuff
because it became apparent that's what we were doing.
We were actually the government.
We had corrupt cops that we had to monitor.
So we needed an internal affairs department.
We need all of these things.
We started modeling like a government.
One example of that is how we ran patch notes.
It used to be, this is actually the very first patch note
in Ultima Online, very first patch one week after launch.
And what we did was we ran forums
to communicate with players.
Think of this as like running town halls.
We eventually actually called it the House of Commons.
We, instead of just writing code,
would actually post up proposed changes to the law
and allow a period of public comment,
just like in the real world.
And then it would go into testing on a separate server.
so that people could go in and try it out.
And then only after that process,
you know, things could be sent back to committee
or moved forward.
We literally just started running it
as if it were a government.
Yeah, we had a whole organization,
online services group that would go through
all the feedback that was coming in
from test center, the community,
and also from customer support would come up
and we all talk about what the next patch is going to be.
Yeah, it's important to realize there were people doing this job out there in the world,
but the title community manager was kind of not a thing.
No, no.
Right.
In fact, I remember the first time we went to my brother Robert and said we want to hire
someone whose job is going to be community management.
And my brother was like, well, well, what is the productivity of their output?
Because they're deliverable.
that can justify a headcount expense.
And he said, well, you know,
they're gonna talk to the community.
He's going like, that sounds really valuable.
It was actually really hard to do.
I mean, now we wouldn't have forced start without it.
But I mean, it was really hard to make that sales.
Yeah, I probably spent 20 plus hours a week on that job.
He was the best community manager we had was Ralph.
And there's a certain thing we learned
what you needed in a community manager.
And we were a connected community.
EA was never used to that.
And because we were a connected community,
we had hundreds of thousands of people
that had a voice out there.
And that's when something happened,
Larry Prost knew about it.
That's how bad, that's how it connected.
Speaking of which, I mean, this is what happened, right?
It's, this period of time was really hard for us
because the lawsuit didn't, literally got settled later.
But it was something that caused a lot of,
tension between the group, the development group, and EA because again, we can't just
live without talking to our community.
We can't be silent.
It won't work.
And our numbers showed that until we started talking to the community again.
And if you're wondering why you can't find like original design Bibles for UO out there
on the internet, it's because they're actually all sitting in an EA legal file cabinet for
discovery for this lawsuit.
I had to send a stack of paper this tall,
and I never saw it again.
No, we never did.
It was just sad.
The other thing is, we talk about community.
We had a big community of all.
Wait, you skipped Richard's on this one.
What was I going to say?
Well, one thing I just want to say about this, too,
is just to go back to something we were talking about earlier,
is that we were a team of about 8 to 12 people,
and we got Ultima Online done in two years and three months.
You compare now to where the industry has gone to where we build these giant teams
To build you know these these amazing products
But I feel like we've gotten into this trap where we think we need 300 people to build something
and we forget about the negative momentum that comes with building these giant teams and
I think we need to remind ourselves of how a small and agile team can do amazing things.
But it is interesting to point out the picture in the upper left of that screenshot there,
which is the team size at the end, which is somewhere between 50 and 100 people that,
you know, only a few months prior to the end was under 10 people.
And by the way, one month later after launch, you see that huge team there?
Want to guess how many and who was left?
Literally, this is it.
Everybody else moved on.
Yeah, and we had 12 people to run this thing.
And I was just like, and then we had.
We had to hire them out of the player base
because nobody inside the company had worked on you.
We were it, everybody else moved on.
The most panic moment I had was when all my programmers
left at once to form another company
that just wanted to leave.
And I go, oh crap, what do we do now?
All right, now we can go here, right?
The thing is the what we'd unleashed, right?
You know, to this day, like for example,
I mentioned the patch notes, right?
So we also used to write essays.
Essays that were, here's what we think philosophically
about the future of virtual worlds.
Today, those essays are articles on Wikipedia, right?
We didn't really realize quite the extent
of the impact we were having.
all of these well-known community sites and networks, IGN,
used to once upon a time started as the UO Vault, right?
And UO Vault, right?
Like UO Vault and Crossroads.
Crossroads, we had to sponsor them.
I actually had to pull them in and run on our service
because they couldn't afford the hits
that they were getting on the sites
and they were actually going under.
I said, don't go under.
We'll just take you, put you up until you get your.
getting on your feet again.
So about a year and a half until EQ and other games
started coming out, they started,
and Ashwin's Call, they started getting on their feet again
and getting enough ad revenue.
We actually hosted those sites to keep them alive.
That's how valuable we thought community was.
It was a great move to do because it definitely
helped the whole community.
Yeah, there are guilds still running today,
holding annual conventions that are on their third generation
of guild members in one family today, coming together.
Shout out LLTS, anybody?
Yeah.
the syndicate, ShadowClan.
And one of my favorite stories, there
was a really young guy, newlywed at the time,
who he'd done cartooning while he was at school.
And he really wanted to be a cartoonist.
So he started making a UO fan comic strip.
And I loved it, so I featured it on the UO website.
It was all about Samwise the Bard and Skull the Troll.
Anybody here read PVP Online?
Yeah, so today, this is Scott Kurtz, Harvey and Eisner
award-winning cartoonist.
You know, stuff like that is what was born out
of this community.
We had managed to build that San Antonio-sized city,
and it gave us fruit in ways that we absolutely never, ever
expected.
So yeah, I mean, some amount of you here in this room
are probably here.
I get people coming up saying.
This is the reason I'm in games.
I get that all the time.
So that leads us to talking about some of the crazy.
So we'll go through this quickly,
because I want to leave time for questions.
So that was the heartwarming part.
And there was some seedier sides to our community.
So we were very excited.
We were going to start our beta.
And the servers spin up.
a male character spawns in.
So we're all online watching.
A female character spawns in.
And the first thing they say to each other is,
do you want a cyber?
And basically, that involved taking all your clothes off
and bowing in front of each other
and typing nasty messages.
That, within a week, had evolved into a prostitution ring
at the end of one of the.
empty buildings along the docks in the capital town of Britain run by a character named Fly Guy
who used our elaborate dyeing system of the clothing to dye his he wore this cavalier's hat
you know it had a big feather in it dyed it bright colors he had a stable of ladies that you would
pay him gold and then they would go and the buildings were empty so he commandeered him
and then you would go into the building where no one could see
And then they would type dirty messages.
And so that was the first thriving business in our game.
Not smithing.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
Not carpentry.
So I mean, the world's oldest profession was true.
And I mean, he made more money at the beginning
than anybody else in our game.
Yeah.
So one of the things we did for all our team
was we put them through CS training.
So we actually had them come in and be actually GMs
in the game, because it helped us.
And I was on call, and suddenly I got a whole bunch
of messages, and basically people were putting in
these runes into the banks where you couldn't see them
until you got into, as you entered the bank,
it teleports you to an island.
They would take your clothes off and rob you,
and then leave you there without any way of getting away.
And so I got my call, and I said, oh my God,
I can't believe this is happening.
And I go out there on the island,
there's a whole bunch of naked people yelling at me.
And I said, OK, I get it.
I'll go get, first, let's get your clothes on.
And then we'll get you moved out of here and teleported out.
But that was, the amount of exploits in this game
were just incredible.
I remember just real quickly on Christmas, I was a knock.
So I was a network operations center.
I ran the knock on Christmas Eve because I
wanted to give the people time off.
So what we did is we had Santa spawn a reindeer.
during to celebrate Christmas.
Suddenly, a whole bunch of,
our spawning system went out of control.
And then we didn't realize that people
could take the Santa suits off the Santas.
And so we had a whole bunch of Santas
running around naked saying, ho, ho, ho.
And then a PK guild formed,
a Santa PK guild formed after that.
It was notorious.
And the person that I hired as my lead programmer
ran that guild.
He didn't tell me until a year afterwards,
by the way, I ran that guild.
I said, you.
Oh, I can't believe that. And then we gave out charcoal, we thought was kind of cool,
to the, you know, to the people, the bad people, the bad reputation people. Then we didn't realize
that, oh my God, that actually could turn their armor into pure black, which made it rare. Yeah.
Yeah. And, you know, what was, what was interesting about these first days is,
you know, the quality of the service was abhorrent.
And it wasn't that we didn't know it.
I mean, we were in there playing alongside everybody, right?
But again, going back to the lack of government,
you know, in the real world, if you have complaints,
you know, there's a variety of levels of government
you can complain to, whether it's your school board
or your neighborhood association or whatever it might be.
In our case, you know, we had hundreds of thousands
of players all in, all seeing the same bugs,
all trying to tell us, trying to communicate to us
in some way, hey, I believe I've seen a unique bug.
It's not unique, but they believed it might be.
And they're not getting a response individually back from us.
And so they think we're not listening.
So they're convinced that we are ignoring
these very obvious problems that everyone is having.
Yet, at the same time, they're really enjoying the game.
I mean, they understood what this moment meant
from a gaming perspective.
And so they didn't want to leave the game,
which they could easily have done.
They could easily have given up and just gone away.
Instead, they decided to have protests in the game.
And because by doing that, by the way,
it made things much worse.
And so they thought, if we don't pay attention
to the laggy service and failures,
crashes based upon overloading areas,
we're just going to double down and make it even worse.
So they would love to go break into places.
This one is in some town, but they also
did it in our castle, in Lord Brutus' castle,
where we actually had to go unlock the doors for them
to let them in.
But then once they came in.
They all took off all their clothes.
They all started drinking heavily, which makes you then vomit.
And then they all started, so not only was the castle just covered in puke,
naked bodies running around, bumbling around.
And everybody's also screaming obscenities.
And by this, they hope they're going to get our attention.
And we, of course, we thought it was the greatest thing since sliced bread.
My favorite was.
My favorite was when they all got in a line and turned around and bowed and mooned all of you in the city of Moonglow.
Yes. And we had GMs approach there because we wanted to control the crowd.
We had to teleport people out and they didn't like that very much. They started mooning us.
So early on our philosophy was when things were going weird like this,
we didn't want to solve it by pulling away from the simulation.
So for example, this here is the city of Trinzic and a group of player killers said,
they formed a carpenter player killer guild.
And that gate up at the front, they just barricaded it
with tens of thousands of armoires and desks and chairs
so that nobody could get out.
And everybody who spawned into Trinzic
had to leave through the tiny little one-tile-wide gate
at the bottom where they couldn't see what was happening
and got hit in the back of the head the minute they came out.
And this siege of Trinzic lasted all the way
till the next patch, which is when
we patched in the ability for axes to chop furniture apart.
So our approach early on was.
let's run with the emergence instead of away from it.
And that's a philosophy that honestly I wish more games
still pursued.
Yeah, give them the tools.
And they actually had the tools to do that and get out of it.
So real quick, because I want to get to the awesome part.
So we had one player that, using the clothing system again,
assumed this character of Hulk Hogan
and would dress basically in red underwear and blonde hair.
And he challenged my character, Blackthorn.
He kept issuing these taunts to me to use the unarmed combat skill to do a wrestling match
And so we totally embraced this and we had a series of wrestling matches. They were player events
And it was theater troops sports leagues
You name it. Yeah, but of course, you know the the peak of player most famous event most famous event. Yeah. Yeah, so
Yeah, this this one's literally in the history books
During the development, this event happened close to the end of the beta period.
We were debating exactly what date it was.
I'll have to go look it up.
But close to the end, and as you might have guessed,
every now and then during the beta, we would do wipes, right?
We'd have to reset the whole service, we'd have enough changes,
the data structures fundamentally change.
And that meant all of us had to go rebuild our characters again, including me.
And when you rebuild your character,
one of the things that was really important for me to do...
was to turn on a little flag called invulnerability.
And because already in all Ultimas and in Ultima Online,
people were regularly trying to gank me.
And so I had the programmers put in this ability
to make myself immortal.
And so people had given up trying
because I was always immortal.
Until this day.
When we had been going around giving speeches,
going town to town, telling everybody,
thank you very much for coming and participating in the beta
and we were getting ready to launch
and how excited we were to be there.
And we were broadcasting the whole GM announce that would announce across all cities at the same time
But we would teleport from city to city to kind of make an appearance and we were at the last appearance here on Trinzic up
on the parapet wall that you can see there when a gentleman by the name of rains
cast a fire field right around where Star and I were standing.
And I strolled into it and I'm like,
ha-ha, you think that can hurt me because I had remembered to turn my invulnerability flag on.
And I thought, ha-ha, I'm immortal too.
And so I walked into that fire field and fell over dead.
And what was amazing about this moment
is to see what the reaction was
both in the community of players surrounding and at origin.
Because again, we had no back channel communication
amongst ourselves other than the in-house phone system.
And that phone system couldn't have all of us
at the same time.
There were groups of us on the phone
together separate from other groups.
And so the QA people see Lord Brist go down.
And they're going like, well, how do we get him back to life?
And Star sees me go down.
And I'm going, whoo, is all I can say, because I'm a ghost.
And so everybody's scrambling to figure out what to do.
And Star comes up with a brilliant idea.
Yeah, so I unleashed a bunch of demons in the crowd.
And then we had GMs protecting him
so no one could loot his body.
But it was really funny just because at that moment,
it really was for us just one of these kind
of joyous emergent moments.
Yeah, I mean, the king was dead, right?
And I think for all of us, that was the moment
that we realized, right?
This was no longer about control.
right? The new rulers of our virtual world that now we all play in all the time.
This was really the moment when we realized the players are going to be the ones who topple
the kings. This was the moment we realized what we had set free. You, right? We had set
you free. And, you know, no offense, but Richard was no longer the ruler of fantasy worlds.
The power was now.
in your hands and from the bottom of all of our hearts
I think we actually want to say thank you
for that. Thank you so much. Thank you for killing Richard.
Don't do it again.
So you know, the CA's promised to give me time signals,
and those lights are so bright, I can't even see the CA.
So we have five minutes.
Five minutes.
So timed perfectly.
Good.
So there's time for just enough questions,
but there's way too many of you.
We have access to the two overflow rooms over there.
So if we run out of time, please meet us over there.
Please do remember to fill out the surveys.
Fives are a wonderful number.
We really like the number five.
All right, Dr. Katt, we shouted out to you earlier.
You weren't here.
We gave you a shout out, a screenshot and everything.
All right.
Yeah.
What's up?
I'm going to have to look on the vault.
I got here two minutes late and I missed my moment.
I just wanted to ask you guys during those first couple of minutes.
Did you also give a shout out to James Van Aertsdalen who tried to make
Multima based on Ultima IV code briefly in the 1980s?
We covered some of the history of previous Multimas.
But not that one in particular, no.
But not that one.
Yeah.
So yeah, shout out to James Van Aerts, Dale,
and to who made the first attempt to bring that up.
Yeah, because how many were there?
It was actually, you guys tried for years.
We talked about it for years and years and years.
We just never really got momentum until Ultima.
All right, next question, anyone?
Yes.
Yeah, I just wanted to say, I was a longtime player,
and both in the counselor and SEER program.
The SEER program is something that I've never really seen
the equivalent of since.
Do you have any thoughts on that?
And having players doing interest events
in a truly massive game.
Yeah, it's a pattern out of mud, right?
Yeah, it is.
It's one of those things that you don't tend to see
done as much because of legal risks
around volunteer systems.
which we had to work around carefully.
And because of scale, right?
It just, you know, it becomes hard to manage.
Yeah, let me take a run at it too though,
which is the problem is when you give them anything,
any powers beyond any other user.
And so the way we, the approach we're now taking
with our new game is to, you know,
if you think about who in the real world
are good storytellers or good chefs to make restaurants
or good architects that make buildings,
there's a natural competition to weed out
bad creators, if you know what I mean.
Their work, their plot of land,
the taxes on it becomes too much and they go away
and somebody who does a better job comes in on their stead.
And that's why normally in a virtual world,
if you unleash too much power to everyone equally,
not everyone is a great creator
and so you end up with a world full of trash.
And so versus bequest power to seers,
we're now believers in bequest the power to everybody.
just give an ability, a cost to put things in the world
that otherwise it gets cleaned up.
And that way only the good creators' stuff persists.
We had in Star Wars Galaxies ended up
eventually launching what was called a storyteller system,
which allowed players to gain access
to a constrained set of tools
so that they could build quests and run events for one another.
But it was a constrained set rather than basically handing
an all-powerful client off to strangers.
Thank you.
Any more?
Oh, come on.
There we go.
Oh, it's a question.
Thanks so much for making this incredible game.
I am curious about the degradation of houses
and sort of major, you know, you worked a long time
to get a house, and then you managed
to find a spot to place it, and then you don't show up
for a while and it goes away.
Yeah.
I'd love to hear more about the design.
Sure.
We didn't have enough space.
When we expected 1 10th of the number of players on the map,
we had left clearings for that many houses.
And instead, 1 in 10 players could find space for a house.
There are features, probably still live in the game,
where those clearings, it used to be before players populated
every space, we would actually spawn NPC camps and buildings
in those.
that you could come in and fight them, the orc camps and whatnot.
And after enough houses were placed,
that feature never happened again, because people couldn't even,
there was no place to spawn those.
So we had to have decay, and we had to have cleanup in the system,
tuning how quickly and how fast,
particularly given that there was unlimited ability to store things in the house.
So to give people some perspective,
you guys think Battlefield or something has a lot of dynamic stuff running around in it?
you know, hundreds of players and hundreds of bullets flying.
Any given arbitrary house in U.O. probably had 20 to 30,000
dynamic objects simultaneously, each of them capable
of running scripted behaviors in real time, right?
So yeah, we had to clean it up.
We didn't have a choice.
Yeah.
And it was also a matter of maintaining interest
for other people as well.
So if someone would just go and claim land and then
never use it. That for us, that was a waste of community space, right? And so
that was another reason for the decay. Thanks. All right, well why don't we...
We're out of time, so why don't we move outside. So we're gonna go to the
overflow space 22... what is it? 2022 and 2024.