All right. I think we're good to go. Our nice little intimate gathering here. We're going
to remember who among you have chosen to come here instead of the Dolby panel that was pitted
against us. So thank you. Like I said, I'm taking down names here. I'm Austin.
Hi, I'm Christian from Ubisoft Quebec.
And we're basically just going to dive right in here.
Yep.
So I want to hear.
OK.
So as I said, I am Christian from New South Quebec.
I'm the music supervisor.
Worked on Assassin's Creed Syndicate, of course.
And on that game, what I did was music direction, music design,
editing of the music, integration for a score,
and also initial research and design for the source music
aspect of the game.
So in this presentation, what we're
going to talk about roughly is how
we define the vision for the music in Assassin's Creed
Syndicate, how we came to work with Austin on the music
direction for the game, and afterwards, an overview
of a couple of music systems from the game,
and also aspects of the score.
So, how this all began. Basically we were at a summer party for the studio, drinking
beer, everything was fun. And there were rumors flying around that our boss would announce
you know the next big project for the studio. And he did. It was, you know, we were going
to work on the next main Assassin's Creed game, Syndicate.
So reactions all around were, you know, people were surprised,
really happy.
And it was an incredible opportunity for the studio,
because, you know, it was Ubisoft Montreal that
did the main games before.
Now it was us, you know, our turn in the spotlight.
So we wanted to make our mark with this game.
As for me, what that meant, we were without an audio director
at that point.
So it fell on me to define the music direction
for the game for that moment.
And our audio director on that project, Lydia.
Andrew wouldn't come in until a couple of months later.
So I did research on forums, articles, editorials,
about what music means to gamers and to Assassin's Creed fans.
Also, I talked with the directors
from the previous Assassin's Creed games
to see how they came about defining
their vision and their direction for the music.
And my conclusion from all that research
was that defining that vision for the music
wasn't about finding specific instrumentation
or style of composer.
It was about really finding what was the philosophy, what
was the way of thinking behind how
we would get to those parameters, those specifics.
So the next step was building a brief for the pitch process
to find our composer.
And there was this word that kept.
popping back in my mind, and it was potential.
For every game, every game has its own unique set
of parameters, their own specifics.
So every game has their own setting.
They take place in their own era.
They take place in their own fantasy world,
or maybe in space.
They have their own story, their own characters.
All that translates into musical opportunities.
For Assassin's Creed Syndicate.
Those opportunities, it's a game about, at the same time,
it's science fiction and it's historical fiction.
That means it's a clash of genres, of eras,
of instruments, of musical influences.
All that is musical opportunities to exploit.
And Victorian London is also shock-full of musical opportunities to explore.
It's full of contrasts, it's full of cultures, it's full of all the social classes from the
poorest child factory worker to the richest banker walking side by side on the streets.
It's also very vivid in the pop culture imagination.
Everyone has expectations of what Victorian London should be.
look like and sound like. Also, our story, you know, Jacob and Evie, the characters,
their brother and sister, their siblings, but they're also rivals, so musical opportunity.
You know, the assassins versus the Templars, and you can go even more abstract, like concepts
like one versus all, past versus present, poor versus rich, all that musical opportunities.
Which leads me for real now to the...
That's a subtle way of saying you moved the slide early.
Exactly.
To the pitch process.
Now that we knew what we were looking for, someone to fully tap into all those possible
opportunities, all that potential, I built the pitch brief that we were going to send
to the composers.
And as it was our first contact with the composers...
We put a lot of attention to the language, the wording,
the tone in that document.
So we were making sure that we would communicate
our enthusiasm as much as possible.
We were looking to drive home the point
that we were looking to be surprised by the pitches,
that we were ready for anything to bring it, to take risks,
to be bold, basically.
Which leads me to our experience working with Austin on that pitch.
He responded to that call with an incredible pitch.
It was bold, risky, like we wanted, and even more.
He rose up to the challenge and basically surprised us with, you know, it was really...
Psychotic.
I'm speechless, so that should give you an impression.
I have to add to that before I kind of dive into my forthcoming slice of this,
that what he's describing was this pitch document which said the exact things that he just spelled out.
You know, challenge us, surprise us, don't be overly caught up by the fact that this
is Assassin's Creed, which has a long-running musical history, treat it as whatever comes
to mind, you know, and whatever your instincts are.
In other words, you're not beholden to the previous musical ideas in the prior games
if that's not what speaks to you.
And of course I thought that they were bullshitting.
Because I thought, you know, it's a long-running and widely beloved musical legacy within this franchise,
so surely they don't actually want to abandon that, but I decided I would take them at their word,
and I was fully prepared to never hear from them again.
And happily, that's not how that worked out.
And what's really interesting about that pitch is it became really the template for what the score would become in the future.
And we would actually iterate upon what that pitch was stylistically to get to the final result for most of the aspects of the score.
So, I'm going to play you what I sent them.
And...
By the way, I want to bring up that who here submitted questions on the gang Facebook page
in advance a couple months ago? I put a post on, and a bunch of people did, although I
think they're all in the Dolby panel right now.
I'm sorry for my voice if I'm downgrading into a 14 year old boy in front of your eyes
here.
It's end of GDC voice.
In any case, I just wanted to make mention of the questions we got in advance because
I've tried to build basically all of them that we got into the talk.
Because one of the questions involved the sort of evolution and the derivation of thematic
material in the score.
And the reason I'm bringing that up now is because that all began at this moment with
the initial pitch.
Because I looked at the...
The material they sent, which included things like the brief about Jacob and Evie as siblings
slash rivals, and that there's a sort of overtone of their struggling with legacy, their father,
and these kinds of things.
And so I said, this seems like something that...
It's about the two of them as a unit, as opposed to two different separate arcs that I wanted to think of differently.
It was all about their journey together.
And then also, just sort of looking at the overview of the setting and what that implies.
And so I came up with a thing that I kind of jokingly...
I'm going to play a little bit of a video that I made, half jokingly, because it's sort of
accurate, called Neo Mendelssohn music. And not actually because there's a period accuracy to
that approach, I actually tend to avoid things that are designed to be period authentic,
is the period. Why are we going to be redundant to that through the score when the game is
already solving that for us? So instead, despite the fact that this is sort of drawing from
a period authenticity, the idea was I want to do music which feels like that of a pair
of sarcastic assassins. You know, one of the things I really liked that the game has a
bit in common with Black Flag was that the main...
The main characters of Jacob and Evie had a lot of personality.
They weren't sort of like the glowery, brooding heroes.
They're young and arrogant and different from each other.
But nonetheless, I'd say they have that in common.
They were kind of cocky and very aware of how skilled they were.
So I thought a musical language which...
It has that nimble light on its feet quality, but there's also a sort of sarcasm to it,
was sort of the idea.
So I sent them, I did kind of a test recording.
That's loud and crazy.
Make sure we are sufficiently high volume, though I don't want to kill you all.
But it was fun, because I said, you know, how about this?
This transcript was provided by Transcription Outsourcing, LLC.
So I sent more than that, but that's kind of like a taste of the sort of, you know,
the neo Mendelssohn.
Although, funny enough, well, I'm getting ahead of myself.
I'll stick with that.
Could you all hear that all right?
Because with the speakers facing away from us, it's impossible to tell what that sounded
like.
Is that all right?
It's sufficiently loud and not weirdly phasy and stuff?
Okay.
So that's just our perspective.
All right, moving on.
That's my turn, right?
All right.
So with the music for this game, we
were trying to achieve, well, a lot of things.
But our major goals were to ensure natural music flow,
musical flow in the game.
What that means, roughly, for transitions between cues,
we wanted to have.
as little amount of fading as possible, as little cross-fades, fade-ins, fade-outs as
possible, and go more towards on-the-grid transitions, so on-the-beat, on-the-bar transitions
from one cue to another, not cross-fades.
What that meant for the music systems, it meant that we would prioritize that music
flow idea over gameplay feedback or responsiveness of the systems as weird as that may sound.
Also, preventing interruptions of the music
as much as possible.
You know how you can get tutorial screens that
would pause the music.
We didn't want that.
We wanted the music to play through that.
That also goes for loading screens, for cinematics,
ins and outs, and all that sort of cases.
Have the music play through that.
And to prevent starting and stopping,
constant starting and stopping of the music
as much as possible, especially for the comeback music,
where that tends to happen a lot in open world games.
You would get into fight scenarios.
The music would start, and then you
finish the fight really quickly, and the music
stops immediately.
We didn't want that.
Which leads me to a gang forum question about how we worked, me and Austin, for asset integration in the game.
And specifically Austin's involvement in that.
Basically, Austin didn't have any direct role in the actual implementation of the music in the game.
But it did have a very important influence on it, because from all the discussions we had at the very beginning about
exactly that, the musical flow, that
influenced how, you know, my style of integration and editing of the music in the game.
Yeah, just to quickly jump on that. I flew up to their offices in Quebec in January,
you know, a year and change ago.
to kick off the project and I, you know, he pulled up his sort of working document of
the plans for the score, you know, the, you know, not so much a cue sheet yet as it was
just kind of like a breakdown of systems and outline of kind of what the plan was going
to be, which was taken from, I think, previous titles and then, you know, molded and shaped
based on where you were planning on.
But what was so great is that on titles like this, it's not that common that one of the
first questions from he and Lydia was, and here's what we're planning, what do you think?
And I said, oh, I get to have an opinion.
That's usually not a problem.
There's one part of all the pitch thing that I skipped over, because this could last for
three hours.
And it will.
We are locking the doors.
It is that we really wanted to have Austin's input from,
you know, as early as possible, from everything
from the systems to the music direction and all that.
Sadly, for some aspects, this didn't happen.
I'll show you later.
Yeah, so the point being that I, one
of the first things I remember saying
is, as someone who has played pretty much all the prior AC
games.
I was always, I always wished we had a little bit tighter control on, for example, the combat
music, and because it's such a massive pet peeve of mine when you're playing games that
have a lot of recurring sort of systemic combat that every time you sort of, even so much
as someone gives you a funny look, this roaring epic music comes rushing in.
And then it's like, oh, no, no, we're cool.
And then it suddenly has to figure out how to stop playing.
And I was just like, I hate that.
It's bad storytelling.
And so I said, can we not do that?
And he said, already planning on not doing it.
And I was like, oh, god, this is so good already.
It was so happy.
Because, yeah, an emphasis on things being musical
so that they can actually serve the experience
and serve the narrative, as opposed
to being just these kind of mechanical byproducts
of a very cool sort of clockwork machine that is designed.
It's like, that's really not the point of the music,
even though we do want it to be pretty reactive.
So yeah, when it came to integration and Wwise,
that was all taking place up at your office
while I was in Los Angeles.
But.
But they were very, very open to my saying, you know,
can we do this, can we do that, can we do that,
and constantly offering my two cents.
Yeah, even though all the music was driven, well,
for the open world part, driven by music systems,
we didn't want to be slaves to that in the sense
that we wanted to see all the possible game plays
and side activities and combat, all the systems
in the open world.
Not as distinct, separate chunks of gameplay,
but are they all interconnected together
and what that means for the music.
So yeah.
So getting back to that.
So for the music systems, what we want to do
is predict the player's intentions
and score their stories.
And it goes back to what I just said, basically.
And only if it's worth scoring. What that means is if you go in a back alley and fight a low level guy and get done with it in 5 seconds, maybe that's not worth having music over.
Compared to fighting 7 high level guys and being in a very tense situation.
That's it.
I thought of it as this very kind of...
subtly judgmental aspect to the score, where it's like some very easily picked off enemy
comes wandering up to you and the music looks at him and says, you're not really worth my
time. Yeah, you know, if, you know, trying to find
out if the player is going on a killing spree for half an hour or just, you know, killing
that one guy and going on his way was basically the core of what we were trying to solve as
a problem in the music system.
Exactly.
Just a brief word.
I kind of obviously already touched on this, so I can blast through this.
But just for me, a big thing on starting any project is to try to define as rigorously
as I can for myself some kind of sense of musical vocabulary.
And I think Jason Graves mentioned this beautifully in his Evolve talk the other day, where he
was...
Because I have the same mentality, which is how can I sort of fence off...
The first thing I will do is I will try to restrict myself as much as possible and restrict myself as tightly as possible so that things start to intuitively have this sense of that feels like syndicate and that doesn't.
The more I restrict options for myself the more things can have that quality.
If it was just everything in the kitchen sink approach, then I would have to restrict myself to the minimum.
then nothing would intuitively feel right or wrong quite as easily.
And I really always try to make every project have kind of its own little musical universe.
So like I said in this one, a kind of modernized 19th century chamber music approach.
And the reason I liked that was not because of the flourishing of chamber music in the 19th century,
though as kind of a cool benefit that is true.
The idea was something that felt light on its feet,
something that felt like an assassin,
something that could easily turn corners,
as opposed to the kind of big lumbering dinosaur.
Emotionally significant, though it is,
there's something kind of large and lumbering
about an orchestral approach that just didn't seem right.
I thought the way they move,
the way that the game's rhythm sort of plays out.
This game...
The Quebec studio was really working really hard to make this game feel really fresh and
really kind of like AC, you know, rethought all over again and to really kind of re-inspire
people to be excited about Assassin's Creed.
And so there was a snappiness to it that I was just loving and I said that's what the
music needs to kind of reflect.
We don't want to go the big melodramatic kind of direction.
heavy percussion, heavy synths, that sort of thing, and wanted to do, to try to be a
little bit more musically intimate, with the caveat being that when we're recording chamber
music and we're pushing right in on these musicians, it's actually way more visceral,
because you're getting bow strings inches away from the mic, and so it feels in this
tactile way right in your face.
And so one of the things I'm going to get to more in a bit,
though, was also evolving that orchestrational palette
through the course of the game as well.
So fencing off as small of a kind of lawn musical playground
for myself as I could, but giving myself latitude
so that it wasn't just this one thing for the entire 30
hours of the game or so.
I'd just like to add that.
What you just talked about, how being smaller ensembles,
you get more the textures of the individual instruments.
That turned out to be a really great contrast
with how London, Victorian London,
being such a busy place filled with noise,
with all the action in there, was a very nice contrast.
That turned out to be a really cool aspect of this score.
Really quickly just about this concept of themes, because of the sprawling nature of
the narratives of these games, it's very tempting to assume that this kind of intense
leitmotif approach would be the way to go, and especially considering that we have sort
of three or four principal characters in the game.
You have Jacob and Evie, and then their kind of assassin cohort who they meet in London,
and then of course there's the main villain.
And I said, you know, I actually don't think, I mean, I love writing themes conceptually,
but I do think it's generally an overused concept because it creates this crutch where
you don't know what to do from a psychoanalytic standpoint, so you just play the theme of
whoever's on screen.
And my attitude to that is, well, but I see them on screen, so what are you trying to
remind me of?
It's the same reason why period music is redundant.
And so I said, furthermore, Jacob and Evie are not, from a musical standpoint, a good
They are not really different characters.
The salient interesting quality was that it was all about them as a single sibling unit,
their relationship with each other and the kind of tension that goes through in the resolution.
And so it's kind of like they're two sides of a single coin and I wanted to make just
a single theme that was preoccupied with that dynamic.
And so...
That said, the game lets you toggle back and forth between the two characters.
And so I said I would, and you know there's missions where you play as one or the other
that are very central to the narrative, and then there's, and in the open world you could
just freely go back and forth.
And so I said I'd love to find some kind of subtle way to delineate them, even if it's
just because I think it's fun.
And so it was all about casting soloists.
And I apparently like wild theatrical soloists.
So on the left is Sandy Cameron, who's a violinist that actually, she's been on tour
with Danny Elfman, and that's a shot from her Edward Scissorhands bit on his show.
And I was in the audience during the first performance of that, and this person came
out and just played the living hell out of this solo, and I thought, I don't know who
that is, but I need to find them and work with them on something.
And then it was very shortly thereafter that Syndicate came into my life, and I thought,
done!
And so I said, what if Jacob, the brother, is associated with these featured violin solos?
And then Tina, who I have worked with for many years, she's the featured soloist on Journey and many other things,
I thought that we can make the sound of her solos that of Evie.
And so the premise being that the score will kind of have these modular solos that can be switched in and out, even in real time, based on who you're playing as.
Also, violin and cello weren't random choices.
Basically, they...
They run parallel in terms of characteristics with the personalities of the characters.
Jacob being more like an upbeat type of character and Evie being more grounded.
And that's how it turned out to be violin the more spry instrument and cello the more deeper voice.
Yeah, and also I did like, it wasn't a central driving motivation, but I did like the idea that there was a slight playing against sort of gender stereotypes.
I was like, I was like, it's sort of.
Because that was one of the first things a few people asked me.
He's like, oh, it's interesting that, you know.
That's unexpected.
Yeah, that Evie's the cello.
And I was like, really?
Well, why not?
Yeah, I thought it was.
But I kind of, when I realized that apparently it did, I thought, well, actually I like that.
So here's, sorry, this started straight away.
This is just a demonstration of some of the systems in the game and how they play back
differently based on which solo.
Well, essentially, exactly what I just said.
Hold on, let me just.
So yeah, it's the same set of music,
but in a different instrument.
Yeah.
And I think it's in three.
I just heard it and I thought,
all right, let's see if these are direct,
I can't hear the sound if it's in direct.
Oh yeah, it's still in the same.
P Shit.
Now this is very interesting to watch.
I normally have never seen him play a real double bass,
but this is completely surreal.
This is also going to be awesome.
Yeah.
The car is ready.
It's a very simple, you know, incredibly simple, from a musical standpoint, demonstration of that.
But obviously it's effectively the same cue recorded two different ways.
So, just a quick word also on the kind of macro structure.
And I'm going to pick up my pace here.
I mentioned this earlier that it was important to me
that the music have a broad evolution.
And that was, I think, one of the big changes
from the initial documentation of Christians on plans.
Instead of saying, okay, we need just a giant bank
of combat music, for example, I said,
well, what if instead of a giant...
In the beginning, we were working with a small bank of combat music that we gradually work our way through as the player makes their way through the narrative, so that even in the open world, the music is reflective of where you are in the overall progression, and that way we can be reducing the amount of repetition, because we're taking music, kind of putting it on the table, and then relatively quickly taking it back off the table.
And I can actually communicate a story arc.
Through purely orchestration and things like that, you know by manipulating the overall palette as things go along.
So even in the open world.
Even in the open world.
Not just in the story.
Exactly.
Like if you're just wandering the city of London and just enjoying, you know, exploring or side quests or whatever,
the music will reflect your overall progression within the game.
Despite the fact that you're not actually engaged in the narrative in that moment, which was important to me because storytelling is, you know, of such paramount importance.
And yet an open world game kind of pushes against the traditional constructs of storytelling.
And so I said I want to have a system superimposed over the overall music.
And so I just wanted to play you a quick example of the way I was kind of...
Starting the score, like these are little snippets from the combat music.
This is just a little mp3 that we'll play, you know, a bit from the beginning of the game, a bit from the middle of the game, a bit from later in the game, and you'll hear, you know, it starts off where, like, combat music is literally just two violins sort of shredding with each other.
Again, that's, you know, the open world combat music, not the mission combat music.
Yes, yeah, there's a whole other, there's a whole other thing there that we're, like, not even really going to get into.
But yeah, so you'll hear it.
And then I flesh it out to the full string ensemble.
You know, by the time we reach the middle again, I start adding in woodwinds.
Which was one of those, I was like, surely they're not going to go for this.
I'm like, I want flutes as my combat.
And no one said anything.
And then I ditched the winds by the end, and it migrates into chamber brass and strings.
So here's just kind of a taste of...
And,well, I went to parody a creepy audio I found on Google.
If you're wondering what happened, have a look at my last video!
More creepy audio!
A fan made a video called School of the Apes,
and made a parody of a video by Jeeeeeeeeeeeeeet.
Be sure to check out his channel!
If you figured what made this video funny,
leave a like, leave a comment, and subscribe!
If you like this transcript, please give me a thumbs-up.
Make sure to subscribe, turn on notifications, and share this video with your friends!
Thank you for watching!
slow
low
You can hear, at least particularly for the composers in here, that the actual harmonic language was also evolving in there.
The idea that it starts off very simple and very kind of plain in a way, and by the end it can get actually quite a bit...
It's a little bit thornier than 19th century music ever actually got.
I called it, the way I described it was, I want to go back in time and abduct Mendelssohn,
but bring him to like the mid-20th century, hang out with Bartok for a few days, and then I'll send him back.
And so that's kind of a taste in that.
All right. Getting a little bit into the combat music system. You know, we won't go
over everything, but that one's interesting because it's by far the most complex dynamic
music system in the game. So it was built based on my experience working on the music
systems on Assassin's Creed 3 and Black Flag and on their DLCs.
And they had all these cool ideas in there, like the notion of having different states
in a combat scenario, like are you hiding from the enemies, are you being chased, that
would have different music cues for each of those scenarios.
Intensity levels based on the number of enemies you're fighting, is it a small patrol or are
you being ambushed by 10 guys, that would have different cues.
Also your health level, are you about to die, stuff like that.
And location based variation of the combat music in Black Flag, the music, the combat
music would be different based on which island you were on.
So that was all good.
Which leads me to our goals for the combat music in Syndicate.
We want to score the player's combat scenario.
You know, tell, score a story in the combat.
Predict his intentions.
Is he on a killing spree like I said earlier or is he just fighting one weak dude and it's
over in a few seconds.
Have variety.
Keep the data streamlined for the combat music system which was much harder than it sounds.
And you know, stay focused on keeping the musical flow as good as possible.
And this was the first version of the combat system, the chart.
And you can see there's a problem there.
Pretty obviously.
Yeah.
It's very complex.
What I ended up doing is just adding my own ideas
to the existing concepts from the previous games.
You know, it's an exponential increase in complexity.
There were a lot of transition cases,
but possible transition cases, which
means a lot more potential musical flow problems, which
we were trying to avoid, and a lot of music
to produce, which is another set of problems.
And this is what we ended up with, roughly.
iteration of playing the game, we realized that we didn't need all those states and the
music being very dynamic, it shifts around a lot, there's a lot of stuff going on.
But it's actually doing the bulk of the work that we wanted the system to do.
And it was doing it better just by playing on its own.
There would be all these little accidents, happy accidents happening as you were playing,
fighting guys.
The music loop would play and you would get the impression that it would react to what
you were actually doing in the game, where really it was just...
doing its thing and playing, there's no system involved.
So that was a really interesting side effect
of the music being very complex.
And that's such a recurring motif,
I feel like, every year at GDC.
Inevitably, we set out to design a really reactive system,
and then we discovered the power of happy accidents
and realized it doesn't need to be as reactive as we thought.
And so I feel like there's this dichotomy
of the adaptive versus non-adaptive music.
And I would actually argue that it's more that
It's a spectrum of the degrees of adaptivity of the music.
And that we're, as an industry in general, we're kind of
sort of zeroing in broadly on what that happy medium is.
Musicality and playing out over a linear space
for the sake of musicality, versus tight
marriage to the player experience.
You know, and as music designers, audio designers,
all that, we're technical people.
It becomes very easy to fall into the trap of making
this huge, really complex, cool system.
And it's actually making your life harder, not easier.
And not even serving the game.
A couple of mechanics from the combat music system, threat, threat level, threat values,
those are, you know, they determine the intensity of the music level, the intensity level of
the music that's playing.
It's a sum of values assigned to game elements and variables,
like what type of enemy you're fighting at the moment.
Are they weak archetypes or strong archetypes?
They'll have different values and have different influence
on the intensity level of the music.
Also, your player level versus the enemy level.
will change its value.
So if you're of a much higher level than the enemy,
you'll have a smaller value, so less influence
on the total threat level.
So less influence on the intensity level of the music.
Next, there's the cool down state.
That replaces what used to be a victory cue when
you finished a fight.
It's actually a slow transition back to silence
or to the next combat.
It's a one-shot cue of music about 20 seconds long.
That leads me to the idea of chains. If you get into another fight before the cooldown,
you know, the 20 second cooldown ends, you get into another different set of music. That's
called the second chain.
And that's our mean to have variety in the combat music
through four long combat scenarios,
where the player would get into multiple fights
in quick succession.
Which is very organic to the way the game is designed,
because it's so easy to create a.
It's a train of enemies where you think you're out of it and you go running and you bring
a lot more.
So the cool down kicks in and you end up bringing a rain of hell down on yourself and the music
is ready to go to kick back in as opposed to the system starting over.
And that came from the idea of trying to tell a story and think how all the game events
are interconnected.
There's a single fight event.
You know, in a movie, if you have someone fighting this group of people, then fighting
that other group of people, then that other group of people, it would be scored and, you
know, there would be a progression there.
So that was our mean to try and achieve that.
Next, there's the character switch.
So what we just talked about, how if you're
playing as Jacob or Evie, you would get the violin or cello
solos.
There are actually different parts of the music.
And that's another way to achieve variety.
Also, the game progression sets.
You heard an example earlier, how if you're early in the game,
you'll get one set of combat music.
If you're late in the game, you'll
get another set of combat music.
set of combat music with all the involved parts.
So different cool downs, different everything,
basically.
So here's an example.
Here's a look at that.
I'm back, man!
God, you lack a face!
And you can see also I couldn't resist the temptation and when you're creating cooldowns
for the higher intensities, later chains, it would almost always be a scenario like
this where it's at the culmination of kind of a recurring and revamping.
combat scenario and so I just to me there was just something irresistibly fun about having these like authentic cadences that that as you're leaving
It's you know, no no no no no
Boom boom because you're like clearly walking away from this thing. That was a lot bigger than whereas the other ones tended to drift out
more
subtly, which was just me kind of applying a general nerdiness to
To you know the way the game would actually would actually play out
So looking back at the result for the combat system,
main takeaway I got from all this is, like I said earlier,
all the little happy accidents that happen.
where you let the music do its thing instead of trying to have a system that's leading
forward all the music.
And that happens if your music is very dynamic and all that.
Not necessarily for different styles of game music.
But it makes me wonder, like that's an open-ended question,
as music designers, we tend to want to control,
in a very micro way, the music.
Is that really always the right way?
It depends on the type of music, but in this case,
definitely not.
And there's a lot of things to improve in that combat system.
Sadly, most of that system was in place
before Austin became involved, and that
was a production imperative.
Next time, I'd definitely like to have the composer more
involved from earlier on.
There is weird behavior sometimes. It kind of has a mind of its own with all the little
moving parts involved. It's not, you know, Skynet levels of awareness, but it does weird
stuff sometimes. It doesn't take allies into account in your fight scenarios and they do
speed combat, they speed up combat a lot. So you do get sometimes what we were trying
to avoid, which is me starting and stopping in quick succession, sadly.
You know, basing the threat level on the player's damage
output instead of his level relative to the enemy's level
would have been probably a better statistic
to base the threat level on, because it's a more direct.
A reflection of its combat effectiveness, basically.
A better handling of many quick game events happening,
quick succession.
And there are some music cues that play very rarely because
of how the system is built.
That could have been managed better.
In other words, some of the downstream high-intensity chains end up becoming almost like musical
Easter eggs.
Low-intensity.
Low-intensity downstream chain.
Yeah, exactly.
Because they can end up...
been quite hard to trigger because you have to basically be in a long-running low-intensity
battle or combat situation which is actually kind of rare.
We're going to actually skip this because we don't want to lose out on time for questions.
Yeah, we'd really like if you have questions.
But basically, yeah, just the long and short of it is there's a whole system in place for
one of these big, you know, one of the big classic AC tropes is the reach high point
which is where you go up to the top and you do your leap of faith.
Not a terribly elaborate system, but there is a system there.
So...
There... and moving on.
And moving on.
It'll be... we'll find a way to put that out there.
I'd like to quickly go over this because exploration music, it's a kind of hot topic for the
Assassin's Creed music fans. Rooftops music was our solution for that. Basically, it's
exploration music that's triggered when you um...
You hang on the rooftops area, it's based on your elevation in the game world and that
triggers the music for exploration.
Why only on rooftops?
Basically that was to avoid cluttering the audio mix at the street level.
We had a concern from the very beginning of the production.
about how this game would end up being very busy audio-wise,
because London is such a busy city.
We had carriages.
We had trains.
We had thugs screaming at you from the other side
of the street and all that.
We didn't want to add more noise to that, so rooftops.
Also, my theory that explorer type players, they will tend to
climb up, they will tend to go on the rooftops to watch the
sunset, the sunrise, to look at that train crossing the bridge
all over there. And that seemed like the better place to get the
most bang for our buck for the exploration music.
And, you know, it's a simple system, really.
It checks for what district you're in, what hour is it,
and it picks the appropriate track for that.
There's day variation and night variation.
And also your game progression will trigger or not
vocal tracks, depending on your game progression.
Yeah, because I said I want to have these soprano solos that are singing in English
text derived from Nam Tate's...
Speaking of Easter eggs.
Yes, libretto from the Purcell opera Dido and Aeneas, but I, you know, with my own melody
but those texts, and I said, and I can kind of comment on what's going on.
In English, you know, I said there's so many of the kind of ethereal vocal solos.
I said, I like the idea that, you know, you go up on the roof and you're looking out over the city
and this kind of wistful music comes in and then the soprano sings right at you, you know,
peace and I are strangers grown.
And it's like, oh, that...
I kind of, that's a bummer.
But I was like, I like that.
And they were, again, such a joy working with Christian and Lydia,
they were totally on board with that.
So it's a simple system, but it's one that is checking a lot of variables.
As side missions and side activities,
I'll only say about that we ended up
using that game progression idea for the side missions.
The 1,000 story stuff, all the investigations and stuff,
it's generic tracks.
They're not composed specifically for the missions,
but they change depending on your game progression.
If you're in sequence eight versus if you're
in sequence four, you'll get different music.
Yeah, so that turned out to be a cool idea applied to a more generic situation, and you know that could be explored further in the future
Yeah, exactly so in other words be you know because there were so many side missions
I couldn't write you know I wrote over three hours of music
but I could have doubled it and still not been able to cover everything and
But there would be you know
Cues that are reused for a lot of different side missions except that depending on when in the game you do it it triggers different
Music so that it's in line with the overall macro progression
In a single playthrough it's difficult to perceive because you only do it once.
Which is actually the idea.
It should just feel like it's organically chasing whatever you're doing, whatever your
story is.
Exactly.
A quick side note about source music, music in the world, the street bands and all that
stuff.
We wanted each district of the city to have a distinct, detailed musical life to them.
So we defined a list of songs from the era and different band configurations that would
fit the mood and type of each district.
So you'll get more folk type bands in Lambeth, you'll get work songs in Southwark, you'll
get music all singers on the Strand, you'll get brass bands in the parks of Westminster.
There's even details like passerby's walking about bands
and they'll pick up the songs that the band's playing
and start humming it to themselves.
That's really cool.
It turned out really cool and we almost didn't get it.
Which leads me to district themes in the score.
We asked ourselves what we could do to take the source music
aspect further.
You know, our black flag at the Sea Shanties,
and that turned out to be a great success.
But we didn't want to copy what was done before.
We wanted to have our own little thing.
So, that's how we came to the district themes, which are popular songs from the era and they
act as themes for each of the city's districts.
Each one of them have their own song.
And that's used for the rooftops music, the reach eye point music, the side activities,
and of course the source music.
The bands and the street musicians actually play those songs too.
Yeah, so the idea is that you hear someone...
The game is about a man on the street playing a folk song. These were researched, authenticated, period authentic songs.
And then as you go up on the rooftop, the score actually picks up this thing and puts it through the filter of the actual score.
which was, to me, a really wonderful way to mix up what I was doing.
I thought of this as Lydia, the audio director's big brainchild, because she's from London.
She was very preoccupied with really carefully choosing these songs that had a lot of personality.
you know, particular to the area of the city that we were looking at.
And I was invited to participate in the selection process, which was really wonderful,
because I was looking at them from the angle of, compositionally, what will I do with this tune?
Yeah, exactly.
And so here's just kind of an example of that.
Champagne Charlie is me name.
Good Freddy game at night, me boys.
Good Freddy game at night.
You won't like it if I come over there!
So you get the idea, these little melodic fragments
that you end up hearing performed a lot.
There's a lot of musicians in the city.
In quick succession, it seems very obvious.
But actually, some of them are really more subtle,
like the Champagne Charlie one was not
the vocal line doing the Champagne Charlie melody.
It was the actual string counterpart.
And that one was actually particularly tricky, because the melody is so bouncy.
By the way, you're all going away with that in your head.
Yeah, it is. It took me a long time to get that out of my system.
That's why, of course, when I was orchestrating it, it's very dramatic.
So, in the last sort of like...
Amazingly fun thing to do on this was the murder ballads.
So these three dashing Aussies are a group from Melbourne called Tripod.
And I had just done a show with them about a year ago called This Gaming Life.
We did a two-hour production with the Melbourne Symphony of songs, like a cabaret show with
full orchestra.
And I was madly in love with working with these guys.
And Lydia brought up the idea of, okay, there's going to be all this source music throughout
the game.
What if there are original songs kind of tucked away inside there that we're passing off as
other period songs?
But they're about the events that the citizenry is witnessing throughout London.
So, you know, as an assassin, you take down some high-profile public figure,
and then shortly thereafter, as you're just walking through the city,
you hear someone singing about that public figure being assassinated.
It's like, wait a minute...
And so we said, let's write these songs to kind of tuck into the game to just flesh out
the world even more.
And they're actually kind of remarkably difficult to find.
But it's a wonderful, you know, I got a lot of messages on Twitter and things from people
who happened on it and were like, oh, wow.
There's a thread on Reddit of people looking for the murder balance.
So here's...
Here's...
Today we brag a different kind of prey
Here at a bugle call, we're feasting on a lord
Perl Attaway is one of your targets
Hark the horses, steer the wheels
And embrace this cold delay
I am undone, the sun has gone, all the pain's gone
Those who fall for something better
Those who talk about how they lived
Loved ones take a long before their work was done
Underground, underground
Leave them behind
So that was a little bit on that.
Just one incredibly quick word here
was just that the Murder Bowels, by the way,
was the most fun time I've had in terms
of the only time in my career as my deliverable requirement,
been sheet music, which was pretty awesome.
But we recorded the score at Abbey Road.
I can get into the one question we're going to have time for and subsequently out in the
hallway as the case may be, on to this whole process.
But the standard, you know, create mock-ups, send them to them, do my whole prep process
and then off we went to Abbey Road and flew through huge volumes of music.
And then just want to make one final note, I am often advocating for the value of being
divisive. And I definitely practice what I preach on this game. Because this has been
the recurring motif amongst long-running AC fans. If you look at the top and bottom comments
from just one of the random YouTube videos, basically this is the worst score ever written
and also the best score ever written. And I'm not going to get into that. I'm going to
And I'm actually okay with that.
I like that we kind of challenged people, and some people completely loved it and embraced
it.
And we knew we're making such an about face from the previous AC games that there's going
to be some that don't like it, or in this case, dear God, no, I hate, hate, hate, hate!
This, Mr. Wintery, coming over to discuss this.
You've got to challenge people.
Yeah, so anyway, I just thought it was valuable to shine a light on the fact that we didn't think we would please everyone, and we were correct.
And so anyway, we literally do have only a couple minutes, but there's a microphone right here.
The housekeeping note, don't forget about doing your evaluations when they show up on your phone.
But any questions?
Yes, Mr. Domenico.
Thank you for this.
I really enjoyed Black Flag and I can't wait to play this game.
Were you challenged by the fact that you knew that you had to create these varying levels
of intensity when you were composing or did you do that after the fact?
Oh, for sure. It was designed from the ground up with that system in mind. It was definitely not like write a piece.
Because they're distinct cues. They're not like cue with added drums or something like that.
It's definitely completely distinct music. And it created some challenges for him as well.
Because I would say, okay, I think that maybe it's going to be a faster tempo.
So he's having to figure out transitions where there's a pretty massive tempo change happening within a cue basically.
And things like that.
Barely no layering. It's all distinct cues.
Yeah, the layering is pretty subtle. And the layering is mainly, I would say, the biggest feature of the layering is actually the soloists.
The violin versus the cello sort of decision.
Awesome. Yeah, that's great. Thank you.
Thanks, man.
Hi. Thanks for the talk, by the way. That was great.
So you kind of skimmed over this at the end, but did you create mockups during the process?
And if so, how did you overcome the fact that, I mean, it's a lot more difficult to do effective
mockups for chamber ensembles?
So I overcame that by being really lucky.
Because I was working, you know, Christian, you know, you get the sense probably that he's very technically savvy.
What you don't know is he's also an incredible musician himself.
And so, there, the sort of leaps of faith, not to make a C pun.
Uh, that are required, um, in, in, because I basically said early on, uh, I'm going to
send you mockups and they're going to be god awful because I'm going to be using all solo
string samples and so, and they're going to phase if ever I have them in unison and it's
just going to be an ugly mess.
And he and Lydia both were like, that's fine.
And honestly, I basically did no revisions of the entire score.
Like, the first combat cue, we moved quickly away
from this very figurative, like, box style, you know,
da-dee-da-dee-da-dee-da-da, to the more waltzing idea.
And once we locked in from that, it basically got no pushback
on any cue of even minor changes,
and including reactions that were the classic situation
of, you know.
getting a note and realizing, oh, they actually like the cue, but they don't like the mockup.
I was very lucky. I didn't deal with any of that.
There was this thing in this project about trust and being able to hear further than the mockups.
Hearing what they're going to sound in the end.
It wasn't always easy, but the fact that the... no, really.
And the fact that the pitch...
No, really.
No, there really wasn't any way to make those mock-ups sound even close, because it was
so much based on the musician's interpretation and the actual emotion they would put into
it.
And the pitch being live helped a lot to extrapolate from the mock-ups.
That is how I bought that trust. When they said, will you send us your pitch, I did an out of
pocket recording session of the full scale production of the score as I was envisioning it,
so that way I could say, here's a mock up of this, here's the final, before we've even gotten
started, so you can hear the trajectory between those. Once they heard that, the mock ups became
less of an issue, because they could always go back and listen to the recording I had done
before we even started on the score and say, ah, so that's the place we're headed.
So then you make the mockup extra bad on that first one.
I needed no help making the mockup extra bad.
I assure you.
All right.
I think we are probably...
Thank you.
If you want to...
Did you have one last question and I'll answer it as we're clearing out?
No.
No?
I'm inviting you, but you've got to go right now.
Thank you.
It's actually related to the previous question.
In film production, you have the film.
It is finished.
Then you write the music.
Then you go to the recording session.
And it's pretty much a streamlined process.
But in this case, especially when doing mock-ups
was really difficult, but you still probably
had to deliver stuff to be approved by Ubisoft
or whatever at different stages, and that the game is constantly
evolving, adding new content, et cetera.
How do you handle that production process?
At what time do you choose to record the instrumentalist, etc.?
Yeah, absolutely.
It's a great question.
I'm going to give an incredibly succinct answer so we can clear out of here for these guys.
But the basic answer is I said to them, what is the absolute latest date that I can get
you the recordings?
Because I do not want to put myself in a position of having to music edit the hell out of these
recordings if something doesn't work quite right.
But also, there were certain aspects of the score, like there were a bunch of cues that required only solo violin, for example, like, you know, a single spawn cue or something like that.
And I was like, those I can do whenever I can do those, and those are easy to redo.
But when I go to London, that's a one-shot deal.
And so I just pushed it as late as possible, and we worked together to say, you know, I don't want to be dropping a giant amount of music on him so that it gets screwed in the implementation, so it can't be too close to the end.
And so, but that was basically the answer.
It's just deliver as late as possible.
And again, they were very trusting that that was going to be okay.
And they were even willing to, when the initial announcement came out of the game, you know,
like E3 and things like that, you know, the instinct was, well, we should record some
of this so we're putting our best face forward.
And I said, I wouldn't, I said, I'd rather put mockups in the, in the E3.
All of our effort and all of our budget towards the final result.
I've been on other projects where they front loaded recording sessions for the sake of their PR.
And it actually hurts the game in my opinion.
Anyway, thank you all so much.