Here we go. Thank you very much.
Hi.
Thank you.
Okay, so as I just said,
turn your phones up as loud as possible,
interrupt really often. No.
Okay, hello everybody.
Thank you very much for coming along here.
Let's see if the clicker actually works. It does.
Excellent stuff.
So my name is Professor Matter Haggis. I have been making games for quite a while now.
I started off with things like Burnout Paradise quite a few years ago on the AAA side of things.
I was one of the writers on Aliens vs. Predator.
I've also done a lot of indie stuff before that, so I've been doing it about 15 years.
I've had a couple of series on MTV2 in Europe.
I've done animations and games for Channel 4 and things like that back in my indie freelance days.
These days I'm actually associate professor at NHTV University in Netherlands. It's one of the highest rated games courses in Europe
So if you're looking at games education really great place to go. So my students in the room
I'm also making a game at the moment called fragments of him
It's coming out on Xbox One and PC next month,
and later in the year on PlayStation 4,
which is really, really storytelling focused.
Now what I'm gonna be talking about today
is a lot of the storytelling and writing methods
that I've used when I'm making fragments of him,
using illustrations from classic literature
and things like that.
You may have also noticed
that I do talk really quite fast.
So I know we've got an international audience here, so not everybody can always keep up if I go really really fast and I talk like that.
So the most big important points are going to be on the screens behind me.
There's a lot of them.
What I'm going to do to make this easy is I'm going to be building up a diagram as we go today.
I do want to reassure you the very very last slide after I said thank you and all that kind of stuff
I will put the full diagram up on screen so you don't need to be constantly photographing
if you think you're going to miss this diagram.
It will be all there at the end, you will have time to take it if you want to.
Hopefully you find it interesting enough to want to take it.
So let's build up this diagram. This is the core part of it.
We're going to roughly build it out this kind of way that we start off with
before you even start writing like this.
Why you would write like this, what actually writing like this is,
and what I mean when we go after writing like this. I want to say by like this is
like, how do we write less? Or how do we write
the same amount but say more? How do we kind of keep the compression
but increase the complexity?
This is really what we're looking at here.
Now, there's three different methods I'm going to talk to you about today.
A lot of this is keying in with a lot of the other narrative design talks you may have heard over the last couple of days.
There's a lot of things that a lot of people are talking about in trying to build complexity in here.
So I've got these three techniques which are going to feed into that central one there.
So the very first part, I want to emphasize this before we even start doing this, is don't
compromise essential gameplay information.
It's really important the player needs to be able to understand what they're doing,
how they're supposed to be achieving these things.
With that in mind, now you can start playing around with your writing.
So keep it obvious, unless it's part of the game for people to not know, but I'll leave
it up to you to understand that.
So really what we're aiming for here is adding value with story.
We want the stories to make the experiences more engaging, the play more fun, the world more
immersive. Because really what story is there for is additional investment into the play activities.
Now those play activities might be shooting a robot in the face, they might be saving a cat
from a tree. But why is it a robot? Why is it a cat? If these things have emotional attachment
in them already, how do we build on that emotional attachment? How do we make those actions feel more
meaningful?
This is really what we're looking at trying to achieve.
We're trying to make meaning within our games.
Because basically we've got this situation where we've got all our players on one side
and we've got a game that we've made here.
And sometimes it kind of feels like story is this wall in the middle between the two of them.
That you've got these cut scenes you have to watch, you have to listen to this dialogue, you kind of go, yep.
Okay, when does this story end?
When can I actually move on to the next piece?
That's not the world we want to be working in.
We want to be working in this kind of way
where the game is right next to them all the time.
They're fully engaged with this.
And then that kind of play experience
is becoming something which is involved with it.
All the storytelling is involved with that play experience
on a moment by moment basis.
It's building out into more complex experiences
and the whole story is interwoven into the game.
So this is what we're really looking for.
To get to this point, we need what we call active listening,
where the story becomes something that they're involved with.
They're not just going, oh yeah, more words being spoken.
They're going, ah, these words are interesting.
This makes my actions more compelling.
This makes the world more interesting to play with.
So we want people to read between the lines.
We want people to be interpreting what's going on there.
What are the characters thinking
is obviously one of the big questions here.
Are they lying to themselves?
Or are they trying to lie to others?
These are really big questions
which you can play with in your dialogue
without having to add extra kind of gameplay mechanics
and extra parts in there.
Basically this idea of interpretation
is a form of engagement.
Storytelling doesn't have to be this passive thing.
It's a form of engagement
when people are trying to understand
and trying to get into the heads of.
of the characters.
So let's keep on going here.
The first technique I'm going to talk about is omissions in the text.
If we want to move on from this, we've got a couple of characters that are going to be
helping us today.
We've got Tess and Gemma.
There they are.
Meet Tess and Gemma.
We're going to be visiting them a few times.
Tess and Gemma are in a motel.
Very nice for them.
Except the motel is surrounded by zombies.
And so this is a fairly classic gameplay situation.
Got a couple of people holed up.
There's guns and there's things to shoot at.
We obviously want to have some good dialogue involved with all this kind of stuff.
Well, I think we've really got kind of three options of how we want to go about this
in terms of storytelling.
Now, one of the options
is that we don't actually really do storytelling here.
We just go, okay,
bring the zombies through the doors, through the windows, start shooting them,
and that's absolutely fine. If you want to go for a completely mechanics-driven
kind of game,
go for it.
I'm not insisting you need to have cutscenes or storytelling and stuff like that.
If you want to make that game, go for it.
But today we're going to be talking more about the writing side of things and how we do this.
So option two is what people go for most of the time.
Probably a fairly standard dialogue interchange.
So let's look at sort of one of the things we might have here.
Perhaps Tess is going to say something like,
do you think we'll make it through till dawn?
And Gemma might come back with,
I don't know, but we'll try.
Okay.
I mean, it's alright, it's fine, that's that standard dialogue for a video game, that's
kind of how we would expect to hear a lot of these things.
But this is kind of quintessentially really passive listening.
There's nothing for you to really interrogate, what's going on inside their minds, they've
just told you everything.
And really, that's just building a wall.
That's just a few lines of dialogue
which are standing between you
and the game on the other side.
And so you want your player to be more involved with that.
You want to have it a little bit more engaging.
So we need to look at this third option
that we have available for us.
So let's go on to this point where I'm talking about this.
Let's go on to the omissions here.
Now, when I say omissions,
I mean that we are leaving out words or information
from the text, from the dialogue that's going on there.
I'm going to give you an example of how this kind of stuff can work.
Shakespeare's King Lear.
This is one of my favourite plays ever written.
It's one of the greatest tragedies in history.
This is an amazing, amazing play.
If you don't know it, I highly recommend reading it.
It starts off with the king, there he is.
These are my brilliant sketches, thank you.
And the king Lear has three daughters.
And to roughly paraphrase Shakespeare,
it starts off with him going something like,
Tell me how much you love me and you'll all get a third of my stuff.
roughly like that. And of course...
Mind stuff. I don't know. Of course you get two of the daughters, Goneril and Regan, who come back
with this kind of response of, well we love you more than anything, we love you more than stars,
the moon, our husbands, can all go screw themselves. It's really this kind of over the
top, overblown, just pouring these words of love out to him. The king's like, awesome,
I feel very nice now, you feel like a very good king, excellent.
And then we get to Cordelia's turn.
Cordelia is the youngest.
Cordelia truly loves King Lear.
She truly, truly loves him.
And that's a wonderful thing.
And the audience understands this.
She has a lot of sides to the audience going,
how the hell am I supposed to say that?
After what they've said, whatever I say
is going to sound wrong.
And so we have the king say, what
can you say to draw a third more opulent than your sisters?
Speak.
Nothing, my lord.
Nothing.
Nothing will come of nothing.
Speak again.
If my slide changes over here.
Oh, slow computers.
Don't you just love it when they do that.
Excellent.
Unhappy that I am, I cannot heave my heart into my mouth.
I love your majesty, according to my bond.
Nor more, nor less.
This is wonderful. She's saying, at some point I'm going to get married
and I'm going to love my husband probably more than I love you.
I'm going to have children. I'm going to love them absolutely dearly
and all of them will have a portion of my love.
I cannot say I love you alone
because there are so many people in my life that I'm going to love.
This is a difficult situation for her and the king doesn't get it.
You've had these other two sisters going,
everything is you, and then one comes back and goes,
I can't pour my heart out like that.
And the audience understands Cordelia's struggle.
They understand that it's difficult,
but Lear does not until it's way, way too late.
I mean, this is a difficult position.
How can you express the inexpressible?
Love beyond words.
How do you even talk about love?
I mean, Shakespeare himself,
shall I compare you to a summer's day?
This whole sonnet is about how it's almost impossible
to really quantify what love is.
And this is one of the greatest writers
in history of language.
Amazing, amazing words.
And he even says, I can't really do it.
So one of the ways we can do this is by using contrast, for example.
So we've got the contrast between the first two sisters and what they say,
and the true love that Cordelia feels, which is almost inexpressible.
And the audience then has to fill in the difference.
The audience begins to understand the difference between these two things.
What did King Lear hear compared to what Cordelia said?
When she said nothing, what did the king hear on the other end of that?
And that's really engaging, because as an audience,
we're always second guessing
where we're gonna end up here.
Quick note, I wanna say,
if you're writing like this for your actors,
please, please don't forget them.
They are people who need to understand
what the hell is going on with your dialogue
when you're leaving things out here.
So tell them what's left unsaid within your script
when you leave a line unfinished.
Those little ellipses that you might love putting at the end of your lines, don't forget to fill the actor in.
It's actually what's been missed out there, otherwise they're going to get lost
and you might get a terrible performance in the audio booth.
So do remember your actors when you're doing this kind of stuff.
Also I want to mention that implication is another form of omission.
The idea where you're implying lots of ideas.
This is an example used yesterday.
That's my excellent picture of Leia from Star Wars there.
She says I love you to Han and Han is kind of being smug.
And he kind of comes back with I know.
He almost feels like he has to be a little chink of light from his teeth when he says that.
It's a bit cheesy but the implication of what's said there is actually much more powerful than
if he just said I love you too which was in the script. That whole breadth of their experience
of Leia going I'm going to go to the end of the galaxy to find you, I will save you no matter
what happens here, I'm going to tell you I love you even though this is embarrassing almost to
say in front of every single other person it's the worst possible time to say it, I'm going to
declare my love for you right now and Han goes...
There's no way I can ever come back from that. I really understand that you absolutely mean
everything that you've just said. The implication of that, I know. So much is put into those little
words. I think it's fantastic. It's really nice writing. So let's go back to Tess and Gemma.
Let's look at their kind of discussion here. Do you think we'll make it through to dawn?
I will try.
Now that's nicer, I think.
I mean, you've got to fill in what's going on there.
She hesitates, I'm sure, but then sounds determined.
And of course, don't forget your actors.
I don't know is the implication there.
So make sure everything's there for people.
Now, if we compare that to the first version,
where it's, I don't know, but we'll try,
I've only taken out a few words,
but it changes the meaning.
It changes the feel of that sentence a lot.
There's more emotions in there.
We've kind of doubled up on the amount of emotional content
without really expanding a lot of what's being said
in the amount of time.
I think that's nicer writing.
So, that was kind of our main option three there,
that was using emissions.
So let's go back to our original diagram
and we're gonna fill that in over the side there.
Any second now, there we go, awesome.
Cool, so let's go on to the second option
we've got available for us.
This is apparent non-secreteurs.
Now, you may know non sequiturs. Non sequiturs are awesome, often used in comedy and stuff like that.
Why did the chicken cross the road? Fish.
That's a non sequitur joke. It makes no sense because it's a sudden change of tone or subject.
Now what I'm talking about really is apparent non sequiturs.
So, although it seems like there's no reason for it to suddenly change, it actually is.
There's a deeper dialogue going on underneath there, and the non sequitur is a way of demonstrating
what that dialogue is.
I saw a piece in X-Files recently where Mulder was sitting there going, oh yes, the killer
did this kind of stuff, and Scully just goes, yeah, I'm not sure how long my mother's gonna
make it.
Complete break in tone of subject and it completely reveals without this big kind of conversation of like,
oh that's very interesting, we shouldn't think about that, but I'm more interested in my mother at this moment.
You don't need this link between it.
Just that contrast is actually sometimes a more powerful way than trying to push these things together.
I think there's a nice example here in Girl Interrupted.
Susanna Kaysen writes this.
It was a spring day, the sort that gives people hope.
All soft winds and delicate smells of warm earth.
Suicide weather.
Tone is established and then that tone is disrupted,
violently breaking this, making a powerful portrait
of the character's internal state.
This is really, really powerful writing
and it's really short writing.
I mean, she could have taken pages to try and write
that same kind of break there,
that same kind of emotional experience.
But just doing that with a couple of lines,
very, very powerful stuff, very powerful.
Another one we've got from a little bit more light-hearted is Waiting for Godot, Samuel Beckett.
Lovely, lovely bit of work. Also mentioned so far in the conference.
Estragon, Turing, I ask you a question.
Vladimir. Ah.
Estragon, did you reply?
Vladimir.
How's the carrot?
It's a carrot.
Lovely.
I love Samuel Beckett.
It's really just weird stuff.
But it's got a lot going on in there.
It's got this kind of comic, tragic kind of thing to it.
You're asking questions that didn't probably get answered the first time.
And if it did, they'd forgotten what that answer was.
And there's this kind of loss of communication going on here.
They're stuck in this meaningless loop of trying to find out the answer
and not really knowing what the question was in the first place.
And that's basically the entire play summarized in two lines of writing.
that is really efficient writing a whole play in two lines i think that is brilliant that's the
power that you can have if you use this technique correctly however with great power comes great
responsibility it's the warning time hooray so there you are you're a brilliant genius writer
with your brilliant brilliant uh non-secretary in your script and this is awesome and then you
go to your producer and your producer can do
I don't think so, no, no.
So a lot of people think that really, really direct writing is the only way to go for games.
This is the only way to write, it's like the really most obvious possible thing you could do.
I don't really agree with that.
I think apparent non sequiturs are really, really indirect.
These are possibly the least direct way of doing something possible.
But they're so powerful.
You're gonna get a lot of arguments about this.
So in every technique from this session
I'm talking about today, it is indirect writing.
It's giving story without saying absolutely
what's in the mind of the people.
It's more powerful for that, it uses their imagination,
but it's gonna trigger a lot of debates,
and I think this one is gonna trigger
the most debates out of a lot of them.
I think it's worth it, I think it's a really
powerful technique if you can get it right.
Once again, don't mess with gameplay information,
but if you get this right, it's a really
great insight to characters.
Let's go back to Tess and Gemma.
So, do you think we'll make it through till dawn, says Tess.
And Gemma comes back with, I...
Don't forget your coat.
Looks like rain in the morning.
That's kind of nice.
I like this one.
Sounds unsure to begin with.
Then she pauses for a moment, she looks out the window at the sky above the crowd of zombies
and in a conversational tone, as clearly covering some fear, she says,
Don't forget your coat, it looks like rain in the morning.
When everything else is going on, that's the thing she says instead.
So if we compare this to the other options that we had, we started off with that one
down the bottom there, I don't know, but we'll try.
And that's fine, that's resolved, it's very determined, that's great.
If we go to the next one, it's scared, but it's resolved, we've kind of doubled up on
our emotional content, so we're doing good work here.
And this third one, well, we've got fear, we've got a little bit of bravado, doesn't
matter, I don't care about the zombies.
It's this determination of, yeah, of course we'll make it.
There's a little bit of humour in there.
There's a little bit of fear in there. It's all these things mixed together.
And something that I think is really, really, really important to games,
even games about shooting zombies in the face,
it's got a bit of love in there.
These people care about each other. They care about...
Gemma cares that Tess actually feels okay.
And she's put on a brave face for her friend.
Or her companion, or her partner.
I think this is a much more powerful way of writing, and I think there's a lot more complexity
with a similar length line as what we started from.
I think that's the power of writing like this, and I think it's really worth looking into.
So...
Let's go back here.
Let's add that on to the bottom part there.
So we've got a change in tone of subject,
it's disjunction really reveals the internal dialogues.
It's great for complexity, it's great for being brief,
and it really gets right to the point
without these overall links of going this to this
to this to this to new subject.
It's a way of skipping out all that stuff
and smooshing them together,
and sometimes getting a much more powerful effect
because of that.
Okay, so the third one I want to talk to you about
is unreliable narrators.
I've got two major parts that I'm going to talk about here.
The first one is actually really quite small, so I'm going to divide them up here.
The first one is quite small on the left-hand side here, which is honest mistakes.
Fairly quick one, I'll just give you a quick example of that.
The next section, the big section really here, is deception.
And within deception, I'm actually going to split that up into two pieces as well.
I'm going to talk about deception, which is lying to yourself, self-deception, and I'm
going to talk a little bit about ungrounded realities.
I think they're both quite important.
And I've got the last one, which is the most obvious one, which is lying to people, deceiving
others.
Okay, so let's start ourselves off with honest mistakes to begin with.
As I mentioned at the start, I'm making a game called Fragments of Him.
In Fragments of Him, there's many stories told,
and one of them is from the perspective of Sarah.
There's my awesome drawing of Sarah.
Tino, if you're watching this, sorry, your artwork's much better than mine.
Sarah has a memory of her time going on a date with a character called Will.
They went to a cinema.
Now, the player actually has a choice of where to sit in this cinema.
They've got to sit in the front, middle, or back.
Now, that's weird, if this is a memory.
Because, I mean, how can there be a player choice if it's just a memory?
There's always going to be kind of one right choice, and the others are going to be wrong choices.
Isn't that right?
Feels like that should be correct.
Or it's just an honest mistake.
Maybe she did sit at the front and we chose sitting at the middle.
That's okay, but whatever she goes, yeah, that's fine.
We'll just keep on going with that.
Because which seat was chosen doesn't actually matter to Sarah.
That bit's irrelevant.
It's like saying, well, the person shot me with a gun,
which was red or blue.
It doesn't matter whether the gun was red or blue.
What matters was you got shot by it.
And you're pretty sure certain about the being shot bit.
so you can understand the priorities of the characters by giving some uncertainty in other
parts of this.
So where we sat, player choice, that's kind of fuzzy.
It's not important to Sarah.
But what happened when she sat down there,
that's certain, that's very important.
And so you get these ideas of priorities
and what matters most to the character
inside their own head.
So those little simple mistakes,
they're tricky to use in your scripts,
tricky to use in your dialogue,
because it can seem like, ah, it's a clue, it's a clue,
they made a mistake, they said this,
but it was really that.
So be really careful using these.
They can fit in there, they can complement things.
But this is why I just said this
was one of the smaller sections.
Basically, active listeners are rewarded with character insight from the contrast between
the certainty and the fuzziness.
And they kind of go, oh, so they didn't care about that, but this bit they're really certain
of.
Intuitively, using this kind of really emotional-driven thinking, they understand intuitively that's
the bit that matters.
And I think that's a nice thing, is getting people good character insight just with a
couple of lines of dialogue.
So let's move on to the next section there, self-deception, lying to yourself and ungrounded realities.
So one of my favourite games of all time is a game called Prince of Persia, Sands of Time.
I think it's a brilliant piece of level design, combat's a little bit new.
Puzzle design is absolutely brilliant, but the storytelling in it is genius.
It is so, so nicely done. If you've not played it, I highly recommend it.
It starts out with a very talented, a very petulant prince who thinks he's awesome,
he's gonna go steal his thing, and he's gonna do the thing over there, and he's gonna go
save the day, and he's gonna invade the city, and he's kind of really full of himself.
He really is quite full of himself.
Like a lot of game characters, to be honest.
From now on, I trust no one but myself.
It's one of the things he says to himself at the start of this.
That's okay, you know, it's fine.
But to be honest, the prince is lying to himself constantly at the start of this.
And as people are listening, we're kind of going,
yeah, that's not going to stay that way for the whole story, is it?
And we're all sitting there knowing this.
We know he's lying to himself and it's helping us feel smarter.
We are actively engaged and going, no, that's not true.
No, you can keep saying that, prince, but it's still not going to be true,
no matter how many times you say it to yourself.
And isn't that lovely that we're listening to dialogue and engaging with it?
It's interactive dialogue without choices, without branching structures.
It's interactive just by the nature of interpretation of dialogue.
That's the power of good writing.
And the player can enjoy anticipating the prince's self-discovery towards the end of it.
That's gameplay.
His self-deception adds to the fun of the game.
The writing adds to the experience.
And that's what we all want to do with our writing.
And the player's work is repaid.
By the end of the game, he's saying,
come with me, please.
He feels the meaning of love.
He needs companionship.
He recognizes there is a world outside himself.
Brilliant character growth,
demonstrated with really nice kind of part of self-deception.
And then that kind of veil falling away as the story goes on.
Mary Shelley also used this in Frankenstein, this kind of stuff, but we get a slightly
different version of this, of kind of ungrounded realities here.
So every aspect of the story is framed for us.
We never really see the truth.
There's no kind of authorial sort of structure sitting outside there, omnisciently looking
down and going, this is the story.
Because we've got this version of reality.
Now reality exists outside of this, but reality is actually framed by a character called Robert
Walton, who is writing Frankenstein, the story Frankenstein, to his sister in a series of
letters.
The thing is Robert Walton is actually writing what he was told by Victor Frankenstein.
So we've got Robert Walton interpreting Victor Frankenstein's letters when he's writing to
his sister.
The thing is Victor Frankenstein is actually sometimes telling Robert Walton what he was
told by the monster.
And so we've got all these different layers coming in here and for all we know Robert
Walton just thought his sister was a bit ill and she might fancy a cool story.
It could all be lies.
and we never know, we never know where the true reality of this is
the reality gets squished and squished and squished until
it might all be true but we really don't know
I think that's a really powerful kind of way of doing it, we only really see through the
reality that they see
and I think that's a really interesting thing because we're always questioning what that is
this is used in a lot of other things, so things like movies like Fight Club
uh... American Psycho of course is a big one
uh...
hello, thank you
We've got other games of course, we've got things like Eternal Darkness, a really great
game, you sort of see the world through the eyes of the characters, you're never quite
sure entirely what is real there.
Grand Theft Auto V, Trevor's Hallucinations, it's very clearly signposted, you're seeing
the world through Trevor's eyes, you don't think that all the gang members have got dog
heads all of a sudden in the game.
SpecOps the line, of course, that's a whole game which plays with the unreliable narrator.
It's a brilliant, brilliant experience.
If you've not seen the talk from GDC in 2012, look it up on GDC Vault.
It's a really, really great talk about SpecOps the line.
Brilliant, brilliant story about that one.
And of course, Batman. I'm a really, really big fan of what was done with Batman Arkham Knight.
I think this is fantastic. Because really, in reality, the Joker is dead. There is no doubt
about this. There's no question really what's going on here. But the thing is, Batman's reality
isn't quite that one. He's slightly moved sideways from reality in this game. We only see the world
through Batman's eyes, and in that reality, the Joker isn't quite dead.
I think that's really interesting as a player, we can kind of think about this.
It's very, very engaging to try and understand what's going on in these.
What is actually real in Batman's world?
What's a hallucination?
Is any of it real?
And also, does it even matter?
And that's a really nice question as well.
Is this a hallucination?
Is that person who we think it is, are they not?
Am I attacking the wrong person here?
What's going on?
I think that's a really, really nice kind of dialogue for your players to engage with
in that game.
So that's that one, that's about self-deception and the ungrounded realities when you're stepping
away from what is really true. Looking now at deceiving others, lying. I like Emily Bronte's
Wuthering Heights, that's a nice example of this one. Again we've got a couple of framing
narratives going on here, we've got Nellie who's talking to Lockwood who's then recording
his version of it, and there's a sense that Nellie might be kind of embellishing her story.
She seems to enjoy telling this story. She seems to enjoy making it a bit more interesting and there's a sense that maybe
She's adding some stuff in but why is she adding this stuff in?
Is she bored?
Is she looking for attention? Is she frustrated with her life? Why is she adding this stuff in and what is she actually adding?
There are scenes where it seems like it would be really weird for Nellie to have been there, but she says she was
but also maybe there's stuff being taken away.
So what do we see?
What don't we see?
What does this tell us actually about her as a character?
Because the speaker is unintentionally
revealing the true selves by the lies that they tell
and the things that they make up.
I think that's a really nice way of playing this.
We see what concerns them.
We see what they're trying to hide
by the lies that they create.
Really, really interesting stuff.
Of course, this is a great thing.
Cresting What Is Real is a really active listening mechanic.
It's a great way of playing with these.
It really rewards players who think about reality
outside the frame of the game that's being presented to them.
They kind of go, this is the reality of Batman.
This is the reality of Nelly.
This is the reality of Lockwood or Victor Frankenstein.
What's going on outside there?
What is the true reality beyond that?
Thinking outside that frame is a really, really powerful thing
for your players to do and a really great way
of engaging them.
So, that was our three options there.
And let's go back and have,
oh yes, let's have a warning again.
Because of course, everything I'm saying here, this is awesome.
Lie to your players.
I'm just telling you to lie to your players.
Whoops.
Inspire your characters to question
the reality that they're in.
Players need clues though, to begin speculating
that not all is as it seems.
This is a really, really important part.
Don't forget to let people come in on this one.
That's because you don't always have to be subtle about this either, you just need to
make sure people understand what's going on here.
So for example, Batman Arkham Knight.
This is not very subtle in telling us what's going on here.
It starts with the Joker's cremation.
You literally press a button and set the Joker on fire in a coffin.
The Joker is very very definitely dead at this point, he's not coming out of this one.
But Bat still sees the Joker. This is really really a big clue that the reality is quite
subjective in this game because he's still seeing him, still seeing this person who we know is dead.
So give clues to what's going on here. Or it's just unintelligible lies and that doesn't add
anything. If people can't tell there's lies, people can't tell there's deception, they're
not going to be actively questioning that.
Right, so let's add that last little part to there and we're going to have one quick more section down at the end there
which is going a little bit further this into clues.
Clues are a really simple kind of part here.
Guide players with well-written dialogue, but if possible, for the best results, go beyond script.
So, there are many, many tools that you can use for storytelling in games.
You've got how the world looks, environmental art, environmental storytelling of course.
How lines are spoken, acting. Don't forget your actors, tell them how to do this stuff.
How characters move, the animation, get your animation team on board with the story.
Interactions, interface, what can the player do, how does the player know how they're supposed to do it.
All of these things are ways you can tell your story.
And of course, please, please, please don't forget your audio team.
They are really, really important in telling your story.
And also, I would also say, just don't forget your marketing team.
there's actually a lot of storytelling you can do outside your game
to give hints, to give clues
so alternate reality games, books, trailers, there's ways of giving clues
about your story
outside of the game as well
so please get them involved with that kind of side of it
so just going through this very quickly at the end here, that's going beyond script
as we've added the last part in, so just to summarize this
and there will be a final screen where all this is nice high-resolution and moment
for you
before you get your cameras out, thank you
Don't compromise, add value with the story because that's really our goal here.
Look for active listening, this is really what we're trying to achieve here.
Leave some words out sometimes, that could be a way of adding a bit more depth, a bit more complexity.
Changing tone and subject quite quickly can be a really powerful way of creating a sense of
internal dialogue going on there. Unreliable narrators are framing reality in their own way,
the player has to question what that reality truly is. And in the end of it, once you've
achieved all these things, think about going beyond script, find out other ways to support this.
And one really, really important question, which I'm sure you're all dying to know,
is that Tess and Gemma did survive until dawn.
That's obviously very, very important.
They didn't need their coat because it didn't rain.
So yeah, I hope this talk's really inspired you for active listening in your audience.
Wow, thank you.
Sometimes you can say more by saying nothing.
Thank you very much for listening, everybody.
Thank you.
Don't forget to fill in the feedback.
And as promised...
There you go. Boom! That is so many cameras. Wow. Awesome. Thank you for listening everybody.