Hello and welcome to my presentation about how a time loop influenced Deathloop's narrative
design.
Before we begin, be aware that there are some pretty massive, unavoidable story spoilers
for the game.
So you have been warned.
And my name is, as you heard, Paweł Krajenka.
And I used to do some translation and interpreting,
and then I switched to game development in 2013,
and I started out as a game designer.
I did a little production, and then I specialized in narrative.
And I am currently lead narrative designer at Arcane.io.
And some of the games I worked on include Heart West,
which is a turn-based tactical, Phantom Doctrine,
which is the same genre but a different setting,
and most recently Deathloop,
which we're gonna cover in more detail today.
So Deathloop is a next-gen first-person shooter from Mark and Neil, and in Deathloop there are
two rival assassins who are trapped in a mysterious time loop on the island of Blackreef and are doomed
to repeat the same day for eternity.
You play as Colt, a soldier without memory,
who can only break the cycle by killing eight key targets
before the day ends.
And you need to learn from each cycle,
try new paths, gather intel, find new weapons and abilities,
and do whatever it takes to break the loop.
But beware, Juliana, who is the other assassin, is out on the prowl and she's doing her best to stop you.
And she can be another player.
So if at first you don't succeed, die and die again.
This is more or less the back of the box description of the game.
And here's how it looked a little bit more under the hood.
So we have four distinct areas on the island.
There's Abdam, there's Carls Bay, the complex, and Fristad Rock.
And you can visit those areas, each of those areas, four times during...
during one of the four times of the day. So there's morning, noon, the afternoon, and the evening.
So basically, if you multiply areas by the times of day, you get up the morning, which is the area
of up them.
in the morning and it has some quests and some content. Then there's up down noon, which is
more or less the same area. The layout looks similar, but there are some new paths that open
up or close in this time period. And there's new content completely different from the morning.
And the same is true for the afternoon. So you get a third set of content on the vaguely the
same layout, but still there are some changes that apply. And in the evening again, the content is
different.
is the same area, but it evolves over time.
And the same is true for Crawl's Bay and for the remaining two areas.
And if you want to be really nitpicky in the game,
those two periods that just disappeared are not actually available.
And if you want to learn more about this,
you may have seen the presentation of my colleague,
Sébastien Mégane-Agné, who talked about the level design of those areas and over time.
And if you haven't seen them, maybe you will be able to see it in replay or on the vault.
So in terms of narrative structure, we first start with the prologue mission,
which is on a special map. And this is basically the tutorial where we introduce
stuff like, you know, movement and
the main characters and the main conflict.
And then we proceed into the guided tour,
which happens on those main core maps
that I've mentioned before.
So Abdaam and the rest of those areas,
but they're arranged in a linear fashion.
We are forcing the player to go to a specific map
at a specific time period.
And we are using this progression to teach them
how the time loop works,
to introduce the main characters,
to introduce...
the main quest, so how do you break the loop, what is necessary to break it, and you may learn
more about the guided tour and how it was conceived from the talk of Danganite
and all that happened on Monday, and you should be able to see it in replay.
by now. So at any rate, by the time you end the guided tour, two things can happen. You can either
die or if you survive, then you go to an evening mission. And after that, the loop is over and the
day starts over in the morning and the player, the game opens up. The player is now able to pick
any of the four available maps from the morning period.
So we as narrative designers have no idea what the player is going to pick beyond the end of the guided tour.
And within any of those maps, there are a whole bunch of stuff that the player can do.
So for instance, if one of the visionaries, so if one of those key targets is present in the map, the player might try to take them out.
Or they might go and do a side mission of some sort, which is not directly connected to any of those main targets.
and there are vignettes, which are just smaller pieces of content, and there are leads, which
are effectively the leads that lead you to breaking the loop, your clues in that direction.
You can also go and explore freely, just play around with the systems and just don't engage
in anything specific. If you are invaded by another player, then you engage in multiplayer,
or you can just, as soon as you enter the map, you can leave.
and that will advance the time to the next time period.
So again, as narrative designers,
we have no guarantee that the player
is going to do any of this stuff
because all of it is completely optional.
And when you leave the map
and you advance into the noon period,
then again, you can pick from the available maps
or you could skip directly to the afternoon
and pick one of the available maps in the afternoon.
Or if you skip to the evening, then you can pick one of the four maps in the evening,
or you can even skip over and start another loop iteration from the morning.
So again, as narrative designers, we have no idea where the player is going to go.
And this level of choice...
is available to the player on each loop iteration.
So if they do one, two, three, four, or more loops,
however long it takes them to complete the game,
each time they have the choice of those,
all of those maps and time periods as they please.
They can skip time as they please, et cetera.
So summarizing Deathloop is an FPS arcane style.
So it has a strong component of immersive sim DNA.
It is not a roguelike or roguelite.
And it has the central time loop mechanic,
which influences basically everything in the game.
And it's gloriously non-linear.
So our big question as narrative designers
was, how do we design the narrative of this game
to support this core mechanic of a time loop,
to support all of this player choice and reward it?
And how do we tell a relevant story in those conditions?
So there were a lot of things that we need to think about and we tried to narrow it down and ultimately we came up with a couple of basic design goals for this project.
And right now it looks very top-down, but this is not what it looked like when we were designing it.
you know, evolved organically.
So our main, our first design goal was that
players must feel that they are in the time loop,
as opposed to a game where if you die, you respawn,
or you, you know, load up an earlier save game
or something like that.
It needed to feel like a time loop story.
In other words, we need to pay off the core fantasy.
So the player must feel that they are in a time loop
and they're looking for a way out of it.
So in that, to achieve this, we tried to create a new normal for the player.
We tried to make the time loop feel normal.
So the time loop is actually mentioned absolutely everywhere.
It's on graffiti, people talk about it, it's in advertisements,
it's in virtually everywhere you go, there's a mention of the time loop.
So obviously, the NPCs are aware of the existence of the time loop.
They know that they're in it.
They are just unaware how long it has been going.
they still think it's the first day.
And the next morning they wake up
and they still think it's the first day.
So unlike Groundhog Day, for instance,
where people are unaware that they're stuck
in this repeating cycle,
here, the NPCs are aware that they're in a time loop,
but they don't know how long it's been going.
And so we are enforcing several ideas that are typical of a time loop story, and we are just
executing them differently. So for instance, everything is replenished the next day. So
there is no money, no possessions, because everything you take, everything you use,
everything you destroy...
is going to be there the next day, just unchanged, unharmed,
completely back to its original state.
And this is also true for people.
So anybody who dies wakes up the next morning,
and they're bright as rain.
So that's why actually Colt, in order to break the loop,
he needs to kill all of those visionaries
within a single day.
Because if he only kills like three or four of them
during a day, they will be revived the next morning.
So he needs to accomplish this task while the day is on.
And so by doing those things in multiple places,
we are establishing the rules of the time loop.
And now that we have the rules,
we can stick to them to create a feeling of consistency
of the setting that, you know,
there are rules of the time loop
and the world operates according to those rules.
So any choices that the player does, makes during the day,
they persist and then they are reset on the next morning.
And it boosts intentionality.
So intentionality is something that is extremely important in an arcane game.
because we want the player to be able to formulate a plan
and then execute it based on the information that they have.
And in a time loop, this works really well
because you repeat the same environments all the time.
You see the same things happen all the time in the same way.
So that gives you mastery over the environment.
You can anticipate what's going to happen
because you've already seen it.
Everybody else has done it before, but they don't remember.
and actually made things cheaper in production overall
because fewer speech variations and less reactivity
because even though you revisit the same location
over and over again, those are always the same people
and they always do the same thing.
And it's important that they always do the same thing
to maintain the solution of a time loop.
So we actually needed to write fewer variations than we would have if, for instance, we were making a linear game,
you know, with a linear passage of time, and you would revisit a certain area and people would need to remember that you've been there already.
So our second goal was that players must progress despite the time loop.
So we have this time loop that repeats infallibly each time,
but we still, in this environment,
we need to give the player a sense that they are progressing in the story.
And to us, the most important thing here was to have a unity of player and the player character in terms of their memory.
So the player starts playing the game, they have never seen it before, so they start taking this world in,
and so must the hero, they must be aligned at any point.
Because if the hero knows more than the player does...
then the player feels like they maybe did a bad job following the story,
and that creates a disconnect.
And we didn't want that, absolutely.
So we need to make sure each time that the hero
knows exactly the same things as the player.
So the hero in our game is Amnesiac.
He's an Amnesiac.
And...
But that created a problem.
Why would our hero suddenly start remembering
now that you start playing him,
although this loop has been going on for...
God knows how long.
So we actually wrote it into the backstory of Cult, Our Hero,
a cycle of amnesia where he forgets everything,
and then he goes back into a period
where he starts remembering things.
And this is where we introduced what
we call the pre-intro scene.
And that's a scene where Juliana.
A picture here is murdering Colt with a machete.
And that is the very first thing that you see in the game.
Then Colt wakes up on the beach, and maybe at first he
thinks it was just a nightmare.
But then the woman contacts him, and he realizes that.
it actually happens.
So the player has seen that, the player now remembers it.
And when Colt makes reference to this,
then the player knows what Colt is talking about.
So they are united.
And the player does a lot of exploration, obviously,
to learn about the world,
but we needed a source of information
that would bring them up to speed more rapidly.
And this is also Juliana, actually,
your nemesis, your antagonist.
of the game. She's the guide and the sounding board. And that is all thanks to the fact
that she also has a persistent memory. She can remember from loop to loop. So we introduced
a couple of characters who have this kind of persistent memory, but we found out that
anybody who was not the hero or the antagonist creates actually a danger to the setting consistency.
Because in most time loop stories, characters don't generally remember that they're in the time loop,
unless they're the hero, and sometimes if they are the antagonist.
Because when there is anybody else who remembers, that's an anomaly,
and the audience starts looking for a pattern. And if they don't find anything,
it's confusing, like why doesn't anybody remember except this guy, even though he is not the hero.
And that was confirmed by our user research team, where we found out after, you know, in the report
that people considered anybody who was not called or Juliana and who had persistent memory,
that it was an anomaly, that there was something wrong, that the rules of the time were broken.
So our solution to this was to make a big reveal out of the fact that somebody remembers.
So for instance, we have this semi-sentient computer called 2-bit in the game,
and this computer can remember from one loop iteration to another.
And before, that was just like a gameplay gimmick, you know, well, not gimmick, but like a gameplay mechanic.
So you would revisit this area, and because this computer remembered the thing,
he would change things around just to make life more difficult for you.
And then it kind of became a part of the bigger story.
And we've decided to make a big reveal out of the fact
that Tubit can remember.
So when you first meet this computer,
when you first talk to it, he makes it a big deal
that, ooh, to tell you that he can remember.
And this is made in a scene where
we take all the control away from the player.
And this is not something that we do lightly.
at Arcane.
So suddenly it becomes a big reveal
that there's this important character called Tubit
who can remember from loop to loop.
And because of making it a big deal,
it becomes part of the story.
And the players are reassured
that this is not just an omission on your part.
And that kind of solved the trouble.
There was also the question why Tubit remembers
or anybody else remembers.
So this is, we consider this part
of the magic of the island.
And we know within the dev team why people remember,
but we never explain it explicitly.
In fact, in DevLoop, we leave a lot
of hints that allow players to make
some assumptions about that.
But we ultimately left it entirely
to players' imagination and interpretation.
And of course, there were people who complained about that.
They felt like we were, you know, just...
We had no idea what we were maybe doing,
and we didn't want to explain that.
But we actually didn't want to explain the magic,
because if you explain the magic,
it will not be as magical as people imagined it will be.
And we thought it would be better to just leave it to players.
So, to summarize, we had two main design goals.
The players must feel they're in a time loop,
and players must have a sense of progression.
And you will see that it informs everything else that we've done, more or less.
So, for instance, themes.
Somewhere over time, or in between time, or it's difficult to say,
the goals that I just presented became aligned with the themes of our story.
Or maybe it was the...
Or anyway...
Yeah, they kind of reflect one another.
And you will see that it's true in a moment.
Because, for instance, our theme number one is people are stuck in vicious cycles
because they aren't mature enough to break out of them.
And that's a big theme.
It's a very relatable image if you have, I don't know, a bad habit
or you've maybe gone through a bad relationship
or you had writer's block or anything like that.
You know that you can relate to an image of being stuck in a rut.
and having difficulty getting out of it.
So in Deathloop, this is presented literally
and figuratively as well, because the time loop itself
is a very explicit illustration of a vicious cycle.
You are stuck on the island.
The same day repeats over and over again.
Everybody is trying to kill you.
That's a sick cycle, if I ever heard about one.
And there's cold and Juliana and they have very flawed
relationship where they're basically killing one another
over and over again and they cannot seem to find a way out
of it. And the same is true for the visionary. So the main
targets and the eternalists which are just the any all the
other inhabitants of the island who are not visionaries or
colder Juliana.
And after a while, we realized that by illustrating this theme,
we are getting awfully close to realizing also the goal number
one, which is the players must feel they are in a time loop.
Because if we can show that you are in the time loop,
then we are making this very explicit illustration
of a vicious cycle being felt by the player and vice versa.
And so our second theme was that memory can be a treasure but also a curse.
And this is basically an exploration of memory in a time loop.
So some characters have persistent memory and how does that affect them?
How does living in a time loop affect their memory and their personality?
And there are other characters who don't have persistent memory,
so how do they function in a time loop?
And Colt is in between those two worlds because sometimes he is
facing the challenges of having...
persistent memory and sometimes he faces the challenges of not having persistent memory.
And that again connects to our second goal, which is to give players a sense of progression
despite everything repeating. Because if you can remember what happens from loop to loop,
then you have a chance of progressing in it. So basically the player's real life memory
becomes Colt's memory.
And we needed systems that would illustrate this divergence
between people who can remember
and people who cannot remember.
Because that creates opportunities for the player
to exploit the lack of memory in the other characters
to form a plan of getting out of the loop,
manipulating the events that, you know.
in their service. And it also creates conflict. And as you know, conflict drives the story and
the world and everything that you do in the narrative.
So Deathloop is a game, in its most general sense, the story of Deathloop is about being stuck in a rut.
And by the end of the game, Colt manages to break his own vicious cycle and therefore,
you know, the big loop. And by doing so, he gives everyone else on the island a chance
to re-evaluate their lives and do something with them.
So let's talk about Colton and Juliana, who are our hero and antagonist.
And they're inextricably linked, not just because they have both persistent memory.
They're also father and daughter, and they're best frenemies on the island.
They kind of really like and really hate each other at the same time.
And they are locked in this vicious cycle, because when Colt is trying to break the loop,
he starts remembering again. So he has this persistent memory. And that is very exciting
for Giuliano because now he is, you know, in equal, they can like talk and have some sort of report.
But Colt is really good at trying to break the loop.
So Juliana, and Juliana loves the loop.
She doesn't want it to be broken.
So she needs to stop Colt from breaking the loop,
but still keep him motivated to try to break it
so he keeps being interested.
Because if Colt, you know, quits, gives up,
and doesn't want to break the loop anymore,
he slides back into amnesia and becomes boring again.
And then Juliana needs to murder him to kind of, you know,
shake him up and make him want to break the loop again.
So as a result, they really have no hope for a healthy family relationship.
And Colt realizes that at some point and he decides that, okay, I need really need to break
this loop, but this time I really need to break it. Because Colt has been doing this many, many
times. He has arrived many times at a point where he was just an inch away from breaking the loop
and he always failed for some reason. And we don't know why.
And the reason why is that he needs to kill all of the visionaries, and Juliana is one of them.
And she stages it so that Colt needs to shoot her at point-blank range in the face,
where she is basically defenseless. I mean, she also holds a gun, but she doesn't fire it.
So that is not an easy choice to make for the player, actually. And this is by design, because
we needed to illustrate why Colt has failed so many times
to break the loop.
And if we can make the player have qualms about shooting
Juliane in the face, then it explains
why Colt did not do it before.
The player feels what all those Colts felt before.
It's kind of meta.
And why you would have trouble shooting her in the face,
is because maybe you like Juliana. Juliana is a pretty cool character.
And there's the trait of that. Breaking the loop will also break Juliana's heart.
She makes it very clear. So actually, if you kill Juliana and break the loop,
she will disappear from Colt's life. So again, they have no
way of having a healthy relationship. But this is up to you to decide.
And because you don't have to shoot, obviously, you can stay in the loop.
And that was this choice that, you know, you will finish the game,
you can only break the loop and finish the game by shooting Juliana in the face
and at point-blank range was very controversial,
within and without of the narrative team. And that is understandable.
But because it was controversial, it made it clear that people really cared about it.
And if there's one moment where I would like you to care about, you know, in Deathloop,
it's this moment.
So my takeaway here is that you always need to take into account what your team has to
say.
and the reservations, etc. But sometimes it will not be maybe what you think is best for the story
and you also need to listen to your story. So my reason for keeping this difficult moment in
is that shooting is the core action of this game. It's a shooter. You spend 20 plus hours
shooting people. So
ending the game with something else in a shot suggests that there is a third option,
that you can do it, you can break the loop without harming everybody, without killing those people.
And that makes it a very different game, if it's the case.
That will also be a very cool game, but it's not the game that we were making.
you know, Colt has gone on the shooting spree to kill everybody,
and you needed to kill all those visionaries,
not because Colt likes doing it, necessarily,
but because it is the only way out.
And if it's the only way out, then it's the only way out until the end.
And one important note is that actually very few players appreciate the ending of Deathloop.
And if you look online, people say like,
dude, this ending is garbage.
but I think it's mostly due to, well, reading the comments.
Yes, people had a hard time pulling the trigger facing Juliana, but what they were most disappointed
with was that there is not enough payoff. So after you shoot Juliana and break the loop,
the game ends really quickly. There is very little of this, you know, the new wall. So you don't
really have the time to, I don't know, explore the island, talk to the people and see how they react
to the breakage of the loop.
And my takeaway here would be to, if you make people make a difficult choice,
make sure that you are paying off that choice by taking your time to show the consequences.
Another group of characters are other cults. So while we're in production,
we start asking ourselves the question,
Why did Colt fail to break the loop before?
And why would he succeed this time?
In other words, we realized that we needed
a character arc for Colt.
But the problem was that it's really difficult to execute
in a game like Deathloop because
if Colt were supposed to go through changes
and kind of start having a different opinion of things
during the game.
we had no guarantee that the player would feel the same way as Colt and would evolve with Colt in the same direction.
So that would create a rift between the player and the character, which we didn't want.
So our solution to this was to give Colt a retroactive character arc, meaning that
Colt is already fully evolved as a character. He already has all the capacity to break the loop,
but he just needs to realize it. He needs to remember that he has
arrived at all those conclusions and that they are right.
So as Colt discovers his past, he grows more confident about the views that he held of Blackreef,
you know, and this whole thing that he needs to break the loop.
And we also needed a source of information that was not Juliana,
because Juliana has too much of an agenda.
It needed to be somebody who the player could trust unconditionally,
so he could trust himself, right? That's where we have to visit Colt.
So in the lore of the game, these are cults from different timelines of the same time loop.
So as time loop goes on, it creates a bunch of parallel timelines,
and those cults come from those other timelines.
And they reflect what Colt was in his previous cycles of memory and amnesia.
What kind of opinions he had and how long he has come in his evolution as a character.
So this actually harkens back to both main themes that I've mentioned,
which is memory, because it shows a progression of cult.
So now he kind of can catch a glimpse of what he was before.
And also being stuck in a cycle, because those cults,
through their faulty opinions or I know undeveloped...
Oh, sorry.
They could not break out of this.
cycle. And it was realized in the game with, again, blocking cutscenes where we take control
away from the player and they're pretty difficult to set up. They have a lot of overheads for LD
and animation, etc. So they're pretty expensive, but we wanted something that would grab the
player's attention 100%.
And yeah, my takeaway here is that it was, I feel it was pretty successful because we gave the player
the information they needed in a way that they could not skip. And my takeaway here is that
sometimes you need to go expensive with those things. So the visionaries, which are the main,
the key targets that you need to kill, they're all the embodiment of the theme that you're
being stuck in a cycle due to immaturity. And some examples include like Charlie and Fia, who
are a couple and they break up every day and then they get back together the next day and
they break up again and go back together and break up again and go back together. This is
really horrible to watch. We have Igor who has this childish dream of being a respected scientist
but he never puts in the work to gain either respect or scientific expertise. And we have
Alexis. If you play the game, you know that this is a man who never left puberty, basically. He is
immature in the most literal sense of the word.
And the challenge with visionaries was to make them likeable and hateable at the same time.
And it was a pretty difficult balance because we wanted players to like them and be interested in
them so they would want to know more about them. But we also wanted players to think they suck
as people and not feel very sorry about having to kill them because the player cannot finish
the game without killing all those visionaries.
And the likability part was actually turned out to be pretty easy. So we gave every one of those visionaries like a big
personality that they were all larger than life and you know pre-bombasting and everything. And that doesn't necessarily
make them likable.
But.
it creates interest.
And over time, interest creates attachment.
And I'm saying over time, and that
is the unique benefit of having a time loop story,
is that you see those characters over and over again.
And so you can get to know them better.
And our saving grace was the humor.
The game has a pretty light tone.
It's very humorous.
So we made those characters very entertaining.
If somebody makes you laugh, you cannot fully hate them.
And the testability part was pretty difficult on the other hand.
So we had the original sin of the visionaries in that they are they
escape the world to create this isolated party island that goes on for eternity.
And they used all of the resources in towns to escape rather than to help.
you know make the world a better place. So the very foundation of what they were doing was wrong morally. And that makes them
acceptable targets. But that didn't really land.
for we need something more immediate, more practical.
So we made them pretty depraved every single one of them.
So for instance, Frank, who is the singer and a mobster,
he shot a man in cold blood
for allegedly beating up his pianist
and he claimed it was self-defense afterwards.
And that was before the time loop started.
So that person would not wake up the next day.
And there's Harriet, who is leader of this cult, and she dips people in vats of corrosive gas
just to, you know, get off. And there's obviously Alexis. So, in conclusion, I think we were pretty
successful here. When you read the discussions online, people are saying that each of everybody
has their favorite visionary. One of the...
8 Visionaries is somebody's favorite and somebody felt sorry for killing one of them, but not too sorry.
So we feel that we managed to strike a good balance there.
And if we look at the eternalists, who are regular, mostly unnamed people who you kill by the hundreds,
and it's really difficult to follow their stories because they die so easily and frequently.
So we only were able to explore some of the stuck in a rut ideas
with those characters, often, literally.
So, you know, they start doing something really pointless
and they say like, oh, I'm doing this thing today,
but tomorrow it's going to be better.
I'm just going to make it better tomorrow.
And tomorrow never comes, obviously.
There's only one exception, which is Pick Craxley.
And that's one of the eternalists, one eternalist who remembers.
This is what she looks like.
You meet her in the game.
in a side quest.
And she's the only non-hostile Eternalist in the whole game.
She is the only one person who is not wearing a mask.
And she is sort of the voice of the Eternalist.
So when you meet her and you talk to her,
it's kind of a save the cat moment for a cult
because the players understand that the cult's quest
is no longer for the sake of cult
or for the sake of Juliana,
but for the sake of everybody on the island.
Peck-Rex, he makes it clear that, oh, you know, those people, those journalists who want to kill you,
they maybe made a mistake. They were used by this, by those visionaries,
and they certainly don't deserve being stuck on an island for eternity, without any memory to put.
So, for to summarize, Deathloop's story is about being stuck in a rut, as I've mentioned.
And we have two main themes, one being stuck in a vicious cycle due to immaturity.
And this is explored with virtually all of the characters in the game
on different levels, more implicitly, more explicitly.
We have the other theme of memory.
And this theme is mostly explored with characters who have persistent memory,
like called Julian or Pic.
And we don't really have character arcs.
In fact, the actions that the characters take
illustrate their personalities.
But those characters don't evolve over time
because it's a time loop and they have no memory.
So they are back to their regular selves
on the next morning.
So let's talk about the features.
So our narrative systems, and we have radio calls,
which are called in Juliana banter.
We have floating messages, which is just floating text,
and hammer lines, which are called one-liners
who are made for the benefit of the player.
And we have all sorts of systems
that are staples of the genre,
and that provide background lore and gameplay hints.
So the radio calls, they sound something like this.
I hope you have the audio.
Frank, know you're coming. No need to thank me.
I wouldn't do that in a million years.
Huh. So you're going to kill your friend.
How does that feel?
What can I say that will make you shut up?
Oh, so rocky.
What are you, hungover or something?
No.
I know for a fact that you are, like every morning since we've met.
Yeah, so this is what it sounds like.
Their conversation between Colt and Juliana over the radio.
And the intention behind the system was to have a vehicle for the narrative that would be unlikely
to be ignored or skipped by the player. There is nothing else interesting happening when those
conversations are happening.
And originally the idea was that we would Frankenstein
those conversations from a collection of openings,
middles and ends.
But that proved to be pretty difficult to execute
from the technical standpoint and in writing as well.
And we were only allowed those conversations
at mission start.
So we had a maximum 20 seconds before the player
would engage it with some other content.
And we couldn't play those conversations in combat because we couldn't swap out, you know,
the reeds of lines for like a higher projection ones or something like that.
And we really, really wanted to make those conversations feel as natural and as fun as
possible.
And we need to remember as well that both Juliana and Colt have persistent memory.
So Juliana should remember everything that she's saying and everything that Colt is saying
and they should not repeat anything without acknowledging that they have already said that.
So this links back to the theme of memory.
obviously. And in our final design, there were really short pieces of dialogue, like 15 seconds
a piece. It was mostly style over substance to make those conversations really fun and free-flowing.
And we only would sell you one piece of information per conversation. So they were easier
to parse and we wouldn't have to, you know, do some kind of acrobatics to put in a lot of
information in it. And each of those conversations only happens once. If it plays, it's gone and you
need to reset the play through to hear it again.
So ultimately we hit a tone that we liked, which is this snarky banter between the two characters.
And of course there was the question of how much content we need to cover the entire game.
So in preparation for that we listed all of the meaningful actions that the players could take
within a map, anything that warranted some kind of reaction.
and maybe, you know, what are the things that happen
in those maps that the player should react to
and would maybe want to discuss that with Giuliano.
Also, we picked a list of interesting topics
from the lore, the backstory of the characters and the place.
And we had some story choke points.
So the critical information that the player needed to find
out before they finished the game
to understand what the story was about.
And that list was obviously developed in close collaboration with our campaign designer, Dana,
to make sure that we are covering everything. And initially we had a list of about 60 of those
conversations and then as the game evolved we ended up with about 70-75 of them.
And only a couple of choke points have a fixed order.
For instance, when Colt finds out that he is Julianna's father,
it triggers a conversation and there are a couple of conversations that come after that,
that can only play after Colt has found out this information.
But everything else, like 90% of those conversations can happen at any time.
So they need to be written in a way that there is no conflict,
that they don't reference some other conversation that maybe happened
or maybe didn't happen at this point.
And we were testing this with a prototype that we called the Trash Talker 9000.
And unfortunately, we don't have time to go into any detail at all about it.
But luckily, I already did a presentation about this during the Digital Dragons conference
two years ago, and it's called Don't Believe Everything You Think.
And if you screen grab this slide, then you can watch it on YouTube in its entirety.
But we executed this system with a massive linear visual script.
It was the second biggest script of the whole game,
and it was maintained by our scripter, Jean.
who was not very happy about it.
And so we had a whole list of very specific triggers
and conditions and priorities for those conversations.
And it needed to be enforced like really tightly
in the script.
And it was obviously revised multiple times
as the game evolved and things were shifting, et cetera.
And I wish we had invested more resources
and more efficient nodes for Jean to use
and some more robust debugging options
because that would have saved us a lot of time and stress.
So yeah, invest in your main features.
Floating messages.
look a little bit something like this and this is glowing non-UI text that contains vague thoughts
and an occasional bit of useful information. Only Colt can see them but he talks to them
and that makes it clear for the player that this is not UI, this is diegetic. And he also told
Juliana that he's seeing those things so Juliana sometimes mentions it and that further confirms
that this is not UI.
And in the lore of the game, these are Colt's thoughts
that were through the magic of the silent,
preserved somehow across time,
and now they're popping back up for Colt.
These are things that Colt had already thought some time ago,
not in this playthrough, in any case.
And from the design perspective,
this is a really inexpensive system
to provide mood and gameplay hints to the player,
because this is just text.
We can put it anywhere in the game.
It doesn't break save games,
and it's cheap in localization.
And this is an expression of the memory theme,
because these are memories of past thoughts, obviously.
And they also offer some reactivity to players' actions.
And Sandra Duval, who was the lead narrative designer
on Deathloop before I was in the company,
she originally came up with the system,
and she spoke briefly about it at the Narrative Innovation
Showcase.
So if you've seen it, good for you.
If not, maybe you will be able to watch it again.
So the funny thing with those messages is that initially they were not actually very reactive.
I mean, the system that runs those messages checks display conditions on map load. So
if you did something during the map, it would not trigger a message. It will only trigger a message
on the next map. So for instance, if you did something in the morning, you would get some
payoff for it in the next time period at noon.
And that was okay in the early stages of the game
when missions took like five to 10 minutes,
but as the game evolved and grew bigger,
people started spending in maps like 30, 40 minutes.
And that was just too distant a payoff.
to work. So we had to circumvent it with scripting. We have some messages that always pop up and they
are provide mood and there are a couple of messages that provide reactivity. So when we first tested
this with players we got feedback that there were way too many messages. They obscured the
scenery which was not appreciated by our colleagues in the level art department
and they were not very useful and therefore they were pretty forgettable.
So we made some changes to this design, we streamlined the lore a little bit, and we
identified four distinct moods that showcase the evolution of cults' thoughts. And actually,
those moods were consistent with those visitor cults.
you know, the other cults from the past they meet.
And so for instance, if there was a cult who is like this very,
you know, brooding, kind of, oh my god, nothing is going to work,
but just doom and gloom cult, and we have such doom and gloom messages.
And there's another cult who is like crazy and he just wants to kill
everybody and he doesn't care because he doesn't remember.
And we also have messages that kind of reflect that berserk feeling.
And each of those moods is slightly visually different.
We include some gameplay information,
some, you know, pull this lever
or watch out there are enemies nearby
or this is a good place to snipe, this kind of thing.
And we made those messages a lot less frequent.
So there were fewer of them, so they would pop up more.
And we added the time variant, which was more visually pleasing,
because you had like one message that would pop up,
and there was a sequence of other messages that went after it.
And we opted for more dramatic setups overall,
just to make them more memorable.
And this is one example of such a dramatic setup,
where you have this giant billboard.
And here is how the four different moods look like.
The difference in the visuals is pretty subtle.
It's pretty subliminal.
But it gives the eye something different to process.
So immediately, it's a little bit more memorable.
So let's talk about the hammer lines.
And hammer lines are just one-liners
from Colt who comments on stuff.
And here's an example.
And in this example, Colt is dealing
with a voice-activated door lock.
Ocean.
Pearl diver.
No, no, no, no, no, no.
It's got to be military.
Bomb.
How is this?
So yeah, these are lines spoken by Colt,
and he comments on objectives, discoveries that he makes,
and attracts the player's attention
to some objects in the environment.
And initially, we wanted to avoid this kind of thing at all costs.
We didn't want the player to, you know, the characters just going around and say like,
hmm, this door looks like it could be opened.
Because we've seen it in many games and we thought that it was really unimmersive
and because nobody talks to themselves like that.
But when we started testing the game with players,
it became clear that people had a really hard time
following the story because it's plenty of discoveries,
plenty of realizations.
And the players were reading something
that had this amazing reveal, et cetera,
and it just wasn't landing.
People were like, okay, whatever.
And suddenly they were asking themselves,
why does the character know something that I don't?
Why do I have those objectives that I don't understand?
So we tested a couple of those hammer lines,
because you know, you hammer the player on the head with it.
And they really worked well.
People started grokking basically that,
oh, something important happened here, now I understand.
And so in the end, we added a whole bunch of those,
like plenty, and this had a pretty interesting effect.
on Colt as a character because it fleshed him out as a pretty chatty guy and it aligned very well
with his persona in the radio calls where he was throwing those one-liners with Juliana.
So my takeaway here is even if you think something is overused or doesn't really work well,
if it aligns with your character,
And if you really take your time to write it and try to make it original and funny and interesting,
then it can work. And that is actually a confirmation of a very old lesson that any
trope cliche or any overused tool can be effective if you use it well in the right context.
So let's go through the
the other systems. So things as notes, tapes, etc. They are known to any Arkane fan and they're
pretty very widespread in the other games. So notes are basically collectible pieces of text
that provide lore and gameplay information. Tapes are basically or audio logs. They're
basically notes but with voiceover.
Overheard conversations is when two or more NPCs discuss something
and their conversation reveals some sort of information
or maybe leads you to some sort of side content.
And speaker announcements are just, you know,
a voice oozing from a speaker and providing some information
about content that you may have missed.
So all of those features in Deathloop are pretty similar
in that they have very little to no dynamic
or reactive content.
they are in fact the embodiment of the infallible repetition of the loop.
They always happen at the same time, they always provide the same information,
they always happen in the same places. And so they reflect the theme of being stuck in a cycle
or of being in a time loop.
So it builds familiarity of the player with the map and the lore of the game,
and it helps them make plans.
So because those things always happen the same way and always provide the same information,
you can plan around them to exploit them for your own benefit.
And we did really our best to make them as funny, varied, and original as we could,
so you would enjoy listening to them or reading them, you know, after a hundred times, etc.
And there's one notable variation in this system,
which are the minicomps.
And minicomps are those computers.
And it's a chat system used by the visionaries that
reacts to player actions.
So they are, in fact, notes.
But they're linked with sort of a script tree.
and they are reactive to some of the actions of the player.
So they're visionaries, they're just talking, you know, shit.
And sometimes if somebody dies, then it loads up a note
where this visionary who is dead is no longer present.
And maybe some of the other characters come in,
oh, have you heard that this guy is dead?
Oh, I didn't know, who killed him?
Well, called, obviously.
And those minicoms provide very important progression information.
They give you a lot of hints on how to break the loop.
And they have this very unique in-game look
with this computer, basically.
So my takeaway here is that if you give a different aspect
to something that is already familiar,
you effectively make it different in the eyes of the player.
So you can get more mileage out of the same,
you know, gameplay system that you have.
And minicoms reflect both main themes.
They're stuck in a cycle because the visionaries always
say the same thing.
And also memory, because if the player does something weird,
then it will comment on that.
So it responds to player actions.
But as soon as the next day falls over,
it's back to the same conversation again.
If you do nothing, they will repeat 100 times
the same thing.
So.
Our main themes, which are also realizations
of our main design goals, are expressed
across all of the narrative systems.
And anything that has persistent or reactive content
links to memory, because it offers players progression.
So radio calls, floating messages, and minicoms
are all part of this.
And any non-reactive content, links
to being stuck in a cycle, illustrates the repeatability
of the loop.
So it gives you an impression of being in the loop.
So those are notes, tapes, the overheard conversations,
et cetera, et cetera.
And so in conclusion of this talk,
each game offers challenges because of its setting
and its gameplay loop.
So you as narrative designer needs to embrace that.
and identify what are your key design problems and maybe try to align them with your themes.
And then you can use that to orient your work because anything you do to realize a theme
also realizes one of your design goals. And each time you try to realize a design goal and
make sure that you're really executing it, it also illustrates your themes.
So it gives a very consistent experience to the player.
And in Deathloop, this was an organic process that evolved through many iteration cycles,
and we were fortunate to have enough time to make it work.
And we couldn't have done that without testing with players and user research.
It was an extremely valuable tool.
And when you have big moments, then make sure to pay them off
correctly to the player. And if you have things that kind of go outside of the story,
make sure to make them big moments and then pay them off. And of course, we should never forget
the rudiments. So themes, consistency, characters, conflict, all of that is important in a time
loop story, in any story. And I would like to thank the whole narrative team at Arkane.
people who we worked with, the people who worked on the narrative before I came and who were very
kind and shared their insights on the early days of the project. So, Saszka and Sophie, thank you very much.
And I'd like to thank everybody at GDC. It's my first time here. And particularly, I would like
to thank Osama Dorias, who invited me to do this talk and who also helped me get into the industry
to begin with. I'm sorry I couldn't be there this year in person, but, you know, sometime we'll
finally do it. And Caroline Marshall, without whom this presentation would be...
a complete mess. So thank you very much for reading my stuff and my fellow speakers from
Arkane Lyon, Dana, Megan and Gilles and literally the whole team at Arkane. And anybody who may have
forgotten, thank you. And if you would like to be in the thank yous, we are actually hiring
a whole bunch of positions, so don't hesitate.
And in case you missed, we had a whole bunch of talks this year.
They're all already done.
But maybe you can see them in a replay or on the vault.
So thank you very much.
I'll take questions now.
Hello, thanks for giving such a great talk.
I wanted to ask about one key shift that happens in the game
that you mentioned, the revelation of Juliana
being Colt's daughter.
This is a giant tonal shift from sort of how the game
was both advertised and how you first experienced it.
There's a line early in the game where Colt wonders
a lot of these data.
Juliana.
There is a narrative reason why they're close to the same age.
What was the consideration for that point?
Because for me and some other people who played the game,
that was a very big shock to suddenly go have this character
who you're in kind of a flirty spy versus spy thing going.
And then suddenly it's like, oh, she's your daughter.
That's a very... that was just suddenly like a big, like, tunnel shift.
Thank you.
Yeah, so...
We...
It was...
you know, the wish of, well, basically,
it was supposed from the beginning
that Colt and Juliana are actually related.
This was a thing that we had to make sure
was revealed fairly late in the game.
So, this whole, let's say, red herring
with them being flirty was basically to conceal,
to prevent people from guessing too early
that they are related.
And because of how fiction works and how relationships
between the main characters are shaped in storytelling overall,
there was actually not many things
that we could use to conceal that.
And so we opted to go in the direction of them having...
Because Colt is completely unaware that Juliana could be his daughter.
Like you said, there's a narrative reason why they appear to be the same age.
And so they're basically two conclusions that you can draw based on the stereotypical
storytelling is that either they are related or they have been a couple.
or the Arab couple or love interests of some sort.
So we leaned into that one thing to kind of distract players
from thinking that the other was possible
and that made it possible to make this revelation
that Juliana is actually called stutter
a big reveal later on.
Very good, thank you.
Hi, thanks so much for the talk.
I recently finished Deathloop, and I really adored it.
I had a question about the visionary missions and stuff.
So how you can, you know, they span through the entire game,
and you can work on one mission in the morning,
working on, like, Alexis,
and then handle another one in the afternoon.
How did you guys handle kind of making it
so the player could...
Jump from mission to mission and kind of like, you know work on them all in tandem without it feeling
Like disjointed there were some missions
I started in like the beginning of the game and then I it was one of the like last ones I finished
So like how did you guys tackle that?
like a nonlinear
approach
Yeah, so that's actually one of the biggest issues that we were facing with the game.
So initially, the missions were a lot simpler than they ended up being.
And we realized in testing that you could actually beat the game in like one hour if you optimize your actions.
So that's where the leads came from.
We basically shifted away from focusing on missions that feature the visionaries, you know, where you need to kill them as the main attraction.
And that was only that started being only the thing that appears on the outside that this is what you need to focus on.
But what you actually need to focus on is to getting the visionaries.
to move from their usual routines to put them,
to align them in a way that you could take them out
at the same time.
And that took...
an enormous amount of iteration and testing and brainstorming and,
you know, redoing the missions over and over again
to make sure that we gave you we give players enough steps in those missions
to for them to feel sufficiently complex so they can complete them very quickly.
But also to be simple enough so you could follow what is even going on, what is the idea behind those leads, those stratagems to put them in different places.
So actually the idea is always very simple.
prevent Igor from going to the party by sabotaging his experiment.
So you sabotage Igor's experiment, and then he goes to the party.
And this in itself is like a very simple idea, but it's built around several actions that
you need to undertake to make it happen.
And I guess that, well, the reply is really a lot of time and iteration.
Gotcha.
Cool.
Thank you.
I have a question then if there's time for one.
So there's this moment in the game that a character goes on a rant and it's called
The Runt.
I think it's Alexis.
And I used to be a management consultant.
I used to be a business person and I literally sent that.
sequence to all of my friends that I used to work with because it reflects the psyche of high
ambition business people extremely well. What gave you the insight or who on the team had insight to write a sequence like this?
I believe this sequence was originally written by Joe Fielder, who is one of our contract writers on Deathloop.
And we asked him, can you do like a rant of Alex's where he kind of talks all about his business prowess, etc.
And he sent us this and it was...
amazing, but yeah, Joe Fielder, I believe he is actually in person at the GDC.
So if you manage to find him, you can ask him the question directly.
Awesome.
Thank you.
Hello, my name is Kim.
Thank you so much for the talk.
I'm a huge fan of Arcane and especially Deathloop.
I wanted to ask if during the building of Deathloop,
if there was any inspiration to either add more visionaries
or reduce the amount of visionaries.
And if there was any thought about like why there's seven,
seven and a half, if you count Tuba or Juliana.
Yeah, so, no, as far as I can tell, it was always meant to be this number of visionaries and not any other number.
Of course, it's an odd number because odd numbers are objectively better in storytelling than anything else.
So you always get three acts, five chapters, seven evil acts and nine visionaries.
or eight or seven.
Well, in any case, no, there was never any plan
to have fewer visionaries than this
because it needed to be difficult.
The idea that you have four periods of day,
so only four missions per day,
but eight people to kill, it sounds impossible.
And that's what was needed for Deathloop to,
you know, how do you break the slope
if there's this impossible task to achieve?
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
And that's all the time I have.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.