As mentioned, my name is Roland IJsselmans, which is very hard to pronounce.
And I'd like to start this talk with an imagination session.
Let's imagine that we're all underwater, that the water has reached the top of this building
out of the San Francisco Bay.
And what if we left it there for over a thousand years?
Well, that's the same question we asked ourselves
five years ago at Guerrilla,
when we started with the concept team
on Horizon Forbidden West.
What would San Francisco look like a thousand years from now
if it had been flooded all that time?
To answer that question, we started looking at studies that showed how the water
would flood parts of San Francisco as the ocean started rising.
And what would happen if it would keep rising?
San Francisco would turn into a group of islands surrounded by the tops of buildings
still poking out of the sea.
And I'm calling them buildings, but over time.
these concrete floors in these buildings would have collapsed.
Soil would have built up on top, allowing plants and trees
to get a foothold, eventually creating
pillars of vertical jungle.
But close to the water surface, where the waves hit,
buildings would be reduced to their mere skeletons.
And even further down, below the ocean level,
corals would start building on top of these ruins.
Building interiors would start looking like underwater caves,
with ocean tides slowly eroding the sharp edges
into round corners, and stalactites
starting to form at the ceilings of these lobbies,
like the one we have out here.
We also explored what the underwater landscape of San Francisco could look like.
How the remnants of the city could hold up underwater after all this time.
Like this iconic landmark, the Palace of Fine Arts,
which would largely be standing due to the use of natural rock
and marble, which is made out of.
Whereas the Ferry Building would have a much harder time.
Only the outer wall is made out of stone.
All of its metal interiors would deteriorate
and collapse after a couple of hundred years underwater.
As for above the water, buildings would also collapse.
The buildings that have been built
with exterior metal structures like this one
would topple over and sand would start to accumulate
on the shores.
of the new shoreline of San Francisco,
covering what once were busy streets
with a thick layer of pearl white sand.
And although I personally wouldn't mind
having a GDC in a setting like this,
we didn't design it for this reason.
I wanted to show you this version of San Francisco
as an example of what the world of Horizon looks like,
as it sets a stage for the different cultures
that live in the world of Horizon,
which brings me to the topic of this presentation.
Today, I'd like to take you on a tour
past two of the key settlements from Horizon Forbidden West
and share with you the design processes
we used when visualizing these settlements.
how we use the world of Horizon itself
to shape the design of these locations and its inhabitants.
Let me first talk a bit about myself.
I started at Guerrilla way back in 2002
after graduating as an industrial designer.
And for the past five years, I had the pleasure
of working on Horizon Forbidden West,
the sequel to Horizon Zero Dawn.
And just out of curiosity,
I know the game has only been out for a month.
How many of you have already played it?
Wow.
And how many of you have already met the Tanakta New Taro?
Wow, okay.
Now, for those of you who haven't played the game,
let me explain briefly what Horizon is about
before we look at these settlements in more detail.
I'll try to do this as short as possible
to avoid any of the spoilers.
So Horizon Zero Dawn is set in a post-apocalyptic world
where nature has reclaimed the land,
just like in the example of San Francisco.
It's a world that for centuries was uninhabited by humans.
And when they returned,
they returned without the knowledge of their past.
They were basically thrown back
into a hunter-gathering society.
This life was made intensely difficult
by the presence of these giant robotic machines.
These machines came in various shapes and sizes,
but they had one thing in common.
They were all extremely aggressive against humans.
This made settling in this world a big challenge.
Now let's look at one of these settlements in more detail,
the Utaru one, with their main capital plains zone.
One of the key defining elements for the Utaru
comes from the machines that roam the lands around them.
Each culture and horizon deals with the threat of these large machines in its own way.
For most settlements, these machines are perceived as extremely dangerous wildlife.
As a result, they fortified their settlements or placed them out of reach of the dangerous
ones.
But for the Otaru, we wanted to try something different.
We wanted to try a relationship with the machines.
where instead of hunting them,
they could grow dependent on them.
But how would you grow dependent
on a large machine like that?
Let me introduce the plow horn.
This is a machine that's designed to grow food.
A large machine that uses its horns to fertilize grounds
and is planting crops with the use
of those seed pouches you see on the right.
It's basically a combine of four lakes.
These plow horns can turn deserts into grids of,
in grid fields, in fields,
in fields in a grid-like structure,
filled with edible crops.
An ideal location for the otaru to settle in.
Right in the middle of their own natural food supply.
And besides food, they would also need resources
to build their houses and clothing from.
One naturally grown resource that they had an abundance of
would be bamboo,
which is a great lightweight construction material
that we started exploring as using as a base material
for their huts.
With the bendable qualities of bamboo,
We started exploring sort of base shapes
as a basis to layer on top the different layers,
the external parts of the hut.
And for this, we took inspiration from a variety of weaving techniques
from all over the world.
One technique that we found very inspiring
was the way that ikebana baskets are woven in Japan.
just like this one.
These baskets make use of lacquered bamboo,
long strips that create beautiful patterns
along the outside with long, elongated, curved lines
all the way through.
And we applied this principle on a larger scale
to the entire hut.
And we were very happy with the unique look
that this was giving us.
Long curved lines make the hut feel like it was grown instead of constructed.
And with that idea we created a variety of these huts,
sort of like giant baskets for people to live in.
While retaining that feel of grown instead of constructed,
we started to look at different weaving patterns, each unique and
distinctive in its own way.
And we felt that we were hitting on a very
honorable and distinctive look for the otaru.
A downside of this type of weaving
is that it's not as protective against the rain,
but it does give really nice,
allows for light to play at night
through the holes in the weaves.
And not just the halls, also the bent surfaces play really well with the lights of the Otaru.
As for where to place these huts, we used the ancient ruins of a satellite array that was built when the landscape was still a desert.
Providing a safe place for the Otaru and adding even more to the unique feel of the settlement.
We started to block out their...
entire settlement on top of a 3D representation of these dishes,
designing a purpose for each and every dish,
like the one on the right,
which was made for cooking and storing food.
The one in the center, closer to the ground,
was their housing unit, housing dish,
where we designed these support structures
to connect the different huts together.
and create paths through the entire settlement.
Again, resonating those long, flowy lines
that we were inspired by, by the Ikebana baskets.
And those pathways eventually ended up on bridges like this one
that connected different satellite dishes.
And just like their houses, these bridges were designed
to look like they've been grown rather than constructed.
to underline the connection of the Otaru that they have with nature.
One of their dishes even still had a giant tree in that
that had grown there before.
And the Otaru hadn't removed it, but embraced it
and created the hanging garden around it,
where they grow their own plants
that they can't find close to their settlement.
And using these...
bamboo techniques, we expanded on not just creating their houses and their environment,
but also their props.
These decoration items and the two lights on the right that have this nice translucent
sheen.
Besides these lights, we also looked at tools to gather props from the fields that are surrounding
their settlement.
and again using bamboo to weave robot parts into handles.
Extending this thought onto even their clothing,
we experimented with creating hats out of woven patterns
and even sandals,
which works fine for these sort of stiffer elements
that people wear,
but it's kind of hard when you're doing the actual wardrobe.
to create bamboo that creates clothing pieces
that look comfortable to wear made out of bamboo.
By combining leaves and machine cables from robots,
we designed these togas that wrap around in a single piece.
Again, creating those longer curves that wrap around the body,
avoiding symmetry and straight parallel lines,
with curved belts and tear-shaped,
and a tear shape around their neck.
And at the center of that tear shape,
a decorated seed pouch to show their appreciation
of the plow horn.
And as an act of courage...
It's not only the plowhorns that affected the look of the Otaru.
To show their appreciation for these plowhorns,
they went into the field and acted as an act of courage,
put their hands on these plowhorns with colored paint.
So if you walk around the horizon
and you see a plowhorn with colored paint on it,
that's because the Otaru appreciated them so much.
This takes me to the second settlement
I'd like to show you.
which is the desert Tanakts, main capital, Skoldingspeer.
For the desert Tanakts, their origin story is almost the polar opposite.
They live in a land with hardly any resources.
And they had a hard time coming by,
which made them focus on a more combatant lifestyle,
fighting the surrounding settlements, as well as the robots.
split off into three clans.
They have their origins, not with the machines,
but in the ruins that they had discovered.
The key defining element for the Tanakt
is a ruin from the old world,
a military memorial that the Tanakt had discovered.
A memorial that was built a thousand years ago
before the Tanakt had found it.
to honor a military unit that had battled against automated war machines.
These great warriors from the past became a key inspiration for the Tanakt.
But for the Tanakt, the only version of these great warriors
that they actually saw was distorted and mangled.
Corrupted data and degraded projection had warped the holographic images over time.
So we as a concept team started exploring
how far we could take this broken projection idea.
How could these patterns,
how could we shape these patterns?
And initially playing with different just color distortion
and pulling at the different angles.
We still felt that this was too close
to the original image of a soldier.
So we took that even a step further
and almost like looking through a disoriented piece of glass
started warping these warriors into these extended figures,
distorting their shapes even more,
which created the interesting and unique silhouette
for these warriors.
From that, we took a color palette and a
a pattern style for each and every one of the different Tanakh tribes.
The Tanakhs are divided into three,
depending on the region that they live in.
There's the desert, jungle and mountain Tanakhs,
and they all reference a different group of military
that they had seen in the museum.
For the desert, it was the forward and aggressive...
operations, and we translated that into this outward motion
and this aggression in that face that you see there.
As for the jungle, they were more trappers.
So their symbology became more inward
with pointy fangs pointed inward,
whereas the mountain tanaks had more of a height and
secure locations high up in the mountains, which we associated with this
more inward and concrete shape language. And from this, for the desert tenact,
we started exploring how this could look in motion,
how we could angle up some of these patterns
and distort them, combining different patterns,
trying to look for that aggression
that we felt was suiting for the desert tonight.
And these are some of the early sketches
that show sort of an overlay of those patterns
onto a character trying to mimic.
the distorted holograms that they had seen in the museum,
where color patterns were painted on
and even additional rubble plates were added
to suggest those distorted holograms.
For us, this wasn't going far enough,
so we created even bigger masks with stranger shapes
and had the colors of these patterns
tattooed all over their bodies.
resulting in masks like this built from robot parts
where they had edged off the different sides
to create the angular pattern
that you saw in those earlier studies.
Adding all those plates onto these warriors
made them look as intimidating as the one you see here.
And again, for them, we also created the tool sets
to allow them to make these things.
This is as far as the characters goes.
What about their housing?
Well, they're fierce warriors.
They're not architects.
So if you can't build yourself,
why not use an existing ruin?
We thought that that would be an interesting base
for them to start off.
As they are in the desert,
there's not a lot of architecture that you can lean into.
So we felt that this solar power plant
matched the view of the world that the Tanakh had.
It would serve them as a nice fortress,
surrounded by these shields that looked like
it was already protected, and a nice central tower
that they could see the lands around them very well.
So this was the base for their architecture and living,
but they still had to put huts on top of that.
And as I said,
they're not that great builders.
And so we started as simple as we could.
Throwing together a bunch of beams,
like a game of Mica dough,
and tying them together at each intersection.
And then filling up the spaces in between the beams
with floors and walls,
allowing us to create these erratic shapes
that also supported the erratic look
that we had in the holograms.
As well as these nice overhanging rooftops
for some much appreciated shade in the desert.
Going back and applying the color scheme
of the desert tanak that you'd seen earlier,
we finished them by painting them in their work colors
and arranged them around the central solar tower
that you see here.
By arranging them in this manner, this outward way,
we started to create a silhouette
that almost looked as aggressive as a silhouette
and almost like an explosion frozen in time,
which we felt was very appropriate
for the aggressive desert tanak.
As we were arranging this,
we noticed that some of the concrete
didn't fall in line with the tanak thinking of decoration.
So we started chiseling into that.
seeing if we could bring back some of the patterns
also on their outside walls.
And then again, using paint and simple wooden decorations
to bring that in line with the holograms
that they'd seen before.
And at the center of this settlement,
there's of course a combat ring,
a combat arena where the Desert Tanak train
to become even better warriors.
And overlooking this combat arena
is their main area.
is their commander's hut,
where he can oversee the progress,
where the commander can oversee the progress
of the Tanakhs in the village town.
We had people come in and question us
when they were looking at this,
saying, well, that's quite a reach, Roland,
when you're having this entire culture based off
A glitch, a misinterpretation of the past.
Isn't that stretching things a bit thin?
Funnily enough, this happens in our world as well.
Where we've interpreted old Roman sculptures
to be white, and this white color has resonated
in so many of the
derivatives that we've created from that time.
Things like even the White House
might have had more color
if we had found at an earlier stage
that most of these Roman sculptures
had actually been brightly colored
instead of
polished white to look better in the museum.
I've been talking a bit too fast, but this already brings me to the end of my presentation on the two tribes in Horizon Forbidden West, Plainsong and Scalding Spare.
And I know my jet lag has been killing most of my this presentation, but I hope you have gotten a bit of an insight of the way that we work at Guerrilla.
but some of the decisions that we've made along the way
and how most of our design choices have been made
not because we think it looks cool,
but because we sort of go out into the world of Verizon
and discover as much as we can,
driving the visual choices that we make at the concept team.
Thank you very much for listening to me being very nervous.
That concludes my presentation.
Are there any questions?
No, I'm sorry, there.
Hello there.
Hi.
As we've just seen, that can get really, really detailed.
How do you know when you've reached a point of like,
this tribe is detailed enough,
we have eight other tribes to look at?
Because it's very impressive
how far in the detail you've gone.
Yes.
Often when we think we've gone far enough,
we get replies that we haven't gone far enough yet.
Because once you start modeling these things,
and it's easier when you're doing things
that are based on reality,
but if you're designing your own things,
you need that amount of detail
to actually show in the models that end up in the game.
So oftentimes I think, wow, we've done a really great job.
Here's the entire package.
They come back and say, wow, all this weaving,
how does that work?
Which material is what?
So we go back and look at it again.
So by the time that that is quiet,
we know that we have done our jobs.
Gotcha, thank you.
Yes.
Okay.
Dude, I love the game.
Amazing art direction, especially, you know,
shipping on PS4, PS4 Pro,
and the PS5 must have not been easy.
In the art direction,
what was the hardest thing that y'all faced?
Because like any other generation, cross-platform,
like what was the hardest thing y'all did?
Thank God that wasn't a worry on my discipline.
We design things to maximum resolution or maximum amount of detail,
so that we were always able to answer any questions with regards to what material,
how things look at, not a microscopic level, but quite a detailed level.
Yes, so I think this is not a question for me.
It hasn't made it any harder for our team.
Hi there.
Hi there, amazing talk.
I really loved seeing the amount of concept art
throughout the talk and just how creative it all was,
which I guess was what the talk was about.
I come from indie, and in the world of indie,
you have a lot less resources for stuff
like having concept art for everything.
So in my experience, we just end up like
making stuff on the fly that might not necessarily
have a concept ready for it.
So I'm wondering, in your world,
how much of this...
Does everything get a concept? Everything that gets made?
Or are the concepts more to guide, like, maybe one version of something, and then the modeler expands from there?
That's a very good question.
Although we do a lot of concept art,
we don't concept art the complete world.
So we create style guides for each of the different tribes.
And those usually have a showcase of a main settlement
and what that could look like, like I've shown you today.
But there are many derivatives of that,
where we try to include as much information.
In the style guide, sometimes not just technical about how a layout would look, but also how some of the people would act, how they greet each other and things like that.
To inform anyone working on this.
how to best construct or build derivatives and settlements.
So there's kind of a trust moving forward to the next levels in the pipeline.
Yes, yes.
It's too big a world to completely sketch out at that level of detail.
I see.
Thank you.
Yeah.
I'm going to take it.
You also heard that, right?
I guess.
I really love the designs you've got,
and especially the research that goes into San Francisco
and building in that water level.
And I'm just curious how much of the concept and designs
come from a game design standpoint
as well with having the flooded sections
and how that leads into gameplay.
How much of that falls back onto you as well?
So the question is how much of the gameplay is involved
at an early stage when we're designing these things.
That happened quite early on.
Our initial, we had taken lessons from our previous game,
Horizon Zero Dawn, where some of these larger cities
had less activities to allow this time to create spaces
that were game design friendly as well.
So in conjunction with game design,
we looked at the different spaces and where to open up,
and where certain opportunities for
certain types of gameplay would work really well.
Thank you.
Thank you, sorry, wait, one second.
I don't wanna take all the applause.
There's been a lot of concept artists creating this work
inside and outside our company,
so please applaud one round for all of those artists.
Thank you.