Okay, so, this is a talk titled,
Idle Games, the Mechanics and Monetization
of Self-Playing Games.
So let's get right into it.
A quick introduction.
I've been at Kongregate for about six years,
directing our browser-based virtual goods business.
Also recently picked up production for a mobile game
called Adventure Capitalist,
which actually just launched about two weeks ago.
And we'll be talking about that quite a bit in this talk,
as it is also an idle game.
I also founded a studio called Level Up Labs.
And we're probably best known for our game Defenders Quest
and are currently working on a sequel.
Kongregate.
We are, if anyone is not familiar with us,
an open platform for browser-based games
with a variety of technologies.
Basically anything that runs in the browser
we're happy to support.
We have around 16 million.
That might be a slightly old number,
but somewhere around 16 million monthly unique visitors
worldwide.
Our demographic tends to be more of a core gamer demographic
than you usually think of with browser-based games.
Heavily male, average age about 22 years old.
Popular genres are more MMOs, RPGs,
collectible card games.
Not really as much of the casual and social games
that you might see on other sites.
We have a platform-level currency called Creds
that you can spend in our free-to-play games.
And we were acquired by GameStop in July of 2010.
We work with a variety of partners that are both
western and eastern, big companies, small companies,
have all published through us,
or distributed through us on the web.
We also, in the last about year and a half or so,
have become a mobile publisher.
And these are some of our games,
we have quite a few more that are out now
and regularly launching.
So that's kind of our core business.
So, that's the good background of where
a lot of this data's coming from.
So I want to open with a question for the audience.
How many of you have played Cookie Clicker or some other
idle game?
Can you put up your hands?
All right.
I want you to leave your hands up if you have played what you
would describe an embarrassing amount of it.
Alright, a lot of hands stayed up for that, thank you.
So that gives us three interesting pieces of information.
One, almost every hand went up for the first question.
These are very popular games, they're well known,
a lot of people play them.
Two, a lot of hands stayed up for playing
an embarrassing amount, which means that people
play them a lot and keep playing them.
And three, there is this sort of self-shame around them.
People don't usually talk about playing games
an embarrassing amount if it's like a really great game
they're proud of, but there's this weird thing
about idle games.
So I want to kind of dig into all of that.
So this is a game called Number.
It was a kind of a spoof parody game Tyler Goyle created.
You want to make your number go up.
It goes up a certain speed.
When you can afford more, you make it go up faster.
It's boiled down to the most minimal level.
And yet, this is actually kind of compelling.
I played this an embarrassing amount, to be frank.
So why is that?
What is it about this genre?
And why are we talking about this in the first place?
Well, for one, it's a birth of a new genre.
We don't actually get to see that very often in the games industry.
Probably the most recent one prior to this was maybe MOBAs,
to see like kind of a legit new genre coming and becoming very popular.
It's only about two years old in its modern form.
And it is very popular. Right now this is a screenshot of the top most played
games on Kongregate in the last thirty days and three of those top five are idle games.
It's so popular
you actually can watch Twitch streams of self-playing games.
Like, the guy's not even playing this. He's just
running it through his browser.
But it's, like, six people are actively watching this, 2,500 people have favorited this
channel of a self-playing game without even a person there.
They have fabulous retention stats.
We'll look at some specific ones,
but these are some of the best retaining games
on all of congregate.com.
And they actually generate really great revenue.
The ARPUs, the lifetime values of these games,
are well above most single player games that we have,
and actually are competing
with a lot of our multiplayer games.
Also, for those taking pictures,
we'll post these slides on our website as well,
so you're welcome to take pictures,
but if you miss some, please don't worry about it.
They'll be available afterwards as well.
So I want to do a quick survey of the history and evolution of
idle games to understand how we've gotten to where we are.
Probably the first one was Progress Quest by Eric
Fredrickson in 2002.
This was a parody of MMORPGs, and it was basically a
character sheet that just ran itself.
It's a zero player game.
You cannot interact with this, even if you want to, outside
of the character creation, which doesn't have any impact
on the game.
uh... it's you know so much so that the uh... wikipedia page kinda cheekily puts
quotes around the word game throughout it
it's not really interactive in any way but
it's still kind of people it was still popular how many people have played progress quest?
Right, okay, this is not a game you can play.
But that many people are aware of it and have played it.
So already we were seeing something interesting happening.
Kongregate in particular actually ended up being
sort of an early breeding ground for idle games.
And I think the main reason is that we have a chat room
that plays next to the games.
And you can only be in chat if you have a game running.
So there was this demand for games
that people didn't actually want to play,
they just wanted to be in chat, but you had to sum it up.
So we started seeing games, the oldest one
that has an idle tag is a game called Kongregate Chat.
It was made just so you could chat and not really be playing a game.
Not long after that, that was 2007, 2008, we started seeing some rudimentary RPGs appearing.
Nowhere near the complexity of what we see in current idle games, but already this idea
of a game that mostly plays itself with very little interaction was starting to occur.
In 2009, probably our most popular early idle game was a game called Anti-Idle.
And this game got crazy.
It was incredibly complicated.
It had active elements and idle elements.
It's actually really different from current idle games,
but it did a lot of pioneering work in that concept.
Tons of content.
It's six years old, and they are still adding new features.
Literally yesterday, he pushed out an update to it.
So it's an incredible game and has been really popular for a very long time.
Cal clicker is one of the ones that got a lot of media attention.
Ian Bogost was trying to really poke fun at Farmville and other
appointment games and social games.
And so the idea was you got this cal, you would click it,
then you have to wait six hours and then you come back and click it again.
And by click it I mean one time, you only get one click per six hours.
And that was about it.
You could invite some friends, and if they clicked on their
cow, you got some moony.
And that was the entirety of the game.
And much to Ian Bogost's surprise, it really caught on.
And he ended up adding some more features to it and
growing out a little bit, but still trying to champion this
idea that social games and farm games are silly, at least in
his opinion.
A quick mention, they're a bit different, but A Dark Room and Candy Box are, you know,
idle games in many ways.
There was a lot of progress that would happen without active interaction.
But they actually are a bit different from most of what we're talking about now.
They are finite, they can be beaten.
They're a lot more puzzle-like and exploration-based.
They're great games and I definitely recommend them if you haven't played them.
But they are a little different from where this talk will be going.
So cookie clicker. This is the one that really kicked it off.
It was actually a parody of candy box. And got really
popular and Orteo was quoted as saying at first I couldn't tell
if people were just going along with the joke or if they were
actually being serious. It turns out they were being serious.
There was something, even though it was funny and you kind of
enjoyed it, there was something extremely compelling about the
system that he set up for it. And I forget what the number
was, but a ridiculous number of players played this game and
continued to play this game.
It was the first major mainstream hit of the genre,
arguably creating it.
So this is why I'm saying it's two years old,
is this is where it really came into its modern form.
And it really established a basis for the progression,
for the upgrading, for all of these tropes that we see
mimicked in most of the current idle games,
this was the game that really brought those into mainstream
and kind of solidified them.
Adventure Capitalist was a kind of an experiment by Cody Veague
who worked at HyperHippo Games.
And it turned out to be really popular in HyperHippo
then put more people onto it.
But it's really a parody of capitalism in idle games.
You notice I've been saying parody a lot.
This is sort of a genre that almost doesn't want to exist.
It's a joke really.
But it keeps, despite itself, being really successful.
And so you actually see a lot of humor in a lot of these games.
And that's a reason for it.
It was one of the first that I'm aware of to introduce offline progress.
So unlike cookie clicker where you had to have it running your browser all the time,
this one would calculate the time between your last login
and just give you credit for everything you would have earned.
This was really freeing.
Now you don't have to dedicate your CPU to watching, you know,
little pointers clicking a cookie.
You could just close it down and come back the next day.
And I think that was actually a big advantage for it.
And it's now actually standard in most idle games.
And it was also just really fun to look at.
There was a lot of animation, bars filling up.
Everyone loves bars filling up.
So it was really compelling.
Clicker Heroes, 2014.
This is one that was a lot more RPG-like.
You hired heroes, you leveled them up, you gained skills,
and your power was measured in DPS, damage per second.
They added the addition of cooldown skills.
Again, this added some strategy and action elements to it.
And it had really great visuals and presentation.
And that's, they didn't actually put all that into the idle game.
This was all repurposed assets from one of their MMORPGs.
But it made it one of the best looking idle games of the time.
And then Tap Titans is not by PlayStores,
but is kind of a close derivative that you may have seen on mobile
that is very similar to Clicker Heroes,
but did a really great job kind of bringing that into mobile.
Alright, almost done with the history.
Make it rain was probably the first big mobile success.
And a lot of that I think was just this hilarious concept.
You'd sit there and you'd flick your finger over it
like you're making it rain with dollar bills.
And it was very viral.
A lot of word of mouth.
People just wanted to show each other this great concept.
And I think that helped it really take off.
The idle elements were actually really limited.
You could only collect so much money
and then you'd have to come back in to get it.
And it would stop collecting once you got to a point.
So you had to really check in regularly.
I had a very aggressive ad strategy where ads were popping up all the time.
Because you're doing this motion, you'd actually click on them.
It was very clever, but I think it actually probably wore down the players a fair amount.
It was kind of annoying too.
So I'm sure it was a great success for a while, but I bet it hurt their longer term retention.
I don't have the data to prove that though.
And they also had this pretty brutal FBI monetization.
So the FBI would occasionally show up, they would declare you guilty.
And you would lose not only a hunk of cash, but actually a hunk of your cash per second.
Which in an idle game is a really big deal.
And you'd have to bribe them with real world money to not lose that.
And that's, that's, that was, I think that's actually what kind of like stopped me from playing the game.
Once I hit that, that was such a negative thing that it, I just didn't want to go on.
So that's a very, very aggressive monetization strategy.
It may have worked well, but again I think it hurt the long term.
Bitcoin billionaire was another great mobile game.
Apple loved it.
It has really nice style, tone, and the topic
was fun and very current.
Presentation is really good.
Just kind of general design is really nice on it.
And one of the best things about it is it's opt-in ads.
This was one, a lot of times people cite Disco Zoo
as great opt-in ads.
This one, I think, also is really worth studying.
If you're ever going to be working
with opt-in ads on mobile, look at the many, many ways
that they do it.
And we'll actually look at a few of them
later on in the talk.
But it's something that Bitcoin did really nicely.
They similarly to MakeItRain had really strong bit,
I'm sorry, appointment mechanics,
very limited offline progress,
and it was actually offline progress
is one of their central monetization elements.
I think this was actually a mistake on them,
and we'll talk about why a little bit later.
Two quick notable entries that aren't really as well known,
but DripStat is really just a cookie clicker clone,
but it had amazing visualization.
You could really understand what was contributing to what.
It has a global live leaderboard,
so if you look in the top left area here,
I can see my global ranking,
and every time I drip more bytes into the machine,
I'd actually seen my rank move up.
And there's actually even real time contributions from other players.
So you can see this plus one gigabyte from user, you know, whatever that is.
That's not me, that's someone else that has just done that in real time.
So even though it's a single player game, you get this feeling that you're playing in
a world with other people.
And that was something that I haven't seen done much in idle games, and this one did
really nicely.
And the other one I want to mention, Swarm Simulator, has only been out for a couple
of weeks, at least on Kongregate.
I'm not sure where it started earlier than that.
It explores a new kind of funnel-based economy,
so they're actually playing around with a different way
of doing the idle game economy,
so that's really interesting.
Even though it's only a couple weeks old,
it's proving to be extremely popular.
So in the last couple weeks, it's been played
a million times on Kongregate alone.
So I think we actually probably will see this one
catching on a lot.
You probably will hear about it if you haven't already.
I definitely recommend checking out it.
It's really nice, even though it's, like a lot of these,
just sort of a glorified spreadsheet
with some really neat mechanics in it.
So, speaking of idle game core mechanics,
what makes these games so interesting?
What is unique about them compared to most other games?
Progress without interaction. This is sort of the most basic thing about idle games is where they get their name, right?
And I should say, I'm saying idle games, you'll often hear incremental games used as well.
If you hop on Reddit, you can get into a very long argument about this.
I'm going to use them fairly interchangeably and not address that debate.
So, progress without interaction. It's a low-pressure experience.
You don't have to be constantly playing. If you go away for a while and you come back,
that's okay, you got some stuff, you can keep going.
It's a very kind of positive growth, positive feedback.
Everything is going up, right?
There's no loose conditions.
You might not go as fast as other people,
but you constantly feel like you're making progress.
And quick check-ins can be very profitable.
Every time you check in and you buy a couple of things,
it shifts up your curve so that you're gaining faster.
And then you go away for a while and you've actually
made a lot of progress even with a very short check-in.
And this is really good for social and especially mobile.
interactions when you're looking for that like I want to pull it out for a
minute make a couple decisions and put it away this type of system is great for
that so what this actually does is it creates a celebratory moment every time
you come back to the game so and a lot of these will actually call it
explicitly so let's say like welcome back you just earned a ridiculous amount
of money you should spend it and so it creates this positive feedback of oh man
I just came back I get to spend all this stuff this is a lot of fun
and beyond that, the longer you're away, the bigger the reason to return.
So if you've been gone for a week or so,
you don't feel like in some games you've fallen behind, here you've actually gotten ahead, right?
And if you go back, you're going to have even more money to spend.
And so, you know, here where I was gone five hours instead of a day,
I get a lot more being gone for a day.
So forced appointment mechanics I would actually say are unnecessary.
Players naturally want to come back because of the way the system works.
And that's a really kind of magical thing.
So even daily rewards I don't see used in these games.
And maybe they could be, but the fact is they don't really need it.
Because the retention is already off the charts.
So here is a chart of retention.
D1, 7, I think, 14 and 30.
Or no, 30 and 90, sorry.
The actual numbers don't really matter.
And you'll notice our D1s look kind of low.
This is the top 10 monetizing games of 2014 on Kongregate.
The D1s look low compared to what you see on mobile.
And that's because there's a lot less friction when you go
to play a browser game.
You don't have to install it.
You just check out the page.
So what I'm doing this is to give kind of a sense of a
baseline of some of our best performing games.
And then, now I'm going to pop on our three idle games that have in-app purchases in them.
You'll notice they dwarf all of our other best performing games.
So, the retention is amazing on these games.
There's something really special happening there.
And that's again, without data rewards, without saying you have to come back to check in,
without any kind of forced mechanics to bring players back.
Another core mechanic is the rapid growth of costs and power and rewards in the game.
So this leads to a sense of progress. It's psychologically fun and satisfying.
That's what number was, right? Your number is going up.
We like collecting things. We like advancing. We like improving ourselves.
and these really, really get into it
and do it as sort of a ridiculous level.
Adventure Capitalist actually writes out the words fully
and you end up sort of speaking a new language
as you play this game.
If you learn what the next multiple of a thousand is called
the duo quadra gentilian,
that actually starts to make sense to you
as you play the game.
Other games will just flat out use scientific notation
because the numbers are just getting so outrageous.
But it's also just really fun to have that kind of growth
and it's a sort of a level of growth
you don't usually experience in games.
We actually couldn't even, for Adventure Capitalist,
the game center leaderboards don't support numbers that big.
We had to take a log, a logarithm just to record high scores.
So the core loop of these games is you log in,
you spend all your cash, and then you log out and you come back a few hours later and do it again.
Now, that sounds kind of familiar.
That's what we see in social games and in energy games, right?
You get a certain amount of energy, you spend it all,
and then you leave and the energy comes back,
and then you go do it again.
But the difference is energy games are this forced mechanic that's put on top of the core game.
While with idle games it has this sort of natural energy system
without the need for an energy currency.
And this ends up being a lot more palatable to players,
and especially kind of like the core gamers who
rebel against the social games and the Facebook games.
We find that they really are perfectly
happy with this kind of a setup.
And I think there's a few reasons for that.
It has a real world analog.
It makes sense, right?
Like you're not dealing with lightning bolts that are just
kind of like added onto it.
It's like, oh, I'm out of cash.
I can't buy anything else.
That makes sense to me.
So I'm just going to come back later when I've got more cash.
Additionally, the player takes ownership over this decision.
The game is not saying, you can't do anything else.
It's, you could sit there, you could wait and actively play it
and probably buy something in five minutes or so,
but you as the player say, I could wait,
but my time's more with Wild in this,
I'm not gonna sit here and watch this,
I'm just gonna come back later.
And so it overall is a,
it's just sort of a better experience,
a cleaner experience, and one that comes out
of the natural mechanic rather than something
artificially put on top of it.
It also counterbalances offline play.
So you get big rewards, but those rewards grow linearly.
And so time actually loses value without interaction.
So let's take a look at what that means.
So here is a curve, this is an exponential growth
where it's saying across the bottom
we have like game sessions.
And basically, in this case I'm roughly assuming
game sessions are kind of a once a day thing.
And every day you get about 10x as powerful as the previous day.
And that's totally normal in idle games, if not even a little slow.
It's also impossible to read like this, so we're going to do a log scale instead.
So we can make it a little more linear and understand it.
So now if you're playing once a day every day, under this kind of rough approximation,
then your daily progress is going to be right in line with that.
Now if you were to play on the first day,
and then wait seven days and come back,
On that, you know, a week later, instead of having the, this is a little weird, but
on your second game session, if you're playing every day, you're going to have about a hundred, you know, ten times what you had before.
Here you have seven hundred. You're gone for seven days. You've collected a hundred for seven days.
What this means though, is even though you were gone for seven days, your actual, is that showing up? Yeah, okay.
Your actual, um...
amount of cash only puts you at about where day three would be
for someone who is playing every day. So even though you were gone for a week, it's not
like you're a week ahead of people who are playing actively.
You're actually only partway to where the next session would have been anyway.
And the thing is, this keeps going. If you're gone for a month, so you're gone for 30 days,
yeah, that gets you up to your 3,000, but that's still only around, somewhere around
the day three of someone who's actively playing.
You can go away for a year.
Come back 365 days later and oh look you're sitting somewhere in the fourth session.
So what this means is that you don't have to cap off learning earnings.
That's why I think these forced appointment mechanics,
but beyond the fact that they're not necessary from a retention standpoint,
they're not even necessary from a game standpoint.
The math makes it, sorry I'm a math major so I think this is really cool.
The math makes it so that offline progress as linear progress
becomes irrelevant because your growth is actually exponential.
So you can let the players keep earning lots.
And they're going to feel great.
I come back seven days, I have tons of cash
compared to where I was.
But in terms of the progress of the game,
they're actually not getting that far.
And this gives you the freedom as a developer
to not be forcing them to do things,
to let them kind of experience it on their own,
and to let the math control the progress.
Something else you tend to see in a lot of these games is tons of goals and achievements.
Lots of unlocks. Adventure Capitalist has 500 unlocks right now. They're adding more all the time.
Part of this is providing moments of joy throughout the game. I mean, the core game is you're making your number go up, right?
And at some point that gets kind of boring. But if you're getting little achievements and little bursts of speed throughout,
that helps break it up a little bit.
It also gives you the ability to have moment to moment optimizations.
So you may be deciding in this example, you know, the...
You have one thing that you can get here.
If you get to 2,000 newspapers, you'll get times 15 on your pizza deliveries.
Or if you get to 2,200, you can get times 3 on your car washes.
you're making a decision now like which one should I try to go for which one's
going to be the better optimization and so you actually do have some decisions
that at least temporarily are meaningful they min max a little bit long term yeah
you'll be able to afford it but you're gonna be able to afford things faster if
you play more optimally so it actually gives some strategy to the player rather
than just number go up faster. Prestiging or new kind of new game plus anyone know
where the term new game plus comes from?
chrono trigger. I did not know that until I was researching
this but apparently that was the first one to ever use the term.
Sorry, random trivia. Now you know.
So you get to choose to reset your game to kind of get a
boost the next time through.
So this one's Tap Titans.
And it's not a force.
You can do it whenever you want.
But you kind of get the options.
Like, all right, now I want to do my reset.
I'm going to get some bonus.
I'm going to completely start over.
But you're going to do it with more power.
And you're going to accelerate through the
early part of the game.
And this is really, really central to especially the most
successful idle games.
It provides a strategic decision to the player.
So a lot of the little min-max decisions,
you know, those are nice, they're fun,
and there's some opportunity there,
but when to reset is a really, really important decision.
Do I reset when I'm gonna double my speed,
or do I do it at one and a half times
and try to do that repeatedly at a faster rate
and hope that it stacks on top more than the doubles go?
There are long discussions in forums about this.
There's a group of math majors that I'm working with
at a university that are trying to model this out
and to pick out the best strategies for idle games.
Like it's actually an interesting question
and a really good strategic opportunity.
It's often tied to a separate currency.
So in this previous shot,
you can see like you earn these, sorry,
relics based on your progress.
And you're only earning like five or 10 relics
despite the fact that you have some, you know,
octillion damage per second that you're doing there.
And so this actually lets you transform exponential growth back to linear.
So now you're getting back into an actual gameplay progression.
You're sort of, you know, taking a log of your progress.
And so the players are seeing all these giant numbers,
but you as a game developer get to turn it back into something that's a bit more linear and more controlled.
And this also leads to a new gameplay loop.
You start getting faster and like your core loop of buying all your upgrades and getting
through it then gets, you know, wrapped around or wrapped within this idea of prestiging.
And sometimes you're prestiging like once a day for some of these games.
And that becomes a second, almost core loop as fast as it goes.
And players get into a rhythm and it's really fun.
So let's go back to our exponential growth curve.
We take our log of it.
Now in the last one, we said that your progress was
basically right in line with the power there.
But when you start doing a prestige loop, your costs are
going up that way, but your earnings are going to be a
little bit below that.
So early on, you're going to be earning above the cost, but
then it's going to trail off, and you're going to be unable
to progress.
This is not a hard wall. The game is not saying you have to progress, but it's going to start feeling slower and slower,
and the player is going to be getting a little bit bored, and so they get the option to do a prestige.
Now when you do a prestige, you're multiplying, I think by three in this case, you're going to multiply your earnings.
So, boom. Now you're taking the exact same earnings line, like nothing has changed in the balance, but you've shifted it up.
And what this means is that the early part of the game is going to accelerate.
You're going to fly through that early stuff and you're going to get farther than you did
before but then you're going to start, you know, trailing off again.
You're going to hit a different soft wall and at some point you're going to decide,
okay, it's time to prestige again.
And you can keep doing this and you're going to keep progressing through the content of
the game but you do it in this kind of repeat way.
And it creates this interesting loop that's really fun for players.
It's this ladder climbing idea. Each time you're going a rung higher
even though you're starting over.
And it gives this amazing sense of progress. It's one of the greatest rushes of an idle game.
As many of you know if you got into cookie clicker.
You do your prestige and all of a sudden you get to buy everything.
And it's incredibly fun. It's a really good player experience.
And it's a core part of the game progression.
regular updates, this seems like a weird thing to call a mechanic, I guess it's more of a quality that we've identified
but because, I think in large part, because the games are fairly simple, there's not a lot of assets, it's all just kind of like spreadsheets and balance and UI, UX
you actually can
iterate on it fairly quickly and what we've seen so this is
the swarm simulator release log that's like every day all of
the you know he's putting out a release with you know not just
like a minor fix like you know a fair amount and what we've
actually seen is that I think I can actually say every single
highly successful idle game on congregate has had a rapid
release cycle of like every couple days they'll do
something new.
It's, you know, I don't know that it's necessary,
but it is a very clear observation that we've seen.
The players react well to it.
With math this weird, like trying to get the balance right
is really hard, so being able to iterate on that
is actually kind of important.
It's just something that we've seen over and over again
is a quality that has been a part of success for idle games.
Make it bumpy. So this was kind of interesting. This was a story from Cody Veig, who is the
Adventure Capitalist designer. Originally he did a very smooth progression curve and
it turns out that was really boring. You know what's coming. There's no surprise and delight
associated with it. So you have your cost curve and your earnings curve and it's totally
flat. You know exactly what you're going to do.
And so we ended up intentionally screwing up the curve.
And that made it a lot more interesting.
You make it bumpy.
And you're gonna have areas of rapid acceleration
when things are going really well.
And then you're gonna have kind of slow parts.
And this provides variety.
It keeps it interesting.
You don't know exactly what's gonna come next.
And that's actually fun to discover.
And then when you start prestiging,
the intersection points, you know, also change.
And so again, you're going to have different points where
things are going to be happening.
Things are going to be going really fast and they're fun.
And other parts where they slow down a little bit, and
maybe you ease off, come back a day later, and then you can
get back into it.
It just makes the whole process a lot more interesting.
So we have, we actually see a lot of these elements in other games.
Like you know, many of them are not unique to idle games.
So like in real time social and strategy games,
you do often see progress while gone, though often with hard caps.
So in Hay Day you're seeing your farm is growing,
but only the stuff that you planted.
And if you go away for weeks,
it's no better than going away for however long your longest timer is.
Mafia Wars, kind of like the energy based games, same type setup.
And even Game of War, sorry, there we go.
Game of War,
um,
the, uh, you have all your earnings,
but there's also a max, um, uh, storage that you can have.
So there is still this idea of earning while you're gone,
and that's still fun for players,
but they all cap it out in a way
that I think misses out a little bit on, uh,
an opportunity there that going,
putting some math into the exponential growth,
um, could, could fix.
Though it would be a little bit weird in these two.
Um.
Chinese MMORPGs. So there's a current trend of becoming very heavily auto-play.
Players, especially Chinese players, are really really savvy at MMORPGs.
They want to get through the early part very quickly and get to the endgame where it gets really interesting, the strategy and the min-maxing.
And they can, you know, these games even can include an AFK mode.
So this is a game called Mythborn.
Looks like an action RPG and in large part is, but if you see like it says auto path
at the top.
Like you start playing the game and it just starts running off.
It kills people for you, then it runs back, accepts a quest.
Like it's all doing it automatically for you.
And in large part like this is like an idle game, right?
It's running on its own and you're just kind of watching it and making occasional decisions.
It's about min-maxing stats. It's about collecting equipment and putting the right things together.
And it's really interesting. It's really deep.
But what we see is that Western audiences often don't react well to it.
And I think this is in large part a problem with expectation management.
you see this game that looks like an action RPG
and you're expecting an action RPG
but then you're getting this, you know,
something that functions more like an idle game.
And so even players who love idle games
often don't like MMORPGs that play like idle games.
So, you know, these are interesting games to study
for some of the stuff that they do
when it comes to min-maxing, when it comes to optimization.
But there's this weird thing.
psychological thing where they don't necessarily set the expectations properly and especially western audiences who aren't used to it
can sometimes have a negative reaction to it.
And then launch games.
So I'm sure you've seen these games around where you launch something, you collect some cash and you buy some upgrades and you launch it again.
That sounds kind of familiar right? It's actually a type loop prestige system.
You know you don't actually have choice over when you're going to do your prestige. It's when you land.
But the idea is still the same.
do some, you know, your core loop, you get to the end, you've gained some resources,
you spend them, and then the next time it's like that ladder rung, you're getting farther
each time. And I think that's part of the reason that launch games are so much fun,
it's that same idea of continuing growth, and we just see that in idle games, it's like
stretched out a little bit with a little more choice, but the mechanic is still actually
very similar.
So, these games actually do monetize.
And I'll admit, it surprised me a little bit when
I think Adventure Capitalist was the first one that called me up,
I was like, hey, can we put in-app purchases in the game?
I'm like, yeah, I guess, but I don't know if anyone's going to buy them.
I am not always right, and I was happy to be wrong in that one.
So what can you sell in an idle game?
I mean, really, the game is just making a number go up, right?
How can you monetize that?
Well, you can sell a cash infusion.
Let's just get a burst of cash right away.
It's usually a percentage of whatever your current rate of income is.
That way it's always going to be relevant to you wherever you are.
Or sometimes they just flat out call it a time warp.
So you can say, all right, let's jump ahead 24 hours.
And you'll get whatever cash you would have earned.
All of your cool-downs finish off.
And that's actually kind of compelling for someone who wants to just jump ahead.
Maybe they're really close to something.
They'll say, oh, OK, I'll pay a dollar to get ahead.
I mean, that's a fairly common mechanic that we see in a lot of things.
It's a speed up.
You can also, some of them will sell permanent speed multipliers.
Adventure Capitalist did this where you could buy a times three multiplier that just
did a permanent times three on everything you earned.
Now that's fun and you accelerate faster but also because of the way
the exponential growth works.
This isn't quite as much, I mean it doesn't progress you through the game as fast as you might think.
So it's fun for players and they do go faster but it also doesn't completely break the game which was kind of interesting.
The instant prestige, so usually you reset and start over, right?
But we actually see games that will say, okay, you can get all of your currency, but you
can stay where you are.
And that's very compelling for players who, especially on games that have longer prestige
loops, being able to say, okay, I'm going to collect everything and keep going.
That actually can be really, really effective.
Protection against negative events, so you know, in Make It Rain, it's all the bribe
money that can keep the FBI off your back.
In Tap Titans, you can actually lose heroes for periods of time, but you can also buy
a shield to protect them.
So that's out there.
Gotcha system. We'll talk about this one a little bit.
Clicker Heroes actually has a gotcha system in it.
For those who aren't familiar with it,
this is like random draws.
Like a collectible card game kind of thing.
And even like event currencies.
So in Adventure Capitalist, they ran a holiday event
where you were collecting candy canes,
you could open presents, and you could actually buy things
that would increase your candy cane production,
that would get you more presents,
that would earn these unique things
that you could only get during the event.
Very similar to something like The Simpsons Tapped Out
or Family Guy Quest for Stuff,
where they have event currencies and specific things there.
You can still apply that to an idle game,
and they have done that.
You do see banners and interstitial ads.
So Bitcoin Billionaire did this really clever thing.
I don't know how readable that is but
you know it says basically
we're going to give you a bonus if you let us show you a banner ad.
And so you say oh cool.
And you actually ask them.
It's like yes please show me a banner ad.
And a banner ad pops up and then you play and earn some more cash.
So the player, it's I think the only opt-in banner ad I've seen before.
You see a lot of like opt-in video ads.
When you do an opt-in ad, like an actual opt-in ad, you'll often get a short burst of cash,
some small bit of premium currency, a brief powerful boost,
a relief of a negative status, or even like a longer term but lower boost.
A relief of a negative status, so another example from Bitcoin Billionaire.
you know, someone divided by zero, you're going to lose a
quarter of all of your bytes. So this actually feels a lot like
the FBI thing from Make It Rain, but they allow you to
just watch an ad to get around it. So it's still that
negative experience, but it's not nearly as punishing for the
player. It's really just saying, hey, you had a bad
luck, now you have to watch 15 seconds of Kate Upton.
So it works out, it's a little more palatable.
So we're going to do a couple of case studies real quick
of games that are on Kongregate that the developers very kindly said that we
could share some numbers for. I'm only sharing per user numbers so no total
revenue or anything like that but at least some insight as to how games are
performing.
So, Idling to Rule the Gods. This is one guy who created this game.
It's not a high production game, but it definitely has some really interesting systems.
Branched out with some new mechanics. It was at a time that we were seeing a lot of direct clones of Cookie Clicker and Adventure Capitalist.
And this did some different things that players reacted well to.
like any of them, very rapid iteration, adding tons of new stuff
made a lot of UI changes. So this is kind of the old UI.
The new one is not drastically different, but there are a lot of UI or UX changes
where there were more options, there were easier things for players to do.
Players would ask for features and he would just do it.
And the players loved that. They loved that it felt like it was growing and improving all the time.
He probably should get an art budget, but that's okay. Sorry, that was mean.
There are a lot of really complicated interactions in this game.
Deep, dense systems that players are digging into.
And that's really, really fun for them.
Crazy math that calculates your
attack as your battle, plus your creating strength over 2,
plus physical over 4, divided by 943.
Which he surfaces to the players so they can start optimizing that, right?
And that kind of depth is always going to be fun for players who want to try to min-max.
The monetization in the game is heavily focused on god power.
It's basically their premium currency.
And you can either keep the god power and use it to provide
multipliers to different areas of the game
or you can spend it and get permanent multipliers.
But the permanent boosts tend to be what players react really well to
in this game in particular.
They do have some temporary boosts where you can do
like a 90 minute boost or even like a boost until you prestige again.
And those sell decently, but it's only about 12% of the revenue.
So it's really the permanent boost or the investment side
that we see selling best for this particular game.
Just to share a couple of charts, this is the lifetime percent buyers on Kongregate.
The first part was some testing data, so please ignore the early part of that.
But, ends up somewhere around 1.3% buyer rate.
So as perspective, usually we see games kind of like,
you're doing okay if you're about 0.5%.
Good games are usually doing 1-2% purchase rates.
A few games will do 3% or higher.
So, it's actually got a pretty good, if not a bit above average, purchase rate on the game.
And the lifetime average revenue per paying user,
so this is lifetime, not monthly or daily
or anything like that,
but the average per paying user is sitting around $25.
And that's actually quite good,
especially for a single-player game.
A lot of our single-player games will get, you know,
$5 or $10 for, you know, a premium version
or, you know, somewhere in that range.
So to get players spending $25 on average
for those who decide to spend is actually quite good.
And overall leads to a pretty decent LTV for the game.
Clicker heroes.
So this one, a couple things that it does really interesting. It does a great job of spreading
value across heroes. So a lot of times all of your old investments, your older
things you get become irrelevant very quickly. This one actually makes them
relevant much later in the game. It keeps it interesting, keeps you kind of
like on your toes in terms of what you're going to focus on.
The use of RPG-like cooldowns, as I said before, it provides these kind of like quick action gameplay and some strategy.
You can see that this list of, these are the cooldowns right here.
And so you have the, sorry I can't quite read it here, but this is the one that I think gives you more damage for like 30 seconds or something and then it has a cooldown for a few hours.
And they can monetize this cool down.
Say quick, you can get your cool downs back immediately.
But it also is just fun.
Like you log in and all of your stuff's cooled down.
And then you decide you're going to go up to the next boss
and you fire them off in the right order.
You want the doubler to go right before the click boost that
goes then before the higher counter order.
I don't know if I'm doing the order right.
But there's actually a little bit of strategy
behind it, which is fun for people who appeals to RPG
players.
Their prestige system involves a currency that has a trade-off between your DPS bonus and your summoning of these ancients.
So you get these hero souls that increase your DPS, but you can also spend those to get these cool bonuses.
And so it becomes this idea, not just when do I prestige, but how do I spend my prestige points, and if so, how do I do that?
more interesting questions for the player.
So again, the core loop is mostly a self-playing game,
but once you start making these bigger decisions,
it's actually very interesting decisions
for the player to engage in.
In terms of monetization,
they have the cash infusion and the instant prestige
that are pretty standard in idle games,
which are those first two that you see here.
Plus one ascension, you can get the hero souls right away.
But they also have this plus three random gilded heroes.
and this is one of the innovations they really brought in.
This is a very simple but effective gotcha system.
These are all of the heroes you can earn in the game,
and you can draw what's called a guilded hero,
which makes that hero do plus 50% damage permanently.
And you can guild multiple times,
so plus 100%, plus 150%.
This is fun from a collection standpoint. You ideally would want all of your heroes gilded.
And then, because you can buy multiple times, you can actually get it so that you want to still keep making purchases and getting these random gildings so that you can increase your power overall.
And because they did a good job of balancing the characters to be relevant throughout,
even if you get some of the lower end ones, those are going to be relevant to you at times as well. So this was really cool.
It allows for multiple purchases.
So looking at their numbers, their lifetime percent buyer ended up a good bit better than even idling through Rule of the Gods
at almost 3%. That's a very strong percent buyer rate on Kongregate.
And I think in large part due to the Gacha system, they actually ended up in a similar $25 ARPAPU.
So doing really well, especially with the extra buyer percentage in terms of LTVs on the site.
Alright, last case study, we're getting through it.
Adventure Capitalist.
So this really appealed to both browser and mobile audiences.
We were able to take it to mobile,
got some great features from Apple and Google,
which was awesome.
It has a really heavy use of the theme,
the tone, and the humor in the game.
So these are some of the managers you can get.
You can see like, you know,
WW Heisenberg is the car wash manager.
Forrest Trump runs the shrimp business.
And it's a Canadian game, so you have this Jim Thornton joke in here too.
For anyone that's a Tim Horton fan.
So that humor really, really resonates with players.
They like seeing what are the names of the managers coming
up, what are the new upgrades coming.
And that turned out really, really nice for just some word
of mouth and some retention, but just in general keeping
the style of the game going.
One thing that I think we did really well with it was have a
really effective ad implementation.
You, the player, we don't pop this up automatically.
The player will have a little button they can press.
And this will pop up and say,
hey, you're looking for a boost, you can get
four hours times two all of your
income if you watch this ad.
And you can only watch five of these per day.
And so it fits the theme well.
Like it's very tongue in cheek.
Like, hey, you watch this for us,
and we'll do something for you.
We really kind of play up the story behind it.
It provides high value to the player.
You get to double your income for four hours.
It's relatively scarce.
So you're not watching ads constantly.
And so we may be leaving some impressions on the table,
but the players are actively making sure
that they can get in and watch as many of those ads
as possible to hit their daily quota.
Which I also think helps, you know, it's only been out for a couple of weeks so we don't know exactly, but I think it's going to help not get player fatigue around the ads to sort of limit it a little bit.
It does have some bugs and people will complain to us that they can't watch ads and I feel like there's no better way to know that we did the ads well than to have people say, hey, I can't watch your ads, fix it.
Like, okay, cool, we'll work on that, but that's awesome.
This is our store.
And it has kind of the normal, the angel claim is the instant prestige.
You can buy the time 3 multiplier and they have a time warp.
The time 3 multiplier is extremely compelling.
You spend I think $2 and you get this permanent time 3 multiplier.
And that converts extremely well.
I'll show you the conversion rates in just a second.
but it is one of the highest buyer percentages on all of
congregate.com. You also can unlock bulk multipliers over
time. So there you see the times 3 is the highest one you can
get. Well, we actually, as you buy the times 3, you unlock
another one.
and it actually keeps going. So we have times 12, times 27, times
I forget what that one was, and then 501 is the highest one. So
players who are, especially the bigger spenders, are kind of curious like how high does this go?
And we'll have people who will go up and just kind of find out how big it goes.
And then they get the big multiplier and have fun with that as well.
So I said they had a good buyer rate.
Remember, Clicker Heroes was doing well at almost 3%.
They're sitting at almost 8%.
It's fallen off a little bit as we got some wider promotion
and played around a little bit with pricing.
But 6%, 7% is phenomenal in terms of the congregate
standards.
So that times three buyer rate, I think,
is an initial purchase is a really big part of that.
At the Lifetime ARPA Pooh, because it has such a high buyer percentage and a lot of people are just buying that x3, you do see the ARPA Pooh is a bit lower.
But it has been heading up as we've been doing a lot of optimization, providing some deeper spend opportunities, adding some opportunity for to engage in the holiday events.
There was this flat period right here and there were actually no updates were added to the game. And people just stopped spending.
as you would expect. So, you know, just like any other game, live servicing is very important to a successful idle game.
And you will see revenue flatten out if you're not supporting it.
In this case, they were actually working on the mobile version of it, but the web stats, you know, faltered until we started paying attention to web again.
What platform is that?
This is, this is, all of these charts are for congregate.com.
We were happy to see that the mobile retention has held up well so far.
Again, we've only been out for two weeks, so I only have so much data, but
D1 retention sitting somewhere around 55-60%.
So, you know, looks like the theory that good retention,
you know, that maintained on mobile.
Our D7, again, we don't have a lot of data yet, but
that's sitting somewhere around 35%,
which we are extremely happy with.
So, yeah, they retain well on web and retain well on mobile.
Mobile ARPUPU also held up.
So this is a cohort chart of congregate data.
And the reason I broke out the cohorts is because we made
some monetization changes.
And so you'll see the ARPUPU is actually pretty low for
people who joined a while ago.
But in the last few months, the ARPUPUs have been sitting
somewhere around $12 to $15.
On iOS we're looking at around $18 ARPAPOO right now.
On Android we're sitting somewhere around $13.
So we're seeing pretty consistent spending patterns across each of the platforms.
The buyer percentages are different because of a variety of things around friction
and having credit card access and that kind of thing.
But in terms of depth of spend for those who decide to spend,
it actually is relatively consistent across each platform.
Alright, and last couple. So, spender categories.
This will, you'll recognize this as a type of chart that Congregate often does.
So we wanted to break out what spenders look like for these games.
And so what this chart is, is that readable up there?
somewhat. So this is by how much they've spent. So this
orange section here is people who have spent less than $10 on
the game. And it kind of goes around $50 to $100 all the way
up to these tiny little slivers of $100 to $500 and $500 and
more on the game.
And so we have this chart for Clicker Heroes and Idling to Rule the Gods.
Adventure Capitalists, remember, had a really good conversion rate.
But a lot of those conversions were at like a single purchase.
And so that's why you see that really, really big percentage of people only spending under $10.
While Clicker Heroes and Idling to Rule the Gods, I had to check a couple of times.
I thought it was the same chart, but they actually are slightly different.
remarkably similar numbers.
But it's interesting, it's important to look,
the vast majority are the under 10 to 50,
with just these tiny little slivers
of the 50 to 500 group in all of them, right?
Now, each of these games has multiple $1,000 plus spenders.
So, just like any other game, you do have big spenders.
If you want to find out more about big spenders,
Carate's CEO, Emily Greer, is giving a talk about them tomorrow.
So I'm not going to talk about them here,
but that's a good talk and I'll just plug her.
But yeah, so we do see big spenders even in these idle games.
But if we were to take this, so this is distribution by how many players are spent in those groups.
If we now go and instead look at how the revenue distribution looks.
I'll go ahead and pop all three of them up there.
So the small groups are contributing a relatively small percentage of the actual revenue.
Sorry, this is hard for me to see down here.
You end up seeing that the groups of the $50, $150,
and $500, sorry, $100 to $500 and $500 plus
are actually contributing rather large percentages
and actually most of the revenue
outside of the venture capitalists to these games.
So just like any of the other successful games that we see,
pretty much every successful game we see
through in-app purchases,
especially outside of the casual,
even in casual, big spenders drive a lot,
if not most, of the revenue.
these games, they monetize, you have to live service them,
the retention is very similar.
They ultimately are just like any other successful game,
or game as a service,
in terms of really all of the numbers that we see.
And that, you know, it's not really just an idle game.
They are games that are compelling and fun
and work just like every other game.
So just a couple of kind of like wrap ups.
Like, you know, what's next?
Make some kind of random predictions.
You know, I think the classic kind of spreadsheet
like idle game is probably going to start to lose favor.
Players have seen a lot of them.
We're starting to see some more sophisticated
visualization and presentation.
So, you know, the kind of like easy, you know,
jump in and create a quick idle game
is probably starting to run out
as we're seeing better production values
and people will take more note of the genre.
I think we'll be seeing idle spin-offs of games and brands.
Clicker Heroes, for example, was a spin-off of Cloudstone by PlaySaurus.
There's an Adventure Quest Dragons spin-off that's actually...
I don't know exactly what the relationship was, but when you load it up it says, like, you know,
partnered with Clicker Heroes. So...
I'm sorry, partnered with Cookie Clicker.
So somehow they worked together to do this spin-off game.
And I imagine we'll see kind of more of those occurring.
I think idle is going to become sort of a genre modifier like RPG. You've got your action RPG, your strategy RPG, your tactics RPG.
Well, you could have idle tactics, action idle RPG, idle match three. In fact, idle match three has been done.
So this was, yeah, Puzzle Fuzz.
which was a uh... andre pelerano is one of our internal developers and uh...
he uh... created an idle match three games so this little bar at the top here
fills up on its own and will match that color and you can interact you can play
faster than it but it will run on its own if you go away it'll keep matching
for you
and you're basically charging up these little characters that are going over
and trying to break their friends free from that uh... amber
gel thingy
uh... but you can just apply a lot of these idle game ideas to other
genres just like uh... rpg
uh... ideas
And I think, you know, so, and where that kind of goes from there is that idle design philosophies are going to start getting integrated into the metagames of standard, of other types of genres.
You know, not all of this will work. Exponential growth is going to be weird in some games.
But I think you gain a lot.
from these types of energy system approaches,
these types of positive progress and feedback,
and trying to find ways to bring that into other genres,
I think is a good bit of where the future is.
And that's, I certainly would encourage everyone
to try making an L game if you want,
it's fun, it's relatively quick.
But trying to figure out how to bring some of this
into other genres, I think is what I'd really like
to see some people do, and we haven't really seen yet.
So that's my talk.
Here's some contact information.
You can check out our developer website.
If you have browser game questions
or mobile game questions, those are your best contacts.
And then my email address.
Cool.
So I guess we can open up for questions.
We have time for that.
Thank you.
Please come up to the mics if you'd like to ask.
Also, just a quick shout out,
if you enjoyed the talk, please give me a good rating.
If you didn't, go ahead and fill it out
because I'd like to at least learn from it,
but doing these evaluations is really helpful.
It helps us learn, and also, if you enjoyed the talk,
please fill it out because then I can give more talks later.
So, thank you so much for coming,
everyone who's heading out, and let's take some questions.
Hi, Matthew Lawrence, Rovio.
Hello.
A quick question on the prestiging mechanic.
So it's actually really vital for player progression in the long run, but it's actually
kind of an advanced level mechanism, and it always requires player interaction to do it.
I've never seen one where it actually leads the player to do it, like part of a tutorial,
and I was wondering if you had any thoughts on how to kind of really encourage players
to get that in the Fatui.
I don't know that I would get into the Fatui.
Like you said, it's more of a later mechanic.
So you do want to tutorialize it.
But it's something that is a complexity level
that you don't necessarily need to introduce right away.
The games are often compelling and fun on their own in the core loop.
And so players are sort of discovering and getting into that.
and then when it becomes appropriate.
So like in Adventure Capitalist,
once you get to 50 angels, you would double your amount.
And so at that point, we pop up a little thing and said,
hey, now would be a good time to check out the prestige system
and kind of introduce them to that.
So I think the best way to do it is to contextualize it
to when it's appropriate to the player.
Don't introduce it too early
because they're not even going to understand it
and they're already likely having fun.
So I think it's mostly about sort of targeting
the tutorial at the right time.
Cool, thank you.
Hello.
Hey, so you spoke a little about how many people are buying these games and how many
people are developing for these games.
What's the ratio, like the saturation, in this genre and where do you see it going in
the future?
I'm sorry, I was asked to repeat the question.
So the question was, you know, what is the saturation of the genre?
Where is it going to the future?
It is starting to get somewhat saturated, especially with kind of like
fast follows and clones.
Those don't tend to have as much success.
The most recent success for us has been Swarm Simulator
and that's one that really branched out and did something
very different in its approach and in the
economics of the game.
So, I think there is still opportunity for, I mean that was two weeks ago.
So obviously there is still, you know, new ideas that are coming out.
There is still iteration that is happening and evolution of the mechanics.
You know, it is something that is gaining attention.
We've had multiple games in the idle genre are getting featured by the big platforms
which means a lot more people are going to be paying attention to it.
It's a great experimentation and kind of breeding ground
for ideas.
And so we'll still see a lot, I think, coming out on browser.
It's a little harder to get big on the web
because you have, or on mobile, because you have to go
through the app stores.
But I think there's still opportunity
for the main idle genre.
And then there's sort of the second layer
of taking some of those approaches
and wrapping them around, like the idle RPG or the idle match
three, where you're kind of providing a little more
gameplay and then trying to balance that
with some idle elements.
All right, thanks.
Thank you.
Over here.
You mentioned that these games require a lot of updating
in order to stay fresh.
Is that updating primarily on the late game or earlier game,
or is it spread throughout the time or the levels
that the player will be moving through?
Yeah, great question.
So the question was, there are lots of updates in these games,
but where are those focused?
What do those updates look like?
So a fair number of them are end game.
And it depends a little bit on how long the game is
when you first launch it.
But a lot of times, players will get through it relatively
quickly, and you do want to provide content at the end
for those that have gotten there.
A lot of the updates are UI and UX.
You don't necessarily understand how players are going to interact with the game, especially
the ones that get really hardcore about it.
They'll start requesting things like, allow me to buy up to 100 of something and automatically
determine what the right one is and then show me my cash per second here.
There's a lot of requests about that.
So a lot of them are usability things that are helpful throughout the entire process.
The early game often doesn't change much outside of maybe some balancing.
Sometimes you find that, you know, when you did the bumpy,
something was a bit too low, and so you may shift that up a little bit.
But in general, you're going to be providing either something on the end
or something that's a little parallel.
With AntiIdle, the one that's been going for like six years,
he's actually just like adding new mechanics.
So rather than just doing on the end, he'll add like another way to,
you know, now there's a little fighting game in it,
now there's a little collectible card game in it.
He's kind of crazy. I don't know that's the best way to put it.
way to go it but and he's been doing it for six years so we had to you know have a
little bit of variety but yeah it's it's really just sort of the the games it's
it's one that I think minimum viable product is very very early on and so a
lot of the iteration is just sort of like public beta testing and something
that's very easy to quickly iterate on and so that's I think a little bit of
what we're seeing with it. Cool thanks. Thank you.
Yes?
Hi, you mentioned that Congregate has games from Flash
and HTML5 and Unity.
Is there any particular type that
tends to be more successful or just common for idle games?
Are they all Flash or some HTML5?
So yeah, the question was whether there's a particular
technology that's better for idle games.
I think I can almost firmly say no.
Adventure Capitalist is Unity.
Clicker Heroes is Flash.
I think Idling to Rule the Gods is Flash.
Swarm Simulator, I believe, is HTML5.
So no, we actually don't see any real requirement there for
one tech or another.
Thanks.
You're welcome.
Any other questions?
All right, well thank you so much.
Again, please fill out your evaluations
and thanks for coming out.