I position myself like this, my leg forward, and...
There you go.
And you can do it like this.
Yeah, not bad, not bad.
Oh, hi GDC!
We're just working on our last balancing patch.
But you're here to hear a little bit more about our talk on For Honor,
learning from a successful launch to a challenging life period.
We'll go through many different parts and very different learnings, like for the life
period, in example, why we started early, why we started one year and a half before,
what we learned to do from doing different type of life periods with different objectives
and different content, and as well...
But we will move forward to the launch, the storm of launch, and what it means to be a game as a service.
What it means in terms of reorganizing your production floor and your production process.
But also in terms of communication, moving to communicating with fans to actual customers.
And the last part, how we moved forward.
So we'll share with you our retention recipe
to create a player routine, but as well bring
some surprises to them.
And on the other side, of course,
how we kept being sustainable so that we could
produce all of that content.
We'll share with you our exact model regarding that.
So see you there.
See you there.