Thank you all so much for coming out.
We're going to spend a little bit of time together today
talking about how we play with magic
and make interactive worlds at Walt Disney Imagineering.
My name is Sarah Thatcher.
This is Brent Strong.
Hello.
And.
When I'm at Imagineering, I have worked in R&D.
So I've done a lot of work in R&D thinking about,
what are the new experiences that we really want to do,
but we don't have the technology for?
How can we build that technology to create that experience?
And equally, how do we, there's some brand new cool things
out there.
What do we do with these?
How do we turn this technology into an experience?
Because ultimately, at Imagineering,
we're an entertainment company.
So, and lately, I've been taking all of that work
and translating it into a new project
as part of the Star Wars portfolio,
the Star Wars Immersive Multi-Day Resort Experience
that is, thank you, that's announced for Florida.
So, that's a little bit about what I do
as a creative director at Walt Disney Imagineering.
And hi there, I'm Brent Strong.
I'm also a creative director at Walt Disney Imagineering.
I've been at WDI for about 13 years now
and spent most of that time working
on new interactive experiences that bring our guests closer
to the magic.
My current project, I'm working on a new project
down at Disney California Adventure.
It's an immersive interactive attraction
that lets guests feel what it's like
to have super heroic powers.
And we're very excited to bring people
into that world as well.
So quick show of hands, how many of you guys
have been to one of our parks around the world?
All right, good.
Most of you will know the things that we're
talking about then today.
As that video outlined, we do have 12 theme parks
around the world.
We have four cruise ships, soon to be seven.
We also have the Alani Resort and a whole host of adventures
by Disney around the world.
Most people think of theme parks when
they think of Imagineering.
But what most people don't realize
is that at Imagineering, we're responsible for every aspect
of the guest experience from restaurants, to shopping,
to rides, shows, entertainment, spectaculars, you name it.
But before we talk about all of that, I want to go back in time a little bit.
I want to talk a little bit about how this all began back in 1952 before we had any theme
parks.
In fact, before the concept of a theme park really existed, sort of where that came from.
And Walt himself was a filmmaker, had wonderful programs on television.
When he set out to figure out what is this idea of a theme park, what is this idea of
a location-based experience, what he did is he gathered movie makers around.
him, some of his most trusted animators, some of his most trusted storytellers, and asked
a very important question.
It was, whose tie is the skinniest?
You'd think so from the picture.
It's a really good skinny tie competition.
But actually it was, how can we put our guests in the movies?
How can we take the stories that they've seen on screen and bring that to life in three
dimensions?
And back then, they were inventing this from scratch.
Since then, we have 65 plus years of experience doing this.
And we've learned a couple things along the way.
And today, we're going to talk about a few
of these best practices, a few of these tips
that we've discovered along the way.
And spoiler alert, a lot of these things
that we deal with in theme parks are things
that you guys have tackled in game design and game
production as well.
It turns out that these missions are very similar.
And today we're going to highlight some of those similarities as well as some of the things that are fundamentally different when you take things off the screen and bring them into three dimensions.
So by way of example, sort of talking about how different these mediums can be,
we're going to go all the way back to the beginning as Walt and those original Imagineers
were coming up with the original Disneyland.
They turned for inspiration to one of the original movies,
one of the original animated films, Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs,
and they turned that into an attraction.
Now in this attraction, they wanted to really immerse you in the film.
They wanted to bring you into the movie.
And so they created an experience where you visited
some of the most iconic locations from the film.
You went to the Dwarves' Diamond Mine,
you went to the spooky dungeons, you went to the forest.
You saw some of the most iconic characters.
You met the dwarves, the woodland critters,
the evil queen.
And yet when people went on this, they were perplexed.
You saw a lot of things from that film
and went through all those iconic scenes,
but you never saw Snow White.
There was no Snow White in Snow White and Her Adventures.
It said right on the marquee, it said her name above the door,
and then you go on, you see all these things,
but you don't see her.
So.
Where is she?
Why wasn't she there?
Well, our filmmakers said, when they were gathered
around that table thinking about how do we
put guests in the movie, they said, OK.
This is an amazing opportunity to give our guests
that first-person experience.
So instead of, as you're going through,
instead of seeing Snow White, you're going to be Snow White.
The witch is going to offer you the apple.
And it turned out that that was a little confusing.
Cool idea, confusing execution.
So part of the confusion was a first-person experience
is just a small part of being in the movie.
It turns out that
Snow White's experience as you're watching her
is a lot different than your experience
of being in this early dark ride.
So you are, for one thing, you are literally on rails.
Snow White is, you're watching her make choices.
She's deciding whether or not to go investigate
this little sleepy cottage.
Why is it so small?
Who could live there?
She's deciding whether or not to take the apple.
You are on rails.
Going through scene by scene, you're
not making any of those choices.
So your fundamental experience is
different than that of Snow White.
So when you're watching something on TV,
say like a car commercial, that car commercial
is getting you to imagine what it's like to be
behind the wheel of the car.
That's their whole goal is to.
within that frame of that proscenium of that TV
to get you to imagine yourself immersed in that car.
And as a simple message for a car commercial, great.
But when you start to add.
When you start to add emotions, when you start to add that narrative complexity, we don't
get to transition directly to the experience of being that first-person perspective.
Because what's really happening is we're ingesting all of that, what's going on on the screen,
and we are projecting ourselves into that world.
We're imagining.
we're imagining what is not just what is Snow White doing,
but what is she thinking?
What is she feeling?
What would it feel like if I were there?
We're empathizing with that world,
and we're creating it inside of our heads.
So to put us in the world, it doesn't
mean making us Snow White.
It means being, it's not just the interpretation of you
in the movie, it's.
your experience, it's your empathy of how we get you in the movie, we make that experience
authentic from what you view it from the inside out.
So when we start talking about building an authentic experience
from the inside out, one of the first things, right
at the center of that diagram, is giving our guests a role.
Making sure that we are very clear about the role
that we're giving you.
In that original attraction, we never
told you that you were going to be Snow White.
And so of course, you expected to see her.
You did not know who you were.
And by the way, being a camera is not necessarily a role.
That doesn't really feel like you're a part of that world.
Moreover, it's important that we give you a role that fits.
It can be really difficult to empathize with a character
whose story you already know.
Snow White has already made her decisions.
Her story has already unfolded.
We know how it plays out.
Mine is just beginning.
So you don't necessarily want to be in the role of a main
character, and you don't necessarily want to hand
somebody a back story that they don't know, relationships
with characters that they can't identify with, goals
that don't resonate with them.
You need to meet guests where they are and give
them a role that fits.
So let's look at an example from opening day Disneyland
that worked out a little bit better,
which is the Jungle Cruise.
Now, in the Jungle Cruise, you have a clear role.
In fact, it's right there on the marquee.
You are a river tourist.
You are here to experience the wonders of the jungle.
You go on a wonderful adventure hosted by a skipper.
That skipper is interacting with you as a tourist.
You are playing that role quite authentically.
Another example here, classic attraction,
is the Haunted Mansion.
Now, here you are a guest of the ghosts.
How do we know that?
Welcome, foolish mortals, to the Haunted Mansion.
I am your host, your ghost host.
Well, we know because the ghosts tell us.
The ghost host himself welcomes us as foolish mortals
into the haunted mansion.
We are invited guests.
And we kept building on that.
We could become passengers on a spaceship in Star Tours,
where we could blast off to a world far, far away.
And again, how do we know that we're passengers on a spaceship?
the entire queue is set up as an airport, right?
It's set up as a travel departure port
where we're going through baggage screening and security.
We're seeing our ship prepped for launch.
There's even a captain who addresses us and brings us
into that world.
So in all three of these examples,
we are going to incredibly aspirational places.
We're meeting aspirational characters.
But it feels like we could go one step farther.
Yeah.
So.
We're going to these aspirational places,
but what if the role that we could play
was as aspirational as the place that we're going?
So in taking this on, we looked at our
Guardians of the Galaxy Mission Breakout attraction in Disney California Adventure.
This is, you are, you start out as a visitor to the collector's collection. I know you're saying,
we just talked about active, we just said how can you make that role more active,
and we're saying you're a visitor. So very quickly as you're going through.
that attraction.
Right there in the queue, you're told
you're no longer a visitor to the collector's collection.
You are an accomplice.
The Guardians of the Galaxy have been
collected by the collector, and they're being held,
and we need to break them out.
And in fact, we need you to break them out.
So Rocket Raccoon, as the brains of the operation,
has figured out that he
He knows how to do this, except he's a raccoon.
It's a recurring problem for him.
So he recruits you to use your human hands
to be able to scan your hands
and defeat the security measures.
So you are a necessary part of getting this to happen.
So you raise your hand, security measure is defeated,
and we actually get to break them out.
So in all of this, giving you a role that is,
in order to play a meaningful role,
I need to know who I am, understand my role,
make it clear.
It's great if it can be an aspirational one,
something that I get to,
and maybe even something that I get to do.
So we have all of that.
Where am I going?
Well, so as we create our worlds, as we bring the worlds of the film to life, now that you
have a role, we want you to inhabit a living world.
When you see Snow White in that frame, for example, she is able to not walk through a
static world.
Static worlds are creepy worlds.
Even the haunted mansion, which is full of dead people, moves.
In horror movies, when things are static, that's how you know that things are about
to get really, really scary.
And so when we bring these worlds to life, we want to create living worlds, breathing
worlds, worlds that move.
And obviously, Walt and those original Imagineers with a background in animation,
were passionate about that.
And so Walt at the time was very intrigued
by these little mechanical birds.
He had found a couple of these
and actually started a small collection.
And these birds, these little mechanical birds,
held the illusion of life,
that same concept that they had in their film animation.
They were seeing play out in 3D space.
And this became a trend in imagining.
This became a cornerstone for us,
this idea of audio animatronics.
And using that illusion of life in three dimensions
to bring our stories to life in new ways.
And this is just a couple brief clips
of some of the highlights.
That one right there, Lincoln standing up,
that was sort of a seminal moment in audio animatronics.
Up until that moment, the animatronics
were very stiff, very stationary.
Everyone thought that Abe was just
going to be sitting there in that chair, all nice
and peaceful.
And then he goes and he stands up.
He becomes more lifelike than anyone had expected him to be.
And we continue to push the envelope here, right?
This is really key to bringing our worlds to life.
This is the shaman figure from Pandora,
the world of Avatar at Disney's Animal Kingdom.
Now this animatronic is incredibly sophisticated.
It contains over 140 functions in the head alone.
to bring this character to life.
And, you know, really the goal here is to take that same level of fidelity
that you see in the movies, right, where special effects animators
are able to bring these characters to life with every tool at their disposal.
We want to give that same tool to our animators in three dimensions.
But most of the things we've been talking about here,
we are an audience to, right?
These animatronics are putting on a show,
whether that's the Tiki Room, whether that's Mr. Lincoln,
even the shaman as you go floating by.
These are things where we become silent observers for that.
That's not Snow White's experience at all.
She's in a world where as she moves through it,
that world reacts to her presence.
That's how we know that she's in that world.
And so to do that, we started asking the question,
can we make that illusion of life responsive?
Can we make that world respond to what you do?
So going back to the collector's collection,
as you're going to Guardians of the Galaxy mission breakout,
you go through, you get to see a little bit of the collection.
And in that collection, there are
some creatures from around the galaxy,
including these little Vilew.
And these guys.
actually react to our guests.
So they're packed with a bunch of sensors.
And as guests are going by, they're looking for big gestures.
They're looking for your gestures.
They're looking for their sounds.
And just like a creature is taking in information
from the world and then reacting to it, they do that.
And they have a personality.
So the idea that, well,
Somebody who's making big motions,
that's a little scary.
But another Vailou who's a little more brave
is gonna lean in and just be really curious.
So each of them have their own personality
and react to you.
And what's really amazing about that happening
is that that role that we gave you earlier
as first as a visitor and then as an accomplice,
it makes you real in the world.
That if the world changes because of things that you do,
that world becomes more real and you become more real within that world.
So when you think about it, if you remove all of the movement from a world,
that's actually how horror movies start.
That's how you know something's wrong.
It feels dead. It feels creepy.
Even the ghosts in the Haunted Mansion move.
the feeling of a static world, it feels dead.
So how do we make it move?
How do we make, and making that responsiveness
actually validates the existence of that person
in the role that they're playing.
So as we bring the environment to life,
we're making that role that you're playing
even more deep and meaningful inside of that world.
So we're playing a meaningful role.
The world is responding to us.
Now we're actually not feeling like an extra.
We're beginning to feel like a protagonist in this story.
And what do protagonists do?
Well, they take action that moves the story forward.
And so one of the really important things
here is to look for a way that our guests can actually
propel the narrative, that their action can
be the impetus for the story continuing.
Now, this is something, again, we're here at GDC.
You guys know all about the importance of players or guests
taking action, right?
Action is the foundation of play.
It's the foundation of challenge.
It's the foundation of so many of these things.
But it turns out that when you go and try and take play,
which people already do in their living
rooms with their families, and bring it into the real world,
you encounter some challenges.
And so for example, when I'm at home with my wife,
my six-year-old, we're playing a board game,
I will do ridiculous things that I would not
do in the supermarket.
When I am playing online with my friends,
I will put my avatar into an outfit
that I would not feel comfortable wearing here at GDC.
There are things that you do that
are ridiculous among friends and in the privacy of your home
that you would not do in a public space.
And so really, the question here is,
how do we encourage guests to play in public the same way
that they would play at home?
Or to put it differently, how do we get a normal teenager to wear a silly hat?
How do we go about crossing that divide?
And it turns out that the answer is something that's familiar to most of you guys in the game design industry,
which is you make a magic circle.
Now, this term was popularized in game design, and essentially, you know, it's that concept
of leaving the real world behind, right, setting aside the rules of everyday life and reality,
and substituting them with the reality of a game, right, with a new context of the game.
Now, the Imagineers back in 1952, you know, 1955 when the park opened.
wouldn't have been familiar with the term magic circle,
and yet they built a literal magic circle around the park.
At Disneyland, we actually have a train
that encircles the entire park that's elevated
so you cannot see the real world from inside of the park.
We call it the berm.
And actually, at the entrance to this park,
as you cross underneath that train track,
there's a plaque that explicitly states,
here you leave the real world behind
and enter a world of fantasy.
And so that's actually the trick.
It turns out that we're not asking you to play
in the real world.
We're giving you an alibi to play in a fantasy world.
We're creating a fantasy world
that happens to exist in real space.
And when you do that, it gives you permission to play.
It gives you permission to act.
It gives you permission to experiment and to role play
in a way that you may not do out in public spaces,
and yet you will do here at Disneyland.
And we see this all the time.
And we've taken advantage of this
by creating a lot of experiences that
allow you to take a deeper part in the story
and really move the story forward.
So one example of this is Agent P's World Showcase Adventure
that is out in Epcot in Florida.
Now, this was actually designed.
He might be here in the audience.
Is Jonathan Ackley out there right now?
If he's raising his hand, I can't tell.
But one of our Imagineers here at the conference
actually designed these games, had
been creating adventure games for home platforms
for a long time, and actually came to Imagineering
and created a series of adventure games
that play out in physical space.
And these allow you to explore the environment,
just like you would in a traditional adventure game.
But instead of pointing and clicking,
you're actually physically moving through the space.
Now, in order to understand this video,
you have to go back to a time
when we didn't all carry smartphones in our pocket.
We actually used to hand out flip phones
for this experience so that people could have it.
But as you're moving through the park.
You are receiving missions.
You are receiving treasure hunts, scavenger hunts,
that allow you to find and trigger magic in the environment.
You interact with physical props.
You deploy satellite dishes.
You receive encoded messages.
You interact with cast members.
You interact with all sorts of things.
And it turns out...
that while the mechanics are very similar to playing an adventure game at home,
there's something very different that happens when it plays out in the real world.
We're all very used to having agency in a world of pixels.
It's very different to have agency in a world of bricks and mortar.
To actually change the physical environment around you at the push of a digital button
is still very magical, right?
That phone almost becomes a remote control for the entire park.
And you're able to find magic right under your nose,
or in the case of this troll, right under his nose.
right, and really make things, you know, sort of magically appear.
Now we've taken this one step farther,
and last year we launched the Play Disney Parks app.
And this is, again, taking that idea of agency even farther,
where you are now able to use the entire park as a game board,
and your phone is able to follow your lead.
Your personal device is able to understand where you are
and allow you to interact with the environment in unique ways,
depending on the story world that you're within.
And so if you take your phone to Peter Pan's flight,
the wonderful Peter Pan adventure,
you're able to collect pixie dust.
You're able to find hidden objects.
And you're able to even make Tinkerbell appear.
If you bring that over to Space Mountain,
you start landing spaceships and preparing for your flight
through outer space.
And pretty soon here, if you bring it
to Star Wars Galaxy's Edge.
Just as you step into that narrative,
your device steps into that narrative, too.
And it can become a Star Wars data pad that is, again,
your gateway to taking action.
You can join the Resistance and go on a mission,
or you might decide to align yourself with the First Order
and support their cause.
So in all of these, the story unfolds
because you take action.
Because you do something, because you act,
the world changes.
And that's the very definition of a protagonist.
The world, your experience of the world,
that story does not continue unless you do something.
Things don't happen to you, things happen because of you.
And so we took that idea and said, all right,
that's pretty exciting as a park.
What happens is park overlay in these little pockets
of discovery throughout the park.
How can we extend that to maybe a classic attraction?
So as a pilot to try out what does this look like,
we launched the Haunted Mansion Ghost Post.
This was a small pilot to figure out
what does it look like for?
people who really want to be protagonists.
We haven't let you be a protagonist in that world.
You've been a visitor, a guest of the ghosts.
How can you, if you want to develop a relationship
with those ghosts, how can you have that
and actually help move their story forward?
So this is a pilot that we did.
It was, and it was really based around this promise
that our ghosts have been making for about half a century.
that a ghost will follow you home.
At the end of the attraction, there's this either promise
or threat, depending on your read,
how much you like ghosts, that a ghost will follow you home.
And so we said, well, what if the ghost's ability
to travel outside of the mansion was in jeopardy?
They don't know why, what's causing this,
but this is an existential crisis if you're a ghost
and you can't haunt people.
So if you care about ghosts.
That's going to be something you want to help solve.
So we created this serial narrative that arrived in the form of a series of boxes.
And building on that subscription box model, our serial narrative,
each box was a chapter in that story.
and delivered a set of haunted objects that became,
as you open them, these aren't just stuff in a box.
These are props that as you play,
they allow you to unlock parts of the story,
advance the story, and actually help the ghosts restore
their ability to haunt.
And we're taking all of those moments,
so these imaginary tips and tricks of illusion.
There are things that reflect.
It's done with mirrors.
So we're using a lot of different imaginary things
to create these reveals, just like you're
seeing in the park with Agent P, and create those reveals
at home and allow you to discover those hidden
qualities of those objects.
You're literally revealing the ghost writing between the lines.
You're creating that story and advancing how do we solve this problem.
And to do that, we do actually use your personal device.
We use a custom app and combine that with some of these objects to make a phantom radio.
So this spirit radio.
can tune into the spectral qualities of all these objects.
And they actually create radio stations,
which become a radio play that you assemble
your own cardboard radio.
And without pairing it, there's an extra bat stanchion knob
that you can use to tune in that radio.
and actually be able to hear the voices of the ghosts talking to you.
So you're creating this relationship,
even though they can't travel to you physically or spectrally.
Not sure how that works as a ghost.
Even though they can't travel to you and haunt you at home,
they are talking to you and talking to you through the problem.
So when you go back to the park, because your phone has been part of your journey all along,
it's been interacting with all of these objects, it has your story state.
It knows where you are, what progress you've made.
And when you come back to the park, the audio on the attraction actually changed.
So you're no longer just a guest of the ghosts.
You are
you are actually, you're special to them.
You are somebody helping them solve a deep existential crisis.
So of course they know who you are and recognize you when you come through.
They're not showing you the ballroom for the first time.
You're returning to that ballroom as a friend, and eventually that ballroom
becomes a celebration for your restoring their ability to travel.
So in doing all of that, building that magic circle
to allow people to play together,
to give them that alibi to feel like they understand
and can do all those silly things
within that circle of play,
the ability to have that discovery
and move the action along,
be the protagonist in their story
and move the action forward.
Now, moving all that action forward, that's great.
That's pretty straightforward, unless you
have some challenges along the way.
You can't just walk into Mordor.
You've got to have some challenges.
This is the basis of the hero's journey.
And who better at making challenges than game makers?
That loop of try, fail, succeed, you guys know what this is.
This is what games are made of.
And those games, it turns out, are an amazing way
to create a hero's journey, to create that challenge that
makes me feel accomplished, that gets me as a protagonist
from point A to point B. I have to try and fail
before I get there.
We didn't invent games, but we use a lot of mechanics
from them in our parks.
So we have your driving in Autopia.
As Brent took us through, you're exploring in adventure games.
And we have a lot of aiming games,
where you are using some sort of device
to influence things from afar.
So.
So that idea is actually really helpful.
We do it on, and it's super useful.
So we end up using it across a variety of attractions.
We got Buzz Lightyear Astro Blasters,
where you're, we have Ant-Man and the Wasp,
where you're shrinking down to the size of a nanoparticle
and taking part in this heroic battle.
We have Toy Story Mania, where you're going through
and playing these carnival games that your friends
from the Toy Story movies have set up.
And in all of these, that mechanic
of being able to influence things from far away
actually is super helpful
when you're building an environment.
The ability to touch things, to interface with things up close
is really exciting.
There are a bunch of illusions that we
can use if we control how close you can get to it,
and we can make that physical world come to life
in a really exciting, extraordinary way
that you can only do in person.
But the ability to influence that at the distance
really expands the possibility space.
In all of that, when you're making console games,
as let's say you're making a AAA title,
most of the things, there are a bunch of things
that you have to consider.
You're thinking about all your mechanics,
what is gonna go into the box,
how those mechanics link together,
how they build together for a story.
We're all thinking about the same thing.
What you're not thinking about is, well, most of you,
probably when you're making a game,
you're assuming that if you're making a AAA game that's
going to take a few hours to play,
there's a place where somebody's going to need to sit down.
You don't really think or say that in,
that's not in the instructions, and certainly not in the box.
You just assume that they already have a place,
a way to display that game, a way to see what you've made,
and a way to interact.
That controller, you assume, is already there.
And for the most part, unless you're a launch title,
you're assuming that they've actually
used that controller before, have
some level of familiarity with it.
Now, when we're making experiences in
in our parks, when we're making these built experiences, all of those things you build.
You build how do I want you to be where you're interacting?
I'm going to build that.
If it's a place to sit, great.
If it's not, also got to build that.
It may not be a screen, but some way to see the results of my actions.
and that way to actually act upon those things.
You're actually responsible for building
all of those things.
So you're responsible for it,
but it also offers up some pretty cool potential.
Yes, so by way of example, we'll go back to Toy Story Mania.
And so in Toy Story Mania, again, you
can't take anything for granted.
We had to invent the place to sit, right?
That ride vehicle is a custom invention for Toy Story Mania.
It's a wind-up toy that you, because you've been shrunk down,
you're able to be in.
It's able to move through the environment.
It's able to spin around.
It's able to provide a bunch of physical thrill
before in between rounds of play.
We also invented the medium by which you're going to see these things.
And in the case of Midway Mini, it's actually a hybrid of physical space and virtual space,
where you're using a physical controller to interact with a virtual environment.
But even that controller is something that we got to invent.
We had to figure that out.
And while there's disadvantages to having to invent a brand-new interface,
most of you probably have dozens, if not hundreds, of hours logged
building muscle memory around your preferred system at home.
This one's going to be totally novel.
It also means that we get to design an interface that is
custom-tailored to the experience.
So where do we start with something like that?
Well, with MidwayMania, we actually start with a plethora
of plywood prototypes trying to figure out the different
ways that guests might interact with that virtual
world using this physical controller.
And as you can see here, we tried a whole bunch of
different designs, right?
We tried things that had.
Cranks on top, almost like a gatling gun.
We had big smash pads on top where you physically hit it,
almost like a high striker.
We had levers that you could pull.
And with each one of these, we play tested.
We brought people in.
We tried it out.
And of course, what you discover is
that the interface and the game are
tightly married to one another.
When you have that sort of gatling action,
you go rapid fire, you need a vastly higher number
of targets on the screen.
Some of these interfaces take away from the feeling
that you're a toy having fun at a carnival
and start to feel like it's a weapon.
Right?
Start to feel like it's a more violent thing.
Some of these are easier for kids to use,
easier for adults to use.
And each of these need to be taken into consideration.
Now ultimately, we decided on the mock-up
that you see down there at the bottom.
It's a pop action shooter.
And just to call out a couple features here,
the way that you actually fire this pop action shooter
is by pulling a little string on the back.
Right, it feels fun, it feels playful.
We spent a lot of time actually determining
what exactly it feels like to pull on that rope.
And what's great is that the interface presents itself
to you in the most intuitive way possible.
Right in front of you, there's a handle to aim it,
there's a string that you pull.
The only instructions that you need to play
are pull the string to shoot.
One thing about that, though, you
have to be able to reach the string.
It turns out that if you are writing Midway Mania, an adult
and a child together, what is a comfortable distance
for an adult is out of reach for a child.
And what's a comfortable distance for a child
is way too close for an adult.
And so we actually had to do some engineering
to figure out the best way to get that interface
into the best ergonomic position.
And so in this case, we actually created
a mechanical linkage between the placement of the pop action
shooter and the lap bar that you pull down in order
to secure yourself into the seat.
So the smaller you are, the closer that pop action shooter becomes.
And the farther and the bigger you are,
the farther away it is, making it always very comfortable.
But that sort of gets into an interesting point, right?
Since we're designing the entire environment,
this interface is just a little part of it.
What if the environment was the interface?
And this is, again, an idea that goes all the way back
to the beginning of the park with, you know,
experiences like Tom Sawyer's Island.
which nowadays has been made over into pirates' lair on Tom Sawyer's island.
What this is, this is a physical space full of challenges for our guests to overcome.
This is an island that's filled with crisscrossing, with a crisscrossing network of pathways,
each pathway with its own unique challenge.
Some are creepy caverns, some are, you know, swinging suspension bridges.
We have nice buoyant bridges that go across the lagoon.
And each one of these provides you an opportunity to sort of put yourself to the test.
But of course, what's challenging for one person
is trivial for another.
It'd be great if there was some way
that you could modulate that challenge.
And we actually did that in Camp Discovery,
which is a new experience out in Shanghai, Disneyland.
This is a set of adventure courses
built into the side of this mountain,
where guests, as you can see here, actually clip off.
You're in a one-person ride vehicle.
It's a harness that you wear that allows you
to perform death-defying stunts
while still being totally safe.
And what's really cool about this
is that at every step along the way, every vertigo-inducing
step along the way, you actually have a choice to make.
You can decide exactly how much challenge you want.
So for example, if the vertigo is setting in
and you're a little bit nervous, you
can take that path to the left.
If you want to put yourself a little bit more to the test,
you can take those swinging barrels in the center.
And if you're really feeling brave, if you really want to go ahead and test your mettle,
you can take those swinging logs on the right.
And as you go through these challenge trails, you're constantly given new opportunities
to challenge yourself.
So again, we know we're preaching to the choir
here in terms of talking about the importance of challenge.
But there is something, again, just like we were talking
about with adventure games, there's
something very special when you take that try, fail, succeed
loop and bring it away from the pixels and into physical space.
And especially when the interface disappears,
suddenly that triumph isn't an abstract triumph.
It's a personal triumph.
It's a social triumph that you are succeeding in real space
with people that you know and love.
And that makes the moment all that much more special.
And so again, to recap here, challenges
are the hero's journey.
They're critical to making you feel like you're
growing and evolving.
There's immense benefit when you can
build the game and the interface together.
It allows you to dovetail those two things in a way that is
more than the sum of either of their parts.
And when you do it really well, the world
becomes the interface itself.
And people are feeling a personal sense of challenge
unencumbered by any sort of interface.
So you're able to overcome some challenges.
You are on your hero's journey.
I think we're gonna need some friends.
Absolutely.
So let's make some friends.
Characters have been at the center
of Disney Parks experiences since the first day.
And building relationships, it turns out,
when you see a character on screen,
you're making that relationship in your mind.
When you meet them in the real world,
that character can see you
and you can feel seen by that character,
which is super powerful.
Being able to meet your heroes is part of our foundation
and getting that experience of I can actually.
I can actually hug Mickey, have that tactile moment of friendship.
So that's super powerful and foundational, something the early Imagineers figured out
way early.
It turns out we actually have a really wide variety of characters, and not all of them
are as comfortable walking down Main Street as Mickey is.
So let's take, for instance, Crush from Finding Nemo
and Finding Dory.
He's not super comfortable walking down Main Street.
In fact, he's way happier to swim in the ocean.
So we made a little window to the ocean
and actually invite our guests in to have
a conversation with Crush as part of the show
Turtle Talk with Crush.
And in this show, you are actually just having a conversation.
Crush is a super curious guy, and it turns out kids are also pretty curious creatures
themselves, so they get along really well.
He can ask them questions, they can ask him questions, and the show evolves based on what
everybody is curious about.
So Crush shares a little bit of his life on the reef,
and that allows you to create this relationship
with the character with a little bit of added technology
to bring that to life.
Now, to extend the work of other characters
that are really tough to bring to life,
when we want to bring them off the screen,
how do we do that?
We have extended our work in audio animatronics,
that you saw earlier, into automatronics.
And what do I mean by that?
Well, we have some characters who also are a little,
who also want to roll around and move their less,
able to, they're less Nikki sized, so how are we going to get them to move around?
Well, we want them to be able to do that autonomously. We don't want to have them
bolted down to a show, bolted down in a show building. And so developing a little bit of
extra technology to allow them both to navigate safely, but enough to understand their environment
so that all of those relationships, that ability to respond to somebody when they're rolling,
when he's rolling around.
out in Tomorrowland, he can go by and actually...
Because he's aware of the world around him, just like all of us, he can actually clock
that person over there, and as he's rolling past, make eye contact, and maybe even get
curious enough to go over.
Of course, because of that eye contact, that's an invitation now for our guests to interact
with him, too.
So all of that is really special in ways that we are giving our characters the ability to
have a relationship and see our guests.
So now I want to pull a lot of the things
we've been talking about together into one example.
We have an attraction out in Florida
called Enchanted Tales with Belle.
This is at the Magic Kingdom in Walt Disney World.
That really employs a lot of the tactics
that we've been talking about so far
to create that deep relationship with the character.
We're going to cast you in a role.
We're going to let you overcome some challenges.
Of course, we're going to be using
some technology along the way.
And in this experience, you're actually
coming to help Belle celebrate her anniversary
with the Beast.
And as such, we're actually going to be helping to retell the story of the day that she met
the Beast, and again, like I said, put a lot of these tactics into play.
So for example, the first room that you move into is not only in...
inhabited. It's not only a moving living world, but it's a world where you actually get explicitly
cast a role. You get to determine what part in that story you want to play. You can be
everything from a suit of armor to enchanted dishware to the beast themselves. You can
see the kid wearing the red cape, usually the most adorable kid in the crowd, but honestly
it works with everybody. You know, gets to be the beast in this retelling of the story.
We move into another room where we have our director, Lumiere,
who again is another enchanted object come to life
that's able to choreograph some of this action
and help us put on this production.
And then of course, the star of the show herself, Belle.
And Belle leads all of these kids in this interaction
where we all become a part of the retelling of this story.
And we were talking a moment ago about challenges,
overcoming challenges.
And we talked about games.
But performance is a form of challenge too, right?
And this is sort of a uniquely social form of challenge, right?
That for a lot of these people, this
is probably their first time really getting up
and performing in front of other people, right?
But doing that.
is an act of bravery, right?
It's an act of connection.
You're helping create a special moment for Belle.
And so when Belle is able to hug you
at the end of that experience, you've earned that hug, right?
You have not just met her, you have actually helped her.
You have warmed her heart.
And she can recognize you not just as a friend,
but as someone who has collaborated with her
and is a deep, meaningful friend.
And so again, we've known this from day one.
There's power in connection.
And connection really comes from not only seeing that character,
but being seen and being recognized by that character.
And when you combine it with all the things
that we've talked about before, there's
incredible power when you feel like you've
earned that connection and really, really
made that friend in a new way.
We get into, we've made all these friends,
we've combined all of these things,
and really one of the amazing opportunities
in building the world, building the world from scratch,
means that we can go after those aspirational moments,
those moments that I see on screen and I go, I want that.
That thing, I want that.
Then we were going back to the car commercial
of you're having the moment of,
that just looks like it would feel amazing.
And it's that feel amazing that we're going after.
So how do we?
bring that magic to life.
We're engaging all of the senses to make that magic real,
to make it feel amazing.
And that feeling of flight, those aspirational feelings.
So it's about sensation.
It's about haptics.
It's about touch.
It's about how do I, the thing that I saw on screen
that looked cool, how does it feel?
Now, this section, I'm going to warn you,
when you're talking about all the senses,
keynote actually is a really, a slide talk,
is a really hard thing to do to communicate all the senses.
So you're going to have to use a little bit more imagination
for this section of the talk as we go through,
because we haven't invented the scratch and sniff slide deck
yet.
Not yet.
working on it. So in Peter Pan this is an opening day attraction and we're starting to get into
this. We're using a little bit of forced perspective to give you that sensation of
flying over London and in fact that perspective that we have.
of flying over it, and you're seeing it underneath you.
That's part of the aspirational experience of flying.
The non-aspirational experience of flying
of I'm in a metal tube, I'm looking out the window
and seeing the clouds pass by, I am a passenger.
If I am flying, I am looking down,
I have the world spreading out underneath me.
And so we continued that into Soarin' Around the World.
in which you are gliding through all of these epic locations
around the world.
And we're literally lifting your feet off the ground.
Your feet are dangling.
And we've added movement to this.
So we're lifting you up and pushing you into and moving
with those images.
As that scene unfolds around you,
you're crossing on top of Everest.
and flying, you feel the wind in your hair,
the sway of the wind as it catches you as you bank around,
and you smell the ocean, the orange groves,
my personal favorite, as you're flying through,
we activate all of your senses.
And taking that activation one step further,
In Avatar Flight of Passage in Pandora,
which we opened as part of Disney's Animal Kingdom
in Florida, you are able to mount and ride
on one of those banshees.
So these are those dragons from the Avatar films,
kind of dragon-y creatures.
They can fly.
They're super cantankerous.
You've got to earn it.
And you're creating a relationship with this thing.
So we take all of what's working well in Soarin,
we're taking that motion, we're moving you with this image,
we're wrapping that image around you
as you're flying through,
bringing it into three dimensions,
and we're also activating your senses.
So you're feeling that sea breeze,
but you're also...
feeling that Banshee breathe underneath you,
because it's not just you flying,
you're flying with your new friend, the Banshee.
Now.
We have some other aspirational things
that we're about to open, Star Wars Galaxy's Edge, which
I have been waiting to step into that world
that I've seen on screen since I was a small child.
And so what could be more aspirational?
We can get to drink some blue milk, step into that world,
smell the smells, see all the sights,
It's going to be very exciting.
And what more aspirational thing in there
when we talk about flying, but flying the Millennium Falcon?
So you are going to get to step into the cockpit.
Just a little teaser.
So in all of this, when you step into that cockpit,
you have been given a very clear role.
You are the new Millennium Falcon pilot.
And with that role, you are engaging the whole environment.
That environment is actually responding to what you do.
Those lights blink.
That hyperspace lever goes.
You're overcoming a bunch of challenges
and moving the action forward.
as you're going through, so you are,
the reason why you go to light speed
is because you pull that lever.
You're in charge of hitting those buttons,
targeting those tie fighters,
and making sure that you get through,
that you move that action forward.
And you're building relationships along the way.
depending on what shape you get that Millennium Falcon back,
that's going to matter as well.
And so your friends might respond a little differently,
depending on how you handled yourself as a pilot.
And all of this bringing together
the wish and the dream of being able to fly
the Millennium Falcon.
So.
We've sort of done exactly what we were saying.
We're building this experience from the inside out, right?
Starting with that role, putting you in the world,
and really figuring out how we put you in the movie, right?
And these are all wonderful tips and techniques
that we've figured out along the way to put you in the movie.
But it turns out that there's one additional wrinkle.
It's not just about putting you in the movie.
It's about putting all of you in the movie together.
These are family experiences.
These are experiences that you want to share
with your loved ones, with your friends.
It turns out that people don't just come to the park
for the attractions, they come to the parks to be together.
They come to the parks to connect with people
that they love.
When you're exploring a fantasy world,
a place that you've never seen before,
it levels the playing field between adults and children
and you're able to experience awe together.
When you wear a silly hat, it's not just a fashion choice.
It is that alibi to play.
It is that opportunity for an adult
to engage with their children in a way
that they may not even do in their own living rooms.
When you overcome challenges together,
when you share a meal together.
when you play together, what we're doing is we're creating indelible memories, right?
We're creating experiences that people are going to carry with them for the rest of their life.
And that's tremendously impactful. It's powerful that these places and that these experiences
can actually bring people together. And that power is one of the reasons that I come to work every day
is that ability through these experiences, that power to bring people together.
And with great power.
comes great responsibility.
Because we have the responsibility
to build that world.
And that's really why we're here today.
Because what we have discovered over the last 65 years
of figuring out how do we put you in the movie
is that it takes more than just some filmmakers.
To put guests in the movie, you need more than movie makers.
You need a whole range of skills.
And those skills are bringing that world into dimensions,
bringing that world to life.
You need roboticists and those same powers of animation
that bring animated worlds on screen.
Those characters live.
with that power of animation.
You need storytellers who understand
how to build a space for the guest inside of that world,
that they have that storytellers who
build that story around our new protagonist, the guest.
How to create those special effects and illusions.
And you maybe need some people who
are willing to move mountains or even build them if necessary.
You need.
and being able to bring those to life,
to activate those surfaces and use them
to tell an infinite variety of responsive stories.
And of course, the people to take it together
into the field.
And.
As you've probably noticed, a lot of these things
have to do with games.
And the qualities that make games so evocative
and keep us playing are also the qualities
that make our guest experience possible, that
make you the protagonist in the world, that
keep the world responding to you, give you challenges,
and ultimately turn into that wish fulfillment.
So thank you all for joining us.
Thank you.
So we have a little bit of time in this room for questions.
We're going to go ahead and take a couple of questions now,
and we'll hang out afterwards.
We went almost to the time limit.
So we'll just take a couple questions, but we'll hang out.
And if you need to find us, we can be found over on the Overlook as well.
Cool, thanks for the talk, really appreciate it.
Can we bring up the house lights a little bit?
There's a lot of really fantastic examples
of people having individual agency
as they're interacting with the park,
and you're in a unique position to have
multiple physical people in the same space.
So I'm curious, I'm glad that you mentioned
bringing them together and showed the example
of the beauty and the beast.
How does having multiple people in a space shape the way that you think about cooperative gameplay?
And what are the challenges and considerations that you have to balance between having emergent behavior and emergent gameplay
with making sure that experiences are contained?
Yeah, that's a great question.
I mean, talking about how we use cooperative gameplay.
I mean, that is really at the core of everything
that we're doing is that idea of co-op, right?
We recognize that almost nobody comes to the park alone.
You're there with your friends.
You're there with your loved ones.
And yes, you are surrounded by lots of other people.
And so we always look for experiences that,
while there might still be some elements of competition,
that there's also some elements of teamwork.
And going back to Toy Story Mania as an example,
the best way to get the high score on that,
I'm going to give a little tip to everyone in the audience,
is not to compete with your friend,
but to actually work with your friend.
There are tons of Easter eggs and hidden targets
inside of that experience that can only be unlocked.
if two of you are working together, hitting tyrants simultaneously,
using your powers combined in order to reveal extra magic.
And that's how we sort of get that idea,
even in that very competitive head-to-head experience,
a little bit of that coopetition.
And as you mentioned, we're always looking for a way
to embrace the fact that there's a crowd of people
and to give you an opportunity to take the stage
and to be at the center of the action.
My question is...
Oh, sorry.
You want to go?
Oh, should I go?
Oh, okay.
Sure.
We'll alternate.
Okay.
I attended a bunch of awesome talks this week about designing for color blindness, adaptive
controllers, subtitles, and I'm curious what the Disney Imagineering approach is when it
comes to designing for all of the senses to make sure that anyone who goes to the theme
parks or has any Disney experience is able to have a good time as well.
Absolutely. Accessibility and these experiences are for everyone. We have an incredibly broad
audience. So in all of the, you saw the development of that control, the midway mania.
We look towards certainly colorblind, but also the ability to, you don't want to assume
the ability to grip.
We want to reach a widest possible audience, so you can use that controller with, you don't
have to use opposable thumbs to use that controller.
So we have a set of guidelines.
We work with a ton of folks who are really...
very talented at looking at accessibility across a variety of categories.
And it means inventing what that accessible thing is for each experience.
How do you create that experience that when you are engaging the senses
that can communicate to that wide audience?
And it's really a case by case basis, but
it's something we think about all the time.
And actually, one of the interesting things about that
is that the process of designing to engage all the senses,
in and of itself, makes the experience more accessible.
I mean, you may not be able to see the visuals on the screen,
but that doesn't prevent you from feeling the motion,
from feeling the breeze, from smelling the smells.
That can still be an adventure.
even if you don't see the visuals.
And likewise, you may not be able to hear it,
but there's a lot to see, there's a lot to feel.
And so a lot of times, yes, we are taking into account
every time we design an interface how
to make that interface available to everybody.
But part of that is just designing
multisensory experiences to begin with.
Thank you.
My question is around personalization at scale.
I did one of the beta tests of an immersive experience at
Walt Disney Resort a couple years ago with my sister.
And it was one of my favorites.
But obviously, that takes away time from other people.
So how do you balance having these extremely personalized
experiences or even smaller seating arrangements so that
people can feel more intimate and more like they're actually
riding the Millennium Falcon versus getting a lot of people
through experience in a day?
That is something we, in terms of that game design loop
of I want to try, fail, succeed, having that,
having the responsiveness and balancing that
with the scale of how many people we are entertaining.
We have
A lot of ways, we have a lot of ways to go after that.
One of the ones that we mentioned in the talk,
we talked about Ghostpost.
That actually allows you to continue that story at home
and keeping that story to having different levels
of interaction.
So for Parks Play app, you're getting,
everything is very responsive
and using the environment strategically
to pay off for those larger payoffs.
so that we can do that at scale and handle
the amount of people who want to play and interact.
Ghost Post has a wonderful version of that, too,
which is context, right?
The fact that when you play Ghost Post,
you're still writing the same haunted mansion
as everyone else.
But because you have this deeper connection,
because you have this insight into the world,
you see different details in that environment
than other people do.
What you talk about is definitely a challenge that we confront.
We have a whole bag of tricks to do it.
But one of those is definitely thinking about how do we extend the time, how do we deliver
personalized messages, the personal devices and things like the Parks Play app.
All of these are techniques to sort of give each of us our own unique experience within
this shared environment.
Hi, when approaching the process and problems that you talked about today,
how do you maintain the perspective and lens through which a kid sees the world
a lot of us, all of us lose as we go older?
Like, how do you know the experiences are going to be received as intended by a kid?
So this is in the perspective setting of literally
understanding what do kids see out of this experience.
I have been in Imagineering about a third of the time
that Brent has.
And so had the experience of, never had the experience
of the parks as a child.
A colleague said, all right.
We're going to judge this.
We're going to put you on a rolly chair,
and you're going to roll through this
and look at what does somebody who is waist high, what
do they understand in this world?
And so seeing, well.
Sometimes you see a lot of crowds of legs.
So bringing those details down to extending them
all the way down to the floor, understanding
what that experience is like.
I like to borrow as many families and friends
that I can and go to the park with them
to be able to understand what is their experience of going
to the parks.
So that empathy as a designer is really important
and it is all too easy to lose track of
this is the experience for me.
You have to play in the, we play test constantly
to better understand our test, our assumptions
about what do you understand, what do you know,
how do you interact, and try to look at it
through the eyes of our guests in all their variety.
Thank you.
Hi there.
Oh, I think they cut us off.
Hello.
Oh, in the case of a lot of my favorite games, I had to lose a lot before I could win.
Do you think it's possible to have a satisfying theme park attraction that actually ends in
loss or failure?
Yeah, well, you know, yes.
But I think that that is defined differently, right?
I mean, I think that we always want you to have a good time.
I mean, the reason that you kept playing that game
is not just because it was challenging,
but because the challenge was a fun challenge, right?
And I think that within the context of our parks,
we need to account for guests who
are going to be able to ride that ride hundreds of times,
as well as people for whom that experience might be a once
in a lifetime experience.
And so we're always looking at, how
do we make sure that it's fun the first time you play it?
And how do we make sure that it's still fun the hundredth
time you've gone through it?
And so a lot of the times we look at sort of variable success
more than digital decisions of failure and success.
An example, going back to Toy Story Mania,
is we have a high striker board that sort of gives you
your score at the end and lets you know how well you did.
No matter what, you get to shoot confetti out
of that cannon at the end.
It is a celebration of however well you did.
But you also get sort of a metric
of how well you did in the grand scheme of things.
And I'll give a slightly humbling example there.
I was part of the design team on Mania,
and I rode that ride hundreds of times before it opened.
It was a tough job.
And me and the other designers had a little bit
of a running competition going on.
I think my personal high score that I ever got
was about 380,000 points, which we thought was,
I thought was pretty dang good.
We opened up, and within a couple months of opening,
we had annual pass holders who had already crossed
the 500,000 mark.
And so no matter how deep you make it, people will go deeper.
But it still needs to be fun that first time through.
And that's always what we're trying to balance.
Thank you.