All right.
Hello and a warm welcome, everyone.
My name is Myles Tost,
and I have the honor to represent the bright minds
of the CDPR level design team here at GDC today.
I've been working as a level designer at CDPR
for more than 10 years now,
and currently have the privilege to lead the level design team
on our upcoming Witcher game.
Small disclaimer, the timing of this talk
will actually be pretty tight, which is why, unfortunately,
I believe there won't be any time for Q&A here in this room.
However, after the talk, I will wander straight outside.
There's this little alcove.
And there, I will gladly answer all of your questions
until I drop.
So once again, I'm so happy to see you all here
and would like to thank you from the bottom of my heart
for joining me.
Today, I would like to tell you a five-part story about how
the CDPR level design team and I learned
of the benefits of missing out.
My hope with this talk is that I can provide you
guys with some insights into the level design of Cyberpunk 2077.
And in the end, a better understanding
and a concrete set of principles of how
to create nonlinear levels that give each player,
no matter which path they pick, a more special experience.
And our journey starts right at the beginning.
It's shortly before the release of our second Witcher 3
expansion, Blood and Wine, in early 2016,
when I, together with the other level designers,
start moving to Cyberpunk 2077.
After four years of working on a medieval fantasy world
with wide open landscapes, relatively limited amount
of ways to play a defined character, no offense, Geralt,
and a third person perspective, I
couldn't wait to switch working on a game that I learned
couldn't be more different in regards to the challenges it
would present.
I was hyped.
So what were we about to deal with?
Cyberpunk 2077 takes place entirely in first-person perspective
in a claustrophobic megalopolis called Night City.
Unlike predefined Witcher Geralt, V, our protagonist,
was meant to allow players the ultimate freedom to play who they want to be.
That is, if we could pull it off.
No pressure.
From a high level, all of our recent triple-A RPGs are based on a few pillars.
That is, the freedom in the story, freedom in the world,
freedom in the gameplay.
When we look at these design pillars,
it's actually the first two which
have been massive in driving the development of Witcher 3.
It's the third one, then, freedom in gameplay,
that was the big new addition to Cyberpunk.
And this is where the gameplay and level design teams
wanted to make a gigantic leap forward.
The inspiration for our ambitions
came from immersive sim titans, such as the original Deus
X.
Mind you, it being CDPR, we weren't the only discipline
with huge ambitions and dreams.
So based off these pillars, we were
presented by our directors with a few design goals.
Style over substance is a model that
is at the heart of Mike Pondsmith's original pen
and paper universe, which Cyberpunk actually is based on.
Why do something in a mundane way
when you could do and go about it in style?
Our goal was to give players the options to generously apply
the rule of cool to their characters
and how they play them.
Likewise, we didn't want them to go do that and then end up
in a dead end or with an unviable play style.
So every option they chose, no matter the combo,
should result in a valid way to play the game.
This is what freedom in gameplay was all about, after all.
And in order to enable this level of freedom,
we were asked to make levels that supported a ton,
a ton of vastly different play styles.
That is melee versus ranged, mobility versus stability,
brute force versus ingenuity, and combat versus stealth.
And we thought to ourselves, levels supported by immersive sim-style systems and build-as-sandboxes,
what a dream.
And they all had to be part of a huge open world and take into account the complex branching
narrative and cinematic focus of our quests with all their possibilities and outcomes.
Oh.
Now, neither the studio nor most of the four to five level designers working on the game at the time
had ever done stuff like this before. That includes myself.
But as insane as it sounded, it also sounded fucking awesome.
And boy, were we up to the challenge.
So, how does one even begin to eat this whale?
This is a question for which it took us a long time to find an answer to.
Our gameplay designers decided to base all of the abilities
and perks on the fantasies of the classes
of the original pen and paper.
We didn't want to have fixed classes in Cyberpunk 2077,
freedom and all that,
but instead allow players to build their own
by mixing and matching a ton of different perks,
abilities, weapons, and cyberware
to effectively recreate the fantasy
of the source game's classes or anything in between.
Knowing this, we decided to structure our levels
around the most purest character fantasies
Cyberpunk players would be able to create.
Our archetypes, representing the original classes,
Solo, Netrunner, and Techie.
The theory was that if a player completely invested themselves
into fulfilling a specific archetype,
they would get their own unique path through a level,
and it would feel rewarding.
If players were mixing archetypes,
they would be able to follow one of the three paths
for as long as they liked.
And if their abilities were not high enough,
they simply found a more interesting way
to traverse the level.
They could simply switch to another path.
What if they followed a path, then got stuck,
for whatever reason, without the necessary abilities
to successfully switch to any other play style path?
So to avoid such situations, we also added a fail safe.
That is the generic path, which was
free from any skill checks.
The generic path would be our fallback to ensure players could always progress down the critical path.
This was super important to us because we pride ourselves on being storytellers,
and we did not want a lack of a player's foresight to get in the way of them experiencing our narrative.
And to encourage better use of play styles,
we also decided that the generic path should always be the most difficult one.
Now, this would often end up clashing with our storytelling requirements,
because it's often easiest to construct a great narrative around the one path
that all players can pass, no matter how they build their character.
And as a result of the generic path being the most difficult one,
conversely, playstyle paths would provide the least resistance,
contributing to the power fantasy they should provide to players.
And this is how that would look like on an actual level.
This is a gig location I had the opportunity
to create the base blockout for early in the game's
development.
And because of that, it reflects our initial design assumptions
really well.
And you can think of a gig as a relatively brief type
of handcrafted open world mission.
First off.
The generic stealth and combat path.
Here, they actually coincide, with stealth mostly being focused on waiting for opportune
timing windows to bypass enemy patrols.
Using double jump, the solo can infiltrate the area through an alternative entrance and
smoothly reach the goal.
That's probably hard to see on these, but...
It is what it is.
The Netrunner can hack devices and manipulate enemies
to create distractions to create their own timing windows.
Back then, we used hackable devices
like a tray of breadcrumbs to lead the Netrunner's way.
And finally.
The techie who could break in and use a completely different route altogether.
Techies initially had their own custom mechanic planned, but in practice it played too closely
to the Netrunner's playstyle.
And in the end, we couldn't really find and afford a meaningful difference between these
two playstyles, which led to the techie being downscoped in importance to a more supporting
playstyle as opposed to his own full archetype.
I also had the pleasure to be part of content team number two.
And my team members were incredible without exception,
and together we were responsible for bringing the Judy quest
line to life.
This is an example from the final game
of our play styles in action on one of my locations, which
we internally refer to as the Braindance Studio.
As a level designer, I was responsible for both the design and implementation of the
location itself, as well as the implementation of the encounters.
Ready? Expect the unexpected!
What?
Got the blueprint. Be there in a sec.
And here is actually the Brain.in studio
played in a completely different way.
While designing and implementing encounters such as these,
we constantly had to balance the different play styles
and adjust our scripting to make sure all possibilities
were playing in concert with each other.
First shot, he's still alive?
I'm here! Got no time to creep around!
Now, NPC behavior would need to adjust to a sudden combat situation, which in theory
as you can see could occur at any time and at any moment of an encounter like this.
While our AI is able to handle a wide variety of situations reasonably well,
thanks to our great work of our gameplay designers and programmers,
in order to make sure our combat always felt right,
enemies would, for example, need to position themselves
towards where we wanted the player to go relative to the player's position.
Basically, what I'm trying to say is that we often had to script
not just the stealth sequences, but also multiple combat scenarios.
All right. So that didn't look so bad.
I actually recall once walking past one of our testers
using our bullet time ability, Sandivistan,
very much a combat skill,
to bypass patrols while stealthing.
Another time, I saw a really good friend of mine
force his way into a building
for which he did not have the proper techie skill
by punching a hole into a window with his bare fists
over the course of a whole minute.
Things looked really promising. So let's ship it.
Now the joke is about to come, Sean, don't laugh yet.
Now, the launch of Cyberpunk 2077 was really rough.
I'm sure many of you in here can relate to me
when I say that making games such as Cyberpunk 2077
is truly a dream come true, at least for me.
And I'm proud to always give it my all
to help do my part in realizing the wonderfully ambitious
and demanding projects we work on at CDPR.
Pouring your heart into a project,
and then having it cause so much disappointment
despite your best efforts, is crushing.
And my heart goes out to all the devs
who have gone through similar experiences.
But you trip, you get back up.
In 2013, I started out in an environment
where we wanted to prove that this small Polish developer
could redefine open world RPGs.
And as a team, we were now back to wanting
to prove that we're serious about learning
from our mistakes and doing better.
It took us a few patches to finally gain some insight
into how fruitful our efforts from level design perspective
actually were.
And overall, it was pretty decent.
Players were happy to experiment with their play styles.
We even added a respec mechanic post-launch
to help them experiment even more.
And also, the balance between validity of play styles
was also pretty good. So there was no,
you know, like dominant place over the other.
Everyone was happy playing just what they wanted to play.
And of course, we saw people play in ways
we had not anticipated.
To me, using throwing knives or silenced pistols
to distract enemies was one of these examples.
However, highly ambitious as we were,
we couldn't help but notice some criticism
that kept coming up.
One was that players didn't really
feel like whatever play style they picked mattered that much.
The experience wouldn't actually drastically change.
And I have a suspicion that sentiment
may have gotten even worse after we added that simple respect
mechanic.
Now, it turns out, though, that on closer inspection,
this problem was pretty complex, and LD
was only one part of the equation.
We also would need to evaluate how our perk system itself
and even our own design mentality affected the problem.
That is, when it comes to encounters on quests,
we basically were trying to create
multiple highly polished linear experiences as opposed
to interwoven ones, where it's up to the player
how much they experience.
If there was a cool or important thing along the path,
we really didn't want the player to suffer
a diminished experience because they missed it.
Also, you guys should have seen my Twitter inbox.
Some of them creatively compared our work
to having combined noodles and raisins.
And waking up to that on launch day was truly something.
Jokes aside though, the positive outlook here is that despite it all, people really
cared about the quality of our work, and now it was on us to show them that we did too.
All right.
So learning from mistakes and doing better.
Becoming better starts with understanding
one's own shortcomings.
And in spring 2022, our level design team
set itself a mission.
We wanted to evaluate what we could reasonably
fix in patches or what we may want to look at
to do better in the future.
And on that note, I know the Project Orion team
is hiring for our Boston studio.
And you can find our devs here running around.
So if you're interested in that, feel free to catch them.
Okay, to figure out what we level designers should do,
the team internally kicked off
a research and development project.
Every LD would try to find one level design-related problem
in Cyberpunk 2077, analyze it, propose a solution,
and present that to the team for further discussion.
And so, I embarked on a new mission.
The problem I wanted to research was the following.
Level design in Cyberpunk 2077 is focused on supporting various playstyles
by providing branching of the nonlinear designs.
Yet, since launch, we have learned that players don't feel like playstyles
and perks they commit to matter much.
Other games feature less varied perks, less options,
and yet those games seem to have succeeded where we have not.
My mission objectives then were the following.
First, I wanted to gain insight into how our level design contributes negatively to the feeling of playstyles not mattering.
And then, I wanted to use that information to improve future designs to enhance the feeling of playstyles mattering and being fun.
So with the problem and my mission clearly stated, it was time to come up with a plan.
My initial hunch was to go back to the formula
and with the wisdom of hindsight,
revisit and analyze the games that inspired us
in the first place.
These were games such as Arkane's Dishonored 1 and 2,
Rocksteady's Batman Arkham series,
and of course, Iron Storm's original Deus Ex,
as well as Eidos' follow-ups, and many more.
Now then, I wanted to dissect our work more closely
in hopes of finding out the differences that
may contribute to our problem.
My hope was that I could then formulate a set of principles
based on what I would find, which we could
use to improve our future work.
And to further validate these principles,
I want to apply them theoretically simply
to see what would happen.
So since I'm in love with the games that I mentioned before,
it would be easy for me to get excited and simply go,
all right, guys.
We just need to build levels exactly like these guys do.
Annoying myself, I decided to do a little reality check after replaying them.
First off...
We put our narrative first.
It's our trademark, and everything we do
is meant to contribute to telling
a great story in an open world that feels real
and affords the player many freedoms.
With, for example, no loading screens,
which meant that building exteriors and interiors always
had to match.
Secondly, because of the size of our world,
we need to make a ton of content.
Cyberpunk 2077 features more than 85 gigs,
almost 40 main missions, and more than 25 side missions,
most of which feature one or multiple
bespoke custom locations.
And thirdly, because of these first two points,
we can always brute force a solution
by simply providing completely different paths
which individually would compare
to a single level in our game.
So that meant whatever principles I wanted to form should consider our production reality
and thus be broken down enough so that we could apply them even on a smaller scale.
And now if this seems like a relatively well put together plan, the reality is that I had
no clue what I was going to find or if any of this would result in anything meaningful.
But onward we march.
And I found two major issues that kept repeating throughout our levels.
It's not like all of them were affected by both of these issues in the same way,
but it's happened often enough that on closer inspection, it was definitely noticeable.
To make sure the generic path was a reliable fallback, we often made it super obvious,
and this resulted in us inadvertently streamlining the experience to the point where,
yes, the generic path was the fallback, but it also became the most obvious one.
Why pick a play style path when the generic solution is so close, easy to reach, and obvious?
Certainly, our guidance systems with paths to objectives being displayed on the mini-map
also didn't do us many favors here.
The other issue I kept finding was related to how we seed cool optional content. If you take
a look at Dishonored 2, for example, and here, shout out to the team over at Arkane,
We're big fans of your work.
We see that as soon as the player actually
moves from the golden path, they are bound
to run into some cool things.
This is a cool way to reward players with unique experience.
But it also means that depending on which path you pick
and what you find there, the information
the player has about the world can be slightly different.
In an effort to make sure that players would experience the best possible narrative,
we often would put the coolest and most important things following the generic path,
because this way we could make sure all players would be able to experience it.
This becomes especially obvious and problematic when we look at the way we would utilize skill
checks. For this, we look at a somewhat extreme example, but it is in the game.
In this mission, the player gets in close contact with a new gang, which prides themselves
on their physical strength.
Oh, you think? The runner we want tried to invade you.
With the extra eyes we give you, you can always land one like this.
So, he knows I'm here.
This one's got a motion sensor. Only reacts when you move.
New models got muscle memory sims. React to your intention, not your...
Following the generic path, me and my intimidatingly skilled colleague Danish
Makievic made sure that you'd see a lot of custom chatter to give a background to this new gang.
It's a cool, it's quite a cool experience actually,
which even features some custom interactions such as this one.
Here you can also see how we somewhat abandoned the one path per playstyle approach.
If you're a netrunner, you don't just want to follow a trail of breadcrumbs with utility
for you, but mess around with devices no matter which path you pick, and same goes for other
playstyles.
Ultimately, we just decided to give people as many cool options as we could fit on the level.
And that worked reasonably well and was also simpler to design for.
Oh, oh, oh!
The main hit here. Look for the camionet.
Okay, and we're in the big main hall of this location.
Now, let's see what happens if the player makes use of their invested skills to unlock another passage.
Stay hidden. Beware of Patron.
Yep, and that's the exit of the gym that we just left.
And it's incredible and highlights how sometimes the cost of enhancing the value of invested skills for the player could be quite low.
Imagine if we had chosen to do it the other way around and treat this side passage as the generic path, with the gym being unlocked by a skill check.
That way, your skill check would have unlocked an awesome new section for you, rewarding you with a cool and unique experience.
To summarize our issues, then.
First, our plan to use the generic path as fallback turned into a bit of a trap on execution, resulting in it often being the most obvious solution which players would pick.
Only too happily, that is.
Secondly, oftentimes we would add reward to the challenge generic should provide by also making
it the path with a cool bespoke experience. To fulfill our goal to present a great story,
we tended to cluster all our cool content related to exposition, lore, cool encounters,
secrets, and sometimes even loot at bottlenecks in the level, like in the end.
That in by itself is not such a big problem, actually,
if you only want to create a cool cinematic narrative
experience.
However, looking at it from the perspective
of creating memorable nonlinear experiences in gameplay,
it's hard to give real value to play styles with this approach.
Revisiting our initial approach then,
we find that the generic path as fallback
is actually one of the main contributors
of devaluing our paths, because on execution,
it ended up diluting the experience
by overemphasizing streamlining to a fault.
As for the difficulty of the generic and playstyle paths,
our approach resulted in a multitude of skill checks
being used to simply bypass encounters.
Which in hindsight, sounds relatively insane.
Players invest their hard-earned attribute in perk points,
and as a reward, they get to experience less of the game.
Well, at least now you guys know where we were coming from.
Equipped with the knowledge of what went wrong, I went back and took a look at many of our
own levels and wondered how we can marry our cinematic storytelling while still providing
varied non-linear experiences in our level.
Truthfully, the outcome of our work wasn't bad.
On the aspect of providing the player rich nonlinear experiences,
it was merely weaker than we had intended.
Based on my comparison between our levels and other games,
I decided to expand on some concepts of what we already knew about nonlinear level design
to also define how we set up the action and reward structure in our levels.
And I call the resulting concept Discovery and Exploration.
Discovery and exploration is a method to structure your level, which expands the concept of analysis
– a beat in which the player observes and formulates their plan – and execution – the
beat in which the player executes their plan.
The concept focuses on setting up choices and providing payoff to give players a more
special experience on each path they pick.
And like the concept it is based on,
it consists of two distinct alternating beats,
each with their own characteristics and purpose.
This method focuses on beats as part of the reward structure
of a level, meaning that individual beats can and should
very much still be flavored.
Is it a more combat heavy or the opposite?
Does it include environmental puzzles, secrets, story
exposition, et cetera?
Let's take a closer look at the individual beats starting with the discovery one.
This beat is primarily about the player discovering their options, making their choices, and overcoming
challenges.
Not always, but often, this is where you will use your informative overwatch, so not much
revolution here.
However, from a narrative function perspective,
this is the establishing shot of your location.
It is here that we set the mood and give the player
what they need to know.
It's also where we plant some seeds
to tease what players might find in later parts of the level.
However, it's important to not overspend your budget here.
So it's crucial to not shoot all of your powder
and save some for later.
Once the player made their choice
and successfully passed through the discovery area,
they now find themselves in our exploration beat.
And the exploration beat provides
a more intimate and linear experience
compared to discovery.
It does this by narrowing down the level
and what the player can see of the rest of the location,
restricting them to the path they have chosen.
The intent is to let the player focus
on exploring and experiencing the choice they committed to.
And this beat is less about making new choices
and much more about the consequence of choosing.
It's the payoff for having chosen.
Now, this is the moment for some cool intimate experiences.
World building, puzzles, special encounters, secrets,
expanding on the context of the level's narrative.
Whatever you can think of to make this cool.
As a result, we get two beats which complement each other.
Discovery is all about providing choices and presenting the player with promises of the
awesome that they're about to uncover.
Exploration is where that awesome lives.
It's the player experiencing the consequences of their choice of picking a path, and for
doing so, exploration rewards the player.
It's not only great from the player's perspective,
but also from ours as storytellers.
This structure allows us to still expose the player
to important narrative elements and cinematic moments
while giving the individual player
a more unique experience.
Used well, the exploration beat can provide more context
for our narrative and build on it and thus enhance it.
Nonetheless, this concept works best
the more okay one is with the player
potentially missing cool stuff.
Due to my research, I do genuinely think it is okay for players to miss cool things if
they do it, and only if they do it by experiencing other cool stuff, basically keeping the net
gain for the player in balance.
Let's look at how that concept might look like applied to our level, the Brain Dance Studio.
We see that the foundation of analysis and execution are there. Classic level design setup.
One beat to analyze your path from a vantage point, another to get close to the action and execute your plan.
When we rethink it with the concept of discovery and exploration, the beat setup changes to focus on providing choices and promising rewards, then granting them.
We still apply the same theory of analysis and execution in Discovery, but our focus changes.
From this perspective, there's actually room for improvement mainly in the payoff the Exploration
Beat provides. More on that in a minute. Please try to make a mental note here.
I mentioned earlier that as part of my mission, I wanted to find a set of useful principles to
help make different paths feel more special. And I did!
In addition to discovery and exploration, these principles are widely applicable, even
on smaller levels, and through specific actions a level designer might use these to improve
on their designs.
Our first of three principles I want to share with you focuses on the proximity of different
paths in a level to each other.
Take a look at these two entrances if you can see them.
This is a bit of an extreme example, but even though the player has a choice here,
does it really feel like a choice worth making?
The proximity of these two entrances leaves little room for mystery as to whether these
paths are actually any different. Remember the BrainNance Studio from earlier and how I
mentioned the exploration beat needing improvement? Well, here we're actually looking at it.
White represents the intended generic paths, and green are the play-styled paths.
What happens is that even when we apply vertical distance to a path,
as long as the paths are close to each other,
they're still perceived as the same path because the proximity results in them running
vertically parallel to each other. And in part to this,
the exploration bead fails to provide meaningful rewards by making
each choice result in a very similar payoff.
So principle number one, then, the perception of distance.
This principle tries to give the players the perception
that they have a choice to make.
Which path do I pick?
The closer paths are to each other,
the less it feels like picking one actually makes a difference.
And while verticality can be a valid way of creating distances
for entrances, the same cannot be said about the paths
themselves.
It's important that your paths are perceived by players
as being distanced to each other to enhance
the feeling of them being different
and leading to different outcomes.
On the extreme end, this is why having completely different
paths through a location is so cool,
but potentially very expensive.
So, what can we as level designers do
to enhance a player's perception of distance
between paths and entrances?
Well, generally, try to design entrances and paths as far away from each other as reasonably possible.
Kind of makes sense.
However, it's not so much about the actual distance between the paths as much as it is
about the perceived distance.
That means, anything that can help make paths feel distant from each other, like building
a layout in which visibility is limited, setting up encounters or skill checks to make access
to the paths more difficult, can also help.
Generally, I recommend a quality over quantity approach,
especially in smaller locations where
it may be hard to properly distance
many paths from each other.
Rather, have two that have a high perception of distance,
then three which are too close to each other.
In the setup here, you can see a typical example
of a playstyle entrance allowing for a separate access
to a location.
This in by itself is fine, but if we
look at the flow of the paths, we
can see that the way the location is built,
the initial question of, I wonder
where that other path may go, is revealed to the player
without them ever actually having to use that path.
It exposes that in the end, the path they pick really
did not matter all that much.
So while principle number one tries to build choice,
principle number two focuses on building, and more importantly,
maintaining an air of mystery around the choices.
Through principle number one, the player
becomes aware that they need to make a choice.
Principle number two, a perception of exclusivity,
prevents them from knowing the alternative outcome
and heightens a sense of wonder.
The more exclusive and isolated a path feels, the more special it can become in the player's mind.
Without a perception of exclusivity, we destroy all chances of players to even wonder whether another path might result in a different outcome.
Through perception of exclusivity, we can also allow a player to fully focus on the experience provided from the path they picked and
This in turn heightens a player's curiosity
about the possible alternative outcomes
they could have experienced.
As a level designer, how do I make my paths feel more exclusive,
especially if I'm on a tight budget?
One of the most cost-effective ways I found to increase
a perception of exclusivity for players
is to limit and control what a player can see.
That means breaking line of sight of the player
to alternative paths and entrances
to prevent them from figuring out how they work
without ever having to use them.
Furthermore, to fully allow the player to focus on the path,
commit them to a choice by using one-way drops and passages.
However, if your game is all about providing freedom
like ours, with little notion of punishing the player,
allow them to switch between paths, but only at a cost.
For example, by making them decide
whether they'd rather stay on the path they picked
or try to sneak past a particularly deadly enemy.
All right, principle number three, I think,
is the easiest to understand, but maybe not
such an easy one to commit to.
For your own safety, please maintain silence.
How are you, Mr. Steve?
Thank you very much.
Alright guys, don't judge. In 2077, even robots need some love.
I hope you could see that. This landed well.
But onwards we march.
Our last principle for today focuses on validating the choices the player made, or rather the
choice the player made.
A perception of uniqueness fulfills the player's desire to have made the right choice while
at the same time heightening the stakes and the excitement of making one.
And for that to work, we need to treat our paths as special
and plan proper payoff for players
and be OK with other players potentially missing out.
This is what creates value in the choices players make.
A choice is not interesting without a proper consequence,
or in this case, payoff.
This goes for narrative choices as much
as for ones done in gameplay, like how
we navigate through a level.
The player did their part. They made the choice.
And now it's on us as designers to make it worth their time and give them a show.
Providing a perception of uniqueness is of course done by making sure we allocate budget
and find affordable solutions to give the players exclusive content.
And this is really where the individual designers and small teams can shine.
And I'm sure many of you have experienced at least one instance where someone kitbashed
a cool experience out of seemingly nothing.
At CDPR, we have so many incredible minds,
especially amongst our quest and open world designers,
who excel at this.
One of those guys is actually Pavel Sasko over there,
our quest director.
Thanks to him and some others,
we can have Nibbles and Iguana as a pet in the game.
Side note, my friend Pavel will be holding a talk tomorrow
that you should definitely check out.
In it, he also outlines how we design
impactful narrative choices for players.
Alright, getting back to providing cool experiences.
We even created a whole type of content in Cyberpunk 2077 we lovingly call Mini World
Stories that gives individual designers the room to mess around and increase the perception
of uniqueness while at the same time breathing more life into our world.
Like the dancing robots.
Or the car bomb encounter for those of you who know it.
As for level designers, in addition to providing cool, unique set pieces and visual storytelling,
perhaps a cool custom encounter, we can also build our locations in a way that we prevent
bottlenecks ending in the same room.
Seeing the exit of another path may remind that it is there and make you wonder, but
it also ultimately tells you that, in the end, all paths lead to Rome.
There's more gain in masking this and hiding away those entrances
to instead keep the player wondering after the fact,
wait, there used to be another path.
I wonder where that went.
As you can see, much like discovery and exploration,
these principles complement and build on each other.
Theory is good, however, but often it
can be hard to imagine how it translates
into practical use cases.
I mentioned at the beginning I wanted to apply
these principles to validate them.
So let's do that.
This is a top-down shot from an experimental blockout
I created for research purposes.
It was created before I started out
on my research and development project, and you can tell.
White paths are the generic play styles.
In the middle, we have the combat one, and above,
in the north, we have the stealth one.
Green paths are play styles, the numbers are entrances to the level, and the letters are
exits or goals leading to a lower floor.
Just as before, blue zones are discovery beats, and orange ones exploration, though, admittedly,
I did not think about them like that at the time of the making of that blockout.
And again, all the symptoms are here.
There's very low payoff for play style paths.
Principle number one, perception of distance, is violated with the playstyle up above, compared to the generic stealth path.
We also violate principle number two, perception of exclusivity.
Starting at entrance number two, players will inevitably see where entrance number one, basically if they hadn't used their skill check, would have started.
Now, equipped with what I had learned, I set out to apply the beats and principles.
The second iteration of this blockout sees a small section added to the bottom right
corner and additional passages down to the lower floor.
But let's get through this step by step.
First, the beat breakdown.
You can see now the distribution between discovery
and exploration is quite a bit more even,
and we have room to provide meaningful rewards.
I added additional ways for the players down to the lower floor
with no direct line of sight to each other,
even leading up to the passages themselves.
At the time the player reaches any of the passages A, B, or C,
they will have been locked into their more linear exploration beat for quite a while,
increasing the perception of exclusivity.
In adding the new section, I tried to enhance the perception of distance of the choices the player has in the discovery beat
by moving the entrances to the exploration beats as far from each other as possible.
I also changed the setup of the paths with the generic path now leading straight through
the middle of the section.
At almost no additional cost, I turned the path going from 1 to B into a playstyle exclusive,
while also providing a playstyle exclusive branch to enter lower floor access C of the
generic stealth path going from 2 to A.
The new section actually looks bigger than it is here.
It's effectively one room and two corridors,
plus the branch, so again, relatively low cost.
Now, let's bring some nuance into this,
since I had this discussion with some of my fellow level designers
after getting feedback from them.
While it's important to make sure vision
doesn't give away how paths work,
we can and should still carefully and consciously work with it
to help the player, of course, build a mental map
and navigate the space better.
In each exploration beat, the player is able to take a peek at the room in the center of this location,
which features a characteristic landmark to help the player understand a bit how they're moving around the location on the path they've picked.
You also have an opportunity to do this when using the hidden passage C.
The vision here provided, however, does not give away how the alternate paths may work.
Finally, let's take a look at the lower floor
to see how the passages enter into that space.
Here, the letters are simply the continuation
of the exits on the floor above.
Notice how none of the paths end in the bottleneck that
is the discovery zone here.
From none of the entrances into the area,
can you actually see any of the other options
the player could have taken?
Now, these were the beats and applying principle number one and principle number two.
What about principle number three, the perception of uniqueness?
Well, with the new section added and the northernmost path being turned into a playstyle path,
I now had the room to enhance the perception of uniqueness.
And let's take a brief tour across the level to see how the location itself tries to give the player unique experiences
and zones to explore, starting with the generic stealth path with the playstyle exclusive branch,
so Entrance 2 to Exit C.
As a player enters this level, they find themselves
in this space over here.
And stealthing past the enemies through the door on the right,
they enter this new room that I added in the second iteration.
Now, it's hard to see here, especially, I
suppose, in this situation.
But there is a hidden passage here
that techies can unlock to reach a hidden underground passage.
And finding that and going through that,
puts you into this situation here, a unique little set piece,
which only those players would be able to find,
that gives more information about the background of what this space could be.
And now, let's take a look at the other PlayStyle exclusive path in comparison.
So, path 1 to exit B.
As those players enter the location, they find themselves in this area over here, where
they actually have the option to look into the room that the other path just stealthed
through.
Moving through a door on the left, they find themselves in the big room with the landmark
I mentioned earlier in, and successfully stealthing through this section on the left side.
They find themselves in this room, where in the background,
there's also a small little window that, again,
looks back into the landmark room.
And stealthing through this, you can make your way down
to the lower floor, where you see this section.
And as you can see, the paths provide
completely different experiences,
each giving their own little slice and impression
on the player, what's going on here.
All right, let's summarize.
I equip you guys with three principles to enhance your nonlinear designs.
Principle number one, distance builds choices,
and you can enhance it by making sure to spread entrances and paths
as far away from each other as possible.
Principle number two, exclusivity heightens wonder,
which you can enhance by limiting the player's vision on other paths
and committing the player to their choice using one-way passages.
Principle number three, fulfills desire,
which you can enhance by reserving and providing
cool content for players and by avoiding
to shatter the illusion for paths leading
to the same outcome by not having them bottleneck
into the same room.
All three of these principles are not restricted to,
but particularly effective at enhancing
the powers of two different level beats designed
to maximize choice and reward.
That is, discovery and exploration.
As always in our design-related disciplines, however,
nothing is always 100% true.
And all these concepts heavily depend
on the context of your game.
Hopefully, this is still useful food for thought for you.
With my research done and principles tested,
I see my quest as updated.
And I'm happy to say that the XP I gained
provided a worthy payoff.
Great quest.
Would play again.
And now.
You know about the benefits of missing out.
I put a lot of heart and effort into bringing you this,
and I hope you found this valuable and fun.
From the bottom of my heart, I want to say thank you.
Thank you.
Thank you for joining me here today.
Doing a thing like this isn't easy.
It's a lot of work, and you know,
there's a lot of imposter syndrome going on
when you try to do this.
However, there's my contacts.
Please feel free to reach out to me.
Also a big shout out to Blake for getting me into this and coaching me.
Thank you so much.
You're awesome.
And thank you to GDC and the Level Design Summit team for inviting me.
I'll be over at the wrap-up area in a moment, ready to answer your questions.
And yeah, see you there.
Thank you.
Also, if you enjoyed this talk, please go check out the ones that my amazing colleagues are about to give.
I'm sure you'll find them insightful as well.
We're here all week, guys!