Good morning and welcome to Marvel's Spider-Man and AI
Postmortem.
My name is Adam Newnchester, and I'm
one of the lead gameplay programmers at Insomniac Games.
Over the past 11 years, I've been
fortunate to work on eight great games at Insomniac.
And for the majority of these, I've been an AI programmer.
On Marvel's Spider-Man, I led the team of gameplay programmers that developed combat.
Let's take a quick look.
My team worked on both stealth and melee combat.
We helped create Spider-Man's combat moves and all of his gadgets.
We also worked on the enemies and bosses,
and I'd like to take this opportunity to tell you about some of the biggest changes and challenges
that we encountered on the AI side developing this game.
So let me give you a quick preview of the topics I'm going to discuss today.
I'll start with some high-level trends related to how we author behaviors and build AI characters.
Then I'll move into how we use synced animations to get a Marvel feel in a game.
From there, I'll give an overview of a few core problems and how we iterated on them with our combat.
After that, we'll look at some procedural animation techniques that we developed specifically for Spider-Man.
And then finally, time permitting, I'll briefly discuss a few of the places where I feel we fell short.
So let's begin with a high-level trend that occurred over the course of development that
I expect to continue, and that is less use of complex behavior trees and more use of
data-driven hierarchical finite state machines.
This happened for several reasons, but the largest was simply that Marvel's Spider-Man
was the largest game that Insomniac Games has made to date.
Spider-Man has five major factions and a few minor ones.
We've also got eight archetypes that are common to all the factions,
and the majority of these archetypes have variations per faction.
There are also several faction-exclusive types and 11 boss fights.
This all meant that we had to create 64 AI classes,
and the majority of these had to have some unique attacks,
reactions, or other behaviors.
We also had to do this with a slightly smaller gameplay team
than our last big game, Sunset Overdrive,
in which we only made 19 classes.
Let me begin by briefly describing how we organize our AI behavior at Insomniac.
We have our own proprietary engine and the vast majority of our code is written in C++.
This is the general architecture that's been in use since about 2012.
From here on, I'm going to also use the term AI and bots interchangeably.
At the top level, we have a behavior tree, and that decides on a behavior to run.
Behaviors can have an arbitrary number of sub-behaviors, but eventually a behavior will instantiate a state.
These are our leaf nodes and they control animation, motion, and perform other player-facing actions.
When we first implemented behavior trees into our Engine,
a lot of them tended to have a structure like this.
This is one corner of the behavior tree
that drove the behavior of ranged enemies
in Sunset Overdrive.
This simple subtree uses 34 discrete nodes,
and many of them just map to a simple AI state,
such as playing an animation,
shuffling around, meleeing, or aiming.
The parameters for the state were largely configured
by the behavior tree and passed through a behavior
that only instantiated a single state.
In order for our AI to function as desired,
things tended to get really complicated.
Nodes often had to utilize numerous kinds
of callback functions.
For example, let's look at a simple node
that is trying to use a state to aim at a target
over a railing.
That node will need to be able to decide if it has to run,
so we have a callback for that.
The bot state that we're using doesn't ever end,
so the tree needs to decide if that state
should continue to run, so we add another callback.
The state we're using also doesn't,
or the behavior tree nodes shouldn't change state
until they are entered,
so since we need to notify another system
when we start aiming over a railing, we add a callback.
The state that we're using doesn't do any weapon management,
so we have a callback to do all of that from the tree,
and we need to notify that same system
when we're done using the railing,
so we add a fifth callback.
Furthermore, in order to get the correct node
to activate at the correct time,
we often needed to consider how a node's parents
selected which of its children to run.
We call that the group policy, and there are three types.
The order of the children could be a priority ranking,
or the order could be a sequence
with each node running one after the other,
or the node whose decider callback
returns the highest value would be the one to run.
And if your behavior tree implementation
is anything like ours, you have plenty of decorators
and flags and other confusing options.
All of this led to trees that worked,
but were complicated and difficult to debug when they broke.
Furthermore, one of the advantages to behavior trees
is that the trees are supposed to be composable
and nodes should be reusable.
We found the opposite to be true when the tree is complicated.
We often needed to think about how both a node's siblings
and its ancestors functioned.
For Marvel's Spider-Man, we recognized that we could not have unique behavior trees or even sub-trees for each of the 50-plus bot classes.
We gradually started moving towards trees that were smaller and more straightforward,
with behaviors that contained a lot of the complexity and logic that was previously entangled in the callback functions.
This meant that we could share structure and behaviors.
Nearly all of our standard enemies use exactly the same behavior tree and set of behaviors.
As a quick example, we have a single node in our behavior tree that handles all of melee combat.
And while the previous subtree that I showed you still exists,
the most complicated chunk of transition logic was moved into a behavior.
So what do we do instead?
As our behaviors became more robust,
we began to data drive more of them.
I want to discuss two of these examples.
The first is a simple behavior that is used
when designers need explicit control over bots.
The second is more complicated
and is used for the majority of our combat.
Both of these behaviors take a piece of polymorphic data
configured in our editor
and transform it into a state or sub behavior.
They do this while encapsulating a large portion of the complicated logic inherent to action game AI.
So rather than have a bunch of behavior tree nodes
that respond to designer scripting,
we made a more data-driven solution.
Let's take a look at the high-level architecture.
Script will begin by creating what we call a bot command,
and these commands go into a bot command queue.
When the queue exists, the behavior tree has a node
which instantiates behavior scripted.
This behavior pulls commands one at a time out of the queue
and uses them to create sub-behaviors or states.
Let's take a look at the individual components starting with our command queue.
All it really does is provide storage for designer commands that a bot is going to execute,
and a simple interface for accessing them.
Next, I want to touch on the bot commands themselves.
The base command itself is really just an interface.
An actual command will use this method
to start whatever behavior or state it needs to
and attach it to the provided parent behavior.
And here's an implementation of that method
in a PlayAnim command.
It sets up some data for a PlayAnim state
and then requests that state to be added
to the provided behavior.
All bot commands follow this format.
They're created by script and added to the bot command queue.
Finally, let's take a quick look
at behavior scripted itself.
If a bot command queue exists and has any commands in it,
the behavior tree will instantiate this behavior.
It has an update function, a consume next command function,
and a handle to access the command queue.
The behavior update is simple.
If the current command is done,
we pop it from the queue and try to consume the next one.
The consumeNextCommand function is also straightforward.
It gets the command queue, checks to see if it has a command.
If there is no command, we're done.
But if there is one, then we tell that command to start
and attach ourselves as the parent behavior.
When the command is done, the previous update function
will just call this function again
and will continue executing commands.
Here's what issuing commands looks like from script.
We first request control of a bot
and tell them to go to a position,
face their target, and play an animation.
And here's what things look like in game.
You can see the bot command queue here.
You can see the bot move to a position,
then face the player,
and then finally play the provided action.
Some of you may be wondering, why don't we data drive more?
And this is an example of why.
There are many times when an AI should not immediately
respond to requests for script control.
They could be jumping through the air.
They could be in a cinematic, playing a hit react animation,
or any number of other things.
Our goal is to data drive the interesting, player-facing
problems, but also handle the difficult, squirrely,
and bug-prone parts reliably in code.
So let me talk about a place where things can get squirrely.
Melee combat in Marvel's Spider-Man is data-driven,
and I want to first give you another overview
of the architecture of this system
before we dive into some of the details.
Let's look at the data first.
At the top level, each bot has a combo config.
That combo config contains a list of combo entries.
Each combo entry contains one or more
combo move containers, and each of these
contains a single combo move base,
and this is the polymorphic data.
All of this data is owned by a component called bot combos.
On the behavior side, we have our behavior tree,
which can instantiate, for example, behavior melee.
When it is time to attack, this behavior will pass data
from bot combos into a behavior use combo,
which will then use that data
to start a sub-behavior or state.
Let's start looking at the bottom of the data.
For the next several slides, I will be showing examples
of structs written in a proprietary C++-like
data definition language.
I'll mark any usage of it with DDL.
All attack actions in combat will ultimately
derive from a bot combo move base.
These structs can represent all of the static data needed to execute, for example, a melee attack.
This combo move has an animation to play, as well as some data describing the timing for the attack.
It could also represent throwing a projectile.
This struct has data for the projectile asset to throw, what animation to use,
where on the bot the shot should spawn, and some additional timing data.
The point is that each of these derived types contain all of the static data needed to start either a behavior or a state to perform the desired attack.
That is to say that these contain the static data to make these.
Let's move one level up the data hierarchy and talk about the move container.
Here's the definition for bot combo move container.
You can see the combo move here at the bottom,
but this struct contains other data.
That data is parameters for defining
how to prepare to execute the move.
These are things like, does the bot need line of sight
with their target to perform the attack?
Does the bot need to be on screen?
Or how close does the bot need to be?
In other words, this, the combo move container,
contains not only the combo move,
but also has data that drives the behavior
of this behavior use combo.
So let's briefly look at it.
It's really just a state machine.
It can choose to wait to perform an attack,
it can go to its target, it can perform a combo move,
and at some point it will end.
It has its own functions for determining what state
it should be in based on the data in the move container.
And it also does things for us like setting
hit react immunities while the attack is active
or starting cool downs at the correct time.
However, the relevant code happens once behavior use combo
has determined that it is in position
and ready to execute an attack.
It calls a transition combo function.
This function takes the move container
and then retrieves some metadata in the container
about the type of combo move that it contains.
If it's a melee move, we prep some state data
and start a melee attack.
Or if it's a throw projectile move,
we prep some different state data
and start a throw projectile state.
In the full version of this function,
this if else cascades for the other 37 combo move types
that we have.
There might be a little bit of cleanup work
for us to do here.
So we've discussed the bottom half of this diagram,
so next we're going to look at the actual
combo entries themselves.
Because behavior use combo may want to perform
more than one move in a sequence,
the combo entry contains a list of them.
to execute one after the other.
It also contains all of the data
for determining when a combo is valid.
For example, a cool down for how often it can be used,
a waiting value to be used
when selecting between valid combos,
a pair of distances that define the range
at which a combo is valid,
as well as a list of other arbitrary data-driven conditions.
The final piece of the data is the combo config.
And this is just a simple struct that contains a list of combos.
Every single one of our AI classes has a unique one of these.
I want to briefly touch on the owner of all of this data, bot combos.
It is responsible for not only owning the combo config, but also for selecting the best
combo to use from that config versus a provided target.
It will use all of the data contained in the combo entries to make a list of valid combos
and return one based on their weights.
Finally, we'll briefly take a look at an example user
of behavior use combo, behavior melee.
It's a fairly standard state machine
that has a bunch of states that it handles
transitioning between in code.
One of them is using a combo.
If it's the bots turn to attack
and bot combos has a valid combo entry,
this behavior will just start using,
this behavior will start behavior use combo.
Here's a brief look at combos in action.
There's some debug display up here.
This character has five combos and active will be drawn
next to each of the combos that he is currently using.
Each of these uses different states
whose static parameters are configured entirely in data.
So that's a high level review of how we data drove two large sections of our AI, melee
combat and script control.
We had two other significant behaviors that were data driven, one for handling hit reacts
and another for responding to incoming attacks by blocking, dodging, counterattacking, etc.
We felt we got a lot of mileage out of working in this paradigm for three main reasons.
The first is that new moves are easy to add,
since you didn't need to change complex transition logic.
The second is that we were able to loosely couple
our states with data.
That is a single bot combo move could potentially map
to multiple states, or multiple moves could map
to the same state if it was appropriate.
And third, this allowed us to pick and choose
what data was presented to the designer
and then handle the messy logic and code.
Working this way allowed us to make a large number of classes
who only differed in data.
That said, there are some definite disadvantages
with our current approach.
Most of these behaviors organically grew into this pattern,
so parts of them can be a little bit of a mess.
You saw an example of this with the giant list of if-elses
in our melee example.
But the real big problem we had for us was that
our tools only allowed us to express the data
in a properties panel, and let me briefly show you
why this is such a problem.
Here's the data definition for
the heavy enemies three-hit combo.
First, we have all of the data for how he can select
to use the move.
Then we have all of the data for how BehaviorUseCombo will prepare to execute the move.
Then we have a bunch of data that every single attack needs so that it can properly register
with SpiderSense.
Then we have the actual data for the melee attack itself.
However, remember that I said this was a three hit combo?
All of this data is repeated twice more.
And it eventually looks like this.
This character also has four more combos,
a shockwave, a grapple, a throw,
and another multi-hit combo.
So yeah, the amount of data needed to be configured
made the system intimidating and difficult to understand.
Improving on this is one of our next big goals.
So let's move on to a section where I can finally start showing a bunch of screenshots and videos.
Synced animations.
Our creative director gave the team a goal
that he wanted Spider-Man to have a comic book movie feel.
Early on in development, we decided that we wanted
a high degree of fidelity in our combat animations
and reactions.
In order to do this, we determined that we would need
to have a system that allowed us to play back
those animations of Spider-Man and his foes interacting.
Our system at its root has the concept of a host,
usually Spider-Man, the attacker,
and a guest, usually his victim.
The whole thing hinges on something we call a sync joint.
It's shown as the white debug sphere in this video.
The sync joint is a joint on the host
which has a position and orientation
that will match that of the guests
when the animations are played back in sync.
We use joint on the attacker because this allows Spider-Man
to perform a synced attack versus a character
that hasn't yet played a synced react.
In this video, you can see both the current position
of the sink joint drawn in front of Spider-Man,
as well as the sink joint's target position
drawn on the enemy.
As the time of impact draws near,
you can see Spider-Man blend into position
to hit his target.
Spider-Man doesn't know if his victim
will play the corresponding sink reaction,
or if he will block, dodge, or play some non-sink reaction.
We actually support several different options
for how Spider-Man accomplishes this blending.
These can be selected independently
for rotation and translation.
The most common case for lining up orientation is called host to guest or center line.
In this case, both the host and the guest rotate to face each other along a line drawn
between them.
We also have support for only using the host orientation or only using the guests.
Neither of these modes are actually used in the shipping game.
The other kind of rotation alignment we use is what we call an external anchor.
This is when another piece of code sets the target orientation for the system.
In this video, when you see debug draw on screen, both characters are rotating towards
the external actor orientation.
We use this here because the player is able to push in any direction on the movement stick
while executing this kick throw and the enemy will be thrown in that direction.
So that is, the direction is set as the sync animation system's
rotational alignment target.
For translation alignment, we have two common options.
The first is when the guest moves into position.
This is called host as anchor, and it
is used in situations like this where
Spider-Man is unable to move.
You'll be able to see the sync joint here on Spider-Man,
and then you can notice the enemy move to it.
The other kind of alignment is when Spider-Man performs all of the translation himself.
This is called guest as anchor and is the translation alignment technique for the vast
majority of attacks since Spider-Man is the one moving into position.
There is an external anchor option for translational alignment similar to rotation, however, it
isn't actually used in the shipping game.
A problem that frequently came up for us
was that the attacker and the victim
could be at heights different
from how they were animated or mocapped.
We have a few strategies for how we handle this.
All synced attacks have an annotated sync point
and a release point.
For stealth takedowns and combat finishers
that use animated cameras,
we can hide floating characters by pulling the camera in
before we reach the sync point
and waiting until after the release point
to push it back out.
In other cases, we can make use of webbing
to handle the fact that the characters
aren't at matching heights.
In this case, the webs are animated
and then we procedurally alter them joint by joint
so that they match where their final transforms would be
if our sync joint was properly aligned.
Another thing that helps with certain situations
is that our character movement system remains active.
If one member of the synced animation
begins to collide with something,
they can pass the translation they failed to move
over to the other participant.
In this case, Spider-Man begins to hit the step,
is unable to fully align with his target,
and when this happens, the enemy then applies
the reverse of that and slides backwards,
and the two manage to sync up.
However, we can't always fix things up,
and in many cases, we just deal with things being off.
This is what happens for most regular melee attacks
as well as a few finishers.
Enemies can use the system to play synced attack animations versus Spider-Man as well.
However, we found that the synced alignment options usually felt unfair.
The more common use of synced attacks was for an enemy to use a non-synced attack and
then if it connected to immediately start a synced reaction animation.
There are two big drawbacks to our synced animation system.
The first is that it only supports two characters,
a host and a guest.
One of the most requested features
towards the end of development was finishers
that allowed Spider-Man to take down
multiple foes at the same time.
I do want to point out a more general drawback to using synced animations is that it quickly
becomes very time consuming to add new attacks or skeletons to your game.
You usually have to make an attack animation and a react animation for every victim skeleton.
How we make use of the sync joint allows us to mitigate this if we want to, but fidelity
will suffer.
We had a goal of combat for Spider-Man that was fast, fluid, and dynamic.
On the combat team, we frequently talked about play style, flow, and improvisation
as being very important things to us.
Having enemies that felt dangerous but gave the player opportunities to flow
was going to be the linchpin to our combat.
The topics I'm going to discuss today are probably very familiar to many of you.
However, as programmers, we often want to create a system,
verify that it's working as designed, and then move on.
And this is not how you make good games.
I want to share with you some examples of the iterations
we went through to get our combat fundamentals right.
We needed to manage attacks and mitigate cheap hits,
or else the game was gonna turn into this.
We have two combat managers that control when ranged
and melee enemies are able to attack,
and they occasionally coordinate with each other,
but they mostly operate independently.
You'll hear me say the word job a lot in this section.
In this case, the job is just a token
that allows a bot to attack Spider-Man.
Our manager for Melee started out simple.
We wanted there to be one attack job
unless the player had recently dodged
and then we wanted to give him a quick break to fight back.
We had a simple scheme,
deciding which bot received the attack job.
We calculated a priority that was the sum
of the time the bot had spent waiting for a job,
plus how close that bot was to his ideal attack range,
plus a bonus value for high-priority mini-boss-style enemies.
Here's what that system looks like in action.
There's a blue line drawn from the enemy
who has the attack job to Spider-Man.
In the top left corner, you can see an idle timer.
When I dodge, that timer becomes non-zero.
This gives me a momentary chance to attack.
This works all right,
but there are still a number of issues.
The first is that I don't get attacked
nearly as aggressively as the timer says I should.
Here's why.
The enemy that has been given the attack job
is too far away to quickly execute it.
Now I do want to emphasize that players weren't actually doing this, but due to Spider-Man's
agility, this kind of situation could arise naturally as they bounced back and forth between
enemies.
we implemented two solutions.
The first was that if there was a bot
that could immediately start an attack
and a bot who had been chasing their target for too long,
we'd allow the job to be stolen
by the bot who was ready to attack.
The second thing we added was the ability
for the manager to occasionally create an attack job
if the player stood too close to a bot
for more than a split second.
Here's what it looks like with those features enabled.
You'll see that as I run past enemies,
the blue line shifts to me.
shifts to a nearby enemy and they quickly try to attack me.
The two concepts of job stealing and proximity attacks
were critical for addressing times
when our combat would suddenly feel dead.
Then we noticed that things started to feel
too predictable in protracted encounters.
So we added an intensity meter.
This meter fills as the enemies attack
and is spent by the manager to either
simultaneously give out a few attack jobs
or rapidly give them out in sequence.
Here's what that looks like in action.
You can see the current intensity value here,
and below that you can see how much we need to accrue
in order to perform the next special attack.
You can see up here what the next special attack type is,
and then you can see the jobs as they are
given out down here.
So let's talk about ranged combat.
It also started out simple.
There was going to be a cool down window
where no shooters could receive attack jobs,
followed by an attack window
where shooters could receive attack jobs.
During the attack window,
we had a maximum number of simultaneous attack jobs,
and there was a delay that prevented the manager
from giving out jobs too rapidly.
Here's what that looks like.
Up at the top, you can see the manager switch back and forth
between cool down and active.
And then you can see the status of the jobs here.
For this case, I've restricted the manager
from giving out more than one job.
This kept things from being completely crazy,
but there are still a lot of places
where things felt unfair.
And the biggest was being shot from off screen.
So we started by saying we're gonna prioritize
giving jobs only to on-screen bots as we can.
You can see that in action here.
You'll notice that as enemies leave the edge of the screen,
that they stop being selected as attackers.
However, there were still times
when all valid shooters were off-screen.
So we made enemies take longer to fire
when they are off-screen.
This gives the player more time to notice
the spider sense warning.
In this video, you can see that when enemies are off screen,
it lasts for 1.5 seconds.
When they are on screen,
the warning only lasts for 0.75 seconds.
By now, things were starting to feel decent
when fighting only shooter enemies,
but things could still be overwhelming
when enemies that used melee were present.
So, we allowed design to specify
an entirely new set of values if melee enemies were present.
If you look here, you can see that not only is the active time slightly shorter, but the
cool down period is nearly doubled.
This felt pretty good, until the players started using air combat.
Then with the slower timing values, it felt like enemies became unresponsive for nearly
five seconds at a time.
We tried disabling the second set of values when the player was in the air, but players
then felt like they were being punished for using air combat, which was not what we wanted.
So we added something that we called air aggression.
Here it is in action.
Once the player performs enough actions in the air,
you can see the air aggression chance change from 0 to 0.5.
This means that for each additional action
the player performs while in the air,
there is a 50% chance that the manager will immediately
exit cooldown.
When that happens, you'll see air aggression active here.
Even after all of this iteration, players still felt that there were times when being
attacked was cheap.
So we made a list.
Performing any action from this list would cause the managers to cancel all attack jobs
that hadn't actually started the attack.
Web throwing an environmental interactable.
Web striking a new target.
Using an air launcher on a target.
Dodging an attack.
Perfect dodging an attack.
Using a finisher.
Jumping off an enemy.
Jumping.
Landing.
Being hit.
And so in all of these cases, we cancel incoming attacks.
Unless you abuse the action repeatedly,
and then we'd allow the attack jobs to persist.
unless that action was a dodge, in which case
we'd still cancel the jobs, unless it was a boss fight,
and then the jobs wouldn't be canceled.
And that still wasn't enough.
Players still felt that there were times
that enemies would knock Spider-Man out of an attack
in a way that felt cheap.
This is the specific case that was
causing a lot of frustration.
Players would properly identify an attacking enemy,
and then they'd try to attack that enemy to interrupt them.
But because of animation timing, they'd get hit.
We created a system we called Beat to the Punch,
which guarantees that Spider-Man will win these interactions.
When the red sphere is visible, the system is active.
Beat to the Punch activates as Spider-Man's attacks
get close to the impact frame.
While active, we examine each incoming attack
and see if Spider-Man's attack would force a reaction.
If it would, then Spider-Man is granted immunity
from that enemy's attack
until he's past his own impact frame.
You can see it in action here.
And as you can see, the system will ensure that in cases where Spider-Man and an enemy
are attacking each other at the same time, Spider-Man beats the enemy to the punch.
This simple system was the last thing that we needed to clear up the vast majority of
our remaining complaints about cheap hits.
So let's move on to every AI programmer's
other favorite problem, positioning.
We've made a lot of shooters at Insomniac
and how our AI decided where they would move to
was based on the needs of that genre.
We annotated positions for bots to fight from
using fire points and we marked large pieces of occlusion
by wrapping them in volumes.
This allowed our ranged enemies to take up positions in cover or at places that are interesting.
Furthermore, melee enemies in a shooter typically just try to get close to the player and attack as often as possible,
and managing the horde and the space is part of the gameplay.
In Spider-Man, we wanted the player to fight a large crowd of enemies, but we didn't want
them to feel like they were continuously being mobbed.
Nor did we want to limit our combat just to large arenas.
We also wanted the more interesting AI classes to be in position to attack more.
And we needed to do all of this while looking good.
We started by using a fight circle like this.
We divide the area around the player into wedges,
and then we'd repeat with more wedges
for additional rings as needed.
We'd do some nav tests to see that each wedge is on nav,
and then we'd assign each enemy
to the wedge he was closest to.
This didn't work for two main reasons.
The first is easily visible in this video.
Simply moving around the space
could easily cause the wedges to become invalid.
This led to enemies frequently repositioning
when there wasn't a clear reason to the player
why they should do so.
The other reason why this failed
was because it tended to look very robotic and choreographed.
We tried adding in some random variation,
but we were never able to get it to feel good.
I'm gonna quickly diagram our solution.
Let's say we have an enemy standing here, who is engaged with Spider-Man standing here.
Then suppose there are some enemies here, and let's pretend like each bot and Spider-Man
have kind of a little circle around them that is their personal space.
We call these bot reservations.
Finally, the edges of navmesh are here.
Our goal is to find the best position for our bot to stand that is outside of all this
red.
We did this with a simple algorithm for finding local minima, a gradient descent hill climber.
This algorithm will iteratively follow the gradient of steepest descent in order to minimize an energy function.
In our case, energy will increase as we move towards the center of the circle and as we move off of navmesh.
It will be zero everywhere else.
Another way to look at this is that we will iteratively
push points that lie in one of the circles
radially out of the circles, like so,
and those points that are off nav
will be pushed back towards nav, like so.
In our game, each of our bots will actually feed five positions through the hill climber.
His current position, and then based on a line from the bot to his target and an ideal
distance we can compute a position in front and a position behind the target.
Then a line segment perpendicular to the first segment is used to select a position to the
left and a position to the right.
Here's how the hill climber would modify these positions.
For the one at the bot's current position,
it will do nothing but already outside of the circles
and inside NavMesh.
For the two lower points, they each lay in a circle,
so we'll just push them radially out of the circle.
For the point on the far right,
we'll push it back towards NavMesh, like so.
The last point lies between two circles. We'll try to simultaneously push it out of both
by adding these two vectors together to get this. However, because that won't work,
we'll need to iterate a couple times and get to our final position.
So at the end we wind up with five potential positions
for an enemy to choose between.
And here's what that looks like in game.
This video is showing the results
of this enemy's hill climber.
Our bot reservations are shown in red,
and the results of the hill climber
are shown as trails of little blue spheres.
We capped the number of iterations
the hill climber can perform at 30.
We did try using more complicated algorithms
like simulated annealing, but we didn't find them
to be of any qualitative benefit.
Once we've generated those five positions,
the hill climber creates a score for each
based on the distance to our current position
and the distance to our target.
We then apply additional penalties
if that point is too close to the target,
too far from the target,
or if moving there from our current position
would likely cause us to cross too close to our target.
We then pick the position with the smallest score.
This worked pretty well for small to medium sized encounters.
However, in large encounters, we noticed that standard melee enemies
could prevent the more interesting classes
from being able to get close to the player.
This was particularly evident if those classes appeared in a backup wave.
So we partially resurrected the concept of a fight circle.
However, this time, instead of giving out positions, we handed out distances.
These distances are used to compute the initial positions
that were fed into the hill climber.
This lets us bias those more important enemies without blowing up the algorithm.
In our game, there's just two rings.
An inner, high-priority ring in which about six guys can stand,
and an outer, low-priority ring where everyone else gets assigned.
In frantic combat though, we still had issues
with enemies repositioning when it felt unnatural.
So we added a final check at the behavior level.
First, we'd check that we aren't already too close
to our new position.
If that check succeeded, we'd compute the distance
to our ideal attack position, then compute the distance
between the new position and the attack position.
Subtracting these values tells us how much repositioning
will improve our current situation.
Based on if we would be moving forward or backwards,
we compare that value with different thresholds
to determine if we should move.
Those threshold values change over time
so that a character who has been stationary for a long time
is more likely to move.
We also have a similar scheme for deciding if an AI should
update their weight position while in motion.
We compute the distance to our current position.
We compute the distance to our new position.
We then compute the distance from our current to our new.
And all of these must be larger than a threshold value
in order for us to update the destination.
Let's move on to a few uses of procedural animation
in Marvel's Spider-Man.
We wanted Spider-Man to be able to use his webs
to stick guys to surfaces.
Unfortunately, we have a lot of uneven and weird surfaces,
and the AI may be in an unexpected pose because of Ragdoll.
We couldn't just naively spawn a model or a decal.
Everything starts with the game
generating an ideal world space orientation,
and then passing that into something we call a web blanket.
The blanket itself is a model of a web
with a six by six lattice of joints.
You can see it here fully extended and locked in place.
When spawned, the blanket will project rays
from a position above the initial position
through the position of each joint on the model
if the model was naively placed at the initial position.
Where that ray hits is where the joint will be attached.
In this video, the raycasts are shown in orange.
If you look closely, you can see that the blanket
is compact when it's first spawned,
and then each of the joints interpolates
into the position found by its corresponding raycast.
If a raycast doesn't hit anything, we rotate that ray towards the blanket's initial point.
This will usually cause the blanket to wrap around whatever it is attaching to.
Additionally, joints are allowed to re-scan for a period of time before they lock in place.
This allows the blanket to adapt to a settling ragdoll or animating character without bunching
up on itself.
We have another case where we allow joints to rescan,
and that is if the thing they are attached to
moves too far from the blanket's initial position.
This prevents the blanket from being
stretched across the entire level
as the door is torn off here.
We planned to have several enemies able to use whip style weapons versus Spider-Man.
Unfortunately, we found that a regular cloth sim didn't give us the results we wanted.
We also couldn't just animate the whips because we needed to be able to reuse animations from other classes.
This was especially important for locomotion and hit react animations because they're so numerous.
We needed a procedural solution that could be fully animation controlled when necessary.
The whips are part of the base model
and they look like this in any animation
in which they haven't actually been animated.
When the sim is fully engaged, things look like this.
For each joint in the chain,
we will track its position from frame to frame
and then we'll naively apply the host motion
to each of those joints.
Then we begin to apply constraints.
We apply a distance constraint to correct for this.
The constraint uses a 0 to 1 stiffness parameter and is performed in two passes, forwards down
the chain and then backwards up it.
We perform half of the error correction on each pass.
Without a curvature constraint, the chain falls through Tombstone's hand,
even though the chain's root is oriented horizontally.
The first pass keeps each child joint aligned with its parent.
The second curvature pass constrains each joint to both its parent and its child.
This prevents kinks in the chain.
The curvature pass was extremely important for making sure that the simmed joints
blended smoothly out of the animated ones.
Here you can see Tombstone walking normally.
We apply a gravity constraint to keep the chain
from floating, and we apply a ground constraint
to keep it from sinking through the floor like it is here.
This character, or this constraint,
uses the normal of the ground that the character
is standing on, which we assume just defines a flat plane.
The final constraint ensures that each of the joints
is outside of the character's move capsule.
Without it, you can see the whip clipping through his legs.
But with it, you can see that the chain
will move around his body.
The actual order that we apply constraints is
gravity, then curvature, then movePill,
then distance, then ground.
Then we iterate over all of those up to eight times
depending on how close the character is to the camera.
For controlling if the chain is driven by animation or the sim, we start by assuming
that it is always simulated.
Then we place events on animation clips when the chain is supposed to transition to being
animated and then again when it transitions back to being simmed.
These events just contain a blend speed.
That speed is used to change a 0 to 1 value that represents what percent of the chain
is simmed.
No joint is ever driven by both sim and animation.
We had planned to give a lot more control to animation,
but we found that we got very good results with just this,
and that more wasn't necessary.
One of our main goals for this enemy class
was to either hold Spider-Man in place
or pull him out of the air.
Therefore, we needed to be able to blend the whip during his
attack animations to arbitrary world space positions
and have them look good.
For each joint in the whip, we compute where it would be
if the enemy was perfectly aligned with their target.
The difference between these two positions is the error.
We then apply a portion of that error
to take the animated joint
to its procedurally aligned position.
The portion of that error we apply increases linearly
as we move down the chain.
And here's what that looks like in action.
This procedural alignment is controlled with four events.
We start blending on, finish blending on,
we start blending off, and we finish blending off.
For the last section, I'd like to briefly talk about
some of the things that gave us a lot of trouble.
We didn't have a lot of time to spend on developing tech
for flying enemies, and this really hurt us
when it came time to develop the Sable Jetpack Troopers
and our two flying bosses, Electro and Vulture.
We wound up having the jetpack troopers just hover over nav.
We then gave them the ability to go off nav
if they could see their destination.
While off nav, they kept a list of points
that would allow them to breadcrumb their way back.
However, even with both of these,
there are still times when you can see them
steering around stuff at ground level.
And here's an example of how that happened.
This jetpacker wants to go to Spider-Man.
The red capsule indicates the physics query
he performed to see if he could fly directly to him.
However, because it clips the wall,
he's gonna have to follow this path,
this blue path along the ground until he,
around the fence until he can actually see Spider-Man.
Oops.
For our flying boss enemies, Electro and Vulture,
they used a collection of volumes
that were linked by splines.
Inside the volumes, the characters could move freely
and they could use the splines
to transfer between the volumes.
However, all of these had to be hand-authored
so it was not a usable solution for the whole game.
Both of these solutions got our game shipped,
but I hope you can see why they're far from ideal.
We had one mission that had a lot of combat
on top of a moving truck,
and it was a never-ending source of pain.
Our nav mesh currently can't move,
and so we had to make the space as simple as possible
so that Botch could reliably straight line to Spider-Man.
Additionally, many states and components
did their calculations in world space,
and this would cause bugs when positions
wouldn't line up from frame to frame.
Furthermore, our engine does not support attachment
as well as something like Unity or Unreal,
and so we had to use specific components
to manually update all of the attached entities.
The final problem we had was with enemies or the player
that got thrown off the truck
being shoved through geometry by the truck
if they were standing next to it.
We solved this by placing kill volumes
along the side of the truck as it moves.
NavMesh was another challenge that we underestimated.
We did get some new features for this project,
such as the ability to perform dynamic cutouts from Nav,
and this was instrumental in getting part cards
and many crimes functional.
However, there was a creative push
to change Manhattan with the story.
As things got worse for Spider-Man,
we wanted to reflect that in the world.
Sable International would set up checkpoints,
prisoners, escaped prisoners would erect bases
across the island, and garbage and debris
would begin to pile up as things went from bad to worse.
Our nav mesh is built and loaded on a per tile basis.
We did not have the time to rework this
because we would have needed the ability
to load different meshes based on various game state,
and we'd need the ability to express
all of that state at build time.
We evaluated generating navmesh at runtime,
but we found the CPU performance to be a non-starter.
Our solution was to generate nav in its most complicated state
and then try and just disable parts of it from script.
Here's an example space.
This is what it looks like during Act 1
when things are normal.
You can see patches of navmesh floating in the air.
And the yellow patches you can see
are places where the designer is going
to try and toggle the mesh on and off from script.
You'll also be able to see holes cut in the mesh
by objects that will be present in Act 3,
but are not currently present now.
And here's what it looks like in Act 3
once the base is actually active.
While this scheme worked well enough for us
to make the base, it was oftentimes buggy enough
that we had to remove crimes or other open world activities
from happening in a space like this during Act 1 and 2.
I'm sure it's a big surprise to most of you,
but we actually had performance problems
running all of our complex AI in an open world.
We ultimately had a limit of around 30 enemies
active and engaged once you factored in
Spider-Man traffic and all the pedestrians.
We typically saw two large reasons for this.
The first is physics.
Here's a typical frame where things have gotten bad.
And I'm gonna highlight the parts of the frame
where physics creeps up as the bot count rises.
Here it is on the main thread,
and then here it is on two of our four worker threads.
It's many, many milliseconds spread out over all the cores.
And while it isn't all directly resulting from bots,
it does grow proportionally as the bot count rises.
The other thing is that a lot of our core AI logic still runs on the main thread.
Here's a capture of our main thread during a normal frame.
The highlighted sections are bot-specific logic,
and they are consuming well over 4 milliseconds of time.
There's even more time when you consider that neither the character move system
nor the animation system are included here.
All right, I hope that you've learned a few things today
and I'd like to leave you with a few high-level thoughts.
The first is that iteration is king.
I hope it's obvious, but it took quite a few tries
to get the things that you've seen in this presentation
to where they are now.
We almost never got things right on the first try
and that was okay because we kept pushing.
With Marvel's Spider-Man, we had to pivot from making shooters to making character action
games.
When your problem fundamentally changes like that, you need a fundamental change in your
solutions.
I know it sounds obvious when I say it like that, but it's actually harder than it sounds.
In just this talk, we've seen how this affected behavior authoring, positioning, and combat
management.
And there were many, many others.
Finally, focus on your game's core.
I believe that Marvel's Spider-Man was a success because everybody mentions how the game makes
you feel like Spider-Man.
And this wasn't an accident.
This happened because we took the time to get our fundamentals right.
Be these player controls, attack pacing, enemy hit reacts, or just the feel of using your
web shooters.
You'll get the best game when you focus on your core first.
Real quick, I'd like to thank a few people
that helped me put this presentation together,
Alicia Lidecker, Andrew Richter, Brad Fitzgerald,
David Kim, Ilan Ruskin, Seth England, Sean McCabe,
as well as a very big thank you to everyone
at Insomniac Games, Marvel, and Sony.
I'd like to remind you all to please fill out
your speaker evaluations and thank you for listening.
And if there are any questions,
I think we've got two mics set up here.
Hi, this game was ridiculously awesome, so good work on that.
Thank you very much.
And so one thing I'm struggling with a lot in my game,
and I'm one of the people who like to torture myself
and played it on hard mode the first time.
So what sort of parameters do you
have to change the difficulty level in hard and normal mode?
So if you remember, I pointed, we had the whole section on timings, that all of those timings can be changed per difficulty level, per faction, and per act of the story.
So the rate at which enemies attack, the amount of time that the game gives you in between successful dodges, all of that changes.
Additionally, we would usually go through on a per enemy to enemy...
basis and identify one or two parameters
that we could tune to make things much more difficult.
An example of this would be ranged enemies
tend to fire in like a five to seven round burst.
And on easy, they will deliberately miss
with like the first six of those.
And then on hard, they'll only deliberately miss
with the first two or three.
So it kind of further requires the player
to react a little bit faster.
Cool, thanks.
You're welcome.
Hi, great presentation.
Thank you.
So, during when you're playing the game,
there are different factions that come across each other.
So, how is the AI set up for that?
And how do different factions react when Spiderman jumps into play?
So...
We have a kind of aggro-based targeting solution
for how enemies choose which targets to attack.
Like, usually in a multi-faction fight,
one set of enemies is aware of the other set of enemies
as potential targets and Spider-Man.
And then there are rules based on how close Spider-Man is
to the target versus how close other targets are
that cause what we call a proximity aggro amount
to increase.
And then every time...
those enemies take damage from another target,
that also adds additional aggro on top of that.
And whoever has the highest aggro is a bot's target.
Thanks.
You're welcome.
Hi.
Hello.
So what exactly was the moment when you guys realized
that the system you had for Sunset Overdrive
and Ratcheting Flank and such wasn't going to work?
It was probably about a year and a half into production
as we were finishing pre-production
and looked at how many enemy classes we had made
and how many enemy classes we still needed to make.
We were like, well, we've made about four.
We've got somewhere in the realm of 60 to go.
We need to pick up the pace.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Hi.
Similar to her question, how do you
know when you need to design a more complex system?
You were talking a lot about the model and data architecture
that you guys had created.
And how do you know that you needed
to iterate from the previous one and get to there?
And then how do you know when you got there
that that would be good enough to not
need to iterate further to even potentially better architecture?
Honestly, trial and error.
It kind of happened because we would be getting feedback
from our design team about, hey, we want to be able to do x, y,
and z.
And they would constantly come back
to us wanting to say things like, hey,
can you move this attack from this character
to this other character?
Or can we have them play this animation instead?
Or can they select between all of these things?
And just looking at, OK, the kind of requests
that we're getting are this.
Therefore, we could figure out a way to do all of that in data
so it's as quick as possible to do the iteration that they're
asking us to do.
And when we got to the point that, OK, we're actually
able to handle 75%, 80% of the stuff
that design is asking us for, that's around where we stopped.
Thank you.
How are we on time?
Hi, really awesome talk, thank you.
Thank you.
I'm wondering what would you say is the difference
between like those systemic enemies in the world
and between them and the boss fights that you guys made?
It's like, are the boss fights are mainly
like heavily scripted, authored, or like a mix?
The boss fights still use the kind of combo systems
that we have.
They typically have, so we had 39 combo moves
and probably about half of those are for regular combat
and the other half are boss-specific attacks.
And bosses usually had their own engaged behaviors.
So we talked about behavior melee,
which is what the normal enemies use.
Most of the bosses would have their own
engaged behavior, like Rhino had his own and Scorpion had his own, which kind of described
how they would move about the environment, but then whenever they got into position to use an
attack, they would reuse the kind of combo stuff that was driven by a designer to say,
you know, do a charge or throw something or jump to another position. Thank you. You're welcome.
How do you divide the work between your designers
and your programmers?
Do the designers work in behavior trees
or in the finite state machines or just in data?
They just work with data.
Our designers don't work with behavior trees
or finite state machines.