Hi everyone, welcome to the GDC Twitch channel.
My name is Brian Francis, I am the invisible voice inside your head.
I am here as always checking out interesting games and talking with the folks who worked
on them.
For those who are not familiar with the GDC Twitch channel, welcome.
This is the place.
We are tied to Game Developers Conference.
Like I said just a second ago, we try to take this opportunity to check out new and interesting
games that are on the market, talk to the people who made them, and hopefully answer
some questions for folks in chat.
who are curious about how they got made.
In the lower left-hand corner of the screen,
I am joined by Bert Beekman of Forgotten Empire.
Bert, how are you doing?
Doing well, thanks, Brian. Thanks for having me.
Awesome. And the game we are playing today, in case you haven't figured it out already, is Age of Empires II Definitive Edition.
You might say, Bryant, this isn't a new game, this is a very old game. This is from 1999.
And I would go, you're right, but earlier this year, the folks at Forgotten Empire and Microsoft worked together to put out a definitive edition for Age of Empires II.
That includes content from the original game, content from the expansion Age of Conquerors,
content from the HD edition, and a new expansion, I think, for this game?
That's what you mentioned earlier, Bert?
Yes, indeed.
Actually, I think there's five expansions currently packed into this one, alongside
the previous game.
So yeah, pretty exciting.
Yeah, this makes it wild because it means Age of Empires 2 has sort of been in development
for over two decades that means? 2019?
2000? Yeah, like two.
It's been 20 years of Age of Empires 2.
I picked the Saladin campaign to do a brief mission in because this is one of the first campaigns.
One of my favorite things about Age of Empires 2 as a game when I was a kid was this game got me through history class, it got me through a bunch of things that I would have otherwise thought were boring because I could play it in this game, Age of Empires.
Um, Bert, I guess I should be asking, did you have a similar experience with Age of Empires back in the 90s, and how did you and your team get started on working with Microsoft on this?
Those two questions aren't linked. I'm sorry, but I'm just trying to make a segue happen.
Well, they are actually kind of linked, because a lot of the people on the team at Forgotten Empires are actually long-time fans of the game we played.
It applies to most of us as kids, we kind of grew up with it, and then we all kind of came back at the same time and formed this team.
Now, how we kind of got involved with Age of Empires 2 is that we all started actually
modding the game.
I think that was in 2011, 2012, around that time period.
And we started looking at Age of Empires 2 at the time.
There was no active development on the game.
We kind of were like, okay, this is very interesting.
There's all kinds of people who played the game when they were kids.
Now they're coming back to this game and developing all kinds of modding tools.
Hey, we want to make something cool with that.
So we started to look into what are the possibilities,
and there was one thing that was not done at that point,
which was adding new civilizations to the game.
So we, you know, fiddled around a bit,
and then after some time we managed to add a new civilization to the game.
And we were like, okay, we can make a new expansion or something.
Adding new civilizations was never done at that point,
as a mod. So yeah, we made a mod.
It was all good, we brought it out, we put it on our website.
We put it on our website at Christmas Eve, which in hindsight was a terrible idea.
But at the time we thought, okay, that's great, because we're going to give the fans and people who are looking forward to this mod a nice Christmas present.
And we were like, yeah, we're going to have, let's say...
20,000 downloads in lifetime downloads, that would be great
The problem was with 20,000 downloads in I think the first hour
Website went down. It was Christmas Eve as I said before so yeah, nobody was around to help us there
so yeah all in all very very
weird and hectic launch of the mods, but eventually the mod got really popular and I think we have like a lifetime
amount of downloads of
1 million downloads I believe, which was way more than we ever dreamt of.
And at the same time, Microsoft was also looking at HD edition.
So we reached out to Microsoft and we were like, hey, you guys are showing interest again in the franchise, in the series.
And we just made this mod that really did well.
Is there some way that we can cooperate? And we did.
We started to work on more expansions for the HD edition at the time and then we started to work on the Definitive Edition as well.
So yeah, we really grew.
Own each of empires and basically builds your under the swamp right on apologies for folks in jet. I
Have something of a cold so I'm trying to muscle through today's stream
I was gonna try I'm trying to catch my coughing and keep it off mic, but apologies if I'm coughing in your ear
Um quick shout out for folks in chat. We are going to take questions
So if you're someone like aqua lute, telanus lurker sauce or robo borrow, um, we would love to hear from you
We'd love to know what questions you have
for Bert and if you'd like to know
more about how this game got made. Bert, my first question for you then
sort of talking about the transition, diving into that transition from modders to
full-time game developers
how did that transition itself happen once you guys started talking to
Microsoft like when did you and your friends sort of go from becoming
a group of modders to becoming like professional developers with what I
assume is an office and a studio
and what was that process like
It's been a very gradual process.
Because we have been working on those expansions for quite some time,
it really allowed us to grow slowly and at our own pace.
So it was not like, OK, we're now hired, we now need to start a studio,
we need to get people together, all in a matter of months or weeks.
No, we literally have years.
to slowly build up and that was actually really good because we uh Age of Empires is a slow game
but we as a studio also like to take it at a relatively easy going in a way like we don't
want to take crazy risks or do crazy things but you know take it take it gently and that really
allowed us to make intelligent decisions and in growing as a studio. Now the thing is we were
actually a virtual studio
We do have some smaller local presences, but overall most of the people are working from home or working from shared offices.
So that's kind of how we're still doing it at this point.
Oh nice, I should have. And then it's actually Lurkersauce brought that up in chat.
Right on, well just to talk about diving into the Definitive Edition, you already worked on an HD edition.
And obviously I know that there's a definitive edition for Age of Empires I and Age of Empires II.
What did you see as the temples for a definitive edition?
What it would need to entail?
What were the project goals of that that separated it from the prior HD edition you've done?
So back in the day if you look at the HD edition the main goal of that was okay
Let's bring Age of Empires 2 back to the players. There were a lot of people who have not played
I mean who still has a CD player in their laptop, for example
Those are all things that you know people like H2
But they had no idea how to play it and that was kind of the goal of the HD edition
To bring it back to the players
And it kind of grew on that, like we brought more content because there was clearly a very strong demand from the community, like, hey, we want more, H2, we definitely want more.
But then when the definitive editions were made, it was more than, okay, let's just bring back H2, let's...
Actually, the whole project goal from within Microsoft and from us as well was,
okay, we need to make the best H2 possible.
That was the intent here.
So it was a very, very different approach.
Instead of just bringing it back, it was like, okay,
let's make sure that everything we have at this point is further improved
and is the best possible thing that we can make.
That's really the big difference and it can kind of manifest itself in many ways as well.
If you look at the graphics, if you put them side by side, you can really see, okay, this
was the 90s and this is no longer the 90s.
You just see it on screen here as well, like buildings now beautifully collapse and crumbling
down or we have the, how do you call that, the...
smoke that comes out of the barrel of the cannon as it fires a cannonball.
Those are all like little details that were not in the original game.
And that really, yeah, make it look a lot prettier.
With that said, like literally every asset in the game has been remade.
Which was not the case in the HD edition. In the HD edition all the graphics were the original graphics.
But the resolution was just scaled up so your viewport was like bigger, larger, but it was still the same sprites.
And now you have much higher quality sprites as well.
Man, the...
What was the process of remaking an entire game's worth of assets for you and your team?
Especially for like a remote work from home team.
Like, I assume...
I assume for not a large amount of people that was a lot of work.
Yes, so this is where we also had the chance to work together with other studios.
The art oversight and art direction, that's something that we all did in-house,
that was all done by F.E., in cooperation with Microsoft,
but a lot of the assets work was luckily done by a partner studio that helped us out.
Now, with that set, it was still a crazy amount of work.
When we started this and we made the list of assets that we actually had to remake,
it was like, okay, this is not just one game we're remaking, this is six games worth of
assets that we're making, which is an insane amount.
And it also took ages to actually review all those.
And also, actually, we didn't have any of the original assets.
Those were all lost.
So literally, we had no choice but to make everything from scratch.
But other than that it was just...
Yeah, two things that were on our side.
One thing was definitely that we have the original art.
And one of the things that we really wanted to stick to was...
Okay, if people have been recognizing this specific unit as being a camel,
as you can see on the screen now,
these camels,
we want to make sure that somebody still recognizes that unit as a camel 20 years later.
So we didn't really have to go around and redesign all of this.
It was more like, okay, we kind of have it here.
It might only be 100 pixels high.
Now it's like, I don't know, four times the fidelity.
We need to imagine what all those pixels in between look like.
But as an overall view, you kind of know what units are going to look like.
And that really helped in speeding up that process.
It helped us, you know, stick to the original design
and, yeah, try to just bring that back.
as good as possible.
Right on, um...
Oh no, go on, go on.
No, I actually forgot my train of thought there, so sorry.
It's okay, um, yeah, um...
Uh, from that point on, moving on from the individual assets,
I guess my next question would be...
Um...
Uh, it would be foolish of me to say that you could just
copy and paste the original code from the game,
the original, like, programming and logic, to make it work one-to-one.
in your new software. What was the process for
rebuilding the scripting and the sort of
like the AI, like a lot of the logic that made Age of Empires
what it was?
Well, I don't know how technical I can get here, but there were a few challenges here.
So we did have the code, we did have the original code to work from and luckily because of HD
we could also start from HD, which was set up more recently.
However, the biggest issue, and that was also an issue that HD actually had issues with,
is that if you take a game that was compiled back in the 90s and now you take it and recompile
it again with late settings.
not everything will be exactly the same.
There were a lot of places where we noticed that
the way you compile the game kind of defines like behavior,
like, okay, there's an unfinancialized variable,
how does the compiler handle with that, deal with that?
And the reason I'm saying that is because
all of a sudden, you recompile the game,
you make not a single change.
accountable and that was especially visible in for example pathfinding like
you can take the pathfinding from 1999 just compile the code again with nothing
new to it and the pathfinding is slightly different and especially for you know you
have a very big passion community still for HTML-2 they will definitely
notice that like hey this is different what are you guys doing like yeah
nothing yet but it's still different yeah so then you need to go back in
there and look at the pathfinding code
make it better, which we also did. We also went in the pathfinding and went a bit more
thorough. But yeah, for engineering it was also not just, okay, it's different right
from the bat, but also a lot of things that were true in 90s coding are no longer true
in 2020 or 2019 coding.
Coding standards have changed, back practices have changed.
What is now efficient for hardware might not be efficient anymore.
So yeah, it's not like you were handed a game that's...
I mean, it still works, but the kind of intricacies and efficiencies from...
They no longer work.
Or are no longer true.
Right on. Going to chat real quick. We got folks like Brazucano3000 commenting that we need unique units for each civ. That sounds like a lot of work.
That sounds like a ton of work. I don't know. I like games like Warcraft that have unique units for every civ, but they still like...
They keep things analogous. I like how Age of Empires does it too. I like that there's all the basic units and then the unique units.
There's also a bit of an issue there. We definitely talked about it. But there's two big things to consider there.
One thing is, of course, that we have now 11 different architecture sets. 35 civilizations, but 11 architecture sets.
Let's assume that we're not going per civ, but per architecture sets.
then still all of a sudden you have 10 times as many units that you need to recognize,
which makes things a lot more complicated.
One of the beauties of Age of Empires 2 is that you see the units and you know what it is.
That's very, very important in RTS games.
I can't quite imagine if you have all of a sudden 10 times the amount of units.
It's much, much harder to do that, let alone with 35 different sets of units.
Not to mention, it's a lot more assets.
and that will take a lot more memory space and hard disk space.
Because it's one of those things as well, this game is still 2D.
A lot of people think that it's actually 3D now, but it's still 2D sprites.
Because we really wanted to keep that old feel,
but at the same time that's also very very heavy on computers.
Like, okay, it's a lot of space that is taken on your hard disk
for all those sprites, all those facets.
So yeah, there's a few considerations before we can look at individual unit skins.
Right on. Moving on, Lurker Sauce has some interesting insight.
The initial size of Age of Empires 2 DE and Beta was 60 gigabytes.
You managed to half that in compression and split the 4K support in DLC.
That's true. I'm sorry we're not playing with the 4K support today.
My machine is bugged. It can do the best it can.
I wanted to make sure we had the best image quality for the stream.
Because unfortunately at 4K we might have had some trouble.
But yeah, what was your process for and decision making process for including that 4K support
and how did you work to the point of including it as DLC instead of making it a main feature
of the game?
That's a really interesting question actually.
So when we started working on this, all the ideas was okay.
Age of Empires 2 has been going on for 20 years. We want to make sure it can go on for another 20 years.
And then you just have to add 4k graphics.
There is, I mean at this point, I think if you look at Steam hardware, a lot of people are on HD or tiny above that.
But it is slightly moving higher and that will always keep on happening.
So in 20 years, maybe 4k will be tiny and then you want 4k graphics, especially in the 2D environment.
And so it just won't be readable.
But indeed, as the chat mentioned as well, this came with a large, like an explosion
in data size, asset size on your hard disk drive.
And at some point in the AOT, AOT2DE beta was 60 gigabytes.
And then we saw, okay, with 60 gigabytes a lot of people won't be able to run that, which
is not the...
intent at all. We want people to play the game and have as wide a range of computers
they can play as possible. And at that point, we're like, okay, we need to look further
into compression. And I think we went down to, I would say, 30 gigabytes. So if you have
everything installed, I think you're about 30 large at this point.
And as the chat also just mentioned, we once were at the point where we had 120 gigabytes
of data size just in the, yeah, I think it was a pre-beta, but that was really, really
big at that time.
And then at that point we really noticed, okay, this is larger than most AAA game coming
out today.
We really need to go hard.
and get that size down.
And we did. At this point,
you can say, okay, I'm just playing with HD graphics.
And then, yeah, it's much, much smaller.
I would have to check the min spec on how small it exactly is, but
yeah, we're in a much better position at this point.
Right on. As you can see in the stream,
folks, just to do, I was about to go through more campaign missions, and I remembered
most of my time in Age of Empires 2 was spent just playing random
Random games, usually 8 player games on islands where I would usually just build a fortified
island and use cheat codes to win the game because I was just a kid and didn't know how
to play this game very well.
But I decided for the purposes of our stream to just boot up a classic game and see how
it plays out in the new HD edition.
Um, uh, Bert, um, we're gonna move on to my, uh, next question, which has to do with the new factions and sort of the new historical bacon thing.
One of the coolest things about Age of Empires, um, Age of Empires 2 for me as a kid was that it helped me learn more about civilizations that they don't teach you about in the American school system.
I don't think you really get a lot of perspective on, say, Saladin and his campaign until you're
in high school, but here I was at age 11 in middle elementary school getting to learn
sort of about perspectives and people that I had never met before.
What was your team's philosophy for building out the new factions?
Not just from a fun standpoint, but from kind of the historical standpoint that the series
is known for.
Well, that's a massive question. I can probably fill a whole stream just answering that.
But it's really interesting, actually.
So, SIF design and how we kind of get to those SIFs and how we approach it,
there's not really like a set process.
When we start working on expansion, and that we learned from all of our earlier expansions, actually,
is we try to approach things regionally.
I think we first did that with the African Kingdoms,
where we kind of focused on African history,
and we kind of went to Southeast Asian history,
and then now for the E edition we're like,
okay, what region is really interesting
and we haven't covered yet?
And then we went to Eastern Europe and Central Asia.
So that's kind of the theme for the civs in this one.
Now,
At that point, you're like, okay, what civs from that region are interesting for Age of Empires?
And that's always the most difficult discussion to have.
At the beginning it's always easy. You can say, okay, medieval civilization, British, Chinese, and everybody kind of knows those and everybody is like, okay, that's quintessentially medieval stuff and everybody can name something about those civilizations.
But as soon as you get a bit more obscure, the questions become a bit harder, like, okay, what exactly sets that apart?
And then you look at a few things that make it really interesting.
For example, we have the Tatars in the game.
And if we think about the Tatars, we're like, okay, we have the story of Tamerlane.
That's a super interesting story to tell.
So we're like, okay, even if the Tatars, I'm not saying they were not interesting, but
even if the Tatars were not as known as, for example, the Chinese or the British, the story
that we can tell in the campaigns is so interesting that we absolutely want those guys in.
So that's one thing, but it can also be something else.
For example, the Chinese, this is again an older sif with an example, you can say,
okay, the Chinese have the chukou nu, their repeated crossbow,
that's a very interesting weapon, and that's something that you absolutely want to have in the game.
Always like, okay, what's an interesting facets of a civilization?
And at that point you kind of, you know, build around that.
So it's not just one thing that makes a disciple, makes an interesting, but always like, yeah, what?
What are a few interesting things that we can start on and then we start researching, we start building?
The researching bit is always very interesting because we try to look at it from various perspectives.
That's history. History is always written from a certain perspective.
It's always in a certain look. I can't find the exact words in English.
We try to keep it, how should I say it, as open-minded as possible.
For example, when we were working on the Tatars, we reached out to some universities from the region.
in the sense of the Middle Ages, that country is no longer around.
So we were looking for universities in the regions, reached out to them,
read research papers from PhD students as well, went to a lot of libraries.
It's a lot of good old-fashioned research in there, to be honest.
Which is actually good fun.
I mean, you can start from Wikipedia, but after that you really need to go to get down and dirty with actual proper research that you can find all over the world.
And that's kind of how we can fine-tune those sys further.
Now, at that point, once we have a lot of information to work from,
At that point it's more like, okay, we're still making a video game here.
We're not just making a history book, because that's obvious.
We're making a video game for people to enjoy.
And that's kind of where you have to say, okay, we need to make decisions.
For example, we have the Kumans that we just added to the game.
The Kumans, they got extinct before most of the civilization nature vampires were around.
Does that mean that this civilization needs to, you know, stop being relevant as you advance through the game?
Yeah, probably not, because then the game will be completely unbalanced.
So this is kind of where you also need to weigh gameplay versus history at that point.
Man, how did it feel to sort of walk in the footsteps of the original Age of Empires devs,
in terms of building and adding new factions, like you're sort of sitting there going...
you know, we're embarking on the same mission that they did in
the 1990s. But we're doing it, you know, with the tools
available to us, you know, and a much faster internet for one.
Yes.
In the modern day.
It was interesting because I've read some interviews about them and how they kind of went around it.
And I can't imagine how they would have to go to like more obscure sips.
Because sometimes it was like, okay, we had the children's books that we worked from,
or we, you know, we had some articles from magazines and we cut those out,
and that was kind of a reference art.
Those are things that I wrote, sorry, that I read.
in all terms to reuse from Ensemble Studios.
And now with the wealth of information that we have on the Internet
and the ability to just say like, okay, I'm gonna, you know,
send an email to the University of Istanbul
to get some research on Central Asian history.
That is something that we now can do and they could not.
So in a way, I really appreciate the work that they did back in the day
in, you know, researching that with the tools that they had available.
right on on king thirty five hundred israeli question on this is still space
in human history you can tell in a new campaigns receipts
At this point we added 35 civilizations to the game, which is a crazy amount.
There is still more, there is still more.
Is that gonna come to Age of Empires? I don't know.
We've been saying for a while now that for civilizations we're probably good.
We don't really expect to add more civilizations.
Never say never, but we don't really expect it at this point.
But for campaigns, yeah, there's loads of stories to tell.
We actually went through the campaigns, all of them actually.
We kind of remade and repolished them where necessary.
I mean, you just played the Saldin mission.
That one is still very, very familiar to the old Saldin, but there were missions that we
completely...
Hoover vault or completely replaced with new ones. And then we noticed like, okay, we have
Aztecs and we're talking and we're telling stories about the Franks, John the Park and William Walton
and there's so many stories that we told, but then we noticed, oh, we never really told them stories
about the Vikings or the Chinese or the Japanese. It's like, yeah, those are...
have a very rich history and a lot of interesting stories to tell.
But yeah, they're not told yet in the Vampires 2 at least.
Right on.
Moving on to that point.
Okay, let me dive into my question basket here for a second.
Let's briefly talk then about working with Microsoft.
You mentioned earlier that the company was able to provide a lot of QA and localization
support when you checked in with them in Seattle.
What was it like as a small to mid-sized team working with a larger company that in this
case owned VIP, obviously?
How did you build a working relationship with them and what do you think other developers
should know about when...
about opportunities like this to work with companies that are open to handing their IP over to you?
Well, where to start? So I have to say we've gone through quite a few
corporations with Microsoft over the years. We started with BlinkBank Mots
and importing that to be an official product.
And at that point, HMVirus was still...
At that point, it didn't have that much attention internally at Microsoft,
because there was nothing in Age of Empires for quite a few years at that point.
So there was no massive team supporting it.
But these things have really changed lately.
If you look at, well, they just opened a new studio just to support Age of Empires.
So those are things that really show, okay, now you're working with a bigger group.
But really, the best advice I think I could give is like, be humble.
Like, listen and look around. They're a big company. Microsoft has been around for ages.
We're very lucky to be supported by a team that has been around for quite some time as well.
we have people who work on AI, like so many games,
also RTS games in the past.
And that really, really helps.
Like these guys know what they're doing.
And being with them, like, okay,
we might know the game better working on it,
but they know so many other things.
And it's more about like, you know,
getting the best from each other.
And that's also what's good about our working relationship
with Microsoft at the moment.
They absolutely recognize, okay,
you guys really know Age of Empires.
please do your thing. We will be supporting you guys with all the experience that we have to
offer and it's a very nice working relationship in that sense.
Right on. I'm going to give a quick shout out for the bottom of the hour. We are going to be talking with Bert for about another 30 minutes.
We would love to take your questions from chat. We've heard from folks like Lurker Sauce and King3500.
But if you have questions about the making of Age of Empire 2 Definitive Edition, we would love to ask them on your behalf.
Excuse me just a second.
Sorry, dealing with the cold and trying to stream video games is very difficult.
Um, uh, Bert, um, let's talk about, I guess, like, you mentioned yourself, um, as a team
of modders, you know, you're sort of lucky to get to come together and make content for
a game that, um...
was popular 20 years ago and now you get to revitalize it and refresh it for the same community and keep it alive today.
What has been your team's approach to continuing that mod support for other users?
Because obviously Age of Empires still has a really good built-in modding tool,
it has an online mod community.
What has been your approach in that respect to letting people take the Age of Empires tools and go buck wild with them?
Alright, so yeah, there's a lot and the thing is like the modding community just doesn't stop, right?
Yeah.
Even as we're talking, there's probably new stuff in development and new things going on.
And that was also a challenge when we made the Definitive Edition, like, okay, the mods tools that were being constantly developed
were actually developed for the old game and at the same time we were making the Definitive Edition
and like every month we were like, okay, this new modding tool came out or this thing just came from the community.
How do we can, how can we ensure that this gets, you know, finds its way to the E?
And that is also more of an ongoing story actually, because at this point Microsoft has also said like,
hey, we're not done with Age of Empires 2, like, we've just released the game,
but now we're going to support it for quite some time.
because we definitely noticed that there's so many people playing, the game is so big,
you can support this for quite some time if you want to.
So that's kind of what we're doing now.
In modding tools, we're not there yet. We're still working on it, actually.
We actually have a patch coming out next week.
I don't think we have shared the exact date yet, but next week we have a very big patch coming out.
where we will be focusing more on fixes for the audio molding, for example.
So there was a lot of people in the community trying around with all their mods,
and they were like, okay, this can be better, this can be improved.
And we took that advice and we implemented that.
So that's kind of what we're trying to do at this point,
because we recognize it as well.
We come from the modding community,
and we want to make sure that that spirit stays around as much as possible.
As time allows, we will continue doing that and providing tools.
But with that said, when we ship the game, we already included some of our dev tools into the package.
So people who really want to get nitty-gritty with things, they can just go to the tools folder and look around there.
And if they have any questions about that, just ask in the Discord or on the forums and I'm quite sure somebody will get to it.
Right on, Lurker Sauce was actually just asking about the audio support, audio mod support,
and just to follow up on their question for them, is it MP3 or WAV support for that tool?
It's actually WEM. It's a specific format. We did make the whole process a bit easier.
I'm judging from his questions, it seems like he has been diving into that quite a bit.
He definitely read the modding guide there, but that guide will be a lot more relevant once patch comes out next week.
Right on. Okay, moving on from modding.
What does it feel like when you're updating this kind of game?
You're updating a game that kind of has the, you know, and you're balancing gameplay for
something that has just kind of the deathmatch mode, you know, the mode where everyone's
just competing and you don't just win by sometimes beating other players but, you know, by completing
monuments and such.
Sometimes the content you're making has to be sort of for the campaign, which is for
mission-driven content.
For updating this kind of content and then creating and adding new things for it
What's been your approach to make sure that something works across all the different game modes of Age of Empires?
So that and so that it works for players who just want that classic experience or who want something new and something that they can sort
Of cook up themselves, I guess if that question makes sense
That makes a lot of sense. You actually just described half of the discussions that we always have.
Yeah.
No, it's actually something that's very, very common.
We often run into issues like, okay, we have this new unit and it looks really cool.
And our team is really happy with it.
And we're like, okay, what can we do with the units?
We can paint things like, yeah, we want it there.
And then we're thinking, oh, can we also just, you know, put it in the normal game?
And then we're like, no, because then the balance will be broken.
So that there's constantly we're thinking about those things.
And it's something that you see very, very often, actually, like, okay, this small tweak
in behavior might work in this instance, but it will break something completely, seemingly
unrelated in other parts of the game.
Now we, as I said before, like a lot of the people on the team come from the Age of Empires
community.
We're usually quite.
quick catching those things which really helped us a lot like when we were discussing okay can we
i'm trying to find a good example here now
For example, if you do an AI update, where you say, okay, we have units that kind of
kite back and forth, trying to evade projectiles.
That's something that we can add, and it makes the game a lot more harder, especially on
the higher levels.
And you might think, okay, that's interesting to add.
Like you have that kiting behavior that you see a lot of expert players do.
Can we put that in the AI?
And then we put it in and we see, okay, the AI can now use it.
The AI has come much harder.
But it's not necessarily more fun, especially for more casual players.
It's just downright annoying.
And then you're like, okay, that's not a good addition,
even though it technically makes the AI better.
But yeah, better is not always better for everyone.
So that's one of those practical examples where you have to look at
everything that goes on in the game.
And Age of Empires II is a massive game. We noticed that while working on it.
And it's not just the game mechanics, it's also that we're working on a game with history.
And we're kind of telling, you know, people's history.
But for a lot of people it's also like, this is their heritage, this is their background, this is their country.
And people can want to make sure that that is...
represent it in a correct way or in an interesting way.
And if you go way off track there, then people will understandably say like,
hey, why do you represent my country like this? It was never like that.
So there's also a historical caution that you need to exercise there.
Man, I didn't even think we'd get to that line of questioning today, because, forgive me, I had
limited understanding of the nature of the DE work here. I guess I'm going to dive into that a little
bit. And I'm just going to sort of get to brass tacks, which is, you know, you're European,
you and your colleagues, I'm sure, hail from a host of different countries. I, myself, an American,
I mentioned earlier in the stream how
I was thankful to Age of Empires for helping me learn a little bit about civilizations
from far across the globe.
What did you learn when you stepped into working on civs that were based outside of Europe
and how did you avoid making those mistakes that can lead to them being stereotyped?
or boil down into something that doesn't represent them.
Like it's hard to just say how and expect that to cover everything.
But it's sort of the only question I can ask is like,
how did you approach that sensitively and like make it fun and compelling
without like without sort of only making it happen from a Western perspective?
But it's going to happen from a Western perspective anyway,
because that's your that's your background.
Like it's sort of all you can do.
In a way, yes. And in a way, we also kind of need to recognize that Age of Empires has
always been a bit of a Hollywood version of history. It's very much like the basis is
history. Everybody starts from history and that's kind of what the whole game starts
from. But indeed, there is some representations that would say that's more Hollywood than
realism.
Not completely, of course. I don't want to say like, we do a lot of good historical research
and sometimes if our historical team is watching a movie, they're like, Jesus, what are these
guys doing? 15th century helmets in an 8th century spectacle, that doesn't make sense.
So that's kind of the level we try to go for.
So, where was I? Right, how do we look at that?
It's kind of something that we kind of talked about earlier.
So we're just doing history and trying to go to find sources outside the sources that we have available.
So instead of going for the children's book or going for the local library, try to reach out to a university from that area.
A lot of people speak English now, they're very very happy to help.
Age Vampires is a very international brand as well.
If you reach out to a university in Peru, for example, and you ask them something about
aged vampires, they'll go, oh yeah, aged vampires.
It's not just known in USA and Europe, it's known all over the world.
And a lot of people are very enthusiastic to help on that and to kind of help them represent
their country and their culture in the game.
And they often also get questions like, hey, you kind of represent the game or a certain thing that happened in the history of the game in a certain way.
And they will be like, hey, but that's maybe not the best way to do it.
And then you can say, OK, can we adapt that? Can we make changes there?
So, yeah, there's a lot of iteration in that sense as well.
Yeah, man, there's that whole field.
There's man, I'm envious in a specific way.
That's like such a great challenge to tackle.
Like you get to celebrate other people's history and culture.
But also just like, it's fun.
Age of Empires is fun.
Like getting to boil, like getting to tackle the challenge of like doing that
deep dive research while, while bringing them part of the community, I guess, is
like, it sounds like a good time.
Like, hey, you guys get to come to the table now.
Yeah, exactly and that's also what a lot of people love and usually that's also where we get the most
fierce feedback from like, oh we now added your history, your civilization to the game. You can
expect a lot of people from those countries all of a sudden reaching out to you like, hey,
this and this and this and this, or this is great, or that is something that is probably a bit weird.
But usually we try to anticipate that as much as possible, of course.
Actually, there was a fun example from way, way back.
I think one of the first campaigns, we were looking at a new civilization.
Like, okay, we're going to add a new campaign for this civilization.
We're like, okay, this guy had an interesting story to tell.
And then we asked at the local community or the people from that country to get some ideas.
And they were like, oh, that's kind of like our local Hitler.
You don't want to glorify that guy.
And we're like, OK, then we won't.
So yeah, it can be tricky, but that's also a perfect example of showing like, okay, what is shown here in Western history is limited, or it is a very limited or different perspective, and you need to be careful with that.
Right on. Yeah, that reminds me of one of my favorite quotes I've ever heard about Age of Empires,
sort of to give credit to the original team, was from a writer named LaToya Peterson.
I saw her speaking at IndieCade, and she was talking about how the Age of Conquerors campaign,
like the first campaign you dive into is the Incans, or Aztecs?
Aztecs, thank you, yeah. And how the Aztecs fought off Spanish conquerors, and in her
perspective she said that's such an interesting perspective for a game to center, especially
given how Age of Empires sort of celebrates...
It's fair to say Age of Empires celebrates the technological advancement of European nations a lot.
Once in this game it gets exciting, once gunpowder and horseback riding get added to the mix and you feel like you're a stronger civilization.
But to have Age of Empires be a game that took this nation and sort of put them on even footing with the Spanish from a gameplay perspective and say,
hey, this is the story of their resistance and their...
perseverance against a conquering group.
Her perspective on that was super...
I already enjoyed that campaign so much when I played this when I was younger
and I thought her take on it was really good.
Yeah, indeed. I think we added like three new campaigns with Definitive Edition.
And all three of them have a very, very different approach to a story we want to tell.
I think one is about just conquest.
It was a good story, so we were like, okay, it's just about conquest, but it's such a good story, we just need to do it.
And then there was one about like...
Well, basically a people that was about to be extinct
So yeah, it's it's it's very very different kind of approaches
That's that that you know that we all want to tell yeah
I guess as a come to think of it as a as both a designer and a modder
Why I want to ask your perspective one thing Age of Empires is a really good
You know RTS war game like it's great when you want to build an army build the most advanced army
You know play rock-paper-scissors with your opponents and figure out what?
what's good against what. How as a designer do you do you make Age of Empires fun when players just
kind of want to do what I'm doing here and focus on building a town and making you know sort of
bling into the economic or wonder victories of the game the more peaceful alternatives which
isn't to say like the peace side is inherently better or anything just more like my favorite
thing in Age of Empires was always just sitting in a room and fiddling with my toy soldiers I
guess more than it was like.
diving into other people's territories and screwing up their stuff.
I guess, how do you make Age of Empires fun
across those different game modes?
That's the first time I'm getting this question and I love it.
So this is really interesting because when we design new content, a new civilization,
there's... I think a lot of... Okay, before I get to that, first of all, like, big credit
to the original developers for making a game that has this kind of...
incredibly interesting learning curve. Like, you can be an absolute pro and enjoy the game in a very different way,
or you can be very casual, just play and build a city and still have the same amount of fun.
And that's the absolute beauty of Age of Empires.
So when we started working on new civs, we always
The balance that we eventually want to go for and the gameplay that we eventually want to go for
Needs to be suitable for the absolute top players. Like they need to play it
It needs to be balanced for them. But then at the same time we're like, okay we have new
Mechanics, new units. Are they also fun for people who just want to mess around a bit, have some fun?
Because then we were like, okay, for example, a unit that has...
Let's say they have extra visibility range.
That can be a strong bonus for expert players.
But a more casual player will be like, I don't care. I don't care about that.
That's like nothing.
For my playstyle, as a casual player, just seeing a bit further, that's absolutely nothing.
And then you're like, okay, it might be interesting for a certain group, but absolutely not for a different group.
And a lot of the bonuses we kind of iterate like that, like, okay, it might be technically a good bonus,
but for a lot of people it's just not the time. And then it just goes out.
So yeah, it's definitely something that is very present.
And it's actually interesting, it's the first time I get the question,
it's such a big part of the development of Neo-Civilization.
Hey, hey, I'm happy, I'm happy that we're getting,
happy that our questions are that good.
Yeah.
We have 10 minutes left, about 10 minutes left,
maybe a little less, depending on how we go.
But we're gonna try and wrap things up
by the top of the next hour.
If you've got questions for Bert, drop them in chat.
I'll ask them, we'd love to have them.
For myself, I guess I might as well ask,
there have been a lot of changes in,
conventions for how people interact with RTS games. That's kind of a UI, UX question is where
I'm sort of bringing this to is I was super surprised when I booted this up and the menu
was really faithful to what I remembered.
Age of Empires 2 being. I was then confounded by the problem of, oh right, I don't know where to research my new technologies
because I forgot that in Age of Empires the tech tree is not just a thing you dive into and tell something to research
because I've been playing Civ and Age of Wonders and all these other games.
You have to go to the buildings and research them as you unlock tier by tier.
With that said, how did you deal with the concept of changes in menus?
How did you preserve the old game while making sure it followed modern menu logic?
That was another big challenge because we noticed that, especially in UI flow,
that Age of Empires did not evolve in the last 20 years. At all.
So we have some catching up to do, but at the same time we don't want to alienate older players, existing community,
but also there's a lot of UI that's just inherent to the gameplay.
Like you said, your technologies are researched in buildings, not in the tech tree.
The tech tree here in Age of Empires is more informative rather than interactive.
And in that sense, a lot of the UI improvements we did was more looking at what do modern
RTS games offer and what do we not have.
And then we noticed a lot of things that were completely missing.
RTS games are a lot about management, about resource management, unit management, time
management, everything is management and oversight.
And then we noticed like Age of Empires just doesn't have that.
that you actually should have.
A quick example, I mean, there's a few things that you can see on the screen right now.
You're making a monk right now, and right after that you're researching a technology.
In the past you could not do that, you could only do one at a time and you would have to come back to your building afterwards to do it.
At the same time, if you click on that monastery, you will see there's two bars on top of it.
One is the bar which is just for HP and then one is the bar that shows how the progress is of that specific technology.
So it's like little things that help you in seeing what's going on in your empire without the need to constantly
Click around the whole time. So what we our approach was like, okay less time fighting UI and more time fighting your opponent
That was really the big
approach that we try to take
Right on.
You can see me in the stream starting to do one of my favorite things, which was build a wall around my territory.
I don't know why. It was always just nice. It helped me organize my space, I think I felt like.
I will grab one of LurkerSauce's questions from chat.
This is kind of a technical question.
How did you guys write... or, excuse me.
Did you all write how things renders that they don't take up much space before,
like before all units would be rendered on the map that did not matter where you moved your view?
They wonder how the compression was done to have it to 50%. So I guess that's the question is,
how did you change how the game rendered? Because we were talking earlier about the
large file size for the game for context.
Yeah, so the render is completely new actually.
So in the past we had, yeah, I think we had 265 colors in total for everything.
So units, terrains, water, player colors, all of that was displayed with just 265 colors.
Now, we also noticed the reason that the HPM Presto was so efficient was because it only
had 265 columns.
That made the assets very, very, very small.
It's like comparing a GIF or a GIF, I don't even know how to pronounce it, to a PNG.
The amount of colors is just staggeringly different.
And that's kind of...
But then we had the issue, okay, we have a DE version, we need to have more than 265 colors.
So what we did then was create specific palettes of 265 colors per asset.
Which means that the color space is so much bigger, so much bigger, but we still have that efficiency.
from the old compression. Like we can still compress to a certain extent
while having a much greater quality
just by doing per asset pallets.
Right on. That hopefully makes sense for people who understand that technology.
I am more of a writer than a programmer, unfortunately.
And before we go, I will grab Hiwata's question. Thanks for dropping by, Hiwata.
What does the future look like for spectator mode for the game?
Uh, they also asked, has that been asked already? No, it's not been asked.
Um, are you guys working on a spectator mode? I should have looked this up beforehand. Are you
working on a spectator mode? And if so, how's it going? And what does it take to implement a
spectator mode?
Yes, so there is a spectator mode in the game. You can go to a lobby which currently showcases
all the games that are currently being played in multiplayer. Now there is still more work that
can be done on that. Just like I said before, like the modding tools, there can be some more
effort and work done on improving that side of the game. But the same for spectator mode.
there is much more that you can do with that.
And it's one of those things where, again,
we have this example of the community working alongside
while the DE was in development.
Like, all of a sudden, there were big spectator tools
specifically for the old version.
And you're like, OK, that is amazing.
That's currently not in VE, so what do we do with that?
So that's one of those things that we're just going to keep on looking at and see where
we end up.
But as I said before...
We do have a lot of support currently going on for Age of Empires 2
and we will keep on adding to this game.
And spectator mode, I'm quite sure there will be improvements to that as well.
Actually, next week there will already be improvements to that.
Mostly bug fixing, but anything that helps in making a better spectator experience is a plus at this point.
Oh man, that's actually...
Mil, funny enough, Mil is asking a question that sort of involves my wrap-up.
Mil wants to know if you and the Age of Empires team will be at GDC at all next year.
I have no idea.
That is all Microsoft's decision and I am at this point blissfully unaware of anything.
That's fine. That actually helps me start wrapping things up.
This has been another stream on the Game Developers Conference Twitch channel.
Thank you all for coming out today, everyone.
Thank you to the Age of Empires 2 community for coming out.
Thank you to all the interested game developers who dropped by.
I guess there's a lot of overlap between the two when you come to it.
Hi Wada, to answer your question that just went up in chat, yes, this will go up on YouTube.
You can watch the entire archive on YouTube or Twitch later this afternoon.
If you enjoyed watching the stream and you're new to our channel, we would love to have you follow us
because we go live regularly with interviews with really great and interesting game developers,
big and small. We've had AAA devs on the channel, we've had great indies on the channel,
everyone from Insomniac Games to...
the folks from
Night in the woods
It's been a great year on this channel. I'm really thankful for everyone who's dropped by and watched
And next year we're gonna keep doing some amazing stuff. The holidays start ramping up for us
So this is actually might wind up being our last stream of 2019, but that's fine
We will be doing stuff in the new year as we get closer to GDC
If you yourself are a game developer or interested in game development and want to go to GDC,
you can scroll down and click on the register for GDC button and get more info about passes
and prices for next year's show, which is from March 16th to March 20th. If you're going to
register for GDC, I'm obligated to tell you that now is the best time to do it because
early pricing will go up in January, I believe.
Other than that, that's about it.
Bert, if they have questions about the making of Age of Empires 2, where should they ask...
or Definitive Edition specifically, where should they ask them?
Most of the communication is actually through the official Age of Empires Discord,
but if you have more specific questions for us specifically, or for me specifically,
you can also go to Twitter, Age of Empires, Forgotten Empires, or just my own handle,
which is scission.ee.
That might not make it to them.
But yeah, we're pretty open to the community.
We come from the community, we're pretty open to them.
We like to chat with them.
So yeah, any place will usually work.
The forest, there's an Age of Empires 2 subreddit as well.
The community is so big, your answers will probably...
You'll find the answers somewhere, probably.
Right on with that.
Have a good day, everyone.
And have a happy holiday, if you are planning to have one.
Bye!