Hello, I am Darren Korb from Supergiant Games,
and I'm joined by Greg Kasavin.
And I am the audio director,
and I do all of the music and sound design
and voiceover direction.
Hey, and I'm Greg.
As Darren mentioned, I'm creative director.
I do writing and contribute other aspects of game design.
We all wear a bunch of different hats at Supergiant
since we're a pretty small team.
And Darren and I have been working together
ever since the Bastion days,
or more than 10 years now,
through...
four different games, most recently being Hades and before that pyre before that transistor, all the way back to bastion we're here to focus on Hades, in particular, and what we did with all the dialogue and voiceover how we got to.
How we got to all that if you play the game, a little bit about Hades hopefully this is some fun trivia even if you are familiar with the game.
The big thing about it for us was that it was our first ever early access game we designed it for the from the ground up, knowing that we would be getting tons of feedback from our community through much of development.
We also made it a roguelike dungeon crawler genre we've never worked in before. We were very interested in infusing this style of play which involves dying and restarting over and over with a continuous narrative so every time you died, the story would
advance that was kind of the thing that we were excited about early on.
Our team size remained pretty small we developed the game over a little over three years and it has been.
It has done really really well for us we're so grateful for the incredible response, including six nominations and the game developers choice awards.
So, yeah, we're still over the moon.
about all that and the other key feature of the game
is that it's our first ever fully voiced game
with a big cast.
So that was a really big undertaking
and we wanna talk about how we got there.
But first, here is a taste of what fully voiced
meant in Hades.
Few tales are told of Hades,
whose very name inspires fear and penitence,
reminding us of the inevitable fate which we all share.
I, however, mean to tell you such a tale.
Listen carefully.
I understand, young Zagreus, that you would seek to leave that bitter darkness for this
bitter cold.
Quite honestly, I fail to see why.
But I'll aid your plight.
Why not?
For I can offer plenty of assistance.
And you soon shall grow fond of it, I think.
Your father sent me.
All in all, I'd rather be on your bad side than his.
Now you can turn back, like a good little man,
or I can send you home the painful way.
What'll it be?
I gather Lady Demeter's already got a frigid hold on you.
Certainly not the warmest member of the clan, now is she?
But do be patient with her, she's been through a lot.
Um, I just wanted to apologize because I think maybe I didn't act very appropriately last time you spoke to me.
But I just really, freely like this job and I promise I will always do my very best so I just hope I'll have another chance.
Pal, thanks again for that nectar bottle from before. Stuff just goes right through me like you won't believe.
Though I hope you're not going around giving that stuff away to every bozo you know.
You know, Prinset, I'd not expect it to run into you again. Not after all this time.
Something I missed out on the house or what?
Not had much company of late is all.
I warned you, short one.
Now you face a foe more terrible even than I.
The only other foe whom I have ever faced who bested me.
Hold, fiend!
You'll walk not one more step toward the light of day, so long as I am here.
So this is just a sample of all of the VO that we have in the game.
This is a little bit of a data visualization.
Uh, that's the sample of some of our 30 fully voiced characters that we have in
the game, we have over 21,000 voice lines in the game, which we did not
imagine we would have when we set out.
Uh, even Karon that you heard at the end there, the guy who just
goes, uh, has 120 of those.
So there's quite a few.
Yeah, we did not know, we did not realize the scope of the voiceover content in this game until we were basically done and having to do triple takes at this. I still don't really believe it this 300,000 word number, but our localization team reinforces that that is indeed the case.
So how did we get there? We will walk you through that process for the remainder of this talk, starting with the kind of macro view, the initial questions that we had and choices that we made drilling down into characterization how we how we casted the different roles and then down into the nitty gritty of our day to day production pipeline.
But starting with these kind of macro decisions, you know, there were some big choices to make when we were starting out on Hades such as what game should we even make, but certain things were foregone conclusions and one of those is that audio and
narrative would be key to this game, that's something that has been key to each of our games, and myself and Darren are closely involved in the, in the conception of each of our games and are there early on to try and kind of discover
the particular vibe and atmosphere that we want, and the audio is always a really, really big part
of that. There's nothing like music and the human voice to immediately sort of create a particular
mood. So we knew we wanted to use that, and we also knew that we wanted to work with Logan.
Yes, this is Logan Cunningham standing next to that giant BAFTA right there.
Fun fact, Logan Cunningham won a BAFTA for his performances in Hades.
But that's getting ahead of ourselves.
He has voiced characters in all of our games
and been a really key part of our process,
knowing that he was gonna be involved.
We're gonna give some examples of each of the characters,
some of the characters he's played in each of our games.
Here's a sample from Bastion.
Proper story's supposed to start at the beginning.
Ain't so simple with this one.
Now here's a kid whose whole world got all twisted,
leaving him stranded on a rock in the sky.
And so he plays the narrator in that game, who is almost the only voice you hear.
He talks to you almost the entire time you play.
So he's he's very much the primary character in that game.
In 2014's Transistor, he is the main principal character in that game as well.
We added a couple more supporting characters, but he really still had the primary role.
Hey, we're not going to get away with this, are we?
And then in 2017's Pyre, we still expanded our cast a little bit more.
We added more characters, but Logan had the only English-speaking character in
the game who is of course, the primary character, the Arch-Justice.
Breather! Dare you tamper with forbidden knowledge?
And so yeah, that's just a little snippet of Logan's performances in these games.
In fact, in Pyre, he ended up playing several more characters,
but that was his his main one.
Yeah, so we we love working with Logan.
We love discovering the just what else, what other kinds of characters he could play.
So it was exciting to go into Hades knowing
he could play any number of characters in this game.
And each of our games is kind of a reaction to the last game we worked on.
And so a special shout out to Pyre, our third game,
for informing so much of what Hades is,
despite the big differences in those games.
In Pyre, it was our first time working with a larger cast.
And we kind of sidestepped the issue of not every actor
is as much of a genius as Logan by having just about everyone
speaking like a gibberish language, where there's
less pressure on it to just be kind
of an amazing English language performance.
But that gave us the confidence to work with a big cast and be able to take that next step into creating a fully voiced game. That was something we were drawn to doing on this game from the start, mainly for this kind of bolded bullet point we felt that it would
help bring these characters to life, despite having kind of limited presentation techniques right we don't have like.
fully performance captured amazing cut scenes and stuff like that, but we do have actors like Logan, who can, through their voice alone, make these characters seem to pop out of the game.
We wanted the narrative to do a bunch of different things, particularly to mitigate the kind of sting of failure that can make you want to rage quit out of a roguelike game, instead of experiencing what's so great about roguelike games which is that they're
so much more fun every single time you play.
We knew voiceover was powerful.
And yeah, it was our time to take the next step
and try to deliver on this tonal range
that we had in mind that could range from serious to silly.
And again, what better way to kind of deliver
on a particular tone than through the variety of voices?
Of course, it raised many questions
about how we would actually pull this off.
Yes, there were risks associated with going fully voiced. In our mind, we'd never tried
having a non-silent protagonist before. How do you reconcile the protagonist's characterization
with how the player feels as that character and how do you reconcile the point of view
and personality of that character and everything? So that was something that we had to consider.
tone and accent, how does the character speak, how should all the characters in this game speak,
the gods, ghosts, and monsters of Greek myth, what do they sound like, and what languages
they speak, and do they have accents when they speak those languages was another consideration.
We knew we were going to have a big cast in this game. The question was how big right how many characters do we want, do we need what's going to what's going to fill out the cast in a satisfying way and how do we find the actors to play them using
the resources at our disposal. And also another consideration for us is you know, not everyone is a BAFTA award winning actor.
You know some of us on the team do voices in the game and stuff so.
Part of the worry there was just making sure that the other performances in the game could sort of
live in the same game as Logan's, who we knew would be very good performances in the game.
So just making sure that there was a sort of quality consistency across the cast.
And then in terms of content volume,
you know, it's a huge game that you can play forever. How many voice lines do you need to
support that and to make it really feel like you're not running out of content at any particular
point? And then in terms of production, you know, what's our budget and localization plan
for a massive game like this? And we're not going to dig too much into that here,
but that was something we definitely considered.
Yeah, so these were big looming questions, but we to quote Zagreus, whatever let's try it was kind of our answer to all of them. And so we dug into actually creating the characters of this game knowing that they would be speaking.
Starting with our boy Zagreus here. This is a painting by Jen Z, our art director, whose artwork you see throughout this presentation. In fact, a big shout out to her for all the incredible artwork for all these characters.
She nailed this character pretty much right away.
There was very little for her to go on
other than he's the son of the god of the dead.
But there really wasn't much to go on for Zagreus at all.
We get asked sometimes, you know, even some players think
that he's our own invention, but he does come from classical mythology.
Particularly, he's referenced in this ancient fragment
of a play about Sisyphus by the poet Aeschylus.
who in this in this quote, the hospital or is is Hades himself so we're doing research into Greek myth and the underworld and come across this scrap of like wait a minute Hades had a son.
I've been studying Greek myths since I was a little kid I never heard of this and that alone was so compelling, just to kind of uncover the story that it became the basis for the whole game.
Jen, you know, was drawn to this idea of, well we were all drawn to this idea of making our first ever so called power fantasy character which is one of the most tiresome ideas in game development, honestly because, like power power fantasy
characters are there.
all over the place, we just had never done one ourselves. We'd avoided the idea of making a
character who's kind of explicitly kind of better than the player, you know, faster, stronger,
better looking, knows what to say in every situation, all that kind of stuff. But we
wanted to subvert the tropes around this kind of idea as well. He's not quite, Zagreus is not quite
what he appears to be. He's emotionally vulnerable. He's kind. He's polite, despite what you may
assume about him.
And really, we wanted to deeply understand his relationship
with Hades as being kind of at the heart of the character.
And we figured if we knew,
if we had a good understanding of that,
then we would get past some of the cliches.
At the bottom of this slide here,
you see an example from a spreadsheet I maintain
throughout development that has all the characters in it.
This happens to have only the row with Zagreus.
It has things like the tone photo reference.
We'll get to Loki there in just a moment,
but it also has things like the...
a highly cerebral tonality stack rank suggesting that the character should be cool, badass, and hot
in that particular order. So if you want to know about our highly artful process, there you go.
But this is a language that Jen and I understand when talking about characters.
We also understand a variety of different references and there aren't too many people at Supergiant for whom all of these references click. They do click for me, maybe, maybe for a few others but you know on one side with with someone like Jen I'm talking
about Alucard and Dante and Spike Spiegel and with Darren, you know we're talking about Loki, talking about the Dread Pirate Roberts.
The Princess Bride is a movie actually we kept coming back to is a really strong sort of tonal analogy. It could range from silly to serious in a manner similar to what we wanted, but this guy Loki here, he had the look he had the vibe, similar
to what we were going for.
So with that in mind, we wrote the casting sides for Zagreus.
We're like, okay, here he is.
Here's our guy.
Let's get some auditions.
Let's see what we could get for his voice.
But we had a lot of trouble finding his voice.
This was a character that was not necessarily in Logan's wheelhouse.
Yeah, and so we got a few reads for Zagreus based on these sides, and none of them were sort of
hitting all of the marks that we wanted them to hit, and we all had something specific in mind,
I think, that they weren't quite achieving. So I ended up recording some scratch for this just
to try to put something in to take a stab at it and just see if we could sort of get somewhere
a little bit closer on what Zag might sound like.
And so this is an example of the read that I did for Zagreus.
I'm home.
Carry on everyone, don't mind me.
That could have gone better.
Well, time to go get killed again.
I'm home.
When I, when I heard that time to go get killed again, I was like, Darren, you've been holding
out on us like how is he.
How Darren does all of our music, all of our sound effects, all the voice recording and, you know, he just casually delivers, you know, the winning audition for Zagreus, of course that was just my initial impression and it's by no means a unilateral decision
so we had to get Darren's takes into the game and present them as part of our team playtest and stuff but everybody.
Everybody liked it, and and we didn't look back, but there were a lot of decisions to make along the way like we played around with zags. It wasn't a foregone conclusion that Zagreus would speak with a British accent for example, Darren, did a take
that was all like kind of in an American accent as well, but we decided, certainly between us I think we both agreed that
The British accent is like the de facto accent of historic Western fantasy right like from things like Lord of the Rings and Game of Thrones, it's just an accent that gets associated with is sometimes totally imaginary worlds, and yet everyone
speaks speaks neutral English.
But we do use the American accent as well to represent a kind of cultural divide in the setting.
So the characters native to the underworld speak American, like us, and characters kind of Greek origin or surface origin, speak with, with the British accent.
And to be clear, you know, I was not expecting to voice Zagreus even several sessions deep into the game.
I think the actual files themselves are called like Zagreus Scratch.
Yeah.
And we just expected to replace them eventually and never ended up doing it.
Yeah, it ended up being kind of a big additional chunk of work for you, but hopefully, hopefully you had fun.
That was good. Yeah.
Now, certain characters like this one are not quite as difficult to cast as others, right?
Yes, that's true.
I think Lord Hades may have been the fastest we've ever found the voice of a character.
We you know, Greg wrote up some sides with Logan Cunningham in mind.
We knew he was going to play this guy.
You know, Logan and I talked about some references like.
darkness in in in Legend, Tim Curry's character in Legend and a couple other
references. And we just Greg sent him the sides.
And this is the read that he did for that with a little bit of processing on it.
Stupid boy.
I told you you'd be back.
How was your wanton ransacking of my domain?
And that's pretty much exactly the character.
I mean, it's just like, yep, that's it.
We heard it. And that was Hades.
Yeah. So then we got to a point where it was time to kind of put it all together, right?
And this, yeah, Darren, when did we make this thing?
This was in August of 2018, less than a year into development. This is a really,
really early build of the game. And what you're going to see here is
you know, you're going to hear Zagreus, you're going to hear Hades, you're going to hear the
storyteller, and it's going to help coalesce some of the tonal ideas that we're working on
through the voiceover here.
Damn it.
I'm home.
Yes, carry on everyone, don't mind me.
The House of Hades, that dark and lavishly appointed lair of the Underworld's king, is home not just to him, but to his willful progeny.
Shut up, old man.
Back already?
Stupid boy. I told you nobody gets out of here whether alive or dead.
Though how was your wanton ransacking of my domain?
Greetings father. My ransacking was a delight, thank you for asking.
So I'll just be on my way again.
Be on your way indeed. What do I care? You shall never reach the surface. Go, see for yourself.
And you may notice if you've played a lot of Hades
that several of these lines shipped with the actual game.
These are really, really early,
and they made it all the way through to the final release.
Yeah, we never can tell with that stuff
what's going to stick.
So we were quite happy with how things were going
at around the time we put together that.
We don't really use the term vertical slice,
but that's kind of like what it was.
Essentially our first production content,
it was expressing this relationship.
between Hades and Zagreus that we were excited about.
But then we got the whole underworld.
It's time to figure out the supporting cast.
We knew we wanted the tone of the game to be much broader
than just what Hades and Zagreus represent.
So we considered a lot of different angles
on who else should be in this game.
One thing that came very quickly was the idea
that the Olympians are gonna be there.
We quickly got a bunch of Olympians in the game.
The Underworld also gives us some of these like iconic characters that you probably know from just any exposure to Greek myth, the Hellhound Cerberus, the boatman of the River Styx, Charon, Sisyphus eternally toiling with his boulder, those kind of characters were exciting to us and we wanted them to be part of this world.
We also thought about, you know, well that our vision of the House of Hades it's almost like a place of business who works there in what roles you know who was.
Who was Zagreus's father figure if Hades wasn't doing it for him and these characters like Achilles came, came from that. And really, you know, we also thought about it from the production angle, how many characters will be even welcome in this game
how many do we have time and room for.
And a lot of our early stabs at these characters just stuck. We got these characters like Achilles, Nix, Hypnos, Dusa, Skelly, they were all in the game, quite early, they tested well with our team we had fun working on them, and we just kind
of never looked back. And a lot of the Olympians came online.
Early on as well, our idea for the Olympians that they're kind of like.
the awkward Thanksgiving family dinner type of idea,
it really informed the characterizations for them,
like Poseidon as the boisterous, inappropriate uncle,
and so on and so forth.
It gave us clear ideas for the characterizations of each one,
and we got them in the game.
And things felt like they were coming together quickly
at that point.
A lot of the other characters, we just kind of trickled in over early access some we didn't even plan for at all, like electo and Patroclus, and it's it's funny to think back on how we didn't even imagine those characters at all.
At the beginning, when they ended up being quite significant to the story but that's that's part of the beauty of early access which will be coming back to again and again.
Yeah.
we have all these characters in mind,
it's time to find who's gonna portray them.
And what is the first question that we ask
when it comes time to cast a new character?
Yes, the question is, can Logan do it?
That's the first question we ask.
And the answer is often yes.
There are five of the six characters Logan plays
pictured on this screen.
The only reason the sixth one is not here
is because he's the narrator and has no portrait.
But yes, Logan plays a bunch of characters in this game.
He's got a huge range.
And part of the idea behind that is embracing our constraints as a small studio,
using the resources available to us.
And Logan is an incredible actor who happens to be very close with us as a studio and
as a friend.
So we consider him to be an incredible resource to use as much as possible.
And so once the answer to that question becomes no, can Logan do it? No, not this character.
Then we need to expand our search a little bit. So we try to tap our network. Can any of us on
the team do it? This photograph here is a photograph from me in high school with Peter Canavesi,
who is the high school, was my high school drama teacher and
He was the moderator for the improv club that Logan and I were in.
He, in fact, plays Zeus and Chaos in this game.
And he did a few voices for us on Pyre.
So, you know, he did an incredible read for Zeus and did a great job as Chaos.
So we were thrilled to be able to work with him again.
I ended up voicing Zagreus and Skelly.
And Skelly is one of those characters where the character was sort of built around this silly voice that I like to do.
Where it was kind of like this. Originally, it was a guy talk to them more like that.
And then but Skelly needed to be a little more high energy and deliver a little bit more information more quickly.
So he kind of got combined with almost like a Joe Pesci vibe, like, hey, boy, hit me over here.
What are you doing? You know, that kind of thing. So that's sort of how I speak a little bit more to that.
But that's kind of how he came about.
Yeah, Kelly, as you can tell is very deeply rooted in classical Greek mythology, and we, we had a lot of fun, you know with him we're testing the boundaries of the tone of this game right and like he started off as, as kind of a joke, but everybody liked
him and we liked working on him. So, so he stuck and he's not even the first time.
something like that happened like do so started off as, as a bit more of like a frivolous character, who became really important to the game and back on pyre, Logan's principal character started off based on like a funny voice that he would do
from time to time so it's just, again like it based on our constraints based on stuff that we enjoy doing, seeing what we could do with all that.
Of course, there would come times when the answer to, you know, can Logan do it would be no.
The answer to, can we keep it in the family, you know, can Darren and Peter Canavesi or any of us do it would also be no.
And then we would have to reach a little bit further.
That's right. Yeah, we had to get auditions actually for some characters from outside of our network of people who are either on the team or people that we knew immediately.
So, you know, we would look for recommendations from people that we trusted, friends of friends, that sort of thing.
Greg spent a fair share of time scouring voice acting, hashtag voice acting on Twitter and other online sources and then sort of cold emailing actors that seem promising for particular characters.
And then once we would receive the auditions, you know, I had several criteria upon which I like to evaluate them is the characterization unique relative to our existing cast can this person kind of slot into the game and not overlap too much with any other particular character that we have is the.
delivery believable and natural? Does it sound like someone speaking or does it sound like
they're reading? Is the accent believable if there is one? That's another thing that sort of
leans into that previous point there. And then this one to me is actually one of the most critical
is the understanding of a text itself.
Does the actor get it?
Are they conveying all the,
are they mining the line for all the beats that are in there
and trying to convey each one separately
and play all of the changes?
Of course, they're sending us an undirected audition.
And in the actual recording, it would be directed.
And if they didn't perceive all that stuff, we could sort of, you know, direct them to add it.
But just hearing that in the audition is such like, oh, they get it.
You know, it's such a relief.
So so we know that it's going to be easy for us in the booth
if if the audition comes back with that stuff in it.
And then, of course, another question we have is, does it meet or even exceed our expectations for
the character? Is it exactly what we're asking for? Sometimes we'll get an audition, we'll hear
it and be like, yep, that's it, that's perfect, that's exactly what I had in my head. And sometimes
we'll get an audition that's like, ooh, that's, I did not expect that. And it's even better than
the thing that I imagined. And so this next character is an example of that one.
Yeah, and this is one of those, you know, you're talking about believable and natural delivery.
That's another one we really, really prioritize highly because even though we have these larger
than life characters or literal gods, in most cases, we want them to just kind of believe
the circumstances that they're in. This is just normal everyday life to them and they should
convey that in the delivery so that we don't try to go for like cartoonish voices. And it's worked
out well for us. So Megara here.
was a really, really important character, in part because she's one of the only characters in Hades that you can't skip.
If you don't like talking to Hades you don't like talking to Dusa or Achilles, forget about them, you could just walk right by and it's fine. But Megara stands in your way.
As the first boss, you're going to run into her over and over again. And with her. We wanted to express a lot of what was unique about this game, where the story is kind of constantly unfolding and advancing so.
you know, when you play a game like this, your own experience as a player is that the first time
fighting a boss is different from the 20th time fighting a boss, and we wanted the relationship
between Zagreus and Megara to kind of reflect the player's own journey. So it's a lot of pressure on
this character to be a lot of things, and we certainly did not have an actor, an actress in
mind. So we did the thing that we would do. We created the casting sides.
and we started to look for actresses.
Though even in this case, we did kind of keep this one
in the family, at least indirectly, didn't we?
Yeah, sort of.
You know, so the actress who plays this,
who ended up playing this character
is named Avalon Penrose,
and she is good buddies with Courtney Vignez,
who plays Dusa in Aphrodite.
and who happens to be married to Michael Aleshy,
who is the voice of Orpheus and a former Supergiant employee.
So it's sort of in the family.
And a fun fact here is that real life Meg and real life Dusa
are good buddies, which is kind of nice.
Yeah, just like they are in the game.
So we're kind of sweating bullets about this character.
Who are we going to find?
And one day we just get this performance
from Avalon Penrose.
Your father sent me.
All in all, I'd rather be on your bad side than his.
Now, you can turn back, like a good little man,
or I can send you home the painful way.
What'll it be?
Yeah, we heard that and we're just like, oh, that's that's it.
It's more interesting than the thing we thought of.
You know, as you can see here, our voice reference in the sheet is something like,
you know, Furiosa from Mad Max Fury Road.
And and this is this just is even even more subtle, more interesting.
The sort of hushed way she's speaking is like, oh, what a cool idea to have this.
antagonist that you fight and have this complicated relationship, have this sort of hushed way of speaking is very cool and and she ended up actually with the third most lines in the entire game. So this is a really critical character and we're so glad that we found Avalon.
And then, you know, to summarize the casting process here,
we create the casting sides,
and that's actually a great tool for us
to align internally on a character
before we even send them out.
So it's actually really useful for us
from a character development standpoint.
And sometimes we have character art, sometimes we'll have some sort of tonal reference image
on the sheet, depending on the particular sides. And then, of course, we ask, can we cast this
character internally? Can Logan do it? Can somebody else on team do it? Can somebody we know do it?
And then if not, we sort of reach outside of our network of actors when we need to.
And then we'll evaluate the auditions, test them in game, gather feedback,
and vet the casting choices with the wider team.
and then we cast the part and we scheduled the first recording.
And this is you and Logan casting Henry the fifth.
This is a picture.
Yes, I can't believe I forgot to mention this is Logan and I,
Henry the fourth in the year 2000.
We're both playing middle aged men, as you can tell from our gray temples.
Yes.
So going way back.
Yeah.
So that's our casting process in a nutshell.
Doing some things kind of fast and loose and seeing what we can do
with the folks that we have.
But now it's time to get into the real devil in the details. So, before we start recording, we need some stuff to record. And that's where the writing process comes in the writing process, you know, snugly fits.
On to a single slide, it wasn't too fancy.
The part where we had a game structure that you could play forever and keep running into the same characters over and over, meant that there was no shortage of content ideas, having like different stuff for characters to talk about.
The part where we were recording very frequently due to early access milestones and stuff like that
solved one of the key issues that writers such as myself experience, which is procrastination.
Nothing like a deadline to spur you out of a writer's block and so on. So when you know that
a great actor like Avalon or Logan is expecting to record some stuff soon, you really want to
do a bang up job and have enough good stuff for them.
Um, you know, I committed sacrilege by writing, most of the stuff just straight into Google sheets or sometimes directly into game data. And in addition to all the story content there was a high emphasis on on so called barks, just the kind of quick repeatable
that mostly Zachary is would say in all sorts of different contexts because again you can play the game forever. We didn't want these lines to be repetitive so by the time.
we play through all the different options. It has been, you know, hopefully hours and hours
and hours and you don't notice the repeats. What really helped was having an outline for the story
early in the process and then from there all the writing was done kind of much more tactically
based on what we were working on at the time, but knowing where it was all going with the conclusion.
Oh, this here is an example of the spreadsheet that we used.
There's the column marked line, which is the actual stuff that the actor records, we're looking at than a toast here there, we've used this format basically with minor changes ever since bastion so it's not fancy but it's worked for us.
There's the line number. We include context information and.
We also include subtext information in that sentiment column.
That's really useful sometimes of saying what's really behind this line.
What does the character really mean?
And Darren is recording without me the vast majority of the time,
so it helps to know what's supposed to be behind each line like that.
And then it is time to record.
Yes, so we're going to show you a clip from the documentary by Noclip called Developing Hell,
Hades Developing Hell, and it's on YouTube. You can find it yourself. But this is an example
of what it's like when I'm recording lines for Zagreus in the booth.
We're good to go here. Let's see. Check. Hey, I hear my voice. Okay, let me just
down a little bit.
I don't even remember what the last thing that was recorded in here was.
I have no idea.
Death area.
So this is when I arrive back
in the house of Hades after being killed by the bull.
By the Minotaur.
It's one bad bull.
First take.
824. That was 823. 824.
Oh, I got the horns.
I got the horns.
Oh, blasted ghost minotaur.
That's probably the one.
As you could probably tell, things got a little weird when I was in the booth by myself for
too long.
So, the process illustrated there, you know, is that for each line, we would do a minimum
of two takes.
We would pre-slate the line, saying the number of the line, recording the number of the line
into the microphone, and then I would live sort of decide what the winning take was,
and then have the actor repeat that into the microphone, second take, third take, etc.
And that is for the benefit of Brad Hagman, who
was the editor of all the voiceover in the game.
So I would send him these sessions,
and he would chop up the lines, and edit them, clean them up,
and name them, and send it back to me for processing.
So I'm going to show you one more video here, which
is sort of an example of how I applied processing for,
in this case, chaos.
So this is the effects chain for Chaos,
who I would say is probably the most heavily processed
character in all of Hades.
So I'm just gonna go through really quickly
all of the effects in the chain.
So first we got a compressor,
then we got an EQ, standard stuff.
Then we've got two instances of Urcam Trax.
It's by Flux.
So it's Urcam Trax version three.
It's a really crazy VO processing software.
And both of them have about a 50% mix in this first one
and then a 60% mix in the other one.
And they have a lot of funky controls.
But that's what is the principal thing
that you're hearing on Chaos's voice.
Then after that, we've got.
just a basic limiter, and then we've got a reverse reverb, and then we've got a regular
old reverb at the end.
So I'm going to play it back, and the way we have it here is this is the track that
I used for recording with no effects on it, and then all the selects will get chopped
out and moved onto this track down below here.
And this is the one with all the effects on it.
So I'm going to play that back now and you can see what that's like.
234. Perhaps this. Perhaps this. Perhaps this. Second take.
And so you can see, you can hear Peter called out the number. He did a take, he did another take,
and he did another take, and at the end he called out second take. And so that is, in fact,
the one that gets chopped out and cleaned up by Brad, and then it gets named.
And you can see all of these are named similar file names,
235, 236, and so on, chaos underscore.
And that is to mirror the name in the spreadsheet,
in the script spreadsheet.
And that's it, yeah, I'll just have the actor record
a single giant file usually.
This one in this case was recorded in the studio.
And then it all gets chopped up and named by Brad.
And then once Brad does all the editing, he sends it back to me
and I apply the processing and render it all out.
One thing I want to give a shout out to is batch rendering in Logic,
which I discovered after Transistor.
It really helps when you put a whole bunch of lines on a track, select them all
and can render them all at once with baked in processing
that that really saved a bunch of time.
So once the lines are rendered, then there are many, many technical considerations to consider.
We want to consider how we name the files. We're going to have thousands of files to organize,
so we tried to optimize them for searchability. We had the character name underscore 0002 was our
naming convention. We had a hunch we were going to need a thousands place for this game,
hence the three zeros in front of the two.
One limitation obviously is that we can't have over 10,000 lines in a single spreadsheet,
but that proved not to be an issue. We got kind of close with Zag, but not too close. It was okay.
And then in terms of file management, we have thousands of WAV files to manage, and our solution
for that was just to throw them all in a VO folder. So we have thousands of files in one particular
folder.
each character has their own sort of actor template queue in FMOD,
and that single queue is used to play all of that character's VO files.
And each actor template has its own settings,
you know, spatial spatialization settings, sound size, distance,
fall off, all that stuff and busing and reverb and whatnot.
So and FMOD, for those of you unfamiliar, is the audio middleware
that we use to integrate the audio into the game.
And then of course, when you have thousands of voiceover lines memory can be consideration and, and can you do stream them or load them into memory.
Basically we were instructed by our engineers, however, to just sort of go nuts and they would figure it out at the end.
And we did and they did.
That's we went.
Yes.
So once Darren would render out a batch from one
of our voiceover sessions, then it's off to me
and I always felt like a kid in a candy store.
I think I have a fairly unique privilege
in being able to integrate the voiceover myself.
I think a lot of writers.
working in the game industry don't necessarily have as hands on of a role in making sure everything is kind of playing the way it's supposed to all the all the timings are just so, and all that kind of stuff.
And this video will show you a little bit about what that process is like.
Greg here to give you a quick tour of how we script the voiceover in Hades using my friend
Thanatos here as an example. Here's Thanatos as he exists in data in this file called npcdata.lua.
We're looking at the data through a utility called Sublime Text, which you can download.
Thanatos has all of his story events in this kind of format.
It's a script-like format developed by Gavin Simon,
one of our engineers and co-founders.
So, you know, line by line, Thanatos talks,
then Zagreus talks, then Thanatos again.
I could put an arbitrary amount of presentation,
you know, through character animations
or alternate portraits and things like that.
And I just plug in the voice lines, plug in the text.
And that's all there is to it at the simplest level.
Events can have various requirements,
and that is how we determine the sequencing of events,
along with some good old-fashioned randomness.
For example, this requirement just says,
you know, you have to have interacted with Thanatos at least one time
for this event to be eligible.
And, you know, over time we just...
added lots and lots of events to Thanatos.
I'm actually going to hit Page Down instead of Mouse Wheel.
As you can see, he's got a lot.
These are just events with Thanatos at the House of Hades.
He actually has a separate entry for the version of him you encounter out in the field.
These events are ordered in a way that makes sense to me,
with the more generic, more repeatable events down at the bottom.
you get the picture. The other half of this is a function called isGameStateEligible,
which started off very simple, letting us do things like determine the chance to play for an
event, say a 50-50 chance or something like that, or required text lines is a requirement I use very
frequently that just says, you know, has this story event already occurred? But as we went on
in development, things got more and more specific. For instance, we added a phishing system in early
access because, of course,
And so that introduced things like required hasFish,
required minCaughtFish this run, hasNoFish, minHeldFish,
minTotalCaughtFish, anyCaughtFish types,
anyCaughtFish types of each,
anyCaughtFish types this run, maxTotalCaughtFish.
So that gives you some impression.
We couldn't have imagined we would need all this stuff at the very beginning,
or even when we first had the phishing system.
But as I ran into more examples of story events where the specificity was needed,
I could add these or in some cases get engineering support to add them.
And that's how we did it.
So if you take anything away from this talk, fish, I guess.
The part the video didn't get into,
kind of the other half of voiceover integration,
is all of the barks, the kind of contextual lines that
play out in the world, Zagreus's quips and stuff like that.
Those are integrated much the same way,
just kind of line by line.
They could have all the same requirements.
either on the entire batch or on an individual line.
So, and again, we just try to have lots and lots of them.
We have a playback system where all of them
will play randomly until the whole table is depleted.
And then we kind of reload the whole table
just to get at the maximum amount of variety
and reduce chances of anything playing back to back,
that sort of thing.
I'm really, really grateful to our QA team
for making sure all this stuff worked because yeah,
the amount of narrative content in this game
kind of...
spun out of control to a certain extent.
And between our early access players and our QA team,
they kept it going and making sure
everything was sounding good.
Yeah, for sure.
I mean, and one of, so once everything is integrated
after Greg has done that, you know,
the process that is mystical to me somewhat
of integrating all the, everything into script.
And we play test internally a bunch to make sure everything is working before we send it out into the world, especially before early access we relied more heavily on the internal play tests where the whole team plays everything.
Early access of course was an incredible source of feedback and we read every piece of it between our discord and Reddit and all the other places that feedback was delivered to us we made sure to read it and respond to it the best we could.
One other thing that was interesting about the early access feedback is that it sort of protected the characters like once they were out in the world. We, we did you know we didn't want to cut a character that we'd already sort of released into the game.
For example, so, so I think Greg was was grateful for that that none of his the hard work that we've done to make these characters could be undone by our waffling on it or something.
I think the early access feedback also helped shore up our confidence in the tone because
the response had been so positive to a lot of the characters and the voiceover
that that it gave us motivation to really keep pushing as hard as we could.
And it was really helpful for iterating on small stuff and fleshing out the characters a ton,
because it really exposed areas where, oh, we could do some more here. We could push on this
here with this character. And it also led to some silly stuff that we ended up doing. So, you know,
lava, when it is under the ground, technically is called magma. And there was a point in development
where we had recorded maybe two dozen lines across five characters where they are saying
the word lava, referring to magma.
And somebody on Reddit pointed this out, and Greg Sott was like, you know what?
We should probably go and fix that.
So here's an example.
How was the lava temperature lately, Lurney?
How was the magma temperature lately, Lurney?
We went back and picked up every single one of those two dozen or so lines across all
those characters.
Yeah, and this wasn't like meanly delivered.
No one was like roasting us for forgetting third grade geology
or whatever, the difference between lava and magma.
But it was one of those things where
I think if left to our own devices,
we just would have shipped this maybe insignificant error,
but an error nonetheless.
And yeah, it's just an example of how our community was
able to help us identify all these little opportunities
to just try and improve little aspects of the game.
They kept us honest. Yes. So, you know, we were just kind of hurtling the early access nature meant that the next milestone was kind of always around the corner. So we were just in the thick of it, making it happen and didn't have a ton of ability
to kind of reflect back.
on the process but something that really worked for us looking back on it was knowing it Hades was going to be an early access game we approach the story like like a serial almost like a TV show with the early access launch being like a pilot, and knowing
that the 1.0 launch would be like the finale so.
With the early access launch we introduced some of the characters, set the stakes, but the story doesn't end there and we just kind of built it out, update by update until we finally introduced the ending in our in our final update before launch.
Having that outline was really, really valuable. It let us, we still could veer off course every which way and introduce characters we didn't anticipate but we knew what the through line was going to be Darren and I, you know, we're not a big
team between the two of us so it was.
incredibly valuable that Darren could just like solo record, not just himself but with basically our entire cast, I usually wouldn't be there, because I would often be still writing while Darren was recording so that was really helped save a ton
of time. And yeah, we would just keep like playing, playing ourselves, watching streams, listening to feedback and it just kept.
spawning new ideas for content.
And we'd always try to make time for the small, so-called
unimportant moments.
Unimportant in quotation marks because they're actually
some of the most, I think, delightful moments in the game
that you can experience, even though they're not strictly
needed.
If you're interested in all the stuff we did with Dialogue,
there's this video from the YouTube channel
People Make Games that delves into it really deeply
that I recommend.
Now the production of the game was not without its challenges,
not least of which were the growing scope of the game.
As we added more and more to the game,
there were more contexts that seemed like they needed VO that
was highly specific to that context.
And so as the game expanded, so did the VO scope.
And it just kind of snowballed.
And the more positive feedback we got on characters,
it made us want to push on those characters more
and give them more to talk about and more to do, more to say.
And of course, localization, as you can see from that terrified emoji,
you know, this was an involved process, localizing the 300,000 or so words in the game.
Early access development also provided its own sort of challenges.
The next big update was sort of always around the corner. Greg, I'll let you, I'll let you speak to this a little more directly. Yeah, the the pressure to get it right the first time as it were so even though we're an early access game and you know technically
nothing's finished and technically everything can still be iterated on.
As soon as we would put new story stuff into the game,
it was as though it came from classical mythology itself
and was instantly canonical.
So it was unthinkable the idea of like,
oh, we're gonna cut this character
or we're gonna completely rewrite this character.
We felt that pressure, but it was a good pressure
because players are really enjoying the characters
on the whole.
And yeah, we were just inundated with feedback.
Players were really enjoying the game,
but they wanted more of it, as is often the case.
And we were just busy recording, sometimes up to three or four
sessions per week.
But there was another significant challenge
last year that is worth mentioning, is this little guy.
Oh, yeah.
There was a global pandemic in two thirds of the way through production.
That that was the thing that happened.
It certainly threw a wrench into our plans a little bit.
We had to do all of our video recording remotely.
A lot of it previously was being done in the actual office.
We had a vocal booth in the office.
that you saw in that no clip documentary. That's where that was happening. And so we just had to
improvise. We had almost a third of the game's content left to record, I would say at that
point. So we just sent all the actors snowballs, blue snowballs here, which is, you know, good
little soldier mic that did the job. Logan used this mic for all of Pyre, so I had confidence
that it would just at least work.
It wasn't going to necessarily match the sound of the mic we were recording them on in the
office and the sort of outboard gear that I had that flowing going through.
But I just figured, well, we just got to get them recorded and all sorted out in post best
I can.
So I did my best to match the characters to their previous recordings to the best of my
ability.
Yeah, and there was obviously such a harrowing time.
And just on the on the project, the idea that our entire voiceover production might grind.
Well, the whole game, much less the voiceover production might grind to a halt.
was really scary.
But Darren, through his ingenuity,
we like barely skipped a beat.
We just kept on trucking
and recorded so much of the most kind of essential stuff
because we were recording all the ending content
at that time, some of the most important stuff in the game.
Yeah, I think Zag had like 3,000 lines left to record just by himself.
It was a lot. It was the most concentrated recording and with a lot of actors. But we
did it. And this was our team at the tail end of the project, all on a happy Zoom call.
And we, you know, the voiceover was
just a small part of the puzzle, but a really, really fun part to work on.
You know, we were able to record a whole bunch of stuff that got a really good response.
Darren and I, I remember we were just frequently really blown away and moved by people's like
positive response to the voice acting because we had so many questions about whether everybody
would be able to live up to Logan's standard and all that kind of thing.
Early access was really, really, really useful
and helping us just catch little details.
And I think our initial assumption
that going fully voiced would help bring
these characters to life, I think proved to work out
very well.
Absolutely.
And in hindsight, there are things
that I would maybe do a little bit differently
or if we were to do on our next, that we
could take into our next project.
would be I'd like to achieve a little bit more sonic consistency perhaps across the different
characters in terms of what microphones are being used, the signal path, and you know maybe next time
we can not have a global pandemic in the middle of the project. It would help help with that
if somebody could get right on that. I'd like to streamline the casting process going forward
probably or if I were to go backward I would streamline the casting process because
you know, when we've reached outside of our network of actors, it became pretty stressful and time consuming.
And we were just kind of always worried about whether or not we'd get the thing we were looking for.
So maybe we'd try to outsource that to a professional assassin who can find actors easily.
Better file organization is something, you know, maybe our giant single folder for all of the VO files is not the best system, perhaps.
And maybe an improved priority system for some of the thornier story events would be would be good as well it would save a lot of qA headaches on the back end perhaps and small bugs that way.
And in terms of some other lessons that I'm taking forward to whatever we do next is, you know, regular recurring VO sessions really really worked well for us for a lot of reasons.
it avoided the crush of stuff at the end. You don't run out of time necessarily to if you have
new ideas you can add them you can't throw anything onto the pile when you already have a mountain
to record all at once. So that's one benefit. I also think
it really gave us time to know the characters.
And for me as a director and for me as an actor,
it really gave me a better understanding
of every single character we were recording,
just living with them for so long throughout the project
and recording them consistently.
So it really gave me a better sense of,
does this sound like it's in their voice?
And how would this character say this?
It was really important for me.
And I think most importantly of all,
one of the most valuable lessons we learned
which was a question that we had when we started this project, was can early access work for
narrative games? And, you know, I feel like for our part it's worked out as well as we could have
hoped in the case of Hades. So, yeah, it really was an exciting way to prove that out.
Yeah, it really, you know, we would have ended with a much smaller and worse game. If we somehow in an alternate reality made Hades without the early access process.
So, yeah.
Thank you so much for listening. We're so incredibly grateful for the ongoing support
for this game. Darren, I know you share my feeling that we're incredibly grateful to
our colleagues at Supergiant who do so much inspiring work to where we just want to...
live up to what they're doing with our own corner of it.
And and we've stuck together all this time,
trying to see how long we can keep going, making games together.
We want to keep on trucking for a while longer.
And having had this experience on Hades, we're excited for what's next.
Absolutely, yeah. I mean, you can't take a look at this image that Jen and Joanne collab on here and
and think, you know what, I'm just going to phone it in. Yeah, you got to give it, you got to match
the caliber of this kind of stuff. So yeah, for my part, I really am grateful to the entire team
for the privilege to be able to work on games with them and thank you to GDC for having us.
It was a delight to be able to get to talk about this, just a sliver of all the work that went into
Hades.
Yeah, and thank you to our incredible voice cast for making all this possible.
See ya.