Hello, this is Monica.
Thank you for coming to our talk about what
being neurodivergent means in game development.
Before we started, there's a couple of things
I just want to say.
First of all, this is a safe space.
We want to make sure we respect each other,
everyone feel comfortable,
and as this is a neurodivergent panel,
we understand everyone is different,
have different accommodations,
so please do whatever you need
to make yourself feel safe and comfortable.
And the second thing is, please, after this talk,
rate us on the GDC app.
It will be very, very helpful to get your feedback
on how we can do better.
The third thing is, after the talk,
we're going to have a Q&A at the wrap room.
It's going to be on the same floor on the other side.
So if we cannot answer your question right here,
please come to the wrap room.
We'll all be there.
And that's it.
Hello.
I'm Monica.
My pronoun is she, they.
And I am a game designer currently working at Shell Game.
I have been diagnosed as neurodiverse.
before I had memories.
Over the years, I have been through a lot of different experiences.
I went from trying, learning how to mask myself,
learning how to behave normally and struggle with it,
to today, I'm standing here trying to tell everyone that
it's okay to be different.
And in the gaming industry,
it's sometimes a very good advantage.
This is why I decided to give this talk,
because during the COVID, I think a lot of things happened.
And to me, I started to notice is
there's, I have a lot of friends who are neurodivers
who are like the most talented game dev I've ever known.
However, a lot of us share the struggle
of having to work in a neurotypical working condition
and has to follow the rules
that does not really work best for us.
And the other...
thing is, I've seen a lot of like, team that has like a
neurodiverse team, but the game is still designed very oriented
towards neurotypical. It has something to do with what we
assume gamers are, which is not really the truth. So to my hope
is by giving this talk, we can start a conversation about how
to design game and how to make game that is for everyone.
The third thing is, my most driving force of giving this talk is I have been helping
with some students and mentor some students.
And I have a lot of people asking me, I have ADHD, I'm on the spectrum, I don't know if
I'm able to be a game dev.
To me it's very shock because of course you are and
I as someone who went through many different career
I can see game development is definitely the career for me, and it's the only place I've been thriving
so
But then I look around, I couldn't give a lot of good examples because there really isn't a lot of game devs talking about this topic yet.
So I hope by giving this talk, by showing so many talented people on the panel,
we can give more people to be like, yes, you can absolutely thrive to be neurodiverse and be a game dev.
I'm very lucky today we have eight different speakers from very different backgrounds
and to share their own stories.
So I hope you enjoy the talk.
I hope this is like inspiring.
And yeah.
We are starting.
The first and the best.
One of the best.
We see how you do, Monica.
Thank you.
We have Samara Jade Sendek. Her name, her pronoun is she, her.
And she's a narrative designer all the way from Australia.
Yoday.
So as you might have heard, I'm Samara Jade,
Teresa,
Sendek.
So welcome to Neurodivergence, Masking, and the Workplace,
where for the next six minutes, I'll be shouting words
at your face about what it is to be neurodivergent,
masking, and what your workplace can do to help you
or help your coworkers out.
So a little bit about me is, yes, I'm a narrative designer,
writer, QA tech from lovely Narm, or QA tech,
as the white fellas there call it, Melbourne.
So all that's basically, so you know I'm good to talk.
I was the writer and narrative designer
on Game of Thrones' Taylor Crowes.
I'm writing for.
A team, well, one of my local teams, Dragon Maze Studios on Enchanted.
I also worked on an Amazon Alexa skill called Daily Boost.
It is with Taberno Voices.
It's not up there.
And all the rest of it, I'm also on G14 Classified Materials.
Hush hush.
So I'm going to begin with a few comforting habits.
The first thing, also from Australia.
I'd like to...
acknowledge the traditional custodians of the land, the Ohlone peoples.
Secondly, I'm going to begin, well, I'm going to begin the actual talk now
with a pithy quote.
Under the present brutal and primitive conditions on this planet,
every person you meet should be regarded as one of the walking wounded.
We have never seen anyone not slightly deranged by either anxiety or grief.
We have never seen a totally sane human being.
So, segueing right into that, we have one of our best buddies from the darkest dungeon, Baldwin.
So, where we go with this talk is that Baldwin has an ability in camp, it's called let down the mask.
So, if Baldwin does this, he relieves a lot of stress on himself. It helps keep him calm,
it helps keep him push helps him push through the dangers of the darkest dungeon.
Unfortunately, it wigs everyone else out.
They're not used to seeing a leper.
This is, this is like they're not,
they're seeing something they're not used to.
So, it's what it's like to mask for neurodivergent people.
It's to cover up, cover up and put anxiety
and grief on ourselves.
And it's because wider society won't see us as...
Sorry, I've got my notes on my phone because I can't read it on the laptop.
I was like, yeah, everywhere I go, I mind how I walk.
I don't touch certain metals.
And it's because I'll feel sick if I do.
And I need to mind how I speak, because I believe it or not
was assaulted in primary school, because I talked funny.
So why are we having this talk?
And why am I breaking out social norms
and laying out some trauma?
So simply put.
practice what you preach with accessibility. And you really can't begin to design or
develop for accessibility unless you start at the studio itself. So, basics. The
keep it simple silly version of masking is hiding character traits to look like
everyone else. We're mimicking, in short.
We look like you, we talk like you, we act like you,
because we'll get the bad stuff.
Like bad stuff will happen to us if we don't.
Like,
like we, like, we have to act,
we have to do this, we have to do this act
because we can't perceive the world
in the way a labeled neurotypical would.
There was a study,
it was a study some time ago.
about, let's just pretend this is a box. So, it was between uh, neurotyp- like
neurotypical and autistic kids. Now, the researcher said there was a very special
way to open the box. These kids, like the neurotypical kids, followed the exact
same pattern. Lift it up, lift it down, turn it upside down, shake it all about,
and then, open the box. Autistic kids just skip the process and open the box.
Unfortunately, under masking, we have to do it the long ways method, otherwise, you know,
we get screened at.
We get assaulted.
We get blamed for when vaccines go bung.
So it's acting.
And that takes us to performative societies.
And what I mean by that is exactly what's on the slide.
Society itself is theater, and daily life is a stage.
So another example there is like, you might be, you know, walking down the street and then you see someone trip and they go,
Oh, I've been fine.
I would have been fine if it wasn't for that thing right there.
And then they just continue on their merry way.
That's performative society.
They just like this act, this dance that people try to do to make sure everything else is fine and seemly.
It's a front that's part of masking for us.
So, masking is the deliberate and often painful attempt to look like everyone else. Again,
we must think like you. We must talk like you. We must act like you to save ourselves.
So, solutions. Masking is bad. Yes, it puts stress on us. It puts stress on the team. And
if no one really knows who or what they're dealing with, consequences can be severe.
So the good news is the things that can help us neurodivergent people can also help everyone
else in the building.
So it's a win-win.
Uh, key items in meetings. So things like, uh, fidget spinners, fidget cubes, uh, like if they
wear collars, collars, that works too. Um, anything to basically help stim. It just takes the pressure
off us, uh, in any given situation. I don't exactly have a stim toy with me, but you might
have noticed me rolling my shoulders and clenching my fists, having a nervous chuckle now and again,
and then pausing to punctuate a point.
That's all stim, that's stim material for me.
And that helps me, helps keep me calm and collected
and deliver this presentation.
Nextly, if we do get overstimulated,
if we do, if like the walls are closing in around us
and we need to bug out, we need an area to calm down in.
This can also work for neurotypical people.
It's like, they're just having a little too much
on their plate.
So, if this does happen, please keep in mind that overstimulation and a meltdown is trauma.
We're doing it to escape a painful context, and the brain will do anything it takes to make the
pain stop. So, in regards to that, have a lot of sick leave. Lots of it. Most anglophonic countries
will have at least, like, five, maybe ten days of sick leave, like, written into federal law.
have double that. Because you're going to have, you're going to run into comorbid depression,
anxiety, fibro, celiac, the works. There's just a lot of comorbidities. And lastly, have
some nonverbal, nonwritten communication. So, I'm slightly dyscalculic. I can't do
maths. My sister is dyslexic. She struggles to read. And I have a lot more friends and
family who just, they can't talk. They can communicate just fine.
you know, not with the pie hole.
It's way more common than you think.
Like, if it, and if you've got deliverables due,
just like, you know, if it can get the point down faster
by like writing it down, by doing a pretty picture,
or hell, if you've got time, let them,
let them make a build.
I knew a guy who actually made a build one time
and, whew, worked fast.
Now, capping off, remember, please, that we are human.
We are doing our best.
Autistic people are specialists forced
to live in a generalist society.
Like, mass media today demands every little bit
of an ADHD person's executive function.
And post-traumatic people are still
trying to navigate horrors no one was really
meant to withstand, evolutionarily speaking.
Like we, and believe it or not, we all do talk to each other.
We are watching you and we do know when and how you treat us
differently.
Everyone on this panel has gift wrapped you a cookbook on how to help your fellow
neurodivergent people. It's one thing to stick A11y on your webpage.
It's another thing entirely to execute it. Now, execute it.
Thank you.
No pressure.
So, going up?
Yep, I would also like to take the opportunity
to introduce the wonderful, magnificent,
magnanimous Mr. Radiant G.
Hello everyone.
I am Radyin Chi, and I'm not really going to have any slides up there.
I'm just going to tell you all a story instead.
I'm Radyin Chi.
My pronouns are he, him, and I'm an indie game dev, artist, writer, and game journalist.
I am also dyslexic.
I actually didn't know for most of my life.
I thought the words and letters moved around for everyone.
It definitely made certain aspects of school
difficult growing up.
And it's a huge barrier when a great new book comes out
that everyone's talking about and I haven't read it.
That said, I don't dislike being dyslexic.
I just don't like when things that could be accessible,
aren't.
I want to start off my section with a quick story.
Once I was talking to someone online about where we thought our
spirits would go when we die.
And I know that sounds like a dark topic to some, but to us, it really wasn't.
It was interesting.
And I remember them saying to me that they wish the afterlife was a library
filled with books of everything that ever happened in history.
And you could just sit down and read it forever.
I jokingly, but also seriously, said, well, I wouldn't wish that because I'm dyslexic.
To which they said, well, you're dyslexic on earth.
That doesn't mean you'd have to be dyslexic in heaven.
My reply?
My dyslexia is a part of me.
I wouldn't want to not be dyslexic in heaven.
That would be losing a part of myself.
I would want heaven to be accessible.
The person I was talking to went silent for a few seconds and said,
you know, I never really thought about disability like that before.
So I hope today that anyone here who assumed anyone disabled would choose to be abled,
if they could, to also rethink the way that you see disability.
When things are made accessible to me, my dyslexia can even become an advantage.
Sure, I'm more likely than my peers to have a typo,
but I'm also better equipped than my peers to check if something is accessible.
Last year I worked on an indie game where our UX UI person, Star St. Germain, shout out,
made an alien font from scratch. It was awesome. One of our mini games involved looking at two
lines of characters and seeing if any of the symbols were mistyped in the second line.
I was the one Star came to to check over all of the symbols and let her know which
ones were too similar or confusing, especially to a dyslexic eye.
We worked together to change the few symbols that needed changing and ended up with a much more accessible game because of it.
Accessibility consulting is powerful and rewarding, and I love doing that.
Now, not to say it's all positive to be dyslexic in games.
I've also had rather poor experiences in gaming due to it, too.
If a game is not accessible, I can't play it.
I have been recommended games and downloaded them only to not be able to read the UI and
have to tell my friends, sorry, I can't play with you.
But you know, that's just how it is sometimes.
And I've also been to cons where I've felt embarrassed that I have to turn away or walk
away from a game demo that somebody is showing or spoken to with derision when I ask a developer
for help with a demo that isn't accessible.
they treat me like a liability. You know, I can tell when I'm being treated by someone in an
ableist manner. It's not hard to pick up on and it's not fun. I admit that I actually cried once
in a demo chair at PAX because I was struggling to play a game and the people weren't helping me
and it was, you know, it was frustrating. I'm not afraid to admit that, like sometimes it is hard.
Yeah, all of that said though.
The silver lining is that every day in this industry,
I want to work towards building a better tomorrow.
And I know that sounds cheesy,
but I really do want to build a better tomorrow
for accessibility, for inclusivity,
so that less people have to feel the bad side
of all of this.
I have brought up several accessibility changes
at both dev and journalism jobs of mine.
And they've gotten implemented relatively quickly
whenever I bring them up.
These changes and step forwards don't just make working a
better experience for me, but also everyone like me
that comes here before or after me.
I'll end this off by saying that.
If y'all ever want to hit me up, my Twitter is right up there.
If you're dyslexic and you want to talk to someone and build community, that's awesome.
If you're not and you just have questions or anything you want to say, feel free.
My DMs are always open.
And last but not least, dyslexic folks in gaming, untie.
Sorry, sorry.
Unite.
Thank you.
All right, next up, I'd like to introduce our first remote guest of the night,
the wonderful Cameron Hopkinson.
Thank you.
Good morning, everyone.
It is currently 6 a.m. here, so if I seem a little drowsy, please bear with me.
So my name is Cameron.
I am a Game Access Push consultant, composer and programmer from New Zealand,
and I am autistic.
Attending events such as conferences and networking events is often described as crucial for anyone
looking at breaking into the games industry, yet I have struggled a lot at events due to
being autistic.
This will be a quick chat about a few things that events can do and have done that will
help make them more manageable.
I am going to focus on in-person events just because of time.
Also, my setup is to do no fault of GDC a bit,
so bear with me for that as well.
But first, a quick disclaimer.
Autism is a disability that has a vast number of symptoms.
Severity of each of these symptoms
varies partly from autistic person to autistic person.
Text speaking, there are some autistic people
that are nonverbal.
They cannot talk at all.
There are some like me who have what is called selective mutism,
where we cannot talk in certain situations,
and there are autistic people that have absolutely no problem speaking whatsoever.
While there is a lot of overlap in our collective autistic experiences,
there is no universal autistic experience.
Not everything in this talk is going to apply to every autistic person,
but taking the following into consideration
will help make your events more accessible to autistic people.
One thing that you can do to make your events more accessible for autistic people is to have a dedicated quiet area.
This gives people a space to go if they need to decompress because everything has gotten to be too much.
This kind of space can easily be the difference between an autistic person having a meltdown or not.
So if you're running an event, please consider having a dedicated quiet area.
The only thing to keep in mind with this is that there will need to be people there to enforce it.
Otherwise you risk the room simply becoming another space for networking,
which kind of defeats the purpose of that space.
If you're hosting a networking event, avoid playing music.
When I have gone to networking events that have played music,
it has generally just made the event louder.
It can get harder to make out what anybody is saying.
A lot of autistic people have auditory processing difficulties.
They make it hard to make out what a person is saying if lots of other people are speaking.
And everyone yelling louder to be heard over everyone just worsens the issue.
And it's not like the music will be audible for anyone or people trying to yell over it anyway.
If an event is a party, then feel free to play music.
But if the aim of the event is for people to network, please keep it off.
Incense and flashlights, which can be a feature of all shows and other occasions, can be highly
distressing to autistic people and can easily lead to meltdowns. One way to make your event more
accessible to autistic people is to avoid these if at all possible. Another reason to avoid flashing
lights is because of the risk of seizures for people that have epilepsy, which happens to be a
common comorbidity for autistic people, which means a lot of autistic people also have epilepsy.
Seizures are serious and can easily lead to serious injury, so minimizing the risk that
someone could have a seizure is very important, not only just for the sake of your attendees,
but for the sake of your wallet because lawsuits can and do happen.
Another way to make your event more accessible is to restrict the number of people who attend.
A lot of game dev events will try and shove as many people into a space as physically possible,
which makes events inaccessible to us for two reasons. The first is that the event,
it means the event becomes a lot of people trying to yell over each other,
which as I've explained already, is an issue. The second reason is that it makes it near
impossible to move around without people bumping into you.
Generally, autistic people do not like being touched unexpectedly.
Filling your event up to fire capacity makes this inevitable.
Also, restricting the number of people at your event helps physically disabled people,
as it is near impossible to move around a cramped venue using mobility aids
such as a walking stick and a wheelchair.
Something I've seen some conferences do is have stickers at registration that
they can play that attendees can place on their badges to tell people what kind of
interactions they're comfortable with. For example, you can have stickers to
indicate whether you're okay with hugs, just handshake, or if you want people to not touch
you at all. You could also have stickers about whether you would want people to
start conversations with you or whether you just want to be left alone.
This is great for autistic people for multiple reasons.
First of all, it lets autistic people easily dictate
how much contact they want with others.
A lot of autistic people do not like being hugged,
especially by people they don't know.
So having something on your badge to tell people
not to hug you will help keep that from happening.
Secondly, it makes it easier for autistic people
to initiate conversations with people.
A lot of us struggle with social cues and neurotypical people,
so it can be hard to determine
if someone is wanting to chat or not.
these stickers can help misguide that awkwardness.
Anyway, that is a small and non-exhaustive list of things that can be done to help make events more accessible.
Hopefully that helps some of you who are looking at organizing events in the future.
And that is me.
And yeah, if you want to...
I won't be at Q&A afterwards because it's virtual.
So feel free to reach out to me if you have any questions
or anything like that.
Otherwise, I will pass on to Emily.
Hi, my name is Emily Stel.
I'm going to talk a bit about my journey and career
in the industry.
Sorry.
I'm going to talk a bit about my personal experiences finding
employment and self-acceptance through games.
I'm at the very start of my journey and career
in the industry in general.
And actually, I'm at the very start of my.
journey and career in the industry and actually work in general.
Last year I started my first job ever as a junior game designer back home in the UK.
I'm also artistic. It's one of my professional and professional goals
to one day be able to say that without all the accompanying anxiety.
There's still a lot of stigma and misconceptions surrounding autism,
and I even worry that being openly autistic could hurt my career,
especially as a designer where communication is such a key thing.
I spent a few years not in employment, education or training,
and the word communication became something of a spectre for me.
As an autistic person, it's easy to look through job descriptions
and see requirements like excellent communication skills
and think, well...
that excludes me, but there's something that took me some time to figure out.
Finding something difficult isn't actually the same thing as being bad at it.
But how can someone with a condition that's usually characterized by a deficit in social
communication actually be good at communication? Well, part of it is practice. Perhaps I've
gained these skills a little slower than most people.
but I can still learn and grow and improve, even in difficult areas.
Part of it is sheer force of will.
Struggling with something often means spending a lot more time thinking about it
than the average person.
And a big part of it is that
communication is a really big concept
and not all of it is actually required to be effective in employment.
So I might not always remember to ask you how your day was,
but I can communicate my ideas about video games effectively.
All right, so maybe finding communication difficult
doesn't actually exclude me from being a game designer.
Is it possible that being autistic
makes me a better game designer?
This is a slightly difficult issue for me. I think there's a tendency in businesses to advocate for
diversity exclusively because of the benefits it can bring, but there's still an argument to be
made that the advantages are irrelevant, and including more people is reason enough to do
something, but I won't push that point too hard right now. Because there are many positive traits
associated with autism, and a lot of them are very useful in game design.
things like curiosity, creativity, and attention to detail.
But for me, it's passion.
I've never been as interested in anything
as much as I am in video games.
And I used to think that was quite sad, like some kind of personal failing.
But now, to have the opportunity to channel that passion into a career and a purpose,
I find it's actually a strength that helps me in my role every day.
And for me, that passion runs so deep that I don't think I could do anything else.
Starting work in the games industry has been both the hardest and the best thing I've ever done in my life.
I spent a lot of years thinking I wasn't capable of very much.
Receiving my first job offer was a real turning point for me, and it wasn't until that moment
that I actually wondered if I could do it.
Through finding a place in the game industry, I was able to start on a path of wondering
what else I might be able to do that I didn't think was possible.
Just being here is a pretty big one.
Employment, or the right employment, can have such a positive impact on a person's life,
but it's unfortunately something that's just inaccessible to most autistic people.
I would really love for as many people to be able to find their own place,
and I hope that the games industry can be one of those places for more people.
So if you would also like to try and help make a place for autistic people,
I have a few really simple points that anyone can think about.
Patience and awareness.
A big struggle for me on a daily basis is being perceived as rude when I don't mean to be.
I find that a lot of people don't ever actually examine social conventions, and one thing
you can do is ask yourself why you think something is rude and whether it's possible to interpret
it differently.
And it's okay if the answer is no, it's just a good habit to examine these things.
So a simple example is eye contact.
Does a person need to be looking at me to listen and understand?
And why does staring make me uncomfortable?
Is it from ascribing a meaning to it?
Can it be done accidentally?
And does that change how you feel?
Don't assume needs.
You'll hear it a million times, but every autistic person is different.
Ask what specific adjustments would help an individual,
and don't assume what an
autistic person is and isn't capable of.
Don't assume what's obvious.
Things like unwritten rules.
I find it really difficult to intuit what's expected of me.
If something needs to be done, then say it.
And if something needs to be done in a certain way,
explain that.
And if you want to be genuinely helpful, explain why.
Understanding for everyone.
Not everyone is open about being autistic.
Most people at some point in their lives will have met someone who is autistic without even realizing.
And having more patience and awareness for people in general can go a long way.
Thank you for listening.
Up next we have Alana Linnaire.
Hello everyone, I am Alana, rhymes with banana if you have an American accent, if you don't, it does not.
And my pronouns are she, her, and I am the lead dev and founder of Toad House Games and Team Toad House.
Toad House Games is a visual novel indie game studio.
Let me just set myself up here one second please, thank you.
We're making Call Me Sarah. Sarah is C-E-R-A. It is wish-listable. Hint, hint.
It's about making friends as an adult and it touches on therapy tools that are useful for people who don't have access to therapy.
I'm also the person... give me a second, I'm pregnant and talking is hard.
Okay. I'm also the person who organized the Palestinian itch
bundle last year that made almost a million dollars
for Palestinian aid.
So although I organized it, thank you to all of you.
I'd like to take a minute just to thank you,
because without you it wouldn't have been as successful.
So thank you to everyone who donated,
volunteered, participated.
I organized it, but you made it possible.
So thank you.
Round of applause for yourselves, please.
Today I'd love to chat about writing neurodivergent characters and stories for neurodivergent gamers.
So neurodivergent is the term when someone's brain processes,
learns, and or behaves differently
from what is considered typical.
Once seen as a problem,
neurodiversity now recognizes the human population is diverse
and brain behaviors that deviate
from the typical can be beneficial, as many people
on this panel have highlighted.
Although not magical.
So be careful, you're not like thinking, for example,
Rain Man, that movie, or there's many examples of magical,
they're magical beings.
Of course they're creative, they've got bipolar disorder.
Not like that.
Beneficial, not magical.
It does include things like autism, ADHD, and dyslexia.
It isn't limited to mental illness.
So neurodivergent is a big umbrella,
mental illness is a smaller thing.
I focus a lot on mental illness,
but we do touch on neurodivergency.
So that said, let me reintroduce myself.
I'm Alana Lanier, I'm the founder and lead dev
at Toad House Games, and I write games
for mentally ill and neurodivergent gamers.
However, when you're writing about heavy topics,
like I typically do, because visual novels
are a great medium for that,
you do have to write mindfully,
or you can trigger your player.
So, what is triggering?
There is a slang term in our community
that triggering is just getting really, really, really
angry about something.
Oh, I'm so triggered.
I hate it.
But when I use the word trigger, I mean a medical term.
It can cause serious health consequences.
It has nothing to do with being weak or too sensitive.
So for example, I lost my dog.
My dog was 18 years old, lived a very long life.
I got her when I was 12.
I lost her.
And two weeks...
Later, I was streaming on Twitch this beautiful indie game called What Comes After.
It takes place on a train, it's about the afterlife, are they dead, are they not?
It's great, play it.
But there's a dog on that train, and I would not have had a live audience to watch me mourn
my dog if I had known that it had touched on dead pets.
So trigger warnings and content warnings are useful.
in aiding gamers who decide if a game is safe for them, particularly in that moment.
It's not meant to make the world a soft place where we can't write about these things.
It's about giving information to your gamers so that they can make the decision for themselves.
I would have waited six months to play the game about the dead dog.
So games used to really add to the stigma,
if you think mental illness,
horror games that take place in mental wards,
you know, that type thing.
So I'll be talking about those.
I'm gonna highlight really quickly
because I want to get to my point,
we're running out of time.
Three really great examples of narrative versions in gaming.
So Celeste, there's breathing exercises built in,
there's distinct challenge levels to match the player,
and it accurately depicts a panic attack feeling
to those who haven't experienced one before.
Very useful.
Life is strange. Realistic themes and mental illness portrayed accurately.
Characters are more than their illnesses, they're proper people.
And there's a link in-game for health-seeking resources. Very useful.
And Hellblade, Sasuna, accurately portrays what it's like to hear voices and experience psychosis.
created with input from people who lived experiences of psychosis,
and allows players to experience psychosis via sound design, environment, and puzzles.
Amazing games, please play them.
But what do they have in common?
They allow neurotypical people, so not neurodivergent people,
to experience what it's like to have mental illness.
So if you already know what it's like to have mental illness,
those games aren't really an escape for you, they're kind of just a reminder.
These are important games and still should be made.
However, they're not able to be played
by many neurodivergent people.
Like, I can't play Hellblade.
So, this is Nicole from Call Me Sarah.
She's our therapist.
So, what do I do?
That sounds great.
How do I do this?
I have a couple of tips for someone who is trying
to make games for neurodivergent people.
So remember your fantasy, it's your North Star.
I'm of the belief that video games are fantasy.
We have power fantasies, money fantasies,
superhero fantasies.
My fantasy for all of my games
is feeling loved and accepted.
So a lot of people don't feel that in real life,
so I want them to escape their life,
play my games, and feel loved and accepted.
I sound emotional, I'm not emotional,
I swear I'm just pregnant.
Show examples of how to handle tricky situations.
So for example, in Good Luck in Home Cooking,
another game of ours, we have like vignettes
that take place in the Kongosaur universe.
Amira self-harms and Kenta, another character,
immediately takes care of her needs
and assures her she's safe with him.
He basically sees it and goes up to her and goes,
hey, saw that happen, didn't like it.
I mean, you probably feel like garbage,
so don't feel bad that it happened.
I don't want you to feel bad that you self-harmed,
but please, can we talk about it
so maybe you don't do it again,
because I'm your friend and this really concerned me.
So not only does it give an example to people
on how to handle the tricky situation
if they see a friend self-harm,
but I got a lot of emails from people going like,
that's what I needed to hear.
No one told me that in real life.
I really needed to hear that.
So it was lovely.
Makes up for all the hate I get from doing the Palestinian
Cryptom.
List common triggers.
So in the beginning of all our games,
I list all the common triggers I can possibly
imagine that happened in our games.
Because it's ultimately up to us to ensure
our own personal safety.
So give your gamers all the information
they need in order to make a good decision for themselves.
So write about the topics, write about the hard stuff.
Go ahead, torture your characters.
It doesn't matter, but tell your gamer
so they can go, mm, Doki Doki Literature Club,
maybe not for me.
Right mindfully, do we really need to see all the details or can we leave some of up to the
imagination of our players? Does the character need to live through trauma in front of us or
is the aftermath what's really important to our plot? That's going back to our North Star.
We have a vignette called Rule for Confidence. Sophia is a trans woman, she's one of the main
characters in it. I made sure she was not misgendered the whole time. I made sure that
we talked about how she felt about things, not...
show the trauma because trans people were the demographic we were writing for.
Why would we re-traumatize the people they live in? Why do that to your gamers?
And remember your audience. Are you writing to educate those who know about neurodivergent,
who don't know how neurodivergent feels? Or are you writing to make those with mental illness
feel represented? So these are my key tips. And for those of you who aren't neurodivergent in the
audience,
How do you do it?
Well, I have some tips for you too.
Hire those with lived experience.
Believe it or not, they're really good workers.
Naturally brings a different point of view to the table,
keeps hidden biases out of your games.
And then there's also cultural consultants
and sensitivity readers.
So cultural consultants are people you interview
as part of your writing research beforehand,
and they're great for reaching out with questions.
Really quick ones,
but especially like during Good Looking Home Cooking,
it was really handy to DM Osama every time.
I was like, I'm not sure, coffee, is that actually allowed during Ramadan?
And he would give me like the list of rules and it was really handy.
And sensitivity readers, they read your game at different stages to make sure that things
aren't that obvious to you or pointed out.
And remember to make sure that they know their suggestions are extremely welcome.
So for Good Luck in Home Cooking, we had a Korean translator who was also a sensitivity
reader because Jessica texts her mom in Korean.
And she was just making sure that the conversation sounded authentic to a Korean mom-daughter exchange.
And she said, my texting app is blue and yellow. Can we do that? Because a lot of people use this app.
So we made it blue and yellow, and it made the game better. So it's important to let them know suggestions are welcome.
So here's my socials.
I'm gonna go sit down,
because I feel like passing out.
Please call me Sarah, wishlisted on Steam.
Toad House Games is our visual novel studio.
Team Toad House is our fan club
and everything else that we do.
I'm Alana, and I would like to introduce Patrick,
who's remote, right?
Great, enjoy.
Thanks Alana. Hi, I'm Patrick. My pronouns are he him. I'm a UI artist and user experience designer based in Japan. I was diagnosed with ADHD and auditory processing disorder around the age of 10.
I was going to start this presentation with an anecdote, something to convince you that although ADHD doesn't seem like a big deal because it's so common. It can affect work performance relationships and even employment status.
But then the anecdote was just going to look something like this chart.
There was going to be a prologue for context, too many details, and then I go down a rabbit hole to
a related side story. I realize I get distracted, so I'm apologizing, and that's seven minutes,
so we will not do that. Instead, we'll start with a simple agenda. I'll explain what ADHD looks like
at work and how we can make things better together.
People with ADHD have chemical imbalances in their brain that cause symptoms neurotypical people experience, but in hard mode.
Symptoms vary based on nature and nurture, while gender, race, disability, and class can have a huge impact on how someone is treated.
Everyone's ADHD is different, which is why I've asked other game devs with ADHD to review this talk.
For starters, these are some of my symptoms.
Inattention.
Our nervous system is actually interest-based rather than importance-based.
Really, anything that breaks consistency.
Neurotypical people go into 30-minute Twitter rabbit holes a few times a day.
ADHDers do this every 30 minutes and forget their job interviews and anniversary dates before breakfast.
Also, breakfast. We forget breakfast a lot.
We understand the work, but the context can disappear.
Hyperactivity, I won't realize I'm tapping my foot
during a meeting until someone gets mad about it.
Impulsivity, what to eat, what to wear.
I just acquired a rabbit farm in Nebraska.
It varies depending on the day.
At work, this means I get excited by ideas
and interrupt people in meetings,
and then I apologize often.
So far, these are common symptoms that probably fit your image of ADHD, but what kind of person
loves note-taking, proactively organizes, focuses like nothing else, and does well in group settings?
All of these are actually coping mechanisms that I've had to learn over the years.
They're examples of masking ADHD, like Jade talked about earlier.
I have working memory issues, so if I can't keep up with my notes, I'm totally lost.
I'm a proactive organizer because I get overwhelmed by a bunch of raw data without filters.
I get into these hours-long flow states where I just forget about everything and it's another
rabbit hole and hopefully I haven't forgotten about another job interview.
I have difficulty reflecting internally.
Lots of people benefit from a group brainstorm,
but I don't even realize I need to brainstorm
until it's too late.
By comparison, solo projects
also become difficult and boring.
All that being said,
please challenge your expectations
of what ADHD coworkers are good at
while understanding how much work
it can take us to compensate.
To remove barriers for people with ADHD,
we need structure, consistency.
and care. Structure, bear with me on this. I'm about to rehash a Fast Company article that you've
definitely already read too many times, but this is important. Without structure,
I am a hot pile of garbage. Let's try to keep meetings short. I fade around 40 minutes. If
you have to go long, have breaks with snacks. Have a clear agenda that's shared beforehand
so we have time to prepare and freak out.
I may take my own notes, but it's good for everyone to agree where meeting minutes will be stored and who's taking them.
Give as much notice for meetings as possible and allow people to choose when they present.
I have difficulty focusing when I'm thinking about what I want to say. It's better to share my work first so I can focus on note taking for the rest of the meeting.
Consistency.
Right here.
If you need me to do something that's important,
a physical reminder is my last line of defense
against my ADHD.
I like it when people give me an urgent task
and have a post-it reminder to go with it,
but please check with your ADHD coworkers.
It can come off as super passive aggressive,
like a post-it war with a roommate.
If you're working remotely, send me a message.
Not yet.
If you're working remotely, send me a message
after you add that JIRA ticket.
It's like a digital post-it.
Kanban boards like Trello are great visual tools to organize tons of information into bite-sized cards.
A couple of notes here. When people go outside these systems, I lose tasks and forget them. So please use them.
Plenty of talented ADHDers find project management software overwhelming.
Try not to make these systems a hiring requirement and be willing to train new hires.
I structured my day into big blocks of time to enable flow states.
Emily told me flow states are like beautiful jam sessions.
Interruptions are like a record scratch that makes the beat almost unrecoverable.
There's this thing called the switch cost effect, where even neurotypical people
take 23 minutes to recover their focus after an interruption, as small
as a random text message.
Plan check-ins and meetings, encourage everyone to set up office hour availability, and don't push those boundaries unless it's an emergency.
Care. Folks with ADHD do stuff that in our non-ADHD-friendly world can come across as rude.
For example, I often don't make eye contact with people during conversations because I can get distracted by facial expressions.
During meetings, I may work on an art task or a sketch.
Doodling actually helps me focus on you.
Think of it like spare processing capacity
that if unused starts working on another task.
I need to keep myself engaged with something
or it'll take over every spare process.
In the office, if I'm wearing headphones,
yes, I am ignoring you.
And no, it's not personal.
Sometimes I'll even turn off messaging software.
All of this is to help me get my work done.
Speaking to managers here, many of us prefer to sit in quiet areas that aren't near an entrance or busy area for obvious reasons.
And lastly, let's just say what we mean. Alyssa Sweetman told me how the anxiety of guessing intent in a workplace that's filled with jargon stressed her out every day.
Bottom line, do your research and check in with your ADHD colleagues, as well as your neurotypical co-workers.
Some may be keeping their ADHD to themselves, so it's important to remember that this is private medical information.
I know I've had mine because I worry it'll keep me from getting hired somewhere.
And giving this talk has been a pretty big milestone in accepting my ADHD. So thank you for listening.
A special note to the people, a special thank you note to the people that offered me feedback on this talk and gave me permission to give them a shout out.
You can find me on Twitter at SheGagari and you can sign up to playtest the mobile RPG
I'm working on called Cyborg Immortal through the website right there. Thanks a lot.
And I'm going to pass it to Ezekiel. That is the wonderful Ezekiel who is next.
I did not miss Q at all.
Oh, right.
Hello.
I'm Ezekiel.
I'm a game designer and a project lead
from Norway that loves his wife, coffee, output logs,
and his kids.
I'm 35 years old, and I'm an Unreal Engine fanatic
since the Unreal Development Kit in 2004.
I'm the project lead on digitally adapted training,
a collaboration with Norway's largest specialist hospital,
and the founder of AECRE and Wise Urban Studios.
We do rapid prototypes, consultancy, and also medical software.
And today I will talk to you about the ethical responsibility of accessibility.
So, oh, sorry.
It all started with a friend of mine suffering a brain stroke in his 40s.
His drive and iron will to rehabilitate made me look into the possibilities of games in brain trauma rehabilitation.
Back in 2019, I pitched an idea to the large specialist
hospital here.
My idea was to reinvent how we approach brain trauma
rehabilitation and how we develop games for it.
By developing a VR framework for accessibility that allowed us
to tweak and adjust features for each individual patient
to their specific needs, we managed
to include patients that normally wouldn't be able
to play games in rehabilitation.
Traumatic brain injury and stroke patients often exhibit
neurodiverse traits.
They may have aphasia, lack of concentration, or disordered
vision, loss of hearing.
And for us to include everyone, we made several
systems, some of which are quite normal in games today.
So we created minigames based on the feedback from health
care personnel and from patients using the
accessibility framework that we built.
VR games and VR games, they see up to 200% increased
engagement in training.
So this is very important.
And here are some of the systems that we did create
for the project.
We had individual VR control schemes like AutoGrab,
HoldToGrab, ClickToGrab.
in order to meet the mouse of people with paralysis.
Games are also playable with one arm, and we can toggle a
switch to convert the right controller into the left
controller if needed.
For visual adjustments, we had highlighted colors and
gameplay and elements like high contrast and easy to read
fonts with voiceover.
after TBI or stroke, up to 30 to 40 percent of the people have impaired vision. And visibility,
improving visibility and adding voiceover helped our users quickly identify important
information. But also immersion is very important. We avoided artificial things like omnipresent
voices. Rather everything comes from a natural source in the world. And this is more comfortable
and is less disconcerting for people, especially those that struggle with attention.
Another important element was creating a relaxing environment.
We built our world with relaxing colors, a tropical island with a cozy beach, sunbeds,
books, fruits, and other things you'd normally associate with relaxing.
This was important for us to sell the illusion to our users.
We also avoided having distracting colors
and clutter in our world.
Finding a balance between believable and overwhelming
can be challenging, but with the help of early workshops
during development, we were able to strike a balance early.
And the early hands-on experience with our user
was paramount to achieving our goal.
Cluttered and overwhelming worlds, loud sounds,
flashy imagery, omnipresent sounds,
and out-of-place elements can be very hard
for neurodivergent users.
The infamous 100% volume splash screen
still haunts games to this day
and can cause problems for a lot of players,
especially those that are neurodivergent.
Some are even exhausted before they start to play the game.
This is not good.
We have to think diversely about our games
and adding features that help neurodiverse players
in any games, not just applied games, is very important.
I encourage everyone here to think about accessibility
to a
neurodiverse scope, not just the normal scope of accessibility.
After all, there is 1.2 billion people that are neurodivergent.
So, why is this an ethical issue and why should you care?
Well, the lack of diverse accessibility features in games
isn't just a gameplay issue, it is an ethical issue. It excludes
people from partaking in an activity that brings all layers of society together.
Not only in applied games, but in all games.
While we still face challenges with internet connectivity
and hardware quality, games has the potential
to be the place where you can socialize as equals,
where social constructs and barriers
doesn't have to hinder us.
If we want a diverse and understanding tomorrow,
we need to experience each other
without limitations and prejudice.
This will be even more important as the metaverse,
whatever shape or form that will take, becomes reality.
So, I ask of you, everyone here today,
help the world become a better tomorrow
by thinking diversly about accessibility,
and please do not leave any gamer behind.
Thank you, I'm Sikil.
Thank you.
Music