that's not at all what it's about by the way. Another round
of applause for Ojiro. The reason I have him up here, I'm
not going to look at him, he can secretly give you guys a thumbs
up and thumbs down if I'm talking bullshit and making
lies up here. That's the whole point. I'm going to try to make
this quick. I'm not that great of a public speaker. Hopefully
we can get to the questions quick and start thinking of them
now.
I should introduce myself again. Nigel Lowry. I work at
Devolver Digital. So you don't need a fucking publisher. But if
you do, ask questions. And that's what this really is
about. It's a little misleading of a title. I think that one of
the biggest things that people need to know is that you don't
need a publisher. I think everyone knows that by now. And
this is what this discussion is about. If you do, start asking
questions. Mostly, like I said, it's going to be about asking
questions. Not right now. No one go to the mic.
But the fundamental part of getting any sort of business
deal at all, including getting a publisher, is to kind of ask
questions. Know everything you can possibly know. People are
still coming in. Welcome. I'll wait.
I'm just kidding. This might be a short presentation. Actually
it will be long because I mumble a lot. But I invite you to start
thinking of these questions now because I think I'm here. I want
to answer them. This is a forum in which I can give you some
information. But I do want you guys to think of questions
because I'm happy to answer as many as I can. And I'll stay
late. I have nothing else to do. I'm a really sad person.
So a few disclosures. The first being I also work at an indie
publisher like I mentioned before. And the reason I wanted
to do this talk is we get a lot of pitches. Literally dozens and
dozens of pitches. Please do not tell my wife I said that.
and it's become very clear that a lot of developers don't really
know either to even ask questions or the right questions
to ask and who to ask them to. Like any industry, gaming is
fantastic, but there's good guys, there's bad guys and
there's good guys that don't know what the fuck they're doing
and maybe, you know, aren't providing all the information
that they should. So maybe I can make some decent points today,
talk about what we look for, what to look for, excuse me, and
what to ask about before signing an agreement.
So this is the agenda, aka last chance to leave before it's
rude. With that said, you know, this is not going to have a lot
of cool charts and data. This is almost all entirely anecdotal
stuff. My intention here is to pass on information to everybody
here from my side of the fence, from the evil publisher side of
the fence and bring to light some of the issues and
challenges that crop up even in our business and things I hear
from developers I talk to.
So any publishers, one board every minute. I'm going to back
up. The things I'm going to talk about are indie publishers.
What is that? What the fuck does that even mean? Publisher
partner. Are those things the same thing? Are they different?
I think that's kind of the crux of this conversation. And then
common issues. Common issues we just kind of see.
So any publishers, a.k.a. one born every minute. When I was
thinking about what I was going to say here, I kept coming back
to this inherent struggle that small developers have on why
they might even look for a publisher. The game market is
wonderful, amazing, but you're all pouring your heart and soul
into these games and it can become pretty terrifying when
it's time to either really work on it or it's getting close and
you want to launch, right?
So often times developers don't want to go it alone. This kind
of made me think of this famous scene from the opening moments
of Legend of Zelda where link is about to embark on this grand
adventure. He walks into this room and some old dude tosses him
a sword and gives him a warning.
link takes it and doesn't ask a single question. Just rolls out
assumes because this guy knows what he's done, been there,
knows what he's doing, is going to give him all the information
he needs. What do we find out? Yes, the sword was helpful, but
it was not the only tool that he actually needed. He needed
quite a few things to finish his adventure.
and there's more things necessary to complete this task
than just the sword. So he didn't ask questions. He doesn't
know who this guy is or what he did. And he doesn't know what
kind of cut this guy has taken off the back end of this
adventure, right? Maybe this guy is getting 75% of all the
rupees that he collects. We don't even know. And what
happened to Link? He didn't ask questions and he ended up in a
shitty sequel. I'm saying it. Sell the two subs.
So publishers have been around for nearly as long as game
developers but I did zero research on the subject so that
might not be true. But what I'm certain is there's always been
this animosity between developers and publishers and
rightfully so. The latest I think most obvious thing is at
the end of every kick starter people mention why are they
doing this kick starter. Well, because they want to avoid
publishers because they're bad, they'll ruin creativity, they'll
take a hold of the game, they're going to cheat them out of
money.
and honestly publishers have behaved badly for years and this
is an absolutely perfect rational thing to say. But this
happens all the time and it's unfortunate and there's some
good people out there and some bad people like I said before
but this happens all the time.
But I do think the game has changed. I think everyone in
this room, this is not news. The game has changed. Digital
distribution, I put the little exclamation marks because I'm
not as good as a Giro at graphics. But I put these sweet
exclamation marks up there because digital distribution is
a point that really changed a lot of things. It bestowed an
unbelievable amount of leverage with the developer that changed
everything because you can get directly to your consumers. This
is an important moment and for now, like I said, it's shifted
this kind of perceived power.
So we've seen those bar graphs, those charts where there's huge
acceleration in the number of games being released on steam,
app store, everything like that. And you can argue a lot of
different reasons. Digital distribution is one. Accessible
tools, less stringent curation on these store fronts. But
that's not the news. Everyone knows there's a lot of games out
here. I especially think this audience knows there's a shit
load of games out there, right? What's interesting to us is,
hey, Evan.
What is news to us, what is interesting to us is a lot of
service providers now. People, whether it is a publisher or a
localization company, there is a lot of things being built up
around any games and any game developers. A service provider
like I said can be anyone from a localization company to a
testing studio but there is more and more of these. And game
publishers are no exception.
The indie publisher market has lots of options now. Devolver
being one. As you can see this is a small example of the
different publishers you can go with. What's important is to
understand each one's direction, their strategy, their
capabilities.
know what is right for your game. The names on this screen,
these two screens, I didn't know there was going to be two
screens. The names on these two screens are just a handful of
companies to consider. They are publishers, game labels,
whatever, but they all have their own kind of thing of
taking your game, working with your game and getting it to a
larger audience. Sony computer entertainment obviously has
their kind of angle to do it. Indie funds specialize in
obviously funding Indies.
and having really, really friendly developer agreements.
And folks like team 17, adult swim and double fine are
fantastic groups that can release your game, but they're
developers themselves and they can offer a lot of insight in
the game development. My point here is the publisher can mean a
lot of different things, so I'm going to lump them all together,
but they all have their own minutia and details of what they
might specialize in. Water, sorry.
Okay. So I want to get to the meat of this. We know there's a
shit load of options. I'm cussing a lot. I apologize.
There's a ton of options out there when a developer wants to
find a publisher to work with and now you need to get to this
vetting process. What's going to work for you, what's going to
work for your team and what's going to work for the game
itself. So most of the developers that we talk to, the
discussion starts around what is the publisher going to do for
me. And then it kind of works its way towards what can you do
for my game. That's kind of an important evolution of that
discussion.
So the best way I thought when I was thinking about what to say
here is to frame this by categorizing this into what are
things that a publisher should do for you and what are things
that a partner should do for you. Now these things aren't
necessarily at odds with each other but they don't also
necessarily always come hand in hand. So this is what I want
people to be careful to when they're talking to publishers,
partners, game labels, whatever it's being called these days.
You need to find out the potential publisher you're
working for and find out what they're going to do for you and
what you are looking for in a partner and reconcile those two
things. Because that's what's really, really important. You
don't want to pay for things basically that you're not going
to use and you want to find a publisher that can do all the
things you need it to do.
So what can a publisher provide? These are the basic
things that people think about when they're talking about a
publisher. A developer can hypothetically do all of these
things themselves. Actually not hypothetically, they can do all
these things themselves. That's why it's called self-publishing
and a lot of people do it. The reason people like Ojiro work
with us is because they don't want to do them and they think
that a publisher can do them better and more efficiently.
So they can focus on making the game. Give the thumbs up right
now. Okay.
your royalty check is due. So these are the base level things
though. These are not things that should excite you. These
are what you should be expecting from a publisher. I don't really
want to dwell on all of them. I'm not going to go into too
much detail but I do want to talk about marketing
distribution. I think these are the areas that are maybe most
foreign to developers and maybe distinguishing characteristics
I guess between different publishers you can talk to.
So marketing. Marketing is like saying I'm a game developer.
It's game development. What does that mean? There's a lot of
things in marketing. There's a lot of different disciplines.
That's PR, that's advertising, that's events. It's everything
that's going to position and communicate your game out to the
world. And this is where you need to start asking questions.
You're going to see this theme throughout my discussion. You
need to start asking questions about everything that this
publisher that you're talking to might do. So the PR teams, for
example. Understand, is it them doing the PR?
is it a team of people doing the PR? Are they contracting this
out? All of these things are valid. Finding out where are
their PR teams. When they say they're going to do PR, is it
just North America? That's not good. There's a lot of people
outside of North America that buy video games and want to be
talked to with their own cultural nuances and localize
the information you're giving them into their language.
do they include streamers and YouTubers when they are talking
about PR? If they don't include YouTubers and streamers, walk
out of the door, lock that door and set the building on fire
because they don't know what they are doing.
advertising. How are they going to spend this money? I think a
lot of times we talk to folks and we'll mention advertising
and they don't even ask what that means. And we then give
the information or at least someone should give the
information to them. But you need to ask how this money will
be spent. They don't look at the line and go great, we have a
great advertising budget. You need to find out what that means
and how they're going to spend it.
events do they go to? Do they go to events? Do they have people
that go to events outside of North America? I think that's
important too. There's a lot of amazing things like bit summit
in Japan, Ojiro went to and there's a lot of amazing events
to go to that are going to spread your game outwards. So
just be mindful of where their PR activities are really
happening.
And then of course a cohesive campaign, right?
You need to look at what they've done,
what is their strategy, what have they done in the past,
how have they customized that for different games?
There's not a template to marketing.
There's not a template to game development.
I guess there is if you're making some really clones,
you know, clone mobile games or something like that.
I didn't look at you for a reason.
Not you, not you.
But you need to find out what their strategy is.
Find out what their beliefs are in marketing.
The other part is distribution. I'm going to be honest, five
years ago, publishers that we know or people I know or any
publisher could tell you, well, I can get your game on steam.
That was a lot of times enough for people to get excited and
sign up with them. I don't think that's right. That's definitely
not right anymore. Anyone can get your game on steam or you
can bypass steam or go on play station. There's itch. There's
all sorts of amazing places to get your game directly to
consumers.
But I will note when I was thinking about this, it's fair
or unfair. Publishers do have their advantage. You should ask
them what these advantages might be. One of the things I talk
about is publishers get direct lines sometimes with a lot of
people at them. Because they have a lot of content, then
people at steam or valve or play station or x box or whoever
You have a direct contact there and there's advantages of having
that for placement, store placement, things like that.
There's things like publisher sales.
Like, again, right or wrong, there's a publisher sale that
Devolver Digital will get and it will increase revenue for these
games.
So you need to ask your publisher what they do and how
they're going to make more money than you would make on yours
alone when it comes to sales and distribution.
And the last thing I'd say on this distribution is look what
else you're going to be amongst with the game, with the
catalog of games that publisher has. To see where you sit.
There's some games, there's some publishers out there or
partners or whatever you want to call them at this point in
the discussion that specialize in things. There's point and
click adventure folks that do really, really good, have a lot
of point and click adventures and you would sit amongst them
and there's some synergy there.
So these are what a publisher like I said should provide. And
I like in this, this is the basics when you're buying a car
and the car salesman says well it's got four wheels, it's got
windshield wipers and it will take you from point A to point
B. Yeah I know that. Sell me on what's next. I think this is the
crucial moment for a lot of developers that don't keep
asking questions. Or the publisher doesn't provide more
answers of what they're going to do beyond those things. I don't
know how to emphasize this enough but these things that you
see up here.
That's the base level thing you should be expecting. So what do
I mean, so what's next? What's after that, right? And this is
where I kind of got in my head this discussion that was going
on, discussion with developers we work with and discussion with
the folks that I work with at my company, what's next step? We
think it's being a true partner. And what do I mean like that?
ask that publisher, ask them about funding, ask them about
things. But these, when you're funding partner, you're going to
ask them some questions I'm going to get into. But you also
need, it's very important to start asking questions to the
developers they worked with previously. That's where you're
going to find a new angle, a new way of maybe assessing this
publisher. Because they're going to tell you what happened,
whether it was good or bad.
another thing, when you're talking to developers from this
publisher that you're speaking with, don't just talk to the
people that sold a lot of copies because they're probably going
to be pretty happy, right? And they're probably going to be
pretty pleased with it. Go find the developer that maybe, you
know, the game was fine but didn't sell a ton of copies
because you maybe can find a new dimension to that discussion.
And, you know, find more about how that developer, excuse me,
how that publisher carries themselves when maybe things
aren't as stellar as, you know, you had hoped.
So what can a partner provide? A true partner, and again this
is where I think a developer needs to start looking and
start assessing more and not stop at what does a publisher
provide. These things like I said aren't easy to ascertain
and the publisher is going to, you know, there's a salesman
you're basically talking to. They want to sell you on them as
a company. And I'm going to speak to creativity and
enthusiasm.
AKA giving a fuck about your game. I know it's language but
that's an important part because you don't want to sign up for
somebody that really doesn't care about your game once it's
signed on. The stage and the spotlight, a personal
relationship and brutal honesty.
So when I say creativity I don't just mean good ideas for launch
trailers. I don't just mean like hey what about some slow-mo
action and slow-mo music. It's going to be beautiful. I'm not
talking about those kind of things. I'm talking about the
creative enthusiasm about every element of your game. That's
just marketing, that's distribution, that's production,
that's funding. Working with you in the way you may have money
already and doing things smart and different.
to make sure you're happy and comfortable. Don't just check
stuff off a list. These are people thinking and being
creative about every part of your game. Again, look at the
publisher's body of work. That's the easiest thing to do. You can
scroll through their YouTube channel. You can scroll through
their website. You can scroll through Metacritic. You can see
what they've worked on. You can see where they've been
successful and where they may be applied creativity to everything
they do. You need to find out if they've done things that are
successful before and how that might apply to your game.
I mean frankly they're going to show you all the best things
they've ever done and the big fancy launch trailers or they
could. I'm just saying a good one is going to show you some
smart thinking. And I'm not going to try and pimp us out as
a publisher. That's the whole point. I just want to talk about
in general. But one thing I do want to reference because I use
this in my discussion with developers as a point of when
you're thinking about every aspect of it. This is a game
called hotline Miami that we worked on in 2011, 2012.
point I want to make is this ridiculous phone number we set
up for hotline Miami. It was late one night and we're
thinking of fun things to do. If you played the game, part of
the game is you get these crazy calls from a telephone. Crazy
messages. We thought it would be fun to, we found a Google voice
number in Miami, Florida and we grabbed it and we left a weird
message and we start leaving this phone number.
you know, press releases, website, social media. So we
sent that out for a week. Never checked it. That would be funny.
What if people start calling you if they leave messages. To open
it up, it's got 4,000 voice mails and like 600 text
messages, which I didn't know you could do on Google voice and
it was very concerning what people were writing.
but the cool thing, my point with this is, is it's not, don't
just look at the high level fancy things, you think, I mean
those are very important, trailers are important, booths
are important, but look for where people are thinking of
things like this that cost nothing and really like this,
engage the community and get them excited and talking about
it. Because that's where I think you're going to find that
difference in creativity.
The next thing is stage and spotlight. A good publisher
should put this developer first. This is important for your
personal fulfillment as a developer but it's also very
important for you as a studio and you as maybe a lone
developer. That when you're done with this game people know about
your work and that you did it. And you were the one that made
this.
and when you're ready to do your next thing, they know who you
are. It's not about necessarily whose logo is bigger, but just
make sure that you are always center stage whenever your
gaming is being presented and not the publisher putting their
name out there first.
And a good partner will do this. And I will be frank with
you, we fight for this, have to fight platforms and first party
people to say, I know what your rules are but you got to take
devolver digital off of this. You need to put the developer on
there. Because I think it's very important that people
understand that they made it. I can't make games. I can barely
put together a power point. I promise you that. And I think
it's important for you and your studio to have that kind of
spotlight put on you.
The one thing I will note and I think, you know, Ojiro is up
here, it's a really good example. Not all developers
necessarily want that spotlight. We were first working together,
we had to go to a twitch stage, what was it, PAX East, we had
some twitch thing.
And he came to me and was like, I'm not super excited about
being in the spotlight on this one. So your publisher, your
partner, needs to understand that and understand what your
little idiosyncrasies might be, what you are comfortable doing.
And maybe you, the publisher, excuse me, not you, the
developer, you, the publisher, might need to speak for your
game, okay? And I'm not talking about marketing bullet points
from a fact sheet. I'm talking about knowing your game inside
and out. Being able to demo the hell out of that game in front
of somebody, speak for you and represent you and your studio
well.
I think this is a pretty crucial part because the whole idea is
you guys can focus on your game. You're not going to be able to
go to every show. You're not going to be able to go to every
event. You need to make sure the partners out there that you
trust will represent your game well and speak kind of in the
tone that you want it to be presented. This one is me almost
tearing up over there when Ojiro was up here.
because it's a personal relationship. You need to make
sure, this is a very aspirational thing, but you're
looking for a personal relationship with these folks.
This person, this partner you're going to work with, they're
going to be a part of your life for 18 months, two years, five
years, whatever it is. And you need to make sure.
that you can develop some, you don't have to necessarily like
them, but you have some sort of personal working good
relationship with them. I'm sorry, you may not want to have
a beer with them and spend the night at their house and staying
up all night playing NBA jam. But you do have to have some
sort of personal relationship with them and you need to
understand the organization of the company itself. The guy that
me, let's say me, that is signing your game, let's not say
me, I'm not supposed to use examples of me.
the person that's signing your game, you need to make sure if
that's not the person you're dealing with on a day-to-day
basis, who is that? Understand how that company works, how that
publisher works and who are the people you can go to and speak
with when things need to get done. And you're not talking to
the person that's just your handler, the person that can
actually execute and make things happen for you. The other part,
I think I have it up here, can they work?
can they contact them at night, weekends or mid-coitus. I know
it's kind of a joke, but you need to understand that we, you
know, you guys don't work 9 to 5. In fact, I'm pretty sure it's
more like 5 to 9 based on the people I work with. You guys
have insane hours, right? So you're going to need someone
there, someone you're going to be able to talk to and contact
at any point. And I think you need to talk to the other
developers they work with to see how that goes. Because if it
says 9 to 5 company and you're going to get an answering
machine or you're going to get...
you're not going to be able to get a hold of them, that's
something important you're going to need to know because
things go wrong constantly as you know.
And then what are the lengths that people are, this publisher,
this potential partner is willing to go for you. A lot of
the people I know I'm talking to and a lot of people I work with
are very small companies and they're the same people that are
making the game, the same people plugging in the computers to the
events. So you need to understand how far this partner,
this publisher will go and they're not too fancy to go get
your breakfast tacos when you need them when you're setting up
your demo kiosk.
And then the last thing is brutal honesty. If you have
those other things, a personal relationship for example, the
brutal honesty won't be a problem. And I mean this is
going to be a two way street when I talk about brutal
honesty. There's a lot of uncomfortable talks that might
happen when you're working with a business like a publisher.
Money is an uncomfortable subject. Not just the initial
talks about money but ongoing talks about needing more money
and then when money starts rolling in from the game being
sold.
understanding and being very clear how that money is coming
in and where it's going. Being able to talk about these things
plainly and openly is very important. And then talking
about, I put on here, tell each other that you suck. You need to
be able to, the publisher, the partner that you're talking to
needs to be able to tell you what they think honestly about
the game. And you need to be able to accept that.
that criticism and either take it or dismiss it. I know we
talked about quite a bit, I was watching your talk and there's a
lot of elements that were like, eh, I personally didn't like
that. Nojira was like, cool, fuck you, I'm keeping it in
there. And it's great. And that's the kind of thing you
need to be able to say to a real partner, right? At the same
time, he needs to be able to tell me, I'm sorry I'm picking
on you, there were supposed to be other developers up here that
are now sitting in the back I see.
The other thing that I would say here is that you need to be
able to tell that partner, that publisher, that you don't like
what they're doing. You need to speak up. If you don't like how
the game is being presented, you don't like the trailer, you
don't like whatever it is, the steam page, whatever it is,
speak up. It's your game. Take a hold of it and tell them that
they're doing a bad job on something.
And the last thing I want to say on this brutal honesty thing
is this comes up in a lot of discussions when I'm talking
with developers and they tell me they're talking to another
publisher. If a publisher guarantees you success, they're
fucking lying to you. There's no guarantee of success. I got the
clearance to talk about this but this guy Paul Hart who made a
game called fistful of gun. It was a great game. It didn't sell
really well. And we talked about it. We were honest with each
other the whole time of what these.
what these projections are looking like and once the game
wasn't doing well, what can we do to hopefully, the game
recouped, made money, but how we can maximize it. Because he
spent a lot of time on this game. And we maybe didn't do a
good job. And he maybe didn't make the best game he possibly
could.
no one needs to point fingers here. You need to be brutally
honest like how do we make this work now that the game isn't
going as well as we hoped. So I think you need to talk to other
developers and see how they handle not only success but not
success. I'm not going to say failures but not success.
There are a lot more things than this. I just have some things
that I thought were important to bring up. This extends like
this, you need to find this deeper level of commitment that
extends past this kind of publisher developer relationship.
This is not an all encompassing list, but my point is I think
you just need to look past the basics.
and what the publisher should give you and look beyond what
you really need as a person. Because you all have different
situations, you all have different circumstances which
you're operating. So you need to look past that and ask as many
questions as possible. So this leads to this last little piece
about some common issues that crop up, right? This is all
again anecdotal, but I thought they were worthy of these
amazing slides that I put together.
Clearly some of these are related to the publisher partner
kind of elements that I just talked about. So I'll make it
kind of quick. Intellectual property, IP, if the game is
your baby, the IP is its soul. So you need to take care of both
and hold on to both. Do not sell your IP. Do not make it part of
the agreement.
There's a lot of reasons why. Obviously, you know, SQL and
things like that. But that ends up being one of the most
important parts of this. And it strangely still comes up in
conversations we have like, do you guys want IP? And if they
want IP, that's a whole other level. You should absolutely
hold on to it. But owning it is just kind of a part of it.
and be mindful how your IP is being presented. And how it's
being positioned overall. If there's damage done to it while
you are promoting the game, marketing game, it doesn't just
affect that game, it affects your studio and it affects any
future games in that series. And the last part is from the best
movie of all time, Spaceballs.
and the idea is your IP is not just your game, remember that,
it is about any sort of opportunities that exist within
it. So whether it's T-shirts, comic books that are made,
movies, feature length film, down well the movie which is
coming to theaters next year. Is it? Okay, good.
I got the IP. But it's something important to keep in mind that
it's not just the game itself. These things do not let a
partner, whoever it is, mess with how your game is presented
and how your IP is presented. I want to have a whole other
quiet talk in a room with each and every one of you about
agreements. Do not settle, do not assume anything in
agreement. Ask the questions, it's your right to do it.
one example, please, please, please be very clear on how the
money flows into the game and back out of the project when
it's done. There's a whole other talk that would be way more
boring than this one but it's really important of
understanding how your game is going to be recouped, how the
cost the publisher might put out there might recoup them, how
they're going to recoup, when they're going to be recouped
because it could be the difference between how much
money you're making like not only short term but long term
as well.
can be very tricky so ask for examples. One thing we do is we
provide a spreadsheet where you can literally see where the
money is going in and you type in the unit sold and the average
unit price and it tells you, shows you exactly how it comes
back out. I think this is so important because you do not
want to be wrong on something like that. Especially after the
fact.
And then I put lock your shit up to developers. Make sure you
have clear agreements amongst yourselves and the freelancers
you work with. We can't help you. If you had an agreement, a
handshake, chest bump or whatever it is about the music
or about some freelance work, if you don't have an agreement,
there's nothing we can do about it as a publisher. That's the
agreement you made. And oftentimes people start asking,
what do I do? Can you guys pay them this money?
and that's not in our agreement. It becomes a really tough
conversation to have. So make sure that you understand, you
know, have a very clear understanding, ideally in
agreement with other people you work with. And the last piece is
poor communication. Do not save changes to the very end when
you're working with a partner like, or a publisher or a
partner.
you need to, if the game is going to be late, bring it up
as soon as you think it's going to be late. Because that helps
everyone including yourself involved. Having, you know,
making, knowing who the decision makers are, talking to them and
being very informed back and forth of what's going on is
super important. I know it's pretty generic to say like have
good communication, but I can't emphasize it enough. You are in
charge of your game.
make sure you're in charge of your game. Stay in charge of
your game. And the last part is related to what we talked about
before, sustainability. I think that's a huge thing that people
don't think about. At least we see it with developers we work
with and developers we don't. Is understanding sustainability for
publisher and your sustainability.
If you sign on with somebody, like I said, there's lots of
them out there that call themselves publishers. You need
to do your research, like we're talking about, that they're
going to be around when your game launches. Because if you
sign a deal and they go away, that's really, really going to
hurt you and your situation. So kind of know who funds them,
right? Who's funding that developer? Excuse me, who's
funding that publisher? How do they have money? And what are
they going to do? Are they going to be around? Right?
but also don't plan for yourself. Plan on your funding.
When you're pitching, do not low ball a publisher. That helps
nobody. You need to understand what's going to take to launch
your game and then what's going to take for those two or three
months after your game is launched. When people start,
when the money starts coming in, you know, Steam, Playstation,
they all pay. It's not like someone buys the game and they
hand you your money. It takes months sometimes, six weeks to
two months for your money to come through. So if you've only
funded your game up to release.
you might have two months that you don't have any money coming
in. And we see this time and time again and it's fine. We
can keep advancing people but I think it's good because if
you're in an agreement and the money runs out and you really
need money and you ask them for more, they could ask for royalty
change and things like that. Things you don't want to get
into.
And also have an idea what your next project is if possible.
It's always good if something doesn't go well you're not
spinning your wheels for a few months wondering what am I going
to do next. I know that's easier said than done from the
publisher up here. What do I have up here? Provocative
recap.
So there's lots of publishing options that a lot of people to do a lot of things very important to understand what that publisher
You're working with what they do what their angle is you know what they do. Well what they might not do as well
Understand your partner complete, and you know everything you can about that partner
and the last part, second to last part is you're in charge
so stay in charge. Never forget that. Never forget you're the
one that made this game. Ultimately they need you more
than you need them. You can self publish if you want to and
that's my last point. Self publish. I mean there's a lot of
people that do it very successfully and it's much better
than getting into a bad deal. I know there might be tough
situations you might be in but you know, you don't need a
fucking publisher. So you can self publish if you need to.
It's better than being in a bad agreement.
And now if you have any questions, I'm happy to answer
them. No questions. Apparently no questions. But thank you very
much for coming out.