VR lessons learned in a level design of Blood and Truth.
So as the title of the talk suggests,
we're going to be focusing entirely around VR.
And starting off, I'm going to touch up on the topics
of traversal and metrics, both of which
are extremely important elements to VR,
as together they create a foundation
of comfortable spatial awareness and movement.
Next up, gameplay mechanics, which I like to refer to
as a level designer's palette, as these are all the things
that level designers should be taking creative risks with
in attempt to make the best possible level.
And finally, we'll break down a level beat by beat,
discussing all the core VR considerations along the way.
Before we jump into all of that, my name's Harry Shirazi.
I'm the lead level designer at Sony's London studio.
And these are some of the games that I've worked on
over the past 10 years as a level designer.
For the past five years, however,
I've been working exclusively within VR.
And I think that as a team at London studio,
we probably make the most expensive VR titles on the market.
So I wanted to share some lessons I've personally learned working in AAA VR,
which I hope will shed light on what I consider to be some must have
considerations whenever making a VR game.
And for those of you who haven't played or seen any of Blood and Truth,
here's the launch trailer for the game.
What do I want? Your operations.
He's not going to start an all out war. He's not big enough.
We're gonna go and find out.
You're just gonna walk in there?
We need to push back hard or we're finished.
For the players.
So from the trailer we can gather that Blood & Truth is an action-adventure FPS
that features some drama in the form of a revenge story, gunplay,
fuse breaker puzzles and high action set pieces.
Okay, so as mentioned in the agenda,
we're gonna quickly review what traversal means
to Blood & Truth.
To embody one of the core pillars of the game,
being the action hero means that the controls
need to be as intuitive as possible.
And here's a clip of how it works in game.
The player is presented with a choice of waypoints.
When they choose one, they press the move button to go.
They can strafe and cover,
but the player is always essentially making forward progress
from one piece of cover to another.
Think of it a bit like an automated roadie run in Gears,
with the ability to shoot the whole way.
And we actually consulted with a former SAS soldier
on how they move in combat situations.
And this concept of staying low
and pushing forward towards danger
actually fits in line with how the SAS operates.
So some comfort considerations to take note of.
We do a small amount of easing in and easing out
when we start and stop moving.
And we also vary the speed
depending on the distance that the player has moved.
So the shorter the distance, the slower the movement.
And this is because we found that moving short distances
quickly was a comfort trigger.
We also deliberately split up chunks at a level
to work with either standing or crouch traversal.
It's moving up and down repeatedly
can also be a comfort trigger too.
Finally, we limited backtracking purely
to where all of our weapons are located.
Given the option to backtrack
across the entire traversal graph,
really increased the cognitive load on the player,
which could easily lead to confusion
with insider firefights.
Given our tagline for the game was be the action hero,
we wanted to make sure our traversal method actually helped the player to fulfill this fantasy.
Here's what it all looks like under the hood. Internally, we refer to this kind of gizmo
information as proxies, so I'll be referring to proxy information throughout the rest of the talk.
As you can see, it's a spline network. Lots of forward and diagonal movements.
Every time we ever rotate the player is during interactive traversal sections,
where the player uses their hands to climb or crawl.
We split the traversal graph into two separate modes.
The different colors on the spline represent
pre or post combat and combat.
And this simply indicates where you can traverse to
depending on if you're in combat or not.
There's also a little bit of extra information
in the spline proxies indicating the direction of travel.
So as a quick tip,
I found that traversing through a white box in VR
with just one material can bring with it
some comfort and readability issues.
Essentially, the depth within your level
becomes much harder to read.
But luckily, this is easily alleviated
by mapping a different color to all the vertical aspects
of your level.
It sounds like a really small thing,
but it really does help to give that sense of depth in VR
that can otherwise be lost.
Next on the agenda, metrics.
So good metrics are important in all games.
But for VR specifically, they can
normalize the base level of comfortable traversal
within your game space.
If you're too close or too far away from something,
then you're genuinely going to feel this.
So this shows the cover metrics that we had in place on our waypoints.
And distance away from the cover was heavily user-tested to ensure the following criteria.
Number one, that the player could comfortably see over the cover.
Number two, that they could duck their head and feel safe in cover.
And three, that anything that we placed on top of the cover, like ammo or weapons, could easily be reached.
To ensure that these metrics were fixed,
we set up prefabs with something that we called snap zones.
And these are the red planes that you can see
over the cover objects.
With the snap zones in place,
all we had to do was move a waypoint towards an edge
and it would just snap into position.
And this took care of about 90% of the waypoints in the game.
And sometimes depending on the circumstances,
we disabled snapping on a waypoint
and we tweaked the location by hand.
To get out of cover comfortably,
we baked out splines and curved them
around the cover objects.
And whilst this was fine for the white box stage,
I wasn't particularly comfortable with the fact
that these curves would always be an approximation.
And they had the potential to be implemented
completely differently by each of the level designers.
So how is this gonna scale?
And what if our metrics had to change
as a result of a user test?
We'd have to go back and update
all the traversal splines by hand.
And what if the next user test
required us to change it again?
So the answer was to set up a metrics based system instead.
Designers now had three different curves available to them,
which could be changed within an INI file.
And this would update all the splines
within the side of the game.
And we still baked out the odd spline here and there,
especially during set pieces.
But just like the snap waypoints before,
this system took care of approximately 90% of the game.
So now that we have a rail-based traversal system,
metrically driven and tuned to comfort,
let's talk about the meat of the game
and explore the gameplay mechanics.
So Blood & Truth's mechanics can be split
into three different categories.
First, we have a number of traversal-based ones.
Next, we have some more combat-focused mechanics.
And finally, we have interactables,
each of which is entirely concentrated
on the use of VR and motion controls.
So now we've established Blood & Truth's traversal,
metrics, and game mechanics.
The rest is fairly classic level design.
So what I'm going to do now is quickly break down a level
and point out the VR considerations involved
in each scene.
And internally, we call this level the HQ.
It's around three quarters of the way through,
so by now the player has been introduced
to all the mechanics of the game.
And here's a quick summary of the mission.
You and your former SAS buddy Deakin
have been tasked with breaking into
a dubious shell company building
and reporting back on any of the information you may find.
Your handler, Agent Carson, has also provided you
with a Trojan to upload to the bad guy systems.
OK, let's step through.
It starts with a classic planning montage,
a filmic technique used in films like Mission Impossible,
where you plan and execute the mission at the same time.
And we don't have any bloody AI within the game,
but still wanted to explore how we
could have you and an NPC work together across a mission.
So first things first, you decide
to recon the shell company building with a drone.
And as we fly over the building site,
we discover the following.
We need to find a way to disable the generator
powering the floodlights,
and that we need a key card to get into the building.
And often one of the things that we find
with new players to VR
is that they can get stuck staring in one direction.
This elevated position here
gives us a unique view of the building site.
And it's just can encourage the player
to look around the scene a little bit more.
And as a quick win,
we literally just reused our on-foot traversal mechanic
for the drone move.
And then we added some post-processing
and a little bit of audio.
And this gave us the impression
that we're actually looking through the camera of the drone.
Okay, so once we've learned everything we need to,
we montage cut back to the safe house.
Now we make a plan to get into the building site.
Beacon will set off the fire alarms remotely
whilst the player disguise themselves as an electrician.
And for these quick in-between drama scenes,
we placed different interactables around the table,
beer bottles, plans, et cetera,
giving the player a chance to role play along with the scene.
To me, this is about as cut scene as it should ever get in VR.
Remember that the player always has control over the camera.
So it's nice for them to have a little extra agency
with inside the drama scenes.
Once again, we've montage cut exactly where we need to be.
In this case, we gain access to the site wearing
our electrician's disguise.
And once we're in front of the generator,
we fix the alarms by planting some remote activated decord.
With this type of interaction, we affectionately
refer to internally as a bod.
which stood for box of delights.
I actually read an article online where a journalist had coined the term
fuse breaker puzzles, which I guess is a much better back of the box quote,
but I might refer to bots throughout the rest of the talk.
So we had three tiers of fidelity for these interaction puzzles.
This one's a tier three due to its simplicity.
We unscrew a panel, put on a deck cord, job done.
Tier two is more of a puzzle and requires at least some thought.
and likely takes a few more steps to complete as well.
Tier one is what we would call a hero asset.
This still uses all the same kit parts
we used to create the rest of our boards,
things like the buttons, joysticks, sliders,
but the main difference is the kit parts
drive fairly bespoke actions,
like tracking an NPC's movements through CCTV.
The really important thing to take note of here
is that we're never pressing X to play something.
We're always asking the player to use their hands
to perform actions.
Okay, so the generator has been fixed with a deck cord.
Next, we need the foreman's ID card.
So back at the safe house,
Deacon has a plan to distract the foreman,
dressed as the maintenance man for his building.
So it looks like we'll have to climb up some scaffolding
to break into the foreman's apartment.
As mentioned earlier, the player can yaw rotate
during interactive traversal segments like this.
We can see this here as the player
is physically pulling themselves along the scaffolding.
And putting rotation into the player's hands like this
is a huge comfort boost,
likely because the tiny inner ear muscles
are responsible for balance or in motion
as you perform the actions.
So once we're in, we give Deacon a heads up over comms.
Again, we don't feature any kind of buddy AI in the game.
So Deacon's presence in the scene
is entirely driven through VO.
And as we start rifling through some drawers,
we can hear him distracting the foreman downstairs.
Eventually we find a lock drawer with the ID card inside.
So here's a screenshot of what our climbing implementation looks like in editor.
These are basically prefab curves that we know to be of uncomfortable limits.
The proxy or gizmo information shows the distance that we can pull ourselves around in.
We also experiment with adding the simulated feeling of weight to the climbing interaction.
Without any of this, although it's completely one-to-one, it also felt like you were superhuman.
So we tune to the balance of an action hero more like John McClane instead.
Okay.
So for a game of blood in the title, we've gone through the first 10 minutes
of the mission and we haven't even killed anyone yet.
So we're going to fix that now.
Job well done on the planning.
We got the ID card and we planted the debt court.
It's time for a set piece.
Base jumping over the river Thames.
So as you can see here.
There's some basic functionality on the parachute,
allowing the player to bank from side to side.
You can also push up or pull down on the parachute cords
to raise and lower yourself.
The editor proxy information here shows how far on the X
and Y we can maneuver within the parachutes.
You can then see how we funnel this in,
so the player lands exactly where we want them to.
It's pretty basic stuff, really.
So Deacon sets off the deck cord we planted earlier,
remotely, taking down the lights
and covering your entry into the building site.
it looks like there's some hired goons patrolling.
In Blood & Truth, as you basically keep making forward progress,
we keep the player from pushing too far forward in combat scenarios
by splitting up scenes into sections.
And these sections open up when the player takes out enemies.
So this creates a pretty simple loop.
Take out an enemy, open up a new chunk.
And this is what the traversal graph looks like within this building site.
The level designers were responsible for the level's layout
as well as all the traversal markup.
And this meant that every single cover point in the game
has gone through some considerable testing
and that we can guarantee the player's always
gonna have a fun route through a level.
So now that the building site's clear,
we can use the ID card that we jacked earlier
to get into the building.
Now, when you break in somewhere,
it makes sense that one of the first things
you might be greeted with is a security camera.
And in blood and truth,
these essentially work as lock and key puzzles.
The player must now either hack the camera
or start a firefight to progress.
So let's take a look at the stealthier approach.
To hack the camera, we use one of the bots
that we talked about earlier.
And we've done a similar kind of thing to this
in flat screen games for years now.
Remember using the analog sticks to hack things
with inside of the Arkham games?
Well, this is exactly the same kind of gameplay beat
that we're looking for.
But because it's in VR,
you have that extra tactility at your disposal,
which should absolutely be factored
into the design of the puzzle.
And we came up with the.
Box of the Delights in the middle of production,
which obviously the producers weren't extremely happy with,
but it felt like we didn't have enough
in the level design palette to break up the gunplay.
So we formed a three-person strike team
and basically designed and implemented them all
within around 10 weeks, start to finish.
And here's what the puzzle used to look like
before we switched out the designer art.
And not that I want to give you the advice of,
if it doesn't feel right, add more stuff during production.
But this is a perfect example of what can be accomplished in a short time frame with minimal resources.
Okay, so whilst we're in this maintenance corridor, let's take a look at the layout and why this makes sense for Blood & Truth.
This security room to the right, in a normal FPS, it would make total sense that the door was placed here instead.
It's a small thing, but it gives the space an extra dimension, right?
It might even feel a little bit more normal,
as it's very rare to enter a building
and have all of the doors facing the exact same direction.
In blood and truth, this was actually a level design challenge.
And we got around this by extending the width of the level
to accommodate doors being on the forward axis.
So looking at the top down,
we can see how the level is split into channels.
And this gives the player some options
and fits in line with our traversal method,
which doesn't feature snap turning.
And when we did use your race rotations,
we designed our level sections to curve
at the same time that the player did,
creating a corridor like feeling
and helping to relax the curve visually.
And this featured most prominently
with inside the run gun sections of our game.
So here's an example from the casino level.
We can see that there's a curve on the inside corner here.
We travel around it following the forward tangent
of the spline at a very relaxed pace.
And we also found that the corners didn't need
to be a hundred percent smooth curve.
So we can see with this next corner,
it's actually fairly faceted,
but it still helps to lead the eye,
which in turn helps the brain to process it spatially.
And here's what this looks like in editor.
Another thing that really helped
is the highly choreographed enemy placement around a scene.
This helps to not only push the action hero pillar of the game,
but it also makes great use of VR
as the gunplay is happening all around you.
So back to our level.
Next, we Jimmy open the lift shaft,
and then we go subterranean by hanging on the underside
of a lift as it starts moving,
and then we enter the evil base proper.
So this is where you want to start putting it all together.
The player's done all of that legwork with Deacon
during the planning phase to get into the base.
So now we increase the intensity curve
and start giving the player some options.
On this floor, we've got a number of different room setups,
which gives this base a labyrinth-like feel.
We've got some patrolling guards
with the classic evil base style uniforms on,
and a fuse breaker puzzle leading into a room full of loot.
The player can actually find an ID card for this room
if they search through some nearby drawers,
or they can hack in.
but this obviously increases the chance of setting off the alarms
and alerting guards to your presence.
For this playthrough, we'll carry on stealthily.
Okay, so let's review the top-down of the space
and look at the traversal network.
So we have our familiar forward-facing openings,
and the space is put up into channels,
leading to a pinch point at the end of the room.
As we progress further through the base,
we come across a variation on a fusebreaker puzzle that gets a little bit more complicated.
Each of these fusebreaker prefabs had prefixed waypoint destinations.
And to help us establish these positions, we created some really super simple metric guides to visualize the interaction range.
There isn't anything dynamic or fancy about this. It's just warping the lines of averaged ergonomics.
In this next room, we force a really large firefight.
This is purely to mix up the beats at a level by increasing the intensity and breaking up the stealth.
So as a combat arena, the space is wide and symmetrical.
The player can choose to progress up either flank or down the center.
It's lit with cover points and enemies flood in from all directions.
And this cover setup gives the player a lot of freedom of movement
and allows them to move laterally from one side of the level to the other.
And we also decided to push the ceiling higher, giving us more varied shooting angles.
and also making it easier for grenades to be thrown longer distances.
So once the firefight is over, Deacon and Ryan update each other
through VO and we head deeper into the base.
So we wanted to chunk in a section that made it feel like the baddies
were still expanding this base.
And this screenshot can show how the art and design teams work
together to present new ideas.
Adding this section and cutting another.
helped us to provide an area where the look and feel is totally different to the rest of the level,
but continues to work on similar principles.
So along with the standard guards, we also have a generator.
And using a kit part from one of our bods,
we can flip a switch to turn off some lights.
And if you do this, a guard will react and go off to investigate.
And this leaves you with one less enemy to take out if a firefight breaks out.
I also wanted to show here what I like to call a legitimate hack.
So we integrated a stealth route on the left side of the level
where you can crawl on the top of these boxes,
staying low and peeking through.
To make things easy for us,
we simply reskinned the vent crawl prefab.
And that way, everything that stays inside of the metrics,
and all we're doing is swapping out some meshes.
So here's a side-by-side comparison.
Once we get through the tunnel,
we get to another bot interaction.
If we found the code on the notepad in the previous section,
we can just type that in.
Otherwise we can hack it,
which again has a slightly more difficult setup.
Earlier, I talked about the fuse breaker puzzles
embodying the same kind of beat
as using a gadget in the Arkham games.
And this intensity graph shows us
how far through the level we currently are.
Studying it, we can see that there are lots
of evenly spaced out drops in intensity.
And although this is fairly typical
in action adventure missions,
it's important to look at it through the lens of VR.
If you've just come out of an intense battle or you're about to go into one,
giving the player a rest helps to avoid something we like to call VR fatigue.
Carrying on with our mission, Deacon takes out a guard and updates us further on what he's seen in
the base. And this further builds on that feeling that we're still on a mission with him.
And the positioning of these narrative moments is something that we spend a lot of time on at
London Studio. This is all in an effort to make sure that the players get a great view of an
actor's performance.
We're getting close to the end now,
so the intensity curve is trending higher.
And this room features a lot of lateral cover,
gaps between creating channels for the player to move forward.
And our cover metrics are ensuring that all the ammo
and grenades are placed within comfortable distance.
And the shelving here also creates a nice cover type
that is completely unique to VR.
With all the gaps between the boxes,
the player has to physically search for an opening
to shoot enemies through.
This could be even more effective in stealth sections,
giving the player that feeling of being a hunter.
In the last room of the level, you plant the Trojan,
triggering a violent shootout on a massive storage elevator.
And this combination of the epic scale of this room
and the dynamic movement you get from the elevator
gives us a fitting combat scenario for the end of our level.
To me, it embodies the power of VR,
transporting the player into a location and situation
that they're likely never to experience in real life.
and giving them a chance to role play as an action hero.
So there we have it.
In summary, pay extra special attention to metric data.
The last and first thing you want to be worrying about
when making a game is comfort issues.
Establish your game mechanics.
Think about what makes them only possible in VR.
It doesn't need to be some super expensive
360 dream sequence.
I mean, those are cool, but even something as simple
as throwing a scrunched up paper ball into a bin
can be quite magical in VR.
Review your level often and keep asking yourself the question,
how can it be more VR?
And finally, play lots of VR games.
Some awesome games out there now that
will serve as an inspiration.
For example, if you haven't already played Blood and Truth,
why not go pick yourself up a copy?
So I hope this little run through
has helped anyone that's thinking
about how to translate their work into VR
and how some of the more typical action adventure principles
can work within the field.
Thank you very much for listening.
You're more than welcome to mail me if you have any questions regarding the talk.
Thanks again.