Okay, hello and welcome to this talk, How the Hell Do You Make Money on Video Games,
which is inspired by the extreme difficulty of actually selling your game here in 2021.
I was thinking about this topic because there were some 10,000 games released on Steam in 2020.
And as you can imagine, most of these games do not rise to the top.
They're not all sales blockbusters.
In fact, most of them, I see stories all the time
about people whose games have completely failed
in their estimation.
But I don't believe that has to be the end.
You got to make money somewhere.
There are a lot of avenues other than sales direct
to consumer that you can make money with
either during production or afterward.
And so.
That's based on my experience. Hello, I'm Brandon Sheffield of Necrosoft Games. We have put out
three games and every single one of them has been funded multiple times by completely different
entities and each time we incrementally improved the game with each release.
And none of them have been huge sales successes,
I'm willing to admit that,
but they have all contributed to the company
continuing to go along.
We've always been able to do our own original IP
and we continue to exist and continue to make new games.
And I'm not the only person with this experience.
So that's why this panel is assembled.
So in general, we're gonna be talking about
the types of money, things you can get from different types of platforms, publishers,
crowdfunding, whatever other stuff to fund development for your games or also to make
money once the game is already released, independent of selling it to consumers.
Without further ado, I would like to introduce everybody else that is on this panel, or rather
have them introduce.
themselves. Just a brief re-intro of myself. I'm Brandon Sheffield, Creative Director of
Microsoft Games, and we have never made more money on sales than we have selling to platforms,
and that's where we're coming from. So let us have everyone introduce themselves. Let's start with
Justin.
Yeah, my name is Justin Woodward.
I'm the co-founder and creative director of Interrobang Entertainment
independent game development team and as well as.
the co-founder of The Mix, the media indie exchange, a platform used to to get visibility
and partnerships for game developers around the world. I'm also one of the lead advisors on the
Humble Black Game Developer Fund, so I helped select titles and get prototype funding for
black game developers. Great, and let's next talk to Ava.
Hi, my name is Eva Carr. I'm the founder and CEO at Glitch, focused primarily on designing systems and also strategy.
A lot of my work is really around, you know, forming deep connections through play and also building a better and more inclusive creative economy.
I think for this talk, I've probably tried every single source or type of funding, except for taking out a loan.
So I'm excited for the conversation.
I'm really focused on co-creating what I would consider the future of play.
through $100,000 to $250,000 equity checks through Moonrise and also $10k grants through
the Galaxy Fund for prototypes for people who are really making games that
are doing something a little different.
I'm trying to think some of the other stuff that you may have seen before.
Before last year, when we had started Moonrise and Galaxy, we shipped HyperDot in partnership
with Charles McGregor of Tribe Games, focused on player insights, mostly usability, progression,
things like information architecture, plus business development. And you may have seen
that HyperDot was recognized for its innovation and accessibility through the Game Awards.
and we're really proud of it, played over by, you know, a half a million people worldwide.
We like to think that we made good money and also made history, which we think is pretty dope.
Some other projects you may have seen around the internet that I worked on, Game Dev Salaries. It's
an open data project. I really love the idea of open data with nearly a thousand entries worldwide.
The goal is really to, like, help people get paid what they really deserve,
and I'm excited to be here with y'all. Thank you.
Mike, let's have you go next.
Hey, everyone. My name is Mike Tucker.
I'm an independent developer based in the south of England.
I've been doing this for 13 years, but formed Bitmap Bureau,
our latest studio, about five years ago now.
And our first game was H8 Heroes, which was a traditional
Steam title, really, but we also bought it physically
to the Switch and PlayStation 4 as well.
But since then, we've gone on to create Xenocrisis, which was kickstarted
a couple of years ago, and we've produced retro versions of that game for the Mega Drive or
Genesis if you prefer, Dreamcast and Neo Geo. But we've also pushed the other physical aspects as
well, so we have like a vinyl soundtrack and the CD soundtrack, t-shirts and so on. And yeah,
we're getting more and more into physical now, and we've realized that there's still a, well,
there's a growing demand for it, it seems, over digital products.
Yeah.
Megan.
Hi, yeah, I'm Megan Fox.
I run, founded, et cetera, Glass Bottom Games.
We are currently working on Skatebird, which you might have heard of, and previously we've
made the games Jones on Fire, Hot Tin Roof, and Spartan Fist.
Kind of like Necrosoft, we have never made much money by selling our games, but also
we've never really made much money selling our games to platforms until Skatebird.
Up until this point, we mostly survived on...
weird combination of grants in certain cases and work for hire.
And this one really weird contract with a games adjacent company, that whole process.
Though with Skateboard, we've since found a lot of other cool things that, you know,
are more in keeping with something a reasonable business would do.
And we've been doing this for like a decade.
I think my tenure was last month or something.
So yeah, we've been at it for a while.
Nice.
Uh, Robert.
Hello, my name is Robert Gurski. I am founder of Black Moon Design, a studio, which is three people basically.
And we are making games since 2005. And we haven't, we've made around 100 games, and we've never
sold those directly to consumers. All our money comes from
business deals, licensing, advertising, and all different types of B2B deals.
So, yeah, for our players, the games are free, which is kind of fun for us.
And for them as well, I guess.
Yeah, so as you can see, there's a lot of different pathways to actually...
continuing to succeed in this business. Everybody here has been in it for a while and very few of
us have had big sales successes. So it is possible. You can do it. So we're going to start.
We're going to start talking about grants with Ava first because I mean so just to start off
a little bit there are a lot of grants that you can get if you're in
Europe, like the EU and Canada and a lot of good grants, but in the United States, it's basically
garbage except for what Ava's doing. So yeah, get us started talking about that and let's see
where we get to.
Yeah, I feel like two of the biggest sources that we just don't simply talk about enough
in games in terms of financing is equity financing and grant financing.
I feel like grants really play a big role in our ecosystem from financing, you know,
experimental projects to leadership training. A lot of people get their first injection of
cash through grants like...
You know, I think Grace Bruxner with Frog Detective,
like literally so many people who are,
especially in Canada through, you know,
the Canada Media Fund or Australia
through Film Victoria or Europe.
I don't even, well, like the UK, I suppose, with Yuki.
But to be considered a grant, I really think that, you know, funding is oftentimes non-recoupable
and is or charitable or matching dollars don't need to really be repaid or anything of sorts.
So I, like we started our whole entire journey with starting with grants. I got my first grant
at 19 with 50k and then it just kept going from there each year.
And I think that it's really important to be able to find,
not only find grants, but also apply for them, get them.
And that's usually oftentimes a lot of studios
get their first kind of injection of capital there.
How do you find them?
Um, that is a good question.
Uh, it depends on where you're at.
I actually, so Brendan, you had asked for, um, you'd asked for some metrics and, uh, I
actually have a lot of these stored cause we love insights over a glitch.
Um, so I, there's a bunch of them that actually, um, are based in different areas.
So I'm just going to focus on the U S for now, because it's the saddest one of all of them.
So really grants are actually very rare in North America, specifically in the U.S., not so much in Canada.
But if you take a look at, for example, where I'm at and where I'm based, Minnesota actually has the highest grant budget per capita in the U.S.
due to a lot of the specific trust that we currently have.
Right now it's like $6 per capita
compared to the national average from, you know,
say organizations like the National Endowment of the Arts
or National Endowment of the Sciences
or whatever that is at like 50 cents.
per capita. Folks over in Canada, Australia, Europe have it better. When you look at orgs
like again, Canada Media Fund, Uki, Film Victoria, they all sit at actually like 25 to 35 USD
per capita. So to show you like where we're currently at.
There's different areas, so I'd say like arts organizations are one of them and oftentimes
those are actually funded by the NEA, which is the National Endowment of the Arts, and then there's
a whole segment of people who receive funding from say,
foundations and foundations have very like specific things that they focus on.
But for example, I am currently, I currently have like a two-year grant for
a leadership grant and that's through a foundation.
So depending on what you're looking for, what type of project you have, whether it's a game or just focused on you as developing as an artist, or you developing as a leader, whatever that is, there's most likely a grant for them, but look for local arts organizations.
look for foundations that are doing some really cool things in this space, and be in a state that
cares because not very many states do. I think there's really only like the most grant dollars
in the United States really are either in Minnesota or New York City.
What I just to jump in to, I think that a lot of it's networking.
Like, yeah, you got it.
You have to know other people who know about the grants,
especially in the United States, like the CMF is very much,
you know, prevalent or the Victoria.
Is it Victoria, Victoria?
Like they have a film. Yeah.
Yeah. Film Victoria has one.
I received a few grants.
I received one from, you know, the covid fund from PlayStation.
I've also received one from the Chamber of.
of commerce for their diversity funds.
This is all COVID and also...
Yeah, but you're in California.
So that's like, just to give people some hope
that occasionally you can get some money
regardless of where you are.
Yeah, yeah, you just have to, and yeah, California is tough.
You got, you just have to hustle it and like figure out where things are.
And some folks in the industry have told, like, kind of put me up on game as to
where to sign up for these funds.
And they're very, very timely.
the Black Chamber of Commerce fund came from California.
That was in Alameda County up in, you know, in the Bay Area.
And if I didn't know that within 10 days, this fund would have been depleted,
I wouldn't have known.
So one of my friends who owns a sound studio down for me
and is like a really good friend was like.
Apply now, apply now, but I wouldn't know that unless I had this connection or also the PlayStation Fund.
Luckily, I'm connected with some of the BizDev folks there, and they kind of told me,
hey, you should apply within this given time. But I would say in the States, that's one of the big
things. Of course, look for them, but also help other people out. If you see one that's for Asian
Americans or indigenous Native Americans, tell the people that you know, because it'll just
reciprocate. Yeah, and I think we can, we might be able to have like some resource guide by the time
you're all looking at this so that you can see some of the stuff we're talking about. But like
Justin said, a lot of this stuff comes up real fast and goes away real fast and there is some,
certainly some hustling involved. I wanted to talk, Justin, more about some of the ways that you've
tried to get
production money because you've done some interesting things and some interesting partnerships
that are very hustle oriented, I would say.
So like I'm always looking for opportunities because I'm like, I'm a super hustler.
So I'm trying to figure out any ways to flip in a, you know, in a way that's like beneficial
to everybody, right?
Like I just want to make cool stuff and cool games and help other people make cool stuff.
So I try to figure that out.
So I've done, you know, I've done kickstarters before I used to, uh, I was at double fine for a few years.
And when fig spun out of double fine, I was the curator, uh, and I helped them with publishing.
Um, and I ended up funding my Jan's on a Bob game through fig while I was working at fig.
So when I was working at fig, all of my money that I got from being a consultant went back into my games.
Like I didn't really.
You know what I mean?
Use that money.
I didn't, I wasn't like balling off of that, right?
And I'm trying to think of other ways like.
Talk about that chocolate shop partnership.
I was fascinated by that.
What?
You tried to, back in the days,
you tried to partner with like a chocolate company
for like in-game advertising stuff.
Wasn't that right?
I tried to try, you know, cream, the ice cream, they have in Berkeley, there's
an ice cream, uh, cookie ice cream company.
So I went over there to do some, this is so ridiculous for super combo, man.
I was trying to find any way to make money or to fund our project.
So I went over there and I pitched to them, Hey, this character could be
your, you know, uh, he eats cookies in the game.
He loves cookies.
He's got a little gut and like, it would be perfect.
Um, and so like I went over to the storefront, I talked to the owner and I
said, Hey, how about we like package a key of our game or demo in your, every
time you purchase a, uh, uh, ice cream cookie, um, snack or whatever.
And they were, they were down for it, but it just didn't allow me to, it didn't
make sense, but I figured out other ways to do that later on.
I was in the IGN in the open house, uh, which was a, um,
an accelerator that GameSpy started.
And when I was there, they really liked what we were doing
because we had like the game has like very fluid animations,
very colorful.
And at that time they were trying to figure,
they are owned by Fox.
So they were trying to figure out ways to get into
indie game development and in-game advertising
and that type of thing.
So I like hustled away to like get them to put production
engineers on super combo man to build out the features that I wanted.
And that was like.
That was probably like $100,000 worth of engineering help.
They helped me set up my pipeline for development when I was,
because I'm not an engineer, I'm an artist and a producer
and, you know, a director creatively.
So like I didn't understand all the pipelines for like,
let's say, get source tree, those type of things.
But since production is my background, that was very important to me.
They helped me set up the whole foundation for the pipeline for our team.
And then I was able to kind of lock that out and build upon that.
And they put a lot of man hours on our game, which was it's not dollars,
dollars, but it was something that I couldn't afford at the time.
Yeah. And when you did I mean, you're still doing Jay and Silent Bob.
Was that a license that came with money or a license you had to approach?
Or how did like how have you leveraged that into additional visibility and success?
That was very serendipitous in that when I was at IGN, I spent very long hours and I
really got to know everything to me.
Everything is, is networking.
I believe if you're a good, you know, if you're a good person and you're helping other people.
So.
When I was at IGN, IGN had this thing called IPL, which was their pro league.
And they had, you know, they threw tournaments. I got, I was working there all the time. So I got
to meet all and become friends with all the video producers. And then when they broke off,
I was still friends with them. And one of the video producers was working at WB. And he said,
I have this friend who wants to make an indie game, which was Trevor Furman. He's friends
with Kevin Smith.
And so he was like, he asked Kevin years ago, can I use your IP for a game?
And so then we, we connected and he's out here in Berkeley.
We just hit it off.
And, and we talked about it.
We, I started creating design documents for the game, what I
thought would be really cool.
And then Kevin hit us up.
And he the funny thing about that was it was not a licensing,
licensing type of situation.
And I've dealt with those.
But it was more like a handshake thing.
In matter of fact, when we went to Kevin Smith's house
and I was with Justin from
from Fig at the time, he's like Kevin's like, don't fuck this up.
Like, I don't know if I could curse my bad and get that out.
But I think it's I think it's a lot.
Yeah, he said, he said, Don't fuck this up. Don't talk business. You got it. You could,
we can do it for this small percentage. And we're good. We just want you to be creative
and to utilize this in a game. And it was a handshake. And then we did all the paperwork,
but it was a very serendipitous, easy thing to do. So it wasn't like, and I'm never going to do
personally, I'm never going to do a cash in, you know, like this isn't like,
I'm not just trying to make money. I want to do something cool. I believe in the ViewSKU universe
and all that stuff. But yeah, I stack stuff. I tell developers to stack stuff. So I'll say,
I know Mike, you work with Adult Swim Games. When I was working on Super Combo Man, I was struggling.
I did the cookie thing. I was working with IGN. I was trying to figure out ways to fund our game.
I didn't know how to do it.
Like Adult Swim said no, all the publishers said no.
I just kept making the game and getting like a bunch of,
you know, press around the game.
I did a Kickstarter.
The Kickstarter was, you know, successful.
I took that Kickstarter.
I hit back every publisher that I talked to previously.
They're, oh, you got a successful Kickstarter?
Hell yeah, we'll jump in.
Oh yeah, I showed, oh, we got Adult Swim.
Hey, investor, we got Adult Swim games.
They put in 40 grand.
Oh, I got an investor and Adult Swim
and look at the articles.
Then I was able to leverage that and just stack.
And then now, since I'm like,
you know, we have all this coverage
and that's what I did with Chronic Blunt Punch
and I don't want to steal any more time.
No, it's like, ultimately it's,
I think it's really important to talk about how
Like the hustling is really like it's something you got to actively do.
And, and that's one of the hardest things with this is that, you know, people put
out games and they're like the game didn't do well, there's nothing else I can do.
But you, you have to have someone on your team who is dedicating some of their
time to doing this kind of hustling.
If like, unless you have some kind of crazy breakout hit there's like.
It's a lot of work, and I think that that's the main,
like one of the important things that I take away
from what you're saying, Justin, is like,
it's not just, you can't just apply for some grants
and then like hope that it happens.
You gotta be applying to grants
and like talking to all your friends and find,
like for me, we got a publishing deal recently
to bring a console version of one of our games out.
And in order to do that, I looked at a list
of
350 publishers.
I went down that entire list,
checked are any of these applicable to what we're doing.
I mailed, I put together like a press kit, essentially,
or like a pitch kit that would hopefully
answer all their questions in advance.
I mailed it to 40 publishers.
Three of them got back,
and one of them signed a deal with us.
And like, you just have to be able to do that.
Like, because...
Your game may not sell.
So you have to be able to do...
Can I add one thing to this real quick?
Sure.
Last, like, so I'll just tell you from this call, when I jumped in the call
immediately, how can I connect someone with someone?
How can I help that person or how, how, what do they connect them?
So I, Ava was talking about all of her stuff.
My, my brain is firing, you know what I mean?
Like.
Oh my god, Mike is in here. I wanted to talk to Mike for so long.
You know, we met seven years ago.
Everyone's yeah. Yeah. Megan's a super hustler.
I see her like on all the shows and like she's always hitting people.
Anyway, I just thought I was like any situation my brain is firing.
How can I help this person? How can I? How can how can I?
How can we help each other? Really? Exactly.
Because it's a lot of time when we talk about networking, it winds up being like.
It's not like networking isn't actually a slimy thing
unless you're a slimy person.
Like it's ultimately just like how,
you know, when I was doing my 300,
going through my 300 publisher list,
I told other people that didn't know that that list existed.
And I was also like, oh, these people came back to me about,
you know, with a no,
but they told me this other thing that they're interested in
which is more along the lines
of what you, my friend are doing.
So like, you gotta be.
paying it forward as well as absorbing it.
But I want to talk more about licensing stuff
because Robert, you've got really, I would say,
unique experience in that compared
to most traditional game developers
because you're making games for dumb phones,
like old brick phones.
You're making, the web game market is still there.
Tell me about what you're doing.
I would say like my story is not unique. I would say it's very,
it was very common back in 2007-8. Everybody was doing flash games and
publishing them somewhere on web, on some portals, anywhere.
And we basically, we tried to go out of it because we
started as a flash game.
developers tried to follow the herd and do the Steam PC huge game that will bring us
money and fame and everybody will love it.
And it didn't work out, surprisingly.
And yeah, and we basically went back to doing small, silly web games.
that people still love to play.
It's and there's
there are a lot of places where
there's demand for small,
silly games that can just
be played anywhere on anything.
And what does that market
look like right now?
And because you're you're looking
at increasingly shrinking markets,
but they're expanding maybe in other
countries or.
the platforms are forgotten and so there's not as much competition.
Yes, there's like a lot we are doing with games for developing countries, like the whole Africa,
India, like a lot of countries where access to very new devices like top-of-the-shelf iPhones is
not really...
possible. So people are playing on what they have basically, which are basically lower end devices.
And they can't play new games because demands, technical requirements are too much.
So yeah, we try to be there and offer them our games, which are playable on such devices.
And how do you wind up?
partnering with licenses and what does revenue actually look like for you?
Because you're not making money on individual sales.
You're doing these kind of bulk deals.
In most cases, we find channels, portals, some kind of like places where
the owner of those places, of those portals, of those like carrier
stores and such, would like some content for their users. They have a lot of users and there's
no content for them. They ask us to deliver the games and we know that advertising is not really
an option because in most of those countries the rates for advertising is not really high.
So we engage in deals that
basically we get some fixed amount of money just because we publish the title on this specific
platform and for users of this platform the game is free and usually the portal owner or the
platform owner earns money on web traffic. Usually those are like in most cases right now
we deal with carrier operators so they charge users for data.
and the game itself is free after you download it or...
Right. So you get kind of small, kind of minimum guarantee buyouts,
or maybe large ones, I don't know.
It's, they're mostly, we work on scale, so we have a lot of games and the fees are not high.
Uh, but it's like not even current minimum guarantee.
It's like, so we get this money and that's it.
It's we don't, there's, there's no more revenue coming, uh, coming in.
So, uh, so yeah, so we, we have to make new games and, and, and publish them.
Yeah.
So you're making games, just grinding them out real fast.
Uh,
Okay.
As far as licensing is concerned, I've been working with Viacom and some other companies recently.
And what's interesting is that I'm hitting console and the PC market and retro.
And what's really interesting and fascinating about that is they have these large companies doing their AAA releases.
So for the smaller releases, they're willing to work with you on minimum guarantees.
And so they're not exuberant.
They understand and their licensing teams understand kind of the indie
struggle and not struggle hustle.
I don't want to say struggle.
Yeah, it's just it's both.
They're intertwined sometimes, but they their teams want to do creative stuff.
They don't always want to do like these big games and like deal with all of the.
uh you know walls that they have to break down in order to make those deals work so they're willing
to work with you on that as far as long as it's not you're not competing with their direct you
know huge large licensing deals that they're doing with you know triple-a companies um
So if you, if you like kind of hit those blue waters with something that's maybe more obscure,
but has its own fan base, that's kind of what I'm going after. Because like, just working with on
the Kevin Smith, Chance on Bob stuff, like I'm not looking to be a multi multi, I mean, I would
love it. I'm not looking to be a super multimillionaire, but I know it has a built in fan
base. So I could build upon that if I have like from our mall brawl cartridge that we released
with limited run games.
I have the data, now I can go and take that to investors
and other people and other publishers.
And again, I'm stacking it.
It's like, look, this made a million dollars,
this grossed a million dollars
just for this particular game.
Like this is what I could do if I had more,
you know, more things to work with.
And on the, you know, on the scale of things
and building like for our game, Gun House,
we have gotten five different.
funding partners for that and each time we made the game incrementally better and so we were able
to like we could essentially sell it to a company for even a small amount of money like 10,000 bucks
or whatever as we will give you uh like this new feature and it's a feature that we want to finish
anyway and so each like each time we get the game a little better and a little better with these
small
tiny buyouts and then by the time we've done all those buyouts now we have a game that is much more
console worthy than before on the backs of these small buyouts and that's something else you can
kind of do. I wanted to talk a little bit about crowdfunding. Crowdfunding is pretty, you know,
there are whole conversations we can have about that but I'm particularly interested in
using crowdfunding to fuel further success.
I know that Justin's talked about it a little bit.
Let's hear, Megan, you've done some pretty good work
leveraging SkateBird into some pretty serious,
into a really good space even before release.
Yeah, so it kind of all started with the,
like SkateBird, whenever I build a project,
I tend to build.
three different versions in my head.
There's the one that if it goes nowhere
and I just have to kick it out unfinished,
there's the one if it does moderately well,
and then there's that moonshot,
I guess it could get this big if I needed to.
And so what I did was I announced Skatebird
with the minimum viable product
looking as good as it could look,
and it started to get traction.
So then I did a Kickstarter,
which was the following six months later,
which happened to be around E3.
Kickstarter snowballed.
Oh, and before the Kickstarter, we are actually in talks with
Humble amongst other people.
They said, no, we were, we were okay.
We moved on to the Kickstarter and the Kickstarter leveraged, uh, it was
a not Kentucky fried gaming show.
It was, uh, I don't know, one of the, one of the not E3 conferences in
2019 that started springing up.
It was like E3 in the van across the street kind of thing, but it worked.
It was fun.
And that got huge really fast.
The Kickstarter went to 3X overfund, just did really well.
That got the interest of Xbox.
And we were able to sign a Game Pass deal within a month.
I'd been kind of priming that for a while
and hoping I could get something.
And then after everything broke,
it's like, oh, hey, you want this?
And then Humble comes back and says something like,
you know, there's more chips in your court now.
Oh, it's like, thanks.
Yeah, boat already kind of sailed on that one, sorry.
But still, like Justin was talking about,
that kind of stacking of possibilities and properties,
things that you could come back to later
ends up being really useful.
Like maybe we go with Humble for a next game or whatever.
Now we have a hot lead there.
That'll make that a lot easier.
Xbox will probably make connections on future games
a lot easier because of, oh, and the Kickstarter
and the E3 and all of that then led to the Enough Interest
that that December, I think it was,
was the first...
video game show, video game awards
that had the game festival concept
that Jeff put together and Jeff Keighley.
And we were one of the 13 games that they chose to tap
to be in the first ever giant steam festival.
And that made our numbers go ridiculously vertical.
And then that again, primed future things.
So yeah, the Kickstarter,
we like to run all of our games
with a Kickstarter at this point,
just because it creates a.
community nexus. Once you've got some kind of community built around something, you've got
something to build off of. You've got directions you can go. And again, like Justin was saying,
once you have the core, you can then take that to people and say, look, this is getting pretty
good trust among this small audience. If you would just give us an introduction or access to your
larger audience or larger funding or et cetera, we can grow this at scales, et cetera. I really
like building from that. And then also working from a Kickstarter means that I'm controlling
my audience.
and I'm growing an audience around my studio or me or my games.
If you go with a publisher like Devolver is great, but whenever it becomes
a devolver game.
Yeah, it's not like your game anymore.
So they pay well, they're easy to work with.
But you don't like come out of that with that audience.
You like to get a tiny share of the devolver audience, maybe.
But really, it's their game.
Where's the Kickstarter approach?
Less money, but over time you can grow something large out of that.
And Mike, I'm curious to hear about your experience,
because Xeno Crisis had, and you've also
done Battle Axe since then, I would
say more of a modest Kickstarter success, which
then you were able to turn into a lot of physical release
success, but across more platforms
than most people would consider.
Yeah, it's a bit crazy, really.
And I wouldn't recommend it to everyone.
But.
For us, it's meant a different stream of revenue
other than just Steam and the eShop and so on.
But yeah, Kickstarter worked really well for us.
It was our first Kickstarter,
so we had to do a bit of research
and just see what elements needed on the page and so on.
We didn't really release it to much fanfare,
but I think because we were producing a Genesis game,
that generated quite a bit of excitement straight away.
So yeah, we, like Megan, we were three times
funded. So that was great. And even beyond Kickstarter, you know, you can start an Indiegogo
page after that. And then you can set up a BackerKit page so you can still make, you know,
keep the revenue stream coming in. And then after that, we opened our own online store as well.
And yeah, we've pretty much exploited every physical aspect we could. We found that,
yeah, there's a growing demand for physical, it seems, especially with
certain storefronts closing and certain consoles now not being supported.
Yeah, I think the PlayStation 3 and the PlayStation Vita are both on the brink of
closing down. So, yeah.
Yeah, we we've got I don't think it's a bit dark here now.
Yeah, we've got the Switch version.
Dreamcast recently did a deal for the Vita version with EastAsiasoft.
They're great guys.
There's the Evercade version, which.
All right. Yeah.
which is essentially a Mega Drive version.
Yeah, we got our own Mega Drive version.
We got the Neo Geo.
Backed that up, that's amazing.
And we got the vinyl as well.
Nice.
And a t-shirt.
So yeah, we really went for it.
And yeah, I think people just love having
cool games on the shelves, you know.
Do you have some maybe breakdown of, even just generally, of digital sales? Because it did come
out on the regular game consoles versus physical sales in terms of how that did for you?
I think if you talk to any indie developer these days, it's all about Switch, really.
The Switch just has such a following now, and...
Yeah, we did a deal for the physical Switch version,
which was strictly limited, which sold out right away.
So that was a real nice bonus for us.
As for metrics, I can't go into too much detail,
but yeah, I would say Switch is the big one, really.
Steam kind of disappointed,
but we did get a Game Pass deal with Microsoft,
which was a great injection of cash,
which we weren't expecting.
But yeah, we continue to produce the physical Mega Drive
and Dreamcast versions.
There are a lot of work, though.
But yeah, we have to.
to get the PCBs designed in China, and then we have to get all the plastics molded, various
things printed, we have to assemble the cartridges ourselves, deal with manufacturing, assembly,
and shipping. We had to hire a warehouse, so it's not something I'd recommend for everyone,
but it's just cool making a game for your favourite childhood console.
And straight away, you have a community there, a real hardcore community who are just really interested in whatever you're going to do in the future.
So, yeah, it's worked out well for us.
So, yeah, I can say that for us, even though we've only done physical on PlayStation 4 and Vita and it was just for one release that in terms of like revenue from sales, I would say that physical was roughly 50 percent.
of our total revenue despite the game being on like eight digital platforms or something like
that physical physical revenue from just two platforms was about 50 percent of our revenue
Justin what was your experience releasing for uh man I wish I had all my stuff let me see if I can
grab some stuff
Let me grab.
Yeah.
So we did, I don't have all my stuff right here.
You know what I mean?
But yeah, we did the, the actual, the cartridge for the NES version.
Yeah.
For mall brawl.
Uh, and we actually developed, and this is the switch deluxe version, uh, version.
We work with limited run games.
But we did, we released vinyl as well, which was awesome.
Because it was all, you know, chip tune, but that was a great experience because of the limit.
I like the limitations of developing in assembly.
You know, partnering with Thomas to create that experience because we were able to develop the game in nine months.
And this was a bigger piece of our, like the chronic blunt punch.
like lore and we put it out there kind of like Curse of the Moon did, like kind of as a piece
to give away for our larger crowdfunding, you know, backers and stuff like that. But
having something physical was quite amazing and to kind of basically reflect what you said,
Brandon, it was like that was a huge injection of money to help us.
with our studio move forward that those physical releases we so we released on switch PlayStation four or five Xbox one as an X.
And we did get some revenue in there, I think it also that's another stacking thing look we're look at what we did we created this pipeline to develop on these other things but.
The NES and the physical Switch did pretty well.
And we just released, we just did a PS4 physical release too.
And those were really good because of the collectors.
And then the game is retro.
So like having a cart, people wanting new carts
is pretty awesome.
So yeah.
It's an interesting, like, you know,
we're talking about post-release revenue streams now
at this point.
And it's.
It's interesting that there are multiple niches for releasing games after,
I mean, re-releasing games after they already exist, basically.
And, you know, like in the case of Xenocrisis with Mike there, you all have...
you know, like, is there a limit to the number of platforms that you can release? I mean, of course,
like, in terms of the power of the consoles there is, but do you see, like, an end to that, or is
this going to be a good thing going forward? And will you, like, put it on the DS or something in
10 years?
I mean, we'd love to get it on as many platforms as possible,
but there's only so many hours in the day and there's just two of us here.
And my colleague Matt does all the technical stuff.
You know, he's a real genius.
So I leave all the assembly and stuff to him. Right.
But yeah, I mean, really, it's down to resolution.
You know, the Mega Drive version is 320 by 224 pixels,
and that ports over perfectly to Neo Geo.
But if you want to put it on the SNES, for example, that's 256 pixels wide.
So then the art really has to be.
redrawn quite heavily and the, yeah, the rim generation as well, that takes a hit because,
yeah, there's fewer tiles that you have to squeeze everything into. So, yeah, we could,
we've thought about Jaguar and Amiga, but, yeah, we also like to, you know, start on new projects
as well. So, yeah, it might be something that we go back to. A PlayStation 1 version could be quite
viable, but you have to be careful not to tread on Sony's toes, of course, you know, you can't just
slap.
PlayStation on your box or Sega on your box.
So, but yeah, with the way things,
the way we have things set up, yeah,
other platforms are definitely a possibility, yeah.
And that's another good point because what,
like, especially if you're a small developer,
when you are continuing development of your existing game
that may not be that successful,
like, not saying you all, but us, for example,
then you're not making new games.
And so you sort of need to almost have that
be a separate pipeline if you can.
In our case, we've been working more and more
with one programmer on our team
becoming like the porting person.
So when we're putting stuff onto new platforms,
we will have them do it
and have them develop the new features
and do the
the ports and all this stuff because otherwise you wind up kind of just like cycling in one space
and you can't move forward and it can be really tempting to just stay there because it's like,
ah, we could squeeze a little bit more money out of this, but then you can wind up getting
into a situation like we were in earlier this year where we had three unfinished games that
we were trying to...
pitch around and figure out how to get through.
And it's like, we gotta, we gotta prioritize
and like just go in, go in one direction for a while.
But then we got this porting person to help out
and she's been great in terms of us being like, okay
we can just put this over there.
She can keep doing that.
It will, we'll get some revenue out of this later.
And then we can continue making new products
at the same time.
It's a tough balance.
I wanted to talk a bit about some more post release revenue stuff. The big obvious ones are platform buyouts for subscriptions like PlayStation Plus Xbox Game Pass at the game store.
All these other kinds of things we've done really small ones we've done decently large ones.
We won't talk about whether subscriptions are healthy for the industry.
That's another conversation.
I think they probably aren't really, but we got to get money to survive.
So let's talk about it.
Ava, do you want to talk a bit about like using platform subscription buyouts and
stuff and turning that into more success later?
Yeah, honestly, my logic around all of this is
the more the merrier and the better that you can stack revenue,
especially with like buyout revenue at the right time
or utilize some of the platforms to bring in players and or increase wishlist numbers.
Those are all huge wins.
It just depends on kind of your goal.
For HyperDot, our entire strategy was actually buyouts
because we didn't have a pre-existing set of players
that we knew were going to be really excited.
quite yet about HyperDot. So we were pretty much all in on trying to figure out which ways and how
we could stack different buyouts, whether it was with Xbox or Epic, etc. So what we ended up doing
was really focusing on, okay, well, can we do like a timed exclusive or something of sorts with...
Xbox, which we ended up doing. And then we followed that up with Game Pass, primarily
to kind of test out the waters on what it would look like to do a timed exclusive, how
long that would be, what the players are like, how many people are actually buying the game,
and what is the kind of uptake.
in terms of like cross promo on Steam.
And then when we entered Game Pass,
we had really planned out that there would be essentially
like leaderboards and a couple of like online ways to play,
especially with the introduction of more levels
that people can actually design.
So custom levels were actually entered in at that time.
So we saw a really huge lift of players
during that time as well.
And then we ended up really thinking about like, okay,
whether it was bundles or sales or any other platform buyouts,
what does that really look like?
And how much are we actually selling the game for
when we're looking at the actual numbers of who is playing?
So our team is really focused on insights.
So again, on our back end, we were really tracking,
like, how many players were actually, you know,
playing the game till completion?
How many players were actually...
turning on the game and coming back to it over time.
We just wanted to know what that looked like and
what the end of the day,
what we were actually selling our game for.
Because to me, when I'm looking at buyouts,
it's not actually development dollars,
it's cash advance sales.
What it really looks like is that you're looking at how much
did you actually sell your game for
with the number of downloads that you actually got.
and the amount of players that actually played your game.
So again, I think it really depends on how you want to stack
and the goals that you have when you're stacking.
But I often say, again, like the more the merrier.
I think it's really smart if you have a couple of goals in mind and can.
talked to a bunch of different platforms.
I know we ended up on like an Amazon buyout towards the end.
And then we really talked a lot about like pricing
after it came out of Game Pass and even during Game Pass,
which maybe we'll go to a little bit later
in like the bundles and sales section.
But I think it's really important
and I think it's a really viable way to think about it.
Yeah, I wanted to talk about a couple of numbers there
that.
I thought of when you were talking about how many people have actually downloaded it and
whatever.
For our game, Gun House, we've been in some bundles, which we'll get into, but because
of those bundles and because of buyouts and other things, we have had...
We don't actually know the total number of people that own the game.
It's basically impossible for us to know how many people own it, but we know it's over
a million.
Then in terms of number of people that have downloaded it,
it's around 250,000.
And then in terms of the number of people
that have actually paid for it,
that is a much smaller number.
Like paid for it individually,
that's probably in the,
I don't actually know the real number,
but it's probably in the 30, 40,000 range.
And that was through like pushing it on every platform.
That's across like eight or nine platforms
that we were able to sell 30, 40,000.
And then I also wanted to say like some numbers for what those buyouts can look like.
For us, without saying specific platforms, we've had them as small as $10,000.
And that was just like from our minds, it was like, OK, it's going to take us two weeks to port this.
We get $10,000.
That gives us like a little like another month or something for one or two programmers.
And then we've gotten up to like $250,000 as well.
And other deals can be in the $500,000 range,
even for an indie.
Then when you get up into like AAA,
you're talking about millions
and that's different sphere than we may be involved in.
But those are some of the kinds of numbers
that you can think about it
and they can all be viable as long as it's worth it.
Like in my opinion, if you take a buyout,
it's got to pay you.
much more, at least twice as much as it will cost you
to make the thing if you're doing it in advance.
And if you're doing it after the fact,
it's got to be like,
I've sold as much as I want to on this platform,
and now I will take whatever other money I can get from you.
Megan, did you have some things to say about this zone?
Yeah, my take is,
I'm less concerned about maximizing.
revenue, like it's important to me, but the important thing for me is to make sure that
my, uh, my ass is covered.
So when I'm looking at backend deals, uh, platform deals, buyout deals are almost all
backend.
Some aren't though we actually got some advances too.
I'm looking less at, well, how much is this going to, uh, go for versus my theoretical
sales on this platform.
I'm looking more at, okay, if I take this deal, does this mean that the game doesn't
have to sell any copies on any other platform and I'm still 2x profitable.
If I can get a deal like that, and those deals do exist,
I take it because, come on, it's worth it.
I tend to view.
So Switch aside, Switch is a special case.
Both of the remaining platforms, Sony and Xbox,
have weird sales behavior.
Like depending on what end you talk to, a lot of them
will find that one of them sold really well, and one of them
sold like 10 units.
It's not that bad, but it's.
It's significantly terrible.
It can be.
So true.
Negligible.
They're like really random and hard to account for.
So if I can find something that says I get big chunk of money and I don't have to worry
about-
The guarantee.
Yeah, the guarantee is huge.
Now, the big problem you run into with that though is great, now you get hundreds of thousands
of dollars at launch, but you don't have any money right now since most of those are going
to be-
Posts.
Really? Yeah, they're post like I believe Xbox deals.
They're they're post.
And just because a game just because a deal you sign is like
at launch date is when it pays out.
Well, most consoles have some kind of billing that's net net 90, net 180.
It's kind of hard to tell.
So you might not see that money until six months after lunch or after lunch.
Hustle that to, you know, hustle.
Yeah, I got it.
And I'll give you my money, son.
You got to have a plan for how to survive, not just through launch or through pre-launch and
development, but also through that. So we ended up stacking a combination of deals that some of
them we negotiated for half upfront, half backend. Some of them were backend. Some of them were
other stuff that we can't actually get into. But suffice it to say, we stacked enough deals that by
launch, we were going to be between two and three X profitable no matter what, which was nice.
And we also had just enough money to make it through to launch.
And that actually ran out and I had to pull from savings, which is getting
to the other point, which if you're going to try and work this strategy,
it really helps if you have some revenue, some portion of money that it doesn't
have to be money that you're meant to spend, like it can be money that you
need to put back within a year.
And that's okay because you've got all these guarantees that say
it will be put back in a year.
But if you've got at least something to draw on,
a lot of these deals become a lot more accessible.
Whereas without that, I mean, sure,
a lot of the platforms are offering really good indie deals
with back-end pay.
Well, how many indies can afford to develop a game
without money now?
So how accessible are they really?
And yeah.
Yeah.
We're in our last five minutes here.
So I wanna get through, kind of combine a couple things
and talk about.
just additional, all kinds of additional places where you can get money.
A quick story that I have always enjoyed is Amanita Games, who make
Machinarium and a bunch of these high-end adventure games,
they found that in the Czech Republic it was hard for their customers to buy,
for older people and a lot of folks to
to buy the game because they didn't have credit cards, they didn't have Steam.
And so they wound up partnering with like a friend who ran a series of newsstands to like print CDs
and sell it for like two euro in like a little paper hang tag thing in a newsstand. And I love
that kind of hustling stuff. So we'll talk about bundles here as well, but I want to start with
with Robert to hear about.
you know, some of the different kinds of platforms that you've put games on, like you put games on
planes, have you done cruise ships? I just want to hear about this kind of stuff and what those
deals look like a little bit. So basically I don't have a like scenario how to get to those deals,
but yeah, like at some point in time we were asked if we would like to
partner with a company who has like those tablets installed in airplanes, but also on
buses and trains, they do all kinds of transportation.
And we said, yeah, sure.
And basically there are planes flying somewhere around Europe with our games, like pre-installed
on those seats.
And yeah, and people are playing them.
And they buy like in number of seats, right? Is that how they buy? Because when I was trying to talk to some cruise ships about selling games, they're like, we'll buy 20,000 units of this or whatever.
So no, we actually we, we have like a fixed amount per year, just because we license those games to be used within the system. Right. And so so I'll
Like I think everybody here said that and I'll repeat that.
Like if you have a game and even if that game is not for everybody, there's a 100% chance
that there's somebody out there, some platform out there that they would like your content.
yeah there's somewhere funding them and and just discussing the deal and and it will happen if
you'll put a lot of work in it it is a lot of work uh every i i believe every game will find
their audience eventually totally yeah i think go ahead uh and
like i said there is no there is no
guarantee way of achieving that. So like you can go to a lot of conferences, do a lot of like
formal networking, go to meetings, cold mailing everybody. But in the end it just happens after
some time if you're a little bit lucky and you put a lot of work in it. That's right.
One thing about the networking.
A lot, if you're watching this, you've heard a lot about networking and a lot
about getting in with important people and yada, yada, try not to think of it
like talking to the head of Sony or whatever you don't network by cold
calling the head of Sony India or whatever you network by working with
your peers and over time, your peers become the head of Sony or whatever.
So absolutely work within your local spheres, local communities first.
And then over time you'll find those people tend to get better and better
jobs and then, Oh, Hey, you just know them.
words of wisdom. Yeah. So we got we got we got 20 seconds left here. We were going to talk about
bundles. Now we can't. But I'm just going to say one great thing you can do if your game just can't
make money at all is put it into charity bundles and it just becomes one more thing that can be
like in the bundle for racial justice or for Palestinian aid. And it just at least your game's
doing some work. Thanks, everybody. Bye. Thank you. Bye bye.