Hi everyone. My name is Hank Howey and I'm the Director of Partnerships for Modulate.
I've been in the game industry for, well, quite some time now in various companies and roles. I
was one of the co-founders of Blue Fang Games and we made Zoo Tycoon back in the day. But today I'm
here to talk to you about the ever-increasing impact of voice chat in games. I don't...
We don't think that's a terribly controversial notion, but one of the interesting things is how
much research there is around voice chat in games, you know, both the good and the bad,
and there's plenty of both, and thought it would be useful to share that data with a lot of you,
some of the studies and so forth, and just, you know, again, talk about voice chat in games.
So the nature of gaming obviously has been shifting for some time now. Ever since 2008,
the largest selling games are invariably the big online multiplayer games. You know,
game usage, gameplay has been growing, you know, really since I've been in the industry and it's,
you know, and it's really, it seems like growth has gotten even more precipitous.
in more recent times and let's say in the last decade, you know, even pre-COVID, 63% of game
players, adult game players, were playing five hours or more a week. COVID obviously did a lot to
increase that, you know, as we shall see. And again, less for I want to play games more than,
you know, I want to go hang out online with my friends because, well, that's where they are.
it's a pandemic, I can't go see them right now. So again, pretty obvious, but you know, bears
mentioning. And then really it didn't just affect gamers per se, but really, you know, having
sort of sharing one's life and social life online has affected everyone from, you know,
kids to grandparents and everyone in between. People, you know, I think understand
now, you know, post-pandemic, kind of what it is to live and socialize online and how it really is,
you know, a thing. You know, and something that I alluded to earlier, which is the games are not
just, you know,
people aren't just going online to play the games per se. I mean, sure, a lot of folks do that, but
again, during the pandemic in particular, people would go to various online places, online
communities, in order to basically interact with anyone socially.
You know, again, it's this phenomenon of folks going online to play a game, per se,
and the game is really just on in the background. You know, I mean,
players aren't communicating about the game.
and what's going on in it and you know if there's a threat and you know but he runs or hides or
shoots back but but um but really then it's in the sort of the in the down times of the game which is
you know when not much is going on people are basically just you know sharing what's going on
in their lives um you know uh sharing with their friends and basically
hanging out. I mean, look at the PUBG numbers of, you know, immune players,
using it as a social platform. You know, it's kind of the bowling with friends kind of philosophy,
or golf with your friends. It's that same notion where, sure, everyone's going online to this
destination, which happens to be a game. But really what's going on is not only gameplay, but
socialization. You know, talking with your friends.
voice chat. And I think somewhat obviously to voice chat clearly it leads to a more
stronger bonds in the game, deeper empathy for other players in the game than mere text chat.
And then here is where we kind of get to that two-edged, we first touch on the real two-edged
sort of voice chat in gaming, the pros and the cons. And, you know, like for example,
you know, in the Women in Gaming study, 80% of women reported being empowered
by access to online voice chat to interact with folks, you know, in kind of new and compelling
ways.
you know, they really, they really, really, they like that. And then at the same time,
you know, just about all of them reported facing toxicity, and in particular, through voice
and voice chat. And, you know, it's this, it's the sad truth.
Voice chat's obviously, you know, and the impact of voice chat in games,
it's obviously very important for various aspects of gaming.
Clearly, with voice chat, players can feel greater immersion
within the game and within the world that they're playing in.
You know, in order to role play and feel,
you know, closer identity, say, to their avatar within the game.
They can express that through voice.
Obviously, for any kind of competitive online game,
voice chat is a must.
There's just no good replacement right now.
In order to get the information to your teammates
and communicate and function effectively as a team,
players have to be talking to one another.
And then, for example, just even, you know, not that long ago,
talking about, you know, proximity voice chat stuff was kind of unheard of.
All kinds of issues, you know, technology, bandwidth and so forth.
And now, you see any number of games and environments that are starting to implement those features.
And, you know, it just, it adds to the, it adds to the experience, you know,
and the player's experience within the game.
Yeah, but then, you know, now we get to maybe even deeper into the dark side of games. And,
you know, I just, you know, called out for the articles here. I'm sure all of us who are almost
invariably in the game community have read or seen or almost certainly experienced toxicity within
you know, online gaming environments via voice chat.
You know, and the thing is, you know, the thing is when people talk about toxicity,
yeah, oh yeah, there's swear words and all that, sure.
But I think we also know that it's way worse than that.
It's way worse than that. You know, players are experiencing
racism, doxing, misogyny,
child grooming, even, believe it or not, even terrorist recruitment, believe it or not,
goes on in game environments. And again, it's all through the use of voice chat.
It's again, it's the downside for sure.
Voice.
You know, voice in general is an intimate form of communication, right?
And despite the earlier figures about, you know, women in gaming and so forth,
you know, these studies show about 60% of women generally seek to mask their gender online,
you know, in the obvious ways, right? They're either using, they're either, you know, they're in a
a male avatar or in some other ways or perhaps not even using voice chat
because invariably when they do reveal their gender
many times toxic behavior occurs from their fellow players. It's just a
sad truth, right?
68% of players experience severe abuse through voice chat, physical threats, stalking, sustained
harassment, stalking both online and in real life.
So again, it's the real cutting edge of voice chat in games and not the good kind.
This is an interesting notion, at least I think it's interesting.
There's a phenomena in, this has been studied, you know,
in the past to a great degree, you know, crowd behavior, when people are
in a crowd and they start to become just part of the crowd
and, you know, they feel somewhat anonymous.
they as a person don't stand out as much
and they can kind of start to be absorbed
and enmeshed into the crowd.
It's a condition called de-individuation,
where basically, excuse me,
people basically lose their external
and individual constraints, right?
So where they might act perfectly normally
in a normal social situation.
you put them in this different environment with these different factors and their behavior changes,
right? And not for the better, not for the better. You know, I think all, one only need to have
watched the news over the past year to see, and certainly in real life, how these behaviors can
play out and how people can kind of lose, lose what are their normal, you know,
and not behave in good positive ways.
And the other factor at play here is which
which environment begets which when it comes to these behaviors, right?
Are people learning this at younger ages and in a more acute fashion because they're online,
because they're seeing all this toxic behavior take place,
because perhaps they're experiencing it and starting to do it themselves?
Do people bring these behaviors online because
you know, and then clearly this happens, right? People have tough days and then they go online
and maybe they're, maybe they act in ways that, that they normally would, you know,
even in an online situation. But it's just, it's the, the behaviors we need to, it's better if we
can tamp down these behaviors and these toxic behaviors that make them, you know, create
environments where they're not tolerant.
right? And they're not set as a norm of behavior. And that's, I think, what we really have to start
to strive for when it comes to, you know, moderating online social behavior and online voice chat.
And then let's talk about children, right? You know, as we can see,
for we, and I don't think these stats are going to surprise anybody. I mean, 40 to 75% of kids
are using.
platforms that they're technically, you know, not supposed to be on, too young to be on, right?
They're younger than 13 and they're going online and they're playing these games and have headsets
on and they're in voice chat and what are they learning? What are they seeing? What kind of
behaviors, you know, are there for them to model, right? Other interesting factors, kids are twice
as likely to just use platform blocking and reporting tools versus, you know, telling someone,
telling a grown-up, telling their parents.
what might have happened to them, you know, within a game, within an online environment.
And bad things can happen. Majority of kids who block a report say the people they blocked and
reported, they find them again. You know, they come in with a different identity, a different
account, boom. And they kind of know where they are, where they were, and they find them again.
Clearly, you know, now these are behaviors that are just, well.
They're heinous.
And some, like child grooming in particular,
these are heinous behaviors.
And it's clear to me,
and I think it should be to everyone,
that we have a moral responsibility
to do something about it, particularly in games,
because it's going on in online multiplayer games.
Kids who identify as LGBTQ,
This is shocking, right? They experience harm at even higher rates than non-LGBTQ players do.
And yet, and again, here's the great side of online games, online environments,
that LGBTQ kids and players, they find joy and strength in video games, right? Going online and
playing games.
you know, because they can be good at it. They can excel at it.
And goodness knows, heck, they might even find kindred spirits online
who they can share both their enjoyment to gain,
you know, but also what they might be going through as,
you know, as kids growing up, you know, trying to find their identity and so
forth. So I think
It's important. It's important. It's important.
Let's talk about, all right, so far we've talked about
the existence of how important voice chat is
both to games and just to us as persons.
We've talked about some of the pros
and certainly many of the cons, right?
But let's talk about money, right?
Because money, money is, tends to get people's attention, right?
It tends to get everyone's attention.
At the very top levels of management in companies,
and right down to, you know, the base layer.
The Anti-Defamation League does tremendous work,
studies and reporting on.
any kind of toxic, disruptive behavior in society in general and online as well.
The 2020 report is a very good one. It's very informative. I urge everyone to go check it out
if and when you have an opportunity. But for example, 68% of players,
68 to 80 actually, are facing serious toxicity.
in their game and nearly 50% of players experience that via voice chat.
And the big news, almost 30% of players leave games because of it, right? They just leave.
They leave your game because they don't need it and they just don't want it. So let's take a
just an example game and talk about maybe some of the numbers. So if you take a 50 million player
game, sure, that's a big game, but there are way bigger games out there as we know. 50 million,
we'll do easy math, right? 50 million players, you have, say, 68% of the players facing toxicity
divided again by the 48% who experienced it in voice chat. And then
a third of those players leave, 28%. That's 4.5 million on a 50 million player game.
Again, my apologies to my friends who are UA specialists out there. There are way more
complex and interesting ways to do this. I welcome anyone who wants to really take a look at it, but
This is directionally correct. I don't think we're off by an order of magnitude by any stretch of
the imagination. On the low side, we might be approaching being off on the high side.
Even with this quick and dirty math, at $10 per player revenue and big games,
it can be at least twice that. You're talking $50 million a year.
$50 million a year. Again, that's for a 50 million player game, but that's a lot of money.
That's a lot of money. At least I think so. And I think it behooves. And then,
well, and then leave that aside for a minute. Think about the human side, right?
Four and a half million players experienced, had a very, very negative experience in potentially
in your game.
right? Because there's nothing being done about the toxic environment.
If you know for those players who aren't toxic. You know you had four and a half million players
you know they had a they had a crappy time and because of that there's a human side.
Just to just add to that again this is these you know this is a VBOX study that was just done in 2019.
Veevok's obviously very involved in voice chat, as we know.
Voice chat players spend twice the time in game as non-voice chat players.
Boom. Right? How does that translate to revenue?
I'm certain it does. It has to. And then voice chat players,
players who use voice chat, five times as likely to be playing
in week number five versus non-voice chat players.
So again, retention, right? Voice chat.
contributes remarkably to for those games that you know that uh utilize voice chat it contributes
remarkably to to game retention uh so it's it's you know it really behooves us not just
ethically again but financially to do something about voice chat in our games and the toxicity
they're in um
Just to sort of finish up here, you know, voice chat technology, it's evolving, it's changing,
it's growing, it's getting, you know, it's getting better and better enabled all the time.
And, you know, some of the big streaming platforms are giving players more control over,
you know, kind of the voice interactions between them, streamers and so forth.
There's technology where folks can, you know,
recognize and adjust for dialogue, even, you know, even language difference between speakers,
which is, you know, more on the cohesive, bring people together side. There's dynamic,
dynamic volume-based proximity chat, you know, as far as, you know, even telling where other
players and even where enemies are, you know, online. So that's all great stuff.
But there is, you know, as far as voice chat and toxicity and moderation there, there are today
autonomous moderation addressing technologies that can be used in games by game runners,
by platforms to moderate and cut way down on toxic chat.
in our games, right?
You know, we at Modulate, we, you know,
I have my Talks Mod webpage signal there,
but if you're interested in this, by all means,
go to modulate.ai.
You can check out the kind of things we're doing.
There are other companies doing it as well.
And I think it uses all to recognize the issue,
acknowledge it.
and do something about it.
And with that, I'm going to let you all go.
I hope you found this at least somewhat informative
and interesting and I want you all to have a
have a great day. Stay well. I hope you enjoyed my
my Wu-Fang swag. There's not much of this left.
Anymore anyway.
You all stay safe out there, be well, and enjoy game playing online.
It's fun.
Thank you very much.
Take care.