Alright, looks like everybody's pretty much in. Um, welcome to the killer portfolio or
portfolio killer talk. Uh, just to start off, can you please silence your cell phones?
All right.
So today we're going to be talking about portfolios
and the practices that we use to evaluate them
and the best way for people
who are looking to get in the industry to get in.
My name is Greg Furch.
I'm a senior art director at Firaxis.
We have some extra guests here.
Do you want me to start?
Yeah, jump on by.
I'm Wyatt Johnson.
I'm a tech art lead at Epic.
I've also been a lead artist and an art director at Epic and have been there for about 11 years.
And we just shipped Robo Recall.
Hi, I'm Lissette Tichi-Montgomery and I'm art director here at Ubisoft San Francisco.
And we are currently working on South Park, The Fractured But Whole.
Sean Robertson, I'm art director at Ghost Story Games,
previously animation director at Irrational,
and I wish our game had the word butthole in it, but.
No such luck.
I'm Gavin Goulin, I'm the lead character artist
at Insomniac Games, working on Spider-Man.
Before that it was Sunset Overdrive.
Awesome.
All right, so just also to remind you guys,
after we're done, 1.30 to 4.30 down the hall,
we're gonna be doing portfolio reviews.
We've got a whole nother crew of art directors as well
to help with that, so if you're interested
in getting some time and getting some advice
on your portfolio, please come by and see us.
All right, so let's start with your origin stories.
How did you guys stumble into this career?
Oh gosh, I guess I'll start.
I got kind of lucky, I'd started in graphic design,
and I had, and this is probably a good story,
just because you can get in from any which random way,
and that's something interesting
and kind of unique about our industry,
but I was a graphic designer,
and I had just volunteered to test a local game.
I was in Dallas at the time.
I wrote a local developer and said,
hey, do you need anybody to come in
and play your game and test?
They said,
Sure, why not?
Out of 300-some people who had emailed at that point, they picked me.
I just got lucky or wrote a good email.
And then once I was there, I just made an impression on the people at the company.
And they were curious, what do you do?
You know.
outside of coming and giving your time for free to play this random game.
And I showed him my portfolio and before too long I had a job.
Totally circuitous and this was 16, 17 years ago so things have changed a lot but the core
philosophy of
it.
You never know what's important, I think,
is the reason I tell that story.
Because you never know what effort and what strings
you're putting out into the world that
are going to be valuable, that are going to tie you back
to the thing you want.
So you're constantly being judged on your presentation
out into the world.
And you don't know which of those threads
are going to come back to be valuable to you later.
Great.
I actually got into the industry somewhat by accident.
I was actually inspired by Pixar.
and then I was looking for an end to the film industry.
So I graduated from school in Miami,
and I quickly realized that there were no jobs
in Florida for me at the time.
So I moved to California with my suitcase
and the workstation I built by myself,
and I was lucky enough my portfolio got me a job
within the first month.
So I started with my first PS2 project
as a character artist.
So I was just mostly pursuing my passion
for character art and character design.
and I think that that translated over from film into games.
I went to Ringling School of Art and Design
and graduated with an illustration degree,
thinking I was gonna change the world
with my editorial illustrations.
And when that didn't happen,
I was lucky enough to get an internship
at the old phone company 9X Science and Technology,
where they helped me bridge the gap
between all of the traditional art that I had learned
and moving over into the digital side.
Once I was comfortable with the digital platform,
I moved over to a small children's edutainment company
doing like 8-bit story,
like click the page and turn the page stories.
All the while really at home working on my real portfolio,
going home every night and just grinding and grinding.
And finally getting my big break at Looking Glass Studios
working on one of their flight simulators.
So way way back
I thought the only way to get into the games industry was to be a fine artist
And I was a terrible fine artist and I didn't get into fine art school
so after
Crushing rejection I ended up going to game art school. I dropped out which I might not recommend to the room but
It kind of worked out.
So, dropped out, moved across the country.
Ended up doing contract UI work
while doing some just day jobs.
And sort of like Sean, I just ended up grinding away
on my character art portfolio,
got into some indie companies,
and then moved on to the bigger ones.
Seems like the story is moving.
One thing I'd like to add to that
is that I've worked with two other artists
that I consider really high caliber.
One was in pre-med.
and dropped out of pre-med and again, self-taught
and really just grinded away.
And another guy came straight out of airline industry.
Like, he was a legit airline pilot
and he was just working on his portfolio
and he just went straight from like airline pilot
onto working as an artist on Bioshock.
So, there are many different paths.
I've worked with some great architects
turned level designers.
Yeah, that's a common thread.
A lot of architects and people who learn CAD
are sort of transferred in.
All right, so this is the one that always comes up.
You know, we always hear you've gotta have,
you know, five pieces, 10 pieces, 30,
whatever it is in your portfolio.
There's always somebody putting a magic number
on what people expect in a portfolio.
What do you guys think about that?
I'll start.
I think the best number is take whatever you have,
divide it in half, and subtract two.
That's the correct number for a portfolio.
It's just, people put too much stuff
in their portfolio all the time.
Seeing the variety of somebody's skills is awesome,
but the thing is is that your portfolio is only as strong
as the weakest piece in it.
And so if we get, you know, there's some strong stuff
and then we get to the end and there's something
that's maybe, you know, not as fully well thought out
or fleshed out or whatever it may be.
we wonder if you have great taste, right?
Because we're starting to kind of wonder,
like, did you see those flaws?
Were you able to understand why maybe this piece
that you hid in the back just because you felt
like you needed to have a gun in there
or some other random kind of false belief
about your portfolio?
we start to question whether or not you're bringing
that same quality bar to all your pieces.
So if you could get somebody who's not you
to look at them, give you some advice on the fidelity
of the stuff that you're doing,
be really, really critical,
and then if you feel like something is weaker,
cull it from the herd, get it out of there,
your whole portfolio is gonna be better.
We've hired people at Epic
that had three pieces in their portfolio.
A junior artist that made three amazing environments
and took three screenshots each, and we hired him.
Yeah, I would definitely stress quality over quantity.
I think what you first have to ask yourself is what kind of games you want to make.
Because I think one of the biggest traps is trying to do all the styles in your portfolio.
I think that is sort of spreading yourself a little thin,
and it's also muting your voice.
So I would sort of approach it from, like, what kind of games do I want to make,
what kind of art do I want to make, what kind of voice do I want to make,
and what kind of position do I want to fill.
because we're most likely looking for a very particular position
and a very particular set of skills,
and we're not looking for the jack-of-all-trades.
Maybe small studios are looking for that,
but mostly we're looking for someone who can come in
and hit the ground running and do one thing very well.
Awesome.
Speaking of that, too, what about importance of a presentation?
How does that impact your thoughts on a portfolio?
So, I think this is ...
you know, very much related to the previous question,
like you're an artist and your entire job
is to present things, whether it's in the video game,
in the end product of the game,
you're presenting things to the audience,
whether it's in your portfolio,
you're presenting your work to a potential employer,
it's all about the presentation.
Part of that presentation is the quality of the art
that's in your portfolio, it's also how you present it.
How many,
Hoops, do I have to jump through to see your art?
One of my favorite examples of the worst portfolio
I've ever seen.
Back when, you know, back in the mid-90s,
I hate to say how old I am,
Ed Looking Glass got a portfolio on a CD
when they still came on CDs,
and I was supposed to open a CD and put it in the computer,
and it was all tied up,
like it was supposed to be a presentation,
like they tied it up with like...
dental floss and it was like a bow and it was like opening one of those bubble packs
with the, by the time I spent ten minutes trying to open this thing I threw it away.
So that presentation completely worked against what you really want is get me to your images
and show me what you have and present them in a clean and simple way.
I think I just echo what Sean said.
I mean, I think we're at a time where all you really need
is ArtStation and then a handful of really good images.
But in those really good images,
if you're making a character, you've got to pose them,
like drop them out of T-pose,
get them in a good lighting situation.
If you're making an environment,
tell a story, light it well,
set an atmosphere in that environment,
and it makes it easier for us to hire you.
If I could just piggyback on that comment about atmosphere.
just for those of you who are aspiring environment people,
that's the biggest single missing thing
for me that I see all the time
is people focus so much on the props
and the creation of the assets
that they forget that they're trying to message something
and elicit a feeling from the person
who's looking at the image.
games are is just a series of images that we're composing and presenting and we're using those
languages to guide the player and tell you where to look and where to go and what to see.
And the soul of the environments get lost inside the pursuit of making a really awesome fire hydrant
and we don't care about the fire hydrant. In fact, I would much rather have somebody who is a little
bit weaker on the technical sides of the art because we'll teach you the tool, that's fine.
If you tell an amazing story with an image then...
You're great.
That's the point, you know?
So it was a great comment, I totally agree.
Yeah, I agree, definitely telling a story,
and I wanna get a sense of your aesthetic and personality.
What are you gonna, what sort of story are you gonna tell,
what sort of personality are you gonna bring to the product?
And having a strong style and perspective
also helps drive that story home.
So where do you guys actually look for talent?
Like when you're looking for an employee or something,
if say a job comes up and you're like,
hey, I need to go find somebody, like I've done this.
I also kind of keep tabs on people,
like I'll actually go ping somebody and see.
But like where do you do that?
And also like kind of also looking
so that you also know what your bar is,
like as you guys are artists as well.
So where do you guys look for to find like potential talent?
I mean, I think there's like a few,
the most common resources would be something
like ArtStation or like Polycount.
And you can just kind of.
go through the more popular people
who are searching keywords and stuff like that.
But beyond that, it's also building a network.
Like I'm, as some of you might know,
I love the attention of Twitter,
so I'm just an active social media guy.
And through that, I'm building connections
with artists of different disciplines and stuff like that.
So when a spot opens up, I have it in my head,
because I was just talking to this person online.
I was just talking about a game that I'm playing
or something, right?
So I can kind of see the work that they're doing
through social media, like beyond.
I think Twitter's a really interesting thing.
It's the art station and...
you know, Polycount, those are like easy go-to's,
but I don't think enough people think about,
you know, Twitter as a vehicle.
It's like, it's a resume you're sending out
with every image you may send,
just make sure you send good ones,
but like, that's a good point.
Yeah, I mean, with your social media,
I mean, I think I said this like last year too,
but you're effectively managing yourself as a brand.
So if you have Twitter or Instagram
or your own like art Facebook account or something,
you're...
facing your audience and kind of showing your work and people are watching, you know, and
it can lead into opportunities for jobs or just contract gigs.
Sometimes the people that I'm really attracted to are people who are intrinsically driven toward being teachers as well as having talent
That's super appealing especially for the field that I'm in now
Which is kind of where the technical art side where there are a lot of big unanswered questions
And it's a confusing mishmash of art and technology
and so that can be an appealing thing too if I see people who keep bubbling up by answering threads on forums and
Providing tutorials and putting out hey, I have good taste and I'm talented and here's something
I know that maybe you don't
That can, for me anyway, that can be really powerful.
Yeah, I think I come across talent in a similar way.
Besides using my network of people that I know,
I'm also looking on social media.
So it's really important what kind of voice you have
when you're on social media.
I think we like to use social media
as a way to vent at times,
but if you're mixing that in with your art,
that may not be the best place
to kind of have two different conversations.
So I would try to really focus on maybe having
you know, a Tumblr that is focused on art
and an Instagram that's focused on art,
and you know, driving, you're using your Twitter
to drive that sort of traffic around.
But if you are, you know, just going on their event,
that may not be the best place to do it.
So do you guys see any new...
Trends emerging like what our specializations and what's coming? I mean, I think there's a lot of
Stuff with procedural generation that's influencing this as well. But vr like what what do you guys see? How does that change?
uh
career paths and what people are kind of kind of learning
Well, I just shipped a VR game, so it's fresh on my mind.
But virtual reality is clearly marching forward
at a really, really amazing pace.
And there aren't a lot of people
that have knowledge in that area.
VR is kind of unique because we're using
all the same tools that we used to use.
Obviously, being at Epic, we're using Unreal
to build all of the bones and guts,
and then we're using some DCC packages
to create assets outside of those.
But the way you assemble them and the problems you have in the presentation
Issues that you have around seeing something virtual reality way different from a lot of the traditional problems translating 3d images to a 2d screen
So that could be an area that's emerging and it's up-and-coming and they're gonna be a lot of jobs in that space if you could
Find a way to contribute some of those projects that probably would you know up your value quotient a little bit for the near future
And even if you get into teams doing work like that,
eventually you're gonna spread out
into other disciplines as well.
So, kind of brings me back to that original point,
just find something that makes you attractive,
that sets you apart, and then once you're in,
you can move around inside that bubble.
So is there anything you guys find is like deficient?
Like there's more demand than supply?
Like tech art is a great one,
it's also a very ambiguous one, but like.
I think from my personal standpoint, level builders,
I think they're,
From where I'm sitting, there's a more rare unicorn
to try to find someone who is interested
and can really, has the ability to assemble a world
with a story and atmosphere.
And not, you know, you see a lot of people building props
and you can go on ArtStation and see a ton of concept art.
And there is a lot of talented level builders,
but a lot of the talented level builders are hired.
So I think that's that.
So when you say a level builder,
are you expecting that person
to also do their own scripting as well?
No, I'm talking mostly from a standpoint,
I mean, that'd be nice, sure.
I'm talking like artistically building out a space,
like from an architecture standpoint and mise en scene.
There is one thing I'd like to add
that's kind of tangent to this.
New things that I see on the horizon.
We are a smaller studio, we have about 25 people.
We are using a lot of freelance artists,
a lot more than perhaps we did on Infinite,
where on Infinite we would just hire somebody full-time.
And I think you're gonna see a lot more
mid-sized studios emerging
that are taking on freelance artists.
because it's a cheaper way to make games.
And I think a lot of people are looking at AAA
and maintaining a 400-person studio is very expensive
and there's a few studios who can afford to do it,
but there's a lot that can't.
So I think you're gonna start seeing a lot of more
medium-sized studios propping up
that are looking for freelance artists
and talented freelance artists.
And I think looking at how you're presenting yourself
on the internet.
is even more important in that case,
because that's where people are looking
to bring in that talent and bring in those freelancers.
I think working on a project like South Park,
we ran into sort of a bit of a disconnect in this industry
when we were looking for talent,
especially when we were looking for animators.
Because of the style of the show,
we really needed some people
with very strong traditional skills
who knew how to do performance.
who knew how to really sell personality.
And we got a lot of portfolios
with a lot of mo-cap slidey animations.
And that sort of skill set is just not gonna translate over
to a game that's very stylized and performance based.
So we had a really hard time finding talent for animation
that could actually do that strong hand key.
The schools are really pushing mocap, motion builder,
you know, very like procedural animation.
But on the other side,
these very stylized personality-based games,
we're starving for animators who really know
how to do performance-based animation.
Super quickly, I'll just add,
if you want to be guaranteed a job in the game industry,
learn visual effects.
There are zero effects artists available.
And probably UI as well.
And I was just about to add UI to that.
UI, VFX, and tech art.
They're incredibly hard to learn,
they're tough to master, but you will get hired
if you are any good.
I would say definitely anyone who can come in
with some technical ability is also gonna
kinda come up ahead.
So if you can write tools and scripts,
if you're really strong at VFX and doing dynamics,
writing expressions.
Anything we can do to kind of push the tech forward
and improve efficiency, we're gonna be looking
for people who can help out with that.
So moving on, what workflows, this is probably an easy question,
but it may not be an easy question, it's probably fairly simple.
What workflows or common pipelines do you expect applicants to actually have?
What are some of the contemporary standards?
I think there are more, there may actually be some more standard things
that are just now very common over the past couple of years,
especially when it comes to materials that we kind of expect.
Yeah, I mean, I think the most...
obvious answer is going to be substance,
like learning a material authoring tool
versus painting, like hand painting textures
or doing it the old school way or something like that.
But I think the key thing to keep in mind
isn't necessarily the program that you're learning.
It's the methodology behind why you're doing it.
You're trying to make things more consistent
so they render more properly.
You're reducing like tedious workflows.
You're not hand painting a spec texture anymore.
It's just.
it's there is because it's part of your material palette.
Yeah, I think that'd be the most upcoming thing,
from my perspective.
Maybe one thing I would add is generally we don't care that much what tool you know.
And that's something maybe I should just touch on for one second, which is I think I see
a lot of students who hyper-emphasize, okay, I know Max, I know Modo, I can do simulations
in Houdini, I know Unreal, I know Unity, I know this, I know that.
None of that matters at all.
I don't care.
I don't even wish to see it on the resume.
I truly don't care.
If you're talented, I will teach you a tool in three months.
Any tool.
So I would much rather see your taste level
and the expression of mastery as an artist
or as a designer, an animator, whatever that may be.
I don't care what tools you know.
That being said, there are a couple of advantageous things
like common game engine, substance,
the main modeling packages.
Those are good to know.
I second that for sure.
The thing with that too is that you're looking at concepts, right?
You're looking at how does substance work and understanding that workflow
more so than which buttons you click.
Totally.
And I think that's the takeaway when it comes to the software packages
and understanding those workflows
and how they'll probably evolve over the next couple years in particular.
And frankly, all the different packages work together so well now anyway
that it's not an issue.
Yeah.
Yeah, I would definitely emphasize
not focusing so much on tools unless you are actually
trying to get into tool development in tech art.
But I keep stressing this with my artists
and that I train in my studio that the computer is just
a tool like a pencil or a pen.
So it's really the art history, all your skills,
all of your talent that's going to come through,
and the tools are just an avenue for that.
people really get focused on learning one particular program,
or I'm going to do this really high-res, amazing ZBrush model,
but if you can't translate that into something I can use in a game engine,
then it's just a pretty set piece.
It's not going to be something that we can actually move around
and work with a decent frame rate and a performance
that's going to actually make gameplay fun.
So, less tools, more talent.
That's a perfect segue to the next question.
Do you guys expect to see content in Engine now?
Like, you know, I know years ago it was like,
hey, here's my awesome ZBrush sculpt with,
you know, whatever, how many millions and billions of polygons.
Now, is that really still applicable?
You know, like what are your expectations when you see it?
I...
If I see like a...
I'm just so over seeing really nice sculpts,
to be honest with you.
Like, and I'm a sculptor, like I...
That's what I do.
But seeing a portfolio of like just really high detailed sculpts
and then it just stops there is the most useless thing for my team imaginable.
I'm not trying to be mean about it, but like...
There's so much more beyond that the sculpting is the easy fun part
Then you have to make the low poly you have to bake it properly
That's the light properly materials have to read well color theory all that stuff
And you don't have to I mean as much as I love unreal
You don't have to put it in unreal. You don't have to learn shader networks and stuff like that. You can use marmoset
There's a plenty of of great tools that make it easy to show something in content. How dare you sir?
I said I loved it though. I love you can use more besides fun, but
But yeah, just the game development goes beyond sculpts, and I know that it's fun
But yeah, you gotta you gotta go further sculpts still have a place obviously right like yeah
Where they used to be like the pinnacle of your piece? Yeah, like it's the dressing now. Yeah, it's like the fun part
It's kind of like concept art
You know 90% of that is sketching and then you have the nice beautifully rendered thing right and it's like everybody wants to do the nice
beautifully rendered
Thing but the reality is your job is actually making like a game model. It's like making something that the team works with it's not
You know getting front row on zebra central the the boring hard part is the job. Yeah. Yeah, it's the job
It's 90% of your day is the boring hard stuff
It's the UVs that you hate and it's the low poly and the optimization and making the LEDs and getting the materials right and all
That other stuff that's the job
It's nicer to see that stuff in Engine, yes.
Whether it's Marmoset or whether it's Unreal,
because that shows us that you've gone through the process,
that you've gone through the workflow,
and you understand how to translate the Materials
that you're trying to create into what the Engine
is actually going to show.
Okay, so the next one, this is pretty easy.
I think it's a constant question that we always face.
Everybody wants to know, should I specialize?
Should I be general? Should I try everything?
What do you guys think?
Yes.
I think the answer to this one is know your audience.
Who are you applying to?
Is it a large company?
You'll probably want to see specialization.
Is it a small indie startup?
They'll probably want to see a lot of jack of all trades.
I think the answer to this is know
who you are sending your stuff to and know
who you want to be as an artist.
Lisette made a perfect point talking about the animation stuff on South Park, because
those people that were applying with mocap reels might have had a chance if they had
customized their work for the job, but they didn't because they just kind of blindly sent
out stuff out there.
It's a perfect example.
Yeah, we always are looking for someone to fill a particular role, so specialization
is important in that way.
I got into the industry because I specialized in characters.
And then as I grew my career,
I started to learn VFX and environment
so I could be a lead.
But it was through that channel
that I was able to gain expertise
in how to use a game engine, how to get my art to work,
how to get, learn rigging.
And it sort of branched from there.
But so you're going to really most likely get in
because you're very good at one thing.
There are studios who look for generalists,
but as at like a.
I'm getting in the industry level,
that's a lot harder for you to fill that role.
I will also say we can all smell from a mile away
the student portfolio that is just full
of the various assignments to teach you
the various aspects of making stuff.
And it's so common, and please, please,
please don't make that mistake,
but it's like, here's the one gun we did in gun class.
You know, it's like stuff like that.
And you just smell it.
You just open the portfolio,
and you flip past the one mediocre character,
the one average gun.
you know, the poorly textured AK-47 from the thing,
you know, it's like, it just shows,
you're just going through the motions instead of-
And unfortunately, they're all kind of going out
at the same time.
They totally- Graduation rolls around
and you're seeing the same assignment
like from the same schools.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So I would highly recommend to make your own vision
of that stuff for yourself outside of the scope
of the class assignments,
because they never make for a good portfolio, ever.
So this is another really common question.
What format is appropriate?
If I'm an environment modeler, do I have a demo reel?
Is that the right way to?
How do you decide how you present your portfolio, I guess?
I'm staunchly against demo reels unless it's animation.
But a lot of it is because if you're trying to show a character and you have a 360 degree turnaround,
I have to wait for it to slowly pan around so I can see its back or something.
All of that can be accomplished in just one shot.
I can just look at one image and be like, okay, that's the full character. I don't need...
four minutes to see a thing turn around,
or I don't want to skip around and miss something
that you wanted me to see, but I'm impatient
because I am, I don't know.
And I skip past something that's vital
and could have been good, but you know.
And again, it goes back to presentations.
Show your best possible image, right?
And if it's based on a demo reel, I could miss it.
I think that surprises a lot of people because I hear a lot of professors and stuff in the
game programs constantly pushing the video reels and we all hate them.
But it's really common with people, they bring their characters with turnarounds and they
have big crazy spine-blazed, I'm going to get sick watching your fly-through video thing.
None of us want it.
So I couldn't agree more.
And they really enjoy your music choice too.
Yeah, I have to say I turn off the music most of the time.
Unless you're actually animating the dialogue
and I need to understand that you're hitting the points
and selling the personality.
So yeah, don't spend an entire week composing a song
because most likely I'm going to turn it off
so I can actually just focus on the content
that you're creating.
You don't get extra points for choosing Tom Waits instead of a techno song.
And I think for modelers,
images and stills are fine.
You don't have to do the 3D turnaround.
I do enjoy new techniques that they're using, like Sketchfab,
where you can upload a model and I can rotate it around and take a look at it.
It's pretty cool.
As long as it's not a billion polys and I have to wait ten minutes for it to load.
So you have to think about...
the art director on the other side.
Like I've got 20 portfolio reviews to go through
in an hour, maybe hour and a half
between all the meetings and the scheduling
and all the planning that I have to do.
So I wanna get in, get out, understand what you're about.
And then if I think you're talented,
I wanna call you back immediately.
I don't wanna have to wait five minutes for your model load.
I don't wanna have to wait 10 minutes for your video
because I just don't have that time.
So I'd like to add to that,
the being respectful of our time.
I think also goes back to the presentation,
a clean and quick presentation.
It's, again, can't say how much we appreciate,
like if we get a portfolio
and we can immediately be into the art
and see, like forget all the fluff, all the intro stuff,
you know, the 20 second, like card
at the beginning of the reel,
like we just wanna see the art
and you have more of a chance of us seeing your art
if you just get right to it.
So I guess the basic rule of thumb is if it moves,
it probably dictates a demo reel.
If it doesn't necessarily move, don't do it.
All right, so let's talk about rejection.
This is always the best part.
Sean.
We all look at Sean.
There we go, Sean.
It's there, it's up on the screen.
I got plenty of those.
So back in the day when I was trying to apply to video game studios, I got a lot of these
and I just kept updating my portfolio, sending it out, get rejection letters, repeat, repeat,
repeat.
And finally, it culminated with me getting two offer letters on the same day from Looking
Glass and another company called Reality Bites.
And at the time when I was doing this,
I was kind of bopping around.
I was freelance.
I was not necessarily in the games industry.
So I had a job, and then I was putting in the time at home
because I knew that the portfolio I had from school,
which was really illustration heavy,
was not going to cut it.
So I knew I had to put in extra work.
But I originally told this story back when,
the first year we did this panel,
to show that just because you do get rejected,
and even if you do get rejected multiple times,
it's not the end of the world.
It just means.
maybe you aren't good enough,
or maybe you're not the right candidate
for the job at the time.
Sometimes we look for very specific things
from a candidate, and especially in the art world,
very specific styles.
So you may be a fantastic artist,
but you may not be the style that we're looking for
for the particular project.
Yeah, I definitely think there's a great.
mindset that a game developer has to have.
I like to say 90% of the times we fail,
and then maybe 1% we do well,
and then 10% we're just kind of all right.
So getting in the habit of just failure
is kind of the default state.
You're going to try to get things in engine
and they're not going to work 90% of the time
until you figure out your pipeline.
And it's going to be the same thing
when you're trying to get in the industry.
You're going to just continue to get rejection
until you get the yes, but it's the yes that matters.
But if you let that first few no's discourage you, you're pretty much dead in the water.
And it's sort of that grit and mentality of just kind of persisting and pursuing your
interests and just keep pushing forward through those no's.
I've been in the industry for 16 years and I have a very stylized portfolio and I get
rejection letters to this day.
And it's just sort of, I'm not the right fit for every position and that's okay.
Sean loves that we show his rejection letter, by the way.
I wish you'd show the one of the studios that are no longer around.
Would you say...
Nice.
Would you say you found exciting employment?
They watched you a lot.
Oh yeah, is that what it says?
Alright, so what are some avenues that can help get somebody in the industry? So if your
portfolio isn't ready for Epic or for Ubisoft or whatever, what are some avenues that
people can pursue that exist now that may not have existed 15 years ago to help people
find their way in?
We can't talk a little bit about it.
I like to chime in on this because I do a significant amount of outreach outside of
the industry to bring more people in.
So one of the things I try to stress with new students is don't wait until you're looking
for a job to look for a job.
There are different ways to make connections in the industry.
There are a lot of game developers who are actually looking for mentees and want to help.
So you are better off building relationships with people in the industry,
and then when you're ready for a job you can say,
hey, by the way, I'm looking.
That way you're not just coming up with the give me a job,
give me money sort of stress,
because you may not be ready,
and it's a different relationship
than building a relationship with someone over time.
Yeah, it's great advice.
Also, you're not going to come at it with that sense of desperation.
You're going to come at it with a little bit more of a quiet, learning-style confidence.
For somebody on the hiring end, that's really appealing.
You can smell that confidence and that kind of satisfaction in your trajectory and that
you're trying and you're slowly growing.
You can just smell that.
Yeah, and you're giving someone on the other side an opportunity to get to know you, and
it's not just about gimme gimme.
And see you grow over time.
You know, that's, you start in that relationship early,
you may not be ready, but if you're showing your portfolio
and showing artwork and it's out there,
and we see that it's steadily getting better and better
and you're improving and you're putting in the hard work,
that's also helpful for us.
Yeah, I mean, if you just sit in, like, your room,
like, making art or whatever, and never show anybody,
no one's ever gonna know who you are, you know?
So if, you know, you make contacts, show your work often.
you know, plant the seeds for future jobs.
Yeah.
So that kind of also goes, like, I think freelance,
you kind of touched on that as well.
Yeah.
Like, and I think more companies are actually
going to individual freelance artists,
and then we are, as opposed to outsourcing houses,
and so we're partnering with individuals.
So I think that also is an avenue in,
going back to that.
what are some qualities that, you know,
since you were just talking about doing it extensively
and so were you, what are you looking for?
The individual artist definitely appeals to me more.
I mean, we've used outsourcing houses in the past.
The problem with outsourcing houses is that
you kind of have to be like, I want, you know,
I know who your good artists are,
and I know who your mediocre artists are,
and I know we're hiring the outsourcing house,
but I want this person and this person on the project,
not these people.
And as an outsourcing artist, you're always, you know,
having that.
conversation with like, I want this person, not this person, as opposed to if I just go
to an individual, I'm hiring that person because of their portfolio and I like their work and
I think they're strong, so I can deal directly with them.
But beyond their portfolio, like what is it you're looking for?
Well, first of all you want someone that's going to show up virtually, you know.
not in the office, but if they're working remotely,
that they're gonna put in the work.
And there's a lot of trust to be put in
if I'm hiring you and you're in a different country
or you're on a different coast than me.
So we need to know, mostly through communication
and just how the beginnings of the project go,
that you're gonna put in the work
and that you're going to take direction,
that you're gonna listen and communicate with us.
Things happen, as far as communication goes, it's great.
It's like, hey, I can't deliver this
because I'm down with the flu,
so I'm gonna be out for like three days.
Little things like that that let us know,
because these are people that are not in the office,
are great, like on top of like,
I hired this person because they have a great portfolio.
This is not at all a sexy answer,
but my experience is that people that are freelance,
especially the individual people,
need to be way more anal.
than normal.
Just that sense of always communicating,
always expressing the state of their work,
knowing, you know, asking when they don't have
the information rather than just sitting there
doing nothing, and then when they're delivering files,
they're delivered to a really, really high quality,
not just the asset, but also the source files,
the organizational structure, all of that stuff
matters a lot more when you're working,
you know, as an external partner.
So I definitely look for people who are anal.
Yeah, I'd say the mentality, especially when you're a freelancer, is that you are providing a service.
You're not just providing art, you're providing a service.
So what that means is that you're working with your client,
you're communicating very rapidly, you're turning things over very quickly,
you're listening to our feedback and responding to it,
you're not getting defensive when we tell you to change something.
Simply because there are factors that may lead to that request.
So just thinking of yourself as a brand and a service rather than just an individual artist.
I think that's probably one of the bigger problems I'm meeting a lot of freelance artists or contract artists or whatever.
Is that they don't realize that they're actually a company competing against the monoliths across the ocean or whatever, right?
So you're not just a person with...
your Wacom and you paint stuff and people give you money.
It's like you need to be professional,
need to be on top of your work,
your quality speaks for future work.
Like you, even if you're just one person,
you're still, you're a company.
Like you're up against bigger studios.
Yeah, I would say if you, especially,
I think attitude is a big one for me as well.
You know, I was touched on not being defensive,
but there's just a number of revisions
that we're gonna have to get to to get to good.
And if I'm
Constantly fighting the client just or constantly fighting with the artists to kind of get them to get to that point
It's just so much more work
To get there and it's I'm less likely to hire them on the next time because I'm just trying to get the game done. Yeah
So this is an interesting question. I think a lot of people that are probably here
Would like to at some point be an art director
What do you guys think is expected in an art director?
And of course, that'll change over the next several years,
I'm sure, but what do you guys think is expected
in that kind of portfolio?
And it's not something that at 35 or 40 years old,
you're like, hey, I'm going to be an art director.
It's something that you probably start planning for earlier.
So what do you guys think needs to be done there?
Again, this is one of those really subjective,
each studio is going to have a different answer.
You look at a smaller company like Campo Santo,
who used Ali Moss, who had never really done games before,
but he has such a striking style
that he kind of fit naturally into that.
Versus if we were looking for another art director,
I would be looking for someone
who has shipped a lot of games,
and that I'm actually looking at the end result of.
the titles and the experience that put together those titles
for a role because we're looking for more senior people.
So that's a difficult question, I think,
to answer, like what's the meaning of life, I don't know.
I know we want to get to questions, but just to chime in really quickly, art direction
is about why, it's not about pretty pictures.
And so as you start thinking more in your career about how to drive maybe to a place
where you're doing some direction or some leadership.
All that centers around the purpose of the art
and how does it serve the goals of the project.
And it's never about whether it's pretty.
Pretty is a outcome of doing a good job satisfying the why.
So if you can find a way to represent that in a portfolio,
that's an interesting problem.
It's probably a whole nother talk.
But that's fundamentally what direction is.
It's satisfying the master of the why.
It's not pretty pictures.
Yeah, I think there's a glorified view of what an art director is.
Most of the time you touch everything and own nothing.
Like you are constantly communicating to artists,
trying to get them to bring things up to a certain level of quality,
trying to get them to understand why you're asking for a change,
asking them to push forward what they would normally do to a different level.
So a lot of it is communication and a lot of it is people management skills.
So you're spending.
less and less time making art and more and more time communicating.
So we're down to our last slide and while we're on this if you guys want to get the questions sooner,
feel free to start lining up at the mics, but we're going to kind of toss this one around.
I think it's a nice one to end with.
What is your best applicant success story?
Like is there an unusual story you've got where somebody got hired that you know about
and how that worked and how it went down?
Do you want to add anything?
Sure. I keep remembering my first intern,
one of my first interns that I got on my project.
His name was Chris Emerson.
I hired him because he was one of the few candidates
who applied who had a really strong art portfolio
and technical skills.
So, he came on board, and he was able to write quickly,
create test levels with shaders
so we could test our characters
that we were getting from outsourcing.
He would say, hey, by the way, I just wrote this tool.
I didn't even ask him to do that.
So for me, it was having someone who came
with a little technical ability and just a lot of drive,
and seeing him grow very rapidly
from being just an intern to being hired,
and now he's at Sony and doing extremely well.
I think it was his attitude and his mindset
and his skillset, and I'm really happy
I was able to bring him in and give him that chance.
Cool.
Early on, on Bioshock Infinite,
the first animator I hired.
His name was Matt Boehm and I believe he was a shoe salesman.
He'd been cranking on his portfolio and he's working at Payless Shoes and he'd gone through
the animation mentor program.
Now he works over at Blizzard and he just did a talk on first person animations in Overwatch.
Awesome.
Not bad for a shoe salesman.
Let's get to some questions. We've got people lined up. Let's start over here.
So you guys were talking a little bit about VR earlier. I'm a VR developer and one of the
things I'm struggling with is finding a way to effectively show that.
without just relying upon the first person's perspective?
Do you have any advice on how to shoot?
Yeah, it's really hard.
We struggle with that, too, when we're thinking about
how do we take marketing shots for this stuff?
How do we do it?
And honestly, what we ended up doing
was composing some shots using a really wide FOV
and just trying to be representative
of what the player would see
without having this really distorted, foveated, you know.
View of what's going on that could induce nausea and was compressed and all the other things that can happen if you're not careful
So we ended up honestly faking it
But we were trying to do service to the and elicit the same mood
So if you look at the marketing stuff that we did for the game, we're using all the same assets the same animations and stuff
We're just presenting it in a kind of manufactured way to elicit that same feeling that you would get if you were actually in the headset
It's an unsolved problem. I don't have a perfect answer for you
Thank you.
Awesome.
Let's go over here.
Hi.
Firstly, I want to thank you guys for all the advice you've done so far.
I really appreciate it.
I've gotten a lot of inconsistent feedback from art professors and video game professors
about including fan art in your portfolio.
What is your guys' opinion on doing so?
From our perspective, we had a few artists showing fan art from Black Shock.
It doesn't hurt, but it can't be your entire portfolio.
Like, it's fine if there's like a piece in there
that it's nice to see like, oh, this person is a fan.
Have they done something different?
Or is it just like a straight up copy of a screenshot?
So if it's in there, it still has to say something new.
And so it'd be, you know, something that you've expressed
and something unique.
There's nothing wrong with doing fan art, but.
if you're applying to a company doing fan art of the game that they worked on,
I mean, you have to realize that people have been staring at this thing for five years,
so you're getting a way more critical look at something,
so unless it's the best fan art humanly possible,
it might get a little risky.
I think it's always good, like you said, to do an adaptation of it,
like do something where you evolve it, because then you get out of that,
but you're still paying some homage to something you like.
You are opening up yourself to a certain level of scrutiny if you are applying with fan art.
Yeah.
So that is the double-edged sword.
Thank you.
No problem.
Okay, let's go over here.
Hi, well just real quick. I really enjoy you being by the way.
Glad to hear it.
But, so I was curious about expanding upon
what is the relationship between the freelancer
and the studio itself and is the pipeline
between the studio and the freelancer
faster than having in-studio people?
For us, a lot of the freelancers that we have,
like we have a few modelers that we have off-site.
Basically we ship them a computer that has the entire IT set up so that Perforce is on it, the
entire build is on it. They can VPN in and sync to the build. So we give them something that's
ready to go and that they're delivering their assets directly into the engine and that's where
we're going to look at them. They're not emailing us or FTP stuff. Depending on the time zone
that they're in, this could be something that comes in overnight so it's just ready for us to
look at in the morning.
For people that aren't as integrated,
we have a few artists that aren't hyper-integrated
into the system like that, or like concept artists.
Generally that would be FTP or email exchange.
But it really depends on how tight you want that to be.
And for the modelers, we really just wanted to see
the stuff right in engine so we could critique it in context.
in the levels that we want it to be in,
and it's a much quicker turnaround.
So with IP confidentiality,
does, do you ever run into any issues with that?
Not yet.
Lawyers have good NDAs, and then we make people sign them.
Yeah.
It would probably, I don't think an illustrator,
or an illustrator, like a freelance artist.
would make that mistake, because I don't...
It probably wouldn't work in the industry again,
because that's really...
Like, the companies...
You know...
If you're going to betray that trust,
then I don't think there's going to be somebody else
who would want to hire you.
Well, not from a betray trust standpoint,
but whenever you're in a studio,
I'm just curious, do you have people who are there,
who keep your servers secure,
while freelancers don't necessarily have that?
Yeah.
Well, I think it depends on the studio.
Like, certain studios, the larger ones
are gonna have certain security requirements from you
and you need to meet those security requirements.
Whether that's having your laptop encrypted
so that if it does get stolen,
you know our artwork isn't exposed.
So I think it depends on the client
and their level of security.
I mean, there are some studios
that are a bit more transparent
in their process than others.
Okay, thank you.
Good.
So I've been working as an art director for the last six months and since I've been working that way,
my portfolio has really suffered because I've been working with other people
and I'm curious how do I get my portfolio up to speed and can I show what I've learned about collaboration
and all those other things working as an art director and how to help my portfolio.
This kind of goes to the AD question.
Yeah, I mean, that's a difficult one because what...
I think the question is, like, what are you trying to show?
Like, what do you want to do with your portfolio?
Like, you know, do you want to go and be a modeler?
So, for example, for me, I want to be a texture artist.
Like, that's...
So, I mean, yeah, I think being an art director
is not really a direct application of...
being a texture artist, to me, my immediate response,
having thought of it for two seconds,
we kind of have to put in the work
outside of what you're doing as an art director
and building up your portfolio in the time that you have
that when you're not at work.
I mean, that's not an easy answer, but.
Yeah, going back to my
you touch everything and own nothing statement.
I think part of being an art director
is selling the vision of what you're making.
So if you can find specific examples of how you directed something, that would help.
But you're also going to have to do some key pieces on the side.
Especially if you're thinking about maybe focusing a little bit more on a different area,
then that's the area you should be spending your free time working on things.
So it is that challenge.
It is you touch everything and own nothing, and you may say...
I drove the vision for this entire scene,
but everyone else did the work.
So it's a different conversation,
and it's a different way of selling your skills.
How would you put that into a portfolio?
Like if I'm, can I show other people's work
and then just have...
Credit them.
You definitely want to credit the people who did the work.
In my portfolio, I give examples
of how I push things to quality,
whether that's me showing paint overs
of what I did to improve textures
and the kind of feedback I gave people.
like giving examples of the process of art direction
may also help.
You could also, if you're looking to do a texture art
kind of path, like doing materials and stuff like that,
you could also do material treatments
for environment art direction, right?
So if there's an environment,
and you're like, this is all the materials that I designed,
you're kind of doing both in that way,
you know what I mean?
So you're kind of becoming more of a tech art director
versus like, you know.
vision and politicking and stuff like that.
Whatever it is you guys do.
Cool, thanks guys.
For animation portfolios,
besides character performance as you mentioned,
do you expect to see animation in the game engine?
Or something like that?
So for animation, do you guys expect to see animation in the game engine, correct?
It certainly helps because ultimately that's the end product that the audience is going to see.
And again, it's not 100% necessary, but if you're selling like,
oh, here are my combat animations that I did, it's okay to see some, like maybe some Maya
Play Glass, but ultimately we want to see how it translates in the game.
It also shows that.
you're aware of the entire process, the entire workflow.
I mean, sometimes seeing a Maya Play Blast
is the equivalent of a sculpture or a ZBrush sculpt
that hasn't been taken through all the hard process of UV
mapping.
And so you want to see that the hard work has been done
and that you understand the limitations that
get imposed on your animations when you
have to put them into games.
Yeah, I want to see how you break up animation,
simply because it's great to have a strong portfolio,
but there's the other side of we may need animations
broken up in a different way to get them to work
with our animation system.
So I want to see that you can go from run cycle
to jumping over a fence to blending between animations
that are needed to a combat scene,
and maybe just showing that strung together in an engine.
and then calling out the separate animations as they happen,
will show me that you know how to kind of set up animations
so that they work within an animation system.
Thank you.
Good. Hello.
Okay, so I am a 3D generalist.
I do, I like doing a bunch of ...
I like doing a bunch of this stuff and I would actually prefer to work at a smaller indie studio.
So my question is, would you suggest I continue doing everything to make the best generalist portfolio I can?
Or find something specialized, then get into AAA, and then go down to something where I can do everything?
What would your suggestions be?
It's kind of a hard one. I mean, the chance that you're taking a risk because chances are you're not equally strong in all of those areas.
Just from the lack of having put in the 10,000 hours it takes in any of those given disciplines to achieve that mastery.
So you're taking a bit of a gamble.
not narrowing in a little bit, maybe just if you have 10 interests, narrow it down to three and try to represent those well
or something, that can still express that you have generalist capabilities without
having that kitchen sink syndrome of the one gun, the one character, the one environment, the three props,
the one terrible UI. We see the same stuff over and over again, right? It's all the same story.
So everyone on this stage probably would have a different answer, but I kind of...
If it were me, I would narrow the scope just a little
to the things you really love so that you can try
to express your mastery in a couple of fewer areas.
And then just in the hiring process,
expressed, hey, I want to be a generalist.
If you really want to be a generalist,
maybe it's about narrowing the scope of execution.
So if you're going to do, for example, a game demo or a level
with a character running around with animation systems
in a level that's very well lit and textured,
and possibly.
showing the effects, if that's what you want to show,
but you're going to have to make sure that one scene is very well executed.
So no pressure there, but instead of trying to do
everything in separate pieces, maybe showing them together in context
or telling a story and conveying an emotion.
People rarely pull that off.
Yeah, they do. It's very hard.
They're the reason why they're game teams,
not game persons.
Thank you
Hi, I'm currently going with through excuse me. I'm currently going through what Sean's going through right now. I don't like you my voice
I'm an editorial illustrator. I've been working in editorial illustration for a little while and I'm moving
into concept art, particularly 2D.
And I wanted to ask if you had any tips
for easing that transition,
basically translating the skills
of generating concepts, et cetera,
all that stuff that comes with that.
I mean, editorial illustration's a very specific thing.
Back when I was in school,
it was always little men doing stuff,
little men holding up dollar bills.
Brad Holland was like the king.
Did you go to school in the 1920s?
Yeah.
Lab coat.
I mean, there's a set of skills like being
able to render a person, understanding color theory,
understanding how to do a composition.
Like all those things apply across the board,
whether you're doing concept art or editorial.
Concept art is really about getting ideas out quickly
that serve the project that you're working on.
and telling a story within that project.
So I mean, you could argue that editorial's
also telling a story, but the compositions
are much more, I don't wanna say highbrow.
I'm losing the word.
I would say fixed?
Yeah, it's not as dynamic.
In concept art, you're definitely
gonna have to work quicker.
You're gonna have to be less in love
with each drawing that you do and be willing.
to do 10 drawings, throw them away,
to get to that one idea that you want to pitch
and you think is going to be right for the moment.
Concept art is not pretty pictures.
It's all about ideas.
It's just ideas.
It's in the job description, conceptualization.
It has nothing to do with how pretty it is at all.
Maybe I can help you answer the questions
by telling you what we use concept artists for.
Okay.
We use concept artists to, one,
At the beginning of a project, set the visual bar of what we think the vision of the game will be.
So, what is the story of this space?
What is the personality of this character?
How does this fit within this world and story?
And then during production, we regularly use concept art as a language between
the art team and the design team to kind of get them on the page of where we're going.
So, for example, we'll use concept art to kind of envision what a combat attack or a combat sequence may look like.
So that the artists and the animators know what we're going for and the visual effects artists know what we're trying to achieve.
And then we can then take that concept art, give it to those artists and then they can get a vision for the final.
goal is. So when you think about concept art, it's not, as you said, pretty pictures.
It's solidifying and bringing a team unified around an idea and a concept.
Guys, we're out of time, but thank you all for coming. If you guys still have questions,
I'm sure we can, we'll be around. We're also doing the portfolio review, so, but thanks again for
coming. Please be sure to fill out your reviews so we come back and do this again next year, and
good luck with everything.