Hello everyone, my name is Tori Schaefer and I will be talking to you about my experience
representing LGBT plus characters in games.
So first of all, let's talk about who I am.
I am a writer and narrative designer. I currently work for Spellbreak, a PvP fantasy game which is currently in beta.
In the past, I worked for Elder Scrolls Online, an MMO RPG set in the Elder Scrolls universe,
and a game called Backbone, which was an indie noir detective narrative set in a dystopian future.
I also wrote for the quest, Manor of Mass for Elder Scrolls Online, which included a
character named Alchemy, who was Elder Scrolls' first openly transgender woman, and that quest
ended up winning a GLAAD award for Outstanding Video Game in 2019.
GLAAD is the Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation and works to create respect to help
endorse respectful representation of the LGBT plus community in media. And this is my content
information. You can see my website, my Twitter, and my email. Feel free to contact me if you have
any further questions or comments about this presentation.
So, how can we ensure respectful LGBT representation in games?
So, we're going to talk about what is LGBT representation, what does good representation
look like. I'll use examples of my own work to show how I respectfully represented the
LGBT community, and I'll give you some tips and tricks to help you create LGBT representation
in your own games.
So first of all, what is LGBT plus representation?
So it's characters in medias who have a minority sexuality
and or gender.
So lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender,
but also asexual, demisexual, non-binary characters.
Any character who is not straight and or cisgendered.
It has a very troubled history, obviously.
I think that's something that's well known.
There's been a lack of representation in media.
There's been stereotypes, harmful tropes, and because of this kind of lack of representation
and negative representation, the LGBT plus community can be very sensitive to how they
are represented, which is why we need to work as game developers and anybody who creates
media to make sure that their representation that we are putting out there is respectful
to the community, more so than, you know, people who are not LGBT plus, characters who
are not LGBT plus.
And we need to ensure that we are understanding and cognizant of those issues
and of that history when we are creating these characters.
So, you know.
What does respectful LGBT plus representation look like?
Going to be giving you some pillars of good representation
that would also apply to other marginalized groups,
if that's something that, you know, you're interested in as well.
So, realistic. Is this portrayal accurate? It's a portrayal that avoids stereotypes and
makes sure that the character isn't defined by their sexuality or gender.
And this is helped by research, making sure that game developers who are working on this content
are as diverse as possible, and also consuming community-approved LGBT plus media,
things that have had a positive response from the LGBT plus community,
and making sure that you understand kind of the types of identities that you're representing.
Is this considerate? Is the narrative considerate of past and current LGBT plus issues?
making sure that characters are not inherently bad because of their sexuality or gender.
The narrative should not punish a character because of their identity,
even if the society that character is a part of does. It's very two different, very different
things. How you represent that person, how you present them in the game can really define if
something is considered or not.
And obviously, once again, mindful of the LGBT plus community
in the past representation, making sure that your narrative
is sympathetic to these characters.
So question, how is the narrative treating this character?
What's the message the narrative is giving to the player
about this character and their identity?
Being mindful of all that.
Explicit, our characters explicitly stated to be LGBT plus.
Do they openly say like, you know, their identity or openly talk about their identities experiences?
But you have to be mindful of doing this without the characters consent having other characters reveal
a character's identity can be, you know, it's just something that you want to avoid both in
games and real life, making sure that you have the consent of that individual, that their identity
can be openly talked about or shown. And just the best way to do that is to make sure the
character is the one telling the player who they are and what their identity is.
Respectful. Is the character's identity respected by the narrative?
Making sure that that LGBT identity is never the butt of a joke. You can have these characters be funny.
You can have these characters make jokes,
but not in a stereotypical,
harmful way.
you have to be respectful of the LGBT plus community and kind of their experiences and making sure that you're not relying on you know,
those harmful things
and being respectful to the community as well on social media, making sure that
on social media your studio, your developers are not making harmful, you know,
jokes or comments about the LGBT plus community
and just being mindful of how that community,
the LGBT plus community,
reacts to your characters and interprets your characters in your stories. If somebody has a head canon that a character
identifies a certain way or two characters have a certain kind of relationship,
making sure that you respect that because that is how that
player is deciding to consume your content so that they are represented.
Making sure that you never feel like they're wrong for doing so or that they're lesser for doing so I suppose so just being
Cognizant of your community and how they consume media and how you treat them on social media and events and things like that
So I'll be talking about my first example is Elder Scrolls Online. I'll be talking about two examples here.
So my first example is a quest in the
Elder Scrolls Online Summerset expansion or chapter
which is an MMORPG set in the Elder Scrolls universe, a high fantasy setting that explores various themes.
From the very get-go in Elder Scrolls Online, it was decided that LGBT plus characters were a part of that universe
And they were just accepted by their society
as to not
alienate LGBT plus players who may be playing Elder Scrolls Online
And also just because we wanted representation to be you know able to put in the game very easily
I think and a lot of characters to identify as that without
worrying about societal repercussions
So there's a variety of LGBT plus characters in Elder Scrolls Online,
but mostly it's gay representation, lesbian, bisexual characters,
things of that nature, which is why I was really excited
when I got the opportunity to work on the quest involving the character
Alchemy, who is the first openly transgender woman in Elder Scrolls.
She is respected by her society, she's respected by the narrative, as I'll get into a little bit.
And she's in the quest Manor of Masks for Elder Scrolls Online Summerset, as I've said.
She does have some predecessors who are non-binary, the god Vivec, the Daedric Princess,
but we wanted to make sure that her character reflected a transgender woman's experience,
and that was how she openly identified as.
So, the manner of Mass Quest, this is just a short description, but Renaid, who is shown
on screen right here, Renaid has asked me to find her brother Liridel and stop him from
joining the House of Reveries.
I must audition as well in order to figure out who he is.
So this is a...
high elf. She's a high elf who is looking for her brother. And she says, Oh, no, my brother's trying
to join an acting troupe. And I want him to be a mage like I am. You have to figure out who he is,
because everybody in this acting troupe wears masks on their face. So she says, you should
audition as well. See who my brother is find out whoever there is so I can talk him out of this
nonsense. And surprise, surprise. Laredel now identifies as alchemy and is a woman.
And that's how you kind of learn through the quest narrative that alchemy is transgender because you're introduced
to this character as
Mernide's brother, Laredel.
And then you learn about this character, Alchemy, and eventually it's revealed that she used to identify as Laredel and she used to identify
as a man and she now identifies as Alchemy in a woman.
So, just kind of going through this quest and kind of seeing if it's, if it's respectful,
you know, is this realistic? Is this a realistic representation of a transgender woman?
So first we made sure that Alchemy was a fully fleshed out character with her own hopes and dreams.
She does feel that she must keep her identity a secret from her sister,
but hopes for her sister's acceptance. Now this is because she's an actress when her sister wants her
to be a mage, but yes it is supposed to reflect the fact that she is a transgender woman.
That she wants her sister's acceptance as that identity as well
She felt uncomfortable in her old identity identity and now feels happy with her new one and more ways than just her gender
you know, she was
Also very unhappy as a major scholar
But we know we wanted that to reflect her kind of change over to
um her new identity as a woman as alchemy
Uh, and she's connected to and supported by other transgender characters off screen
She talks about those experiences and how those people have helped her kind of um, you know
Embrace and really love her new identity
But we never show those characters in the class just because of time constraints and character constraints and things like that
Is this considerate
So we made sure that alchemy was an ally to the hero and accepted by her sister
We wanted to keep it very positive for this kind of first for way for a
This first time representing a transgender woman in elder scrolls
You know online in elder scrolls period
We make sure that the player never reveals alchemy's identity without her explicit consent
The player does advise alchemy if she wants to talk to her sister or not, but the player never
says her identity or tells other people about her identity.
It's all alchemy doing that.
And Somerset, her society, you know, her homeland of the high elves, Somerset,
accepts her identity and doesn't really care that she's transgender,
which is, again, going with that overall theme of LGBT plus characters
being accepted by the society or their societies and elder scrolls.
Um, is this explicit? Alchemy openly admits that she is transgender. She talks about her past identity and her current identity.
She discusses other transgender high elves in Summerset that she's met and she talks about their experiences as well in um,
dialogue after the quest.
And she speculates that there are many such individuals all over Tamriel. Um, this was something we wanted to write into the quest because
we wanted to make sure that players who are transgender, whatever race they decide to play, if they were an orc,
or a nord, or a dark elf, that yeah, you exist too in the world. It's just not high elves,
you know, it's everybody. Every race has kind of this,
these individuals.
And she talks about that, and we just wanted to make sure that players felt comfortable role-playing
as their own characters, you know, as a transgender identity.
So.
Is this respectful?
Alchemy's identity is never spoken in a joking or harmful or mean-spirited way
You know, she's referred to as a woman as she is
um
the player never is able to make harmful comments because we didn't want to like
Upset LGBT plus players who may be playing as that character for that option to even exist
Just make sure it's very respectful all the way through
She's featured a number of marketing materials for Somerset, but she was also included in our International Woman's Day post last year
Which a lot of players were really really happy about that
We included her in this community picture just a small little token meant so much to so many people
again, making sure that social media is also respectful and representing LGBT plus community
is very important in games as well.
Nothing's perfect. We did have representation concerns. I think you're always going to have
concerns about the content you produce in the media and the representation you produce,
you know, in any media.
Stereotypes. Yeah, it's a stereotype that LGBT plus people are actors.
That's truth.
It's that I don't think it's particularly harmful stereotype,
but it is something that a lot of media does or talks about and things like that.
And now it's just something that we decided that she fit in.
Well, this was we created the
the acting troupe and the lore of the acting troupe before we introduced Alchemy,
so this was just something that we felt she fit in too well,
but we had to be cognizant that this was a stereotype.
Her appearance alchemy wears a mask
Everybody in the manor of masks or sorry everybody in the house of reveries, which is her acting troop wears a mask
They talk about it all the time. They talk about why they do that
But you know, we have a trans character who is wearing a mask and is never really shown her face again
This was part of the lore before we introduced alchemy
But we were cognizant that that may have been something that was you know
something that we wouldn't have wanted to do but
it did fit into the lore in the game.
You know, and that's just something that we had to kind of be cognizant of.
But unfortunately, you know, we did have a character whose face was was covered.
The resolution, the ending resolution is very quickly handled.
We wanted to show that Renai accepted alchemy and loved her still
and just have a very positive experience.
But yeah, it happens very quickly because that's kind of the quest
is only so long and the narrative is only so long.
So we wanted to make sure that the resolution kind of came together in a very positive way
We're aware, you know of these issues
um
But you know, sometimes the gameplay just kind of you can't have perfect representation the way that you really want it to be
Uh, and she's the one and only uh the point of this quest alchemy was the only transgender woman in the game
Which creates much higher stakes is less realistic portrayals of the many facets of transgender people the more representation you have
The more rounded your representation is because you can show different sides of that identity different facets of it. Um
But yeah, definitely, you know wanting to include alchemy in this content and then build on her representation, which i'll talk about
in just a little bit
So as you can see, fan reaction was super positive, super great.
I was really happy with how the community accepted this quest and just loved this quest.
You can see these comments that I'm including here.
Just like super excited.
I've had fans come up to me and be like, oh at the end of the quest when they hug I cried
because it meant so much to me.
So just, you know, it's a quest that means a lot to me, a character that means a lot
to me because of how...
Much it means to other people which is what representation is really all about
Representing these the LGBT plus community is for the LGBT plus community first and foremost that they feel respectfully represented
And they're and they're gonna be excited and happy to be represented
Here's some fan art just wanted to include this I really like these uh, these pieces and how they came out
Alchemy and then we won a GLAAD award in 2019, which I was I'm super honored that we were able to win this
Um, and they just kind of really caught on that the story
Reflects the reality of transgender people today, even though it doesn't explicitly talk about
Like, you know, we're not doesn't you know
We're not accepts her sister for who she is, you know accepts alchemy, but you know, we we use that kind of
narrative about being a mage and a scholar to kind of show that without explicitly showing that I suppose you could say
So yeah, and then building on representation.
I Merck Meyer was a DLC came right after this.
It's about our guardians, the lizard people and Elder Scrolls,
and their Lord just has that they can change gender,
that they are able to do that with the help of their tree gods.
And in that society, they are going into really all about change,
accepting change.
So I was able to create.
Well, I concepted and wrote for a quest, a small quest where there was a transgender man and a transgender woman character.
And then I also wrote a book called The Grand Transformation, just talking about how society celebrates this and celebrates when Argonians, when one of their members of their tribe changes their gender.
So, the next example I'm going to talk about is a character in Backbone. Now Backbone is a noir
narrative game about a raccoon detective living in dystopian Vancouver. It has very heavy themes
of racism, misogyny, and yes, homophobia. It's a society that is heavily homophobic,
and most of the LGBT community, the LGBT plus community is heavily closeted for their own
protection. And those who aren't are rejected, you know, they might.
be sent to jail, rehabilitation camps.
It's heavily influenced by homophobia in America and Russia.
And, you know, this created a new challenge for me.
How do I create respect representation in a very disrespectful game world
with a very disrespectful and homophobic society?
So, you know, thinking about that, I concepted and created the character Sofia.
So Sofia, who is not pictured here.
These are two main characters, but when I concepted this character and created, she did not have any art associated with her
So i'll just be talking about her today and kind of how I created her character and how I I?
Concepted her to be a respectful presentation, even though she herself is disrespected by her society
Uh, so sofia is a lesbian npc who has been rejected by her society and her family and forced into homelessness
um
So, just thinking about my four pillars, is this realistic?
Unfortunately, yes.
Sophia has a developed personality and opinions, we made sure that she was a fully fleshed out character,
but her lack of status as a homeless individual allows her to speak openly about her sexuality to the player character.
And unfortunately, homelessness is just a common issue within LGBT community, especially youth,
especially teenagers or young adults because of being rejected by their families.
Sophia does reflect this. So yeah, trying to make her as realistic and fleshed out as possible.
Is this considerate?
I made sure that Cynthia was a sympathetic character and a victim of her society,
not of the narrative that her society was the one who rejected her and didn't accept her.
And I wanted to allow a member of the LGBT plus community to speak about society's discrimination
against them. I didn't want you know, I didn't want to make sure that I'm sorry, I didn't want
her mother to talk about her experiences or her friend or somebody else, but for Sophia to be able
to talk about her experiences herself.
to give a voice to that community.
Is this explicit?
I mean, Sophia does openly state that she was in a relationship with another woman.
And she shares that story with a brutal honesty
to the player character,
wanting to make sure that the player understood what
her identity was and how society did not accept that.
Is this respectful? Um, the player character does not make any assumptions about Sophia or judge her
Maybe the person playing the game does but we did not want the player character to do so
You know the play creature just ask questions allow Sophie to give her own thoughts in her own opinion
And we also researched and tried to avoid lesbian tropes in media,
such as like a lipstick lesbian, dead lesbian syndrome, these are common tropes.
Trying to avoid those to make her not a stereotypical character.
Or a stereotyped character, I should say.
Of course, we had concerns, you know.
She has a tragic backstory.
Her backstory in her current life, very dispiriting.
But this is a result of her society, not so much that the narrative, you know, is punishing her for her identity,
but that her society has punished her for her identity.
She's a mouthpiece. She's acts as a voice for her entire community
And as we know different perspectives lead to more rounded narratives. This was just unfortunately because of limited characters limited time
It's a short game and you know, this was kind of a character that I was a little concept out
Who was able to talk about her experiences because of her position in society, you know
if she was just walking down the street or if she was you know, I
in a crowded bar, she wouldn't talk about these experiences, but because of
you know, where she was at the time and what her
status was, she was able to tell the player character, like, yeah, this is what happened to me
and this is who I am.
One and only she's the only openly NPC we meet
again short narrative closeted society
We wanted to make sure that we had this representation
But it would you know, it's always nice to have more of a presentation and a more rounded LGBT plus, you know
representation to show your audience and your players and to talk about and to having your story
So yeah, so just two very different experiences for me
and experiences to write about and to research and to give,
but always making sure that no matter how the game world
sees the character, that I as a creator
and the narrative that I help create
is respectful to those characters.
And that's all about those four pillars.
you know, being respectful, being considerate, being realistic, being explicit.
You can do those things and make sure that those are elements
that your narrative has, no matter how your story kind of sees this character
or your your society of that world sees the character.
So just some tips. How can we ensure that our games have respectful LGBT representation?
Research, research, research.
Making sure that you understand these identities, you understand their history,
you understand kind of where these characters are coming from.
Hiring for diversity, and making sure that your studio welcomes that diversity.
If you have LGBT plus people in your studio or in your creative team,
they are able to give a much more...
like a better insight into that community and to that representation.
Studio initiatives to create that diverse representation being,
you know, leads need to be the ones to say, hey, guys, let's make sure
that we're creating a diverse cast, a diverse story and supporting designers
who want to create that representation, giving them the time to research,
giving them the resources needed, making sure that you're positive
about that initiative of creating those characters can go a long way.
As I said, your social media presence needs to be LGBT plus positive as well,
making sure that you are not saying anything rude or degrading and keeping that LGBT plus positive
representation going throughout all of your studio initiatives, marketing, things like that.
And consulting the experts. I talked, you know, about diversity readers, but
And there are a lot of individuals who you can hire on as a diversity reader to play your game and to play through the narrative to give you, you know, notes about the representation that you are presenting.
Another group you can talk to is GLAAD.
They are a media group.
They are there for consultation and to give you advice about your game.
Gamer X, the group that talks about a lot of game like.
gamer perspectives, but they are another resource that you can reach out to.
This website, Queerly Represent Me, has great examples of video game representation,
a lot of information that you can read through, just another resource that I found very helpful
in my own research.
Yeah, so just the takeaways I want to kind of say here is that LGBT plus characters and narratives deserve a place in games
They deserve to be represented
And representation does not need to be perfect to be respectful
You know
you're gonna have hitches within your gameplay within your narratives and you're just going to have to try to use as
Much, you know as much of those pillars as you can to ensure that even though there might be you know, some
Issues that overall you are giving a respectful, you know
Story for this character to be to be a part of a respectful role
And fans will respond positively to respectful representation
I know it can be scary because when you get it wrong, the LGBT plus community is very upset
But you've got to you know
Know that when you really try to put yourself out there and create that diverse representation you will get
a lot of, you know, excitement and tears, honestly. And it's just very important for
the community to be represented and to be shown in media and video games is included in that.
Great. So let's work together to ensure that every game has respectful LGBT plus representation.
Like I said, you can contact me if you have any more questions or comments.
I have my website up here, my Twitter, my email.
Feel free to reach out.
I'll answer as best I can.
And thank you so much for sitting through this presentation and hearing what I had to
say.
I hope you have a good evening, afternoon.
Thank you.