Hello, GDC.
Yeah, we can get a little crazy.
It's the end of the day.
Let's hear some applause for these panelists right now.
Welcome, this is the state and future of tabletop games.
If you're not in the right spot, this is your moment to walk awkwardly out of the room while we all watch.
Everybody's in the right spot? That's good to know.
This is going to be a discussion, it's going to be an open discussion.
I've got some amazing panelists here, and I'm going to introduce them here in just a moment.
But before we start, I want to introduce myself. My name is Noxweiler Berff.
I am the creative director and general manager at Hunters Entertainment.
I'm honored to be here, and I'm just as interested to hear how this panel goes as all of you.
I'm really excited by the people that are up here, and we're going to go a little bit more into that in just a minute.
But before we start, they've asked me here at GDC to make sure that you know a few things.
First of all, the silence is for your phone, not for you.
We definitely want to make sure that all your devices are turned off, out of respect.
We're not getting rings and interruptions in the middle of this engaging conversation we're about to have.
The other thing, though, is that feel free to interact. You just applauded. You can do more.
Great. Let's keep the energy high and let's have a good time.
Without further ado, I'd like to introduce you to your panel today.
We have some amazing guest speakers up here.
Elizabeth Sampat, would you like to introduce yourself?
Sure. Hi, my name is Elizabeth Sampat.
Mostly, I've been working in digital games, a lot of mobile games.
I've worked on Subway Surfers, Plants vs. Zombies 2, Hungry Shark World,
but what a lot of people don't know is I actually got my start in indie role-playing games
back in like 2006, 2007.
I also made an independent game called Deadbolt that was an IndieCade nominee,
I think back in 2013, and I'm just really excited to be up here.
Thank you so much.
Carol Mertz, you're next.
What do you want to say about yourself?
Hi, I'm Carol Mertz.
I am a senior game designer at Exploding Kittens,
which is a mass market board game publisher.
And I work on design and development
of those mass market games.
So I worked on Hand to Hand Wombat,
which had an accessibility post-mortem earlier today,
you may have seen,
as well as Exploding Kittens Recipes for Disaster,
Exploding Kittens Two-Player,
and many, many more that are coming out later this year.
So I also, before I was in board games, I worked on a lot of indie games.
Some of you may have played Hell Couch at a previous GDC,
and other various indie video games and things.
But yeah, that's me.
Thanks for being here.
Thank you.
Ming Liu, would you like to talk a little bit about yourself and what you do?
Hi, everybody. My name is Ming Liu.
I now work for 90s Soundfire UX as a Senior UX Research Manager.
I'm a big fan of tape top games and Half-Rich.
experience. This time I attend to this round table. I'm really happy I have this chance to
talk with everybody about the tabletop game. We're really excited to have you. Thanks for being here.
Last but certainly not least, we have Cole Worley. Would you like to talk a little bit about
yourself and what you do? Hi, my name is Cole. Hello. My name is Cole. I'm the creative director
at Leader Games, co-founder of Worley Games. I designed Root and Oath and Pax Premier and the
upcoming game ARX.
And I do a lot of work helping to organize the studio as well.
We're a small studio based in St. Paul, Minnesota.
But we have about 15 people and we are dedicated to making our weird games.
Amazing. Thank you again for being here.
So we've got a number of great panelists here. We're going to get right into it.
We're going to have a conversation.
I've prepared a few questions just to get us started, but then we're going to want to open it up to all of you.
So when the time comes, if you have questions, we're going to ask that you very orderly,
in a way that you can understand each other, you're going to break up here onto either side.
There is a microphone here and a microphone on this side.
But only when I give you the word that we're going to actually break off into audience questions,
I'd say don't start lining up right away.
You're going to be standing there for a little while.
All right, well, let's jump right into it and let's talk about this and find out exactly how these panelists feel about where we're at now with tabletop games in the year 2023.
The first question that I have is a pretty straightforward basic question that's going to give us a bit of an overview of what we're talking about today.
What is the most important innovation in the tabletop space at this time?
I'm going to start with Carol. Carol, do you want to speak a little bit on that?
This is the simple question.
I honestly, what I'm seeing right now is a lot of publishers really pushing toward ecological sustainability.
I think this is also, you know, when we get into the future, this is going to be shocking also what I talk about there.
But we're seeing a lot of publishers getting really excited about looking for ways that we can go to production and use...
recycled materials, think about ways that we can cut down on
components and, you know, space in shipping containers, things like that.
It's really interesting to see. And then we've got like the Green Games Alliance,
which I don't know if any y'all have heard of this, but they just released this amazing paper
specifically covering this and specifically on how
publishers and designers can be taking this into greater consideration. So yes, that's
To me, I think, is the number one biggest innovation and most important innovation that we're seeing right now.
It uses a lot of paper. It's no joke what we do in our industry and creating so much waste.
And there are ways that we can improve that. So that makes a lot of sense.
Thanks, Carol. Elizabeth, do you want to take the question?
Sure. As you probably won't be surprised from my background, I think one of the most interesting
things that's been happening lately is sort of the blurring of lines between tabletop games and
digital games. A lot of digital games having companion apps or getting digital versions of
games so that you can, you know, play Lords of Waterdeep on the airplane without bringing a
whole bunch of cards or that kind of thing. I think the sort of, you know, they've always been
quite separate, I think, but I think
In a way, that's bringing the joy and the togetherness of sitting side by side and playing a board game together,
places where you wouldn't normally be able to.
It's interesting that you bring that up. We're actually going to talk a little bit more about that in depth in just a little while.
It's exciting, yeah. Cole, do you have a thought?
Well, just building on that, I think one of the biggest changes in the past two, three years
that is really changing how games get made and played is
Not just the shift to digital spaces, but also the shift of the conversation around games to digital places.
Now, they've been in digital places for a long time, obviously.
We have websites like BoardGameGeek and venues like Reddit and Twitter, where there's always been a lot of discussion about board games.
But increasingly, sites like Discord and Discord servers are becoming real hubs for not just...
the discussion of games, but the generation of new games.
So, you know, many game series, and I'll just sort of reference two,
in the conflict simulation world, the COIN series,
the counterinsurgency series, and the levying campaign series,
which are two fairly complex historical game series,
both have extremely active discords that have produced
literally dozens of new iterations of the games,
many of which are going right into publication pipelines.
So we're seeing a real democratization of the publishing process and of the development process,
and it's happening in those kinds of digital spaces.
Yeah, I don't think anybody can argue that it's changing everything.
You know, there's a lot of different tools that are out there, but Discord has definitely changed the game.
Ming, would you like to take the question? Do you have anything you'd like to say?
Yeah, I want to talk. Because in China, the tabletop development history is quite different with the Western world.
Maybe in these three years, because of from maybe from 2020, because during the pandemic,
in China the main case of this is that the modern technology has made it possible for gamers to
select to play with friends online. Now a lot of tabletop games, the players can use the app.
play with friends online.
So more and more times, like such as us,
we talked with our friends, said.
Let's play together this night.
We open a new room on the app, so we can simplify the process
by only needing to click on application
and lowering the entry bar when we play the game.
So mobile apps are making things more accessible for everybody.
Yeah, I don't think any of us are going to argue with that.
OK, let's move on to the next question.
What game or games do you feel are innovating the space
currently and why?
Ming, why don't we start with you this time, if you,
or do you want some time to think about it
and I can bounce back?
Yeah.
This part I will talk about maybe like such as
script murder I just talked with during my themes.
Because script murder is the most famous,
famous, sorry.
That's okay, no, take your time.
The form and design of the most popular tiktok in China, because people can play the character
they choose and play with other fans together, be like such like a LARP game.
The core of this game is to create a social and immersive experience,
making players feel like they are not just playing a board game,
but also part of our ARP,
where they can perform and fully immerse themselves.
Okay. Cole, what game or games do you feel like are innovating the space currently, and why?
Well, I think one of the interesting things about tabletop is how the different sectors of innovation often don't talk to each other.
And then there'll be these moments where a particular mechanism or idea sort of cross pollinates.
And I think we're right on the edge of one of those moments or maybe in one when it comes to the cross pollination between what's happening in the indie RPG scene and what's happening in tabletop.
One of the games that really blew me away that I've played recently is Ross Cowan's The City of Winter.
I played The Fall of Magic, was quite impressed with it.
But The City of Winter.
does something really remarkable, which is that it's essentially a collaborative storytelling
game, but it provides about two steps more structure than most collaborative storytelling
games.
And the result is that it has an incredibly intimate and profound storytelling generation
system that is great for players who are usually uncomfortable working in that form.
And I think we're going to see a lot more games, tabletop, more traditional board games
building on some of those storytelling practices.
If I could jump in there instead of giving my own answer.
I couldn't agree more.
I think that you even see that coming from the indie RPG section.
Those role-playing games becoming almost more board game-like.
I'm thinking a lot about the work of Avery Alder, who's a phenomenal RPG designer with
The Quiet Year, where you're sort of making a map.
Also, she has Ribbon Drive, which is a game where basically you're telling a story about a road trip that you're all taking together.
And one of the core mechanics of the game is actually that everybody brings their own mix CD or their own playlist.
And the playlist actually informs what happens in the games.
So I think particularly when you're talking about what's happening on the bleeding edge in tabletop RPGs.
You see them pushing more and more towards having more tactility and physical components,
and I think we're also going to see sort of the lines blurring between tabletop board games
and tabletop role-playing games in the future.
Can I offer just a small footnote to your reminder, which is that both a lot of Avery Adler's games
and also The City of Winter and Fall of Magic, it's worth noting, are produced domestically.
And they have really amazing physical productions, but they're produced in Washington State.
and are very conscious about the sustainability of their materials.
Great job just tying like all three of us together there.
Perfect.
Carol you want to add anything?
Yeah so for me I think it's less about necessarily innovation and more about
leaning into the needs that we kind of discovered among ourselves during the pandemic.
Like this sense of isolation, the sense of needing connection.
We're seeing a lot of these really beautiful games like we're not really strangers.
and the mind and wavelength and these things that kind of develop
more verbal intimacy among players in a really interesting way that allows people to feel more
connected even if they can't play in the same space which I think is something that is really
special that we're seeing right now in the mass market. So this is stuff that people who are not
traditional board game players are seeing and engaging with and to me I think that's really
special and a really interesting way of pulling people into this space that we're seeing more
now than we've ever seen before.
I mean, the pandemic changed everything.
Oh, yeah.
Especially with GameSpace, I think it carried people through a lot, you know?
And the way that it's evolving because of that, I think is really interesting.
All right, let's move on a little bit here.
What advice would you give to designers for developing games for the future?
In kind of the, I don't want to say post-pandemic,
but the pandemic world that we're in now?
I mean, like, what advice would you give those designers?
Do you want to start, Carol?
Sure.
I mean, like I said earlier, thinking
with environmental sustainability in mind,
that starts at the design concept.
So thinking about how you can develop games that just use
less but do more is something that
is going to be really important.
Also, right now, as we're seeing,
obviously the economy is softening a little bit,
and publishers have less money to put into games.
Cost of goods have to stay lower.
So figuring out how you can keep your component costs down
is going to be.
how you're going to find a publisher who actually wants to publish your work, right?
So, you know, thinking in those lines, we're, you know, we're solving two problems here.
helping the planet by reducing greenhouse gases,
and we're also making games that are more affordable
for our players and that are more affordable
to produce in general.
So that's kind of where I would suggest
that especially new designers start thinking,
especially as they're starting to pitch
to their first publishers,
doing that conscientiously and being able to say
to their publishers, hey,
let me help you become more sustainable
is I think a really, really smart move right now.
Great. Elizabeth, do you want to start with something?
Sure. My answer is a little bit more touchy-feely,
just based on the kinds of games that I make.
I would really strongly suggest that you think about what is
missing in your social interactions with the people that you want to play with.
Because if any game is a two-player game or has more than one player,
that game is fundamentally about social interaction,
first and foremost, before anything else.
So, if you're starting, when you're starting working on a game,
think about what you want the social experience to be,
what you want the social dynamics to look like,
and then start thinking about what is an experience
that you would like to have that you haven't had in games.
I think something a lot of new designers sort of get hung up on
is wanting to almost recreate their favorite game
or the game that made them love games as a child.
But really, if you look at all of the wonderful experiences you're having,
and...
You sort of catalog them and you ask yourself,
what's missing and how can I get there?
I think you'll end up with something
that has a really unique proposition
that would be highly marketable
and also compelling to people.
Yes, I love telling people to think
about their players as components.
Yes, so like these are bodies that you can utilize.
Use it, like, right?
Yeah.
That's interesting.
Players as components, that makes sense.
Cole, do you wanna talk a little bit about this?
Yeah, I think.
It's so important to tell new designers to emphasize the degree to which games aren't
created by a single person.
Even if you are a single person alone, you need those player components.
You need them to help you make the thing.
And so any game that gets made is made because there was a community that rallied around it
and that helped you take the game across the finish line.
So you have to pay attention.
A good starting game designer is also going to be a good community manager
at some very core level.
And one way to do that, kind of riffing off the recent comment,
is to think about the urgency of the game.
There has to be a reason for them to want to play.
And one of the best things that you can do as a new game designer
is ask yourself, why does this game need to exist at all?
What is the urgency?
What's the thing that is making me want to finish this?
And if you could find that argument,
the urgency of your game, then you'll
be able to rally other people to that flag.
And that's going to help create the community that's
going to take the game across the finish line.
Great.
Would you like to talk, Ming?
OK.
I will give some advice based on Chinese background.
So my advice is IP crossover and mutual learning
can better complement the tabletop game and the video
game, which are not at odds with one another.
And the second is for the tabletop game
to grow in popularity in China, they
must be combined with other entertainment medium,
like variety shows and the internet and the television
in order to gain.
Mutual publicity, strengthening their social aspects as a selling point, and drawing more players as a fresh form of entertainment for daily life.
Great. I'm going to actually veer us off the road here a little bit, because I have kind of a sub-question to what I just asked.
As designers yourselves, what tools and methods do you use to start a project? And anybody who wants to jump in can just start.
Interestingly, during the pandemic, we leaned so hard on tabletop simulator.
Oh yeah.
And now that we're also just in a hybrid work environment, we still use it a lot.
It sucks. It feels like you have forks for hands, but it's so helpful because you can rapidly iterate,
you can change things up, you can pop in a brand new game in seconds.
And that's made a really big difference.
Fuck, having forks for hands isn't so bad sometimes.
Forks for hands.
Do you feel like you would have used it if you had been in a position where you kind
of had it?
Absolutely not.
No, we would have avoided it at all costs.
Like you know, obviously we do prototyping in-house, you know, like we'll do rapid prototypes
as quickly as we can, mock it up in Illustrator or whatever and print it out.
But again, talking about sustainability, that uses a lot of materials and if you're wanting
to rapidly iterate, moving into a digital space is such a good way of doing that.
Can I ask you really quickly, how do you gather playtest materials and like when you're working with a team and they're giving you feedback on something that you're testing out in that space?
What do you do to kind of collect that information and then utilize it?
Are you talking about just play test data play test data specifically with a digital space like working with folks. Yeah, I love recording it like that's it. That's something that I pulled from video games is like you'll see a lot of play test discussions talking about like well, you can just record your play tests if they're digital. So I like you know will play over zoom. So I'll record the zoom call will do screen share.
We record what's happening on the table and we record players' reactions.
And that's ultimately where you get your information.
It's so truthful because sometimes you get playtest,
you have to filter everything because you're not sure how the people who are
undergoing the playtest are honestly responding to what you've given them.
And so you've got to kind of filter it through that.
But when you have that video content that you can look back on,
being able to then kind of witness their reactions to things tells you a lot.
Yeah, you can tell when people check out.
You can tell when people are having fun.
It's so important.
Yeah, we do it at hunters all the time.
Anybody else want to jump in?
So I want to say something about TTS, a tabletop simulator, because it really, I mean it trans,
I think everyone who works in the industry professionally, it transformed our workflow.
The iterative loop that used to depend on your poor play tester having to go to FedEx
after work to print and assemble a new copy and hope it's done in time for their Friday
game night, that's gone now.
Now we get to push out versions and it starts looking a lot more like video game development.
And so I want to offer a very technical comment about TTS for people who use it to test, which
is the most valuable thing you can do when you're using TTS, and this is so specific,
so sorry about narrowing the scope of this panel, is to turn off caching.
And to host the files somewhere where you have direct access to their links.
So getting a direct Dropbox link.
And the reason for this is then when you export using InDesign and you
export all your files, you load up TTS and you don't have to do anything.
All of the cards are now the most current version.
And I wish someone would have told me that eight months into the pandemic
after we spent so long updating all these silly JSON files.
I mean, the main tool that I feel like I use are.
You basically ask yourself the question when you're starting to design,
what do I need to implement a new adjustment to this game and to test it?
And just write out the test as if you were doing a factory study.
What are the steps?
And then get better at those steps.
Spend some time learning InDesign.
Spend some time learning Tabletop Simulator.
And if you don't want to pay for Tabletop Simulator,
know that there are many good free alternatives, including
ScreenTop, which is fully browser-based.
Likewise, many of the things that InDesign does
can be done in other pieces of software.
Great.
Does anybody else want to jump in on this?
I guess one thing that's more geared towards indie developers than people who are already
working inside of a company.
I know one question, when I was doing a lot of talks about tabletop game design, one of
the number one questions I would get is, how do I even get playtesters?
And I would say that the number one most important tool you have are your friends and your family,
because if you pitch them a game idea and they don't want to playtest it, that's already information for you.
Like, I hate to say it, but that's the first and best funnel,
because if what you really want to do is make games,
you need to make sure that you're working on something
that people are interested in playing.
And so relying on the people who care about you most,
first and foremost, and who might be willing to go
a little bit outside of their comfort zone
because they like you, if they're saying no to you,
maybe move on to the next idea.
Yeah, like if your pitch can't be on the back of the box and somebody looks at it in retail and is like,
yeah, I want to buy it, then nobody's going to buy it.
Right. Even if it's the greatest game in the world,
you have to get the first couple people to buy it and tell their friends about it
and force them to play it.
And if you can't get those first couple people, no one will ever know.
So, it's a little like the practice of writing rules,
where if you find yourself having a hard time articulating a rule,
there's a problem with the design.
The English language is a fabulous tool. It should be able to handle the rules of your game.
When you're actually boiling it down and you get that log line for your game,
do you do that at the beginning of your process or at the end after you have the entire game?
To me it's more like, I don't know if you're familiar with the way that music is made,
but often what a vocalist will do is come in and almost a cappella do what they call a scratch track,
which is just...
laying down the vocals and then the session musicians will come in and they'll lay down
the instrumental tracks and then at the end the singer comes back and does the actual vocals
and that's sort of the way I think about like the elevator pitch or the log line.
You come up with one first, and that gets people into the door.
And then the more you see how the game evolves,
the very last thing you do is you go back
to that original elevator pitch or that log line,
and you ask yourself if that makes sense
and if there needs to be any alteration.
Yeah, man.
We're game designers.
We playtest that shit.
Exactly.
Iterate everything.
Well, I think about a pitch for a game
as the star that everything else is orbiting around.
I've been working over the past couple of years
with this designer, Joe Kelly.
on their game Molly House, which is about queer culture in 1720s London.
And it's mostly about these houses where people were allowed to explore all kinds of different
identities and the crackdown by the various early versions of the police, even before
the police had really formed as an institution.
And the first time I played their game, I found the game to be a total mess, but the
design, there was something about it that was very compelling.
The core pitch was good.
And then every time I would play a new version, the game was completely different.
but they were still orbiting the same star.
And so when I'm looking at a design,
I don't really care if they're using the same mechanism
or if they have a clever little mechanical hook.
I'm really interested in what are the attributes of the star?
Because, and so allow yourself, if you're working on a game,
to change things, to really dramatically reconfigure
your game, especially if it's true to that initial pitch.
I want to make a little space here for Ming.
Ming, do you want to jump in on this?
Yeah.
I maybe talk about skills based on China, because I will give our guys an example.
Such as the whereof of mirror host initial user based on what's small due primarily to
the offline experience.
To ensure a positive gaming experience,
every player needs a qualified host,
and the players need to master extremely fine
turn-design communication techniques.
But after the app launched,
so more and more people can play by easier handle.
They can talk to each other by voice
and tap the walls with other things.
the same group, they can talk with them.
So the designer need to think, maybe based in China,
need to think how it can be easily understand for the players.
Because in China, most people just want to play the game
with friends for a short time.
They don't want to pay a lot of time to study.
how to play the game.
So based on China, need to be quite easier
for everybody can play.
It's the most important part.
That accessibility, do you have any advice
for how to create that in your game design?
Yeah.
It's most for them, it's easier to understand
how to play the game.
And they can use the tool or the other mechanics
to easy to join the game and play the game.
Great, thank you.
All right, does anybody want to jump in on the last of that,
or should we move on?
Let's keep going.
Now, we've already talked a lot about this already,
but I think there's so much more space for us to explore it.
How do you see digital tools interacting with tabletop games
in the future, and should it?
I think we all have opinions on this,
but let's start with Cole.
Cole, do you want to take this?
I'm curious if hand-to-hand wombat was developed
using Tabletop Simulator.
And so I just, I want to ask that question before I provide my answer.
Do it! Yeah, yeah, yeah.
It's a long story.
We've got the time.
So Hand to Hand Wombat evolved from a very, very different game
that was testable in Tabletop Simulator,
but unfortunately, obviously the physicality of it prevented.
So for those of you who are unfamiliar,
Hand to Hand Wombat is a very tactile social deduction game
where you close your eyes and you build towers.
And one of the people is...
sabotaging those towers.
So, you don't know who that is.
It's just some bad wombat.
And doing that in Tabletop Simulator
and getting all of the sizing right
and importing all of the models and everything,
you need the physicality.
You need the hands.
Like I said, the players are components in this game.
So unfortunately, Tabletop Simulator.
But we did push it as far as we could go until we got to that point.
But it was an interesting process because we had to playtest it during the pandemic.
But yeah, Handy Hand Wombat is one where we actually decided to cut down on cost of goods.
by incorporating the phone timer instead of incorporate,
like we didn't want to add the additional cost
for our players by having some custom design plastic,
you know, timer that has an audio alarm.
We decided folks already have phones in their pockets,
you know, those phones are accessible
so they can modify how the alarm goes off,
they can set it to vibrate, they can set it to a sound,
whatever they want.
and that that's gonna cut down on the cost of the game.
Well, the reason I asked you about it
is because it's one of the few games I knew
that was made during the pandemic,
which to me doesn't show its pandemic pedigree.
We were working on my game Oath during the pandemic
and its development took a turn, mostly for the better,
during the pandemic because it changed
the way the game worked.
We had a version of Oath that we played literally
the day in the office before we shut it down
where players took single action impulses.
It was a kind of radical branch of the game.
It was sort of promising.
Then the pandemic happened, and we changed how the game worked
to give players a little bit longer turns
because it was so much easier to play test digitally
if someone just takes their turn,
and then we know that in the course of the game,
you're going to be taking eight turns
with four or five actions rather than 60 turns
with lots of little interrupts.
And I think that we're starting to actually see
in the crop of games that have come out
in the past couple of years,
the marks of design during pandemic, for better and worse.
You know, one of the examples that comes to mind is Isaac Childress's new Gloomhaven
title, Frosthaven, which to me is like barely a physical object.
And I like a lot of things about the design, but if you've ever tried to open up the
box you'll ask yourself the question, is this supposed to be a board game at all?
I mean, it's so large.
And one can see how they developed it extensively using digital tools, but it maybe wasn't
as designed to be a physical object.
You know, so I've had this, you know, we've been sorting through this problem when it comes to questions of, you know, introducing games with interrupts.
Interrupts are really hard to do in a digital space.
Even when you're running cameras and you can see people, it's just hard to communicate that.
And I compare that to design work, you know, something like Sid Saxon's I'm the Boss from the early 90s, which is a game entirely built around interrupts.
Something like that I feel like just couldn't exist in the current mode because of these digital tools.
It's hard enough to have a logistical conversation on Zoom, let alone an interrupting mechanic.
Right, and so I think that there's been a lot that we've gained from using these digital tools,
but they are also steering the design conversation away from certain kinds of designs.
Do you, as a follow-up to that, do you feel like there are things that you now do completely
different in your design studio based on what you've learned from that?
Or are you trying to move yourself back over to some of your original techniques and processes?
When it came to the development of ARX, I didn't build the TTS kit for the first year
of iteration, which was a lot of work.
And it was done on purpose because I wanted to make sure that the core action loop of
the game was players sitting around a table and having that back and forth.
And then once we got to the more serious development work,
of course we had to move it into DTS.
But we've had to introduce kind of safeguards
to protect our design practice from too much digital thinking
in that early stage where it's particularly vulnerable.
Amazing.
Ming, do you have anything you'd like to add to this?
Yeah, for this question, I think the digital is quite
useful for the board game, such as some games.
When we first take the box, we play the game, we need to read the rule.
But it's the first time, we can't make sure the rules I understand is right or is wrong.
So the first time if I use the board game and use an app, we can check my think is right.
Okay, we can play together and use the app help us to check every step is good.
We think it can help us, okay, maybe it's kind of easier for everybody to play the game
as the first time.
So it's a guide in initially learning the game.
Yeah.
Okay, great.
Do you want to jump in?
Do you have anything that you'd like to add, Elizabeth?
Sure.
I think one thing that's really important when we think about this is that
There are definitely things, as we've sort of discussed already, that you can do on tabletop
that you just can't emulate in digital, but also the other way around is very much true.
Like if you look at what's going on in a typical CCG versus Marvel Snap, like there are just
some mechanics that work better in digital that you would not really be able to emulate
in a tabletop space.
But on the other hand, you know, as somebody who was initially, you know, designing tabletop
games.
back in 2006 when there weren't a lot of digital components,
what I really learned in sort of like trying to create like Java apps to help with my,
so that people could play my RPGs on IRC to let you know how old I am,
is that the magic of a tabletop game is that when players are bought in
If you've missed something in your rules, sort of the social contract or the fact that
human brains are sort of elastic and nimble, they can sort of, you know, glide over that.
But if you, for example, forget to say what size dice to put in your game blowback,
which definitely happened to me, if you try to emulate that in a computer,
computer doesn't give a shit. Like, it will just break.
And so I think one thing that's super useful about
Getting more digital tools involved or trying to digitize parts of the tabletop game experience
is that it makes you a much tighter designer.
You have to make sure that everything is really buttoned up in a way that you can sort of
get away with if you're not trying to make it digital.
Let me ask you really quickly, how do you integrate or even think about video content when you're making something?
Do you consider that? Do you think about how maybe a tutorial might be used or how maybe you can utilize it within the course of your game itself?
I think when we start thinking about incorporating digital content into board games, I think
the most important thing is to think about how players are interacting with it and to
make sure that it makes the game more accessible and more approachable in some way.
The idea of just tossing in something digital because it feels trendy I think is really
frightening to me because that
Takes away a lot of what makes board games magical and that is engaging with people around the table. Right? And so I think that's a heavy consideration.
Do you ever think we're going to get to a place where like VR or some other technology is going to allow for that intimacy still and be able to be digitized so that you'll be able to find that still but not be at the same table?
In my opinion? Yeah, absolutely not. Yeah.
The physicality is so key.
If you're not in the same room, it's not happening.
I mean, you can have a valuable experience digitally, sure.
But you're not going to have that same level of presence,
that same level of human interaction
as when you're sitting around the table,
as when you're sharing cards, as when you're
touching the same components.
It is just such a core human experience to me
that no digital replacement is ever going to take over that.
That's well said.
Does anybody else want to jump in on that?
I couldn't say it better.
Oh yeah, no, I mean, neither could I.
Well said.
Okay, let's move on.
This is again, you know, we've talked a little bit around this, but let's codify some of it.
What are some of the best lessons from the past four years that creators can carry into the future?
Do you want to start, Cole?
The last four years?
Is this a pandemic question to Scott?
This is a pandemic question.
Specifically, like we've already talked around it a little bit, but the idea that, you know,
we have changed the way that we design, we've changed the way that games are made.
We've changed the way that games are made.
Well, I mean, I'm going to kind of circle back to what I was saying earlier, which is,
I think it's important to recognize that we're making games, we're making these objects,
and we can think about the games as objects that we're selling.
And the problem with that way of thinking is that after the game is sold, our relationship
with the player ends.
They've bought the house, they're the new owner, and they're not going to call us for
plumbing advice.
I think that one of the things that I feel like I've had to really learn, and Root is
a big part of this, is that players want a lot more from the publishers, and we should
think about...
a continuing relationship with the player.
And this doesn't just mean expansions and DLCs and other kinds of content.
It means treating the game and the players who gather around it
as sort of parts of a community.
And I don't mean community in a cynical way.
I mean like an actual community that is oriented around a passion for something.
One of the things about Root that I don't mention very often,
but I guess I'll mention here because, you know, not that many people are watching.
is that Root was not designed to be expanded at all.
We built sort of four factions, and then we did really well on Kickstarter,
and so we thought, OK, we'll figure out how to put two more in.
But we had no idea that we would ever expand the game.
And at this point, it would probably cost someone about $300 to buy all of the expansion content for Root.
But we didn't build that content because we wanted to make that money.
We built the content because the community wanted us to support the game.
And so we realized that what Root was wasn't something that we got full control over,
that it was something that we were negotiating with the audience.
And so I think one of the big takeaways I've had,
I just think that the pandemic made this clearer because it made the communities a little bit more graspable.
Even though...
We weren't sharing the same kind of convention spaces with them.
I could see them on Discord playing the game.
I could read their conversations in different forums.
And I realized the games that we were making weren't just products that we were selling.
They weren't just objects that we were creating internally.
These were objects that people were gathering around and forming communities around.
Yeah, you've mentioned Discord a couple of times now, and that's obviously been a tool that's helped you a lot.
Do you feel like theand community's a loaded word, right?
But like, the groups that have formed there, the community input that you've gotten,
do you think that that is something that in the future you're going to lean on more heavily than you have in the past?
Yeah, well, we already do. I mean, we have...
Leader Games is oriented around the Woodland Warriors Discord, which is a wonderful place.
We sponsor all kinds of contests there.
And we even design our games in such a way that we create kind of a new, smaller Discord
to handle a lot of the testing.
And then over the course of testing, we build that Discord up.
And then eventually it can launch its own community or just sort of re-merge with the
main community.
But it's something that we think about a community's engagement with the game basically in the
very first design meetings where we're talking about the nature of the game.
I don't want to talk too much about my group and my company, but we do have a group called
Action Rangers, and we built them in as community managers, moderators, and playtesters.
They use our Discord in a very similar way, where they become the experts on the game
for us, so that they're also able to self-regulate and help build and answer questions, even
when we're not able to.
I mean, they beat us to most of the explanations about our own games before we can even get
in there now.
Well, I'll add one small thing about that, which is a lot of our community members will generate digital tools for supporting the games.
We have a chance to do anything in one of those tools.
In the case of Oath, players would have frequently asked questions about cards.
We would post them on our website.
And eventually a player built a fully searchable, wonderful card database that basically houses all of the different interactions with Oath's huge card base.
And they've even built that back into the tabletop simulator so that if you mouse over a card it'll start loading all the community answers.
So these are people that you want to empower.
Yeah, absolutely. You never want to say no to enthusiasm.
If I can riff a little bit on something you just said earlier, I think one of the biggest
lessons from the last four years is that even though it has been a significant amount of
time since the very first lockdown, I think for a lot of people, social interaction is
still fairly fraught.
And people are still reaching for not just their comfort TV shows or their comfort movies, but also like their comfort games.
And so I think you are going to see more of like the idea of...
Games as a service or expansions or sequels moving more into the tabletop realm because
people are really, you know, having structured rules for social interaction takes away some
of that anxiety about, you know, learning how to interact with people again.
And I think reaching for a game that is familiar, that you already love, but is just a little
bit deeper or...
A sequel to that just makes that a little bit more comforting, I guess.
I think people are getting really into like cozy games and that kind of thing.
I think people just, yeah, they just want to be, want to feel comfortable with their friends.
And that's not something that a lot of the last four years has given us.
Yeah.
If I can jump in, I totally agree with that and I feel like whether or not it's about, you know, developing community through expansions and continuing to support the same project, I think from, you know, from my perspective as a mass market designer, I'm thinking about how can I create approachable, accessible games to bring new people into the community.
To introduce new people into this way of experiencing each other, of playing with each other, of building relationships.
And that to me is something that, like, I think the pandemic, like I said earlier, like, that has introduced such a great need for that.
And also thinking about, like, can this game be played over a Discord call?
Can this game be something that brings people together even if they're not in the same space?
I think that that's something that's really important to be thinking about as a designer in this current age.
Do you feel like you have also found, like Cole had said earlier, that there's a desire for your games to be, not that they weren't before, but perhaps more organic and to be expandable and to have more built upon them?
potentially i mean so again coming from mass market we're thinking about
like what what is actually going to sell on the shelves at target or walmart and
frankly expansions don't
i mean if we're being honest so so it's less we're thinking less about
necessarily expansions
and more about how can we continue to support our players so
for the game that i did uh... exploding kittens recipes for disaster
We gave you 130 cards and we gave you some recipes that we developed in-house and then
blank recipe books.
And what I mean by recipes is ways of mixing those cards together for unique experiences,
unique ways to play the game.
So we're encouraging our players to engage with our game in new ways,
engage with each other, be creative, and explore game design on their own.
And beyond that, for Hand to Hand Wombat, for example, we posted
some different alternative gameplay modes that they could play online. We
posted accessibility recommendations so that
new people could approach the game from a perspective that a game
designer would recommend. Things like that, I think, are really
viable ways of continued support for players without necessarily having to
enter into the expansion space. Great. Ming, do you have anything that you would
like to add? Yeah. One time I talked with one creator that's the CEO of the
Armyscape. He also gave me some some opinion.
Because the tip-top game is a kind of leisure that allow people to interact in person and
away from technology in the information age.
But some people, they are not social driving and prefer a quiet experience and less competition.
So he makes the product, the guy can play by himself, because they make the perfect
products.
Finally, crafted single player products are necessary
for this type of player.
So,
so they focused on improving the quality of the product
by having detailed historical research
and to add correct gameplay elements.
So this allows players to gain a great sense of fulfillment
and reward well-play.
So starting with solo play and building off of that
into your multiplayer experiences?
Yeah, it's the opposite way with the multiplier.
Great.
Well, listen, I only have one more question, and then I'm going to open it up to the floor.
If you do have questions, you can start to line up at either of these microphones.
I appreciate you bearing with me as I've asked these questions.
I want to say right now that the panelists didn't have any idea what these questions
were going to be, and they've done a phenomenal job.
So as you're lining up, can we give them a round of applause?
Uh, yeah. Uh, the last thing I'm gonna ask, and I warned some of you about this one question,
but if you were on a desert island and you could bring three games with you, what would they be?
We'll start over here. Carol?
Yeah. How many people are on the devil- the desert island with us?
As many as you want. As many people, but only three games.
Okay. A fake artist goes to New York.
Consenticle.
And...
A deck of cards.
Okay.
Yeah, that's a good answer, actually.
That is a really good answer.
Thank you.
I do my best.
It's like a mini-game.
What do you think?
There's an out-of-print board game that I love called Attica.
It's probably my favorite board game of all time.
I'd say Sentinels of the Multiverse with every single expansion.
That's a lot.
And then I'd probably say Mon Cala.
I love it.
Okay. What about you, Cole?
Oh my goodness.
Alright. This answer would change daily.
But at this moment,
I would say a deck of cards,
probably a copy of Blood on the Clock Tower,
and maybe an obscure, not obscure,
but a train game. 1817.
Okay.
And poker chips for the train game.
Yeah, poker chips. You've got to have the poker chips.
Ming, do you have games that you'd like to
name out?
The game now, I'm like,
it's...
I already take the game today.
Okay, you've got it right here.
So you're already ready for your desert island.
Yeah.
Okay, let's go ahead and move over to some questions.
We'll start over here.
Would you like to start?
I'm not really sure how to best ask this,
but as we move through, you know, 10, 15 years from now
where 3D printing is...
Much cheaper and you know basically everyone under 30 has interacted with one in some meaningful way.
Sort of business or design wise how can tabletop design kind of cope with that and utilize it, leverage it to create different experiences?
We've started, we're having a real active conversation at our company about 3D printing because
what we're finding is that it's not worth
the money and the time and the effort to design extremely good box inserts, because some fan
is going to make one that is better.
And they're going to post the STLs on Thingiverse or sell them.
And so
It's kind of meaning that for us, we move away from the auxiliary stuff, because rather
than making something calibrated for the ultra true fan, we know they're going to make their
own bespoke solution to those problems, so we'll just focus on the things that they would
have trouble making.
That's great.
All right.
Thank you for the question.
I will say, we had a fan that actually created an entire Discord bot for us for Alice's
Bissing, and we of course ended up paying them for the work and ingesting it into our
full process, but it was incredible the amount of work that people are willing to put into
those things.
What do you have for a question?
Hi. So, picking up on some of the themes that you've been discussing this afternoon,
post-pandemic in this more isolated world, I feel like 2022 was a bit of a watershed moment for solo
gaming, games like Final Girl. And I feel very conflicted about this myself, because I do agree
with the idea that in tabletop games, at least 50% of the components are the people. And the value
for me in tabletop gaming over digital gaming is...
The social interaction.
But on the other hand, I have friends now who have gotten deep into tabletop games,
who were never interested before, but they've done so through solo games.
So I just have an open question to all of you.
Do you feel threatened by solo games?
Do you feel like they're...
If they can have an interaction with multiplayer games,
how you design for solo versions of, for example,
something like Exploding Kittens,
is there a mass market appeal to that?
Big, broad, open question, but just, yeah, solo games.
How do you feel?
Should visual novels feel threatened by books?
I think that while my practice with game design is fundamentally around human interaction,
I think if you're designing a solo game, there are things that you can do, again, in a tabletop
game that you can't do in a digital experience.
The tactility, I think, is great.
There was a great game, oh I'm forgetting the name, by Kevin Allen Jr. way, way back in the early 2000s.
I think it was called Sweet Agatha, where basically it was a book and it was a mystery and you sort of had to cut it apart
and put it back together to figure out what happened to Agatha.
And I think there's something really magical about that.
It's, you know, sometimes you want to have that kind of interesting tactile experience
and you don't have other players.
And I think, you know, there's nothing wrong with that as long as you're really thinking
about what is this solo experience providing that you can't get in any other medium.
Great.
Thanks for the question.
Do you want to add anything?
I'll just add that, you know, solo games are played alone but experienced together.
Yeah.
Because solo players love talking to each other about the experiences playing their
games.
And when they're in a real community, that means that.
Yeah.
I agree.
Even for a game like John Company, a negotiation game, it was worth the time and the effort
to find a good solo designer to build a negotiating bot for that design, because the community
is that organized.
Great.
Let's take a question from over here.
I'm a game developer, but I absolutely love playing board games, especially when I can get the friend group together.
But because I'm a game developer, I'm not familiar with the design process for board games.
So one of the things that you said that I found was very interesting was that you use tabletop simulator for prototyping.
So I was curious what...
If you think post-pandemic, if that will continue to be an important prototyping tool?
And if, what particular feature is the most important?
And what doesn't it do that you wish it did or could do better?
So I use it primarily at this point for viability testing,
because player response is not going to be the same.
They're processing so many more things when they're trying to figure out the software.
They're trying to figure out how to interact.
They're trying to understand why there are forks for hands.
So, like, doing all of that makes the gameplay experience notably different.
And it's really, really important to do, you know, the tail end, the very least of your work.
So, it's a little bit of a challenge.
I think it's a good thing that we're
able to do this work in the physical space.
But it has been great for rapid iteration and viability testing
for, you know, identifying where's the fun factor, where do
we dig into this, that sort of thing. And balancing, like,
basic balancing type of stuff. It's so good for that.
Great. Thanks for the question. Let's start with a question over
here, please.
I'm getting into the board game space, coming from the digital end of things, and I've been
doing a lot of physical testing with playgroups and stuff like that, but as someone who doesn't
have a huge following, what's the easiest way, or the various ways that you would recommend
to actually get a game onto shelves?
Because I have a game that's working, but it's like, how do I find the audience for
that game?
And maybe that's a longer question.
I have an answer for this.
So I'd say two things.
One, look for other communities of designers.
If you live in a city that has an active pro spiel scene,
it's a great scene.
One of the people, you know, there
are a lot of designers who are in a similar place.
And one thing you can all do to help each other
is to play each other's games.
In terms of finding the right publisher,
the biggest piece of advice I give to folks
is that publishers are not here to grade your game,
to say that this is an A-plus game, we'd love to publish it.
What's happening is that you have something you want, which is your game to be published,
and the publisher is also looking for a successful game, and they have their own interests and
market share and all these concerns, and if those two tumblers line up, then the game
gets published, and if they don't line up, it doesn't mean anything's wrong with your
game, it just means they didn't line up.
So look for publishers that are doing work.
that is adjacent to what your game is doing.
And think about your pitch to the publisher,
not just this game's going to be the next Magic.
Actually, don't tell them that
because they'll stop listening to you.
But what you can say is you can say,
look, I saw the kinds of games that you're working on.
I think there's a little bit of a hole
in what you're publishing,
and I think this game would fit in that spot.
That's great advice.
I mean, it's apples and oranges, you know,
when you pitch something and it just doesn't land.
It doesn't necessarily mean that the game's not right
somewhere, it's just not right with that publisher.
All right, thanks for the question.
Over here, sir.
Hi, so one thing that I'm seeing a bit with, for example,
Mansions of Madness that ties in with a lot of the things
that you have all been talking about today
is leveraging the tactile experience,
but still providing for expandability
in the digital through a digital medium.
and how do you think, because I'm suspecting that this is going to become more common,
it just makes a lot of business sense as well,
but when you have these communities that form around the game, like you're mentioning,
and you also have potentially publishers that want to continue to capitalize on it,
How do you feel about sort of retaining control of that core idea when you've provided more
a tool set and the game is sort of infinitely expandable, or do you just not do that?
Does anybody want to take that?
You've got to let it go.
I mean, when Root came out, we started getting fan factions about every week.
And at first they were, to use a word used earlier today, curios, just kind of fun little
things.
And then there were 20, and then there were 50, and then there were hundreds of them.
And we just sort of let it happen.
And we actually tried to support our games.
At Whirlygig, we actually put all of our games in the Creative Commons, which feels right
because many of them...
use art that's in the public domain. So I want all the games, all the icons, everything,
it's all in the Creative Commons. And we include very easy to disassemble kits for people who want to raid those files.
And at Leader, we always build card templates, things like that, provide access to the community. We love sharing our files
because it's going to bring a lot more people into the tent than it's going to scare away.
Yeah, I think that would be the one thing that I would suggest too, is developing creative tools that can also guide your players in the direction that you would like to see them go.
Like I said, like about recipes for disaster, right? Like, we don't necessarily want our players developing their own cards because that can break the game in Exploding Kittens really, really quickly.
But developing a recipe and assembling a handful of cards is a really fun way to explore and learn and grow with the game.
So just as an example of ways that you can sort of help create some guardrails for your players.
Great, thanks. Thanks for the question.
Hi, I think today you've talked about digital tools such as Discord and Tabletop Simulator.
And I'm wondering whether there are other digital tools that you have been using such as like
tools for balancing game economy or say generative tools for like rapid prototyping.
Does anyone want to take that?
My favorite, although this is mostly used in the digital space,
my favorite tool for modeling a player economy is something called machinations.
Yes.
Yes, it's so good.
Basically, you put in all of your faucets and your sinks,
and then you can simulate hundreds or thousands of rounds of play,
and you can see where you need to tweak things,
and you can do that all in real time without having to get out any components.
It's brilliant.
And my favorite, Google Spreadsheets.
Yes.
It's essential.
I use a fair bit of Python, actually,
if I'm working on any kind of event system
that I can build a model of.
I'll build it just with Python.
And then more recently, I've started
using MC Dice, which is a Monte Carlo Dice simulator
developed by a person who's probably in this room.
And it is exceptionally good if you need to very quickly model anything that involves
different kinds of die rolling and things like that.
And I use this both when doing kind of preliminary design work, but also when we're actually
doing play tests after we run a particular combat, I will run it through the simulator
and say, okay, how likely was what happened?
That's really smart.
Ming, do you have any tools that you use?
Yeah, the tool I use is when I play.
So we were mirror hosts because I played with my friends.
I just create a room, my friends joined the room.
We wrote the character and then we played the game.
When I was on the evil side, I just said,
I'm a good person and I tapped the decision
with my partner, fantastic.
So the voice and the text is quite different.
I think it's quite easier for us to play,
such as because in the past, we need to open the eye,
no words, just use the words, kill this guy,
or do the other things.
It's quite easy for us.
One last question here.
So this question is for Ming, specifically on Chinese market.
So.
under the current circumstance of the tightening up of publication number.
issued by the government.
What do you see, and especially since you pointed out, it's very important
to have a combined force from all platforms to gain publicity of your game,
of your IP.
Usually it takes a lot of resource to do that, to pull that up successfully.
So what do you think, where do you see the future of indie
tabletop games developers?
in Chinese market in the next five years maybe.
Yeah.
In Chinese market, the most important I think is about the culture.
Like just this morning, the course says about the history.
We currently also have the script and products that come in with history elements.
Because based on this, more culture come in with the products.
Kind of like the Chinese famous culture, separates to the overseas.
As more and more people know about the Chinese culture and new products.
I think this during this part can make more people know the Chinese culture and then also for the Chinese person
because like some children
if you
If you ask them, listen, history,
they think, oh, it's quite difficult.
I don't want to.
But you tell them this is a game.
You are a player.
They want to play the game.
And during the play, they know the knowledge.
They learn the history and a lot of other things.
It's a good way for them to education
or a lot of other things.
Amazing. We are out of time. I want to thank everybody for joining us.
And I want to thank the panelists, and you can too now by applauding for them, please.
I have all their information up here.
It's been up here for a little while.
If you take a photo, you'll be able to contact these folks across the internet.
Make sure to let them know on social media how you feel about this panel.
And I want to remind each and every one of you, you have the ability to fill out a survey.
If you like these panelists, if you like this panel, please fill it out.
It takes less than 30 seconds.
It helps us out.
It helps GDC out.
It helps everybody out.
It helps you out so that you can have good content next year as well.
I want to thank every single one of these panelists.
They will be outside for a little while.
If you have further questions, they
may be there to follow up with you.
And thank you again.
Enjoy your GDC.