Hello, everyone, and welcome to our talk.
The topic we will be presenting today is Simulating Tropical Weather in Far Cry 6.
Before we begin, let me introduce myself.
My name is Emily Zhou, and I have been a technical artist at Ubisoft Montreal for the past four
years.
Colin will introduce himself a little later when he covers the second half of our presentation.
The game that our talk is centered around is Far Cry 6,
the latest installment of the Far Cry franchise.
If you're not familiar with Far Cry,
it is an open world first-person shooter series
where each title takes place in a new environment.
In this case, we introduced the players to Yara,
a fictional Caribbean island
that was inspired by Cuba and other countries.
Here, players will take on the role of Danny Rojas,
a local rebel fighting to topple the regime
of dictator Anton Castillo and his son, Diego.
Far Cry's dynamic open worlds are a shining trait of the franchise.
Each world has a life of its own,
with many systems constantly interacting with one another.
Now, to add a tropical island experience to the mix,
we needed something that would be new to Far Cry,
a complete dynamic weather system.
To give you an idea of what dynamic weather entails,
here's a quick sneak peek at what you might see as a player in Far Cry 6.
Today, we will be presenting to you our weather system
in its entirety.
As such, we have condensed many topics
into the following categories.
To start, I will go over our inspiration and core controls.
I'll then explain how we tackled material wetness
by covering each asset type.
Following that, Colin will step through the technical details
for each rendering feature that supports weather.
And lastly, we will conclude with some final thoughts.
For our inspiration, we looked at the weather for various tropical locations, such as Cuba.
Island locations are typically home to very distinct and varied tropical weather.
At the start of the project, research was conducted on tropical scenery and weather
so that we could give our players an authentic experience as they explored our world.
We soon found that we needed to incorporate both the iconic, sunny weather shown here,
as well as the flip side of tropical weather, which includes heavy rain and thunderstorms.
We needed to emulate the way that weather could change back and forth drastically, sometimes
within hours.
We then took these elements that we wanted to highlight and included them in our concept
art.
Yarrow was pitched as an ideal tropical paradise.
It should serve as a convincing escape into our game's fantasy.
However, our art direction wanted
to contrast the picture-perfect weather
with foreboding thunderstorms.
And when the player gets caught in a storm,
the rain and wetness should be felt and should be convincing.
And of course, Yara is an island.
So the ocean is a key part of the equation, even for weather.
With that in mind, let's translate the direction
into goals for implementing weather.
We want to have a collection of different weather states.
We want the weather to be dynamic and varied.
We want a system where the transitions make sense.
For example, a storm should be preceded with darkening clouds
and followed by remaining water puddles.
And of course, everything needs to be efficient and fit
within our budgets.
We must emphasize here that this weather system will
be for an open world game.
Our decisions are often influenced
by data and performance budgets and the need
to support all times of day and all locations in the world.
Let's move on to our implementation, starting with the core weather controls.
The weather manager is the core code for our weather system and is what essentially drives weather behind the scene.
It contains information used to define and control weather, some of which is exposed as settings in our weather database.
Consider the weather manager as the back end of the system and the weather database as the front end.
Let's go over the setup for our system, starting with the weather preset.
The collection of weather types is referred to on the project as weather presets.
These are defined in the weather database using the exposed parameters from the weather manager.
To get an idea of what we can achieve with these parameters,
let's step through some of our final presets and compare a few of their values.
For the few clouds presets, we use low cloud coverage values shown in the bottom right.
In comparison, the Broken Clouds preset
uses higher cloud coverage to give us big, fluffy clouds.
Next, we can see that the Mist preset has added light fog
in the distance.
And in comparison to that, we have our Heavy Fog preset
with fog values cranked much higher.
The next few presets will show the progression
of rain intensity, starting with light rain, then moderate rain.
followed by heavy rain, at which point the rain intensity is maximized and the sky begins to darken,
which leaves us with our most intense preset, the thunderstorm, which adds lightning.
Now that we have our weather preset building blocks, we need to create a cycle or a weather pattern.
In the very beginning, our initial idea was to collect and use real-world meteorological data from cities like Miami.
As shown in the image, we obtained the description of weather at every hour from a period of time in 2013.
Although it would have been nice to use real-world data
to drive our forecast, we wanted more artistic control.
The method that we ended up going with
was a similar text file, but we timed our chosen weather
presets ourselves and designed up to five full day
cycles per region.
This freedom also allowed us to showcase our weather presets
where they look the best.
Now we need to take some time to discuss regions.
The world of Far Cry 6 has been subdivided into three main regions,
West, Central, and East, each with its own visual identity.
The West region was the dry region, Central was the wetlands,
and the East was the jungle region. To enhance these distinctions, we wanted
our weather to differ between each region as well.
Note that our definition of regions also extends to smaller zones, such as
interiors and caves, and anything else that artists might need
to define.
For each region, we exposed min and max curves
to limit certain weather properties.
This was how we altered weather based on where the player
is moving around in the world.
An example usage case would be how we set the max fog curve
to zero for the indoor zones
to prevent fog from appearing inside.
The limitation to this is that
if your indoor area has windows,
you would see the fog disappear outside
as soon as you walked in.
And this is why we assigned our zones very carefully.
Our weather manager then took in all the potentially overlapping
regions around the player and interpolates the curves
accordingly to output the adjusted weather.
The weather manager also needs to allow
for overrides, such as for gameplay missions
and pre-rendered cut scenes.
For example, the opening mission of the game
has the player fleeing through the city streets
in the middle of a nighttime thunderstorm.
Additionally, our game is available in multiplayer co-op,
so weather needs to be replicated for all players.
This flowchart illustrates the final order of operations.
So to summarize, we first consult the forecast
to get the weather preset at the current time of day.
Then based on where the player is,
we apply regional adjustments.
This gives us the current weather state,
which can be overridden for gameplay.
Finally, we use this weather state
to update the wetness, rain, and lightning with time
and output the final parameters.
These are variables like wetness factor, rain factor, et cetera,
which we can now access to drive visuals, audio, gameplay,
and so on.
Now that we've established the inner workings of our weather
manager, we need our materials to respond.
In other words, how do we make our assets wet?
Wetness is a huge component of weather.
When it rains, we need to see the world change.
And this means that every asset now
needs a wet state so that we can properly
blend from dry to wet.
The risks associated with creating a wet version of every asset are,
one, there are too many assets,
so requiring any extra data will add a lot of production time.
And two, our art teams all have their own asset pipelines and shaders.
We could be risking a lack of cohesion,
which would be very hard to control given our project's scale.
So our final solution was to work in parallel with asset creation.
To do this, it needed to be simple and unified as much as possible.
We also decided that it would be primarily tech artist driven
and it should work out of the box.
This means that we should be able to drag and drop assets
in the world and they should get wet properly in the rain.
Of course, some materials receive more detail and polish,
but for the simplest props or legacy assets,
wetness should work without having to revisit them.
So let's dive into our wetness implementation.
First and foremost, we split our solution into two parts
by having two wetness types, static and dynamic.
As their names imply, static wetness
is for objects that will never move,
and dynamic is for objects that will move.
Static wetness applies mostly to our object bank assets,
which includes props and structures.
Their wetness level is determined
by using the wetness factor parameter provided
by the weather manager.
We also use a wetness shadow map to mask out
wetness where appropriate.
Static wetness will be the simplest visually
and will be applied in the deferred lighting pass,
which means it will only be applied in one spot.
The pros to static wetness is clearly its simplicity
and the fact that everything can be tweaked at once.
But the con is that there is no flexibility at all.
Dynamic wetness is reserved primarily
for weapons, vehicles, and characters.
Their wetness level is calculated by raycast
to detect exposure to rain.
Their wetness also includes a bonus feature
called local wetness, which handles submersion in water.
For dynamic wetness, the visual change
will be applied in each individual shader, which
means that we can tailor the look a lot more.
The con to this is that we now have
to manage every shader that could
be used for dynamic assets.
First, let's look at the static wetness type.
The main wetness calculation we need
is the wetness shadow map, which includes objects that are,
for example, under a balcony or indoors.
This is important because we use our props a lot,
so their wetness should be accurate no matter
where level artists place them.
Since our static wetness is applied in the deferred lighting
pass, we store the wetness shadow
in our deferred shadow pass.
We then simply multiply the sample shadow
with the weather manager's wetness factor
to get the final wetness.
Let's look at a wetness shadow example.
In this scene, there are lighter, dry concrete patches
on the floor and on the wooden table as well.
But more importantly, let's look at the wetness shadow.
As you can see, it works quite well,
but there are some precision limitations, particularly
on vertical surfaces.
If you look closely at the highlighted areas,
you will see some speckled details.
This is because the cutoff was originally
a very harsh line, which we softened using dithering.
Now let's move on to how we apply
the visual of static wetness.
We first referred to photo reference
to analyze exactly what inputs we would need
and what changes they should drive.
The two visual changes that we identified as necessary
were darkening the albedo and increasing the smoothness.
Some materials like cardboard would darken,
but wouldn't get too shiny.
And materials like tiles would not darken,
but would get much shinier.
And some materials fall in between.
The key to all this was how absorbent the material was.
As a result, the input we chose was porosity.
Porosity is most directly related to albedo change.
For example, high porosity materials
like dirt, fabric, and raw wood will become saturated
and appear very dark.
On the other hand, low porosity materials
like plastic, marble, and metal will
have water pooling on the surface
rather than getting absorbed, which means that the colors
should be unchanged.
But now that we have our input, we could just use a porosity map and move on.
Except for one problem, not every material can afford an extra texture map.
That would exceed our budgets for not much reward.
So now we need a way to derive porosity whenever a porosity texture is not available.
And this is where we introduce porosity factors.
Since porosity and smoothness are properties that are conceptually connected, our solution was the following formula where the two porosity factor values are just floats that we could specify per material type.
This formula essentially generated a porosity map with all the details of the smoothness map, but with its values lying in the range that we specifically curated.
Luckily for us, our object bank shaders
already had a dropdown of material presets
with hard-coded PBR values.
All we had to do was insert our porosity factors in there.
This kept the artist workflows completely unchanged
and prevented any setup bugs.
So now that we finally have the porosity input ready,
we can look at the central apply wetness function that
is called from the deferred lighting pass.
The code can be referred to later,
but what we essentially did was darken the albedo
according to porosity, except that the material is metallic,
boost the smoothness, and note that we used porosity once more
to get even more control, and finally,
replace the specular reflectance value with that of water.
So for an approximation with very few inputs,
it would be impossible to get every material response
correct.
It was more important to judge the bigger picture rather
than individual assets.
This helped us avoid an endless loop of tweaking values.
Here's a dry versus wet comparison
for some of our materials.
Now let's look at a full scene of assets transitioning
from dry to wet.
Now let's switch gears over to dynamic wetness
used for our characters, weapons, and vehicles.
These assets all have a wetness component
that keeps track of their wetness level.
As mentioned before, characters and weapons
perform a ray cast every few frames
to check their exposure to rain.
Since vehicles are larger in size,
these actually need more than one ray cast.
When exposed to rain, dynamic assets
will increase in wetness level slowly
before they are fully wet.
And when no longer exposed, they will also dry slowly.
The per vertex local wetness calculation
handled submersion.
So if a character wades halfway into a lake, for example,
their lower half will appear wet.
Now, if we recall, the benefits of dynamic wetness
was that we could customize the way we applied wetness.
To gather our ideas, we once again
revisited real-world references, such as staring at parked cars
outside in the rain.
For character clothing, we utilized the same approach
as for our props.
We used an existing dropdown menu in our shaders,
but also added an upper limit to the final smoothness.
This was just to give us even better results for wet fabric
specifically.
Character hair was the simplest change we made.
We only used one set of porosity factors.
At the early stages of brainstorming,
we really wanted a way for hair to actually clump together
when wet, but it was too ambitious for our scope of work.
For skin, we wanted rain to be visible,
but not in a way where scrolling could look unnatural
or distracting, so we went with a subtle approach
by using a static texture,
which contained a droplets normal map and a wetness mask.
With these applied, the skin material wetness
was quickly finalized.
On our project, weapons and vehicles are closely related.
They are both gameplay elements and are seen up close
from the first person's perspective.
For this reason, we gave these assets animated rain effects,
which were applied using animated textures updated
per frame.
These effects were divided into two parts, streaks
and droplets, which were applied on vertical and horizontal
surfaces, respectively.
For the streaks, our input data was only one texture,
which packed in a streak mask, a normal map, and a height map.
The scroll mask was what actually
drove the vertical movement of the streaks, which we applied
in local space UVs.
We made sure to only apply the streaks when
the asset is oriented upright or upside down.
In the latter case, we reversed the scroll direction.
For the droplets, we supplied another texture
containing a normal map, a height map, and an ID map.
To drive the animation here, we sampled the droplets two times
to vary the pattern of droplets fading in and out
with varying timing cycles, which was
made possible with the ID.
One thing we were still missing, though,
was the tiny static droplets that
tend to build up over time on hard surfaces.
So what we did was squeeze them into the height map texture
later on.
We also made sure to use manual MIPS on the droplets texture
to reduce sparkling artifacts.
As we all know, adding a feature often
results in unexpected issues and edge cases popping up.
One issue we faced was that wetness effects were
showing up inside vehicles.
This was because our vehicles sometimes
share materials between the exterior and interior
to save on draw calls.
So the fix for this was simply to use the red vertex paint
channel as an interior mask.
Once this was painted by artists,
we could remove the interior rain effects,
except, of course, in edge cases,
such as when our convertible cars put down their tops.
Another problem came up when moving windshield wipers
were implemented by our gameplay team,
while rain streaks were added by our 3D team,
resulting in no interaction between them.
What we did was pack in a windshield gradient map
and set up the shader to mask the rain according
to the current gradient value.
We then pass this value over to gameplay to hook everything up.
This is a very small feature that we never actually planned,
but inconsistencies like this can really
take a player out of an experience very quickly,
so we were happy to add it.
For vegetation, we originally used the static wetness
approach, but this led to two very big issues.
Firstly, trunks and plants near the jungle floor
were actually getting shadowed from the rain, which
was very strange to see in nature.
And secondly, we were getting bugs explaining that the trees
were looking metallic.
And this was because the flat leaf cards were giving off
a uniform reflection of the gray sky.
And the visual was so strong that it effectively
reduced the realism of our trees by exposing
where the cards were.
To fix this, we converted vegetation over
to the dynamic wetness type, just
so that we could tailor the wetness in the shaders
independently.
Of course, this meant that there would now
no longer be any shadowing.
But 99% of the time, our trees are not hand-placed indoors,
so we went through with the swap.
In the end, we used the droplets texture
on the leaves, which finally matched reality a lot better
and fixed the reflection bugs.
Terrain was the final area to conquer.
Not only is it always in the player's point of view,
but as we can see from these photo references,
it also requires a lot more detail.
Let's first summarize very quickly
what we need for our terrain.
The primary textures used include albedo, normal,
smoothness, and now the new texture, porosity.
These properties are stored in a virtual texture atlas
that we use for the entire world.
To see more about this system, you
can refer to our past talk on terrain.
Note that roads and terrain decals
are all baked into the virtual texture atlas.
So it really is one complete system
that we needed to apply wetness to.
To make terrain wet, we actually just
used the same apply wetness function shown earlier.
The key difference now for terrain
is that the transition was changed.
We didn't want a linear fade, as we thought this
was a bit too artificial for something
with such a large surface area.
So the new transition we created was our raindrop splatter
effect, as shown in the video.
To do this, a height field simulation
was done on the GPU, which took in some simple parameters,
such as drying and spreading speed for the splatters.
The resulting animated mask was used as our custom wetness
factor.
Another thing to note was that we
chose to temporarily increase the terrain
porosity at this point just to accentuate the effect
with darker splatters.
Now that terrain has its wetness applied,
we have to turn our attention to the largest visual feature
needed to present wetness, puddles.
Puddles are also a heavily desired feature
for our direction because they would provide reflections,
which ultimately makes the environment and lighting much
more appealing.
The setup for puddles was very simple.
A puddle itself is a terrain decal,
but all it contained was an alpha gradient and a checkbox
to only write to terrain porosity.
The gradient served as a pseudo-sign distance field,
which allowed puddles to build up from the center.
We only had a few puddle decal variations,
which were scattered by our existing terrain and road
recipe systems, similar to how cracks and potholes would
be scattered.
We calculated the puddle wetness based on the terrain porosity
and the puddle factor provided by the wetness manager.
Once we had the puddle wetness, we once again just
altered the gbuffer values accordingly.
What we did was slightly blend the albedo
to a muddy puddle color and blended this evenness to 1.
For the normals, however, we initially used a flat normal,
but that now brings us to our next implementation, which
was puddle effects.
The two types of puddle effects comprised of rain impact
ripples, which are the circular ripples that
simulate rain hitting water, and wind ripples,
which are the small waves that occur when a gust of wind
pushes the puddle surface.
It would have been perfectly acceptable to have
flat, undisturbed puddles, but we really
wanted to take it one step further
and tie in our weather elements.
So we generated a tiling animated texture,
updated every frame, to be used for all of our puddles.
Our input data was a single texture
with two normal maps packed inside, one for the rain
ripples and one for the wind ripples.
The output was a single animated normal texture.
So for the rain ripples, we sampled the normal texture
twice to have two overlapping layers of flipbook animations.
These are faded in based on the weather manager's rain effects
factor, which will ensure that these ripples only appear
when it is actually raining.
For the wind ripples, we scroll the texture
based on the current wind direction and intensity.
As a result, this effect can be present
whether it is raining or not, such as when puddles are still
on the ground just after a storm.
Finally, we blend these effects together
to get the result that we use for our puddle models.
This concludes the collection of shader changes
we needed to support material wetness.
And now, Colin will take you through the technical features
that allowed us to render the weather.
Thank you, Emily.
Hi, my name is Colin Wyke.
I'm a 3D programmer at Ubisoft Toronto,
where I've been for the past five years,
and I worked on Far Cry 5 and Far Cry 6.
Now that Emily has shown us the intricacies
of the weather manager and the wetness,
the implementation of the wetness,
let's take a look at the rendering features
we needed to realize dynamic weather.
But first, let's take a look at the technical constraints
that we had.
Our game shipped on nine platforms,
spanning multiple console generations, as well as PC.
We were aiming for 4K 60 FPS on next gen
and 30 FPS on the previous gen.
This was also our largest open world to date.
And as Emily mentioned, we have a full day night cycle
in an open world,
which features indoor and outdoor environments.
And now we need to do all of this with dynamic weather.
Let's take a look at a sample scene and see how these rendering features come together
to complete the depiction of our weather states.
First, we have atmospheric scattering.
Then we have the clouds on the horizon and overhead.
Then we have volumetric fog obscuring regions and producing light shafts escaping from the
clouds.
Next, we have cue maps and reflections.
Notice how the power lines are reflected on the road.
And finally, we have rain and lightning,
which complete the scene of an intense thunderstorm.
Before we look at individual techniques,
let's start with a primer on our lighting model.
We use physically based formulas and aim
to be energy conserving as a goal.
New for Far Cry 6, we have a higher quality
multiscattering diffused BRDF and a GGX specular
BRDF with multiscattering lobe and support for area lights.
The chart on the right.
shows how we handle specific materials, but one surface type of note was translucency,
which we use for vegetation. For translucency, we wrapped the diffuse lighting for subsurface
scattering and added a second diffuse lobe to simulate light going through the surface.
You can refer to Steve McCauley's i3d talk from 2019 to learn more about these improvements.
For global illumination, we use a light probe system
where probes are placed by artists throughout the world
and baked daily to incorporate changes in the world.
GI data is stored in voxels.
We pack 13 frames of data, 11 of which
are time of day increments to give coverage
to the sky and moon.
There's one key frame for local lights,
which is mostly used at night, and one key frame
for sky occlusion.
But there's a problem.
These GI probes don't include clouds or any impact from the weather.
The solution that we had was to fade out indirect lighting
when cloud coverage is high.
This could create a problem if local lights were in the key frames
in all the key frames.
But since they're isolated to just one, we can avoid fading
artificial lights during high cloud coverage.
Additionally, urban environments tested the limits of the system.
We leaned heavily into the sparse nature of the data.
and the variable probe size to increase precision near
and within indoor environments.
We use the Brunton Sky model and Pretham Sun model
with improvements made such as Ozone.
This setup involves lookup tables calculated offline.
And previously, this was generated at runtime,
but that was very slow.
Artists create four skies, humidity 0 to 1,
turbidity 0 to 1, and we blend between these at runtime to get variation. You can check out our
GDC talk from 2015 about lighting in Far Cry 4 for early implementation of these concepts.
Here we show the effects of humidity and turbidity parameters on the optical depth
lookup table and the blended in-scattering lookup table. We blend four pairs of data
together to get our final result.
The green arrow points to the blended result for each frame,
and the red arrow points to the lookup tables
with the greatest weight for the frame's humidity and turbidity
parameters.
This is what gave us our stunning sunrises and sunsets,
which you see casting beautifully
on the edges of the clouds.
That leads us to our next subject, volumetric clouds.
So why do we want volumetric clouds?
Simply put, a skybox is not sufficient.
It has poor results in motion and is
difficult to blend between different weather states.
A skybox is also more of a backdrop
where we wanted something more grounded
and interacting with the world.
Additionally, we needed our clouds
to respond to weather and varying cloud coverage.
Our eventual solution was built on prior work as listed here.
The most important part of cloud lighting is extinction.
As light travels through a volume,
it loses energy due to the interaction
with water particles that clouds are composed of.
This extinction is determined by the Beer-Lambert law, which
we will henceforth refer to as transmittance.
Extinction consists of both absorption,
which is actually quite low for clouds, and scattering.
The light that eventually hits the eye after being scattered
is measured in terms of radiance.
Single scattering refers to when light enters a cloud
and encounters one scattering event
before traveling in the direction towards the observer.
Multi-scattering refers to when the light encounters
a near limitless number of scattering events
within the cloud before traveling in the direction
towards the observer.
Here we show the effects of single scattering on the clouds.
Next, we isolate the effects of multi-scattering on the clouds.
And finally, we have
the effect of both. Notice the greater sense of depth in the clouds.
All of these scattering events can be modeled by a phase function, which projects how much
light and in what direction it will travel after it's scattered.
In this diagram, we have the oval shape representing the phase function approximation of light
scattering after the scattering event at the blue dot.
On the right is a plot of the double-lobed Henye-Greenstein
phase function we used in our implementation.
The real phase function for clouds
would be much more complex and far too expensive
to calculate in real time.
You can reference this and other lighting code
in our bonus slides.
All of these scattering events can
be modeled by a phase function.
Let's talk about how we authored cloud data, which
represents the density of particles in the clouds
to be used for scattering techniques.
We created base and detail noise textures
containing mixes of noise types and frequencies, which we
collapsed into a single channel.
These textures are then volumetrically sampled
and blended together to create cloud shapes.
Next, we generated a weather map to be tiled in the world
and scrolled in the wind direction
from a weather manager.
This builds our XY formations of clouds and enables us to smoothly interpolate between levels of cloud coverage.
We also have a curl noise, which contains 3D vector data, which we use as an origin offset when shooting rays into the base in detail noise.
Finally, we have cirrus cloud texture, which we map hemispherically to the sky,
and cirrus horizon texture, which we map in a cylinder around the camera.
Let's put all of these together.
Here we start with a clear sky and just
our atmospheric scattering.
Then we add the cirrus hemisphere and horizon clouds.
Then we add the weather map, and you
start to see the xy shape of the cloud formations.
Then we combine the gradient texture
to define the shape of the clouds.
This cumulus gradient ended up being the only gradient
we needed to ship, although we did experiment
with other cloud types.
Then we use the base detail noise volume texture
to get the distinctive cumulus cloud shapes.
Then we use the detail noise volume texture
to erode more detail from those clouds.
And then finally, we add the curl noise texture
to get the wispy details on the edges of the clouds.
Ray marching is the process we use to draw clouds efficiently.
It involves shooting a ray from the observer
and evaluating at specified steps.
At each step, we integrate the density from that point
back to the sun or moon.
We then convert the optical depth
that is returned to transmittance,
which can then be used to approximate
single and multi-scattering.
We then integrate this transmittance along the segment
and accumulate single and multi-scattering
for the raymarch total.
We also apply the extinction to the transmittance,
so that affects later ray steps.
This general process for each pixel is as follows.
Calculate the origin from the pixel ray march, sorry,
from the pixel and ray march,
the density transmittance, optical depth and scattering,
both single and multi.
Calculate the cirrus clouds
if there is non-zero transmittance.
Use the single and multi scattering values
to calculate the radiance from the phase function.
And then finally calculate atmospheric scattering
and blend the clouds in front
using inverse transmittance as a mask.
It would be far too expensive to ray march at the full screen resolution, so we do so at half of the screen resolution.
We have a radiance and transmittance texture, as well as a history radiance and transmittance textures, which we temporally reproject from the last frame.
We fill these runtime textures using a checkerboard rendering
process.
We do a single ray march for each pixel quad
using a checkerboard offset combined with the curl noise
offset to get the ray origin.
This ray march result is single scattering, multi-scattering,
and transmittance.
We project the history into the current frame
and then gather the neighborhood and reject
based on heuristics listed.
We then use bilinear interpolation of the neighbors
and spread the result.
of the ray march over this area, fading the history over time.
The result is stored as radiance and transmittance history
that will be used for the next frame.
Particularly of note is the process
we use to store the radiance.
We encode with blue noise to help
mask the noisy artifacts inherent to ray
marching at such a lower resolution.
Notice on the right, we do a 2x blur of the blue noise,
and it converges to gray, while the white noise does not.
This looks pretty good, but there's still a problem.
We're missing shadows on the ground.
This makes it really hard to determine
where the clouds actually are.
And in reality, they're directly overhead the island.
We tried to raymarch shadows from the G-buffer,
but that was far too costly.
The solution we landed upon was projected cloud shadows.
It was a simple orthographic projection, nothing fancy.
And the resulting shadow texture will
be used later on for volumetric fog
to get light shafts from the clouds.
And here we have the clouds on the ground
and also on the water.
Next, we have the volumetric fog,
which is used for environmental height fog, as well as local
fog from the weather presets.
Our implementation uses a frustum-aligned voxel grid
presented in prior work.
We have local and global fog based on weather,
as well as local fog used for different biomes.
With the volumetric fog, light shafts are created by shadows evaluated within the cells of the volume.
And here is where we have some problems.
Here's a brief overview of the volumetric fog process.
We prepare our scene depth information in the first three steps shown
and call local fog volumes to screen tiles,
and then we'll cover the remaining steps in the following slides.
We fill the cells with a radiance.
And we do so using the local and global densities of fog and fog particles, as well as lighting from the sun, atmosphere, indirect lighting, point and spotlights.
Note that we use temporal filtering on last gen instead of the upcoming bilateral blur and this would require a history buffer that is reprojected into the current frame and faded out over time.
This requires more memory and is unfortunately,
has some ghosting artifacts, but it was a cheaper solution.
We also use the same phase function
as the volumetric clouds.
Here, you can see us filling the volume.
After we fill the cells with irradiance,
we calculate the continuous sum towards the back of the volume.
Now, we can sample any voxel for full irradiance accumulation
from the eye to the destination.
And finally, on NextGen, we do a two-stage process
of a bilateral blur in the x and y-axis.
Blurring in the x-axis outputs transposed,
and blurring in the x-axis transposes back
to the original orientation.
This optimizes reads and writes of the textures.
But there's still a problem.
On the right, you can see stair-stepping
in the light shafts, which is an artifact of sampling
the shadows.
We want this to be completely smooth,
and the bilateral filtering helps,
but it doesn't completely solve this.
The next approach we had was to blur the actual shadow maps.
And one benefit of this approach is
that it can be reused in multiple places.
Here we see the process for exponential blurred shadows.
First, we convert and downsample three near-shadow slices
from our cascade shadow map from the sun.
Then we blur the slices and downsample again.
As you can see, the result is significantly smaller
than the original, which is more optimal for quality
and performance when volumetrically sampling.
Let's take a look at a sample scene with no fog
from our weather manager.
Here we have the fog on its own with some less
than ideal artifacting.
This is the result of blurring the irradiance volume
and screen space.
It's better, but there's still artifacts
that suggest the shape of the voxels.
And finally, we enable the exponential blurred shadows.
To this point, we have not mentioned
how we actually apply the clouds.
We apply atmospherics, clouds, and fog at the same time
to save on bandwidth when writing to areas of the screen
where both are visible.
You can see here that the cloud shadows
give nice light shafts in the fog.
One final detail of our composite pass
is that we apply the final value with blue noise
at the final screen resolution.
This combined with the temporal AA post-process
further eliminates ray marching artifacts
visible in the clouds.
Now let's talk about reflections.
Reflections are crucial to completing
the visual concept of wetness.
As Emily mentioned before, we used values
from the weather system to determine what surfaces are wet.
Then we perform the process where rays are path traced
using the G-buffer positions and normals
to pixels and screen space to be reflected.
This does most of the work of reflecting objects
in the scene, such as trees, sky, and clouds
on the surface of the road, as well as the mountains shown
on the water surface.
For more information about our SSLR,
as well as our hybrid ray tracing solution,
see my colleagues Stephanie and Ihor
talk about performant reflective beauty in their talk.
But what happens when we don't have enough data
for screen space reflections, such as when we view water
at the angle shown on the right?
We need a fallback where there is no data
to drive the screen space reflections.
Our fallback comes in the form of cubemaps,
which need to show time of day changes, weather, clouds,
as shown in the sunset reflection on the cloud,
or the car on the right.
Our QMaps are generated at build time in positions determined
by artists, and they need to be relit
with our atmospheric scattering, clouds, and fog.
QMap data is baked and stored as albedo, normal, and smoothness,
as well as a lower resolution depth map.
To achieve acceptable performance, we relight just one face of the cubemap each frame, except in special cases such as cinematic camera cuts.
The process starts with generating a sky-only cubemap containing only atmospheric scattering, clouds, and fog.
Then, the sky-only cubemap for our fallback reflection is used on our ocean.
Then we were like the scene using,
sorry, the scene face using the baked cubemap data.
And finally, we composite the sky cubemap
into the relit scene cubemap,
giving the final result shown in the bottom right.
We progressively update a single face,
each frame attempting to process cubemaps
when streaming in new areas.
After the relighting process,
cubemaps need to be filtered for blurrier reflections
on rougher surfaces.
One large problem that we had was overcast lighting and weather.
Sometimes it was just, it just wasn't dark enough and it could appear flat.
We want the clouds to have contrast and we also want to have blue sky breaking through.
There were several reasons why this was happening.
One such example was our authored sky were too turbid and gray.
If you want blue in your scene, in your natural lighting, essentially, it comes from here.
But be careful.
There are otherwise, if you put too much blue,
then your whole scene will get too blue.
We also had issues with the fog washing out the image.
And to fix this, we fade fog based on cloud coverage.
We had skylighting that was too bright because the clouds never
reached the horizon in the cube map.
And there's also a blue band in our cube maps
that contributes to this brightness.
Clouds of uniform thickness.
could also wash out the image, which is why we limit the cumulus coverage to 0.8 even in a storm.
So now let's move our attention to rain. Remember, the weather system
keeps track of a rain factor that we use to drive our particle systems.
it was very apparent early on that our existing CPU particle system would not be able to produce
the number of particles that we wanted for rain. Therefore, we set out to create a GPU particle
system to render rain effects, and in doing so, we ended up with a generalized system
that supported many other types of effects as well.
Here's a brief overview of our particle system
you can refer to later.
In summary, we use compute shaders to emit, simulate,
sort and render all of the particles on the GPU
with minimal interaction with the CPU.
For any particle system, you need billboards
or geometry rendered in the right order.
Our solution was a bitonic sort to order the particles all at once.
This algorithm is massively parallel.
And while it has a higher average cost than something like a radix sort,
it was one of the lowest worst costs,
which is important in game development to avoid frame time spikes.
Once we have a set of visible particles sorted and ready to render,
we need to filter which particles need to be rendered in which paths.
We used a prefix sum algorithm to effectively eliminate
the empty space in a buffer to a sorted list
of visible particles that are just for a single pass.
This is also a highly parallelized algorithm
perfect for the GPU.
Let's go through some of the particle effects
that we had for rain.
The first particle effect we want to look at
is the rain streaks.
We experimented with refraction, blur, and reflections,
but we ultimately used transparent textures
to achieve the look of rain in photography, which was
part of our art direction.
We used two frames of variation and a normal texture
to aid in the lighting.
We recycle rain streaks in a cylinder around the player
to ensure the number of rain particles remains consistent,
regardless of how fast the camera is whooping.
To add continuous variation to the particles
throughout their lifetimes, we used a 3D noise texture
mapped to world space as turbulence.
And finally, the emission rate and direction of the rain
is determined by the wind values provided from the weather
manager.
Since we had many indoor and outdoor environments,
we needed to occlude rain where it was not plausible.
To do this, we created a rain shadow map.
that we can reference to determine if a rain shriek or splash was occluded.
This was a directional shadow set up to cover the playable area near the camera
parallel to the rain direction.
Then we stored this in our regular sunshadow atlas shown on the right.
And the colored image on the left
is used as a lookup table to convert UV space
into the atlas texture.
The rain shadow map only contains static scene elements
and is updated in sections each frame.
The next particle effect we want to talk about
is splashes that appear when rain hits
a surface near the camera.
Initially, this was driven by a GPU particle event system, which emits new particles when
a parent particle hits a surface on the depth buffer, terrain, or water.
And this means we get splash particles on any surface which is opaque, including vehicles,
characters, and weapons.
However, we didn't necessarily want these splashes to be on sides of buildings, so we
incorporated a slope factor.
Another problem that we had was we weren't getting enough splashes because not every particle we checked for collision would generate a splash.
So therefore, we spawned more particles in a volume around the camera and snapped them to the depth buffer.
For both rain streaks and splashes, we wanted pixel lighting, especially at night.
However, this was far too expensive and vertex lighting just wasn't good enough.
What we did was create a system for generating spherical harmonic light probes for each vertex
of the particle. Each of these probes calculates third-order SH coefficients and incorporates sun,
point, and spotlights. This gives us better than vertex lighting,
but is much cheaper than pixel lighting.
In addition, we can sample normal maps of particles for directional lighting and better specular highlights.
Here we see an example of a particle billboard of a sphere on the right, and it only has a diffuse and normal texture.
The next particle effect we needed was lightning bolts for our thunderstorms.
For this effect, we created a ribbon or trail system. We started by creating trails automatically
left by individual particles, but extended this by generating particles and tessellating
geometry between each particle. We call these linked emitters. Using the linked system,
we emitted particles in the cylinder moving from top to bottom, increasing the turbulence
in the center of the volume and fading out at each end. But this alone was not very realistic.
we needed to make the lightning effect the world around it.
First, we generated an omni light and placed it in the scene
so that lightning would light the environment.
Then we had to address the clouds around the lightning bolt.
We applied lightning to the clouds in the upsample pass
so that lightning doesn't end up in the history buffer
and cause ghosting.
And in order to determine where in the clouds to add light,
we use sun scattering factor that we
saved in the green channel of the cloud ray marching pass.
And our implementation functions essentially like a column light.
The next rendering feature is the ocean.
Improvements we made to the ocean rendering
were mostly to support the tropical environment.
However, ocean still needed to be affected
by weather in two ways, Beaufort level and wind direction.
Our previous screen space tessellation
had issues with shoreline waves whenever the ocean was
parallel to the view direction.
It lacked a lot of detail in the distance.
And for more information on our previous implementation,
you can see a previous GDC talk we had.
So we added a new type of tessellation to support sharp waves for weather and improve the distance
visual and support shoreline waves. The tessellation we chose for our ocean was the
i-sub-d tessellation scheme. This basic algorithm subdivides the ocean mesh into
a from the single two triangle quad down to subdivided triangles you see near the camera.
It is a progressive refinement algorithm that will subdivide into smaller triangles,
each frame as they get closer to the camera, and merge into larger ones as they get further away.
There is a performance limit on the number of operations that can be done every frame,
so we fill a buffer with keys to perform these operations.
This led to a list of a lot of empty space.
This was an area of the sub-D algorithm that we found to be unsolved, and we needed a solution to this problem.
So we used the same prefix sum algorithm from the GPU particle filtering on a different type of data.
In our world, we have fresh water that meets the ocean,
therefore we needed to blend the previous screen space tessellation to the sub-D tessellation.
To do this, we use the displacement and normals of the fresh water as input in the intersections of this tessellation type and blended in that range.
And then we use simple stencil testing to avoid redundant pixel shading of the water meshes.
The Beaufort scale is a empirical system that relates wind speed to its effect on bodies of water.
Here we show how Beaufort levels coming from the weather manager can impact the look of the water.
And this is going to be Beaufort level 0 to 4.
The Beaufort levels themselves are tuned with data
such as wind speed, amplitude, and scale,
as well as choppiness.
That was Beaufort level 1.
And here's the value.
Sorry, these values are used to drive the wave simulations,
which we will show later.
The Beaufort level also includes settings for shoreline waves,
such as amplitude, frequency, speed, steepness,
and number of waves.
The Beaufort levels include settings
for foam, which you can see accumulating
alongside the increased wave size.
And this is Beaufort level 4.
Here we have the ocean wave buffers
that we generate every frame
in order to create motion in the waves.
These buffers can be mapped back and read on the CPU
for physics calculations, ocean level,
sorry, and ocean level,
but we disabled this due to performance limits.
The world space FBM was created
to get sharp waves up close near the camera.
Using the world space buffer,
sorry, using a world space buffer
gave us the ability to generate normal directly
instead of from screen space like we did previously.
This gave us better details up close as well as in the distance with mipmapping.
Next, we used the FFT simulation for waves in the distance.
We adjusted our original implementation to respond to Beaufort level and wind parameters.
We also added the accumulation channel to the texture to create persistent white caps
on the waves.
To prevent tiling in the distance, we used the FFT buffer as a cascade at a different
scale as well as a Perlin noise wave texture.
Here we see the FFT buffer we started with.
Notice the tiling in the distance.
Then we have the FFT cascading,
the FFT cascade eliminating some of the tiling.
And finally, we have the scrolling Perlin noise texture,
which is removing the rest of the tiling.
It does a good job of simulating the effects of wind
on large patches of water in the distance.
Related to the new ocean tech was the inclusion of shoreline waves, which we needed for our
tropical beaches. We had far too many shorelines to cover, so we needed a procedural method,
which led us to choose the Gershner wave formula.
We used multiple parameters such as amplitude, speed, and foam to control the visuals.
The last rendering feature we'd like to talk about
is the tree bending, which works in conjunction
with the wind direction and magnitude coming
from the weather manager.
We improved the tree bending settings
by adding noise and bending amplitudes.
Combined with the wind values, this
gives us an exaggerated movement in the trees that reflects
our stormy weather conditions.
These settings are controlled by artists
when setting up tree trunk skeletons.
The movement could sometimes exceed the tree's bounding box,
which could be problematic because they could suddenly
be cold.
And ultimately, the feature was limited
by being plausible when zooming into the distance.
To conclude, we'd like to share some of our final thoughts
from both tech and from tech art and programming perspectives.
For me, things that really drove our success were limiting the complexity,
studying references, reducing production dependencies wherever possible, and
identifying the biggest wins so that we could focus on what sells the weather the most.
For future work, we could simplify the database further.
We could also set up an easier way
to debug and review weather without overrides confusing us.
We could make more use of wetness effects
and push our presets to be more extreme.
And lastly, we could always investigate
procedural weather patterns as opposed
to our hard-coded forecasts.
Thank you, Emily.
For rendering takeaways, as you saw, there was a lot of tech to maintain.
There were a lot of interlocking parts which needed to be polished both separately and together.
The biggest recommendation we have is to finalize these things early.
That means your data formats, data and processes.
You don't want any of these things changing too far into production.
For future work, there were several things listed,
but one thing I find most interesting
would be to use the same tessellation for both water
and terrain and use the same atlas for virtual texturing.
We would quickly like to thank the 3D teams who
worked on this feature and everyone who
helped us along the way.
As you can see, it was a collective effort.
Here's a list of references for the talk.
And with that, we'd like to close out
with a video of our final results.
All right, thank you for joining us today.
Are there any questions?
Thank you for a nice talk.
I'd like to ask about the QMAP relighting.
How did you handle shadow maps for relight QMAP?
I believe shadow map is outside and then shadow map is
assigned to main view custom areas.
Yeah, so one of the things that we noted in our problem section with overcast
lighting was that we don't have any shadowing in our cube maps.
So, yeah, we didn't have any shadowing.
That's something we'd like to add in the future. Thank you.
Hey, great talk and a lot of awesome information. Thanks for doing it.
I had a quick question. You mentioned you had some undesirable effects when in interior spaces with some of the weather
and that that led to constraints on sort of how you were working with like the fog disappearing through windows and stuff.
What sort of solutions and constrictions did that put on like your concave spaces and interior spaces?
So for our zones specifically, we did run into a lot of issues, particularly for the indoor zones.
As we mentioned, the change happened immediately. So you will see these changes if you have windows.
What we did was if there's ever an open space or an area with windows, we made another zone,
essentially, where we would solve these issues.
Hello, great talk by the way, it was very informative.
My question was related to performance.
It sounds like there was a lot of features
that you had to add to the base shaders
to get all this wetness and stuff.
Were there any challenges regarding optimization
and keeping that running at all times
to dynamically switch between things?
Yeah, so I would say optimization wise, everything had to be designed so that your cost would not increase when the weather turned on.
So like Emily talked about with dynamic wetness, we had to assume the cost with the trees to be.
wet dynamically as part of that cost.
So I guess the thing is we would have to optimize as much as possible,
but we essentially have wetness as something that could be turned on at any time.
Okay, thank you.
Awesome, thanks for the talk.
I was very curious about your static wetness specifically
because it sounded to me like you
were doing that as a deferred rendering pass instead
of complicating your materials.
And I just wanted to make sure that I understood that
correctly.
Is that true?
Yes, so basically in every shader,
we would be assigning the gbuffer properties.
And then in our deferred lighting passes
where we would assemble all these properties
and perform the lighting.
So what we did was just basically
defer our wetness solution.
So instead of applying it in every shader,
which would incur some more costs each time,
we do it all at once.
Awesome.
I just had a quick question.
Thank you for the talk, by the way, really, really informative.
I had a quick question.
You render out a rain shadow map.
I was curious.
It doesn't seem like you reuse that for wetness.
No, that was specifically just for particles.
We tried to use it for other elements in the game like vehicles.
But as we said, it only included static information
because it would be far too costly to update that every frame.
So it's really just to give us directional
directional occlusion information for particles.
So essentially, you wouldn't see rain when there was an overhang
that would block it.
whether it's indoor, outdoor, or both in and outdoor.
Thank you.