Hello.
Hi.
Thank you all for coming.
I'm happy to have this chance to do this post-mortem now after 40 years.
You may have noticed coming in that there's a little card on your seat.
This is a gift from the fine folks at Digital Eclipse who have made a wonderful interactive documentary about the making of Karateka.
So that's a Steam code so that you can play and interact with this documentary.
And if you have
a smiley face on your card.
There's three smiley faces somewhere in the room.
Then your card is even more special and valuable.
And I'll explain what that's going to be.
But everything I'm going to talk about, Karateka, you can also delve into the documentary.
And that's a great kind of parallel supplement to this talk.
So how many of you remember 1982 from your own actual memories?
How many do not remember 1982 or weren't born yet?
How many of you didn't raise your hand either time for some reason?
We'll talk about that later.
So I was 17 years old.
I was a freshman in college when I started making Karateka, and I was 20 when it shipped.
So this is the story of a game development, but it's also a growing up story.
I went from a kid to a young adult while trying to make this game, and also trying to carry a full course load at college, but I'll get to that.
At 17, I was already a somewhat seasoned Apple II game developer.
So I want to just take a minute to kind of
back up and explain what that experience was.
These comic book panels are from my new graphic novel memoir, Replay.
This is the project I've been working on for the last three years.
I won't have time to talk about it today, because we're just going to talk about Karateka.
But this book is available in the GDC bookstore in the North Hall.
And I'm going to go straight there after this talk, and I'll do a book signing.
But for now, I'm just going to use this book as a convenient source of illustrations of moments in Karateka's development.
This one shows me at age 11 and at age 12, right before the Apple II entered my life.
So as a kid, I was more into writing and drawing comics, making animated movies.
I wasn't particularly technical.
But I made money drawing caricatures at the local booth, at a local fair.
And I used that money to buy my first Apple II computer.
her
So there was equipment.
There were kids there who knew more about the equipment than I did.
And then at a certain moment, there was a TRS-80 and a Commodore PET.
And then a friend of mine got the first Apple II that I had ever seen, which was even more amazing because it could do color.
So I put all my caricature money into this purchase of an Apple II.
and when I realized that this was a machine that I could use not just to play games but also to make games which were in effect little interactive animated movies I just put all of my energy into that so these are the artifacts of my programming environment
in 1979.
Of course, in those days, there was no internet.
So to learn to program, you had to just read books, articles, and magazines like Creative Computing were very important.
There's this book by David All with program listings.
So you'd type in the code, the basic program, and then run it.
And from that, you kind of learned how BASIC worked.
Now, about this time,
something really mind-blowing.
I mean of course Space Invaders the same year had arrived in the arcade and that was like the first arcade game that I played that was actually fun.
There was pinball and there were games like Tank War sort of alongside the pinball machines in the bowling alley but Space Invaders was a craze because it was addictive and it had thumping bass and it was just immersive, it was cinematic.
Whereas the computer games at home were kind of beeps and buzzes and blocky.
But some genius
who I only knew as the name on the screen, M. Hata, programmed, somehow programmed Space Invaders for the Apple computer so I could play Space Invaders at home and it looked, it played just like the arcade game.
So this, I mean, obviously it blew me away, but what I realized was that this game wasn't programmed in BASIC, it was done some other way.
Machine language was
you know, it was hard to find out what that was or how it worked.
It wasn't fully explained in the manual, but I realized that to do a fast action arcade game with high-res graphics like this, it needed to be done in machine language.
So I spent a few years, got to the point where I could actually program
and what I did is I programmed my own version of Asteroids.
That was the game that was in the arcades after Space Invaders.
It was the next craze.
And I figured Space Invaders had been a bestseller, and whoever M. Hata was, he was probably living in a castle on a mountaintop somewhere.
And so I thought if I could publish my version of Asteroids, that would be the next hit, and I would be set.
I would be a published software author.
And I actually
finished this game and I signed a contract with Hayden book company, publisher of Sargon, the best chess game.
But unfortunately this was around the time that Atari sent letters to software publishers that were knocking off their arcade games as discs and told them you can't do that anymore.
So Hayden got cold feet and never published my Asteroids.
I was disappointed, of course, but I started programming a new game using everything that I had learned making asteroids and using those skills to program a game that was nothing like asteroids.
Yeah, that was my death bounce.
And this was sort of like the end of my five-year self-taught programming apprenticeship, because in doing Death Bounce, I mastered page flipping and programming in assembly language, all the skills that I would need to make Karateka.
This was also my first contact with Brøderbund Software, my favorite publisher, which I knew about from reading Soft Talk magazine.
I saw this ad in Softtalk.
I sent them the floppy disk, and Doug Carlston himself, one of the founders of VoterBun Software, called me back.
This was very exciting to me as a freshman in college.
The phone in the dorm room rang, and it was Doug Carlston on the other end.
But they didn't want to publish Death Bounce.
They thought it was too similar to asteroids.
Doug sent me a copy of Berterman's latest hit, Choplifter, by Dan Gorlin.
How many people here have played that?
Yeah, okay.
An amazing, incredible game with fast actions, cinematics, a scrolling background, and a helicopter that really moved and felt like a helicopter.
So, that was an inspiration.
And I should mention again, Soft Talk Magazine, because that was really my window into the industry.
Everything I knew about who was making games or what the companies were,
It was from my subscription to Softtalk, and Softtalk had a best-seller list that they published every month of the top 30 best-selling games.
So my dream kind of focused on, I want to make a game that's going to get published by Broderbund and is going to be on the Softtalk top 30, like Choplifter was at this moment.
and
It's interesting to me to look at now because it documents the whole creation of Karatek and of my early games.
And of course, the journal is handwritten.
What I used for school, for typing papers and so on, was this Smith-Corona typewriter.
The Apple II that I had in my dorm room that was taking up the entire desk was useless for that because, for one thing, it had no lowercase letters.
And also, its memory could hold the equivalent of about three pages of text.
So this was my development environment.
And this is the first mention of Karateka that I found in my journal.
And I did these sketches.
I had an idea for Karateka and for another game, which I called Animated Adventure, which I never made.
The direct inspiration for Karateka was a game called Swashbuckler by Paul Stevenson.
Anybody here?
OK.
Yeah.
I mean, that game had large sprites and it was probably the first fighting game, the first combat game I'd ever seen.
It wasn't really fully animated.
It was kind of like alternating between key frames, poses.
But I thought, if I could do a game with big sprites, like Swashbuckler, but have smooth, fast animation, like Choplifter and Space Invaders, that was kind of the idea for Karateka.
And at this point, the idea was two guys fighting on a mat.
You would score blows and earn points.
In this talk, I've taken some excerpts from a journal and put them in big type there, so you can see what I wrote at the time.
The journal reminds me that before I could make any game, I had to make the tools to make the game.
There was no Photoshop or anything like that.
to do graphics, especially in assembly language, there was nothing off the shelf.
So the first step was to write a program that would let me, using the up, down, left, and right cursor keys, turn pixels on and off on the screen to draw shapes like these, which I mocked up in my program, which I called, with great imagination, Draw.
This was my graphics utility.
And eventually I added other functionality to it, too, to cut out shapes with rectangles and be able to blast those shapes to the screen anywhere and to then play them in order to do animation.
So that summer I was, you know, creating the tools.
Anybody recognize the game that I'm playing there on the screen?
Yes!
For my man who should know.
Yeah, Bill Budge, an inspirational genius.
His games were somehow so far in advance of everybody else's.
So I included this entry in my journal because it's interesting.
Scrolling landscape and storytelling, cinematic storytelling, are hallmarks of Karateka.
But two months in, I considered that and rejected it.
And here's what I wrote in my journal.
trying to put mirror fighting in a real life setting would render the game banal even tasteless no, karate is karate and it should be played on a blue mat as I originally planned I love having a journal for many reasons but one is because it always reminds me that I'm just as articulate and convincing in defending my wrong ideas as my right ones and by the way if you're
For anybody who wants to read my whole journal of my college years, making caretake, and so forth, I've published it as a book, an e-book, and it can be downloaded from my website.
So five months in.
So I'm in school.
I'm taking a full course load.
I've decided to major in psychology.
I'm spending more time on my Apple II game development than I am on my courses, so my grades are terrible.
I'm on the verge of flunking out.
But even on the Apple II, I can't find the time to work on Karateka because I've got these two other projects.
I'm trying to improve Death Bounce in response to Broderbund's publisher feedback.
And I've taken a gig with a local startup from Yale Computer Science Department faculty to make a game to teach kids the alphabet.
And I'm actually getting paid for that.
They're going to pay me $3,000, which I can use to buy computer equipment, things like a printer and a disk drive and more memory.
So I have this project that I'm super excited about.
I think it's got more potential than anything, but I can't find the time to work on it.
Any game developers here think that sounds familiar?
I included this slide because the other thing that I'm perhaps spending even more time doing than working on all of my courses put together is going to the movies.
Yale had undergraduate film societies which on 16mm film showed movies from the past decades that I was too young to have seen the first time around and foreign films like this 1982 Hungarian film which really impressed me and so I was getting this cinematic education because I wanted to be a filmmaker too as well as wanting to be a software developer and I couldn't really decide between these two careers but at Yale at that time it was not possible to major in either of them
So I mean, there were no courses in game design.
So I was majoring in psychology.
But this is why I had, like, it was always hard for me to find time to move ahead in my development schedule.
So this is a pivotal moment.
Seven months in, I revised my vision in a way that's inspired by Choplifter.
The idea is that now there's a story.
and there's a helicopter.
This is a modern version of a Bruce Lee movie where your helicopter lands on the roof and you have to fight your way into the bad guy's headquarters and rescue your girlfriend.
This is not a screenshot, this is a mock-up that I did in
in, well, Drax.
I should say, if anybody reading the journals is confused, after I named the versions of my program Draw 1, Draw 2, Draw 3, for a really big upgrade, I incremented the final letter instead of incrementing the number.
So Draw became Drax.
And then if you read on to the Prince of Persia journals, it became Dre and Draz.
So if you ever wondered what that is, now you know.
By the way, this Bruce Lee version of Karateka had a digital timer that was ticking down.
You had to win before it ended.
I ended up not using that in the game, but I did use it in Prince of Persia a few years later.
So I was pretty handy, by now, with Drax, my software animation package with an installed user base of one.
But when I drew these sprites and tried to animate them, it came out kind of disappointingly choppy.
As good as swashbuckler maybe, but it wasn't the smooth animation that I was seeing in my mind's eye.
So it was my dad who suggested, you know, why don't you film somebody and look at the film as a reference.
and my mom was taking karate lessons at the local dojo and she recommended the karate teacher, Dennis, who agreed to do the karate moves for me.
So my parents had a Super 8 camera which I used to film Dennis doing these moves in profile.
That film, unfortunately, has been lost.
I mean, I usually try to keep stuff, as some in this room know.
But stuff disappears.
It's kind of a reminder how amazing it is that I have this much stuff left as artifacts of Karateka.
But that Super 8 film, I don't have.
I do, however, have the second Super 8 film that I shot a few months later.
And that's my dad.
My dad does not know karate.
But he's about the same size as my mom, so he put on her karate outfit and I asked him to run back and forth in the woods in front of our house in Chappaqua.
There's me directing.
And because it's pixel versions, you can't really tell when that character, that rotoscope character, stops being my dad and starts becoming Dennis.
So that's the finished game footage we're seeing there.
And there's the rotoscoped footage that I used.
My dad climbing up onto the car became climbing up a cliff.
There's me in my bathrobe being the bad guy.
And there's my sister, Emily, standing in for the princess.
Yeah, so now you may wonder, how did I go from Super 8 film to pixely animated sprites?
The Apple II obviously had no video in.
It also had no Super 8 input.
So Max Fleischer, the guy who created Popeye, actually had invented something called the rotoscope in 1915.
He used it later to make a really cool animated cartoon of Superman.
And rotoscope is basically just taking live action frames and tracing over them.
frame by frame to create the animation.
So I thought I could do the same thing if I could just find a way to trace the frames somehow into the Apple II.
And there was no scanner, there was nothing like that, but there was a tool that I thought I could adapt to this.
It was a graphics tablet called the VersaWriter.
Has anyone here ever seen one?
Yep, yep, I'm seeing hands.
Ah, GBC is amazing.
There's hardly a room on the planet where I would have seen hands go up there.
The VersaWriter was already old in 1983.
I think it shipped in 1980.
And the Apple II had these two potentiometers that were the game paddle input used to play games.
It was perfect for space invaders.
But the makers of the VersaWriter had the insight that if you used those potentiometers for a kind of a pantograph,
you would return two values from 0 to 255 that could then be transferred into X and Y coordinates.
And Roberta Williams had used this to create the graphics for her high-rise adventures.
So, I used my AB scenes earnings to buy myself a VersaWriter, and I used it to trace
the tracings of the film frames.
And this is a frame from Replay where I've kind of redrawn that.
Anybody remember the moviola?
This is what we used to, it was for home movie editing of Super 8 film, you know, cutting and hot splicing.
So I just used the screen of the moviola to trace with a pencil on little squares of vellum each frame, actually each third frame of animation to get six frames per second.
which I hoped would be enough.
And there, that was the process.
The next step, of course, was to trace the tracings with the VersaWriter.
So this was kind of an experiment that required a lot of upfront investment and expenditure.
I hoped it would work.
But until it was done, I didn't really know for sure.
So my journal records that kind of eureka moment when, after the laborious
three-step process of filming, getting the film developed, tracing, tracing the tracing, and then in Drax, pixel by pixel, cutting out these rectangles and then animating them just to see if it would look like motion.
It did.
And I mean, there was Dennis, you know, doing his punches and kicks.
It was magical.
So that was like a
very satisfying moment and a huge relief.
The next question, though, was, I mean, these frames were, they were very rough and scribbly.
That had been one of the questions in my mind, like, would the VersaWriter work for things that were so small?
Because, like, Roberto Williams' drawings were pretty big and filled the whole screen.
Here, we're really down to the, you know, the character that's 40 pixels high, so would it,
with
There's the cleaned up character.
And I was, of course, studying psychology at the time.
So this was also interesting to me in terms of just how our minds construct the illusion of movement, like when we're watching a movie, how we somehow imagine that the action is continuous and imagine that something is real, even though it isn't.
So yeah, here's this journal entry, which, as usual, I was a year off in my time estimate.
But I thought I was going to finish Karateka that summer, 1983, the summer that Return of the Jedi was released and cost me at least one day of development time.
At this point, this is during summer vacation, I changed Karateka from modern to medieval Japan, inspired partly by these woodblock prints by Hokusai, which had really strong, simple compositions.
I mean, beautiful in their own right, almost like comic book frames.
but also I thought, you know, would it adapt well to the simple graphics of the Apple II.
There you see my scribble sketches, you know, starting to block out, you know, the various moments in the game.
And this is a mock-up of the first
the first gate.
I'll get to that later.
But these features that took a few minutes to draw in Drax actually took then weeks or months to implement.
So to get that gate into the screen, into the game, I had to break it down into rectangles.
Because to cut out the whole gate as one rectangle would have been super slow to draw that huge rectangle.
So I made as few rectangles and as small as possible.
And even so, it really slows down the game once that gate comes on screen.
I mean, the Apple II was 40 bytes across.
Each byte was seven pixels, and the high bit would flip between purple and blue, or green and orange.
The odd-numbered bits were one color.
The even-numbered bits were another color.
So just the simple things like moving an object on the screen required a lot of tricks, things like pre-shifting and page flipping, lookup tables.
It took time.
This journal entry I kept, too, because it reminded me how often I played games while blasting music on the record player.
And that just somehow added the cinematic excitement that I was experiencing in my mind.
Playing Choplifter with Raiders of the Lost Ark soundtrack just made it so much better.
And the next day, I decided to put music into Karateka.
The Apple had a built-in speaker, and Woz had helpfully included a routine for playing music in the Apple II Redbook.
of
I don't have time to do the full Death Bounce post-mortem today, but with a card on your seat, you can actually play in Digital Eclipse's Making of Karateka.
You can also play Death Bounce in all its various builds, see how it evolved, and to the point where I abandoned it.
And Mike Mika has actually finished Death Bounce and updated it so that you can play it and enjoy it.
So I feel vindicated that after 40 years, Death Bounce has finally been published.
So summer 83, I didn't finish the game as I had hoped, but key elements were already in place.
It's a series of guard fights going towards a palace.
And at this point, the map ended here at the entrance to the palace.
Then there's one room.
You enter the palace.
You fight the bad guy.
There's the princess.
You win.
And I added something that, I mean, today we would call them cut scenes.
But just to kind of keep the game from being visually monotonous, after each victory, the game would cut to the villain and show him sending out the next guard, and also show the princess increasingly enthusiastic and hopeful.
And this, of course, is not a screenshot, but a Drax mock-up.
I had to cut out these pieces and put them into the game.
And you can see my little Scribble storyboard up at the top.
Overall, the game started out, the game design started out much more complicated and progressively got simpler in the course of development.
Originally I had different kinds of kicks, different kinds of punches, blows would do different amounts of damage depending on various factors, and also you could turn around and fight from one side to the other.
I had all these ideas which, partly because they were so difficult to implement, but also just because
As the game became sort of more cinematic and more of a story, like doing a detailed, authentic karate simulator became less and less a focus.
And also the controls, I wanted it all to fit onto one two-button joystick.
a lot fewer buttons than we have on today's controllers.
On this slide I put the word alpha because I think that's the point the game was at now.
That's the word we would use today.
And of course back then didn't have those stages of preconception, production, alpha, beta.
I just called it finishing.
This slide
nothing to do with games but it was at this point that, you know, just from being in college and going to films, I saw Kurosawa's Seven Samurai for the first time and it blew me away, it became my favorite film and about the same time I got this big book of Disney animation which was a wonderful story told by Disney animators, early Disney animators, about how they had developed these techniques and, you know, how they had experimented
to invent what we now call the technology and the art of animation.
This was so inspiring to me.
And I thought, computer games are also an art form in their infancy, like animation was for these guys and like silent film was 80 years before.
So all of these things that got discovered and added are still waiting to be discovered and added for computer games.
Obviously, with the Apple II, I couldn't do anything like the beauty and the emotional power of a Kurosawa film or a Disney animated movie.
But at least it sort of set the bar.
It created the intention.
And within what I could do, I wanted to try to get some emotion and human feeling into Karateka.
And this inspiration, this influence, arrived at a point when the game was already at alpha, but certain elements were still malleable.
And so I could still change things and still kind of scale up.
my ambitions notably for the storytelling aspects of the game.
This was a Christmas break, always vacations were a chance to work on the game and get a lot done in a short time because at school there were too many distractions.
The role of my friends and family as sounding boards and input, I can't overestimate it.
It was so many of the great ideas in Karateka came from people, I was showing them and building the game and they would say, oh why don't you do this?
And in this case,
You know, I was showing the game to my dad, and I don't remember exactly how he commented, but I realized that all the arcade games that were super addictive, like Asteroids and Space Invaders and Pac-Man, had a conflict of interest.
In Asteroids, whether it's Asteroids or Pac-Man, you've got a job to do, like clearing the screen of rocks or eating all the little dots.
But then there's also something that adds suspense, like the Flying Saucer in Asteroids can arrive at any moment, and then you have to
react to that.
Karateka didn't have that, it was just a series of fights.
So the idea that I came up with to add that was the hawk, that the villain would have a hawk on his shoulder and then, so you're ready for the next guard, you're gearing up for the fight, but then the hawk can arrive at any time and you sort of have to be ready for it.
And then every good game design needs a trade-off.
There can't be a dominant strategy that if you just do this, you'll win.
And in Karateka, it was the two stances, the fighting stance or the standing stance.
So the idea that if you're standing, you can run faster, but you're vulnerable.
But if you're in fighting stance, you're protected.
But then it'll take you twice as long to cross the territory and have to end up fighting twice as many guards.
That was my version of the asteroid's flying saucer.
of
instead of just holding on the screen with nothing happening, the game would cut away to show the next guard running towards you.
And it would cut back and forth.
And there was a silent film by D.W.
Griffith which had, you know, the hero is running towards the waterfall where his girlfriend is, I think, tied to an ice flow by the villain and is floating towards the waterfall.
So it's cutting back and forth between these two things with faster and faster rhythm as he's trying to save her.
So I thought, well, I mean, cross-cutting had to be tried for the first time in silent films.
Like, in the early films, like, there was no guarantee that that would work.
Like, wouldn't, you know, the audience be like, what happened to the hero?
Like, why are, wait, we're in a different place.
What's going on?
If you look at the really early silent films, they have no cross-cutting.
They just all happen in one place.
So try that for games as well.
And again, there was the question like, will it be frustrating or confusing for the player to suddenly have their controllable character disappear from the screen and they're looking at something else?
Will it be frustrating, disorienting?
But it worked.
And the thing that made it work was having a different footstep sound for the hero running and for the guards coming.
Because once those two different pitch footsteps was added, suddenly it became clear and it worked.
And it worked so well.
that
theme for the hero, a theme for the villain, and a theme for, you know, a love theme, and then the music kind of tells the story of the game as well as the visuals.
One limitation, by the way, was that you could only play one note at a time with the Apple II speaker.
And because it took all of the computer's processor power to play a note at the desired pitch, it's basically just having longer pauses before toggling that memory location, it meant that the animation on the screen had to be frozen while the note was playing.
So the cinematic animations of the game were all kind of characters striking a pose and then playing a few notes.
And then you could animate and then play another
arpeggio.
That's how we had to do it.
So it was at this point that I eliminated the map, which had taken so much work to program, but the cross-cutting worked so well that I didn't need it, and actually it was better without it, because there was a certain suspense of like, you feel like you're gaining a lot of ground, it must be getting close to the palace, and you can see that the cross-cutting is going quicker, it's taking the guards less time to reach you, but you don't know exactly how much you have left to go.
And I also like to eliminate things like meters and numbers, inventory, anything on the screen that kind of detracts from the composition.
Again, I was really inspired by Hokusai's woodblock prints, and I wanted Kerateka to have a really strong, simple, clean look so that somebody could walk into the room, and even if they weren't playing, would look at it and go, oh, and kind of be drawn to the screen.
So the map had to go.
Another really important element that I added at this point, fairly late, and again I think it was my dad who was watching and saying, I can't tell who's winning watching you fight.
And I realized that the sound alone wasn't enough, so I added these, what today would be called GUI, but I just put these comic book stars on top of the
the animation to show when a blow landed and it was like orange or blue depending on which character it hit.
So that helped make the fights a lot more readable.
You could also see where you'd gotten hit, like if it was in the head or in the middle.
Also, my journal reminds me that at this point I decided to change the title of the game and to call it Black Belt.
That didn't last too long.
So these are the frames of the climbing up cliff that I filmed my dad with the car.
And so you can sort of see how it went from the sketch, the storyboard sketch, to the Super 8, to the tracings, to the sprites.
And the Digital Eclipse product has a wonderful feature called the rotoscope theater, where you can actually
overlay these layers and you can try to see this animation in different ways and play with it yourself.
So kind of get a feeling of what that rotoscope process was like in an interactive way.
Another late but really important change.
Until now I'd been using the same animations for the hero and the enemies.
They were all the same and it was actually the same shapes just mirrored.
but
you have
suddenly you had enough time to see what the enemy was doing and react fast enough to change your next move.
Like, oh, he's hitting me, I'm going to back up.
Or he's vulnerable, now I'm going to kick.
So now, for the first time, again, so late in development, Karateka became more than just button mashing.
I mean
Sometimes features get cut.
By the way, the hawk is something that at this point I still hadn't implemented.
I was still debating in my journal that I might have to cut the hawk.
It's just going to be too much work.
There's no time to put it in, but the game needs it.
Here's one feature that I left in, even though looking back it's completely optional.
When you back up all the way to the left,
and you fall off the cliff.
I mean, I thought it was logical.
I thought it was funny.
And I always feel that every chance to use an existing game mechanic in a new way makes the game richer and more coherent and is valuable.
And in this case, Karateka had so few game mechanics, and one of them is moving from left to right.
So if you move too far to the left, it wasn't.
Anyway, I was determined to keep the falling off the cliff in, and I did.
The text prologue was also a ridiculous amount of work to program because I'm inspired obviously by Star Wars.
I was reading George Lucas's biography at the time.
It's probably what I was reading 40 years ago today in March 1984.
According to my journal, I mentioned that book.
But that text prologue, which I thought gave such a cinematic feel, I had to copy and paste each line of pixels and redraw it one line up, which is why it has that sort of choppy feel.
And it's kind of slow.
But I thought the scrolling kind of gave it a certain gravitas.
So I took the time to do that.
Anybody in this room have, yeah.
Sorry if this triggers traumatic childhood memories.
I have this sketch where I first drew the puzzle.
I actually considered several different options.
There was one that was more forgiving and one that was even more brutal, where you actually had to bow, which was impossible.
So I took that one out, which I thought was kind of a shame because there was really no use for the bowing mechanic in the game.
It's just kind of a nice optional thing that has no real function.
I mean, it's harsh because you have to start over from the beginning of the game, after having fought and won all those battles.
You could say it's a little unfair, but I thought it was logical because, you know, the princess has been waiting in this cell in the enemy's palace and suddenly the door gets kicked down and some guy in a karate suit walks up to her in fighting stance.
What's she going to do?
Of course she's going to defend herself.
The game has so few controls that switching between fighting stance and standing stance is one, so I wanted to use it.
I did find the memory to add the hawk.
At this point, as this DRAX screenshot shows me, the hawk was purple.
I wanted to use more colors, but any Apple II programmers here will immediately understand why that made my life a misery and created all kinds of ugliness.
It's that high bit.
You know, it was just better for the whole game to be orange and blue with no green and no purple.
So
This is the version, this is the point at which I put the game on a floppy disk and sent it to Brøderbund.
There's the cover letter.
I also submitted it simultaneously to Electronic Arts.
They actually didn't answer.
If they had, my life would have branched in a way I can't even fathom.
Everything would have been different.
This is me with my mom and my other sister, Linda, before I left for California.
We're at my cousin's high school graduation.
I was 19, and I would say this is the moment where my childhood ends and my life as an adult software developer begins, because this is when I took the plane to Broderbund.
Yeah, I mean,
I'm
I guess today you'd call them game designers, because they were at Vertebrand, but they were not programmers, and they weren't responsible for developing a game, and yet their input was creative.
This is where I met Danny Gorland, the creator of
Choplifter.
This is a screenshot from his next game, Airheart, which he was in the course of developing and which he showed me.
So you can imagine, like, what this meant to me, to meet these people who I had seen in the pages of Soft Talk magazine.
I had seen their names on title screens.
Now I was actually meeting them and they were talking to me like normal people.
I was completely starstruck.
One of the first things that happened was the other programmers at Birdobin kind of took me out for beer and pizza and they just
told me how I'd missed the golden age, how things had been so awesome a few years before.
You know, when Broderbund was a small company that cared about quality and cared about its employees, and now it was just a big corporation.
It was all about profits.
And so this is the 1981 article that I'd read about Broderbund that made me want to work with him in the first place.
So by 1984, you know, that first round of programmers felt that, you know, those days were gone.
I wrote in my journal
after I got back from that beer and pizza night.
Yeah, it was inevitable.
Computers aren't just for hackers and hobbyists anymore.
They're for the mass market.
So for anyone here who feels like you were just born too late and you missed the golden age, don't worry.
There will come a time when you'll talk about the game development adventures you're having now, and people will react the way that you're reacting now to this.
The Rubber Room is where Gene and Lauren kind of, Gene was a former Disney animator, and they had skills beyond anything that I had ever seen before.
Lauren animated a leopard, a running, leaping leopard that was going to be another enemy in the game to add to the villain's menagerie.
It is like, OK, he's got a hawk.
He's also got a leopard.
And Gene drew that.
That was his first draft of the palace that's at the beginning of the game.
The Rubber Room was a room that I
is
as literally the castle on the title screen as you see it.
So my main job that summer was to add two more levels so that in the top you see my submission version where the game ends right after you enter the palace.
There's just a room, you fight the bad guy, game over.
And then the bottom version where that room turns into a whole corridor.
You have to fight a whole other series of guards.
There's that gate trap at the end.
I'm sorry about that.
And then down below, there's another series of rooms and a dungeon before you get to the princess.
And I also should mention that that summer, Karate Kid came out.
It was playing in theaters.
It was a huge hit.
Everybody was talking about karate.
Karate was in the zeitgeist.
And I was terrified that, once again, I've missed the boat.
And there's going to be another Apple II karate game first.
And nobody's going to care about this one.
So that sort of added to my sense of pressure to finish the game.
So this is interesting.
This was one of the things that I learned at Berterbund, meeting real programmers for the first time, who explained to me better ways to do things that I'd never thought of before.
The lookup table, so simply, instead of calculating the position of every pixel, you just create a table of 192 values, because there's only 192 vertical lines on the screen.
And then you just look up the one you want.
That lets you animate much faster, because it's faster to look up than to calculate.
and
So we went into Doug's office and showed him this version, and said, look, we can put this on the B side of the disk.
So that if anybody accidentally puts the disk into the drive upside down, it'll be playing upside down, but they won't know what they did.
And they'll be like, what?
What?
Is it something with the computer?
And so they'll end up calling tech support.
And then Birderman tech support can say, well, sir, have you checked the disk?
because maybe the disk is upside down in the drive.
And so they, okay, thank you, that fixed it.
And who knows, maybe then they would just go on thinking that that's the way software works.
We didn't really think Doug would agree to do it, because as the CEO, he has to be aware of profits.
And the cost of goods increased, because this meant that disks were duplicated on an assembly line.
So somebody had to actually flip the disk over manually and press another button to record data on the B side of the disk, which normally was empty.
So we never thought he would agree, but he did for some reason.
Another late change of the strength bars became discrete triangles.
And again, this was another step in the direction of simplicity.
Because I had this whole system of, you know, if you do this, this way, if the enemy's doing that, the blow does more damage or less damage.
But all of that calculation, I finally realized, it's not adding to the player's enjoyment.
What does add to the enjoyment is a feeling of suspense.
That, you know, OK, I'm one hit away.
If I hit him once, I win.
Or if you're down to one hit, if he hits me once,
I'm dead.
So that suspense was more valuable than the subtleties of karate fighting.
There's so many forks in the road in the development over two or three years.
Every choice you make, there's always reasons on both sides.
But ultimately, in retrospect, I can see that I was just making the choices that would take this away from being a karate simulation and more towards being a kind of interactive movie.
At some point, you kind of realize what's the strongest thing about the game.
What's the thing that you should just double down on?
And for Care to Take It, it was that.
So package design.
In those days, they still consulted programmers about things like box copy and how the game was going to be presented.
Or maybe it was just me.
I don't know.
I just kind of annoyed the marketing people by wanting to be involved in this process.
But there's an early box sketch, as you can see, clearly inspired by the Star Wars movie posters.
and the box copy, which, again, I didn't like the marketing department's version, so I kept trying to rewrite it.
So by the time the game was finished, at some point, the summer ended, I had to go back to school.
Nobody thought I would.
Most of the Broderbund other programmers had either gone there straight out of high school, you know, and some of them actually had not finished high school because they got a programming job and that seemed more important.
So I think everybody kind of thought, ah, when September comes around, he's going to stay.
but for some reason I was determined to go back and finish university.
And so I did, although the game was not finished.
So the final touches, the copy protection and all that stuff, had to do remotely, mailing disks back and forth.
And here's a note from Roland Gustafson, the wizard who did the copy protection for all of Vertebran's games.
Copy protection was like putting a frame on a painting.
It meant that, of course, every disc was crackable.
But trying to make it uncrackable or more difficult to crack, it was like this sort of fun competition between Roland and the pirates, who would then call him from Sweden or wherever to exult in the cleverness that they had found in defeating his copy protection mechanisms.
So it was definitely serious and also good fun.
I want to see a GDC classic copy protection post-mortem.
And I want to hear Roland talk about that.
The leopard, tragically, once I was back at school, I decided that we had to cut it.
It just couldn't make it at the game.
It broke everyone's heart, including mine.
It was already animated.
Lauren did a beautiful job.
This was echoed 19 years later when we had to cut the sand griffin from Prince of Persia, the sands of time, in order to ship by Christmas.
the villains biggest monster, biggest pet that you never get to fight.
The final box art was a beautiful painting done by Thomas Blackshear, who I recently found out, thanks to Twitter, is an incredible artist.
He has an amazing body of work.
He shows at museums.
And the original painting is at the Strong Museum of Play in Rochester.
I was really lucky to have an artist of this caliber do the art for Karateka.
And that note in the middle, that was Gene Portwood, who sent me the comp by mail, of course.
It goes without no need to repeat.
There was no internet, so everything was done by mail.
So when the game shipped, I was... It was kind of remote and kind of abstract to me because I was told... I knew that it was in stores, but there were no computer stores, you know, on campus.
I'd gotten one shrink-wrapped copy in the mail.
So, you know, I was kind of just waiting to hear, like, are people playing it?
Do they like it?
Occasionally, like, I would get some mail from Brøderbund with a, you know,
a little
This was about the time that I upgraded my Smith Corona portable typewriter to a Mac, 128K Mac, which Apple had a special deal with colleges for a student discount.
So this was right about the time that computers, Macs, started to appear outside of my own dorm room.
There was now a room in the basement which had Macs and printers so you could actually use them to write papers and so forth.
Down the hall was David Pogue, who was one of the other first people to have a Mac.
And I remember we would exchange disks, fonts, things like that.
Veda Cook did the ports to the Commodore 64 and Amiga.
So for anyone who played those versions and is curious about the differences with the Apple II version, the Digital Eclipse Making of Karateka has interviews with Veda and those versions.
which really go into detail about the capabilities of those machines and the kind of the artisanal choices and craft needed to basically remake the game for a different machine that had different strengths and weaknesses.
One of the strengths of both the Atari and Commodore was that you could play real music with chords, not just one note at a time.
And so my dad reorchestrated the music to take advantage of that.
So,
Yeah, so I got my first letters from players, from people who had played Karateka and gave me feedback.
And of course, before Twitter and the internet, that meant that the person had to put the letter in an envelope, put a stamp on the envelope, and mail it to Brøderbund, who would then mail it to me at college.
And one of the first letters I got was from John Romero.
of
And so when I got home, I still had the letter.
And sure enough, with this wonderful header font and everything, it was the second fan letter I ever got.
So John says I answered him.
I hope I did.
I'm glad.
Maybe someday he'll find whatever I wrote back.
Softtalk by now, sadly, had gone out of business a few months earlier, so I never, Karateka never made it into the Softtalk top 30.
But Billboard magazine had started tracking software bestsellers.
So in April 1985, I got the amazing news that Karateka was the number one selling game.
My high school dream had been realized.
That's how I became a published game author.
And this is where my making of Karateka journal ends and becomes the making of Prince of Persia, which is another story.
So if you need to run, my website has more info behind the scenes about making Karateka video and my graphic novel replay as well, which I'm now going to, I think we have a few minutes for questions, and then I'm going to head down to the GDC bookstore
Starting at one, I'll be signing Replay, my graphic novel memoir.
This is the project that's consumed my last three years just as fully as making Karateka consumed me 40 years ago.
It's my memoir of making games in the form of a graphic novel, and it's also the story of my family, including my dad, his childhood adventures as a refugee in World War II, long before he composed the music for Karateka.
And I have to mention, if the little card that you found on your seat when you sat down has a smiley face on it, you have a free copy of Replay waiting for you at the GDC bookstore.
Thank you.
Thank you all for coming.
In 1984, you used to say, my goal for this summer is to finish Karateka.
If it is as big as I dream it might be, it should be enough to launch me to the video game world.
After 40 years, how do you feel about your sentence?
Well, I think it worked.
I think Karateka launched me into the video game world, just as I was hoping.
It's rare that we make a plan and it actually comes true.
Thank you for a very interesting talk.
I'm really inspired by your journaling skills as well.
Do you have any tips, or after so many years of journaling, how you can keep it up over the years and anything else?
Yeah, I think the key is to make it a habit.
Habits are so powerful.
You get the habit of picking up your guitar and strumming a few chords every day.
At the end of 10 years, you're an amazing guitarist.
I developed a habit of sketching, just drawing what I see around me at cafes and game developers conferences.
And somehow I learned to draw and ended up drawing this graphic novel.
With the journal, I just developed the habit that at the end of every day, I would just write a few lines.
And once it becomes a habit, it's harder to not do it than it is to do it.
And some habits can be negative, like reaching for that, whether it's the box of chocolate chip cookies that you pick up at the grocery store on your way home, or that fourth espresso.
But journaling is a really positive habit that I'm really grateful to have started it so early.
I have a question.
Since it is GDC, I feel like the technical question is warranted.
This is before hitboxes or hurtboxes or anything.
So how were you actually calculating contact?
Like, what made you decide, okay, this aspect of the sprite is the hit and this is the hurtbox.
Like, what were you doing to calculate all the interactions?
Well, the Apple II had no concept of a sprite.
Right, exactly.
So they're just pixels on the screen.
So it's really up to the programmer.
In this case, I had, like, I was tracking the
you know, the distance, you know, the X and Y coordinates of the player and the enemy so I could tell how far apart they were.
And I knew what frame of animation each one of them was on so I could say, okay, so this frame, like if you're fully extended and a kick and you're this close to the other character and they're not in one of these three poses that would qualify as a dodge, then it qualifies as a hit, therefore branch into the hit reaction.
And then, of course, as to what is the hit reaction, again, it's code.
So I could say, well, if you're in this position, like if you're in the midst of punching, then it cancels your punch.
But if you're already this far, then your blow is going to land as well.
But all of that was sort of hand-tuned and handmade, basically.
Mike actually asked at one point, when he was doing the Karateka remaster that's in the Digital Eclipse game, how exactly did the
in
I think now is probably a good time to wrap it up.
It's going to take probably a few minutes to walk over to the North Hall.
I hope some of you will come, and if you have somewhere to be and you can't come to the signing, maybe we'll run into each other later.
If you enjoy graphic novels or if you're curious, please check it out.
If you hate graphic novels and have no interest, but you feel a little bit guilty for having pirated Karateka in your childhood, and you just want to support my current creative efforts, then there's copies at the GDC bookstore.
Thank you.