My name is Ken Wong, and I'm the creative director and founder
of a little development studio called Mountains.
Our debut game, Florence, came out
on Valentine's Day last year.
I was the game's designer, and I also worked
on a lot of the art and story.
I'm excited to be here today to share with you
some of the things that I learned
from working on this game.
And there's lots of spoilers coming up,
so I hope that you've all played the game.
I have a lot to talk about, so we're probably not going to get time for questions, but I'm
going to stick around in the breakout alcove later on.
So if you want to follow up with me, just hang around and we'll go out there.
And please remember to fill out your feedback surveys afterwards.
So the plan for today, first of all I want to talk about the setup of this project, like
how it came to be.
Next, I'd like to talk about the evolution of the game idea, as it changed quite a lot
throughout the development.
Then we're going to look at some of the highlights of the narrative design and the interaction
design.
And I'd finally like to wrap up with sharing a couple of the other takeaways and lessons.
But first of all, let's talk about how this project came to be.
So five years ago, I had the great privilege of working on Monument Valley as the lead
designer for us two games.
Monument Valley is kind of an unconventional mobile game in many ways.
At 90 minutes, it's a very short game.
It looks like a puzzle game, but it's actually really easy, and it's more about the journey
than the reward at the end.
It's a quiet and a relaxing experience.
And from top to bottom we designed this game not for gamers, but for people that don't
usually play games.
And the game's success gave me confidence that mobile players want high quality experiences.
It gave me the confidence in myself as a designer and my ability to make bold design decisions.
I decided that the next challenge that I wanted to take on was starting my own studio.
So three years ago, I moved from London to Melbourne and started Mountains.
This is our producer, Kamina, myself, programmer Sam, and lead programmer Tony.
Because of the success of Monument Valley, I was able to secure a partnership with Annapurna.
And at the time, their new interactive division
had not yet released any games.
But the team included former members of Sony Santa Monica,
who published Journey, Her Hercum, and more.
When I met with them, I felt like we shared the same goals,
to make beautiful, unique games.
So we signed up.
And I faced a lot of challenges when I was starting the studio.
But fortunately, funding and publishing
were sort of taken care of from the start.
In my opinion, many of the aspects of how we made games that us two worked really well
for a certain type of game.
And I wanted to carry these over to my new studio.
Probably the most important of those is lots of iteration.
We want to make innovative games and often that means taking a couple of tries to get
something right.
Our planning includes lots of room for failure because failure helps us gain the knowledge
and understanding about the thing that we're making.
To support this process, we do a lot of user testing.
We're not especially rigorous about it,
just friends and other game developers
who come to visit the studio.
But we don't usually tell these play testers anything
about the game, and we don't tell them how to play.
They should be able to work all of this out from the game
itself, as they would as a regular customer.
And lastly, we think that short games are OK.
Like.
it's okay to make shorter experiences.
Monument Valley taught me that there are many busy people
out there that would rather have an experience
that's short but higher quality throughout.
I had hoped to keep productions short and tight
at Mountains, I actually wrote into our employee handbook
that Mountains would ship a game roughly every 12 months.
And this is how Florence actually turned out, 22 months.
The first six months could be described as a period of ideation.
We went through several different prototypes just to figure out what game we wanted to
make.
It then took a further nine months before we could play through this game, this experience
from start to finish, and to learn how to make a good chapter of Florence.
And then finally it took about seven months of revisions and polish to bring the game
to launch.
When I started Mountains, I didn't have in my mind
a particular game that I wanted to make.
Now, of course, over the years, I'd built up a long list
of game ideas that I would love to make one day,
but I didn't know which one of these would be a great fit
for this team with this budget at this time.
I think having a clear vision for what you want to make can be a great benefit,
but I also think it's valid to find the idea organically
through a process of experimentation and discussion,
and that was the case with Florence.
Instead of a game, I had a starting point, an area for investigation.
And what that was, was manipulation of 3D objects on a touch screen.
I feel like a handful of games have actually pulled this off,
including The Room and Shadowmatic.
But I wanted to see if we could find our own solution
to this particular challenge.
Our first prototype to explore this was called Parade.
Parade could probably have become a decent game.
But I realized I wanted more than just solid mechanics
and good level design.
I wanted to make an emotional impact.
So our next prototype included a more human element,
human heads.
The idea was to put human heads together
like 3D jigsaw puzzles or like Rubik's cubes.
I thought that this mechanic would allow us
to explore identity and psychology.
I thought it was pretty cool,
but once you put one human head together,
doing more heads just kind of felt like more of the same.
I still thought that the idea of 3D jigsaw puzzles had potential,
so I came up with a list of five things that we could use 3D puzzles for,
and what the team really honed in on was a game about a relationship between two people.
If I were to write out what the concept of the game was at this point,
it would be the story of a relationship told through 3D jigsaw puzzles.
We would reuse the structure of Monument Valley,
a linear series of chapters,
and each chapter would be a variation
on a 3D jigsaw puzzle as a metaphor
for the high and low moments in a relationship.
It had taken us six months just to reach this point,
and throughout this process,
Annapurna seemed to be patient.
Thanks, Hector.
They know that you need to break a lot of eggs
in order to make a hit indie omelet.
But the next nine months were a real uphill battle.
I slowly realized that my initial exploration direction of 3D manipulation was just not
going to work out.
It turns out it's really awkward to manipulate 3D objects on a touch screen, and the third
dimension actually wasn't adding anything to the storytelling.
So we switched to 2D puzzles.
They were clearer and more straightforward, but our concept of the game was becoming simpler
and simpler.
And I was wondering, is this what Anna Burna had signed up for?
We also really struggled with how to make a good chapter of Florence.
It felt like for every four ideas we had, three wouldn't work.
We'd spend two or three weeks creating a chapter prototype, only to find out that the emotion
or the story just didn't come across.
Sometimes we would have to throw away all of that code and all of that art and start
again with a different approach.
As the game designer and the founder of this young studio,
it was really disheartening work.
Everyone around me was really supportive,
but I couldn't help but feel like my team and my publisher,
they were trusting in me and I was leading them down
the path to disaster.
But gradually, we found mechanics that did work.
A few chapters started to feel really strong,
like they would actually make it into the final game.
More and more levels started to not be jigsaw puzzles at all,
and we opened ourselves to using whatever mechanic was needed
in order to tell that story beat.
We also let go of the idea of each chapter
just being one mechanic.
Instead, each chapter became like a container
that could contain one mechanic or several,
interspersed with non-interactive image panels.
The game kind of...
began to resemble a cross between WarioWare
and an interactive comic book,
and I began to use storyboards like these
to plan the chapters.
You could now describe the game
as the story of a relationship
told through different touchscreen mechanics.
In July of 2017, 15 months since we started the company,
we could finally play through the game
from start to finish in a very rough form.
It wasn't good yet.
Many of the emotional beats just didn't land,
and the ending just didn't feel right.
But I now had a complete first draft
that worked well enough that I could reflect upon it
and start improving.
And at this point, I was confident
that some version of this game would actually ship.
Let's rewind a little bit and talk about narrative.
I personally don't enjoy most narrative games.
I don't have anything against them, they're just not my cup of tea.
But sometimes not being a fan of something can be an advantage.
Game designer Zach Gage does not like word games, so he made a word game that he felt
addressed some of the genre's shortcomings.
The result is Spell Tower, which is really, really good.
So sometimes I think a skeptic or an outsider is able to find a different way of doing things,
perhaps an approach that the genre enthusiasts missed.
So when I talk about narrative in Florence, I'm really coming from the perspective of
someone who doesn't enjoy most narrative games, but who loves other forms of narrative, like
film and podcasts and all forms of visual storytelling.
One of the first tasks to do with narrative was to cast our two main characters.
My first instinct was to try and make them as blank as possible.
Maybe never give them names and no particular character traits and make them ethnically
ambiguous.
I thought at the time that making them as generic as possible would sort of make them
as relatable as possible to the widest audience.
I can't remember how we got the idea in our head to go in the opposite direction,
to make these characters very specific.
Perhaps we found it difficult to write a story for characters with no personalities,
or maybe we just realized that creating an average person is just impossible.
I found guidance on this topic in an interview with Constance Wu
about her television show Fresh Off the Boat.
She talked about the impossibility of representing all Asian Americans in just one show.
The pressure only existed because there was only one show depicting the Asian American
experience.
But what they could do was tell an authentic story about one particular Asian American
family.
By making these fictional characters specific, detailed, flawed, deep characters,
they honored the complex and the varied lives of real Asian Americans.
So, as the primary writer, I decided to fill the characters with details
from my own experiences and those of my friends and family.
Establishing our characters' ethnic backgrounds
helped anchor their identities and inform their relationship.
Like me, Florence was born in Australia
to ethnically Chinese parents who emigrated from Malaysia.
Her surname, Yo, is my mother's maiden name.
Like many of my female Asian friends,
Florence has a sometimes tense relationship
with her mother, who she only speaks to in Cantonese.
Krish, on the other hand, is Indian-Australian.
I love the idea of a dark-skinned, hairy,
creative guy being our object of desire.
Krish's family is based on the family of a Sri Lankan friend
from high school, and his surname
comes from one of our producers at Annapurna.
My South Asian friends all told me
that Krish would probably be very close to his family.
So Krish introduces Florence to his family early on in the relationship,
while Florence keeps the whole relationship a secret from her mother.
Our couple happen to be two people of color, of different faiths,
and they're the children of immigrants.
This is such a mundane, ordinary thing in Australia,
which is where we made this game, and where the game is set.
Believe it or not, we exist, we have lives, and we fall in love.
It's so normal, and yet this representation is meaningful because we're still not used
to seeing people of color and people of different faiths as the central characters in the stories
that we tell.
We received so many tweets and emails from people who played Florence, who felt themselves
represented in a video game for the first time.
Before I was a game designer, I was an artist, illustrator, and art director.
Telling stories with pictures is my native language.
That background really shaped how I designed games, and you can see that influence on Monument
Valley and also in Florence.
Both games use almost no words, but make heavy use of visual composition, color, and music.
It took us a long time to find the Florence art style.
Here's a couple of experiments that happened along the way.
In the one on the left, I'm definitely
trying too hard to come up with a really unique art
style for this game.
The other two are a bit more subtle,
but I still don't think they quite set
the right tone for the story.
I'm actually not very good at drawing the same thing over and over again,
but, especially characters.
I've never drawn a comic longer than a single page,
so it wasn't immediately obvious to me that we should borrow
from the language of comic books.
But once we went down that direction, it totally made sense.
I took visual cues from slice-of-life graphic novels and zines.
These would often feature incredibly personal narratives
and would often be printed with limited colors.
The resulting art style is simple and ordinary
and it's kind of rough around the edges,
but it brings a sense of vulnerability and authenticity.
These two mock-up posters were some of the first images
that I drew in what became the final art style.
When I drew the poster on the right, I was like,
that's it, that's the hero image of the game.
No other game looks like that,
and I would love to see that as the banner
on the App Store one day.
Another consideration with the art style
was that many people would be playing this game
on their phones.
A traditional comic page with like five or six panels
on one page, that would feel quite cluttered
in this context.
and on this size of screen.
So our comic strip sequences
are almost all single width panels.
They scroll up and down, more like a website
or like a social media feed than a comic book.
And this lets people focus on one image at a time.
Music, of course, plays a huge part in the story.
And we were very fortunate to have Kevin Penkin on
as our composer.
I could spend this whole talk on all the amazing things that his score does, but it's probably
best that Kevin give that talk another time.
Today I just want to touch on one aspect of the music, and that's that we realised that
the two main instruments could act as the voices for the characters.
We knew quite early on that Krish would play an instrument, which ended up being a cello.
One of Kevin's first assignments was to write Krish's theme,
which is the music that you hear when Florence comes across him in the street.
You only hear the cello when Krish is around or when Florence is thinking of Krish.
Florence also has a theme, which actually comes from Kevin's audition track for this project.
It's played on piano, so the piano often serves as the voice for Florence.
When it came time to write music for the character's first argument,
I asked Kevin to just write a cello and a piano having an argument,
and it just worked perfectly.
A few months before launch, we had two curveballs
to do with the narrative that we had to deal with.
The first was a conversation that we had about gender and sexuality.
Anna Perna asked us if we would consider allowing the player to play as either a male or female
version of the main character.
And the player would also be able to pick the gender of the love interest.
Only the art assets would change, and the story would otherwise remain completely identical.
Creating two different sets of assets
for these two characters would extend production,
so Annapurna was prepared to increase the budget.
And I was a bit shocked.
I didn't expect a publisher to ever propose
increasing the scope and budget of our game.
Internally at Mountains, we had discussed
the topic of gender at the start of the project.
Arriving at a female protagonist and a male love interest
was the result of many different considerations.
For example, as the primary rider, I wanted to ride a straight couple because those are
the experiences that I know firsthand.
We liked having a female point of view character to add to the underrepresented field of female
protagonists in games, and we liked the idea of a male person of color as the love interest
as they're also underrepresented, and it helped us avoid the trope of the manic pixie dream
girl.
But Anna Perna's suggestion asked us to revisit
all of these decisions.
I think there's definitely a game to be made
in the same mold as Florence, but with gender options.
Is that a better game?
Does it tell a better story?
I don't know.
Every member of our team cares about representation,
but as the designer, I'm not sure if making this change
late in the game would have been
the best way to achieve that.
In the end, I made the call to stick with the path that we were on,
and only a few months away from completing.
I had really come to know these two characters,
and I really wanted to see their story through to the end.
The second late development was the rewriting of the ending.
Since the beginning of development, the story had always been about two people coming together,
breaking apart, and then, 30 years later, meeting again by chance.
And we even prototyped this ending.
I wrote this version of the story when I was recovering from a really difficult breakup.
But over the ensuing year of development, I'd gotten to know Florence really well.
She felt like a real person to me.
and I really wanted the best for her.
Slowly, I understood what all of my teammates
and collaborators had been pushing for this whole time.
Florence's story shouldn't end
with a chance reunion with Krish,
and it shouldn't end with her meeting someone else,
someone new either.
All this time, I had told Florence to let go,
but then I always ended up leading her back to Krish.
It turns out I was the one who needed to let go,
to let go of this ending that had been so personal to me
that I once thought was the reason that I wanted to tell a story at all.
This part of Florence's life needed to end as it began,
with Florence by herself.
But because of the time that she shared with this really amazing person,
she became more confident, more independent, and more fulfilled.
So how do we say goodbye to Krish?
I really thought that was important.
The last time that we saw him, he was packing up his things on a rainy day, and he left
his toothbrush behind.
The worst.
So I wrote this tiny little goodbye.
As Florence is clearing out her office, ready for the next stage in her life, she finds
an old photo of Krish.
Florence smiles, it's a happy memory.
We hear cello for the final time.
She puts the photo in the box with the rest of her images,
the rest of her things from her past, and we close the lid.
So let's move on to the final way
in which Florence tells a story, interaction design.
In general, I think there are some ideas of what a video game is that could be summarized
as traditionalist.
I think a traditionalist might say that game mechanics should all be about challenge and
skill, that games should be about choice and agency, and that games should last a few hours
long.
That doesn't come from any particular manifesto or anything, that's just my impression.
But I think that a lot of what being a creative and an artist
and a game designer is about is questioning assumptions
and searching for new perspectives.
Some of the insights that informed Florence
are that game mechanics can be instead used
to evoke a feeling or an idea, that we
can use whatever game mechanic we need in order
to tell the story, and that games can be whatever length
they need to be.
Many of the games that have helped me question
what a game is and what effect game mechanics have on us
include Passage, Papers, Please, Gone Home, and Everything.
On this project, I was particularly inspired
by the vignette games of Jenny Jiaoxia and Nina Freeman.
Jenny's game, Consume Me, is coming out soon.
And remember, if you think it looks a bit like Florence,
it was her work that inspired ours,
and not the other way around.
So let's take a look at how some of the mechanics
of Florence work.
None of the mechanics are what you would call deep
from a systemic point of view, but that's not the point.
In vignette games, mechanics are often about evoking a feeling or an idea,
or perhaps bringing up similar memories that the player has,
and thereby creating an empathetic connection with the character.
A great example is the toothbrush interaction.
It's such a simple action, but it says so many things at once.
The interaction is not difficult at all, but it's repetitive enough to suggest
monotonous work. The presence of a progress bar
signifies gamification, as if Florence is living life
for the sake of arbitrary completion.
The fact that of all the moments in Florence's day,
we're featuring her brushing her teeth,
say something about how exciting her life is at this point.
Many of the interactions in the game
are simplifications of what we do in real life,
perhaps even the things that we do on mobile devices.
So the game is using the player's familiarity
with mobile interfaces to tell a story
while also creating a connection
between the player and Florence.
Other interactions in Florence are more abstract
or are activities that are metaphors
for what's going on emotionally with the characters.
One example of that is the chapter called Fragments.
The player has to tear up an image of Krish piece by piece.
But it's a metaphor for Florence losing Krish from her life.
This is where the touch screen can be so powerful,
the player is actually having to tear Krish apart
with their bare hands.
In this chapter, we wanted to convey
that Florence is really nervous for her first date with Krish.
Forming a speech bubble out of puzzle pieces
requires just enough brain power and just enough time
to make the player feel like it's taking effort for Florence
to think of the right words to say to Krish.
The resulting speech bubble itself
is a colored shape with no words in it.
And this suggests to the player that what's important
is not what was said, but what it took to say it.
Krish, on the other hand, responds pretty quick,
as if he's relaxed and confident.
As Florence and Krish go on more dates,
the puzzles get easier,
and the player applying the metaphor
understands that Florence is becoming
more comfortable around this person,
and the words are flowing easier.
We found that revisiting mechanics
was a great way to show that the characters
or the relationship had undergone change.
Here we see a different take on the speech bubble mechanic
when Florence and Krish are having their first big argument.
We're still creating speech bubbles out of pieces,
but the shape of the pieces and the way the characters
talk over each other produce a very different feeling.
The final two chapters of the game
are sort of a best of compilation
of all the mechanics from the rest of the game.
It's as if Florence and the player
are using everything that they learned along the way
in order to complete this phase of Florence's life.
Finally, I'd like to talk about some of the takeaways
I have from working on this project.
I'm very proud of what Our Little Game accomplished.
The success of Florence was enough for Mountains to secure new projects, so Our Little Studio
will continue to exist and to grow, and for that I'm really, really grateful.
But despite all of the awards that it's won and all the wonderful reviews and word of
mouth, thank you all, Florence only did sort of okay.
It made its money back, and then some.
We could afford to raise our salaries a little
and do a little sponsorship, but we're not at the point yet
where we can completely fund our next project by ourselves.
It makes me wonder how premium games fare
when they don't win Apple Design Awards
or when they don't get constant featuring on the App Store.
I think if your business plan is based around
premium mobile, you're up for a really tough challenge.
I don't know if that's any more challenging
than standing out in the free-to-play crowd.
Some industry commentators would say that Game Pass style
subscriptions will be the next big thing.
But we'll have to wait and see who that benefits.
A couple of stats.
iOS makes up 88% of sales and Android 12%.
But know that Florence is not yet out on Android in China.
Speaking of China, China is our biggest market on iOS by far,
over 40%.
That's almost double the next biggest country by sales,
which is the US.
So China is a massive and important market.
Just a couple of anecdotal player patterns very briefly.
We didn't expect that couples would play this game together,
but we saw that happen with our demo,
and then saw that continue on with the full experience.
We heard of people that played Florence just after a breakup,
and that sounds really painful to me,
but we heard that it helps the healing process.
Some parents told us that their kids played Florence,
which is not something that I expected.
Like, I thought that it would be
a nostalgic look back on dating,
and I didn't really anticipate the effect of people,
you know, playing Florence
before they had started having relationships.
Many people told us that they played Florence on the plane
or in public transport, and they usually shared this
because the game made them cry.
And I couldn't help but notice that a lot of these stories
about crying came from men.
And I think maybe this would surprise some people
because they'd think that Florence was sort of a game
more targeted towards women, but I think this signifies
that men are actually more than open to having
emotional experiences in games and sharing that.
Oh yeah, men cry too.
Almost out of time, this is not Florence.
This is A Gay's Life, a free web game
made by Huang Gao Le, a 27-year-old developer
from China.
A Gay's Life borrows heavily from Florence's art style
and mechanics, but it tells its own story,
that of a man discovering his sexuality
against the backdrop of Chinese family and social dynamics
based on Huang's own experiences.
Unlike Florence, it introduces the element of choice
and makes heavy use of text.
It's only available in Chinese and has been played
more than 1.6 million times.
This is the greatest impact that I could have hoped for,
for someone with less privilege and resources than us
to be able to benefit from our work
and use it to tell their own story.
I don't feel particularly possessive over any of the techniques or insights that I've
discussed today.
So if there's anything in Florence that you feel is useful for you and your work, please
feel free to borrow, adapt, or steal.
Right now, games could use a wider variety of stories from a wider range of creators,
and we couldn't be happier if Florence helps people achieve that.
Thank you very much.