Hello friends, I'm Alexander Swords. Welcome to my home office here in Melbourne, Australia,
giving this presentation under very different circumstances to what I had intended.
The session is The Forest Paths Method for Accessible Narrative Design. I'll just clarify
straight off the bat, the accessible part of that is about the fact that it uses plain
language, it uses simple definitions, and the method is designed to be accessible.
accessed by the entire team.
So to clarify your own ideas
and help you collaborate with the rest of your team.
This is me.
I'm not gonna go through everything.
I've got qualifications.
I've done stuff.
The thing that I'm really proud about though is the Forest Paths method.
It's an accumulation of many many years working across a bunch of different mediums.
Basically it's come from a design philosophy of making sure that the power of all stories is recognized in this process.
It's plain language.
It's accessible, which means it's also very practical.
It's not high level at all.
It will literally help you understand how to create the drama that you need to,
to connect with the audience that you'd like to connect with.
It is collaborative at its core,
and it helps you integrate considerations that are wider
than just the narrative design.
So obviously your narrative design impacts the rest of the game development process,
but it also impacts a whole bunch of other things
like streamers, marketing, accessibility, and so on.
You'll see here that I'm starting with a blank spreadsheet.
I think sometimes it's very good for examples to begin at the very beginning.
So literally all I've done is opened up this spreadsheet and renamed it.
You'll see at the top left there it's called High Concept Formula.
You'll have to excuse me, I'm going to look at this screen because it's bigger.
This is also the benefit of doing this talk from my home office.
So we've got a spreadsheet here and for the first step
in what we're trying to do this is probably one of the
the best ways of starting using a high concept formula. Again this
is about making sure you're asking yourself the
right questions more than anything else but it's really super simple.
You have the player which isn't the player
has a character
performs activities. You'll see that these are variables, and you're probably guessing these as we go along,
that manage resources to overcome obstacles.
goal, whatever that might be. So these are the elements that need to go into a game.
Super simple stuff. This is probably a really good place to, you know, if you're starting
ideas for the first time, you're just brainstorming. A really good way of kind of getting your ideas
out just in a table with you and your team and try and work out the kind of game that you're
trying to make.
I am going to use an example that I've been thinking about,
which is going to be a bit more of a mature game, a bit of a game for
adults, and trying to get away from
conflict, so to provide a bit of a
slightly different example to what you might expect for say a shooter or
a horror game or something like that. So basically the idea that I had was
that this is about an old man
who lives in the city and as unfortunately what happens sometimes is
with old people they end up being the last people in their friendship circle
to to be alive unfortunately they last
longer than everyone else important to them and so you know there's
a lot of isolation that comes with that so
the idea of this game is that this old old person is is taking a journey
back home to try and reconnect with their roots
essentially because that's where they made all their lifelong friends and so
they want to return back there
And the general kind of gist, I mean the impetus for this idea too was that I wanted to create a game about
it is about the friends we make along the way, so hopefully we'll get to a narrative design
which achieves that before I finish this video. And I also will say like
My goal for today's example too is to just get the narrative design to a point where we could come up with a really good solid place to go forward designing a vertical slice.
Because it is a new idea and the role playing kind of aspect of this would be that we're a studio maybe, or I'm playing as a solid developer who's coming up with an idea maybe to go for funding or maybe to pitch to the team.
So vertical slice is what we're aiming for.
So, the character is an old man
The activities that I've been thinking of
are, you know, so where we want to... I'm going to set it in Australia so we can
travel across Australia
typing skills ahoy and then making friends
which you know I guess is you know it's about relationships I guess you know so
resources so time is a factor maybe fuel is a factor and maintenance of the
vehicle maintenance
maintenance... 10 amps? maintenance of the vehicle
I don't know if that's how you spell maintenance
anyway um uh the obstacles uh distance
loneliness
um i feel like in resources we do put in relationships here
I think, because you know we're managing them. It's something that we're managing
and hopefully we'll get something out of it.
And the goal is to return to where we grew up.
Cool. So that's a pitch for a game, right?
So, you know, the player is an old man
who's traveling across Australia,
maybe making friends as a way of managing time and fuel
and the maintenance of their car,
you know, through these relationships,
overcoming distance and loneliness along the way,
hopefully, you know, to return to where he grew up.
I'm very comfortable with that.
as a pitch. This would be something that I'd automatically be able to take to the team
to start getting their ideas about whether all of these aspects
or elements we want in the game as they are
and start those conversations about
mechanics in particular. This feels a little bit
kind of walking simulator
so far and that's probably where I'm going to
take it from this point forward.
So I have just jumped forward a little bit to save you watching me doing some of the tedious stuff.
Basically what I've done is created a matrix here and set up what we need to go forward but
what we're going to do next though is this is exactly what we just did, our high concept formula.
I've stuck the word can in front of it, I put the question at the end of it and that
now makes it a dramatic question. So can the old man travel across Australia making friends?
managing time, fuel, maintenance and relationships
to overcome distance and loneliness
to return to where he grew up.
Those of you who are familiar with the dramatic question,
there's no surprises there.
Those of you who aren't familiar,
just have a quick Google.
It's not very deep to understand,
although the use of it can be super deep.
But the next thing we want to do is have a look at this matrix.
Now, simply put, from left to right is time progressing through the game, through the
gameplay experience.
And then each of these are sequences, and each of these sequences are broken up into
– I've got five different elements.
These elements that I've got here are from the variables that we've got from the high
concept formula.
But these elements should change depending on what genre you're doing, what type of game
you're playing.
you know, what questions you're trying to answer for yourself.
And so, you know, they might even change over the process of doing this.
But the first thing we will do is across the top here we have,
so this is the dramatic question.
This is where we want the answers to that dramatic question.
So what I want to do though is, this is feeling like a bit of a walking simulator, so the answers
to these questions are either yes or no, and because of the genre of walking simulators,
generally a yes is the player feels like that they can move forward through the experience
without any kind of really hard pushback.
Obviously a no is the opposite of that. A no is when the player feels like they can't move forward without a definitive
gate being opened or you know an obstacle being overcome.
But for us it's a walk...
of to feel like there's any two impediment here. You know these resources shouldn't be,
shouldn't ever completely deplete. They should only be concerns. These obstacles should never
be absolute at any point for most of the experience. I want to mix things up a little bit though.
And we're going to have a no here.
And the reason why I want a no is because he wants to return to where he grew up.
This is a very tangible goal, but I kind of want to say no to achieving that tangible goal
so that we can explore what intangible goals that he might achieve along the way.
So.
you know this is a case of you know usually in cinema terms they call it you know
um not getting what you want but getting what you need in this case he wants to
return to where he grew up but i want to explore what he needs
and you know this is a game that i want to be about the friends we make along
the way so in this case here what he wants is to return to where he grew up
but what he needs to do is make friends and so that's the experience that i want
to put the player through
So that's going to be a no at that point there. I don't know what that looks like yet.
The good thing about this is, you know, I've got drama there and it's just an intention.
I don't even know what that looks like yet and I don't need to.
Also, when you're doing this sort of stuff, it's perfectly fine to start with intention
and then work your way into detail. That's perfectly fine.
And that should be what your process is.
The other cool thing about this is that if you want to, you can get your whole team
in front of a screen straight away with this blank document.
and start working with it
and then maybe do some analysis along the way or just start with intention
you know that sort of thing. The other thing that I think I'm going to do
because it is we're in walking simulator kind of territory is
I don't think that obstacles are so important as
themes are
You know, because it's about making friends and doing that, you know, there's different
themes that kind of arise from that.
Also too, you know, he's in a very interesting situation being an older person facing isolation.
There's some themes there that, you know, we want to investigate.
The other issue is with walking simulators, you know, theme is at the heart of those,
you know, so we want to see that reflected in the design that we're doing as well.
I think the other thing too is, you know, because there's a very simple progression
here, there's not going to be too much of a difference in goals going forward.
So I don't really feel like it's something that we need to track through this process.
So, you know, I'm going to put something, I'm going to put intended audience there.
instead. Now part of the reason for that is, you know, we're making this as a game
for an older audience or for a game for an audience rather who's really
interested in engaging with a specific style of story and this kind of
narrative content so
I'm going to draw a line underneath it just to mark it as this element is not a narrative design element
it's a functional element, it's not meant to necessarily impact on anything above it
but anything above it, that line, will impact what is below it
and I think it's important to kind of keep in mind
you know, who our intended audience is and what effect our narrative design is going to have them
through this process.
So, yeah, the other thing that I want to do straight up as well
So we do have, in the Forest Paths method, I do have dramatic forces
And these are, they're broken up into two groups
One is dramatic forces over time and the other is between elements
And we'll start with over time
Because usually what you want for a cohesive narrative design
Is some dramatic force being applied that starts at the beginning of the game
and ends at the end of the game.
And that's, a dramatic force is basically
a way of understanding the relationship
between what the player is expecting
and the drama that's being introduced
by what is unexpected.
And so, you know, straight away,
what I want here is there's going to be a transformation
here.
And so transformations are essentially when any element in your narrative design
is having its context change. It's being transformed
as the context around it is being changed or the definition of it is being
changed. So you know typically the example that he
uses, you know, if you have a warrior who's just a warrior and they think
that they're just fighting and all of a sudden it turns out that
they're a prince or a princess, you know, the context of that character
is changed.
there is a transformation there from just warrior to warrior prince or warrior princess
in that kind of instance. This transformation though is, you know, we want the story to go from
traveling home to making friends along the way, which so I guess what we what we want is, you
know, it's not about the
and but about the journey. So we're changing the context of the story here.
There's a transformation of what this story should mean,
that it's, you know, it's not about reaching the goal, it's about the journey
along the way.
Yeah, put in notes for yourself. I have a terrible memory.
I designed this entire system because I have a really terrible memory.
Why should I remember this sort of stuff when I can just create a system?
to understand these relationships that come with the diagram.
And obviously what's good about this is that other people can see this
and be able to follow it with you.
So yeah, I'm not sure that there are any...
Yeah, I would say the other dramatic force over time is a reversal.
And we're not really sure what it is yet,
but there's definitely a reversal here from a yes to no.
Reversal of fortune.
This is the traditional definition of what a reversal is, a reversal of fortune.
I've expanded that definition to include all reversals where you have one element
that changes from one state to its opposite. In this case it reflects the traditional understanding
of fortune going from good to too bad, but there's no reason why it couldn't be from...
you know if it's art style from black to white if it's you know if it's time from night to day
you know that sort of thing is a reversal and then we've got probably should start looking at
any kind of low-hanging fruit that we have as well i mean we don't really have any kind of
story there but we can just kind of look at things and go okay you know begins the
begins the journey there. I'm not going to put ends the journey
there because we want this transformation
and this is a no so and we still don't know what that means yet
but maybe then you know what we can kind of do is actually just look at
activities and help activities decide for us you know what the story
will be and different things. So you know this is pretty simple so
there's two activities here traveling across Australia and making friends.
So why don't we just put travel with a capital because I'm a stickler for things like that.
Making friends.
Travel. Travel. Travel.
I'm going to leave that one blank because we don't know what we're doing there.
And this one's going to be making friends.
Cool, great, we already have a really nice structure there as well
so you know there's a rhythm there the player will be able to
identify and I think you know that's good there's some
structure there that the player will kind of understand about
Resources, so basically I think what's going on here is, you know, the other elements that
we've got here are probably going to want to inform us before we even really want to think about
what the actual story is, although, you know, they need to stop to make friends.
Yeah.
Cool. Okay, so what we might want to do then too is actually now just kind of work out what
resources we'll want to use and when. I feel like, you know, at the beginning it's going to be all good
and at the end, you know...
bad maybe this is a work in progress and then what we've got along the way well
what we could probably do is just go you know so let's just make a fuel thing
here and a maintenance thing
here and then a time thing here. Great, awesome, we've ticked off. So you know this isn't to say
that these resources aren't necessarily an issue like in any other point of the narrative design
but it just means in these particular sequences this is what we're concentrating on. In sequence
two it's going to be about the player having to stop to manage fuel and the way they're going
to do that is by making friends with someone. That seems pretty simple.
What we might do... Is there a theme there? Well, from the beginning we know that isolation is an
issue. That's something that we want to explore from the beginning. And, you know, the evolution
of that, I guess, if they're making friends or talking to someone, is, you know, the time left.
alive and what to do with it, I think. I mean the cool thing about this is we can
just kind of drop in random ideas here.
Shouldn't be touching my face, coronavirus.
Drop ideas, like just ideas of things that we do want to
to work with here, and then just fold them in
at this point. So maintenance here, I mean I feel like...
you know losing health as an older person fits really nicely with maintenance being
um the issue there so and i guess fuel does too how much fuel is left in the tank how much time
is left alive how much maintenance uh you know maintenance versus losing health you know there's
so what i'm going to do this so this is another dramatic force at play here where you have um
you have two elements that have a relationship that cause you know that that create drama in
this case it's a it's a synergy
between resources and the themes.
Fuel equals time back drive.
And it's important to note these sorts of things.
I mean, this one's basically just for yourself
as a narrative designer, but I guess,
but even in this kind of scenario,
if I am the narrative designer,
but it ends up being handed over to a writer,
and you know, the writer knows that this is the gold.
This is, we want something really special
out of this relationship between resources and themes.
in this case particularly being fuel and time left alive.
So yeah, and maintenance and losing health, you know, this is probably another synergy.
I'm not even going to talk about the type of note there. We just know that that resource maintenance and losing health is a good synergy there.
Yeah, okay, so I don't know about the last one yet. And that's...
Okay, I think we can leave that there. So do we have enough for a story?
Intended audience. Yeah, so what I'm looking for here is like what impact it will have on
the intended audience. And I think beginning the journey, travel, all good, isolation, you know.
I want there to be a sense of hope for the intended audience.
So, you know, it can't be all doom and gloom.
And I'm hoping that, you know, the beginning of journey, the traveling,
everything is all good at the beginning, you know.
So, you know, I want even though this isolation here is the thing,
you know, they're doing some kind of decisive action.
you know, so for the intended audience, that's hopefully what they'll be excited about at the beginning of the game
and what they'll kind of engage with.
So, the...
We probably should look at the ending.
And I feel like we're getting a long way ahead
with some of the other stuff
without having the ending kind of nailed down
and it's probably time to do so.
So our clue here at the moment that we've got
is that things are all kind of all bad
in terms of the car, in terms of,
that's the resources that we're managing here.
But I can't help but think.
that if this is a no, they're not necessarily getting to return to where they grew up.
That there is, you know, there's some kind of synergy here.
even though I don't know what that means yet, although I've got a kind of a sense of where that might be going.
The other issue is we have another dramatic force over time here
between this sequence in the resources and this sequence in the resources as well.
There is an escalation here where maintenance is a problem.
you know, I guess I'm making the decision to make this a dramatic force, right?
This is, we're in the second half of the game here, we want some kind of drama in
that sense of impending drama, and that can come from an escalation.
car suffering, to car dead.
These are my notes,
they don't need to be the best writing in the world.
I'm gonna put a blue on that to let me know.
So that's another dramatic force over time escalation.
Now this isn't progression,
progression doesn't necessarily need to be noted on here.
Any escalation is something,
an increase that is beyond what the player expects
in whatever element you're dealing with.
So we're dealing with resources here.
So it looks like if you've got this escalation here leading towards the ending,
the ending is that the car is all bad. So that means it stops, you know, car is dead.
You know, I feel like
that is
Yeah, all bad. Car is towed. Time is the resource here being managed because car isn't.
functioning, you know, so that's where the sense of urgency is. I'm going to pull this
escalation back to this one here because the car's not functioning here. So, you know,
we've got this escalation. It's still a car suffering two, car dead.
but it's just happening one sequence beforehand. So now we need to work out
how we're going to get this character from
wherever they've stopped here
to their destination.
I guess where we're going with this is that he's not going to survive this journey, unfortunately.
So, old man passes away in a car.
To explain this, because the car isn't functioning either.
Car towed to the town where he grew up.
So yeah, so you know in this case then we've got the new friend responsible
you know for returning old man and car to the town where he grew up.
That's a really heavy ending but you know a really powerful one.
and I think that ends up really heightening this sense of,
it is not about the journey,
because unfortunately he didn't survive the journey,
but he did make friends along the way.
So it's definitely a case of him
not necessarily getting what he wanted,
but he did get what he needed in that.
It does obviously pose a bit of a problem for what the player is doing here,
but it's not necessarily a problem.
But the player controls new friend.
perhaps. So what I might do actually is that the car is towed
the car is going to be towed to the town. Old man gets
lift with new friend but old man
passes on the final leg.
leg as well. So, you know, this would be a case of the player is driving the old man
back to, along this final leg, back to the old town and then he passes along the way.
And there's something I really like about that. It means that, you know, it's a bit of a shift for the players' perspective because now they're playing this new friend who they've possibly never met before.
But there's also something really lovely to be had there about this new friend being responsible and so this player being responsible for the final moments of this old man that they've had this really kind of strong relationship with along the way.
But we've only got a few minutes left and we're aiming for a vertical slice.
So what we probably want to do here is have
something kind of worked out, at least two sequences where we have, you know,
something kind of fleshed out a bit better for a vertical slice experience.
What I probably want to do is have.
a travel sequence and a conversation sequence in this. So you know what we probably want to do
is, you know, this is probably going to be our vertical experience.
that we're aiming for. So we just now we just need to make sure that this is the
section that we've got complete to hand over
for the rest of the team. So traveling
talking to themselves while driving
responding to
music they're listening to. Cool, so that's... look, we're putting nostalgia there. The nostalgia
from the themes is going to be prompted by the music they're listening to. Traveling...
branching dialogue. So the player gets to navigate, I guess, the internal thought process
of the old man making friends.
through dialogue as well.
There doesn't need to be any trade.
There doesn't need to be any kind of inventory management.
And I don't want this to be about conflict either.
They have to stop,
stops to get something minor.
Something minor.
Actually, stop to get.
noise investigated so you know there's a bit of a foreshadowing there about the car is kind of on
its on its last legs um stops to get noise investigated um making a friend maintenance
talks to um what do they call them uh talks to repair man no repair person
Because they're not all men.
It's really bad that we have this kind of gendered language ingrained in our English.
Stops to get noise investigated, talks to a repair person.
And now I know that this conversation is going to be mostly about the car's health,
but some of it will also be, you know, they'll be referring to their own health as well.
and maybe that'll be a bit of an issue. So the cool thing is I don't even need to
necessarily know who this character is that they're talking to.
This is enough that I could go to the rest of my team and have a start
starting a conversation with them about what this looks like.
So intended audience, losing health,
intended audience, you know, relating to other people that are common.
Yeah, I mean I know it's a bit of a cliché I guess for old people to talk about what
ails them, but you know, I want everyone in the team to know that this is what we're aiming
for, that it should be actually about two people relating to each other, you know, about
this experience.
So there's going to be something about the character that this old man is talking to
obviously that they will be able to relate to the old man.
We also, you know, so we've got this synergy here, we also know that this escalation needs to work.
So if we're creating this for the vertical slice, we know that these elements here need to function to deliver on the promise of, you know, this transformation that runs through the entire experience,
as well as this escalation that needs to be paid off in the second to last sequence.
Cool, so we've got that sequence there.
We do want a trailing sequence though.
Resources.
I'm not really sure there are any resources that are being managed there that we need to include here
because it is about nostalgia. To a certain degree we don't want any resources here.
Maybe we even just want to let the player drive for as long as they want to drive.
This is a slow game.
And so what could be interesting
for our intended audience is a time for self-reflection.
which isn't something that, you know, older people necessarily are short of
because, you know, with the isolation comes time for them to think for themselves
but, you know, this is a bit more of a structured, you know, it's almost a bit of a
could be a bit of a structured meditation, this sequence, in its style
and, you know, let's put that there
And for us in Australia, you know, these long drives are part of our culture,
you know, and part of a long tradition of what it is to be Australian
because we live in such a big country with cities that are so far apart.
So, you know, I think this is something that a lot of people,
particularly in Australia, would kind of relate to.
And there is something kind of,
you know, structured meditation around these long drives.
You do get in a frame of mind that you don't necessarily get in
when you're traveling to work or even just sitting on your own in the house.
So I feel like, you know, if our goal is to achieve, you know, enough of a narrative
designed to go ahead with developing a vertical slice, I feel like we've got that here.
I'm just going to put talking to themselves in the sequence here so that we know
story-wise at least where we're going here.
So the cool thing is, right, we now have what I call the beginning of a narrative design pattern,
and part of the reason why I don't call it a template or I don't call it a plan is because
some of this stuff has very specific detail and some of this really just has vague intention and
some of it is perfectly blank. And that's because this pattern is evolving. This should be a living
document that kind of evolves as the team, you know, develop the game. It should evolve as
iterations kind of happen.
And hopefully what can happen is because you have this diagram that starts to put these
kind of dramatic relationships together between the different sequences, between the different
elements, you'll understand the implication of any changes as development goes forward.
Obviously, I haven't taken you through the entire method this time around.
So if you are interested in the method more, please take a look at the book.
And it's less of a plug to buy the book.
It's only not for a lot of money available on Amazon at the moment.
but it will explain to you and give you more examples about how to use this method.
But you know, what you can take away from this right now, even if you don't look at the book, is
you know, ask yourself these questions when you're starting to put an idea together.
Think about these different elements and start to think about how they relate together,
you know, as you're kind of deciding what variables you want in the game.
And then start putting your ideas into a matrix.
Ignore the dramatic forces, ignore the Forrest Pyle's method if you like,
but just start understanding that you should be working in these matrices,
you should be breaking the game down into elements,
the design pillars of your game, and then trying to understand how.
these different elements relate to each other at any given moment in the game
and what the relationships, you know, how those elements
evolve over time through the play experience.
Yeah, so I hope that this has helped give a bit of an insight into the method.
And even if you're not interested in pursuing the method, just a way of
understanding how you might want to kind of organize your thoughts going forward
and trying to get from those different stages, from intention into detail
or from working on your own, clarifying your own ideas
into working with your team in a collaborative way.
Thank you very much for tuning in and watching this video.
I really appreciate your time and that you have a thirst for knowledge about narrative design.
It is an evolving art, science, ongoing experiment.
So any feedback would be very, very grateful and available on Twitter.
So please reach out if you have any questions or comments about this.
And I hope I do get to talk to you all in person really soon.
Thank you.
So I'm just going to take the opportunity to summarize some key points.
The high concept formula was the kind of first big one that I started using.
There's the variables there for you as well as a bit of an explanation and some examples.
Take a look at those in your own time.
Also, these are dramatic forces over time. This is the list. You've got the reversals,
you've got escalations, you've got transformations. Obviously, storytelling is very subjective,
so this is about actually establishing what's expected, and then these dramatic forces should
be above what is expected. This is the changes that you should see over time in your narrative.
And then we've got these dramatic forces between elements.
The synergy, opposition and absence, didn't use all of these in the example today.
Absence in particular is tricky and comes from Japanese traditional storytelling more
than anywhere else, it seems from my research.
But also there's just the list there for you to refer to again later.
So thank you, that's all from me today.
I really appreciate you spending the time,
even virtually, to come to my talk.
I am available on Twitter, please reach out.
I always love to get feedback from people.
And of course, if you want to see
the Forest Paths Method in full,
if you want to see more diagrams and examples,
then the book is available.
I really appreciate your time and your support
and the opportunity that GDC is giving me
and presenting to you today.
Keep on making great stories.