Hello everybody! My name is Vera, and I'm the art director and founder of Ovil Studio.
I'm from Moscow, Russia, and I have the honor to be invited to their own table, One Reason to Be.
In this panel, I and the other remarkable participants will share our stories about making games.
When I was discussing a potential theme of my speech on this evening, the organizer of the panel told me that it would be interesting to hear a story about the issues that I faced making games specifically in my country, some unique experience that I had.
And I started wondering, what part of my experience is unusual and so very special?
Well, I actually didn't realize it.
So, it's one more task for me and GDC to figure out the difference between making games in my country and around the world.
Meanwhile, I will be happy to see every one of you in this panel,
where I'm going to share my story about how we build games in Russia
and about how I built my own successful company that already counts 30 people in just 3 years without any investments.
Thank you and see you there!