Hello, and welcome to Keyframes and Cardboard Props,
a look inside God of War's cinematic process.
My name is Erika Pinto,
and I'm the lead narrative animator at Santa Monica Studio.
Today, I'm going to talk about everything that went
into the creation of the scenes
like the one I'm about to show you.
Of course, just a heads up,
there are spoilers for God of War ahead,
so if you haven't played the game,
I don't know if you wanna leave or just let it be spoiled.
It is time, my son. Look around at what you have done.
Come on, we gotta go!
You saw.
There's no time, look!
I have a plan!
Jump!
Hup!
That was your plan.
You're both tracked.
Let's give it up for our cinematics team.
Man, they worked hard on that.
All right.
So at the beginning of this project,
our creative director, Cory Barlock,
came to the cinematics team and said, I have a vision.
I want to create a seamless, immersive player experience,
and I want to do it with a camera that never cuts.
Not anywhere in a cinematic,
not between gameplay and cinematic, never.
So our question was, how do we do that?
I'm going to tell you how we did that,
and I'm going to do it step-by-step
using the scene I just showed you,
which we lovingly called the flying boat jump.
So named because Kratos and Atreus
jump off of a giant flying boat.
This is one of the most complex scenes in God of War
running the gamut of our entire production pipeline,
so I'm going to be referring back to it
throughout our presentation.
First, I'd like to talk a little bit
about the people involved in creating a cinematic.
At the top of our hierarchy, of course,
we've got our creative director,
who provided the overarching vision of the story
and oversaw the broad strokes
of the cinematic production process.
We had our writers, Matt Sophos and Rich Galbert,
who would present the director's vision
in the form of scripts.
Our director of photography, Doria Razzi,
who designed the detailed plan for executing that vision
scene by scene with a consistent cinematic language.
And there's the rest of our team,
such as our animation director, Bruno,
who provided the context for our character acting choices
and would give feedback on the animation quality.
myself, the animation lead,
responsible for the day-to-day production process
and ensuring the animators had everything they needed
to work to the best of their abilities,
also providing feedback.
All of our animators, several of which
aren't in this photo, sadly,
but they were expected to maintain
a certain level of self-autonomy
with ownership of their assigned scenes
from start to finish.
They would work very closely with our cinematic artist,
who would wrangle the cameras,
and they would send all of that data
over to our integration team
to put the scenes into the game engine.
And of course, we can't forget our support staff,
such as our producers and our outsource coordinator
who made sure everything was running smoothly
and getting done on time.
I'd like to break down our production
into three main phases where we were able
to streamline our workflow for no-cut cinematics.
Pre-visualization, or pre-vis for short,
everything we did on set at the mocap stage,
and scene assembly and polish of all of that data.
So let's start with pre-visualization.
And if you see the picture in the background,
you might get a little hint of where we went there.
Let's start with a little history.
On previous God of War projects,
all of our layout was done in Maya.
This is all right, our camera language was pretty simple.
We really only had one main rule,
which was to keep the camera alive.
So we didn't have any static shots.
You can see it might move to follow Kratos' gaze.
It might push in a little bit to focus on his daughter
as we come into the scene.
we would use cuts to show details and character reactions.
But there wasn't much attention paid
to lens choice or anything.
This was pretty passable,
but we realized this method did not work with no cuts.
Here's a very early test scene from this current project,
and I'm gonna kinda rip it apart
and talk about the failure points.
This is my scene, so I can do that.
So, you could see, first of all,
the characters tended to freeze in place.
We didn't really know what to do with them,
and that forced the camera to swing around
and traverse great distances
without really any motivation to do so.
I was trying to get reaction shots on their faces
as they talked to each other,
but again, since I froze them in place,
I didn't really know what to do with the camera,
so it would move around kind of awkwardly.
It wasn't really grounded
the way a real camera person would behave.
If you look at the start of a scene,
you could see that the camera is just way too high.
A person would have to be floating in the air
in order to get that shot.
And then it very quickly swings around
and starts going backwards across an entire field.
And it was also just a very time-consuming process
for something that didn't yield very great results.
What we really needed was someone
with experience in staging,
who could help us tackle oners
in a more sophisticated way.
So that's when we hired Doria Rossi.
And with Doria on board, we began to think about
staging our scenes as a complex dance
between actors and the camera.
We would often use top-down diagrams to plan the scenes.
Most of the time this was just done on a whiteboard
with some markers, but here I've cleaned it up
a little bit for you guys so you can see.
Here's our camera.
The red dot represents Kratos and he's carrying a boar.
The green dot over here is Atreus
and the blue dot is Freya
and they're all going inside their giant turtle house.
Let me go ahead and play this scene for you.
Hello?
If my laptop would cooperate.
Hang on just a second.
Come on, don't break on me.
Place him on the stave there.
You can see the camera follows Kratos in
and parks behind her as Freya goes up to her shelf.
Atreus comes in from screen right.
You want a balloon?
It's better this way.
Yeah, my father doesn't like people either.
Boy.
Whoa, you don't.
Hold him still before he hurts himself.
And Atreus kind of moves off to one side and stays out of the way.
And you'll notice that the camera is constantly doing minor little movements to shift the focus from one character to another.
I need two more things.
Fresh red root grows just behind the house.
Can you pull a cluster?
You'll see Atreus will go off screen,
and then the camera moves and parks behind them again
to let Freya and Kratos have their little heart
to heart moment.
I know you're a god.
Not of this realm, but there's no mistaking it.
He doesn't know, does he?
About your true nature or his own.
That is none of your concern.
The gods of these realms don't take kindly to outsiders.
Trust me.
I know.
When they find you.
And they will.
They'll make things difficult.
And then for you film lovers out there,
this is our little homage to Citizen Kane.
Whatever you're hiding, you cannot protect him forever.
Brought a trace into the back that kept him in focus.
But you're right.
Doesn't concern me.
Now if that staging diagram got a little crazy
and looked a bit like spaghetti,
that's because, well, staging a wonder is very complicated.
All right, so we had our diagrams and our staging ready,
but how do we actually create the previs?
Well, animators might recognize this sort of thing.
We often shoot reference to see how our body mechanics work
and get a sense of timing.
Most often we just set a camera down somewhere
and shoot ourselves.
This was Sophie Evans getting some cool Kratos motion.
And this works great for our gameplay animators.
They use it to, you know, figure out new moves.
And the cinematics team was wondering,
well how could we leverage that for our cinematics?
Could we take the camera off the tripod
and start shooting scenes with it?
Yes you can.
Some of the benefits of this were we could easily test
different styles of camera,
and Dory wanted to try a documentary style,
you know, more grounded and using handheld.
It took very little setup time.
You could just grab an SLR, grab a couple animators,
go outside and shoot.
It was very quick to review.
We could shoot in a couple hours,
do a review with Corey,
and do reshoots within the same day.
you would get a lot of surprising human interactions
just riffing off each other from take to take
that you might not think about
when you were sitting at a computer doing layout in Maya.
Plus, it's just a lot of fun.
You know, you get out of your chair,
you get a little exercise, you look a little ridiculous,
you confuse all your neighbors around you,
and it's pretty awesome.
Some of the challenges, of course,
are memorizing lots of lines.
We had several very chatty characters in this game,
plus learning that complex choreography I just showed you,
and since we had no cuts,
the animators had to keep all of that in mind
while we were shooting at once.
What we were trying to do is establish accurate timing
for the camera to figure out how much time was needed
to transition from composition to composition.
And we also had to figure out how we were going to deal
with characters of differing sizes.
You know, we had little Atreus and we had some dwarves,
and then we had normal-sized humans,
we had super-sized humans, we had orcs and trolls
and dragons and everything.
How were we gonna do that?
And finally, how would the principal cast
react to our acting?
I mean, we're not professional actors,
we're just animators,
and would they be influenced by our previews?
Let me show you some videos of that live-action reference.
Let's see the damage.
In relation to the fire. Let's see the damage.
Stuffing game.
You can see as our solution for the characters of differing sizes,
we tended to just have the animators walking around on their knees.
They're the dwarf characters.
This helped us get accurate eye lines and compositions for the camera.
For this scene, we needed to shoot a vista,
and we happened to have a handy little overlook on our balcony
down to the dev team floor.
I've never been this close to the mountain before.
Thank you.
One of the disadvantages of walking on your knees is you don't get a good sense of accurate
timing for how long it takes to move around.
You can see our animator Mike there kind of shuffling, but our principal cast was able
to walk around freely, so you can see he's a lot more active.
I just love that, that's so cool.
This is one of our earliest tests,
when we had extra time, so we went out of our way
to build a giant ogre.
Our animation director got in on the fun.
But even then, we were still trying
to get some real work done, and Dory wanted
to test this camera move where he kind of snuck
in between us, and then we parked in front of him.
And it worked out pretty well.
So let's take a look at the live action reference
for the flying boat jump.
Action.
You can see we had a prop, a tripod.
Originally we were gonna start the scene
with some kind of a lever pull,
but in the end we ended up going with a player interact
where you're trying to push off
the broken piece of the ship.
Here we're trying to get a sense of the timing
of the VFX, that mist that's coming up along the floor
and sliding over to reveal Zeus.
It is time, my son.
Following the mist over to the hallucination Kratos.
And with this previews, we were able to quickly test whether this transition from third person
camera to first person camera was going to work.
And back to third person.
Avi Yaini, everybody.
He was great.
Very bewildered Atreus.
And back to our first person camera.
and back to third person.
And when Dory realized that this was going to work,
we all got really excited.
And it was great to be able to see it this early
in our previous production process.
There's our barrels rolling down the street.
This also let us quickly figure out
how many takes we were going to have to shoot on stage.
You can see right there, we cut,
and that was going to be the end of the first part.
And then we would do the second part of the landing
with some hand-keyed stuff in the middle of the scene.
And up you guys go.
That was your plan?
They're both cracked.
So for many scenes, the live action reference
was actually enough previs to take directly to stage.
But some were a little bit more complex,
and we needed a way to actually visualize
the game environment.
So for this, we used rough motion capture, or mocap.
We had the luxury of having our own Vicon space
within our studio, but with Oners,
this actually became a necessity.
So some of the benefits of that was that we could actually
work with characters of varying sizes
without having to shuffle around on our knees.
We could see our actual sets and props to scale.
We could get more accurate plans for our principal shoot days
we could figure out how many different mocap volumes
we would need and figure out how we would divide up
our environments to accomplish that.
All of that data could then be sent over to the stage
to prep for our shoot.
And anything that we shoot could also be exported
as a prototype to be put in the game engine.
Some of the challenges of working with motion capture,
of course, are learning to operate a mocap system.
Blade is not the most user-friendly piece of software,
and we would often have camera issues
getting all the cameras calibrated.
Our virtual camera's monitor often shorted out
due to cabling issues, so we had some hardware difficulties.
MotionBuilder was unstable with our plugins sometimes,
and tended to crash when we worked with a very large scene.
So stuff like that.
It was also a much slower iteration time
than live action previs because you had to set up the volume,
you had to get the animator suited up,
we had to shoot the thing, we had to tear it down,
then we had to assemble the scene,
then we had to render it.
So it was a little more difficult to iterate quickly,
at least a one day turnaround just to shoot it.
It tended to divert our animators away
because they were getting in the suit and shooting,
and it was a lot of fun,
but then they were spending time shooting
instead of animating.
When production ramped up significantly,
we would hire temp actors to fill in those roles.
But the concern was always that because the animator was not in the suit and in the moment
with the pre-vis process, they might have less creative input in their ownership of
their scenes, so we were always concerned about that.
We're thinking of maybe ways to involve the main owner of the scene, but then hire temp
actors to fill in the rest of the characters for the scene.
Here are some examples of where we used rough motion capture for our previz.
This scene was important because we needed to see the relationship of the table and the
characters and the location of the fireplace and the cauldron within her house.
So we really just wanted to see where everything was and also figure out how Kratos was going
to dunk the head in there.
And you'll see in the rough mocap, the arm was kind of obscuring him, so we opened it
up for the final shot.
This was a test of how we might shoot
some very large characters.
We just marked up a cardboard box
and puppeteered that guy around.
This was important to actually see the environment,
that face in the mountain,
and figure out where we were going to place
our characters in relation to the scene.
So going back to flying boat jump again,
this was our rough mocap previs.
This was shot pretty early in the production of this scene,
so you'll notice that the entrances and exits
hadn't been figured out yet.
Kratos is coming in from a strange location.
Time to end this.
Yes, my son.
Really, the purpose of this test was to see
how this composition would look with the two ghosts
and the boat in the background
and having Atreus standing there.
And then was everything going to get too busy
or could we frame it so it looked really nice?
So we're really looking at this composition in particular.
Ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, ah!
Back up, back up, man.
Yeah, one of the things of having Vicon
in your own studio is that everyone can hear you.
And cut.
Thank you!
They were usually pretty good sports about it, though.
I'd like to talk a little bit
about the importance of business,
which is basically giving your characters things to do.
This is something movie folks understand pretty implicitly,
but can sometimes be overlooked in games,
especially when we just have so much content
we have to crank out, you know, hours and hours of content.
But again, when we had no cuts,
it was very important to give our characters things to do,
because this gave us opportunities for the camera
to look away from the characters.
Again, we can't do cutaways,
but having something for the camera to look at
and motivate to look away from the character's face
was important.
Business would also provide motivation
for getting the characters to move through the space.
And if you think back to our early tests
where the characters were kind of freezing
and that caused the camera to swing around
and do weird stuff, giving them business helped move them.
Finally, you could get a lot of nice nonverbal insights
into a character's personality by giving them stuff to do.
And this would help our actors get into character
and stay in character throughout the scene
and not worry about what to do with their body.
So these are some examples of giving our characters business.
You can see we put Freya up on a ladder
and messing around with some herbs
to help sell her character as a witch of the woods.
And Sindri's freaking about carrying that gear.
But really also selling his nature as a craftsman
and being dedicated to his work.
And his work is junk.
Those things are accurate.
Point! Point.
I just love the idea of Brock eating something, and I won't spoil where he got that meat from,
but if you play the game you will find out.
This is an example of getting the character to move through the space by using business.
We had all these cups and bowls and stuff on her table that she was using to cast her
spell, and she could go over there and work with that.
Leader of the Baneer once, yes.
No longer.
And you did not think it important to tell me?
Here's an example of how we used a prop to do something
that looks like a cutaway.
Quickly move down and look at the knife,
and then come back up.
And again, here we focus on Freya,
and then we're using the bowl to kind of create
a new composition.
Avi, everybody.
And using those effects to then draw the camera up
to go up to Kratos.
You may have noticed a big part of business is having props.
And Sony's main motion capture studio
has an entire prop building department,
but for Previs we're on our own.
So we tended to gather whatever materials we could find
from the mail room, from trash cans,
leftover items in the hallways,
used lots of duct tape and created stuff like this.
We've got our tree, we've got the big ogre,
some kind of deer.
Sometimes we would use markers
and marker up something like Mimir's head
so that when we shot our rough mocap
we could see it in the mocap space.
And finally, for those scenes where we literally
could not humanly shoot the scene,
we went back to traditional layout.
The big benefit of this is you can do anything,
so we can craft those big, super epic God of War moments.
The challenge, of course, is that it is super time consuming
to create and iterate on,
and it's hard to establish real world timing
because you're not physically doing the actions
with your body.
But let's take a look at some of the cool scenes we did.
Hold on!
If you can see how much the composition changes
and also having Credoc pick up the axe with his other hand
All right, we have a small clip of traditional previews
for the flying boat jump.
And originally, this was going to be
almost a different scene entirely.
So we had this whole moment where these icicles
were gonna break down and break off
the front part of the ship.
But then the rest of it is pretty similar
to what we ended up shooting and animating
for the final product.
We've got the barrels rolling down, or whatever that is.
and then they crash.
And an interesting thing to note here
in the original previz is that Kratos jumps first,
so it was a cool change to have Atreus lead the way
in the final version.
All right, so once you've got your previz all done,
you've got it approved, it is time to go on set.
All right.
On previous projects, we would sometimes
do our set construction, our rehearsal,
even our shoots, all on the same day.
We didn't have a virtual camera because we were doing all the camera work in Maya.
So there was a little bit of room for choreography experiments, letting the actors run around
and see what they could, you know, come up with.
But again, no cuts means it's not really great to try improv.
This scene was really the only time we were on stage and didn't have Previs ready, so
we just kind of winged it.
And you can start to see some of the same failure points
you encountered in our early tests.
What is it, boy?
Some very unmotivated camera motions
because the actors had frozen and Dory needed
to go and see their faces.
So we just kind of swung around to try to get their reactions.
And then we had to swing back around because we had
to get back to game camera.
So there wasn't really any motivation for that move
either, but we wanted to see Atreus' face
and we needed to get back to the game.
In the end, this data, I don't know,
we just didn't like it, so we ended up throwing it out,
and we did a proper previs pass,
and we came back to the stage later.
It also helped to have more context
for where the scene was taking place,
and it was taking place in a boat.
Again, I said nothing.
All right, let's shoot some previs for the boat.
What is it, boy?
You can see here we were able to figure out
how to get the actors to face the camera.
You don't hear that?
Dory was able to do some more thinking
about how he wanted to do the lensing.
What's going on right now?
And we would do a zoom in
and get a really nice intimate shot here.
Lots of voices, angry.
You really didn't hear that?
No.
We had this nice moment with them.
It felt
And then we could use the motion of Atreus turning to sit back down on the boat as motivation
for the camera to move and get back into the camera.
So again, every scene had to be meticulously planned.
So no more winging it on the set, have pre-vis every single time.
Another big aspect of not winging it was breaking up
our mo-cap shoots and having a specific tech day.
So no actors on set, just the animators and Dory
and everybody who needed to be there to review
our exported data and our videos from the previous process
with the stage crew, discussing and reviewing any props
we would need for the shoot day,
dividing up our volume space,
figuring out which sets we wanted to construct.
laying down tape for all our major choreography beats,
and this was useful when we had our mo-cap previews,
we could actually measure that in MotionBuilder
and get that all down.
And finally, just go over our shot list,
finalize any last minute details
so that when the actors showed up,
they were ready to go and we could just start rehearsing.
Now getting those assets to the stage for Tech Day
posed a little bit of a challenge,
and that's where we had our tech artists give us an assist.
They wrote a tool for us which we called
the Maya to Motion Builder tool,
and that allowed our animators to export
our proprietary animation rigs into Motion Builder
at the correct scale and orientation,
and we didn't need to bake anims or anything,
so that saved us a lot of time.
One of the big pain points, however,
was exporting our environments into Motion Builder.
See, on our project, we use a proprietary thing
called ref nodes, which are similar to like Unity prefabs,
and those need to be converted to regular geometry
in order to be compatible with MotionBuilder.
And this was a very slow process.
I mean, there's just hundreds or thousands of assets
in just this one piece alone, the house.
That converted geo then needed to be parented under a node
so that it could be moved from world space
to the mocap space, which is like that green space there
at the origin, and then back again after the shoot.
And this was all done by hand,
so there was lots of room for human error,
especially when onboarding new team members.
So we're now developing an automation tool
similar to Maya to MotionBuilder,
but for converting environment geometry.
Once we're on the set, there were quite a few people there.
We had our creative director, of course, our writers.
Our director of photography was there,
the animation director was there,
the animation lead was there, our producers were there,
our dialogue coordinator, the stage crew, and animators.
Whoo, lots of cooks in the kitchen.
So it was very important to define roles on the set
so the actors weren't getting overwhelmed
by feedback coming from too many directions.
What we ended up doing was having our creative director
or writers focus with the actors on their performance notes.
Our director of photography would focus on staging notes.
and our animation director would focus
on any kind of body mechanics notes.
So if anybody else had feedback to give
for any of these things, they could go to our point people
and give them the feedback,
and then they could relay it to the actors,
so the actors knew who to go to when they needed feedback.
And what would the animators do on set?
Ooh, we could use them as stage hands.
Again, they were owning their scene,
so they know it and they know all the elements within it,
so they really were helpful in being able
to present the previous videos and talk through it.
They could inform other people about any entrances,
exits, key poses, props that were needed.
They could assist with any stand-in work,
any kind of extra bodies needed
that we didn't have anybody suited up for.
And of course, they were taking notes
on any info coming out of the shoot
so that when they got the data back,
they were ready to hit the ground running.
Here's a few examples of animators as stagehands here.
I'm playing a dead body.
Yep.
And you can see our creative director,
writers, and our dialogue coordinator in the back,
making sure everything's running smoothly.
This is a scene that actually got cut from the game,
but I had a lot of fun playing this creature in the water,
and then our stage crew did an awesome job
building this boat for us that could move around
and act like it was on the water.
Sit down.
This is not a game.
Here you can see our boat rig
being used for a more intense scene.
This is the introduction of Jormungandr,
the giant world serpent coming out of the water.
And I'd like to take this moment to talk a little bit
about multiple motion capture spaces.
And I'm gonna pause it here,
and you can see we've got our main actors in the boat here.
And you've got me in the corner,
and what the heck am I doing with this little thing here?
It's kind of hard to see, but you can see a monitor
of what Dory's seeing through his virtual camera,
and here's Kratos and Atreus,
and we've got this giant snake.
Now, obviously, we couldn't build a giant snake.
It wouldn't fit in the mo-cap space.
So what we used was a tiny little box with markers on it,
and I was acting as sort of a puppeteer of the snake.
And then we would take that data and offset it in real time
so that, from Dory's point of view,
he could see the snake in the right place.
and then this little green spot being held by Bruno,
our animation director, was being held up
so that the actors would know where to look
to represent where the snake would be.
Whew, a little complex, but we made it work.
All right, here we've got some onset footage
from the flying boat jump.
Since this was a pretty physical scene,
we ended up using stunt actors.
Here we have one of our stunt actors acting as Kratos,
and he would also double as the ghost Kratos.
And you might see Dory over there kind of offset.
We wanted to keep him out of the way of the stunt actor
so he would not get punched in the face.
And also, it allowed him to get in
and really get that first person camera
without interrupting the actors.
So he's being offset as well.
Like I mentioned when we did our live action previews,
we were gonna break it up into multiple pieces.
So we'll see the second take where we've got our observers.
We've got a stunt stand in for Sonny as Atreus.
Okay, coming in close.
And then we've got Kratos in the back there.
What the hell's that?
And since we had already shot the data for the ghost,
we could see that within the virtual camera.
We gotta go!
Look, there's no time!
Look!
We hadn't animated the barrels yet,
so we just kind of pretended.
And go.
I got a plan.
Jump.
And then here's where we cut,
and we go to the traditional animation for the big fall,
and then we have our final take where they land,
and you know the rest of that scene.
Now what is your plan?
All right.
So after everything is done and shot,
it's time to get all that data back
and assemble it and polish it.
And the first part of that is editing.
I know what you're thinking.
What? Editing?
Why are you editing a one-er?
It's all one shot.
Well, we tried to avoid editing as often as possible
because it's exponentially more difficult
to blend two takes together versus cutting.
But sometimes you have to account for multi-volume scenes
for very large environments.
Sometimes you have to think about unintentional mistakes
that might have happened on set.
Maybe you're getting a really good take,
but then there's just one line that the actor flubs,
so you wanna just do a little insert there
where they get the line right,
and then you'll just merge those two bests together.
Sometimes we need inserts for clarity or script rewrites.
Occasionally we'd have a play test
where the players would give feedback
that they didn't understand what was going on,
so we might do some rewrites.
and shoot something to help clarify that scene.
Also, timing passes in case a scene was running long
or needed some extra time,
we would insert or cut things down.
Cut, yeah.
Also, any changes to level design or environment art,
like you saw in the mocap previz,
we hadn't figured out the entrances or exits,
so sometimes once we nailed that down,
we would do a quick reshoot and get those entrances
nailed down and blend that all together.
Challenges of editing.
We had some limitations with Maya
because blending takes together is hard.
We weren't having too much luck with the tracks editor,
so what we ended up doing was using
Motion Builder's Story tool,
which let us edit pretty quickly
and get some macro edits going.
And then once we were happy with the rough timing,
we could then work on anim layers and constraints.
Now there's a bit of an art to choosing where to edit.
You're trying to find the best blend.
And what you're looking for is character position and pose,
whether they match pretty closely
across two different takes.
Of course, also the camera position.
Again, because we're not cutting,
you need to make sure the camera's in a pretty safe place
so that you're not getting some weird motion
once you're going between the two takes.
It's a bonus if your carriages are off-screen
when you're doing the edit,
because then you don't have to worry
about blending them together.
Let's take a look at our story tool for flying boat jump.
Yeah, I know, it looks a little crazy.
Let me break it down for you.
These two tracks represent the ghost Kratos and Zeus.
And what we were doing here was working
and getting those punches looking really good and physical,
so we did a bunch of edits for timing.
Up here we've got Atreus.
This is about the moment when he pushes
through the two ghosts, so we,
oh no, why is my battery not,
I'm sorry, let's plug that in.
All right, here we go.
This is where Atreus was pushing through the two ghosts.
We wanted to make sure that felt very physical.
Here we actually ran out of data,
so we were copying and pasting extra punches.
Yeah.
And here we've got a little take of Atreus.
This is probably an old screenshot
and they were probably gonna insert that up here
to help Atreus slide.
And let's go ahead and play this shot
and you can watch it, go along with it.
Here's those physical punches.
Here we've got Atreus's push through coming in.
Extra punches, bam.
and this take of Atreus sliding down.
All right, some results of that.
Of course, the ideal was always to get our scenes
nailed down with one perfect take,
but it ended up that over 50% of our cinematics
needed major editing or reshoots or merges.
And all of our cinematics required at least some minor edits
to accommodate our finalized environments,
make sure our pose were matching, et cetera.
That's not a great track record.
So how can we get that percentage down?
Really what we need to do is focus on our tools
and communication to make sure we have everything we need
before we go on stage and after we go on stage
to help us get our workflow moving more quickly.
Oh yes, animation.
It's time to do the fun stuff.
It's time to animate those cool creatures
and those crazy stunts.
And also the not so fun stuff like bandages and chains
and ropes and vines and all those spline IK
everybody loves to do, yeah.
When you're using cuts, it's often simpler
to compartmentalize your thoughts into smaller task chunks
and focus on one shot at a time,
such as this 150 frames, that's not too bad,
you can keep track of what your curves are doing there.
But with very long runners like God of War had,
the animators had to keep the entire scene in mind
while they're making edits,
because if you're working on a layer
and you make a change and you forget
that you made that change,
it might ripple down the entire scene.
So if you're not keeping track,
hours of your work could get wrecked.
The actual process of animating
is the same as it's been for years,
but the mental focus required grew quite a bit.
So let's take a look at some of our awesome
and keyed animations.
I got to do that one.
In between all my meetings and spreadsheets.
Stay behind me and protect our flank.
Yes sir!
And of course our flying boat jump.
Some quick numbers about our animation team.
We had an internal team size of about seven animators
at peak production.
We had three different outsource teams,
two vendors helping clean up our body
and one vendor for facial solving.
But our internal animators would have ownership
of all the scenes, including our outsource ones,
so that they could assemble the outsource data
and make sure everything got integrated
and keeping track of the debugging process.
In hindsight, we wished we'd had a larger internal team
because as our contractors rolled off,
we would have to transfer ownership of all those scenes
to all our remaining team members,
and we had over 100 cut scenes to keep track of,
so that was a lot.
Also, just tracking the sheer amount of content
and scope creep, we had a lot of level design asks
that weren't originally in the script,
but we would need to help tell the story
of level design as well.
So now we take into consideration
all of our narrative moments, and not just cinematics,
as we work out our scope and our schedule.
Onto our polish, we had what we called the buttery smooth patch.
What this was was just really troubleshooting those seamless transitions between gameplay
and cinematics to make sure our no-cut language was working.
The main things we were looking for was pose matching,
and that seems pretty obvious,
but it's important to establish those standard poses,
and any time it's changed,
make sure you communicate them widely across the team.
Make sure your pose library is updated,
and see if you can find some tools
that helps the animators match poses and animations
across your scenes and characters.
matching the velocity of the gameplay animation
into a cinematic and back out.
Each of our characters had a zero joint
that indicated their position in the game.
And in the case of Kratos, the player,
the camera is also attached to that zero joint.
So any kind of errant motion was gonna cause
some weird jarring camera blends.
The zero joint's velocity also informs the engine
of what state the character should be in,
whether he's walking or running or idle.
So if it's not matching the actual action of the scene,
if you've animated your cinematic so Kratos is running out,
but your zero joint is frozen,
then the game engine thinks he's standing,
so then you're gonna see him pop into an idle pose
at the end of the scene.
Finally, thinking about metrics.
For any interactable objects such as doors or levers,
we need to get those exact metrics set by the gameplay team
for how close the player should be to that object
at the start of a cinematic.
Here are some issues with buttery smoothness.
You can see this magical door.
We hadn't figured out the metrics
of where the player should stand,
so you'll see Kratos actually walk backwards
as he's starting the cinematic.
Oh, or not.
Let me do that again.
Here we go.
Yep.
Little lerp there.
Still can't get the doors open, huh?
Quiet.
Here you can see some of our debugging tools.
You can see there's a little arrow down here
showing the velocity of the zero joint at any time.
We're trying to debug why those pose match matches are happening.
This scene, you'll notice that the log and Kratos
become out of sync.
Oh, what's that sliding all about?
Let's go into that debugging tool,
and you'll see that at some point,
the log's zero joint stopped moving,
so it thought that it should not be moving forward,
while Kratos kept walking along.
So just taking care to do all of that buttery smoothness.
Here are some issues with the flying boat jump.
There was kind of a position misalignment
and we didn't have any transitional motion
to get the player into the place where they needed to be.
We didn't do that.
And also for some reason it wanted to play that part twice.
I don't know.
At the end, the lighting hadn't been put in yet,
but you can see that there's a pose mismatch here
between the normal idle and the combat idle.
In this particular iteration, Kratos flew off into space
and then aligned up with the ship.
The zero joint also, if it wasn't in sync with the body,
sometimes there were clock physics problems
because it thought the character was somewhere else.
So you would see his skirt would flip out there.
And again, pose mismatches.
This was always the pops between the end of the cinematic
and the gameplay.
Here you might see the characters drop down.
That might be because IK or collision's turning back on
and we haven't quite aligned them to the ground plane.
So we're trying to figure out where that's going.
Another big part of polishing our scenes were armor variants.
Kratos has many armors.
And again, because we can't cut, we can't hide any armor swaps
on a cut to get into our cinematics.
Some problems with that were, of course, obstructing your face.
We need to be able to see Kratos' face
during certain cinematics, but certain pauldrons
would obstruct it, and that's troubling.
Penetrations, we'd have stuff going into
other parts of the body, other parts of the armor.
This was a pretty extreme example.
I don't think this was ever actually in any cinematic.
Some solutions to this were making slight body adjustments
to fix our penetrations.
We could often cheat the camera
so that if an offending object,
from the camera view it doesn't look like it's penetrating,
then it's resting properly on different armors,
such as when he's resting his hand on his bracers.
from a specific camera angle, it looks fine.
And when all else fails, we plead with character art,
can you please just adjust this pauldron a little bit
so I don't have to deal with it anymore?
Of course, there was one scene in particular
that was a beast, and you might recognize this one.
The rope.
Kratos had to sling a rope over his shoulder,
and he couldn't hide it.
It's close up on the camera.
All the pauldrons were clipping through,
or it was floating above,
and what were we going to do about this?
Oh, man, that's a tough one.
What TechArt ended up doing was rigging up a rope for us
with four different joint chains
and four different rope meshes,
and our animator placed them at different heights
to cover the range of variation
between our different shoulder pads.
then the integration team would script the visibility
on each of those rope meshes to turn on and off,
depending on what the player had equipped at the time.
Yes.
Why'd you say nothing?
Another thing here is our axe pommel.
Sundari rests his elbow on it,
but this particular pommel had a blade.
Oh, man. Okay. For this one, we just tweaked the animation
to have Sundari wrap his arm around the blade.
In any other pommel, it still looked like
he was resting his elbow on it.
But our favorite one, and one we probably got the most bugs for,
were what we lovingly called the Kratos nip slip.
What is that?
Yeah.
That was an easy fix.
You just rotate the clavicle a little bit.
But just, it happened so many times.
We got so many bugs about that.
There we go.
Fixing all the bugs.
All right, let's wrap it up.
So although we encountered many challenges
on the path to realizing this vision
of a no-cut narrative language,
overall we felt our new pipeline helped us achieve success.
Our final cinematics looked pretty close to our previz,
even when it was shot in live action.
And we were able to create smooth blends
between gameplay and cinematics.
So let's take one more look at the flying boat jump
and the many pieces that came together to create it.
It is time, my son. Look around at what you have done.
Come on, we gotta go!
You saw.
There's no time, look!
That was your plan.
You're both tracked.
Thank you very much for coming.
Thank you.
We have some time for Q&A, so we've
got a couple microphones here if you want to come up
and ask me any questions.
Anybody?
All right.
Hi.
Hello.
Thank you for your presentation.
Thank you.
I'm Christian.
So I had two questions.
One, did you guys use VCam all the way through to the final
cut scenes?
Yes.
When we shot live action reference, we
wouldn't have the VCam.
We would just be using an SLR.
But any time we were using rough mo-cap on the stage, we
would always have a virtual camera on set, yes.
Yeah, did the virtual camera actually help you guys translate
what you were doing with the VCAM to the final cutscene you would get in the game?
Yes, I mean the data was being recorded from the virtual camera,
and then Dory could take that, and he and the cinematic artists would take that data,
and they would do some cleanup by hand in MotionBuilder
to get the final look and do some minor adjustments here and there,
but the raw data from the virtual camera was always the baseline for that.
Cool, and then...
As far as studio-wise, do you guys
enjoy this process with the motion capture, the VCAM?
And will you use it again on future projects?
I think it's a lot of fun.
I think now that we've got our pipeline set up,
it's definitely a tool we can use in our pocket
whenever we can.
It's really helped streamline our previous process
and helping us iterate as quickly as possible.
So it's definitely something I want to keep using.
Cool.
Thank you.
Yes.
Hi.
Thank you for the talk.
Another question about VCam.
Can you say something quickly about this deciding
between shooting VCam with the actors on stage,
or shooting it offset from the actors,
or shooting it separately?
Most of the time we would try to keep the virtual camera in lockstep with the actors in actual space.
For Flying Boat Jump it was just an issue of Dory really wanted to get into the shot he wanted for the first person thing.
So that's what he requested in Offset.
So he didn't have to be like right on top of the stunt actors while they were doing their stunts.
But most of the time the camera and the actors were in the actual space we wanted them to be in.
Cool, thanks.
Are you using MotionBuilder story mode to blend both facial capture and body capture together?
The question was, were we using MotionBuilder also for the facial capture?
No, we did mostly body cleanup in MotionBuilder, and then we would do all of the facial cleanup and pasting in Maya.
Oh, OK.
And then also, what was the frames per second
when you're making the cinematics in Maya
or Motion Builder?
We would shoot at 30 frames per second.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Thank you again for the talk.
It was super informative.
How much of the team came from more of a cinema background?
And how much interplay was there between cinema and games?
And what kind of challenges from the game side
versus maybe a more cinema side did you
have to kind of consider?
For our animators, we tried to hire specifically
for cinematic, so people, if they hadn't gone
through film school or anything,
that they at least worked in cinematics on previous games.
But our real rock star was Doria Razzi.
He comes from film and he's done a bunch of stuff
and he had the eye for doing it.
So he was really driving the look and feel of our scenes.
Hi, could you tell me a little bit about
why you created the tool for Maya into Motion Builder?
I'm a little more familiar with Motion Builder to Maya.
Yeah, because most of the time we're animating in Maya,
all the gameplay animators work in Maya,
and all of our rigs are set up to work with Maya,
and we have several tools,
and just the way that the rigs are built
to work with those tools,
it makes it a little more proprietary
and harder to translate directly
into MotionBuilder one for one.
So the tool was just a way to get those proprietary nodes
kind of stripped out and locked down
and putting it into MotionBuilder.
And it also goes both ways.
So we would go then from MotionBuilder
once we cleaned up back into Maya
and back onto our proprietary rig so we could keep working.
we would go then from MotionBuilder
once we cleaned up back into Maya
and back onto our proprietary rig so we could keep working.
So like easier for pose mashing and motion building.
And also our rigs in Maya are at a different scale.
They're not one to one in meters or whatever.
So we would have to scale everything up
when we brought it into Motion Builder
and scale it back down when we came into Maya.
Thank you.
Hi, I have a question because I noticed that the stunt was a woman and the main actor for
Atreus was a child and did you have some trouble with the difference of the performance? This is
the first question. The second one is Atreus' main actor is a child so I would like to know
if you had a problem because the child is growing up really fast and during the shooting it could
be a problem.
Yes, the question was about the challenges of working with child actors versus a stunt
actor who was an adult.
Yeah, I mean, as much as possible, we tried to use Sonny.
Occasionally, he would have to be in school for certain hours, so we would bring in a
stand-in while he was in school, and we would try to hire actors who could.
mimic the motions of a child as much as possible,
but of course there is advantages of using
an actual child actor, it does look a little different.
So we would then have the animators kind of try
to match the data across and try to create
a consistent workflow.
As for Sonny growing throughout the production process,
that was a concern.
It didn't affect us too much, he did grow an inch or two,
but it wasn't enough to cause a big problem for us.
All right, before I let, oh, yep, go ahead.
Hi, one last question.
Great talk.
You mentioned cinematic artists, I believe, doing cameras.
How big was that team, how many people?
I mean, Dory was doing a lot of work
and then he was able to bring in a second person
to help him out.
We had a third person who was helping out
with the VCam on set, and then the other one
was focused mainly on motion builder cleanup.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Hi, my question maybe would have been better for Dory,
but maybe you can help me out with it,
because I was wondering with the single cuts,
with the no-cut directing that you had,
that tends to be kind of exhausting
for long periods of time as a spectator.
Yes, as a spectator.
What did, um, like, how did you guys, like, sort of make it so that you could actually play the game for, you know,
the way people play, which is several hours generally, if you can, like, you get into the story and not have you be exhausted by the time you're finished?
Yeah, I mean, Dory's right there.
You can come talk to him afterwards.
But I think it's just about having enough interesting
things happening on the stage and making sure
that the staging is very interesting
and the characters are moving around
and having things to do to keep the eye going.
And as for viewer fatigue, yeah, I
guess Dory might be the guy to answer that one.
Yeah, because that's mostly because I'm thinking, you know,
For example, in The Haunting of Hill House,
they have that one episode that's just no cuts for like 20 minutes,
and by the time you finish,
you just want to die.
It's exhausting and depressing and very sad.
Yeah. It might be that once you're back in gameplay,
you feel like you're in control again.
Maybe that helps alleviate some of that as well.
Right. Yeah.
Yeah.
Okay. Well, thank you.
Yeah. Thank you. All right.
Just before I let you go, we are hiring.
We have many positions open,
so make sure you check out our website,
you can come talk to me, leave business cards,
especially animators, if you have what it takes.
Come see me, or I think we have a recruiting booth
downstairs, but yeah.
Thank you again for coming.