Hello, everyone.
My name is David Huang, and I was a senior animator
on Anthem.
I was responsible for creating the traversal animations
for the player character.
And my name is Daniel Nordlander,
and I was a senior gameplay designer on Anthem.
I was responsible for the player character, controls, and camera.
So during this talk, we're going to discuss
how we created Anthem's flight mechanic,
as that was a unique selling point of the game.
We'll explore how creating video game characters that look and feel great to play requires
close collaboration between design and animation.
Even though our day-to-day work might seem totally different, with design determining
things like physics values, movement tuning, cameras and controls, we tend to provide the
bigger picture that animation works within.
Our work relies heavily on one another,
as we're both responsible for the look
and the feel of the traversal mechanics.
So to fully explain how we created flight in Anthem,
we need to give the whole picture
rather than just an animation by itself.
It's important to take into account the design side
and how it relates to the flight system
to really understand how to create our animations.
We hope to give you insight into our process,
inspire other character designers and animators
to use these techniques in their own work.
To give you an idea of what the kind of game Anthem is,
let's kick things off with a quick trailer.
You are the chosen few, protectors of our world.
This is your time.
Incoming!
Fire!
Out there, you will fight the unimaginable.
Feel the power of your javelin.
It's precision.
Rely on each other.
Unleash your power.
You are freelancers.
So, in Anthem, players will fly, swim, fight, together, in a dense open world.
So, what does that mean for the player character?
Well, our key goals were to support a full 360 degree movement experience
that allows for seamless transitions between movement on the ground,
through the sky and underwater using four distinct superheroic characters.
These characters are embodied through armored exosuits called javelins,
which make you bigger and stronger and give you superhuman abilities.
Each one you get into makes you a different class of superhero.
The Colossus is a super strong tank.
The Ranger is a versatile warrior.
The Interceptor is a fast and agile ninja.
And the Storm is a magic user with special powers.
The key power that they all share is the ability to fly.
So to give you some background to how and why the flight
system works the way it does, let's back up a little bit and
look at how it all started.
What you're about to see is from an early
prototype of the game.
So Anthem always had exotic traversal
as a major part of its core gameplay.
But as you can see here,
it was not always in the form of flight.
Technical and design problems
made true flight seem impossible.
So we experimented with alternatives early on
in the form of rocket-powered jumps,
free-form climbing, and wingsuit-style gliding.
So these mechanics worked really well together,
but in the end we decided to go a different route.
So why is that?
Well, the mechanics gave us the verticality that we were after,
but they didn't feel fluid enough
and failed to satisfy the superhero fantasy, which
is that anthem's core.
And what's more superheroic than flight, right?
So we realized we needed to lean more into the power fantasy
of wearing an exosuit with jet packs.
Why would you climb slowly up a cliff
where you can just boost past it using your thrusters?
We decided to implement freeform flight,
but we knew that in order to succeed,
we needed to solve some very specific issues.
The first issue is if you can fly above the level,
we have no control over what the play space is.
You can ignore the entire level layout,
skipping past mission objectives,
and you have free sight lines of the entire map, which breaks
our performance and streaming.
The second issue is if you can fly,
you don't really need to think about how you traverse.
You just kind of fly in a direction
and wait until you get there.
There are no interesting skill checks, choices, or risks,
which makes it boring when really it
should feel exhilarating.
So to address these issues, first of all,
we added a flight ceiling above the level.
To make it feel less limiting, we didn't make it a hard collision,
but instead applied downwards force on players getting close to the flight ceiling
and added presentation to make it feel like turbulence.
Since the ceiling was hand placed, we could tailor it to our needs
depending on the layout in that specific part of the level.
This allowed us to get control of the play space again
and prevent performance and streaming issues.
It also made the player have to fly through the world rather than above it,
preventing them from ignoring the level layout completely.
So we also added the overheat system.
When flying, your engine builds heat until it overheats,
forcing you to crash land and keeping you grounded
until the engine has cooled off again.
So what this achieved was it gave us control
over the ground to air ratio of a player's experience
and gave players a reason to engage
in ground gameplay again.
We then layered in ways to cool off your engines
during flight.
For example, by flying downwards, skimming over water,
or flying through a waterfall.
This gave the player interesting choices while flying
and added a layer of skill to how you choose your flight path.
So now we had a framework for how flying worked in the game.
The next step was to figure out how to control your javelin.
So our biggest challenge here was
making the transition between ground, flight,
and underwater movement feel completely seamless.
We started out with more traditional airplane controls,
where the left stick on the controller
steers your character with up and down being inverted.
You could freely look around your character with the right stick as you flew through the world, as you can see in this video.
So the main issue that we found with this was that the control scheme was simply too different from the ground controls.
The transition between the two modes was jarring and players often started their flight with a nose dive into the ground.
So we experimented a lot with different controls
to try to solve this problem.
At one point, we even had the trigger button
work like a gas pedal, which felt amazing,
but kind of makes it difficult when you're making a shooter
since you need that button for the gun trigger.
So we ended up with left stick controlling your speed
while steering was done with the right stick.
We wanted you to be able to look around
and have the character go towards the direction
you're looking when you press your movement stick forward,
just like it works when you're on foot.
So this approach made the controls a lot more simplified
and intuitive.
It allowed for seamless transitions
between traversal modes.
And instead of struggling with the controls,
it made the players feel like superheroes.
The main thing that we lost from this
was the ability to freely look around the character.
But on the other hand, this also gave us more control
over the framing and angle,
which became helpful when creating animations,
as we knew exactly how the characters' movements
would be presented to the player.
So we had a framework for flying,
with the controls finally figured out.
The next issue was to make those controls translate
to really nice movement feel.
We started out with a more realistic physics model,
which simulated drag and realistic velocity inheritance.
But as is true for many games,
we quickly realized that it's better not to worry
too much about realism,
and just make it feel as good as we can,
no matter how many laws of physics we needed to break.
And we kind of broke all of them in the end.
So while your speed is analog, we
did have a binary boost state that
triggers a lot of the presentation on the character,
such as animation post changes, effects, camera shake,
field of view adjustments.
So this boost state was triggered
when moving your stick forward, so you'd immediately
feel the kick from the boost, even though your character's
analog speed would take a second or two to reach its max.
So whether it was for controlling your speed,
your side-to-side movement, or your steering,
we had a similar setup.
We had curves controlling desired speed
based on your stick movement,
acceleration and deceleration towards this desired speed.
Modifiers making a light push on the stick
give a slower acceleration than fully pushing it.
We also checked for how drastically
you tried to change direction,
so we had more control over how it felt
to make small adjustments versus larger movement changes.
So all of this allowed us to get smooth movement
that worked well for different use cases.
We had limits in place to ensure we never went faster
than the game could stream in the level.
The limited speed felt okay for flying forwards,
but when flying downwards, it felt artificially slow.
Luckily, the streaming constraint did not apply
to vertical movement, so we implemented a curve
which allows you to go faster as you're flying downwards.
You reach double speed going down versus going forwards.
We actually tried to push it faster than that,
but it kind of made it feel like you're hitting a wall
as you go from a super fast dive to flying forwards again.
So a problem with all of this is that it actually
makes falling faster than flying straight down.
We tried adjusting the fall speed to be slower
to compensate, but it kind of made it feel
like you're falling through syrup.
So it's definitely weird physics behavior
that falling is faster than flying down,
but as it didn't really cause any actual exploits
or issues in the game,
we actually ended up shipping with this behavior.
So now we had a framework for flying, intuitive controls,
and nice feeling movement.
So the next step was how to best present
that movement with our camera.
First of all, we used camera dampening.
So what this does is have the camera lag behind the movement
of the character it's tracking.
The goal was to get a less static feel
to the character's position in the screen space,
get a better sense of direction, as well as
to help you anticipate obstacles.
The only issue is that dampening leaves the camera behind the direction you're going,
instead of anticipating it.
So we did some math to create a reverse dampening effect, which gives you the result you can
see in this video.
When turning, the camera leads in front of the player, panning slightly towards the direction
you're steering, and offsets the character to the opposite side of the screen.
We also did a similar calculation
where we tied a small amount of camera roll
based on your character's steering speed,
so the camera tilts in the direction you're steering.
This was done to give a better feel
to the direction you're turning towards,
as well as to improve the feedback
of how strongly you were turning.
We also tied camera framing, pitch,
field of view, and shake to the pitch of the character.
We used this to get more control over framing your character
and the world as you fly through it,
so you could easily tell what was going on
and where you're going.
We widened the field of view and increased the shake
as you flew straight up and down to give a more visceral feel
and convey the sense of speed even better.
We also frame things differently when going up versus going down
to better fit the needs of the player.
When going down, you end up right behind the character,
so you see the point you're diving towards
and the world below you.
But when you fly straight up, we show a lot more
in front of the character, so the player easily
can judge if they will collide with something
when they decide to start flying forwards again.
So we had a framework for flying, intuitive controls,
nice feeling movement, and a camera
that presented it all well.
The final piece of the puzzle was
to look at how we can differentiate
all of these things based on what javelin you're wearing.
So because Anthem is a game which is designed for co-op,
it was very important that players
are able to move at the same speed
so they can stick together as a group.
So when it came to differentiating the javelins
and their movement field from each other,
we could only rely on things like custom jumps,
different steering rates, and switchback times.
In general, we used the Ranger
as a standard responsiveness tuning,
and went up and down roughly 15% per suit.
But this only got us so far.
To truly push the movement field difference
as far as we needed, we relied on animation to save the day,
which brings us over to David's domain.
Well, once we get the time values and the framework
from the design, we can adjust the feel further
through animation.
To exaggerate the speed or sluggishness,
we can clamp the values in the blend spaces
or spring-flow in the values to dampen the motion even further.
We separate the suits on the visual side through many ways.
Initially, all the suits look very unique,
as you can see from the base models and colors.
But once the players start changing things
with the array of paints and bit packs,
the differences start to get pretty muddy.
So the first thing to figure out when working on a suit
is the main base pose, creating an easily identifiable
and recognizable silhouette that separates it
from the other suits at a glance.
The Lancer is our stereotypical Rocket Man posing.
The medium speed pose has a spread out glide style,
and it goes into an aerodynamic facet pose,
stretched out with its arms back at its sides
and legs closer together.
Since our flight has an analog speed system,
so you're not just in one speed
and transitioning to the next,
where you can be feathering the input for half speeds,
we're always constantly blending the different speed sets,
which means we need to be aware
of how the poses look together in the mid-range.
so they can't be too different from each other,
or they won't blend well.
One of the pitfalls to try to avoid
when creating the poses is twinning.
It's easy to make the poses too symmetrical
and look like a T-pose,
basically making sure to offset any limbs slightly
if they need to be similar.
We also break out the poses through added layers
being on top well,
but it's best to try to fix this in the base pose.
Also in the faster speed, I make sure to not collapse the arms and legs too tightly to the body.
This gives the pose room to move and breathe and avoids clipping when the additive layers are running on top.
For all the suits, the medium flight speed shows the most character of the poses,
and we need to make sure that those unique parts bleed through when in the faster pose,
since it's easy for them to fall into the straight body, arms to the side posing.
For the Closses, I made it more upright with a bigger silhouette and less aerodynamic posing
with its arms wider and flexed at its side, treating the Closses as though it was a big
massive rock getting pushed forward from its jet engine, and not caring so much about aerodynamics.
The Closses has a faceplate visor that doesn't animate and only points forward, so we needed
the suit to be more upright to at least somewhat look like the visor area is pointing in the
right direction, instead of looking down.
I also made the legs closer together to bring more focus on the arms and the silhouette,
and I bent the knee to offset the back leg plates to avoid some clipping and to vary
up the posing from the Lancer.
For the storm, I really leaned into the superhero posing
that emphasized the cape and the right arm.
I made the left arm flex outward,
which spread out the cape better along the shoulder.
To showcase the magic arm, I pulled the right arm out
from the body for that clear silhouette.
I also did a tuning pass on the cape physics
to get the motion flowing just right,
which was a bunch of random tuning values,
so it was a lot of trial and error.
To get the gun streamlined against the body when in flight,
I added an offset atom to the weapon holster
to keep the gun from clipping the cape.
For the interceptor, I leaned away from the hummingbird flapping motions for the wings,
and instead used them like fins or rudders.
To keep the lines of the interceptor's model really clean, I always aimed for an arrow
type of graphic in the posing.
So the arms are always straight out with flat hands, and even in the faster pose, I made
sure the arms were separated from the body silhouette, and not tied at its sides to still
create that graphic.
I also bent the left leg like the storm, but kept them streamlined for more variation.
So the boost transitions, one of the places
we wanted to spend some animation bandwidth
was to sell that awesome feeling of flight transition
from the neutral speed to the faster boost speed.
We want you to feel that initial jolt
as soon as you press the throttle forward
instead of just a speed blend.
All these boost transitions follow the same type of style.
They open up quickly to a big anticipation pose,
then reversing shape and tightly collapsing
while moving forward in screen space,
eventually opening up slightly to settle
into that fast speed pose like an overshoot.
Which is another reason I made sure to open up the fast B-pose more to give them room to collapse tighter in the transition for contrast between the transition and the normal fast flight.
We also layered on top more animation and camera shake as well to sell that boost feel.
For the base pole setup, to make the physics and blending
into and out of flight easier, we
kept the y-axis facing up the whole time
and only rotating the capsule and the yaw,
which is how every other state works in our game.
It simplified the physics by putting more work and content
on animation.
So basically, the capsule and the physics model
never rotated in the other angles,
but just visually did it through animation.
That means for each javelin, just the base poses for flight
had nine animals for each slow, medium, and fast speed.
So 27 for each suit, just to get the visual roll, pitch,
working for the blended speeds.
And this decision did not just affect poses,
but every one-off motion, like the boost transitions,
enters, and barrel rolls, had to have
at least nine different variations as well
for the pitch and banking.
Even more if it needs to blend well back into the normal flight loop smoothly for the varied
speeds.
An example would be the boost transitions that needed 18 per suit, 9 for fast and 9
for medium to blend out smoothly in case you had little or full input forward at the end
of the transitions and while still being able to steer.
Also, keeping in mind that all the additive layers
had to work with these base poses and one-offs,
so different variations are mainly for hip orientation
but slight pose adjustments,
because any big rotation changes
might give you unexpected results.
These are one set of speed poses in Maya
with the trajectory pointing forward,
so you can see the pitch and banks
were all done just visually.
But this is what the banking poses look like in game.
The top row is the faster boost poses,
and the bottom row, the medium speeds.
You can see how the poses are just slight adjustments
of each other and how much the camera angle
is varied from the Maya trajectory.
So always make sure when posing
to work with the in-game camera in mind
and test in-game constantly.
What you see in Maya might not be the proper framing
when you're playing.
This is a representation of our layer stateful structure.
While the main base stateflow is running or transitioning,
we actually have all our additive poses
nested in a layer above them that are constantly running.
This allows us to blend the different additives on and off
independently from the transitions for more control.
Also, it lets the additive loops continue to play out
rather than restarting constantly every transition
so you're not just seeing the first same part of the loops
all the time.
We also have the turning additives split into two different layers so that we can offset
and delay the turning additives on the upper body from the lower body or vice versa, which
breaks up the linear way the additive motion would be applied on the whole body.
We use breathing type of additives
to break up the static poses and linear blend spaces.
There are two main breathing animations,
which are being layered on and blending
to create an organic feel.
There's a drifting type of motion
that varies the position of the limbs in screen space
and comes through more in the default speed.
The second is an air current shake type of motion
that is more pronounced in the boost,
which gives the feeling that the suits are tensing
the faster it goes from the air current
and causing it to shake more and drift less.
The turning additives are offset animations
created from the neutral base pose.
While we have the base poses to show the pitch and banking lean,
we use turning additives for reactionary motion
to make it feel more responsive to stick input.
It's the same concept as look or lean additives for turns or runs,
where it might take the body and the root motion
more time to rotate,
but the layered additives help lead the motion first
and remove some of that delayed feeling.
In the banking, it creates a twist and a lean
in the movement direction.
How big or small the additive post change created in Maya is,
is also another way to vary up the different feel of the suits
working in conjunction with the design tuning values.
Where the interceptor's turning additives
is a big motion to show responsiveness,
a suit like the Storm's turning is more minimal and graceful.
And for the pitch up and down, it breaks up the pose
and by curving the bend of the body backward and forward.
So it would just, or it would just be a flat pose
since the up, neutral and down base poses
don't have any spine rotation when they blend by themselves.
All the suits have different types of steering.
The Interceptor uses arms and wings
in a twisting banking motion,
where the Clossage is used more of an arm swing for steering.
One trick to creating the additives is in Maya.
You can have the turning additive offset poses
in a layer above to mimic the state flow.
Then when creating the base poses and animations,
you can cycle through them on and off
to check how it affects the base pose.
Also to make sure to use FK when rotating limbs
rather than IK when creating offset animals,
which would result in getting random rotations
instead of discrete, deliberate rotations
only in certain axes that you want.
To create the crashland state,
it's basically just an erratic additive layer
that is layered on top of the current flight layers.
So you can still steer and the flight underneath
and still work the same as before.
This technique can be used to layer on any type of motion
to create different status effects as well.
For example, either turning off all the additives
to create a freeze effect,
or really hard shake for a shock effect.
A great place to really sell and vary up the feel of the different flights was the one-off
motions, like the Lancer's enter.
Initially, we had the body really shooting forward of the trajectory and in screen space
to show the speed, but that caused a lot of gameplay bugs with the way it would need to
slow down and blend back to the trajectory, or flying off the screen when entering flight
facing left or right before the camera could catch up.
But we wanted to show the frantic power of the enter's atoms.
We accomplished that in the motion by first dropping the body
as though the Lancer was in free fall for a split second
before the boosters kicked in.
And to convey the power of it, I twisted the shoulders
when the boosters kicked in and had the arm shooting back
and grabbing onto the air to show it's stabilizing
from the initial power of the motion.
You can see the Lancer pops into a crouch pose
right away at the start and does a big pose change
that shoots forward into the horizontal flight pose
within four or five frames.
but then spends the rest of the frame time
settling in and stabilizing to sell the motion.
Like in fighting games, where it pops into the hip frame,
then spends the rest of the animation time
with overlap and settle.
Initially, the shoulder and body twist
was animated and built into the enters,
but next time I'd have the twist on a layer instead,
so it can be more varied and randomized.
The cost in general has the same type of motion as a Lancer,
but initially the body moves downwards more and backwards
instead of forwards right away
to sell that greater weight from the delay.
You can see the comparison here where they end up
in the same place at the same timing.
So instead of spending the time to stabilize like the Lancer,
it takes the Colossus longer to transition
to that horizontal pose.
And the arms are also delayed more to show weight,
but the full motion is still the same amount of range,
which helps for design.
The Storm's Enter is a mix of the Lancers and the Colossuses.
It has a big pop at the start,
but then blends forward into the horizontal pose
more slowly like the Colossus
to have that graceful storm feel.
For the interceptor, since I started animating the double
and triple jumps first, I went a bit crazy
and I knew I wanted to enter with more extreme motion
and I wanted to show that it had more speed
and agility than the Lancer.
But the Lancer's enter was already as fast as it gets
for that default motion.
I debated about entering using a twist type of motion, but that was too similar to the
barrel rolls, and then at first I tried using a front flip, but that caused an initial confusion
on the button press with the double and triple jumps, not knowing what happened right away,
whether it was a flip jump or an enter glide, so I went with a back flip.
I need to make the visual language very clear and the motion deliberate on the button press
to avoid any confusion.
So saving the backlit motion for enter glide
shows a clear, unique, big motion that you're in flight,
which looks and feels fluid for the player camera.
Also using a front flip for the exit anem
blends well with the triple jump flow.
That was one of the many lessons for me
in understanding that flight is only one state
in a chain of motions,
not just thinking of it as a separate state on its own.
Realizing how it feels to transition in and out
with the other states was really important.
A benefit of having one animator on the full traversal loop,
from jump to fall, hover and flight and swim,
gave a consistent feel and fluidity between all the states.
The consistency can come down to stylistic animation choices,
but can also depend on small differences of a few frames
or blend times in transitions.
The barrel roll was another one-off motion that we had.
For the Lancer, I made sure the barrel roll was very slow,
a very nonchalant, I've done it a billion times maneuver.
I thought of it as a very low effort veteran soldier
type of move where it's sluggish
and doesn't tighten up too much in the roll,
which is characteristic of the Lancer,
but also shows a contrast with the Interceptor.
For the Colossus, I initially was going to propose
a slow type of barrel roll that shoots out flares,
like a military carrier plane.
Then we opted to lean into a shield mechanic
and just added a shield arm override.
The Storm's Evade is just using the Lancer's barrel roll.
Since the storm is invisible most of the time
with a lot of visual effects,
I didn't feel the need to create another set,
especially with the time we had left.
And using a longer blend out,
we could hide the end pose differences.
The interceptor was basically a retarget of the Lancer,
but I added two more spins in the row
and tightened up the pose in the spin for a sleeker silhouette
and also shortened the recovery time to show it being lighter
and more agile than the Lancer.
To save animation costs, the barrel rolls are nine atoms
that we ended in a blended pose
between the medium and fast speed,
which we used the longer branch out back into flight
instead of doing 18 or 27 atoms.
It's such a big motion that it didn't need
to blend perfectly back.
So as you can see in the end,
when creating an animation system like Flight,
it's very different than creating one-off animations.
There are a lot that goes into getting the feel just right,
and only so much you can do through animation alone.
Having to depend on things like physics values,
tuning, cameras, controls, visual effects,
and countless small things all add up
to create a bigger picture.
It's really a marriage between design and animation
with lots of back and forth,
and even good communication
between the different departments.
Yeah, we truly feel that animation and gameplay design
are two sides of the same coin,
especially so when creating exotic traversal abilities
for player characters,
which are so dependent on player input.
One side influences the other,
and we hope to have shown how our different parts aligned
to create the final experience
that we deliver to our players.
To close things off, we just want to give a shout out
to our amazing team over at Bioware,
without whom we never could have realized the flying as well
as we did.
While we focused this talk around animation and design,
adding the ability to fly to a game
has huge ramifications across all disciplines
and how they do their work.
It required tons of collaboration and communication
and was truly a team effort.
These are just some of the key collaborators
that helped us bring flying to life.
We're honored and proud to be here today
to represent the entire team's hard work.
Thank you very much.
So, I don't know, do we have time for questions?
One, maybe two.
If anyone has any questions.
There's mics over there.
So hi, congratulations on your game.
I also played it, fantastic flight system.
My question is, there are games like Gravity Rush,
don't know if you played them, they don't have a ceiling.
And they don't impact gameplay without having a ceiling.
What was actually the decision that you made to just cut out the open world feeling of
flying everywhere?
Why did you implement that in the beginning instead of just experimenting with it?
Sure thing.
So we actually did experiment quite a lot, and Gravity Rush was one of many reference
games that we actually looked at on how they solved this problem.
It's a really good game, by the way.
I really like it.
So the thing with that that's interesting is what they do is they tend to hide it with VFX or things like that
that kind of blocks out the world when it's really far below you.
So we tried some approaches there, but I think the main concern there was still that
you didn't really have to fly through the world, you could just fly above it
and at that point you were just kind of taking off into the distance and you sat there for a long time without really needing to interact.
or do anything with it, and it tended to become kind of boring.
So that was the thing. As soon as we lowered the ceiling a little bit
and made you actually have to fly through the world,
we found that players were way more engaged by it.
So that's why we opted for that.
Okay. Thank you very much. Thank you.
Okay, if we have any more questions,
we're going to be out by the exit over there.
And just approach us,
and we're going to find the breakout room together.
Okay. Thank you. Thank you.