As the slide states, I am Brian Vinisky,
senior technical animator at Avalanche Studios.
I'm located in the New York City office
right in the middle of Manhattan.
Our other two locations are actually both in Sweden,
there's our OG studio in Stockholm,
and then our newest studio,
which officially opened last year, is in Malmo.
Our most recent games that you may know about
are the latest installments in the Just Cause series,
with Just Cause 4 having been released this past December,
Mad Max, Rage 2, which comes out on May 14th,
and notable self-published games,
such as The Hunter Called Wild, as well as Generation Zero,
which actually comes out this coming Tuesday, March 26th.
This is actually my third time speaking now,
so hopefully I've settled in
and I can give you a good experience with this presentation.
Today, I'll actually be talking about the content workflows
that we've employed for both the gameplay and cinematic teams
that began from the ground up during Just Cause 3
and evolved over the production of Just Cause 4.
I actually wanted to call this talk Maximizing Animation
and Cinematic Content Workflows for a AAA Project
that utilized two different DCC software packages
with a team size smaller than a typical AAA team,
but the full title wouldn't quite fit on the schedule board,
so I had to make do.
In all seriousness, the reason why I wanted to talk
about the work that we've been doing over the last few years
is because I truly believe that what we've been able to do
with the scope of our projects,
as well as the team size we've had, is quite remarkable.
It's not only a testament to the tools and processes
that have been employed, but by the fantastic teams
that I've had the pleasure of working with.
I'm gonna set the expectations going into this
to better help you understand what I'm going to talk about.
Consumers will look at your product.
They're going to see shiny things.
They're going to rate your graphics,
how you compare to other games, so on and so forth.
At the core of it all, though, everyone here
is producing content in very similar ways,
using workflows and methods underneath that shiny finish.
A large focus of mine over the years
has involved a lot of process.
And with that said, I'm not going
to give you a groundbreaking new piece of tech
during this talk, as it is, in fact,
about using and manipulating things that do already exist.
While I love sharing my thoughts and process,
I'm not saying this is the definitive way to do anything,
but it did work well for us.
Now, while a good portion of this talk
is focused on cutscene work, it's not a narrative talk,
so I won't be going into detail
about that side of cinematics,
although certain parts of our pipeline were created
to allow for the extra work that came into narrative changes.
It's also not a talk about the overall look of anything
or the in-game tech behind it.
And it's not a talk that discusses creating high-quality,
high-quality content,
or how to hit a certain level of quality.
It is about managing large quantities of content
and making the lives of the animators a little easier
through decisions and work done to improve
the process of content creation
during the production of Just Cause 4.
And I wanted to make sure that no matter the position
that you are in, whether it be a small studio,
large studio, or maybe just yourself,
that you can take back a few things with you
and without the need of a programmer or some special tech,
do anything that I presented to you
as you don't always have the luxury of programming support
or an army of tech artists or tech animators by your side.
I also wanted to make sure that this talk was accessible
for any level of knowledge.
Because of this, I'll probably go over things
that some of you may already know or have done yourselves
in order to better help those who may not know
about those particular topics.
This is even more prominent when I get
into motion builder specifics
because of the greater lack of support
that you find out there compared to, say, Maya.
Slight heads up, though.
This talk is about to be a bit of a hodgepodge
because I have some odds and ends
that I do want to share among some of the bigger tasks,
so hopefully you don't mind a bit of random tips or tricks
mixed in with pipeline and workflow.
In an effort to keep this talk as accessible as possible,
I want to make sure I define some terms
because I found that in practicing this talk,
a few different disciplines across the studio
weren't quite sure what they were.
I had animators asking me what JSON was
and programmers telling me that I don't need
to explain what JSON is.
I'm just going to lay this all out here for all of you.
So DCC refers to Digital Content Creation Application,
and for this talk, the DCCs that I will be mentioning
are Maya and MotionBuilder.
Mobu is shorthand for motion builder.
JSON stands for JavaScript Object Notation,
but simply put, it's a language-independent data format
that lets you store data to be accessed
in a very straightforward and logical manner.
If you're aware of what a dictionary is in coding,
JSON looks and behaves very similarly on the surface.
Headless refers to running Maya in standalone mode,
which means that you're using full-on Maya
in all of its features, but it runs in the background
without actually opening up its visual component.
Baking and plotting, as animators and tech animators
should already know, is the process
of converting animation data to key frames on every frame.
Since this term is different between applications,
I just want to make sure that everyone knows
that baking is the term for this in Maya,
and plotting is the term for that in MotionBuilder.
TA in this case is short for technical animator.
Mocap is short for motion capture.
And when I say JC3 or JC4,
I mean Just Cause 3 or Just Cause 4, respectively.
Now that you know those key terms,
here's a brief overview of what's to come
over the course of this talk.
I'm going to examine the two main DCC packages
that we used, Maya and MotionBuilder.
This includes what we were working with
from the JC3 pipeline,
and what we did differently for JC4.
Additions made to that pipeline,
and the tasks that we tried to automate
as much as possible.
And speaking of automation, I think
it's worth looking at the batching process that
was set up at the studio.
A standalone UI was created that allowed us to quickly set up
customized batch scripts for any tool or process we had in Maya.
Finally, I'll end up by going over our cutscene tools
and how we set up the content for running the pipeline,
as well as get a little in-depth on how
the actual transferring of content between Maya
and MotionBuilder was achieved.
Now in order to better understand a bit about my job
at Avalanche Studios, it's important to define the role
of a technical animator at the studio,
as every studio within the entire game development world
seems to have a bit of a different definition
for what a tech animator or even a tech artist should be.
To illustrate this better, I've thrown some buzzwords
for you here up on the screen.
And the tech animators at our studio, all at the very least,
should know a little bit of everything
and have proven the ability to pick up new unknowns
and very quickly adapt and learn.
For myself alone, I've dug into everything involved
with the animation process to some degree.
I've built a ton of Python-based tools and scripts,
supported both the gameplay and cutscene teams,
dug into state machines, in-editor content,
and have worked with each and every department in some way,
from the vehicle team, AI designers,
graphics programmers, almost everyone.
Because of this, a TA at our studio
needs to be ready to roll with the punches at any moment.
They also need to be able to solve the overall
major problem, which is how will we maintain
so much content when we are limited in our time
and personnel?
Another aspect of being a TA at Avalanche
is that each project utilizes DCCs and workflows
in a bit different way.
Now this leads me to the question for JC4 specifically,
Maya or MotionBuilder.
While we were mainly using Maya for Just Cause 3,
we did have some tools created during development
that allowed for animators to push an animation from Maya
into Mobu and also take an animation from Mobu
and bring that back into Maya.
However, this was not extensive enough
to have MotionBuilder be anything
other than a supplemental tool as opposed to a standalone.
As a Maya guy, it did take me a while
to really appreciate what MotionBuilder could do,
but now I do realize that the things it does well
compared to Maya, it does really, really well.
I've also seen firsthand some passionate debates
between folks on which one is the superior product.
You'd actually be amazed at how heated they actually get.
Just kind of an anecdote, I made a Twitter poll recently
while prepping for this talk to kind of get a gauge
on what people use, and the results were pretty staggering
at how much Maya is loved.
But if you actually go back and check this thread,
there's some really, really heavy
MotionBuilder lovers there,
especially if you see Brad Clark.
He's always up on MotionBuilder.
You should check out this thread
if you wanna see kind of the debate that goes on.
So, when asked by our MotionBuilder,
Why not both?
It did almost seem like a death sentence to say yes
to building up a pipeline that could truly support
two DCCs, considering at the time there was only
one tech animator, myself, and six animators to support
in two pretty different pieces of software.
But our team was pretty split up on preference
and expertise, so I decided it was more beneficial
to allow them to all work the way that they wanted to
and were comfortable with, considering the lack of time
that we actually had to complete the project.
especially since we were dealing with so many different factors
that worked better in one or the other.
Since many other studios out there do, in fact,
use both MotionBuilder and Maya,
we knew that building up this pipeline wasn't a crazy idea,
but the challenge would be to develop something
that was robust enough with our lack of people power.
Now, in order to try and explain how overloaded the team
actually was in working with a AAA open world title
such as Just Cause 4,
I do want to start off with a few quick facts.
On the gameplay side of animation,
we had six animators to support.
And no, the one and a half tech animators
isn't like a King Solomon cut the baby in half thing.
That's just me quantifying that I was the only tech animator
for the first few years of the project.
And we brought on TA help a little bit later on.
About a year, year and a half left in the project.
In the end, we had around 7,200 unique animations,
and among six animators, that's quite daunting to manage.
It equates to about 1,200 animations per animator
for the entire project,
very roughly 2.7 animations per working day
over the course of roughly two years,
which is kind of the amount
of actual production time we had.
Now factor that in with the amount of time necessary
for things like polish, XNs capturing,
throwaway R&D work,
and meetings that everyone loves to be part of.
Now, as far as preference for those six animators,
we had one person who was 100% MotionBuilder,
never touched Maya, one person who was Maya,
never touched MotionBuilder,
and the other four were sort of a mix in between.
As far as the pipeline goes,
we did have to follow this structure,
which I know that many studios who utilize
both MotionBuilder and Maya actually do follow.
You start with MotionBuilder to handle any sort of mocap data
using the tools it has, such as animation stitching,
pinning, and the take system for organizing content.
You then move that content over to Maya from animation,
polish, and finaling.
And then from Maya, you export to your game.
In our case, since we did have an animator that only used
MotionBuilder, he would stay in MotionBuilder until he was
ready to export to the game.
And from there, I had a process set up that would
allow him to pass his content through Maya when exporting.
And we needed to do this to make sure that all of the
correctives and the custom rig features got picked up before
they got exported to the game.
Now, keep in mind that we were not using
any sort of runtime animation or rigging,
so it was extra important to make sure
that we stream everything through Maya on export
to ensure that quality control.
All right, so let us dig into Maya.
I need to think about what we already had from JC3,
what we needed to do for JC4
that would get us to where we needed to go.
We already had many basic tools that you probably expect
to have in a AAA game pipeline,
but after working with them for an entire project cycle,
we were able to pinpoint the pros and cons,
figuring out what to improve on.
Matching parent spaces and IK, FK limbs,
as well as setting up constraints
have been very standard for years,
but how could we improve them
or even use them a little differently than before?
Did the tools we have overcomplicate things?
In the case of foot planting, animators on JC3
had to manually tag the content when this was occurring.
How could we automate that?
How about all those scripts and random tools
that animators find online, install or use,
and then they just end up breaking Maya
for all the tech animators and it's a joy to fix?
There could have been a better way to handle that
and essentially animator-proof things.
There were also attachment tools that would help set up
weapons and props for animators,
but they ended up being so cumbersome
with too many buttons and options
that we actually just got rid of them.
Animators tended to have their own workflows
and set up attachments on their own ways,
and a lot of this was in part to outside tools
that they had found or just processes
that they were so used to that
I didn't really have to worry about that.
We also had a file browser for the animators
where they could find and open Maya files from within Maya,
as well as multi-select files and folders
for batch exporting animation.
Finally, a tool from Maya to MotionBuilder and back to Maya
did exist, but it was very limited,
and we didn't really have a good system to transfer multiple
takes back and forth.
Now just visualizing some of this right now,
we had a lot of those processes broken down
into one button clicks for JC3,
thinking that it would be easy and awesome for hotkeying,
but in many places this really wasn't efficient.
This did allow for a few things like
space and IKFK matching,
to have the ability to be used as hotkeys,
but the physical UI was sort of a nightmare
and a hassle to navigate.
All of our tools also had their own dedicated UI window,
which was a pain to keep track of
as well as organize visually.
In addition to these tools, it was sort of the Wild West
when animators started to download these third party
tools and install them themselves, or create random
shelf buttons for Mel and Python scripts.
Going back a slide, we did have animator-organized third-party
tools, but they were completely unsupported by tech animation.
Essentially, we gave the authority to one animator
who oversaw this process.
He used the network folder to add scripts to,
and then called them in a custom user setup file
that any animator could grab.
It worked well enough, but it wasn't really
something that I could oversee or easily quality check.
So because of this, all of our supported as well as
unsupported tools.
came together like that shoebox full of cables
and wall chargers that you keep in the closet
just in case you might need them someday.
Now, for Just Cause 4, instead of trying to add more,
the focus was to see where we could scale back.
Like those constraint tools,
what else didn't we actually need?
What needed a restructure?
What tools needed some serious code refactoring?
When it came down to it, we almost started from scratch
on many things.
There was also a lot of refactoring
and some decisions made to either completely get rid
of things that were barely if ever used,
as well as to push to automate as many things as possible.
This led to the main goal.
Instead of trying to solve every little issue,
we would give more power to the animators.
We realized that we didn't have to try
and make every little thing a button
or try to solve every single problem.
We also realized that the animators in the end
didn't want to work that way.
So simplicity became the goal.
Now, in order to reach our goal of simplicity,
we started focusing on efficiency, speed,
user preference, and customization.
The first thing we did was tie all of our tools
into one main toolbar that can be set and customized
as the animators themselves want.
After watching other GDC talks or checking out
online resources, I realized that many other studios
tie their tools into one specific animation toolbar.
So I wanted to set out to do that first.
but also give it a bit of something extra.
If the animation tools are open on Maya close,
they open when you reopen Maya.
They can be docked or undocked.
You can pop out tools if you only need one,
but don't want the entire UI in your way.
If you like the UI,
but you don't really want to use certain tools,
you can completely hide them from the tool set.
You can also rearrange the order of the tools
if you use one more than others
and prefer it at the top of the stack.
Instead of having animators click a ton of buttons
or use convoluted interfaces to set attachments,
for JC4 we created a simple one-button
attach-detach system that could easily set up
specific attachments, as you see here,
with a parachute and wingsuit.
Underneath the hood of this process,
it detects which rig is active,
and then when the attach function is run,
just sets up the active rig accordingly.
Further, thanks to the power of space switching,
once attached, you can quickly set specific
as to how you wanted things like handles
or buckles to follow the character.
Now, IKFK and space matching are pretty standard these days.
So what we set out to do, instead of reinventing all of
this, was to evaluate and refactor the way that we ran
these tools to create quicker times for both running IKFK
matching and space switching.
Single frame matching almost happened instantaneously now.
And if you wanted to match for the entire timeline, it really
only took a matter of seconds.
Now something that was introduced back on JC3 to our rigs,
the further enhanced quicker speeds of space,
and further enhanced by the quicker speeds
of space matching, was what we called
the driver root control.
You can see it here being that giant brownish colored
control above the character's head,
when it's not selected,
that is controlling the entire character.
Now say you want to animate the entire character
here dangling, with both arms and legs in IK.
You can easily place the driver root to the position
you want to rotate them, set the space for hands, feet,
and the cog control to this driver root,
animate it, say, tilting left and right,
and then space match all of these controls
at once back to world space, where you can then
polish each one individually.
I kind of like to call this a locator on steroids,
because it functions the same way that many animators do
like to use locators to bake and transfer animation.
But having it built into the rig and ready to work
with the space matching gives you
immediate out-of-the-box functionality
the second you reference a character into your scene.
We also introduced rotation order matching.
The rigs themselves were set up with best practice rotation
orders on all controls, but adding the ability
for an animator to change the rotate orders
of the controls on the fly gave them even more control.
We also gave the animators the ability to create custom
selection sets on the fly that were also
simple to make hot keyable.
Multi-select the controls you'd like to group together,
click Create Selection Set, and that's it.
Now you've got a custom group of controls that you can grab
instantly.
Even more power was granted to the animators
to be able to set up their own custom pick walking
for anything.
On JC3, we did have pick walking on the character rigs,
but that's it.
In order to set those settings,
we would have to hard code it into the rig.
This time around, the character rigs
did have default pick walk settings,
but the animators could customize this
any way that they would like,
and also add pick walking to whatever else they may choose.
We also added a custom scripts tab to the tool set.
That tangled mess of third-party scripts and snippets
were turned into official, unofficial scripts.
The TAs can add third-party tools officially
and per force for deployment,
and animators can locally add anything
that they want to their Maya scripts folder,
and then magically populate that tool nice and neatly here.
There's no need to override
or create a custom user setup file.
It's all here for you to pretty much use out of the box.
All those random Mel and Python scripts
that were now nice and neatly organized
were also labeled in a way that anyone
could see and understand.
All custom scripts have an auto-create shelf button.
The ability to hide and show what you would want
just like our official tools.
And a customized help pop-up that includes a unique command,
which through the use of metadata,
create custom runtime commands that, when sourced,
to allow for the animators to easily apply
to hotkeys and marking menus.
Now, I want to show you one specific example
of workflow improvements that actually took away
the power from the animators, but it was not power
that they really wanted.
So here's one of those.
On JC3, any time we wanted to grab footstep data from a file,
we needed to have an animator go and manually tag any time
a footstep occurred.
They had a tool that easily allowed them to scrub through
an animation and click left plant, right plant, left plant,
right plant, so on and so forth.
You can see here that the red and blue foot placement
markers that are getting set for all the frames where a
foot will hit the ground.
While this is a pretty simple and easy process to do,
it's really monotonous and it takes up a lot of time.
That's time that takes away from, say, actually animating.
On JC4, I wanted to take this out of their hands
and automate that process completely.
All it took was a pretty small script.
Now, don't worry about trying to read this.
I'm gonna break it down for you.
I just wanted to kind of give you an idea
of how small that script actually was.
The first thing that we need to do
is find the distance between the ankle joints
within consecutive frames.
For example, let's say you're looking at a run cycle
and the left leg of a character
is swinging back down to hit the ground.
On frame seven, you grab the position
of the left ankle joint in world space,
then you grab the world space position
of the left ankle joint on frame eight.
You can then calculate the distance apart
that the ankle joint has traveled from frame to frame.
Here's a simple function that can return
the difference in distance of two points.
Here, we're just saying that we want to evaluate
the left and right foot joints,
and then depending on an animation being a walk or a run,
there is a predetermined threshold
that is slightly different based on the fact
that the distance each foot moves,
depending on the gait of the character locomotion,
is pretty different.
If you look at a run cycle,
the ankle joint will have a further distance
between frames than a walk cycle.
So what did this threshold actually do?
We know that when the foot is planted,
its position doesn't change a whole lot from frame to frame.
This value simply says, do not bother even looking
at anything greater than this.
It was sort of a hacky but efficient way
to filter out any non-obvious,
any obvious non-planted values,
as sometimes those can otherwise mistakenly get tagged
by the character's leg movement when not planted.
Now here's the bulk of the script
that takes these factors into account.
We analyze twice here, one time for each foot.
The analyzation goes through the timeline,
finds the current value of the world space position
of the foot on each frame,
and compares that value with the world space position
of the foot from the previous frame.
If a distance value is less than the frame before,
as well as less than the frame after that,
we tag the frame the foot is planted.
By tagging the smallest value of movement
in a particular range of values,
we assume that the script has found a planted foot.
For walks, we also added a filter
that made sure a foot wasn't too drastically rotated up
and down or twisted, since the slower nature of walks
meant that the distances of the position of the feet
weren't as drastic from frame to frame.
So surveying the pitch and roll of the foot
gave us another good indication that a foot was actually
planted and flat on the ground.
Another really nice thing that we could do from here is take
the footstep data, and depending on if an animation
is a walk or a run, determine when you'd hear a cloth sound.
The character almost always hits the point where their
legs cross each other after a step.
For runs, this was two frames after a step.
And for walks, it was five.
Thanks to this consistent behavior, we can automatically
gather cloth sound triggers.
And not only are we gathering footstep data, but cloth sound
data, this made the audio team extra happy, as they do not
have to worry about manually tagging all
of this in the game.
They were already benefiting from the automatically tagged
footsteps, as was VFX as well.
So hey, we just made the animators, the sound team, and
the VFX team pretty damn happy.
To the surprise of the animation, VFX, audio teams,
and myself, this method had a really good success rate.
I'd say about 85% to 90% of footsteps and cloth
were tagged correctly just because of this.
The rest was manually fixed, as sometimes extra footstep tags
snuck their way in, or a tag here or there was missed.
But the amount of work to do that small bit of cleanup
was a lot less than actually going
through every single animation and tagging those footsteps
by hand.
Now let's see this in action.
Here's a run.
And by quickly scrubbing,
we can see where the foot is planted.
The right foot there is planted on about eight or nine,
the left on about 17 or 18,
right on 28, so on and so forth.
Now, we run the script,
and it cycles through the animation
as it evaluates each foot.
When it is done evaluating,
we get our auto-generated footstep tags.
Let's actually check and see how accurate this really is.
We got a right footstep on eight or nine,
a left footstep on about 18 or 19,
a right on 28 or 29,
a left on 37, 38,
right on 47, 48,
and a left on 57.
So it's pretty accurate.
And just for fun, let's evaluate four feet
and run this script on a llama,
which is the newest of the animal heroes
in the Just Cause series.
All right, here's our auto-generated data now.
There's a right rear footstep about six or seven there.
A left rear about eight or nine.
Right front about 11 and left front is around 12.
All right, that's pretty good.
Ooh, quick moving over to Mobu now.
Here's what we had custom on JC3.
Yeah, nothing custom.
While we did have a way to send Maya content to MotionBuilder
and then MotionBuilder to Maya, that entire process
on the MotionBuilder side of things only involved making
sure that you save your MotionBuilder file with the
take that you want to transfer over to Maya saved as the
active one.
The only Maya-specific tools that we really had were just
the Maya tools that grabbed FBX files and transferred
animation onto our Maya rigs, or would bake down and export
animation content in Maya out of FBX.
Our goal for MotionBuilder was to actually make some tools.
Now, we did actually have some animation tools
that my counterparts in Sweden had developed over the years,
but there was nothing that existed for project
and workflow-specific needs for us on Just Cause 4.
So now we were developing actual MotionBuilder tools
and allowing animators to use it as more of a standalone tool.
We wanted to extend the default HIK rigs
to allow for more from within MotionBuilder
in terms of things such as retaining root motion data,
weapon attach data, and any other reference
aside from the default HIK controls.
We also needed to drastically improve the process
of sending content from MotionBuilder to Maya.
It became necessary to send multiple takes
from within a MotionBuilder file over to Maya,
which then handled animation content
on a one-animation-per-file structure.
In addition to multiple takes,
we also had to send full cinematic sequences
from MotionBuilder to Maya,
just as we had to do the same from Maya to MotionBuilder.
Now I'll detail that a bit more later
when I actually talk about cutscenes.
What we had on JC3 was the basic default HIK rig
with no additional features.
What we needed for JC4 was to add extensions
to the HIK rigs so that we could pull that data,
retain it, and modify if necessary.
We actually start off with Maya,
we actually start off in Maya with the A pose character,
T pose it, and characterize it.
Now this is our base to work on.
From here we can either build a Maya rig
or an HIK rig from within Maya.
With the MotionBuilder rig, we actually took that
and brought it into MotionBuilder as an FBX.
And that FBX that was generated,
that was brought into MotionBuilder
has sort of an auto build function
that we run in MotionBuilder
that creates the rig extensions
to things like the root bone there
that you see, it's a yellow arrow,
and a bunch of key reference joints.
Possibly you can see here,
I put a cursor on the right hand's
plus sign cross-licking thing,
there's a left side one,
and there's one on the chest for aim target
where animators could animate the...
motion data for where the character was pointed.
So now they actually had controls on these things to
animate those in MotionBuilder, and it's easy to
actually port that data over to Maya.
Now the team has a custom MotionBuilder rig that they're animating with.
Now that the team has a custom MotionBuilder rig that they're animating with, they need
to be able to push that content over to Maya.
On JC3, animators would have to save their MotionBuilder file with the take that they
want to transfer to Maya as the active take.
Since animators were utilizing Mobu much more this time around, and especially for the animator
on our team that only used MotionBuilder, this really wasn't going to cut it.
Some files could contain as many takes such as this one.
So we needed to make a way to quickly get any and all content
out of MotionBuilder.
We developed this UI that allows you to pick and choose
whatever animations you want, which then get plotted down
and completely stripped down so that the result is a simple
skeleton that is very simply able to be quickly brought
into Maya and transferred to the Maya rigs.
Now it may not be a ton, but these changes did make
MotionBuilder much more accessible as a standalone
tool for the team.
Also, I don't have it listed, I don't have it
shown here, rather, but I have it listed.
There was a batch tool for the Xsens content
to bring into MotionBuilder,
but it's literally just a button
that kinda asks what directory you wanna import,
so for sake of visually not being too pleasing
or interesting, I'm just listing it here
to tell you that we did have a batch way
to bring in Xsens data to our animation,
or to MotionBuilder, rather.
Now, this section isn't quite as long as the others
because it was at the core,
but it was really at the core of everything.
I'm gonna restart that sentence.
This section isn't quite as long as the others,
but it really at the core of everything
was making everything quicker and more automated
for both the tech animators and animators.
This batch processing tool became the central core to
running heavy processes into and out of Maya.
Everything was streamed through here.
The way this works is that the user selects a batch process
from a list of JSON files that we've made for them.
This could be an animation export or a
Mobutu Maya transfer.
When they select a file, any options pertaining to that
file show up on the right.
The user can tweak those settings as necessary.
When you load a script, any directories with files that
pertain to the script also pop up on the left.
When you select a folder, the files within that directory
show up for you to multi-select and run the batch on.
When you run a batch, a tab pops up
with the UI that runs a Maya standalone thread
and batches your content headless.
You are able to run different processes at multiple times
at once without ever actually opening up Maya.
This is optimal for computer performance and speed
of data processing.
It's also very optimal for being 100% animator-friendly,
as they do not have to worry about anything
from command line and could potentially
customize these batch options themselves.
Now, quick look under the hood.
We have a very simple JSON dictionary
where we state some rules and list out
all of the options for the user.
In this case, we're looking at our Maya animation exporter.
We tell this file what file types to look for,
which directory to look for them in,
which batch process to actually run,
the version of Maya standalone to use,
and all the options that we wanna list here.
Now using as an example animation exporting,
these options let you create things such as toggles
for maybe turning on or off the generation
of a debug animation file,
or a line edit for customizing what you want
to call the Perforce change list
that all your animations get added to.
We set the type of UI widget, what to label it,
the default behavior, and the command that we will use
to pass the state of each option
through the Python batch file when running the process.
which then magically populates your options here,
as seen a minute ago, whenever you hit that select,
and whenever you hit that select batch script option,
you can choose your specific batch.
You actually see that here I have a few batch scripts
that I've set up for myself.
Some of these are actually official scripts
that were checked into Perforce.
Some really aren't.
There's like a cut scene AnimExport02 and 03 here
that were just kind of local things
that I quickly set up for testing.
But essentially you can either do anything
for yourself locally or do something
that you could check in and allow animators
or any other person to use.
So in the end, thanks to this nifty batch tool,
not only was I able to set up anything for myself
really fast to start churning out lots of content
through Headless Maya,
it opened up a ton of time-saving possibilities
for the animators, too,
and not just for export animations.
In fact, even though our pipeline called for content
to be passed through Maya before export to the game,
our MotionBuilder-only animator used this batch tool
in conjunction with the FBX takes batch exporting tool
that we had within MotionBuilder,
and he never once actually opened up Maya, not once.
We just had the batch script set up for him to select all his
FBX exports here, and then the tool would go through each file,
throw the animation onto the applicable rig,
and export that to game.
And now just with the few months ago,
MotionBuilder 19 coming out with a headless mode,
I plan on actually upgrading this
to adding headless MotionBuilder into the mix.
A world where we're pushing MotionBuilder content
to and from Maya, exporting it out to the game,
all without the need of having to open up any visual DCC
is really a world that I want.
All right, on to cinematics.
We had two full-time team members
as far as managing the actual animation and camera content
goes.
One of these was myself, and the other was our cinematic artist.
In the end, we had about 56 unique sequences.
This number also doesn't include our single camera, single cut,
in-game scenes that were used to quickly set up missions.
Our smallest sequence had about five shots
that made it up, with our largest sequence
having up to 60 cuts.
While all characters and cutscenes were bipedal humans,
we had 12 unique rigs of various heights and sizes
to manage and make sure that they were
correctly used in shots.
Between all of these characters and sequences,
we had about 65 minutes of actual cutscene footage.
Yes, sorry, that was a phrase in the question.
We did have 65 minutes of cutscene footage.
Now actual hands-on production for cut scenes
didn't even start until about halfway through the project,
and we literally didn't have actual content to work with
until about six months before we went gold.
So that's, uh-oh.
Looking at the process, this may not seem too daunting
when you look at what we were working with,
because it's fairly straightforward on the surface.
In creating JC4, like any of our other AAA projects
at Avalanche Studios, we work with outside vendors
for all motion capture and content solving
when it comes to cinematics.
To start the process, we have a narrative team at the studio,
as well as a cinematic artist who
worked on the story and dialogue, which then,
those ideas were transferred into storyboards and animatics
to try and lock down things like pacing and camera work.
Once this was nailed down and our actors signed on,
we had a shoot.
The shoot involved both our Avalanche Studios cinematics
team and our vendor working together with the actors
to best replicate all the factors that our animatics had
tried to prove out.
When the shoot was done, the vendor provided us
with all the takes that were shot during the shoot,
and our team at the studio went through
and selected which content that they wanted to use
and have the vendor solve for us.
After this, there was some back and forth
between us and the vendor to make sure
that our character rigs were set up nicely
for things like good proportions
based on the actor proportions,
and then the content was solved on our rigs,
polished, and delivered to us
as baked-down skeletal animation in the FBX data format.
Each shot was delivered as a separate FBX file
with camera, characters, vehicles, weapons,
and props for that shot.
The content was then brought straight into Maya,
transferred to our Maya rigs,
and then exported to the game from there.
So we're done, right?
In a perfect world, yeah.
But making games is hardly a perfect process, right?
Going back to that gameplay pipeline
we were already working with, we had this pipeline.
Once we started getting cinematic content from our vendor,
we added that content in a similar fashion
to what we had already done with the gameplay content.
This transfer is quite easy to do.
We set up a batch script that takes all the delivered
baked down skeletal mocap data,
and since the skeletons are a perfect one-to-one match
with the Maya control rigs,
we transfer and bake that animation over quite easily.
Now of course, since we're making games,
random emergencies or unknown needs
may come from out of nowhere.
Needs that with the luxury of time and a larger team
can sometimes be met handedly.
But time and numbers were definitely not on our side,
so, yeah, did not really please us to go this way.
But for the sake of brevity,
I'm not gonna go into a post-mortem right now
pertaining to this issue.
I will say that as a technical animator,
my most important role is that of a problem solver.
When working out any issues, the first thing you do
is assess the situation and come up with a viable solution
based off of that.
So going back to our cinematic content integration process,
we needed to be able to do this.
After we got our content into Maya on our game-ready rigs,
we needed a way to get our cut scenes back into Motion Builder
to allow for dealing with changes, tweaks,
and critical fixes or updates.
Now some of you may be asking,
why would you actually go backwards?
And I get that it's not ideal.
It's kind of why I paused a little earlier.
But simply put, our cinematic artist
who handled the camera work, sequence edits,
and any cut scene setup was 100% a MotionBuilder guy. 100%.
Just like that other animator.
This guy did give his best try to learn Maya.
He really did give his best effort,
but the amount of time that it takes to make edits
using the tools that MotionBuilder has,
not only mention the great frame rate
that it gives you for playback,
Remember, animation caching in Maya
just happened a few months ago.
We really couldn't do what we needed to do
without being able to take our Maya files
with that solved motion capture data from the vendor,
put it back in a motion builder,
and then send that back out to Maya for final approval
and export to the game
once any new edits and changes were made.
So in order to best explain
how we tackled our cinematics workflow,
I want to break down one of our cut scenes
that we had put through its paces.
So let's start by watching the full cut scene.
Load up the truck! We're leaving in 60 seconds!
Did you organize this ambush?
Si.
Most of the stuff we recovered is standard black ammunitions.
But I also found some of these.
We're not sure what they do.
We didn't want to mess with them.
Um, there's a bunch more left in the truck.
Good. Fine, Sohento.
These could be useful.
Anyone have a screwdriver?
Are you adding that to your grappler? No jodas.
You have to make do with whatever you find.
What are you going to do with that?
Que chimba!
Black Hand are coming, Sargento!
Mierda! Listo, I'll drive the truck.
I've got a chopper nearby waiting to extract this.
Make sure you get there in one piece.
Gracias, parcero.
All right, so that cut scene shows our main hero, Rico,
meeting with one of his supporting pals, Sargento,
who gives him the part that he adds to his grappling device
that allows the player to use the airlifter in-game
to pretty much turn anything into a giant flying mass.
This particular cut scene has a good mix of characters,
vehicles, weapons, and props,
so we're managing a lot of different types of content.
To start, let's look at the process that we need to take
in order to get our Maya content into MotionBuilder.
We have our Maya files shot by shot,
but MotionBuilder doesn't really work this way.
We needed to take these individual shots
and transfer them into MotionBuilder in one long sequence
so that they can be set up properly
for editing in story mode.
So I love JSON.
I use it all the time to store data settings
for anything and everything I can.
It's everywhere in our pipelines.
It's probably in yours too, even if you don't know it.
It is the base at which our Cinematics content workflow
is driven.
Using the power of JSON files to organize all of our cutscenes
was the solution that not only bridged
the gap between Maya and MotionBuilder,
but it organized our content in a way
that it's really easy to parse and locate with a simple call.
Every cutscene had a master JSON file
for the cutscene data, which included the scene name,
the campaign that it was part of, all characters, props,
shots.
vehicles, and weapons that appear in the entire cutscene
at any point.
Then we had a JSON file for each separate shot that told
us the specifics for that particular camera cut.
We again have the campaign and scene names, the shot number,
the characters that are actually in that cut, the
props in that cut, vehicles in that cut, and weapons.
We also have the start and end frame numbers stored.
Now just to better illustrate what this means for us,
let's just take a look at a few select shots
within this cut scene.
In the first shot, we have just Rico in this dirt bike.
Since there's nothing else in the scene that isn't already
part of the environment, only these two items are stored in
the JSON file for this particular shot.
The second shot is only Rico, so he's the only
thing that we store.
The third shot sets us back to a wide angle
that reintroduces the dirt bike
and brings Sargento into the scene with those two trucks.
I'm gonna skip over the fourth shot to the fifth one
since this shot includes a little bit of everything.
All four characters are seen as our three vehicles.
You can actually see the dirt bike
a little bit behind that tree.
That also includes a prop,
which is the crate in the back of the truck.
And if you can't tell,
the rebel there is holding a weapon in the middle.
Now in an effort to not completely force you
to look at code, here's what this looks like
in a more visually pleasing way.
Because we have all this finer detail
stored the way that we do, I don't actually
have to open up Maya to find out
what is in any given shot, which I'll say
is even far easier, quicker, and nicer
than trying to find this stuff on a spreadsheet.
I can also run a cutscene export, headless, in our batch tool and filter it down to only,
say, Sargento, because maybe we made a small rig update or added a secondary animation
pass on his jacket.
This batch process that we set up will parse every JSON file for the scene, and instead
of wasting time opening shots where Sargento doesn't exist to check that he's there, it
will immediately go straight for only the files that he's in.
For a small team like ours, this time savings,
when you think about the number of characters,
scenes, and shots that we're working with
was a huge, huge win.
Now, this also made it easier to shot by shot
deal with our Maya to Motion Builder transfer.
Now, let's start our content passing process
on the Maya side.
It's time to take our entire sequence
that is cut into multiple files in Maya
and stitch that all together into one giant sequence
of content so that it is Mobu-friendly
for a cinematic artist to use with the story mode
and camera switcher.
A short look into this part of script that does it for us.
I promise I'll go quick.
When we run our process, we open a fresh Maya scene.
Let's call this the master file.
We immediately start at negative 15,000 for a frame.
This just ensures that each individual shot
is having its content transferred over
and it doesn't trip up the shot before it.
Before this actually though,
the JSON file for the whole cut scene itself is red
and all cameras, characters, et cetera that exist
are referenced into the Maya scene.
And now that everything exists in the Maya file that we need,
we loop through all the individual JSON file shots,
referencing in the corresponding Maya file shot,
and adding all the animation data for characters,
weapons, et cetera, sort of in chunks.
So if you were to transfer that data over one by one,
you would kind of do it with like shot one goes here,
shot two goes here, shot three goes here.
And it's kind of stacked one after the other.
Once all the shots are fully transferred
into this master Maya file, there we go.
Once all shots are fully transferred
into this master Maya file, all keyframes are grabbed
and moved up to frame 101, so we're not dealing
with crazy negative space on the timeline.
You could easily just make zero your start frame,
but I personally like to leave frames zero to 100 open
in case any necessary padding might be needed.
Now, as you can see here, though, we have all rigs,
cameras, and everything else kind of nice
and neatly spliced into one.
Now, there's another script that actually
bakes all this animation down, cleans up everything,
and only makes sure that we have skin characters
and baked down key frames on the bones.
Once this file is exported to FBX,
it's ready for some story editing in Motion Builder.
So picture this, the Maya file you just saw was baked down,
transferred into MotionBuilder,
it's made its way to the cinematic artist,
this person's made all the necessary edits
to the cameras, character positions, whatever.
This person goes up to you and says,
Brian, it's ready.
So now we're there.
I just wanted to skip the whole part of his editing.
Here's that MotionBuilder file.
Since we're ready to send it back to Maya,
we need to split that up,
we need to split up every single one
of these individual clips that exist in Story.
And then we need to export them out into each individual file,
into individual Maya files, as per our pipeline,
in order for us to finish off the scene and get it in game.
In order to do this, we need to run some commands in Motion
Builder that export out data that
can be brought into Maya quickly and with little to no load
times.
Using the Send to Maya command or opening an FBX straight up
into Motion Builder means that you send everything
all at once into Maya.
And it's not necessarily the cleanest result,
so we don't really want that.
File sizes get really huge, as evidenced by the FBX scenes
here on the right.
And these can take forever just to open up in Maya, or
MotionBuilder even.
To avoid these long and arduous transfer times, we
break down the MotionBuilder scenes for transfer, then fit
them back together in Maya.
Not only do we have to break each of these clips down and
export them separately, but we need to make sure we do so in
a manner that doesn't export out large file sizes.
Since we're getting close to the end here,
I'll spare you more long code explanations
and just sort of briefly run through this process.
We first create a component list
for everything in the scene,
then gather all the start and end frame data
in a list for each shot.
Then we plot all animation to the skeletons.
And once we've plotted,
we grab the root joints of all skeletons
using our component list to search from.
Then we iterate through all of that, making sure to grab the
entire hierarchy of each individual skeleton as we
create clips per character and export out a separate file per
character per shot.
Our results look like this.
And include file sizes that range from mere kilobytes for
cameras and anywhere from about a half a megabyte to 10
megabytes per character, depending on the complexity of
the skeleton and the length of the shot.
Rico would happen to have the largest files
with background characters having less, for example.
This is much, much more manageable now
than those giant MotionBuilder files that you found.
These files truly contain Jeff skeletons
with baked animation data,
sort of like what you saw before
when we were exporting our FBXs
from MotionBuilder into Maya for the gameplay side.
They do look exactly the same as that.
And shot by shot, we can now open up a fresh Maya file,
reference in only the rigs for the assets
that actually exist in each specific shot.
And it only takes a matter of seconds
to reference these small files in,
which we then transfer the animation
onto the Maya rigs from.
Which then kind of obviously takes a bit more
than just mere seconds to do,
but it's a lot easier to do.
It's all streamed through the batch tool.
The transfer script for taking those exported pieces from MotionBuilder does all the referencing,
baking, and file cleanup in a snap.
We can process multiple shots, scenes, whatever, much more quickly than by using the default
built-in transfer setups.
I did mention earlier that Maya was necessary
for secondary animation policy, I believe, and here's why.
One awesome content tool that we had in Maya
was the motion generation tool.
It could use a number of different solvers
from Maya dynamics, such as spring or bounce,
and then take in some user settings
and process that based off
of the root motion of the characters.
We could batch through entire cut scenes in Maya
and run an auto secondary animation patch
on all characters very quickly.
Now I think our first pass maybe took about a week
to add secondary animation to all those cut scenes.
You can see here Rico's straps are not really moving,
mirror's here, nope, now it's moving
because we just applied the motion generation to it.
All right, the extra special thing about this tool
is that we can run it through a PlayBlast script
that we had in conjunction with Batch,
and we would actually get a directory of MP4 video files
for each Maya file shot to see the secondary animation
after the fact.
This is super useful for going in and making sure
that certain shots might need to be fixed up
or certain shots were fine after a run.
To wrap this all up, what we were able to accomplish
included better workflows.
more power and customization,
a lot more automation and less manual work,
a full 360-degree pipeline between Maya and Motion Builder,
and all this helped us churn out a ton of content
that we wouldn't have otherwise been possible
unless we had a small army to help us.
Now, while there are other studios
that have similar tools and workflows,
I do hope that this talk at the very least
gave a new perspective for those of you that are familiar,
and for the rest of you, I hope you've enjoyed
a bit of the behind-the-scenes and under-the-hood
that I have presented.
Before I really conclude, I do want to extend a huge thank you to these three guys here
who all helped me in some way.
Brad Clark, he's the co-founder of Ringing Dojo,
he's there on the left.
He was always available to help answer
any MotionBuilder specific questions that I had,
as I was pretty new in setting up
more advanced features in MotionBuilder.
He still does, he's really helpful,
and you can probably ping him on Twitter,
and he would be happy to talk about MotionBuilder with you.
He actually made a quick video demo for me
just on how the camera switcher worked out of his own time.
It was like a 15 minute demo, and it was super helpful.
John Molaska, he's in the middle there.
He actually gave a talk this past Monday
at the Animation Bootcamp about freelancing for animators,
so check it out in the vault if you weren't there.
He came on board actually for a few months
when I was cold, alone, and in desperate need of help.
He really made it, he was really an integral part
of a lot of the motion builder setup that you saw,
especially the exporting take system
and kind of working with animators on what workflow worked.
Now finally, Cole there on the right,
he was responsible for many Maya optimizations,
including a bunch of that custom script stuff that you saw
that's really, really cool,
and that motion generation tool.
Also, they aren't listed or shown here,
but my animation team's awesome.
Despite all their crazy, crazy demands,
they truly make me a better TA.
so I really wanna thank them.
And also thank you to the conference associates
in the back who have helped out.
If you see the red shirts, thank them.
This really wouldn't be possible without them,
all this organization and stuff
that none of us really would wanna do.
They do for us and it's super awesome.
And hey, thank you to you so much
for coming to my talk today.
Looks like we have about...
six or seven minutes for questions
if you wanna ask any questions,
or you can just see me outside of the hall,
I believe across the way or something.
There's a overflow room somewhere.
But yeah, follow me on Twitter.
I'm at TechAnimator.
My email, brian at techanimator.com.
Yes, I have all those.
So yeah, thank you so much.
I was wondering if you had a headless version of MotionBuilder as well?
We do now.
I mean, we're looking into moving to 2019, but it's literally headless MotionBuilder
just started happening like a month ago.
And also, did you have something to generate all your JSON
files for your cinematic stuff?
We got JSON files from the vendor at first.
But we actually did have to do quite a bit of just kind of
error checking and manual work just to make sure that they
kind of were set up properly.
But kind of once you set those up manually the first time,
you're kind of good.
And it was also a really nice way to sort of catalog and
understand what was in those scenes by hand.
Okay, and last one. What's the reason for having different files for all the shots in the cinematic?
For the JSON?
No, like in your engine you have like different...
Maya files for each shot?
And couldn't you have one big animation for the whole cut
scene?
That was more done just for frame rate reasons in Maya.
Because when you have content that's
like a five-minute cut scene, you really
don't want to work with multiple characters and all that
when you have a giant Maya sequence of, say,
8,000 frames.
So we just kind of broke those down into quick little files
that you could kind of go in and update one.
The idea between that was that if you're in Maya,
you're in the polish phase, and you're not
changing your camera framing or anything like that,
and you're literally just polishing content.
Okay.
Thanks.
Hi, I also talk, and I just want to ask
the name of the extra tools you use in Maya
from rigging?
From, sorry, you phrased that question?
The extra tools you use in Maya for rigging?
For rigging?
Yeah. Oh, we build our own.
What?
We build our own.
We have all auto rigging tools that we build in-house.
So everything is all Python scripts
that I sort of started from Just Cause 3, just from scratch.
So it's all automated stuff.
We have a bunch of scripts in-house.
And we build Blueprint files using JSON as well, actually,
where I just kind of state, this is the name of the control.
This is the size.
This is the color.
Sort of everything offsets all that.
And then we just run that Blueprint.
And it just automatically builds our rigs.
And by any chance, can you say me an equivalent?
in right and...
To build rigs?
Yeah.
Equivalents to build rigs right now,
I know a lot of people use something called Mgear,
which is pretty robust.
I can't think of anything else
off the top of my head right now.
All right, thank you very much.
Yeah, thank you.
Anything else?
All right, that's it, thanks.