Hey, everyone, welcome to our panel about making commercial indie games as a professor.
In this session, we're going to hear the stories of four professors slash game designers.
Four brave souls who decided it's in fact possible
and maybe even a good idea to mix this volatile combination
of demanding professional roles.
Four daring adventurers who looked academic tenure criteria
dead in the eye and asked themselves,
can I please have some game industry-style crunch with that?
So it's a bold proposition if there ever was one,
but clearly it's also a meaningful one.
After all, as game designers,
aren't we all a little bit of mad scientists?
eager to throw away the shackles of commercial demands
in exchange for unbridled academic freedom,
which brings us to the big dramatic question
that we are going to address today.
Game design academia, is it living the dream
or is it surviving a nightmare?
Well, let's find out about that.
Now, before we go there though,
it's time for introductions.
Now, Michael, I'm about to start a new position
at Northeastern University.
But for the past eight years, I have held a joint position
between the College of Education and the Department
of Emerging Technology and Design and Business
at Miami University of Ohio, where a few years ago,
I got my tenure, which is a key element of Miami
being that it's an R2, which means that they have
high research activity and tenure criteria are substantial,
but they also have a significant teaching load.
So my scholarship is about games and aging.
And my latest project is called Brukel.
It's a horror game based on the authentic memories
of my at the time 92 year old grandmother
that has stole two players in her own voice.
So that's me.
Our next panelist is Chris.
Hi, my name is Chris Totten.
I'm an assistant professor of game design
at Kent State University.
I'm also the program coordinator
of our animation game design or AGD program.
So I have my own indie game studio pie for breakfast.
My tenure home is on Kent State's Tuscarawas campus in our College of Applied and Technical Studies, and I teach classes in our program at three of the campuses within the Kent State system.
You know, I've done my academic stuff includes, you know, writing books about game design and level design.
I co-founded the Smithsonian American Art Museum Arcade.
But I'm here to talk about my games through Pie for Breakfast, the first of which is...
La Mancha, which is a tabletop storytelling game based on Miguel de Cervantes' Dom Quixote.
The game was successfully funded on Kickstarter in November of 2018 and released commercially
in the fall of 2019.
And my studio's current project is a game called Little Nemo and the Nightmare Fiends,
which is done in collaboration with another indie studio, Pixel Please.
and based on the work of animation pioneer Windsor McKay. It was just funded successfully
on Kickstarter back in March of this year and is currently in development for PC and Switch.
I think I'll just jump in there.
Go ahead.
All right.
Hi, everyone.
I'm Tracy Fullerton.
I am a professor and also director emeritus
of the USC Games Program at the University of Southern
California.
Also, I hold the Electronic Arts Endowed Chair
in Interactive Media.
And I am the director of the Game Innovation Lab, which
is my research group at USC.
My tenure home, which was awarded way back in 2008, is within the Interactive Media and Games Division of the School of Cinematic Arts.
And so that is one of the two major schools at USC that make up the collaborative
cross-campus USC Games program. Today I'm here to talk about my games that I've released
commercially through my work at the Game Innovation Lab. So in 2017 I released Walden,
a game which is a six-hour long open world translation of Henry David Thoreau's Walden
or Life in the Woods.
And so this game was first released on itch.io and then on PlayStation and Steam, and by the time of this viewing should have been released on Xbox. So you can check that out.
Along with my earlier game, The Night Journey, which was a collaboration with the media artist Bill Viola,
these were two of the first four games released through the USC Games publishing label.
So this is a publishing label that we have through the program.
that offers opportunities for students, faculty, and innovative independent designers to have their
non-traditional games released to the marketplace. We think of it as something like
you would have a publishing label through a university. This is a publishing games label
through our university. So I'll pass it to Dave. Looking forward to having a discussion today.
Thanks, Tracy.
Hi, everybody.
My name is Dave Beck.
I am a full professor at the University of Wisconsin Stout.
And within the School of Art and Design,
I'm the founding director for the game design program
at Stout as well.
I'm actually now more in the directorial role
for the school, as well as an upper administration.
I'm actually in now a one-year interim position
as associate provost for the campus.
So, really looking forward to applying some of my game design background
to new types of systems across the entire campus.
My background is really in pure art.
Lots of modeling, animation, world building.
The two games I'm probably going to be talking about the most today are Tombow.
It's an interactive, essentially an interactive film
that has elements of history and environmentalism
focused around a river on, kind of in the upper Midwest.
And I spent a number of years just working on that as a solo artist and designer for the game,
creating that and releasing it as that interactive experience on Steam and Itch.
And then I'll also hopefully talk a little bit about Distilled as well, my current project.
As of right now, this presentation that you're watching, this is on Kickstarter as we speak,
and I've been working on this over the last couple of years.
This actually started...
as a project in Scotland, where I was doing quite a lot of research,
ended up deciding to create a board game.
So kind of jumping between those different worlds,
much like Chris had mentioned as well.
So that's me.
And again, I'm really excited to be here to talk with everybody today.
And I'm going to hand it back to you, Bob.
Yeah, awesome.
That's excellent.
And as you can tell, we had a lot of fun preparing for this session
and sharing our stories as academic game development journeys, obviously.
bind us together. And as we were sharing these, well, for lack of a better word, war stories,
we quickly realized that we needed a structure to keep ourselves on track and to avoid too lengthy
tangents during the session. So as we're all professors, we ended up making a diagram that
they've turned into a wonderful illustration. So as we pull it up here.
In a nutshell, being an academic game developer puts you in between the field and academia. So
ideally, there's a strong exchange with the field as you introduce it within the university
structure and your program. And we identified these six key elements in doing this, which we
will be used to drive our discussion today. However, before we do that, we should probably
discuss the big elephant in the room.
Why on earth would somebody want to do this?
You know, we could, we could all be indie game developers
making games or professors writing papers
about game design and make life a bit easier on ourselves.
Right?
So why did we decide to do this guys?
Well, I can jump in.
I'll jump in.
Cause I think I might've started pretty earlier.
You know, for me, one of the reasons to go to academia, coming out of industry, was that I had seen a model of other art forms where people had done really truly experimental work, you know, new genre defining work within the confines of the university within sort of, you know, a place where new ideas and taking risk was
valuable, right?
Sometimes that's not true in a purely commercial setting.
And even in indie work in the arts,
it's very difficult to be truly experimental.
So, you know, one of my motivations for going to academia
and starting my research lab was that I wanted to make
things that were outside the norms of, you know,
what you could experiment with, you know, sort of on the edges of the game industry,
I want to go into full experimentation mode. So that was that was one of my motivations. So
I don't think I realized it would be as hard as it has been. But, but it was one of my core
motivations for even going to USC in the first place. Right. Yeah, I think what the way it worked
for me was was was somewhat similar, because for me, it was also about I just want to
I just want to be able to make the games that I want to make.
I want to experiment and push things as much as I can
as an artist, rather than having to be commercially dependent
on whatever I end up making.
And I think for me, that's the biggest, especially
on tenure track, once you've got your tenure sorted out.
And that's something I'm sure we'll discuss later on as well.
But once that's sorted out, it gives you
a lot of freedom to some extent.
Maybe not.
I mean, what are your experiences with that, guys?
I.
I'm similar background. My background is in, you know, architecture and the arts. And when I was in school, you know, we had professors, even operating their own firms within the School of Architecture and
doing both industry work and academic work.
So this is something that is very familiar to me.
I've always thought that game development
seemed like it fit neatly
within a more studio art style practice
where you are doing your work, creative work,
and that becomes part of your validation,
but then also, you know, you do the,
typical work of an academic.
So those are things that I was,
I wanted to find a place that would allow me
to do that kind of stuff.
Other points that do strike me
as really important in this job too though,
is that, you know, I think this helps me certainly
with credibility in the classroom.
You know, there was a time before
I was doing quite as much indie development,
but maybe I was just teaching the software
where somebody might be like,
Well, why should I listen to you? You've never published a
game before. And now, you know, with my own independent
practice, the students like that's not even really a factor.
You know, the students will be like, well, yeah, we know that
you did these did these things.
You know, and then again, the creative freedom aspect.
Frankly, in a practical sense,
the academic job pays my bills.
And then I don't have to rely on the commercial performance
of some of my games.
I can make weird experimental stuff.
I can go from tabletop to video game.
I mean, I'm working on a Game Boy game right now.
as a side project. And I can do that because I can put out a broad scope of things based
on just experiments I want to do.
Yeah, and a little bit contrary to some of the responses,
I kind of fell into it.
I tripped and fell into a giant puddle of game design.
That sounds messy, and I guess it is kind of messy.
But I decided to be, actually, from the beginning,
I have always wanted to be teaching in higher education
and being a professor.
Originally thinking it was going to be more art,
traditional art, sculpture was my background.
But my love of technology and games
just started to kind of intertwine
with my interest in research.
And so I went from being a sculpture instructor
to a 3D modeling instructor to a game design instructor.
And so my research practice has followed that as well.
So a little bit different, but like many of you have said,
it's probably more complex a route than perhaps, definitely
more complex than others.
But I wouldn't trade it for anything.
That's actually interesting that I didn't know that value. But
like that, that kind of resonates with me as well.
Because like, well, as being, you know, from Europe, higher
education is pretty affordable. So I just get, you know, I got
my master's, I'm like, well, I could get a PhD now. And I just
kept going. And then I had a PhD. And I was like, well, let's
try for a professor. You know, it kind of just kept going like
because I've always wanted to make games like ever since I was
eight years old, I've been making games.
But yeah, just getting the degree
since it wasn't super expensive in Europe,
that kind of put me in this position
where I ended up doing this.
Yeah, go ahead.
I was gonna say real quick,
I do wanna jump on and validate the point
and echo the point that you just said
where you were like, I just wanted to make games.
With all the professional answers, I mean, there is a big element of this for me where it was like,
no, I am making video games. Hear that nine-year-old me? Like we're making video games now.
Totally. All right. Well, I think that was great to open everything. Let's look at that diagram
that we're talking about and address the six key topics. And we decided to do this chronologically
for everybody watching. So, you know, when we start these projects, when we want that academic
freedom.
we need funding to start making our game though.
So panelists, what's your advice regarding funding?
Oh, well, I'll start this one
cause it's gonna be probably be different
than some of the others.
So again, kind of falling back on that artist mode
because that's my background, what I knew
when I approached making Tombow,
I actually didn't think that much about funding
which probably might've been a mistake.
But what I thought about is money and funding was time.
I needed time.
I needed to figure out how to have dedicated time
outside of teaching.
So for my approach, and I say this
because there might be some of you out there watching this,
I actually decided to just apply
for a number of artist residencies.
where I could essentially have a month, two months, three months, where all I'm doing,
I'm in literally a cabin in the woods or some other institution somewhere else, where I'm
able to just focus on that.
So that was one big approach that I decided to take.
Obviously later I did need to find funding to support some of the vision I had
but to get it going and really for the
A good majority of that project was done at these residencies where all I'm doing is waking up
Making work going to bed seven days and it's like heaven. The idea is just heaven to me
And so yeah, I don't regret that.
I've really loved being able to take advantage of that
in my projects to have nothing else outside distractions.
So not necessarily a good answer to your question,
but a different type of funding this time for me.
Right.
Yeah, I mean, for me, it was also not necessarily
like finding the big pot of money.
Is that an R2, it's less research intense.
So even though Miami has some support for finding grants,
it's minimal in comparison to R1s.
But my position at Miami did come with an endowment.
So I had some money every year that I could use
for creative pursuits.
So that was really helpful.
But for me, it was mostly applying for some internal grants
like a research leave, a summer scholarship,
those types of things.
But when I started Brukle,
I think it was mostly a matter of like,
well, I wanna make this game regardless
and I've had no money to do it.
I'll still make it over the weekends.
In hindsight.
I think one of the things that I would like to do on a future game is look for more money
for it.
In my background, when I was working in a research lab back in Belgium before I moved
to the United States, we used to go get the big pots of grants and it was like with an
entire research lab, like, okay, we're going to get a grant of half a million to a million
dollars and we make games for health.
But again, even though Brukel has a very strong educational component, I think it would be
a lot harder to find that kind of money rather than.
when you're doing a game for health type of project.
So for me, it was very intentional.
Let's see what I can do if I have no money.
And then afterwards, if that goes well,
it will only get better when I start looking for games
that might be more fundable.
But it's always going to be a little bit of that balance.
I don't know.
I think it's also interesting to, once again,
highlight a point you made.
a lot of the funding does seem to be in games for something.
And I think one of the points that have come up
in our discussion is that sometimes these games
aren't necessarily games for something, they are games
and they might have some other component,
but they don't necessarily fit neatly
into the games for education, games for health areas.
And so like myself, I've gone for,
you know, internal grants to do a few game projects. You know, we have access to summer
research scholarships. I haven't really taken advantage of any of those, but you know, that's
something that we do at Kent State. But, and then of course, you know, there's external things.
You know, I'm in the early discussion stages of an NEH grant and things like that, but
you know, part of what we do is, you know, I've utilized like elements of our program to also
assist. So same sort of thing where it's like you're not necessarily going for formal funding,
but there are already these mechanisms in place that'll give you student help, you know, the
ability to have students get compensated for their time in the summer and things like that.
And then of course, you know, I've also done.
more industry-based funding. Again, both the projects I'm talking about today are Kickstarter
funded. So that does give a little bit of freedom in the subject matter of games, I think, sometimes.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think that's a really great point. And what I'm hearing resonates a lot with the early
days of my project. So I started making Walden back in 2007, right? And there was no sort of
funding available for a game like Walden at that time.
I will say that we had gotten funding for The Night Journey back in 2005 through the NEA,
but that was through Bill Viola and it was a media arts grant.
He's a well-recognized artist.
There was a whole path there for a media artist who wanted to make a game.
there was no path for a game designer who wanted to make an art game.
And so we did have early funding there for the prototype of Night Journey.
But when I set out to make Walden on my own, there was nothing.
I mean, I could have applied, I don't know, for some grant in the sciences
to make a game, maybe about global warming at Walden, right?
Or something like that.
But that's not the game I wanted to make.
In fact, the team talked a lot about this. Should we go for the funding that's out there?
Should we sort of turn the vision of the game in order to fit into a category of grant? We actually
decided not to, and so we went without funding for the first five years of the project. It was all
volunteer work, and we did get a really nice little like $25,000 internal USC grant, which
you know, that's not a lot when, you know, but it paid for some things,
some students and things like that.
And then it was really what one of the things I would advise, and this is, you know, just happenstance, but I think it's because we're all out there doing things, is that the world changed.
And people start, you know, they start, there were decisions on the Supreme Court about what games are and what kind of, you know, sort of creative speech they are, and there were, you know, changes inside of the organizations that provide grants, right?
So during the time that we were working.
These grants from the NEH came,
Digital Projects for the Public became possible.
The NEA included video games specifically
in their call for media arts grants.
These things began to change, right?
So while things may seem hopeless when you begin,
if you work hard, what we wound up having
was a super articulate prototype
when those opportunities arose,
and we were able to apply for the NEH
and the NEA grants that were coming.
you know, to life during our work. And, you know, as Dave said, that money made it possible for us to
really build our vision out. I mean, if they hadn't come at that time, we probably would
have finished our little game. It would have been like a lot of academic games. It would have been
sort of, you know, of a certain quality, right? But we really had a vision for a commercial game.
And those grants allowed us to build that vision out and to really polish and
make sure that the and work with scholars and historians in a way that we couldn't otherwise so
so I guess one of my advices for people you know who are out there saying oh no one's funding games
like mine is that's okay keep going right yeah yeah no one's funding it yet right not yet exactly
yeah yeah awesome awesome um so let's move on to the next topic that we have to address what how
does your process change when you're doing this within a university context what is
What is different about is what's unique about it.
So let's talk a little bit about that.
It's slow.
I mean, I come from industry, right?
So, you know, we would make these, you know,
massive games and ship them, ship them and get them out.
You know, we were always building
our technology infrastructure
and our team was getting like more and more experience.
And in academia, you have this situation
where you're working with students.
Maybe at most they can give you 10, 15 hours a week.
I mean, that's the extreme.
But then they start crunching on their capstone projects and you lose them.
And then you got to train a whole new group of students every couple of years.
You know, they sort of transition out.
And you yourself.
I mean, Dave's list of things that he's doing.
I was laughing when you were saying it because I was on that track too.
I was, you know, chair.
director of the whole USC Games program, blah, I was like, you know, dying, right? So how do you do that? And how many hours do you eke out a week to spend on your own project, right? So the whole thing has to become this extended experience that is not, you know, I mean, obviously, in industry, they work long, hard hours on games, but that's what they get to do. You are working long, hard hours on games.
and you were running departments,
and you were grading and teaching and all that stuff, right?
And that's funny you say that, Tracy,
because that's exactly right.
I mean, for me with Tombow,
I think I took about three, three and a half years
to make it, and I said, I'm gonna do this on my own.
that artist mindset. I'm going solo on this and for the most part I did and it
took longer but I was yeah chair at the time and then director for the school
and I had to literally put it on ice for six months right deep storage and then
summer would come and I just furiously go but it was interesting to talking
about process is that
for the second time around for the game I'm working on now,
very different of course with a board game.
But I knew from the beginning,
what I'd learned from Tombow is,
I am never doing a project just on my own again.
I just, I need a team.
I kind of graduated from the artist mindset,
which is very much doing this on my own,
to more of a developer's mindset
where a team we can accomplish things faster,
better, more efficiently.
But most importantly, in my perspective,
We all have our different skill sets that we're bringing to the table,
and it's just going to be that much better.
We're all doing that much better.
So yeah, I would agree, slow.
Summer is my friend.
I really do focus on that.
With a teaching-focused school like Stout,
so much of our time is dedicated to the classroom during the school year.
So yeah, I echo that.
I would say molasses, red tape, hoops, all of those things at an institution
definitely, unfortunately, infiltrate into the game development process too.
Yeah.
I think, you know, because what resonates a lot with what you just said, Dave, for me,
is like the solo part of it.
Like I'm, I don't think I will ever be doing a game entirely by myself.
Um, again, because, uh, you know, I had a lot of roles to cover as well, um, as a
professor and I think what I should definitely have done better is the life
work balance part of it, because it really becomes a lot, you end up doing
these insane hours and like, I mean.
I got a burnout through it.
Like, I don't know if I would be divorced right now if I hadn't done all that,
even like it's, it's been pretty rough.
And I think one of the things that you want to take into account is just like,
yeah, you, you want to make sure you get help from other people that can take
certain parts out of your hands.
Cause even if I look at Bruko right now, I'm like, If only I could have spent
more time on the marketing, but like, I, you know, I've already got a burnout for
it, like, right.
And I'm still feeling like I should have pushed harder.
So I think for me personally, and I know that's a very personal thing, but.
like making sure that your process involves
your life work balance.
I think that is the thing
that I should have done a lot better.
Aside from that, I think for me,
it was a pretty straightforward process.
Like I tried to do it as much as I could
as I would have done it if I weren't a professor.
But at the same time,
it's something that you have to be very aware of
that you are doing two different jobs
at the same time almost,
and you need to cut yourself some slack a lot there.
So I think that would be my biggest advisor.
you know, 2020 hindsight thought about doing all this.
Yeah.
The way I balance it, too, is I try
to do something for the game every day,
even if that's like I make a few sprites.
You know, having that.
constant progression is nice, especially, you know,
with Nemo, like we're hand animating it, right?
So if I can get a few frames in, it's really helpful.
And one of the things that you all mentioned,
the collaborative part of it,
what I like about working on teams, especially,
and with my current project.
I'm working with non-academics as well.
And we start to keep each other kind of honest.
You know, if I go down an academic rabbit hole,
they're the one that can push me back and be like,
but it's gotta be good for speed runners.
You know, something that like, I'm not even thinking about.
Sorry, speedrunners. But then, you know, on the flip side, I'm
the one who can also be like, well, you know, here's how we
should approach the art. And here's how this can become
a study of this media, and then that becomes the thing we end up getting pressed for.
So that collaborative element is really good. I totally agree with Bob that, you know,
something's going to fall off. For me, it was also definitely marketing. And yes, you know,
please take care of yourself. You know, for me with three kids, like I can't afford not to.
I just want to say that's
what you just said, Bob, about you might not be divorced.
I mean, that really touched me.
My experience, I actually have never done a game,
well, board games,
but I have never done a digital game just by myself.
I'm very team oriented.
And I actually got sick partially,
partway through the development of Walden.
I had breast cancer and had to go through chemo
and radiation and surgery
and all those great, wonderful things.
And because I had this team,
I thought the game was going to stop.
And it was the most wonderful thing I've ever experienced is that they kept going.
You know, um, when I couldn't come in and when I just didn't have the energy,
they kept going, it was actually extraordinary to, to experience.
And that I, even though this is like one of the worst periods of my life, it was
also, um, really a wonderful thing to have experienced the dedication of that team.
Wow.
Yeah.
Actually, now you mentioned that because I had some students that, you know,
I had in class at the time and some of them contributed like a 3D model left and right
for the game.
And, you know, I have a lot of support from them as well.
It's, you know, it's definitely something I should mention as well.
It was heartwarming to see how much support you can get.
in that way while you're going through hell and back.
And I wonder if we would have received those kinds of support
if we had been in a commercial or indie studio, right?
So my dean just said, whatever you need, right?
And I think that's something specific to academia
when you go through a crisis like that.
That's interesting. Yeah, I wonder, I hope that the people
watching this, especially if you're on the tenure track, or
you're thinking about that.
Again, Tracy talked about advice earlier in another response.
And I think that don't be afraid to reach out to others for support.
I think it's so important to to seek that and don't think you have to do it
just because you're going up for tenure, that you have to do this on your own.
And I think we'll see less of that as games evolve.
But still, I think that's important to note, too. Right.
Well, let's move on to the next topic and that one is ownership. So how did that work for you guys, the university take all the revenue or, you know, do you see some return on all the time you invest into the project as well. How did that work out.
Anyone want to jump in.
So I can I can start
At Kent, we have a collective bargaining agreement.
which says that it defines anything like this as a work and stipulates that it is the property of
the faculty member. So this is again one of the things that attracted me to this position in
particular. I've worked for universities where that was not the case, so you you know would maybe try
to cordon things off in a certain way, but
Part of our agreement, but also what has shaped the culture where I am, is that because we own
the work, they actively advise us to do stuff like this, because if we're happy in creating work,
and then can go out and be like, I work at this great place, that is good for the university.
I would, a piece of advice, if you are earlier in your career,
I would say is, and yeah, the academic job market
is what it is, but look into those things
and see what, again, ownership and things like that there
might be, because that is an important part of this journey.
Yeah, I'll just chime in. It's pretty much the same at University of Wisconsin-Stout.
I think one asterisk to put on that, though, is that there is, at least in Wisconsin,
a very clear law about if a student creates something as part of a class,
then they are having ownership of that. Rightly so, right?
So that's one thing that I kept all of my game development
when I was working with students, if I was on any projects
outside of the classroom as its own independent entity.
And then the only other thing I'd say too, and this is kind of one that I'd be
curious to see what other people think about.
I've always been in this weird realm of
I'm using the computer my university has given me.
I'm using the software as well.
I'm making a not-for-profit game.
I'm not profiting off of Tombow.
But at the same time, that's one thing
that I know has always been a little bit of a foggy area.
So that's one area that I'd be curious to hear
what others think about, too.
Yeah.
Yeah, sure.
I mean, I actually don't really care
about if the game is going to make any money or something.
You know?
I don't need to get additional salary from it
because that's why I'm doing this in the first place
that that's already covered, right?
So I was originally, I had hoped that the university
would just want to publish it,
but they were like, nope, we're not going to do that.
But that means that, you know,
you get to do everything yourself
and you also get the rewards for that.
So I ended up setting up lifelong games
and then publish the game myself.
And that worked out fairly well, I would say.
But yeah, Miami, it's a similar principle, I guess,
from what you guys have been talking about.
You can keep the ownership for it pretty easily.
And it worked out that way, but, you know,
it all added into the surprise of how much work
this was actually gonna be,
because now I'm also managing my own company for it.
So yeah, that was definitely a stressful thing to do
when you're not expecting it.
I think this is a really topical issue, by the way,
because,
Most universities, most research universities, especially where there are grants involved,
and this is true of USC, do claim ownership if there's federal grants involved, right,
of research and specifically a patentable, what they call inventions, right? There's rarely any,
you know, language around
more copyrightable works, which is where games fall into, right? And at USC, you know, the policy
is that basically the university owns patentable works that were created through research grants,
but there are traditional exceptions for works of art. And so it was unclear that the IP policy was
written.
in, I think, 2001 or 2000, I don't know, it's like some insane number of years ago.
And in it, it says, you know, exception for works of art.
And then there's also this whole thing on software.
So
Transcribed by https://otter.ai
works of art that are software are not even considered.
And so we had to go through this process
where we actually cleared both,
we cleared Walden specifically as a work of art.
Night Journey is obviously a work of art made by an artist.
And so we went through and cleared it as a work of art.
And therefore the rights are retained by me.
And I include the team in that.
And then what we decided to do as a team was publish it through USC Games, our publishing label,
and to actually return all of the profits. I can't even call it profits, because it costs so much to make over the years that it's really not profit.
But we return everything that is made by the game to the lab to fund new students and staff in the maintenance of the game.
And, you know, if we ever
got enough to maintain them in making new games, right?
So that's our sort of ecosystem that we determined.
Now we could have another other artists,
other game artists like Peter Brinson
does something similar,
but we could have just as well decided to take it out
and make a company since we owned it.
But we determined that it was more important to us
to maintain this ecosystem at the university for innovation.
So that was our choice.
Dave, you'd mentioned software in particular. And I think this
is one area where it's important to talk up open source software
under my collar shirt that I wore for the presentation the
rest of the day I've been wearing my blender shirt.
Blender now has a 2d tool set, which is what we are animating
little Nemo in. So I'm very big on that. But yeah, I mean, we
try to
where we can adopt. We try to stay like keep those things
again cordoned off. So we don't fall into any of those muddy
areas. But, you know, and then whenever we do like summer
internships with students, you know, I either have them intern
with pixel, please, you know, the the other organization.
Or, you know, that is where Pie for Breakfast will act as a separate entity that they are taking the internship with. It's not just like a research assistantship or something like that. So, you know,
Trying to think about those things. It's also a good lesson for students too, because it does
actually like if you are using free software, it does start to get into, well this is a way to
think about how to manage your own studio because now you're like, where can I cut costs? I can cut
costs by not having to pay the subscription for Maya or something like that. So it's like a little
bit of studio management in there too. That's good.
Yeah, yeah. And I'm going to use that to segue in the next part,
because like, yeah, one of the resources that you can use at a
university are obviously students. And I think for me,
because, well, with Brooklyn getting big, I, I had students
involved as well, and to a lesser extent, I guess, then, you
know, it wasn't like a lab that was doing it. But I recruited
some students, like, hey, do you want to help out with some 3d
models that I will not really have the time for making? And
In the end, I asked them, OK, in exchange for your work,
you want some compensation.
Some of them wanted something, others didn't.
In the end, Brooklyn wasn't a big money maker.
It just broke even.
But I was able to give every student what
they wanted in exchange for their work.
So I'm pretty proud about that.
But yeah, that brought some help, but also
a lot of concerns as well.
Because even though.
you know, being able to show off Google to my students that
looked what I made, and they're like, Oh, my God, that's really
awesome. And talking my teaching about and this is what happened
when we did this and that in the project, or, you know, show the
project manager inside or the marketing side of Google to help
my classes. It also brought some, some friction with it as
well. For example, I had one student that was going to
program everything, but it really didn't work out. And
eventually, I have to just be like, look,
this is not going to work.
I'm just going to do this myself.
And I'll give you credit for the work that you've done.
Although, I don't think anything actually made it to the game.
But I'm like, if you want to use this in some kind of a way
to time that you invested it, I'll
do whatever I can to help you out.
It's still really stressful, because obviously you
don't want to do that.
I mean, you bring a student in because you like their work,
and you anticipate it's all going really well.
But yeah, that was a thing that makes things a little bit
harder for me as well.
So for our next topic, I mean, I kind of already did it myself.
But like,
teaching students. Any thoughts on that, guys?
I think if I could jump in kind of talking about somewhat of what you you
mentioned, Bob and Tracy had mentioned this a little bit earlier, too.
I think, sure, the the the sad part about working at an institution trying to
develop a game is it takes a long time.
It takes a lot longer.
But I think one of those benefits is this symbiotic kind of.
incubation, at least for me, that I have where I can bring ideas that I'm working on into the
classroom when I'm teaching. That might be project management or that might be a new type of workflow
and then I'm bringing that to test it and prove it and show to the students and teach them.
but then I'm also learning stuff from their games if I'm overseeing a capstone project.
So I think that's one really wonderful advantage of working within the confines of the institution
is that is a freeing thing of the institution. I think that larger commercial studios lack that
ability to be so flexible and change over time. So that would be one thing I'd definitely say
that I appreciate about kind of that teaching relationship with students.
Yeah, one of the things that came up when we were building that diagram, I don't know if you have the diagram up right now.
I do now.
All right. Well, I mean, you can see among all those bubbles, you know, we have like university program students kind of huddled into one area, but then we have that big arc of arrows going into the field, and then, you know, the rest of the arrows kind of weave their way back to the university program.
That's one of the things that
I think doing this has really been a benefit in the classroom is that, you know, people think of
like teaching as this other thing sometimes. And I don't, I don't agree with that at all. I think,
you know, all of this stuff feeds itself, where if I do something in my game development,
I mean, you better believe I'm going to go talk about that in the classroom. And, and
offer a perspective, whether it be in
how I model my class to be like what it's like in the real world.
Whether I take when I'm teaching animation theory, I mean, one of the best
things was this past fall when I was making my PowerPoint.
So I'm like, I have a bunch of gifs from hand-drawn animation for a little Nemo
in there of squash and stretch.
OK, get Sprite of Flip put in PowerPoint.
That was all that was really great.
So you can see it like actual working models, not just me showing Looney Tunes.
though I love Looney Tunes. But, you know, then you can really offer perspective on what it's like.
It's not theoretical anymore. It is real. And, you know, we get to make that come alive to the
students in such a way that they see what it's like to really get into the industry instead of,
again, sort of like a...
fiction that they're fed about what it's like getting into the industry.
So I think that's a really important point is that you can start to have real
conversations about this as a job.
So just to build on that a little bit, Chris,
also they can graduate with a shipped game. So, you know,
this is invaluable to the students, right?
And so, you know, for me, it's, you know, you, what we do to solve the problem that,
that Bob was talking about was maybe, you know, maybe are they a fit? Are they, do we have the
capabilities? Because a lot of times in the beginning year, we, we basically have all the
research labs present what, what jobs they have open. And then people come and visit our working
meetings.
And they sort of gravitate towards what their expert,
you know, what they can do and what the project needs.
And often if there's not a fit, they'll just fall away.
And it's sort of like this thing where
we have a kind of trial period before we actually hire them.
It's like an internship. It's like a in-school internship.
They visit, they listen to us working, they say, I think I could do this. I say, why don't you give
it a try? Let's see if it works out, then we hire them. Right? It's a kind of a test in a way.
We also have been very lucky in getting placements of graduate research. So the
university has a graduate research program and a number of our students get
research appointments, and then we can ask to have them placed in our labs.
And with this kind of method, we get people who are being paid.
They have a stipend. They get credits.
It's actually a real appointment for them.
And that's a level of commitment beyond just hourly student workers that I think
has worked really well for us throughout the process.
I think, and to go back a little bit to, you know, you were bringing up the structure of like, sort of the early work like tryout period, right?
I think that's one of the things that I've learned through working with students on projects like this in our internship course is the ways in which you do have to bend your process a little bit, you know, if, if I'm working with a animator, who's been in the industry like five years or something like that I can be like, all right, go make a run cycle, and they'll go make a run cycle.
But working with.
the students, it's almost like, you know, you really have to bring them in and, and, you know,
their entry level to junior, and you have to, you know, I can't just say, go make a run cycle,
or if I do, I might have to redo that run cycle later. But, you know, we've started to.
we've gotten better about doing things like, and I'm speaking mainly as an animator right now,
or artist animator, I could do something like I do all the keyframes of the animation and
then I hand that document, the keyframes off to the junior artist.
And then I say, all right, can you do the in-betweens?
And a model like that, it's a little more work for me.
But the student has that baseline
so that everything comes back way more coherent, where,
you know, so you do have to change your process
a little bit.
But it does.
Or your design.
Just to kind of, one of the things that we found
is sometimes you find students with special talents.
And we have put.
features in based on those special talents, right?
Like one of our students was really great
at animating hands, which we hadn't had.
And so in the original design, there were no animated hands.
And so we had the student, he was a graduate researcher.
He's like, let me try this, right?
And so he did it and we're like, oh my God,
let's add this to the game.
That's awesome too, because their hands are not easy.
Hands!
You're good at it.
So teaching is obviously a really big part
of the professor game designer.
But the other part is, how are you going to be evaluated
by your university?
Now, I realize that we're taking a lot of time
to discuss all these topics, and we
need to make sure that we wrap it up in the time slot.
So I'm going to go a little bit off script,
because our last two topics are dissemination and validation.
But I feel like those are two topics that are close together
so that we can address them a little bit faster.
So.
What do you guys think?
How do you disseminate your games?
How do you make sure if university respects
what you're doing and values it for tenure
and for all sorts of performance reviews?
So as the pre-tenure person on the panel,
I'm gonna start off here.
I'm actually in somewhat uncharted territory for my unit.
So I'm kind of the guinea pig.
You know, our program was just accredited last year.
So we are,
and there has not been a tenured.
person in my field yet. So a lot of this has had to do with contextualizing these works properly
in a way that people can understand, like, from other fields, what these are. Because the school
in a high level is in support of this kind of work. But, you know, and I'm actually working
on my tenure documentation right now. You know, my
yearly check in thing. So I have to do a lot of extra work in my
narrative, for example, to describe like what it means to
publish a game. If I publish something quick, you know that
try to contextualize that, you know, kind of build it out to be
like, well, that something quick and small, like a game jam game
might be the equivalent of doing, you know, maybe a
smaller paper. Whereas, you know, if I spend two years on a
game,
like La Mancha or like Nemo is, you know, gonna become,
you know, try to contextualize that in steps of like,
well, this is like prepping a book.
So you have to do a lot of explanation and working with,
you know, if you have like a faculty mentor,
that's the best.
We have a great mentoring program in our program.
So, you know, that's really helpful,
but learning how to, I guess,
describe these things is one of the biggest things that I have to do.
I think what you said about mentorship is really good. I'm glad you brought that up, Chris, because
especially for those that are on the tenure track or perhaps just getting into it,
academic instructor, adjunct, finding others that have helped blaze that trail is going to be very,
very helpful to have them as allies. And I would say too, just as a kind of a...
somewhat of a tangent. I'm in the School of Art and Design, and so when I created Tombow,
I was already tenured. But what I did was, yes, I put it up online. I did the things that many
game designers and developers might do. But I also, because I was in my art and design department,
I had an art exhibition.
I thought that it would be a great way to demonstrate
to my peers that this should be held as a work of art.
So I had the game, but then I had process.
I had this, people were calling it my Pinterest wall,
but it was basically about 500 images, sketches, images,
that I put up on the wall.
I 3D printed a number of my objects
modeled from the game too.
So kind of trying to create this overall process
to help others that obviously we know it.
We're surrounded by people that don't,
frankly understand what we do and how we do it,
but it's a nice way to bring that to a level
that they might understand.
And I found that to be quite successful,
even though it seemed like it was extraneous
and I didn't, I thought,
I don't know if I should do this.
I was very happy I did at the end
because my colleagues who would have been tenuring me
if I was on the tenure track at that point
would have fully understood what I was doing as well.
Yeah.
Oh.
Okay, real quick. On the point of seeming extraneous, though, that is actually another
way that you can play the game with this. Totally, yeah.
Is that, you know, okay, so I made a game. Now I can publish papers about what I learned from
publishing that game. How the game, you know, again, based on 400 plus year old piece of
literature.
expresses the piece of literature and the themes within and things like that, you know, you start
to treat this as a piece of literary criticism beyond just being cool game product. So I think
that is also a thing you learn how to do is.
turn this untraditional publication into traditional publications. And you can probably
get like a few years of traditional publications out of something like this. So that's another,
again, it goes back all into that loop of make thing, have it feed your other
traditional types of validation. Yeah, yeah, I would agree.
Sorry. Yeah, I think for me, the same thing applied there like.
I learned at the university, as long as I can show that people care about it in some
way, whether it's through publications getting accepted or through rewards or awards or all
that kind of stuff, that helps tremendously.
Or even the amount of downloads that you generate, publishing that in your 10-year dose, it helps
a lot.
So, you know, I can resonate a lot with those things.
I think the thing that I want to add, though, is like...
I would love to see a category for professor made games that like festivals and everything.
Because a lot of the times we, you know, with Brooklyn, I had to go up against big
companies and like, it's still that, well, it's great, but I feel like I'm always just,
you know, playing in a competition in which I'm completely, um, yeah, overwhelmed or,
yeah, I'm not at the same skill level.
I put it, that's such a funny point, Bob.
I, you know, I want to tell you just a little funny story really early on.
I had submitted the night journey to the IGF and they actually called me and they're like,
oh, you know, we really want to honor this, blah, blah, blah. Would you mind if we put it
in the student category? And I was like, do you know who Bill Viola is? I was like, I don't think
that's appropriate at all, right?
And you know, I think what you're saying, Bob, is really interesting because, you know, we're not indies, we're not commercial, and we're not students, right?
And we live in this wild land between, you know, academia and indie development, essentially, that, you know, it's a wonder we get anything made at all, right?
I just want to go back to the question of tenure and validation for just one second.
So when I went up for tenure.
There were no places to exhibit your work, right?
I mean, when I worked on For Tenure,
it was like the year before IndieCade did its first awards.
Okay.
So one of the things that we had to do was think about,
okay, what about the grants?
So we had that NEA grant, right?
And that's always been in my mind
that I began to understand how,
when you get validation in the form of a grant,
that that also helps your tenure story.
All the things you guys were saying.
So Dave, I really resonate
with what you were saying about exhibits.
So I've done a lot of focus on getting the works exhibited
because that tends to hold more weight
than commercial sales.
Though commercial sales are, you know, nice.
They're nice to put in there,
but exhibits in important venues and
Awards are often really, you know,
whether they're supposed to be or not,
they are important when people evaluate
your tenure case, right?
And grants, the people who voted with their money,
essentially, to support the work that you're doing,
really, really important.
Yeah.
And, you know, you mentioned Professor Gaines.
in particular, Bob.
And one of the things that I think
is really interesting about this is that, first of all, I agree.
And I also agree with the addition
that we talked about this before,
where the traditional forms of validation
seem to be for games for x, games for y.
Like Tracy said, we are in this weird in-between position
where we are kind of doing commercial stuff.
So it's not totally for x or y.
Um, but, you know, maybe like my, my board game, La Mancha had some educational
aspects to it because it was based on literature.
Um, I wouldn't call little Nemo informative, but I would also
call it a commercial video game.
Um, so I think what's interesting to me about these though, and what I think makes
them great.
works that can be academically validated is that we have to be a little more thoughtful
in our game development. We can't just make like cool video game. We've got to make cool video game
but it's got to have this other element whether it be we are thinking analytically about the design
or using a process in a new way or it does have some connection to education or something like
that.
where we're interpreting a classic work or something.
So, you know-
I call it what Dave described is,
we call it design research.
Yes. Yeah, yeah.
And we frame it that way when we discuss it.
We say creative research, yeah, yeah.
But yeah, I mean, this is what architects do.
This is what graphic designers do.
So,
So I think it has both that academic element, but then what's great about this is that it also becomes commercial curiosity.
We have like these games have that like commercial that some some novelty that gives them a little bit of an edge in the marketplace because they're interesting because frankly, we have to feed the academic part.
And then it also ends up feeding the commercial part.
So I think that's worth.
pointing out and also like talking about in how these games
are distinct and why they should be a you know different category.
Yeah well I think we're running out of time here so
to wrap things up because we just discussed the six topics
I'm gonna ask for each and every one of you and maybe like in one sentence
if there is one piece of advice you could give to whoever is watching right now
what would that piece of advice be?
I'll go first, and I said it already once,
but don't be afraid to ask others for help.
Bring other people to your team.
It's a long process, it's a hard process.
You're not an expert of everything,
even though you might want to think you are,
need to feel you need to prove it.
Ask for help.
It's gonna be the best decision you'll make
towards a future project.
I would say choose your idea carefully.
Don't just do the cool game you think you want to do.
Choose an idea that has some depth
that can really be used for this academic rigor,
this design research that has potential for funding,
that has the potential for this commercial curiosity.
Choose your idea very, very carefully.
I would say as an instructor, you're in an important position of power, even if you know, like pre tenure people don't often feel like they have a lot of power, but you know you are you are.
valuable member of your community
and valuable to your students.
And I would say, you know,
these types of projects will bring a community together.
You know, use them as a way, you know,
we talked a lot about students getting shipped products,
try to use opportunities like this that you're having
to also, you know, help your students,
help other people along, try to climb that hill together.
um you know team up and and accomplish amazing things and you know use this to the benefit of
the education you're providing. Right and mine would be to build up your community around your
game from day one including the students but also the community around your game because you're
going to need that community for your game to be validated and to get all the good things that you
can have from making a commercial game as a professor. So anyways with that we've come to
the end of our session.
Again, these are only four viewpoints,
but we hope they were very useful to you.
And I'm really hoping that we're gonna see more sessions
like this in the future.
After all, in the end,
this is all about helping as many game professors
as possible to be active developers,
as doing so plays a key part in facilitating
those three big arrows in that diagram,
where the academic gaming landscape improves the field
with high quality scholarship and capable students.
And with that, I'd like to thank you all for watching
and enjoy the rest of your GDC.
Bye-bye.
Bye-bye!