Good afternoon and welcome to today's classic game
post-mortem on Paperboy.
My name is John Solwitz.
I am a principal technical director at Electronic Arts.
But today, you will not, in fact, be hearing anything
about Paperboy Frostbite or Paperboy Origin.
Actually, my credentials to do this presentation
have very little to do with Electronic Arts.
I hope I am qualified to give this presentation
because I was part of this really wonderful team.
the team that created the original arcade version of Paperboy.
In putting this presentation together I interviewed most of the members of the
team and it is my goal today to share with you our
our shared memories of making Paperboy.
And just to be clear my talk today is mostly going to be about
the original version of Paperboy.
the one hopefully you played somewhere
in some dingy arcade somewhere,
one or two quarters at a time.
For the purposes of today,
I broke up my presentation into the seven parts
of the seven days of the week,
each part representing a different phase
of development of Paperboy.
I thought this was cute and somehow appropriate.
So, without further ado,
the story of Paperboy in seven days.
On Monday, we go to.
Ideation.
I started work at Atari Games in October of 1981
as a microprocessor programmer.
I was actually rejected the year previous
by Postcard, no less,
but I was a diehard arcade game player
and even more a diehard Atari Games player,
so I reapplied, somehow got an interview,
and miraculously got through that interview.
That was the start of my video game career.
I ended up working at Atari for about 10 years.
For my first assignment, I was paired up with this guy,
a designer named Dave Ralston.
Dave is actually a designer artist
who started his life in games
as a pinball designer for Atari.
He started at Atari almost exactly a year before I did.
Turns out it was my great fortune and pleasure
to work with Dave for the next 18 years.
It is rare indeed to find this kind of partnership.
I feel very blessed indeed.
Dave had been working on this new hybrid pinball video game
called Aka-R. Aka-R, by the way, took its name from Rich Adam,
who is the engineer, the creator behind Gravatar.
Rich had signed a creative document, aka Rich Adam, Aka-R.
So we took the name.
A little time later, Atari renamed the game Sentinel
before we took it on field test.
Dave and I worked on that game for around nine months,
really tried to get the pinball video thing working,
never really did, so we went back
to a conventional video game.
And off to field test we went.
The game did not last long.
The test did not go well.
We were crushed by this other game.
Perhaps you've heard of it.
Robotron?
Thanks Eugene Jarvis. This once again proved
Toyer's Law, named after Dave Toyer, he of Missile Command and Tempest fame,
which states, your first game will be a real dog and ours surely was.
Shortly after the short-lived disaster of our field test,
I think we made around 70 bucks in a week or so,
I really felt my career was over.
And so we conducted a post-mortem,
which was typical at the time at Atari.
And so going into that meeting, I thought that was about it.
But Dan Van Eldren, who was then Vice President
of Engineering at Atari Games, instead told us,
amazingly.
Great try for a bunch of rookies.
What are you gonna do next?
This, by the way, in my opinion,
is how you start to build a great game team.
I wanna talk about Atari coin-op for just a second,
largely because as I interviewed the other people
on our team, a very common thing that they said
that was working at Atari was either the best job
they ever had or one of the best jobs they ever had.
And so for me, I'll tell you one of the real reasons
it was for me.
We worked at one of the few centers
of video game making on Earth.
And these games were all made
within spitting distance of each other.
You could and would regularly walk out of your lab
and go into an adjacent lab and play somebody else's game.
And these were the games that were in development
during Paperboy.
This was an incredibly creative atmosphere,
and you could learn about what it would take
for your game to be successful,
and frankly, get a little intimidated in the process.
I loved it.
Back to Paperboy.
Around the time of the sun setting of Akka,
our day presented a few ideas
at the Atari Cointot Brainstorming.
This is February of 1983.
This particular brainstorming was at Bajaro Dunes,
which is near Monterey, California.
Dave showed us this idea for a kid riding down the street
delivering papers on a single transparency
for an overhead projector.
PowerPoint was yours to come later.
And oh, at the end of his presentation,
he flipped the transparency over
and showed us what it would look like
for Paperboy to ride down the other side of the street.
Ironically, of course, he never did.
At the end of the presentation, Dave was awarded three
Atta Boys by Atari leadership and won the
brainstorming.
I freely admit it took me a while to come around
to a game about Paperboy, a game about a kid
delivering newspapers.
I, after all, was into games like Asteroids,
Battlezone, Missile Command, anything with a missile
or maybe a football in it.
So the idea of working on a game about paper delivery
was a little strange to me.
But Dave kept working on the idea,
and sooner or later I came around
and came to my senses and joined the team.
At Atari, to get a game started officially,
you had to survive what was known as an initiation meeting.
You would present a thin game description of the game,
you know, in our case, you know,
Paperboy delivering newspapers, avoiding characters,
some idea of your hardware,
and maybe a schedule, things like that.
Because Dave had successfully won the previous brainstorming,
us getting through the initiation meeting
was, in fact, pretty easy.
And so the day after we successfully
got through our initiation meeting, we began development.
So on Tuesday, we go to pre-production.
Let's talk about what the paperboy is made of.
First, to do that, I have to talk
about the people that made the hardware for paperboy.
The first is Doug Snyder.
He was the hardware engineer on the Paperboy hardware.
Doug was responsible for the design and the layout
of the hardware that was to become Paperboy.
It's an interesting thing about working on new hardwares
as a software engineer.
I am a programmer after all.
You never really know if the bug is hardware or software.
And I can remember many times trying to convince Doug Snyder
to argue with Doug Snyder about that it was in the hardware.
Let me just say I lost most of those arguments.
Doug ended up designing most of the hardware
that I would eventually use at Atari.
Linda Sigovic also joined our team at this time
as our technician.
Linda partnered with Doug to fabricate, debug,
and improve the hardware throughout development,
basically to keep the hardware alive.
A technician back then was about just as much
of a part of your team as, say, a build engineer is now.
Unfortunately, and not to the credit of Atari,
Linda was laid off not once but twice
during the development of Paperboy.
She was, however, absolutely instrumental
in the making of the game.
At the heart of the Paperboy's hardware,
leader renamed system two was the T11 or Tiny11.
As this is a design-focused presentation,
I will not gush on about how cool the T11 was.
It was basically a PDP-11 on the chip.
But I will say, after working on a 6502 for a while,
this was awesome.
Also, for those who care,
the programming language in Paperboy is Bliss, not C.
My guess is that I have personally written more hit games
in Bliss than anyone else on Earth.
Sadly.
That skill set is no longer in demand,
and frankly, my knowledge of Bliss is long since gone.
Atari was moving away from vector-based games
when Paperboy began, so we went to a raster-based game.
Using a straight bitmap wouldn't have worked
for performance reasons,
so we went to a stamp-based hardware.
The Paperboy, or System 2 hardware, is
a very basic stamp-based hardware on today's standards.
There is a scrolling play field,
and on top of that, there are 32
what they used to call motion objects.
Now people call them sprites.
And on top of that, of course,
there is a two-bit alphanumeric layer,
all in eight-by-eight pixel stamps.
So pretty conventional there.
But Paperboy did have something new.
Typical raster arcade games at that time were displayed in 320 by 240 pixel resolution,
what was also known as standard resolution.
Doug Snyder, our hardware engineer, allowed one of the real big innovations of Paperboy,
the use of medium resolution.
Basically he increased the speed of the video circuitry, and in partnership with a company
called Wells Gardner, our monitor manufacturer, created a new monitor that could display.
not 320 by 240, but instead 512 by 384 pixels.
I suppose compared to high definition,
and certainly to 4K, this is downright quaint.
But to us at the time, it was awesome.
We knew pretty early on that we did not want
to have a conventional controller.
Atari Games actually pressed the teams
to do new and original controllers.
largely to differentiate the games in the arcades.
I mean, after all, what is the thing that you notice
when you walk up to an arcade game cabinet?
You notice the controller.
In building our controller,
we had the very good luck and fortune
to have a guy named Milt Loper join the team
as our mechanical engineer.
Milt and Dave had previously worked together on pinball,
and so they knew each other.
Milt is a seriously creative designer engineer
who was responsible for.
several of the Atari controllers.
Although I think the joystick,
excuse me, the handlebar controllers on Paperboy
are his finest work.
Although of course, he also invented
the salad bowl controller behind 720,
and I think that's pretty cool too.
Of course, Atari had a rich history of controllers
well before the handlebar controllers on Paperboy.
In fact, the Paperboy's controller has a rich ancestry.
It went kinda like this.
from Battlezone in 1980 to the Bradley Trainer,
also in 1980.
The Bradley Trainer was a project
that the Atari Games did with the DOT,
and so part of that was to take the Battlezone controller
and turn it into a more of a textile controller.
That controller you can think of being
as the stepdad of the Star Wars controller in 1983,
and the Star Wars controller,
think of the stepdad of being the Paperboy controller.
1985. In fact, Milt used, as a mock-up, the Star Wars controller and onto that he bolted
a set of red anodized bicycle handlebars that he got at a local bike shop. Probably a kid's
bike shop. But through this controller we were able to prove that you could in fact
control the motion of a kid riding down the street. So it worked. The Paperboy controller
went through several iterations.
The biggest iteration was the ever-shrinking width of the handlebars.
This was because you could apply an enormous amount of torque
onto the controller through those handlebars.
At Atari, we had a thing called the Steuben Test,
named after Dave Steuben, who was the head of engineering at the time.
Dave is a big guy.
And if your controller could survive Dave,
you could manufacture it.
Sadly, several of the Paperboy prototype controllers
died horrible deaths at the hands of Dave,
including one time where Dave actually removed
the controller from the cabinet.
Somehow, Milt was able to, through this process
of destruction and reinforcement,
build a controller that could eventually survive
and was manufactured.
The controller had one other problem.
it had a problem with buttons.
You can't see them if you are slightly shorter,
say the height of a kid.
So we would regularly have people coming up to our game
and playing it without ever throwing newspapers.
This is kind of like Temple Run with bees
and you get fired at the end.
This we finally fixed by putting the start buttons
on the controller itself.
so that at least you had to find the button
to start the game.
Of course, we needed to build a street.
Dave and I were both big fans of Zaxxon,
which came out in 1982.
Zaxxon is an isometric game.
If you haven't seen it,
you basically fly a spaceship through essentially a maze.
It scrolls from upper right of the screen to lower left
in, as I say, an isometric perspective.
This was a very early example, maybe the early example,
of a scrolling isometric game.
But Zaxon presented us with a bit of a problem
because it is in a 60 degree,
kind of natural isometric perspective, 60, 60, 120, 120,
pretty standard drafting isometric perspective.
But this gave us a few problems.
First, it made scrolling for us more complicated because
we were scrolling at odd angle to the playfield hardware,
so that just meant drawing was a lot more complicated
for us.
Also, it meant that we would be showing just about as much
of the sides of the houses as we were gonna be
of the fronts of the houses,
and the sides of the houses are not playable surfaces,
so kind of a waste of a lot of real estate there.
Finally, the other problem was that the handlebar controllers
were gonna be at a pretty strong odd angle
to the direction of motion of the kid.
So that meant if you push the handlebar controllers forward,
the kid was going at a 60 degree angle to them,
which felt unnatural.
So this is what we did.
We crushed the x-axis and brought it down horizontal,
parallel to the bottom of the screen,
and also, of course, to the top of the screen.
This solved a few problems for us.
First, the lots now were built parallel
to the scrolling play field,
so we could draw this thing row by row.
Secondly, papers generally flew horizontally,
parallel with the bottom of the screen,
which meant aiming was a lot easier.
And at least now, the controller itself
was parallel to the fronts of the houses,
and the kid was only 45 degrees off angle.
So that felt a lot better.
It simplified some other systems too,
but those were the big reasons.
One of the first things we did, of course,
was to build a house.
Actually, the first house we built, I think I saw for like three months.
The houses, Dave was able to build houses extremely efficiently.
This is a lower cost house here.
There are 73 total unique stamps in the base construction of that house.
Houses range from around 70 to as expensive as about 135 stamps.
Of course, windows, doors, shrubbery, mailboxes, signs, trees, lamps.
These were all areas that were placed on top
of the base houses in the margin above
the scrolling play field.
They, of course, were also reused for the neighborhood.
The grass itself was randomized from around eight stamps.
That meant that Dave was able to build houses
in about a 10 by 10 stamp sheet
of about 80 pixels to 80 pixels.
Pretty efficient.
To our world, we added characters.
We were also very lucky to have a phenomenal character artist
animator join our team.
Will Noble was responsible for the development and creation
of pretty much every character in the game,
including the boy himself.
Creating characters at that time out of motion objects
was a painfully slow process.
You would go from concept sketch work to
grid paper, graph paper where you color in pixels,
to Will sitting over Dave's shoulder,
hand entering those pixels pixel by pixel
into a thing called the pixel processing system.
Those would get transferred to our main VAX
using a floppy disk.
Well, let's just say that for Will
to have created the number of characters
that the fidelity and richness that he did
speaks to, in that environment,
speaks to his wonderful talent.
First thing that Will focused on was, of course,
the paperboy himself.
The paperboy was, went through, was not that,
it looked very much like this early in development.
He was iterated on a bunch of times
to improve graphic fidelity, add a bunch of moves,
we did color cycling in the spokes,
but largely he looked that way.
He's a kid on a bike with a basket in front of him.
We saw the back of the paperboy for a very long time.
It was actually much later
that we finally got to see his face.
And that was because we finally started doing things
like title screens and side panel art for the game.
And so we always kind of wondered what he looked like.
In the end, I'd like to think that the paperboy
takes a bit of a likeness to Alfred E. Newman,
but that's just me.
Our first set of characters in the game were, well, weird.
They remember that most games in those days were pretty damn abstract.
But our first vision was not conventional, to say the least.
Traffic in the streets included rolling pianos and boats.
We had ginormous snails in some of the driveways.
And in fact, we also had ducks in business suits.
By the way, if you want proof of the kind of creative space,
the kind of creative license that leadership gave teams
at Atari, this is it.
So with a single street and a very weird set of characters
and a very basic rule set, we went to Focus Group.
It did not go well.
We had built a game that did not resonate with the players
because the reality we created, well, was unreal.
We were, of course, mortified.
But then a couple of very good things happened
as two new people joined our team.
The first is a guy named Don Trager.
Don joined our team as our product marketing lead.
Don's first big task on Paperboy was, in fact,
to run the aforementioned disastrous focus group.
And instead of telling us how horribly we had done,
we all knew that because we had watched
the whole damn thing from behind a one-way glass.
He told us about the positive things that the players liked in the game.
They liked riding the bike down the street, kind of.
And they really liked knocking that one lady with the shopping cart over.
So those were good things.
He made us focus on the positive.
As a testament to how bad a focus group it was,
at the end of the focus group, one of the focus group participants, a kid,
walked up to Don and asked him where he might buy some acid.
I will talk about Don a little bit more a little bit later.
Second guy to join our team at that guy was Brighton Daw.
Brighton had been the project lead on a few games up to that point.
He was the project lead and lead programmer and mine behind Cloak & Dagger.
Atari management as you can imagine was having a hard time seeing the potential of our game.
Including by the way the current project lead of the game.
But Brighton liked our game and volunteered to take over
as the lead of our project.
He was given that assignment
and immediately injected positiveness,
organization, brainstorming,
and just basically a jolt of energy to our team
that we very much needed.
Brighton stayed with our project
for the rest of the development of Paperboy.
And on Wednesday, we go to pre-production.
We needed to rework our game.
We needed to rebuild the only street that we had created.
But before we did that, the characters had to change.
In response to the focus group, we recast the game.
We did manage to keep a handful of characters.
Death, the wolfman, and the aforementioned lady
with the basket, they all stayed in the game.
But we cut all the other characters.
We knew that we did not want to go with a purely conventional cast,
because after all, the average character you see in a neighborhood riding around
is neither very exciting nor something you probably want to throw a newspaper at.
But we did, so we kept it a bit strange,
and in the end of development of Paperboy,
we added about 18 more characters for a total of 21 characters in the game,
including the bees.
Dave was responsible in addition to this
to the creation and art of the six vehicles in the game.
Their role, of course, is to keep you out of the streets
and to run you over when you go there.
Streets needed to be reworked,
or one street needed to be worked
as response to this focus group.
Up to this point, we had built the street house by house,
but this was not gonna scale.
We needed a different solution.
Dave's answer to this was to construct two five-foot-long foam core storyboards and to
transfer the line drawings of our inventory of houses at the time to those two foam core
storyboards.
He did it kind of like this.
And then he put a plastic sheet on top of that so we could draw on them.
Onto these two storyboards we drew.
the characters, the obstacles, the paper bundles,
the paths of the objects as they moved into the world,
and triggers, anything that you would interact with
on that street.
And so it went from this to this,
and that that course became part of Easy Street.
We did this original layout on what would become Easy Street
outside on a sunny Saturday.
in a marathon creative session in the atrium
of the 1501 building, 1501 McCarthy Boulevard, Milpitas,
drinking beer.
This beer came from the previous night's
beer bash at Atari.
Both Dave and I remember this as being
one of the great creative days of our careers.
In a sense, the muse came to us with a keg.
This became our blueprint for construction
for our first street.
We did have a bit of a problem.
We wanted to take score away from the player
for breaking the windows on his customers.
At the time, you could not lose customers,
you could only smash their windows.
But back then in the arcades, and probably true now,
you just don't take score away from players.
So Lyle Rains, who was the creative director of Atari,
who's one of the minds behind Asteroids, of course,
came up with the idea of separating out
damage bonus, breakage bonus, from the core score
so we could take score away from the player
and get away with it.
I think it worked.
So, with a newly cast first road,
a fully laid out first road,
and a somewhat improved scoring system,
we went to our second focus group,
and it generally went well.
We got out of our focus group
what we needed to get into production,
confidence that we were building the right game.
And so on Thursday, we go to production.
We went to production with key takeaways.
We needed more depth in our game.
We only had one road.
Paper delivery needed to be a whole lot more interesting
and more important.
And the sounds needed a lot of work.
So we used the same construction techniques
we had on the first street to build two streets.
But before that, we gave our first street its name.
Easy Street, it had been unnamed up to that point,
and to that we added Middle Road and Hard Way.
But, as with all games in those days, we had a problem.
ROMs were expensive, and we were running out of space.
I suppose that's true of games today, too.
The good news is that Paperboy is largely
a patterned learning game, so giving the players familiarity
by seeing some of the same house designs in the game
was really not a bad thing.
So we ended up leveraging our base house design significantly.
This house here, which is, of course,
the first house you see in the street, of Easy Street,
is in the game six times.
This here house, 116 Easy Street, about halfway
down the first block, you see also about six times.
In fact, in Paperboy, there are 60 total street addresses
made of 11 base house designs,
and nine cross streets made out of one base cross street.
So we were able to fit the thing in ROM.
A popular idea at the folks' groups
was the idea of a training course.
Now, of course, the training course in Paperboy
is essentially a bonus round.
Paperboy was not the game that invented bonus rounds.
But it was a break in the action for us
and a way to bring in new game mechanics.
Our first idea here, by the way,
was to have a field covered in windows and mailboxes.
But we landed on a more pinball style theme
with knockdown targets, that sort of thing.
I don't think Dave was very happy
with the bonus round of the training course.
He wanted much more dynamic elements,
moving targets, that sort of thing.
and he wanted the training course to progress day to day
based on your previous actions from the previous day.
But I think it worked,
and I think it changes the rhythm of the game.
I think arriving at the end of the street to a grandstand
gives a little bit of magical surprise.
Paperboy is really, of course, three games in one.
The three streets are completely independent.
In fact, we were even considering for a while,
a bit too late, releasing Paperboy
in three independent episodes.
But because we released it all as a single game,
we needed to tie those three streets together
and reward a high score for the player
who did the best on the accumulated score of all three.
We called this our Grand Slam high score table.
The Grand Slam system and much more
was written by a guy named Bob Flanagan.
Bob Flanagan was and is an outstanding game programmer.
Bob started at Atari on Paperboy,
but then is the only programmer to work on not only Paperboy,
but Marble Madness, Gauntlet 1, and Gauntlet 2.
Also, I should say, Bob and I are both currently employed
at Electronic Arts, and we count three more alumni of Atari
at EA for a total of five.
The map screen we needed to add because we had given
the player at this time the ability to lose
and then gain back customers.
I think the map screen has to be one of the earliest
examples of a meta game, certainly in the arcades.
You were on a very basic level managing an economy.
That gave you a bit of a break in action.
But here's what I really think.
Real paper boys, if you remember them.
would start each day by getting a bundle of newspapers,
like you see in the game, cutting them open,
and then rolling each newspaper, newspaper by newspaper,
taking a rubber band, putting it over those rolls,
and taking those papers and putting them in their bags
as they go out on their day.
For me, I think the map screen is a metaphor for this,
because it prepares you for your next day.
So it is our homage to Real Paper Boys.
As a byproduct of these game systems,
we gave the player a choice between good and, well, evil.
We never really did think of the boy as a hooligan,
but you did have a choice.
You could spend your game trashing every house
on the street and just save one,
or you could focus on being the best paper deliverer
possible, but of course, to get the best score,
you needed to do both.
But I think this player choice, this trade-off,
kinda works
the paperboy. You must remember to deliver only to customers, not the non-customers.
If they are not your customer, break their window. Remember, death comes on a Tuesday.
Thank you Shadowcast Pictures and Freak Films. I have left for last, of course, the incredible
soundtrack of Paperboy.
After all, didn't we always leave sounds to the end?
We had two key people on audio,
both with the title sound designer.
On the left, you will see a man named Hal Cannon.
Hal Cannon was responsible
for the excellent Paperboy music, the soundtrack, the score.
Hal also composed the music for Marble Madness,
Gauntlet, 720, and a bunch of other games at Atari.
Hal mysteriously left Atari somewhere in the mid to late 80s
and basically was never seen again.
He's the only person of the original team
I did not interview for this presentation.
I hear rumors that he's in Lake Tahoe, I just don't know.
Earl Vickers joined our team as the lead sound designer
and our main contact into the audio group.
He is responsible for all the sounds
and the voice in the game.
He has not disappeared.
He is still active in the Atari community.
Earl Vickers was instrumental in the addition and usage
of the Yamaha YM2151 FM synthesis music chip.
Wiki says it was the first Yamaha single chip
FM they ever produced.
Earl just thought of it as freaking magic.
Added to this was a very cool speech synthesizer
from Texas Instruments.
Speech was being added to pinball at the time,
so it was natural that it would come to video.
Earl Vickers composed most of the lines of dialogue
you hear in the game.
Earl also conducted the auditions within Atari
for the voice talent we used.
We, of course, did not pay professional voice talent.
For the narrator, he chose a fellow game programmer
named Peter Thompson.
For the narrator, we were thinking we wanted to cover
and dramatize the character,
we wanted to over-dramatize the character of the kid,
to give the kid a gravitas not associated
with paper delivery specialists,
to create a hero or perhaps an anti-hero.
The voice of the paperboy was done by none other
than our product marketing manager, Don Traeger.
By the way, a bit later, Don helped to start
the whole electronic arts sports business,
among other things.
But I think him doing the voice of the paperboy
was his finest work.
Years later, Don was at a trade show
working for electronic arts.
He walked up to a Bally Midway booth.
and where they were demonstrating a sequel to Paperboy.
The booth guy demonstrating the game showed him the game,
and then at the end of the demonstration looked at Don
and said, sir, are you familiar with Paperboy?
To which Don said, sir, I am the Paperboy.
And walked away.
The Paperboy's lines themselves are split
into basically three categories.
The first of which was as a response to dying.
These were pretty much, pretty easy hooks to put in
because after all we knew when they were dying
or he was running into something.
You hear them clearly because that's a good moment
of the game.
The second set of lines, next category was as a reward
for putting newspapers directly into a mailbox.
Again, simple hooks for me to put in.
Again, a very nice moment in the game
and easy to recognize.
The third set of lines, I think, were, well,
the most interesting.
They were basically the kids' observations
on the characters in the game.
This is basically a commentary as delivered
from the paperboy's perspective.
We were trying to anticipate what the player was thinking
as they played the game, and then give it a voice.
Sadly, mostly because these cues stepped on other audio and the complexity of just figuring
out when a character was on the screen, a lot of these cues never made it.
Mostly because, in the end, we ran out of time.
Not too surprisingly, we crunched to get the boy ready for test.
I myself worked something like eight weeks of seven days a week in the lab.
I want to take a moment now and pause and I'd like to thank my wife Donna for putting
up with me during this time.
She was my girlfriend at the time.
Without her doing that, I just would not have made it.
But in the end, us putting this game together was a labor of love.
One thing happened as we got close to field test.
People came into our lab and started playing our game.
At Atari, you knew you had a good game when at lunch,
people would come in and play your game.
After all, it was the only place
that you could play this game in that lab.
And so we spent the weeks and months
getting ready for field test,
watching people play our game,
playing our game ourselves, and iterating on it.
And in the end, I think it prepared us
pretty well for field test.
And so on Friday, we go to field test.
First field test was conducted at Golf Land Sunnyvale.
Tari did a lot of, this is on El Camino for those of you who know it,
Tari did a lot of field testing at Golf Land.
It was close to where we were, it was a big arcade.
We knew our competition was there, and frankly, they knew we were there.
Linda Sinkovic, our technician, was responsible for
the care and feeding of our game and the arcade.
So one of the core things she would do, for example,
would be to change ROMs as we did iterations.
She remembers quite fondly putting a bunch of credits
in the game for the kids that were waiting in line
behind her as she did that.
Due to the success of Marble Madness largely
and of System 1, Atari rebranded the Paperboy hardware
at this time to System 2.
The biggest change to the hardware was the splitting off
of a separatable ROM board, which is,
you see on the right there.
so you could do a ROM change without changing the whole cabinet.
The other biggest change was taking our very cool three-box cabinet
and turning it into a more generic one-box cabinet
and removing our very cool side panel art.
Oh well.
720, Accelerator, APB, Super Sprint
are among some of the games that got built on System 2,
but I think largely they were all built as whole games
and not as ROM changes.
Field tests for Paperboy lasted for about four months.
We spent that time watching people play
and doing iterations.
We collected data, games even then recorded
and aggregated player statistics, and iterated.
We talked to players.
You could do that then as they played the game.
Paperboy earned well and consistently.
It didn't break any records,
but it held its earnings over a four-month period.
such that at the end of that period,
we were able to convince,
or maybe the earnings were able to convince,
Atari leadership to build our game.
And then, of course, at that point,
it became Atari's game.
So, on Saturday, we go to manufacturing.
Paperboy was first shown
at the Amusement Machine Operators Association show,
AMOA.
in Chicago in the fall of 1984.
It was shown alongside of Marble Madness,
but not sold then.
Marble Madness was.
Paperboy was first sold at the Amusement Showcase
International show, ASI show, in the spring of 1985.
And manufacturing would have begun right about then.
Here are some pictures of Paperboy
on the manufacturing line.
In the upper left corner, you will see Dave Rauston
playing the game on the line.
In the lower right corner, you will see a row of Paper Boys on the line.
I cannot tell you how ridiculously wonderful and singular experience it is as a game maker
to see your game on a manufacturing line.
In the upper right hand corner, you will see a somewhat redacted picture of the Paper Boy
launch party.
This was an all day, all night affair.
Atari marketed the game as usual,
although there were a couple things that were a bit different.
Typically, they would sell games through sell sheets and print ads,
and that was about the same.
But one thing that was different was that Dave and I were lucky enough
to actually be featured in some of these print ads.
I'm not sure that Dave and I were the first featured in print ads,
but we were pretty early.
You have to keep in mind that in a few years previous to this,
Atari did not even allow credit screens in its games.
kind of made themselves, so this was a pretty big deal,
and I think Dave and I enjoyed it thoroughly.
Another thing was that Atari, the summer of 1985,
conducted a world's greatest paperboy competition,
complete with a fake neighborhood, summer 85.
And in the end, around 3,000 units, 3,500 units,
were produced and sold for about 2,500 bucks each.
We were all hoping for maybe more than 5,000 units,
but the Paperboy was expensive,
and well, it was 1985 in the arcades.
And now about the Nintendo Entertainment System.
In every reasonable, independent, quantifiable measure,
the System 2 crushes the NES.
It has more bits.
It has more speed, it has more pixels, it has more RAM, it has more ROM.
Hell, we had a custom controller, a beautiful medium resolution monitor, speakers, and everything.
Every single metric except one.
As I mentioned, the Paperboy arcade sold about 3,500 units in the spring of 1985.
Three years later, in Mindscape, ported Paperboy to the NES
and to manage to sell, oh well, two million copies.
Obviously, we were all very glad of this.
We were very excited, frankly, quite blown away.
It took me, personally, years and years though,
after this, to ever realize
that the days of the arcades were numbered.
Paperboy derivatives have been published
on lots of platforms.
both as faithful ports and true sequels,
but I think, unless your game has been ported
as an LCD video game,
you have not really made it.
And so now we come to the true post-mortem.
I'm not here to bury, paper away,
So on Sunday, the papers are heavier.
So in terms of a true postmortem,
first we have to talk about what we wish we had had less of.
This was a less than wonderful day, the day that we
learned we were being sued.
We learned this, by the way, first in the press.
Two kids claimed that they had sent to Atari
the idea for Paperboy.
Now we knew.
that Dave had shown us the concept for Paperboy
well in advance of when they even claimed
to have sent it to us.
And Atari was incredibly supportive in this,
but it still hurt.
I myself learned about this waking up one morning
and hearing a news anchor on my radio tell me about it.
This was just kind of interesting.
In December of 1985, we were informed that folks at the CPSC
were concerned that perhaps we were teaching
bad bicycle riding habits.
You know, riding down the wrong side of the street into traffic.
Actually, if you're interested in this kind of thing,
almost exactly a year ago, The Daily Show, Trevor Noah.
did a thing about games teaching guns.
And he actually used Paperboy as a reference
for how kids don't actually learn
how to smash all the windows on the street through games.
So I recommend it if you're interested.
And in terms of what every programmer wants less of, bugs.
So if you see the newspaper going
behind the back of the Paperboy.
It is not, in fact, a wraparound Steph Curry throw.
It is, in fact, an ordering problem between the papers
and the paper boy.
Similarly, if you see the paper boy riding
through solid objects, this is, in fact, a priority problem
between the paper boy and the planter
that should be behind him.
This is a great bug.
I learned about this bug two weeks ago.
doing the presentation for this presentation.
So you see on the screen two different houses
with this on the screen.
What's interesting about it is, well, they
both have the same address.
The house on the left is properly
numbered 111 Easy Street.
It is the last house on the first block of Easy Street.
The house on the right should be numbered 110 Easy Street.
It is the first house on the second block of Easy Street.
Turns out if you get hit crossing the road between these two houses, it screws up the
addresses of every single house on the second block.
But days after manufacturing began, and weeks and weeks after the ROMs were burned, we heard
about this rather amazing bug.
For those of you who have not heard of this bug, I will describe it to you.
At the end of each round, of course, right in front
of the grand stand, there is a yellow line.
You ride your bike up to the line.
The game ends for that round.
But instead, if you feel so inclined,
you may take a hard right turn at the end there
and cut into that grass area.
It turns out if you do that, well, you ride forever.
And you get millions of points in this kind
of surreal stamp play field.
As I mentioned, I learned about this literally the day
of manufacturing began.
I learned about this and those cabinets
were on the manufacturing line.
I was, of course, somewhat panicked.
But it turns out this was a mode problem, of course,
because you're skipping the trigger line
that's under that line by doing that little cut.
But what's really more interesting and pretty neat,
I think, is that the fix to this bug was two bytes.
In fact, it was really.
four bits.
This was basically changing a constant 77 to a two,
and a branch equal to a branch not equal.
That impacted one and only one ROM, which saved my life.
In fact, this was the only ROM change
that Atari ever did for Paperboy.
And I think you can still see this bug
if you'd like to in the arcades.
I know it's available on YouTube.
And in terms of things that I wish there were more of,
well, first this.
David always wanted indirect shots.
He wanted the ability to kick things off of an obstacle
and break a second story window.
In fact, lots of the houses in our game
had fully functional windows.
that could have been broken if I could ever have gotten
the newspaper there.
But unfortunately, this really screwed up
the collision system, so we never really did it.
In fact, lots of targets up there never got reached.
This house was the poster child for that one.
We always wanted to knock over
a potted plant at the top of that house.
As you may have noticed in this presentation,
there are initials of several of the team members
hidden in the vehicles of the game.
Dave's initials are hidden in the construction sign
in front of the dirt jump ramp.
Dave may argue with me on this one,
but to me it is not a random fact
that the hat color of player one is orange,
and the second player is blue.
Orange for player one, blue for player two.
At Atari, Major League Baseball was a really big thing.
I myself am a diehard Giants fan.
Dave was a diehard Dodger fan.
Orange for player one, blue for player two.
I'm just saying.
In terms of things that I really wish there was much more,
our team stayed together for a while.
Dave and I would not leave Atari for another six years,
and in that time, we managed to build
three other games in that time.
But in terms of things that I wish there were much more,
the joy of writing Paperboy,
the incredible creative freedom and license
that Atari Games gave us in doing that,
the fact that I was the first person
to ever see anything in Paperboy, I do remember that.
This was not my only time at the rodeo.
I've launched and shipped plenty of the games since then,
but it was my first.
Over the years, I have heard the stories
of people who've played Paperboy.
I've heard people say,
hey, I just played your game in the lab.
Hey, I played, hey man, this game is cool.
When will it come out?
Hey, I played Paperboy in the bowling alley the other day.
I remember that I used to play Paperboy as a kid.
My son and I play Paperboy together.
He really likes it.
Pretty cool, really.
I hope you have had some joy in playing Paperboy 2.
And that's Paperboy in seven days.
I hope I will be able to answer some questions in a second,
but I wanted to leave you with this from Random Encounters.
Whoa!
Woo!
Hey! Keep driving! Lo-ho!
I'm on a walk with Junior like any other day
I'm not sure how it happened but the babies rolled away
I'd positively panic but it happened last week too
Plus I'm just the babysitter losing children's what I do
Babies rolling down Easy Street
Oh that baby
I'm trying to get my pants on but they're really freaking tight
Why I'm in the street I haven't got a clue
At precisely 9.08, I come out my door and wait, and leave out a luring bait, for the paperboy I hate!
Sing!
Steve Cars is what I do.
Give me all your money and put it in this bag.
I need it for my wife cause she's a shopaholic hag.
Hey come on make it snappy, this ain't no deja vu.
I rob you almost daily because robbing's what I do.
I don't get all this fuss, I'm just a normal guy.
Who takes his normal rocks and collects souls when people die.
I love to read the funnies on the entertainment news.
I'm not that weird, it's just a thing I do.
I think we have a few minutes for questions if anybody's got any.
I have five minutes for questions if anybody's got any.
Okay.
Hello.
Hi.
Hi. Fantastic talk. Really loved the whole process and hearing the story about it.
I was curious, after the release of the original paperboard, did you have any hand or work or influence on the derivatives or paperboard 2 that came out years later?
Not at, Dave had some, I had none.
Atari, you did not do sequels at all.
Imagine, I work for Electronic Arts now, so this is.
Shh.
So at Atari, they actually told you not.
So Dave and I immediately started focusing on 720,
and that became my life at that point.
And then Atari added Tengen to do derivatives,
and at that point, we got more involved.
but not a lot. Those games are really driven independently.
Thanks. Of course.
I just noticed when you were
showing all the different vehicles with the associated people, the one with the motorcycle
the initials didn't seem to match. What's the story behind that?
Oh my god, I can't believe you asked that question. So that's
Milt Loper. That's CR on there.
So I just talked to Milti about that for a while,
really trying to get it.
So he, I don't think I'm getting anything.
So he was pretty heavy duty motorcycle gang kind of guy
before he worked at Atari.
And the best he told me was CR stands for Crazy Rooster.
That's all I got on that one.
Thank you.
I don't think it stands for that, by the way.
Anything else?
I was a paperboy when it came out and I loved this game as a kid.
I could never get more than about halfway through though, so my question is, can you
beat it?
Can I beat the game?
I can get through it.
These days, hell no.
Back then, yeah, I could get through most of the game.
Hard way, it's a little hard for me.
Dave is an awesome player.
Yeah, I've never been the greatest player on earth, but yeah, I did okay.
There's great videos of people who are really good at the game, of course.
That's pretty spectacular for me to watch.
All right, so I'll throw two quick ones at you.
So you cracked me up with the comparison of hardware on the Nintendo, but I'm probably,
in fact, show of hands, who played the Nintendo version?
Yeah, that's probably most of us.
I never actually got to see the arcade.
Wait, who played the arcade version?
My God.
All right, so 50-50.
Hey, that's pretty good.
But nevertheless, did you guys have any hand in the Nintendo port at all?
Did they at least consult you or anything or just kind of popped out?
to my recollection, it was magic.
In fact, look, so the byline at Atari Games,
the one I worked at was, coin up the real Atari.
To say we were looking down on the home was,
that's an understatement.
So we were privileged kids working
on these incredible hardware.
So, no, I really didn't.
I think I would be dishonest if I said I did.
No, that's fine.
They did an incredible job on that game.
Honestly, that's what I grew up liking.
And then the other one is literally on my Nintendo Switch over there, there's a game
called The Video Kid.
Are you familiar with this game?
I am not.
Anybody in here familiar with The Video Kid?
so a couple people, it's basically 80s nostalgia on Paperboy.
Oh, excellent.
So the fact that, and you didn't even know it existed, right?
So I'll show it to you at the end because I got my Switch.
But, I mean, how does that feel that you're still literally influencing games and styles
and it's, you know, I'm sure there's mobile games and all these things based on this design.
So it was that story I told at the end and that very much is, I don't make it through,
you know, I've been in the business a few years now, and I don't make it through a year.
without walking into some meeting.
And it's typically an executive who's been playing my game
when they were a kid, saying, well, here's John Solitz.
Yes, he's the technical director on this project.
But what he really did, he worked on Paperboy
back in the 80s.
I love it.
Isn't that exciting?
Cool.
Thank you.
So did Atari have any guidelines as far as, like,
average gameplay per quarter?
Yeah.
Yeah, you were trying.
So everything was about, um, uh,
Yeah, you want to have 30 to 90 seconds per credit.
Paperweight actually came out at $0.50 a play,
somewhere in there.
And what was really interesting was some of the stuff
that I actually cut from the presentation was,
one of the things was that you knew
you had to hook the player in 30 seconds.
And the positive thing that that did for the team,
it focused the whole team on core gameplay.
I'm sure a lot of us have been on game teams
where they don't focus on gameplay,
they focus on everything around gameplay.
but if you got to grab somebody in 30 seconds,
it focused you.
And so the idea was that if you didn't get the player
within 30 seconds, they'd walk away.
So in terms of earnings, somewhere, as I recall,
a couple other people probably, Franz, you know better,
so 30 to 90 seconds, somewhere in there,
is what you kind of want to turnover rate.
Oh God.
Franz Lanziger.
Hello. Thank you so much for this trip down memory lane for me.
That was quite an experience.
I had the privilege of working with John at Atari for a couple of years.
When you mentioned bliss, I thought, oh, my God, I totally forgotten about this.
So I used sixty five or two on Crystal Castles, but then I worked on Gremlins,
which never made it out the door in bliss.
So I qualify my thing by successfully shipping.
I just wanted to, yeah.
So I do have a question.
What other projects did you use Bliss on?
It was 720.
720, and then you moved on to C probably?
Yep, C++, yep.
C, straight C.
Yeah, so Bliss, for those of you,
I bet nobody knows what Bliss is.
It was a high-level language, sort of like C.
It sort of looked like C.
You could actually do if-then-elses and loops.
And the processor underneath was something entirely new, was 16 bits all of a sudden,
not 8 bits. So, very exciting. Anyway, thank you so much.