Hello and welcome to the diary of a modern PR campaign.
Today, we're going to talk about how
to plan your game's promotion.
I'm Thomas Reisenacher, and I'm also very happy that you're
here.
Thanks a lot for coming.
As for every GDC talk, I've been asked
to remind you to switch your phone to silent
and also rate the session after it's over.
So before we dive into how we plan a campaign, something
a bit different, a little thought experiment,
but I think it will help you understand
the main point of this talk.
So we have here a blank space and we have you.
And that's you going to meet a friend at a coffee
and suddenly you see someone coming up to you,
poking his head out, he walks up, comes closer,
puts his hand up, has a cup of coffee,
then says, do you want to buy this cup of coffee
for three dollars, just made it, it's really good.
What are you gonna say?
Hell no, like I don't know who you are,
why should I buy a cup of coffee, this is weird.
However, this is I think one of the main 2 problems that a lot of games PR has this day
that there's a lot of literature and a lot of people are very good at getting the game
out there and get some awareness wants to be a website a big you to go right to the
end.
But without the right context and without the right build up,
that's probably a weird situation.
And that's something a lot of games face these days.
And a second problem, of course, is just
the sheer number of games, which makes PR and marketing
activities very necessary.
If you imagine the same situation,
but with a million people that come up to you
offering a coffee, it's probably even weirder.
And you're going to say a lot of, hell no,
I don't want your coffee.
So.
Within the first two minutes of the talk, we already found out that selling games is actually coffee.
And stick with me, that might sound weird, but throughout the talk, I'm going to explain to you more also how we can be that guy that sells the coffee, but actually makes a sale and actually gets people on board with it.
So topics for today, the first half is going to focus on what
really sells a game, and the second half
is going to focus on the 5 phases on a PR campaign.
So that's a bit more practical bit.
And in the end, there's going to be a short summary.
And obviously, this is a very broad topic,
how you plan a whole PR campaign.
So I can't go into detail into every aspect of it.
However, what I can do is try to show you the big picture
and then refer at points where I have some good literature
or some good links, refer you there
so you can look up details.
for the more detailed task within the PR planning.
A few words about me before we start properly.
I'm Thomas Reisenecker.
I founded Future Friends Games.
It's a small PR agency in Brighton in the UK.
And through my career, I've worked on over 40 games,
some bigger ones like League of Legends and Smite,
also some quite small ones, indie titles
like Anomalous Phono at the moment,
or well, Ignorance Dram for Watergolf.
Within the talk, you will only see my opinions and my learnings throughout the years, but also those from other people.
And most importantly, I also did something called the Indie Game PR Survey,
where I asked studios about their PR experience, and 128 of them took part.
And a couple of those experiences and statistics you're going to see in the talk.
However, I couldn't fit all of it in, so if you want to get all the data, you can follow me on Twitter, and I'm going to post those after GDC.
And you can also write me a DM if you want, and I can email them to you.
So that the one what really sells games the question that was becoming more and
more important important in my field of work where I saw games doing really
well in terms of PR but suddenly they're not selling it obviously a big part of
that is because they just so many games now but even considering that they were
quite a bit of a lot of games that did well in terms of getting the name out
there, but then actually didn't perform in terms of sales so it was a bit like
my mission of the watch it like trying to figure out why this happens.
So I just tried to do it and I started looking up if I can find out what really moves the needle for a game.
So the first thing was maybe the most obvious one just looking maybe just the quality of the game maybe just about making a really really good game.
because whenever you give a PR talk, I'm sure there's people coming up to you afterwards
and say like, look, I don't need PR, just make the best game ever.
It is fair if you can do that, but just a very good game, is this enough?
There's a really good Gamasutra article on the topic that tried to find out how many
Steam games are there that have extremely good reviews, but hardly any sales.
And the verdict of the article is, a lot.
Those hidden gems.
I like numerous so just making a game is definitely not a fact that that just get to get out there
and definitely makes it a hit.
Moving on thought maybe it's a brand maybe it's about having a good name, but then there
are lots of example like this prison architect very successful game.
So the 2 million copies for uptightness can assemble so 6,000 copies in the first 2 months.
So you can see that even with a big name a big brand it doesn't guarantee that you've
got to be successful.
Maybe it's the media I thought.
Maybe it's about being on a lot of websites.
There's an example I worked on.
It's called Blackboard Crossing.
It's a very nice narrative game.
It did extremely well in terms of PR.
It got nice reviews.
It got good coverage.
In the end, however, it didn't sell well.
It was selling, according to Steam Spy,
5,000 sales in the first six months.
You see, that's not nothing, but that's not impressive.
Moving on, maybe thought maybe it's YouTubers and streamers.
This is something that came up quite a lot.
I think you warned it two years ago that people said,
like, if one of the big ones covers you,
this is going to make it for you.
But then there were a lot of threats coming up like this.
Then Marshall made a game called Kick Man.
It was covered by a big YouTuber,
has 703 million subscribers, gets 70,000 views,
which results in 15 copies of sales.
So you can see also a big YouTube video
doesn't necessarily mean you're going to sell a lot of copies.
And then look for maybe it's different platforms and in all
fairness to switch is doing quite well now, but probably by
the time that talk is over on you to is already hot of the
silence which because it's such a gold rush now and also the
other platforms don't necessarily guarantee any sales
numbers.
The same is for social media will select a lot of examples
there even if they did well on the other doesn't mean that
would necessarily sell well.
What is the next step of the professional you just panic
because you don't know what you should actually do that make
the game sell.
But what you can do is next step was what I did is just turn to people that may be more clever than me and I just asked them and did the in the game. Piazza V and one of the question was what do you think I'm telling you again what helped a lot.
And the strongest answer was store features that was the thing that helped him a lot like 45 people out of 128. This is pretty good and it all of them got features.
They said sales for really good.
follow-up websites you to listen social media and then a bunch of other stuff
interesting deals and use that this is quite high up considering a lot of
people had actually is that this but those that had them said they were quite
successful and pretty much in the end you can also see print magazines but
it's big caveat that a lot of people were like I just don't know if I even
was covered in a print magazine because I don't pay attention so I don't really
know.
So as a follow-up question we also asked what what helped the bid this is the
things you see in blue here.
And suddenly you get a different picture.
You suddenly you see there's a lot of things that are quite strong.
The top 5.
Um, nearly equal up in the terms of how long the bar is,
which is probably also related that a storm feature for a sale,
you can actually see if you convert into an actual sale,
whereas for PR things and YouTube videos,
you can only guess if that would be a sale or not.
So if you look at the graph in the end of the day,
it doesn't tell you a whole lot.
It just tells you it's really different per game,
and there's a lot of factors to play together.
So my answer for myself was there is no magic bullet of the one thing that can tell you
game really well.
However, there is a couple of games with a magic bullet.
That's like Bob T did it with Twitch and Cuphead just looks really good and gets featured by
Microsoft.
But that's that's not that's not an average game.
If you talk about 99 percent of the other games, they're going to have to figure out
something else.
So what is that?
How can we figure that out?
So instead, the next step was, instead of looking at the different media, the different outlets you have,
maybe it's better to just look at games that did well and then figure out why they did well.
So here are four examples.
There's a game called Northgard that did extremely well.
It has over 500,000 owners on Steam, wasn't any big discounts yet,
so that's probably also pretty much the copies they sold.
So really, really good.
And there's a second called Open Journey, which
is regularly in the app charts.
It's doing extremely well.
It's also doing really well on Switch.
Within a week, it was refinanced to Switch port.
So why were they so good?
The answer for them were quite easy.
They got store features.
Northgard was doing really well in terms of Steam.
It's a strategy game.
It got really well reviewed.
And Steam just kept recommending it, kept recommending it.
And then it became very successful.
And after they've been very successful,
they got more PR feedback.
And Open Journey is a game that looks extremely beautiful
on an iPhone.
That's also what Apple knows.
They've been featuring this game a lot.
If you look at App Annie, it got over 4,000 features
over the last couple of months.
So I guess that's one way to go down the line,
is just make a game that plays really well in terms
of a store feature.
But obviously, this is not very secure,
because you're not controlling if you get a store feature or not.
So this is a risky option what are the options that to against the extreme the
well one is called niche and a Kickstarter had phenomenal community building
campaign and in the end of the day it had over 80,000 owners and steam again
without really big discounts anything so did quite well in terms of how big the
game was and another game called the first 3 by so the developer called it
really did also extremely well
and he did a really great postmortem that shows you how he did well.
And this is what I call a launch build up.
This is a second route you can go down.
This is a longer PR campaign where you really work it.
But in the end of the day, that usually,
especially in the climate of today's PR,
really tends to pay off.
We look at David Whealy's post-mortem,
just very short here.
He just basically showed a graph how much website
wizards he gets.
And as you can see, he has loads of different spites
from little activities.
So this is like his stats he had for launch.
It's really good.
But he explains really well how he got there.
It was not one big thing.
It was.
a couple of gifts going well it was a couple of ready post going well couple of into post
to really work at him with everything he did he got a more newsletter signups and really
build a community that helped him along the way also in terms of media which I would explain
it.
But.
So the area want to focus on today's to launch build up.
Not because of Amy for so feature is bad.
But you can build up for launch and still get a feature which is fine.
But you cannot just focus on the soft feature that what would give you the build up so it's a more risky way of the 2.
So in the end of the day why did those 2 games sell well and I think this is space explain with this graph this is called a sales funnel.
And a lot of PR a lot of studios, I think a very focused and very good at the first stage getting awareness just getting that game in front of people.
This is something, there's a lot of literature on this topic.
However, if you only see the game once,
that's like the guy that just holds a coffee in front of you.
That probably doesn't convince you to buy it.
If you think about it, which games you buy,
it's probably the ones you see in an advert,
in a couple of articles, in a couple of YouTube videos,
and they keep coming up, and you're like,
oh, there must be something about this one.
It keeps coming up.
So that's what we call the consideration phase.
That's where we want people to get in the next step.
And after that, if they still keep seeing it,
or if they find the game is really cool,
they probably become your customer.
And that's your goal.
So it's not just getting the awareness,
because that's the first step, and it's very helpful.
But without the necessary means, you
don't get them to become a customer in the end.
And if they like your game, or you're
very good at even talking to them later on,
you probably make them into fans.
So if you know about that, one really important thing is,
if you have a small or mid-sized game,
whatever you do, you always have to think about
how you can get your audience to become a customer or fan.
And one way to do it would just be on website articles all the time, be on PC Gamer every day.
But this is really hard.
So what you want to do is, you want to find a place where you talk to people.
This could be a Discord, this could be a newsletter, this could be something where whatever you do, you try to get people there.
Because once you've signed them up, once you've liked their Twitter page, you can directly talk to them.
And you don't depend on outside sources that maybe feature your game or maybe not.
So this is a thing really important in the beginning to already figure out where do you want people to go a really good example was the send us from my gross. What did it was to meet a free pizza, but you could only get it if you sign up for the discord so they knew if you sign up for this cut they can keep talking to you. There was a really good kickstarter called new bottles and if you want to play the demo of the game you have to sign up for the newsletter. So again they already thought about how can we talk to people after they've seen this demo.
And another thing about the South on the which is a bit of fortunate is.
It only looks really nice here because it's up with the colors and actually the bit like that so it's it's way harder to transfer those people down those different ranks and through reminding them and through sending the different things.
And this was by the way made by a really good purpose by Chris to cross the.
So next up, we want to look at how we actually, knowing that,
how we do that PR campaign.
We do it in five phases.
And this is the power timeline.
It's probably something you've seen before.
And I think the big two important things on that
is the game reveal.
So it's not the announcement, but the reveal,
what I understand it is the first time
when you have a big trailer that you send out,
the first time you contact press about it.
So you can maybe talk about it before in a pub,
and you show it to make a couple of tweets,
show it to some friends.
But the reveal is the timing you make it official.
And then there's the launch.
And as a PR person, most people come to me here.
This is a couple of weeks or a month before the launch.
This is usually too late.
You can make a game a bit bigger there,
but you can't really make it blow up
if it wasn't good before that.
This is the equivalent of someone.
If you'd a coffee guy that wants to sell the coffee and you just one day before you start selling it and you just like
Oh, take 50 flyers and just put them out somewhere. This is not gonna this is not gonna do it
So actually your whole PR campaign
It's just a whole thing game development is PR and it's marketing as soon as you start working in it
you actually make something you probably want to sell and every decision you make on the way is
Working on this goal to make that game selling get it out there
It doesn't matter if it's the name doesn't matter if it's website all of those things
So the first phase, five phases in total we're going to talk about, is the setup phase.
And this is, I think, by far the most important phase.
This is one a lot of people don't take as much time as they should.
And I think, as advice, if you can hire a PR professional, if you get some consultant,
if you have a friend, you can ask how did they do their PR, and they can help you a
little bit.
This is the phase when you want to get them on board.
because we actually do here if this when you learn to put a coffee to people
actually want to buy.
This is really important if you could hear if you make something that people
want and you can also describe it all the other way along the line is quite
easy, but it's really hot if you make a really bad coffee in the best thing says
him can't get it out there.
So the top 5 things you want to do in the setup phase.
The number one is you make it game that people care about and you learn to talk
about it.
And what I mean by that is,
there's a lot of very similar games.
If I've seen so many people contact me
with really good puzzle platformers,
and it's a shame because they're going to be good games,
they're going to be eight or nine out of tens,
but there are so many good puzzle platformers
that that is not enough.
You need to have a 10 out of 10
if you want to have a good one there.
Whereas on the other hand, they worked on a surfing game called Surf Alterius.
And let's just say it was not game of the year.
It was alright.
But it was extremely easy to PI it.
And the fact for that is just there wasn't any bigger surfing game in 10 years.
So it really your PR starts here just picking someone that's going to be easy to promote
that people have an interest in.
This is called the difference between push and pull PR.
Push PR means you make something that people don't necessarily want that much and you just
push it on them, which works.
You can get on websites if you're good PR people.
You can buy advertisement, but you're always going to get stuck in the first phase of the
sales funnel.
You're always going to get awareness, but you never go into consideration because they're
not actually that into that game.
Whereas pull BI is something you make something quite exciting
that people want, and then it's quite easy to get it out there.
And that also plays along with press.
Press usually covers things that they
think are either big already or are going to be big very soon.
And then they cover it, and people click on it,
and press is excited.
And they cover it more, and people click on it more.
And this is the circle of the life spiral.
That's what it's called in the blog post I found.
And again, if you don't have that spiral that
keeps kicking off, you're going to have a really hard time
further down the line.
So once you figure out what game you want to make and what should have an appeal you want to learn how to talk about it.
Free things they used to do before I start working on a game all police. I make a friend says this is you go to a party you go to friends.
These have to be really good friends like the honest friends the friends that would tell you that they have a bad haircut.
And you go up to them and you just pitch them the game of one or two sentences.
They ideally should be in your target group, so more hardcore gamer, more casual gamer.
And if you tell them, hey, I'm going to make Super Mario, but you don't play Mario, but you play a cow,
you can look at it like that.
Because this is a really bad pitch, and they're going to tell you, and they're going to tell you in your face.
They have no reason to be polite.
they just going to be like all right, this is this a bit with
and once you figure out this short friends test those one or
2 lines to describe the game on a really high level I usually
make something for the short text. This is just like a
couple of words that really described the games really
tight so people know immediately what it is and that
they usually make one key a key outbreak or a key gift
that you can lose use for the campaign.
I want to cut that nail down you want to move on to a longer
text which is described again.
And this is quite early to do those things.
This is still the preparation phase.
But if you nail that down here, quite good.
All the other things, all the press releases,
all the pitch emails, all the social media updates
you're going to write, they're going
to be extremely easy compared to when you do those things later.
You have to change things all the time
and adjust them all the time.
The second thing is, before we go into PR planning,
is picking your news feeds.
So news feeds are talking points that
should be interesting for press.
I've just listed a couple here just had a good which one I think a good or not
so good
game announcement looks pretty well what works with that I think it would be a
little which is usually the first trailer this is your your big chance to
get to get in front of people to the most common thing the most talked about
thing of the game
you can make a first game play video because it's quite easy to do
Pia stance can be really good if if you can pull them off also on the GDC what
you can find the talk about guerrilla marketing for me if you're interested in
that
Ports are quite a big news, especially like for switch to
Xbox sites, depending where you make a pot.
Different feature videos that just describe features of the
game, a release date is usually quite strong.
It's actually stronger than the release.
I think it also has to do with the SEO of websites, because
gamers are going to Google, when is this game coming out?
So that's the news that their website won.
There's also a bunch of news feeds that are not as good.
They're not absolutely terrible.
Like, don't bin them.
but they are not been a great day usually you have to find them up with
one of the other new speeds or a couple of them to make an interesting for
press just a demo alone today usually doesn't do it unless you can is really
really good
so you should figure out what talking points you have about you get
What you want to do next is you pick the right channels.
If you want to talk to press and influencers, usually email is the best, it's the easiest.
There's a couple of people who prefer social media, but in bulk, just use emails.
And also, if you get in touch with people, if they ever talk to you,
make a nice list of what people are interested in and keep emailing them.
And then you want to figure out how you talk to your players, how you talk to your audience.
It can be, again, it can be a newsletter, it can be Twitter,
Discord is very popular at the moment if your game where there's more discussion involved.
Also Imgur is great, image hosting platform, we just did that for what the goal,
had a post with over 200,000 views, although it did really hard with press,
it was really working well there, so I think it's worth doing some research in.
And again...
you have to pick your channels here and keep in mind which is the one channel that you want all
people to go to, which is like the end of the sales funnel. Should they all sign up to the
newsletter? Should they all end up in the discord? Just agree on one and then try to get all the
people there so you can keep them in the loop.
Next on this we make a PR plan it's quite straightforward it looks like that. Usually we do it per week and then also put a more detailed one. The important thing is you want to have a topic you want to make sure you have all the assets in there. So whoever makes the asset knows what is needed when and then we just usually stack that by different target groups. So there was a PR plan for a switch game and there was a.
a layoff for gaming press that covers all games and the just get really important news
but then the Nintendo side to cut like small and use as well because they were just more
interested in the game and then also the different social channels when we want to talk to them.
Some tips if you want to be a plant because if you just sit in front of an empty
excel sheet it can be a bit scary usually it's easiest to start at the release date
and then work your way back.
I would always leave 2 to 3 weeks between those and
yeah, it's for especially for press because they need some time to recover during that
those P a P it's.
There was an interesting study by Big Games Machine that found out that most press prefer
to get their review kits three weeks ahead of launch.
and also just be sure to double check dates something I think most people forget this
can be easily overseen especially to change things around but always just really look
up bank holidays look up different game releases that you don't launch the same day as destiny
and also look up different events and that's a couple events of the absolute no goes don't
do anything during those events unless you can stay obviously.
which for me would be GDC and E3 and Gamescom.
There's loads of other local events,
but I think they're not as dramatic.
However, if those events take place,
that's an absolute no-go zone to do anything,
unless you're at the show.
And after we have the PR plan, it's just a short thing
to set up your monitoring.
There's a couple of good tools.
Like you could set up alerts with Google Alerts.
TweetDeck is a really good Twitter app
where you can just set up an alert for your game.
And Promoter is a really cool tool.
It just costs a couple of euros per month,
but it basically sends you a little notification
every time a gaming website writes about you.
So it's really easy to stay up to date with that.
I was elected to similar weapons to go to crew, a group from plug-in and just so
it shows you how much website traffic is that website has really really helpful
because imagine you're again the Spain and you're going to write about the game
which one is the bigger one.
There's loads of the things that this website seems really big, but it's not.
So those of that type of top 5 to do is in the set-up face also keep as I said
before I think it's worth spending a lot of time on this faith and getting it
right and then the other things we get way easier.
So next up we have to pre really reveal before we show a first big trailer and this is like how you test and we find a
coffee.
So you want to set up those channels also be sure to sign up to the time on database so you can get linked to the twitch
database to stream it can take it in.
And this is the face with that community building very popular
is using screenshots at the day so every Saturday, you posted
a gift with the test act does a lot of press writing about it
it can get a couple of free tweets and you can just like
see what people like about the game.
Also going to local events is quite nice and that face to
just get some extra feedback.
And this is a good time to experiment with a game here
called overland and they had a buck with.
a dog that became very big and it was one of the most successful tweets.
So they keep making big dogs.
And this is not something you can predict or participate,
but this is something you can find out
when you do regular things in this warm-up phase.
And then we come to the reveal trailer which I think is that before but I think
it's one of the most important things you can do.
So you prepare that a lot and the in the games Bell survey.
Actually there was a set of spit
shocking.
We asked who made your launch trailer and 82% of people said someone in the
team.
This is really not good.
I think your reveal trailer and your launch trailer
should be something you should put a lot of effort,
a lot of attention, and also money in if you can.
Because if you think about it,
this is literally like if you make a coffee
and you try to sell it in a little bag.
This is the first and only thing
a lot of people are gonna see.
So really take your time and get those trailers right.
That's not a specific formula which trailers for great and
which weren't that always like guides like making one minute
to make it very short, but then the things like the goose game
that makes a 3 minute game play video which goes absolutely
viral mental so I think that the key role is just like it
really has to tell you game off really well.
And the last tip is like don't brush his face.
On the really finish it when you reveal trade is ready because
you can only really again wants.
And you want to make sure that that hits.
So then you read again and then we go into the pre launch phase and actually if you if you do your cup campaign this is the launch build up and this is actually quite a long face we do a lot of things having those light it's quite short because it only means that you execute a lot of things that we planned already before.
What we want to do in the pre-launch phase is just keep pushing, keep getting those news feeds out, keep updating your community, keep building all your channels.
Sounds easy here, it's a lot of work to do.
Store optimization is a thing you should at least look into here at the latest here.
For a lot of curated stores it just means trying to contact the platform holders and making a store page.
For Steam it's a bit different.
Steam is completely driven by algorithms.
And there's a really great talk on YouTube
from Matt Trobiano and Lauren Klinik
called More Than Luck, Strategies to Success in Steam.
Definitely recommend watching it.
It really explains to you how the algorithm works
and what games Steam pushes out.
Basically Steam looks into how much money you make then per second.
So it's not so important how much money you make,
it's important how much money Steam makes.
A couple of notes just on that.
What is really good for Steam store optimization is also always keep in mind you don't want
to get as many people into your game to buy it.
You want to get the right people in because they should not leave bad reviews.
They should like your game.
A really good example is Superflight, a small indie game from Berlin.
And what they said in the short description is this is a great game to relax for half
an hour and chase the latest high score.
This is not something usually a PR person would recommend you to say,
because that doesn't sound great, that doesn't suggest anything major,
but it just really tells you what the game is,
and people loved it, they bought it, it got recommended,
more and more people bought it.
So it's quite good being really descriptive and really honest here.
In this phase, it's always a good time to attend shows and do different previews.
There's a really good blog post series on the website of icopartners.com that goes through
different events and explains to you what is what and what to do.
There's a really great TDC talk about how you should build a booth at an event so you
get attention from people.
And the one tip I can definitely give you, if you attend an event, make your press appointments
beforehand a couple of weeks if you can.
You won't catch them on the show floor.
It's really important to set it up before.
Also if you send out the new speech if you contact press try
to think and headlines help them right easy headlines by the
game. I did a to talk about the topic last year's if you want
to look that up that's on the to see what the most of you to
and surprise just a couple of little extra tips on the
pre-launch phase.
Never never never and not to release that before you pass
certification I did it for a couple of games. It doesn't
always work out great and then you have to postpone your
release date and this is really bad.
You can also use your community to get on board with streamers and YouTubers.
It's something you see in the tweet that Mike Rose did.
It was just like saying to his fans, do you have any YouTubers you like?
Just ping them and I can send them a key.
And actually that tends to work quite well.
If they get a lot of pings from people that say you should play that game,
they will pick it up after a while.
And to really good links to find contacts and that that I always if we
website we can look up press e-mails is really helpful and which is really hot
to find out which to stream us could cover your game and the cycle twitch
metrics which is great because it shows you different stream us per country and
you can feel to them by game is really helpful.
We come to launch face and dislike sound like a big thing but if you've done all
that but well actually launched a is not that crazy it's more like a launch party.
You obviously have to have a launch trailer.
You should launch your game, send out a press communication,
reach out to YouTubers and streamers,
and blow all your social horns.
But again, if you've set up everything right
and if you've worked on that game for a long time,
this is not actually the busiest day ever
in terms of PR marketing.
Obviously in terms of development, something different,
but not in terms of PR marketing.
One important thing is I would definitely encourage they want
to use especially on seems really important to get reviews
there's a newsletter from my partners that shows how many
games came out each week on steam and how many didn't get
any reviews and there's loads of them so if you have a
community definitely try to get them to review a game or
get the friends to be with again.
So the last face is supposed to launch face.
This is a busing relevant as a game called a mellow
and it actually had a second biggest days after 2 and a half
years to tell.
But then in the Indie Game PR survey,
we actually saw that most developers, 60%,
stopped promoting the game two months after release.
So why does this happen?
It probably has to do with how successful the game is.
There's a really interesting.
uh... blog post that tries to figure out if you can predict steam sales from your
week one sales and basically the formula found out is
that whatever you're going to sell in week one if you multiply that by five this is what
you're going to sell in the first year and it seems to be
obviously not super accurate but quite accurate
Obviously try to manage to use cost encourage players to review them and
also talk to them if something goes wrong for the present influences
built and keep your fan base for next games and the last point is plenty updates right if
you make an update and you can bundle up with a big little past and like you see here always move
for die get a little Rick and Morty crossover and bundle it for 60% sale.
Then you can actually make update updates after your game is already out still a little press story.
So that's the 5 points in for the post-launch phase.
And now a really quick summary.
It's just, if you're planning a campaign, keep in mind,
pick if you want to do a launch build-up or focus
on the store feature.
Keep the sales funnel in mind for whatever you do.
Keep collecting those people to places
where you can reach them again.
And the summary of the PR timeline is, first phase,
make sure you have a game that's interesting,
that people actually want to buy,
and to learn to talk about it.
Preview real phase, test a bit, really focus
on getting the trailer right.
Reveal the game.
Thank you pushing it in the pre launch phase could getting it
out make the news piece make those updates in the audience
launch a game and in the end of the post launch phase which
probably have a look at how long and if you want to support
the game after thanks a lot for listening.