Can you hear me okay? I tend to talk too loudly, so I'm going to try to gauge this in real
time. Yes, I am going to talk about the Banner Saga but I'm basically going to use it as
a...
sort of stand in to discuss this sort of subtitle, this should probably be reversed,
Own Your Choices. Out of curiosity, who here was at the Game Sound Con?
Okay, good. Most of you were not. That's what I was hoping.
Because I am going to dovetail a little bit with comments that I made there.
Of course, I guess I should say who was at my talk at GameSoundCon.
Because those don't necessarily correlate.
The fundamental takeaway then, as today, was all about owning your choices.
So much of what we do as composers is about making decisions.
I'm a big fan of the notion that basically all technique, musically, whether you're talking
compositionally or production or anything like that, that's all very learnable.
And so the thing that separates me from you and you from each other and everybody,
and not in a better or worse sort of way,
but just what literally makes us not the same person,
are the choices that we make.
And generally speaking,
I don't know if you want to call it the system,
or just kind of the environment, the competition, whatever it is,
makes it sort of daunting and scary.
to actually make those choices. So, that is, I think, my assessment of what it is that we actually do.
I'm a big fan of that picture, by the way. There's usually only semi-relation of the images to what I'm talking about.
In this case, it's fairly on topic, but I figured, you know, someone cosplaying Metal Gear Solid, I have to put that in my talk somewhere.
Weirdly enough, I don't, I think I typed...
like mystery or something into Google image and it took us right into our own backyard.
I was very happy about that.
So in other words, the idea is I want to talk about the philosophy.
What is the composer's actual role?
Because I don't believe it's actually writing music.
We are storytellers.
Much like LeVar Burton.
And storytelling is about interconnectivity.
Storytelling works when you connect with the person you are telling a story to.
And at the end of the day, that's all music composing is about.
It's about meaningfully creating these connections and tapping into some core truth,
which I would spell with a capital T.
Something that feels universal, something that feels very powerful.
Even if it doesn't... genre, all these things don't matter when you're talking about that.
It's just the idea that I have connected with you in a very sort of primal way.
But in a way, that's sort of a whole other talk.
And so today, the whole notion of owning your choices
is really more about how we go about doing that.
How does one...
make those choices, or another way to put it is, how does one sort of create, how does
one create?
How does one synthesize creative ideas?
And I don't think that we do.
I think creativity is an act of discovery.
That's a very lame and on-the-nose image for that, by the way.
But, point is, the greatest ideas musically, and in all creative acts, what makes them
great is that they have that very magical quality that we call inevitability.
And I think another way to put it is that we need to be seeing what we do as not so
much making ideas, but getting out of their way.
And letting them kind of be created as they want to be created on their own.
Which is a bit antithetical to the notion of owning your choices, and I understand that.
You will embrace my mixed metaphors.
But the idea is, you know, if you are getting out of its way, it's because what's happening
is embracing archetypes we all know and understand.
It's about understanding basic psychology and understanding what the listener's takeaway
is going to be.
What aspects of the music are they actually going to latch onto?
And I think that the way that we do that is simple.
And this was kind of my big point at the GameSoundCon talk,
was to say that creative courage is basically the only thing that separates people from...
The presuming technique to be a level playing field,
that if you feel like you have less technique, say,
in orchestration, that's very improvable, that's learnable.
So assuming all people are equal on the front of technique,
what often ends up being the separating point
between those who are the most successful and those aren't
is the act of creative courage.
And that's what owning your ideas is all about,
is actually finding something.
And no matter how.
Weird and novel it might seem, owning it and fully committing to it.
A way that I like to think of it is that every decision we make, especially when it comes
to composing, but every decision we make period, whether I sit here and I keep fiddling with
this deciding at what point I'm actually going to drink some of it, that is no different
than a compositional decision in that every decision we make separates reality in that
moment from all others.
based on other decisions we might have made.
So if I, you know, decide to just randomly walk off the stage and leave
and everyone sits here in silence saying like,
what kind of weird performance art did we just come here to
and do we get our money back?
I would have separated my reality and all of yours
into a slightly different one than if I actually give my talk.
And every compositional decision,
bear in mind I understand that it's on these tiny little microscopic levels where, you know,
Writing that C sharp in this octave versus that octave is not necessarily going to change
the future of history, but it is a different reality than if you had chosen the other one.
And the people that I think run into trouble,
and whose music ends up being creatively somehow never quite there,
are the ones that are so paralyzed with fear by having to commit to that choice,
that they try to straddle multiple realities.
And it ends up being basically bland and generic,
and it has no commitment, has no creative courage.
And I understand that if you take this idea down the rabbit hole,
it becomes very terrifying very quickly.
But that ultimately is...
What separates people. So, I'm going to use that to talk about this game that I just finished
that I had a really wonderful time to work on, a really wonderful time working on rather,
called The Banner Saga. I am in no way trying to proclaim that I made good choices, or that
the music is great, or that you'll like it, or anything like that, but I do feel proud
that I did commit to those choices.
And that's why I like to use it as an example.
So hopefully there might be some things
that interest you about the actual process itself,
but the idea behind presenting this score
in addition to the fact that it's just brand new
is that I do actually feel really good
about the commitment to the choices made.
So I want to give you a bit of a rundown.
I see I have at least one of my photographed gentlemen here.
Are you the only one here right now?
Well this is John Watson, one of the three sort of core members of what we call Stoic.
He's very worthy of your applause. As you can see, they had a very successful Kickstarter.
There's no time left though, I'm sorry to say. So you have to put your wallets back
in your pocket. But 20,042 people beat you to it, so that's okay.
Actually did anyone here back the game? Yeah, alright, awesome.
I didn't even occur to me to ask, but that's really cool.
Out of curiosity, why did you?
I know you.
Why don't you tell me?
I really liked the setting.
The art was really impressive.
And I kind of felt like I had a little bit of a personal stake
in it becoming really cool.
Well, I couldn't agree more.
The visual style of this game is extremely.
engaging and striking and unforgettable the instant you see it.
And that was, which, that little screen grab only gives you the tiniest sense of.
But, um...
Just a quick overview on the game itself.
For me, the most important takeaway is actually the right half of the frame there, which is
Alex Thomas John Watson and Arnie Jorgensen.
And for me, the takeaway there, I know this is slightly on a tangent from the point of
my talk, but when working with people, for me, who I'm working with is always by far
the most important thing.
It doesn't matter what kind of game they're making.
It doesn't matter what genre it is or what genre, inevitably, the music will then be
in.
These are people that I want in my life.
Then I'll go off the edge of a cliff for them.
And I feel like I do my best writing in that situation anyway.
And of course one would if you actually care about the people.
So at some point I just made the career decision of that's actually going to be
That's going to be how I make all my career decisions, is what do you mean to me as a
human?
Because, you know, it's not like you are going to date every person you meet or marry every
person you meet, and we don't see that as a problem.
We're like, no, no, you choose people because of what they mean to you, and they choose
you for the same reason.
And when you're collaborating with someone, especially on a thing like this, a Kickstarter
totally independent game.
Where there is no lifeline from a publisher or somebody to give you money when you're over budget and over schedule and all those things.
You're in it with people. You're not in it with an entity.
And it's really important. So that's a side note.
But that gives you a sense of why I immediately jumped on board.
It was the same response that you had.
I saw what they were making.
They called me out of the blue.
And they said, they were halfway through their Kickstarter
and said, we're interested in working with you.
Take a look and see what you think.
And what got me was learning their story
of quitting their jobs to make their dream game
and completely just diving off into unsafe waters.
It's responded to me because that's commitment to creative ideas, that's owning your choices,
and that's having a huge amount of creative courage, and I really, really respond to that.
So here's a little bit of a look at the game, but the first question I always have to ask
is what is this about in a fundamental sense?
Not what is the story or the narrative or who are the characters, what are their names?
I love all of that.
But the key thing is to say, what is the actual emotional idea that matters?
And in this case, what I really responded to was that it was this wonderful combination of sort of desolate lonesomeness
with kind of proud warrior's regal courage.
And it was a wonderful blend of that kind of wistful look at the world ending.
is normally treated with a frantic hysteria of like,
how do we save the world?
And this game said, no, no, no, you can't.
And you're not even going to try to.
You're just going to try the weather of the storm.
And you're sort of powerful Viking inspired characters,
Viking mythology inspired characters,
and you're basically taking it in stride.
And I thought, that's a hell of a thing.
And it reminded me in a way of Battlestar Galactica's
emotional landscape, which I really loved as well.
And so I wanted to play for you
from my giant speaker there.
Um, I always end up screwing this up.
Oh, great.
Um,
I, I, this was the very,
essentially the first thing I wrote,
which was a theme
trying to capture
everything I'm saying.
Um,
so you can hear it's very,
you know, even though it's a,
it's a turn-based strategy game
that has very much a kind of adventurous
quality to its narrative.
But like I said, the question is always, what is this actually about, though?
And it's about something very kind of quiet and lonely, but proud.
And that's what I was trying to capture with this. ♪
See, it's nothing crazy.
So this was one of the very, very first things that I wrote in the immediate aftermath of
their Kickstarter ending.
The next thing, of course, before figuring out, you know, this is all just me laying
the groundwork before I start making these choices that I'm then going to have to really
firmly commit to.
The next thing, of course, to think about, in a big way, is a game.
What are the game's mechanics? How do you actually play the game?
And not in a sense of what does the genre imply.
For example, this is a turn-based strategy game, and they're very deliberately kind of
paying homage or drawing inspiration to games like Final Fantasy Tactics.
But to me, looking at things like that is not really about musical inspiration.
It's about knowing what the interaction is like with the game itself.
Which is something that for those of us, those of you,
I like of us better,
who work in film as well, that's a question that never comes up.
Because you have basically one way to interact with a film,
which is to sit and watch it happen.
And, you know, sometimes you're in a theater and you're really engaged with it,
and sometimes you're like doing dishes and kind of occasionally looking over your shoulder,
and then like the toilet paper commercial comes on,
and you, you know, that's when you like go get your drink or whatever.
And it's like, but bottom line is the fundamental relationship is the same.
With games, the way in which you interact with it varies tremendously from one game to the next,
and that's obviously what mechanics are all about.
Knowing that, because it informs...
The emotional experience that you're going to have is really important to me.
So this game has a few different kind of modes within it,
but the big kind of cornerstone of it is this turn-based strategy,
which you can see is very much kind of almost like a chessboard,
you know, superimposed onto these gorgeous paintings, basically.
And all using traditional 2D animation and, you know, the art.
It's a shame Arnie's not here, because it would be awesome to...
I'm not going to make him listen to me gushing about what he did with this game because it's really amazing.
The turn-based mechanics have a very specific kind of emotional feel all their own, just as mechanics.
For example, it's not a very fast-paced game by design.
They were looking for something that felt very kind of mature and methodical, like playing chess.
And so to me that said a lot.
And if I had just looked at the mechanics in a sense of what the genre means,
you know, XCOM is also a turn-based strategy game.
But that's the exact opposite way I would describe XCOM.
XCOM is all about trying to make you feel like...
My personal opinion on the newest XCOM was that it was almost trying to be turn-based while pretending it wasn't,
because it was so energetic, and this was owning its chess-like quality in a way that I really responded to.
Where sitting there and contemplating your move for 10 minutes might be what you do.
And as it turns out, it's a son of a bitch to figure out how to score this.
Especially when games like XCOM are the big comparisons happening at the moment.
Which is like, if you do this, you'll just vaporize because there's so much sound and
energy coming out of you, out of the speakers and whatever.
So understanding, you know, first, what's the core underlying idea emotionally in terms
of what's this game actually trying to achieve in a narrative sense or an emotional sense?
And then how is it going about pursuing those?
So I have a video.
Hopefully that's muted.
Yeah, there's music in the video and I didn't want you to hear that.
You're not ready!
But I wanted you to just see what I mean.
This is just a random capture off of YouTube from someone's playthrough, I believe.
Or it might have been one of the tutorials, I can't remember.
But it's, you know, you can get a sense of how it moves.
And there's a lot of implications that come from that.
And there's ways to approach this that might make it feel slower, that might make it feel
faster, and neither of which are necessarily better or worse than the other.
It's just sort of a decision you have to make.
But I can tell you that I was afraid of the score making it boring,
because I think on its own it's not, but it is definitely very introspective and methodical,
and if the score kind of gets too excited by that fact, we might make something that's just...
That's, you know, has an audience of a quarter of the size of this room.
And I, you know, so that's where, again, me as an investment in the developers of the game,
I care about them as people, which means that I don't just want to write music that I think works,
but I want to make sure that I do my part to contribute to their game doing well.
I don't want to screw them as like family men and parents and humans.
And so doing justice to the game stems from just a belief in investing in them personally.
And...
And that ends up weighing in.
The other challenge, by the way, that you can probably guess just from looking at this,
and this is a very simple battle to excerpt from,
is that they could be like five minutes long or they could be an hour long.
And that can be tricky.
So here's kind of a crash course in the evolution that the music went through.
This was the first thing I wrote, which is the worst thing ever.
I didn't realize it was the worst thing ever at the time, of course.
This might be a touch loud.
That's my warning to my friends in the back on the console.
This first part is okay, because it's, you know, it's sort of tense,
but it's not...
These are mock-ups, by the way, so apologies.
They're not necessarily great.
But it kicks into a lot of it, because actually,
to me what's really obvious about this first version
is that I had not yet played the game.
Cause I was like, let's just see what happens if I go all out with some like crazy sort of like, you know...
I don't even know what inspired this.
Yeah, the theme's in there.
But it's not totally horrible, I can see.
Funny enough, slow-paced turn-based strategy, this really doesn't work because it reminds
you how slow everything's moving.
But strangely enough, when you put this on the loading screen when nothing's happening,
it works great because everyone's super excited to like, launch into their slow-paced battle.
But I'm- but truly, that was a nice- that looked like it was there and that actually
seemed to work.
Um...
Okay.
No more.
Um...
So I thought, OK, what if I went the hard opposite?
And so actually, we tried that initial test of the theme.
But what if we put that in?
And so I basically did some elaboration on that
and went as far the opposite way to go as possible.
I'm going to skip ahead here.
You can see it's just sort of generally orchestral,
which is another.
I'll get to it in a little bit, but sort of deciding what your instrumentation and that should be.
But I just started presuming something kind of vaguely orchestral.
But I think it's a false assumption that we should just default to that, which we often do.
But in this case, I definitely did.
And so I was trying something that's very kind of, you know, gentle.
And I quickly decided I hate that too.
And part of it was that even though I like that it's not really about battle,
these characters, as I really dug into the heart of the game,
the idea that came up through conversation with the developers at Stoic Studio was
these are warriors who fight because they have to, not because they want to.
They are extremely badass at it.
They are big vikings and giants and mythical creatures,
but they don't actually have a bloodlust.
And that was very intriguing to me to try to really capture in the music,
how they fight.
with a sense of reluctance.
And that first piece kind of embraced that a little too much, or it didn't interpret
it the right way, I should say.
So here's something a little further down my...
But man, I wrote this score for two years, by the way, so that's why there's like lots
and lots of trial and error happening.
Which I'm a big fan of, by the way.
You get on as early as you possibly can so that you can actually explore ideas and make
something that's not just top shelf, you know.
So here was something where I thought, okay, it's a lot sparser, and there's a definite
tension to it that was absent in the previous version, but it's still nowhere near the energy
level.
And this was fine.
Honestly, this just felt very unspecialty.
It's just percussion.
It's noise.
But I did kind of like the sense of angst that it was landing on.
So to the next.
I was exploring the game, the actual sort of moment-by-moment mechanics within a battle,
and there's a moment at the end when either you or your opponent has one guy left,
and it launches what they call pillage mode,
and it's kind of like bells and whistles go off in a Vegas casino that's like,
it's almost over!
And so I, as an experiment, tried some music that would kick in for that moment only,
which was this.
And it had kind of a lumbering quality to it, and that instantly seemed to feel pretty close.
And there was a big takeaway that I got from this also, where I thought, you know, this
gameplay actually can support more energy, more activity.
But I realized, and I don't like to be overly sort of musically technical in situations
like this, but there's a very low harmonic density.
I said, if I kind of hold in one place harmonically, I can actually build up a lot of activity,
and it doesn't feel distracting and annoying and horrible the way that first piece did,
which was zooming all over the place.
You know, when we're sitting here like low-tinnies, we're almost like a pedal.
Um, seemed to suddenly let me widen my sense of energy.
So then I tried to apply that back to...
Because remember, this was written specifically for the end of maybe an hour-long match.
And so I thought, what if I take that same mentality and apply it to earlier moments?
And so this was what I came up with after that, which is...
There's movement, but you can hear it's very kind of musically stable.
And that seemed to be the sweet spot, which I would never have tried this first.
And this is super quiet for some reason.
It's so tiny on my screen, I can't aim accurately enough.
But you get the idea.
Very slow progressions.
So, that of course is only half the struggle.
How it's actually going to be implemented is a really big part of it.
And that, in this case, it was much trickier.
Because I didn't just want to like make a five minute piece that loops or something
like that because that's, that's, it's too easy and it also misses the point of, it misses
the opportunity to tell a story within...
the game within an individual match, where especially if you're playing online against
somebody else, there's a really direct attempt being made to outwit and defeat the other
person. And to just have some piece that sort of loops through that is missing the opportunity
to sculpt the emotional experience that you, the player, are going through, which is true
of all games.
And so...
But the question was how do we implement this?
Well, we had one huge thing going for us, which was really awesome.
And I have that screenshot up there to show,
because the person has clicked something on the UI
that shows you the stats of all the units.
And one thing that I really loved about this,
from a turn-based strategy standpoint,
is there's no random roles, really.
This is 100% stat-driven.
And it's very simple.
You know, the blue number is what we called, like, armor, basically.
And the red number is strength.
And so, you know, like the guy in the top there that has eight armor could be dealt four damage by the guy down to the right that has twelve strength.
So it's very just simple and arithmetic.
Which means there's a lot of data under the hood to potentially create hooks to attach...
score variables to, to drive the implementation of the music.
So there was a real opportunity to get very, very granular with the music and chase, in
a very specific moment-to-moment, incredibly accurate way, what's happening in the game.
So we created a...
a sort of formula for a thing we call vitality, which is basically just
weighting the individual stats. There's also a third number you can see in the little star
above there, two main ones that we call willpower.
And we basically came up with a way to weight the individual value of those three,
and then stack the two teams up against each other, and whichever team is losing
that vitality number fastest,
the system basically says is losing, and we can track that all in real time because
It's very easy, it's very simple.
And so the initial idea was,
oh this is great, I can really make something
really intensely branching and with a lot of layers.
And almost instantly
discovered that is a god awful idea.
Because, if I sit there
and I'm playing like this,
and the music is, you know, like these bassoons going
da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da
And after 10 minutes of careful consideration,
I make one mouse click, and then the music is like, no!
Because the stats changed.
Suddenly, I'm like, Jesus, what did I do?
And so on mechanics of this nature,
something that synchronous was actually hugely distracting.
Which is interesting, because I'm always
exploring ways to how to make the music more adaptive,
more adaptive.
And here, that actually was a big problem.
So this is essentially.
what we ended up with, where it's, this is just, you know,
sort of a DP screen grab, but this is conceptually the way it works, is that
we have sort of sections based that
the system is essentially listening for a percent drop
in that vitality amount, and as soon as you hit it,
it allows, whenever the loop reaches its end, to then proceed to the next one.
So I basically write like a 10 minute or 12 minute piece,
more or less.
and then accordion it into individual sections,
and the way it's implemented means that
if I, you know, attack my opponent,
and therefore have done the damage necessary
to kind of take it to the next segment in this scheme,
It will only actually advance once the music reaches that on its own organically anyway,
which will be at some point after that has happened.
It's as soon as one second if they happen to have done it at the end of the loop,
or it could be the full duration if they happen to have done it at the beginning.
But either way, they won't actually really notice,
because it proceeds into the next phrase and idea of music,
which is already a natural consequent.
of what you were hearing as it was.
And so that the emotional arc of all of these in total
is actually very gradual.
So you don't really feel these stark changes,
but it's able to track.
And then you can see it splits,
so that you have kind of the winning,
if your team is losing that vitality amount.
less quickly than the other, then you are winning.
And so it takes you on, like, the upper path,
and it takes you onto the lower path if you're losing.
And then occasionally, if it's really a long game,
you know, we put caps on the number of loops
so that the music just has, like you can see,
there's a little insert ending
that I have a couple examples of in there,
where it might just end and then wait to come back.
So that there's just kind of a nice rhythm
and it just feels very organic to the gameplay.
So all of this doesn't address what's the palette?
What should it actually sound like?
What choices do I make in terms of instrumentation
and orchestration?
And like I said at the beginning,
I kind of hinted at this qualm because I
think assuming it should be orchestral is actually bad.
If we do that, everything will sound the same.
So I had kind of started that way.
I was playing around with some electronics.
I was really excited about this particular kind of distortion,
and every time I put it in, all the guys on the other end would say,
I think our speaker is broken.
And then they realized, no, that's just a sound he's using.
And I got a very polite, yeah, don't ever use that again.
But otherwise, it was fairly orchestral.
I did notice that I was not really using the strings much, though.
And that was interesting to me.
Especially, I think that might have been just reactionary
to having just come off Journey, which is like string bonanza.
And so I thought, you know, I just
happened to notice that it was very centered around the brass.
So then the thought occurred to me,
what if I just committed to that?
I've never done that before.
And I remembered an experience that I had.
At Carnegie Hall about 10 years ago, on the left is Jerry Junkin, who's basically the
most famous wind ensemble conductor in the world, and he's the best.
And he commissioned a piece that when I heard the premiere of it at Carnegie Hall, it completely
changed my life, which is John Corleano's third symphony called Circus Maximus, which
sounds like this.
And this is a loud motherfucker for you on the console.
And the final note of this piece, as demonstrated by this photo of a performance of it, is
a percussionist firing a shotgun.
It's a fully surround, like what you're hearing right now is 16 trumpets in a circle around the audience.
And then percussion back behind you.
And it's, it's, it was the largest wind ensemble commission in history at the time.
It may still be.
And they're like up on these balconies just doing this Haley Torch sort of fanfare.
None of the band on stage is playing yet.
Whoever I was walking into Carnegie Hall before hearing this piece was not who left that day.
I've never been hit. It was like a sledgehammer to the face, this piece.
It's 40 minutes long. Here's the full band.
Yeah, I decided not to spend the rest of my talk just letting it play out.
But it's worth seeking out.
And so I thought, what if I did...
A wind ensemble score.
And then my brain went to the next sort of ludicrous conclusion of
what if I called this guy and got his wind ensemble to play it?
And amazingly, when I just cold called him out of the blue,
he said, that sounds super cool, let's totally do this.
It helped, by the way, that this game was being developed in Austin, Texas,
and he happened to live there.
And so there was a sort of hometown pride thing, I think, that played into that as well.
So even after arriving and saying, OK, I'm just going to commit to wind ensemble,
I've never done that before, especially coming off
of such a strong string music-based background.
That was a little bit daunting.
But there was also something missing inherently from that.
Because as you can see here, at the core of this game,
as well as everything else I've said.
It's a father-daughter story. And I needed something very intimate,
something with a lot of heart, a lot of soul, to capture this notion of a father-daughter story.
I mean, you can really see it beautifully in just this one image,
that there's a big story happening, but there's kind of an intimate gateway to it.
And that was important to figure out, how do I tap into that?
I have no idea why this shows up that way, but isn't that super awesome?
That's super strange.
Around the time that I was grappling with this, this showed up on YouTube.
Hey!
This showed up on YouTube.
I'm going to play my music.
This was like the most humbling and awe-inspiring thing I'd ever seen in my life.
She could exhale herself.
She was totally speechless.
If you're not familiar, this is Taylor Davis.
She's incredible.
I think I spent the rest of my talk talking about her.
But I saw this and I thought, I just want to work with someone that does cool shit.
And this was mind-blowing to me.
I couldn't believe it.
So I thought, okay, I'll have one string instrument.
And I'm going to play this.
So I thought okay.
I'm going to play this.
That will be my, that's the soul, that's the thing that I pit this like 60-piece wind ensemble
of 10 French horns and 5 trombones and just 7 percussion, big group, I'll pit that against
the one violin.
Of course, we do not record them simultaneously, so we do not have the acoustical issue faced
with that.
She actually lives in Detroit and recorded all of it from there.
But it gave me something to help really separate all of this apart.
And so you can hear a couple of different ways that that manifests in the score.
So you hear it's a window ensemble.
I also wanted her to play with how the violins sound.
I said, I said you probably have a nice one that you've invested all this money in,
but you probably also had one you played as a kid that's like a crappy practice one.
I want that one. I want one that sounds rustic and worn in.
And I also want you to give the tuning pegs just a little bit of a tweak before you play it.
And so I ended up with something very kind of rustic and naturalistic sounding.
It almost sounds like an accordion as a result.
But I also thought, you know, this is going to be very important for keeping, especially in the narrative,
the combat can be grounded in that father-daughter story as well.
So here's an example of how that plays out.
So it has a peculiar effect of making a big group sort of intimate.
And to me, it seemed like, it felt like sort of, uh, combat with purpose in a way.
In a strange way. I hope it is. That's how it felt to me.
And obviously I'm really committing to this notion of her as an overdub, because you're hearing her very up front in the mix, in a very present and strapped, obviously strapped sort of way, which is by design.
She does not sound like she's on the stage with the rest of the group, whereas there's a very live sound intentionally, and that's by design, so that you really feel this like one against the rest.
That gives you a taste of that.
So on this last slide, you'll notice
there's a whole shitload of crazy looking dudes.
That's one of these guys, which was
the last sort of major consideration
to take into account here.
Like, what can I do to kind of force myself down
some kind of interesting path?
Again, everything here is all these choices
that I'm feeling compelled to commit to hard and fast
are organically stemming from the game.
I'm not just arbitrarily making them.
And so, the sort of the enemy, the sort of lurking specter that's hounding you in this game within the narrative is these big, sort of biomechanical guys they call the Dredge.
And I thought, you know, they bring a very otherworldly, an alien, not in the Geiger sense, although kind of, vibe to the game.
And I wanted to have that represented some way in the score.
Now, I say that hesitantly because I don't actually really like or advocate for...
These very sort of direct, on-the-nose corollaries, musically, where it's, you know, like an obvious
one would be, I'm scoring a film that takes place in China, the music should sound Chinese.
I'm like, but why?
We already figured out the whole China part on account of the movie taking place there.
So what does that actually do?
Like, if there's something inherently, emotionally about Chinese music that is going to bring
that thing that you need, that's great.
But then that also means you could be doing a romantic comedy, and that's the perfect
thing for there.
And that's the way I tend to think, is to say,
okay, there is another worldly vibe.
Can I help bring it in the music in a way that actually
feels complementary and isn't just layering redundancy?
And so I started to think about that.
And that led me to a couple of friends of mine.
Randon Graves, a composer, and Viking Jesus.
And Randon, in addition to being a great composer, he's a really talented and acclaimed didgeridooist.
Didgeridist.
And Viking Jesus is, he does like video game, metal video game covers.
And I met him on a video game's live performance.
And so I thought...
Uh, didgeridoo seems somehow perfect.
And this is where my intellectual justifications for things just completely vanishes,
and I'm like, I don't know, it just, I just think it needs it.
And also, not so much metal guitar, but prepared electric guitar.
And I thought he would particularly enjoy that, because one of the ideas I had was,
I said, do you own a guitar that you never use?
And he said, well, no, not really.
I said, do you have a friend who would?
And he said, uh, I can get a hold of one, but why?
And he said, I'd really love to sample the sound of it being sawed in half.
Um, like an electric guitar that's mic'd and ready to go, and you're recording the amps
take away from that experience.
Um, it's like putting your ear to the window as you listen to someone be murdered.
It's like, I don't want the sound of what's going on in the room, I want to hear what
it sounds like on the outside of the room.
And he was like, sure!
And so that's, here's what kind of all that added together sort of sounds like.
Also what was cool was the Dallas Wind Symphony, which is Jerry's ensemble,
and we recorded in their concert hall in Dallas, which was awesome and terrifying.
It's not wired for headphones or anything.
We had to do all of it without click tracks. It was insane.
So we're going to be able to quit on some of them.
And now you can hear the actual produced live version
of my chattering bassoons.
So in the interest of time, there's
still something else missing.
And a big component of the Kickstarter campaign had been these things they call the Godstones.
And which is a brilliant move on Stoic's part, where basically as a way to offer a very cool
tier to really high paying backers, they said throughout the game your caravan is going
to go wandering by these giant sort of...
almost like gravestones to the now dead gods.
That's part of the kind of mythology of the game, is that this sort of polytheistic world,
sort of like ancient Greece or obviously like sort of the Viking lore, the gods had all
killed themselves in this giant sort of war and everyone left on earth survived and basically
were left
And so they're alone and realize, oh, life I guess just goes on.
So that kind of forms the emotional framework of like, we're all that there is.
There's no one coming for us, there is no one going to help us,
because they're facing this new sort of doomsday scenario,
and there is no sort of higher power to whom to turn,
which is very important for the emotion of the game.
And so they said, we want to have reminders, though, that that is the case,
by putting these tributes.
And so they said, if you give us whatever it was, like a thousand bucks,
we'll make you a hero, and we'll make you...
A Godstone.
And you can name it, and you can come up with its backstory, and we'll fit it.
We'll make it work.
And it was brilliant, and who would have guessed that there were all these, like, bearded people
who have a lot of money?
And because they all, like, all these Vikings came out of nowhere, basically.
And so the game has almost no spoken dialogue in it.
It has very interstitial VO.
And I always felt like there needs
to be something special and unique that
happens that's proximate to these.
And so I pitched this idea.
I said, what if your caravan kind of bursts into song,
and there's almost musical tributes,
almost like source music threaded into the game's score?
What if we tried something like that?
So that led me to start thinking about, well, I need singers.
Shortly before the game's kickstarter, this video...
Please tell me all of you have seen this.
Everyone has seen this?
Raise your hand regardless of anything.
What the hell's wrong with you? No one does anything.
All of you... Well, you're watching it now, so you've all seen this.
This is Maluka. Are you here somewhere?
Yes! Okay, she is among us.
So this is obviously Skyrim done in a way that's just staggeringly beautiful.
And this showed up on YouTube a few months before the Kickstarter,
and people were talking about it in all the comments, and I went and watched it,
and I was like, oh my god, I have no idea how I'm going to incorporate vocals,
but I clearly have to.
And part of the motivation behind reaching out to someone who had put something on YouTube
was that...
The whole game was born through the online world.
And I like the idea of committing to that as well.
The idea that people who have earned their livelihood and built their reputations as
musicians on the internet would participate in a game that was also launched from the
internet.
And that to me just felt like a sort of spiritual alignment that I really liked.
And so as soon as this notion of what if I wrote sort of folk songs for these...
for these Godstones.
And I got these amazing singers
who I had not... I didn't know them,
I just knew their YouTube videos.
So Maluka was the first,
and then shortly thereafter I met this fine fellow.
This is from The Hobbit, The Misty Mountains, and this is Peter Hollins is his name.
And he likewise, he puts, like Taylor and these others, he puts content on YouTube as
his livelihood.
And he's a phenomenal singer, incredible vocal producer.
And so I basically reached out to him and said, I need, I need like manly vocals.
And also, there was another singer who I don't have video of, unfortunately,
named Johann Sigmundsson, who did the VO for the game.
And he just sounds like a Viking.
And so I called him and I said,
please tell me he's not actually a singer.
Because I want, like, a Viking singer.
I don't want this guy that's gonna try to sing-sing.
I got that covered in a way that's very authentic.
As you can see, there's five of Peter.
Uh, some spoil- uh, spoil of riches.
Um...
So I had basically a trio of singers and we add it all up.
Here's kind of the aesthetic.
This is Johann.
And then how Peter and Johan together...
Singing in Icelandic, by the way. My apologies once again to Miljko.
Johan speaks Icelandic, Peter and Miljko not so much.
And it is a bizarre... Does anyone here speak Icelandic?
That's what I thought.
It is mind-blowingly complicated from a syllabic perspective.
You didn't realize that your tone could make these moves.
So then here's all three of them plus Violet as well.
So it's sort of like folk music.
It's an invented folk music, but it's very much informed by that general aesthetic.
And of course, this particular musical excerpt is sort of, I'm not going to say what it is,
avoid spoilers, but it's of central importance in the game, so of course I also add in the
full wind ensemble as well.
So by the time I got to the end of this, and I started playing it for people, they were
like, wow, this music is really weird.
And this doesn't really sound like what we were expecting.
And I didn't even really notice.
It had been almost two years of work of just sort of finding things and seeing what felt
right.
And by the time I end, I just realized I had been sort of committing to all these choices
along the way.
And in the aggregate, a million of these kind of odd choices, but what firmly believed in,
culminated in something...
That seems to be a bit different.
And again, I make no claims of if it's good music
or anything like that.
That's not up to me to decide.
That's up to you guys and to whomever else.
But I did feel confident that I did not waffle
on these decisions as we went.
Which is just, again, the reminder of how we actually go about doing this.
This is, in my GameSoundCon talk, I mentioned a guy who the economists referred to as
the Feasting Vicar in a wonderful obituary I read.
His name is Robert Capon, and he was a sort of minister slash food critic?
And he wrote very eloquently about...
food as sort of like a way of life.
And it was very tied into his Christian beliefs.
And he was an incredible...
I never heard of this guy, and then I just read his obituary
and I found him to be a wealth of inspiration
for how to be a composer with integrity
because he basically said,
perfection should never be your goal
because it's not even possible.
There's no point in trying.
So the whole idea is to basically just commit to the choices that you make.
Believe in them fully and know that some are going to fail.
Some are going to fail spectacularly.
But if you're going to fail, fail like the Hindenburg.
Don't fail in some way that doesn't even matter.
And this was what he fully believed.
So much so that he would intentionally eat and make things that he knew were terrible.
Because he wanted to experience something that tastes truly shitty.
And then when he makes something that's really special,
suddenly he really appreciates that all the more.
And I thought that was really actually quite beautiful.
And so it can be summarized, there's a Samuel Beckett quote from Worst Word Ho, where he says,
ever tried, ever failed, no matter, fail again and fail better.
Because you have to remember, we are our choices.
That is what makes us one composer versus another composer.
If you see this as sort of your first instinct, is that very first...
box or whatever, I guess it's a diamond with the way I've oriented this, on the left.
Every single person in this room and every other composer ever in history can think of
that.
Which means that if we all start there and we stop there, the art dies immediately.
And it's all of our collective faults.
Not to mention the fact that it's extremely hard to have a career where everyone is the
same.
You know, at that point, one entrepreneurial person says, oh, well, what if I just...
I'm going to make a music library and then everyone can just buy that because it doesn't matter who you hire anymore.
And that person, who we'll refer to as HZ, can profit enormously.
And I say it with love.
Now actually, but there is truth to that.
If you create something that becomes so de facto norm, and then everyone does the same,
then whoever basically figures out the best way to package it is going to do the best.
It's not about the music anymore.
Which means the only way to penetrate to the right side is to just make a series of choices
from which there's no coming back.
And some of them are going to work better than others.
But you end up somewhere that's a spot that only you occupy.
There's a Steve Martin quote where he says,
be so good that no one can ignore you.
And I actually don't think that that really applies in our world,
where technique is so learnable and where...
sample libraries and the ability to hire orchestrators and all that means that
that from a skill level everybody's capable of being the same. We've kind of
Harrison Bergeron'd
music. I actually think that's wonderful in this particular instance so that what
separates us
is you. So I would say be so you that there's just no one else.
That you're the person that does that thing. You're the only person that would
make those choices. And it's not about them being better
or being worse. It's about the fact that you're the only one that would do them. And
there's gonna be people that respond to that. Never mind
liking working with you and all of the wonderful lovey-dovey details.
So in other words, our choices is what we sell.
That's what we charge for.
It's not actually music in some other sense.
Thus, it's always very important to just own those, know that those are all that matter.
And in what few minutes I have left, I would be happy to take questions.
And I will, I think you should probably run up to the mic for the sake of the recording,
but I will also restate them.
And I've failed if no one has a question.
All right.
Beautiful.
Awesome.
You got a lot of brave decisions as far as, um, you know, having the violinist
bring in her oldest violin against the whole stage, um, the didgeridoo, a lot
of cool ideas, and I love how they came together.
Are you doing the mixing?
Are you making those decisions or do you have someone that you work with on a
very intimate relationship to make sure that those ideas come through the way
you intended?
Everyone hear that? I assume. Yeah?
So, I, on this particular score, because we recorded the wind ensemble in kind of an unusual way,
I essentially mixed it myself. Normally, I don't like to. I don't consider myself a mixer.
You know, I'm kind of an idealist who thinks of my job as putting dots on paper.
But, you know, in this world, in this economy, sometimes you have to...
To be able to hire so-and-so, you can't hire X.
But in this case, we actually had the budget, and I did hire my mixer,
but what he did was actually more like mastering.
And the biggest reason why was actually not so much
the weird combinations of solo, tracked, shitty violin, played beautifully,
and didgeridoo, and things like that,
but because we hired this mad scientist of a recording engineer named Keith Johnson,
who's a Grammy-winning engineer who's worked like a hundred times with that wind ensemble,
and he's like...
This maniac, who, he, he, we, when we record into Pro Tools, we're not getting, uh, stems
of, of, you know, of, we're not getting basically the feed off of every mic. We're getting these
submixes that he makes that we can't open up. He has this weird custom box that looks
like something from the Apollo program that he made.
Um, and he's sitting there, we were recording, you know, he sets all the levels, he won't
let anyone touch his gear, so setup takes like two days because he's like 85 years old
and putting up all the mic trees himself and won't let anyone touch his stuff, and so he,
he sets it all up, he, and he has this, literally, like there's no faders, there's no, it's,
it's literally like knobs, and it's, it's the size, you could fit it on this podium,
and I'm looking at it and I'm like, you've got like 50 mics going into this thing.
And he's got pre's and he records everything at like 192k.
He does these really high resolution digital recordings.
And like I said, he's a Grammy winner for surround sound mixes.
And so, but it's funny because they said, you know, normally rule of thumb is
you set your levels, you fool around with things, and then you set it.
And you only change things as problems arise,
or as you try to achieve a certain kind of effect.
And I'm watching him, and every single take,
he's doing this, moving all of his things around.
And they're like, they warned me ahead of time.
They said, you're going to have a heart attack when you see him
working, because you're thinking,
because we don't have stems.
We don't have the individual mics in Pro Tools.
So they said, you're going to freak out.
But what it is, he has a photographic memory
and has memorized the conductor's score,
and he's changing balances, like one bar
before they're about to happen.
And I was like, that's bullshit.
And then we record it and sure enough, like I'm sitting, you know, like Jerry's conducting
and I'm sitting there in the booth and I look and I see there's like a giant thing about
to come and I watch him like reach over and make an adjustment and then bam in the orchestra
and I was like, my God.
So for that reason, because there was still six months of work on my end after the recordings
of the big orchestra, and I was still writing a lot of those folk songs and things like
that, there was still a lot of implementation that had to be done, so I needed to be able
to work on those mixes immediately.
And so I basically, we ended up, we had four stereo mixes that were basically like four
subjective perspectives of the orchestra.
that he created as submixes.
So it's not really a traditional mix.
I basically had to do it myself, which was fun.
But, you know, you're...
Talk about owning your choices.
There's no backing out of that.
Yeah?
Great presentation, by the way.
Thank you.
I hope it's helpful.
I hope so, too. I think so.
I'm glad you hope so.
That is in no way comforting to me, but thank you.
A lot of notes.
So when scoring games as opposed to films,
do you still try to approach creating an overarching structure,
or do you think it's different?
Pat it out.
No, absolutely. In fact, I think it's even more important in games
because the natural structure of games tends to splinter apart the music so much
that it's very easy for each cue to kind of be its almost individual little musical universe.
And I feel that that's not... I mean, you know, if you're familiar with Journey,
Journey is like kind of manic, depressive, obsessive about this idea of a single structure.
But truthfully, everything I do is, you know, I tend to have, you know, one theme...
that is written to carefully be able to map the trajectory of the whole game.
Which means that I can't really start writing until I know what all the main story beats are going to be,
what all the main... bear in mind I'm talking about narrative games,
although non-narrative games this would potentially apply to as well,
if there's any kind of sense of, like, difficulty.
Like, even like Tetris, for example.
But, anyway, yes.
Overall sense of structure, hugely important.
And hopefully, you know, if you play the game, you can feel that.
You can sense that.
Just an intuitive sense that the tension is rising,
that the overall sense of stakes and scope
are increasing in tandem with the game itself.
And the way you do that is by controlling your parameters,
is by saying, what am I choosing not to use now
that I'll then use later as a way to add more oomph?
And so definitely.
Thank you.
When you talk about owning your choices, I'm curious as to know, like, how do your meetings go when you get revision requests, or do you not even entertain revisions?
Of course! No, no, no, no, yeah, absolutely. You will like it! Please don't let the checks stop coming.
Oh, of course, no, for me, those are not antithetical concepts.
In fact, they are very mutually supportive concepts because someone will throw out an
idea – bearing in mind that owning your choices is all about going down some path
that you've really never been down before, and it's about creating something that you
feel like, I didn't know I knew how to do this.
When someone offers you a suggestion, you know, like if I'm writing a piece for Wind Ensemble
and the note I get is, make it more orange,
I have no idea what the hell that means, but it does make me think
and rewrite and revise in a way that I wouldn't have on my own.
And so then I end up going down an even more of an interesting path.
So yeah, to me, I actually think writing is in the rewriting.
I love...
Throwing things out because then I feel like, because I just always assume that my first instinct is terrible.
What I like to tell people is, what most people don't realize is I am a god awful composer.
I really am terrible, but you just haven't heard 99% of what I wrote because I'm fairly good at curating.
So, and the notes are a helpful way to actually be able to do that.
All right, let's lightning round through the last two of you guys.
All right, fight to the death between the two of you.
It's on you.
Thank you for your presentation.
And my question is, usually, at which point
do you bring live instrument and live musician?
Because I have heard that you have somebody record it
right after you came up with the main theme melody of Journey.
Yeah, no, it's true. Journey I recorded on day one. Tina Guo, the cellist, and Amy Tatum, the bass flute player, were recorded on day one before there was even concept art or a remotely playable prototype for Journey as well.
If you're tracking a soloist, I mean these are friends of mine, if I just call them and I say,
will you come over and read this, they will.
Or I'll give them 50 bucks to just sit in front of a microphone, even if I end up throwing it out.
But I would much rather the developer hear something that sounds the way it's supposed to sound
and feels the way it's supposed to be.
Especially when you're talking about, like in the case of Journey,
there's cellists and then there's Tina Guo.
She does not, I don't know what she does, but it's sorcery, which means that if, if,
if I cannot be sending them mock-ups, and you'll have a stroke if you're like, oh, I
get used to the mock-up, and then you hear her, no brain should have to make that leap.
You gotta start with her.
It's the safest thing.
And so, obviously you can't do that with a full orchestra, so mock-ups are pretty key
there.
So in that case, I tend to try to wait until the last possible second so I can keep changing
the music over and over and over again.
But for soloists, early and often.
Don't break the bank, but they'll work with you because it's just a one-on-one thing.
Thank you.
All right, thank you.
Nice work, man.
Nice work.
It's all yours.
Cheers.
Good man.