Ladies and gentlemen, please welcome event director of the Game Developers Conference, Megan Scavio.
Good morning and welcome to the Game Developers Conference.
The gentleman about to take the stage to present this morning's keynote doesn't really need much of an introduction.
As the creator of some of the greatest games ever made, from
Railroad Tycoon through Pirates to the Civilization Series, he
has already taken on, taken his place on the list of legendary
game design icons. And he's not done yet. So please join me in
welcoming the Director of Creative Development at
Firaxis and the father of computer gaming, Mr. Sid Meier.
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you very much. It's great to be
here. The title of this talk is the psychology of game design.
Everything you know is wrong.
I was going to call it, you know, people are funny, gamers
are goofy, it's all in your head, or everything you know is
questionable. But I thought everything you know is wrong,
kind of get the juices flowing, maybe get a little more
interaction. The premise of this talk is that ‑‑ is there
any way to get the slides up in the back of the hall?
is that game play, game design, is a psychological experience.
Game play is a psychological experience.
When I design a game, a lot of my games are based on
historical topics, the history of civilization,
railroads, pirates, and the way I would generally
approach those topics is make it realistic,
make it true, make it about, the more historical
I can make the game, the better it would be,
the more.
railroad-y the game is, the better.
The more pirate-y it is, the better.
And what I found in taking that approach
was that a lot of what I thought I knew was wrong.
And the reason was because I really hadn't...
taking into account what really happens in the player's head.
And once that became an important part
of kind of my design process,
things started to become a lot clearer.
So, the premise here is that
by acknowledging that the gameplay
is really a psychological experience, we can...
Save ourselves a lot of time in certain areas.
It makes certain parts of the process easier.
It certainly makes other parts of the process
more difficult.
But at the end of the day,
I think we end up with a better game.
In the process, as we kind of explore this idea,
we're gonna kind of run into a few psychological concepts.
Egomania is one of them we'll have to explore.
Basically, if you play Civilization...
you are an egomaniac.
I mean, it says right on the box, you know,
build a civilization to stand the test of time.
And you're there like, oh yeah, I can do that,
I can do that.
No problem.
So you are an egomaniac, okay.
We'll also be looking into paranoia,
delusion, and self-destructive behavior.
This is ways that players actually
kind of make the game less fun for themselves.
Things they do to
to kind of detract from the fun of the game
in ways that as a designer,
we can try and minimize those,
preempt those,
and try and prevent that from happening.
So those are some of the things we'll be looking at
in the course of this talk.
So the first area where psychology
really kind of plays an important role in game design
is something I call the winner paradox.
In real life,
you don't always win.
There are, what, 28 teams in the National Football League,
and only one of them gets to win the Super Bowl.
There are 25 teams in the NBA.
You know, they all go to the playoffs, I guess,
but at the end of the day, there's only one team
that gets to hold the.
golden trophy of NBA champion-ness or whatever that is.
So in the real world, you don't always win.
However, in the world of games, you pretty much always win.
And the psychological phenomenon is that the player
doesn't really complain about that, doesn't object.
That's not a problem.
I don't get letters saying, dear Sid, I loved your game,
but I won way too much.
And this is actually true of other forms of entertainment.
You know, Rambo, you know, at the end of the movie
he's going to come out alright.
Sherlock Holmes always solves the mystery
by the end of the chapter.
I think this is kind of fundamental to entertainment,
but it's certainly something that we're aware of
in designing video games,
that the player's looking for a satisfactory conclusion.
That might not always include winning,
but very often it does.
And this idea of kind of a satisfactory conclusion
to the game, I think, is something to really keep in mind
in the design process.
Some of the tools that we have at our disposal to create this
journey for the player through the game, reward and
punishment. In other words, good things happening to the player,
not so good things happening to the player. There's an
interesting dichotomy in how these are deployed in games.
When you reward the player, you discovered this cool place on
the map, here's 100 gold. The player
gladly accepts that, doesn't question,
did I really earn that, do I deserve that?
Players are very much inclined to accept anything
you give them gladly and feel it was their own clever play,
their own incredible strategy that earned them
that cool reward.
On the other hand, if something bad happens to the player,
your game is broken, there's something horribly wrong,
the game is cheating, it's really important
to be very careful with the setbacks
that the player experiences that is the game.
It's important that the player understand
why those things happened, and especially
how to prevent that from happening the next time.
And any time you can kind of plant that seed
of the next time in the player's head,
you're well on your way to this idea of replayability,
that the player's going to play again.
Next time I'm going to try something different,
maybe that might not happen.
So a big part of the value of these games
is in their replayability.
So any opportunity that you have
to plant the seed of replayability, I think, is important.
And by really carefully handling the idea
of punishment and setbacks, where,
where you explain why it happened
and how it can be rendered the next time.
That's very important.
In terms of rewards, another key thing
that we think about is the first 15 minutes.
One of our rules of game design
is that the first 15 minutes have to be.
Really compelling, really fun, kind of almost a foreshadowing
of all the cool stuff that's going to happen later in the game.
And these rewards are really a way of making the player feel comfortable in this world.
Letting them know that they're on the right track.
They're on their way, cool stuff is happening, and even cooler stuff is going to be happening later on.
And these early rewards, you can almost not reward the player enough.
in the very early stages of the game
to kind of get them invested, get them committed,
get them to be part of the world that you're creating.
Now this doesn't negate the value of difficulty levels.
I'm not advocating an elastic difficulty
that always pushes the player forward
and never provides any challenges.
A number of years ago,
I gave a talk on difficulty levels
and was very convincingly made the point
that four difficulty levels were the perfect number
of difficulty levels.
There needed to be one for introducing the player
to the game where the player could basically always win,
one for the casual player,
one for the player who's really experienced,
and then the fourth difficulty level,
which would be the ultimate challenge.
I was wrong about that.
Apparently we need nine difficulty levels.
The latest Civilization IV has nine difficulty levels.
And it really points out how this idea of progress and advancement...
is so rewarding for the player.
The reason we have these difficulty levels
is to give the player this feeling
that there's always another challenge out there,
that they've mastered this level,
they're ready to move on to the next level.
And that's another reward,
is this idea of getting to the next level in the game.
you want your player to feel that they are above average.
They're doing well and they're going to do even better
as they go deeper into the game.
I think that, again, if you kind of follow
the first 15 minute rule, it's very important
that you kind of start the player off
with a very positive experience.
The unholy alliance.
This is a concept that I want to trademark.
I think this is a really cool idea.
I missed out on the
uncanny valley
And I never trademarked interesting decisions
but unholy alliance, I think is a
as a concept
that
in many ways
Defines the relationship between the player and the designer
The Unholy Alliance is an agreement
that the player and the designer make with each other.
I'm going to pretend certain things,
you're going to pretend certain things,
and together we'll have a great experience.
So one of the things that we pretend as designers
is that the player is good, you're really good.
That's kind of a mantra from us.
That we want the player to feel good
about the play experience and themselves as they're playing.
And one example, perhaps of where this kind of went
off the tracks is in the history of flight simulators
going back a number of years.
Early on, they were kind of easy to play,
very accessible, you'd shoot down a lot of planes,
you'd have a lot of fun.
And then we got to where every succeeding iteration
of flight simulators became a little more realistic,
a little more complex, a little more of a simulation.
And pretty soon the player went from I'm good
to I'm not good, I'm confused.
My plane is on fire and I'm falling out of the sky.
And the fun kind of went out of them.
And I think we have to be aware of this phenomenon
that it's all about the player.
The player is the star of the game.
Their experience is what's key, what's critical.
And keeping them feeling good about themselves
is certainly an important part of the experience
that we provide for them.
Another part of this unholy alliance is the player's role.
The player really needs to be willing
to suspend their disbelief.
They need to inhabit that character.
They need to take on that role that you're providing them,
whether it's a king of a great civilization
or managing a railroad or being a cool pirate.
The player has to be willing to suspend their disbelief.
That's part, they're part of the bargain.
When we go to a movie, my wife,
I ask her after we've seen a movie,
how did you like the movie?
A lot of times she'll say, well,
I came out of that movie twice,
or I never got into that movie,
or I never came out of the movie.
Very aware of the value of suspending your disbelief
to enjoy the experience or to make it more compelling.
So part of our job is to help the player
to suspend their disbelief.
And I think in some ways, those of us that are old-time
designers have a little bit of an advantage there
in that we.
We worked in the good old days of 16-color graphics
and things like that where we really had to work hard
to get the player to believe that what was happening
on the screen was the management of a great empire
or building a railroad system or things like that.
So I think having that experience was helpful
in really understanding some of the challenges
of getting the player to suspend their disbelief.
One of the other.
agreements that we make, I think,
in this unholy alliance with the player
is the idea of moral clarity.
And let me give you an example.
Here's a screenshot from Civilization Revolution
where we're negotiating with the great Genghis Khan.
And one of the comments that I got back
from playtesters was,
these leaders are very,
kind of cranky and aggressive.
I might be winning the battle against them,
they might be down to their last city,
and they're still kind of up there saying,
hey, you'll never take me down,
I'm the greatest civilization of all time,
come on, attack me, I dare you.
And they said, well, that just doesn't seem right.
They shouldn't have that attitude if I'm winning.
And my question was, well, what would you like them to say?
Do you want them to say, oh, please don't hurt me,
we have only one city left,
and there's women and children there,
and please leave me alone?
To me, that's like a moral dilemma.
I mean, I want to win, I want to capture their city,
it's Genghis Khan, for goodness sake,
but I'm faced with a moral dilemma.
I think it's more satisfying, and that's something
we discovered, it's more satisfying to win against
bad Genghis, cranky Genghis, than it is if
there was some kind of a moral cloud over
the actions that you were taking.
MAD is a concept called mutually assured destruction.
How many of you remember the Cold War?
Let's hear it for the Cold War, okay.
The idea of mutually assured destruction was that
we had all these nuclear weapons
and the Russians had all these nuclear weapons
and we could just blow each other up anytime we wanted to,
but the reason we didn't was because we knew
the other side had all these nuclear weapons.
And there's an amazing parallel to that in the relationship
between game designers and the player.
The player can actually destroy the experience
at any time they want to.
They can quit the game, they can play in a way,
in a different way, they can cheat,
they can do all sorts of stuff
to kind of destroy the experience.
And as a game designer, we can mess up the game as well.
We can kind of lose the thread of the fantasy.
There was a game that we were working on
at MicroProse many years ago
that kind of illustrated this to me.
It was an adventure game, and basically,
you kind of started at the beginning of the road,
and you adventured your way on down
until you got to the castle.
you know, finally got to see the king
and had gone through this great adventure,
and when you got to the king,
all of a sudden it was revealed to you
that the king who you thought was a good guy
is actually a bad guy, and everything was turned around,
and you had to go back down the path,
you just come back to the beginning
to do the real thing that you were supposed to do
in the first place.
To me, that was us messing up the game.
I mean, basically, I can imagine the design meetings,
imagine the look on the player's face when they realize
that all this work they've done has to be,
was in vain, and the surprise, and the amazing design,
they'll think, what an amazing design to surprise me like,
and I said, no, that's not what they're gonna think.
They're gonna think I just wasted eight hours
on this stupid game, and so.
they would, at that point, they would mutually,
assuredly, destruct the game, I believe.
So there are ways, I think, again,
that we need to be careful that we're true
to the story of the game and value the player's time.
Another part of this alliance I think that we make with players is in the area of style.
Things that convey what the spirit of your game is.
If you start the game off and have kind of a light-hearted music, atmosphere, cartoony graphics,
and all of a sudden people's heads start exploding.
then you haven't lived up to the alliance.
You're not giving the player what you promised them.
On the other hand, if you...
you know, if you have dark foreboding sound and music
and it ends up being a very simple game,
again, you kind of are fooling the player.
And you know, if I'm playing a game
that starts off light and happy and cartoony,
all of a sudden, you know, terrible things start to happen.
You know, that's when the player.
loses their suspension of disbelief,
and turns off your game and moves on.
So I think the only way to kind of maintain
the suspension of disbelief, which is critical
to keeping the player in the game,
is to really make that a priority
and use things like humor style, music, atmosphere,
all these tools to be consistent
and keep the player in your world.
So probably where it became most clear to me that
player psychology has absolutely nothing to do
with rational thought was in the process of putting
together the battle system in Civilization Revolution.
My background is in mathematics and science and programming
and I think of myself as a logical person.
And what we did in Revolution was we would show you
before a battle what the odds were.
In this example, our attacker here has a 1.5
and the defender, the barbarians, have a 0.5.
They would have a one, barbarians are basically one,
but since they're uncivilized,
they take a 50% penalty for that.
So they're only 0.5.
And part of the fun of being a designer is kind of throwing
those little things into the game, you know, uncivilized.
Minus 50%, ah, take that.
So, in this case, as a mathematician,
this would be a three to one battle.
1.5 to 2.5.
You know, three to one, the attacker should win three times,
the defender should win one time out of four.
Very clear, very simple, you know,
that's what mathematics says, that's the way it should work.
That's not the way our players saw it.
Basically, at a certain point,
players feel they are going to win the battle.
And they would come to me and said,
you know, I had this battle.
It was three to one, and I lost.
I was like, well, yeah, you know, three to one.
You're going to lose every once in a while.
They said, no, no, you don't understand.
It was three to one.
Three, three's big, one is small.
I had the big number.
Shouldn't I have one?
So I realized, okay, there's something going on here.
So we adjusted our system by actually breaking the battle
up into kind of more atomic little battles
to make the results come out more
than the player expected.
And then I watched some more players playing.
This time the player had won against three.
The player had won, the little tiny one,
and the AI had the big gigantic three.
And I watched, and lo and behold,
the player won the battle.
And I said, doesn't that feel wrong to you?
That you with your little tiny one
won against a huge three?
And they said, no, doesn't feel wrong at all.
I had, you know, clever tactics and strategy, clean living.
It all adds up to me winning.
So we realized that something was going on there
psychologically that isn't exactly mathematics.
I'm not sure what it is, but it's not mathematics.
So we made a few adjustments, and I said,
okay, now are you happy with the way combat works?
do expect to pretty much win every time. So okay, that's
fine. We can live with that. Anything else? They said, well,
there's this one little thing. I'm okay. Here's a two to one
battle. Are you okay with winning most of the time but
every now and then losing a two to one? The player said, yeah.
I'm okay with that, two to one.
I should win most of the time,
but every now and then I can lose.
So okay, good.
So what's your problem?
Well, I had this 20 to 10 battle,
and I lost.
It was 20 to 10.
I said, yeah.
20 to 10, I had 10 more than the 10.
I had 20.
I said, you know, it's not two to one, 22.
No, it's 20 to 10.
That's a whole different odds than two to one.
Okay, so we actually adjusted, you know, okay.
I can see you have 10 more, so that's a lot, okay, cool.
Okay, so now, you know,
made the adjustment, gave the game back.
Now are you happy?
I lost, which is okay.
We've had this discussion, I understand now,
that every now and then I'm gonna lose a two to one battle.
But right after that, I had another two to one battle,
and I lost again.
How can that be?
How can I lose two two to one battles?
I mean, one I can understand.
The computers have to get me, obviously.
Okay, so we actually take into account
the results of previous battles.
Now, when we do our combat calculations.
And then the player was very happy.
And we don't really do this just to make the player happy,
but it's really, when something happens in a battle like this
that feels wrong, we start to lose that suspension
of disbelief, the player comes out of the game
and starts to pay attention to other things
that are going on, not what's in the game.
It's all part of the process of really trying to maintain
the suspension of disbelief as the player is playing the game.
And something really kind of clear and instructive
about this process, I think, you know,
the interaction between logic and science and math
and psychology kind of really became clear to me
in this process.
And, you know, I think it all makes sense,
but it's very counterintuitive.
And I think one of the things about,
really including the psychological part of things
in game thinking and design is,
it's gonna run into a number of counterintuitive things.
And we'll see a little more of that later,
but there are many times where that actually
can work to your advantage.
And it's not always quite the process
that we just went through.
So this part is called My Bad.
times when I really screwed up and kind of came to realize that it was because
my brain was too logical and scientific and I hadn't really included a lot of the
psychological aspects of what goes on in games
The first bad bad thing I did
in life was to make Civilization a real-time game.
The original prototype of Civilization was real-time,
kind of inspired by SimCity and that genre of games
where you're kind of watching something grow.
SimCity, I think, inspired a lot of designers
to branch out in kind of construction-oriented games,
growth games.
But what we found with the real-time version of Civilization
was that the player really became an observer,
was watching what's going on, was really just an observer.
And the mantra that we had in mind for Civilization
was it's good to be king.
And we found that when we made it a turn-based game,
all of a sudden, lights went off.
All of a sudden the player was no longer an observer,
they were the star of the game,
they were the key ingredient, and they made things happen.
Kind of ironic since Civ is now the poster child
for turn-based gaming, but Civ actually started off
as a real-time game, and that was my bad, sorry about that.
Another bad thing that I did in the original civilization
design was to include this idea of rise and fall.
Wouldn't it be cool if you built this cool civilization
and then you had this kind of setback
and it started to crumble and just before it disappeared
you rescued it and you came back to win
even more strong and powerfully than you did before.
Wouldn't that be an awesome experience?
No, not really.
What we found was that just at the cusp of the crumble,
most players would reload a save game,
and they would never experience the glorious re-rise
that we had in mind for them.
So Civilization is basically a game about progress.
It's a game about rise, rise, and more rise,
and not so much the fall.
Another badness that I perpetrated was in the original
civilization tech tree.
The idea that I had in mind was that technology would be
this interesting path of kind of discovery through
the darkness and you would kind of never know where
the different paths of technology would lead.
It seemed to me totally wacky that you would be thinking
back in 3000 BC, okay, if I discover ironworking,
someday I'm going to have gunpowder in nuclear weapons.
So we randomized the tech tree, we did a lot of things
to make that process kind of mysterious.
But once players realized, generally the second time
they played, that there was gunpowder out there.
Their only goal was, how do I get to gunpowder most quickly?
Give me the road, don't randomize,
don't mysterious-ize this thing.
I know there's gunpowder out there, you can't fool me.
And we understood that players want to be in control.
They really want to know what's going on.
And the kind of broader lesson from this for me
was that any kind of randomness really needs to be treated
with a lot of care.
We also had the idea in the original Civilization
of these kind of great natural disasters.
You know, wouldn't it be cool to have
like volcano Krakatoa blowing up or the plague
and all these kind of famous world events
happening in the game, you know, kind of randomly?
No, it wouldn't.
Again, whenever anything random happens to the player,
paranoia strikes in.
Paranoia was one of our early...
psychological feelings.
The player feels that the computer did that,
rolled that random number just to make their life
more difficult or they were just about to win.
So, random events have to be treated very, very carefully
because if they're significant,
basically the player will find the worst.
and most paranoid explanation for what just happened
in the game.
Randomness at a low level certainly helps a lot
to variety, replayability, things like that,
but really need to be careful with randomness
at a really significant level.
I'm gonna skip the covert action rule.
That's kind of boring.
The dinos game was another mistake that I made.
a while back I gave a talk called, you know, Dinosaurs,
the Three Glorious Failures.
Basically that was a game that I thought would be very cool,
tried to create, did three different versions.
One was a RTS type game, one was more of a strategy game,
one was actually a card game.
And none of them really kind of gelled together.
And I was disappointed, I thought dinosaurs are very cool
and I may be able to make a cool game about this,
but it never really.
came together for reasons I'm not quite sure of yet,
but what's interesting to me though is that
after Civilization, that's almost the best known game.
When I talk to people, when I run into people,
you know, besides Civilization, the other question is
where's the Dino Dukes game, you know?
So this game that I never made
is like the second most interesting game for gamers.
So that was my bad, but I'll,
Life is not over yet.
And Civilization Network, this is a new game
that we're working on.
Civilization for the Facebook platform.
A lot of kind of fun game concepts that we get to play with here, you know, people playing on kind of an interesting schedule, you know, maybe a little bit of time a day, a little more time a day, kind of making the game interesting if you're playing at the same time as other players or if you're playing at different times as other players.
The idea that you're playing with friends so that you won't that we can really focus a lot on cooperative gameplay also include competitive gameplay
Individual gameplay all different kinds of gameplay mixed together. So this is really kind of a fun
fun world to take civilization into and
One of the ideas that we were that we played with here was the idea of being able to give gold
to other players.
It was like, wouldn't it be neat,
wouldn't this lead to all sorts of interesting possibilities
if we put into the game the ability
to give gold to other players?
You could say, I'll give you this much gold
if you do this for me, or I feel sorry for you,
I'm going to give you 300 gold,
or hey, please give me some gold, whatever.
There'd be this fascinating diplomatic negotiating dynamic
that would arise in the game.
What we found, however, was that nobody ever gave gold
to anybody else.
The thought did not cross their mind
to give gold to other people.
I don't know what this says about the human condition
or the future of mankind, but it's kind of a sad commentary,
I think, another bad idea that I had.
in the blurb to this presentation
was to explain how to save millions of dollars
in game design.
And so if you're interested in that part
of the presentation,
this would be the time to pay attention.
One of the techniques I think that's very, very important
in making AAA games on a shoestring
is to really use the player's imagination
as a very key tool.
No matter how good your graphics are,
no matter how cool your technology is,
what's happening in the player's mind,
the player can always visualize something
more compelling, more dynamic.
So the goal of everything we do
is to make something happen in the player's imagination
that is...
that is really cool.
And often, we don't have to literally show everything
in the game to make that happen.
If the player can imagine what's going on,
you know, imagine what Napoleon is doing
when he's not actually on the screen,
imagine what's going on behind the scenes,
then we save a lot of money by not having to create
all those assets and do all those things.
And one example, again, from Civilization Revolution
is this screen here.
All right, it says.
foreign rulers seek your favor,
the Sultan of Zanzibar sends you a caravan of exotic gifts,
including seven dancing bears.
The principle here is something I call go with the flow.
In other words, if it's something the player
is already inclined to believe,
if it's something the player wants to believe,
it's very easy to make that happen
in the player's imagination.
The player looks at this and says,
Oh yeah, foreign leaders should be seeking my favor.
And exotic gifts, cool, they should be sending me.
And seven dancing bears, that's very cool.
So it's happening, in your mind, the bears are dancing,
it's all happening up there.
Because I'm inclined to agree with this sentiment right here.
And we actually don't have any dancing bears.
There's no Sultan of Zanzibar, there's no caravan.
But by going with the flow, we've saved ourselves
millions of dollars in not having to create all these
models and textures and assets and all this kind of stuff
because the player wants to believe this.
And all we have done is basically put up a text box.
Now that allows us to save our resources,
our time, our energy.
for the things that are kind of harder to sell,
the things that the player might not be so inclined
to believe or kind of want to see
brought to life with all sorts of cool graphical stuff.
Another technique for saving millions and millions of dollars
in designing games is to use,
take advantage of what the player already knows.
players bring lots of their own information to games and they
don't have to, a lot of that doesn't have to be reinforced
literally. Pirates for example, a game where people bring a lot
of their own knowledge to the game. So if they see a swordsman
with a black curly mustache, they probably know that's going
to be the evil.
meta villain that they're going to have to sword fight and we
don't need a whole lot of back story to explain how he got that
way and what his childhood was like, et cetera, et cetera.
Black curly mustache, okay, bad guy, time for a sword fight.
Millions of dollars saved in back story.
So these are just a couple of techniques by which you can
kind of focus, I think, your energy and your resources on.
what's going to be really impressive, what's going to be new,
and what's going to be hard to sell in the game,
and take advantage of things that the players
are going to almost automatically provide
through their own imagination.
Let's talk about artificial intelligence for a moment.
AI is often a place where psychology
really comes strongly into play,
because the AI kind of represents your opponent, the enemy.
And whenever you're in a kind of conflict situation,
your psychological juices are flowing even more strongly.
You're really committed and invested in that conflict.
And so a lot of players project a lot onto the AI
because they feel this competitive situation.
And there's a number of different philosophies about AI.
My point of view is not necessarily the only point of view.
There may be other points of view,
but I look at AI as one element
in creating an integrated overall experience for the player.
in a single player game, like most of the games we're talking about,
again, the key, the star of the game, the key experience is the experience that the player is having.
And so AI is kind of a tool to craft that experience,
to customize it, to make it seem even more real
to the player.
There's another point of view, which is that the AI
should act like another player, another person,
should have human-ish characteristics
and should feel like another player.
I don't actually subscribe to that philosophy.
There's a couple things that I've seen
that make me shy away from that.
I'm not saying it's absolutely the wrong idea,
but in my experience, if an AI has human characteristics,
one thing we talk about is, I want it to surprise me.
I want it to be tricky and clever.
No, I don't think, when AI does that,
most players feel that it's being stupid,
it's being, it's dumb, because there's a fine line
between clever and dumb, and the player is inclined
to see the AI as being dumb.
If the player, if the AI does something really brilliant,
the player will assume that the AI peeked behind the scenes
and looked at my numbers and looked where my stuff was
and cheated, basically.
So there's a lot of kind of psychological.
stuff that goes on if the AI acts in ways that are
kind of out of the norm.
And they generally lead to the player kind of jumping out,
losing that suspension of disbelief and trying,
and kind of blaming the AI for what's going on in the game.
So the way that I approach AI is to make it almost a metric,
kind of a solid,
competition against which you play,
but which you can kind of feel
and your advancement as you go on.
You get this real sense of progress.
There's this improvement metric
that the AI is kind of predictable,
kind of solid and steady,
and you're the one doing the brilliant things
and the clever things and getting better and better
versus the AI.
Another thing that AI can do is give you feedback
when you're talking to the leaders in civilization.
They often comment upon what you're doing
and how, you know, whether it's good or bad
or whether they like it or don't like it.
When we're playing a single player game,
kind of feedback validation is really important
because you're kind of.
the only person there, and these AI characters
are kind of your only friends at that point in time.
So having them acknowledge what you're doing,
be aware of it, is really validating for the player,
and is something we found in Civil Revolution
was really important, that the more that the other leaders
in the game kind of reflected on what you were doing
and reacted, the more the player felt that
but somebody understood them, you know,
kind of, you know what I'm going through.
And they weren't just kind of playing in a vacuum,
they were playing in a interesting world.
Okay.
I talked a little bit earlier
about self-destructive behavior.
Ways that the player actually can damage
their gameplay experience.
And one of the responsibilities that I think we have
as designers is to protect the player from themselves.
And there are a couple of places where this
really becomes an issue.
One is how do you handle the idea of load and save?
I've watched people play Civilization
where before every battle, they save the game.
If they don't win, they reload that saved game,
play the battle again, save it, until they win the game.
To me, that's not really playing the game that I designed.
That's not the experience that I think is most interesting.
It really doesn't require you to have a flexible strategy.
It doesn't kind of require you to think ahead.
If you know you're going to win every battle,
the game, I think, is a lot less fun.
So in Civilization Revolution,
we actually save the random number with the save file,
so that if you reload the save file,
you get the same result in your battle.
You know, ha ha ha.
You know, that'll teach you.
I guess people did find a way to get around that,
but by providing the player perhaps too easy access
to loading and saving, you may actually be
diminishing the experience for the player,
and that is something to think about in game design.
In Pirates, we actually only allow you to load
and save the game when you're in a port.
As you voyage around, you need to live with the consequences
of that voyage.
And kind of by building it into the fantasy of the game,
I think it's a little less obvious that we are trying to
kind of control your load-save behavior,
but that's something to think about,
is finding ways to build your load-save restrictions
kind of into the fantasy, the story of the game.
Another area where I think we can damage the gameplay
experience for the player is in providing them too many options,
settings, things that they can kind of customize in the middle
of the game. There's all sorts of good things that the player
should be able to customize, whether you think the joystick
works this way, whether you're left-handed or right-handed. All
those things are key.
But there's been a tendency that I think has kind of
gone away more recently, but to kind of open up
all sorts of game play decisions to the player.
And to me, you know, that's kind of wrong.
We're, as designers, we're here to make the game
and not to kind of hand it over to the player and say,
you know, I'm not sure how this game should work.
You know, you figure it out.
So, kind of being careful with the types of things
that you open up to player is one thing to think about.
Another is cheat codes.
Again, I think it's a way that players can
actually damage the gameplay experience for themselves.
I remember when we were working on Civilization II,
Brian Reynolds brought the game and I looked at it
and there on the main menu was cheat.
It was like play a quick game, play a random map,
play a game, cheat.
And I said, you know, Brian Cheek, on the main menu?
He said, yeah, it's cool, you know,
you can bring in tanks in the Middle Ages
and run over people, and you know, it's cool.
And I don't disagree that it is cool.
In fact, I watched my son when he was playing,
you know, have a wonderful time bringing in all these tanks
and running roughshod over the pikemen of the Middle Ages.
It's like, but Brian, does the main menu,
can't we just vary it one or two levels deeper?
Because I kind of want the players to play the real game
first before they start experimenting with the cheats
and the Easter eggs and things like that.
The good news is that this cheating idea
actually led directly to the idea of modding.
which is very powerful.
Certainly, Civilization II was a breakthrough for civilization
and added an incredible amount of variety and energy to the Civilization series.
This is a picture from Fall from Heaven.
There's a happy ending to the story of Cheat.
And modding has been a very cool addition,
kind of allowing players to exercise their inner designer
and become part of the community process.
So, cheating, I'm not so sure,
but modding is definitely a cool thing.
Another kind of psychological skill I think that we need
to develop as designers is listening to the player.
I'm kind of assuming at this point that you've bought into
the idea that game design is an iterative process,
starting with a prototype and kind of building on that,
getting a lot of play, getting a lot of feedback,
building a game over time, and if you do that,
you're gonna spend a lot of time talking to.
the players, the people that are playing your game,
getting their feedback, and taking advantage of that
to make your game better.
But what I found in that process is that
it's really not that useful to kind of take literally
what your players are saying to you.
There are different kind of ways
that players will react to the game.
One is to kind of provide you with solutions.
You know, I think you should take this out.
I think you should change this.
I think this should work this way.
Occasionally that's useful, but a lot of times that really
doesn't take into account other parts of the game
that that would break, et cetera, et cetera.
And it's tempting to kind of discard that.
You know, that's not going to work.
I know that's not going to work.
You might have even tried that.
But I think it's important as a designer
to get some real value out of that,
to drill down to what is motivating that solution.
What is wrong?
What is the kind of thing that the player's feeling
or doing that is unsatisfying
that leads them to kind of suggest the solution?
And a lot of times, you can find something
that is consistent with your game design
and your game ideas that will solve that problem for them.
It might not be the exact solution that they propose,
but it will solve the problem in everybody.
Everybody's happy.
Another type of comment that you might get back
is kind of the opposite of that.
It's an emotion, you know.
It doesn't feel right.
I'm frustrated, I'm confused.
Again, very little information.
And again, it's kind of our job as designers
to figure out what is it that's causing that emotion?
What can I change to make that emotion go away
if it's a bad emotion or to strengthen that
if it's a positive emotion?
Another important, oops, don't look at that slide.
The last thing I think is important about talking
to your players is knowing their individual personalities.
A lot of times, it's very helpful in deciphering,
decoding what they're saying, because a certain player
might not like that type of game
and is never going to be happy.
There are certain players we call Mr. Anecdotal,
who will be convinced something has happened.
that you know is impossible,
we'll just kind of harp on that one thing that,
there are people that are very generous,
kind of afraid to say anything bad about the game,
you almost have to force them,
I know you hated something about it,
come, tell me, tell me what it is.
So kind of knowing the personalities of your players
is important in, again, in deciphering
what they're really trying to tell you.
And kind of really tapping into this resource,
which is really invaluable,
the gameplay experience of your testers
as you're playing the game.
So what is the point of all this, you might be asking?
I'd kind of like to wrap it up with this idea of
the epic journey.
I think this is what we're trying to create for the player,
is an epic journey.
I think I should trademark this one too.
Epic journey.
Keep that in.
There's so many genres, so many styles of games,
so many different ways of gaming.
But I think in a way, they can kind of all be encapsulated
in this idea of an epic journey.
And how do we use psychology to make our journey more epic
and our epic more journey-like?
You might be asking.
Here are a couple of tools
that we have to make that happen.
I come back again and again
to the idea of interesting decisions.
That's really the core, the basic fundamental pieces
of your game are these decisions
that you're giving the player.
And the journey is the process of exploring
all these decisions and seeing how they relate
to each other and playing through them.
So think about the decisions that you're giving your player.
Are they ones that encourage them to project,
to think into the future?
You know, if I do this, what is going to happen?
Do they have interesting, kind of not taken paths?
And the coolest decisions are the ones where
the player chooses path A, but they're kind of saying,
well, next time, you know, that path B
looks kind of interesting, too, so I'm going to play
next time and try that other path.
Those are the really powerful decisions.
If you can build them into your game,
you're well on your way to creating.
The epic journey.
Learning and progress.
This is fundamental to the journey.
The idea that you are constantly progressing,
you're constantly at a better place than you were before,
you're smarter than you were before, you're more powerful.
It's kind of fundamental,
but it's easy to lose track of this.
I think that you cannot...
reward and acknowledge and reflect this progress
too much in a game.
It's very important for the player to know
how they're doing, what value has this last half hour,
this last hour been to me in terms of playing.
I think World of Warcraft does a great job of this.
The level system makes it very clear
the kind of progress you made,
and their ways of building this idea,
which is very powerful, into your game.
One more turn, this is another way of making the journey epic.
It's a concept that we relate back to civilization,
but it applies to almost every game.
The idea that the player is constantly
kind of leaning forward.
They're anticipating things that are going to happen later.
They're looking forward to their plans coming together.
They're wondering what's around the next corner.
You can foreshadow, you can kind of just let people know
that cool stuff is going to happen soon.
And it draws them very much into this
one more turn phenomenon.
And it kind of all comes back to this idea of replayability.
That if you create a fantastic journey,
and the player comes to the end of that journey,
they suddenly realize that this is only one segment
of this epic journey.
This journey is much more epic than they even thought,
because this has only been a part.
The epic was a part.
It's like epic squared or epic cubed.
And replayability kind of plants that seed
and makes that happen for your game.
So these are some tools, some psychological tools
that make your game the coolest epic journey of all time.
So now you know everything.
Thank you.
We have a little bit of time for questions. There are some folks
with microphones. I'm sure much of what I've said is wrong and
you're going to correct me on it. But I'd be happy to take
any questions or thoughts. If there's anybody who would like
to ask a question. Look for someone with a green, raise your
hand and look for somebody with a green shirt and a microphone.
Right here.
What do you normally tell your animators, designers, artists,
exactly how you want the art for particular games to feel?
How do you explain to them what you have in your vision?
The question is, how do I explain to animators and artists
what my vision is, what I want them to do?
There's a couple dimensions to that.
A lot of times, I will actually build a prototype myself
using pieces from other games and things like that
that kind of create the big picture
so they know what they're doing fits into the bigger picture.
One of the issues, I think, with art
is often it's easy to get kind of a keyhole
and only focus on the one thing that you're making.
The other thing that I think is important
is to kind of let your artists be artists, be creative.
Put a pretty big box around what you want
and let them surprise you with something
that's even cooler than you imagined.
So one is having a prototype that they can always go back to
if the question is how does this fit into the game?
What is it supposed to do?
But then let them be artists.
I think that games as a collaborative medium
really need to take advantage of all the talents
that you have available to work on it.
So I try to let the artists be as creative as they can be.
Question, here?
Hi.
You talked about player egoism and that sort of approach to that players come come to approach games with
And I guess I'm having a hard time like figuring out like do you think that?
you know this egoistic approach to games is kind of prefigured by the themes that
that you give them like you know you're going to build a civilization you're going to become
a railroad tycoon or do you sort of pick these themes because you anticipate that this is what
players like how players want to feel with when they play a game?
I think one of the fundamental attractions of gaming
is that you can go to places that you can't go in real life,
that you can inhabit characters that you probably
don't have the opportunity to do in real life.
And I think it's kind of the Walter Mitty fantasy.
I get to be a dashing, swashbuckling pirate.
I get to run a great civilization.
So we definitely look for topics that are epic,
that are big, that kind of really empower the player
and make them much larger than life,
because I think that's what you're looking for
in a gameplay experience,
is something to kind of take you out of.
the real world and into a cooler world.
Take you out of your real life into a cooler life,
take you out of maybe your real character
into a cooler character.
Epic is definitely part of our thinking
in putting together these game worlds
because they are, I think at the end of the day,
that journey just feels cooler
if it's been through thousands of years of history.
through the high of the Spanish main,
ending up with that horribly evil guy with a mustache,
you know, et cetera.
So yes, we definitely choose kind of epic,
larger than life situations,
because I think it makes a more compelling game,
and it also taps into a lot of common knowledge and fantasy,
which we can then use in building the game.
Question over here?
Hey, with the limited amount of time that people have to play games like as an adult,
wouldn't it make more sense to make a single epic journey rather than having to play through it like
two to the n times? I think people appreciate the value of replayability. I mean there's sequels
out there. So if you had a great experience with a game, you often want to do it again.
I don't think people, people do have a limited amount of time
to play games, but I think they select what games they want
to play in that limited amount of time,
and it's even more important for that reason
that they're playing a game that they like.
So replayability kind of allows you to play a game
that you know you're going to like
with that limited amount of time that you have.
Hello. I have a question about the flight simulator point you
made earlier. I've worked on racing games for a while. And
the last one we released was Midnight Club 4 last year, which
critically got slammed because everybody thought it was too
hard. And we worked really hard to make it so you didn't have to
win to progress and succeed in the game. But the conception was
that people were really, really frustrated when they weren't
coming in first all the time. And I was wondering if you had
any advice or solutions for trying to condition the player
to accept that they're not going to win.
all the time.
You're definitely walking uphill there,
walking into the wind, I think the expectation
is out there that you're going to win.
I think you have to do a lot of work
to make it fun not to win.
Certainly realism and authenticity are cool things.
but you have to work hard to sell that idea.
I'm a big Gran Turismo fan, but even that game,
I think you still end up winning very often,
even though it has the real feel of authenticity.
Good luck, but that's a tough one.
done. Over here. Hi, you were talking about how it's really
good to present the player with choices and when it comes to a
lot of games lately they've been doing a lot of the moral choices
like good or evil. Is it more positive to do that and have the
player expect a certain outcome or would you rather see games
start moving into the morally gray area where it's more
uncertain? That's a good question.
I'm not a fan of morally gray games.
I think that this alliance, this unholy alliance
that we made with the player, to me,
excludes that, unless you're very clear up front
that this is a game about gray moral choices.
because you're asking the player to invest this time.
One of the analogies I use is like
showing up on your first day at high school.
You're kind of wondering, what are the rules here?
Who are the cool people?
How does this place work?
And so you're kind of very vulnerable early in the game
and you want to kind of be encouraged
and kind of know that this time that you're investing
and spending is taking you down the right path.
And the idea of the morally gray choices
and things like that, I think it always plants
the idea in the player's mind that,
I might be on the wrong track here.
All this time I'm investing now,
this might be just taking me off in the wrong direction.
And I think that's an opportunity for the player
to kind of say, you know, maybe I should try something else.
I think you have to be very clear if your game is about
morally gray, ambiguous choices,
that you're gonna make sure that wherever they go,
something interesting is gonna happen.
That they're not gonna be allowed to go off
on some dead-end path,
because they made a poor moral choice.
Given the number of trends that you have seen come and go during the course of your career,
what would you guess would be the next big trend in gaming?
Where do you see the avant-garde idea coming from in the future?
It's a really cool time, I think, to be a game designer.
We certainly have seen the indie games movement
put a lot of new energy into gaming.
We have new platforms, whether it's Facebook
or the live or places, browser games,
a lot of places where the whole kind of big budget thing
has gone away and opened up a lot of new opportunities for.
for gaming, you know, where do I see gaming going?
I think this is the year of civilization, frankly.
Um.
I think there's a Civilization 5 maybe coming this year,
and a Civilization Network, so in the immediate future,
I think this is the year of Civilization.
Looking further out, there's so much energy and dynamism,
I think, in this industry, that it's part of, I think,
what keeps us, every day, looking to see what's new,
and that's a big part of the excitement, I think,
of being part of this industry.
Over here.
Hi.
Throughout your presentation, you've
talked a lot about how people hate failure in video games
and avoid it.
I would like you to speak a little bit more
on how you can make a video game that just keeps getting
better and better, or if that is possible,
and how you personally avoid the feeling of losing or failure
in the video game.
I think almost every video game is built on the idea of progress.
Now that doesn't mean that progress is free or automatic or guaranteed,
but the player wants the basic experience to be one of getting better, learning, progressing.
But the more that feels earned, the more satisfying it is.
So in order for that to feel earned,
there has to be the potential of a negative outcome,
the potential of something bad happening.
And when that happens, I think one of the key points
is that the player understand.
why it happened and what the player can do
to prevent that from happening the next time.
I think that that's a win-win in many ways
because the player is now thinking about
another way of playing, about playing again,
which you've also added to the value
of the next piece of progress
because it was won in spite of this adversity.
So managing the kind of reward and punishment process
is really fundamental to game design.
Over here.
Hello?
Hi.
You talked earlier about trying to maintain
the player's idea of winning, always wanting to win,
and the whole problems arising with the load save issues.
A lot of times when I was playing Civ...
Even though I'd win the game, it much became a point
about trying to beat my own score.
And in order to do that, I had to take much more of an edge
by, you know, and it did come down to that whole
load save issues.
I hated it when I lost a one, or there was something else
I needed to get me to the next point.
So my question to you is, how do you accommodate your design
when the player's not just trying to beat the machine,
but beat themselves?
I think that's another dimension of progress in one way,
that you feel that progress against your own score.
Whether you use the load save mechanism to do that or not,
it's kind of your own moral choice, I think.
Games give you many, many ways to play,
and you get to pick the one
that's hopefully most satisfying to you.
some of the talk about self-destructive behavior
was kind of oriented towards,
maybe there's some things we shouldn't make that easy
because at the end of the day,
you might not feel as good about your victory
if you use some of these things.
And in Civ Revolution,
we actually had these kind of Iron Man modes,
or we would actually keep track of the number of load saves
that you did, and that would be mentioned
along with your score, so you could kind of,
By doing it without loading and saving, for example,
that would actually be something that would be noted on there
and let you feel even better about your final score.
Hi, Sid, over here, all the way to your left.
In regards to the social network gaming,
There is a rampant kind of issue with cloning of games.
So there's like 12 farm games and 22 island games
and 73 sim games now.
How do you foresee the protection of your IP
or your kind of your big civilization network?
Because it's an issue for everyone
who's developing on social networks.
That's definitely an issue.
I think my role is to make the best game that I can make.
We're doing, we're playing the game almost daily right now
and we're putting in all sorts of cool stuff.
So I think the way that we try and deal with that
is to make the best game that we can
and in that way make it very difficult to duplicate
because someone would have to go through
that same testing experience
and trying all the same dead ends that we tried
that didn't work before getting to kind of what does work.
I think that question is,
my role as a designer is just to make
the best game I can make.
What the industry does is,
It's kind of out of my hands, but I love my job,
so I'm not complaining.
Right here.
Hi, thanks for the talk, loved it.
My question is about player expectations.
Do you always have to acquiesce to these?
Have you ever purposefully flown in the face
of what the player expects?
And you're about the example of the math
and the soldiers, three versus one.
Is there a deeper immersion achieved if a player's belief is rectified and he gains a feeling that he understands the mechanic rather than just having a vague notion of math that he was using before?
I think the fundamental purpose for dealing with the combat situation the way we did
was to not give the player a reason to jump out of the game to suspend their disbelief.
That was kind of our primary goal.
What I kind of realized though in going through that process was that in some ways the player is actually right about what they're feeling
that
In a computer game, you know, we say the odds are three to one, but the player isn't actually rolling the dice
You know, they don't actually see that process. That's all happening somehow in some mysterious background code that
some designer wrote that they may or may not trust.
And so they're kind of at the mercy of the designer.
So if bad things happen there
that they can't see the reason for,
this paranoia is really gonna kick in.
So that by making the odds,
the outcomes kind of conform
to what the player's expectations were,
we kind of damp down this paranoia
and also keep them in the game.
So that was kind of the thinking process
that we went through.
We don't always try and meet the player's expectations
exactly, I mean, there have to be surprises,
have to be new things.
I put ballroom dancing into the new Pirates game.
That was a surprise to a lot of people.
Might have been one of the things on the my bad list.
So we do try and surprise players,
but not in kind of fundamental things
that determine their success or failure.
Hi, thank you, great talk.
Kind of a follow-up to that question.
In the way that your nine difficulty levels work,
does the math get more honest at the higher difficulty levels?
And second follow-up question,
your personal preferences in gaming,
do you enjoy games that are unabashedly difficult,
like Demon's Souls?
First question was,
how are the difficulty levels implemented?
There's no simple answer to that.
question. I think that again, AI difficulty to me is a full
range of tools that we use to create a customized experience
for the player. The first difficulty level is one that
basically takes you on a tour through the game. You're probably
going to win at the end, but you're going to get to see all
the cool stuff that happens, and you'll understand that the next
time it'll be more difficult.
And with Civ in particular, the highest difficulty level
is something that has to totally kick your butt every time
or else you don't feel satisfied.
It's a point of honor just to survive the highest level.
So we're customizing those difficulty experiences
using all sorts of different tools.
Do I enjoy games that are very difficult?
Generally not.
The problem for me is I pick up a game
and if I'm not really having fun
in the first 15 or 20 minutes,
I'm gonna say I'm not gonna really invest
the 10 or 20 hours it's probably gonna take
to start to get some fun out of this game
or really explore it.
So I'm, I guess, a pretty typical consumer in that fashion.
Over here.
During your slide presentation on my bad and the design
mistakes, there was a brief mention of an espionage game
mechanic that you didn't feel was very interesting to talk
about. Can you briefly summarize what that was and what you
learned?
Yeah, we call that the covert action rule.
Covert action is a game I wrote many, many years ago.
And basically, it was an espionage game and there was this kind of
interestingly complex mystery that you were trying to unravel with
people in different cities doing different things to do dastardly things to the world.
And in the process of unraveling that mystery,
you would go into these action sequences
where you'd sneak through a building in open safes
and clues and guards would chase you
and you'd follow cars around and you'd break codes
and unravel these circuits,
all sorts of cool action sequences and puzzles.
And based on our pirates experience,
we thought that was very cool.
Because pirates, for us, was a really neat combination
of action and role-playing and strategy
and all this kind of stuff working together.
But what we found was that...
there are really two games fighting very hard
against each other.
That you were in the mystery part of the game
and you're trying to put together the clues
and figure things out and you say,
okay, I need to go to Cairo, you know,
and break into this building and that's the next,
you know, it's going to take me
to the next step of this mystery.
And you do that and you kind of have
this cool action sequence and you pop out
of the building at the end, you know,
maybe five or 10 minutes later, and it's like.
what was I, what was that mystery again,
why did I go into that building?
And the two games are not necessarily better than one
was the rule we call the covert action rule.
The center of gravity of your game
kind of has to be in one place.
Everything else kind of supports that, enhances that,
but you've got to figure out,
is the center of gravity in the action,
is it in the strategy, how does that all work?
And when we look back at Pirates,
we realize that the center of gravity of that game
is kind of in the strategy,
that the ship battles, the sword fights, et cetera,
are kind of quick and clear enough
that you don't lose the thread of what's going on
when you come back to the strategy game.
I think we have time for one more question.
Is there someone?
Yes.
Thank you. When I was much younger, I had a lot of time to
devote to playing your games. I love the detail. And as I'm
getting older and I'm getting all these responsibilities, I'm
finding the detail overwhelming. So I'm wondering, is a situation
like mine, the aging gamer, is that playing a role in your game
development process? And if so, how are you dealing with it?
I have to say yes.
I mean, I'm an aging gamer myself,
and I think there, we have certainly evolved
from a kind of a hardcore-based,
hardcore gamer-based industry
to now we're seeing all these diverse audiences for games.
And I think, in a way, Civilization Revolution
was kind of my response to complexity of games.
I think there are players that don't have
10 or 20 hours or 40 hours.
10, 15, whatever amount of time it takes
to fully enjoy the fabulous Civilization PC experience.
But you don't always have that.
You might have a, you know,
and you might want to play a game with someone
who's not that deeply into Civilization.
So Civ Revolution was an experience
that was geared towards that audience.
And it was something that I found
very interesting to design.
It kind of tapped into, in many ways, kind of,
where I was in terms of gaming,
I wanted to sample a lot of different games.
And so I think we're seeing this incredible diversity
of games these days.
I mean, from games that take only a few minutes to play,
games that you play every little bit of time every day,
games that you sit down with and totally devour,
that take tens and tens of hours.
I mean, it's a great time to be a gamer.
It's a great time to be.
in this industry because we have all this variety,
all these possibilities, but there's definitely,
I know, an aging gamer demographic,
there's a casual gamer demographic,
there's hardcore gamers, there's all sorts of gamers.
And once a year we all get to get together
here in San Francisco and celebrate ourselves.
So thank you again for coming, and it's been a pleasure.