It's a little bit late in the afternoon but we'll try to keep you entertained.
So the name of this talk is the Paradox DLC model, planning for the long term.
And the astute among you might notice that there has been a change of speakers.
I was supposed to do this talk together with Johan Andersson, but unfortunately he had
to cancel pretty much at the last minute.
So instead, my esteemed colleague Shams Georgiani will be jumping in and doing this together
with me.
All right, so does everyone know who we are?
What is Paradox?
No one?
Some of you guys, anyway.
So I can take this off.
Again, thanks everyone for being here.
So we're going to go through this presentation,
and we'll be talking a little bit about our DLC model.
And hopefully towards the end, we'll do a bit of a Q&A.
You can kind of ask us if we have.
are head screwed on straight or what the hell is going on.
Tell us if this makes sense or not.
But one of the reasons why we are here
is that we get a fair amount of shit for our business model,
to put it mildly.
If you go and check out any of our user scores on Steam
right now, you'll see a lot of thumbs down,
and all they write is the DLC model.
So that's part of the reality, but we also
have an equal amount of people that defend it and support it
quite a bit.
And we have an even greater amount
of people who just buy the games and DLC.
to hell and back.
So we're not here to defend the DLC model, but we're here to
explain and elaborate a bit about why the business model
looks like this, and to shed a bit of light behind it.
And hopefully there's a bit of takeaways that you guys can
take with you as you go on and make a ton of money, hopefully,
off of your DLC plans.
Right, so it's kind of a two-part talk.
We're talking a little bit about the business model.
And that's more your area, I guess.
And I'm going to talk about our design practices
and how we decide how to do features
and what kind of features we do in these expansions.
So my name is Henrik Foreus.
I'm a game director at Paradox.
These days, I usually do, or mostly do,
game design, creative supervision, and product
management.
But I've had my hand in our games since 2001
as programmer, scripter, and all kinds of things.
And I'm probably best known for Crusader Kings II and Stellaris
most recently.
Yeah.
So.
Cool.
My name is Shams Jorjani. I've been with Paradox about eight years.
I work on the publishing side, so I'm very much the corporate douchebag in that sense.
So where Hendrik makes the games fun for you, I'm on the other side doing other things.
We'll get to that.
I've done mostly about just about everything at Paradox from marketing, production side,
but most notably I've run, been in charge of our game's portfolio for the past seven
years.
So all the bad stuff we've released and signed, that's my fault, and all the good stuff I've
been just partially responsible, you could say.
I've also been part of the management team,
and I'm very much in charge of running
part of the business models stuff.
So I could do like a five hour talk about the business models
straight up today.
So I was happy to jump in.
But I'll take it all from here.
Thanks.
So Paradox 2.
How many here have played a Paradox game?
Please keep your hands up.
Fantastic.
How many of you have played a Paradox game
for more than 10 hours?
How many of you have played a Paradox game for more than 100 hours?
More than 500 hours?
More than 1,000 hours?
More than 2,000 hours?
More than 3,000 hours?
Okay.
So.
Awesome.
Fantastic.
First of all, thank you.
Secondly, this tells the rest of you who haven't played a Paradox game, who hasn't played a
Paradox game?
Oh, there's a few of you.
Okay.
Poor.
So Paradox Games have, since their inception,
always been niche games.
One of our unofficial slogans has been,
a game for everyone is a game for no one, essentially.
And we've created these very hardcore sandbox procedural
games that have been very much focused
on historical settings.
This is where Paradox started.
Paradox made these historical games
and worked with regular publishers.
This was in 2004 before there was digital distribution,
before Steam.
So we worked with Atari.
And Atari published our games the same way
they would have published any old action game.
And after a while, we realized these guys have no idea
how we weirdo strategy historical gamers behave,
talk about games, and enjoy them.
We have to stop working with that publisher
and become our own publisher.
So many of you may be standing in front of that challenge
right now, do I self-publish or not?
We asked ourselves that question in 2004.
There was a gentleman called Fredrik Wester, who's now our
CEO, who came in and presented a business plan to the people
who owned Paradox then.
And he said, you've got to become your own publisher.
They looked at the plan and said, get out of here.
We're closing everything down.
And they actually closed everything down and gave it to
Fred, who bought the company for one Swedish crown.
From that point on, Paradox started becoming a self-published company.
And once in a while, these games did fairly well.
We had our niche audience, they cost next to nothing to make,
and we kind of scrambled to survive during those harsh years.
And after a while, we kind of had a bit more success and decided,
hey, we're pretty good at publishing these weirdo niche games.
How about we find other weirdo niche games and publish those?
And that's what we started doing.
But we had a shoestring budget, so most of those games
were actually not that amazing.
So over the years, we've released about 120 games.
Most of them are not amazing.
We've had, that doesn't mean that people didn't work really
hard on a lot of these games, but we had to do what we had
to do to survive.
So that's a kind of a background that Paradox has had.
Nowadays, we've grown quite a bit.
We're still, we consider ourselves very much still a
niche publisher in that sense.
But we've had a lot of success.
Depending on what AAA game is failing currently on Steam,
we'd be considered top five or top 10 publisher, depending
how you do it.
And we've done that by sticking to our guns and kept doing
those kind of really weird niche strategy games.
Over the years, we've branched out.
And sometimes we've done stuff that's been more mainstream,
like Magicka.
And that did fairly well.
And that allowed us to keep pouring more resources into
our core business, which was the strategy games.
So nowadays, we have about 200 internal developers who are
making strategy games of different sorts.
And then we do a lot of publishing worldwide.
And we'll get back to the type of what that essentially is
meant for the design side of things.
Most recently, we released Surviving Mars last week,
which went well.
We also quite recently bought Triumph Studios, a Dutch
studio who makes the Age of Wonder series.
And two and a half years ago, we bought White Wolf from
CCP, who were not doing that much with the IPs.
We're big fans of vampires as well.
So over the years, we've kind of developed a secret sauce.
And it's not so secret, essentially, because we talk
about it all the time.
But we have a basic formula for what we consider is a
paradox game.
And as I've kind of tried to maintain focus for the
portfolio over the years, we try to stick to these pillars.
We feel that these pillars are the
the thing that makes a Paradox game a Paradox game.
And not only that, we think that these games,
the games that follow these pillars,
fundamentally result in a stronger business model.
And this is a really important aspect of this.
Most of us, I don't know about you, Hendrik, but I started in
the games industry because I wanted to make games.
And then I ended up not making a single game, of course.
But that's how things go.
Most of us, our first passion is maybe making games.
But then we quickly encountered the realities of
making games, which is ultimately it's a business.
It's a business and an art, but without paying for your work.
it, you know, very quickly becomes something else. So Fred, our CEO's main focus has always been
building a business and he's always built a business for the long term. It's always we always
view games and our function in the games industry as a marathon, not a sprint.
We're quite confident that if we make it to the tenth game,
it's probably going to be good.
The challenge is to get to keep to make games
so you get to that tenth game.
I don't know if anyone here plans on retiring
after they make their next game. I don't think so.
A lot of us want to keep making games.
So we retain focus on what makes the business model kind of work.
So we talk a lot about the business model,
and it's something that's deeply ingrained into our games.
It's a fundamental part of it.
And we feel that games that do follow these pillars actually just result in a stronger
business model that allows us to make more money.
And more money allows us to make more games and better games.
We think that these type of games are largely underserved,
and we also understand them fairly well.
And just briefly, I'm not going to run through them
in terrible detail, since most of you
are already familiar with the type of games we do.
But a paradox game should be infinitely replayable, ideally.
I just checked the numbers yesterday.
The median play time for Hearts of Iron 4 is 202 hours.
Median play time.
If you look at, again, Hearts of Iron.
About 34% of everyone who's bought the game has played it
more than 100 hours.
Half of the people who ever bought Hearts of Iron, since
it was launched almost two years ago, still
play it once a month.
So we have crazy retention numbers, mostly because I
don't think those players have anywhere else to go.
So the games need to be infinitely replayable.
We want the games to be intellectually challenging in some form.
We want them to challenge the mind, not the reflexes, although they do also have that
inaction component from time to time.
We want the games to cater to some kind of creative aspect.
We want you to tell us a story in our games rather than us tell you a story.
The games are not made beautiful necessarily by graphics.
but by the gameplay.
So we feel that graphics are there to serve a purpose.
They're not the ends themselves.
And we like the games to be accessible in some way or form
so you can get into them.
We fail quite at this often.
We also want the games to be something
you can nerd out about.
If you have real world knowledge about Flak 88 canons,
that should help you in the game somehow.
A number of games that I just want to show you briefly
that we think that really live up to these kind of pillars
and we draw a lot of inspiration from
and are humbled before the fact that we can learn a lot
from these type of games.
Literally every single game here that is not currently
published by us, a lot of them aren't,
we'd consider paradox games.
It's just failures on my part that I didn't manage
to sign Tera or Hearthstone.
That would have been a pretty hard game.
So I'm coming back to the business model.
And this is the really important part.
So by having a game that somebody can play 1,000 hours
in, if you've spent 1,000 hours playing the game, it's
probably not going to be that hard for me to convince you to
spend one more dollar in it.
If you look at the average spend you've had over the
lifespan of the game, you're getting quite your money's
worth compared to most other forms of entertainment.
I argue quite heavily, and nobody listens to me again, hope, luckily, that we should
put a big, fat, juicy number in the main menu of every single Paradox game which tells you
how much money you spend per hour of entertainment.
And I'll dare you to find any other premium game that can beat our numbers.
Maybe free to play games, but I don't think you can find that
in the premium space.
So we just see people spend more in games where they are
spending more time.
It sounds very simple, and it is true.
It's harder to make.
Games that do not focus on art or games that focus on systems and procedural stuff just get better mileage out of development resources.
SimCity 5 had about 80 artists that were working on it. City Skylines was made by a team of 8 people.
By not focusing on art, we focus on stuff that gives us more mileage.
By having modding in our games, we actually are pushing the
costs to other people, which are fans.
They create variants of our games.
Ultimately, we think that every single game has a Dota
or a DayZ locked inside of it somewhere.
But we as developers can't find it.
It can only be found once it's put in the hands of you
players, because you guys are much smarter than we are.
I mentioned that already.
Actually, duplicates, sorry.
We also.
By having games that follow this model, I actually see also recurring revenues.
People come back and spend money over time.
People that actually spent a thousand hours in our games are less likely to go to a competitor
as well because they're locked in because of the sunk cost fallacy or whatever reason.
If you invested that much time in the game, you don't want to let go of all that.
This is why I still play Magic the Gathering after 20 years.
And finally, these games are quite hard to make, which, at
least in the grand strategy space, we consider ourselves
not having any real competitors.
So this has led us to a position where we still keep
making niche games, but we know that niche games don't
mean small by any means.
Our basic philosophy is that if we create something that
is niche, we can make it small.
very pure and uncompromising. We will create such a satisfactory game experience in the
core audience that they can't find anywhere else. And they will, after a while, start
talking about the game in terms that you might not recognize. And then other people will
actually...
not maybe relate to the game, but they will relate to the player fantasies.
And while the core gameplay is pretty niche, the core fantasies that we have in our games,
the player fantasies, ultimately the reasons why people play the games are quite strong.
I'll give you a good example.
Crusader Kings 2 is about running a medieval royal house in an obscure part of Europe.
The game does not necessarily look that amazing, it's quite hard to play.
The game has still sold almost two million copies.
And the reason for that is that it has a pretty basic and relatable...
player fantasy, which is to rule as a king or queen.
And that's something everyone here has experienced or
fantasized about at some point during their childhood.
That fantasy is strong.
And through shows like Game of Thrones, that fantasy is
enhanced, and it's there, and people can relate to it.
Other examples is EVE Online, for instance.
You hear these amazing stories about EVE Online,
that people have gameplay experiences.
And you're like, that sounds super cool.
I want to experience that.
And people try it out.
And then it's like doing your taxes for three hours.
And then you maybe discover that, hey, I like doing
my taxes for three hours.
So one thing we know that niche does not
mean small by any measure of the word,
as long as we are uncompromising and really
try to stick to the basic tenet that a game for everyone
is a game for no one.
And I'm going to hand it over to Henrik in a bit.
But this model has developed over a few years.
Henrik will describe what our DLC model looks like today.
But in the past, it didn't work this way.
We used to release a game, and then six months later,
we had an expansion.
And that more or less replaced the old game.
And we did another expansion six months later,
and that made the last expansion obsolete.
So it was a very serial way of approaching things.
And we know that our games had a life cycle of about two,
three years, and then they became obsolete, more or less.
So I've harped on about the business model because it's something that drives a lot of the design decisions that we make,
and it's one of the fundamental things that ties the company together.
And we'll be able to come back and talk about, you know, as we wrap up,
on why we think this DLC model is literally the best thing for us as a money-making company,
but most importantly, it's the best thing for our fans and the players.
People who want more content and DLC from our products
are benefited by the fact that we work with our current DLC
model compared to the old one.
It's quite easy to look at the product page for Crusader Kings
and just see that, oh my god, these guys have $270 worth
of DLC.
They're evil.
Well, on the other hand, you could have bought the base game of Crusader Kings in 2012 and
never bought a single piece of DLC and you'd still see multiple updates every year and
tons of content for free.
So our usual kind of what we say to people is that you don't want the DLC, don't buy it.
And that works, you know, in some respects.
So I'll hand it over to you now.
Cool, thanks.
I'm going to harp on a little bit more about the business model, unfortunately, but stay with me.
This is from the perspective of the development studio.
So we've already mentioned that our fans are pretty hardcore.
They play our games for a very long time.
And they used to do that even in the old days, with Europa
Niversalis 2 and Victoria 1 and so on.
But we didn't really capitalize on that.
So the long tail existed, but we didn't make any money off
it, really, which is sad.
So we came up with this new DLC model. Instead of every other, every new release of an
expansion obsoleting the previous one, they would all be modular. So it's like going into a
candy shop and picking up the stuff you like into your little bag. And they would be able to
play nice with each other regardless of the combination of expansions or DLC that you
bought.
And we thought that games should have an indefinite life cycle.
If people keep playing it, we want to keep supporting it
and keeping it fresh and releasing new stuff for it.
We thought that, actually at the time
we didn't think that we learned that,
that we can go as high as 50-50 free and paid features,
when you think of our development time for an expansion
and the patch that goes along with it.
And that's fine.
People will perceive it as one whole experience anyway.
So these days we release both expansions and something we call immersion packs or story
packs, which are less heavy on the code content. And here is actually the current downloadable
content page on Steam for Crusader Kings 2. It's not that bad actually, because we've come to
the realization that we should bundle up our stuff. It used to be like 80 different DLCs
there, which was extremely off-putting and hard to navigate.
So we've taken some flak for the model,
but what I say to everyone is basically
that all these DLCs, even if you just buy one or two of them,
will allow us to keep developing and improving
the game for an indefinite period, basically,
which is great for everyone.
So instead of tailing on, we're tailing, or tailing off, we're actually tailing on. This is
monthly active users for Europa Rosales 4 since, what is it, July 2014. And as you can see, it
just keeps growing. It's pretty amazing.
I don't know if I know any similar game that has a similar curve, to be honest.
Our games models end up having a very similar curve to free-to-play games that are run as games as a service.
So our premium games come pretty close to actually just replicating that.
We're spending more, I think we're spending like triple the amount we're spending now, today, on Crusader Kings
compared to the year before the game was finished for release.
Yeah, it's pretty amazing.
I mean, these games are getting quite old now,
especially Crusader Kings 2.
And it still looks like this.
So Shams talked a lot about the business case.
And from my perspective or the studio perspective,
it's more like expansions drive up the monthly active users.
No question about that.
Old expansions keep selling so that the base game sales are
actually quite eclipsed by all the expansions and DLC
that we release.
And we want to cater to different types of players,
find new demographics and target groups for our existing games.
And of course, it gives us some sales and marketing flexibility
to do pre-order bonuses and other gimmicks
that we can throw out there.
And as for that first point, that expansions actually
drive up mall, here's that same graph again
with the various expansions and content packs
for European Resolvers 4.
And you can see that they coincide quite nicely
with all these bumps.
Now, there are some other bumps as well.
And they are actually sales campaigns and holidays
and stuff like that.
So there is a reason for them too.
And they probably contribute as well in keeping interest
and driving up monthly active users.
But expansions are extremely effective to get this tail
or curve that we like so much.
And as for old expansions that they keep selling,
here is two examples.
The Old Gods for Crusader Kings 2.
It was released in 2013, and you can see there
how many units in thousands that it's sold since then.
And we see the same pattern, even better actually,
for European Resolves 4 with Common Sense.
And when you have 15 expansions, that's starting to
get to be a lot of money.
And we want to cater to different play styles,
different types of players.
It's particularly suitable for a game like Crusader Kings 2,
which is almost a hybrid between a strategy game and an RPG,
in that different expansions can take a different tack.
Some of them can be pretty RPG.
Others can be more internal politics.
Some are even into the supernatural and fantasy stuff,
which is slightly controversial, but appreciated
by all our fans.
And about sales and marketing flexibility, well,
we can whip up things like this, some with more effort
than others.
And it's quite neat.
You can give it away at fan gatherings and stuff like that,
since it's all neatly modular and plays nice with the base
game.
But of course, there's a player case as well.
And I already mentioned that I think
it's good for players to see their beloved game live
pretty much forever, or for a very, very long time at least.
And also the fact that they can buy and pick and choose
whatever expansions they like.
It's just a sad fact that there are so many completionists out there who feel that they have to own everything and that we are thus, you know, doing a con job or something.
It's too bad.
So the idea with longevity anyway is that games should never feel abandoned.
We will keep improving the base experience as long as people keep playing the game and buying our expansions.
So even if you don't buy any expansions,
we're going to keep it fresh, and people
are going to notice that the game is actually getting better.
If you come back to it two years after stopping playing,
it will be a better experience.
And the other point was modularity.
You buy what you like.
And with our model, you can actually try things out in
multiplayer, because what the host is running,
everyone can use.
So that's pretty neat as well.
It goes back to learnings from watching our fellow Swedish
developers at Dice.
famously released map packs that divided the player community.
So we kind of decided that we want to have inclusive DLCs that allow more people to
experience the DLC without dividing the player community.
Yeah, it was also kind of a technical challenge to get that to work.
But I think it's a great, great idea.
Right, so let's take a look at the design approach here,
because it is quite a challenge to churn out
this many expansions and come up with new features that
are perceived well by players.
And I think that it's all about player perceptions, really.
It's not about what the developers want to do.
So first off, if you want to do this,
you've got to have a very solid base game.
And the trick there is to make the game feel absolutely
complete, even if you don't own any expansions.
It's going to feel, it's going to have to feel like a
complete experience, basically.
Or it'll come back to bite you.
And you're going to have some fun core loops.
That's what you should focus your efforts on, making sure
that the base game you release has excellent core loops that
are addictive and fun.
And you can save all those darlings, all the extras, for
later, because you can rest easy in the knowledge that you
will probably release a lot of expansions.
Of course, you also need to prepare for that fact.
You should think about all the expansions you want to release
over at least the first couple of years.
So you should have design outlines for that and the code
base to support it.
And if you boil it down to two principles, when you design
features for expansions that people pay for, principle
number one is that they have to be visible.
It has to have a visible impact, or people will not
understand that you put a lot of effort into it.
So no matter how much work you do under the hood, it's not
going to be well received unless it's
immediately visible.
So here's an example of that.
We added something called Aegis to Europa and Rosalis 4.
Once you install that expansion, you
can immediately see in the main interface
that there's a little thing there.
You're in this age of reformation, for example.
The other main principle is that good expansion features should be atomic in a way. They
should be standalone, unentangled, and independent from as many systems as you can
possibly make them. This can be very hard, of course, but if you can't make the features
atomic and standalone, you should put them in the free patches and updates instead.
One big no-no, another tempting thing, as a designer especially,
is to add a paid feature that you don't
want to build on in a subsequent expansion after that.
That's going to be very tricky.
You're going to be limiting the number of people who actually
can buy and enjoy that second upgrade to those features.
So don't paint yourself into a corner.
And with that in mind, we have found
that there are certain types of features that are
excellent material to make paid.
First off, features that add new ways of playing,
of achieving old goals in a new way.
Say that you take territory through military means
in the base game, but then you add
a way of doing it diplomatically in an expansion as well.
progression is super good as well. If you can add a system where you can level up or gain new
ranks or rank up in some old system, that's also perfect. It's pretty stand alone atomic.
And then there's customization stuff, like we made a DLC for Crusader Kings 2.
It's a barber shop, basically, where you can change hair and beard of your character.
And it's a little thing, but it's kind of cool and it's extremely standalone and not
entangled in anything else.
Purely cosmetic.
And then there's faction unlocks, which is, it's not just us doing this, I think other companies
have also found that it's perfect for this. And the reason is that there is a risk when you add
more features to the game, that you get feature creep, the interface gets cluttered with new
things, but if you do faction unlocks that doesn't happen because it adds a different way of
playing the game with mutually exclusive interfaces basically.
And then you can do quality of life UI things.
And I have an example of that coming up.
So here's an example of a faction unlock in Crusader
Kings 2 on release.
You could only play Christians.
And that had a distinct play style.
But then with expansions we added things like Muslims in sort of Islam.
And with this expansion, the old gods, we made it possible to play pagans.
And it's a completely different experience.
The Christians mostly play nice and abide by diplomatic rules.
They have to use... they have to have a reason to go to war and all that boring jazz.
But the pagans, they're all about raiding and pillaging
and just declaring war, taking concubines, having a good time.
We also added 200 more years to the gameplay,
which was quite appreciated.
But the cool thing about this is if you don't play as the pagans,
it's the same old thing.
So the pagans are a different way
of experiencing the same game.
Here's another example.
It's the diplomatic macro planner
from European Missile List 4.
It basically gathers up all diplomacy in one place,
and it was very appreciated.
So it's a new interface that you get with this expansion
mandate of heaven.
But it's very separate from everything else.
It's just a convenience thing.
You don't have to have it.
The game works just as well without it,
which means that it's standalone and very modular.
So a perfect feature for a paid expansion.
And there's one more example of progression.
Instalaris, which has a really cool tech system.
The technology system Instalaris is basically
a collectible card game almost.
So it's very easy to slot in new technologies.
And what we did here is basically we added a new layer
of late game technologies for progression and ranking up.
And in this case, it's very visible in some cases,
like the Planet Destroyers and the Titan class spaceships.
All right, so those are some good types of features
that you can actually charge money for.
But there are also bad features.
And trust me, we've made plenty of these as well,
plenty of mistakes.
So you can do these things, but the point
is you cannot charge money for them.
So you shouldn't try to make core gameplay changes that
alter the experience for players who have the expansion.
That's a big no-no.
You shouldn't try to make or charge money for minor improvements. Balance and bug fixes of
course should be free. And you should not try to make features that mess with a thousand
other features in the game. That's a pretty bad idea.
So here's an example from CK2.
In Crusader Kings 2, armies are not standing around on the map,
and they are mobilized or called up when you need them.
So they're peasant levies, essentially.
But I thought it would be a really cool idea
if the professional troops that actually existed at the time
could also be represented in the game somehow,
and that as the eras progress, the peasant levies
would be phased out, and people would start
using retinue troops more.
However, while this was well received,
it also messed with the core gameplay in significant ways.
It's completely upset the balance of warfare,
if you had the expansion or not.
And it was also a feature that we really
wanted to build on in subsequent expansions,
but we couldn't because we painted ourselves
into a corner.
And here's a more recent example, a Blitz combat tactic from Hearts of Iron IV, which caused pretty much an uproar on the forums.
In itself, it should be pretty suitable as a paid feature, but it was kind of a minor thing.
It was one combat tactic among many, and it was perceived that this should have been part of the base game.
It was also unfortunate that it was called Blitz.
You know, it's pretty iconic for a World War II game
to have a Blitz command or combat tactic.
So it kind of backfired on us.
We've also done some entangled features.
This is a system we added in EU4 called Estates.
It's basically internal political factions
that create gameplay for you as a ruler.
You need to keep these political factions happy,
or they will start causing you all kinds of troubles.
But they can also give you bonuses.
The problem with this feature, or one of the problems with it,
is that it kind of messes around with every other thing
in the game.
whenever we release something new, we have to consider, well, what will happen to the
estate's mechanic if we do this, etc. So, pretty bad idea. Should have been free.
Which brings us to free features.
There is nothing wrong with this.
And I think we spend at least 50% of our development time
actually doing free features.
As long as you have a strong theme for your expansion,
they are perceived as a whole thing.
The free and the paid part make for one experience.
And that's also how I see it as a designer.
I really ideally want people to kind of mix them up and not
know what is free and what is paid.
Doesn't really work that way, but you can dream.
So free features, using them, you
can replace old mechanics that you don't like much.
You can mess around with the core gameplay.
And people will still perceive that the game
is kept fresh and cool, and you're doing interesting shit.
So everything I said was bad in a paid feature, you can
probably do as a free feature.
There are some other pitfalls that don't have to do specifically with the types of features.
You should remember to stick to what the game is. This is also something we've forgotten sometimes.
And what is the game? Well, it's partly what we think it should be, what we thought when we created the game originally.
But it's also what the players think that the game is.
And the biggest mistake you can make
is probably add new restrictions on players.
Now, there is a case to be made that our games, at least CK2,
is hard to learn and easy to master.
And that's kind of the pyramid upside down, right?
So I had the brilliant idea that let's crank up the challenge
and make the game a bit harder.
So we added defensive alliances and other things to the game
that were supposed to crank up the challenge.
But people just felt that they'd been
put in a straitjacket instead.
And that's not a good place to be.
So don't mess with agency, the player's freedom to act.
And then there's, of course, feature overload and UI
clutter.
And it's a challenge because it completely contradicts the high visibility requirement
of paid features, right?
But if you have a lot of visible features, what are you going to end up with?
Well, it's going to be a pretty overloaded interface.
Another huge mistake is to, as developer, think that, yeah, I like the Black Sheep Turks.
You know, we should expand on that experience.
It's an awesome faction.
But unfortunately, most players will not see it that way.
They have their preferences.
And we know that there are certain countries that are a
lot more popular than others.
Germany.
Germany, Prussia, the Confederate States of America,
the Eastern Roman Empire, all of these are super popular.
For some reason, don't ask me why.
But when we do an expansion about India or something, yeah,
no.
So just don't go there.
It's a sad fact.
So what actually, what do players value?
Well, initially we thought that, hey, let's
look at Steam review scores.
That's a great metric.
And it was a pretty good metric originally, but then less and
less so over time as there was more and more rage about our
DLC model particularly.
So there's a correlation between steam review score and
actual revenue, but it's weaker than you might expect.
So as designers, we look more at actual revenue now than we
do the steam review scores.
And we also came up with a neat little formula or spreadsheet
that we employ to estimate the value for money
for our expansions.
So these are some CK2 expansions.
And we've divided up the features into different sizes.
And each size gives you a different sort of score.
So we then sum up that score, and we divide it
by the price point.
and then we get a pretty arbitrary value for money. It works pretty well. We want that value
for money value to be at 2 or above ideally. But as you can see some of our more popular
expansions are actually way below that or a bit below that. So old gods had 1.8, it still did
extremely well. So the flaw with this formula is it doesn't really consider the free
features that we release along with the paid ones.
I mean, I know for a fact that the Reapers do, which didn't really contain that much paid
content, was extremely well received, mostly due to the free stuff. So people keep mixing this
up and it's to our advantage, of course. So we're still working on improving this formula or
spreadsheet.
And now we come to Johan's part of this presentation.
So sadly, I'm not going to do it justice.
But it has to do with other types of challenges that are
not related to design specifically.
About the architecture.
Well, the code base will keep evolving all the time.
And that's interesting in many ways.
But it's going to help, at least in our position it
helps, because we have so many live projects.
We can do a lot of improvements in the engine.
We have the close of its engine, and we have a middle
layer called Gemini.
And if you can do improvements there, it's going to benefit
all the games.
And Johan really wanted to stress that you should keep the code simple and readable and not
over engineer it. And that's very important for us because in our organization we have to
move the programmers around a lot and you know they need to understand the code pretty much at
a glance. So don't get too clever.
You also got to keep the code maintainable.
And I know one thing he wanted to bring up was a simple
little trick.
If you have a get function, for example, you can pass
along a text string as an argument or
pointer to get the tooltip.
So you only have one function.
You following, Chance?
No.
You only have one function to work with.
And you don't have to have a separate tooltip function.
And you should try to have a clear programming guideline
or standard that everyone follows.
As for the technology itself, well, it's
a virtual file system.
We treat our DLCs exactly like mods.
They're pretty much the same thing as far as the game is
concerned.
They're packages that are treated as modular changes.
And you can toggle them on or off at load time, which is
convenient.
So if you buy House Lords or full plate music or whatever,
you can turn it off if you don't like it or if you get
tired.
And then there's the process, the project
management of it all.
And it's very important, of course, to plan ahead.
should have the design ready in time. The designers should be,
you know, one step ahead all the time. And you should have a
scalable UI that is easy to work with and make room for more
stuff because you will add more stuff to the UI. It's
guaranteed. And it's important to remember that you have to
repay tech debt.
We have a pretty aggressive schedule
when it comes to releasing these expansions
and we don't have an infinite amount of people.
So sometimes we have to cut some corners
and accept the fact that we will have to do some hacks
and hard-coded solutions.
And these accumulate and get worse over time.
So it's worthwhile to take some time to catch up.
And we usually schedule a couple of weeks
in between certain expansions to catch up on our tech debt.
Most importantly though, you need to understand your players.
And if you can use reasonable metrics, do so.
You know, if you have telemetry, use it.
If you don't have telemetry, add it.
And you should listen to your hardcore fans.
to some degree, I suppose, don't listen to them too hard
because they are a pretty vocal minority.
But as long as they keep it constructive and positive,
you should listen to their stories and what they tell you.
And you will understand them, probably,
if you play the game yourself.
And sadly, not all people actually play the game
and enjoy it.
So how can you expect your players to do so?
Right, so if I were to summarize this somewhat unfocused
subject, it would be keep your design modular and stand alone.
And this is for the paid features, of course.
And you should think about.
player perceptions more than the time you spend developing
something or how hard or complex it is.
The only thing that matters is how players perceive it.
So remember to make your features visible and to be
perceived as giving high value.
And you need to have a maintainable architecture.
There's probably something here to add on the business
side of things as well.
I think that you touched on something that's really
interesting in the sense that we built the company by having
a very transparent and open and very close dialogue and
relationship with a lot of our fans.
We try to listen to them.
We have our forums that have over a million active users.
And what's happened over the years is that not only has
a lot more people have come into the Paradox ecosystem
that are not familiar with the games or don't...
Everyone has their different types of stories.
So the vocal minority is...
They get a critical mass in their voices.
That's heard in a completely different way today.
And it's heard differently because they also have tools
which allows them to get...
hurt. So on one hand, I mean, we're getting a lot of complaints on the DLC model. On the
other hand, we have more people than ever that not only buy the stuff, but they keep
buying it. And, you know, we end up with a silent majority that are in the game, enjoying
the features, and not shitposting on the forums.
So there's always this balance of trying to find,
how do we keep in touch with the players
and listen to what they have to say
and balance that out against.
what we're doing and what the silent paying majority is doing, because at the end of the
day, they are the people we need to please, because they keep paying us.
If somebody doesn't agree with some of our practices, it's somewhat hard.
There's another interesting point that I think we could make as well.
I took the point here, is that I can't stress enough, and I've said it a million times,
but it's really what I love.
It's the business model.
Games that follow these give us a robust protection from
changes in the market.
And I'll give you a good example.
When Steam rolled out their refund policy, and for those
of you not familiar with it, the Steam refund policy said
that if you played the game for less than two hours, you
could refund it, no questions asked.
And this was rolled out without informing a single
publisher or developer, as far as I know, and nobody I've
asked had heard of it before.
And they even had a big grace period of six months back, you could just refund anything.
If you had a game, let's say you had an indie game that was very narrative and story driven,
you could start and finish it in less than two hours, you were utterly and completely screwed over.
by that policy change from Steam's side.
It's ultimately a good policy change.
It protects the consumer and makes our positions as gamers a lot better,
but that developer's business model is completely screwed.
And when it comes to a Paradox game,
well, good luck getting past the main menu in two hours.
So it's a silly example of how the business model or the way
we do things actually allow us a fair bit of protection
from stuff on the outside.
I think a lot of us have seen the
The image of Mona Lisa being cut into small pieces and they're selling the pieces in separate
pieces as an analogy of how games are destroyed today and discrete parts being sold.
Pieces that people should be in the game and belong in the game.
And I don't want to get into this big discussion about entitlement, but it's something that
we end up thinking a lot about and talking a lot about.
It's also feasibility.
If that was true, it would take us 10 years to develop a game.
And it would look bad at the time we released it.
And ultimately, I think that whenever
we have a good balance between quality of life improvements
that we would give away for free and do screw-ups where we charge
for features that feel like they should be in the game,
that's where we get more hate.
But ultimately, I mean, the game is called Crusader Kings, not Muslim rulers.
So I don't feel that necessarily if we charge, if we put that into the kind of Mona Lisa DLC like we described,
that's not necessarily a comparison that I feel is kind of fair.
But it's, perception is ultimately reality and I think that...
The issue we have today, perhaps, with a lot of people that are upset with the DLC model,
is a lack of us explaining the rationale for why the model exists,
and what, ultimately, what kind of additional value they get thanks to this model.
A lot of people might just now simply just not want it.
Other people in the community complain that we just do too
much stuff that's nice, and they want everything, but they
can't afford it.
And we should stop doing stuff, therefore.
But I have a hard time getting behind that argument.
Coming back to my original statement about the key metric
of having a number in the main menu that tells you how much
you spent per hour of entertainment, I think we
should really do it every time the
complaints become too loud.
I even argue that we should increase
the price of the game.
And this is, of course, everyone just wants to shoot me when I say this.
But arguably, if you bought Crusader Kings six years ago,
it's a much, much, much better game today.
And we're still only charging 40 bucks for it.
People go nuts when we don't lower the price of the game.
I think we should raise it.
It has arguably more value.
And the concept of we should lower the price of things over time
because it's old.
it doesn't hold up to me.
People, I think, look at how,
you know, and this is the reality,
we have to deal with people's and players' behaviors
and conditioning through other games,
and then they apply that to the lens of our game.
And it doesn't really jive to me.
But again, I can't change perception and reality.
I can just try to explain the model
and show them how they get additional value.
And I can, black and white, show why
we would have never been able to create all this cool content
if it wasn't for the fact that we'd created all the DLC.
Cool.
I don't think we have anything else to add to that.
We'd be happy to take questions.
Hi, my name is Carl Henrik.
And two years ago, Johan played me for your coding style.
Sorry about that.
I worked with him a long time ago.
My question is, how do you manage
QA-ing so many different combinations of the game?
So the question is, how do we manage
to QA so many different combinations of the game?
well I don't have a perfect answer for you except that our QA department is doing a really good
job. But they have like a smoke test protocol that they go through where they don't exactly
try every combination of DLCs. That would be redundant because we're confident enough in
um the architecture that most of them will work together. But they have a protocol for that.
Hi, I'm Oliver. I've really enjoyed Paradox Games over the years. My question is, how do you plan for what you want your modders to be capable of, knowing that some of your community won't have all the expansions, and the modders will probably be assuming you have all the expansions? I know in my own mod work that I just click all the boxes, yes, you must have this, this, and that. How do you plan for that?
All right, so if I understood you right, your question is,
how do we plan for modders wanting to use features from
all expansions or different expansions?
Well, that's a really good question.
We actually talk about it a lot right now.
If we should, for example, have the cosmetic stuff be in
the base game, so basically for free, but it's not shown
in the game unless you have the expansion.
So that's one approach.
And I think we're moving towards that.
So for example, event pictures from expansions might be in
the patch, in the base game.
but you don't see them. But modders can use them then for whatever mod they want to do. So it's a
complicated situation if you will. We don't think further than that at the moment but it's a
good question.
Hello there. My question is, when working with other developers for titles like Tyranny or Surviving Mars, how do you work with those studios to have their DLC model?
So the question was, how do we work with third-party studios when it comes to the business model and DLC model?
So a bit of insight on how it works. We get about a thousand, I get about a thousand pitches every year and we say no to almost all of them.
We end up maybe signing five games per year.
The process that we have, obviously being a niche publisher, ends up saying...
We only do games that are RPG management or strategy games ultimately.
Another factor is that we only work with people who buy into this and think this is a great way of working.
We never try to force down IP or business models or culture or way of working with developers.
But what we do is that we explain how we work
and why we work that way.
And if that's something that's attractive to people,
they pitch and approach us on the same basis.
And we learn from their experience
and try to change it.
So what we do is that we do more or less this talk.
But we do it with each and every developer.
And we do it many times over to try to help educate and help
people understand why it's a more.
robust way of doing things.
And especially for the development partner studios,
this means that they'll be funded for six years
working on a project.
instead of making a game and then hope it sells so they can
keep working.
This fundamentally gives more job security
to the third party developers that we work with.
So hopefully, they think it's an attractive model
for that reason alone.
But ultimately, we never sign a game
unless it has this potential.
There are exceptions.
We published Pillars of Eternity with Obsidian, and
it's a linear narrative story-driven game.
And I said, not every game lives up to the pillars
perfectly, as the grand strategy games
that these guys make.
But we do exceptions.
for the benefit of thinking long term,
we'll be able to make a game that fits the game more.
So Pillars of Eternity, while it doesn't match the pillars
quite perfectly, the second game we
made with Obsidian Tyranny, we felt
lived up to the pillars more and should
be able to adapt to this business model better.
But that didn't quite play out either.
Turns out it's really expensive making RPGs.
So happy to hear that.
Thank you.
Hi, my name is Rutger.
I work at Abbey Games.
We also make strategy games, so this
sounds really interesting to us to be
able to support the game for longer than we can do now.
So I have experienced this new DLC model of yours.
I bought Hearts of Iron 4 at launch,
and I bought a few DLCs, the ones I liked.
Thank you.
And I felt it worked really well.
But I was wondering how you can deal with, for example, players
that come in late, basically.
that enter the cycle halfway through.
I have experienced this myself with Europa Universalis.
I was like, I want to play this game.
But there are so many things to choose from, and I don't know.
what to do, basically.
That's a great question.
The question was, so what happens with the players that
don't get on the train from the get-go when it's just $40
by get into it now?
Somebody who comes to the Crusader Kings page, and this
is a really good point.
A lot of the hate, I think, comes from those people
because they're just overwhelmed with what they're
seeing, because they've been conditioned, again, by other
games that I'm getting an incomplete experience unless I
buy the other stuff.
But it's still a car you're getting.
Leather seats is not a part of the core experience.
That's the kind of comparison.
And I think that there's an issue there.
And this is something we talk to Steam, too, all the time
about how can we create product pages that more clearly explain
to people what is necessary to be able to play the game.
The most common thread I see on our subreddit
is which expansions are essential.
And I wish that people said, you don't need to get any of them.
They're optional.
And that's the half answer some of the times.
But clearly, you get a better Crusader Kings experience
if you buy more expansions.
We design it that way.
But it's a good enough experience at that level.
So in part, we need to do a better job of explaining
this in our product pages.
But another part of it is also.
you know, and this comes back to the business model, a lot of the times people come to the
pages when they want to buy a game, and this applies to anything we do, most of the time
we just, we've consciously made the decision that we want to buy the product. That's the
main pain of actually making the purchase, we want to talk about psychology. Once somebody's
made the choice and conscious effort to, that they want to buy the game, what they're then
presented with, which of these different options will give me the greatest value?
And if you're looking at one that is priced at about $280,
which is the total of the CK2 DLCs.
You kind of feel like, I can't afford that, that's too much.
And you kind of feel like you're losing out.
So there's another layer of psychological pain.
But we do counter this by having frequent and quite deep
discounts and sales through promotions.
So that person that comes back and says, holy shit,
everything is 75% off, they're buying that DLC, the total
package that would have been $300 is much cheaper, but
we're still making a healthy chunk of change.
So one more question, they tell us.
But we'll be available for questions outside afterwards.
Thank you.
Hi, I'm Scott.
I have a kind of similar question.
You mentioned the phrase, hard to learn, easy to master.
Do you worry that with the infinite life cycle that you
mentioned, that problem will just be exacerbated?
You ask so the question was do we think that the games become harder and harder to learn over time?
Yeah, as you add more and more features even free ones for example. Yeah, well, that's a that's an excellent question as well
And it's definitely true rights, but that's another reason to keep
To do like faction unlocks and to add new new ways of playing that are
preferably mutually exclusive with other ways of playing,
rather than overloading players with oh, so much stuff.
So if you start as a pagan, it's still a manageable experience.
And if you start as a Christian, it's also a manageable
experience.
But when you put all these things together,
it's a rich game with a lot of different ways to play.
So I prefer that way of doing things in general.
And I think that we've gone a little bit too far with the
stuff we've added to both CK2 and perhaps
even more so EU4.
But you're correct in the fact that it's a greater challenge.
We need and do put more emphasis on learning,
teaching at the game.
The problem is we created Tutorial one time, and perhaps
the best example of where we failed horribly has been
Crusader Kings 2, or even Victoria 2, I think.
where everyone knew that the tutorial was broken
and you couldn't finish it for like a good nine months.
But we didn't do anything about it
because that's not how people learn the game.
They go on YouTube and watch Let's Play series.
So it's been really lazy on our part.
Yeah, I mean, we've learned to do things properly
with, I think, the Stellaris tutorial,
which is a huge step forward.
And that's the way we're going to do stuff from now on.
As well as in the future games that we do.
Thanks, guys.
Love you.
Thanks so much, guys.
Thanks.