is improving the culture of critique,
communicating across disciplines.
It's a companion talk to a talk I gave last year.
I'll talk a little bit more about that in a moment.
But why is this needed?
Why do we need to talk about critique?
Why do we need to talk about
communicating across disciplines?
You know, both of these things are part of our daily life in game design, but they're
often things that we don't really focus on.
This is also true often in art school, as both a student and teacher, I often found
that we assumed a lot about critique without ever really focusing on it.
I'll talk about that in a minute.
But when we don't focus on it, and when it goes poorly, as unfortunately it all too often
does, our efficiency goes down, morale certainly goes down, and especially when we think about
communicating across disciplines.
we start to lose good ideas that aren't being communicated,
ideas that come from elsewhere, from others,
from otherness that we miss.
And when we miss good ideas,
the quality of our work goes down.
So these issues are really important,
and they're issues that are certainly very dear to my heart.
Before I started working in harmonics,
As an artist, I spent about 10 years as a teacher.
I taught at the Royal School of Design.
I taught at the New York Academy, among other schools.
And during that time and since that time,
I've continued teaching in lots of workshops
at places like the Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fisher Price,
Turbine, also at Harmonics.
And throughout all this teaching,
One of the things that has been, was always really important to me,
and something I loved thinking about, was critique.
How do we assess each other's work?
How do we talk about each other's work?
It seemed to be something that a lot of other art teachers
didn't focus on.
They tended to have a kind of throw the students in the water
and let's see how they swim approach.
That's, I don't want to, that's not the case of everyone.
There are certainly a lot of art professors and teachers
who also think about this a lot,
but it was something I really enjoyed thinking about.
And it was something that I brought over when I started working at Harmonix.
And over the last eight or nine years, I've had the real pleasure to first start off as
a character artist on Rock Band 3.
I was the lead environment artist on Fantasia, Music Evolved, returned to some character
work for Rock Band 4, and then back doing...
environmental stuff with some wonderful abstract,
musically reactive, abstract sculptures
and harmonics music of VR.
And more recently I've been doing some UI work
on Sing Space, the karaoke game from Harmonix
that'll be coming out really soon.
It was being demoed down in the Unity booth.
Some of you may have had a chance to try it this week.
In addition to that, outside of work, I've been, I was a co-founder of a group called
Secret Portal.
We're really interested in using VR in public spaces and really finding ways for people
in physical and virtual worlds to interact with each other.
And we've done a number of installations and theatrical performances at the Museum
of Fine Arts in Boston over the last three years.
So, last year I gave a talk called Maximizing Critique, and that talk really focused on
strategies for giving and receiving feedback kind of on individual levels, and really focused
on this idea that everyone is responsible in this conversation.
If you're giving or receiving, there are ways to make that conversation more valuable.
This year I'm expanding from that and having a companion piece to that, which is pulling
the camera out a little bit and looking at the overall culture of critique, especially
how we communicate with disciplines other than our own.
There'll be a little bit of overlap, but they're really companion pieces.
Was anyone at my talk last year?
Oh, great.
Thanks for coming back.
There'll be a little bit of overlap, but not much.
I'm really trying to cover a lot of new ground.
And if you weren't at the talk last year, you don't need to.
Neither is a prerequisite for the other.
So let's talk a little bit about communicating across disciplines.
We were all in our own disciplines. Here's a kind of variety of them that
exist in most game studios and within that there's a lot of areas where we
overlap, where it's easy for us to communicate, we share common ground.
But there's a lot of places where we don't overlap. We may have different
languages for describing the same thing. We have different kinds of experiences,
different points of view, and that is when it's really hard to communicate.
In many ways it's almost like we're communicating across cultures.
and that's when communication can break down.
However, it's during those moments
that communication is the most important for us to have
because that is when we bring our difference
into the conversation, our unique point of view.
So ironically, the most difficult conversations
are the most important to have.
Maybe that's not erotic, maybe that's just part of life.
But in any case, it's certainly the case here.
And so, now here's a little bit of a review from last year.
I'll kind of go over it, not too long,
but I just want to make sure we're on the same page
on a couple things.
As a teacher, I used to always ask my students,
especially our freshman students, what is a crit?
Because that's what we call it in art school,
we call it a crit, we don't call it,
and I said, what is a crit?
What is this thing short for
that we're about to engage on?
And many of them didn't know.
Many thought it was, well, is it short for criticize?
Some thought that.
Some thought it was short for critique.
And for me, it's a very important distinction
between those two words.
And it gave us a chance at the very beginning
of their semester, at the very beginning of their freshman
year, or sometimes in their senior year
when this would come up even.
What is that difference and why is it important?
Well, to criticize from my point of view
is about more personal preference.
It's about being more judgmental.
It's about a first response.
It's very surface.
It's very subjective.
Whereas critique is much more objective.
It's about being more analytical.
It's about taking a thing apart, looking at all its parts,
finding out how they work together,
and then maybe trying to put it back together again.
That's critique.
And you know what?
Critique doesn't even need to be judgmental.
You don't even need to be judgmental to have
a great critique.
If you take something apart and understand how it works,
you've served a great, that's a very valuable act.
But you can also then be reflective on that process and in being reflective start to think
how is this thing working in the ways it can, how is it not being working in ways it should
and then you can start to be not so much judgmental as assessing.
How is this thing working?
And that's where the judgments come out of but those judgments are then based on a foundation
of knowing the thing on its own terms.
That's critique, right?
That's very different than criticism.
And as I talk about critique throughout the rest of my talk
today, that's the type of activity
that I'll be thinking about and referring to.
One last thing from last year.
We often think of critical conversations
as being a kind of one-way street,
going from giver to receiver.
And I think that's very much not the case
if it's a two-way street.
Everyone needs to be involved.
Everyone is responsible for how the conversation goes.
If you're receiving the information,
you need to figure out how you're receiving it well
and what you can do to improve that information
you might be receiving.
I covered a lot of that in my talk last year.
And if you're giving the information,
you also need to be thinking about
how is this person receiving it?
Am I presenting it in a way that's the best,
that will help them understand it most clearly?
And so you need to be thinking about how your work will be received.
Let me give you a quick example about a time at Harmonix where I wasn't doing that as well
and we needed, it became a problem.
That was in the early days of Fantasia Music Evolved, we created all of these gray box
layouts which we found a really fast way, just literally using gray boxes, to create
them in engine so we could really be experiencing them with the Kinect.
And it was great for us, but nobody outside our team could understand what the hell we
were showing them.
It was completely abstract.
We knew it, but they didn't.
And so we couldn't get good critical feedback from them because they didn't know what they
were looking at.
So we had to make sure we brought in a concept artist to do a wonderful draw over on them
so that it became clear, and then we could start getting great feedback because people
understood what they were looking at.
But just a quick example to talk about this idea of thinking from the other person's point
of view.
How are they going to be receiving your information, and have you given them enough information
so that they can understand it in order to give you some good critical feedback?
Which brings me to the big theme of, not the day,
I don't know how the rest of your day has been,
the big theme of this hour, and that theme is empathy.
You need to be empathic when you,
oh see this is John, and that's not empathy.
That's not it.
That's wrong.
Empathy is not being overly sympathetic,
caring about someone, bleeding heart.
Those things are important.
We have those sort of a role in our life,
but that's not empathy.
It's not empathy at all.
So that raises, what is empathy?
Empathy is the ability to imagine
from another point of view.
So if you think, you know, John here,
he is thinking about this, the person in the painting,
in their world, in the world of that person,
how would they see other people?
What would those other people look like?
Trying to see from that point of view,
but however, we can't ever really fully do that.
We try to do that, our imagination is blurry,
the image we have.
Often it's even missing pieces.
We try to see something from someone else's point of view.
And that's an important part of empathic communication.
Because when we realize that we're trying to see
from another person's point of view
and we are failing to do that,
there are holes in our image,
we are then in an inquisitive mindset.
Because now we're ready to start asking them questions
to fill in those missing holes.
That's the core of empathic communication.
Trying to imagine and trying to improve that image
through the act of engaging with another person.
And so in the course of preparing for this talk,
I spent some time talking to many
of the different departments at Harmonics.
And my goal was to find out,
how do we feel we are perceived by others?
Because often that perception shows some of the,
some of the ways in which we are misperceived by others, the ways in which we are seen that we don't care to be seen by others,
that are actually false,
the kinds of ways that are not good to think about when we actually enter into a conversation.
So here are a few of those that I found as I talked to people around harmonics.
The artist often felt that people feel it takes us too long to make our work.
The designers often felt that they just are creating work for others.
They don't feel that way themselves, that's how they feel other people see them in a pejorative
way.
The producers felt that people think they don't care about quality, that they only care
about the deliverable.
Programmers felt that sometimes people think they just are there to kill good ideas.
QA said, you know, sometimes we feel that people think that we're just unskilled slackers.
people in operations and in my course of talking to people in harmonics, at one point I realized,
wait a minute, I've been talking to a lot of people who are involved in my initial team,
the creative process, but there's a lot of other people in this company that I also involve
in critical feedback on, critical feedback on different levels.
In operations there's one of them, people in the IT department, people who are admins,
they deal with critical feedback all the time.
Let me bring them into this conversation also.
And they felt that, you know, other people often see them as people who do things that
are trivial and easy.
And the executives often felt that people see them as just giving disruptive directives.
They want to just be helpful, but when they say something, people think, oh, it came from
an executive.
We've got to stop everything and just do that.
And that's the way in which they feel that they're misrepresented in the way that people
see them.
Now, so these are the ways that often people feel that they are seen.
which probably shows there's some kind of truth in there,
probably means a lot of people do see people that way.
And if that is the case,
and if we go into a conversation with someone from QA,
with a designer, with an executive,
and we have this notion in mind.
no empathic communication is gonna happen.
Empathic communication has already failed.
We've already failed to have
a really productive conversation.
But rather, we should start thinking about
how people wanna be seen.
So it was my second question I asked people
when I was talking with them.
How do you wanna be seen by people, other people?
And the artist said, you know,
we wanna think in terms of aesthetics and experience.
and the designers said, well, we are really able
to help contextualize our work.
You know, these are the ways that people wanna be seen.
They're also the things that people
from different departments feel they bring
their unique perspective to the creative effort.
The producers said, you know, we really facilitate process,
we want people to see that in us.
The programmers said, we want people to realize
that we think in terms of systems,
and it's a really unique and special way of thinking
that is helpful for everyone to understand.
QA said, we want people to understand that we actually have a robust understanding of
the game across all disciplines, so we're a great resource for everyone to really help
understand how things function in lots of different ways.
Operations said, we really work to create a better work environment so that everyone
can be working more efficiently.
And the executives said that we enjoy contributing to the process, and we want people to understand
that.
We want people to understand that we're just contributors.
We aren't actually being directive necessarily.
Sometimes we have to be directive, and we need to find ways to clarify that.
as the executives told me.
So these are ways that people want to be seen.
And if we can go into our conversations thinking that way,
how does this person wanna be seen
and seeing them in that light,
then right away a lot of the empathic communication
is gonna take care of itself.
Because empathic communication is vital to everything I'm going to talk about over the
next rest hour.
It's vital to efficient critical feedback.
It's vital to communicating across disciplines.
But there is a shortcut.
So get this and then you can, if you leave, no don't leave.
But here's the shortcut that is really helpful, that will also help kind of go over all the
other strategies I'm going to talk about.
And that is that remember the behavior is shaped by a wish to be respected, be heard,
and be valued.
One of the things that used to really annoy me and scrape against me when I'd hear teachers
do it when I was a student or hear of other teachers doing it when I was a teacher in
art school was they would say to the students, okay, we're going to have a critique today.
You've got to leave your ego at the door.
In some context that might work.
If it's a context in which that teacher
has given those students strategies
to effectively leave there, he goes at the door.
But often that's not the case.
Often they're just putting the whole onus on the student.
And here's why I hated that.
I don't use the word hate lightly.
I really disliked that because.
it put the students in a position where now, you know, we care about our work.
Everyone cares about their work.
It is hard to hear that your work isn't working well.
Right. That's the case for everyone.
You know, if you look if that makes you
feel giddy to hear that your work stinks, then you're some weird exception.
And but.
So it hurts, right? That's just the way it is.
Now, if you have been told you need to leave the ego at the door, what's going to happen?
You hear your work isn't working efficiently, and now you feel bad because your work is failing,
but you also feel bad because you're feeling bad.
Right?
Oh, shit, I'm supposed to leave my ego at the door.
Everyone else here can do it.
The teacher told me I should do it.
I shouldn't feel bad.
And now I feel bad about feeling bad.
And my brain is all in this.
And guess what I'm not hearing?
I am not hearing the feedback.
It's not coming through.
It's not being communicated.
And so these things aren't just about being a bleeding heart.
Oh, we've got to care about people's feelings.
We've got to think about them, which is true.
But that's not the reason for this.
The reason for this is if we're not
thinking about these things.
If we're not validating people and making them feel heard, then they will be unable
to hear the really vital feedback that we need to give them.
When you do this, you can be harsher in your critique than you can if you don't, than
you are able to if you don't.
So this isn't about just being nice.
It's actually about being harsh in your critiques and rough in your critiques, but having the
foundation upon which that can be accepted and understood.
So we're going to talk about two different strategies, two different areas of strategy,
types of strategies over the rest of the talk.
I'm going to divide it into kind of two parts.
One part will be things we can do before the conversations that involve critical feedback,
and then it'll be about things we can do during the actual conversations themselves.
So before the conversations, I'm going to kind of go over three types of strategy areas
that we can do before we have these conversations to help lay the groundwork for effective communication.
One is we can create inclusive structures.
So these are things that can happen more
on a structural level within a company.
One is we can start to have kickoff meetings
as part of our structure
for whenever we're working together.
There was a time when we were working
on Fantasia and Music Evolved
where the concept artists were down the hall
and they were making these amazingly beautiful
concept artists, drawings,
and they were working with a narrative designer.
And at the other end of the hall, those of us who were on the environment team were doing
more rapid prototyping of gameplay ideas with the gameplay designers.
And we had never talked to each other really clearly at the beginning.
So the design, the narrative, actually let me pause for a minute.
One thing this example also shows is interdisciplinarity often is within disciplines itself.
right? The concept artists, modelers, and technical artists, even within art there's
lots of different disciplines involved and the same is true I know of other departments.
But in this case, we had designers, one type of designer down the hall with the narrative and the concept artist,
another type of designer down the other end of the hall with us on the environment team,
and we were all doing this wonderful work.
We were making these great interactive toys, interactive environments,
that had all these wonderful rules about how you had to interact with them,
and the people down the hall were designing all these wonderful, beautiful art things,
but we weren't talking to each other clearly.
And there started to be a lot of tension,
like who is driving this cart here?
Are we supposed to be listening to them
in driving our gameplay?
Are they supposed to be listening to us
and doing narratives that overlay the gameplay?
And it would be possible to work in parallel,
but in this case we really started to diverge
and we started to have tension with each other
because we never had a kickoff meeting.
Say, who is responsible for what?
How are we gonna be doing this?
How are we gonna be working in parallel successfully?
It hadn't been defined and it created a lot of tension.
that was unnecessary.
And what also would have happened, or would have been helpful for us, would have been
if we could have had a regular communication throughout that process.
If we would have been meeting regularly to talk about how things were going, so we could
kind of stay in the loop with each other's work.
And one great way to do that would have been to have regular group critiques.
Group critiques are a great way.
to share work, but they need to be part of the structure.
And what's even better is if you can have a structure
for the group critique itself,
so you're not just throwing people into the water
and asking them to swim.
What I'm gonna share with you now over a couple minutes
is a technique that I found incredibly helpful as a teacher
and there might be parts of it you can pull
to use in the studio environment.
I've used it successfully in the studio environment
harmonics many times.
But it's one way to do critique.
The reason I'm presenting this to you is it gives you the example of a way to structure
critique.
It is by no means the only way.
You need to find your way that works best for you and your context.
But I just wanted to share with you once, you understand the idea of what it means to
structure critique.
And this is a pretty rigid way of doing it, to be frank.
This way of structuring critique has two parts.
Part one, you've got to get to know the damn thing, right?
All too often, when we go to critique something,
we start talking right away.
We feel a need to start judging it or assessing it right away.
But that doesn't make sense.
You don't do that.
You meet someone, and as you're shaking their hand,
you say, gosh, I really think you're not a very nice person.
Or, gosh, you don't judge that person right away.
We realize we've got to get to know them.
The same is true before we give the critical feedback.
And here are the steps that I do in this process
to get to know it.
First, we spend some time just describing it objectively.
This water bottle is about four and a half inches tall.
It's about two inches in diameter.
It's clear plastic.
Just the basic objective qualities that are there.
What's the purpose of this?
It gives us some time to not be judgmental.
Not judgmental at all.
It buys some time to just be with the damn thing
and just look at it.
and not think about whether we like it or not.
We're just with it.
Second part, describe your subjective reactions to it.
Gosh, when I look at this water bottle,
it makes me feel a little thirsty, which is good,
because I can drink out of it.
When I look at this water bottle,
I think it makes me feel big, because it's
smaller than a regular water bottle.
It's making me feel big.
That's raising these issues of scale.
So I'm just starting to describe.
And again, non-judgmentally, what's happening inside of me?
When I look at this water bottle.
It reminds me of the water bottle they used somewhere,
sort of in art, that makes more sense, right?
When I look at this, when I'm looking at this,
it reminds me of an Andy Warhol painting or something, right?
What's happening inside my brain,
what's happening inside my body,
just describing it objectively.
Again, getting to know it,
getting to know it on its own terms.
What is that thing doing?
Before I try to judge it or assess it,
then part two, analyze it.
Begin by analyzing, by finding out,
what's the goal of this thing?
What was it trying to achieve?
You know, that might be a larger goal
within the art direction or within the gameplay.
What's the goal of this thing?
Second part, what were the maker's intentions?
How was the maker trying to achieve that goal?
What were they trying to do with this?
And now, you've got all the parts you need.
You now have experience, you've taken the thing apart,
you spent time with it,
you understand how it works on its own terms,
and now you have...
the objective criteria you can use to assess it.
And that's the last thing.
How does it work to achieve its goals or fall short?
Now you can do that.
That, for me, a great process of critique
that's worked really well for me for many, many years
and has had great success.
But one key word here is that word how.
Not just is it achieving its goals or is it falling short,
how is it falling short, right?
What are the ways it's doing that?
Again, it gets an idea of assessing it
and really figuring out how it's working on its own terms
and by its own system.
Final way that we can be inclusive on a structural level in our companies is by brainstorming,
bringing people from diverse departments and disciplines in together to brainstorm around
a problem to get all of their points of view.
If that's part of the structure, things can go really, really well and really efficient
and everyone gets buy-in and feels like they're part of the same, solving the same problem.
This worked really well in the Beatles.
in the Rock Band Beatles game where they had to create all these wonderful
dreamscapes and so they detected there was all kinds of limitations.
So they brought artists and engineers and the designers and everyone got into a room
and they started to brainstorm solutions and before long they came up with a great way
that became a really successful solution.
But it worked really well because everyone from all the different disciplines was in
right away and had a stake in it.
They had been involved in making that decision.
So we talked about some ways to create inclusive structures
that we can do before a conversation.
And those are things that often happen
to happen on a structural level.
But now we're gonna spend some time talking about ways
we can prepare before the conversation
that are more individual.
Maybe I'm not in a position that I can change
the structure of my company,
but there are things I can do individually
that will help these conversations go well
before the conversations even take place.
One is by researching ahead of time.
This is something that I still continue to this day
to work on, which is before I go ask an engineer, hey,
you've got this problem with the shader graph.
Can you help me?
Spending 10 minutes, half an hour,
doing some research on my own, maybe
I can find the actual answer and not have to bother him.
Or at least I now understand the vocabulary that's
specifically related.
So if he starts talking about, oh, you
need to use a dot product there.
Now I've done some research.
I know what a dot product is.
I don't have to have him explain that.
So I've done some background on myself.
of myself ahead of time, it's going to help the whole conversation go well.
Another is preparing with quick prototypes.
This is a prototype I made for the early versions of Harmonix Music VR for the trip sequence
that involves kaleidoscopes.
I just slammed together some tech we already had just to see how kaleidoscopes felt.
We knew it worked, it helped us see that it worked really well before we went into critiquing
it and then we were able to build out the systems we needed to create this more complex
kaleidoscopic system that was in the shipping.
experience. Another way that we compare ahead of time
is with visualizations. This worked really well as I was working on UI on Sync Space.
Initially I wanted to make sure we had this tablet which had all kinds of information
that you had to read to choose your songs, to make all kinds of selections. And I wanted
to feel like this machine that could, this like...
wonderful contraption that would open up almost like a Swiss army knife, could unfold and
fold back in.
And so I made this paper prototype so I could start showing people really quickly, hey,
here's how I want to imagine it working, here's how I imagine it flipping around.
So we had this visualization we could then talk about, which was really helpful.
Because then we could help the critical feedback go really fast having that.
Then as we continued to work on it.
The designer that was working through this with me, Brian Chan, did these wonderful,
wonderful illustrations whenever he was doing the UI design for it, which were just great
and helped us talk about it a lot easier.
And also made it easier for me when I was scrolling down the design document to find
things I wanted to find, because I could see them visually.
I didn't have to skim over a bunch of text.
And those things ended up resulting in this tablet
that we have in seeing space, which
ended up achieving all my goals at the beginning.
It's this fun thing to play with in addition
to being functional.
And that's an objective opinion.
That's an objective fact, actually.
It's not my opinion.
I hope you find it fun to play with.
So another thing we can do is we can prepare by defining problems before we have a critique.
One issue again came up in Sync Space was we had this HUD, which I had fallen in love
with.
We wanted to have the HUD as this robot, it would follow you around and all the song lyrics
would be on it, and it was great and interactive, but we realized that it just wasn't working.
So before we had a critique about it.
we realized, OK, what's the problem we're trying to solve?
So we can really focus this.
The problem here was that the HUD needed to be more flexible.
It needed to be able to fit in more specific spaces
rather than dominating the whole space.
And so we were able to, by having that focus
and defining the problem, we were able to really quickly
start talking about solutions for it during the critique
that ended up with this other version of the HUD.
It's more like a movie screen or a slide screen
that opens and closes around the space.
So a third area of things we can do before the conversation
are we can do things structurally
to help build relationships.
Some of these are structural and some are individual.
One thing we can do is just share your appreciation
and respect for someone.
This seems like a little thing, and I almost
didn't even put it in this talk.
But I have a little thing for this.
It's when you see something.
say something meaning you know if somebody did something that you really
like just let them know you know there's a time I work when we're working on
rock band 4 I was working on the crowd figure assets and one of the lead
designers Greg Lepiclio came by and said actually the creative director
whatever I think he's a creative director on that project he said you
know hey Jeff I noticed you were working on those character assets are looking
really wonderful there I really appreciate I was really enjoying them
the other day and that meant a lot to me it was like wow first of all
Greg actually was noticing the crowd.
That's awesome.
And he actually knows what I've been doing.
It meant a lot.
But later, when we actually had to have a critique
about those crowd assets,
and they actually weren't working as well as we needed,
there was a great foundation for that,
because I knew that Greg was already coming from this place
and actually appreciating them.
And so now that they actually weren't doing
what he needed them to do,
it was a lot easier for me to hear that,
because I knew kind of where it was coming from.
So, these things are just little things you can do that help build a relationship so then
when you do need to have critical feedback later, you've already got a strong foundation
for that to happen.
Another is just asking for help.
There's another thing I did recently.
You'd think I would know these things better
since I'm talking about it,
but this is, I did this recently,
a lesson I haven't even fully learned myself,
which was I'd been working in the animation on this project,
and often in Unity, those of you who work in Unity
may know this thing where if you.
If you re-animate something, if you re-parent something
and move it around its hierarchy after you've animated it,
it's broken, the animation keys don't work anymore.
I've been suffering with that for a long time,
complaining about it, but finally I mentioned it
to the engineers on the project,
and the lead engineer said, you know what,
we've got a tool to fix that.
It's been there all the time.
I just didn't know, I'd never asked about it.
I hadn't reached out across disciplines to say,
here's this problem I'm solving, can you help me do that?
So here's why this is important,
and here's why it's relevant to this talk.
By reaching across disciplines, asking for help,
two things can happen.
One, you can save a lot of time,
because things may already exist to help you, right?
But two, it's another way to build relationships.
By doing that now, by helping each other,
we're building stronger relationships.
So when we do need to give critical feedback to each other,
we're doing it on a stronger foundation.
So these are all ways of building relational foundations
so that when we do need to give critical feedback,
we have a much stronger foundation for it.
And the last thing is we can do organized events.
We do a lot of these greater harmonics.
We go bowling together once a year.
We have game jams once a year.
I'm sure you guys do things like that often in other companies.
If you don't, I strongly suggest you do.
But here's why I put it in here.
I put this here, too.
I almost took it out, also.
But I put it in here because I was remembering that often,
when I go to bowl, I just get so into the bowling and loving it
that I'm forgetting, hey, this is also an opportunity for me
to be.
Meeting a lot of other people in the company that I don't normally meet and talking to a lot of other people
I don't normally talk to and that's what these these things are for and so when your company does these
Really taking full advantage of that and using it a chance to really build relationships
outside of the the ones you usually have
So these are the three things that are really helpful for doing things before
conversation starts
They're not the things, they're some things that are good examples and there are many
more.
It's not an exhaustive list, but some things I thought would be helpful to talk about today.
Now let's pivot a little bit and talk about the second chunk of things, ways of strategies
and techniques.
And that is things we can do during an actual conversation that's involving critical feedback
across disciplines.
And the first thing that's helpful to ask here is
what helps conversations go well in general,
especially conversations when they're across cultures, right?
Well, if we think about it,
when people are communicating,
if there's someone from China negotiating
or having a conversation with someone from the United States
or across cultures, what's really helpful in doing that?
That's right.
It's a moderator, right?
Moderators are people who come in
and they help to facilitate empathic communication.
They do that by helping to focus the critique,
helping to clarify the communication.
They help to see, and they're able to see
the conversation from the outside.
They have an objective point of view
and they can really then focus on
how the communication is happening, right?
That's great, but why is that relevant to this talk?
Because we can't bring moderators in to our company
just to help everyone talk.
Certainly when it's one-on-one talk, one-on-one we can't.
And the answer to that is that anyone, anytime,
can be a moderator.
That's right.
you can be the moderator.
Even if you're in the conversation,
you can be inside of it and outside of it at the same time,
acting as a moderator in the whole conversation
to kind of help facilitate that conversation as it's going on.
Let's talk about some ways that we can be moderators
of our own conversations.
One is by helping to define your own unique perspective.
These are some images of Wes, the drummer from Rock Band VR that was made by Sean Witt,
this wonderful artist we have at Harmonix.
And I just love that drawing.
I'll look at it more after the talk.
But one of the things that Sean,
he was working on this character,
he always works on characters,
was able to bring to critiques,
when people would have critiques about the characters,
how they've been through the rest of the game,
is Sean's able to say, look,
as my perspective as the figure artist,
I really understand the narrative background
of this character.
I really understand his psychological makeup,
I understand his personality,
and therefore I understand that he should have
a certain kind of voice when we give him
the voice actor for him.
or I should understand certain other things because of my point of view.
He has that unique point of view that he can bring to this situation.
And we can all focus on that.
What is your unique perspective?
And you can identify it.
Don't just start talking before you say, here's the perspective I'm coming from.
And sometimes you might be coming from perspectives that aren't your normal one.
You might say, you know, as a player, when I'm playing through this game, I find x, y,
and z to be the case.
You can define that perspective that makes your feedback unique.
And why is this helpful?
Actually, another thing we can do
is we can also invite others to do the same thing.
So in the course of a critique, say, hey,
Brian, as the designer, how do you see this issue?
Or Sully, as the engineer, how do you see this issue?
So we can invite people from their unique perspective
to offer their input and advice.
It establishes value of all points of view,
and it really helps to be moderating
these conversations in the very act
of having the conversation itself.
Another way we can act as moderators in the middle of a conversation is through reflection.
Reflection is when we kind of rephrase and reflect back something that someone has said.
This is a wonderful painting that Gianna Ruggiero did when we were in the pre-production process
for Harmonix Music VR, and it was for where the dance scenes could take place that are
part of that experience.
And some of the feedback was, you know, it just doesn't look like a very musical place.
Now, in Jian's point of mind, it was a very musical place.
You could have musical bushes, you could have musical trees.
It was very musical.
And so this is where reflection gets to be very helpful.
Because Jian could say, well, what I hear you saying is that we...
this place is a place that doesn't have elements that can be musical at all.
And that gives then the person she was talking to, the designer, a chance to say, oh no,
no, that's not what I meant.
They could, you could have musical bushes.
What I mean is that we need to find a different place itself, which then gave Gianna the chance
to be reflective again.
Oh, what I hear you saying is we need to find a place that something about that place itself
is musical, a place we associate with music.
Ah, yes, yes, that's right.
So you can see that idea of reflecting back.
rephrasing and reflecting, in this case we ended up placing it in a gymnasium like a
high school dance, with a place itself that was a place where we go to enjoy music and dance.
So some things to remember about moderating through reflection.
First, rephrase.
Don't just repeat.
Second, it's an amazing, excellent way of translating,
especially when we're working across disciplines.
People who are coming at this from an engineering point
of view or from a design point of view,
they may be using words that mean something different
to them than they mean for us.
Because disciplines often speak about the same thing
in different ways.
And so reflecting is a great way to make sure
that we're all on the same page and understanding together.
It's also a great way to show that you're listening, right?
So suddenly it helps to validate the people you're talking with.
They feel listened to.
They feel heard.
It shows that you care.
And why is this important?
Because it helps others hear you, right?
Especially if your feedback is going to be harsh, right?
If they're saying something and you're able to reflect back to them, you've understood
what they're saying, you really are on the same page with them, I understand what you're
saying but we just can't do that in this case because of X, Y, and Z.
And then if you want to be super awesome, you can say, but that was a wonderful idea.
And you know what?
Why don't you help us figure out the next solution?
Let's all work on this together, right?
Validate, incorporate, get people involved, make people feel invested, and it's just,
those are all super helpful things to do.
Another thing we can do to moderate when we're in the course of a conversation, if we can
moderate by asking questions when we're giving feedback.
An example of that was we had these new cloth physics that had been designed for the characters
I was working on giving hair physics to for Rock Band 4, and it was a new system.
And the engineer who did it initially had made it so that these top joints there were
not constrained.
it was different than our old system and so it wasn't working the way that I was
used to working it wasn't working the way that
that uh... the old system had wasn't working the way I designed all the assets
to work with it
and I could have gone to him and said hey this is wrong it's not working right
but I decided I stopped myself and I said wait a minute I'm going to ask him some questions first
before I give that feedback
you know so I said
You know, why did you do that?
Why did you design it so that's the default?
He told me, and it actually was an interesting way.
Actually, for our next game, maybe we
could design the assets to do what he had in mind.
But unfortunately, I hadn't designed them that way.
So I was able to say, oh, I see that.
That's an interesting way.
Maybe next time we could do that.
Let's do some R&D after this to figure that out.
But right now, unfortunately, the assets
are designed to have the top joint constraint.
So could you please make that the default?
And he said, oh yeah, sure, no problem.
And he did it.
So asking questions before giving feedback
is really helpful, because we have
to assume that our assumptions are false.
And this was actually something that I also
learned from one of the engineers
during when I was meeting with the engineers.
One of our engineers, Fitzi, said during our feedback,
he said, you know, when I'm talking to an artist,
I just have come to understand that I'm going to be
wrong at least three times.
You know, the first thing I'm going to think is going to be wrong.
He's just come to understand that his initial assumptions are going to be false, and that's fine.
He understands, because we're working across cultures,
that the way he's thinking about something isn't the same way the artist is thinking about it.
It also saves energy and time by asking questions,
because we could suddenly get to the heart of the issue
right away, and it certainly saves energy,
because you imagine if I'd gone to this engineer
and said, hey, this system's broken,
now suddenly he's upset, I've got all this anger,
we're all angry, there's a lot of energy being wasted,
right, so this saves a lot of energy.
It also helps people feel included and valued,
like a lot of the other things we're talking about today,
that gets to the core of empathic communication.
But you can also moderate by asking questions
when you're receiving feedback.
So, if you're receiving, and this is a great story for this,
this is one of my favorite stories of this talk.
Mitch Fletcher is one of the artists
that I've worked with for a long time.
Amazing, wonderful guy.
He was working on Seeing Space with us,
he's the environment artist.
He'd gotten some feedback in a bug from someone in QA,
and that feedback was the art looks unfinished.
And Mitch said, you know,
In years past, I would have been angry and I would have said,
what the frick does he know what he's talking about?
I'm the artist.
But he said, you know what I've come to realize?
there's something there.
If he thinks the artist,
if that person thinks the artist is unfinished,
other people are gonna think the artist is unfinished.
And this game is not for artists,
this game is for everyone,
and that's a good piece of feedback.
Now, so I need to start asking him some questions
to clarify it.
So I can say, wait,
you know, I can send back a comment on the bug.
What is it about it that feels unfinished?
And to kind of try to get more information, right?
That that bit of feedback,
even though it wasn't phrased well,
was important because it was like a piece of coal
that hadn't been crushed into the diamond, right?
There's a diamond in there,
some really good feedback that could be really helpful,
but he needed to ask questions to pull that feedback out.
And he did, and then he ended up really doing
this wonderful redo of this musically reactive art
that's up in the sky as we're singing in Sing Space.
And so a couple notes about this process of asking questions when you're receiving feedback
as a way of moderating.
One, just remember that non-artists often find it difficult to talk about art.
And that's the case, you know, this talk is in the art track by hoping everything is kind
of relevant for a lot of people who aren't just artists.
So you can apply that to whatever.
discipline you're in.
Non-whatever you are often find it difficult to talk about whatever you do.
But that doesn't mean that they don't have good ideas and opinions about it.
And so sometimes you need to ask questions to get to the core of what they're trying
to express.
So we talked about a number of things
that are helpful during the conversation,
just a quick review of them.
And be participants and moderators at the same time.
Some ways to do that are defining
your unique perspective and helping other people
to define theirs, rephrasing and reflecting ideas back.
and making sure to ask questions.
Certainly this isn't an exhaustive list,
there's a lot more, but I think those start to get
at the idea of what things you can do
to act as both a moderator and a participant
at the same time during a conversation.
Before I close, this is one thing that came up
as a question a lot when I was presenting this,
is you know, sometimes we just disagree.
Sometimes, you know, I want an apple and you want an orange and we're just never going
to agree on that.
Right?
So the question was, well, what do we do then?
How do these strategies help us to solve that problem?
Right?
Well...
One thing that can be helpful is you can find a way within your company to have a structure
in place that will help you to deal with that situation when it happens.
And earlier in the week, and I can't stress this strongly enough, earlier in the week
there was an amazing talk, I think it was on Monday, it was called Managing Conflict
on Small Teams.
It was by Rebecca Saltzman from Finji, and she went over some of the strategies that
they'd use at Finji for dealing with this specific issue when there's conflict.
I would strongly suggest you take a look at that.
You might find some great ideas for that.
But you can also work, the overall thing that's
important is having a structure in place,
either on your small team or on the larger teams,
so when there are complete disagreements,
that people will be able to know what to do.
It won't be on them to figure out what to do at that point.
They will have a structure and something
that they can do in that moment.
But even just using all the stuff
I've talked with you about today,
focusing on empathic communication.
When we get to those points where we just disagree, we can often find that the strategies
I've talked about today, we can find ways to disagree with respect and understanding.
If I've started to understand your point of view, even though I still disagree with it,
I at least understand it and I can still respect you.
We're not going to get into a big fight over it if we use a lot of those strategies and
techniques I've talked about today.
And in fact...
And this next point that I'm about to swipe to
comes out of lots of talks with my wife.
My wife, Jane Hesser, is an amazing artist
and she is also an amazing therapist.
And one of the things that she has taught me
is that, you know, the metaphor, the analogy is this.
When you break a bone,
it's stronger in the place where it heals.
And that's true also of emotional relationships.
When our emotional relationships break, they are stronger after being healed.
We can all probably imagine that.
Having an argument with someone, getting through it, finding it,
we're stronger in our relationship having gotten through that.
And so when we have these moments when we disagree,
and we use strategies like I've talked about in this talk,
or others that you can think of,
to find ways to get through those disagreements,
then we can not only just be...
but not get along, we can actually use this as a way to bond.
Our relationships can actually really improve through this process.
So in closing, here's just a quick slide
that summarizes some of the things I talked about today.
I've already reviewed a number of these at each point,
so I won't read through them all again.
But the most important thing with all of these
is to remember that you need to behave
with other people's experience in mind
in order to give feedback effectively,
and especially when we're communicating
across disciplines.
And you need to do that, you need to focus
on empathic communication.
And empathic communication is entirely based on the ability to have empathy, and empathy
is that ability to try to imagine something from someone else's point of view, recognize
that you're unable to do that, that there are holes in your image, and that you need
to become inquisitive and try to ask questions and fill in those gaps.
Thank you very much.
I hope you all enjoy thinking about this stuff
as much as I do.
These are, I think, super important things
for us to think about as an industry,
and I would love to keep this conversation going.
Please take down my email, talk to me afterwards,
and I would love to find ways
to keep this dialogue moving forward
and to keep talking about these issues
and finding even more ways
that we can be incorporating this as an industry.
Thank you all very, very much.
Right, so I designed this to be plenty of time for questions.
And so we've got a good chunk of time.
If anyone has questions, you can please just use the microphones
that are in the room.
Hi, great talk.
When you get together with different people,
do you ask them to prepare in any way?
And I'm asking this because when we have reviews,
I often notice that a lot of people come to the meeting
and are all busy.
They didn't get a chance to review any material beforehand.
How do you deal with different people
and the different levels of preparedness?
Okay, so you're asking, when people come to a meeting, how do I make sure that everyone's
on the same level?
Some people might be more prepared than other people are prepared?
Yeah, how do you avoid doing work in the meeting and having people prepared beforehand?
Oh, having people prepared before the meeting.
That's a really good question.
I think often in the case with...
with art, and so this may be different for different disciplines, but often in the case
of art, if we're dealing with a critical feedback, we want to have a critique about something,
that's often not so vital because we're kind of, we come to it, we're not going to, we're
going to, part of the critique itself is to have time to experience it and that gets us
all on the same page with it.
But there are times if that art has very, very specific design constraints, then some
people don't understand that, then they're going to be less.
So I think the thing I try to do in those cases is before the meeting, it kind of goes
into the preparation process, figure out what are the essential elements that everyone needs
to know.
If there are design constraints that people need to know, if there's art direction constraints
that people need to know, let's just make sure we have that.
out right away so that people understand those issues and try to find a succinct way of telling
what those issues are.
And that works, I found that to work really well in an art context.
In a non-art context, I can't speak to, which, are you an artist or are you?
and I do a lot of different things.
It's different expertise, so it's indeed different for different people.
I imagine it would be very different, and that's one of the reasons I would love to start
expanding this conversation out to non-artists, so we can start talking about
some of the strategies that are helpful in other disciplines for doing these kinds of things.
Because I would imagine that in an engineering meeting...
that is the level of preparedness people need to have
is much greater coming into the meeting.
But I can't speak to that
because I don't have that experience.
Yeah, no, but that was helpful.
Thank you. Okay, great.
And that also reminds me of one little thing
that I had all my bubbles of the different departments.
My bubble for engineering initially said coders.
And in the course of my meeting with them,
I said, oh, wait a minute, you guys.
I've been meaning to ask you for a long time.
Do you guys like being called coders?
And I found out that a lot of them don't.
A lot of them think it's like calling you a pixel pusher.
I said, well, yeah.
And so I said, well, and so I found out,
what do you like to be called?
And so I changed it to programmers here.
And it wasn't the case.
Some of them thought coders were fine.
But some of them didn't like it.
Yeah.
Hi.
So as you know, especially working on a big team,
this is a journey,
and the journey is sometimes fraught with pitfalls.
And I think sometimes I've encountered situations where there is a loss of respect and then
therefore like a loss of trust.
And with that comes baggage, especially if you know the dev cycle is long.
And so I guess from your point of view, from your past experience, what has been the best
way to resolve, you know, these more like...
ingrained and deep-seated issues have taken a while to kind of like form that ball.
Oh, yeah, that's a great question.
So the question is what what can we do and over a course of the time people haven't been paying attention to a lot of these
issues and therefore things have festered and now people have lost respect for each other. How can you repair that once it's happened?
That's a great question. I think I mean the
There's the easy answer and there's the hard answer.
The easy answer is to kind of negate
the foundation of your question and say,
well, the best thing to do is to start making sure
you have a culture in your company
of doing these types of things early on
so things don't fester and get to that point, right?
So that's the easy answer, but that kind of doesn't help you
in your question at all, right?
Because you might be dealing with this
in a specific case right now.
And I think that the best way to do that is
Gosh, I don't know. I'm just kind of talking off the top of my head now that if I were in that situation
I would try to
Find a way to get as many people on the team to recognize what's happened as possible to be transparent about it
So look we have developed
a problem here. We're not communicating well. Try not to personalize it if it's just one
person or another. Don't personalize it. Don't say, hey, you've really gotten to be angry
here and we don't like your anger. That's not going to be helpful. So try to find ways.
We aren't communicating as well as we can. Acknowledge that the structure has been the
problem. Blame the structure. We've had a really horrible structure for the first half
of this project. There are a lot of things we haven't done that we should have done.
And that was a mistake, right?
And what we need to start doing now is finding some ways that we can fix that.
Because we don't learn, aren't trusting.
List what's happening.
We find that we're not trusting each other anymore.
You know, list that out.
Acknowledge that it's happening.
Blame the structure for it.
And then say, bring everyone in.
And don't say, okay, and here's what we're going to do to solve it.
Right?
Say, okay, as a group.
We need to start figuring out how we're going to solve these problems.
Let's all start thinking of ideas for this.
And then maybe some of the ideas in this talk can be things that can get that conversation
going, but the conversation itself should be a participatory process.
So everyone's invested.
And once everyone's invested, there's going to be a lot greater chance, if it was their
idea, right, there's going to be a lot better chance that they will do it going forward.
Is that helpful?
Yeah, that was very helpful.
Thank you.
Great, thanks.
Hi.
This is a kind of a similar thought process of, is there anything you guys do specifically
to educate team-wide how to implement these techniques and have an effective conversation
or anything you do team-wide to help establish that process and structure, whether it's like
just having a mini-workshop on-site or things like that.
Is there anything specifically you guys implement to educate the team?
That's a great question.
The question is, what can we do on site?
What are some things we can do to implement this?
And just kind of ways that we can
make sure everyone's on the same page with these ideas.
Well, last year, a couple things.
One, Harmonix has periodically brought in outside consultants
to run workshops with lots of people
around the company about facilitating communication.
And that's been super helpful.
Another thing, last year, after my.
my previous GDC talk, on maximizing critique, after that I gave the talk to the whole company
so that there's another way of making sure we're all on the same page with that.
And then in the process leading up to this, and this has been a little bit more individually
motivated on my part, but I've actually been going around and getting feedback and getting
input from all the departments, which has really been helpful in already starting some
of these conversations.
And I don't want to say that I was...
These conversations, a lot of them were already happening, right?
And it wasn't that I started these conversations at Harmonix at all, but as I started talking
to the different departments about it, it helped to bring those conversations out and
help other people start talking about it more.
So that's been really helpful.
And in fact, I think that talking to individual departments has in many ways been more valuable
than talking to the company as a whole, because we can have these nice little individual conversations.
So some combination of that.
Does that help?
Does that answer your question?
Yeah, thank you.
Yeah.
Hi.
You talked about like for certain things
where people just disagree
and there's, it's not a matter of miscommunication.
Like they're just kind of butting heads
against fundamentally different things.
And you mentioned like processes
for dealing with that situation.
Yes.
What are some examples of that?
Well, one, which if you have access to the vault,
that talk I mentioned from last Monday,
and I'm not going to,
Rebecca Saltzman's talk was amazing,
and she gave some great, great ideas for that
that they use really well.
And,
So I would really suggest you, that's a whole big other topic.
And I think if you, I can't recommend highly enough
that you watch that.
I was blown away by her talk on Monday.
Rebecca's?
Rebecca Saltzman.
OK, got it.
S-A-L-T-Z, S-A-L-T-S-M-A-N.
OK, thanks.
And yeah, it was on Monday.
And I can give you more reference to that
when you come back up there.
Any other questions?
Hi, thank you so much for your talk.
I actually am an assistant producer and I do a lot of feedback gathering for artists,
but I do it across multiple different offices.
So we'll do Chicago, France, Russia, and here in San Francisco.
The biggest issue I have is getting all these people from all these different offices on
the same page regarding...
what they want to go in the general direction for the artist without inundating the artist with
million different ideas and concepting, you know, 16 different things. Do you have any great suggestions on trying to get all these different
people in all these different time zones on the same page?
That's a tricky one. So yes, we did harmonics. We've been doing a lot of people working remotely and we can all kind of talk. We use Skype a lot, which has been super helpful, but we're not working that remotely. We're kind of we're some of our people like three hours apart, kind of spread across across the United States, as we're still able to kind of be with each other at least once a day. It sounds like the struggle you're having is people are like globally like people.
Yeah, we usually do global conversations via Skype to try and capture all these things,
all the ideas and stuff like that, but it's always the hardest part is getting the very
first foundation and then building up from there.
And we try not to get the artists involved because we tried doing that initially, and
it just became 16, 17 different concepts that took weeks on end to do.
And we're trying to not have them do that.
So you're trying to define what the initial goals are
that then you can disseminate to everyone else?
Right.
And who is involved in that initial conversation
of defining what those?
Usually it's our marketing, production, high tier usually.
And what would some of those kinds of things be?
What would be the product that that team
would be figuring out?
Usually these are like key art.
So I work on World of Tanks for console
and we do like splash screens
for when you load into the game.
We do news article, things like that.
We'll try to use the art in multiple different ways.
Yeah.
Things like that.
That's a tricky one.
There's a certainly, so the issue is like,
a lot of the key art and things that need to be done
for marketing, how can that be integrated
as part of the team development?
Right.
Yeah, that's a tricky one.
Because it often needs to happen independently,
but the stuff you're doing is really
how this team who's been so invested in the work
that they've done, this is how the world
is going to see their work.
And unfortunately, often, the way
the world's going to initially see their work
isn't the way they want the world to see their work
after being invested in it.
And a lot of tension can be created there.
And I just, if there's some way, and I see you're,
to find a way to make people feel engaged and part of that process
without then, what you said, like having all these different concepts involved.
I think that, you know, maybe it's a question of having something you've done
and then asking, opening up for feedback on it, and a very constrained,
you know, like, not open feedback, but saying, here's what, here's what we have
and we need some feedback on you, here are the things we are concerned about.
So people, you know, but that is an issue that I think happens in a lot of companies
and it's just something that...
is something to really work on.
Because I think people, you know,
a lot of those artists and people
who have spent so much of their time on the work
and then feel that the way it's being publicized
is out of sync with all the work they've done,
that can really create a lot of morale issues.
And so I think that finding ways,
either from the beginning or toward the end,
to incorporate the feedback of the artists.
And not in a way that asks them to do the work themselves,
but in a way that somehow asks for feedback
so they feel as though they're part of the process.
I think it's really important.
Like a preemptive meeting with the artists themselves
away from the others.
Perhaps, every company would need to do it different ways,
and different companies are different sizes.
And so I don't know the specific strategy
to be great for your company.
But the goal, what I do understand is the goal,
I think, would be great.
And the goal would be to help everyone,
as many people as possible, feel invested and involved.
And that would be the goal.
So I'm not sure the specific strategy would be helpful.
But often having the goal.
is the key, because the strategies often end up falling out from that goal.
So even that answer, the question I didn't answer so well a moment ago,
like, what do you do when people really just disagree?
Well, what's your goal for that?
Our goal is to come up with a strategy that works in our company
that we can all agree on, that when we disagree,
here are the steps we're going to follow.
And so that's the goal, and I think every company
can start to find its own way to implement that.
So I kind of answered both questions at once there.
Did I answer your question?
Did I give you a sense of that?
Yes, you did.
Thank you.
All right.
Thank you very much.
Oh, yeah.
Thank you for the talk.
So in our team, professionally, when we're discussing our own work, we tend to try to
implement these processes, but we backslide a lot during social hour.
So specifically, like if we're playing games together.
People can just get really like brutal and want to double down on like oh
Why would they have made that art decision like that shitty and that looks like crap and having that
ends up creating backslide
During our own critiques. Yeah, you have strategies for discouraging that kind of behavior when it's not in a specific work situation
But it's affecting work
Yeah, that's a tricky one, right?
Because we can't, it's a great question.
So the question as I understand it is,
it's one thing to make sure you can have a structures
and language at work that everyone kind of follows
to stay on the same page.
But often outside of work, people start to use
really derogatory or insulting or harsh language
about things that then starts to leach back
into the relationships at work.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think.
that's again, it gets just to come back
to the larger cultural thing.
You can't tell people what to do outside of work, of course,
but what you can as a company start to really encourage
is, hey, these are efficient ways to work,
but they're also great in our regular life.
I think if these ideas are presented in that way,
you know, like, hey, you might find that this stuff
is not just helpful for you at work,
but it's also helpful for you outside of work.
You just suggest that as a way to kind of encourage people
that this is not just a culture here,
but it's a culture to behave in life that's helpful.
And then also.
even outside of work, catching that,
if people are talking that way,
standing up and saying, hey, that's really not helpful
when we talk about it that way.
And I think if individuals can take that on themself
to realize that, you know, it's like a lot of other,
kind of touches on a lot of other issues going on now,
right, like when stuff's going on in society
and you see people behaving in some horrible, horrible ways.
Is it, you know, can you just ignore it or is it your responsibility to kind of say,
hey, that's not, that's not awesome.
And this is what you're saying.
It's not nearly as bad as what's going on outside this room, but if you.
find ways to take it even outside of work if you see that happening
say hey that's that's not really helpful we talk about that way even even here
you know what or you can even your instead of judging it you can just turn
it say
what what was on the examples you said that they would say like that you're
like
like we're playing games together at lunch that somebody might start like
bragging on the art style
Yeah, like, well, the art style book really sucks.
Then you say, well, what is it about it that you don't like?
Just instead of telling them they've done something wrong,
you can encourage them to rephrase it.
Oh, what is it about it that you don't like?
And if they continue to use, just
start kind of pulling from them until you've pulled out
from them helpful language about it.
Even if it's not impacting you, what you're doing then
is you're starting to give them a moment
to learn how to rephrase things that are helpful.
And if you just kind of start doing that all the time,
other people might start doing it too,
and then people start to really learn
better ways of speaking.
That's one strategy, but it's a tricky situation.
Is that helpful?
Yeah, yeah, thank you.
Awesome.
Well, that's our last question.
I'm gonna be up here as long as I can,
and then I'll also be in the hall,
but depending on how many people it is,
if anybody wants to stay,
I will stay as long as anybody wants to talk about anything,
so we may end up in the wrap-up room around the corner.
Thank you all so much for coming,
and thanks for staying.