Thank you for taking the time to watch my presentation,
which is titled Creating Ghosts from Across the Pacific.
Hi, everyone.
My name is Jason Connell.
I'm a creative director and art director at Sucker Punch
and was art director on Ghosts of Tsushima.
I have an art and background, art and computer science
background, roughly 17 years experience doing what I do.
I come from a background of lighting.
shaders, lighting and color and cinematography. And yeah, and if you want to reach me, you can
reach me at my Twitter here at Art Envelope. I work at Sucker Punch Productions. Sucker Punch
Productions has been around for coming on I think about 25 years and they've made some super cool
action games. I've been there for about 11 years. I was a big fan of Sly Cooper and a super big fan
of Infamous.
And I came around the time that Infamous 2 was being created.
And eventually we went on to make a game called
Infamous Second Son, which is made in Seattle.
And that's actually really about where we're located.
We're located across the water from Lake Washington
and Bellevue, which is just super close to Seattle,
for those who don't know.
And so that was kind of our backyard,
creating this open world action game with a guy
who has superhero powers.
And that power of doing right by the details,
not all the details, but the details to sort of capture
what Seattle could feel like was a great learning for us
because our next game was about bringing
the authenticity of an open world environment
to a place that is pretty far away from us.
And we had to really utilize some of our skill sets.
But really, frankly,
we had to develop a whole lot of new skill sets in order to make this work. This is very
very different from Seattle. So and it was also far back in time and I'm talking of course I'm
talking about Ghost of Tsushima. Now you know this time we're not creating Seattle we're creating
or representing a culture that we do not know.
It's not familiar.
It's not local by any stretch of imagination.
We are not inherently experts.
And it's certainly not anywhere close to 1274.
In fact, it's so long ago
that it's hard to actually dig up history about it.
You know, Ghost of Tsushima is an open world.
action samurai game inspired by real events in history. The Mongols invaded in 1274.
And to make this game, we really had to partner with people across the Pacific to make a game
that respects the genre and the culture. We effectively had to change the way we make
games and had a lot to learn along the way.
Now everything that I'm going to talk about today is super important but it probably could come off
at some point and it sounds like you know maybe each one of these topics is just too laborious
and you may ask yourself is why is this actually important you know um that I'm going to talk a
lot about how much time it takes to sort of solve some of these problems and you might think well
that's a huge tax on making fast decisions and you know we all want to fail fast it's video games
it's creative endeavors.
That's true, but it does take time to sort out some of these issues.
Simple things may seem more complex, but to us, solving these issues and developing these
relationships with our consultants and stuff was sort of the cost of entry.
So why is this important?
It's important because we felt like we had a duty to treat this with care, to fulfill
the expectations of the genre.
and to do so with thoughtfulness, because that was our goal. We wanted to create something that
people who like this genre of movies or books or other games that could be excited about it,
but it was viewed as something that was done with thoughtfulness. So to this day, Ghost of Tsushima
has won some various awards, including some specific accolades by Japanese gamers and press.
Famitsu 40 out of 40 was super humbling for us.
And recently Nate and I got,
and extended to the rest of the studio,
awarded honorary tourism ambassadors to Tsushima,
which is just like the coolest thing
that's ever happened in my life.
But it did take a lot of work to get here.
So let me share a little bit about our journey
in making this game from across the Pacific.
This talk is broken up into four sections.
I'm gonna talk about how Ghost came about.
sort of hinging on, almost didn't come about because of a single fear,
sort of our transition into having to take the position of learning. We're directors and leaders
and that's how we've made games. We've built upon, you know, we make decisions built off our
expertise, but this time we're going to have to sit down and listen to somebody else tell us what
they think is right for us in this particular game. And that's a different frame of mind.
as well as the complications of once you do become that student, you do hire consultants,
you're going to get feedback about history and culture and sometimes that goes in conflict with
the game you're creating.
and you gotta sort that out.
And I'm gonna share with you some of our insight there.
And lastly, it's kind of a form of its own,
it's like entertainment consultant,
is what inspirations do you have
and what inspirations specifically we had for Ghost.
Let's start off with talking about the beginning.
So it was August, 2014.
We just created Infamous First Light.
And it took us a little bit of time to figure out what we're going to do next.
We knew we had the opportunity to create a new IP, and we had some ideas.
And these ideas, I'd said we had something like 150 people at the studio at Sucker Punch.
These ideas that we had were very broad.
They were cool ideas, but they were very broad.
And you take every single person in the studio and they form their own
slightly different variation of what that idea could be.
And it was just really hard to bring it to a super sharp, simple idea.
And that's what we needed.
We needed an idea for our next game that was...
We didn't want everybody to be on the exact same page, because that's what,
you know, having variation and differing opinion is what makes great games.
But we needed something that was sharper and more simple and really powerful
and that our 150 people weren't going off wildly in different directions.
And what we decided is that we needed another strong player fantasy to fulfill.
And frankly, we've done this before, right?
Second Son, or excuse me, Infus, and Infamous in general,
is a superhero player fantasy,
or the Sly series is about being a thief.
we have expertise here, and this was something
that we've done a great job with in the past.
So we knew we wanted to do that again.
What's the super clear player fantasy we wanted to fulfill?
So we talked about being a medieval knight
and what that might look like,
a medieval knight simulator or something like that.
Or, you know, hey, we could do a modern thief game.
And we have some expertise in the past.
Some of those people are still at the studio.
Hey, could we do this?
And then we had the beauty, the samurai,
the game that we ended up making.
But.
We actually crossed this one out really fast.
Nate and I, we were like,
we're totally culturally inexperienced here.
I'm not sure if we know how we can make this game.
We don't have cultural experts.
We don't have experience hiring that many
to make a game as big and as epic as we'd like to.
We sort of had this moment of fear.
So we were cursed down Knight and Thief
for about two more weeks.
I don't remember how long it was exactly.
And then we came back and we're like, you know what?
We love samurai stories. We're huge fans of samurai cinema, Kurosawa, or you know, I know
Nate's a big fan of graphic novels like Lone Wolf and Cub or Usagi Ujimbo. We're so inspired by this
that we felt like we should at least give it a shot. Because at this point in a project, if
you don't have enough ambition and passion to carry you through...
now you're not going to for the next four or five years. I mean these games would take so long to
make. So Samurai it was. We decided we were going to try it. We gave it some heart and we started
working on it and we had we had we had we had ourselves going in a direction. But we still
had that fear in the back of our minds. How are we going to do this thoughtfully? We had this
very real cultural journey that was in front of us that we needed to understand and figure out
how are we going to accomplish it?
The interesting thing is that very quickly we realized,
well, we do have some pretty big advantages.
For example, we had people within our organization
that we had worked with for a long time
that were Japanese, that were big fans of Sucker Punch,
that we could talk to and give them the pitch
and tell them what we were planning on doing
and just get their feedback.
And Shuhei Ishida-san was so excited about the game
and gave us some feedback
about how we might be able to create it
that it gave us ambition
that we might be able to pull this off.
And frankly, for us to...
be successful here, we didn't know how much we were going to be doing this, but we did know that
there were some things we're going to have to change in the way we make games. First of all,
every time you make a game, somebody's going to get hired. It's animator or a graphics engineer,
producers. This time, there was this whole new subset of team members that we were going to
have to hire that we had never experienced working with in the past.
people that even at that point when we started, you know, we knew we had a, for example, religion,
we needed somebody to help us with Japanese religion because we were totally inexperienced
here. But as time went on, that team, that list just grew and grew and grew. But we knew that
we're going to have to kind of reshape our minds a little bit about what type of team members we're
going to need in order to pull this off. And
going to have to do research. Now, every game, especially these big games like this, you know,
there's lots of research that goes in, like shader research, you know, for example, but not
to the level of like historical, religious, you know, cultural, deep cultural research and
consultants guiding it. It's just something that we've just totally never done before. And these two
were going to catapult us into, um...
being absorbed with information. We're going to constantly be giving information and that
really catapulted us into the second section I want to talk about. So we had Ghost. Our fears
of creating it were defeated by our excitement and some of our partners and like you know,
Shu being so supportive so early gave us enthusiasm to move forward. But now we have,
we are put into a position where we
no longer can just sit there and be directors about literally everything. We had to sit down
a little bit and sort of frankly buckle up and take in information and realize that we're not
gonna be driving literally everything. That's good. And I'm gonna talk a little bit about that. So
we sort of had to become students. And becoming a student has got a couple things in common,
like you gotta show up, gotta have an urge to listen, gotta have a yearning to learn.
probably going to accept the fact that you don't know everything.
certainly about checking assumptions. I saw a samurai movie one time. That's great. It might
have some great information in there, but it's great to sort of check those assumptions with
some consultants. They might be like, yeah, but it doesn't work the way you think it might. And
that was really good for us. And frankly, the most important one around the topic of being a student
is really getting into research and especially field research, if you can. And for us, it was
really beneficial.
because that's the really exciting one. We actually got to go on a trip to Tsushima in Japan and do
real research and that's just so much deeper than your typical cursory kind of, well,
Google's not cursory anymore. You can learn anything on Google, but this was just so powerful
for us that it helped augment the work that we're already doing from a research angle.
photos that we were looking at and documents we were reading online, actually getting to
go to the place.
And I took all these pictures I'm about to show you.
I kind of went there thinking, you know, you know, this is gonna be one thing, but it really
provided proved to be sort of beneficial in ways that I, I hadn't.
from that trip feeling the way I did. I really went into that trip thinking, oh this is gonna
be great. We're gonna go on this epic trip to Japan. You know, we're gonna gain a ton of knowledge
of what it is that we were building and how to create it effectively. And this did become true,
right? You know, Tsushima and greater Japan and all this, you know, on our entire trip this did
become true. We learned about, you know, what did the buildings look like? How tall were they? What
materials were they made of?
You know those cool katanas and no-dachis and odachis?
Like, how do you create a sword?
What types of foliage should we use
in certain climates of Japan?
Thousands of photos, hundreds of pages of note,
two trips to Japan with 10-plus members
of our sort of senior leads and directors.
We brought back an enormous library of photos,
drone footage, you name it, to reference from.
It was awesome.
All right.
To me, the real beauty was so, so much more important
than that.
It was building new relationships with people
that were going to guide us, passionately guide us
and desperately guide us.
One, they had so much energy for helping us.
And we were so inexperienced here,
like just learning the types of questions we need to ask
and, you know, and how to document it and how to...
uh, categorize our notes. Like it's just, there's just so much to take in. But the human connection
with some of these people, like, uh, the guy in the black shirt here, his name is Jonah, Jonah Nagai.
And he worked for Sony Japan, helped organize our first trip. I was on this trip with him and he was
so invested in answering any question we had, you know, introducing us to food. He took us to this
shrine, which is where one of the warriors that fought at this actual real invasion, he fought
and died here on this beach.
there was a shrine here commemorating this fight, took us there, took us to the beach where the
invasion actually happened. It's called Komodohama Beach. Honestly, I thought it was just gonna be
those photos and sort of just like what we're making and what became true was I was so invested
from
an emotionally perspective, emotional point of view. Like I came back home thinking I really
want to do right by all the people that helped us and the new colleagues that I have and the
new friends that I had. I really wanted to do right by the locations that I saw and I think
our entire team felt that way. And so you have this like personal investment that's far bigger
than just creating a piece of entertainment and it really helps drive your ambition and your passion
and your patience to to tackle some of these very challenging problems ahead. So that personal
investment is very real.
When you take on a project like this,
you're also going to learn a lot about various things.
Here's a katana or a tachi.
A tachi, I can't remember exactly what this one is,
but you learn a lot about how a sword is created.
And this right here is called a suba.
And suba is just this hand guard.
And that's what I kind of went into this trip
thinking it was.
And then I went to a sword museum,
and I realized, and this sword museum was just insane.
They make swords, they have old decorative swords here.
and you realize this Suba is not just a hand card, it is a hand card.
It's a lot more than that.
It is icons of just artistry and mastery. Just beautiful pieces of Japanese artwork
that I just kind of thought was a cool looking hand guard. And you realize that sometimes it's
connected to family, sometimes it's connected to stories. There's so much art and craft that
goes into a single sword. And that, even that little piece of inspiration, that little nugget
of knowledge, drives so... You come back home in months later and it drives so much energy to create.
our own weapons and our own swords and getting those details, not just to be cool, but if we
had a character that was, her name was Masako, who was going after the people that killed her
grand, her grandbabies, she's a hunter. And so going after, you know, when we have to create
this piece of artwork, it's not just a generic piece of cool art, it's connected to who she is
as a character in an artfully poetic way, deepening her story or deepening our main hero story, which
is Jin Sakai, the Sakai storm, you know.
deeply connected to him and his pushing out the Mongol invasions, which, you know,
they say that a windstorm came and pushed them, pushed the Mongols off the island.
And that's, that's like us being inspired by the artistry and the craftsmanship,
even in this single Suba. And so that research trip did give us a lot of photos.
It did give us a lot of great, you know, references guide,
but the personal investment to do a great job coming back home and saying.
Man, Jonah was a great guy.
I want to do right by him.
How can, you know, and feeling that you're now
you're part of a team and that inspiration
carried us through so many, so many hard times.
And I can't recommend a trip like that enough.
We did have to grow our team.
We grew our team quite a bit.
This isn't all of them, but these are the types of positions
that we sort of grew in terms of the consultants
we bring on.
We had a number of people from Sony Japan
that actually helped us from the very beginning.
Yuhei Katami actually ended up moving over to the US at some point and he actually worked on our project full time for a number of years.
He's a great producer, a great consultant, he's just incredible.
And so we've surrounded ourselves with some internal folks and then we actually surrounded ourselves with some language consultants,
some Mongolian language consultants. We had one person very early on to just help us understand religion,
the difference between Shintoism, Shinto and Buddhism, or a temple.
shrine, it was very confusing. And it's even more confusing for 1274, predating the Meiji restoration,
it even gets more complex. And so having someone that was just an expert in this very complicated
area was so helpful. Obviously our game's about combat. There's a ton of combat consultants that
we had, and all of them are just exquisite and just amazing and just so so helpful.
And we even had some people that weren't necessarily brought on to be consultant guides, like Shigeru
Umabayashi was our composer, one of our two composers.
and he's Japanese, and he would see our game
and he would give us feedback.
And of course, it was just like so great
to get feedback from our Japanese composer
and to hear his voice and to just understand
what he thought we were making
and what we could do to make it better.
So even though he's making the music
and I couldn't wait to hear the music,
I was also excited that he was invested enough to say,
hey, you know, maybe these plants could be different.
And that was excellent.
So we've equipped ourselves.
with new colleagues to guide us and we've sort of gotten into this position of learning,
like really sitting back and taking a seat, taking a position of learning from these guides.
So now we have these historical guides and we have these consultants, cultural consultants
surrounding us, but we still had to make a game and sometimes there's this conflict, you know, the
Something the guide says is very different than what you need the game to be, and you have to resolve this conflict.
And this is where all I can tell you right up front is that the majority of time it can take to get these problems right.
Because it's about balancing, you know, how can the game be an incredibly fun game,
but also a poetic and artful and thoughtful experience.
And that takes time, and it takes time getting to know your consultants, it takes time getting to know your game.
And that's a huge part of what we do.
And so I'm going to talk a little bit
about some of our examples and some of our goals
with what we were doing.
So at the very top, it's important to really highlight
what we were building.
Now, we are not, and we never wanted
to be a sort of a Tsushima one for one, rock for rock,
stone for stone, building for building simulator.
First of all, the game, it takes place in 1274.
It's just so long ago, it's hard to even understand
exactly where things were.
But furthermore, that's not our team size, it's not our goal.
It's actually, our goal is to really just get enough
of those details right to transport you
in an artistic and respectful way.
If the details are really important,
we're gonna get them right.
We're not gonna mess those up.
And we surround ourselves with people to get it right.
But outside of that, we want you to feel
transported and it make it feel memorable for you.
And actually, this is just for its worth.
This is exactly what we did the second time we made the game in Seattle.
But, you know, Pioneer Square doesn't look anything like our Pioneer Square.
It has similar brick types and material types.
The Space Needle is in the game, but it's not exactly in the right spot.
And, you know, we were there are two bridges, but they're sort of nowhere
near the same type of bridges that we have here.
it's about the impressionistic view of something,
a blurry-eyed view showcasing sort of the feeling of a place.
If people's perception of Seattle is rainy and wet, it is.
Then we should deliver some version of that.
And maybe we push it.
And we may be expressive.
So we're trying to create a Tsushima that
can be expressive and artful and entertaining,
but culturally thoughtful as well.
Now, if it's not about getting every single detail right,
there's a problem.
There's a misunderstanding.
Right?
And if weThreeD implemented that,
then we did all the erasers and everything else.
that's great. You might think that saves you some time, but I'll tell you, I don't know if it does,
because literally, as soon as you invite your consultants to sort of kind of partake in giving
feedback on every axis of your game, you realize very quickly that every department is going to
be affected by this. So you have to plan for the time. So just to run through a couple things
that you may not consider, I've heard all of these on our game.
There's an instrument in the game that's playing.
Was that instrument really around in 1274?
Or those outfits, they don't really look like
the history reference that I saw.
Or that family crest, it's real and it's a modern crest
and it belongs to a modern family.
This could be sort of looked at poorly.
The story moment is anachronistic
or the architectural style is off
or the dialect is too modern.
It's not about, I could go on and on,
it's not about getting all of these right
because we don't have the time.
We could work on this for 10 years
and you could get some of these wrong.
It's just creating them is tough.
But which ones are important?
That's the ones you wanna work with your guides on.
Which ones are the ones that we must get right?
And which ones are gonna be transportative?
And you wanna get those right because.
really know what a torii gate was before I took on this project. I kind of knew, but you know,
taking on this project you learn very quickly what it is. But you know, in our team we started
first putting the gates in the world and you google a torii gate and you're going to get
something like this pretty quickly. You're going to see something modern, it's a little flashy,
it's larger, it's not of humble origins, it's of you know pretty big origins.
and you work with your consultants pretty early and you realize this is not really representing
an authentic view of old Japan. This feels very new and modern and you get guidance that like
maybe you should head back into a more natural feeling where you feel like they're made out of
natural pieces of wood. They're humbler in size to represent the smaller community that Sushima
had.
There's a lot of amazing shrines on Tsushima,
but we were representing it a little bit poorly at first
in our first kind of look into it.
So it's about going one level deeper on those details
to make sure that you get them right.
And so thanks to our guys for helping out with those details.
And there's a lot more,
especially around religion that I could go into,
but I'm gonna hit a couple other topics like naming.
Now, naming a hero for a new IP
that nobody's heard this name before.
it's so hard. You want it to be short and sweet and has personality and easy to say,
you know, regardless of what you're making. You want these memorable names.
And, you know, we had this complication here that, you know, was brought up. It's like, oh,
well, are we going to name him in the English version? Are we going to name him
like it would be in Japan where you'd have the family name and then the given name? Or are we
going to do a European style or, you know, how my name is like Jen Sakai, Jason Connell.
And we actually had to talk about this, because all your scripts will have to be written this way.
You know, it's a pretty big change if you're going to do it in English.
We had to talk about it. You had to create time to have this discussion,
which we've never had this problem before.
Now, this problem ended up solving itself because we decided to make a Japanese localization track,
ship with every single copy, and you can select it from the very first menu in the game.
We realized that this is going to solve itself.
We're just going to let people play the way they want to play.
But at that time, we did consider the options early on. We had to discuss this. Our consultants
brought it up. I think Ryuhei brought it up himself. And there are other issues that we
had with names. Like we had a character whose name shipped with Yuna, but her name was Yone
for a very long time. And that name actually came from one of our Japanese partners very early. Now
her character over time started morphing into a character that had modern ideals and sort of
that name Yone.
sort of started clashing with sort of her character type over time and we started getting
feedback from our consultants and our kind of partners that her name didn't really fit with
who she's becoming and man we had already done written some stuff we had been working on this
name for a long time and to us Yone and Yuna sound so similar we don't know and so we're
completely blind to this and so you have to trust in the people that you're getting guidance from
and so for this particular example
even though we didn't understand and maybe we were even perplexed, you have to ask them and you have
to trust. And when somebody says, oh, the character doesn't feel like it matches the name, it really
kind of pulls you out of the experience for them. If the name felt very old, it was an old feeling
name and this character was very modern in their ideals, that's bad to us. I don't want that for
any of our characters. So even though we had production sort of things to sort out, we ended
up changing the character's name. Now, again,
I could continue going on and on and on with a ton of examples.
In fact, probably could give a two hour presentation about all of these types of examples, but
that's not the point.
The point is.
This stuff, it takes time.
It takes time to sort them out.
It takes time to realize which consultants
are the right people to handle different types of,
tackle different types of problems.
It takes time to hire consultants.
The whole process takes time.
And even with us being pretty committed to it,
it still takes a lot of time.
So I think that's one of my most important points
that I wanted to convey in this, is
that even though our team treated this very, very, very
seriously, it still just took a lot of time.
I do think there's some things I can share though that might be helpful. So here were a few ways
that we, you know, when we get a piece of feedback that we could potentially see the feedback be
broken up into different types of answers. So we'd get a piece of feedback and talking to our
consultant they would say, oh you know what this is an okay thing to experiment in so we'd be good
to go and we would try some experimentation.
We'd get some feedback that's just like a hard no.
This is super, you know, you need to avoid this.
This is, you know, it's not what you think it is.
And we just full stop, we just listen.
Sometimes there's game needs
and the game has to function a certain way.
There's, it's gotta be fun.
We want the progression to work a certain way.
And
that doesn't mean we don't listen to our consultants at all.
We just kind of keep going back saying, okay, what if we try this?
Or what if we try that?
And typically we can find something that works, that feels comfortable,
and we can both have our cake and eat it too.
And then sometimes, it's my favorite, you can have feedback that inspires design
and inspire big design changes.
Let me give you a couple examples.
We at one point in the script had seppuku, which is this act of sort of killing oneself.
and super clear feedback very early on that that was something we should avoid.
It's out of time period. It felt like we were shoving it in because it's a trope.
We thought it was very interesting. We certainly didn't want any of that. So we actually rewrote
that out and we've never looked back. It was the right decision and we're really glad that we removed it.
We get feedback about architecture in our game.
So we did have a lot of architecture that was Kamakura period inspired.
And if you know, that's actually the time period that these buildings were built.
And there was a certain way they looked.
But at some point we started experimenting with other types of building structures and we got some feedback that why are we doing this and we would talk to them and what we learned is that you know what, it's actually great if you do a good job with establishing Kamakura as the base, and then you're sort of exploring in architectural styles to try to create unique feeling across the island or little pockets of, you know, you know, memorable locations and it was okay to experiment and that was that was good for us to hear. Same thing with outfits, by the way.
Sometimes the game has needs and our game specifically we wanted no mini-map, we wanted no compass, we didn't want...
we wanted to be able to look around the island and see what you want to do next, but
Tsushima is like hills everywhere and super dense forests. We have a horse...
You've got to ride a horse, you've got to fight, you can't be on steep inclines.
So we actually had to flatten some areas out.
We still have lots of hills.
We had to flatten some areas out.
We had to de-forest a little bit so that we could get that, you know,
those flat areas where you could see where you're going next.
And we had to work with our consultants about what the right feeling was.
And we eventually got there in a great way.
But that was a lot of where the game had needs.
And lastly, we used to have hunting in the game because I think it's very common.
And, you know.
have bow, see animal, must kill.
There's this like feature that's hunting in games
that is great for a lot of games
and we didn't particularly want to go deep on it.
But moreover, we got feedback that hunting deer
was just so strange because hunting mindlessly
didn't really fit into the culture of Japan.
You know, it was sort of like they had a lot of
huge respect for animals, especially these deer.
So, okay, we had to reevaluate this.
At the same time, we were discussing ways
in which we could, you know, maybe
make Jin fall in love with the island? How can we inspire him to really feel like he's being guided
by the island more? And this changed the way that we treat animals. Sort of, next thing you know,
the wind came up, and then we had birds. We de-incentivized killing deer, and sort of,
and kind of gave us a whole new look at some of the way we treat animals in the game.
So I'm going to talk a little bit about some of the takeaways for some of the areas where our consultants and our guides came into sort of almost like conflict with some of our game goals and how we sort of maybe overcame some of those and some of the takeaways.
Well, first of all, 1274 was so long ago that there were.
a numerous amount of historical discrepancies and variation in what we were kind of researching.
It was just kind of all over the place. We had to surround ourselves with enough guides that
would give us good feedback and we would have to take the best approximate guess to sort of solve
some of our historical-based issues. You know, we surround ourselves with the facts and try to do
the best we could. Each example, as given by the previous section with the four quadrants,
challenges. I mean, they're different teams, they're different challenges,
they're different levels of passion. And sometimes, sometimes it's even
technical hurdles. I guess it's, it's, it's, it's can underline in bold this,
but it's just so different for each piece of feedback that you might get.
Now, one thing that we did was really helpful is we had Rie Katami, he was
sort of our point person, he was at the nexus of almost every single piece of feedback that we
tried to address. In fact, actually, he became so close to some of the team members. I know for me,
in particular, I utilized my, my, my, my relationship with Yuriyuhei grew so much
throughout the part of this project, because I would talk to him so much. I'd be like,
hey, what do you think about this? Hey, what do you think about that? You know,
anytime he and I, or one of their leads had an idea about.
Doesn't matter if it's an animation thing, you know, how the character holds a sword,
or a story thing, or an architectural bit.
we would call him and say, hey, what do you think about blah?
And if he didn't know, then he would kind of go down the list
of he would know who to talk to and would either point us
in the right direction or he would take
on the problem himself.
He was so invested in having that single point of contact
allowed us to be very proactive in our endeavors
to sort these problems out and point at them
as in the ideation phase, not wait till they're already
through production.
And it was also made it really great to, you know, I think this is a great goal.
Luckily for us, it never turned into an us versus them or, you know, game
versus history in a real, you know, conflict like negative sense.
It was very collaborative.
And it was that way because it felt like we had, you know, people like you
to helping us that were just part of the game team.
Like we were just trying to create a great game together.
And that collaboration.
is key because we are a team.
And I can't say this enough too, that it really
isn't about getting all the details perfectly fit
and right, and even our consultants would guide us
here.
It's about very specific ones are very important.
But it's enough to earn that belief and that trust
and that respect.
And then the rest of it's how do you
create the great piece of poetic entertainment
that we were hoping that we would create?
And that sort of goes on to talk a little bit about the next session.
You know, that's a little bit about how we dealt with some of that feedback
and how entertainment and sort of our guidance along the way could sometimes collide.
And hopefully that's helpful to you.
But this next section is really,
I wanna talk about what inspired Ghost
and how frankly, this is the other pieces of entertainment
ended up being sort of their own consultants in a way.
I wanna talk about our, frankly, our inspirations.
We talk a lot about various types of other consultants
that we had that were very specialized
that we brought in to help create the game.
But one very important strategy is that we study the works of all of these great creators that came before our game was even an idea, or even sometimes before we were around.
How have Japanese artists and filmmakers and Japanese game developers depicted Japan in the past?
Or maybe Japan-like places, if that's a made-up place.
So our goal was to create a piece, you know, an entertainment piece, a piece of
a work of art and a game that sits right next to the artistry that we were,
frankly, inspired by so much growing up.
You know, frankly, we had decades of entertainment consumption.
that have been ingrained into who we are.
And so we really believe that looking
at some of these neighbors, some of our most
influential pieces of work, could really help guide us.
So I'm going to show you some of the inspirations that we had,
ones that we held onto really tightly,
even though it might have taken some time for a while for us
to really see the benefits come out.
So we did set out with a few very distinct visual
inspirations in mind, famous simplified illustrators.
from Japan like Hasui Kawase featured really low detail style block print artwork
Bold and high contrast yet really impactful. You don't really see the rocks and the sand in these illustrations
But what you do see is the memorable shapes the bold colors
It's it's very curated and there's a lot of overlap with this simplified look and feel
to this wonderful game called Breath of the Wild
that showcases really great, you know, kind of restrained
and disciplined use of color
and this like single beautiful species of grass
that's like a love leaf,
like a loving leaf flowing through in the wind.
It's beautiful.
And there's this low noise feeling,
this high color and saturation
and this great curated feeling to both of these.
So the question was,
could we take these types of inspirations?
and apply them to a more realistic samurai epic?
That was the question.
And this proved to be pretty hard.
You know, we were frankly inherently Western game artists
and our goal was, left our own kind of path,
was sort of heading towards the path of general realism.
And so a common goal in games
is to create these realistic spaces.
And we just got done with Second Son,
which was like, had a little bit of that realism
and that grittiness.
You know, Seattle's very different.
And we kind of really headed this way pretty hard, but it just felt like something wasn't right.
It wasn't really transportative. It wasn't very memorable.
And at one point, it certainly didn't feel like some of those references that I just showed you.
And at some point on the project, fairly early,
Shuhei Yoshida-san gave us feedback that his memory,
and this is great, his memory of Japan is that it was more green.
He felt like it was missing that.
And I just really liked that.
I thought that him saying his memory of Japan is a memory.
Because memories are this blurry thing
where you don't see every single tiny little detail, right?
Really, the only things that resonate with you,
something will stand out.
So if we were going to create a fern forest.
why would we go with the one on the left when we could honestly head more in this direction where
we create a fern forest that is single and species type it's like all-consuming like we
want to leave you with the memory of a fern forest it's certainly more saturated more green
and hopefully you step away from that feeling like I visited the Fern Forest and I know where it is now.
And this had a lot of overlap with, you know, some of the references that I kind of mentioned
earlier and certainly some of the paintings or the illustrations that I mentioned as well from Kawase.
So this was resonating with us and so we started taking the game in this direction and
boy the visuals exploded everywhere.
you went in the game, you could find this magnificent, beautiful, simplified, yet still
gritty and kind of realistic if you wanted to look at it. It had realistic features, but it was very
simplified in like species. And that was so important to us. This was so important to us,
the noise, like the low noise to try to match this like feeling, was so important to us that we
created tools that our artists could use to find areas where there was too much noise in the game.
If it was red, it was too noisy, and the artist could go in and do a pass to remove the amount of noise.
And therefore, you could have this... you could very quickly and easily isolate that this rock texture here...
It's a great rock texture, but it was very noisy, and you could go in and address it,
and simplify it down, and let it sit down, and sort of be complementary to the art style that we were trying to go for, instead of this...
realistic noise to the frame.
And this was wonderful because we're making an open world game,
and this was our visual target.
And where we landed was sort of in the cinematic,
stylized view of the game, where there
was minimal sort of species around the world in terms
of foliage, but really, really, really impactful and colorful.
And at the textural level, we try
to remove as much noise as possible
so you see the details that matter,
which is sort of a theme for this entire topic,
or this entire talk.
And that manifested into multiple different types of biomes
and an art style that sort of resonated
with our fans in the end.
But it's not all about, obviously, style and color.
There's tons of other areas we were inspired by
that changed the course of the game.
Cinematography could go on and on about the types of cinematography that we were inspired by.
I'll just say that we looked at a lot of old and new samurai movies and we would look for patterns
and there were patterns that would pop up in a lot of these films and one of them is which
is like a centered framing with a human or a subject matter and in the very very center but
it's very equal framing and so we would look for these patterns and then we would look for areas
whether it was in marketing.
or in the actual game cinematography that we could utilize these patterns in our own ways,
because we know it would resonate with other fans that had watched these types of films, etc.
Here's another one.
Duels.
If you've seen a samurai movie, there's this,
it's not about the duel, it's about the human tension
that's so palpable between these two fierce warriors
that are sort of standing behind this beautiful backdrop.
Everything is just so amazing around them,
and yet there's just this silent tension
between these two people.
You know, I didn't grow up necessarily watching samurai movies.
In fact, I grew up watching what most of us would feel like
in the West or in the US might be more
familiar to, which is Westerns.
And they have the same thing because they are inspired by that.
There's the same human tension is so palpable between two gunslingers.
That is, it's two people with a sword.
And so we really felt like this was a great thing to capitalize on in terms of like put into our
game having that human tension because you've seen it in samurai movies and it's real and it's human
but it was also familiar. So what we did is we created
a number of very specific duels in our game.
And those duels are set against unique backdrops,
really a beautiful display of environment art.
There's this human narrative that usually is going on
between you and the person that you're dueling.
It's fairly serious.
They're actually pretty tough too.
And there's a cinematic that happens before
that builds the music.
It's really built around having tension before the fight.
We would also create a feature later on called standoffs
that would let you have systemic duels.
more often, more frequent at your own discretion.
But getting that attention was really key for us.
We also were inspired by a number of books, whether it's graphic novels
for entertainment, or if it was documentaries and books that would
help us understand the history.
You know, both of them do so much, but you know, the entertainment based books,
the graphic novels, the artistry in them, we could learn, I think what we learned
was like human connection.
variety of types of complex relationships, whether it was, you know, protecting a young kid or,
you know, something about betrayal, like somebody that might betray you.
And certainly the books we learned about just how can we best depict the Mongol invasion
and do right by what these history books could help us help us out with.
So we looked at several books as well.
Sometimes our research and our kind of entertainment inspiration overlap,
and our historical research and our kind of love for samurai cinema overlap.
And in one particular way, it came out with just this like crazy, interesting, super new idea for the game.
So we're big fans of, you know, movies, Kurosawa movies, these movies that have wind and movement in these famous samurai classics.
But turns out, I mentioned a little bit before, but the wind also had a major part in the actual history.
of the events of 1274, the invasion.
The belief is that this windstorm,
known as the Divine Wind,
sort of pushed the Mongols back to sea
and protected Japan, not once, but actually twice.
And that's kind of an incredible story,
so incredible that we really decided
that we should underline this.
And it ended up becoming a mechanic in our game.
In our game, the wind, if you haven't played it,
the wind...
sort of kind of pick the wind's next target and the game's particle effects
on the wind would sort of blow in the direction you need to go next. So many
reasons why this was a fun decision to come to but it took
that historical research and understanding. It took the years of
samurai movie watching that we kind of were so inspired by.
And it took us sort of kind of coming up with a variety of ideas to get there.
And so those overlapping themes really helped us come up with a really poetic and great feature
that really propelled the game in a lot of ways.
So one of our greatest inspirations in the end came full circle.
We're finishing up the game and I mentioned that, you know, we were so inspired by Kurosawa.
We actually ended up having a mode in the game called Kurosawa Mode and it was introduced
into the game after working with the Kurosawa estate, showing them our game.
sort of having a couple back and forths, answering some questions, and really trying to faithfully
show them what we're trying to create. And so much of our game is inspired by the art and the
cinematography and the storytelling of a Kurosawa classic. We were just so honored to get to have
this relationship and to have this feature and to have it named such. Because in the end,
the fans of our collective,
you know, whether it's games or watching those films,
our collective biggest fans together
could enjoy this crossover in this way in our game.
And that was kind of like,
the sort of towards the end of the project.
And it was just this really rewarding moment
for everyone here at the team.
So just to kind of recap, we talked about how Ghost got started with a simple player fantasy
idea that almost wasn't Samurai because we were scared of this topic. We were scared of how we
were going to do this, you know? And I'm so glad we went back and really chose Samurai. It was the
right choice for us and I'm so glad that we kind of faced that problem and that challenge head-on.
and didn't let our fears sort of tear us away from our dreams.
We talked a little bit about our kind of journey
into taking a little bit of a backseat,
learning from people, the art of learning, if you will,
and just being really proactive
and developing, frankly, new relationships
with a bunch of amazing people
that help make our game great.
And this is where the relationship is forged, right?
Like the complex problem solving
between game and authenticity and what happened in history
and, you know, making entertainment.
original story versus the true events.
This is where the relationships of all of our consultants
thrived and came alive.
And hopefully that section was helpful
in sharing how we dealt with some of those subjects.
And lastly, way before we ever decided to make this game,
we were fans of the genre.
So of course we bring forward our own kind of depiction
of how it.
how we would hope it could be represented,
how we hope it can be appreciated.
And so those inspirations are really important.
And sometimes those inspirations
are guided by consultants as well.
Other consultants can give us feedback
about its representation in Japan
and how they might, may or may not view it.
But those inspirations are kind of
what starts you off to begin with.
So you have to have them throughout the entire game.
You know, so to sum up, you know, creating massive pieces of entertainment,
they take years to create.
Five years to create, six years to create.
Games are, they're so complicated and they're minor miracles
that they get finished at all sometimes.
You know, and this is saying you're going through a lot of extra work
and you might ask, why go through all that extra work?
You know, the years spent talking about these reference points,
the labor, sometimes reworking, you know, names, you know, for us, it's.
we really wanted to create a game that thoughtfully represents a culture that is not our own.
And then that comes with a sense of responsibility. And if we wanted this to resonate with the wide audience...
in a way that all those classic samurai films did for us,
or some of those games and books that I mentioned did for us,
then we really need to pay attention to this.
And we need to take it seriously.
So make no mistake, the responsibility is real,
and it's super heavy, and it takes a lot of energy
and patience.
But like most things, it requires strength
in relationships with people around you,
especially things like this.
That team that you develop along the way.
can be really transformative in the game that you can create.
So we're honored.
you know, that it played out the way it did. And we did learn from many mishaps and lapses of
judgment along the way, but we cannot really express how thankful we are that to all the
consultants that did help us on this project, as well as all of our teammates in Japan,
the localization team, recorded audio, people that recorded audio from us from Japan, like,
it's just the list goes on and on. So I'm just going to put a big loud thank you out to the world.
for anyone that ever helped give guidance and feedback on our project and helped us understand more what we are creating,
so that we could make something that fits the expectations of a great samurai game, a great piece of samurai media.
So thank you all for helping us recreate Feudal Japan from across the Pacific.
So thank you for listening to my talk.
Sucker Punch is hiring if you're looking for a new adventure.
Cheers.