So thank you again so much for coming.
So I've done amazing projects.
I'm grateful for these jobs on which I composed, lots of mobile games.
My latest job was this music for an exhibit at the Kennedy Space Center.
And I also have worked as an arranger and orchestrator for some amazing projects, which
I loved and am very grateful.
So just a couple of brief reviews, mostly for developers.
Developers know that music provides the emotional depth of the gaming experience.
But the score of your game is also a powerful branding device for your game.
It defines the genre, aesthetics, the world, characters, factions, the story, time and location.
What's most powerful to me is how music makes us remember the entire gameplay experience.
Remember for a moment the iconic theme for Mario or Tetris or Halo.
As soon as I mentioned these titles, do you guys have like an instant picture,
memory picture of the music to these games?
For instance, I personally will never forget my experience of playing Modern Warfare 2,
which was really frustrating. I kept getting killed on one level.
And I always associate that gameplay with that droning music in D minor
that just went on throughout the whole level.
And that's my physical memory of just that awesome game that kept beating me.
So, for a game composer, one of the most important tasks is to create a sonic world that fits
the vision and the aesthetics of the game like a glove, and to make the game a memorable
experience, because this is what we remember.
In today's market, there are thousands of games, there's an ocean of product.
And maybe the goal of this talk is to actually make developers aware of the fact that you could use the score as a powerful branding device of your game, a very specific score, a very unique score that has a very specific sound.
and fits your game perfectly and sounds like nothing else,
or somewhat like something else, but is very unique.
And ultimately, the most important thing
is that good music will always elevate
the production and artistic value of your game.
So with this talk, which is kind of very practical,
I hope to give you practical tips
on the collaboration between developers and composers,
or developers and the audio team,
and how to find the style, the voice of your score.
So when you're ready, when the developer is ready
to commission the composer to write music,
regardless of how big or small that score is going to be,
come to us with a very clear vision of your game
because composers will always try to support
to the best of their ability the vision of that game.
Talk to us about the aesthetics. For instance, I'm a very visual person. I respond really well to
environment art, character art, costumes, weaponry, just all the visual components that make up the game.
I mean, I'm kind of an okay game player. I do play a lot of games,
but the aesthetics of your visual aesthetics are going to really inspire me.
Now, we also discuss in these collaborative conversations that happen first,
something I call tone lineage.
I could describe it like, how is your game going to be similar in tone?
And I'm talking about overall tone.
This is the overall gestalt of your game.
How is your game similar in tone to games that preceded it?
And then we talk about...
how is your game going to fit in that lineage of tradition and innovation?
These are two very powerful concepts for me.
I love and adore the tradition, I've studied the tradition.
So basically there's this whole spectrum between very traditional,
very conventional games and also very innovative,
fresh, completely unique games that sort of hit you
and come at you from left field and of course the whole entire spectrum.
In my own composing, I've composed a lot of traditional music
and I also have tried to push myself and be innovative on some projects.
So these are all questions that we discuss in these opening conceptual conversations,
which I love and adore. It's my favorite part of the collaborative process, these opening
lunches or Skype conversations when we talk about ideas. And ideas flow back and forth
between the creatives, between the developers and their composing team or composers.
One of the most important goals that I set upon myself
when I collaborate with anybody, game maker, filmmaker,
is to understand as much as I can about your taste,
musical taste.
We talk about your favorite soundtracks from similar games
or your favorite soundtracks from your childhood
because all of us are so much driven
and defined by our taste.
Our taste in music, our taste in art, our taste in games.
in cinema and as a collaborative composer
one of my biggest tasks is to learn as much as I can about your vision,
your ideas and your taste. And I just by asking questions, you know, tell me what you
like.
And I do it with game makers, I do it with filmmakers. It always helps me to
understand what kind of music
you're most likely to resonate with and respond really well.
Ultimately our job as composers is to find that signature style, signature sound
that's going to define your game as a sonic experience and that's going to
become that memorable experience. So that's again conversations and
prototyping and the goal is to have that signature style for your characters and
for your game.
So the kind of questions, so basically the process for me always has been from the bigger picture,
which I called Gestalt, kind of coming down and focusing in on more details. So, so far I talked
about the big picture, ideas, concepts, aesthetics, style, lineage. Now I'm going to start getting
more specific and these are the kind of questions I ask my collaborators. So what musical elements
will work for your score?
And actually, I've been very blessed to work with really articulate game developers,
and sometimes I have to kind of ask more questions to get more information.
And then the other question, which is just as valid, is what elements do you not want?
What elements will not work for your score?
And we kind of go and make a list.
So basically last year I worked on this amazing collaborative experience.
It's a game called Mayhem.
It's, okay, let me now get this straight.
It's a mobile, synchronous, multiplayer, like eSports, shooter.
It got awarded at South by Southwest.
I'm proudly wearing the shirt, the t-shirt today.
And so it's like a...
I'll show you a couple of visuals.
I wanted to speak about this game today
because it was a beautiful collaboration
and the developers were very articulate.
It was like one of these perfect, perfect situations
of beautiful back and forth and collaborative process.
So just a couple of visuals to kind of give you a sense
of the visual aesthetics.
So they were really good with their conceptual guidance
in their briefs and I called out literally from their brief,
this is, everything is a quote.
This is what they told me.
The game is a sci-fi adventure, not too distant future.
The costumes and weaponry blend the past and the present.
And so it's not too advanced, not too sci-fi,
not too far in the distant future.
This is one of the most amazing metaphors
I've ever been given by a collaborator.
I loved it so much.
This was in their brief.
More aliens, less Star Wars.
So for somebody like me who adores science fiction
and really lives and breathes the whole vernacular,
the whole.
you know, fantasy, science fiction, horror,
this quote meant more than like hours and hours
and hours of conversation.
So I would encourage your collaborators
to kind of give you these metaphors
because they're a powerful tool of collaboration
and they really save us a lot of prototyping and headache.
That was also part of their initial brief.
So the visual style is a blend of sci-fi and contemporary war game.
So this is what they wanted.
They wanted the music to be exactly that middle ground, not too sci-fi,
which would be too much electronica and synths, or not too much action,
which is like the big...
Because I'm known for doing a lot of action games like Gears of War,
or big strings and big horn melodies.
So exactly middle ground.
and not too sci-fi.
So a couple more visuals.
So then we started, so after talking about
these more specific details,
then we got even more specific.
global considerations for the score.
Music is a tertiary audio element.
The sound effects and the environment ambiences
always take precedence, because they're
part of the auditory experience.
Music is a tertiary audio element.
So then we start getting even more focused on the style.
So they wanted a hybrid style, which
is a little bit of orchestra and electronica.
They wanted pulsing synth textures,
because that's modern scoring.
They wanted ambient pads to suggest science fiction.
and sprinkle some sound effects here and there
to spell out that the game is a science fiction game.
So this is all, again, from the wonderful brief
I received from my collaborators.
So what they did not want, and this was, again,
just as useful as anything else,
is they did not want big, soaring melodies,
especially no brass melodies.
They did not want busy chord progressions.
And they did not want bombastic choir,
because choir is associated with more like epic fantasy,
and they did not want that.
So I'm going to go ahead and play you a little bit
of the gameplay just for fun, and then I'm
going to play the music.
So you have a chance to see the visual,
and then you have a chance to focus on the music.
So here's a little bit of gameplay from this shooter.
So for the composers in the audience, I also wanted to play just the music alone,
so you can isolate all the elements, you know, the groove, the pulses,
the very non-melodic material, but still kind of, you know,
still orchestral, except no soaring melodies.
So this is for, okay.
Okay.
So there were a couple of campaigns,
I wrote a couple of battle tracks,
and then there is obviously the menu music,
and this is again from the directions I received
from my collaborators.
Much less stressful, serious and foreboding,
subdued, not frenetic,
because the campaigns are very frenetic.
They did not want massive choirs,
they did not want drums,
and they did not want loud string melodies.
Again, I was just so lucky to have
this incredibly wonderful guidelines
given to me by my collaborators.
And this is what I did with these guidelines.
You
Okay, so this was that collaborative experience.
I wanted to now switch gears and talk
about another fantastic collaboration,
which is my most recent job.
It's not a game.
It's my music for a museum exhibition
at the Kennedy Space Center.
I got this job through a game connection,
and also the composing was 3D movies
and also interactive pods, so I figured it's interactive
and I could present it here.
It's called Heroes and Legends.
That's the name of the exhibition at the Kennedy Space Center,
and it hosts the American Astronaut Hall of Fame.
Here's just me standing in front of the exhibition.
I wanted to acknowledge one of my most cherished collaborators,
an extraordinary person and professional, John Rod,
the recording, mixing, and mastering engineer on this job
and all my jobs, all my projects.
John, would you please stand up and?
Thank you for a fantastic work and always just making everything sound so awesome.
So basically I'm going to play for you one musical piece which was accompanying a 3D
film that tells a story about the Gemini 8 mission.
The Gemini 8 mission was in 1966 and for the first time there was a manned capsule and
also an unmanned.
ship called the Agena that they had to undock and it was really complicated and that's one instance where
Things went wrong with something in the capsule. There was some mechanical malfunction and the mission had to be aborted
So my music was supposed to be on and that's the that's the capsule. That's just the experience here in the theater
You're watching this amazing earth. Everything is 3d and
The capsule just flies right in front of you right above you
so
The music for this 3D film was supposed to capture,
it was modern action, and it was supposed to capture
first the joy of space, because the first thing we see
in a 3D movie is what we see from inside the cabin outside.
And then I had to have action music
for the malfunctioning system, and then there's
this increasing level of tension and peril.
Ever increasing tension, and the stakes get higher
and higher with each musical structure,
and I had to build this, and keep building,
and keep building.
And at the end, the mission is aborted,
so I had to capture the hero who's been defeated.
So the people's lives are saved, which is good.
They kind of failed the mission, but we saved their lives,
so it's still a success.
This is how the conversation went with the clients.
The first idea that they presented to me is they said,
we really liked the movie The Right Stuff.
It's a film from 1983.
Have you guys watched The Right Stuff?
Raise your hands.
So it's like one of these iconic movies about cosmonauts.
It's scored by Bill Conti with a very traditional score,
totally orchestral and beautiful, melodic,
almost like Bach, almost like classical music.
and they did not want choir. This was one of their requirements.
Now I thought to myself, well, that score is awesome, but it was composed in 1983.
So now how do I sort of turn their idea around and still make them feel as if they're giving me the idea,
but like kind of put my ideas like in their brain.
So what I suggest, that's a very important skill for composers to have, to kind of...
share ideas and be really open, be really respectful,
but also present ideas and make your collaborators
think that they came up with the idea.
So I said, how about we approach this entire score.
and make it modern and timeless.
So the timeless component is going to be the classical music,
classical big strings and horn tunes and melodies
and classical chord progressions, almost like Bach.
So we have that classical component,
which is our timeless component.
But as far as the modern sound is concerned,
I mean, all of us have grown basically listening
to these very modern, pulsing, electronic percussive scores.
So I felt compelled to.
have very strong percussion arrangement and synths.
So that's how I combined the traditional melodic themes
for the heroes and orchestra with very modern arrangement
with busy percussion and synths.
And it worked beautifully.
So that's how I sort of turned their idea around and added my own input.
And they totally went, I mean, they just really loved the music.
They went with the idea.
So I cannot show you the movie because it's part of this 3D thing.
So I'll just show you some screenshots from a very early
rendering of the movie that I was given.
It just shows you mostly the inside the astronauts.
And that's the capsule and the Agena undocking.
And they spin.
So, that's another visual.
So here, I'm going to play the music and there's like seven structures, beauty of the space,
and I'm going to point as the music progresses, you'll hear it very clearly.
It's really, the music tells a story very clearly.
So let me now play this music and you can imagine the story that the music tells.
Have a great week.
Thank you for watching!
Okay, here's the last image.
So I wanted to open now for questions.
I'm eager to answer your questions.
Please be sure to fill out the evaluation forms.
That's my email.
It's okay to contact me.
Check me out on Twitter and everything else.
I welcome your questions now.
Thanks.
Hello, Pankaj, thank you so much, that was fantastic.
I was just curious if you'd be willing to share any techniques that you like to really
give that lower end ear candy that is great in your mixes, if you have anything that you
particularly enjoy, because obviously just the orchestral samples probably can't produce
that low warmth.
Okay, so we recorded brass and strings live.
Sometimes I use a little bit more,
like one more cello or two more celli,
but then the real magic is John Raud sitting right there.
He's fantastic.
He's the one who really shapes that low end.
Because I've worked so much in horror and fantasy,
there is always that.
music competing with the sound effects.
And I had so many conversations with people in horror games
basically saying, that's your biggest goal,
how to shape, how to sculpt the low end
so we still hear the machine guns
and they don't sound like popcorn.
But so that the music really works,
see because all we hear, sound effects, folly, dialogue,
it all goes into the ears.
So the music has to be very carefully sculpted
around the other elements in the audio.
And me coming from a genre background,
having done a lot of horror films and a lot of my music.
having been cut and not used. I learned the hard way to be incredibly sensitive, but talk to John,
he's going to give you the magic, the actual technicality. I just write the music, the notes.
But it starts with you putting in the musical elements.
Do you have any particular nice combinations?
I have ways, I have a really specific way how I voice the brass.
I always use octaves, two octaves, sometimes three octaves.
I worked for many years for the orchestrator of Hans Zimmer,
called Bruce Fowler, and he taught me how
to add one extra lower octave in the tuba.
So I have a particular way how I voice the brass that's just really heavy, like really punchy,
and it really kind of shows in all my orchestrations for Steve Jablonski.
Same thing with the strings, just really beef up the low end in octaves,
but never like in anything less than an octave.
So in the composition, in the arrangement, that's what I do, just kind of beef it up.
Awesome, thank you.
Thank you.
Hi, so for the developer who may or may not be somewhat musically inclined,
Do you have a sense of that you prefer to have direction from them in non-musical terms
like timid, warm, you know, sensual, or that you would actually, to what degree are you
open to very specific, like I want this to be an oboe?
Thank you, this is a perfect, awesome question.
Thank you so much.
The best collaborative process is if the developers
speak with their composers in terms of ideas.
First, talk to us about ideas.
Talk to us about emotions, mechanics,
storytelling, tradition, innovation.
The large, big concepts, so that's the one aspect
of wonderful collaboration.
The other collaboration is music.
Just give us like five MP3s and say,
well, I really love this.
Follow, you know, I like this about this,
I don't like this about this other thing.
So when we have both the concepts.
and the music equally represented music in terms of style guide from previous games or movies.
This is just the best because we know your concepts and your vision,
but we also know the kind of music that speaks to you and you feel is going to represent your game.
So if you only talk to us in words, then words are slippery.
I mean, we could talk about music and I'd say one thing, you interpret.
So there could be this misunderstanding.
But when it's the sense of concepts and aesthetics and ideas,
Also reinforced by your favorite music that you feel is gonna fit with the game.
That company, the company that made Mayhem, they did give me two mp3s.
They said this is what we like.
Make it like this, but unique for our game.
So I would say the best collaborative approach is ideas and your favorite music combined together.
And then the composers, they have ways of filtering, they have intuition and just skills and experience to filter.
And also, all of us, I encourage all composers to just play as many games, watch as many movies, learn the genres, learn music,
because that kind of becomes part of your intelligence as a composer.
I just voraciously play games and watch games all the time, so that's what we do.
But I would say...
concepts and music.
Yes.
Hi. I was wondering for the Gemini 8 piece,
how, or do you have a process for going from the general timeline
of the presentation of the film and the,
to the specifics of like tempo, things like that,
like does the overall length of the piece help determine your tempo?
Do you set that independently?
motivically, the structure?
So that's a really good question.
So the entire 3D movie is with dialogue.
So all the music was under dialogue.
And all the three, because it's like a documentary,
essentially, except it's really elaborate
with special effects, which you didn't see here.
So that's one of my first assignments,
and it's very challenging.
People ask me what's the happiest
and most challenging part.
The happiest part is these conceptual conversations
I just spoke about.
They're the funnest.
research and concepts is awesome.
The hardest part is when I open the blank template
and the movie's there, it's lined up,
and my job is to pace the music,
really structure the music,
so I always begin globally, that's how I work.
Not everybody's like this, that's just my process.
I would kind of mark the movie,
remember that chart I had with the...
energy curve kind of going up, so I had to sort of...
And then you have to hit beats.
In any linear media, which cinematics in games are,
or film scoring, or this 3D entertainment,
it's linear media, so we have to hit
moments where the energy changes, or the story changes.
So that's the first thing I do, and it's challenging,
because I haven't set the tempos yet,
and sometimes I have to lock these markers,
so I lock the markers, and then I experiment
with different tempos until I find the right tempo.
Thank you.
Hi, I have a question about discussing budget
with developers, like, you know,
if you get even just one live musician,
it can help supplement the sample libraries.
And I was wondering if you have any tips
on how to kind of communicate with developers
about recording budgets or anything relating to that.
That's a really good question.
Most of my games are, I mean, this is purely samples.
But I always make a case, if there's like one musician,
for instance, this is just a wild example, electric cello
that can add so much texture and variety.
And the cello seems to be such a magical instrument
for media scoring.
It's all conversations.
It's all trying to sell the idea that even a small, tiny budget
by adding one instrument can add so much artistic value.
And it's a conversation that you have to have.
But I would say, try to start small.
You can't really say, oh, we have a small mobile game.
I'm going to record orchestra.
Because they're not going to need that.
And they won't be able to afford.
but basically suggest how about we have one very versatile instrument,
maybe a wind instrument or a plucked,
plucked instruments also work really well,
or maybe electric cello,
and then work with one musician,
or maybe work with three musicians, or four.
This is something you can afford,
and it's a small part of the budget, but adds so much.
So the whole idea is that you're going to spend a little bit of money
and get so much more on your return of investment.
That's how I would approach it.
That's how I've always approached it for all these years.
that I worked, I still work with a lot of independent games
and mobile games and indie films,
and the pitch is always the same.
Let's just spend a little bit of money
and get fantastic live cello player.
I just did it on my horror film with a very low budget.
So the idea is you spend a little bit of money
to get huge result.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Any more questions?
I think we're out of time.
Okay guys, I'll be outside if you wanna talk to me.
Thanks again so much for coming.
Thank you.