I'm Carol Shaw. I've been a producer for a long time. I'm going to talk like years, like 15 years or something.
I'm going to talk about different specializations in production today.
And specifically, I'm going to give you, it's a more pragmatic and practical presentation about
the seemingly endless new and different types of production roles
and how to match up a particular role.
with your skills and interests.
So this is more about,
you don't wanna just be a general producer,
but you have maybe something special to grade at,
and you wanna figure out how to leverage that
into a specialized production role.
It's also a talk about how to adapt your production style,
this is all about style,
to different situations before
and during and after development.
And it's also a talk about production methodologies
and how to work with them when you start a new project
or join a project that's already in.
So this one represents Agile.
And we're also going to talk a little about Waterfall.
I'm going to adjust one thing really quick.
Or I'm not.
But that's cool.
In larger projects, we're going to dig right in.
In larger projects, producers end up supporting many different disciplines.
In smaller projects, they can support many multiple areas.
When I joined Spore as a producer, I was managing different parts of the project.
But by the end of the project, after we'd ramped the team up, I had, you know,
moved my interests into the two areas where I had more expertise.
So I had some time while the project was spinning up
to work on lots of different areas.
But by the end of it, I was fairly specialized
and working mostly with the online components
and working with PR and marketing.
So I was a producer that was a little bit more focused
looking outward from the project
rather than looking inward at the project.
The four primary areas we're gonna talk about
regarding disciplines in game development
are gonna be art.
And that includes both external outsourced art,
internal art, and UI.
We're going to talk a little bit about engineering.
Oh, there it goes.
That's what engineers look like when they code.
Producers didn't know that.
We're going to talk a little bit about design and production
for design, specific production for design.
And we're going to talk about online.
And it's kind of hard to see that slide,
but it's a slide of available servers for an online game.
Before we jump into all that though, I want to talk
about the different gradations of game development
within organizational structures.
So initially you, whoa, hey guy.
Initially, you have a game.
It's a single game or a single project based around one IP.
And that's kind of the most fundamental project
that would need some sort of production help.
A good example, I mean, there's a million of them,
but like Gone Home is one game by one studio
that is about one IP.
But then you start adding in other things,
and you have a franchise.
So this would be multiple games or products
that are related to one specific franchise.
So this is a good example.
I like to use this The Sims, which I worked on as well.
And that one's a game where there's
multiple iterations of The Sims.
There's Sims 1, and Sims 2, and Sims 4, and maybe a Sims 7.
And then there's all of the content packs
that come along with it.
Franchise.
that's gonna be a franchise, so that's gonna be
multiple products that are based around one IP.
When you add a bunch of those together,
what you end up with is a studio.
So that's gonna be multiple games or projects
based around multiple IPs.
So a good studio that's an example of that,
I think, is Double Fine.
So they released Psychonauts 1 years ago.
They're working on Psychonauts 2.
They just released a VR product
that's Psychonauts and the Rhombus of Ruin.
So, you can look at them and say, like, they have,
and then they have other one-off games,
like Broken Age and Headlander that they made that,
sorry, I have a little bit of a sore throat
because it's GDC, so hang on.
So, you can look at them and understand
that they're more of a studio with different IPs
with different products around them.
And then next...
you end up, if you have lots of different studios
that are all grouped together,
that's more of a corporate entity.
That's gonna be something like an EA.
So within EA, there's a lot of different studios.
One example is Visceral.
But Visceral has many projects that have multiple games
based around individual franchises,
but also do multiple franchises.
So Visceral does Dead Space,
and there's multiple Dead Spaces.
They did Godfather, there was multiple Godfathers.
But they also, BioWare is also part of EA,
and they have Mass Effect and all the Mass Effect products,
and then they have Dragon Age and all the Dragon Age products.
So that's what you kind of get up to the corporate level.
And then next, this is supposed to represent publishing,
which I had a really hard time figuring out
how to represent a publishing producer.
But publishing, a video game publisher is a company
that publishes video games
that they've either developed internally
or they publish those created
by an independent video game developer.
So they might draw in games from other studios
that they help publish.
And typically they manage the marketing.
Sometimes they help out with the QA
and user experience testing.
And they often handle distribution.
So, you know, Sony and Microsoft have big publishing arms.
So, they're big corporate entities
that have multiple internal game studios typically.
They also make hardware, but they also have a publishing arm
and you'll see stuff published by Sony
like Journey was published by Sony.
If you play that game, you should.
It's a great game.
Now that you have a good overview of what the different corporate structure of all the
different game development opportunities that are out there, what I want to start doing
is talking about the different specializations that you'll find within some of those different
companies.
And basically I'm going to go through it the way I talked about those disciplines, so art,
engineering, design, and online.
We're going to talk about the different specializations of producers within those different disciplines.
So we're gonna start with Art Outsourcing Producer,
which is a very specialized version of an art producer.
Typically, art can be produced in lots of different ways,
and very few, unless they're very small studios,
produce all their own art anymore.
Often they outsource art to cheaper overseas organizations.
Doesn't matter where you live,
somebody is always going to be overseas from you.
And basically, they need somebody who's going to run that part of the business.
So the things that you're going to spend your time in,
if you do an art outsourcing producer job, you're going to be in email a lot.
You're going to be in Excel a lot, both to keep organization of your project,
Excel or Google Docs, because you're also going to be worried about the budget.
You're going to have to work in all different time zones,
because you're going to be having calls and meetings to review stuff
at all different times.
But you're also going to need to have somewhat of an art eye.
So you're going to need to be able to give the art director.
feedback on the art that you're receiving,
whether it hits his or her quality bar
that you're looking for.
Because basically, the art outsourcing producer might say,
okay, we're gonna do all the concept art internally,
and then we're gonna outsource the modeling and the rigging,
and then we're gonna get it back
and do all the texturing and animation.
So coordinating all of that isn't gonna be an artist's job.
That's gonna be an art outsourcing producer's job
to make sure that everything kind of
goes down along that path.
The skills that you're going to want to bring to that are going to be like a very,
very highly attuned attention to detail because stuff can just get lost,
particularly when you're dealing with outsourcing houses that don't
necessarily have English as their first language if English is your first language.
But you need to be able to manage that and keep things in order.
There's some good and bad things about each one of these,
and I talk to a lot of different people.
I've never personally been an outsourcing producer,
but I have a friend named Sarah,
who was one for me at another game company
that I worked at called Njimoko.
And I asked her what she liked about it, and she said her favorite thing about it was managing
the relationships, because she got to meet people from all over the place and help manage
the relationship to get something done together as a group.
And working with people and understanding their needs and what fulfills them, that was
her reason for wanting to do that job.
But for her, the negative was that she felt
really external to the game team.
Like, she was often isolated in her work.
She didn't really work on the game itself.
And that felt somewhat isolating to her,
and it wasn't an ideal career path for her.
But if you're somebody who's maybe a little bit
more introverted, and you like art,
but you're not an artist, it could be a pretty good role
for you to think about.
Next is sort of an art-adjacent producer.
You're not an art producer, but UI is a type of art.
So you're not doing environment art, you're not doing character art.
The UI art's a really important part of the game development process as anybody who's
made a game, unless you've made one that had no UI, which there are some of those that
work.
But it's really challenging.
It's a good challenge.
You're going to focus on both 2D and 3D art typically.
You're gonna have some experience working
with user experience design,
and you're probably still gonna work with engineers.
So I did this job a little bit
when I was working at Telltale Games,
and I found that it was a really interesting role for me
because I liked working with both artists,
the UI artists and the developers
who were actually doing the UI engineering.
And I really enjoyed my time there and my background
in doing user experience was super helpful there.
So if you've done some user experience learning
at some point in your career, this is a really good area
because the first time user experience is an extremely
important part of the UI process and I loved working on that.
Like for me, I worked with a producer for a while
and she always said like the first five minutes of the game.
This was more for AAA games or it's more compact
for mobile games now.
But the first five minutes of the game
were the most important,
because that was when the player
was gonna either play the game or quit the game.
So the first time user experience
is a really important part of the game to develop.
And the UI team is typically in charge
of that entry tutorial.
And for me it was really interesting
because I got to mediate a lot of discussions
between a UI artist who wanted something beautiful
and really cool and really interesting,
and the UI engineer who said,
yeah, we don't have time and our engine doesn't do that.
So you kind of become that person who is the mediator between those two things.
And that's the production role you fill there and
you facilitate some sort of an understanding between those two groups.
So that you get the best thing that you can for your customers.
And it's a really customer focused role.
I think that's what I liked about it.
Again, sort of staying in that UI and customer appreciation area,
I like to put localization producers here, too.
That's another very specific specialized production role.
It's really good if you already know multiple languages.
It's definitely a role where there's a lot of opportunities.
Like I haven't met the game company yet.
that said, if I could find a good localization person,
I just wouldn't hire them.
Like, everybody wants them.
They're not easy to come by.
Your focus is really going to be working
on getting the translations created for the games,
probably working with an outsourced house to get that done.
And localization integration testing,
which is everything from,
is the translator giving me stuff that is...
appropriate for the language of the country.
So, if it's translated, does it still make sense?
And if it's a funny game, does it still funny?
If it's a serious game, is the translation still serious
and does it get the same point across?
Having a background in QA or working for one
of these translation companies that's out there,
both good areas for you to have
if you want to go down this road.
Although, if you can get a job as an associate producer
and tell someone, you know, I also speak Spanish
and I'm really interested in localization.
you're gonna be fine.
Like, people are always looking for localization folks.
Again, it's another one of those where attention to detail
is probably the most important thing
that you can bring to the table,
because you're typically gonna be managing anywhere from,
if you're just doing e-figs,
you'll have like three or four different languages,
and I think Spore shipped in like 21 languages.
So, it's a pretty wide variety of things,
and you get some kind of interesting problems,
like in Spore, which is a game I worked on for EA.
We did it in Thai, and Thai is not a character high,
it's a character and a half high,
and that really wreaked havoc with the UI of the game
because nothing fit.
Like when the translations went in,
we're like, oh, that's terrible.
And so then you end up working
with both the translation team,
but you also end up working with the UI team
to make the UI dynamic.
So you get to work with a bunch of different people,
and it can actually be a really interesting job.
So, you know, one of the things that I think is an awesome piece
about doing localization processing.
is it also makes games more accessible for more people,
which I think is just cool.
Like I just think that's a really good thing
in our industry for anybody to be able to play any game
is just a worthy goal.
But I also feel like there's,
and this I only have anecdotal information about this
from a couple of the different games I worked on
that were highly pirated,
is that localizing actually decreases piracy.
Because a lot of times people in countries
that don't get games in their native language,
will buy a pirated version that's been done in their language,
whereas if you offer it in that language,
they will give you money for it, which is so crazy.
So I think that there's a big case to be made for localization.
There's a big case to be made for having a dedicated localization producer managing that.
Again, this can be a fairly isolating role, though,
because you're not typically working on the game features.
You might be coming in towards the end of the project,
so you might not even see the game while it's in development.
And to me, that's also a really fun part
of being in game development is seeing it be super crappy
and then get super awesome.
So, you know, it can be a hard role
if you feel like the need to be, you know,
in on the ground for a game development project.
So, let's shift gears a little bit and start talking
about the engineering specialized producers.
And we're going to start with the game director.
Sorry.
We're going to start with Development Director.
So Development Director is a good production specialization
path that you can go down if you're a producer.
And typically, you're going to do this
if you're really interested in scheduling and project
management.
Excuse me.
Typically, you're going to be doing things like putting together schedules for projects.
You're doing a lot of, you know, use a traffic cop.
You're doing a lot of, like, you over here get this done.
You over there get that done.
And you're doing a lot of facilitation of mostly engineers trying to get their jobs
done.
And it can be a really satisfying role, and I'm going to tell you why in one second.
I have a friend, a very good friend I've worked with for a long time who's development director.
I asked her for a reason.
I haven't been a development director,
so I didn't have like a, why would I love this job?
Because I don't actually think I would love the job.
So I couldn't make up something there.
So I asked her, and I'm gonna read you a quote
that she gave me.
She wrote, I love working with engineers.
One of the great fallacies of engineering
is that it's not a creative discipline.
and that could not be less true.
One of the hallmarks of a great engineer
is their ability to function as an elegant thinker
who is able to cut to the heart of a problem
with efficiency and grace.
That takes incredible focus and creativity,
and the ability to harass a bunch of brilliant,
creative minds to do great work
is what gets me out of bed in the morning.
And I actually love that quote,
because it makes me actually think,
oh, maybe it would be cool to be a development director.
And I think if you can look at engineers,
and it's a,
Grace Hopper, Alan Turing, and Ada Lovelace,
who are the three engineers that my engineers I work with,
were like, those are my three favorite engineers
that I think are just brilliant.
If you can work with those types of minds
and get good work out of them,
I can imagine that being a fairly satisfying career path.
And you're doing a lot of scheduling
and you're keeping things a lot on track.
In fact, if things go off track,
it's probably going to be seen as your fault.
And that's definitely one of the minuses of this whole situation.
When things go well, no one really considers why that is.
But when things go bad, you're typically holding the bag as the development director.
So there's a really high level of responsibility.
So this is a good role for you if you are interested in scheduling, you're interested
in management, you like working with technical brilliant minds, and you like having a high
level of responsibility for the success of your project.
Like there's a big risk reward payoff in the development director world.
Okay, so this is what I do now.
I'm a technical program manager for Amazon.
I work on the Lumberyard game engine.
And I put this in not because I work
at a game development company anymore,
I work for a game engine company,
of which there are quite a few now.
Like Lumberyard's only one of them.
There's Unity, there's Crytek, and there's Unreal.
So there's a lot of different jobs,
and within a lot of large technical companies.
There are also a lot of different, more technical roles.
When I came to Amazon, they were like, what do you do?
And I was like, I'm an executive producer.
And they said, yeah, we don't have that job family here.
And I had to sit down with the management and say like,
okay, if you don't have that job family here,
let's figure out what my skills are
and where they're gonna be most applicable.
And what we came up with was a technical program manager.
And it's a fairly high-level job at Amazon.
It's like a career path job.
It's not like an entry-level job.
And basically, my job means that I manage
multiple ongoing interdependent projects
across different functional groups.
I coordinate roadmaps, I plan releases, I run sprints,
I run triages, and I assign bugs to engineers.
And I needed to have a basic understanding.
This is kind of what got me
and got the technical in front of my name.
is I needed to have an understanding of how engineers do their jobs,
which I have from just years of working with engineers.
So again, this is another role where if you like working with engineers
and you like seeing everything kind of come together and be wonderful,
this is a good one for you.
So before I did computer stuff, I was a cook.
I was a line cook. I used to take orders and put them up and I ran the kitchen.
So I was the grill cook and I...
I had the guy on my left who was making salads and I had the guy on my right who was doing
saute pans and I did all the grilling.
And it was my job to make sure that everybody's food came out at exactly the same time and
was beautiful.
And I kind of think that's what I do in my job now.
Basically I'm coordinating all of the different projects to come together at the same time
and get out and be exactly what we want so that our customers will want to keep coming
back for more.
The other part of my job that I really like that's really the interesting creative piece
of my job is that I ensure that technical design and implementation meet the product
requirements.
So I work pretty closely with product managers who are coming up with the ideas of things
that can be in the product and help make sure that everybody on the product knows the right
thing to do to get that outcome.
So that's the more satisfying parts of my job.
It has some ups and downs, I'll say that about it.
You know, I definitely feel like it's not as creative
as some of the roles I've held in the past.
I'm not doing the product management side,
so I'm not creating as much as I have
with regards to technical project specs.
And that's fine with me,
because there's other parts of my job
that are very challenging,
and I love the engineers I work with.
I'm not working with artists anymore,
and I kind of miss seeing art.
And it makes me go out and play more indie games,
because I just crave sort of seeing
wacky, crazy art in my world that I don't see at my job.
So I think when you're being a development director
or a technical program manager, you have to kind of commit
and say, what I want to do is I want to manage projects
and be successful at that.
And I need to let go of maybe some of the creative aspects,
or maybe I'm not that interested in that.
Satisfying for me about game development
is getting the job done.
So, talking a little bit, like switching gears again
and talking a little bit about online.
So, mobile product manager is a new sort of avenue
for producers to go down.
And this is one that's a little more appropriate
for most mobile games.
Like most mobile companies have one or more
mobile product managers.
And then they tend to be a little bit more focused
on things like customer retention,
player behavior analysis, things like revenue generation
are really big areas of study for mobile product managers.
They usually collaborate with designers, so there's a lot of opportunity for them to give
some creative input in their job.
And they usually have monthly, quarterly, and annual revenue targets.
So if you're somebody who thinks, you know, one of the things I really enjoy is having
a way to quantify whether my job is going to think I'm successful in my job, there is
no better way to do that than to make money for your company.
Because people will notice it and you will get credit for it.
So if that gives you a lot of satisfaction at work, this is definitely an area for you
to consider.
If you have a business background, if you're into data analysis, if you like statistical
analysis, this is another really good area for you to be in.
It's a really good training ground for sort of executive management, not necessarily project
management, but executive management within a small to medium-sized company.
One of the ups that I found from working with product managers that they really enjoyed
is they spent almost their whole job worrying about customers.
I worry about, am I going to get to the finish line in time?
they worry about is the customer going to get to the finish line in time.
And I think that that's a pretty satisfying way to think about your job.
Another really important piece of it is, you know, if you're at a small company
and you're a good product manager, you're helping pay the bills for the company.
So your coworkers can pay their rent and you guys can have pizza and things are good because
your product manager is thinking about how to generate revenue all along the way.
And that's a really nice feeling to pay rent.
I enjoy it.
It's a good thing to do.
It's also a pretty new area.
Like mobile hasn't been around that long.
And that means that there's a lot of room for innovation and experimentation.
So if you're a person who says like.
I think this might work.
And you can make a data analysis that it will work.
You can almost always find a manager who's going to say,
yeah, let's give it a go.
Let's see if your idea works.
And they won't all work, but most of the companies
that have people like mobile product managers
are OK having some measured amount of risk
in the types of things that they do,
because some stuff works and some stuff doesn't.
And if it does work, you have clash of clans.
So not too bad.
The downsides were you really don't necessarily play the game itself on a daily basis.
A lot of these are going to be live games that have ongoing new content coming into them.
And that might be something that's really important to you.
You really want to be able to play the game and have that experience.
You might not have time to do that, so you have to put your trust in the other people that are working on the game.
And one of the other people that will be working on the game
a few years for a company called NG MoCo.
And your primary job in this role
is to make sure that the online game is being
updated on a regular basis.
So in this world, your game doesn't,
you're not finished when you launch,
you're just getting started.
You have so much more work to do once customers actually
come in.
And you're typically worried also
about generating online revenues.
You're going to have a product manager that you
work with on this.
But you're also going to be doing things like,
so you're going to be worrying about money.
You're going to be worrying about when is my game going to get approved from the app store.
You're going to be worrying about whether my servers are up, which is that red and yellow.
You don't want that much red.
Trust me, it's not good.
And you want to look and see how popular are the servers, how are things going.
That's just the WoW server list because that's a great long-term online game.
They are experts in live operations.
They have lots of live producers at Blizzard.
You will need to know some about server management and data operations.
So you'll need to understand like, how are my servers doing?
Am I getting enough data back to be able to make decisions about my product?
And you're going to be a conduit.
You're going to be doing a lot of mediation between the designer and the product manager.
Because the product manager is going to say, I think this product is, this feature is going
to make so much money.
And the designer is going to say, that is terrible.
We would never want to do that to our customers.
And you as the live producer are gonna have the opportunity
to mediate between those two people.
And if you like your team and you have fun
working with people, this is a great job for you
because you're gonna be able to use those people skills
to help solve problems and help people get their jobs done,
which is really what producers do to me.
So, you know, me, this is a server chart from New Relic
and this is just app response time.
This is the kind of stuff I used to look at
pretty much all day on one of my monitors.
And I feel like my job was intrinsically tied to the servers.
If the servers were down, two things happened.
One is my customers couldn't play my game,
which is terrible, and you never want customers
to not be able to play your game.
But the other piece was we weren't generating any revenue.
If there was no servers capacity,
then nobody could get in to play,
and nobody was gonna give us any money.
And those were not great moments.
But what those did give me was an opportunity
to work with some really dedicated DevOps professionals.
So I worked with some engineers who made it their life's work
to A, try and keep the servers up the best that they could.
And when they went down, they did heroic efforts
to get them back up.
And that was a really, that's like being in the trenches.
I've never been to war, I've never been in the military,
and it is, I'm sure, not as bad as that.
But it is definitely quite an experience
to have your servers all go down.
I think there was an AWS outage this morning
that probably freaked a lot of my coworkers out quite a bit,
but I wasn't there, so I have to really rather.
Plus, here at GDC.
So the other thing that I found really fun
about doing online production is that you really are.
things all the time for your customers.
And you get to see, I love working with communities
and I love people and seeing what they're doing
and getting to see how they're playing your game
and then going onto the forums or Twitter or anywhere
and sort of seeing what are they saying,
what would they like to see next,
and having the opportunity to build those features
into a game and have people go,
oh my gosh, they actually heard me and listened to me.
That was extremely satisfying for me.
And in packaged games, you don't get that.
In packaged games, you ship and either if you're
digitally distributed, your boxed product, it's out
and there's no changing it.
So that was a super fun thing for me
and I feel like being in live production is great for you
if you like change, if you're adaptable,
if you like working with people,
if you get excited when things happen
that are beyond your scope of ability to...
to prevent but that you really are excited about resolving.
So I think it's a really fun and exciting area of production
that's very different from, like if you were a producer
10 years ago on a box game, they just had nothing like that.
Next one I wanna talk about is publishing producers.
So at the end of the.
you know, here's a game and all the way up to the publisher.
Publishing producer is a relatively new kind
of producer that's been around for a few years.
It tends to be a little bit more senior.
So this could be interesting to you somewhere down the line
in a career if you decide.
I like things like traveling and meeting new people
and seeing new kinds of games and making money
and I'm really into a few different things.
And I feel like.
Publishers tend to work as a publishing arm of a company.
So it'll be either a developer who makes their own games,
but also as a publishing arm,
or a dedicated game publishing company.
And they typically handle things
like marketing, distribution,
but the publishing producer's gonna be able to,
you know, keep their eye on production
all the way through the development of the game.
to ensure that there's a financial and critical success
because the publishers only get a big money
if the game makes money.
You need exceptional people skills for this.
So if you decide you want to go
become a localization producer
because you kind of like swimming in your own lane
and working on your own stuff and not talking.
to a lot of people except on email,
then this might not be the job for you.
Like, this is a job where you are gonna be
schmoozing people and going out to do stuff.
If you don't like going to parties,
please don't become a publishing producer.
Like, it will not be a good job for you.
You also need a broad understanding of game development.
That's why I say it's maybe a job that's for later on in a career,
because you'll need to have some sort of knowledge of everything from initial pitch
through and including shipping the game and doing after marketing.
So you're gonna spend a lot of your time
doing communication, so you're gonna need to,
you know, be on email a lot, you're probably gonna
have a couple of different Slack channels
for different teams you're working with,
and you're gonna be a Skype expert.
You also need to be super organized.
If you aren't organized, you're gonna lose track of stuff
because you're not necessarily living it day to day.
You might work on a project with an external developer,
only have every two weeks you have things with them,
and you need to remember to ask them about it
when you talk to them.
And lastly, you need to be sort of the paragon of enthusiasm and positivity.
So, you know, for a publishing producer, they're out talking to the people
that are making these games who are in the trenches, and this is the role
where you really want to be the guy who brings along, the guy or woman
who brings along, you know, that, like, sense of excitement and positivity
and that everything's going to be okay,
because you're helping them make everything okay.
I talked to a couple of people.
I've never been a publishing producer.
I talked to a few, I actually had a whole bunch of people
who when I asked some friends,
they were like, oh yeah, I was a publishing producer
for a while.
So I got a lot of feedback on this one from people
and they have a lot of different reasons
for wanting to do it.
I think it's another one of those jobs
that you take on when you want to be.
thinking about moving it to upper management.
So they wanted more insight in how decisions were made from above.
And then a great quote from one friend was,
I've always been a fan of games as a new and relatively unexplored art form.
And I want to help those trying to push the medium
in new and interesting directions find an audience.
And I was like, that is the most lovely altruistic reason
I can possibly imagine for being a publishing producer.
Good job. Like that was awesome.
But, you know, he also said he gets lonely
and he misses the creative dynamism.
of a, he was a producer before he became a publishing producer and just worked on a game
and he misses it.
He misses that dynamism of working with a group because now he mostly works with a bunch
of publishing, to develop studios that are publishing.
Another friend of mine said his worst.
He loves his job and there's a lot of great stuff he gets to do and he loves delivering
good news, but he also has to be the bearer of bad news.
And you can really destroy people's dreams if you're a publishing producer, if you pull
the plug on their project.
And you become the person that has to actually communicate that to somebody.
And that's a really terrible place to be, and you have to be able to be okay with that
some of the time too, because that's going to be part of the job.
Sometimes things are going to go great.
sometimes they're not going to go great.
As a publishing producer, you have to be prepared for both sides.
All right, so I said I'd talk a little about design producer, and here's that moment.
I think of design producers as feature producers, and that's pretty much the most traditional
type of production that there really is.
I don't want to spend a bunch of time talking about it today, because I think you probably
got a lot of information if you were here for Aaron and Ruth's sessions earlier today,
and they probably covered most of the ups and downs here, and I don't want to cover
stuff that other people already talked about.
If you want to talk about this more, I'm happy to.
I've done this job.
I know lots of people who have done this job,
and I can give you some feedback on it.
But if you decided to go into production,
which I assume most of you in this room did decide that,
or you wouldn't be here at the production bootcamp.
then you probably have a pretty good idea
what a feature or design producer does.
There are some new types of roles.
I worked at Telltale for a while
and they have a design associate.
It's kind of like a design producer
except it's more to go in the design track,
which I think is a different,
other interesting specialization,
but I think of that as a design specialization.
That's a talk for another day.
Okay.
So those are the types of specializations that I'm going to cover today.
And now I want to switch gears a little bit and talk about how some of these different
specializations vary when you're working on a small team versus a large team.
So when you're working on a small team, you're pretty much going to wear a lot of different
hats.
You're going to have the opportunity to try maybe two or three of these types of specializations.
So you might be the art outsourcing, UI, and localization producer on a small team.
And that's an interesting way for you to start experiencing
the different types of specializations
and sort of see what might be appropriate for you.
One of the things I like that,
is this is what represents a dive deep,
which is an Amazon leadership value.
And basically what it means is,
you will dig in and do whatever needs to be done
to get the job done.
And I think that's like a hallmark of any producer.
But I think that when you're on a small team,
it becomes even more valuable as a skill,
that you're able to say, I am not super excited
or I am super excited, but I'm gonna jump into this task
and even though it's kind of not quite in my bailiwick,
I'm gonna go for it
and I'm gonna try and get something done.
One of the downsides to small teams is there's limited growth opportunities.
So pretty much if you have an EP and a senior producer and a couple of producers, there's
not a lot of growth opportunity and there's not a lot of opportunities for really getting
in and really becoming a specialized producer.
And I feel like that can be okay for a while,
but if you do say, like, I really want to be a DD,
you're probably going to need to move on
and end up in a larger team.
Because when you get to a larger team,
that's when you start seeing these different types
of producers break out and spend all of their time
focusing on one specialization.
And that's when you can get the best experience out of it
and understand what's going to be right for you.
There's also room for growth.
You don't feel like, oh, I hope the senior producer wins
the lottery, because then maybe he won't come to work again.
Then I could have his job.
But in a large team, you have a lot more opportunity
for movement around.
And then if you stretch that out and you become on a large team,
but within a studio that has multiple projects, you can say,
oh, I can also move over to that project.
Or if you're in a corporate environment,
you could actually move over
to a completely different studio.
I really like, you know, BioWare's games,
and I've been working on Dead Space,
but man, I'd love to work on Mass Effect.
Like, that kind of opportunity is there for you as well,
especially if you have a specialization
and you know they need it.
That's why localization's an awesome one,
because there's always room for localization.
I'll stop talking about that now.
All right.
Within that, though, there's a series of hard skills
that I think all producers need to bring to the table.
And again, different specializations
are going to have different hard skills that they focus on.
On the left is all the project management stuff
that I've had to use in the last couple of years.
Project management and communication.
This didn't include email.
Email producers live and die by email a lot.
Although I like that Slack is actually starting
to take the burden of email off a little bit.
It's nice and it's a little more fun and manageable.
But mostly fun.
I actually think Slack is pretty fun.
But I would become an expert in some of these things.
Like one of the things I learned on one of my first projects
that I was working with Jira,
it was years ago when Jira was still pretty early,
was somebody made me an admin,
because I was a producer.
that made sense at the time.
And I learned how to create workflows in Jira.
And it's something that I use to this day.
Like somebody knows they can make me an admin in Jira
and I can probably set up a workflow for them.
15 or 20 minutes and get a project kicked off.
And that's just a great skill to have,
even though it didn't take me very long to learn,
but hardly anyone learns it.
So you can go sign up for a free JIRA account,
and you can learn how to do this on your own.
And then you start developing those skills
that become part of different specializations.
Like it is a really good skill
for a development director to have.
It is a really good skill for a TPM to have.
Not necessarily a skill a UI producer needs.
In the middle are two of the producers best friends Excel and and Google Sheets. I love Google Sheets
I wish I could use it for everything. We don't really use it much at Amazon
just because well, it's Google and
I use Excel a lot, but I love Google Sheets for being able to see projects getting updated.
I worked with an external development shop for a while, and we could have meetings where
all of us sat in Google Sheets and we updated it on the fly together live.
That's incredibly valuable as a production tool when you're working with distributed
teams, which almost all of the production specialists could eventually do.
However, on the far right, those are all of the first-party...
development platform.
So if you have to submit to Steam,
or you have to submit to iOS, or Sony, or Microsoft.
Different specializations have different parts in that role.
So it might be that you're the producer who goes and reads
how iOS requires you to do your user experience design.
Well, that's on the iOS portal.
Or you're the producer who, at the end, has to actually
submit the app for distribution.
That's a completely different other part of the portal, and
it's a completely different specialization.
But, these are all really good things for you to understand.
What are the requirements of the first platform holders and how can I make sure that my area,
my area of specialization is doing the right thing so that we don't fail submission because
of my stuff.
So those are some of the hard skills.
There's a lot of different hard skills.
I think that we're going to talk a little about development
methodologies, and that kind of leans a little bit
into the hard skills as well.
But I want to talk for just a second about soft skills.
Empathy is, at its simplest, awareness of the feelings
and emotions of other people.
It is the link between self and others because it is how we as individuals understand what
others are experiencing as if we are feeling it ourselves.
This is probably the best soft skill that I can tell any producer to bring to any specialization,
particularly if you are managing people and particularly if you are one of the specific
producers that is mediating between two different groups.
This is an area where you can bring,
like I have in my past been terrible at empathy,
like super terrible, and it's been a skill
that I've been working on over time,
because I think it's a really important production skill
for me to be able to say.
If that person can't get that done, why is that?
Like, what are they feeling
and how are they going through their job
that is not enabling them to do their job?
So I feel like that's probably one of the biggest
soft skills that you can bring to the table
in any of the specializations,
but particularly the ones where you're mediating
between a designer and an engineer
or an executive and an artist.
This is a book, you'll be able to see my slides online.
This is a really good book about difficult conversations.
This is another really good one if you're mediating
or managing between different groups,
because I feel like this is what producers do a lot
if they are the type of producer who's working with groups,
not necessarily the ones that are swimming
in their own lane as much.
One of the other things I think is a really important soft skill
for production is team health.
I think that no matter who you're working with and which part of the organization that
you're working with in your specialization, team health is really important because if
you and your team aren't happy and aren't feeling good about their work and don't have
a good work-life balance, that is partly your responsibility because your job is to get
the project out the door and team health is a huge part of that and that's become more
important as time has gone by.
And specialists, within specialist producers,
have a really big role to play there.
And it's a super fun thing to do.
Like, worrying about team health means
that you get to plan cool things for people to go do.
And I think that that can be a really positive experience
as a producer.
One of the things I use at my current job
that's less about ordering pizza,
the ordering pizza side of team health,
and a little bit more about making sure
we're getting the job done team health,
because that also is a very positive impact on your team.
We use some parts of Agile, and we use some waterfall.
So I'm going to talk a little about
the parts of Agile that we use.
Have you guys, anybody used Agile?
Everybody, sweet.
Has anybody used strict, crazy strict Agile
for game development?
Wow, yeah, that's one.
So, you know, for me, when I think of how we've used Agile
on the projects that I've worked on,
these are really the four areas that I tend to use the most.
So I like to use user stories for game development
because it makes sure the engineering team
is actually thinking about what's right
for the user experience and not relying on built as design,
which is my favorite answer as a producer
to get from an engineer when I say,
yeah, but it doesn't work.
Hey, it's built as designed.
So, you know, user stories are a great way around that because you can say, like, the
user needs to be able to create an avatar, right?
That's a great user story.
And then you can flow out everything from that to actually get that work done.
I love daily stand-ups, not necessarily because I use them in the strict Agile way, but because
I get updates from my team and it helps me sleep at night.
On days when I don't go to my stand-ups are my worst days for wondering, like, is the
train rolling?
Are we getting everything done that we need to get done?
I like to use incremental development.
And I think that's a really good one for specialized producers in particular,
because it helps you figure out,
when am I going to be able to give a report about my part of the project
to another part of the project?
And what's going to be in that?
So if you say, like, I know in this sprint,
we're going to get this amount of work done.
I know from previous sprints that we actually get three quarters of that work done, then
I can go out and say, hey executives or other teammates, here's what I think we'll have
done in two weeks.
And if a combination of the stand-ups and knowing that that incremental development
in sprints is happening, I as a producer are going to be able to work with other producers
and be able to report to my management what's getting done in the project.
And personas I really like and I use them both,
I used them a ton when I was doing mobile development,
but I use them now even though I don't share
what I do with them to as many people.
In mobile development you use them
because you're trying to figure out like,
what are the product features that we need to prioritize
based on who's using the product?
And you have all the data telling you
who's using the product.
In my current job, I don't really have that,
but I do have the idea of who's using our engine
to do what right now, and thinking about those personas
and figuring out how to do feature development,
even though it's not necessarily tied to revenue,
I still find very valuable.
Waterfall, this is not the fanciest waterfall slide
in the world, but waterfall's pretty basic.
It's been around a long time.
You know, it's sequential, it's non-iterative.
If one thing slips, it causes lots of other things to slip.
I tend to rely on it to do upfront schedules,
because I just want to like,
like when I'm trying to schedule something out,
just to get sort of a vague idea,
a straw man of when something might be done.
but they tend to, you know, I say your mileage may vary
when you use Waterfall, they're easy to create,
but unless somebody's actually really actively updating it,
it becomes out of sync pretty quickly.
So I tend to, you know, look at that and I say,
you know, what I end up doing is I say,
I use a combination of these things.
And, you know, it sometimes leads to mayhem and chaos,
but what I usually get from it is,
I take the pieces of Agile that work,
I take the pieces of Waterfall that work,
I try and combine them,
and figure out which works best for which specialization I'm doing at that moment.
So for live production, my scheduling is completely different than what I do as a TPM at Amazon.
So you know, again, your mileage may vary.
This is something that you'll adapt for your particular specialization, and you'll have
to work with other people on it.
Like you have to get your engineers to buy in with whatever production methodology you
use.
or you will get nowhere really, really fast.
So you want to be having those kinds of discussions
at the beginning of a product
and try and move things along in a way
that makes sense for your particular product.
All right, last slide.
Pusheen, because there should be a cat
in every presentation.
All right, what should you major in?
So if you're in college right now
and you're hoping to become a producer someday,
you should major in whatever the fuck you want.
Basically, I sort of feel like you should also take some engineering classes, but you
should major in something that's going to give you a broad knowledge of humans and what
we've done with the society that we've had for millions of years.
And for production in general, you're going to work with so many different kinds of people
doing so many different kinds of things.
Having a broad base of knowledge is the best win.
I am a terrible artist, which is why I drew not one of my slides.
I am really literally a terrible artist.
But I took art history classes because I love art, and that gave me enough information for
me to sit down with a game artist and be able to have a conversation where I don't sound
like a complete idiot.
And it also makes me enjoy it.
Like I actually have an appreciation for the art
that happens in games, even though I can't do it myself.
And that's kind of why I think, you know,
what should you major in?
Really anything.
It's what you learn along the way
and what you want to bring to the table
for the job that you want to have down the line.
All right, should you take classes in Agile?
Should you take classes in anything?
If you want, you should.
I don't know that I would take an Agile class.
I think there's plenty of information online
and it seems like all of those Agile classes are like,
come to San Francisco for an all-day Agile class.
I can't think of anything that I would find more boring.
Sorry if you teach Agile classes.
But, you know, I think if you're super interested in it
and you want to become, you know,
a super technical project manager,
maybe it would be a good thing for you.
I still think there's plenty of stuff online.
I think there's other classes you can take.
Like I took a Java class a few years ago
just because I wanted to learn
about object-oriented programming.
I'm not going to become a programmer.
I have no desire to do that at all, although I have tons of respect for programmers.
But it just helped me be able to have more intelligent conversations because I had taken
a little bit of time and learned a little bit more about something I didn't know about.
So I'd say yes if you want.
How do you get into production?
So if you're somebody who's not in production now, but you want to be in production, and
you don't have any experience and you don't know anybody in the industry, look for an
entry-level job.
And you might find an entry-level assistant producer job, but it's more likely you'll
find something like...
excuse me, a QA job.
There's still a few of those that are feeders
into a production group.
Like I worked at Telltale, they feed people from QA
into production all the time there.
Or look for a community manager job,
because most people know how to use social media.
Learning how to use social media is, again,
something you don't need a class in.
You can kind of learn that online.
And that leads you down the path
of getting a foot in the door.
Understanding community and understanding
who's playing the game is actually
a super valuable producer skill
for almost any of the,
production specialization, so that's a good foot in the door.
When you're a producer and you've joined the company,
find a mentor, find somebody in the company
that is doing one of these specializations
that you're interested in that's more senior than you,
and ask them to go to lunch.
Take them out to lunch, it'll be worth it.
You don't need to have a formal mentor relationship
with them, but if you have a relationship
where you can ask them a question here or there,
they know who you are, they start seeing you
around the company, that's a really good thing to foster,
and it gives you somebody to talk to
about something you're interested in,
which is super fun and why we are human beings.
Another thing to do when you join a company is finding a champion.
And a champion is a little bit different from a mentor, because a champion is going to say,
I think you're valuable, and I want to help you get ahead personally.
Like I want...
And those do exist, particularly in some of the larger companies.
And what they'll do is they'll, you know, work with you, they'll see what you're good
at, they'll understand your value.
and hopefully they'll help you get ahead within the company.
They're definitely harder to find than mentors,
but if you find one,
take advantage of that relationship and work with them
because it's a great way to learn about a company
and learn about how to improve yourself within the company.
And that's it.
I have some time for questions.
If you ask a question, please do it at the mic, because I'm going to lose my voice in
about 10 minutes, and I don't want to have to repeat everybody's questions.
Hi.
So first, very helpful.
So thank you.
So one of the things I've noticed, actually it was at Amazon, so I was at a PM at Amazon,
and then it's a PM at Microsoft, technical producer at someplace else.
So how do you kind of like bridge the different titles in different places?
Like, how do you kind of describe your role in a resume when you look for things, kind
of like keywords to bridge the things?
And then as an addition for that, what do you do if you find yourself at a production
role that is very, very specific to the place you're at?
And how do you can then advertise yourself to other things or grow into other things?
Yeah, so I think for the first part of that, you know, what I tend to do, it's really easy
to write too many things about a job.
And I try and look at like the three things I do most.
So what are the, you know, within a week,
what are the three things I do most?
For me right now, the three things I do most are
roadmap planning, sprints, and bug triages.
So those would be the three I'd pick,
even though I do like a bunch of,
like I do contract management,
I do all this other stuff that I just don't think
is as relevant for whatever the next job I want.
So what are those three things that I do
that are gonna resonate in whatever I wanna do next?
If you're doing something, is that your first question?
Is that?
Okay, so the second question with regards to
if I'm doing something and I kind of want to go
in a different direction for a job that I see
that doesn't have, it doesn't usually need the skills
that I'm working with now and aren't part of my resume.
I'd probably try and figure out another way
to get some of those skills and that might be
participating in a hackathon or a game jam
and say, you know, like go to a game jam and say,
you know, I really want to be the person
who helps pull together all the art.
because I've never done art, but I think art would be more interesting than localization.
So try and find the experience somewhere else if you can't find it within your own company.
Thank you.
On your last slide you had bullet points about finding someone to mentor or champion you
as a young producer.
Do you have any advice for people who want to get into mentoring or champion people less
experienced than them?
Yeah, I mean I think that if you're at a company that's big enough, go talk to HR.
and say you want to spearhead that,
it could be as easy as if you have an internal spam list
that's like, I'm selling my cat carrier.
It could be just as easy to say,
I'm looking to mentor,
here's the three things that I do most with my job.
But HR typically also has people who might be interested
and might be able to help you do that
if your company has an HR person.
What if you don't have an HR person?
You don't have an HR person?
Well, do you have a company spam list?
Ah, there you go.
Yeah.
Or ask managers, ask other managers too.
Hi.
Hi, my question was about mentors and finding a champion.
Do you think it's appropriate
if that ends up being the same person
or would it be better to have it be two separate people?
I kind of would end up thinking it's two separate people because I think, you know,
the champion you want to be the highest person in the company that you can get.
And the mentor, you really want to be somebody that's in a discipline area you want.
And it's not necessarily that that's I mean, if it's the same person, that's fine.
But I would I don't know how that would work.
Like, I don't know that many companies are the same person.
is like a senior, like unless it's like you wanna go
into marketing and you want the CMO and they also are like,
yeah, I think you'd be great in marketing or whatever.
So I don't think it would work out
that it would happen very often,
but I don't think that there's a problem with it
if it did work out that way.
Thank you.
Hi.
Hi, first of all, thank you for being a producer.
And my question is, you touched a little bit about agile classes, but what are your feelings
and thoughts about like agile scrum project management certifications?
Are they worth it?
You know, I think in tech companies, they might be a little bit more worth it.
I'm not sure they're in game companies, just because I just don't know that many game companies
that use strict.
agile scrum techniques.
Like they just, they're just,
they need just to be modified.
And I think that's because games,
unlike software, games actually need to be fun.
And I actually don't know agile,
I don't think agile scrum actually addresses
like the fun factor of games very well.
So I think that a lot of companies try and use it
to the best extent they can,
but then have to veer off at the point when they're like,
once you get all those independent pieces together
at the end of scrum,
In technical software, that's fine.
Like, your accounting software, it's great.
Two and two does equal four.
I'm done.
You know, but in a game, that rarely happens.
Like, when you get to beta in a game,
you're like, oh, I actually, eh, not so fun.
You know, that's bad.
So I don't know if the certification matters
so much in games as it does, as it might in other areas.
That said, I know people who have gotten it.
You know, I guess it sort of depends on who's hiring you
and what you bring to the table from that training.
I think you'd probably want to be able to articulate
what you got out of it pretty thoroughly.
Thank you.
Hi.
On one slide you had a bullet point about personas.
Can you just touch on that real fast?
What is that?
Oh, personas, oh sorry.
It's basically a fictional biography of a typical user.
So a persona might be
Like in the case of a whale in a mobile game is a persona.
You'd be like, oh, it's somebody who plays the game
x amount of time, spends x amount of money
over x amount of time, and sort of fits that.
Or some other persona from a mobile game
might be somebody who plays the game x amount of hours
but never spends money, but I serve them this many ads.
So there's another way to look at them.
So it's some kind of user profile.
Yeah.
But it's usually fictional.
You usually sort of create them and then try.
A name and all that kind of stuff.
Yeah.
Hi.
Very interesting talk.
I run a small studio down in Costa Rica.
And the problem that I have is that I am not a producer.
My background is computer science.
And since we're a small team, I got
pulled into the production area of the company.
So the image of a game producer, it's
non-existent in the Latin American area.
So.
What would be your advice to me in order to try to increase,
because we tried working with a remote producer,
but it's not working.
So what would be an advice just to improve the process
that we're having right now?
Are there people who call themselves project managers?
No, we're seven people.
Oh, seven people.
So it's just me, and then art, and then programming.
Yeah, I mean I think in that case you might want to think about ways to get your group
to be self-producing.
So that, you know, I mean somebody, whoever's the lead of the project.
So thinking of another friend's small company and basically if they all are individual contributors,
but the person who owns the creative vision of the company needs to have that ownership
of this piece needs to fit with this piece needs to fit with this piece.
There has to be somebody who says, I'm going to own that.
even if each person is responsible for putting all their own tasks in Jira.
And making sure the sprint, you know, they put this stuff in the sprint.
There still needs to be somebody who sets the sprint up to be populated with tasks.
And that probably ends up being the project lead or the founder.
Sorry.
Thank you.
Hi.
What would be your advice for someone who wants to laterally become a producer in a
company that doesn't have a lot of producers?
Is there an acknowledgment that there's a need for producers?
It's kind of like a lot of people act like producers because there's a lot of leadership that, you know,
people take initiative and everyone's kind of got their own area they're in control of.
But, you know, as somebody who wants to kind of be a producer...
How much overtime do you want to work?
I actually work pretty long hours already.
Okay, I mean that's really the, at the end of the day,
and this goes for most jobs,
the job that you want needs to become the job that you do.
And if you need to do your own job,
if you're an artist and you need to still produce
all your art, then on top of that,
you also need to provide the value that you'd provide
as a producer for somebody to see the worth.
So it's not, it's really hard to convince somebody with words
that they need something.
You really have to do it with actions.
And that's really not a great answer for somebody
who's already like, ugh, I'm already working
like a gazillion hours.
So, yeah, but it's really like doing the job you want
before you have it.
It's how to get promotions too.
Yeah, on a following note, I work in a mobile gaming company,
and I want to eventually work for a AAA console company
in a production role.
What's some advice you might have
for that kind of transition or marketing myself?
Yeah, that's a hard one if you...
I mean, I was in AAA and then went to mobile
and then came back to AAA, so...
I think it's a tough jump from mobile to AAA,
and I think you probably need to figure out a way.
And really, one of the biggest differences
is the quality of the art and the environments,
typically is the biggest chasm I've found.
And the technology as well, just behind game engines.
But you need to figure out a way to get yourself
some of that experience.
You need to find a project to work on, again,
in your copious amounts of spare time.
Thank you very much.
Good luck.
All right, well, thanks very much today.