Hi everyone, my name is Santo Averio Ojeda.
I'm a director at Brujería at Work, which is a local arts collective based in Canada
of different artists and collaborators working together to make unusual game experiences.
And this talk called Making Witches Talk in Don't Make the Night is about our first project,
which was released in 2019.
And the talk will cover some points about the narrative design as well as gameplay loops
that we used to make the game and how we approach the more non-linear method to develop the story.
So specifically what the talk will cover is identifying the bias in storytelling. So that
means how we made sure that
The story didn't favor one specific storyline or character or preconceived notion of what the story means.
Crafting mechanics that carry stories, so making sure that the storytelling is really solid with the game design loop.
Then relying on visual cues, how we use art direction as well as...
So we're going to be talking about the overall story,
and how we used general game design to tell a story without outright telling it in the text.
As well as building an arc and developing non-linear storytelling.
So how we really went into making sure that from beginning to end,
the overarching theme of the story made sense as the player begins and ends the game.
So to cover those points, I'll also go into a little bit of the background.
of how Don't Wake the Night came to be and how we wanted to create this game with a very
experimental approach.
So a little bit of background is Don't Wake the Night was a game that was developed between
2017 and 2019.
It's a 2D point and click game with visual novel elements that tells the story of a community at a crossroads.
And the players basically tasked with finding out why this community is facing this conflict and seeing if there's anything they can do to help these community members, you know, come to some solution.
So the practicals are developed in part, and thanks to provincial municipal funding in Ontario.
and Toronto from the Ontario Arts Council and Toronto Arts Council,
which allowed myself and several collaborators to bring this game to life. So a little bit of
background on myself. I've been making games for quite a while now and I specialize in Indigenous
Guarani-inspired stories, knowing that I was kind of the first project that I took on.
that was very much influenced by that and that I worked on with other collaborators.
And with Don't Wake the Night, it was very much also inspired by 2D animation and 2D animation design.
As a background, I come from 2D animation, but then I kind of veered into game design,
and so I kind of combined the two together to create the design for this game.
As well as working with other folks local to Toronto to release this game to itch in 2019 and most recently was released to steam in October of 2020.
So, generally, Don't Wake the Night has a core gameplay loop of two different aspects.
That happens between two main camera views.
So the first one that you see here is kind of a scene overview of a bird's eye view,
where you're able to see all the characters in one scene.
You're able to see, you know, if they any like clickable elements in the scene,
you can click around and interact with.
The environment itself, you can see if there's any conversations available to view with speech bubbles here, which when you click them, they take you to the second scene overview, which is the one that is more directly visual novel inspired.
So basically, the player will interact and then switch between these two views, depending on whether they're interacting with the environment or whether they need to view character dialogue to gather more context about what's happening in the game.
So one of the key aspects to this loop that we really wanted to get across is that the player
themselves are omnipresent, which means that you know they can you can view everything at once
but they're also absent at the same time. So you have a degree of influence in the scene but
you can't talk to the characters directly, you can't
You can't control individual characters as a player,
so you can kind of influence their actions,
but not directly make some kind of final decision
on their behalf.
So you're able to affect the environments
by touching several objects in the scene, which
elicit reactions from the characters themselves.
But again, you can't actually talk to the characters
and make choices on their behalf,
but you can view their conversations.
Depending on these different objects that you're touching the scene.
So you're primarily a bystander who's seen, but who's not seen, but felt, not heard, but sensed.
So it's a kind of spiritual presence where, you know, you can sense it, but you know, you can't see anything concrete, you can't necessarily, you know, reach out and touch something physical.
So with this gameplay loop, it was also very...
heavily inspired by Guarani storytelling and spirituality.
So that's something that I generally work pretty closely with in narrative design as well as
gameplay design in general. So basically the player is meant to emulate a spirit where
They are not permitted to talk to these living characters,
but they can kind of influence the scene around them.
So that's kind of something I'll also touch on shortly in more
depth, but basically that's kind of what influenced
that gameplay decision.
So one of the.
most challenging aspects of Don't Wake the Night is having to identify the bias in the narrative.
So since the point of the game is to be a bystander, this means that
there's no actual influence on character dialogue. You can't really,
you know, make decisions or change anything. You can only really kind of watch what happens.
So the only choice that you really have is to view the conversations in, you know, whatever order that you would like to.
And the main challenge behind this approach is building a narrative that is not heavily biased towards one interpretation of the story or one particular character.
So we had to make really sure in reviewing both the gameplay loop and the actual dialogue that
You know, one character was since being focused more over others.
So there came a point where, you know, we had the dialogue in spreadsheets.
We had the dialogue on several different documents and we had to like,
run search and see like, okay, does this character get mentioned a lot more
than this other character?
Is this character getting enough dialogue lines so that the player can
actually get an idea of like what type of personality they have or.
Um, what type of, you know, interest they might have.
Um, so obviously this can vary because some characters might be more reserved than others so they talk less.
Uh, but the key aspect is to at least give the character to,
you know, enough space so that they can like,
express the personality that they we've assigned them and to also make sure that,
uh, you know, this game does not really have like a main character.
The main character in theory is the player because they are the ones that
And that's the main focus of this gameplay.
But, you know, we were really careful that that bias was identified pretty early.
Because the mystery of the story is that there's a conflict that you're tasked with solving, but there's no context.
There's no actual direction on what that is.
So the point of the game is to really, you know, listen in on these conversations and kind of gather clues and hints to...
make you understand a little bit more of what the characters might be going through,
while still not getting the full picture. Because at the end of the day, you're a stranger in this
community and you've never met any of these people personally. You're just kind of dropped in and
you're expected to kind of know what's going on. So part of the mystery of the game is to
kind of feel out what conflict is and whether or not, you know, some conversations
reveal more of the nature of that conflict or whether they're just more,
you know, playful, everyday kind of small talk conversations
between people who know each other.
So that meant because of this narrative direction that the bias
had to be rooted out pretty early in development.
So from the very beginning in creating a narrative system
that's grounded more nonlinear storytelling and storytelling techniques.
We had to really make sure that the conversations had a main idea, that they were abstract, but that they still made sense.
So we favored abstract conversations over anything that was linear or contextualized, just to really favor the type of direction we were going for.
And a particular way we approach this in Dueling the Night is basically by posting questions that players might already have about the game coming in or asking questions about what might come up later in the game, but only skirting around the answers.
You know, not giving the full answer, just kind of like half of it, or even just a small piece of it.
And this is usually shown in the game by characters alluding to something that happened or
mentioning something or an event that the player never actually saw. So that could be like a
character saying like, you know, something happened last week and I didn't like it.
Which, it just says something, right? So there's no actual context as to what happened.
So it doesn't really let us know anything, and it doesn't really, you know, give us any clear
context. But what it does tell us is like two key things, which is one, the passage of time,
and two, the character's personal reaction to that. So we know that
It happened last week.
We know that the character didn't like it.
So it's more similar to bumping into two people talking
to each other and kind of coming in halfway
into their conversation.
And generally when that happens, you
have to gather context from them to understand and catch up
to what they were talking to.
But.
Of course, in this game, you don't have any kind of direct interaction with characters,
which means that you can't ask them those questions.
You can't ask them like, oh, what was this about or what did this mean?
You're just kind of overlooking them as they talk.
So it's almost like peering into this somewhat intimate,
maybe personal conversation that you have no context of,
and then kind of trying to get the impression that characters have of it.
So it's nothing concrete or informative, but it can tell you a lot about intent and personality.
So it can tell you a lot about, you know, whether this character, what their general disposition is
in any type of conversation. It might tell you that this person is, you know, good enough friends
with this other character to actually divulge that to them. Or it could be that, you know,
this character is just very open and they tell everything to everyone.
So that's also another approach we took really closely when we identified, you know, what kind of characters we want to work with.
So there's about seven characters, eight characters that you know you see regularly throughout the game. And these characters, each have like a specific personality that really influences their narrative style so even just in this screenshot of the opening
cutscene of the game, you can see that the character on the left.
tends to be a little bit more, um, maybe like short tempered,
uh, and the character on the right tends to, uh,
get into trouble but also tries to avoid trouble at the same time.
Uh,
so we kind of came up with like very basic dynamics between each character so
that we could work out what kind of conversations they could be having,
what might they like to talk about? Maybe the character on the left, um,
The character on the left likes a certain type of activity. The character on the right likes gardening.
So maybe that could somehow influence what they like to talk about.
And the mechanics of the game were very much influenced like from a narrative first perspective.
So Don't Wake the Night was very much a game that started out you know with the story being
written first and then the game mechanics came second and so was the game design.
So in the game, you know, we have these characters, they're each named after a specific role that they play in their community.
Things like gardener, listener, actions that they take in their community to basically make sure it runs smoothly.
So all those kind of things like names and locations and some backstory were developed and fleshed out before we really decided on what kind of mechanical approach we wanted to take with the game.
We definitely knew that.
It would be a more narrative focused game with text dialogue and characters talking to one another.
We just weren't sure whether or not, you know, how these characters being
interacting with one another, how the player come in to make sure that these characters
talk to one another or, you know, what would happen, you know, to the ending and
things like that mechanically.
So this meant that the mechanics also had to accommodate.
A certain style of nonlinear storytelling so that players could access key components in the game at the right time
And parse information in a way that was more fluid and out of order
It's also a shorter game. So it's about 20 minutes
And that also meant that the approach that made the most sense was a point and click route to kind of give that
Omnipresent feeling where you're kind of looking over all the characters at the same time
And we also had to narrow down the amount of character conversations
by the number of interactable objects we actually wanted in the scene.
So with that in mind, it also became important to give players a chance to
always go back to conversations if they wish to review any previous dialogue.
So when you view dialogue once in Doming the Night, it's not locked away forever.
You can always, you know, re-trigger the same environmental cue.
And then go back to that conversation and review it and see, you know, if something makes more sense reading it the second time.
And part of that is also that because the conversations are non-linear, it might mean that you read, you know, conversation A first, then you go to another conversation, conversation B.
And then after reading that, you know, maybe you pick up on something that is like, oh, I think.
This previous conversation might have had another reference to the thing that this character is talking about, so you decide to go back.
And now that conversation makes a little bit more sense than it previously did.
So that's the kind of narrative loop that we wanted to encourage to make sure that, you know, you can still view older conversations at any moment in case that helps in contextualizing what a character is saying.
And this also helps tie in the sense of non-linear movement in the game, since there's no prerequisites
to access certain conversations and they don't have to be completed in a specific order.
So the only prerequisite is that you have to interact with that environment asset.
So usually that involves like in the game either you know wrestle a branch or you touch a trunk or
you drop a fruit from a tree and that like elicits a reaction from the characters and it makes them go
You know, break out into different conversations.
That's the only requirement really to access conversations.
But other than that, you can just do them in any order.
You don't have to, you know, click the branch first or click the trunk second.
The only thing in the game that is really a more binary choice is towards the end.
Once you have viewed all the conversations, the game will offer you to end it
by basically adding one more object to the scene.
And if you click that object, it will bring up a choice of three different endings.
And you can kind of choose what ending you would like to view,
and then it takes you to the credits and to the cutscene that wraps up the game for the player.
And generally with the narrative cues, we also made sure that one thing that really helped also contextualize the player into the scene was having cutscenes at the beginning and the end of the game.
So the game will open up with about a minute long cutscene that is animated by hand and that kind of brings the player into the world that the characters inhabit.
So it will kind of...
You know, show you what the characters are doing before you actually start the game.
And it will give you a little bit of like an initial context as to why you're there
and maybe what the characters are looking for.
So in this case, the characters summon a spirit because they want help from this
spiritual being to like solve their community conflicts.
So that's kind of shown at the beginning to help contextualize that event a little
bit more.
And then at the end, there are cut scenes that are shorter,
whether about maybe like 20 to 30 seconds long,
that just help kind of wrap up
any kind of loose threads of the game,
but still keeps it very open.
So that the player is encouraged to kind of go back and replay the game to see the other endings as well.
And on top of that we also used a little bit of voice acting in the opening cutscenes and
the ending cutscenes because we found that it also really helped give a sense to the
character's personality. So we worked with several different
People for voice talents to make sure that each character kind of had a character or a voice actor that
made sense to their character and
that way when you're watching the opening cutscene you are already kind of getting a
little bit of an impression of what each character is like
so in that sense if you have any kind of animated cutscenes or
scripted cutscenes in your game that can also help
Um, contextualize more information about the characters without giving too much away in the text.
So that way the player kind of has an idea of what to expect from each character.
So the last piece and related to the animated cutscenes that helps
kind of tie everything together is the visual design of the game.
In the game, this is one of the screenshots from one of the endings.
In the game, each character is designed around a specific animal.
So they have masks on their back that represent a different type of animal that is common
in South America.
So like alligator, capybara, jaguar, you know.
types of deer and eater, things like that.
So the reason why each of them is characterized with an animal is also to kind of, again,
feed into that visual cue of what personality they might have.
So like the character that wears the capybara mask is very friendly, very kind of
open to conversation, and also a bit naive at the same time.
Then the character who is represented by a drag war tends to have like a more, a stronger presence and can be maybe a little bit intimidating, but they're not like, like outwardly hostile or anything when they're in conversations and things like that.
So we try to, we try to link these.
um, animal symbols to the characters, you know, cause it relates to their
environment, relates to the culture that is inspired by Guarani culture.
And it also helps kind of attach some kind of narrative device to them to help
contextualize what their motivations might be.
So it's something subtle, more subtle than let's say, like the anime cutscenes or
anything else about their character design.
And when you're viewing the conversations, you'll see these masks on their back.
So it's almost like they're still looking at you, but just from another perspective.
So as I mentioned, a lot of the characters in the world are directly inspired by Guarani
storytelling that I personally grew up with.
So Guarani is a nation, an indigenous nation that is spread out between Brazil,
Paraguay, Uruguay, parts of Bolivia and Argentina.
So the values that I grew up with generally were around accountability and personal responsibility to your community,
which in this sense, you know, it's a lot, the game is a lot about, you know, how do you handle community conflicts?
And how does restorative justice work for these particular characters?
You know, what are they looking for? And those are the kind of questions that the player might want to think about without having an actual answer.
So one of the important things is that we don't, you know, in the game narrative and the game mechanics, we don't punish the player by picking a specific ending.
Because at the end of the day, they also don't know the answer. So that's kind of one of the main ideas of the game is that it's okay to not know the definitive narrative answer to what some of the characters might be asking or wanting.
The whole point of the game is just kind of to like experience their conversations and experience a kind of imperfect nature of trying to solve a conflict without really knowing anything about it.
So this was kind of the basis that I used to help me answer some of the questions and solve some design challenges.
In creating a mysterious story that didn't lead players astray.
So the main, uh, the really like most important point there was that
the player still walked away with like a sense of story, a sense of place.
Uh, so they might not have the answer, but they knew what happened, uh, just
in that particular moment that they were in, uh, you know, they, it's almost
similar to, you know, being at a certain place, but not having all the answers.
And similarly, many of the character aspects that I mentioned, like the masks, are derived from Guarani art as well, and they reflect each character's personality, you know, the animals they're assigned to.
And I had referenced before as well that the game also relied quite heavily on to the animation, so everything that was animated in the game was animated through Toon Boom.
Parts of it were also animated through Photoshop with like...
Usually by coloring it in, but the actual like smears and like in-betweens and all those were done in Toon Boom.
It was all done by hand as well, and since it was a very kind of small self-contained environment that these characters were inhabiting,
2D animation really also helped to bring out their personality.
So it became really crucial to like really over-exaggerate.
animations and to really overextend styles to make a lasting impression.
So generally that means that it was really about exaggerating those smears and exaggerating
those actions so that even when the player is viewing, you know, more bird's eye view of the
game, you can still see the animations and feel them very clearly and they kind of tell you like
a little bit more about the mannerisms or personality of a certain character.
In the main view, sometimes there are characters that are like fidgeting with their hands because they're very anxious.
There's other characters who like might do other things like, you know, rest their face on their hand, like they're thinking about something.
So those little cues also help a lot with establishing what kind of mindset each character is at.
So that's also something very useful to think about.
We're trying to use animation to also tell a story without having to rely too much on the in-text dialogue.
So coming to a close here, just to summarize some of the things that I've gone over.
So basically, a lot of what we solved in this game was that we wanted to limit information to the player and let them fill in the gaps.
So we wanted to kind of...
meet them halfway and let them try and fill in the gaps to contextualize what's happening in the game.
That way you know you're kind of leaving it a mystery and they can speculate on what you know
what might have happened, what might have taken place while not giving a definitive answer. So
we wanted to really make players think about it, come up with different possible
Um scenarios that come up in the game so that way you know technically every player is right
in a way you know no matter the different scenarios they can think of to kind of fill
in that gap it's technically correct so that's what we also wanted to work towards.
We also wanted to allude to a larger narrative so we wanted to foreshadow a lot of things that
don't actually happen in the game itself so we wanted to foreshadow oh this character had a
relationship with this other character, but now they don't really talk anymore.
Or maybe, you know, this event happened where it soured some relations
within the community, or maybe this one character who doesn't appear in-game
is referenced in some way, and that also kind of helped escalate that kind
of mysterious nature of the game.
We also wanted to assume player curiosity.
So we wanted to assume that the player would be curious about what's happening.
We wanted to assume that the player would interrogate the design.
So one of the key takeaways is also that, you know,
we planned around the player's interrogation of design.
We wanted to give them, you know, some autonomy in that,
even if, you know, there are some things that they might not influence directly.
And that's the end of this talk.
Thank you so much for taking the time to listen me go on about
this little game.
And if you wanted to check out more of Bricketty at work or more of my work,
you can check us out brickettyatwork.com or Twitter brickettyatwork.
You can find me at babbygoth on Twitter,
or you can check out my personal work at santoredo.com.
I'm currently working on a newer project about indigenous cyberpunk that will be announced
in the future, so I hope I can talk about that in the future as well.
Thank you.