Not sure what I did to earn this already. Thank you so much for being here this early in the
morning. I know there's so many more better things to do at 9, like sleeping. So, thank you for being
here. My dears, I was told to remind you to turn off all your buzzers and all, you know, devices
that you decided to bring in and emit sounds, you know, whatever that is. You can fill it in.
This talk is long as hell.
So basically I'll do as much as I can.
I'll be speaking quite fast
because I want to show you a lot of things.
Now we will finish in like 55 minutes,
hopefully when I'm efficient.
That means that there will be no time for questions.
However, I'm going to stay with you, of course,
till I'm dead in a wrap-up room in 305.
Okay, 305, this is where I'm going to be after this talk.
And then we can,
know, sit together and chat for like, I think, two hours I have for you. So I hope that I'll be able
to answer all the questions. So having that out of the way, I'm really glad we have audio. I hope
that that's gonna stay. Shout out to our technician. He's amazing and helped me out a lot.
Thank you so much, sir.
And having that out of the way, let's go.
So my dears, my name is Pawel Sasko and I'm a Quest Director in CD Projekt RED.
So what I do, I direct quests, open world and cinematic departments in our studio.
We are the teams that design and implement the story together with our amazing writers.
Now, today I'll be talking to you about a few things and I'll mention a few words about me so
you know who the hell I am, but I promise this will be short because this is not about it.
Then we'll talk and look into the narrative pipeline inside the project. This is a really
important element of really how we build the games and really the reason why those games are good.
Of course, you know, there will be some level of simplification to this pipeline because
otherwise we would have spent here hours just discussing important elements to it.
And then I'll move on to Key Quest Design Lessons.
I have divided it into three parts for you so that you can kind of wrap your head around it.
There we'll be mastering the plot, structuring the narrative, and improving the design at the end.
All of those lessons are actually designed in a way that they're supposed to give you as much takeaway as you can.
However, I have prepared takeaways at the end as well.
However, each lesson is kind of a thing that I learned throughout many years in the industry.
Things that I didn't know really at the beginning.
I don't think they are trivial. I don't think so.
Otherwise, I would have probably known from the very beginning what to do, but I didn't.
And I want you to know now.
So, moving on. A few things and a few games I worked on. I'm in the industry almost 19 years now.
I've worked on a bunch of indie games that you never heard of and a few games that have actually
never been released. If you are in the industry long enough, you will actually get to that point
that your game is shut down throughout the production. So, each of us has to go through
that painful process. Then, I managed to join the Two Worlds 2 team where I was a lead writer,
lead quest designer, and then joined our Witcher 2 team.
During the Witcher 2 Enhanced Edition work, I was just helping out with things, debugging,
and learning from my fellow designers.
And then from The Witcher 3, I was a senior quest designer, did a bunch of main story
and side quests, and became a lead of the team from Hearts of Stone, and led the team
through Blood and Wine, and then Cyberpunk 2077.
After we shipped Cyberpunk, I got to other departments, which is open world and cinematic.
And right now we are working on Phantom Liberty.
It's around a 60 people team,
so shout out to them because I love them.
And some of them are here actually.
So thank you for being here.
Now, my dears, let's move on to the narrative pipeline first.
Hopefully this part won't be too boring for you fellow game devs,
especially people working on a story.
I think this is a very valuable slide,
even though it might not look that appealing.
But I tried to put a picture there, so here you go.
There are a few things I wanted to point out. First and foremost, our games are about the story.
The story is the most important factor in them, always. We want to seduce you as a player.
We want to take you on an adventure to our worlds and really make you feel how it looks like.
That's why we always start from a story outline.
Our writers, in a small group, prepare first a story outline, and again, that outline can be
actually really short. It can be really like, at first, a few pages, maybe even less. And then we
feedback that outline, and it grows, and we get it to the point that we can start working
on a quest design document.
And this is when the Quest Design team steps in and they start working on the designs.
Those are like designs that you can say look like something between game design and a movie scenario.
Something like this. There are elements of a dialogue there, but not too much.
It's just an example. We do not really write dialogues in those documents.
And of course, that iteration process on the design documents, it happens together with the cinematic design team,
and also the open world team, and also others like writers, for instance, and other important departments in our company.
We are trying to include as many voices as we can.
And then we move on to the draft implementation. Actually those documents are used, when they're
approved, they're used to actually produce a base for all of the departments to be on the same page.
And then we start working on first blockout locations. So this is when our level design team
steps in. We are starting to work on the first drafts of the dialogues. So basically the quest
designers are like sketching them out. We do not write them, we just sketch them out basically
what the scene is about. We do include first elements of gameplay.
That's basically we want to make sure that the quest is playable.
And then this whole process concludes with actually something that various companies called
first playable. For us it's just draft. And when the quest is playable and all the quests are
playable, that means that the whole game is playable. And that is basically the goal of the draft stage.
And afterwards, we move on to pre-alpha, alpha, pre-beta, beta, and then we polish the game and ship it in that, period.
This is how it looks like though in practice. So when you have the story outline, we iterate the hell out of it,
and then when it's approved, it goes to quest design, iteration happens there,
and to the draft implementation with iterations are happening there.
What's important is that it actually can be...
Disapproved, you can call it. It can be sent back to the previous stage. And I think this is a key thing,
like why our things are working the way they are working, because we basically do not
resign until we are really, really happy with whatever we have produced. And sometimes we
do a lot of iterations and we bounce a lot back and forth between those stages.
And every single time when we actually move on and let's say update something in a meaningful way
on the draft implementation level, we also go back and really try to update the documents,
at least till the alpha stage. That was the most boring part out of the way. Let's now
focus on the key quest design lessons. So, my dears, the thing is that I will need to
talk about the story. And to talk about the story, I need to spoil you some things.
So if you didn't play Cyberpunk 2077 or Witcher 3,
you need to leave the room.
So I think everyone's gone.
That was supposed to be gone.
That's the last warning, really, to turn off the video
or just leave the room.
I'm trying, I will do my best not to spoil too much,
but I'll have to spoil some things because I
will be using examples.
So let's move on to the first stage, which is mastering the plot. I will be talking about three
major lessons here, engagement, impact, and believability. This slide is only for you for
tracking where we are. We will now talk about the engagement. When we were working on The Witcher 3
Blood and Wine, the opening quest, The Beast of Beauclair, there was a moment when you as a player,
you as Geralt, you go in and you investigate.
And then there is this moment of autopsy.
There's this guy chopped off on a table.
The quest was designed by Blazej Augustynek,
our lead quest designer.
And what we wanted to do there,
we wanted to make sure that as a player,
you'll be intrigued by what the hell is happening.
You know, like why this guy is chopped off in such a way.
And every single detail that you actually find out
throughout this investigation is
introducing some new things that you wouldn't expect.
And every single step is actually surprising in a way.
And that is a, I would say, like one of the elements, one of the factors that's really
driving us when we are constructing our story. We want the player to want the story. You don't have
to shove the story into players throat, you can structure it in a way that player is craving for it.
And player really wants it. And the key thing that I wanted you to memorize from this is that
by subtraction of key information,
you can actually make the player really intrigued and really curious about what's going on.
And the investigations actually are a really interesting typical element of that.
And Witcher 3 is really a detective game in a fantasy setting. I loved, I think it was PC Gamer
that did this article when they actually properly identified what Witcher 3 was trying to be
when in terms of a genre.
This is a detective game in a dark fantasy setting.
And not that many people maybe felt it from the very beginning,
but when designing the quests and so on,
we were using a lot of investigation mechanics,
and that naturally sent us to actually creating many more stories
that will be simply about finding out what the hell happened.
Now, another example I wanted to show you is from one of the most beloved quests from Cyberpunk 2077, The Dream On.
This is one of the opening scenes. Let's watch it together.
As you can see, in this particular scene,
we have set it up in a way that there is a deliberate
subtraction of information.
Look at another example that I have prepared for you.
Here at the moment when you're actually, as a player,
doing the investigation, there's a moment when you're
actually getting to this back room,
there are those big machines there.
When you scan them, when you can see actually
on the scanning in the UI, you can see that
it's an unknown tech, that it's a system
that is not in a database, that it's basically being not recognized.
As a player, you are taught actually that using the investigation mechanics and scanning basically in Cyberpunk,
you're going to find out what happened, what it is, and so on.
In this case, Patrick Mills, the quest designer for this quest,
and Rafał Orkan, the writer for this quest,
they have decided to actually very deliberately remove those informations for the player
and really say, you know, I know that you are using the scanning
and you want to know, you want to find out what actually happened,
but you won't find out.
And this is really, really deliberate play with the player.
And throughout that, and it's really, really important
that when you're constructing your story by doing this,
you can really make the player very curious.
And I brought up, of course, the Dream On
as one of the examples of such quests,
because I think it has done it the best
out of everything that, out of the quests
we have at Cyberpunk 2077,
but both Witcher and Cyberpunk
are actually full of such examples.
We'll be moving on. I could be talking much more about that point, but I want to give you those nuggets of knowledge.
So we will now jump into the impact. And this is one of the more powerful, I would say, lessons that I can give you.
When we are creating the story, we are trying to, from the very beginning.
created around those emotional banging moments.
What you're seeing here actually is Judy.
She is broken down after the moment of what has happened to her friend.
I'm not going to spoil it much more, but it's really heartbreaking.
And as a player, you have met Judy already.
You get to know her, you know who she is.
And then throughout that storyline,
you also get to know Evelyn.
And at this point, there is a moment
when you actually face her.
And it's a really heartbreaking moment
when you actually see her makeup dripping down her face.
And it really makes you, as a player, empathize with her.
And when we are creating those stories,
we always try to think about those emotional moments that
really are going to drag the player to our stories.
This quest was designed by Sarah Gruemmer, who's sitting here in the front of row, and Magdalena.
And Magdalena Zych, who is the writer of this quiz,
they did a phenomenal, phenomenal job on Judy's storyline.
And what's interesting is that from a very, very beginning,
we didn't have that moment.
But when working on that storyline,
we discovered that we actually have to add it.
And it was fairly early, of course,
when we discovered that that particular beat has
to be in the story.
And this is what I want to encourage you to do.
Like, when you're actually crafting your stories,
think about those emotional moments.
Like the moments when you can really like punch the player or your reader, your audience into the gut and really make them feel things.
Because this is the most important thing.
And when I'm always training like my younger designers, we always tell them that we want to
teach the designer, to control what player is thinking and what player is feeling.
And that is really your job as a narrative designer.
I always, I really believe in that.
You really need to try to control what players are thinking and feeling.
Super important for building good impactful stories.
Another example actually comes from The Witcher 3,
when I was working on the Battle of Kaer Morhen.
That's the quest I designed and implemented.
And I needed a moment for Ciri to actually make a decision
that she is not going to be hunted anymore.
She's not going to be a prey.
She is going to be a hunter,
and she's going to be going after the wild hunt.
But to do so, I knew that I need a substantial event
that will really break her inside.
And that was the moment when I proposed to our writers team to kill Vesemir.
And at first, they weren't sure if we should be doing that, but throughout the discussions with
Marcin Blacha, our story director, we reached the conclusion that actually it's a really good
decision to basically really make Ciri, make that step, make that change.
You know, some of you might be a psychologist. I'm a psychologist by education. There is a lot of
events in our lives that actually can tremendously change us. You know, like for instance, people that
have been in concentration camps, like there's a lot of data that shows when they left them,
they were completely different people. And that incident, what happens in their life and changes
them really tremendously, is something that they kind of needed, right?
To build it in a game, I really had to be very careful.
That's why I picked Vesemir,
because his character is built up
and prepared really well.
You get to know him throughout many quests.
So that's why this moment was so impactful.
And also, I wanted to do something
that players wouldn't believe that we will be doing.
I wanted to surprise you in a good way, I hope,
basically to drag you to our storytelling.
And that is the second point I wanted to make here.
Like really, when you are building those impactful stories,
no holds are barred.
Like you can do anything that is needed to make the player feel things.
And here's another example I wanted to show you.
There is a moment when V wakes up on a landfill in Cyberpunk 2077.
Let's watch the scene together.
So what's interesting is that when you're actually creating your stories, you can create them around
the emotional impactful moments, as I said, but sometimes it's difficult. Those things need a
proper build-up. It takes time, it takes screen time, it takes a lot of pages in a book, a lot of
pages in a comic book to really build it up properly. So what you can do is also build your
story around something that, together with Tomasz Marchewka, our story director, we call it cool scenes.
And normally, when you are actually
working with the designers, a lot of them
will actually propose to you lots of different cool scenes
and things that could happen.
The thing is, I do not think that this
is a proper way to build a story and tell a storyline
and tell an emotional story.
However, you can do it.
You can actually think about those banging moments that
really stay in your mind and kind of intertwine them
in your story.
And here is an example of basically Takemura
going there and basically delivering the justice.
Dex is the guy that double-crossed you in Cyberpunk 2077. You probably know that. Hopefully you played
the game. It serves multiple different purposes. It kind of concludes the storyline of Dex as a
character. It introduces Takemura.
as an important main story character here for us.
And it's also a short, concise, very punchy scene
that's very memorable at the same time.
We had a lot of discussions internally
if that should be an actual objective for the player.
Maybe you should be asked to really go after Dex and do that.
But throughout many discussions, you know, weighing pros and cons,
we reached the conclusion that it would be probably better to just have
Takemura take care of that and use it.
Bless you. And use it as an introduction.
So, one last thing for you to memorize here.
Outside of those emotional moments, you can also think about great scenes,
but this is always, I would say, secondary to the
great emotional impactful stories that you're building, but have that in mind.
If you only have the storyline that's constructed out of the cool scenes, you'll see that there's
no soul in your story.
There's a great storytelling, I would say, theory about fire and embers.
Maybe you heard about it.
It's basically the fire is everything that is the soul of the story, and embers is really
what I see.
You know, is the VFX, is cool shit happening,
is, you know, transformers beating the shit
out of each other.
This is basically like great stuff happening in a screen,
you know, great visual spectacle,
but there's no fire, you know, in it.
And I think like we as storytellers and narrative designers,
we always need to take care of the fire that is there.
That concludes the impact.
I need to slightly speed up because I'm talking too much.
So right now we will move on to believability.
As an industry, and I'm here speaking about also myself,
we are sometimes very uncomfortable with actually
giving the player the moments when there's nothing to do.
And there are moments when you are not
supposed to run in and basically build something new
and you don't have any new objective.
Look at this example.
This is a moment when you actually
had your intimate moment with Judy,
and you're there embraced.
Looking at her, having a smoke, and there's nothing else going on. There's nothing else to do,
there's nothing else to be, it's just being with her. And being a human is really a lot about this.
Like we intuitively, as human beings, we know it. Like when you are with your loved one,
you do not like hug and then run to take out the trash, right? Because that's the next objective.
You normally spend time with them, right? You embrace them, you just look into each other,
and this is what you do. And as a studio, we have learned that, actually, that we need to make,
give space to our characters to really shine on the screen, to really give them time
to do all of those elements.
And there's so little games that actually do it.
Like you can probably search in your memory.
There's literally few examples that come to mind.
And that really is so powerful when you're
building the characters.
But you, of course, need to use your empathy.
your personal empathy and try to feel, you know, what is the proper moment.
And of course, you know, the fact that this slaps so much in Cyberpunk,
it's a work of our amazing cinematic design team that makes sure
that those moments are really properly timed.
Cinematic animators, they make sure that, you know, all the animations are really fluid.
Look, look how believable she is, how she acts, you know, when she looks at you.
And this is the, this is how you see her in the game,
because your face is literally next to her.
So when you have those moments, don't rush.
Another element, another moment is like, there's this situation when you're actually together with Panam, right?
Like there is the sandstorm coming and so on, you're supposed to sit with her and so on.
And I remember watching so many YouTubers and streamers and so on, influencers,
playing our game when she actually put the legs on your legs and everyone's like,
What's going to happen now?
Because that's so unusual.
That's so unusual for characters in a game to do that.
That's normal.
That's human.
We never do that.
That should be just two characters in idle
and over-the-shoulder camera just talking to each other.
That's what we are used to.
But that's not life.
That's not how people act, normal people.
That's why our cinematic designers, when
they were working on that scene, they
had this idea actually to start introducing the connection.
between V and Panam that is sort of getting born here, you know, the moments when she actually does this, you know.
So those human-like moments are really important.
And I know I'm talking too much and I need to move on.
I wanted to point out something, something super important.
Make sure that in your storyline,
when you are building a story, it's not only about the plot.
So when you're meeting the characters,
they are not telling you about what's next to do,
what's our next objective,
but there are also moments when they are themselves
and they speak what's important for them.
That's why there is a moment when you go
for a coffee with Kerry.
That's why there is a moment when you just lie
embraced with Judy and there's nothing else going on.
That's why there is a moment when you're with Panam here, she puts her legs on your legs,
and you're just there together. And they do not talk about the plot. They do not talk about like
what's next to happen about Yorinobu Arasaka Saburo and the chip in your head and all that.
They don't.
They are people and they talk about what's important for them, right?
So please remember about this.
When you're building a storyline, do not pack their only plot,
but also characters, who they are, and make them speak about themselves.
And that's important, especially in AAA,
because like we normally don't have a budget to basically pack it all in.
And it's important to reserve a bit of that budget to be able to do those things.
Please remember about this.
Now we'll move on now to the next section. This pretty much concludes the mastering the plot.
Now we'll talk to you about structuring the narrative. And there are three parts here,
brevity, choices, and consequences. Now some of those elements are pretty much separate talks on
their own, but I will try to give you as much as I can during this talk. So first and foremost,
The cinematography and cinema industry, a long time ago, has figured out how actually from
the movies eliminate so-called busy work. And what I mean by that, there is a situation when
you're together with a character, you find out about something, and then you go into another
character, and you talk to them, and basically refer everything, and you sort of go on and
repeat everything.
This is pretty basic when it comes to storytelling,
but I see it all the time, even in the movies, in games especially.
So there are situations when we, as designers,
we need to look really in our writing, in our scenes,
but also like in a structure of our quests and be like, OK,
when are we actually repeating information and when things are not needed?
Because when you remove the fat, when you trim the fat,
then the story becomes much more punchy.
Here's the example from Battle of Kaer Morhen.
So there was a moment when I knew
that we had to actually plan out that scene.
And that's the scene that Igor Sarzynski,
right now he's our narrative director.
Igor was working on that scene.
We knew that at this point,
we don't really want the player to discuss with Ciri
every single nook and cranny
how that the defense of Kaer Morhen is going to be.
Because you're going to see it in a moment.
So why the hell have it talk them about it?
So that's why we basically decide, okay, let's just use a simple cut here.
And they say, Geralt says, okay, you know what, let's just focus on it and discuss it in detail.
That's it. It cuts and then you're in the action basically as the Wild Hunt is attacking Kaer Morhen.
The next thing I wanted to point out to you is...
Something that actually we have been learning throughout Witcher 3, but I think we have
mastered it or maybe get closer to it during Cyberpunk is how you do your exposition.
And when it comes to Cyberpunk 2077, everything is, you are all the time in action there,
in the shoes of you. We have almost no cuts. We have no cut scenes. You're always there
yourself. Because of that, we had to be very strategic about how we divide the information.
And before I explain, I need to mention to you the signal and noise theory.
Maybe some of you heard about it.
Signal is all the messages that you want to give the player.
All the important information, everything that you want the player to learn.
Noise is everything that player can do in the same time,
therefore making the signal less visible.
So, for instance, here's the example that I'm showing you right now, the moment when you're
going for a reconnaissance with Takemura. At first, you're actually walking with him. This
is something that we call internally walk and talk. You're walking, basically, and Takemura
tells you and V, they talk about things that are slightly less important.
Because here, the noise is high, I can go naked, I can jump around, I can do things, throw grenades maybe,
you know, and not really listen to him. The noise, but the potential noise, is quite high.
And the signal is pretty low, because I can do so many things. But then, as a player,
you actually get at the top of the building, you sit down together, look at Takemura.
Then the signal is high and the noise is low, because I have control over the camera, I know where the player is looking,
and then I can actually give the player all the important information about the plot and the characters.
So when you look at all that sequence, you can see that sequences in Cyberpunk, and they were like that in Witcher 3 too, but to a lesser extent.
You can see that sequences in Cyberpunk, they are divided in a way that you have moments when you're together with the character,
when noise is high and signal is low.
And as a player, you can do weird stuff during that, but all the most important information
are always delivered when you're focused on the characters.
Because we wanted to make sure that you understand as a player that we don't lose you as an audience.
So it's a really good trick, in a way, to divide your exposition like this.
Ask yourself a question, okay, what actually is the important part of my narrative and what is not?
Or what is slightly less important? And what is only maybe your ego,
your ego speaking, and you wanting actually the player to get all of those important
story informations, everything about the world and backstory and all that.
Maybe it's really not needed.
Maybe it can be really something that we call an opt-in design, so a player can actually decide,
okay, I will actually listen to it deliberately because I want,
but if I don't want to, I'll go naked and throw grenades.
One last bit that I wanted to mention. This is fairly difficult to do and it requires, I think,
quite a lot of skill, but you know we are in GDC and I think it's a perfect audience to talk about it.
Exposition in general is difficult to do well and
A bit in Witcher 3, but I think in cyberpunk we kind of learned it, how to do it well.
And here's an example when you're actually walking together with Jackie into the Konpeki Plaza.
There's this moment when this lady that works there, she greets you.
And she has a uniform, that's cool.
But she also has real skin.
And her skin is like dark gold.
It's like a dark gold kind of a shade.
And it's surprising in a way, because it turns out that in this world,
and your skin is a part of your attire, you wear it to work.
That's basically a normal thing.
However, here in the story, we never address it.
There's not a moment when we in the story point out finger to that
and tell you that as a player.
But you can actually understand it if you look at what's going on.
You can actually understand, oh, so this is what this world is.
This is how it's constructed.
And it's normal and natural to be like this.
And, you know, when you are moving through Cyberpunk, you actually see lots of those.
So, you know, commercials, for instance, that we have in the game, the TV, the radio,
all of them are actually about this.
They're the subtle exposition.
And subtle exposition is about the values that are underlying your narrative,
underlying your world.
And we wanted to make sure that those values stick through,
but they are never directly given to you.
We never point our finger to it, almost never.
We basically try to make you soak in that world
and really be in that world.
Let me move on, because I'm far from being brief, so that concludes the brevity point.
Let's move on now to choices and consequences. Now, my dears, this section is really gigantic and
I could have a completely separate talk about this, so I will be deliberately picking just some
elements of that. There's more to it, but there are some things that I think are really important,
or things that I learned throughout our work in CD Projekt Red.
This example that you're seeing right now is Geralt, who is facing the tree, you can call it,
the heart of the tree. And then there's this choice that you're supposed to make. Now,
what we have done here deliberately as designers, we have built up
both sides of that story, both sides between those you're choosing, so that you have no idea
exactly what's going to happen. This is an example of the choice where actually bad things happen no
matter what you choose. We sometimes do that. Sometimes we don't, but sometimes we do and
that's a matter of a play between us as creators and you as an audience. In this specific case,
we wanted to make sure that you will make a bad choice no matter what.
And that was the design.
However, all of those sides are actually very carefully created and very carefully structured.
As a player, you don't really know what's going to happen,
but both sides sort of have been presented to you.
And those emotional dilemmas, those interesting dilemmas,
are like, they are making the best possible choices you can actually have in your game.
Really, like, when you're choosing,
choosing if you want to do a quest or not is not really an exciting choice.
Maybe if you want to have sex with a character, that's probably also not exciting because everyone will choose it.
So because of that, it's really good to think about what is actually a moral dilemma and what is really not obvious.
What is really not obvious? There's so many things in our world that are not obvious
and things that everyone fights on social media every single day.
It is not that difficult to create those dilemmas
and make sure that the player has really something to think about.
In here, actually, you have another example.
There is a moment when Placide,
he's one of the frontmen of the Voodoo Boys gang,
so he actually double-crosses you,
and as a player, I'm pissed at this guy.
And when I meet him, I want to fucking punch him in the face.
And what happens?
The game gives you exactly that.
And this is what we learned actually throughout working
in Witcher 3 and Cyberpunk 2077.
When it feels right that the given choice should be there,
then we as a designers, we should provide it to the player.
Because in most cases, it means that we have created
that situation in a way that as a player,
you're really believing you should be able,
you should be given the choice
and given the option to do so.
And that's always like a philosophy that we have
that when we were playing our quests,
you know, throughout working on them,
We always ask ourselves, OK, does it feel fine that I can't do something here?
And sometimes it does.
Sometimes you may want to not give a choice because you want to make a point.
And that's also fine.
You just need to be conscious about it as a designer.
For me, it's really amazing when I watch like streamers and YouTubers, influencers,
when I see them play our games and they literally at the moment
when they say, I fucking hate this guy, I want to punch him.
And then the choice comes in.
When to do that, like that happened with Fingers, that happened with Placide,
this means that the design was on point and we have actually felt right because then as a player
you were in shoes of V, you felt you're not forced into any choices and you really feel,
okay, the design's provided me that I can be that person. I can really role play that person.
I really need to speed up. Now when
We were building the race for the crown in The Witcher 3 for Skellige.
There is Cerys, she is a daughter of Crach an Craite, and then there's her brother Hjalmar.
They are both on a race for a crown, but as a player, you are really presented with a choice that is not a good one.
This is a negative example that I'm showing you right now.
The Cerys in the story, she has been structured in a way that she will be always a preferred choice by our players.
And in a way here, we didn't do...
too well preparing that choice. And that's why I'm giving you this example to show you that it's
difficult and we do not always get those things right. Because Cerys was preferred by many people
because she was more interesting as a character, she looked better than Hjalmar, she had more
screen time simply, she was written in a better way, and then when you have Hjalmar who has so
many downsides, much less people will choose him. So you need to think about those things.
When it comes to Cyberpunk, actually, we have discovered that also a very interesting factor,
which is the star power. We have Keanu Reeves playing Johnny Silverhand in Cyberpunk 2077.
We have Idris Elba playing in Phantom Liberty. We need to take into account the fact that every
time when we have a star, players are going to fall for a star almost all the time.
Therefore, Johnny Silverhand, when you meet him first time in Cyberpunk, he's a real asshole.
Because we wanted to make sure that we draw this really big arc from him being a horrible person
to the point that you actually really like this guy at the end and really understand him.
But we thought about this from the very beginning, that star power of Keanu Reeves in this case,
he will skew your choices. He will skew your choices and he will make you want to be with
him more than if that would be some random generic character.
My dears, that will be the choices.
Now I'll move on to consequences.
Let's look actually an example from one of the quests
that I've done for Cyberpunk 2077.
This is a moment when you are going back
to Totentanz club.
You could have, as a player before,
met Maelstromers in Old Food Factory
where you could have killed a bunch of them
or resolve that situation.
This quest is much later and let's look at this example.
In here, actually, you can see another example.
There is a moment when you go into Totentanz and there's Dum Dum.
You know, if you managed to, if you actually made a deal with Maelstrom, he's there.
Now, what it is, as a designer, I am doing telegraphing.
This is how we call it.
We are at the moment when you have actually made your choices.
Those choices come into something.
And at the end, when you meet that character, he is there talking to you in person.
And I, as a designer, I'm telegraphing in as many levels as I only can.
There is a moment when you walk in, then there's the dump, there's Dum Dum. Or if you kill them,
there's Patricia, that she basically takes a rule over like Maelstrom and so on, she's taking care
of it. And you talk to them, the story develops in a completely different way. They walk you
through different paths, they walk you to different rooms. This is called telegraphing.
When you're showing your consequences to the player, use every possible trick you have to make them realize that is the choice.
One of the things that we have realized when working on Cyberpunk 2077 is the fact that when consequences are too subtle, players won't see them.
And I will show you more examples of that in a moment.
Here, the choices, the consequences that come in, that are really clearly
telegraphed, are always the best. And players are always surprised and they love it.
They really love it. And it's not really that expensive in terms of budget to make.
So, those choices that are really, really delayed, and sorry, consequences that are really,
really delayed, are always the best. In here, you could have made the choice in prologue,
and this quest comes in really late in the game. It's a part of a storyline of Kerry Eurodyne that
is pretty much one of the last main characters that we're introducing to the game.
You as a player, you probably forgot what happened.
That's why when you walk in, they have a chat.
And in that chat, they say,
Hey, is it that gung, that zeroed Royce in All Foods?
That's the reason why that line is there, because I'm telegraphing to you.
Hey player, do you remember? You did that. Do you get it? Yes, Royce, All Foods. That is the
reason why those lines are there, right? Telegraphing on every level, because like,
the game of Cyberpunk is gigantic. Players don't remember all of those characters,
everything that happened. Besides, I don't know what happened in their life.
Player could have played, you know, 10 days straight for 20 hours every single day and got
there, or they might have took five years.
The player, you know, their kids might have born, you know, in the middle.
Who knows what happens?
You know, you never know what happened to the player,
so that's why you need to telegraph very clearly.
Another example, actually, this is the one that is a negative example, I would say.
We've put a lot of effort in Cyberpunk 2077 in television and radio content.
And again, players who actually paid attention to that
liked it and really appreciated that.
But most of players didn't.
Most of players actually didn't realize that it's even there. That's why when you're actually
designing the consequences for your choices, design for visibility. This is how I call it.
So think how you can actually show it to the player in any possible way. When you're designing
something that's super obscure and nobody will see it, it makes no sense. Really, it makes no
sense to spend that budget because for the player, something that that player didn't see, it doesn't exist.
And again, maybe their Redditors, they will go to Reddit and, you know, they will read about it and they will be all excited that it actually is there.
But that is a fracture of your player base.
Majority of them, if they don't find it, they assume it's not there.
And this is what happened for Cyberpunk, quite a lot actually.
Like, a lot of our consequences have been subtle.
There have been situations where characters appear somewhere, they're mentioned, you know,
you can meet people that you have saved, you know. For instance, in this example, you know,
depending on your choices there, some of the TV content changes or radio content changes.
Pretty much nobody realized that for quite a long, for quite a lot of time, you know.
People claim that it's actually not in the game at all. So really designed for visibility,
especially when you're spending as much budget as we have spent on all of the radio and TV content.
My dears, that concludes consequences. I'm actually not that bad with the time, though. I'm horrible. Okay,
let's move on because we have like four more, but you know, thankfully we have a whole day. So
we'll be talking about over-design, bravery, novelty, and effectiveness here. I have
quite a lot, so I'll be short on it right now.
There is a moment when we as designers, we really feel that our ego speaks to us, right? And we want
to make the most, the best possible life simulation we can. An example here, Panam is here sitting in
a bar, sipping a beer in the prologue of Cyberpunk. You can actually meet her. And throughout the,
you know, early stages of the work on the game, through conversations, hey, should she maybe
finish the beer, get into the car, leave, drive to Badlands, you know, meet the nomads, you can
follow her, see all of that.
Okay, but what the hell is the point of that? You always need to ask yourself a question, okay,
why this is even in the game? Why I would be even adding that? Details are amazing when they matter,
when there's some kind of a meaning behind them, when there's a reason behind them. Adding that
stuff really makes no sense. And always when you're working on the things, you need to ask
yourself a question, am I actually designing or over-designing at this point?
I remember throughout work on Cyberpunk 2077, one of my designers changed his title on Slack to
Quest Overdesigner. So another example I wanted to show you is the example from Cool Metal Fire.
This is the quest. This is the moment when Johnny Silverhand, for the first time,
takes over your body. And in here, actually, what I did
Together with cinematic designer, Åukasz Åšliwa, we've made a decision that there's no point of actually V as Johnny,
because Johnny has control over everybody at that time, to meet the Rogue and with her actually talk about everything
and really repeat everything that was said.
We've decided to use a cut here and basically jump directly to the most important things.
And then there is a moment after that when you wake up in that hotel.
You feel you have blood on your hands, you know, because you're like coughing badly and so on.
Rogue is there and it turns out they already talked and established everything and she knows
all the important elements. So this ties up a bit to the brevity I talked about,
but also like we knew that, okay, we could actually design here an amazing long scene
and do all of that, but we felt it's really not needed. Because in most cases,
it will be just repeating the same information.
And that is the overdesign. I'm speeding up slightly because we are short on time.
So now let's go to the bravery. Now, I really want to, I really love this quest,
but this requires some introduction before I'm going to roll that clip. So, my dears,
there's a quest in Cyberpunk 2077 when you meet Joshua Stephenson. He is a convict, and he,
during his time in prison, he decides to go back to God. He wants to die.
But dying a specific, and he knows he will die, he is sentenced to death,
but he wants to die in a specific way. He has a purpose.
He wants to die and become a symbol for everyone else.
And in our world, we have something called brain dances.
As a brain dance, you can record that brain dance and make someone else
exactly feel and experience what you feel.
So what Joshua Stephenson does,
He gets in contact with a brain dance studio and they agree on so that he will die on a cross.
And they will record that as a brain dance for everyone who's a follower, for everyone who can
actually go through that experience. And there's a lot of build-up leading up to that scene. I
wanted to make sure that you know all the context because that content is really important. We pay
a lot of attention to that.
We had incredible writer Marcin Blacha, our story director, who wrote the dialogues for this quest
to really make sure that we flesh it out before actually that happens.
Let's look at it and watch it together.
I honestly love this scene.
At the very beginning, when we were working on this quest, when the designer who actually
designed it, Przemek Tarczynski, when he came to me, actually this quest was about something else.
At the very beginning, you as a player, you're accompanying Joshua Stevenson, in the end
you are delivering him to brain dance studio, and this is where it ended.
And I told him, Przemek, but we have this amazing interactive scene system.
I want to be in the shoes of that Roman soldier who actually hammers him to the cross.
Because this, you can really put the player in that experience and you can really make the player feel it.
And you can really make it be like this.
And our amazing cinematic team really made it happen.
And I honestly believe that we as a AAA industry, we are so scared of new topics.
of things that require bravery,
and I'm talking about artistic bravery.
This quest has a lot of context.
It's not an edgy scene for being an edgy scene.
It's a scene about the person,
it's a quest about the religion, about belief.
It's the really gruesome and dark world.
That's why all of those elements
about religion, spirituality,
and being in close connection with other people
actually matter so much.
And this is a very important element to have in your game.
In most AAA, and I'm speaking about this because the indies are actually doing a much better job here,
in most AAAs you don't really see that. We are so safe with everything that we are building.
There is another example I wanted to show you.
Actually, when I was working on Bloody Baron storyline from The Witcher 3,
there was a moment when I came up with the idea of Botchling,
you know, this miscarried child that Baron has.
And there was a lot of concern.
You know, we had some young fathers in the company
and they were pointing out to me that they are maybe not too comfortable
with having a zombie child in the game.
But when we talked, I told them what it is about.
It's about domestic violence.
It's about this broken father who's
a parallel to Geralt, actually trying to do his best
and actually understanding all of his shortcomings.
And then there is a moment when he actually
takes the botchling in his arms and walks with him.
That whole sequence when he carries him in the files,
in the game files, I actually called it peregrination.
Because he goes in to actually undo in a way as much as he can to do what he has done to his family.
And that was important. It's not a shocking value just to be there.
I wanted to talk about something that wasn't talked about.
And again, we are talking about 2012. At that time in AAAs, you didn't see topics like this.
Nowadays, it's maybe slightly different, especially in the indie space.
But at that time, it was something that nobody has ever done before.
And we really wanted to do it because we believed that this artistic bravery.
This is something we should be doing.
This is our responsibility.
And especially this is how I see it as a director in our company.
And I know that a lot of directors are with me in this.
We have a purpose of basically doing something else, something different.
Because you as players, when you come to us and you play a game from CD Projekt Red,
it needs to feel like our game.
And it's not safe.
And we'll be doing things that sometimes nobody else will do.
There is another example from here.
There is a moment, one of the most beloved endings to Cyberpunk 2077,
Don't Fear the Reaper.
There is a moment when actually, if you have built a relationship with Johnny,
who will at some point offer you that he can actually join you
on this one-to-one suicide mission on Arasaka.
That was something that our quest designer, Eero Varendi, proposed.
He felt that it was needed in this given moment
to give the players something like this.
And we were like, this is so fucking bold.
We should probably do it.
And that was basically how the conversation went.
We really wanted to give you that option as players,
and we found out ways how to do that.
If you go in there solo on Arasaka,
when you die, the credits roll, because that is your ending.
And of course, you know, a lot of players proven us
that they are able to beat it really well, that whole sequence.
My dears, there's much more going on, and it's six minutes left.
So we are going to speed up even more.
I wanted to show you one of the scenes, an example where our interactive scene system is used here
as a matter of novelty. It was an important element of the innovation that we've been doing
for Cyberpunk 2077. Let's watch it together.
Yeah, I don't see any brick here.
So, my dears, this scene actually shows so many innovations that we have done in Cyberpunk 2077
when it comes to first-person perspective storytelling.
And I wanted to mention this because of the MAYA principle that I wanted to explain to you.
Like, MAYA principle is something that...
I think can guide us a bit when it comes to working on a new novel things for our games.
And basically defines that you should actually provide as much novelty as you only can,
while in the same time trying to stay somewhat
relevant to the player, somewhat familiar, so that player is not lost. That is the way how we've been
building our interactive scene system. As a player, you kind of get it. You know, you're there, okay,
you can look around, even though at first, actually, a lot of other players didn't know
that they can move their head in the scenes. They felt that they were just stiff because this is
what they were taught to before. In time, of course, players learned, you know, that they can
actually do it. And incredible things about the scene done by Michal Zbrzezniak, our cinematic designer.
Amazing thing about the scene is that you can see how much staging was changing.
You know, the characters were moving, you were in a place, but actually the plans were changing.
You know, there was Royce in the background, you know, when the door opened, he was there,
then he walks into you. We're actually, by changing things in the front of you,
changing your frame.
It took us actually a lot of time to get to the point that we understood how to build those things.
So when it comes to the novelty, I really advise you to stick to the MAYA principle.
When you're like maybe worried about like just going too wacky and doing something that, you know,
your game won't find its place on the market, it will guide you in a way of like how to do.
And what to do. Another example here is like, actually coming from one of the quests I worked on,
you need to establish the rules before you break them. This is a pretty simple rule. A lot of young
designers really love to break the rules and they want to break all of the rules into first show the
rules that you have them, that you have established them to really be able to break them. I need to
speed up slightly. So that's why we'll move on to effectiveness right away.
And here is one of the elements of effectiveness I wanted to talk to you about is the fact that
you as a designer, you can really design your story and everything you have for the team you have.
When I was actually working on like a Supreme Quest, I knew that my cinematic designer,
in this case it was Michal Zbrzezniak that I mentioned before, and David Cordero, an animator,
they actually are both guitar players and they fucking love that stuff.
So I knew that I can really basically design the whole concert when you are putting together
samurai band, you're there in the shoes and playing with them. And I think this requires
actually a lot of skill because you as designers, you need to have bonds, human bonds with your
teammates. You need to know the people you're working with because sometimes some certain
stories or elements you will be able to pull off and others you won't be able to.
And treat them as assets, treat them as resources, as a thing that you can really help out with,
be together with that, and build together. But this requires you to know the people you're
working with and know their strong sides and weak sides, because then you can really build it for.
I will just glance over those really fast, but this is the last two points.
Pay attention to what other designers are building.
This is an example from a quest from Philipp Weber, The Parade,
in Cyberpunk 2077. When we designed that quest in 2019,
we already knew what is in the game. Therefore, it was actually pretty easy to
know that we are providing something different than other designers.
Believe me or not, but if you're working with creatives and, you know, probably
some of you definitely feel it, creative people
actually come up with the same ideas very often.
You know, separate people will come up with the same ideas.
That happens really.
A situation when you actually have the team that communicates well
and knows what the hell is happening in the game
is really important because then you don't copy each other's ideas
and you don't reuse the same solutions that you already have.
And the last, last moment, a shot from Pyramid Song, a quest by Sarah Gruemmer.
This is one of the quests that's actually one of the primary examples of situation
when whole team was put so much on the same page. This is one of the most beloved quests from
Cyberpunk 2077 where all of the disciplines collaborated really well. Sarah, basically,
Sarah is our expert. She knew everyone in the team. She knew their capabilities, knew what
what to do, and she knew how to push their buttons to really push them to do their best.
My dears, that concludes this part.
This is a speed run at the last moment.
So now I'm actually moving on.
Here are actually a few slides that are basically takeaways.
I'm just displaying them for you here.
Of course, this will be on GDC Vault, so you can take a look.
All of those points are actually already in the presentation.
So this is more of a sum up for you
so that you know what's going on.
And here's the last part.
And now, I wanted to thank you so much for being here!