First is a talk about can you make a good game
with a good play mechanics.
But before that, let's starting by introduction of me a bit.
So my name is Sun, and the real name is Prasert Vidyagan.
And some people might already guess
that I come from Thailand, a country which
people have a very long name and too hard to pronounce
and to remember.
But so please feel free to call me and remember me as Sun.
So nice to meet you.
So, I came from Thailand, but I actually now live in Japan for longer than 10 years now,
and I used to be a lead game designer for a game called Final Fantasy XV.
And I used to be in charge of these characters,
and implement the way their behavior in the real-time gameplay,
like how they walk, how they talk, what's inside their mind.
I write AI because I specialize in emotional AI and its application.
to the thing I call CX, which is Character Experience.
And our studio used to be part of Square Enix Japan,
but now we've become a different studio.
We call Luminous Productions,
and we're still under Square Enix Group,
but separate from Square Enix Japan.
And that's about me and my studio.
And, well, it's my third time here in GDC, though,
but I'm still so feeling excited to be here
and to talk with you today.
And let's hope we get a good fun from my talk today.
So, let's get started.
So, can we make a good game without good play mechanics?
This is a very tricky question, but before we go there,
let me, for the sake of clarity and make sure we're on the same page,
let me define a bit what we think good gameplay mechanics is.
When we talk about good gameplay mechanics,
I mean clear goals and rules for the players,
meaningful sets of approaches,
appropriate challenges, and appropriate reward,
which is kind of straightforward.
So you might say that, well, a play mechanic
or a game mechanic is a quality
that makes a game a game itself.
So let's imagine we want to draw a graph
that represents balance between a fun
that comes from game mechanic
and a fun that comes from other aspect of game,
then we might get something like this for a game.
Right? So gameplay mechanics just come first.
But what about other media that is not game?
Such as interactive toy, interactive art,
interactive media, or some kind of applications?
You might get something else, maybe like this.
But why do I talk to you about this? Aren't we supposed to talk about game
in this lecture? The reason is, boundaries between
content genres have become vague these days.
In the past, games are games and non-games are non-games.
But now we get very gradations of genre happen in between
and there's a lot of contents in between.
And sometimes you get some kind of strange contents like,
well, a character social game
that you just push one buttons
and then just repeatedly push the button
and then they fight for you
and in the end you won the battles, but it's fun.
And sometimes you get something like a narrative VR experience,
which is very immersive,
but you rarely have anything to choose at all.
But it's fun.
Yes, and we can spend our 30 minutes here to define
what is game, which one is not,
which is probably game, and which one is probably not.
But I'm not going to do that today,
because no matter if you call them a game or not,
it's a game designer's job to design them anyway.
You see, we call ourselves game creators, game designers,
but actually our jobs are wider than that.
Sometimes we have to make some other things.
Maybe we should just call ourselves, I don't know,
interactive content designers, I don't know,
but we just call them game designers.
But it depends on your company and your project
on what you're actually making.
So make sure you ask yourself,
what the content or the game you make,
the fun balance of it, is something like this,
or like this, or like this.
And if your contents or your game that you are making has a bigger balance of fun from other aspects,
rather than gameplay mechanics, then what do we do as a game designer?
Should we just give up and let the writers write a good story?
No, maybe not like that.
So, this lecture is not about talking that you should write good stories, you should have good...
graphic, but I'm here to tell you that game design is more than just game mechanic design.
It's more than play mechanic design. If you have a good game design, we can cover the other area, too.
We can make sure that our game is more fun, and it might not be fun from play mechanics,
but it's fun that can only become when we apply a good game design to our games or our
contents that might or might not be game. I don't know.
So, if you say that a game mechanics design is a primary skill for a game designer,
then I might say that the non-game mechanic, but the game design skill,
is maybe a secondary skill that we actually need.
So, our goals today, so I'm not here to tell you that we don't need good gameplay mechanics,
we need it.
But, to learn how to see...
the values, other values game could possess from other perspective
might teach us how we can make game a better thing and might teach
how a new way for us to enhance our game
and because you're gonna need it someday and believe me you're really gonna need
it in the near and near futures
So the approach we're going to talk today and we're going to use today is the approach
I call defining the verbs.
So let's start with something simple, something that I like.
Personally, I really love ice cream.
So we do it with ice cream.
So what do people do with ice cream?
What do you do with ice cream?
Yeah, we eat.
So if we decide that the eat is a thing we do with ice cream, then we decide ice cream
to maximize taste, like what they do around here in San Francisco.
Some may recognize this, this is our famous ice cream in San Francisco.
I've been taking this picture around these days for the talk, but not for me, but yeah,
I love ice cream, though.
But if, what if we define another verb that people can do with ice cream, let's say, like,
to Instagram.
then can we get something else?
Maybe like this?
No, maybe no, because good designer
can balance visual and flavor.
So you don't have to define a new word for that.
We can still balance visuals and flavor, right?
But if, what if we put all we have
to the new word into Instagram?
What if we care about appearance
more than more equal than its flavor?
What do we get?
We might get something like this.
This is ice cream in Harajuku in Japan.
Very flashy.
And this is what happens when you define a new verb
to Instagram, when you invest everything you have
to a new value, the ice cream you possess
that might not be to eat, and you get something new.
You get a new product.
So it's applying to everything in our product designs.
When you get new verb, you get a new value for your product.
When you get new value, it means you can come up with new design approach for it.
And this is also applying to game too.
So what do people do with game?
If it's to play, if it's yes, then you need a good gameplay mechanic.
That's the way it should be.
But if there are other words that we can define that players do with games, and if we can
define that, maybe we can find a new approach of thinking of how we can improve our games.
So that's what we're going to talk about today.
Verbs.
So today I've already...
I will tell you seven verbs here that people can do with game, starting from to play down
to the bottom of the list, which is the order of awareness to designers.
And we go one by one and see our newest perspective that we can get from game design.
And maybe you can...
We might get the same game or game design from the new perspective,
but to get a new perspective means you get a new tool for it.
So I think it's interesting that we explore these works together.
Starting from the first work to play, and then the second work, which is...
To explore.
To explore a game is fun.
And sometimes people mix it up, like, to play, because it's really close to each other.
But for me, to explore doesn't really need challenges, when to play needs challenges.
Imagine sightseeing.
We go sightseeing.
We love sightseeing, right?
But why do people go sightseeing?
Do you really need a challenge there?
Like, if say, if you go to Bali, or you go to Phuket, I don't know,
and you don't have obstacle, you don't have challenge in your trip,
would that gonna make your trip feel boring?
Maybe no. It's fun anyway to see new things, to see unseen things, to face the unexperienced.
Exploring is fun in itself.
And there are lots of ways we can do to improve that.
But one technique I'm going to tell you today is the technique called itemizations and visualizations.
So when they say itemization, this mean to,
well, people brain can easily recognize
thing that is symbolized.
And it's good if we make this countable,
the number of thing that you haven't seen
or the location that you haven't been.
Imagine in the new seamless open world game,
is like radiation like this.
So it's cool and stuff, it's believable, but you don't.
You can't really count how many areas or how many places you have been
because it's all connected to one place.
And you feel like there's something missing about it.
You don't know where the area starts, you don't know where the area ends,
and your brain cannot recognize it easily.
And it would be better, like, imagine the old game
where all the maps are separated in this grid,
and it's really easy to recognize that I've been to this area or not this area.
And to solve this problem, there are lots of ways we can do.
And one thing we can do is to use visualization using UI.
Or you can use approaches that Japanese usually
do in their society, which is a thing called Stamp Rally.
That's in Japan.
Stamp Rally is an activity that when
in the festival and in the fair, the children
will get a paper of a kind of book.
And they have to visit lots of places to get a stamp.
And if you collect all the stamps, they're going to get a prize.
Now, this is technically a game, though,
but what I'd like to say is that you don't have to add this in the game,
but the process of having people to do something
when they go to some place is really clever,
because it symbolizes the idea that this area is one area.
So instead, you get the big, open world, seamless area
that cannot be easily defined as in locations.
When you put a point that people have to do something,
and you have people to do that, the user to do that,
people form a kind of imaginary boundaries
of the concept of what location it is.
And then they can make it, they can count it,
and they can feel that they can fill in some kind of list
and feel better when they do explorations.
This is one of the things we can do.
Another thing that might be interesting is to say that motivation might change during explorations.
First, it might be exploration for the sake of exploration,
but later on, when you nearly complete the list, it becomes exploration for the sake of completion,
which asks you to play a unique gameplay.
And that's not a bad thing, I just want to state that it's a kind of different thing.
So takeaway for exploration. Exploring is fun in itself.
Can we use itemization and visualization to add value more to the explorations?
And how do you use the sense of completion to urge the player to explore more?
Okay, so we go to the third, the next verb, which is the thing you can do with game, which is to
roleplay.
So, by roleplay, I mean you savour the characters and their interactions,
you savour the story, you savour the world itself by being a character.
And there are actually two types of roleplaying.
The first type is the being you type,
when you become an invader or a named character.
You customize it, you become someone.
Or the type of being him or her,
that you become a particular characters.
And, well, whichever is fine too,
but it's really important that we make it clear
about it in our design,
because we're gonna need different kinds
approach for our designs.
Let's go for the type being you first.
For it being your role-playing design, it's really important that we don't put too much detail as personalities into our characters,
and trying to leave in the room and allow a chance for the player to express the way they want to be,
express their thoughts, express their personalities into a character inside the game.
But if we only get...
the vague role for it.
Players will just gonna be themselves
like they are everyday,
which is maybe boring.
So, in contrary, it's really important
that we give them a concrete role
or concrete situation that players to act.
The role should be concrete,
so players know what to act.
But the details in it, the personality,
should be left open for the players to express themselves.
That's how you can balance the B&U type
role-playing design and have the players
have fun playing that role the best.
And there are other types called being him and her role-playing design.
And in the game that when that there are only cut scenes
Well, you can make a game like that, but it would be more like cinematics
But if you're making a game that and you want the user to role play to act as a character in the game
It's really important that you make sure that the character the people the user know
what character would do in each situation so they know how to act, especially in the first part of the game when
when the player doesn't really know much about the characters. So I would suggest we start with
stereotype stuff and then add some more detail the further on when users spend more long and long time with the characters inside the game.
And I've already talked about this a lot in my last year GDC talk about character experience design
in the talk called Walked on my friends, giving life to AI buddies in Final Fantasy XV.
And it was available in GDC vault, so if you have interest, please check on it.
I think it's very interesting topic too.
One more thing that we should state about being him or her role-playing design is that
don't ever let the player choose between being himself or being the characters.
One bad example of this is a game where you play as a character with a short temper,
and always say things before he thinks, and ruins everything.
So you want to be a more loyal player to the characters,
and inside the conversation you have a choice like this.
It's going to be fine, because whichever you choose,
you can be the character anyway, and you can express yourself by choosing A or B.
But what happened in many games and many developers is that they put a new choice like this,
which, you know, players want to choose it because they want to make the situation get better.
But as soon as you choose them, you're going to destroy the characters itself.
Because this character, he should think, he should talk because he thinks,
so he shouldn't come up with these kinds of things.
So you have to choose it and then he will go off of immersion, which is not good at all.
So, you can't stop player from being themself anyway, so make sure that all the choices
express characters, but different variation in choice choose express the user himself.
The choice choose, all choice should express characters, and user should choose one choice
to express themselves.
That is the best way to create a role-playing design game for being him or her type.
One last thing we should state about role-playing design is that about projection swifting.
Although being him and her type role-playing design,
there are time that user become themselves,
and there are time that user become characters in game too.
And normally, player tends to be the character
in the part where there are much narrative stuff,
and they tend to be themselves in the part
where there's more freedom.
So, and this is completely fine, but we, as a game designer, we should be able to distinguish
both of this and make sure that we don't put, we don't allow unnecessary freedom to let
the player destroy and to create conflict of what character should be.
So, takeaway.
So role-playing is fun in itself.
How do we define a concrete role for a player to act?
And how do we make a game that allows users to express themselves
without making a conflict to the given character settings?
So we go to the next verb, which is to create. Well, creation is fun and I bet
that many users really want to be game creators.
But to... Well, we should turn user into creators, but...
Turning user into creator is not the same thing as turning user into designer.
It doesn't mean that we should give them level editor and have them do level design for themselves.
Creation can be more simple and more casual.
It could be something like customize the characters or take a picture, draw a picture, write something or name something.
like what they do in No Man's Sky,
where they allow you to name a new planet or a new species of animal when you discover them,
which is really clever, because creation can come very simply,
and there's no one who doesn't know how to name things.
But make sure that you have a way for people to share their creation with other users.
But however, there's one trap that usually happens now that putting a screenshot and
selfie system is a trend in our game industry.
So there's something like this.
Hey, I've added a screenshot selfie system in the game.
That's right.
Well, maybe it's not enough for me, I guess,
because some people might not, some user might not really want
to care and to use this kind of system.
And you might say that we don't want to force them.
Yes, we don't want to force them, but that means a waste,
a waste to turn that user into creators.
So the things that for me that I would do to,
the approach I would do to this problem is.
I think players' greatest creation is the gameplay they have or actually play itself.
The adventure itself is already a great creation.
If the game could find a way to turn the user gameplay, the adventure that it has been,
into something they could share easily, then I think it's going to be very simple.
Like what I did in Final Fantasy XV, where I have a snapshot system.
So when you play the game, the AI characters automatically shoot a photo for you,
and in the night, they will show this photo for you, and you can share it.
And all they have to do is to press the share button,
although even if you're a player that does not care much about creating stuff,
you can still share it because it's simple.
But you can still be feel proud of it that it's your creations
because default is only yours and it wouldn't happen if you want to play the game.
So I've talked about this a lot in my last year GDC talk about Prompto Facebook,
how about the AI auto-snapshot your adventure in Final Fantasy XV.
And it's also available in the GDC vault.
So you have time, please check it.
So takeaway, creation is fun in itself.
Can we find a way to allow players to have that fun in our game?
Can we find a way for them to share their creations?
And for those players who doesn't care much about creations,
can we find a way to change the game experience into something,
into creation for them to share?
Because the play experience is the best creation
that the user has actually made.
Okay, we go to the next verb, which is to communicate.
To talk and to socialize is funny itself, right?
Maybe not.
Yes, sometimes it's fun, but most of the time it's a pain when it's forced.
Personally for me, I think conversation is the most painful type of communication.
Because if communication is a game, I saw that it's a game that allows users to force other users to do communication, you see.
I say something and someone has to reply to something.
And you're forced to say something, and that's not fun.
I mean, so maybe, I don't know, I don't think we need much verbal communication in a game.
Instead, I think we should make good use of instinctive communication urges, like nurturing
and prank.
For nurturing, I believe that people in Indonesia, they love to help each other.
If given the right situation and the right grammar to do so, they would do so.
A good example of this is for Dragon Quest X, which is an online game, and in the world
map you can see other people fighting monsters in the world map.
And you cannot go and help them by directly killing monsters,
but you can use a share command to help them give a buff stat for the other users.
And what do you get? You don't technically get anything, you get thank you.
But you do it anyway, because people like to do that.
And you do it and you feel fun, and their communication happens.
That's a good way to encourage communication in the game, which is fun, and not forcing.
One more thing is that prank.
Prank is fun. Everyone loves to do prank.
But if the game suggests it too obviously and makes it too painful,
it's not going to be good.
But there's a wise way to do it.
And there's one good example of one of the mobile games for girls
which allows you to create your own boyfriend inside the game.
And you are allowed to, well...
dress your boyfriend in a stylish fashion and stylish costume.
And since it's a game about fashion, there's a feature that you
can recommend the clothes, the costume to other people's boyfriends
and you can change other people's boyfriend's costume
and dress. So people use these functions to change
other people's boyfriend into something like this.
Or they can actually recommend a swimsuit or other people's boyfriends,
which technically means you can undress other people's boyfriends.
And they do this all the time.
So when users get back home and log into the game,
they're going to be surprised to see their boyfriend naked
or dressed in stained stuff, and they're going to laugh,
and they're going to say, OK, I want to revenge this.
And they're going to find some other players,
and they share, they recommend other dresses,
and undress them, and do whatever.
And their communication happens.
And what's interesting is that the game makers never tell people to use this system for pranking.
They all know that this is a fun way to use this system,
and their communication comes in, and it's not forced.
So this is a good example of doing this.
So communication is fun when it's not forced.
Can we give the right situation and the right grammar to do so?
Can we encourage nurturing?
And can we subtly suggest pranking?
The next verb is to broadcast and to watch.
So now game has become more sports, like eSports.
So when we design game, we should design game
that is not only fun to play,
but a game that is fun to watch also.
The game doesn't mean for the audience.
But maybe most of us here in this room
doesn't create eSports game, right?
So I don't make eSports game,
so this is concern me, right?
Well, wrong.
Because live streaming has become one of the new standards
that the user use to enjoy the game in general,
not only for eSports.
And actually, I admit to you that this is not
for streaming and stuff.
It's not the area of my expertise.
So I cannot go too much deep into this topic.
But still, I feel the need to talk with this to you guys.
Because we know that streaming happens in our game.
But not many put this into their design process.
We know it's happened.
We neglect it.
But what about?
But it's time me and you start to think of this seriously and try to put it in our game
design process.
Can we think of a game design that can turn users into streamers more?
And can we make a game that is fun to stream and fun to watch?
I think that's a good homework for both of us to find a new generation for our game design.
And the last keyword is a new keyword too, which is to fan create.
So when you say fan creation, I mean fan fiction, fan art, doujinshi, fan game, anything that fandom creates.
And this is similar to the last keyword.
So we know that it's happened, there is something in it, but we normally don't care and put that in our design process.
But you see, making fan fiction, making fan art is fun.
And if that's the way the user enjoys our game,
so why not we design our game to make that happen?
But how do we make it happen?
What kind of game design we make to make sure
that the user is going to love our game?
Because a game that has many fans
is not the same thing as a game that has many fan creations.
To think about this, we must analyze first from the reason, from what fans actually create.
Fans normally don't create a new game because it's difficult,
and fans normally don't create new characters.
But fans usually create a new story from the already existed characters.
So you can say that characters are a story machine in itself.
It's a catalyst for contents.
As long as you have interesting characters,
they're going to be the chemicals.
stuff between that and they're gonna be constant going on and on.
So what's really important to that you make sure that you create a
character that
they care about.
When they say the character they care about, it means the character that they cannot neglect,
the character that feels something about it. The feeling could be anything. It could be love,
even hate, even curiosity, want to know more about characters. Hate is fine too, anything is fine.
The worst thing that could ever happen to your game character is that no one cares about that,
everyone forgets about that, you don't feel anything about that. So hate is completely fine.
And when people feel something about your characters,
they're gonna have a wish in their mind.
Like with love, they're gonna wish
for his and her happiness.
They're gonna wish other love him and her too.
With hate, they're gonna wish for his and her unhappiness.
Wish other to hate him and her too.
With curiosity, they want to learn,
they want to analyze it,
and want to learn more the characters.
And when they know something,
they want to share it to other user too.
And what important is this wishes.
become inspirations because the user can make their wishes come true by creating new contents.
And that becomes fan creations.
So I think the most important thing is that wish is the base inspiration for fan creations
and it could happen when you create the character that they care about.
So the takeaway is that being a fan is fun,
and it's even more fun to create a new thing
inspired by the game.
Since the characters are the energy source of the fandom,
can we make sure that we create the characters
that the user will care,
and can we create their wishes for the characters?
So here we are, seven verbs here today, which are related to fun.
And what's important is that, especially for the last two,
we already know it's exit, but we never put it
until our game design loop.
But I think it's time that we do.
Before I end today, let's go to the last trap.
If I announce you today that I've already made a new game like this
Well, actually it's for children age 4 and 6
But I didn't tell it to you, sir, and I have you play
And you played it and say, my game is silly and it's too easy
And complain about my game, should I care?
Well, maybe not, because I created this game for 4 and 6 age, year old kid
What I like to say is that you can't possibly please everyone with one content.
You have to focus on your target and sell the right game to the right people.
When I told you at the first of this talk that you should know the fund balance between
your games, it's really important too that you try to estimate what your user expects
your game content balance to be.
Although if you create a very fun game, they come from other aspects,
but if your user expects your game to be fun from gameplay mechanics,
they won't be satisfied with your games.
So user expectation control is really important.
Don't let the user expect and be disappointed by whatever we can give them
or don't plan to give them at all.
So for the conclusions, can we make a good game with good play mechanics?
Yes, depending on the content you make and your user expectation too.
Play mechanic is a super powerful tool, but to rely only to it will limit the possibilities of what your game could be.
So, let's be a game creator who knows how to make a good game with both good play mechanics and other approaches too.
The end. Thank you very much.