This is amazing!
Hi.
My name is John To.
I'm a writer at Bungie,
and that was the voice of Lord Shaxs,
one of our most popular characters
from our first-person shooter, Destiny 2.
Shaxx is the announcer of Destiny's Crucible,
which is our arena-based player versus player mode.
Today, I'll be talking about how our team found
that a well-written, supportive character like Lord Shaxx
can enhance the player experience in competitive game modes
while telling an important story, the players.
I've been working on Shaxx since Destiny the Taken King, our first big expansion, and I
brought the shoutcaster quality to Shaxx's dialogue.
I've been the fictional creative behind Shaxx's backstory in Grimoire and background lore
since then.
I worked very closely with senior designer Andrew Weldon, who's sitting right there.
Andrew masterminds the triggers for Shaxs in nearly all of Destiny's Crucible modes.
He is an expert on the player's PvP experience in Destiny, and he uses that expertise to
decide the different contexts in which Shaxs speaks.
Before we go deeper, here is a quick overview of the talk.
I'll be covering the writing process
in the development of Lord Shaxx
as Destiny's first PvP announcer character.
As a part of that process,
I'll broadly cover Shaxx's development history
as far as his writing goes.
The character changed pretty dramatically
between Destiny 1 and 2, as you're going to see.
Then I'll go into how Shaxs helps tell the player's story
in the context of Destiny's PvP mode, The Crucible.
I'll also cover how we continue to iterate
on the techniques that we used in writing Shaxs
through a new character called the Drifter.
And Drifter is Destiny's newest announcer
in a new competitive mode called Gambit.
And finally, I'll share the writing pillars
that I developed over the course of this process,
and will continue to use for future announcers in Destiny.
So first up for the uninitiated, who is Shaxx?
He is the voice of Destiny's Crucible,
and the Crucible is our collection
of arena-based player versus player modes in Destiny.
Shaxx is unique from most first-person shooter announcers
found in games like Unreal Tournament and Halo.
in that both of those games featured disembodied voices as announcers
that reacted to the player and gave game-critical information
but were not in themselves characters.
Lord Shaxx is an announcer in that vein,
but he also exists in the Destiny universe with a history
and has a personal stake in the players, in all of you.
Here's an example of what Shaxx sounds like in Destiny gameplay
from the Taken King expansion.
One final push and victory is yours. Triple down!
This is amazing! Outstanding!
You're unstoppable! Seventh column!
Another battle won. On to the next fight.
So as we just heard, Shaxs is a little bloodthirsty,
but he loves our players.
In the fictional world of Destiny,
Shaxs is a super-powered defender
of the last city of humanity,
who no longer fights on the front lines.
He's given up that role to train new guardians
of the city, who are the players.
Shaxs didn't start out this way, though,
and it took a bit of work to get him to where he is today.
Lord Shaxs' original execution in Destiny 1
was a dystopian drill sergeant,
and the team identified several problems with that
at the beginning of Taken King's development.
While Shaxs delivered game-critical information,
he was an announcer who lacked character.
Many of Shaxs' lines focused on repeating player objectives
that were already fairly obvious.
Capture and defend, Guardians!
Very little dialogue was dedicated to who Shaxx was in Destiny's universe,
and he had a limited relationship with the player
that sometimes boiled down to berating them for mistakes.
Fight back!
Control the zones!
Shaxx cared about players' successes, but not as much as he could,
and this was about as pleased as he got.
Nice work, Guardians. Your efforts have been noted.
I'm about to play another clip for you.
This is what the early version of what Shaxs sounded like in D1.
Listen carefully to the clip and compare it to the one
that we just heard.
Think about how often Shaxs speaks, and it won't be much.
want.
All enemies have been
eliminated. Last guardian
All enemies have been eliminated. Last guardien
All enemies have been eliminated. Last Guardian, revive your te
So for those unfamiliar, that was an example
of a pretty intense gameplay sequence in Destiny.
Our player was fighting one on three
and had to kill the entire opposing team multiple times
in order to win without dying themselves.
But notice that Shaxx lacked streak announcements.
He lacked general excitement for what was going on,
audible excitement being a big part of the earlier clip,
which was actually later in Destiny's development cycle.
This golf announcer tone during Destiny 1 made Shaxs unique from other shooter announcers,
but as a result, Shaxs did not share the player's excitement during the climax of their gameplay.
We took a new direction during the Taken King expansion by doing a couple of things.
On the design side, we added features like streak announcements that built up on each other as the player gained momentum.
We shifted our direction in writing as well.
Lenny James, Shaxs' voice actor,
is a Shakespearean-trained stage performer with supreme powers of projection.
So we gave Shaxs a more vibrant personality with more lines while keeping instances of
that dialogue still relatively short.
The end result was something like this in Taken King's Crucible.
Triple Town.
Their crest belongs to you now.
Their glory lies shattered.
You're in the lead.
No one shares the glory of that one guy.
FIGHT FOREVER, CARDIAC!
So as a result of these deliberate writing and design additions,
Shaxx took steps to becoming what the team refers to
as the supportive space dad that he is today.
I don't think you know how to give up.
Good recoveries.
On top of streaks and a more boisterous personality,
we had Shaxs actually reference his backstory
from Destiny's Grimoire cards.
Shaxs' dialogue changed to reflect
that he is a decorated war hero
who loved his job on the front lines
and gave all that up to train new guardians of the city,
like the player.
What I wouldn't give to fight again beyond the walls.
I would tear out a Vex heart with my teeth.
I would sear the Cabal with my burning light, challenge the Fallen Kells to personal combat
and scatter them.
I...
I've been watching too many Crucible matches.
Now, how much does this lore actually matter to the players?
I'd argue on its own, not much.
However, it gives us a background to anchor Shaxs with.
And it's something for the character to speak to
as a frame of reference to relate
to what the player is doing.
This is key as it's what allows us
to put the player on a pedestal
and make the Crucible all about them.
No matter what Shaxs starts off saying,
he'll always bring it back to our focus,
which is the players.
When I take the enemy vault, I look them in the eye,
and I tell them, this is mine now.
I see you do, too.
This new Shaxx worked out pretty well,
according to our audience.
There are a lot more Reddit threads about him
than pictured here.
Some players went so far as to claim
they engaged with PvP content in Destiny
simply to spend more time with Shaxx.
Two Reddit threads as a result of the team's work
stood out to me over the years.
The first was from a deaf player
who was disappointed that there were no captions
in the Taken King to capture Shaxx's dialogue for them.
And we finally got the tech to support it in Destiny 2.
This player was not disappointed.
Lenny James, Shax's voice actor, is phenomenal,
and he can turn a 50-cent line into a dollar.
But in this case, for this fan,
and apparently everyone in this thread,
the dialogue triggers and the writing for Shax
carried the experience.
This will be more important later.
The second thread was from a player suffering from multiple myeloma, a type of blood cancer.
He cites playing Destiny as an outlet that helps, and Shaxx Lines in particular as something
to help keep him motivated.
This meant a lot to me personally, because my mom passed away about six months before
I got my first job in the industry.
But what was my takeaway from all of this?
I realized that even without a traditional plot,
the team and I had succeeded in conveying a strong character
for Shaxs through his endless enthusiasm
for watching the players fight each other.
The player's story is at the center of every Shaxs line.
A vast majority of Shaxs's speech
is triggered by player actions.
And even when Shaxs is talking about himself,
it's in reference to the player.
As an example, players can choose between three classes in Destiny.
Titans are armored super soldiers, and when a Titan player goes on a streak,
Shaq says something like this.
With ten Titans like you, I could build all seven columns and shake the pillars to their core.
Hunters are Han Solo scoundrel types, and when a Hunter goes on a streak, Shaq sounds like this.
With ten hunters like you, I could make the frontier safe again.
And finally, warlocks are mystical scholar warriors.
When a warlock goes on a streak, Shaxx reacts like this.
With ten warlocks like you, I could turn ideas into weapons.
In each of these lines, Shaxx is acknowledging the player's class, a little bit of what that
class archetype is like in the fiction of Destiny, in other words, the player fantasy,
and is also reacting to what the player just did.
The end result is that it feels like Shaxx is watching you, constructing a narrative
out of your gameplay.
Over time, players feel like they know Shaxx as a character
because he seems like he knows them.
Plus, the sheer amount of time that Shaxx spends
speaking to a player in PvP can be greater
than the time it takes to clear Destiny's campaign missions.
So therefore, pursuing storylines in competitive modes
where the presence of players alone encourages engagement
can be very valuable.
To help support the story of Shaxx as a former frontline fighter turned coach,
he has a presence in the tower.
And the tower is Destiny's social hub where all players congregate to manage gear,
speak to NPCs to advance quests, and hang out with each other in a non-combat space.
Shaxx has a ton of ambient lines in this state where he gives gear and bounties to the player,
but practically none of these lines have anything to do with that gear and those bounties,
and instead serve to support the idea that Shaxx is still watching Crucible matches
when you're not in the arena. He's always happy to see you and he acknowledges you as a fellow veteran.
You're doing good work in the Crucible. The recruits need to see it.
When you've finished your business with him,
he's jealous that you get to go out and shoot guns,
and he doesn't.
I'd be right there with you if these rookies could just
learn to fight by themselves.
And as you walk off, you can hear
Shax continuing to train guardians in the Crucible.
You can't fight when you're that tense, guardian.
What's wrong with you?
Relax.
Relax more.
I said relax!
This serves as an outside context for Shaxs
when he's not announcing Crucible matches.
It furthers the smoke and mirrors
that Shaxs is alive when the player doesn't see him.
So to recap real quick,
Shaxs' announcer lines built on a character
to serve as a point of reference
in order to help tell the player's story in the Crucible.
The Iron Lords, six fronts,
the Twilight Gap where Lord Shaxs earned his name.
None fell more guardians than you.
We further support this experience by allowing the players to visit Shaxx in the Tower to
continue to build a relationship with him outside of the Crucible.
Both of these things, announcer and ambient dialogue together, encompass the Crucible
narrative experience.
Shaxx is a guy who's done what you've done.
He concedes that you do it better and he sings your praises, telling you your story to you
as you crush your enemies.
He's a window into the Destiny universe,
and he offers a way for you to make an impact
on that universe through his reactions.
I wanted you to win,
and you set the whole bloody world on fire.
Good.
Shaxs is your personal bard,
your advocate, and your hype man.
We felt so good about how we executed on Shaxs
that we repeated these narrative techniques
using a different character, the Drifter,
in a different mode called Gambit, to equal success.
Alright, alright, alright. Let's see what we've got.
Fallen on the horizon.
If Shaxs is a supportive coach, the Drifter is a shady uncle who encourages cutthroat behavior.
Red Legion, these lowlifes took the tower from you, right?
Make them bleed.
The Drifter ships the players around the galaxy
in a sci-fi Winnebago called the Derelict.
He drops them into war zones across the solar system
where they compete against other teams
to see who can kill the most stuff.
and bring back the most stuff, which Drifter will gladly pay them for.
The PvP twist is that players can enter into each other's warzones as invaders to kill each other,
naturally for more stuff. And it looks and sounds like this.
This is what the Taken feel, revel in this.
One down.
That's two.
Ten seconds left.
You make this look easy.
Drifter is an echo of Destiny 1's newest expansion, Forsaken,
which has the player questioning their morals
in an Old West-style story.
This necessitated a different dialogue style than Shaxx,
even though both characters are announcers.
Drifter is a grittier, less idealistic version of Shaxx,
but he shares the following qualities.
He never berates the player directly,
and he even encourages you when you lose, just like Shaxx.
Hey, not every hunt's a good hunt.
Doesn't have to be.
So count your loot and come see me again, huh?
Drifter has a backstory, just like Shaxx,
that informs everything that he says.
He's a person with a history and a reason for existing
and for wanting the player to succeed.
What a haul!
I promise you, I'll do something special
with all these moats.
Something that'll make you shiver.
We've talked before about how Shax's presence in the tower adds to the character's detail
and shows a side of him outside of the Crucible.
You can't fight when you're that tense, Guardian.
What's wrong with you?
Relax.
Relax more.
I said relax!
I just like that line.
We did one better for the Drifter, and we gave him a ship to haul the players around the galaxy in.
It allows him to give pep talks to both teams before a Gambit match begins,
and we use this to paint a portrait of the kind of person that the Drifter is
across the course of many matches.
All right Mavericks, ready to see what you're fighting today?
Fallen on the horizon
Six fronts Twilight
Fallen have bad
Hit them first. Yeah, I was at twilight. Yeah, my grandma too. Who was it? Shoot some fallen
It's time to bang knuckles.
The Fallen changed things for us.
Made Titans famous.
Go pay him back for it.
No one hated the Fallen more than Saint-14.
They say he's dead.
I don't buy it.
So to recap, though Shaxx and Drifter are vastly different,
both utilize similar narrative techniques
in order to tell the player's story in Crucible and in Gambit.
In the Crucible, players train to protect the last city
by fighting other guardians in combat drills.
In Gambit, players are airlifted into war zones
across the solar system to engage the enemies of humanity,
and the Drifter will pay them for the spoils.
So you've heard our thought process in writing for Shanks and the Drifter,
and why we think that it works to tell the player's story in competitive modes.
If your team is interested in telling the player's story in PvP,
consider these pillars in your writing.
The first pillar is consider a character for your competitive mode,
not an announcer and not a disembodied voice.
An announcer gives game critical data to the player and leaves it at that.
That's functional and it's fine,
but you're missing out on a powerful story channel.
A character has a relationship with the player that is grounded in the fiction of your universe.
You can convey this relationship in a couple of seconds of dialogue or less if you plan
carefully.
A character can facilitate both game-critical information like score and objectives while
being a real person.
Drifter, for instance, would not update you on score in the same way that Shaxx would.
Writers need to be intimately familiar with the game
and its gameplay mechanics in order for this to work.
You must write from the player experience
in order to be effective.
Don't use your dialogue here as an opportunity
to publish your own unique brand of Sumerian poetry
while the player fights for their life against other humans.
You are not publishing on paperback here.
You are making metaphors out of game mechanics
through snappy dialogue.
So understand those mechanics
and understand those timing constraints.
Meanwhile, designers need to understand the character that you are both striving for.
Designing the triggers for where a character speaks says something about that character.
It's just as important as what the character says.
Both roles are absolutely vital in this and the more in sync you are with each other,
the more coherent your character will be.
The second pillar is know your character and their role in the fiction.
Ask yourself, who the hell is this person?
Because the better you know them, the stronger your dialogue will be.
Know your character's relationship to the player.
This way, when you're writing dialogue, a character is speaking and not a game mode.
In game writing, there is a natural desire to simply use dialogue to restate what you already see
in order to explain something better or to give something more context.
This is especially true in competitive game modes
against other players, where there is more at stake
than simply role-playing.
You'll be tempted to only give game-critical information
in these modes because dialogue is expensive
and the window to deliver it tends to be small.
And that's fine.
The player needs to know what's going on.
But design and UI should strive to be as clear as possible
without dialogue because you are sacrificing
a potential story channel every time.
Hearing a character acknowledge an exciting play
that you just made can be just as important
as updating you on score or on an objective
because in competitive modes,
those exciting plays, those are the story.
I could feel that in my bones.
Did you hear that?
My soul just shivered.
Was that all of them?
That was all of them.
So here's an example of knowing who Shaxs' character is.
This is a picture of my father.
I have higher resolution photos, but he
didn't want those distributed.
When I wrote Taken King's Shaxs, I
looked back on who Shaxs was in Vanilla Destiny,
and I thought of him.
I thought of my father.
He would be deeply disappointed whenever I failed.
And rightly so.
Show me a better way to rear a child.
You can't.
But destiny isn't about child rearing,
so we figured our audience could use some compassion.
In writing Shaxs for The Taken King,
I instead thought about the 12-minute window
on some days when my father was pleased by something
that I did.
And I thought, what if Shaxs was like that, but all the time?
I wrote from this perspective on my first batch of Shaq's lines.
The result was that it became clearer that Shaq's was someone who had gone through what
the player had, respected them for it, while giving advice and acknowledging their successes.
Something like a father figure or a coach.
Our audience understood it pretty quickly.
The third pillar is write to your actor through iteration
and allow yourself multiple revisions,
if possible, before ship.
Don't let anyone tell you that it's just PVP dialogue.
Playing the game with the dialogue that you've recorded is vital.
Just because it's a competitive game mode without a plot
doesn't mean that the dialogue experience can't be improved.
Players will notice the dialogue of Destiny's competitive modes
gets a lot more attention today than it did before The Taken King.
And make sure to write to your actors.
As I mentioned before, the second take on Shaxs
took full advantage of Lenny James' projection
as a Shakespearean-trained stage actor.
Casting Todd Haberkorn for the role of the drifter
also changed that character from what we internally
had pictured as a deep-voiced McCree type
into more of a smoky Clint Eastwood who actually goes up
in pitch when he gets excited.
So pay attention to your actors.
Watch other stuff that they're in,
because they'll change your writing in a good way
if you use them well.
The fourth pillar, above all, appeal to the player.
Relate to the player, understand their experience.
Over time, we removed Shaxx lines
that were even remotely negative to players when they lost
because certain parts of our audience
did not appreciate being kicked while they were down.
On the other side of the spectrum,
one of the best ways to appeal to a player
is to speak to player actions.
Oh yes, the battle lines have been drawn.
Call the Praxic Order, call the Thanatonots, the Jinsin Scribes, call everyone so they can witness you!
Make sure to congratulate the player when they congratulate themselves.
You want your streak and climax lines to fire at the same time that the player leaps off of the couch in real life.
But you can only find these when your experience is solid.
Try to have a good idea of what your climax moments are from the player's perspective as you're writing.
Now here's an example of all of this coming together.
I apologize for the audio, it's a raw feed, it's going to pop a little bit.
Enemy captured zone A.
FIGHT FOREVER GUARDIAN!
F*** YEAH!
Dude, did you just hear that?
FIGHT FOREVER GUARDIAN!
You neutralized home's C.
F*** yeah!
F*** yeah.
Dude.
Did you hear that?
Chill.
Strong words.
And finally, above all, flatter the player.
Put them on a pedestal.
Flattery almost always works if it's genuine.
Oh my, this is, this is beautiful.
You continue to be my greatest success, guardian.
So in summary, one of the coolest things
about working on video games is getting
to make something out of nothing.
And we did that with Shaxs.
We created a character that people cared about
because he seemed to care about them.
Shaxs does not take part in a single in-game Destiny cut
scene.
Aside from one small cameo, he's not
in a single campaign mission across the lifespan
of Destiny's first five years.
And yet, people like him.
It's because Shaxs' plot is the player's action
in the Crucible.
It's a story that never ends if your players stay engaged.
Shaxs takes full advantage of video games
as an interactive medium.
The success of Shaxx in-game has led to things
like a Todd McFarlane action figure,
t-shirts, internet memes.
It's because our artists are awesome,
but Shaxx is pretty cool too.
Again, this is all despite the fact
that Shaxx has very little screen time
in the linear narrative of Destiny.
At the end of the day,
Lord Shaxx is just a series of dialogue lines
that listen for specific player actions before firing,
and it creates the illusion of a buddy
sitting next to you on the couch
who loses their shit at the same time that you do.
For your team, obviously, the flavor of your character
will change based on your game and your fiction.
But the intent should be the same.
Tell your story as player action.
As we've shown, it can be pretty gratifying.
Executed properly, this kind of dialogue,
deployed in competitive modes, can
be used to connect with your players on a visceral level.
I hope you try it.
Your players will thank you for it.
That's all.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Andrew Weldon, as I mentioned before, is here.
He is available to field design questions.
We'll be out in the hall after this.
If you guys are playing the Allegiance Quest in Destiny
right now, where we are asking you to choose your loyalty
between the Drifter and the Vanguard,
the lady who put that together, Mallory Schleife,
is right there, and she'll be outside, as well,
to field questions about that if you guys are interested.
Pierre Serret, who worked on Gambit as the primary designer,
is right there.
We'll all be outside.
We don't have time for questions.
Thank you very much for playing.