Well, my talk is the holy grail of multiplayer level design.
It's levels for competitive and casual play.
Briefly about me, my background comes from the Unreal
Tournament mod scene, especially Unreal Tournament 3,
where there was the kind of hardcore, old school,
low poly map pack.
And also, I am a level designer at Hi-Rez Studios,
where I do multiplayer level design, mostly on Paladins,
but a little bit on Spite and some other stuff.
So before I get too far into the talk,
some definitions, because I realize competitive
and casual are kind of loaded terms
when they're used in like blog circles.
And by competitive, I'm really talking about eSports,
I'm talking about tournament play.
And by casual, I'm basically talking about everything else.
I'm talking about recreation play.
But these definitions do get a little bit fuzzy
because I'm also talking about the motivations
of competitive play and the motivations of casual play.
So like you could be a very skilled e-sports professional
and choose to play, to goof around with friends,
to explore, to have many of the different
sort of casual motivations for play.
And likewise, you could be a new player
who's still learning the game and are playing to win
and playing to improve in a sort of competitive mindset.
And when I'm talking about the Holy Grail,
I'm talking about maps that really serve
both of these audiences, serve this huge range.
So with that in mind, we all wanna make
kind of the greatest multiplayer maps, right?
So what are the greatest multiplayer maps of all time?
And for some of you, what may come to mind is Facing Worlds
from Unreal Tournament 99.
This is a map that, for those who haven't played it,
it's capture the flag, it's these two bases out in space
on this asteroid, and you're frantically going across
this sort of narrow pathways, and there are sniper shots
going either way, and there's camera-guided rockets,
and it's just ridiculous and frantic.
Some of you may have thought of DM17 or Longest Yard from Quake 3 Arena. This map also happens to be in space.
It's very open, it has jump pads, it has portals, and it's also kind of dominated by the hitscan railgun,
which means that the only way to avoid that is using these movement mechanics on the map, and it's very fast.
Some of you may have thought of Blood Gulch from Halo.
I guess it's kind of in space,
but it's more of an organic landscape
and it's one of two maps in the original Halo multiplayer
that had vehicles in it, or for multiplayer at least.
So some properties of these greatest of all time maps.
One is that they have these big open environments
that makes them pretty easy to learn,
pretty easy to navigate.
They also have pretty iconic themes,
or really recognizable themes.
There are bases, there are sides to it,
or it's in space.
And they also generally offer sandboxes of play.
These maps have different mechanics
that you don't get from other maps,
like with Facing Worlds you have the Redeemer rocket,
and with the Halo map you have the vehicles.
But I also mean sandbox of play
as these maps are really good foundations
for custom games and for mods.
Like probably if you played Facing Worlds
you did slow-mo with...
really dumb AI and insta-gib rifles and all sorts of nonsense.
These maps also kind of create their conflict through their simplicity. These are maps that
on facing worlds, if you're running to the other side and another player is running to
get to your side, you're going to run into each other. It's a pretty simple map.
But somehow through all these properties, these maps aren't really played competitively.
Like they are played at LANs, but they aren't played in tournaments. They aren't played for cash money.
So what maps are their sort of competitive counterparts?
For Unreal Tournament, it's maps like DM Malevolence.
This is a sort of dense interior space
with sort of three arena format
where each of these arenas has power weapons
and power items that you want to control.
And really, it's a lot more complex
and there's a lot more strategy to moving around this map.
For Quake, it's maps like Lost World
or Arrow Walk or Blood Run.
These maps also have that kind of dense interconnectivity
and these a lot more complicated pathing.
For Halo, it was maps like Chill Out and Damnation,
which are also this kind of three arena structure,
very dense.
This one has portals, which is a main source
of its complexity, and about controlling items.
So if you think of these properties again,
they're complex, the themes kind of stay out of the way
and can even be disorienting with their simplicity.
And it's a focus on core mechanics.
You don't see the nuclear rockets,
you don't see vehicles on these maps.
And instead of the conflict through simplicity,
it's about item control.
It's about moving around the map for power weapons.
And that means if you're playing these maps
for the first time in sort of a one-v-one
with another new player,
you might run circles and never see each other.
And as a result, some of these maps aren't played casually,
or they aren't the maps you play
when you're first learning these games.
So what's going on here?
Because none of these maps are bad.
And in fact, all these maps are awesome at what they do.
One way of thinking about this is kind of an overlap of audiences.
And this model here is from David Serlin in 2009, talking about fighting games,
where he argued that for a fighting game to be successful,
you need to have that strong, hardcore, competitive scene
and really cater the design around that.
And then the casual audience will kind of follow and congeal around that.
And if you fail to serve that competitive audience,
then the whole thing kind of dissipates,
and it won't be a very long-lived game.
We also see this with MOBAs, where
by really serving that competitive audience
and creating kind of the virtuous cycle of e-sports
viewership, ranked gameplay, we can get players engaged
and retained for a really long time.
But this isn't something that's true of all games.
Like if we think of platformers, if we think of speed running
as kind of the hardcore competitive equivalent,
That's kind of an outlier, right?
Like that's not the more extreme version.
It's almost a completely separate game.
And if we as designers are trying to create a game
that really serves the maximum of these audiences,
and we do that with platformers,
we're gonna end up in this really weird niche
that doesn't really serve anybody.
So that's something to keep in mind.
Also this isn't just first person shooters,
although that's what all my examples are from.
We see this with action RPGs, we see this with MMOs
where there's a difference between the hardcore players
and with new players.
We also see it in the real world with, for example,
this is from paintballs.
The example on the right here is a speedball
variant of paintball where you have two teams of five
and each player fills a role.
And it's very...
very competitive structure.
It's symmetrical and it's balanced.
You're playing to win.
And on the left is scenario paintball,
where these players are reenacting historical battle.
And because it's a historical battle,
you know who's going to win and who's going to lose, right?
Like these players aren't playing to win.
They're playing for very different motivations.
Another way of thinking about this,
that's kind of the way that casual and competitive
and casual and hardcore gets thrown around
is often in terms of, oh, those filthy casuals,
those low-skill players.
And it's actually a lot more complex than that
because, at least for first-person shooters
and with most games, there are these.
kind of games within a game, and it's layers of skills
that players are developing.
And for us, it's the first layer is mechanics,
where it's just moving and shooting
and being able to navigate a 3D space
and being able to even use a controller and a mouse.
And that's tens or even hundreds of hours of gameplay
there that sometimes we undersell as designers.
And once you have basic competence in that, which again,
is maybe tens of hours.
Then you can start learning map specific
and game specific knowledge and tactics
and how to use items and how to move around the map
and what angles you need to control.
And then from there, once you have competence,
and again, that's another huge arc of mastery,
then you can start worrying about
sort of tournament level strategy,
which is the meta game, character picks,
bands, maps, that sort of stuff.
And all while doing this, you're developing
some parallel skills that are your ability
to communicate with your other players,
your ability to handle the psychological pressure
of competition, your ability to not tilt in competition.
But the key thing here is that as designers,
sometimes we have a bias towards
sort of the tactical strategy side of things,
and there's a huge amount of gameplay we can serve
just by focusing on mechanics.
Another way of thinking about this briefly
is in terms of psychological models
and traditional psychology.
The one that I found most useful for thinking about this
is self-determination theory,
which basically argues that there are,
you can categorize intrinsic human satisfaction
into competence, autonomy, and relatedness,
which in game design terms is kind of like thinking
mastery, choice, and teamwork.
You can also think of relatedness
as kind of relative competence or relative autonomy.
And the important thing here is that this doesn't line up one to one with some idea of casual and
competitive and that's kind of deflating the more mainstream filthy casual use of casual.
But still taking all those different ways
of viewing this problem in mind,
what are some ways that we can support casual play?
One is with sort of rebound and chaos mechanics.
So the Blue Shell and Mario Kart
is a really good example of this
because it's an opportunity for a new
or lower skilled player to catch up
and subvert the experience of a better
or more experienced player.
But with first person shooters,
we can also do this with random weapon starts,
random weapon timing, objectives that are random.
We also wanna make sure that the maps are easy to learn.
So this example here is kind of a rough,
abstract diagram of Chill Out,
which I brought up earlier.
And the green dashed lines are the portal routes.
So even though it's a very simple layout
that's not too hard to understand,
those portal routes make it very confusing
for new players and can be very disorienting.
We also want to put a ceiling on tactics and strategy.
And this is what Facing Worlds and DM17 do really well.
Through the simplicity of their layout,
there's not really room for tactical play,
or at least not at the same degree
that we see in tournaments.
But sort of in conflict with this,
or something that we have to balance with this,
is offering up a sandbox for players.
Because not everybody's going to care about the same things.
Not everybody's going to learn the different mechanics
at the same pace.
So Halo does a really good job of this with their vehicles,
because some people like driving more
than they like running and gunning.
And some people hate driving,
and they don't have to use those tools
if they don't want to.
It's a really good way of exploring different play styles.
And it's something that the Battlefield games
have done an excellent job of serving.
On sort of the more technical level designing side of things, we want single scan arenas.
Basically what I mean by this is zero scan is kind of like walking into a closet that's
small enough that your field of view encompasses everything and all the information is known
as you walk through it.
A single scan is a little bit like walking into a room where you have a blind spot on
one side.
And in order to see the whole room, you have to scan and...
reveal that information.
A multi-scan room, if you think of that sort of shaded
square in the middle as a pillar, you have to keep moving
and keep looking in order to maintain information.
So we want to keep things simple,
we want to keep it single scan.
That's basically how Facing Worlds and DM17
and Blood Gulch operate.
So some ways to support competitive play.
Kind of in contrast, we want multiple options.
We want complex options.
And even what I've drawn here is pretty simple.
But like the examples to the right of that are,
they look a whole lot like facing worlds actually.
And that doesn't generally lead to a lot of
tactical variety for players
and can turn the competitive game stale.
We also want to make sure these options are resilient.
And basically, when you get into some state,
you can recover from it.
And that means you don't want to be spawn camp
for a whole match.
But it also means, like in MOBAs,
you don't want to fall behind on the farm
and never be able to recover.
And this is really with e-sports in mind,
because we want dramatic games.
We want stories.
And one mistake early on is, if that means the whole game,
that's not very exciting to watch.
We also want those multi-scan arenas.
Again, this is kind of the foundation
for a lot of that tactical play.
If multiplayer maps were just the single scan arenas
and were all very simple spaces,
then it would just be about who has the better
mechanical aim, who can hit their target most reliably.
So, what about the Holy Grail maps?
What about these maps that do both of these things?
You probably noticed that there are a couple of maps
that I haven't mentioned, and maybe to some of you
that seems really weird.
So Dust 2, for example, is a map that,
yep, Dust 2 is a map that does both of these things
very well and serves both a competitive
and casual audience, and that's partly because
it has just the right amount of complexity
that you can form different tactical options,
but it's also very clean geometry.
It's 90 degree angles.
It's very open, clean spaces.
There are a couple curves in the map,
but for the most part it's on 90 degree angles.
For Halo there are maps like Lockout,
which it's a very dense space, it's multi-tiered space,
there's a lot of verticality to it,
but it's also these kind of additive structures
floating in space that are connected by bridges,
which makes it much easier to understand
where you are relative to other structures,
and very easy to navigate.
It also has the added bonus of exploding barrels,
and like this jump pad elevator thing,
so like.
How can you not have fun with that?
For Quake, it's maps like Campground,
and there are a couple others,
but Campgrounds is the one that.
really fits this the best.
And it still follows sort of the competitive format
where it's this three arena structure
and these hallways interconnecting them
in sort of dense ways, but doesn't rely on portals,
it's not overly vertical, which makes it pretty easy
to understand each of these spaces and how they connect
and lets you navigate the level pretty quickly.
It's not hard for a new player to pick that map up.
So some properties, there's kind of an intermediate
complexity to these maps.
They're readability focused environment art,
they aren't really aiming for some really strong thematic.
But aside from that, it's kind of like,
there's not a lot of overlap.
These maps are all kind of specific solutions
to each of their game's designs.
We can't take Dust 2 and put it in...
and halo and expect it to work.
We can't put lockout and counter strike
and expect that to work.
These maps are specific solutions,
which is, if we're trying to make maps like this,
then what can we take from this?
And also, some of you are probably wondering
why I call them holy grails.
To my knowledge, this is just kind of the term
I personally use for it.
And part of it is this idea that the Holy Grail grants
eternal youth, that it's, in terms of multiplayer games,
you don't need a lot of these really good maps
in order to keep your game alive.
Like there are still 24-7 Dust 2 servers.
That's incredible.
And, you know, especially with increased fidelity
expectations and the cost of delivering that fidelity,
being able to create a couple of really good maps
rather than 50 okay maps or 50 specific audience maps,
that's...
really good if you can do that.
But I also call them this
because the holy grail isn't real.
And like my example with platforming and speed running,
you may end up kind of serving a niche
or running into some problems with that.
So another way of thinking of that
is kind of the ultimate vanilla.
Basically it's a flavor that doesn't offend anybody.
And everybody can bring their own personal flavors
to vanilla and it still works with vanilla.
You can have peanut butter vanilla,
you can have sour gummy vanilla and it still, yeah.
So, some cautions around pursuing a Holy Grail map.
So now I'm gonna talk about paladins
and sort of my quest for a Holy Grail map.
So this is Paladins.
We are a team-based first-person shooter.
We have two teams of five.
Each player is choosing a unique champion
with their own abilities.
And each character also has a whole bunch of customization
that happens in this kind of out-of-match loop.
We also have objectives.
There are capture points, and there are payloads
you're pushing.
And we're also following the sort of free-to-play
games-as-a-service model.
So we're constantly trying to update and make it better.
And it's not like we've.
shipped it and we're done and we'll do better next time.
It's like no, we're still trying to find ways
to make it as good as we can.
So some history, just for context for what I'm going to cover.
Paladins really started as more of a MOBA
with a first person perspective,
and then moved into more of the class-based
first person shooter it is now.
And part of that is there were a lot of perception problems
when the game went to closed beta
as this kind of MOBA with first person perspective
where.
There is...
just genre conventions around first person shooters
that weren't quite being met.
And part of that is that we moved from a high time to kill
to a medium time to kill.
We basically had a time to kill around 15 seconds,
which is insane, and moved to somewhere
between like three and 10, depending on what characters.
I forgot to mention, but we also have classes.
We have like healers and tanks and DPS
and flanking characters.
So like the 10 seconds is like two tanks brawling
versus the three seconds is two flanks having a duel.
We also, through the process of closed beta, went from this sort of chaotic, unpredictable
gameplay to something a lot more deterministic.
This was really in service of our competitive scene and there was a whole lot of what just
happened to me moments in our playtesting that we were trying to resolve.
And basically with all these design changes,
for level design we were trying to
sort of keep up with the game design.
And I meant going from these sprawling MOBA inspired maps
to a lot more traditional, tight, FPS style maps.
So basically we went from maps that look kinda like that,
and this is from the summer of 2016,
this is after we shrunk the map down multiple times.
And this is also a view of the map
that's only showing about a third of it.
And we went to maps like this,
which is much more recognizable
as a first-person shooter style level.
For perspective, that's about the size difference.
That's Enchanted Forest on the left.
That's kind of the old style map.
And again, that's after we shrunk it down multiple times.
And that's our kind of current approach
to level design on the right.
So through this process of taking those mobile maps and shrinking them down and
taking and making new maps in that style, we developed a set of principles.
One thing is that we want strategic variety.
We want to make sure that every time you're going after an objective or
doing any kind of play on the map, you have multiple options open to you.
We also wanted to keep the maps pretty simple.
And this is mostly speaking to our characters' abilities.
We have larger than life dodge rolls and AOEs
that can fill the capture points.
We want to make sure that players aren't tripping up
over little bits of geometry that don't matter
for our kind of gameplay.
We also want to center on the core mechanics.
We found with some of the maps that they ended up
being kind of sniper dominant,
and our players didn't respond very well to that,
or at least our competitive scene didn't.
So we kept it focused on that sort of healer tank DPS
holy trinity.
And we also want to limit zoning and allow recovery.
This is going back to that idea of resilience
and our sort of competitive principles.
And specifically with these older maps,
the most dangerous locations was the route
to get to the objective.
Because the way those maps were designed
and just the constraints around that kind of design
is that whoever won the first fight for an objective
could then push forward and zone
and prevent the other team from even being able to contest.
And that was the optimal strategy
and you'd see it in competitive play
and it was just, oh, it was rough.
Another principle that we have,
this is a little bit more on the environment art side,
is that we wanna make sure that what you see
is what you get.
We have characters that can fly,
and we wanna make sure that as you're going over rooftops,
you aren't hitting invisible walls.
And that really defines a lot of
kind of the level design problems we run into.
If we rephrase this sort of thinking in terms of our
casual and competitive and holy grail divide,
most of these things were in service
of our competitive players.
Like even the idea of simplicity,
sure that helps casual players,
that helps that motivation,
but a lot of it is still like just the nature of the game.
So some results of these iterations.
As a team of level designers, we felt a lot better
about our maps.
They were a lot easier to make, they were more fun to make,
and they were a lot more fun to playtest.
And our metrics were up, we had better retention
and engagement from our closed beta feedback.
And we had a much healthier competitive scene
where it was actually engaging and exciting
to watch our players compete
because there were multiple strategies available to them
and it was exciting.
But in terms of subjective, sort of anecdotal player
feedback, it was a little bit more lukewarm
than we had hoped.
So basically what we thought we did was something like this.
We thought we had that kind of MOBA or fighting game
situation where if we served our competitive audience,
we'd be set.
And we could just keep making the best competitive maps
we could and we'd just keep doing that forever
and the game would be awesome.
But I think what we actually realized we have
is a bit more like this where our competitive scene
is kind of an outlier to what
a lot of the more casual audience wants from the game.
And with our change to these maps,
we ended up missing the mark a little bit
and losing some of that audience.
Or at least we still have players on our forum saying,
I kind of want those old maps back.
Which to us as designers is like, oh no.
So what some of those players want is really more variety.
They want bigger maps, they want asymmetry,
which is another way of getting variety,
and they want the stronger themes.
One of the best things about those old maps
is that you're besieging an enemy fortress
with a big siege engine thing,
and it's like the theme of it is really rich,
and that's something that we've kind of moved away from.
So a way for us to try and understand basically this casual competitive divide better is with
public test queue. This was a queue that we set up for this last year. We only recently shut
it off, but it was running for basically a whole year of public gray box maps. And if you're a
player who was at level 14, I think it was,
You could play test these maps and after each match
you'd get a feedback form saying,
what'd you think of the map?
And sometimes we had other specific questions
we were asking as well.
But the main idea is that we wanted to
better understand our audience,
better understand kind of that Venn diagram.
And we also wanted to test specific experiments,
which I'll go over in a minute.
We also wanted to reduce the risk of creating
sort of lukewarm maps or these sort of false grails.
So this is Sand Bridge, this is a test queue map obviously.
This is a map which I designed specifically
to challenge some of the design principles
that we had set up over this course of iteration.
I created these really elaborate flank routes
and these really dominant sniper towers
and there are portals in the map
and I thought players would hate it.
But.
It was actually one of our highest rated maps
in the test queue at the time.
But also we had competitive players coming to us
and saying this is why I don't play the test queue,
this is terrible.
And that just kind of highlighted this divide
that we'd started to realize.
So the map I made after that in trying to,
in trying to understand this better was Sewer,
which, hint, hint, if you call your map Sewer,
Yeah, so I designed this map specifically
for healers and tanks, and I want to really
boil it down into that calculus of just healer tank math
and really limit the options for flying characters.
This is kind of no-clipped into the wall,
so it makes it look like it's open space,
but it's actually all enclosed,
so you can't really fly anywhere,
you can't really flank that much,
and yeah, on average players didn't like it so much.
And this is Corey, this is after we went through
the sort of gray box pass.
This is the final art as we released it.
And with this one I wasn't really testing
any specific experiments.
I wasn't running any wild ideas.
This was just me trying to make the best map I could
and use the test queue as kind of a vetting process
to make sure we weren't releasing a lukewarm map.
And while it was popular in the test queue,
once we actually released it with the final art,
we found that it was a little bit lukewarm.
Like we did get some weird feedback
that we hadn't expected.
Players were confused and disoriented.
They felt claustrophobic.
And partly that's speaking to most players' inability
to evaluate gray box maps.
it's also speaking to that divide in our audience
and that we can't do competitive and casual both.
So if that's the case, what's next?
For us, with this realization that our casual
and competitive scenes don't totally overlap
and we can't just make awesome competitive maps forever.
We've created new game modes,
and we have a team deathmatch mode,
and we have sort of an onslaught,
king of the hills style mode.
And these are opportunities for us to create maps
that are really in service to casual audiences.
We can do a lot more map dynamics,
we can have asymmetry,
we can do all sorts of wild, crazy things,
and our competitive players won't care
because it's not for them.
It's awesome.
But, of course, we're still moving forward with that
to try and figure out how to best answer that question.
So, kind of the main takeaway from all of this,
through this process, the main thing that I learned
was this kind of audience check.
So, basically, every time I am designing something new,
I ask myself this series of questions.
Who all are we designing this for?
What are their needs?
And again, think back to the self-determination theory,
competence, autonomy, relatedness,
what are we really offering up
with this map or this game mode?
And how does our design serve those needs?
And because these questions are kind of hard to answer,
there's kind of the follow-up question of
what steps can we do to answer these questions?
And that's really what we did with the test queue.
So basically I want to rephrase the idea of
us all wanting to create the greatest map of all time
or a map that belongs in the ranks of facing worlds
and instead think of it as designing maps
to serve our audience.
That's my talk.