Yeah, welcome to Ghost in the Empathy Machine, exploring the player-character connection
in Life is Strange, True Colors.
I'm Jon Zimmerman, the narrative director at Deck Nine Games.
Thank you so much for coming to our talk.
Especially considering that Wyrtle is happening next door.
It's pretty cool.
I would be there right now.
I'm Zach Garris, formerly the Chief Creative Officer at Deck9 and Creative Director of
True Colors and currently the VP of Story at Telltale Games.
So to kick things off, we have 30 minutes, let's do a brief history of narrative.
Three thousand years ago, storytelling consisted of basically one thing.
was people hanging out around a fire and a poet singing about stuff that happened that
was inspiring or compelling, like Achilles' Rage and the Homeric origin.
2,500 years ago, poets realized they could start pretending to be Achilles, and story
became something that was performed.
Yeah, there we go.
And the audience went from hearing someone tell them
about a narrative experience to watching a narrative experience
unfold and seeing the drama and the comedy on the faces
and the body language and the vocal tones of the actors.
500 years ago, we invented the printing press,
which led to the novel.
And now audience members could experience the interior spaces of Achilles or any other
character and they could imagine what was going on inside the hearts and minds of the
characters.
A little over a century ago, motion pictures.
Now we can physically put the audience on the battlefield next to Achilles or other
things.
Few decades ago, video games.
And now digital media is something that the audience can directly interact with,
leading us to games like Life is Strange.
So when we're looking at this arc of storytelling's history, we just want to
call out the movement of the arc is one toward interiority.
It's toward empathy.
The audience has gone from hearing someone talk about a story, to watching people perform a story,
to imagining the story from the inside, to physically seeing the inside,
to now, through agency, participating in the story themselves.
Yeah, great. So as Zach just laid out, all of narrative history and really human history
has led us to video games. So let's talk about what makes video game narratives distinct.
It starts with the controller. Video game narratives are about control. We control a
character usually, and we call that the player character. The player character is given tools
where they are able to act upon the world. We sometimes call these verbs or interacts.
And the world is usually filled with non-playable characters,
or NPCs, for the player character
to interact with or against.
One of the most crucial decisions
we make as game writers is the question of prescription.
How prescribed versus how open is the player character
experience?
So let's look at a spectrum.
On one end, you have Player Avatar from Stardew Valley.
He or she can be molded out of 24 skin tones, 73 hairstyles,
hundreds of combinations of clothing, whatever name you
wish, and of course, dog or cat preference.
And on the other end of the spectrum, you have Kratos.
Kratos is not an avatar.
Kratos is Kratos.
You do not customize Kratos.
You do not make choices for Kratos.
Kratos' verbs are move, jump, and smash.
So getting a little more nuanced,
here is a character like Max Caulfield
from the original Life is Strange.
Max is obviously a character, she's not an avatar. But as a character, she is designed
to be open for how the player wishes to interact with the story. She begins the game shy and
passive. Her relationships are mostly blank slates, giving us a lot of agency to craft them.
And her core objectives align perfectly with the players.
She is seeking to understand the world
and the people around her as we are.
She's confused about her power
and wants to learn more, just like us.
And she's undecided about many things,
including her romantic entanglements,
giving us a lot of space
to get to make those choices for her.
Now let's compare that to Chloe
in Life is Strange Before the Storm, the game we made.
Chloe is far more toward the Kratos end of the spectrum than Max is, and this makes sense
because Chloe began her life as an NPC in the original game.
She wasn't created with player control in mind.
Instead, Chloe is really bold and really aggressive and often angry about one thing or another.
Not as angry as Kratos, but still angry.
She's opinionated about the people in her life and her backstory, the trauma she
suffered from her father's death is critical to who she is.
She's decidedly not a blank slate.
So despite sharing a franchise, the experiences of being Max and Chloe are
by necessity very different.
And this was something that we only really came to appreciate as we
were making Before the Storm.
At a certain point in the scripting process.
we really faced a choice of whether to soften Chloe's personality and try to turn her into more
of an open player character, or retain all of her personality, those wonderful rough edges,
and try to find other avenues for bringing the player into the story.
And you can see which one we chose.
So it turned out in the end that having a prescribed player character actually wasn't a hindrance.
It was a massive gift.
Because if we could get the player into the headspace of this very singular character,
we will have achieved, here it comes, empathy.
So how did we do this?
Let's talk about the building blocks.
Not having a power, like Max's rewind ability in the first game, our tools were very, very basic.
We would explore, interact, express ourselves, and make decisions.
So, explore, that's simply pathing around the spaces that Chloe lives in, the spaces that are important to her,
interacting with the objects that reflect her personality,
and being rewarded with her thoughts, and sometimes opportunities for action.
Expressing herself through dialogue,
through dialogue choices,
and through opportunities for play.
And then making decisions, sometimes big decisions,
about her personality, about her morality,
about the people she cares about.
Everything the player did in Before the Storm
was filtered through Chloe.
It's why the most important relationship in the game,
we realized, wasn't between Chloe and Rachel
or anyone else in the story.
It was between the player and Chloe.
That was the relationship we came to care about the most.
With every interaction that we built,
we strove to build out Chloe's interiority.
That's the thing that we focused on.
And hopefully as we did that,
we were bringing the character along with her
into her headspace, cementing that empathic link
we were trying to build.
It's one thing to do that when it comes to elements of the story, like rebelling
against your mother's dickish boyfriend or falling for Rachel Amber, hopefully
most players are going to be ready to go along for that ride.
Uh, but it's more challenging when it comes to a deeper and
more complex emotion like grief.
So that's the, the, the foundational, uh, mechanical link between the player.
and the player character in Narrative Adventure,
but we want to focus on something we discovered
in Before the Storm, something that ultimately led
to why we made True Colors at all.
And that's a scene we call Junkyard Smash.
So this is the end of the first episode.
It's building suspense.
Chloe just spent the day
with the most popular girl in school.
Chloe is 16, her father recently died.
She is filled with anger, she is alienated, she's hurt,
and she just had this magical experience
for someone.
opposite to her in every way, took an interest in her life.
And then they arrive at this junkyard, and inexplicably that person turns on her, hurts
her and abandons her.
And we enter the free-roam space where the player now is on the sticks and has control,
with the goal stated to them, fuck this place.
We replace traditional verbs that allow for choice in terms of how you want to interact with the world
with the loud interior voice of Chloe's need to smash things.
And she really does.
In fact, she begins to project the people in her life that have hurt her the most
on the junk that she finds, and she smashes all of it.
A mannequin for Rachel.
A camera for Max.
It's hard to see, but that's a toolbox for David.
And then something magical happens.
Up to this point, the relationship between the player and Chloe is one of spectator and angry girl.
Very few players are feeling the rage she's feeling.
In fact, the playfulness of the verbs themselves frame a kind of entertainment from watching her be angry.
And then she finds her father's car.
And we just found this working on the story,
trying to come up with what would be
the most compelling narrative movement to the scene.
And that relationship between the player and Chloe
in this moment shifts from spectator and subject
to a real alignment.
If people cried in Before the Storm,
they almost certainly cried in this scene.
We take minutes with it.
We frame it cinematically with the score.
We show Chloe taking in the car and reeling from it and players
slide right into that spot.
And then we gave them another smash and we ask you to pull the trigger.
And it destroys Chloe.
And when we discovered this, it really surprised us.
And we realized that there's a power
to interactive storytelling in terms of its ability
to engender empathy that we didn't really understand.
Most of the fan letters we get are from people
who demographically don't have a lot in common with Chloe.
Some of my favorites are from people
who are 50 years old or older.
men who say their relationship with their father was improved or something they had closure from
because of experiencing Chloe's journey. That humbled us and blew us away and so
ultimately led us to wanting to make a game about empathy.
Yeah, so we were
fascinated by those letters we received, the reactions we received, by this extension of
empathy to all different kinds of people into, as we laid out, this really singular character
of Chloe, right? Not being an avatar, not being someone that you craft,
but someone that you role-play and you inhabit.
So when it came time to concept the next game, Life is Strange, True Colors, we
started with a set of questions and interests that we carried over from
before the storm, like what would it be like to experience that kind of empathic
connection in the real world, outside of games?
How would it shape you as a person?
And what would a power based on empathy allow us to do as storytellers?
So fast forwarding over many, many months of iteration, here's what we landed on.
As before, we start with a player character.
This time she's named Alex,
and the player is going to control her the entire game
to interact with the world.
We get to explore as her, hear her thoughts, make choices,
but now we wanted to extend
that player character experience outward.
So we came up with this empathy power for Alex
that functioned like a prism,
projecting us through her into the interior spaces
of the NPCs in the world around her.
It starts with auras, showing us that an NPC is feeling an emotion,
and when we use our empathy power, we're rewarded with the NPC's thoughts
in their voice about the emotion that they're feeling.
And we actually discovered something really interesting
while we were writing these NPC insights.
Players enjoyed hearing them,
but with all the different voices coming into their head,
they would begin to feel lost and disconnected from Alex.
And we solved this in a really simple, but we think really interesting way,
which was capping every NPC insight with a short follow-up thought from Alex.
Sometimes it was just a couple words, but it would reflect or react in some way
to whatever emotion she just connected with.
And it was a really small shift, but it had the effect of realigning the player to Alex.
It brought them back into her as the player character after they'd taken that journey
into a different consciousness together.
They were side-by-side again, experiencing that emotion together rather than separately.
So let's look at how that relationship functioned in one of the bigger power moments, which we call NOVAs.
In this scene, Alex has asked Eleanor for help finding Mac.
And at one point, Eleanor seems to become confused, disoriented,
and she starts eliciting a surprisingly strong emotion of fear.
So we use our empathy power to connect with that fear.
And when we do, her aura suddenly explodes outward.
It literally colors the world around her.
And here's what that looks like when that happens.
She looks terrified.
I can't leave her like this.
Holy shit.
So the only part we missed at the end there was seeing that fear aura completely project
outward, seeing it surround the space.
And then we go back into a free room and we're exploring the space again, right?
So that's what gives us the entree into exploring Eleanor's emotion.
We're now going to path around and Alex and the player are going to be side by side exploring
Eleanor's fear together.
So we're going to interact with objects.
that are connected to it, we're gonna hear insights,
and ultimately, we're gonna be inside Eleanor's thoughts
and we're gonna fill out an understanding of that fear,
of that emotion of hers.
Now, once we've explored Eleanor's emotion,
we come away understanding the cause of it,
that she's suffering from dementia
and she feels her grasp on reality slipping away.
And hopefully what we were really going for, the crux of all of the sound design,
the cinematics that you saw, was to try and engender some of that feeling that we
captured with Chloe in the junkyard of not just being the spectator, but
participating in the emotional experience.
Except now it's not just our player characters, right?
It's Eleanor's.
We are through Alex sharing in a different character's emotional experience.
We're projecting our empathy outward.
So now that we've been armed with this connection and this empathy for what Eleanor is going through,
we're set up to make a difficult choice on Eleanor's behalf. Alex realizes that Eleanor
has forgotten her brother's death and is unaware of his funeral that evening.
Do we remind her, even having felt how much pain that's going to cause her?
So all the fundamental tools from before the storm were all there in that experience.
They're just projected outward.
We explore another's world.
We interact with the objects important to them.
We express through another's voice and we make moral decisions that impact them.
We really loved using this power to explore
the empathic connections that games can build.
We loved getting to create power moments
like the Eleanor power moment and explore something
that we would never get to do if we were tied
to just one player character experience.
And when we brought empathy from the meta in Before the Storm to the plot in True Colors,
we came to understand it far better and explore it far deeper than we did before.
The more we explored it and the more we read, we discovered something else about empathy
that really surprised us.
Empathy is complicated.
Who knew that?
Also, just side note, thanks for bearing with us with the tech.
I know it keeps cutting out.
It's GameDevs. I think we're 99% of the time we spend with tech is broken.
So maybe it feels familiar.
Did you plan it that way?
It's not, it's not intentional.
Okay. Yeah, empathy is complicated.
We read a lot.
Organizational psychology, behavioral psychology, social science,
spiritualists, gurus.
Empathy is a bit of a buzzword lately too.
It's a positive. It's a net good.
It's a virtue.
I think often when people talk about the positive elements of empathy, what they're really talking
about is compassion.
Empathy is when someone else's emotional state overrides yours.
When your best friend is mad at you and they say something dumb or a place of anger, what's
the best way to react to that?
It's probably not to immediately be as angry as they are.
It's equally wrong not to pay attention to what's making them angry.
But that's the complication.
That's the thing that really became interesting to us.
So as often happens with story development,
the thematic and conceptual exploration
ultimately came full circle and influenced the plot.
And the entirety of the fifth episode
of True Colors is about this.
So when we end four, Alex gets shot in the head
and thrown down a mine.
She wakes up and she has to, in a very surreal series of exchanges,
perform the empathy power on herself,
and go through constellation points in her life that have wounded her the most,
and that have coded her to be the person she is.
Sadness over her mother's death.
It's the first time we're going to see Alex shooting a Nova out of her own.
the terror when their father abandoned her brother and her.
One of the harder moments in the game,
Alex has to sit in a version of the orphanage
she grew up in and watch as
potentially adopting parents would approach
and she would feel all the reasons they didn't pick her.
And she's sensitive.
I'm sure she's a sweet girl, she hears, but she's not for us.
It's the kid who's been in all those fights, right?
There's just something off, wrong with her.
And we watch Alex explode in anger.
I think it's my favorite shot in the game.
It's really cool.
Why do we do that?
It's because she needs to face the lies she's told herself
because of the wounds she suffered.
She needs to actually practice a kind of self-empathy.
And from that place, she finds peace.
She finds what we discovered in research
is known as emotional self-integrity.
She's contended with her demons,
which puts her in a place where she's actually ready
to deal with other people's.
And that's what the game became about.
It's not to say empathy is bad, empathy is wonderful.
It's an extraordinary thing.
But like most powerful things,
there is risk associated with it.
So what does this mean for narrative adventure
or empathy in storytelling?
MLK says the arc of the universe bends toward justice.
I think the narrative arc of story over the last few thousand years bends toward empathy
in a certain way.
We're striving to get closer to each other.
Why do we love stories so much anyway?
What is it that they provide?
I think they build maps.
It's not my idea, but...
A lot of writers think this.
They're maps.
They show us the way to go.
They show us how to find peace in our lives.
That's how a 50-year-old man can play Chloe
and come away from that experience
enriched in his relationship with his dad.
So John, as he often does and has done for years,
challenged me last night.
He said the best talks he's seen at GDC
conclude with some kind of call to action.
And he asked like, what's our call to action?
We didn't have one.
We were just making a presentation about empathy
and I thought a lot about it.
And I don't think it was until right before this talk
that I realized what I wanted to kind of end on.
And I, pardon me for how dark this may sound,
especially when the Wordle presentation
is applauding right now.
Something I think a lot about as an entertainer
and as a game designer is the state of our kids.
I think our kids are in a certain kind of crisis.
More than any other generation in history,
they are involved with tech.
They deal with interactive media every day
and more hours a day than we did when we were young.
And anxiety, depression, suicidal ideation,
and loneliness, loneliness are at all time highs.
And I'm not a doctor, few game devs are, and I don't know the answer to this, but
surely a part of it has to be that the places we build as devs, it's what we do.
We're builders.
The digital places we build are places that strengthen.
There are places that teach emotional self-integrity.
And from there, how to love across difference
and how to build meaningful relationships
and how to practice empathy in a healthy way.
That's my hope for what we can do.
I think that's my call to action.
Thank you.
Thanks, everyone.
We have lots of time for questions, so please come ask them.
We have microphones on both sides.
Oh, there we go. Okay.
Hi, my name's Eric, and I was late, but great talk.
Um, it's not exactly a question, it's more of an endorsement actually.
Um, I think you guys are doing great work. I think...
I haven't played this game, but I really want to.
And as game developers, we don't have time to play games.
And we just spoiled the ending for you.
No, I know, right? I'm just like, holy shit.
But, um, is everyone here, uh...
I have a solution and I'm going to implement it one day and anyone wants to come along
the journey.
I actually volunteer on a suicide and crisis hotline and I've been doing that for about
two years.
I've got about 500 hours and if the stars align and if everything works out, I would
like to make some sort of roleplaying suicide and hotline game to encourage everyone to
have empathy for our fellow human beings and our struggles.
And if anyone's interested in that,
they can contact me later.
What's your name?
My name's Eric Chow from Honor Games.
Thank you.
Yeah, thanks for sharing.
Any other questions?
We probably have time for one.
Great talk. I'm curious, like you depict kind of like the inside of the head of very different characters.
And what was your process to depict them authentically and the state of mind that they're going through?
Yeah, I can start on that. We spent a lot of time, a lot of time, a lot of thought, a lot of reading, a lot of talking.
We have a writer's room. There's a talk.
a few days ago about the importance of writers room.
Maybe some of you were in that, yeah.
Yeah, our experience validates that.
You need a team of a diverse set of experiences
and perspectives to come together
and consider something as nuanced and important
as the topics that we hope to deal with.
So I always think about exploding the idea of write what you know and changing it to
know what you write, you know?
As a writer you have to feel a sense of not that you are ever a master with these topics
because how can you be?
But just that you know that you have immersed yourself to a point where.
where you feel comfortable being able to be in that world.
And if you don't, then you have a writer's room
to help you and share that burden.
Thank you.
Yeah, thank you.
Yeah, please.
So you gave the example of the junkyard scene where what the player's doing and what the
player's feeling doesn't really match what the character's feeling and that was kind of
intentional because you brought it together later on. I'm wondering if there were any moments
you have in mind where the player was unintentionally not feeling
in line with what the character was feeling and what kinds of things you did to address that?
Do you stand by that?
I mean, the first time we introduced Alex's power
in True Colors, it's deliberately off-putting,
strange, shocking, kind of overwhelming.
She flips out in anger and beats a guy up
and kind of ruins her day.
We were doing that to put the, on two levels.
Like on one level, you know,
you're not angry and punching Mac.
You're not doing that.
That's not what's happening.
So you're like, what the fuck?
But then neither is Alex.
Like, Alex is also like, what the hell?
Like, what did I just do?
I don't have control either.
And I think we found a harmony there.
We were a little bit concerned at that.
And there were voices on the team
who thought that would be really off-putting.
But then we just leaned in and we decided
that's actually a pretty interesting way
to engender a closer connection
between the player and Alex out of the gate.
Yeah, I think also...
You know, we have different language that we use to talk about this idea.
Like, we're always talking about where's the player and where's the player character, and
how close are they, and when are they separate.
And the answer isn't always that they have to be in lockstep with each other.
Sometimes, like I think the junkyard scene is actually an example of this, you can find
a greater...
harmony by beginning from a place of dissonance, because you can't expect the player to be right
there with your player character experiencing something difficult or unique right at the
beginning of the scene. But that's where we get to use our tools and create a sense of play to draw
the player into it. So I think, you know, there's almost a musicality to it, where you can think
about like a dissonance.
and an assonance that builds over the course of a sequence where you hopefully land at
a place that comes together and finds that poignancy.
I think we have time for one more question.
And then I want to remind everyone I was asked to remind you to fill out your surveys about
the quality of the talk.
And then we're probably going to head down the hallway and hang out in the main atrium
area if anyone has follow-ups or questions or want to talk about anything.
Please feel free.
Hey, I'm Blake from Gorilla.
I just wanted to ask you guys, based on my experience
building sequences like this, and you guys
do it extremely well.
it's very hard to get across exactly the kind of thing you want to get across in the early part
of the process when asset fidelity is really low. You know, you don't have that music yet,
you don't have that final interaction, you don't have those animations. How do you guys build this
stuff? What does it look like in the early days to make it sell, to get across the idea that it's
like going to be there eventually? Yeah. Can I do this one quickly? Yeah. I think about, I use this
phrase in the talk deliberately, I...
I think about the grammar of constellation points.
What galvanizes the room in an early idea
will be one particular moment, one concept, one thought.
What if Chloe finds her dad's car?
And everyone's like, fool, fool, oh my goodness.
Okay, let's start building around that.
Let's build from that.
If the constellation points are strong
and you learn to know and trust your instincts,
oh, this is a good framework.
then the music that comes afterward, both actual score,
but also the music of all the artistic elements,
the performance, the actual dialogue, all of it,
it'll be fantastic.
And conversely, if the constellation points
are not clear early on,
that's really a page one problem,
and you wanna look at that again.
It takes time.
I'll just add too, like, we're very lucky that we have a tool set that lets us script
the entirety of the scene.
So like a screenplay for a movie, we can show the power of the scene on the page or if it's
not working.
It goes both ways.
And that is the ultimate proving ground, right?
And that's, we encourage in our studio everyone to read the scripts.
even when they're in their rougher states,
because we want to use that as kind of the ultimate litmus
of like, is this hitting people?
Is this galvanizing people?
Do the artists want to make this?
Do the animators want to animate this?
If not, then we know there's something wrong.
Okay, yeah, no, I just wanted to say, that's it.
We have to go.
Thank you very much.