Our business is joy.
The hard work we do goes into building tiny machines of joy.
We build, package, and ship joy.
Our ultimate goal, regardless of how much we argue, stress,
and struggle, and God knows we do,
is to bring joy into the world.
We are all part of the joy industrial complex.
As game developers, the fruit of our labor is joy.
If an industry can have a soul, ours is joy.
So how can it be so hard?
How can it be so hard sometimes to get up in the morning?
How can it be so hard to keep a studio running,
to find job security, personal health, or even a decent wage?
How can it be so hard?
And how can we make the struggle easier?
We are fragile and frail people.
Sometimes we fall, sometimes we fail.
But we are also capable of deep compassion
and sublime empathy.
And we always aim for joy.
My name is Henrik Jansson,
and I will be your moderator today.
The questions asked here are what we will discuss
during the panel.
But first I need to address why the panel
looks very different than planned.
Tom Hall, the co-founder of id Software, and Nicole Lewis,
head of publishing for League of Legends,
were supposed to be here.
They both had to cancel suddenly yesterday.
Life comes at us hard.
Thankfully, through friends and friends of friends,
we have lined up a new set of panelists.
And I would now like the panel to introduce themselves.
I'm Brie Code. I'm the CEO and creative director of a tiny studio based in Toronto called True Love.
Before that I was a lead programmer at Ubisoft Montreal on Child of Light and three Assassin's Creed projects.
And before that I wrote AI for a company of heroes at Relic.
Hi, I'm Dr. JC Lau.
I'm currently a tech producer at Harebrained Schemes
working on Battletech.
Before that, I was at Bungie as a test engineer
working on Destiny 2 and its DLCs.
And before I entered games, I was a professor
in the philosophy of race and gender at Virginia Tech.
Hello, my name is Osama Darius.
I'm a game designer at Warner Brothers Games in Montreal.
I'm also the coordinator of the video game programs
at Dawson College, and I'm the co-founder
of the Montreal Independent Game Awards.
Hi, I'm Raf Koster, and I'm a game designer
best known for MMOs, Ultima Online,
Star Wars Galaxies, MetaPlace,
and I think this might be my 20th or 21st consecutive GDC.
It's a long run.
So the first topic I'd like to bring up is my first job in games.
Finding a job in games can be hard,
but I also like to talk about how do we leave a job.
I've seen too many developers leave a trail of burned bridges behind them.
And I would like us to talk a little bit of how to leave.
Could the panel please talk a little bit about how you got in,
but also how you got out.
If you have switched jobs since then, how did you leave?
Any advice at all?
Reverse the order perhaps?
Sure.
So I got in through friends.
And I think that's not unusual.
A friend of mine got lucky and landed a contracting job
doing video games.
And from there, ended up hired full time.
And when they needed designers on Ultima Online,
he recommended me.
And there I ended up just ridiculously lucky and on the right project at the right time
I think a lot of what I'd say about that is
That luck needs preparation, right? If if I hadn't been doing the right kind of thing beforehand
I probably couldn't have gotten the job as
far as leaving
Gosh most of the times I've left have been very very stressful and unpleasant
I once left a job over the fact that I was asked to fire a group of people that I had
been mentoring for two years, for example.
And I wasn't allowed to tell them that's why.
That was not fun.
So I actually had a completely different career path. I studied political science and I worked as a shipping agent
And I had a love-hate relationship with the job. Meeting people was fun, the captains and the crew and doing the paperwork is boring
So I went to another love that I had before which was graphic and web design and I just
Completely self-taught, I became a freelancer,
I did all the wrong things, didn't make a lot of money,
but at least that allowed me to learn Flash,
and Flash allowed me to make games,
and my games were terrible,
but they were good enough for a portfolio.
That's how I landed my first job in the industry.
I left that job because basically I was too nice, and I don't mean that in a good way.
I didn't fight for my rights, I didn't fight for a salary, and I realized after years and
years of just waiting patiently for people to acknowledge what I deserved and to give
it to me, that people that were much more junior than me were actually making higher
salaries.
And when I asked to fix that, to mend that, I was given answers and excuses.
So after six years at the same company, finally enough was enough.
And by leaving, I almost made double what I made before.
So it's basically that.
The games industry is my third industry, I would say.
So I'm Australian, and in Australia,
you can do a law degree as an undergrad.
So I actually started my college with an arts law degree,
and I went on to become a lawyer.
I worked in family law for several years,
working on child representation.
in divorce cases, which is, as you can imagine,
not a super fun place to be when you're 22 years old.
Yeah, and then after that,
I decided I wanted to be an academic.
So then I did a dissertation
in moral and political philosophy.
So I ended up with a PhD in philosophy,
and what do you do with that?
You become a philosophy professor,
because either that or there's that joke
about going to McDonald's and asking people
if they think they want fries with something.
So, when I was an academic, I was like, well, I have these skills, but I want to make games.
How do I leverage my background into a games job?
And so I actually applied at Bungie as a tester, and I'm like, I have a PhD, I would like to
be a tester.
And so that was a really interesting conversation, but I guess they gave me the job, so that's
cool.
And so a lot of it was talking about how those skills transferred.
So I talked a lot about like how I have particular communication skills and
organizational skills and how I could apply them to a particular role.
And I can't say I've left a lot of game shows because I'm the baby on this panel.
I've been in the industry for about four years.
But although statistically, I'm one year away from.
the average career length for a woman in games,
so let that sink in.
But yeah, so one of the reasons I did leave
was it was a combination of studio culture
and also wanting to make an impact.
And depending on your studio size and its composition,
it can feel hard to make an impact.
And so I wanted to go somewhere where I could
feel like I was making a difference and being effective
and seeing change that I wanted.
So.
Yeah, that's pretty much my story.
I got into the games industry by accident.
I wanna go all the way back to high school.
I grew up in the country and I hated living in the country.
And I figured out by looking at what's possible
in my high school that I could finish high school
in four years instead of five if I moved some classes around
in a way that my teachers didn't approve of.
and took summer school,
and the courses that's supposed to be remedial,
but just take it, and they couldn't stop me.
And so I finished high school when I was 16
and went to university with absolutely no savings
because I never had a summer job
and hadn't thought that far ahead.
So I had to put myself through university
by working two jobs and keeping my scholarship.
And again, I kind of like figured out how to make it work.
And I thought if I do computer science,
I can get a degree.
and know I can keep my scholarship because it's not subjective.
Like you just stay in the lab until your program works and you know you have an A
and then you know you have your scholarship and you know you have a degree.
I graduated when I was 20 and the dot-com crash just happened and there were no jobs.
and I realized I didn't want to be a programmer and I hadn't thought that far ahead either.
I kept my student job for a while and then I got a credit card and I went to Europe.
I thought that moving from the country to Vancouver had been so expansive and interesting
that going to another continent would be interesting too.
And I thought I would figure out what I wanted from life and what should I go back to school
and study because I felt like I wanted to do a do-over.
And then what I discovered was that I ran out of money and went back to Vancouver with
eight dollars left and needed a job and started applying for every programming job I could
find and I was very, very, very, very, very, very, very lucky.
to get a job at Relic Entertainment in Vancouver,
which was an amazing experience.
I loved it from the first few weeks,
and I knew that I would stay in the games industry forever.
So I wrote AI Code there.
I worked there for a while, but then I was like.
I did want to try to live overseas for a while, so I went to Australia for a bit.
I came back to Canada
and then I started my own studio.
And a couple of the times that I left studios, not all of them,
one of those jobs was really amazing.
All those jobs were amazing.
Being a woman in a workplace dominated by men is not easy.
And research shows if there's less than 30%, I think, of women,
then women get sidelined and stereotyped and talked over in meetings
and men attribute the women's ideas to themselves.
And these kind of things really happen.
eventually you kind of reach a point where you are just not able to develop
your talents and your aptitudes at the speed that the men around you are and it
makes more sense to go somewhere new. So that's why I left a couple of mine.
I'm coming at you from extreme privilege.
As a programmer, I've never been afraid to leave the game
industry, which is a blessing for that not many others
and specialists in the gaming field have.
My first job in games was my first real job,
if you did not count summer jobs.
And it was as a programmer for games to be broadcast on TV.
I failed my college, I did not know C++, and I lied to get in.
I was asked to start in three weeks, and that's when I got my first book on C++.
It worked out.
It was a different time.
So if we talk about this first topic, and then if we try to
think of one time where we realized that this is so bad
or so good, an opportunity on the outside.
Sorry for making that sentence a complete mess.
Have we ever had such a good situation and good offer from
the outside that you need to leave?
Or was there ever a situation so bad?
that you felt you had to leave.
And I can, when my boss was screaming at me
that she would kill me,
that's when I left my first job.
So, who would wanna go first on that?
So, let's see, my first job in games that I left,
that would have been when I left Origin
after making Ultima Online.
I'd come on board on Ultima Online when I was 23, 24.
And after only a couple of years,
I was actually the lead designer of it
by the time I was 25 when it shipped.
And I knew nothing about the wider industry at all.
I didn't know anybody.
I just didn't know anyone.
I didn't know what I had actually accomplished.
like I was oblivious to it.
And I was highly opinionated,
highly, highly opinionated,
very sure of myself in terms of what we were doing.
But that meant that despite having just shipped this game
that was a really big deal,
Some of you are young enough to not even know how big a deal it was at the time.
It was a really big deal, but I didn't realize how big a deal it was.
EA actually put me on the list of people to be laid off
because I was opinionated and thought that they were idiots
in terms of what they were doing with online games.
I got rescued by managers who...
I owe an enormous debt to people like Gordon Walton and Rich Vogel
who mentored me through this period.
But they launched an Ultima Online 2 project and I was very carefully left out of the team
for that, so they wouldn't let me lead a new project.
They tucked me away on the live team, which turned out to be a blessing because the live
team made the money and the sequels all got cancelled.
And eventually part of the reason we left is that the follow-on project that I was working on
also got cancelled because they just didn't know what to do.
So that ended up being good. We all left and landed a new one called Star Wars Galaxies.
But it basically was a case of, wow, here's an org that is so dysfunctional
that they don't understand where the money is coming from, where the value is coming from.
They don't even understand this whole new category that they just opened up
and is theirs for the taking. So they just let it wither on the vine.
EA did go on to lose about a billion dollars in online games in the space of the next four
years, so leaving turned out to be the right thing to do.
But it was a really strange experience to not be aware that I'd done something great.
gradually become aware and then be ignored for it by that company.
You know, it's a good reminder that companies, even though they're often made of very smart people,
companies can be really, really stupid things. Like really, really stupid. So don't trust companies.
So I made the mistake at one point in my career where I started highlighting my soft skills as my strongest skills.
This is actually true.
They still are my strongest skills.
I work really well with people.
I even earned the reputation that I could work with anyone.
For the record, I don't want to work with anyone, but I can if I had to.
So I was hired in this one particular company that will go unnamed for that, for the soft skills.
I have hard skills as well, many of them. I have 12 years in the industry, I've shipped different sized games, over 20 of them.
I have a track record for delivering.
However, I focused on soft skills because I felt that this was something that was not
favoured in the industry.
We don't look at it, we don't ask about it, and this is a mistake.
People are promoted to positions of leadership based on their hard skills instead of being
given other promotions that doesn't put them interfacing with people.
So, you know, like telling someone that you're working with you're going to kill them, things
like that.
So what happened is, at this one particular company,
I worked for a person who was a little bit manipulative,
and by a little bit I mean completely.
He realized really quickly that I knew how,
that my team liked me, they trusted me.
So for the year or so that I was there,
and don't go on my LinkedIn to find out which company I'm talking about,
I was not able to change this person's mind once about anything.
to the point that everyone has imposter syndrome,
mine went through the roof.
It was gradual. At first it was like, okay, he's more experienced than me and he's worked on more
games and he's dealt with more people and I started listening and then at other points when
his, whatever he suggested would have a 50-50 track record of working, um, I started making
excuses for it while we tried it out and eventually near the end I realized I'm just a mouthpiece
for my team. I'm a lead designer by name only. I'm not doing anything except translating.
Because he had lost.
all trust, or rather, the team had lost all trust in him.
So I was being used as a figurehead.
And that's when I decided to leave the company.
That's not, my job title is not figurehead,
it's game designer.
Okay, I'm gonna preface this with also,
please don't go on my LinkedIn,
because my time in games has been relatively short,
so it'll be really easy to pinpoint
where things are happening.
So I'm gonna kind of couch this in very general terms.
There was a point before I started in games proper,
when I was leaving academia, where I did some work
in both games journalism and also in working on consoles.
So kind of games adjacent, not really in games.
And one of the things that I discovered quite quickly,
like Asama, is I had a particular set of skills that were,
easily transferable but were considered soft skills.
So given my background, I've done a lot of advocacy work.
I do a lot of speaking about diversity and inclusion.
I have written and published on these areas.
And very quickly on these teams that I was on,
I became the person that was the one
that would take things up to the manager
on behalf of the team.
So I was, at one point, I was the...
coordinator for a team of 24 people and they were all people that, and we were based in Seattle but
none of them were actually from Seattle and some of them, for some of them English was not their
first language so then I kind of ended up being like a sound of the mouthpiece for this team
and I would bring things up to the manager and it got to the point also for me where
I was in this weird role where I had this particular set of coordination and like management skills
So I wasn't expendable in that way,
but it was apparent that I was not included
in a lot of the conversations at that leadership level.
So it came to this point where they kind of just,
I was getting siloed in a way that was not
kind of making me effective for my team.
And I like to say most people don't leave companies, they leave managers.
And I think that is true in some of these cases.
It's about those interpersonal relationships and
whether or not you can sustain them will also determine what your day-to-day is like.
And I think that is one of the key things about how you can,
like, why people leave is just...
you know, sometimes it gets too hard to try to maintain that relationship.
Sometimes there's a lot of labor that you have to do in addition to your day job
to maintain that relationship. And sometimes it's just not worth it.
So if you get to that point where it's just basically your daily death by a
thousand cuts, it's probably time to leave. Yeah.
Um,
I was an AI programmer at Relic and was a really technical programmer.
If someone can't figure out how to do something, they can give it to me and I'll figure it
out.
When I started at Ubisoft, in Quebec there is a stereotype that women make very good
managers.
So shortly after I started, my boss asked me to manage the team.
And I had applied for a lead programmer position because it had been the only one that was
on the website.
And I was an intermediate programmer when I did that, so it was pretty cool.
So I said yes, because of course I'm going to take a promotion.
And I was, I'm not a good manager.
Like I, it's not what my, maybe I'm an okay manager, but I'm a better systems programmer.
But I said yes.
And for the first two years, it was really hard.
Every time I had to speak in front of my team of like eight friends of mine, I would get
the shakes and the stomachache, which I did every morning.
And I managed that team and then I managed a team that was twice that size and then I
managed a team that was three or four times that size.
And then I became a lead programmer on Child of Light.
And near the end of Child of Light...
Two things happened on that project.
One was that I had a really incredible boss
who knew that I wanted to be a producer
because I was so happy with getting the promotion
and with feeling useful that I wasn't thinking
about what I was actually good at
or what I should be doing.
I was doing what I was asked to do
and I really liked doing what I was asked to do.
So he knew I wanted to be a producer
and so he showed me his entire job.
Like he would be like,
oh Bree, come over here and see the resource management tool.
And I was kind of horrified at what a producer's job was.
And I realized I definitely, like, I can't do, that's not my path.
And what path have I been on for five years, seven years, seven years?
And near the end of that project, I also, like, well, we were shipping,
like, we were crunching, and I discovered I had a life-threatening illness.
And I couldn't tell them because...
they needed to stay focused. I blurted it out to my boss as he was putting a lot
of pressure on me one day and his eyes almost fell out of his head. I learned
not to tell people that way. And then I went into surgery the day that we put
the thing in the box and that it was out and the reviews came out that day. When I
came out of surgery the reviews were starting to appear on the internet.
And it turned out that I was absolutely fine.
The surgery worked and I'm fine and I'm completely fine.
But my life sure came into crystal clear focus
and I experienced something called post-traumatic growth.
Because I didn't know I was gonna be fine.
We were shipping that game,
I didn't know what was gonna happen.
And so suddenly everything became really clear
and I knew where I wanted the industry to go
and I knew what was missing and what I wanted to do.
And so, and I started doing it and I realized that that organization wasn't
the right place to be doing what I wanted to do, that innovation happens
outside of established structures and that it happens in a startup and
that I have to do a startup to be able to be doing what I want to do. So that's why I left.
We are talking about a little bit on skillset and finding out who we are as people when we grow into the industry.
And I just met a game student at a university who was having issues with, or a bit of a problem with choosing if you wanted to go into 3D modeling or 3D animation.
I couldn't help her with that because, you know, I'm a programmer. I'm so bad at drawing that I'm banned from using the whiteboard in many of our offices.
But I was able to tell her that the choice we're making
are very rarely career defining.
It may influence her first job, but it will not necessarily
influence her full career.
And I wanted to tell her that you are not your career.
You are not your job description.
But, you know, I just don't think that quick on my feet.
So I didn't.
I wish I could.
But I would like a little bit if we can talk about how we change roles over time.
Bree mentioned kind of sliding into something because it's expected of you to be good at
that because of different reasons, or how we move and change because we are curious
and want to investigate things.
So, practical ways to broaden our horizons, basically.
If anyone wants to take a stab at that, Bree?
So, my boss on Child of Light taught me
that in most setbacks there are opportunities.
And it doesn't mean that the setback is fair.
It doesn't mean it's how it should work.
But it means that the game has changed
and you can sometimes find new ways to play from that.
And I think that, you know, every time that something's gone wrong in my career,
maybe I haven't known at that moment that it's actually a push forward,
and it hasn't felt good in the moment, but it's always worked out to be a giant leap forward.
When I was doing AI programming at the beginning,
it was because that's what the team needed
and then I really liked it.
And then when I became a manager,
it was because it was what the team needed.
And even if it wasn't the best long-term career path for me,
it taught me how to be able to do stuff like this,
speak in front of people,
and even just speak to people at all
because I was never very social.
And then when I, you know, got sick and figured out what I wanted to do,
I discovered a theory in the field of stress psychology,
which kind of explains why about half of people find video games boring
and also suggests a framework for how to engage and retain those other half of people,
which is the basis of my studio now.
The thing about not being your job, though,
it doesn't work for me.
We're all different people and we all have different needs.
And work-life balance has never been something I've needed.
So I'll throw that out there.
And it's not popular, and don't follow my example,
because you probably have to work life balance.
So I think the thing about not being your job
or not being your job description is
kind of apt.
Okay, so given my background,
and I like to joke about this because my,
it was just a little bit of background.
I come from a really kind of traditional
like Asian parenting stereotype thing.
And I meet that trifecta because I'm a doctor, a lawyer, and an engineer.
And my parents love that.
And then I'm like, I'm a game producer.
And they're like, what is that?
So one of the things is while I am all those things, I also am more things than that.
But I also, I'm not, so I'm not just those things.
But there are skill sets that overlap for all those things.
I like to talk about skill sets more than job descriptions for two reasons.
One is, job descriptions vary wildly between studios.
This is also true of titles.
This is true of what your day-to-day looks like.
And the other thing is skill sets are pliable,
and you can leverage those for a lot of jobs.
So when we were talking about soft skills,
those are necessary for any kind of,
like there's a set of soft skills,
including communication and organization,
and being able to work in a team,
and having some sort of initiative that are relevant for.
basically all game jobs where you work in a collaborative environment.
So talking about those is I think a more kind of vague but useful way of describing yourself.
And the other thing about what you, so this is going back to what Herrick was saying about
how you change those roles over time.
There are things that you can care deeply about that don't fall within a job description.
For me, I care really deeply about diversity and inclusion issues.
I can't go to a studio and be like, hey, I care deeply about diversity and inclusion,
give me a games job.
That's changing now because studios are getting D&I managers, but that's not really super
common right now.
I can't just be like, hey, I care about this stuff, get me a job.
So a lot of it is making spaces and carving out those careers for yourself, I think.
So one of the things I did was I have this particular interest, and when I was at Bungie,
I found a way to have conversations about diversity and inclusion with initially my
manager and then the head of my discipline, and then it went all the way up to the studio
leadership, and this is how we founded the Bungie Diversity Committee in 2017.
Our studio at the time was having these conversations,
so it was also lucky that I could just segue into that.
But there are ways to have these conversations
about what you care about,
and to carve out those spaces for yourself.
I think one of the things that also helps
is because our industry is young,
and we still have a lot of technology that's developing,
there are spaces to find,
Nothing's being done in this particular area. Like how can I get into that space or you know?
There's like this new tech that we haven't really explored
How can I leverage my expertise to kind of develop that and we have these opportunities. So yeah, we should take those
So professionally speaking who you are it's what you do
and you're able to do whatever you want.
I proved that myself because I didn't study anything related to game design at all.
So who I was professionally again was a shipping agent,
but I was only a shipping agent for a year until I decided to explore other things.
And then I picked up other skills.
Your skills are malleable and intangible, but you can pick them up.
And then I became a freelance graphic and web designer, and that became who I was.
And that's what I thought, at least.
But that wasn't what was important. The title wasn't what was important.
It was the skills that I carried over.
However, people only interface with...
titles. So when I became a game designer, it's because I transitioned from the graphic
and web design skills, added a few other skills that were unrelated, and now all of a sudden
I have new skills. I mentioned before I was a coordinator of the video game programs at
Dawson College. Before I was a coordinator, I was a teacher. I became a teacher of level
in video game design when I only had three years of experience.
How did that happen?
I was interested in becoming a teacher,
but I knew it was probably gonna be along a faraway road.
Like, I was still very new to the industry,
but some people saw that I had some potential.
I don't have stage fright, that's one thing.
I like spending time with people,
even if I'm not paid for it,
so I could spend more time with the students
and get them to the level that they are.
I'm naturally, I have these skills that I learned
when I was a shipping agent before
that I carried over again.
So, all I had to do was leverage that
when an opportunity came.
and the opportunity came in the form of a teacher that cancelled three weeks
before a class was supposed to start. So I had to teach, or rather they were
looking for someone to teach narrative, nonlinear narrative design in the
Dragon Age engine, three weeks away when nobody in Montreal knew that engine.
And so I had three weeks to apply and potentially possibly get the job.
But I couldn't wait to get the job to learn the engine,
so I had to start learning the engine beforehand.
And I didn't have time off to take from work,
so this was part-time.
So I had a full-time job in the day.
But I did it because this was an opportunity
and I really wanted it.
And also, I don't need work-life balance
and don't follow my example.
I don't sleep much.
So I did it and I got that job and I performed fairly well.
I had pretty good evaluations.
So when the time came for the coordinator of the level design program,
because this was a level design program to step down,
they looked at who had really good evaluations and they offered it to two of us.
The first person declined and I accepted, except with an asterisk.
I love level design. I was a game designer when projects were really small.
So when you did everything, you weren't specialized at all.
I did AI and UI and level design and mission design and name it, I did it.
Economy design, things that narrative, things that on the chart now people are
surprised that the same person can do them.
This is just that's another problem of the industry that I won't go into.
But you can do that and you can do all these things.
Basically, for me, I approach game design no matter what, like telling a story,
whether it's economy design or narrative design.
So I just leverage skills.
So what happened is I wanted to teach, I wanted to have a game design program.
They didn't have one.
And they said that they were not willing to hire someone to create the curriculum.
So I said, okay, I will.
But I didn't study education.
I didn't even know what a curriculum looked like.
And they said, how are you going to do this?
And I said, well, I'm going to approach it the same way I approach game design.
I look at games, I reverse engineer, I write my documents, I proceed,
we make mistakes, we iterate, and then we'll have something that works.
It's easy, right?
No, it's not.
It's hard, but the thought process behind it is easy.
So the director said, fine, we'll give you an example curriculum.
This is what it looks like.
See ya.
Six months later, I booked a meeting, and he was surprised to see me.
I had a curriculum for a game design program.
because I spent the time to do it.
He was surprised, he thought he would never see me again.
That was the end of that.
But what happened is he looked at it,
I actually put effort, I didn't, I'm not,
at this point I think I had five years of experience
in the industry, so I didn't take it upon myself.
I got a lot of people to come and consult, and we worked on it together, and I credited them for it.
And technically I had all the language wrong, but the work was there.
He assigned me a technical writer for a week, she helped me fix it, and we had a program.
I pitched it to the Ministry of Education, I prepared for weeks, I was sweating bullets.
They asked me the most basic questions you could imagine, like, what is game?
So they accepted it because, you know, this is my expertise,
and the part that they see as the needed skills,
they don't know if I have it or not, they see end results.
And all of a sudden, I became a coordinator,
in addition to becoming a designer,
in addition to becoming a teacher,
in addition to becoming a shipping agent,
in addition of becoming a graphic web designer.
And now, tomorrow, if I want it to be something else,
all I have to do is look at the skills that I already have.
Oh, did I mention I was also the co-founder
of the Montreal Independent Game Awards,
which is a festival, so I'm also an event planner.
And the skills that I needed to learn
that I didn't have as a game designer
to become an event planner were actually really small,
because planning events is very similar
to planning a game or, you know, leading a team.
So who you are is really who you want to be.
Don't let titles stop you.
I'm not sure what to say after that.
When Henrik wanted titles for the slide for, you know,
Say What You Do, a few years ago I just started saying,
just put down Game Designer.
Just put that down.
Because, you know, I've been a CEO.
I was a vice president of Disney.
whatever. There's like a hundred of them, so it's not as big a deal as it seems.
I've done art. You can actually go on Spotify right now and stream my folk music album I put
out in 1999. Like, for real, it's out there. You know, when I was a kid, my parents and my family
used to say, oh, you'll grow up and be a writer and a teacher.
I think I actually did end up doing both those things.
The reason why I make games is because it lets me do everything.
I make games because it lets me do art, it lets me play with math, I can do some programming,
I can sometimes write the soundtrack music, I get to read about and then talk about ethics
and philosophy and try to persuade people in the industry to pay attention to ethics.
Not being so successful on that front, but I keep trying.
I get to work and help manage communities.
The list goes on and on and on.
And in the end, to me, it all ends up being wrapped up in Game Designer,
because it's just aspects of the job, one way or another.
I probably, you know, if I made a large enough pile of money, I have to admit, I'd probably
get in a van and go tour the country with an acoustic guitar.
But I mean, literally, my degree, the thing that I left behind to go make Ultima Online
was actually a Master of Fine Arts in writing poetry.
I think, you know, the who are you thing is really that all of us are many people.
We're different people depending on who we're talking to, we're different people depending
on the situations we're put in.
And the key to it is really to not stand still, to keep looking for new ways to dig into yourself
and new ways to dig into the world around you.
and find fresh new combinations.
Oh my God, I guess people are match three puzzles.
Yeah, I mean, see?
So that's, yeah, game designer, yeah.
The path we travel is very weird.
And what I meant with you are not your job description
is your job description is.
or your career is that I'm still the little fat kid, or rather tall fat kid, who just
got out of that jock hole I was living in and making something a lot different than
what they could even imagine.
So you know, we're different things, we're amazing beings.
But we also have friends, local and international friends, and we meet through a multitude of
channels.
And, you know, we hang out on Twitter and we meet on, we like each other's posts on Instagram and
put bunny ears on each other on different types of snap chattery apps.
And many times we prefer the company of others who are not game developers, but we all
build our own networks to get by and...
feel safe, feel strong, and grow as people.
And I think Rafe, Raph, I'm sorry.
I take Rafe particularly from non-Americans.
It is a common nickname, actually.
But I'll try with Raph.
You'll see why in just a second.
So and of course, we meet at GDC,
and we listen to colleagues, friends, or total strangers
opening their hearts.
to share hard-earned experiences.
Most of us have support networks like this.
And I know that Raf had input.
Do any of you know my name?
Like my actual name?
No?
Rafael Ricardo Coster Villanueva.
Soy Latino.
The familia puertorriquea, my family is Puerto Rican on my mom's side, nobody has a clue.
Nobody knows that.
Raff Coster sounds like some kind of, you know, some Dutch-German, which is in there,
and like I'm an 8th Irish too and whatever.
I grew up.
in New York, Massachusetts, Florida, Georgia, Tennessee,
Peru, Barbados, Haiti, and Maryland before the age of 18.
So I really hate it when somebody says,
where are you from?
I, there's this thing called third culture kid,
which is people like me, and there's probably a bunch of you
here, actually.
We are the people who grow up without living in any one culture long enough to feel as it is your own.
Like, yes, I have an American passport, but I had lived, like, in raw time, before I was 18, I did not grow up American.
I went to a British school system.
I grew up speaking other languages.
I completely missed the Ness.
Like just skipped it.
It wasn't a thing, right?
And you know, that can leave you feeling anchor-less sometimes, right?
on the negative side. On the positive side, it can make you feel like you live everywhere
and like all cultures are wine in different bottles, right? It can leave you feeling like
there's profound similarities and that the similarities are far bigger than the differences.
When I got into games, it was, and specifically when I got into games, it was online games and
back then,
Not that many people were online, and it was a crazy kind of a melting pot.
There were all sorts of people.
One of my friends on one of the early text mods was one of the world's top experts in
grasshoppers.
You'd meet people, because it was a text mod, another player was blind, but he could play
a game with a screen reader, even back then in the early 90s.
When I got into the game industry, that sense of shared experience of this games and game
playing being a common culture was important.
But not just the larger game, the game playing culture, but the game making culture turned
out to be a family for me.
The most impactful thing probably in my whole career
was not a job, it was not a game title.
It was when one of my bosses at the time, Gordon Walton,
he called me into his office to do a one-on-one
because he'd just become the manager of the team
and he said, hey, so how are things going?
What are you up to?
I said, I'm working, you should know that, you're my boss.
And he said, oh, well, are you happy here?
I was like, there are other places?
Yeah, no, there's this whole industry out there.
Oh, they don't know who I am.
That's ridiculous.
He said, what are you talking about?
Of course they know who you are.
No, nobody's ever tried to recruit me.
People here won't promote me.
I don't think anybody cares about anything I say or do,
honestly, you know?
And he said, wow, what are you doing next week?
And I said, working.
You should know this.
You're my boss.
And he said, no, you're not.
And he bought me a plane ticket.
And he flew the two of us to Oregon,
where Chris Crawford was holding a game design
retreat at his house.
And he sat me down in front of this house,
next to Steve Moretzky, Noah Falstein, Bob Bates,
Brian Moriarty, and said, this is your group.
These are your peers, these are the people
that think the way you do, that love games the way you do.
And that's why this is my 20th or whatever consecutive GDC.
Because frankly, those, the execs at whatever,
they come and go, right?
But I still have dinner with those guys every year.
Right? Because yeah, the business people, they make their pile of money,
they leave and it's just as well. Right?
But these people, right,
that's, you know, that's the family.
That's what actually makes the difference through all the shit.
Cause there's plenty of shit.
I'm going to have to cut it a little bit short.
I'm sorry for cutting in now.
We're just running a little bit short on time.
I'd like to mention that yesterday I had a dinner with
my peers, my friends from Iron Storm in Dallas, where we made an Akronox, and it was a beautiful,
beautiful thing to get five people together after 20, almost 20 years, together every year at GDC.
Those are my people. That's why I wasn't at the Nordic party. Suck it. I want to touch on
organization a little bit, because I think it's very important.
For the long-term health and sanity of our industry,
I firmly believe we game developers need to make deeper efforts
in order to improve our working conditions.
We have seen a terrible year of layoffs.
We have seen studios shut down or decimated by forces
seemingly beyond our control.
Our business is very cyclical.
Companies might need to adjust to handle shifting circumstances,
but the effect of those adjustments, that are often called layoffs,
end up on the shoulders of game workers and their families.
So can we just do a real quick, and this seems severely disrespectful,
but a quick panel thought on the recent year, what it means for the future
and how it can be combated.
That was hard to say.
That was easy to write.
Combated. How we can fight it.
Anyone?
I can start.
Okay, so like I said, I'm the baby on this panel.
I have not been in the industry for that long.
But I entered the industry after, I'm not even going to say, but the thing about ethics
in game journalism, I entered the industry like knowing that there
happy in series of layoffs, I entered the industry after knowing that this place is
unstable and basically just bananas. How does anything ever even get made in games?
And so I know that there is this anxiety that comes with making games and I think the thing that
keeps us going is that element of solidarity. We plan, we know that these things are going to
happen and we
plan for them, we try to make contingencies.
And I'm, okay, I'm gonna keep this short.
I'm also an elder millennial, so I love social media.
And I think that being able to hear these stories
and speak to the people who are directly experienced,
experiencing these things is really important
for us being aware of what's going on in our industry
and being able to connect to groups that can.
help us support each other is really, really important.
So I guess for the future,
I want to see more of those connections being made.
I want to see us be able to connect
and strengthen those connections as we make them.
Because I think ultimately,
it's one of those situations where
a rising tide lifts all boats.
We need to be able to support each other
and know that when other people are suffering
and be able to help them alleviate that.
and that's what's going to keep us all together.
Can I add something?
Really quickly, most of us are good people
who care about others.
That's been my experience, every company.
I've worked at five different companies,
most of us are good.
Make a concerted effort to identify the people
who care about others, who are not here
only for the paycheck or the bonus,
and help them in any way that you can.
and build trust between each other,
and identify the people who are not that.
Our industry is very finite.
We cannot have infinite jobs.
So why are we accommodating people
who only care about themselves?
We have a problem with who we promote
to leadership positions.
Most of our directors are actually dictators.
And we need to stop that.
Who is more powerful?
One director, or everyone under him combined?
I said him, I meant them, sorry.
Who?
A director cannot do anything if we're united.
So identify the good people, please.
Form a strong partnership, and then we have power.
Otherwise, we're complicit.
Thank you.
So the path forward.
In our industry of joy, it's crooked and winding,
and we frequently find ourselves in forks in the path.
Our choices matter, and our landscape is ever shifting.
From my view, the business of joy is a magical place,
but not all magic is good for us.
Empathy, curiosity, and compassion
are our most transferable skills, so please let's use them.
We will close this panel now with a few choice words from our panelists.
Thank you so much.
Those were my choice words.
Innovation happens outside of what we already know.
And new audiences and new technology are the two kind of places we can look to innovate.
Underrepresented people have a hard time in our industry.
There are real problems that we can all work together to solve
and be curious about why they're happening and have clear eyes
and look at how they happen and fix them together.
But there is something else that is true,
and I'm sorry to everyone who's not underrepresented to break this news to you.
If you have a unique perspective that has not been explored by the industry yet,
and if you manage to build a degree of expertise by going through a lot of shit,
your ideas are probably more valuable than those of your peers.
Because you are the one who's going to do something that is new and opening up a new audience.
It's not fair. It's true though.
Okay, so as probably one of those people,
like I've, there's been so many times
where I've been the one, like fill in the blank
whatever you want to say in the meeting room
or in the studio or in my team.
So, and I think that one thing
that we're starting to realize now
is that those people have always been there
and the face of the industry is not your.
Sorry, cis-haired white dudes, but it's not just you.
And so I think it's important to recognise that and to lift those people
up because we've always been here.
And sometimes doing that will mean, actually not sometimes, basically every time you do that,
that means you're challenging an existing norm.
And it can be scary to challenge an existing norm.
So be brave, do those things, like, you know, amplify those people and.
That's, I think, what we need to do to make us all collectively better.
So, yeah, that's what I got.
For me, games have always been about connecting.
Connecting people, connecting ideas.
They're the things that I would hand out to my classmates at recess
because I didn't speak their language well enough,
but we could do that together.
And to me, the industry and then the colleagues and the rest are about connecting.
I think we're always just stronger when we come to understand one another
and understand our similarities and differences.
So that to me is at the heart of this.
It's at the heart of what we do.
So, you know, I guess I'd just say go out there and go do that.
Another point?
Yeah, if you...
We've got time.
Oh, we've got...
Okay.
Three more minutes.
I did want to mention something, a thought that I had before.
Not an ending statement, but as a clarification.
I was very privileged throughout my career.
I was given a lot of opportunities and I was able to fill them and get these jobs.
I wasn't implying that all you have to do is work hard and things will be showered your
way.
Everyone's situation is different.
What I was implying is that nothing is stopping you from acquiring skills.
You don't need to have that.
If, sorry, you don't need, there are no barriers to acquiring the skills if you know where
to look.
So reach out if you're, damn, that is a terrible thing to say because it's absolutely not true.
Can I reset and start over?
Got it.
You're not what you studied.
assuming that you even had the privilege to study.
You have a lot of potential.
However, not everyone's privilege is equal.
So be mindful of that and keep just trying
to push a little bit more.
That's it, thank you.
Can I add one more thing to that?
The most inspiring advice anyone ever gave me
in my career was when I said that because,
like I was complaining to a friend that,
someone was getting ahead who didn't deserve it and I saw someone else who really deserved it
but who was a woman not getting ahead and I said that she will get ahead in the end,
like in the end it will catch up to him and my friend said to me like no it won't, he will fail
up and he will fail up and up and up and you need to set different targets to compare and like.
My life is really easy. My life has been really easy. My career in the games industry has been pretty easy compared to everyone else who I graduated with.
So when I compare my opportunities to the guys that I work with, I get frustrated. But when I compare my opportunities to like many other people I know, I realize how easy it has been.
And it has to be about something like it's about can I achieve what I want to achieve and what I'm capable of in a realistic framework of what's possible.
Okay, we're coming up on 59.8 on my clock here, so I guess we don't have time for questions
from the audience, even though we would love them.
I'm trying to see any time if there's any police here.
Oh no.
OK, so let's wrap this up.
Thank you so much for coming.
If you do want to grade this or give us some kind of
feedback on the website, I'm not fully sure how that works.
Please remember that Tom Hall and Nicole Lewis, who had to
be yanked out of here on very short notice, will get tagged
if you do that.
Give us any.
bad feedback. So please give feedback, but be mindful so we don't splash our stuff on
other people. Thank you so much.