Hi, everyone. Welcome to our GDC panel.
I am so excited for what you're going to see today.
My name is Nika Noor.
I'm the executive director
of the International Game Developers Association Foundation.
We exclusively work on increasing representation
and diversifying the video game workforce.
We really believe in making sure that every person
who wants to make or play games deserves a chance to do so.
And today, we're going to focus on a really special topic.
We're going to be talking about building pipelines to find, grow, and retain diverse talent.
But enough of that, let's get to our stellar, stellar panelists.
Let's do a round of introductions, starting with Movel.
Hi, I'm Movel, and that's my dog, Poppy, that you can hear in the background.
She's barking outside.
So I joined Unity in October of last year.
So I haven't actually stepped foot in the Unity office yet
because of the pandemic.
I work on the inclusion team.
I head up inclusion for Unity.
We have a small team there.
We focus on lots of different things
which we'll talk about later,
but I'm really enjoying working.
There's a difference for me
because I haven't come from tech,
but inclusion is inclusion wherever you are.
There are nuances depending on the different industries,
but...
Inclusion is primarily about inclusion.
So it's about people at Unity as well.
I'm loving it.
That's me.
Awesome.
Davina, how about you?
Hey, everyone.
I'm Davina Mackey.
I am the Director of Support Services and Operations
for PlayStation Studios QA.
I've been at SIE, Sony Interactive Entertainment,
for over 16 years.
started from the grassroots and I've basically worked my way up. I'm also the president of
Black at PlayStation, which is one of seven affinity groups at SIE and I've been president
for five years. So I'm enjoying, you know, my space, doing DE&I work and supporting
underrepresented communities and we're really doing some interesting
work now at SIE.
And my whole thing is,
if we can make an impact
and make representation of underrepresented people,
black people specifically in my realm,
we can improve the representation in tech
or in the video game industry.
That's where I'm focused.
Awesome.
Trinidad, how are you doing?
Hi everybody, Trinidad here.
I'm the head of diversity and inclusion at Niantic.
I am passionate about people.
I'm passionate about policy
and I'm passionate about impact.
And so my mantra in life is stay ready,
don't have to get ready.
So I'm always ready and I'm always ready to educate,
empower and utilize my genius
to help people understand why.
All of this that we're about to talk about is imperative,
not only to the business, but just to us being better humans.
That's awesome.
Well, let's dig into it.
Let's see how we're actually developing
the actions and pipelines behind these great thoughts.
Davina, do you mind sharing some of the initiatives
you're working on at your company?
Yeah, so we've had a very impactful year, I should say, and I would say prior to the pandemic,
we were stuck in culture awareness, you know, we really didn't have strategy.
We have a new leader in DE&I, her name is Tiffany Hester. She's an amazing individual that
introduced strategy in the
E-net space is what we call it at SIE.
And so that happened.
So we had new D&I leadership
and we also had the John Platt,
who is the CEO and president of Sony ATV,
which is our music licensing division.
He had the...
the guts to go to our Sony leadership and ask them to support social justice
for underrepresented communities, specifically the Black community.
And they allowed for him to put together a $100 million donation
that Sony specifically is supporting social justice initiatives.
And each division within Sony was able to partake in that $100 million.
So each of us got a piece.
So PlayStation received, you know, a pot and we split it with our UK counterpart.
So there's a portion going to the US and a portion going to the UK.
And from that, we've built relationships with several organizations that promote social justice initiatives.
I can only tell you the few that have been announced so far.
So, for example, Gameheads, which is in the Bay Area, we're supporting them.
Black in Gaming, which is a part of the IDGA Foundation.
Black Girls Code and Hidden Genius Project, which is.
is for men. So a million dollars was donated to them from SIE, specifically those four organizations.
There are three other organizations that we're working with. One I can announce, which is the
Black Collegiate Game Association, and that organization has a network of 16 HBCU universities,
are historically black colleges and universities.
we're doing all sorts of great programming with them. They have a scholarship that falls under
our PlayStation Career Pathways, which is what we've developed based on the social justice
initiatives that we're doing. And so BCGA has a scholarship program where they support students
that are upperclassmen with hardships and finances. And so we're
working to make sure that our Black students are able to actually graduate. We were told that
some of them will drop out of school for as little as $2,500, $5,000. And so if PlayStation
can support those students in making sure that they complete their education, to me that's a,
we're in the, going towards the right direction. The next part for us is internships because we
want to.
improve the channels that we're reaching in talent acquisition.
And so we're working with several organizations to build programs that will allow us to bring
in students from HBCUs specifically.
We've never, like SIE has never tapped into HBCUs as a TA channel for resources, our recruits.
And so
Now we have the opportunity to bridge that gap,
bring in new talent from HBCUs,
and hopefully land them a position and career
in the video game industry, specifically at PlayStation.
That's awesome. I love that level of investment. Wow. If you told me three years ago today that
this was the future, I wouldn't have believed you. So I love it. I love where I can say this. Maybe
you can't say it, but I love it when companies put their money where their mouth is. Fantastic.
Thank you so much. Trinidad.
I know you have been working relentlessly, tirelessly, sleeplessly on driving impact at Niantic.
You do so many things. Mind shedding some light with our audience on maybe your current role and your current initiatives?
I'll piggyback off Davina on the GameHeads tip because we also are supportive of GameHeads
and we just launched a certificate class with Cal State USMB, Cal State East Bay, not USMB,
Cal State East Bay, and in partnership with Unity and Oculus, and it's a certificate program
around, well,
Unity, VR, and AR. And so it's just the beginning and we're excited because the goal,
the long-term goal, is to find ways to infiltrate colleges, HBCUs, local communities that don't
have access to possible this AR, VR gaming space, even just the tech that's going out.
finding ways to get people just a taste for it, a desire for it, getting it in front of them.
And so the beauty of Gameheads is that they have a program where they can teach youth and young
adults from a thought inception all the way to getting it on a platform on how to navigate
this game industry. They have, they have.
something that actually works, right? A lot of their students are at USC. A lot of their students
are interning at some of our companies and working with us. And so how do we get that in front of
HBCUs? How do we get that in the South, in the Carolinas? How do we get that in Detroit? And
so these are ideas and the vision that we have. So this is the first step.
step number one. We also are, last year we hosted a program called the Treehouse Apprenticeship
Program where we are creating an unconventional pipeline of boot camp talent and Treehouse has
pivoted so now we are pivoting to find a new partner to continue this program because last
year was successful. We hired seven people from this unconventional background, never worked in
tech before in QA and in UX.
I mentioned earlier, I like changing policy.
It's not sexy, it's not something that on a GDC panel,
people are gonna be like, ooh, that's so cool.
But we are actually changing how we track
our marginalized ethnicities and genders.
that there is a broken system of the EEOC
that the US requires.
And it's broken because two or more races
could be white and Asian.
And in tech, white and Asian is a majority.
So like that's even misrepresenting data.
And so for me, I want the data to be as pure as possible
because then we can make the right decisions
based on the communities that we have within our company.
I also believe that we're looking at salaries, reassessing where people are to make sure
that there's no pay disparities.
These are things that like, again, not sexy, but matter.
Right? And so I like to do a combination of both low-hanging fruit and high-hanging fruit.
I like them to both because low-hanging fruit is fast, easy, we get short winds, people are excited, they go,
woohoo! And then the high-hanging fruit, which takes like three to five years, you know, it's like,
ugh, are we done yet? But no, but we have these small winds. And so I do think that
There's a lot around our Black Developer Initiative that's hot, it's new, but it's also not easy.
Let's talk about it. You know, at Niantic, we are an AR platform company. We focus on augmented reality,
we focus on mobile games, but we really want to be the platform of the future for augmented reality.
How many black augmented reality developers do y'all know?
I'm pretty sure it's like the 2% of the 2%,
but they're out there.
And so we're really trying to get awareness
around the fact that we wanna empower,
but building a program to be equitable
in a space that has for years been unequitable
is one where.
it's taken us time. We made the commitment in June of last year and it took us six months just to
really make sure and inform this development program to make sure that we're proud of it.
And so we launched it in February this year. We're on to our second cohort right now. We just
announced who our second cohort is and we're recruiting for our next cohort. So I mean,
these are little things that we're doing, but at the end of the day,
We're just scratching the surface.
We're not going to reverse 300 years of systemic racism
overnight, actually 400 years.
So how do we go about making sure
that not only our leaders are accountable and committed,
making sure that we're still engaging our communities
and our partnerships externally and in our backyard,
but then also building a culture that's of inclusion,
where people can bring their genius to work.
So.
These are all things that are toiling into my mind every day as I'm, I'm, I wake up, you know,
I'm not a coder and no offense to y'all coders, but like, I can't just like close the laptop
and stop thinking about this. This is, this is a long-term of thing that I hope I get to see
some in my lifetime, but I'm not banking on it.
Thank you. Thank you so much Trinidad.
And thank you for thinking about this even after five.
I think that's the tenacity that's important
to keep the spirit going.
Now, Mavel.
people talk about diversity initiatives
and kind of refer to them, especially in bigger companies,
almost as if they're US-centric structures.
But that's not true,
because you're dealing with a whole other region of the world
and a company that's doing it across multiple continents.
Talk to us a little bit about your experiences
and what you're working on over at Unity.
Yeah, I mean, the thing is,
We have pretty much the same kind of issues in the UK and in the EMEA region,
which is obviously Europe, Middle East and Africa. But I focus predominantly on the kind
of European side of things, so UK, France, Germany, Finland, places like that, where we have offices.
But it's really a tricky situation trying to deal with inclusion and diversity in Europe,
because a lot of the legislation prevents people from even measuring diversity.
and inclusion in some countries in Europe is actually illegal to gather data about people's
ethnicity, for instance, or whether their sexual orientation. So it becomes really difficult to
gauge where you should focus, right? Because we know that what gets measured gets done. And if
you can't measure something, it's really hard to kind of figure out where you should be focused.
However...
what we've decided to do at Unity is to kind of focus on where we can focus.
So we're able to gather data in the Emei region on gender. We're not able to gather any information
on ethnicity, but we're able to gather that data on gender. So we focus our efforts primarily
on gender, but that doesn't mean we don't focus on other areas. We just can't do it in a very
shall I say in your face or explicit kind of way because we can get ourselves into trouble for
doing that. But we do realise that there is still issues within countries in Europe as it pertains
to ethnicity and other what we call in the UK protected characteristics which are you know
things like LGBT status, religion, socio-economic status. So there's all those things that we do
focus on we just can't necessarily measure them.
So some of the things that we're doing in Unity on a global level is looking at,
and Trinidad mentioned it before, is looking at our data.
So we're taking a very data-based approach to pay equity, recruiting, retention,
and promotion at all levels, because we recognize that these are things
that we can control, because we have our own data.
Right, so that's one of the things we're focusing on.
We're also looking at introducing targets.
They include hiring retention targets.
to increase representation of women across all unity offices, so that's across APAC, EMEA and the US,
and also looking at increasing that representation at Black and Latinx level in the US.
And then some of the other things we're looking at is making sure that all of our leadership are
able to kind of deal with some of these issues, right, because a lot of the times
leadership want to be helpful but they don't necessarily understand the issues.
So we've just spent the last six months embarked on a leadership training course.
We brought in an external provider to look at how leaders at director level and above can understand race and inclusion in the workplace.
And we're kind of making sure that we're embedding those practices.
We've just finished the training.
So we're now completing plans for each leader to have targets on how they're going to embed their learning.
And then of course, we're doing things,
some of the similar things that Davina
and Trinidad have been doing.
So we're partnering with, I think,
nearly two dozen community organizations and nonprofits.
Some of those, most of those are in the US,
but we've just recently started partnering
with some in the UK.
So we've got the Black Tech Sales Network here.
And then we're also partnering with people like
Nolevate Black, Blacks in Gaming, Queer Tech,
all the other standard ones that you would see
across the US.
And then we're also doing a number of recruiting initiatives.
We attend five major recruiting conferences per year.
And then we do specific targeted recruiting exercises
with each of the directors.
So where they want to increase their representation,
we actually sit and focus our attentions
on how they can do that.
So we're recruiting specifically for under-representation
and making sure we're increasing that within our leadership.
So we're doing a number of things and we're trying to make sure that approach is consistent from US to APAC to EMEA.
But as I said, it's slightly challenging sometimes when we can't kind of gather that data.
But we're still making sure we're focusing on those things because the issues are the same wherever they are.
I said at the beginning that my background isn't in tech, my background's in inclusion.
I've been doing this work for 20 years and the issues are the same from industry to industry.
So we're just making sure that we're focusing on people.
and trying to do what we can to improve the experience of everybody that works within Unity.
Fantastic. Thank you so much.
Look, because we have such an incredible panel here,
I would like to pivot to an important topic.
We talk about...
targeting recruitment data, making sure that we've got, you know, this representation there
and that they are well served from, you know, an earlier point of someone's career. We've all been
there. We were all bright eyed, bushy tail, let's go get it done. Rah, rah, rule the world.
And sometimes the world kicks us in the back of our knees.
And this industry is quite relentless, not even just to marginalize folks, but it can be quite
unforgiving and relentless. The average turnover rate of a gaming professional,
according to the IGDA Developer Satisfaction Survey, is two to five years.
And at least from the IGDA Foundation side, every year we award and support 100 different types of
scholarships and recipients that we walk through. And time and time again, especially people who've
been in the industry for a while, we are seeing underrepresented talent face severe imposter
syndrome.
feelings that they don't belong,
that they weren't meant to be leaders,
that they can't be promoted
or that they shouldn't shoot for the moon
and become a vice president, et cetera.
Ladies, how do we tackle retention?
Not just at the company level, but on an industry level.
How do we keep these awesome people
that we are investing time, money, research into
into this industry because it is such a shame. It is such a shame to see diverse talent leave.
Trinidad, why don't you kick us off?
It starts with a people-first mentality within management. And I like to call managers the
frozen chosen. They're hit from both sides. They're hit from
executive leaders, giving them direction, objectives,
and then you have individual contributors who you manage,
who have their concerns, and depending on the company
and how they communicate and how transparent they are,
you're stuck, you're stuck in the middle.
I do think that a lot of companies need to invest more time,
more education, more empowerment to their managers.
educating them on how to be an inclusive leader,
how to inclusive hire, also...
empowering them with opportunities for stretch goals,
to show their leadership skills and be developed.
Another thing I would say is,
it starts at the executive leadership level.
If you really do believe in this DEI journey
or DEIB journey, DEI-EB,
like, I mean, we can add acronyms to that as well.
you have to show it at your leadership level. I mean your board, I mean your executive leaders,
do they look like the communities that you're trying to attract? And if they don't, that's a
hard miss in my opinion. Leadership is not something that, leadership in gaming.
The work so particular, oh, we need 20 plus years of experience.
Uh, we have a mobile on, on our call who didn't come from the game industry.
I didn't come from the game industry.
I'm a leader, Movel's a leader.
And like, I truly believe that at the executive level,
all you need to do is give them a little bootcamp,
have them meet some industry professionals
and pillars within the industry.
And they too can be an industry professional and leader.
And I think that's just a nuance.
It's something that we wanna do just because we can.
And I think it's a blocker.
I also believe that we have to start looking at the way
that we...
recruit. I also think that we're sort of happy with only a certain schools, you know, we recruit
like we have, there's just there's a lot of opportunity here and if these companies really
want to put their money where their mouth is, which all of them seem like they're doing,
we need to start pouring into some of these colleges.
that are less represented in this space and offer them opportunities to create a program,
create a school pipeline, also empowering more programs like GameHeads.
doing you know partnering we say that we all partner with black and gaming and
Latinx and gaming and gay gaming professionals
how are we uh keeping the companies that partner with these organizations
accountable to actually hiring the talent from these organizations
because we can run all these uh
career fairs, and they're not really, they're a waste of most people's time if you don't have
recs in hand and you're not willing to interview people on the spot, or at least get some type of
schedule where you're like, boom, we're committed to interviewing,
to getting to the second round, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
You know, and so I just truly believe that there's a lot of performative stuff happening in our industry.
I do believe we have some great DEI leaders.
We have some great DEI practitioners, Davina, great DEI.
affinity group leaders, like, have been in this space for so long, and it's unfortunate
that only the resilient last. And the thing is, and that's not, that should not be the case,
you know, and that's the problem, right? People ask me,
How has your last couple of years been? I was like, yo, I felt like I've been in a boot camp.
I've been in the game industry only three years and it feels like 15, you know, and
Davina, God bless you. You know, I'm not sure how long you've been, you know, able to endure.
And obviously Sony's taking care of you, right? Like, so if you find a good place,
then you could flower and foster and grow more power to you.
But what do we do about those bad managers? Because people leave these managers, not necessarily these companies.
I think all of the companies that are on these panels are dope.
But I don't think all of our managers are prepared to manage people who don't look like them or may not represent what they represent.
So why are we not focusing on our management styles and how we empower our culture, and we're focused more on a pipeline?
you know, your pipeline is trash if the manager who the person who is coming in through the pipeline
doesn't understand how to work with them, empower them, see them, give feedback.
Announcement feedback is not a dirty word.
And guess what? Anybody who's listening to this, if you are a manager and you manage a Black,
Brown, marginalized gender or ethnicity person,
You better give them feedback because if you don't,
you're telling me that you really don't care
about their growth and empowerment at your company, period.
That's a systemic crack.
White and Asian people don't like
giving black people feedback.
Are you scared?
You think we're gonna yell at you?
Come on.
You give your buddy a feedback at the bar with a beer.
Like give me the same due diligence and give me feedback.
That tells me, and yes, I might not like your feedback, so oh well, my best professors in college.
ran me into the ground with feedback.
And I was just like, at a young age, I didn't understand.
I was like, I just hate this professor.
But that's the class that I learned the most from.
My old bosses who, one was a Jamaican woman,
God bless her soul, you know who you are.
Like, she would just run me.
Like, you need to, and she was a chief diversity officer.
That was my bootcamp.
She cared about me enough to tell me,
Trin, if you don't change your ways here, here, here, here,
you're not going to make it.
And look where I'm at today.
Because she gave me feedback.
And I'm telling you right now, I've had more bosses than none
give me no feedback whatsoever.
They're, oh, you're doing great.
And then you realize.
I mean I'm still here, you haven't fired me, but I need to grow, I need to develop,
tell me what I'm doing wrong. I know I'm not doing everything perfectly. So I'll pause there
because I think that those are things that companies overlook because they just want
to focus on a pipeline, but not focus on
the rotten apple that is rotting and creating a stench. And you're like, hmm, why does nobody
want to work for this manager? Or why does nobody want to work in this organization?
I mean, if I take a magnifying glass, I could probably figure it out.
Incredible.
Davina, from Trash Pipelines to Feedback,
I know you've been at PlayStation for quite a long time.
You are one of those early, early, I don't know,
maybe not that early, maybe Trinidad's right.
You know, we're living in dog years.
You know, what are you, what do you think here?
Are you just resilient?
I would say I'm an outlier.
I used to call myself a pink unicorn.
I'm now a white unicorn because PlayStation has like,
five Black directors, two of which that are senior directors, right? So specifically at Black at
PlayStation and SIE in general, they are making changes and our leader, I love our leader,
Jim Ryan, he has come in and he has made some instrumental impacts that has allowed us to do
a lot in DE&I. First, he understood the need for DE&I and he brought
a very strategic and seasoned individual with Tiffany Hester.
And what we've been able to do, and he's also changed HR, so now we have Orit, who is very
instrumental and knowledgeable about, you know, just the talent that we bring in.
So,
Trina, you mentioned so many key things. One of the first things that
PlayStation has done is they've changed their performance management tool.
and framework, and it includes cultural leadership values.
And within cultural leadership values,
which now is not just about what you do
and your goals that you accomplish,
it's about how you do it,
but within that is embedded DE&I.
And so we specifically can carve goals out
within DE&I space.
So I can talk about being a Black at,
the Black at PlayStation president within my goals.
And my manager is now,
understanding that because it's a part of the goals for SIE, and he is going to rate me on
doing that job. So hands down, that has been a big change in making sure that, you know,
how we execute, how we treat our employees who are underserved, you know, all of the things that
is needed is there. DE&I has been an impact as well because what we understood is...
is there is a gatekeeper, there is filtering in talent acquisition. We all know this. And Merveille,
you mentioned data and Trinidad, you also mentioned this as well. You know, we have
all sorts of data in the gaming industry about women, so gender is there. We know, you know,
you know, we know demographics on other areas, but you really don't see much in race or they don't.
allow us to make it public, right? And so, like, I did a presentation that showed that, you know,
nationwide, the Black representation in the U.S. is about between 5 and 7 percent,
Black representation in tech. When you come to Silicon Valley, though, that decreases down to 2.5
percent.
right? So that's like half of the, you know, representation and nationwide.
But when you go to the universities, you'll see like Stanford, if you look at the engineering
program there, they're about 5% Black representation. So there's this mis-under,
there's this misnomer that, you know, there's not enough Black talent, for example, in the pipeline,
but that's not true. There are gatekeepers, these managers that Trinidad has talked about.
that have unconscious bias.
And, you know, I think that's a new fancy word.
Let's just say what it is, is prejudice, right?
And the companies are not doing a great job
at providing training and holding them accountable
for being prejudice, point blank.
And they're keeping talent out of the pipeline, period.
Or if we do get into the pipeline, again, I say that I am an outlier because I came from the grassroots.
I was a project coordinator when I started at Sony, at SIE.
And because I had great managers like Dave Moran, shout out to him, and he allowed for me to grow.
I also took accountability for my career and was able to level up.
And you know, they also pay for my education. So I didn't have my undergrad when I started and
Sony paid for it. And then I went back for a master's degree, Sony paid for that.
And I promoted each time. So I'm an outlier. So I won't say that there are many like me.
However, I think that there are programs that we're putting together within DE&I space that
is allowing us to do a couple of extra things because
I believe we, as an underrepresented community,
have to take responsibility as well.
So we are looking at providing awareness
that there are opportunities in the video game industry,
starting in middle school.
Because if you tap into middle school kids
and let them know the talents that they have
in computer science skills, or even the arts,
so music and, you know,
visual arts, like, you know, creative drawing and all those type of skills that they can get can
translate into a career in the video game industry. So we're under the PlayStation Career Pathways,
we are working with those non-profit organizations through the Social Justice Initiative
to build programming that starts at the middle school level and ensure that we can create pipelines.
that start there. So we're working with schools, we're working with the universities, and then
creating programs within Sony that allow for that talent to come in. Specifically, HBCUs
is our target as well. So creating the pathways, creating the internships.
Sony's internship is a challenge.
Like if you're not at a certain school,
it's pretty much challenging to get in.
So we're creating a separate internship program
that allows for talent within the HBCUs to pipe in.
And those internships are not one set of season.
They basically start as a freshman.
and then come back as a sophomore,
and then they come back as a junior
and come back as a senior,
and they end up with some sort of apprenticeship opportunity
and an actual career at PlayStation.
That to me is impacting the pipeline.
I think the place where we've not targeted yet,
but I think DE&I, Tiffany is in, or Reed are handling this.
is the unconscious bias that we face, making sure that those gatekeepers, we break that down as well.
And we've asked for data. We want to know things like how many Black managers are there,
how many have been promoted, how many are being paid equitably, you know, with their peers. We
want to understand.
when there is the riff, how many are impacted, how many black employees are impacted, and what is the
off-boarding, right? We want to know these things because we know if we understand the metrics, then
we can bridge the gaps, and if you don't have the metrics like Movel says, then you really don't
have really a justification to base what you're doing off of. So, you know, I said a lot, but
I just think that if, you know, 2.7% in tech,
Black representation is bad and it needs to increase.
And if you go into the game industry,
I think it's less than 1% from a survey that IGDA created,
you know, based off of GDC attendance, right?
We have to do better than that.
There's, so when you look at, you know,
underrepresented communities play games.
They hold large markets that need to be tapped into.
And if they are playing your games,
why not make sure that the people have opportunities
to see themselves represented in games correctly,
that people are making the games represent them, right?
I think that it would bring more revenue
to our game companies,
and they just don't realize that yet.
Mouvel, how does Unity tackle retention?
I know that you all focus on what you can focus on.
So how do you focus on retaining talent?
So, I mean, all of the things
that both Trinidad and Givino have said
apply to everyone at Unity also.
And I think the biggest issue is with the gatekeepers
and identifying talent, right?
Because even when we get people in from under,
it's classic and it's not just in tech or in gaming, you get people through the door and then
you don't recognize them as talent so they don't progress right and then that's what happens in
terms of your retention rates they slip because if I'm not progressing and I'm not seen as talent
why would I stick around right so people leave. So what we're focusing on at Unity at the moment
and I'm personally working on this is building a sponsorship program for our underrepresented
and what we're going to have is our senior leaders our senior most leaders
be responsible for sponsoring an individual from an underrepresented group who decides
to nominate themselves, because we're not going to have the gatekeepers nominate who
talent is and who can then have a senior leader sponsor because then we're just going to perpetuate
the same old, same old, right? So you're going to decide that you're talent and you're going
to represent yourself and say, I'm going to nominate myself for this program. And then
you will spend, the program is going to run for about a year, so you'll spend a year being
sponsored by some of our most senior people within the organization.
And we've chosen to focus on sponsorship rather than mentoring,
because mentoring only takes you so far.
Sponsorship allows the senior person to advocate for their talent
when they're not in the room.
And that's not to say they're going to say to you,
say to somebody, give that person a job because they're my sponsee.
It's about saying, hey, you should talk to Trinidad.
She's really talented.
Because we know that when these discussions about who's talented take place,
it's very rare that somebody who's from an underrepresented group is even mentioned.
And that's because the gatekeepers have not put them forward as talent.
They've not been given some of those career-defining opportunities
that would allow them to stand out.
So we have to be explicit about how we manage that.
And that's why we've decided to create a sponsorship programme.
So these people then have that one-to-one key into leadership.
They'll get to see how the business itself operates.
They'll get to mix and mingle with people
who are outside of their management chain
so that they can then see for themselves
what it's like outside of their management chain,
but also those people are exposed to them.
And what we hope will happen there is that
once we've got one cohort through this process
and people can see that talent
does not just look like one thing,
we're hoping then that people start saying, oh okay actually there were some really good people
came through that talent that sponsorship program last time, let's have a look at talent in a
different way. We really want people to start re-examining what talent looks like because if
we don't we're not going to retain people because ultimately no one's going to stay somewhere
they're not growing and I love what Trinidad was saying about feedback because you know again
outside of tech, in tech, people are afraid to give people of color feedback and I don't understand
why that is.
You know, I have a teenage daughter and I used to tell her,
if your teachers are not complaining about your bad behavior,
if you behave badly, it means they don't care.
They actually do not care.
If they're talking to me about your behavior,
that says to me they recognize you as talent
and they want you to do better.
And it's the same in the workplace.
And all of that generic feedback,
you're doing great, means nothing.
It's just, it's the smoke screen
for not telling you what you really think.
Because at the end of the day,
they're going to be high performers who are from underrepresented groups and they're going to be low
performers. But in order for people to progress, they need to know that they're a low performer so
they can improve, right? And that's part of how you retain people. You give them that constructive
feedback that is not always favorable, but they're able to understand this is where I need to grow.
So we're really focusing in on that aspect of things. So we're taking the top down and the
bottom up approach, but then also the training I mentioned before for our senior leaders and
directors and above. We're expecting them to take what they learned.
and start helping that trickle down
into the management chains.
And that's why we're gonna be working with them
on an implementation plan as to how they then take
some of that knowledge that they acquired
and pass it on to the gatekeepers
so that they can actually start fixing
some of those issues that occur
where we've got some of those bad managers
who have unconscious bias or just racist tendencies
or sexist tendencies.
Because what we start doing is focusing on those people
and giving them the tools to do better when they don't.
you then have the reason and the rationale for saying,
it's time for you to leave this company.
So that's where we're focused at the moment.
Fantastic, and thanks so much for that.
Do you mind, Movel, actually kicking us off
with our last question as we wrap here?
I'd love for every panelist, starting with Movel,
to kick us off with, what piece of advice do you have
for the next generation of talent,
for the many yous who are watching this and going,
I wanna be them, I wanna do that.
You know, what are we telling folks these days?
At least what would you tell them?
Do you know, I will tell people what I tell my daughter,
which is you can do anything you want to do,
but there's gonna be people who try to obstruct you.
And so.
For me, it's not about trying to get a seat at the table if no one wants you to be there.
You make your own damn table. Or you burst the doors down and tell people,
actually, I'm talented. But it starts with you believing in yourself.
And so it goes back to that same feedback conversation. I want to tell teachers to
give feedback to students. If they're not doing things they should be doing, tell them.
If they're talented, recognize that.
and actually showcase that and put it where it belongs.
All too often, children who are talented
from underrepresented groups at schools
don't get told they're talented or we hide their talent
or we have them help other kids out in the classroom
as opposed to saying,
let's create a gifted and talented programme
where we can focus on these kids and get them to shine
and move them through processes sooner
if they're ready for it.
So it starts at that stage.
So I would tell teachers to identify talent.
and actually focus on it and give feedback where someone isn't performing to their best abilities.
And then talk to those individuals and tell them, you know, hear what people are saying to you.
Don't shy away from feedback and criticism. Ask for it. If it's not being given to you, ask for it.
Because you know, deep down, you know if you're not doing a good job.
right? And so sometimes we sit back and we want to be told,
yeah, you're doing an okay job and we accept that. And then we complain that
actually we're not progressing. But if you know you're not doing a good
job, ask for that feedback and ask for very specific feedback also. So people
will say, you're doing fine. Okay, well what does
that mean? How am I doing fine? And if I'm doing fine, how can I improve?
When I used to go with my daughter to her
parents evenings, is what we call them here, where you had a chance to speak to
teachers. They would always say, she's doing great.
and I would have a little pen and paper and say, okay, great, how can she improve on that? Great.
What else can she be doing? And I expect people to be asking those questions for themselves.
We have to take responsibility for our own development, especially if people don't want
to help us with that. So that's what I would tell people is take your development seriously,
advocate for yourself. It's not always easy, but if it's not easy for you, get yourself a mentor,
get yourself a sponsor, get someone to speak for you, because that's important also. And it's fine
at Unity, we're creating that program,
but there's absolutely nothing wrong with individuals
going and speaking to a senior person and saying,
I like the way you work.
Trinidad, I love how you speak.
I love what you stand for.
Would you mind mentoring me?
So, you know, don't sit back and wait to be told what to do.
Take your career into your own hands.
That's what I would tell people.
Fantastic. Thank you.
Davina, piece of advice.
I would say take accountability for your career first.
And if you want to get into the game industry,
make sure you're doing things like participating with GDC,
going to E3, and understanding the various organizations that
are in the industry, the various publishers and game
developers, right?
Make sure that your college experience
is specific to the discipline that you
want to get it within because it's
going to give you a higher success rate in getting a job.
Make sure you get an intern and get a mentor as sooner than later, right?
If you have a mentor in your college years and you have people that can sponsor you,
I think that that also levels the playing field for you.
Make sure you take negotiation skills because there's nothing wrong.
I know one of the underrepresented, one of the things we do that we can improve most
is we don't negotiate well enough our salaries.
when we're coming on board to these companies.
So take negotiation skills and don't be afraid
to understand what your value is and ask for it
because you really only have that one chance, right?
And then the other thing is once you get into the company,
understand from an HR perspective
what training opportunities you have.
And make sure you always level up your skills
by making sure you keep abreast of the training that's there
and keep your skills sharpened.
And then, and you need to ask your managers
for one-to-ones on a consistent basis
and understand what the expectations are,
you know, for your specific job.
And if you're touching base on a cadence,
that means that you shouldn't be surprised
at the end of the day.
when you end up with your performance appraisal.
And then you also should be doing
your individual development plan
so that in three to five years,
you know the trajectory of your career.
You know where you wanna go.
And then get those networks
because don't only rely on the people
that you know at your current job.
Black in Gaming is a great network of people from various publishers and development houses
where if you get to know these individuals, you have opportunities elsewhere.
The networks are great.
So that is my advice.
I know that's a lot to chew, but and it's a lot of work.
This is not easy, guys.
You know, if you really want to get into this industry, it's fun.
It's rewarding.
I think, you know, I can't complain.
For 16 plus years, I've been able to do various things
and have a ball.
And, you know, people in my family regard what I do highly.
Like I'm some big shot.
I even got asked for my autograph at the airport
because I had my badge on and I thought that was insane.
But, so there are perks to being at.
some of these companies and it's enjoyable work. So now you know that's my advice and then just
have fun and make sure that you're just you're not working just for a paycheck but you have
substance and it's building you know you personally but also have work-life balance
and that's that's all I'm going to say.
Fantastic, thanks for that. Trinidad, mind closing us out with your last thoughts and piece of advice?
Sure, so my advice is very simple. I think number one is network and I think this is something that
everybody has said on the panel is network, network, network, network. We could put our
names out there, we can say that we're in this industry and that we're here to help.
But I can count on my hand how many people actually take that opportunity and reach out and actually try to network.
Black in gaming is there.
Latinx and gaming, gay gaming professionals,
game devs of color, IGDA, IGDA, IGDAF.
Like, you know, like there's just like,
there's so much that you could essentially just tap into
and say like, hey, I'm interested.
I don't know where to start.
You could start at any of those places.
And it takes being vulnerable and stepping out and saying,
hey, I don't know everything, but I'm interested.
I've never been hit with resistance in this industry.
You may not get a response right away.
You may not even get a response, but you will get one.
And so for me, I think that's something that's overlooked.
And yes, if you're an introvert,
I understand there are ways that you can write a great email
that catches someone's attention.
There are ways that you could send a LinkedIn message,
you know, that is captivating.
Use your genius. Use your gifts. And then also, once you network, offer them something.
Is there anything I can do to help? Is there a volunteer opportunity? Is there...
I find that sometimes it's even hard for me to be like,
that's a good question.
And that makes me wanna come back with like,
all right, here you go, here's an opportunity,
here's an idea, I want you to do this.
And so another thing is when anybody meets with me
for like an introductory or one-on-one,
I give them assignments and I'll see how serious you are
if you actually come back with the assignments.
And those assignments are not for me.
Those assignments are for you.
So understanding exactly, like taking the time
to maybe not have it correct in the sense of like,
you know what the future holds,
but actually like be like, hey, I have some ideas.
I don't know what my future could hold,
but I'm really interested
and I just wanna get in the industry.
Like, where do I start?
You know, having those conversations
and then being open, open to feedback.
Because one thing I know is,
at least on this panel, we all give feedback.
And we all give feedback because we care.
And I can't say that I've, you know,
this generation behind me,
I wanna work for some of y'all, y'all are so smart.
But it's also like, if I'm coming to you with feedback,
listen, I'm not hating, I'm not hating on you.
I want you to succeed.
I want you to make it in this space.
And it takes the Davinas, the Movels, the Nikas
who've been here longer.
who can come in and give you that feedback in a way that because they understand the scope and they understand the journey.
So I think those two things are being able to network, being able to tap into the resources that are already out there.
I'm pretty sure.
You can rerun this and you can listen and you can hear these things and you can Google search all of those things that we mentioned game heads, black and gaming, all these organizations in the UK there's Code Coven, there's a bunch of, you know, organizations out there. So how do we tap in? You have to do your work.
And then at the end of the day, you're like, dang it,
I forgot everything that was just said.
Hit up Nika, hit up Davina, hit up Jovel, hit up myself
and be like, hey, I'm really interested
but I just don't know where to start.
Go for it.
Awesome. Well, thank you to everyone.
And thank you to our lovely panelists.
Special thanks to GDC for creating the space
for us to have these collaborative discussions.
I really, really support Davina, Trinidad and Movel.
Look them up on LinkedIn and Twitter.
They're doing some of the most important work
out there in the industry today.
They are building out the future for folks,
for your studios, for your talent.
And sincerely.
What an incredible discussion.
What a powerhouse of women leading the way.
I cannot wait to see what everyone does next.