So it's been 17 years since Doom was released.
It's kind of funny that we've never done a post-mortem anywhere on this game.
Which is kind of crazy. But now we're here to do it.
And so what we're going to do
is kind of go through the development of the game on a month-by-month basis.
We're actually going to start
about a year before we started on Doom to kind of
foreshadow some things in the future.
Okay. There's a little bit of volume. Um. Okay, so we'll start
in December of 1991. Uh. Actually, yeah, okay, so.
Actually it wasn't December, was it? It was like.
Anyway. It's like.
As far as you know, this is December 1991.
It's August 1991. And, uh, we moved id software to Madison,
Wisconsin.
Where I went to college.
and we went, we visited in the mid, mid-summer,
and the place was great, just like that picture there,
it was awesome, lush, green, everyone having fun.
So then we just, we moved the whole company,
which was only four people at that time.
And then when we got there, you know,
that's kind of what happened to us.
And so we couldn't even go outside anymore.
We had to kind of stay inside.
So, we were working on Commander Keen at that time, and during that, you know, last half
of 1991, we basically saw that there was this computer called the Next Computer that was
created by Steve Jobs' company, and it looked really, really interesting.
It was an amazing workstation, and we basically, during December, kind of finished Commander
Keen.
And we went on our, like, two-week vacation.
But John Carmack didn't go on vacation.
He's going to stay and program, especially if he
wanted to program a NeXT computer.
So he ordered a NeXT computer COD, but he didn't have a car.
And it's snowing and freezing.
So that's John going through the snow to the bank
to get the money for COD.
So when the guy shows up, he can pay him the $11,000
and then.
we finally got our next computer.
And that was in December of 1991.
We start working on Wolfenstein 3D,
and we really just kind of messing around with the next.
It wasn't until the summer, like half a year later,
we actually used the next computer
to do the hint manual for Wolfenstein
and some Commander Keen brochures.
Yeah, it was worth a lot there for us.
We were planning on using it later.
It turned out to be a very important computer for our
company. So right after Wolfenstein shipped, we were
contacted by a company named Imagineer and they wanted a
Super Nintendo version of Wolfenstein. And so we were very
excited about getting our game on a console. And so we hired a
guy to start working on a contract because we've got other
games that we've got to make.
All right. So now it's November of 1992. And we had a year
previous to this, November of 1991, actually shipped our, I
think it was our third, third FPS. It was our first texture
map game called Catacomb 3D. And so it shipped a year before this
time. But after this point, we decided that we're going to make
another FPS.
And surprisingly, to some people,
surprisingly, Doom was actually the fifth id software FPS.
Those are the other games that we had done that were shooters.
Originally, Hover Tank 1 was just colored walls
that you kind of drove your tank through.
And at that time, it was kind of a harsh, creative environment
to make an environment come alive.
And so I would put a green cube, and that's a tree.
essentially in my mind, you know. And, uh, Catacombs 3D actually had textures on the
walls and that gave it a lot more sense of space and a lot more fun, and you can cast
your magic spells and blow things apart and stuff. And then the others you probably know.
Spirit of Destiny is a sequel to Wolfenstein, by the way. Um, so, we basically start working
on, uh, some of the tools for the next FDS, for, start working on Doom. Um,
programmers in the audience might recognize the acronym WAD, which stands for Where's All the Data?
That's actually made after the fact. We were in a cheap apartment called La Prada,
and Carmack was downstairs working on stuff, and we had used LUMPS in the previous games and stuff.
And I was working upstairs doing the Doom Bible, and he called up and said,
I need an extension, like, what's a bunch of LUMPS? And I said, WAD?
Or someone said, yeah, that works.
OK.
A lot of lumps.
So a lot of people started using that.
And then the Lucasarts or the?
Yeah, and then Lucas, yeah, Dark Forces later
named their files GOBS.
So everyone was kind of coming up with another three-letter
extension.
Yeah.
So after we were in these apartments
and kind of putting together the file formats for Doom,
it then finally moves to the Black Cube in Mesquite,
which was just down the street from the apartment complex.
And thank you Google for providing a picture of Tony's
Tower, which there is no other one on the internet.
Yeah.
So we basically start thinking about what is Doom going to be?
What is this next game?
It started with a name.
We played a lot of D&D for years before we
started making Doom.
And so we decided that this was going to be one of our D&D
inspired games.
uh... karmic was really excited to do a game had demons in it
and uh... you know we all agree that we just did not see so
the hands of the middle of the world
that's what else is it
so that i was going to be a little bit
so that will be
tom thompson's tom starts uh...
working on the doom bible right after we move in and then he finished it at the
very end of november of nineteen ninety two
And it was basically a whole kind of a design document for a lot of the game.
A lot of the sketches of like where all the levels are in the game and the names of stuff.
Progressions you go through, lists all the tools, all that kind of stuff.
I mean you can look it up on the internet.
This is kind of part of the beginning of the design doc here to kind of say like what Doom is.
And you know there were a lot of, we were coming up with all these ideas for the technology of the game and like what it's going to be.
And we felt like really sure before making the game what it
probably was going to turn out to be like.
We knew what the technology advances were going to be.
We had an idea that we were going to be doing some dark
subject matter.
It was going to be like not bright halls with Nazis in
them, but like dark, scary hallways.
I call it Scary Dark Fast.
We made a lot of halls because of Tom's last name.
So the theme.
So part of the design was.
you know, Tom wanted to do, like what we'd done in Wolfenstein,
a progression that was like level to level progression.
Yeah, I mean, yeah, like people really expected that from Wolfenstein,
and I think that was not the place to innovate, essentially.
I think that was a really good, I can complete a chunk, you know,
and perhaps frustratingly complete a chunk, but I can, you know, get there,
and boom, I have a success, and that was a good sense of accomplishment
that was very important to this kind of game.
And then...
And then John was thinking about the technology and what he could do with the tech and he was like,
he didn't really, he was starting to lay down some of the basic data structures,
but he also was thinking big.
So John wanted one big world.
He just wanted like one big level.
Everybody's going to run around the level.
You could like see through doors and then.
So then it was like, okay, well, okay, it's one big level and we're doing sort of science fiction.
What's the other data there?
Yeah, science fiction with demons and stuff like that.
Well, let's make a big base, you know, and then a lot of places to go and kind of sense of place and so on.
So we start calculating, you know, how much memory are we going to use for this game, because, which they are doing,
while I'm doing about a month of work on this big world and all these things and little nuances and...
and we're like calculating sprite sizes, map sizes.
And there's this cool computer room,
and there's all these tunnels.
And we're like, there's no way that this is going to work.
I mean, we don't have enough memory.
We can barely go above one megabyte.
So we're like, we have a new design.
Do you do new design?
We're going to just kind of do levels.
So that's funny.
I remember something about that a month ago.
Yeah.
So that was not fun.
So Tom was not very happy about that.
I feel something snapping.
Mentally.
You know, like when we were in Wolfenstein,
I had, since it was something that was not
an elegant part of the engine, I had to really, really, really
fight for push walls.
but I was like, you're going to be walking through things,
opening doors, you got to have some secrets.
You know, I'm like, I grew up, you know, playing Mario
and stuff like that.
I want secrets.
And so I really, really fought for football.
It finally got in.
It's exciting.
So that was kind of like snap zero of like, you know,
why am I fighting for something that would make the game so fun?
And then sort of like, what was that month of work that was lost?
But in that sense.
Did you hear that?
In that sense, I mean, Carmack was
trying to get the best technology out there
and what he could, the best way he can innovate.
And I was trying to do the same and just like that kind
of flash heads a bit.
Yes.
So now we'll focus on December.
We're all working.
We know that like half the month is gone for vacations and stuff.
Even though we're doing Doom and it's exciting,
we're still human and everybody should be taking vacation.
Everybody.
everybody. But at Christmas, you know what people go. So
here's a picture of Tom with hair and you know, he's, he's
using. Thanks. Thanks, everybody. I've lost my glasses
while I'm over there. By the way, as advice to any of you,
if you ever invent anything, just go get a patent on it.
Regardless, because copyright, because at this time,
I was at the desk and I was kind of, man, my wrists are kind of sore.
So I had my girlfriend sew this three years before computer wrist pads came out.
And it's kind of always been a long regret of mine, but...
Could have been rich.
Anyway, but...
My wrists were happy.
That's all that's important.
Anyone could see...
Perhaps there's an Altic Lansing speaker on the right.
This is all ancient technology.
But the next computer was actually like a Mac right now.
It's basically the same operating system
that you're using right now with the Mac over it,
with the Mac UI on top of it.
And thanks, Pepsi, for sponsoring this slide.
The nice old calculator, for some reason, is using that.
So then we move to January.
January we were beginning making the game.
And there was a, you know, with us, these games never have
like pre-production where we like draw a bunch of concepts
and then kind of vet things.
You know, when we make something, it goes in the game.
That's just the way it is.
So we immediately start creating the technology
and we start creating the artwork.
And we're very confident that what we're making is going
to be pretty awesome.
And so we put out a press release.
in January as we basically begin making the game, telling the
world how revolutionary the game is going to be. And the press
release had, like, here are the big features that we had at the
end of the press release. And each of these features in the
real press release, which you can, like, Google on the
Internet, has a whole bunch of explanation behind it. And
probably three or four of those didn't even make it into the
game.
Don't do a press release before your game is actually out.
There was a gardening section that just really didn't fit.
Yeah, it was like decades later.
Then we get into February.
That's when we actually start making art.
We were trying to do new things.
So instead of just drawing pixels in deluxe paint
and making the art that way, Adrian,
who was a really amazing pure artist,
he would draw the.
the actual characters. And then we started making them in clay, modeling them in clay.
And we had an X computer that had a video camera that was set up to capture the monsters
as they were put on like a lazy Susan that could rotate eights. We had like a post that
would mark off eights. And so we would take kind of a picture of it and run it through
a program called the
Well, yeah, they said, what's the name?
We're putting stuff in, and separate things are coming out,
like palettes and stuff like that.
I just said, like, Fuzzy Pumper Palette Shop or something.
And that's that.
That was the name of the tool that we
made to take these 16-bit images through a video camera
and palettize them into VGA's 256 colors, the Fuzzy Pumper
Palette Shop.
So Adrian only did a few of these clay models,
and then that was it.
There's no more.
He's not doing that anymore.
Because every time you can animate them, the clay just rips.
Because we had to light them, so when you light clay, then it goes...
Yeah, it was...
It's all over.
It was new and weird, so we kind of stopped doing that.
We basically got the engine up and running pretty quickly,
you know, throughout January and then into just the very beginning of February.
and we took some screenshots uh... and uh... actually we made a bunch of alphas
and stuff while we were making the game and how many of you have actually seen doom alphas?
not that many people
cool so you'll get to see them all those hands will be raised in about two minutes
so we have uh... the first level that uh... that tom was working on
actually got in the game is E2M7
uh... but it was supposed to be like the first level in the game
We had a different UI, and that was the first crate maze ever made in the game.
Thank you.
Yes.
But part of that was basically John was worried about, like, too many polys in the environment,
you know, because he wanted fast, fast, fast, and then really have a blazing fast game.
So I kind of made crate maze and things like that that were more orthogonal and very occlusive,
so it would be fast, faster, and faster.
So we were experimenting with UI.
We had, like, that's Tom's basic UI that he drew himself.
And then the other one, was it?
I'm available for art duties later.
Was there the other UI?
Was it done by Adrian?
The second one is done by Adrian.
No, I think I did most of that.
He did the shell, and I did the text.
OK.
This is my girlfriend's chainsaw.
It's a Macaulay Eager Beaver.
Sitting.
I used to be sitting on one of my arcade machines, but I sold it, so now I'm sitting in my garage.
And if you come over, you can like go like that.
But it's kind of drippy and stuff. It's an old chainsaw. It doesn't work anymore.
So you can see there, there's like a power cable going to the video camera that was used to digitize the actual chainsaw.
And so all the actual weapons that you saw in Doom were just toys that we bought at Toys R Us.
And we just kind of held them in front of the video camera and took a snapshot.
and uh... we only have so many toys and is like three or four
so it is kind of took pieces and kind of slam them together and the likes pain
and kind of edited on the stuff so
but the plasma gun in the bfg are kind of the same the same weapon
uh... below where you are the better are you can do
but
it was fine for that
that's not that actual shotgun
the decoder
the city for the for the cap
We'd actually play with these toys at work.
We were just really busy working.
And at this time, basically, Carmack, you know,
really wanted efficient spaces.
So he says, get books on military stuff.
It's basically, you know, give me cement buildings,
you know, bunkers, very squarish things and so on.
It'll really run fast and be very efficient, you know.
And I was like, okay.
And then went over and looked at various things like this.
that were not very inspiring. Yeah, it's kind of block, you know, it's sort of like that
movie, you know, it's boxy but good. Well, you know, it's not that great. So, so, you
know, so Tom made a bunch of levels that were a bunch of cement blocks basically with some
other textures put on it and they just, they weren't that fun to go into because it was
like corridors with rooms that you kind of go into and, you know, it might make sense
when you're playing a game where, you know, hey, demons have taken over a military base
so.
make it look like a military base and have demons sitting in the rooms but
flow-wise it just was no fun it was bizarro so
so it wasn't that cool but we
actually made a uh...
made a demo our first pre-alpha
of the game
and uh...
that's what we have here hopefully it'll play correctly
the lens flare rendering that we did back then was great yeah lens flare was awesome
over the text
so yes evil unleashed was our subtitle back then
And so this was basically the first level that we made using the data structures we created and
DoomEd which was the tool that I wrote to create the levels and
and you can see the the second gen UI there with like automap in the top right and
And this was the first time the monsters were rotating in the engine
Yeah, and again the interface was made sort of larger show there be less actual screen real estate to render again. It was a
for performance thing is gonna be faster if there's you know like sort of
sixty seventy percent of the screen to render
but it doesn't look that cool when uh... most your screen is taken up with a bunch of UI crap
it's it's kinda like old school like uh... like a game like system shock or something
where it's important to have interface around you because you're physically doing things like that
but here you're just like it's in a raw environment and it doesn't really
yeah I wanna see his head you know so
so um...
so we you know we have the UI there we could actually put a UI in the game see it's not
working too well take it out
And yeah, there were items at this time. You notice on the screen. I believe there's a
Sandwich both a sandwich and a heart of Lothar on the same screen
There were a lot of like the captain's hand was a key to a door
And so there's a lot of esoteric and I more like adventure II kind of things since it was one large world originally. Yep
Let's see, is this the same
Yes March
finally get past February. In March, something interesting happened while we were making
the game. So 20th Century Fox contacted us because we did Wolfenstein, which is a pretty
fast game. And they thought that we would be the right team to make Aliens the game.
And so we already have a technology running.
You know, we're ready to start running with Doom.
And they kind of stop us, because we all love aliens.
Especially Adrian.
Yeah, especially Adrian.
So you know, the shapes of the monsters.
We had Giger books all over the place in the art room.
So the bathroom, you know.
Yeah, totally.
I don't know what that means.
We talked about it for half an hour.
That's about it.
It was like, hey guys, here's a really awesome opportunity.
We talked about it, and we're like.
you know what, I don't want to give up creative control on this game, you know, this could
be something that's like really original, but we do like the idea of running away from,
you know, we were talking about demons already, so it's like, well it'll be kind of, you know,
alien-ish. Sci-fi with demons, that the mix of science and sort of mythos and stuff like
that was one of the true powerful things, the juxtaposition of that. Yeah, if you're
in space you kind of expect fighting aliens, but you don't expect fighting hell, so that
was something we thought was going to be cool.
So we decided, let's not do the aliens attacking the space
marine. Let's do the hell demons attacking the space marine.
That'd be more original. It was back then. Really? So then we
start doing, I'm working on this level, which is the second level
of the game, UNM2, and you can see the horrible, you know, that
wall texture with the brown crap on it, and the red stripe. But I
was like having to explore, like, forget the cement square,
you know, rooms with
the hallways at 90 degrees and stuff.
I wanted shapes that were more interesting.
And you can see these are like real kind of early textures,
but I was trying to make a level that didn't feel realistic,
but you could still kind of identify it as a place
that might be military base,
because you're kind of at a science station on a moon.
So I wanted it to be more interesting to explore.
So that's where I started to play around with.
Lots of contrast in room heights and contrast in lighting.
Because the engine does really great lighting.
In fact, on this slide, the Doom engine did something that I don't know many other engines do.
I think the Build engine did it, but it does what's called diminished lighting,
where the light gets darker automatically through the engine as it tries to render off into the distance.
which means that you have a game that's just automatically scary.
You don't even have to really try, you just kind of just draw some stuff,
make the light a little bit, you know, medium, and it's just dark in the distance.
And you can have like a really bright, a bright light in the background to create silhouettes of stuff.
So the Doom Engine was really amazing for creating scary spaces
because it just made it scary automatically.
And then?
So then I made this room, which I don't think to you guys is very impressive looking,
but back then...
This was the room that really changed the look of the game because this was the, before
all that other stuff that you saw, this was really like the room that showed, hey, we
can have like high ceilings with, you know, banks of computers up, you know, higher than
the player and show like a real, you know, how high can this get?
What kind of scale can I get in this game?
This was almost one of these, we're kind of defining the possible scale of the game and
this is one way that we're doing it through this room.
It's a very important difference in that most games, which is kind of where we started, are doing a very functional
Oh, I could be here in this space. There's a console that I could use kind of thing. Where this was kind of an abstraction or a
different almost the
artistic choice to
to to just elevate and and make things grow and be huge and big and different
And that was like this room is like the start of something like very large that really defined Doom and that was brilliant by John.
Yeah, just the abstract level design instead of trying to be realistic is really what this room started.
And so we basically, everybody loved it. The artists came in and were like, that's it man.
So that's it. The game is, the level design is set.
You know, basically we're going to be doing the abstract stuff.
But then disaster struck.
What happened? We all had to stop working on Doom.
It's so drama-filled, this whole game.
The finale of Days of Our Lives.
The Super Nintendo version that we had gotten a guy to work on
was not finished, and
Imagineer was not pleased.
It had been, you know, since I think the summertime,
so it'd been like about nine months,
and they hadn't heard anything from us, and we're like,
oh, what?
you know, oh, that guy was working on the port. And we
couldn't get a hold of the guy. And like it was, it was, it was,
you know, it was a nightmare situation because we couldn't,
we couldn't get it done basically with somebody else.
And so, and so basically we stopped working on Doom right in
the middle kind of and basically ported Wolfenstein to the
Super Nintendo. And so the whole team jumped on it, artists
jumped on art, you know, just like stop Doom.
I have a programming degree and I've been doing design for a long time, but I pulled
that out and did the bonus screen where all the junk bounces around on the screen at the
end.
Everybody's like, we're not going to help.
We've got to get done with this thing.
We've got to get back on Doom.
We wanted to ship it Christmas, so we all jumped on it and it took us three weeks to
just blast out the port.
and that's including all of the, you know, put rats in there
and green blood and all of that stuff.
For some reason Nintendo didn't like, you know,
like swastikas and Hitler and stuff like that.
So you fought the Statmeister Meisterstat.
Yes.
Of, you know, whatever.
We had to get it out.
So then, you know, we could kind of get back to it.
Work on Doom.
Started again after that three week.
Like, what the hell?
And then.
And then I was working on that E1M2 level and I made this thing
here, which is like a, you know, it looks kind of innocent. It's
this, it's this, these stairs that kind of go down. But the
way that the code was structured, it caused a recursion
problem when John was traversing his sector list internal data
structure. It slowed the game way down because it was looking
into something that had to go in and out of a list.
recursively and the game super started chugging and he liked the way that the game was starting
to look so he wanted to fix the problem instead of hey just draw a bunch of blocks.
Yeah so that was the cool moment there because I was sitting there giving constraints and
said I'll do the best I can with these blockers things and John just said.
hey, this looks cool, screw you, make your tech cool.
Fix the engine, dude.
This is really cool.
That's the great part of the tension
of a team of great people is the ability to do that.
So the way that he was storing the sectors internally
and traversing through them wasn't any kind of rocket
science or anything, but that's kind of why we
hit this problem with this area of the level.
So basically, John had to fix the problem.
And so he started reading up.
And then the BSP tree was born.
This was based off of work by a guy in the audience here.
His name is Bruce Naylor.
And he had researched this for, I
think it was back-based culling off of 3D models.
And John had read a white paper on it and decided, hey,
I could use that into basically that culling algorithm
to cull out non-visible sectors inside of a level.
So.
he adapted that algorithm into the engine,
and it was instantaneous.
You know, super fast.
And that was great.
So John Carmack was impressed about, like,
this looks really cool.
And he could see that, and that's
what led him to technology.
Yeah, and that was great, because the whole industry's
been using BSPs now for a very long time, a couple decades,
I think, since then, almost.
So then we get to April.
We work on another alpha.
We kind of get another alpha out there.
This is like some of the text.
I don't know if you guys can read it,
but this is some of the text out of the readme file
that we always put in all of our deliverables
that we kind of send out.
And these were just sent out to like beta testers
that we've known for years.
So it was just a few people that we sent these to.
But we kind of reached what we felt was an alpha milestone.
So this is-
People called like football.
Pushwall and Fruit Basket.
Yeah, actually, that's the name of some of the testers.
So we're using a DOS extender to take advantage
of 4 megabytes of memory.
So we're not limited to the lower 640k.
And down at the bottom left, you can see the little two dots.
That's kind of our frame rate counter down at the bottom,
since we didn't want to put a big number on the screen.
Hey man, if this gets out, you can all kiss your autographed Doom handbooks goodbye.
So, you can explain the difference.
This room is a little more sort of a story-based thing.
When, like Doom was a great game with sort of, you know, things jumping out at you
and just pure, you know, raw experience, which was brilliant about it.
At this point, my thought about it was, hey, there's, you know, speaking of aliens,
uh...
What Jim Cameron did that was so great is he showed you just at the start of the movie,
there's all these people's transponders in this one place over there.
And your journey is towards that, so you have a deeper and deeper and deeper sense of dread as you head to it.
And so that was the very, very small, simple story I was trying to inject on there,
is just that sense of deeper dread underneath the scary sort of experience.
But as you know, it's kind of boxy right now in this version.
Yeah, this is one of the early boxy, hey, do military boxy room kind of stuff.
And that's why you can see it's...
Yeah, and at the time we had to, you know, we're trying to find a texture style and stuff.
So the silvery cool one was like kind of realistic looking.
It was kind of a really interesting...
More spacey.
Yeah, more spacey and kind of cool and the stone and stuff.
So we kind of stuck with what was okay to do.
This was E1M7.
And, you know, there might be some people out there.
that have played E1M7 a million times. This is like the really
early version of E1M7. So if you play the level a lot, you
totally know where you're at in here, but how different it is
from the actual release game. This is a lot of, still using
these is a limited amount of textures. We didn't have that
many textures back then because we kind of were dumping a lot of
effort into the modeling and the texturing or the characters
having to pixel, you know, basically do pixel editing of
the characters, cleaning up all the frames.
That was a lot of work to clean those guys up.
And it's the weekend here, so none of the demons are there.
Taking some time off.
Knocking one back.
That's the end of E1M2.
That's E1M6.
You can see I was playing around here with actually the,
I did all the programming of everything
that happens in the environment in the game.
So all the flashing lights, the stairs, the platforms,
the switches.
all that stuff I was coding all of that and testing it in my levels. So while I'm making
the levels, I'm testing the functionality of the levels at the same time with cool features
like, hey, it'd be cool if this, you know, there's some lockers. It'd be really cool
if there were some demons in the shower here. That's what that's supposed to be.
You know, you get dirty, you know, killing and maiming and all that stuff. Consigning
souls to hell and all that stuff.
At this point I'm very glad he was doing some of the gameplay stuff right now because sometimes
it's difficult to get gameplay stuff in sort of a technical focused company.
So I really wanted teleporters in the game.
Teleporters were my new push wall.
So I like stole one of Adrian's graphics and I colorized it red and I stole his metal texture
and put bands around it.
here, can you make this teleport to another one of these
somewhere else in the level?
It's like, OK.
So that was awesome.
I was like, I'm free.
I can make it all.
I can go over here and do special rooms and all.
It was nice to be able to do that.
So it was non-snappy.
Yeah.
Yeah, this was basically E1M2.
And I think that's probably the end of that video.
Yeah, we had little signs and stuff in there.
These are real early signs that don't exist in the Finnish game.
It's like programmer art or designer or whatever.
It was programmer art.
Dark Hall.
There's the exit.
Why, why?
Cute.
Yeah, that's basically everyone that was in the company at that time.
The very bottom there.
So it was a pretty small team.
And then we get to May of 1993.
And so we put out another pre-beta. I don't think this is
like maybe a minute. But we're improving the game. We're making
new builds. It's funny that they're not out all over the
place. So it's good to get the video here. So we were like,
this is getting more real. We got a lot more textures in this.
You can see the UI at the bottom is totally changed up. We're
just playing around with new things. We have a font.
Yeah, now there's a menu system.
And so we took some of those little markers on the side
there are kind of taken from Wolfenstein.
But we basically are trying to kind of fill out the menu
system so we can program some stuff in there, some more
functionality so we don't have to put command line parameters
to enable functionality.
We got our skill levels in there because we need to put
stuff in the levels.
Like while we're making the levels, we got to.
be able to put, you know, monsters of varying difficulty in there. So, like, now we're getting
more, you know, just kind of more of the game, more of the game actually going. So, yeah,
you can see they just disappear now, but, hey, you can shoot them. Pop. You can shoot
the, you shoot the demons, they disappear, you know, not fun, but, you know, at least
it's working. And in this, so yeah, I think this was pretty much the whole thing, this
little bitty level.
but it gave us a lot more textures, some shooting, new UI,
menu system, so we're kind of dumping a whole bunch of stuff
in there with just, it was just two of us programming at that
time, just me and John. But the artists are doing a lot of work
redoing, you know, the bullet clips and the armor and, you
know, the artifacts that you pick up, because in the game
you actually were picking up a lot of artifacts, it was
keeping track of items that you picked up, even all the way
until October. So...
eventually decided that that was not gonna be a fun thing to do, picking up all these items.
We're doing that in Wolfenstein, but it wasn't something that kind of fit inside this game.
And there's, I think that's Tom's.
Yeah, you think that? I think Adrian did that, I'm pretty sure.
That sort of speaks sort of to the original One World design being like turned into like map that you go through.
Yes, we were at June.
In June.
I think Jay had talked to Computer Gaming World, which is the really cool magazine back there
for PC games.
And so a guy named Chris Lombardi came out and he did a preview of Doom.
It was a two-pager.
This is just one of them.
And he did a really great job on this preview, sneak peek.
And so they actually, in this issue of CGW, they did two previews.
One was called Companions of Xanth, and one was Doom.
and they got Companions of Xanth on the cover
with a kind of a mention of Doom on it.
So that was really cool that we actually got
ourself mentioned on the cover of a magazine, finally.
The first time that we actually got any kind of press
was I think on the phone after Wolfenstein,
we did like a radio interview with somebody.
And so that was really exciting.
And random.
Yeah, and so it was cool to see, you know,
the first time that Doom was in something,
we're right in the middle of development.
So now July hits.
Yeah, and at this time, you notice Doom has a lot of variety and monsters.
At this time, like a month before, there was nothing flying.
There was a bunch of going, it's going, you know, and shooting stuff at you,
throwing stuff at you, coming and destroying you and stuff like that.
And again, it was sort of a fight to say, you know,
there needs to be something flying. I realize, you know, this is.
fake 3D and stuff, but there needs to be something flying, something that can come down at me,
you know, something that doesn't have to be in the same path that I am, you know, something
that can come up and, you know, scare the crap out of you.
Finally, after a lot of effort, then finally we got the flying skulls and things like that.
But it was kind of a fight, you know.
And that kind of led to...
another little snap in my happiness, like trying to, you know, this should be obvious,
you know, why can't we just, you know, do this and that's cool.
Anyways, so, at that time, there's like Id and there's me and there's a circle of, you
know, people having fun and really loving what they do and talking to each other and
I'm kind of like isolated and alone like the sad clown.
So yeah, Tom wanted more creativity.
Things were getting optimized out of the design.
And so we kind of felt that Tom's vision was kind of too
much for what we were trying to boil the game down to, which
is pure speed, DMs, keys, doors.
Since it's scary dark fast, things like I wanted were
like environment dangers, things that were different
from a bunch of hallways and green slime and stuff like
that, and in the end, it's just like, well, it's difficult
to be.
the thing was a pure thing and it's difficult to be on the fifth version of the same thing
and seems they've done a few more of those
uh... that you just want to know get your creative yayas out and uh...
he was kind of ahead of the design game where we're trying to
yeah considering I was making trees out of like green blocks
I was kind of like uh... you know I was ready to explode
so
So then we get to August, and so then Tom leaves.
We depart.
We parted ways, and we had a meeting and just parted ways.
And after the meeting, I felt a deep sense of relief,
because this thing has just been eating at me,
and been unhappy, and not getting my creative juices out.
And that led me to the realization
that.
all like all of us wanted was creative happiness. Creative happiness always wins and it will
make things sort out. So Carmack wanted creative, his technical creative happiness and to do what
he wanted to do. John had thought in creative happiness, you know, he's getting to do a lot
more design, you know, that he's brilliant at instead of just like being hampered by tools
and stuff like that. And this allowed me to get out. Unfortunately, I kind of did Rise of Triad,
which a number of people like.
uh... but it was sort of like wolf of stein
one point five you know
and i i i i'm really proud of the death match death matches incredible like
crazy things going on drug missiles you know and playmalls and stuff
uh... and actually there's a inside story
uh... the god mode of rise of the triad
is actually something john did
while no clipping through walls in wolfenstein
because he would sit there and he turned no clip on to like go look at a
different room or something
and then he just kind of go,
ooooh, I am moving through walls, I will destroy you all.
So that kind of turned into a God mode.
The actual sound effect.
And they're like, ooooh, I will destroy you all.
Kind of an inside joke.
But the thing I want to get,
the point I want to make about that though
is did Rise of the Triad,
but then eventually years later.
I did get to get my creative yayas completely out with Anachronox, which is a space game
which had characters which really told, had a really sense of space and I'm really proud
of the writing and the experience of that.
Yeah, Tom actually was developing Prey after Rise of the Triad and he left 3D Realms, they
kind of renamed themselves, he left 3D Realms while he was on Prey to help
a startup, Ion Storm, so he could make anachronox,
his giant RPG.
Yeah.
Prey was an interesting project.
I had sort of an interesting thing
that kind of showed up a little bit in anachronox,
but it's a series of combined classes
that each kind of contribute to each other, three primaries
and two that add to each other.
But that just wasn't creatively working out,
and the team wasn't really happy with it
either, the way things were going.
The one thing that I do like that is in Prey is grab pass, so you can just walk up the wall.
I had the very perfect image originally in Prey of being able to go like this and throw a grenade
and have it bounce on the ceiling like that and wait for somebody and like that.
So it would be a great death match kind of thing.
Anyway, so then Tom goes and eventually he does an acronax, but during this time Tom's gone.
Tom was creative director and he was on the project for 10 months and now there's a void
And so we need to hire some other people because I'm not going to finish doing all the levels myself
Because I still have you know programming to do in the game and everything, but you know
I just did one one to say one more thing and
That can you stand over here?
All right, what's your mic at me? I?
Just wanted oh yeah, I just wanted to say that
I am proud to have worked on Doom, and after 18 some years, I can wear this shirt and say
that, you know, I wrote it.
Yeah, that'll be $20 for another shirt to come off.
We actually made Wolfenstein shirts that way as well.
So Wolfenstein 3D wrote it, and then we
did a bunch of the Doom ones while we were making the game.
It's pretty funny.
Yeah, actually we came up with, I think I did the Roadout shirts,
and then I did the Go to Hell ad.
And then Apple did these really simple couple word ads.
I think they stole it from me personally.
Oh, yeah.
OK, so now we have to hire some new people, right?
So we just hired two more people to replace Tom.
Dave Taylor. Everybody knows Dave, hopefully. And then the
legendary Sandy Peterson who was working with Chaosium on
Call of Cthulhu and a bunch of other stuff. So he was a well
known designer back then. So then these guys jump on the
game. Sandy is taking over Tom's design work. Dave is doing a lot
of programming for us to get the game out. You know, we get into
September. We're making a lot of progress on the automap. Lots
of levels are getting done.
in the style of game levels back then. And we get the DMX sound drivers. We didn't have
enough bandwidth to do the sound drivers ourselves. So we actually had a guy named Paul Radek.
He wrote the sound drivers that he was licensing out. So Dave got those hooked into the game.
So we actually get sound effects and everything. In October, we finally get another build of
the game. It's a pre-release. And it's
getting close, you know, we're only, I think, what, two months away from release at this point.
So, so the game's looking better. You can see way more textures in it, the lighting's better,
we have a lot more time to make more of an environment in this game. So this doesn't
have the sound effects in it because it would be annoying, but you can see how much more
work's been done to that really simple level, and it does take a lot of time.
when you're making levels to just keep going over and over the same area
and refining your texture alignment, your lighting, and your effects, and your placement,
and everything that you're trying to do in these things.
Making a great level requires a ton of iteration and a ton of play.
You need to play your own level.
And so I play these things a lot.
And this isn't even the final version of it because there's no lift there in the final game.
You can see that even the sky is different.
That's like, trying to be realistic, it looks like, you know, you're on Phobos and there's
space above the mountains, which, sure, space would be black like that, but it doesn't look
that good.
You know, a black void like that doesn't, it doesn't feel as good as something that
has more light, so we kind of made it, we changed the final, the final, uh,
the final sky to actually be light colored.
So the level actually felt a lot better.
Yeah, if you put stars in there, they would kind of alias or something.
Yeah, they would drop out and look samply.
You can see that we're picking up items.
We're keeping track of items.
And next to the Doomguy's head, we have the lives.
So we still had those kind of things in the game.
Even at the intermission screen, it was keeping track of your rewards for items
that you picked up and stuff.
But I basically just didn't think that.
Like this was a, this is like, I felt like this is a pretty modern game, let's get rid of the things that arcade games had in them.
So, I didn't like the idea that you would have to have lives and like you could end the game and kind of get really mad because you tried really hard to get through like E2M5 or something.
So, I got rid of the idea of lives and if you get killed you just go back to the beginning level infinitely as much as you want.
And we have a save load feature in the game where you can save it at any second while you're playing and reload it instantly.
So it would be, you know, there's a high probability that players would be able to actually finish the game and get through it.
So you can see here, walking through E1M2, how much different it is.
You can see that these fireballs from these guys are still, I think it's Tom's art.
Yeah.
The fireballs that they're throwing is old.
But at least you can see the game getting more done.
And really, the next step past this point was the final game.
It was just the next revision of all of these little layers
of graphics and level design and menu systems and stuff
like that.
So you can see, I actually had to run a TSR program called
Fake Date to allow me to record the demo,
because we had a time-locked press release version
that we sent out.
It's hard to say. I don't think you can set the date manually
inside of DOSBox. So going forward, November was like, okay,
we're at the very end. We've got to hurry up and get this game
done. So we're all doing final polish work on it. So a lot got
done. The first IPX multiplayer in a game was created, like a
fast shooter game. The word deathmatch is created. I came up
with that just while I was thinking about, you know, what
kind of mode that would be.
We put co-op in there because it just seemed obvious that you'd want to go through the
game together with friends.
We finished all of the extra 10% of the game that it takes to really make it feel polished.
And then we got modems working and all the game maps were modified to handle all the
game modes that we had with all the difficulty levels and everything.
So it was really just tons of polish at the very, very end.
and we were spending more and more time at the office.
The Usenet was going crazy because everybody knew
the game was coming out for a whole year,
so they were inventing all kinds of stories
and new games based off of cheat codes that we had.
Actually, the internet created some cheat codes,
so it was just like really furious at the very end.
That last November, December was pretty crazy.
And then basically that was December 10th is the day that we
are putting the game up on the net. We had a 30 hour stretch
at the very end of no sleep, 30 hours, everybody just running
the game on every machine. We had a last minute bug that was
like, it was a really crazy bug that only if you knew everything
about the technology would you know how to debug. But basically
the game runs on a timer, so.
even in the future with 50 megahertz, 50 gigahertz
processors, this game will always
run at the correct speed.
But in doing that, using the timer at a low level,
interrupt level, basically if the timer starts
at some crazy random value when the game starts,
there's a possibility that it could hit zero.
And at that point, the game just locks up.
So we sometimes saw the game running on a bunch of machines
and would just randomly lock up for no reason at all.
only only Carmack could figure out that it was the timer code
that was wrapping when that happened. So fix that bug and
then it never you know, that was just like during that last time
fixing that bug. And it was the last thing that we had in the
game. So ironically,
doom is uploaded to my college computers, you know, decided
Wisconsin upload the game to the college University of Wisconsin
FTP server, and everyone was waiting for it. So we had
You know, we had to try and get in there, get a slot in there to do an upload, which is what we did.
And so, you know, we were using a modem and putting the game up.
And it blew up the whole server.
And then we had to get on the phone with the sysop of the FTP server.
And then we had to have him kick everybody off.
And then we had to slot in again because we had hundreds of people trying to get onto the server to get the game.
And we couldn't even get the game up on the server because they're sitting there.
And then it blew up again.
So...
the second time the game blew up and and uh...
and then basically had to tell him to just lock everybody off
so we could just upload it
and so he did that
and now bucky's happy
and then the game was uploaded
uploaded to the world and made its way across all the bbs's and uh... you know
everybody knows the rest of the story
uh... we went on to make doom 2 and quake and
and that weirdly
uh... level ten of doom two was mine
what the diamonds and what that was a funny moment.
And so that's it.
That's the story of how we made Doom.
Thanks everyone.
We can do questions.
First of all, I would like to, this is an odd job.
and really like to thank everybody that like gets the games and downloads them,
because you're just kind of like sitting in a room doing like this thing because you like
to play it, you know, it's like I want to play that thing.
And then all of a sudden, oh, this is really great, it's like, you know, okay, nice to meet you,
I don't know how this happened, but it's kind of cool.
So questions, anybody has questions?
It would be great to hit a microphone so everyone can hear it.
So to me, one of the sort of most interesting dynamics in
Doom was the variety in sort of enemy attacks and just sort of
the timings of them and so on.
I was curious as to kind of where along the process or how
much, did they come out the way you'd planned or was there a lot
of change throughout in terms of like fireball speeds and enemy
run speeds and shotgun timing and whatnot?
Yeah, everything in the game was totally iterated on like
heavily.
So, you know, we made really best first guesses.
The game frame rate, the rendering rate was locked at 35
frames a second, even though it could probably go 70.
We made it 35, so the rest of the game would run evenly on
more systems.
And we ran the internal AI at 10 frames a second, so we
would have a good speed for the enemies.
We don't want them coming too fast, because it's just not
very fair or fun.
So we put first guess values in for everything, the damage,
how the damage scales on weapons.
the weapon firing rates, how much per second damage that could possibly be, to try and
perfectly balance all the weapons so, you know, what you were having to decide was if
something's really far away, you want to use not the shotgun, and if something is big,
you want to use the rocket launcher, and stuff that's really far away, use the pistol or
the chain gun.
So we did a ton of balancing on that to try and kind of even out the damages and the times
that they would fire.
And I'd have to say it just felt...
perfect, you know, even years later when we played Deathmatch in other games and come
back to it, it just, it just, we got really lucky balancing all the damage.
Thank you.
I can't see you over there.
I guess there's a hand over there.
Hi.
Hi there.
So now that the game is, well the game has been finished for a while and ported for a
lot of systems.
Do you guys go back and think that there was any element that you want to change?
And also, which port do you think is the best and the most, best representation of the game?
I don't have anything that I want to change other than, you know, I would go over the
levels probably and just do some more polish on the levels.
But they really, they feel great and I think the game is...
I really don't have any, like, I don't look back and go, oh, man, that was really messed
up.
Like, you know, with Quake, there was some damages with the rocket launcher I would probably
change.
But with Doom, it just seemed right.
I guess we've got one more question.
Yeah.
Hello.
I'm Carlos.
First of all, thanks for coming.
I recently read Masters of Doom, and it reminded me of kind of like when I was growing up,
people had with John Romero, like, you know, someone who was very excited, very passionate
about what he was doing. One of the things that I thought about was how you guys always
wanted to make like the best games around you. You wanted to compete with the greatest
and you wanted to break new ground and, you know, make the, you know, use like CarMax
technology and apply it in design in ways that nobody had seen before. And you then,
when you disagree with, I think, I saw a YouTube interview with Matt, like Matt Chat.
Matt Chat, yeah.
you say you disagree with some of the decisions that were made in Quake and you ended up,
you know, doing your own thing and you still wanted to, you know, make your own, you know,
great first-person shooter in your vision of it.
Right. So as a creator,
what made you transition from, you know, that passion towards, say,
AAA games, towards a different focus now, towards, say, social space?
Well, I...
played deathmatch like constantly for years and love
deathmatch. I really deathmatch is like one of the most fun
ways to play a game for me. But nowadays going into the into
the latest games are not they don't feel the same way. They
feel like I feel like I'm going slower through the world. And I
really like the doom and quake speeds of the player run. It
felt like they're more skill based than, you know, like,
then then just like aiming.
at somebody with a rail gun, not as much fun for me.
And as a designer, it's way more challenging
to make a game that hundreds of millions of people
will like, like say social games.
It's much more of a challenge to try and get back
to the roots of what's fun and to make it palatable
to way more people.
So I still have some really great ideas
for some shooters that I'd like to make,
but right now.
You know, I've moved through, we've both moved through a lot of different kinds of designs
in our careers and it's fun to touch a lot of different areas.
Well, I think John's genius is seeing the next thing
and perhaps the timing has been off occasionally, but when Carmack
and I made a joke first level of Super Mario and left it on John's desk,
he closed the door when we came in after, you know,
crashing and stuff and he said, we are out of here.
He knew it.
They said, this is it.
We're out of here.
Boom.
This is a success.
The scrolling?
And yeah, with the tile scrolling stuff.
And when we did Monkeystone together,
it's like it was a very early cell thing.
The cell carriers didn't really have it together as far as games,
but that's the biggest thing now is mobile games and stuff.
So it was brilliant a little early on that one.
And now it's striking the forefront again with social games
and sharing it with Brenda, the brilliant Brenda.
Thank you.
Thanks, I think that's it for questions
because we have to run to another talk.
Yes, thanks everybody.