Thanks for coming.
Thanks for giving me a reason to escape our little paper
world for a few hours.
I'm enjoying seeing some different textures here.
I'm quite inspired by this.
But today, we're just going to talk about paper and building
a world out of paper, a very touchy, feely world.
Let's just move this on.
There's me.
There's my Twitter handle.
I doubt that we'll have time to do questions,
so you can always ping me a few questions afterwards
if you've got any.
Well, hopefully you've heard of Tearaway already.
But if you haven't, you should have a good understanding
of what we've been building the last couple of years.
So I've been personally with MM since the beginning,
working on the visual design of the company and its games,
the playful anarchy of how they've come together.
Visually and having some kind of influence on some of the music and directing the intros and just giving it that molecule
atmosphere. And now I'm lead
lead creator on Tearaway, a smaller subject subset of the MM team
concentrating on making something very adventurous and and portable for the PlayStation Vita.
So in case you haven't seen what we're doing,
I'm just going to do a little recap on the trailer
that we released last summer.
And it gives a little bit of context
on what I'll be talking about.
Because otherwise, you might be wondering
why I'm talking about giant fingertips and paper world.
So here we go.
You should've gone a better bet Better for your head
Better heads meet short tie
You should've gone a..
ARRRR!
Better for your head
Better for your head,
And see,
promise it to me
Promise we have a seat
Fin, I hate you so much.
I'll never play the game again!
I'm gonna...
I'm gonna die.
I'll never play the game again.
DinDinPearly.exe has stopped communicating
Thanks very much.
So I'm going to start off by saying this.
I'm going to start off by saying this, I don't like digital things.
At least, I don't really like things that react in a digital way.
I like things that you can really see the hand of someone else in the creation of that thing.
And something that you can really feel it in your own hands, very tangible.
Now, my first experience with game design was with MUDs.
Not that kind of MUDs, this kind of MUDs.
I grew up in a very rural area and just mainly sort of played
around with making games myself out of whatever I could lay my
hands on, just making up my own rules and just getting messy
and getting hurt.
And I think we all enjoy returning to a childlike kind of playing around of materials, identifying their unique properties,
how they react to you and how they react when combined together.
Kind of things that leave a mark, not just on what you're playing with, but on you.
And I think a lot of that came through in LBP, the sort of playful making, the cut and paste, the doodle and sculpting.
Experimenting with what happens when you combine materials together and throw them around.
So...
When we were handed a Vita, on the surface,
it seemed like the complete opposite of that.
It's very clean, very sleek, very shiny.
Not exactly a bucket of mud.
But it's covered in inputs.
You hold it in your hands.
It's a personal experience.
So perhaps we could use it in a way
to create some kind of tactile, messy world
that you are holding.
And that was the real jumping off point, that it is held by your fingers.
I've played a load of games, I've pressed all these buttons a million times,
and the games have never really commented on the fact that I'm pressing these buttons,
and what are my fingers and my thumbs doing? Do they have a part in these stories?
Do video games like, you know, sort of, are the boss characters sort of living in fear of your thumbs?
You know, these terrible whirling beasts that are outside of their world, like, controlling their destiny.
So maybe that we could play a little bit more with the idea of what a game is and what it means to
hold it and to play it.
And we started coming around to this idea of creating a more playful intersection between the game world and the real world.
A lot of that came from the excitement of the Vita's rear touch panel.
And if you could actually see your fingers, like, in the game world, it would kind of genuinely feel handheld and...
and kind of immediately more engaging.
And that was kind of the first element of
just trying to break down this fourth wall
between a game and reality.
We started to concept and prototype various finger puppet characters.
At this stage, we were experimenting with making your fingers the main characters in
the game, something that we iterated a lot on and ultimately ended up implementing in
a slightly different way, which is a whole separate talk.
But if we were going to make a world that you...
that you'll go push your fingers into,
then obviously we'd need to make something
that you'd want to push your fingers into.
This particular scene from Flash Gordon
has traumatized me since I was very young.
Particularly anyone in the UK,
that actor was the number one
sort of children's TV presenter at the time,
so seeing him do that was horrible.
So a lot of game universes, they look really amazing,
but they're not something that you necessarily would want to touch.
You'd be sort of putting your fingers in and touching someone's eyeball
or a spike pit or something like that.
We really needed a world that could do all of these things.
And my particular personal style is distinctive shapes
and silhouettes, a look that can be diluted when trying to do
that in a full, more conventional, 3D way.
It took us a little while to work out where to get the influence from that would really just combine all of these things together.
And it came from our desks.
That's my desk. You might be able to make out a couple of computers in there somewhere.
Not very popular with the cleaners.
And it just seemed like the perfect material,
as we were kind of screwing up our concept art
and throwing it around and abandoning it.
We just started to create landscapes
without even sort of thinking about it.
And it's a material that's kind of seldom celebrated.
It's usually a negative term.
We talk about paper thin or paperwork.
We thought, let's have some paper play.
It's tactile and creative. It's kind of under threat a little bit from from e-readers and all the digital stuff.
I kind of don't really feel that in the future someone's going to make a game out of Kindles, but who knows?
So, I think this statement is kind of true,
except that it's very easy to think that paper craft is low poly,
and it's not low poly at all. It curves, it flexes,
it needs to have a lot more simulation under the surface.
It's all of these things that make it interesting,
the imperfections, the limitations, and the movement.
So this is our first test render.
Had this sort of miniaturization feel.
But you can't really see the imperfections.
And also, it was trying to do two things at once.
It's carefully painted and made of paper, but it didn't
really strongly look like either of them.
And then this is our first prototype. It's very simple, isometric look. The floor was kind of interestingly tactile.
We're not very papery and the finger doesn't really look anything like a finger.
But there was kind of some interesting stuff happening with the real world game world interception. I'll start playing it so you can see.
See how you use the rear touch to cut things out,
and then they fall out into the real world.
Something that traveled through into the final game
in a very different implementation.
But we needed to go bolder, have more contrast with the finger, just be more easily identified from a glance.
So we just stripped out all the texturing, so far back that we've actually only got one texture in the game.
This is an abstract concept from the time, the sort of opposite of the boxy isometric prototypes.
We really wanted to stay as true as possible to the material and the limitations of the construction.
And by designing and building and remaking and paper
and repeating the process, we were
able to get something much more handmade.
All the imperfections appeared.
The limitations in the material meant
that we had to redesign some things that were more
ingenious in their construction.
And the way they were folded and formed
suggests certain types of animation and movement.
This is a concept video from the time with the aim of just
resetting our brains a little bit about the kind of gameplay
interactions you can have in this paper world, so that it's
not just a re-skinning of traditional game language.
It doesn't really make sense to have a spike
pit in a paper world.
So paper just became the whole ethos behind the game,
not just an art style.
It needed to be the way that everything was constructed,
the way it moved, the way you interacted with it,
and just not work it with any other material.
And by restricting ourselves to just this one material,
we had to just think a little bit differently.
There's no, like I was kind of alluding to earlier,
there's no real point to having an ice level
or the usual fiery lava level in a paper world
kind of annihilate the entire world
if you even put a single match in.
So the limitations really gave us some focus.
It just meant that we could work on an engine
that just simulated that one thing
and just did it really well.
I'm talking of which, here's a little glimpse into our paper engine.
So here I can just step through, I can see it down there.
So drawing out a sheet,
start building a world,
put some
some tears in it, see those traveling around.
I think it's often, it's not the actual paper texture, but it's more the fact that the edges are a little bit wobbly and
As I was moving as well, you can see how it's got a little bit of noise on it, so it's all jittering around.
And we can peel bits up and make essentially more three-dimensional shapes.
Here's another one.
This one's a little bit more structural, so we put the sheet down.
But this time, we start giving it some form, giving it some height.
And you can see the tabs automatically being added.
But it's not actually a solid cube,
it's just made out of a single sheet of paper
that's had all the folds put in for us.
That debug view shows the plan view
of the shape on the floor,
just so you can kind of get a grasp of what's going on.
And then as I change the kind of
The angle of the walls, you can see how the plan view is updating so that you could actually print that out if you wanted to.
You can just keep going on till you made a really stupid face.
Right, stick enough of those together you end up with a world.
A fantasy world, realistically created is how I really like to think about it.
And this world is all based on natural forms
infused with a feeling of folklore.
Mainly because it's a lot more interesting to make a natural world out of paper.
You know we could we could make an urban cityscape,
but we've just been making boxes whereas trying to design a tree or trying to you know get that kind of more curvaceous
feeling is just way more interesting.
You can see there's like hardly a single straight edge in any of those shots.
But it doesn't matter how papery the construction of the world is if it's not responding,
if it's not moving or responding, it's not going to feel papery.
So,
that realism of the construction really helped with our goal of just making it feel really touchy feeling,
because the simulation required in building it would mean that it could also react in a simulated way.
So here's a mesmerizing example of Iota running around
in a circle.
And you can see how, I could watch this all day,
how the paper's just squashing up and down.
It makes me so happy.
And it's just like guiding the character,
sort of pulling you through the world.
You just want to run along the edges of things.
Here's a slightly different example.
Jumpies and puddles.
You know, just making jumping in puddles really fun to do.
Take another step through the world, go on the adventure.
A slightly more dramatic version from the trailer is just the way that, you know, you can use the fingers to
push up through the world and have it reacting.
And I don't know if you can see around the finger,
it's also showing using the rear camera of the Vita that you see through into reality.
So we've got this mad sort of
intersection of game world and real world.
A few more examples, but you will have seen those in the trailer.
So the way we try and bring the world to life
really breaks down into simulation and animation.
Simulation for the things that you're doing as a human,
this sort of godlike force that's holding the Vita
and interacting with it.
And then we have a different kind of overtly animated style
for how the world is reacting to you influencing it.
Kind of think of it more as like real and magical really.
So the animation.
We're going for a kind of stop-motion style
to just kind of remind you of the fact
that it is moving of its own accord.
This doesn't normally happen to a sheet of paper
sitting on your desk.
So it just makes it more characterful, more interesting,
kind of more real than real.
Our technical artist, Stefan, has written loads of custom stuff so that we can simulate bits of paper moving around.
This is a first ever test of the main character. That's actually just their leg.
We wanted to make sure, you know, their leg could do really characterful and interesting ways. It's bending and, well, not stretching. Paper doesn't stretch, but
you know, all that kind of different transformations.
A few more examples here of the stop-motion look.
This is our motion capture studio.
We do our animation in a stationary cupboard.
Get the irony.
And we want to make sure that the characters, I'll just set our animator going, we want
to make sure that our characters do have personality.
They're made of paper.
It's doing terrible things, the sap boy.
I want to make sure that their personalities and their emotions fully bring them to life
so that we don't just end up with folded bits of paper with eyes stuck onto them.
We don't want to just celebrate the medium of paper, but really convey some messages
with it.
And the final reason for building a world out of paper
is so players can get involved themselves
and really extend that intersection of game world
and real world and take stuff outside of the game.
So although we're building a world that's
very, very personal to us and learning the skills that we
need to build a relatively cohesive adventure,
Crafting with paper is just a way that we can make sure that all players can really get involved with
this world, whether it's customizing
in-game elements like this particularly demanding squirrel or
Being rewarded with plans to print out and make,
kind of like digital, I mean non-digital, physical trophies,
kind of way more personal.
I've kind of found it's pretty hard not to pick up a little paper craft elk
once it's sitting on a desk near you.
I'm predicting that 2D printers are going to be the next big thing.
And ultimately it just gives us a way for players to have fun
adding to what's already there.
Break down that fourth wall and bring elements of the game world into their own lives.
Here's some examples of what people have been doing in a recent thing we got fans involved with.
And just find things in the paper world, customize them, print them out in the real world, take photos of their collections,
invent new games using them, or just feed them back into the game again.
And basically just have lots of lots of creative fun. Remember why we play games in the first place.
Splashing some puddles, make some mess,
terrify their teachers.
So just wrapping up, that's how we got to where we are, how and maybe most importantly
why we decided to focus on one material to make our touchy-feely adventure.
By having paper run through the entire decision process,
it's really helped us focus on a core,
make sure that the tech would allow it to happen,
and really concentrate on doing that one thing really well.
And then there's the freedom of the limitation.
It's just one material.
We needed to come up with new ways to interact with it
and travel through the world and reset our brains.
And we spent a long time on LBP, and we
didn't want to just fall back on some of the older ideas.
And also, it's fun.
It's a pretty mad thing to do, too.
Try and build a world out of sheets of craft paper.
Make it move and react in ways that you'd expect
and some you wouldn't.
But it's been a fun challenge,
especially when we see what fans are starting to do
with taking stuff out and building things themselves.
Thank you very much.
I don't know if I have time for any questions.
I've got like 30 seconds apparently.
Any quick ones?
No?
Any chance for some felt DLC?
Some felt?
I like it.
Maybe.
With the paper tearing, how did you explore it and kind of arrive at the look you had
for the edges of the paper as the world was built and torn and all the little bits you
have that kind of describe the kind of inside of the paper underneath the color that you
have on a lot of the paper edges to get that kind of texture to be there versus it just
being a hard edge of a cut piece of paper, that kind of that torn?
Oh, so the torn edging is applied as a separate texture that gets mapped around the edge of
the paper as it comes apart.
Right, it's brilliant, yeah.
Thank you.
I think that might be it.
Okay, thanks everyone.
Oh my god, let's get dry.
Oh, that's still on.
Let's get dry!