Welcome to Changing the Game, Cultivating Female Talent in AAA Studios.
I'm Victoria Setian, Senior Producer at Avalanche Studios.
So, why are we here?
Well, in 2019, the gaming audience is almost 50% female,
but only 22% of game developers are women.
It's important to have more of our audience reflected in our development teams.
And keep in mind, of that 22%, even fewer of those female developers are in leadership
roles, which is extra important to note because according to the study by Merida L. Johns,
companies that have the best records for promoting women outstrip their competition on every
measure of profitability.
In other words, your company will be more lucrative.
So how do we make this happen?
Well, it's easier to de-bias organizations' practices
and procedures than to de-bias mindsets.
Which brings us to this talk.
We'll cover three areas.
The first is adjusting outreach methodologies.
The second, retaining and fostering female talent.
And the third is developing that talent into leadership.
This talk is largely research-based
and references will be provided.
And before we begin, here's a little bit more about me
and what brought me here today.
I'm a lifelong gamer.
a comic book enthusiast, and on my weekends I'm an Armenian folk dancer. I've also worked in AAA
for a while in creative and production roles, most recently Just Cause 4 and its DLC. As I mentioned
before, I work for Avalanche Studios as a senior producer. Let's take a look at how Avalanche is
doing on the road to 5050. Avalanche has three offices, Stockholm, Malmö in Sweden, and New
York City in the United States.
We haven't solved the problem yet, but we are taking steps to change things.
Change is a process, and I'm proud to be a female developer at Avalanche Studios Group.
The fact that Avalanche is supportive of this talk and showing these numbers demonstrates
their commitment to improving female diversity, starting with a fun fact.
The design documents of Just Cause 4 refer to our player as she and her.
Another fun fact.
Two years ago, I couldn't have given this talk.
In 2018, I was promoted to senior producer.
That day, the studio manager called me aside
to congratulate me on being the first female developer
to become part of a leadership group
in the history of the New York studio.
So change is happening, but it can be slow.
So let's kick this off and see how we can get to 50-50.
One, reach out to younger female audiences.
The end goal is increasing our female talent pool and getting more resumes.
And it starts with adjusting our outreach methodologies.
One of the primary reasons women are underrepresented in technology
is schools don't encourage girls to pursue tech careers.
Remember that phrase we all used to use when we were kids?
What am I going to be when I grow up?
Well, kids start thinking seriously
about their careers in middle school, which
is also when girls begin losing interest in STEM.
They continue to lose interest as they
go through high school, which is when many outreach programs
begin.
So action items.
Like I said, I am a producer, so this talk
will end each section with action items
that you can start making change today.
So the actions here are start outreach efforts with middle schools and educate girls on the
various roles in the industry. On top of our poor timing, girls don't think of game development as
a possible career path because they don't know what it means to work in games and the sort of
positions available to them. How could they? We're not educating them young enough on the potential
careers in games. For the record, these are about 9 to 12 year old girls we're talking about.
And even during this young age range,
they consider factors like gendered expectations
and even family planning as they wonder
what they're going to be when they grow up.
Female representation in games.
So we've educated girls that games is a career path
and the types of roles available to them.
Now let's show them that they have a voice in the medium
and they exist in the games themselves.
It's a well-trodden topic at this point,
so I'm not gonna hang too long here.
You may be familiar with the actress, Gina Davis.
She's been in incredible movies like Thelma and Louise,
Lego of Their Own, my personal favorite, Beetlejuice.
She's also the founder of the Gina Davis Institute
on Gender and Media.
There's a ton of great research at the Institute site
that goes further into the importance
of seeing yourself reflected in media.
And the motto of her Institute is,
if she can see it, she can be it.
These are the women of Avalanche Studios.
I did a poll asking what characters in games you identify with.
That when you play as these characters, you see yourself reflected back.
And when I look at this slide, it fills me with joy because I see my colleagues and friends
staring back at me.
But it also makes me a little sad because quite a few women felt they didn't have a
character they identify with.
So the action here is keep it up.
There's still so many types of female characters
we haven't seen yet.
So many of my colleagues that aren't represented.
Give them a voice.
Combat unconscious bias.
So now that we're showing young girls
there's jobs for them in the industry
and we see them as exemplified
by all these great characters.
Let's help them get in the door of our studios
by combating unconscious bias.
Unconscious bias is attitudes or stereotypes that affect our understanding, actions, and
decisions in an unconscious manner.
These biases, which encompass both favorable and unfavorable assessments, are activated
involuntarily and without an individual's awareness or intentional control.
The critical takeaway of the study is...
Women were less likely to believe they belonged in a particular job when the advertisement
used masculine wording, and they rated masculine jobs as less appealing.
The image here from the study is an example of one job ad done in two ways, with masculine
wording and feminine wording.
It's also important to note that feminine wording had no impact on the amount of male
applicants.
You'll get the same amount of male applicants, but you'll get an increased amount of female
At Avalanche, we are taking strides to address unconscious bias by training our hiring staff
on best practices on biases and reviewing job postings for masculine wording.
This is due to an initiative started by a lead male developer who wanted to root out
implicit bias wording in our job descriptions.
Visible presence of female developers.
Now that we've got these women in the door,
let's restart from step one,
but this time incorporate our female developers
in our practices.
It's not enough to show that there are women here.
But we also need to highlight women in senior and leadership roles to show two important things.
One, women are part of this industry.
And two, it's possible to get to the top.
Some of the ways you can apply this research and thinking is include women in your outreach efforts.
Have them join for school visits and recruitment off-sites.
In your press events, marketing materials, and conventions.
Let's see more women on the E3 big stages and big presentations where lots of young
women can see them.
If you're posting team photos on your social media or website, make sure it includes at
least 50% female developers.
And include developers of all levels to show girls the full breadth of the career ladder.
When I was working in Los Angeles, I volunteered with WIGGY and Girl Scouts of America on a
game design patch, teaching middle school girls about how to make a game and all the
various roles in the industry from QA to audio.
It was hosted by a panel of women in various roles in the industry and all over the career
ladder.
And at Avalanche, we have school visits to the studio where we explain the different roles in
game development. We have off-site recruitment sessions that include female members of the dev
team, and we work with game design schools on figuring out how to admit more women.
The actions here are include more women in off-site recruitment,
marketing, press, and games, and make women in senior and leadership roles more visible.
Part two, retaining and fostering female talent.
Okay, we've got more women in the industry,
but our work has only just begun.
One, internal support networks.
Internal support networks are internal groups
within your studio that encourage people to connect,
learn from each other, and grow.
Involvement is elective.
Group settings are valuable because we support each other,
we can be sounding boards, learn from each other,
host workshops, or sometimes just ask questions
that our male colleagues wouldn't be able to help us with.
It's great if you can get women in senior roles involved
to get access to role models within the network.
All three Avalanche offices have women's meetup groups
and dedicated Slack channels.
In our New York office,
we have a bimonthly dedicated meeting
where we've twice hosted our Respect and Assertiveness
in the Workplace workshop.
Actions create internal support networks for female employees.
Two, mentorship.
According to 48% of women, the number one top barrier in tech
is lack of workplace mentorship.
And that's sad.
There's many ways to mentor, including education,
identifying skills, listening, offering guidance,
career planning.
And if you're mailing want to mentor, go for it.
Research shows that a mentor's level, not gender, impacts career advancement.
Throughout my career, I've been fortunate to have mentorship, primarily from men.
They've helped me in various ways, sending me books and literature,
helping me plan my career path and aspirations, to helping my voice be heard
by senior management. Mentor or recommend mentorships.
Now we've got all these excellent ways of supporting our female developers.
They're going to take on the world, right?
Oh, three, master suppression techniques and strategies.
Well, that sounds scary.
So what are master suppression techniques?
Master suppression techniques are strategies people or groups of people
can use to dominate or humiliate others in a subtle, indirect way.
In the 1940s, Norwegian psychologist and philosopher Ingeld Nisen
first published research on master suppression techniques.
Decades later, in the 1970s, Norwegian social psychologist Berit Aas did further work on
the framework, establishing that they are used in specific combinations and situations
in regards to women.
There are five techniques, and thanks to the Institute of Gender Equality in Sweden,
research was conducted on how to combat these techniques using counter-strategies.
I also want to give a quick shout-out for those who don't know,
Alloynich was founded in Sweden, so it's pretty great to see that the gender equality in Sweden
made such excellent strides in this area.
I'm quickly going to give an overview of each master suppression technique and its counter-strategy.
The first is making invisible.
It's acting like what the speaker is saying isn't important or valuable by drawing attention away.
This can be done by interrupting or doing more subtle things like making noises with your chair
or being on your phone, lack of gestures or response. The counter strategy is called
take place. Stay calm and self-assured and highlight the unacceptable behavior.
Hey, would you mind putting your phone away?
Next is ridicule, mocking and laughing at the other person, infantilizing or otherwise degrading them.
An example of something like this is the phrase,
hysterical women or silly girls.
I remember shipping a project.
It had taken a lot of time and energy and effort
and we shipped successfully.
The game did very, very well.
And shortly after I was called in a meeting
with a room full of all of my peers.
And there were two male executives in the room.
And one male executive decided to call attention
to the effort that I had put into the project.
And the other male executive turned to me
and patted me on the head.
I didn't know what master suppression techniques were,
and I certainly didn't know the counter strategy
for what to do in the moment while I was being ridiculed
by someone in leadership.
The counter-strategy is question.
Stay calm and ask, why would you say that?
Or in my case, what did you mean by that?
Withhold information.
Not getting access to meetings, documents, news, invitations,
et cetera.
The counter-strategy is require cards on the table.
Point out the pattern and why it's necessary to have this information to do your job.
Request that if you can't attend something to please reschedule.
Double bind.
Whatever you do, you are wrong.
If you're direct, you're a bitch.
If you're a good listener, you're too passive.
The counter strategy here is called change the pattern.
Recognize what your priorities are and what's important to you.
Then clarify the rules.
For example.
Maybe you can't stay late. You have to pick up your kids or you have some errand to run.
So clarify the rules. Say, hey, I need to pick up my kids, but I know that this is due tomorrow
at two o'clock and you'll have it by the time that you've asked for it. So you're clarifying
that you understand what the rules are and that you're working within the bounds of your
constraints. Heap blame or sometimes put to shame. Someone making you feel bad for something that's
not your fault.
An example applicable to the workplace is getting a task that's too big for the timeline,
and the woman blames herself for not completing it in time, even though that's an impossible
scenario.
The counter-strategy is intellectualize.
This is one of the more difficult counter-strategies because it's mostly internal.
Try to become aware of these feelings of guilt and objectively take a look at them and ask
yourself, why do I feel guilty?
Try to put yourself in other people's shoes.
How would they look at the situation?
Take it a step further back and see if there's something that maybe happened before that's
making you feel guilt or shame about the current event.
I just want to point out that most people who use master suppression techniques are
not consciously trying to be destructive or hurtful.
Remember what we said about implicit bias earlier?
These are generally some conscious maneuvers.
So it's really important to give people
the benefit of the doubt when employing a counter strategy.
And even the research goes into that as well.
So if you or the woman on your team
are trying to employ a counter strategy,
I encourage you to please come from a calm and neutral place.
We are all human and we all make mistakes. The actions here are understand master suppression
techniques. Only by learning about these can we become aware of them and educate women on counter
strategies. Be a champion. You don't have to commit to being a mentor or running a whole
internal support network to make an impact. The opportunities to be a champion are endless and
typically spontaneous.
We learned about the concept of being a champion in the workshop of our women's group that I mentioned earlier in the presentation.
For example, if you see a woman getting interrupted, say,
Hey, I think Tori was going to say something. What's up Tori?
Tori, we haven't heard from you yet. What are your thoughts?
Or remember those master suppression techniques and counter strategies we just talked about?
Well, some of those counter strategies actually require having somebody as a sounding board to talk to.
Be that sounding board.
Or teach a female colleague about what master's
impression techniques even are and introduce them
to the concept of counter strategies.
If maybe you don't think you're up to the task of mentorship,
but you see someone who might be a really good mentor,
broach the topic with them and then connect them,
if they're open to it, with the person who could be the mentee.
The action is be a champion.
Part three, developing talent into leadership.
We've empowered our female developers with support systems, mentoring them and educating them.
Now, how do we get them into leadership roles?
One, sponsorship.
So real quick, what is sponsorship?
Sponsorship is a program.
High-performing women need to be identified by senior and executive team members.
These senior team members then need to seek out opportunities for these women
and then advocate for them.
Highlight their qualifications and why they'd be a great fit for the opportunity.
Help them climb the ladder.
It's also really important to note that this is dedicated work.
It needs to be tracked and followed up on to ensure that steps are being taken to help
move these women through the sponsorship program.
As you move up within an organization,
it's important to have the sponsorship of someone
who has enough leverage in the organization
to make things happen.
Otherwise, it won't be effective.
In most senior level jobs, you need sponsorship
to make it to the very top.
This action is probably pretty clear.
Start a sponsorship program.
Shift leadership framework.
For this section, I will be referencing the fantastic paper
from the Harvard Business Review,
Women Rising the Unseen Marriers.
Becoming a leader involves much more
than being put in a leadership role, acquiring new skills,
and adapting one's style to the requirements of that role.
It involves a fundamental identity shift.
Organizations inadvertently undermine the process when they advise women to proactively
seek leadership roles without also addressing policies and practices that communicate a
mismatch between how women are seen and the qualities and experiences people tend to associate
with leaders.
These women make it into leadership roles, then essentially get pushed off a cliff into
a framework where it is difficult for women to succeed.
It's like getting dealt a hand of cards and realizing everyone is playing a different
game.
These policies and practices that require a shift are due to something called second
generation gender bias.
powerful but subtle and often invisible barriers for women that arise from cultural assumptions
and organizational structures, practices, and patterns of interaction that inadvertently
benefit men while putting women at a disadvantage. So why does this happen? Well, the lack of women
in leadership positions means women climbing the career ladder have no one to model who has dealt
with the same barriers as them.
And if they model themselves after men,
they're more likely to run into these invisible barriers.
Some jobs are inherently geared towards men
because they require flexibility
that a mother might not have,
such as extensive travel or consistently long hours,
or undervaluing skills typically exhibited by women,
such as building a team or avoiding a crisis, soft skills.
This leads to the double bind master suppression technique
where whatever you do, if you're a woman, you are wrong.
If you're direct, you're a bitch.
So how can organizations help?
Research states that mentoring and leadership programs
are necessary, but not enough.
I'm gonna repeat that statement
because I think it's really important.
Research states that mentoring and leadership programs are necessary, but not enough.
There are critical additional steps that must be taken to level the playing field.
First, second-generation gender bias education.
Teach both men and women about these biases so they become more visible and can begin
being addressed.
Craft safe spaces for leadership identity.
Women should be able to focus on the job, not overthink these invisible barriers.
A coaching relationship, a women's leadership program, a support group of peers in which
women can interpret messages is critical to their leadership identity.
Anchor development in leadership purpose.
Focusing on purpose can also lead women to take up activities that are critical to their success.
It allows them to look past what might make them uncomfortable or insecure
and engage in building new skills in a way that feels authentic to them.
Imposter Syndrome
Research shows that imposter syndrome is highest in high-achieving women.
So that means women in these leadership roles.
So what is imposter syndrome?
It's women who experience the imposter phenomenon maintain a strong belief that they are not intelligent.
In fact, they are convinced that they have fooled anyone who thinks otherwise.
The action here is understand imposter syndrome,
because this is largely something internal that women have to overcome.
However, peers can help by being aware of its existence, and if you see someone who
might be struggling with imposter syndrome, connect them to a mentor, an internal support
network, send them literature, send them a book, be a champion.
Family leave and parenthood.
Earlier we discussed how girls as young as 9 are considering having a family and raising
kids when they begin thinking about careers.
And the reality is society is teaching them they should be.
In a 2018 survey conducted by the Center for American Progress,
mothers were 40% more likely than fathers
to report that they had personally
felt the negative impact of child care issues
on their careers.
Women are still doing the heavy lifting when it comes to childcare.
The graphs here are from Women's Work, Mothers, Children, and the Global Childcare Crisis.
They illustrate the difference between time spent on childcare by men and women.
Sweden ranks the best.
It also has the least difference in weeks in a year spent on unpaid childcare for men and women.
But even the best ranked countries still skews towards female caregivers.
And the US? It's one of the only countries in the world that doesn't have mandatory paid
parental leave. Unsurprisingly, this is having an impact on the careers of women and their career
trajectory. So you can see here, even if women have access to flexible work arrangements,
they're not necessarily going to use those flexible work arrangements.
According to the paper, Breaking Gender Barriers, and where this graph is from.
Having a policy and allowing women to use it without penalty are two different matters.
Researchers call this the flexibility stigma, and it arises because women are effectively punished
if they take advantage of flexible work options to raise children and work simultaneously
or take a time out from tenure to have children. The moral here is that it is not enough to simply
offer flexible options. The options must be exercisable without consequence.
Real quick, let's take a deeper look at the government offerings of Sweden and the United States,
both because that's where the different avalanche offices are based, but also because Sweden did so
well in the rankings. In Sweden, both parents receive 480 days, that's 16 months of paid
parental leave, at roughly 80 percent of their salary. The days don't expire until the child
turns eight. In the U.S., maternity leave is three months and it's unpaid. For fathers, you get one
month, also unpaid.
So you may be wondering what we can do on an organizational level if this might be a government issue.
Well, our New York office has taken a cue from the culture of our Swedish counterparts via our flexibility policy.
At any time, we may see a colleague let us know they have to go help their child or work from home due to child care related responsibilities.
There is no guilt. If you have to leave early to take care of your child,
Avalanche trusts you're going to do what you have to do.
Some colleagues have also made specific arrangements to work from home on certain days.
This is equally important for both parents.
Consider if a father goes to take care of a sick child so that the mother can continue working for the day
versus the traditional vice-versa scenario.
The actions here are pay for parental leave for both male and female employees.
Paternity leave is just as important as maternity leave.
Support a flexible work policy.
And create a culture that normalizes child care.
These are critical for female leaders.
As their responsibilities increase in the workplace, they do as well at home.
Okay, we've made it through all three parts,
so I'm quickly going to summarize what we spoke about today.
According to the paper, breaking the glass ceiling,
companies that have been successful in breaking down
barriers have programs with the following characteristics
in common.
They are specific to the organization.
They are inclusive.
They address preconceptions and stereotypes.
They track progress.
They are comprehensive.
And they have CEO support.
This is Pam Hulfe, CEO of Avalanche Studios Group.
Diversity of perspectives and experiences
make both our games and workplace better.
As an industry, we can and must do much more
to empower and inspire those who identify as women
to consider a career in gaming.
Only by doing so on every level
will we as game developers start to reflect the diversity
of a global player demographic.
Thank you, PIM.
Here is a quick overview of all of the action items
we have discussed today.
If there's one takeaway from this talk, I hope it's the slide that you screen cap or
take a picture of.
Be a champion.
Is there any one of these that you can bring back to your organization?
Maybe more than one.
After watching this talk, if someone asks you what's the point of a talk like this,
or is this even a real problem, consider this.
System justification research has demonstrated that injunctification,
People's tendency to defend the status quo via considering whatever currently is as natural
and desirable and the way that things ought to be is an individual-level process that can account,
at least in part, for women's continued under-representation in male-dominated areas.
Just because things are the status quo doesn't mean they're okay.
And remember that quote from the start of the talk about how companies that have women in
leadership ranks outstrip their competition on every measure of profitability?
There's no reason why we shouldn't be trying to change things.
So if someone asks you about this talk, tell them, yes, this is important.
And I'm really glad you asked me.
Let's have a conversation about it.
Change the conversation by having the conversation.
Change the game.
And maybe one day, we can go from this to this.
Thank you.