All right, welcome everybody.
Thank you for joining us.
I'm Kelly Snyder.
I'm a producer at Bungie and one of the co-founding members
of the Bungie Diversity Committee
and former lead of Xbox Women in Gaming.
And we're here today to talk to you
about how you can foster diversity in games.
So kind of moving beyond the 101 of what is diversity
and moving into kind of the action steps
of what can we actually do as studios to help.
tangibly foster an inclusive and a diverse environment.
Which isn't to say that any of us here are perfect.
Nobody's got it all figured out.
Even this panel, we could be a little more diverse.
But we wanted to get together and talk to you guys
about what we've learned, our experiences,
and so that we can all share and learn and get better together.
Yeah.
So we'll do some quick panel introductions.
Sure.
So is that on?
Yeah.
OK.
I'm Elaine Chase.
I'm the vice president of global brand strategy and marketing
for Wizards of the Coast.
I lead the Magic the Gathering business there.
And in addition to my day job, I'm
also president of the board of Child's Play,
the charity for children's hospitals
and domestic shelters.
I'm Mary Olsen.
I'm the executive producer of the internal game development
team at 343.
We make Halo.
I'm Leah Hoyer.
I am the vice president of creative at Telltale Games.
Hi, I'm Joy Lau.
Hi, people in the corner.
I am a test engineer at Bungie and also a co-founding member of the Bungie diversity
committee and before I worked in games I was a professor in the philosophy of race and
gender at Virginia Tech.
Awesome.
So, in terms of format, each of our panelists is going to come up and give a short talk
talking about what they've done at their studio and then we're going to move into, I've got
some questions for them and we're going to discuss them as a group and then after the
panel is over we'll be available for if you guys want to come up and ask us questions.
So.
And Elaine is going to come up and kick it off.
Thank you.
So as I just said, I'm Elaine.
And I work at Wizards of the Coast.
And I make Magic the Gathering.
I've had the honor of working at Wizards for 19 years.
We're primarily known in the industry
as the titans of tabletop gaming.
But a few years ago, we started investing heavily
into building up our digital gaming capability
so we can bring our brands, Magic the Gathering and Dungeons
to life.
and the way they really deserved.
And as we started hiring, we realized
that we didn't really have a good talent
pipeline for the new set of skills
that we needed to bring into our building or for diversity.
Because I hope that you all realize
that having a diverse set of people
brings in greater skill set.
So we took a hard look at what that was.
And we realized that over the 25 plus years
we had been a company, we had been relying really heavily
on the passion of our fan base to fill our applicant pool.
And that just really wasn't going to get us
where we needed to be.
And so we looked at how we were presenting ourselves
and what we were saying.
And we realized that on top of that,
our culture had kind of drifted
and we didn't really know what we stood for anymore.
And if we couldn't clearly articulate what we stood for
and why it was awesome to come work at Wizards,
then how could we possibly convince other people to do that?
So we started a internal effort
to define our mission and values.
And that alone, that whole process
is worth its own GDC talk,
which maybe I'll give one day.
And Joe's actually going to talk about Bungie's mission and vision, mission and values process
in a little bit.
So I'll cut to the chase and just say that the number one value, as stated by our employees
ourselves, was diversity and inclusion.
And so we took a really hard look and said, okay, well, how are we living that?
And how can we be better?
And what can we do to make sure that we're doing that to the very best that we can?
And so the things I'm going to talk to you today are focusing on the applicant journey.
So you've probably been in a bunch of talks today already
talking about the player journey and the importance of a funnel
and getting people through the door and making sure they stick.
And so that's the kind of things that we're
going to focus on for my part of the talk.
So some things we did.
We revamped our career website to showcase our mission
and our values, to feature the diversity of our employee base,
highlight our amazing family-friendly benefits
and charitable activity, just try
to be overall more inspirational for people
trying to join the company.
We're doing more targeted recruiting and employment
branding at local venues, like the Grace Hopper event
and Geek Girl Con in Seattle, as well as hosting tech lady
events at our office.
We're doing industry talks like this one.
And we're generally just being louder and prouder
about waving our flag as an employer of choice who's
actively looking for diverse candidates.
So once we have people's attention,
the next step is to craft a really good job description.
So the critical thing to think of here
is that your job description.
is the first conversation that you're having with the person
that you're eventually going to hire.
So when you think of it that way,
think about showing off to them what the team they're
going to join is like, what the culture is like,
so they can really envision themselves in that environment.
Emphasize how they can contribute to success,
the success of the company, not just at the individual level.
Try to keep any requirements list to a minimum.
So studies show that men will apply to a job description
where they meet about 60% of the requirements
on a requirement list.
Women tend to think requirements are requirements
and will only apply if they meet 100% of that list.
So instead of requirements, think more of things
like skills that will help success,
or things that are a plus, or things
like that worded differently than just requirements.
Avoid loaded words.
Gendered is really obvious, but also avoid words like rock star and ninja and things that can evoke kind of a bro-centric mentality.
I guess if you work for Rockstar Games, you can use rock star, but that might be the exception.
Clearly state a commitment to diversity and actively invite diverse applicants to apply.
And then here's actually the most important point.
Have your job description and show it off to the people in your company, to a diverse group of people, and have them comment on it and see what they say.
You'll be really surprised to hear what they might say in terms of things that seem innocuous to you,
but to somebody reading it from the outside, just kind of turns them off or makes them question if they'd be a good fit or not.
So you take all that, and let's see what that looks like.
So up on the screen is a portion of a revamped job description for a design manager in our Magic R&D team.
So I'm not going to read this to you because it's really long, but you can capture it, and of course it'll be up on the vault later.
So you've got this great job description. Now what do you do with it?
So you've got to go out beyond your normal channels,
go out beyond your website, go out beyond LinkedIn,
and go to places where diverse pools of candidates will be.
Go to places like Women in Gaming and Blacks in Technology.
Go to diversity groups at your local colleges.
The point is, if you go where they're gathering,
they're going to know that you have a commitment to looking
for them, and they're going to be more eager to apply and see
themselves in your company.
So then.
Make sure you're actually getting them in through you
to your interview stage, right?
Like you don't want to just leave it out there
and leave it to chance.
You actually want to talk to some of these people.
So I have my own kind of personal management rule
that I require my hiring managers
to at least talk to a woman.
Now, you don't need to hire for diversity.
You don't, that's not the point, right?
And the point here is not to say you need
to have diversity hire slots or anything like that.
The point is, is if you talk to people,
you'll find people with skill sets
that maybe you never would have found otherwise, right?
So thinking about that applicant journey again,
thinking about that funnel, you want
to get as many people into that funnel
as you can because then eventually you'll
get them more out down the other side.
And then when you actually have people in,
live it in your interview.
Have a diverse group of people interviewing on your panels
and that they're talking to.
You want that for two reasons.
One is you want to make sure you've
got a broad amount of feedback from your own employees
to give you a broader sense of what
that candidate is capable of.
And the second reason is because you've got a greater chance of that candidate
seeing someone like them thriving in your company.
Right? If you see someone like you thriving, you're more likely
to think that, oh hey, maybe this is a place that I can be successful too.
So, shout out here by the way to
Ken Trupp on our R&D team. He's a design
designer there who crafted this job description. He's a great ally
and that leads me to my last point which is allies and the importance of allies
in your company.
So we've got our head of magic R&D design group is Mark Rosewater.
And just last week he answered this question on Tumblr that I'm going to pop up in a minute.
And this one I am going to read out loud to you.
I get that you're trying to mock diversity and inclusion,
but I think it comes from an ignorance of what it means to feel excluded.
When you've lived your life in the majority,
it's easy to take it for granted
when you see yourself represented
in the products and entertainment that you use.
But every time we branch out,
and I'm not exaggerating, I mean every time,
and represent a new group of people,
I get heartfelt messages from them
about how much it means to them
to see themselves in the game.
The reason Wonder Woman and Black Panther
have been such cultural touchstones
is because they're allowing new groups of people
to experience something they've never experienced before.
I get that it's easy to mock that when it's something so basic to your experience that
you don't even recognize that it's a thing you'd miss if you didn't have it.
But I beg for you to try to see life through other people's perspectives, just as I always
talk about how good designers see their game through different players' perspectives.
Try to take actions that build up the world and make it a better place for everyone than
to tear it down for others to make your world better in comparison.
So thank you to Ken and to Mark and to all the great allies I have at Wizards.
and here in this room, and everywhere else in the industry.
Because this helps.
Thanks.
Yeah.
Hi, I'm Mary Olson.
As I mentioned, I'm the executive producer
for the internal development team at 343 Industries.
And we make the, we create the Halo franchise games.
So I'm happy to be here today.
Diversity in our beloved industry
is a loaded and complex and extremely important topic.
I will attempt to draw lessons that
relate to fostering diversity of thought, gender, background,
culture, perspective, abilities, and skill.
But I want to be up front with that.
I'm coming to you as a cisgendered female
and will be sharing some of my personal experiences
to illustrate lessons we're learning.
We need to be fostering diversity at all levels.
This conference is a good example.
If anyone, this conference is a good example
of the industry side.
So if anyone has been to GDC 10 years ago versus today,
it's a completely different conference
and with a lot more focus on inclusivity, and it shows.
Then as studios and organizations,
we also need to be looking at diversity.
And some of my colleagues on this panel
are going to go more deeply into that.
And then there's what we can do as individuals.
And that individual learning and influence
is the piece that I'm going to focus on today.
Before I do that, here are a few of the tactical efforts
we do across 343, Xbox, and Microsoft.
Microsoft's mission statement is to empower
every person and every organization on the planet
to achieve more.
So that's our foundation.
Xbox has diversity-focused initiatives that provide community, advocacy, and a strong presence across the company and in the industry,
like Women in Gaming and other organizations like that.
Gaming for Everyone focuses on diversity in our fans.
We have inclusivity-focused core values.
And at 343, we have a diverse senior leadership team.
And that has made a tangible difference in our ability
to attract and retain diverse employees.
We've changed our approach to hiring and recruiting
and the language we use in job descriptions as well.
Some of the stuff that Elaine was mentioning
and some ideas from her that I plan to steal.
And Microsoft has a number of valuable trainings
required for managers, for example,
around unconscious bias and dialoguing across differences,
which I've personally found really valuable.
Beyond initiatives and practices,
I believe that fostering diversity
lies in the attitudes and actions of individuals
as well as teams and companies.
Each of us has a responsibility
to challenge our assumptions daily
and grow in our understanding of the issues we face
when it comes to making needed change.
Here are a few anecdotes from myself
and drawing from other people on our team
to illustrate the need for ongoing growth and change.
Because we have a long way to go.
So I've spent most of my 23-year career in audio production
and leadership for games thinking
it was enough to just be a woman and show up.
I'm really results-focused, and I've always been heads-down
and really immersed in the game that I'm making at the time.
Outside of that, my time goes to my family.
I have two AFAB kids.
That's assigned female at birth.
They taught me that.
They teach me a lot every day.
Beyond just staying heads down and focused on the job,
this is hard to admit.
I have spent a lot of my career being part of the problem
and fueling the problem.
I've sometimes, what I mean by that,
I've sometimes been really hard on women
that I've encountered along the way.
And I really have had this expectation
of all of them to be really high performing superstars,
representing womankind as like its highest caliber
at all times.
And I've since realized that a really big part of this problem is that there's only
room for high performers for any minority group in this industry.
And one of the signs of progress that I hope we see and that we do start to see is when
there is room for solid average performers and the whole spectrum as there is with the
kind of majority.
So I think that'll be good progress.
Microsoft hosted a dialogue across differences training,
and we were asked how inclusive we thought
our respective teams would be to someone coming out
as trans or queer in our environment,
on a scale of one to five.
And the first thing that popped in my head was,
well, five if they're high performing.
And so that really uncovered, that was enlightening for me,
and it really uncovered this bias
that I've been carrying around.
It's not until more recent years, honestly,
from trainings like that, from long conversations
with colleagues, keeping the conversation going,
long conversations with my now young adult kids.
who are trying to work out their place in the world as well,
wrestle through some of this.
And more than anything, the process of building and growing
and fostering a team and strengthening a team,
that I've really started to challenge my biases
and assumptions in a meaningful way
and have transformed my personal thinking
about what it means to really be inclusive.
I still put the game first.
That's still a value that I have.
The difference is.
that I now realize that building a diverse team
and having a diverse team is putting the game first.
That's what we need to make the best game that we can make.
And this is a worthwhile journey.
A colleague of mine who is in a leadership position
at our studio had feedback from a former manager
that she's aggressive.
She's a self-aware person and it didn't fit feedback
she'd gotten in the past.
So she dug in further with him wanting to understand
if the feedback.
was his opinion or it had come from other people on the team.
He admitted that it was just his perception.
So she took the time to talk to him
about how common this perception is
of women in leadership positions.
And she sent him some articles to help give him
more awareness of this specific type of bias.
This was a situation where he lacked awareness
and once brought to his attention,
he was extremely receptive and eagerly read
the information she sent and asked her for more.
That was a start of a conversation
and a real change in their relationship.
So she was willing to educate and teach the behavior she wanted to see and he
was willing to learn and it transformed his management style. I had a person on
my team raise concerns and give some critical feedback about a peer and he
came back to me later with really different feedback.
he hadn't realized that this person had a disability,
which explained the issues he was having.
And most importantly, once he was aware
and he changed how he was interacting,
his concerns were alleviated
and his feedback actually took a total about face.
And he and other people on the team
have now called out how her disability
is a strength on our team, not a weakness.
She brings a unique perspective, some highly developed skills as a result, that no one
else on our team has, and she's a strong advocate.
I want to call out too that it was really impressive that he came back and actually
admitted that and took the time to change his feedback but also say, hey, look, I just
wasn't aware.
I think it's so important we have to be willing to stumble and learn as we go.
This is not a perfect journey because we're all kind of figuring it out and there's a
lot to learn.
We recently had someone on our team leave,
and this wasn't the reason she left,
but in her exit interview, she noted the locker room talk
that she experienced day to day among the people around her.
And it really, she didn't wanna stop it,
she didn't wanna be the fun killer.
So instead, she just remained uncomfortable
and just dealt with it.
It made us realize that we need to proactively create safe opportunities to discuss unique challenges of different groups of people like this.
And we need to train and educate managers and people on the teams in such a way that we're creating advocates on our team.
Sometimes it's just helpful to have someone else be speaking up for you.
And here's the final story that I'll tell.
I was wrestling through what to share for this presentation
with a few of the leads on my team,
sharing with them that I find it really hard
because it's so important for us
to keep this conversation going,
but there's also a sense like you're never doing enough.
The next morning, one of them shared this story with me.
On a Friday night, he and his daughter
were talking about their day as he tucked her in.
He told her that he had lunch with his boss
and she asked, what's his name?
And...
He said, well, my boss's name is Mary, and she's a woman.
This apparently blew her mind.
And she lit up and started asking a bunch of questions
about how I got into this position.
And at several points throughout the weekend,
she let him know that she wanted to be his boss one day,
like Mary.
I think she's probably already the boss.
He was hard on himself because.
Her worldview up to this point hadn't shown her
that she could do something else like that.
And that was a worldview he felt responsible for.
I'll also mention that she's three.
So good news, there's still time for her
to develop a broader worldview.
He thanked me for helping teach his daughter
that she can be anything she wants to be.
And they're now having very different conversations.
It's also a reminder that showing up sometimes really
it's not enough, but it can help make a big difference.
So if you feel like an outsider, don't stay in isolation.
Find mentors, others who understand, advocates and support.
And if you love making games, stick around
and do what you can do to affect change
and develop our industry.
To everyone, no matter what your background, make room.
You can be part of this ongoing conversation
and part of change in your individual day-to-day life.
Thank you.
Hi, I'm Leah, and like I said before, I'm at Telltale.
I am here in part to share all of this,
and also I'm gonna tell you a couple stories,
because I work at Telltale.
I think every person in this room is here
because you maybe are encountering a problem,
you've seen issues, there are certain things
that you're looking to change and solve
while you're working in this industry.
Maybe you're hiring people.
And it's of course very important for you to figure out
exactly, specifically, what is that problem
that you might be trying to solve?
It might be some existing culture,
it might be problems of recruiting.
But once you identify that, the thing that I really
want to encourage everyone in this room to be thinking about
is truly the power of why.
Like why is that thing something
that you are looking to change?
Something that you are looking to solve?
You have to be really honest about the various factors
that might go into that.
And.
To illustrate this, what I actually want to say is,
I'm going to tell you a pretty great story
that I actually think can be a good illustration
of sort of the power of why.
Before I came to Telltale,
I actually worked at a company called ArenaNet,
known for their Guild Wars franchise.
And about six months into my tenure there,
the entire company got an email from our HR department
that said a colleague of ours,
who we used to know as a man,
wanted to be referred to by the pronouns of she, her,
was going to be using a different name.
She was going to be fine if you asked her any questions.
She knew we were gonna slip up and maybe make mistakes.
But also if there was anything that people
didn't maybe feel comfortable asking her,
talking to her about the HR department
was gonna be there and be open to discussion.
I was so kind of taken by the fact that
this person who I was actually good friends with, you know, hadn't talked to me even directly,
but had felt like, you know what, I know this is going to be a problem.
I want to rip the Band-Aid off, honestly, just once so I don't have to go around to
320 people, and went to the HR department looking for guidance and help, and they really
stepped up and said, look, if it would be easier, we will send something out, and we
can make that announcement and know that this is someplace that
not only are you saying it, but that we are saying
that this is absolutely something
that shouldn't be an issue for the company.
It should be something that everyone
should be very accepting of.
And I never once in the entire time that I was there
heard a negative comment, any kind of like rude question,
anything along the way, because the other thing
about the culture of this company
was that I knew it was never gonna be tolerated.
And I think the other people working there also knew that.
This person, it was legitimately not even an issue
for the entire company because this person
was still our friend and still our colleague.
The thing that I was most kind of taken with
was also over the next six months,
two other people had the same transition
and went through the same process
with very much the same results.
And I will say, first off, huge props to these three women
for going through what was obviously going to be a difficult personal transition and being honest
with who they really were. But I also know from having talked to them that it was easier for that
second and third person, like somewhat easier to know that they were going to go through this
process, make this announcement, because they were going to be accepted at least at their workplace.
There was that like strength there.
that I think was something that was just built into the culture of the company.
And so I look at that as when I think of the why, the why was that possible as I look at what
ArenaNet sort of developed a culture over time. First off, they make Guild Wars and in Guild Wars
2, this right here, five of the core cast members of the story of Guild Wars. Two of them are a
same-sex couple.
One of them is a young girl with physical limitations.
And what I love about the stories that are in Guild Wars
is that's never what the story is about.
You know, the story is absolutely
about dealing with the struggles of video game stuff.
You know, I mean, there's big villains,
and there's big problems, and there's dragons,
and there's world things to solve.
And we just have great representation in the characters
and in the story of that game.
And that.
is I feel really interesting because I think what happens at ArenaNet is first
off any company starts off saying things like we value diversity, we think
inclusivity is important. Well actually not every company does. Every company
should and make sure at the baseline that's what you're doing in your
workplace. Whether you're an individual person, whether you're a person who's
hiring and managing people, whether you run a company, it is important to say it.
you
and people talk about how talk is cheap, talk is a good start, right?
From there, though, they also were very much backing it up with their actions.
The actions that clearly, as we all know, speak louder than words.
And what I think is great about the game company that is making entertainment,
they made stuff that backed up their idea of inclusivity and diversity.
And we have an ability in this industry to do all of that,
to change the dialogue, not just in our companies,
but in society, and I think that's amazing.
And here, it's actually tough for us to even look back
at the history of ArenaNet and say,
well, where did it start?
There's kind of a chicken and egg thing here.
The truth is, it doesn't matter where you start.
You can start by making something,
you can start by saying something,
you can start by putting your actions out there.
But as you start to go through that cycle and build on it,
all of a sudden, you turn that question of,
why is this a problem to,
why is that company doing such great stuff?
Why is it feeling that,
because they say, they act, and they make.
I also now wanna talk about a slightly different issue
when I moved over to Telltale.
I showed up as the head of the creative department,
which is writing, design,
creative directors, voiceover,
and we had.
really bizarrely huge from my perspective number of open spaces for
narrative designers. And I was having discussions with people and they were
saying things like, well it's such a strange thing that we do here at Telltale,
we'll go down to Hollywood and those people don't understand interactive or
we'll go to game studios and most game studios just don't care about story the
way we do. So getting a person who really is a good writer or narrative designer
is like almost impossible. It's like finding a unicorn. And I was like, okay.
That's an interesting conundrum and I do understand what they're talking about because, hey, we
are looking for folks that are definitely different than what's going on in the industry.
And to be honest, it also, we're looking as we're filling these things with diverse voices.
That's super important because you know we tell stories and stories are universal and
stories need to represent all of us.
what the suggestion I had is like, hey, could we could we see about making unicorns? And I kind of
got some blank stares. And the whole point was to me, if you are just looking to people in, say,
the video games industry who are already working in the video games industry, you're never going
to make the video games industry more diverse. You might borrow.
or steal some diversity from one company,
but now they have the same problem,
or you might get certain talent out there,
regardless of however they identify,
you're going to be pulling it from different places
and we're not going to change it up.
What if we went out to people and gave them a mechanism
that if they just understood at their core
what it is that we do, could we be their first job
and really find something that was awesome?
So what we actually did is something we called internally
our Unicorn Summit.
And it is our creative workshop that we actually
did this time last year.
We, towards the end of 2016, put out an open call.
And what we asked was people submit a statement
about why they would like to work at Telltale
and why they would like to be part of this creative workshop
that we put on.
And they had to make a twine.
And twine is a quick, easy to understand,
you can all pick it up, way to do a simple,
interactive story around a prompt.
They sent those two things in and we just said,
look, we don't really even care about your resume.
We don't wanna know any of that.
We took all the names off of it,
looked at those two things,
and we invited 22 people to come be part
of our day-long creative workshop.
The diversity that we got in this thing
was actually really astounding.
It was about 40% women.
We had age ranges from 19 to 57,
which also, absolutely,
Age in the games industry is also something we really need to be looking at.
It's not okay to say that people sort of age out of being able to make great content, or
that you have to get a certain amount of experience before you can make great content.
And we had a wide variety of racial diversity.
From this, at the end of the day, what we did after getting this is ask people to redo
the thing that they submitted to us, and we looked at that, we got a chance to actually
see their soft skills, how they worked, how they were part of it, how much they took feedback,
all those things, and we actually made two offers.
Both of them happened to be women, but it was because they came, they showed up, it
was their first jobs in the games industry, and they are amazing at what they do.
We are so happy to have them on our team.
I don't think we would have...
filled out what we needed to do at the time
with the right kind of candidates nearly as quickly
if we hadn't actually opened up the pool.
And I know that was brought up earlier.
You've got to think about how do you go out
to different groups of people.
So really, in summary though, with all of this,
I would like to encourage you to think about,
say, act, make, all around your why.
And I think if we're all doing that,
like,
Why is it the way it is?
How can we do these things to make it better?
We are going to see greater diversity in our industry
in the very near future.
Thank you.
Hi, in the interest of accessibility,
I want to give a shout out to the AB guys
for giving me this box to stand on
because I couldn't see over the lectern.
Cool, so hi, I'm Jo.
I am a test engineer at Bungie,
and I was also one of the founding members
of the Bungie Diversity Committee.
And in my talk, I'm going to look at our studio
and our values and how we live our values
through our game development.
So let's start by talking about
where this all came about for Bungie.
So our studio's been around for a little over 25 years,
and early on, our culture was very informal.
However, we are now a considerably larger company,
and we recognize the need to foster diversity intentionally,
proactively, and I think most importantly, with structure.
And so in late 2016, our leadership recognized
that our organizational growth required us
to basically evaluate and write down
and codify our company values.
So just a little bit about values.
Values aren't meant to be a kind of checklist you just go through and you're like, yeah, achievement unlocked. Yay
like it's a thing that you live and
Our values are intended to remind us of how we work and how we treat each other
so these are things that you embody and
So what I have here is our first draft and this was shown to the company and after we did that
We realized something was missing
So we didn't have anything that captured our commitment to diversity and inclusion.
And like sure, there's a sense in which you can kind of imply it from the other values,
but we also felt like it was important enough to stand on its own.
So we went back and we redrafted a seventh value and this is what it looks like.
And you can also see all these values on our website, so don't feel like you need to read them all.
So, it was important.
in the elements of this value here,
like the wording and the imagery
really needed to reflect the value itself.
So it shows a broad range of people
from our studio and our community.
And the reason that we wanted to do this
is because just talking about values
without the action behind it was just really meaningless.
And we wanted to have this genuinely represent who we were.
I will also say at Bungie,
we encourage employees to
self-organize and engage with diversity values, I mean diversity issues. So we have the studio
LGBTQIA club, we have bungee ladies, we have bungee people of color, for example. So with
leadership supporting more diverse practices and employees driving these kind of grassroots
organizations, it was just this really perfect opportunity to focus on diversity. And that's
basically what we did. So we focused on diversity. We formed literally focus groups that
talked about diversity under three sub-pillars of the studio,
our game community, and the industry as a whole.
And so we had over 120 people in the studio participate in these discussions.
And so what I'm going to do for the rest of the talk is
kind of just cover a couple of things that we've done under those three pillars.
And I just want to point out this is not an exhaustive list or anything by any means.
It's things that we're all learning and things that we're planning to do.
So.
Yeah, so here's our first pillar, which is our studio.
And here are a couple of things that we've done.
So we formed the Bungee Diversity Committee
with 10 members and we have clearly defined roles and goals.
And this sets a clear expectation for our involvement
with the studio because we are a volunteer committee.
We operate as an advisory and an advocacy group
for the studio so people can bring questions to us
and consult us.
And we facilitate discussions internally to make sure that diversity is a topic that is
at the forefront of people's minds and that people can openly ask questions and that they
have a space to do that.
We also work with leadership in improving things like transparency and communication
and helping to empower leaders and managers in becoming better allies through providing
training and studio resources.
And I know like Elaine and Leah have already talked about this a little, but we also work
with recruiting and HR and we do a lot of the things that they've mentioned, so I won't
talk a lot about that.
But we are also moving to look at blind, like we're helping recruiting with blind reviews
of applications, for example.
So we have made progress there.
Okay, so our second pillar is that of the community.
And the opening line from our diversity value is...
We want everyone to feel their identity is welcome
in our studio and in the worlds we create.
And this is kind of really the centerpiece
of the community pillar.
And so I know I've talked a lot about pillars
and there's pillars everywhere,
but this is where it gets weird
because there are two sub pillars.
So it's like you have diversity
and then you've got your three types of diversity pillars.
And now there's like pillars all the way down
with these two sub pillars.
So the two sub-pillars, people at our studio have a place in our community.
And people in our community have a place in our games.
So on the first side of that sub-pillar, last year we had a presence at several events that
we felt embodied our values.
So this picture is actually one of us doing a Let's Play at GigaCon, which is a convention
that happens every year in Seattle and it celebrates.
women and girls that work in STEM and games and comics and yeah, so we
We had just like shipped d2 at this point. So we were just kind of showing a group of girls what our game was like and
This is really important because these are events that we staff with bungee employees and it gives people a chance to see
People who look like them and have them think I could do that
Like I can I can be a game dev like that's cool
And yeah, on the other side of the pillow here, we have our community.
And our community team makes a really strong effort to highlight and celebrate a cross-section of our members.
feature a lot of diverse streamers and artists and cosplayers, and the face of our community
is diverse, and we want to send that message to everyone.
So I know I'm main a Titan, so I have my Titan shirt on right now, but even if you're main
a warlock like this person, you still have a space in our community.
Okay, cool.
Finally, our last pillar is that of the industry as a whole.
As we move towards an increasingly global studio,
we really want to make games that embody our values.
And so we tried to do this through a game
you might know of called Destiny.
The characters in our universe
are representatives of humanity.
And they cover different axes of representation.
So we have race and gender and ability
in the LGBT spectrum, for example.
And we want these to reflect that the world is diverse
and that our player base is diverse.
But it's not just that.
We want to celebrate and normalize these facts,
because that's just how it is.
Outside of our game, it's also important for us
and our values to support our employees and people
in our industry.
So for example, one thing we did last year
was we joined with other companies in entertainment
and tech in submitting an amicus brief.
And
Basically, the point of this, the idea is just to acknowledge each other and to show
that we have each other's backs.
And this is really important for people who are from underrepresented groups.
So it's really simple and effective.
It's just a way that you can say, I see you and I support you.
And for someone that doesn't hear that a lot, that really goes a long way.
And finally, we also want to continue driving these discussions with our colleagues and
peers, so all of you.
So.
We're all learning together and we're all going to be working towards a common goal.
So I really encourage all of you to continue these conversations and share information
and share ideas about this and just keep those dialogues going because no one is perfect
but we can all get closer to being better together.
And that's all.
Thanks.
Thanks so much to our panelists.
So we're going to go into a little bit of moderated
questions.
And to kick it off, one thing we want to talk about
was a little bit on microaggressions.
So often, the pain of being a minority
is often felt by a lot of little things
adding up over time, kind of the death by 1,000 cuts.
And Joe, did you want to give some extra context if anybody's
not super familiar with the?
Yeah, I just like without like giving specific examples of microaggressions, I guess one way to understand it is
like suppose you're in a small studio and there's only like you know you're one of 10 people
and you're the only member of an underrepresented group at your studio and let's say every single
day someone like each one of your colleagues comes up to you and like makes an like a passing
microaggressive comment and
you're just like, okay, like, you know, I don't know how people react to microaggressions.
But what that means is for each of those interactions, the person that's doing that
action has experienced one microaggression in that they, you know, directed one at you.
But for you, you've received nine of them. And now multiply that by the number of days
that you work there and scale up the studio.
And that is what the death by a thousand cuts is really like.
It's like you get tired of this stuff.
Yeah, and so one thing that makes sense
is that if a lot of negative things
can add up to make a big difference,
I think it's also possible for a lot of positive things,
micro affirmations, if you will, to add up
to make a big difference.
What are things that you guys have found in your studios,
the little things that make a big difference?
I got two.
Excited.
OK.
The first tangible achievement that I did when I got onto the executive team at Wizards
of the Coast was I got better feminine hygiene products in the bathrooms.
Seriously, I went into the bathroom right after I got promoted and looked and went,
and went, wait, who am I going to complain to?
Me?
Right.
So seriously, like little things make a difference like that.
And then the second one I wanted to mention
is, so at the Child's Play auction this past December,
one of our speakers that we had, who's
very active in the hospital community, she uses a wheelchair.
And she let Child's Play know that.
And they built her a ramp to come up onto the podium, right?
Like, if you were in a wheelchair,
you wouldn't be able to get up here where we are right now.
And she came up to do her speech.
And the first thing she said is she
gushed over the fact that she has done speeches tons of times.
And this is the first time someone had provided her a ramp.
And that made her feel normal.
And it's just those kinds of things
can really make a difference to make
people feel like it's normal.
I also think allyship is a really important point.
And I know some of you mentioned that as well.
So there's a study that shows that people
are more likely to believe other people that look like them.
which I don't know what it's like.
But...
Even on diversity topics?
Yeah, so it's like, what this means is white men are more likely to believe other white men,
even on issues of diversity.
So, take from that what you will.
But what this means is, if you have that,
it's like, if you are in that position to be able to speak about something
and to support someone that is underrepresented,
then, like, do that, because...
And it doesn't have to just...
And I'm not just, like, saying this to the white men in the audience, but, like, you know...
if you're white, or if you're straight,
if you're able-bodied, if you're cisgender,
use your voice to help everyone else
that isn't in that position.
And I think that's really,
I think that's one of the things that helps
is just acknowledging that there are other people
that are not like you that exist,
and normalize the fact that they are there
and recognize them, so yeah.
Yeah, thanks.
Thank you for those two claps.
Yeah.
Cool.
So.
In general, what have you guys, like what are some of the biggest challenges that you faced
and what are some of the biggest lessons that you've learned along the way?
Yeah, I will say when I first moved into the games industry I used to actually make
cartoons for Disney for a living and that's what I wound up doing and then
transitioned through my work there into working at Xbox actually and in gaming and I
was when I first came there, honestly, I got a lot of comments about the fact that I wasn't a big Halo player.
Sorry.
And the fact that maybe I wasn't a real gamer in a lot of ways, even though I will tell you, like, I play all
sorts of games. I play a lot of D&D. I play a lot of some of, and I play a lot of mobile games, and I
play a lot of actually video games, but just because I wasn't mainly a first-person shooter player,
Somehow I was sort of like, my cred wasn't that great.
And I would say that when I started to be then brought
into sort of leadership teams and got promoted,
and I will say in three times in my career,
I've been the first woman to come into say,
a senior leadership team or running a group of things.
I definitely in the first several years of my career
in the games industry, I wanted to fit in.
And I think I was then trying to because a lot of that was,
you know, kind of hitting at me
in sort of microaggression kind of ways,
that sense of like, oh, ooh,
maybe they don't think I belong here and all that stuff,
to a point where I started to believe it.
And then after a while, I was like, no,
you know what, I got this.
But once you realize that too,
what it also made me realize
is that it is actually my job to speak up.
It is my job to be like,
I think that we're thinking about this
from a very narrow point of view.
And so over time, that's really the thing that I learned.
It was a challenge that then became something that I know
that each one of you can do that,
sort of in the idea of like the ally.
But it is literally my job,
and while it shouldn't be necessarily put on me
as the only woman in some of those rooms,
you know what, if it's not me, who else is going to do it?
And sometimes it's a lot of pressure, but I take that on.
And in a way that that's the way that I've
started to see change.
And you actually get a lot of people acknowledging it
and giving you more respect.
I think one thing that I've realized and tried
to say to a lot of people in my team
is this concept of really well-intentioned people.
and how outdated the kind of colorblind, well-intentioned colorblindness kind of concept is.
Outdated feels like the right word.
Like, it's just not where we are anymore, and it's not valuable.
And so the kind of well-intentioned comments that I mean are like, no, no, I love everybody,
I treat everybody the same, I treat everybody equally, I don't even just think about who
they are.
I just like...
You know, I just think they're all awesome, and stuff like that.
We can't afford that, because then you're managing everyone as the same person, or then
you're interacting with everybody as the same person.
That's actually not appropriate.
We need to recognize where people are coming from.
We need to recognize who they are, see them for who they are, not be colorblind.
Not be like, oh, we have love in our hearts, and we see everyone the same.
I mean that's a well-intended, I see that so much with people who just really want to do the right thing
and have no idea that that's the wrong thing.
And so I think that's something that, we try to bring awareness to, but that's something that I think is something that, you know, we're just, there's just not room anymore.
I think as an industry also we are very competitive and we're also conditioned to avoid failure.
this is the thing about being an ally, you will fail at some point, but it's okay.
It's like, you will make mistakes, like in the examples Mary and Leo were talking about,
like you won't get everything perfect all the time, because if you did, we wouldn't need to be here.
Yeah, like you'll get called out by people you've inadvertently hurt, but use this. I think what
the important point from this is, is take that as a like moment to learn from that, and
just acknowledge that you've done something that's not awesome, apologize, take it as
a teaching moment and move on.
And that's what it, and I feel like part of allyship is to do that and not, like you know,
and like to continue supporting the people that you've hurt instead of just like doubling
down on it, which I don't believe any of you would do, but yeah, it's, but what we need
to do is assume good intent on both sides.
So just make sure that, you know, if you are hurt, someone...
Let someone know that you've hurt them, but then also don't assume that they did that
because they were being an ass necessarily.
Maybe they just need to know.
I actually wanted to riff a little bit on the colorblindness kind of comment.
So it's important to treat people as individuals, but then it's also important to kind of pull
back and look at the macro trends that you see, because sometimes when you just focus
on individuals, you miss the larger trends that are happening.
So a really good example for this is, in the past,
when we've decided to send people to GDC here
as training opportunities, it's been a conversation
between an employee and their manager, right?
And they kind of decide, hey, is this the right place for you
to go?
Is this the right opportunity?
This year, for the first time, the executive team
looked at the list of the couple dozen people
that were on the list to attend GDC.
And I noticed that there were two women out
of the couple dozen of people on the list, myself
and one person from my team.
And I said to all the other dudes, hey, there's only two women and it's me and someone on
my team, what's up with that?
And we identified a thing that we just didn't realize that was there, right?
And because of that, now there are a bunch more people who are here.
At least one is sitting in this room right now.
Yay, Marissa!
Oh, and Allison's over there too.
Yay!
Awesome.
Thank you.
Welcome.
So switching gears a little bit
While many of us are working on increasing diversity within our studios
sometimes we can have members of our own communities who are
Less than enthused about the topic of diversity to put it generously
Have you guys kind of tackled that issue?
Wait, you mean people in our community might not be 100% gun-headed?
So I kind of feel like right now I should just pull out my phone and look at the most recent
notification I have from Twitter right now. I think that would be fun. So the thing about
magic, I'll talk about magic specifically for a minute, the thing about magic is that our
community is interesting in the way that it's a face-to-face based community, which is a little
bit different than the communities that most of you guys manage.
And because of that, there's a lot of really good positive stuff that goes on in that community.
I love my community so much.
They are the best, really the best people in the world.
But there's also people there who decide that for them it's more fun to annoy those people,
right?
And the issue is that I can't just like block their account.
I can't just, you know, keep them out of the game, right?
Because the community for magic is beyond.
kind of a platform like that, right? Like the community for magic is the world, right?
So I can't ban people from the world, right?
At least not in an ethical or legal way.
And I can't make them stop being mean, right? Like I can't do that either.
So the question is kind of what do you do there, right?
How can you try to make sure that your community,
the wonderful goodness of the community that's out there knows.
that you as a company have their back, especially recognizing the limitations that you have
as a company, right?
Like it's a really kind of hard thing to balance.
So I wish I could say I had it all figured out.
Unfortunately, I don't.
I like to think that we make decisions that move us in the right direction.
And I'll say that we've gone through some really tough times lately with some things
that have been going on with people even pulling people from outside of our community coming
and attacking our community members just to be mean and rile people up.
And it's nice because sometimes I get things like I actually came to work one day
when we were having this tough time and there was a handwritten letter that someone
from our community had sent me just a, hey, I just wanted to say I appreciate what you do.
And I keep that pinned up before my desk.
Any other thoughts on that?
Yeah, so I guess like we
So like Destiny is an online game so our community is slightly different but we also build mechanisms
into the game to minimize toxicity and encourage fair play. So when you play if you're running
around in the world you don't automatically start voice chatting with people. Like we don't have
open voice chat, we have guided games which allows people to like you know find other people like
they enjoy the place like if they enjoy the same play style and
you know, over time that helps to make friends.
And I think one of the things about our community
is also making sure that we elevate the positive voices
there as well and, you know, amplify those ones
because those are the ones that we want,
like we value them and we also have,
and so like, you know, just to get back to Elaine's point,
Like, you know, there are things that are going to happen.
And so one of the things we want to do is just make sure
that we can mitigate for those situations.
So, you know, for example, we have a player support team,
we have a security team,
and we will investigate these sorts of things.
Like, you know, if people are being toxic members
of the community, we will investigate and we will ban them.
Because if you want to have a place
where people feel safe and welcome,
sometimes you have to do that.
Yeah, it's letting your players know
that you have their backs.
It's going back to that back swing.
Yay.
So some quick closing thoughts.
So if someone in the audience right now,
if they want to start something at their studio,
at their company around diversity
to help increase inclusion, what are some immediate next steps
that you think that they can take?
I will talk about another story from ArenaNet.
When I showed up, there was a women in games chapter.
But I will say you could do this with any kind of diversity.
in games group. There was a small group of about five women who would get together for lunch every once in a while,
but they even came to me as the first member of the senior staff that was a woman and were like,
you know, we'd love to make this bigger and not just us
having lunch and talking about some things. And what we wound up doing was just putting out an open invitation.
We did it around the beginning of the year, but you know what? Any day's a good day to start something and said,
let's have a brunch. Let's start off with a breakfast meeting and it's the games
industry so it was like 10 a.m. But we brought people in, we served mimosas and
we had pastries and it was an hour and a half of us whiteboarding about what are
some of the things that we would love to do as a group that was a concrete thing
we would produce like an event or
items or a giveaway or a video we could share with the community.
There were all sorts of things that we put up there and then asked everyone that was
on that showed up, who by the way, out of a company of about 300 people, 75 showed up.
And it certainly wasn't all women.
It was a really lovely group of folk who not only showed up to that first one, but stuck
through it the whole time.
And as we had these ideas, then we just asked everybody to vote with their initials, go
up and say, okay, what are the one or two that
you would put your time behind, that you would actually
be excited about, which allowed us to winnow it down
to maybe three ideas that then teams went away,
and then we picked one the next month
that we did the same thing with mimosas and more pastries.
And said, OK, we are going to make an event.
And what we wound up doing, and actually some of these ladies
also came to it because ArenaNet's also
in the Seattle area, and we did a regional event that was
about it was sponsored by our chapter of women in gaming but it was about
producing your own career and we brought people in from all sorts of different
disciplines to talk about their experiences it was open it was very
candid we were you know but it was also with the idea of hey you know what there
are things that sometimes you don't always think about if you're a person
who
feels maybe like you can't ask for a raise,
you can't ask for a promotion, you can't do those things.
And we just came together and said,
this is a problem we see,
but it's also an event that we produced together
that really galvanized our studio around,
hey, this is a cause we believe in,
this is something that's important to us.
And it also was honestly great recruiting message
to put out there to be like, yeah, we value this.
We're given, you know, we're spending money
and giving people's time to do it.
So I would really encourage you,
regardless of how small it is,
or do you work in a shared workspace,
or you're doing some other things,
like get people around the idea of how can we
not just work with ourselves, but share outward,
and that'll help.
That's the act, make, say, act, make kind of thing.
By doing that, you're going to make
a better culture internally,
because you're putting it out there for people.
I would also say that just as far as a next step, just something you can do.
Take stock.
Like, I've, you know, even being part of this panel, I've, I've, or
I'm gonna go do more things.
I'm gonna steal.
You should, the next thing you should do is hit, sorry.
is go, not literally.
The next thing you should do is go and take stock
and ask yourself if, as companies and as individuals,
if you're doing everything we mentioned,
which should be a minimum bar,
a minimum bar at this point in our industry.
And then we have so much further to go.
So then, am I doing all those things?
You know, and even if you're not in a place.
that you're necessarily in charge of certain things,
go talk to the person who is.
So what can you do?
There's something probably you can do that you aren't doing.
I know we aren't doing even the things that
were brought up here.
And so that's a next step that you can go back and do.
And just whatever that one piece is,
that you can go take action.
And then we're a little bit further.
Are you?
Sorry, I almost hit you.
All right.
Well, and with one minute to go, we're going to go ahead and wrap up.
Some quick housekeeping reminders, don't forget to fill out your surveys.
And also, we're the last panel in here for the day, so we'll be up here at the front
if you guys want to come and talk to us and ask questions.
So thank you all for attending.