OK, I think we're ready to start.
Welcome to the Art of Severed talk.
It's kind of weird because the game is not out yet,
but it will be soon.
A couple of years ago, I did a talk
about the art of Guacamelee.
And they put the video in the vault, and I watched myself.
And apparently, I have an accent, which.
I didn't know about that. So hopefully everyone can understand me properly. Let's get
started because this is a bunch of stuff. So I work at Drinkbox Studios as a concept lead. We
developed about a mutant blobs attack and most famously guacamole.
And for Severed, we had been doing platformers
for a long time, and we were kind of saturated a little bit.
So let me take you back to the magical time that was, 2013,
when we were wrapping up Guacamelee.
And all these ideas for new projects
started to come up in the studio.
Chris Harvey or someone, one of the founders, had an idea of making maybe a touch game,
an iOS or something like that.
There was some other ideas, maybe like a Cursed Warrior or something.
These were all just ideas, nothing tangible yet.
It got me thinking of doing something very different, just to have a new set of challenges
and change it around a little bit.
Around that time, I'm also having...
uh, just, just different ideas about memories and, uh, being away from, from my family.
Um, I remember, I distinctly remember, uh, weird moments with, um, with my mom where,
like, I think we were wrapping up guacamole and, like, um, just...
talking to her on the phone.
And I'm just pacing around the room,
and she's giving me some nice advice.
And I remembered some other advice that she had given me
like six months before.
But the image of the memory was me pacing around the room
having a phone conversation.
with this disembodied person.
Which was very interesting because usually
when you have memories, nice memories with someone,
you have kind of like a place and a smell
and maybe what they're wearing,
maybe the scenery is different.
But all these memories started to be kind of the same
even though in my mind they were different.
So kind of thinking about that as kind of like
an emotional kind of core for a game.
And all of these ideas started to come together.
And at one point, it's kind of like it starts to simmer and then all of a sudden like starts boiling and you're like
Okay, I need to do something now. So I
Did a concept video which I'll show you right now
So I would go home after work and like that week a couple of days of the week and make this really rough
concept pitch for what eventually would become severed so
I'm gonna show you
This doesn't have audio, it's just images.
Oh, no.
OK.
Is it playing now?
Yeah.
So I just animated this in Flash very, very roughly,
as you can see.
It's just basically a square tool over and over.
But the idea is to create a mood for what the game could
be, kind of packaging all the stuff that some ideas
from the studio and some ideas kind of packaged
with what I had just been talking about, the memories
and all that stuff.
So the plot, I wanted to have something very mysterious
and not as operatic as Guacamelee,
or not as prototypical.
And at that time, I called the game Slash,
which I thought it was pretty clever
with just like a division symbol,
meaning obviously like slashing around,
but also like the divide
that this character is going through.
And now here is like some example of what the navigation,
how I envision navigation being.
And this is kind of borrowed from an old game
called Shining in the Darkness.
It's a precursor for Shining Force.
It's like a obscure Genesis game.
But basically you're in the middle of the town
and you act as kind of like the axis around it.
So you can choose to go, say, to the tavern
to recruit people or to the shop or whatever.
In this case, this is like a transition.
You're inside, and you're like maybe buy something.
The idea was that you can make a 2D game or make 2D art
presented in a way that you can have a spatial relationship
that feels more three-dimensional,
kind of like those old school dungeon crawlers or something
like that.
So I wanted to make something simple, something
kind of like a palette cleanser.
from doing all this platform or something that was easy and cheap to make, and we can
create a lot of content out of it. That's kind of the exploration part of it, and here's
kind of like what the combat would be. A character shows up, maybe like a Pokemon, and then you
go into battle mode and you have…
your life bar or whatever, and all this lashing, I was
interested in keeping it simple, so not having like a
shield or anything that you're carrying.
So everything is like basically touch control.
And I mean, this is like incredibly crude, as you can
see, this is now like.
like, wow, this looks amazing.
But that was not the point.
The point was to like, hey guys, this is the idea
and this is how it sort of plays.
And I see concept pitches or concept art as kind of like.
I think good ideas just generate better ideas.
So if you have a seed, and then hopefully you
end up with a full crop once you share it
with a team who are also very talented.
And then just some ideas on how to expand magic systems and stuff
like that.
Maybe you have to draw.
some pictographs or something that create a magic spell or something like this.
Maybe it's complicated to do that kind of detection, but anything goes at this stage.
It's just like a cheap drawing right now. I remember being very nervous about sharing
this with the team, because I had spent some weeks thinking about it and a week or two
making it.
and it was like a Sunday midnight deciding whether to send it or not to
to the founders of the team because I know it like at this point this is
completely outside of the wheelhouse of what we've been doing as a studio like
just from Guacamelee just switching to something completely bizarre with like a
very dark atmosphere like a sword fighting game we've never done a full
touchscreen game so it was like kind of weird to be pitching this thing and
So for the first day I sent that,
nobody kind of mentioned anything.
And I'm like, okay, maybe they didn't see it or whatever.
The second day, like Tuesday, nothing.
Hey guys, did you see the email?
It's like, yeah, yeah, we saw it.
Oh, okay, okay.
Cool.
And then like a week later, like, okay,
I think we're gonna, we like it.
We're gonna do a prototype with a bunch of other ideas.
we're doing.
Basically, this is the pitch,
and this is just some mood
kind of sort of storytelling thing.
I mean, coming back to the Cursed Warrior
kind of idea that started it all.
So, this was the pitch for me.
Like, having a single-player touch-based experience
with really easy to make backgrounds,
just like flat art.
It's just short, make it arcade-y, you know, like it doesn't need to be graphically amazing.
6-8 production cycle, like very quick turnaround, or way quicker than what we've done before.
Low detail characters, continue with like a graphic theme.
We don't even need to do main character, because it's first person.
Like we don't need to do all those animations and stuff.
The combat, keeping it very simple, very light.
And the storytelling will be very minimalistic
and kind of like in the background, not in the foreground.
So I mean, what could go wrong?
It's like, this whole thing looks so solid,
but everything went wrong.
So we did that prototype among with other ones.
This is some animations that Ben Thomas did.
He's animator at Drinkbox.
And I was away during this prototype.
We did like a two-day jam at the studio
and I was away in Mexico for vacation, so I missed it.
But they did a prototype.
They reused the Samurai Jack backgrounds
for the Eternal Game Jam, which I thought was cool.
So let's go through all these points.
Single-prey touch-based experience.
So to put that in context,
we're also doing super turbo championship edition.
So we're prototyping this stuff.
At the same time, we're doing like Guacamelee DLC
and porting and doing the sort of Guacamelee 1.5
at that time.
And Guacamelee was a pretty straightforward formula.
Like, everybody got it.
It's like, Metroidvania with, like, melee combat.
to the power of Mexico and then that's basically Guacamelee.
But when trying to define this single player
touch-based experience, it's like,
well, what is this experience?
Is it action?
Is it adventure?
How much is it?
You know, like Zelda has puzzles.
Are we doing puzzles?
We're looking at things like Mike Tyson's Punch Out
because we like that combat, the rhythm,
like waiting for weak points and stuff like that.
We're looking at the awesome art for Year Walk and things like that, where the storytelling
is very moody, although that doesn't have combat at all, it's just like a puzzle game.
We didn't want to do like a Mexican game this time.
It was just too much pressure to keep going with all that stuff.
And something like Myst, I thought,
was an atmosphere that was very interesting.
But also elements of Zelda, but also like it's not
top down, this game is.
So you know, touchscreen for Ninja, I was like, oh,
for Ninja, yeah, of course.
It's like it's not that gameplay,
but there's something there.
It feels good to just like cut fruit, right?
And Infinity Blade, of course, except Infinity Blade has a dodging mechanic and it's third-person
and the graphics are fantastic and you don't explore too much and you don't fight more
than one enemy.
So it's not really a template that we can fit our game into.
So that was incredibly tough to do because everybody kind of took...
their experience of this is what an experience means,
or this is what touch base means,
or action adventure means.
And we were not kind of in the same page,
so it was hard to find exactly the genre.
So single player touch base experience
was a very difficult thing that we didn't think
it was gonna be difficult,
and we kept coming back to that problem
to try to finesse it.
It turns out we were doing a dungeon crawler.
But we found that out like a year into production.
The easy-to-make backgrounds, okay,
well, like, at least we can do this.
Like, we can finesse what the game is,
but the background production
should be pretty straightforward.
This is some early navigation concepts.
So basically, the idea is to have like a scroll,
kind of like a Flintstones background
that keeps looping around.
And that's basically dividing quadrants, right?
So the tower is like north, east, south, the cave, and west.
the other passage or something, and then cross-dissolve between them.
These are just some early explorations on style and things like that.
I kind of like the brushy kind of texture part of it.
which we actually couldn't do
because it was very expensive to do sprites for our engine.
So we had to go back to do something
more like Guacamelee, where it's like
graphics and gradients and just verts.
These are just kind of all over the place,
because we're figuring things out still.
So you can see, we're going to have NPCs,
how much of an adventure part of it.
We're going to have towns, what it's going to be like.
But I drew this image, and here is where I feel like,
for me, it kind of started to turn around.
Because it just struck a chord, or something was here
that was very interesting.
So this was kind of like...
the beginning of going in that direction.
At the same time, we're figuring out how to do the concepts of the rotation and combat.
So here's like a quick battle mockup.
You fight, but then you turn.
Maybe you go to the cave.
Maybe you keep walking.
We keep going around.
This is all not in Engine.
This is just a quick animation I did in Flash.
And it has some parallax in the background, which is weird,
because when you rotate, there's no parallaxing.
But it looked cooler with it.
And doing something like Year Walk,
where when you move forward, then more stuff shows up.
I'm just going to go quickly over this.
These are some other tests.
Something that was very difficult is to determine arbitrarily how much is moving forward, how
much is a unit of moving forward.
Is it like a soccer field?
Is it like two steps?
Is it like how many steps forward are you doing?
That was kind of like this test with this house on the right.
On the left is kind of like an early kind of dungeon kind of idea.
This is, again, this is all stuff that as we're getting the tech ready, we're figuring
out what are the rules of this world for the navigation because it's not as easy as just
doing the scrolls.
There's a lot of rules like how big are the doorways, how far can you see things, that
kind of thing.
In open areas, you cannot do diagonals, so limiting it to the cardinal directions, things
like that.
we didn't think before starting.
It didn't work at all.
It was terrible.
Like, you don't feel like you're rotating.
You just feel like you're moving side to side.
And that was not a good thing for a game
that you needed that 360 kind of look.
So, one solution was hotel virtual tours,
which is basically a panorama.
Basically, it's like a cylinder.
with flat images on it.
So Google Maps kind of uses this also.
So if you've ever seen like a panoramic picture app,
this is what they do.
It's basically a mesh that is a cylinder around you in 3D
and you're stitching together pictures that are 2D.
when you move around, then the mesh deforms.
That deforms the image.
So I'll show you in a minute how it looks.
But basically, this is my crappy diagram drawing.
Because we needed one cylinder, of course, for the first layer.
But you also want to have that depth.
So that meant having to do a second layer and a third layer.
So it's three cylinders in our engine
where we're mapping this to the art.
This is a test that Steph Goulet, the art director, did.
I don't know if I can play it, yeah.
He did this in 3D Max really quickly
and has like the cardinal points.
just so the rotation, but you see like the ground layers
has three different colors.
So like now you're in layers three now
and that kind of thing, how would that work?
It's obvious that it was really hard to figure
that stuff out given like this test doesn't look
as good as what it ended up looking at.
But that was the trial and error with this thing.
And we started to be very concerned
about being able to pull this off.
Because it looks so simple, but it didn't scale
that way at all.
At the same time, I'm doing more exploration on the style,
so it's just like some palette cleanser images
before it gets too technical.
Again, exploring mood and that kind of thing.
Now, the ground, the layering is visible there.
So this is what we ended up attempting as a first test.
So for the outdoors, it's okay if the cylinders
are just kept like that because the forest is organic.
It's fine.
But the indoors, we didn't want it
just to be in circular rooms.
So we did this thing where when you map things
to a cylinder,
it deforms it.
So if you have a normal plane, it just naturally deforms.
So if we pinch the art, when it deforms it,
it makes it feel like there's a corner there.
So this is final art from the game.
And each of those kind of bubbles,
that's like a cardinal direction in our game.
And this is what, oops.
this is what mapping it to those cylinders looks like
as you're navigating now in the game.
So, eventually we had to do,
I mean, this is very polished.
We didn't figure this out at that time,
but it was kind of refining that process
to the point where.
It feels like you're in a 3D space, but you're not.
You're just in a cylinder.
The camera moves a little bit,
and then you're just teleported to the next node.
So this is kind of like what Google Maps does.
It just cross-desalts between them,
and it just works for some reason.
Like, it ended up being not distracting when you're playing.
You just accept that that's how the world happens.
So, easy to make backgrounds.
It's super simple.
All you need to do is 2D art of an interior,
distort it with some action or script in Illustrator,
map it to a cylinder in our engine,
and you just make sure to not tilt the camera up or down
because there's no art there.
and you need three of those layers.
So, no, it didn't, it was not simple at all.
And at this time, I should mention,
like, pre-production, getting all this stuff ready
already had taken like four to six months, informally,
because we were doing some Guacamelee stuff,
but that, like, short turnaround game
was also not gonna happen.
And at this point, this is like a year after the pitch.
And we made this concept video.
We wanted to do an announced trailer,
but we didn't have the tech running yet or anything
to show for after all this work.
So we decided to animate, kind of have
like a target of what the game would look like.
So I'll show you real quick a portion of this concept video.
Also, the music is by the amazing Yamantaka Sonic Titan, who signed up to do the music, the soundtrack for the game.
And they did an amazing job.
So, this was animated by Ben and myself, also using Flash.
And some of the concepts are shown there.
A lot of this stuff we don't know how to do.
Like, all this stuff is just like,
this would be cool to do,
but we don't have the game structure yet.
So this is just like conceptual things at that moment.
and introducing some NPCs and characters that kind of made it up.
Some of these were reused from the earlier tests that I have made.
But somehow it starts to, these ideas are starting to generate more ideas and getting
the team excited to make this.
So yeah, the idea was just create kind of like a crazy visual kind of dump on this and
see how much we could try to do for the game.
So that's like, we're in the timeline,
this is where we're at, right?
So we decided to do like a vertical slice,
a demo at that point.
These are just some rough storyboards
for kind of the first dungeon of the game.
And this is just some concept art.
I kind of like, I wanted the dungeons to not be monotonous
or just be brick walls.
Definitely wanted a moody, kind of dark, kind of aesthetic.
But also, combined with on the left,
there's kind of, maybe you reach kind of like
an internal garden or something like that.
with some stuff that looks kind of like there was a culture there or something,
and maybe something off-putting or creepy, like those plants that look like eyes.
We're starting to do concepts that now are tied to game areas, so this is like another
quick test just to see how much we can reuse.
Now we have established some stuff like how much it's going to be foggy in the background.
We're going to just have three layers deep that you can look into.
And obviously the outdoors,
we just make it as though they're giant walls
so that it's clear, the direction,
the cardinal directions are clear.
So there's some concepts of the house
at the beginning of the game.
This is kind of taken with that,
that first image I showed you guys
that was, that struck a chord with me,
that was kind of like the reinterpretation
of what it would look like in the game.
Some exploration on forest and palettes.
It was very quick, just reusing things.
How can we block doorways?
How can we make the dungeon not look the same
if there's just doors and nodes like that?
So finding some variety, maybe with vegetation,
maybe with what you see through the doors.
Excuse me.
So I want to jump a little bit to the characters.
Because some stuff in the characters,
there's not a lot of...
Like it's not like Guacamelee, it's not like a parade of NPCs in the game,
but there's like a bunch of characters.
It's some sketches of our main character, Sasha.
She's this warrior that's in search of her family.
And at the beginning I thought she would be like in her 20s or 20 year old or something like that.
But as we're developing the game, we realized we're doing a rites of passage kind of story.
So then the design shifted to be more of a teenager,
just so that it feels like she doesn't understand the world yet completely.
She doesn't have that maturity yet.
And I wanted to make her kind of racially ambiguous.
We're like, kind of like a mixed heritage or something.
Like, we're doing a fantasy game,
but I didn't want to be tied to doing
something that's inspired in Norse mythology
or something like that.
That's kind of like the established thing.
So we couldn't make anything.
And even the language is gibberish
and people think it's Spanish,
for some reason or something.
So, yeah, so I want to kind of like an exotic
kind of look for the family and for Sasha.
But I really want to talk about the enemies.
And at this point, we have four enemies.
I mean, like at this point in the timeline,
not in the game.
We started doing four enemies and those took a long time.
The iterations, it was slow, it was not working.
So then we made some adjustments
and we decided to prototype one enemy per week.
So we had two months to make eight enemies
and that's a lot of work.
But I wanna show you because this is, I think,
the most fun I had during the process.
So I'm gonna go over quickly.
I can talk about this after.
Basically everything starts with an idea.
Graham, or in this case David Rusak, Graham is a producer.
He's one of the founders.
David, he wears multiple hats, but he was in charge of doing the design of the enemies,
the paper design.
We had this giant Google Doc, and he would write some ideas.
In this case, I'm just going to go over one of the enemies.
It was called DemiGhost at the beginning.
And the idea was to have an enemy that would split apart
and maybe attack you in a flurry.
Because when you're prototyping these enemies,
they need to work in tandem.
Because you're not fighting one on one like a boxing match.
You have to fight one, and then another one appears.
And now they need to work.
sort of together so that it's fun for the player.
So the behaviors needed to be different
so that you're not just like spamming,
dragging your finger around like crazy.
There's like some strategy to it.
So in this case, this was an enemy
that the more you engage with it,
the more you attack it,
the faster, the more aggressive it becomes.
So when Wednesday comes, David writes a proposal.
Then on Thursday, we meet.
I go over it.
I selected some visuals from like the giant pool
of different sketches that Ben and myself had made
for like a year and a half.
In this case, Ben had this cool ghost guy made of ghosts.
Because we didn't want to have just guys with axes
or zombies or something like that.
You could do anything at this point,
so why not a ghost made of ghosts?
So it would disband maybe, and I don't know.
This was just like one visual idea.
And I just throw like three different ideas to the team.
So the second one was another of Ben's sketches.
This guy with like multiple mouths and multiple wings.
And I thought that was cool.
So maybe they're actually different.
Like when they dodge, they actually disband.
And then they individually attack.
And then they kind of mush together and recombine into one.
And the third one is kind of more like, okay,
more like a ghost or a blob or something.
Your slasher maybe has a normal attack,
but at the bottom maybe has a heavier attack
where it summons the statue back into life
and then attacks you like that.
So then, that's Thursday.
Friday, we meet Alex, who's doing the programming,
who would do this really amazing flowcharts of the enemies.
Basically, this is the behavior of that enemy.
You have the idle stage, a timer to the attack, and then.
If unparried, then it repeats.
If parried, this happens.
And that's kind of like a nice kind of portrait of our enemies
in this just scribbly pages.
So we decide what the behavior is.
We like sort of certain things about some enemies
or the aesthetics, and then we decide.
So then that Friday, I go back to the desk
and I kind of clean up.
In this case, we realized we needed,
we liked the guy with wings.
So we realized we needed kind of like a distinction
when like it's aggressive and when it's not aggressive.
some animation notes for them, like when they
recombine, like we don't want to make the animation
completely expensive, so maybe just like
just make it like that and then they just combine already.
And the severed post, so in this game you
chop the enemy parts and that's kind of like
your currency in the game.
So we needed that variety, so we chose a guy with wings
because nothing else is dropping wings at that time.
and we wanted kind of that variety, so that would be cool.
Then Ben goes on and does the...
starts to rig up the animation file
and starts to talk to Alex about prototyping the anime.
And in the meantime, I do like a finished polished pass
of what the enemy would look like.
In this case, I chose blue
because none of the enemies at this point were blue.
We wanted something colorful.
The wing is how this enemy attacks.
So change the wings from a feathery look
to more like a razor sharp kind of look.
And it was important that it was not floating around,
but like the wings are actually having to carry this body.
So this is what the animation looks like in our file.
We've switched to a boom at that point,
and this is Ben's animation on the attack,
one of the attacks.
This has been iterated and is polished,
but I just wanted to show you what it looks like.
And this animation polish happened later,
but on Monday and Tuesday of the next week,
we review the enemy as it's being prototyped
as Alex has time to program it
and Ben has the first pass of the enemy.
And then Ben polishes up until Thursday,
because on Friday we already started
the next cycle on Wednesday.
So I'm gonna show you what this guy looks like in game.
And this is actual game footage.
So the attacks are there.
We change it.
We have to do a state where it's catching its breath.
And then if it gets too aggressive, then it splits up.
And now you need to manage the different attacks
from different directions to use the screen a bit more.
and then severing and then you collect your wings.
So for this, the interesting thing is that
this is just one enemy in this arena,
but there could be multiple ones,
so it makes it more dynamic and more difficult
as the game keeps evolving.
So low detail characters, yes, I would say they're graphic and simple looking, but I
wouldn't say low detail because a lot of the detail in these characters comes from their
behavior and iteration and how...
how they need to convey the information for the player.
Because it's a very intuitive game,
we wanted to make it extra clear
where the attack is coming from,
not like you feel it's unfair
because you've died against this guy like five times.
You need to kind of learn from that.
And that's like a lot of work for the animation team
to convey that as an enemy is attacking you
from the front in a 2D game.
And this also piggybacks on the simple combat
using touchscreen.
Because yes, the combat is simple and intuitive
for the user, but not for us making it.
To make it look seamless and simple,
it's like a lot of work that goes in there.
And combat is the main focus in the game.
So that's something we cannot skimp on.
We cannot like,
just, yeah, I mean there's other things in the game.
There's like exploration and characters
and stuff like that in the storyline.
But the combat is the main thing,
so we really need to make sure we prioritize that
and make sure the combat was very deep.
And so for minimalistic storytelling,
Originally I didn't want any dialogue in the game,
but we're not Journey and we couldn't do it.
It was so hard.
So you can like spend like two months
trying to do a tutorial with just pantomime
or you can just like, okay, fine,
let's do a text box or something.
So we went with the text box.
But I do think we succeeded in doing like a minimalistic story for the game. It's kind of
like it's in the back. It's kind of
it's very moody and
it's not too direct, but that makes the player more engaged in a way to try to discover
the meaning of some things without having to handhold them through the storyline.
So I don't want to talk too much about this, because I don't want to spoil anything.
But I'll show you real quick, this is at the beginning of the game.
This is the tutorial I was mentioning.
This is the mother character.
And just like trying to convey, I mean, yeah, you're conveying the rules of the
game at this point.
But also, it was important for the characters to feel like characters.
This is kind of like a glimpse at the relationship
that Sasha has with her mom.
And it's just in like the small choices
in the animation and the posing.
Because it's basically two poses,
but it's important to convey things
through the character design
and through this choice of poses.
That was very hard to do, so I'm crossing it
because it was really, really hard.
Like, minimalistic stuff, or narrative stuff,
it's always super complicated.
So, to recap, how am I doing with time?
To recap, the single-player touch-based experience
Yes.
What you need to do is define it.
Because this was a problem that was constant for us.
Like just putting everybody in the same page
was incredibly difficult.
So we discovered we were making a dungeon crawler.
Like that was the closest genre.
But that came after like a lot of trial and error.
And like looking at games that.
they don't fit that genre.
And sometimes, like, when you say, like,
oh, let's make this game an X game,
like a Metroidvania or like a fighting game,
there's like a stigma to those genres
because like other mediums have more...
like, you know, genres that are more emotionally based instead of mechanically based.
So, sometimes there's like, I didn't want to jump into doing that, right?
Like, I just want to make a game that's fun and interesting and engaging.
But by not having that label, that made it a bit difficult.
So, in a way, it's counterintuitive.
You kind of sometimes have to start with something that's pre-established
because that will make it easier.
So for the easy to make backgrounds,
I mean, if you're mapping 2D art to a cylinder
and all that stuff, you're not making it easy on yourself.
It does look way, way cooler than any
of the initial concepts.
But it blew up the project.
It was not a 6-to-8-month project.
It just became this giant game that we still
thought in our minds that was like a small game.
So when that happens, I mean, the solution
is like.
It could be like scale down, like, okay,
let's go back to this arcadey slingshot game.
Maybe it doesn't look as good,
but at least we can finish in time.
Or, okay, let's just keep going with this scaled up version
and make sure you make kind of like
the psychological change to make.
Okay, we're not doing a six-month game,
we're doing a two-year game.
So, that's also adapting.
from what I just said.
Like, there's an initial plan and sometimes you're like
very...
worried to deviate from that plan.
But it's all, timelines are very difficult
in this industry and things change
and you discover new things about the game
and what you wanna do.
So you do need to make some judgment calls
and make sure everybody's on board with that
and adaptation is very important.
For the characters.
I would say yes, you need to identify
what's the center of your game.
For us, it was the characters,
so we definitely spend a lot of time and detail with those
because that's what's gonna make the game good.
And that allows you to not spend a lot of time
worrying about some more irrelevant things,
but when you're trying to do everything,
you're not gonna accomplish
The biggest thing though was maybe it won't be a huge revelation for you guys because you're smarter than me, but
Simple does not equal simple to do so a lot of this thing was like it was simple because it's just simple to explain
But to execute like very subtle
Combat or our story or something like that. There was a lot of care and a lot of things that it simply was not
It was not simple to me
And, you know, this is storytelling.
It's not such a thing.
Like, you still need to do the whole iceberg, you know?
And then, if you want to choose to show only the top 10%,
that's cool.
But you still need to build the whole thing.
And in a way, you know.
Less is more, like it is more work.
Simple and storytelling, it doesn't happen.
It's just be constantly iteration and headaches.
So don't think because you have less things
to show in your story, that's gonna make it simpler,
especially in a game where like it depends
on the mood and the storytelling.
of our character.
Because in a way, you need to be more careful
because you're not showing everything.
So you really need to show only the specific,
the good things.
And that means there's a lot of work
in just taking out all the excess stuff.
But, you don't need to listen to all I've said because I think mistakes are actually
okay.
I think learning from experience is so, so valuable.
I think people sometimes dismiss that as failure or something like that.
The mistakes we made here were crucial for us to improve the game and to improve ourselves as developers.
If someone asks me...
if I would go back and try to do the whole thing
knowing what mistakes I was gonna face
and the tough parts that I was gonna face,
I don't know if I would take that chance
if I didn't, if that meant I didn't get to experience
the failure of that.
if I was told to go back, knowing what I know now,
knowing all these failures and mistakes,
then yeah, of course, of course,
jump back in that DeLorean and fix things,
make sure this is the priority,
this is what's gonna happen, definitely.
But you want that experience.
You want to go and try it and fail and try it again
and fail and try it again.
If someone just gives you the answers to the test,
sometimes it's not actually useful at all.
So I encourage you to just don't listen to me
and just do your own thing.
And that's it.
I have the trailer here.
Just really real quick, just to get some perspective because I haven't shown much of the game
Because it hasn't come out yet
To put you in context a little bit
Oh
I don't know if we have time for questions.
If anybody has any questions, you're welcome.
Thank you so much for taking that challenge and doing it.
You probably just allowed me to win a bet.
I've been talking to a few technical guys.
I'm a 2D artist and wanting to try something like that.
And they said it couldn't be done.
So thank you.
Real quick, though, about your ring setup.
When they move forward, is the ring?
moving into them or are they moving into the next ring?
Does that pass ring?
Yeah, it's kind of tricky.
So the question is, with that three-ring setup,
what's actually happened with the camera?
So the camera is moving forward in Z.
Like, it's actually moving.
Our engine is actually 3D.
It houses that cylinder.
But when you move away from that cylinder, it starts to deform.
and it starts to break.
But at that time, that's where the cross dissolve happens.
So basically, yes, the cylinder is deforming
and the layers in the back stop matching perfectly.
But then you cross dissolve
and then they don't match perfectly
and then you get to the center of it.
And your brain just kind of like fills in the rest
and it's like, oh, it's fine, I just move forward.
Yeah.
Hello, first of all, thank you, Augusto, for making Guacamelee and Sever with your team.
To me, it's a really great experience to see this kind of games being released.
And my question here is...
I know this is not based on Mexican culture, but to me it still feels really similar to some things you did for Guacamelee.
Like, I still see the monsters as some sort of alebrije.
It has a little bit of influence, and that's great because you are representing your culture.
I mean, it's almost impossible to...
I don't know, distance yourself from that, right?
And so my question here is,
are you guys planning to continue doing things like that,
pushing different cultures into games,
and maybe making things like fantasy, man?
Because fantasy is just often dwarves, elves, and things like that.
I mean, there are so many mythologies that could be explored,
and the games industry seems to be a little bit fixated on those archetypes, you know?
So I don't know, what are your thoughts on that?
Yeah, I mean, I love all that stuff too.
That's great.
It's just kind of think we want to sort of stand out.
It's like we're a small team.
We really need to make it look different.
So yeah, and whenever you, sorry, so like,
this talking about like adding the cultural aspects
of making like a fantasy game and how,
yeah, it's hard to distance myself from the Mexico stuff
because I just like it.
So I'm just gonna do it.
It's not like somebody forced me to do
the Guacamelee stuff.
But yeah, as soon as you add color to monsters,
then you get alebrijes, because that's what they are.
And they're very unique.
And we didn't want to shy away from the color.
In a way, having a very colorful game
with such gruesome themes, you're chopping enemies apart.
So if you make it very dark and moody,
then it starts to feel very weird.
You start to feel off.
So we wanted that balance where like it's still a game, it's still abstracted.
You still feel a bit uneasy but you don't feel
it's not a gory game because of the graphics are stylized and the colors are very vibrant.
So that kind of compensates that and makes this really weird.
Like that dissonance is what makes it interesting for us.
Awesome talk.
Appreciate it.
Thanks.
Just as a gameplay systems designer, super fascinated for me to see somebody approach
making a game starting with art and theme and mood and emotion and then gameplay systems
being figured out later.
Is Guacamelee the same?
No, Guacamelee was...
Every game is different.
For us it's not like...
For this one it started with that.
For Guacamelee it was more like...
What about doing a game in Mexico and just like the visual stuff.
And there was like a bunch of ideas that fit really well with that.
But like the dimension idea for Guacamelee and like the idea of
melee moves as platforming,
that was sort of a separate idea.
And it just kind of magically merged seamlessly.
Thank you.
Yeah, I think that's it.
Thank you guys for coming and enjoy the rest of the GC.
Thank you.