Hey everybody, it's 5 o'clock.
Hope everybody's having a super great GDC.
For people just coming in, there are some seats down the front rows.
Don't be shy.
So I gave a talk last year about game studio management and how studios should be structured
and I was surprised to learn that, oh, I still have a bunch of things that I'd still like
to say about that.
But this year I'm giving a kind of a different talk,
Game Studio Leadership.
So this is much more about what you personally,
as a studio leader,
things that you should maybe be considering doing.
It's called Game Studio Leadership, you can do it.
I'm a little nervous because it's all new material,
but I'm confident that I can do it.
So it's going to be fine.
So just a little bit about my background.
A long time ago, I used to be a circus performer,
a traveling juggler with a number of different troops
like the Fryhoffer Circus Troop right there.
And inexplicably, I went from there
to start becoming a programmer at IBM.
Then I was working at the phone company for a while.
Then I managed to get the phone company
to send me to graduate school
to learn about virtual reality,
and that I leveraged into a job at Disney.
So sorry, phone company.
And then I was at Disney for seven years,
and then I, about 15 years ago.
I moved to Pittsburgh.
I started teaching at Carnegie Mellon University.
And also I started a studio called Shell Games, which started as a small studio and has grown
quite a bit.
So a lot of the lessons I'll be talking about here, a lot of it's going to be what I've
learned kind of running Shell Games over the years, but also these other organizations
that I was a part of were very instructive to me about different ways to deal with leadership
in creative situations.
Here's some footage of what Shell Games looks like on the inside.
We've got about 105 people.
We reproduce multiple games at a time, typically between 6 and 12 games.
It's not at all unusual for us to be working on.
If you're wondering how we got that cool footage, it's very simple.
Just drones flying around inside.
That's not distracting at all.
Yeah, we're not gonna keep those up full time,
we tried it, it's not good.
So who's this talk for exactly?
So it's definitely for people who are interested
in taking on some amount of studio leadership,
or maybe you're already doing some studio leadership.
I've tried to make it so that it will work
for people doing small studios
with just a handful of people.
And also maybe you had a small studio
and it got a little bigger and it got a little bigger
and oh my God, you're really freaking out right now.
And so growing studios, growth is a very,
one of the most challenging parts of studio management.
Or maybe you're not really running some independent studio.
Maybe you're part of some large gray entity,
but somewhere deep inside that entity
you're running a small team.
And a lot of the same things apply.
And so we'll talk about some of those things as well.
So I call those embedded studios.
So when it comes to studio management,
I often think about airports.
Airports are kind of like snowflakes.
Have you noticed how they're all different?
Like no two airports are alike.
They're like radically different from each other.
And some people say that studio management
is like airport design.
No one seems to know the right answer.
And no matter how you do it, people are unhappy.
Right?
And I know that sounds, you know, people say that.
But I'm here to tell you that no, you can do it.
You can do leadership inside a studio.
So now why would you do this anyway?
Like why does someone go and take
on the ridiculous endeavor of starting
and trying to run a studio?
Now, for some people, you know, it may be that you just don't like the idea of working
for someone else.
Or maybe you tried working for someone else and you got tired of making the wrong games
with the wrong people the wrong way, right?
And you have a fantasy about, like, I'm just going to cut these chains and I am going to
go out and I am going to do things the right way.
Here's a movie to illustrate that.
We got our audio up there.
Scott, are we good?
All right.
Here we go.
This is the story of one who will become leader of the great Rebellion.
She-Ra, Princess of Power.
That is the best echo ever. I just really like that echo.
I know there's a lot of people out there saying,
yeah, no, I get it.
I really, that's what I want to do.
I want to pick up the sword
and I want to go out there and do this.
But some of you are saying like,
but I'm not sure, She-Ra, I'm not exactly relating to that.
She-Ra is not exactly someone I'm relating to.
And if you feel that way,
I would like you to consider that every woman
who comes to GDC, 95% of the time,
they see male role models on stage
and that's how they feel.
And so we can all kind of, you know, think about being She-Ra.
Like, we can handle that just for one day, for one moment.
Because one thing I really...
I mean, it's exciting, we're seeing more women come into the game industry.
One thing I'm really hoping to see is more and more women running their own studios.
Is that right, ladies?
Yeah.
Because I'll tell you ladies, if anyone can do it, you can do it.
Yes.
Actually, ladies, actually if you'll indulge me, just the ladies right now,
what I want to get is for the honor of Grayskull on the count of three.
All right, ready?
One, two, three.
For the honor of Grayskull.
Oh, that was kind of awesome.
Sometimes there's parts in the talk that are just for me.
It's okay, that's okay, that can be a thing.
All right, so, you decided you're gonna start a studio.
You've got the fantasy, you're gonna go and do this.
So you have the plan.
So here's the plan, simple plan.
Number one, build a studio.
Number two, make awesome games.
Yes, this is the plan, excellent plan.
Before we embark upon this plan,
we should consider what a game actually is, right?
So games interact with the mind, right?
So games are machines that interact with the mind.
And this is why they're so hard to make,
because the mind is super complicated
and machines are super fragile.
But it's cool, because when they interact with the mind,
like, amazing stuff happens,
and the machine produces joy and money, right?
That's amazing. So that's what a game is, a machine that interacts with the mind to produce joy and money.
Of course, who would not want to make that? That's amazing.
Right? So how are you going to do that?
Well, you can work on your own, but you can only go so far on your own.
So you've got to get some people together, right?
So you get a group of people together and they're going to work on your game.
And this sounds great. This sounds like a great thing to do.
That's what building a studio is.
And this is not easy because unfortunately the world is a chaotic place.
So in this talk to represent chaos I'm going to use the ancient Greek symbol for chaos,
which many people are aware is the sharknado.
All right, because the world is full of chaos that wants to rip your studio apart.
It turns out that game developers want things like they want to eat and have a life and
all these things that require money and they require freedom from distractions.
So chaos can come from an awful lot of places.
And how are the developers going to deal with this chaos that's going to rip apart the game
development process?
They're not.
You're going to do that.
That is what you're going to do.
When you picked up the magic sword, that was the deal,
that you're going to be the one that deals with the chaos
so that they can focus on the process of getting
the game made.
And this is the difference between leaders and followers.
The thing to think about is that what good followers do.
is they excel in orderly situations.
An orderly situation is set up,
the followers are kind of given some kind of marching order,
and they go and they do it super, super, super well.
That's what followers are about.
Leaders, on the other hand,
they need to excel in chaotic situations.
Now, everybody does some amount of leading and following
anywhere in their job,
even if you're just sitting down
and you're going to code something up,
you run into kinds of chaos and you've got to deal with it,
and you've got to take some level of leadership in that.
But the leadership I'm talking about is the leadership that destroys the chaos that will
destroy your studio, right?
That's what you as a studio leader, that is your job to kill those sharknadoes that want
to rip your studio to pieces.
And that's tough, right?
Because you're like, oh my God, I don't want to deal with all that chaos.
That's really hard and that's really difficult.
And I'm here to tell you, you can do it.
You can do it.
And we'll talk about how you're going to do it.
Okay, so how are you going to do it?
You need to protect the developers from all this chaos.
And that's what building a studio is.
A studio is a boundary and a border that kind of finds a way to keep the chaos away so people
can focus on making amazing games.
And one of the main ways they're going to do that,
one of the main things that keeps chaos away is money.
If people have money to take care of their lives
and their food and their rent and all that,
they can focus on doing the things that they love
and the chaos can stay away.
The leading cause of ripping studios apart
is not having enough money to kind of get your stuff going.
So we'll talk a little bit about that.
But all that goes well, then you get rid of the chaos
and everybody can focus and you're making amazing games.
But...
Where are you going to get this money from?
Right? Because that's a question.
And hey, before we even talk about where you're going to get the money from,
where are you going to get the people from?
Like where are these people coming from?
So maybe we better revisit the plan.
Alright, plan. One, build the studio.
Okay, and then what?
Then you're going to protect the studio.
And you need to protect the studio
with money and other things.
And then you're going to make awesome games.
Okay, so build the studio, protect the studio,
make awesome games.
Let's pause for a moment now to talk about
some of the concrete things in terms of building a studio.
I'm not gonna go into a lot of detail about these.
I'm just gonna kind of skim over it real fast
because you can find out about this stuff in other places.
But if you haven't done it before,
one of the first things you're gonna wanna start with
is getting some kind of lawyer
because you need a lawyer to help you do things
you can't do on your own.
Like for example, start a legal entity,
starting a company of some kind.
You're gonna want to do that
because it's a form of protection for you.
and for your other employees.
And a lawyer will help you do that.
Likely you're going to want some kind of accountant
so you can help get the taxes done
and get those sorts of things rolling.
And you're gonna need some kind of payroll service system.
These things are all easily obtainable.
Anybody who starts a hairdressing shop or whatever
has to do all this, you can do it too.
So I'm not gonna dwell on that.
You're going to have the question of office space.
Do you want to, are you just going to work out of your home,
just work out of Starbucks, or are you going to get some kind
of office space that you rent?
You're going to have to work that out,
talk to a real estate agent.
You'll have the question of insurance.
Is your, are you as a studio owner providing
health insurance and all of that?
Of course, there's going to be equipment.
Are people just bringing their own equipment
or are you providing equipment?
And then of course, finally, you got to have some people
for this studio.
So there's your quick eight step process
to getting a studio built right there.
You need to do at a minimum.
Those, those eight things.
And now some people say, no, wait a minute, wait a minute, wait a minute, wait a minute,
wait a minute, why are we getting a bunch of people in here?
We haven't even decided what the studio is doing.
Shouldn't we have like an idea?
Shouldn't we start with like I have this grand vision of the perfect game
and then I will go out and get the people for that perfect game
and go and do that?
And that is a way you can go and do that.
But there's a lot of people who advise that no, that's not the right way to do it.
There's an excellent book that I encourage people to check out called Good to Great.
It's a study of companies that started out pretty good and eventually became great and stayed great for 10 years or more.
And it finds patterns between them all, how they all similarly excelled.
And one of the things that it found is they did not start with an amazing idea.
That isn't how they began.
They went at it differently.
Instead of saying, I've got a great idea, let's get the right people for that idea.
They instead, they used this analogy of a bus, right?
The idea is, you could say, hey, I've got a bus and
it's going to this very specific place.
Let me get people and let's get them on the bus.
But they say, no, don't do that.
Get your bus.
Go get the best people you can.
Get them all on the bus, and then all look at each other
and say, now where should we go?
Because if you have a bunch of smart people together,
then they're going to do something really smart.
Ideally, you're gonna get people smarter than you, right?
And they are gonna do something really smart.
So one of the principles from that book is,
first figure out who, and then let the right people
figure out the right thing to do.
So that's something to think about,
and something to consider.
Certainly, if you're,
Building a game development studio, you're going to be having the three main types of
game developers.
Sometimes referred to as dwarves, elves, and men.
Other times referred to as engineering, art, and design, slash marketing, slash everything
else.
Right?
And that's sort of a joke, but also everyone knows it's like, no, it is really kind of
like that.
These are three different groups of people who think about the world in really, really
different ways.
And you're going to need those different people, and you're going to need to be ready for the
fact that they're not going to agree on everything.
Okay, so that's fine.
So you're going to get a bunch of great people, and now, now what are you going to do?
Well, one other thing to think about is other ways to look at people.
You want just, you're like, sure, I want great artists and great engineers, but is that enough?
Am I just looking at skills?
So, I got this interesting formula from Paul Stefanok,
who used to work with us at Shell Games,
and I found it very interesting and very useful,
that often the right way to think about developer value
don't just think about skills.
What Paul suggested to me, and I still believe is very true,
is that you take skills and you multiply that by enthusiasm,
and then you multiply that by respectability.
Now, what is respectability?
That's a crazy word, though.
Why would you even say that?
It's a complicated idea.
The idea is this,
the ability to make others feel respected.
Okay? Not how much respect you show to others necessarily, and not how much respect you've
earned from them, but how much you make other people feel respected. I know that sounds
a little oblique, but I totally agree with Paul that if you give everybody scores on
these three numbers from like zero to three, and then multiply those three numbers together,
it gives you a pretty good sense of how much someone's value really is. Because someone
with like a three in skills and a three in enthusiasm and a zero in respectability,
like has zero or possibly negative value even. Maybe there should be a negative
respectability, I don't know. So someone who has all twos has an eight, someone who has
all threes has a twenty-seven, like it makes a big difference. But these are three really
important things to think about when you're trying to pick the right people. And yeah,
even three times three times zero is zero. Now a lot of people may have heard, um,
Jason Vandenberg in past years has talked a lot about the big five personality types.
And this is, psychologists in the world don't agree on much, but this is one thing they
all agree on.
That when you want to evaluate like what are the types of personalities that people have,
there are these five spectrum.
Are people more curious or more cautious?
Are the introverts or extroverts?
Are they more nervous or are they more secure?
These opposite ends of the spectrum.
And then what you can basically do
is for almost every individual,
you can kind of do a little test
and figure out where do they reside
on each of these spectra.
So this leads to a question,
what personality type is best for game development?
And the answer that people figure out pretty quickly is like, no, all of these things have pros and cons.
Being more curious is a pro, but it can get you in trouble, but being more cautious is a pro,
but it can also make you too safe.
Every single one of these has a pro and has a con.
And ideally, most people quickly realize what they want is they want to cover the spectrum.
They want a mix of people that will have little red X's in all the parts of all five spectra.
Which that way, great, we're covering everything.
We got people who are thinking about risk
and people who are thinking about adventure,
you know, all of those things.
With people who like to just stay in and work,
people who like to go out and network, that's all great.
But the important thing to realize is,
these are all opposites.
These people are not going to agree with each other, right?
Just inherently, what we're saying is,
if the optimal studio covers all these bases,
the optimal studio is at odds with itself all the time.
And guess whose problem that is?
It's your problem, right?
Because when you picked up the sword,
oh my God, now that's totally your problem.
And a related question,
we often think about what skills do I need?
What skills do I need?
I talked about skills and enthusiasms.
An excellent question is what enthusiasms do I need?
What kinds of champions do I need?
Because sure, you have people who are good at this
and good at that, but what are people excited about?
Maybe someone's not good at playtesting,
but they're super excited about it,
and they really wanna learn about it,
and they really are going to defend it, protect it.
Maybe someone really cares about user experience.
Maybe someone really cares about marketing the studio.
Thinking about having a diverse collection of enthusiasm
so that you have the right champions in your studio
is really important.
So those are some tips for getting the right people.
Okay, so check.
Number one, we built a studio, we had a lawyer,
we got great people, now we're good.
So now part two, we got to protect the studio from chaos.
And we're going to do that by going out
and getting some money.
I keep this little statue in my office
that I found somewhere.
I love it because it just, for me,
it sums up finances in the game industry perfectly.
right? The money's right there. Just grab it. Just go ahead. Just take the money. It's
right there. Just go and get it. Right? But unfortunately, going and getting it is not
so easy. And even once you do get it and you give it to the developers, they go through
it super, super fast. So money is on your mind a lot if you're going to be making your
own studio and trying to run it. So let's talk about the four different ways that you're
going to get money.
Number one, scenario one, you use your own money.
You're independently wealthy, you have this big sack of cash,
you're like, let's do it, let's make this awesome game.
That's great.
If you can do that, excellent, good for you.
And I've seen a lot of people do that.
So often they'll do it by scrimping and saving,
but they'll do it.
So let's just talk about how that works.
So there's your studio, and you're going to put your own money into it.
And that's great.
And then, boom, it starts making games, and the games start coming out.
And then you've got your big vacuum machine on top,
and it sucks the money out of those games.
And then it puts them back in.
And hopefully, this virtuous cycle just keeps going on to infinity.
Now of course we all know that sometimes that doesn't happen.
We had a great roundtable this morning.
People talked about, oh, we made a game,
we're so successful, and then we got complacent.
And the money dried up and we got in all kinds of trouble.
But this is the easiest and best situation.
So if you're already rich, good, congratulations.
You're in a good position for this.
But we're not all like that, so let's look at scenario two,
which is the work for hire scenario.
And this works this way, all right?
So we've got our studio, where's the money come from?
It's not our money, it comes from somebody else.
Somebody says, hey, make a game for me.
And then, well, what happens with this game?
You produce the game, but it's their game, not yours.
See, I made the games a different color
because it belongs to them now.
And then do I bring down my money pipe
and suck the money out?
No, they have their own money pipe.
and they're gonna suck any money that the games get
and it goes away and you don't get any new money for that.
But at least you got to make games and that's cool
and you got to do that.
So, oh look, there's my sad dry money pipe
and like nothing's happening with that.
And some people are like, ugh, I don't like this.
The whole point of my own studio is
so that I don't have to make other people's games.
And if you feel that way, you probably
want to avoid work for hire.
But work for hire can be really cool.
You can work with amazing world class partners.
have a great time working with them,
and then when the project's over,
and they're going all insane,
and they're getting ready to lay people off,
you're like, that's cool, we'll go work over here now,
everything's fine, good luck guys, we'll let you have that.
So you can, if you enjoy it, it can be really great.
Our studio, we've done an awful lot of work
for hire over the years,
we've stayed completely independent because of that.
It's not uncommon for us to be doing 60 to 80%
of what we're doing is work for hire,
use the profits, and then to use those on our own IP,
is not at all unusual.
Then there's scenario three, used to be super common,
the publisher scenario, now it's less common
and now it's a hard one, but it comes and goes.
So let's just be clear about how that works.
How's the publisher scenario work?
There's your studio, and what happens?
Okay, they put in a bunch of money,
but some of it's your money.
They kind of expect you to put some of your own money in.
That's kind of, they're like,
we need you to have skin in the game, Mr. Shell.
Okay, yeah, I got it.
We'll have some, that sounds gross, but we'll do it.
And then you make the games and depending on how the deal works, right?
Sometimes you own them, and sometimes they own them, and sometimes you own part of them,
and so that's negotiable.
So some games are owned and some aren't.
And then what happens with the money?
Like, you both bring money pipes of different kinds,
and you have a big wrestling match about money pipes,
trying to figure out who can get how much and all that.
and this is a kind of the traditional publisher relationship which can be
really nice for
uh... studios because it kind of reduces your risk but you still
have home run protection if you got a big hit you can still get really rich
off of it and that can be pretty nice
but publisher deals are harder to secure than they used to be
And then scenario four, investments.
All right, how's this work?
All right, I got my studio.
It's all somebody else's money.
You know, you might put your own money in,
but you probably won't, right?
So if somebody else has brought their money in,
this is great, this sounds good so far.
I don't have to worry about my own money.
And what do they want in exchange?
Oh my God.
Right? Oh, suddenly it's not your studio anymore. Well, you still have part of it, but most of it is
gonna be theirs, or maybe, I don't know, there's gonna be a big fight about who owns how much of a
studio, and then you're producing games, and you own some, and they own some. Now, the money pipe,
like, sucks the money back in, and that's pretty cool, but, like, wait, now whose money is this
now? That it's not totally my studio anymore? Now, it depends on how you work that out, right? And
the idea of majority control, and who has, who owns more than half of the studio, ends up being
really, really crucial.
And it's really hard for game studios to get investor money sometimes, because
investors generally are coming from the tech sector. They're not thinking about games
as games. They're thinking about games as a platform. How is your game a platform? I don't want to hear
about the game. I want to hear about your platform, right? And what do they want? They want 10x, right?
10x. What does that mean? It means, well, if I give you two million dollars, I expect to see
20 million dollars back for my investment. Oh my god.
That's a lot.
Really?
Your game is that good that they're going to put in 2 million and get 20 million out?
You've got to be pretty bold to be able to go and tell them that story, but people do
it all the time, right?
In case you're not...
In case you're not clear on what 10x means, it's this many.
Like, it's a lot of monies.
It's a lot.
But particularly if you've got a platform story,
it can be very valid and it can work out really well
in a lot of scenarios.
So those are the four main scenarios for raising money.
Now, some people do just one, some people mix and match,
and then there's others.
We didn't talk about crowdfunding.
And I didn't talk about that because almost nobody can survive purely on that.
People use that as a supplement.
You might also get grant funding for something you do, right?
And that can be a supplement, but again, nobody can subsist entirely on that.
And so if you're going to keep a studio going over time, you're going to have to be thinking
about this a lot.
And if you don't like thinking about money and you really don't enjoy it, well, then
you need to do something different.
Let me ask you, does anyone know who that is?
Say again?
Walt Disney?
It is not Walt Disney.
That's a good guess though.
A close relation, right?
Right.
You know, anybody recognizes Walt Disney, but who recognizes Roy Disney, right?
Roy was there with Walt every step of the way.
When they created the studio back in the 20s, it was the Disney Brothers Studio.
Roy was more or less the CEO of that place almost the entire time.
But he realized that having Walt as a front man
was a better way to get business
because Roy was a consummate businessman.
He knew how to make the money work
and Walt sure as hell did not, right?
Walt was bad with money.
He was a creative genius who wanted to do
these incredible, beautiful things
and when it came to money, he was kind of a scary disaster.
But Roy was there to kinda deal with the money.
So you've gotta think about, are you cool?
Are you into the game of getting the money
and dealing with that?
If you are, that's fine, do that.
If you're not, get some help,
because you're gonna need the help,
because it's never easy.
Okay, so we got the people,
and somehow we got the money.
Awesome, finally, studio's done, studio's protected.
Now I can get to what I've always wanted.
I'm gonna make awesome games.
I'm not gonna make awesome games.
What is happening?
No, no you're not,
because you run the studio now,
and that's not your job anymore.
You have a new job. Your job is optimize the studio. That's your job.
And you're like, but wait a minute, wait a minute, wait a minute. I've got my people and I've got my
game. Everyone knows a great game is the most important thing. That's my top priority. No,
it's not. Your number one priority is making sure that your team has everything they need
to make a great game. Your number two priority is making sure that game is great.
So let me just make that clear.
Your team's top priority is making the game great.
Your top priority is making the team great.
Because if you're not gonna do it, who's gonna do it?
There's no one else who's gonna do it.
And that has to be your priority.
And again, if you're not up for that, if you're not ready for that, you want to think twice
about really am I the one who's really going to run the studio because it's the primary
responsibility of leading a studio team.
And it's tough, man, because the team wants all these things.
They want all this stuff and if they don't have the stuff they're not happy.
And if they're not happy you don't have a good game and everything is bad.
They want so many things. Oh my God.
They want like an alphabet of things,
right? It's actually not a whole alphabet.
It's weirdly a half of an alphabet,
technically a half of that.
Also, now this one in particular is the alphabet of happiness, TM.
And you're like, I don't want to solve these problems.
I don't want to, I got to find ways to get people excited about their work and make sure
they like each other and coach them.
And really, that's, you know what?
When you picked up that sword.
You signed up.
And when you're like, what do they expect from me?
Really?
They expect me to do all this.
This is what they expect.
They did, because when you picked it up,
you know what you said?
You said, I'm a superhero.
That's what you said.
And that's what they expect.
Now you know you're not a superhero,
I know you're not a superhero.
And they kinda know that too,
but they expect you to be one anyway.
Right?
That's what they expect.
Because, and when you're a superhero,
every problem is your problem.
Every problem at the studio,
it's like, well you can't say,
well that's their problem.
No, it's all your problem.
It all goes to you, right?
And that sounds terrifying and daunting,
but guess what?
You can do it.
You totally can.
So I'm gonna give you practical tips
on how to be a superhero.
All right, practical superhero tips.
Number one, you wanna get organized.
Get yourself organized.
Now a lot of people are like,
wait, I'm a creative person.
Like, organization is death.
Organization is the end of the world.
It's terrible.
It's not right.
I like what Flaubert had to say.
Be regular and orderly in your life
so you may be violent and original in your work.
Right? Being orderly is a way to be powerful.
Or as Alton Brown says, organization will set you free.
And who's your main enemy?
The Sharknado.
The opposite of chaos is order.
You want to find ways to be orderly.
When you are orderly, you protect your studio
from the chaos that will rip it apart.
So even if it's not in your nature, find ways to be orderly.
And I'll give you some tips.
One, get a notebook.
Because your memory, it sucks.
People are like, hey, you need to do this.
Oh yeah, I'll remember to do that.
No, you won't.
You totally won't.
You got a million things to think about.
Your brain can think about five things at a time
if you're lucky, right?
So, get a notebook.
I really recommend the book Getting Things Done.
It's a little out of date in practical wise,
but philosophy wise, it really is great
at helping you become an organized person.
Note the subtitle, The Art of Stress-Free Productivity,
because that's the goal, to be orderly
in a stress-free way and get everything done.
At a minimum, you're gonna want a to-do list.
of course, so that you remember to do things.
You're gonna, of course, you're gonna have a notebook
for general notes about this and that,
but you're also gonna need a hot list.
And it took me a long time to understand about a hot list.
I've been using the same notebook now for 20 years.
I'll show it to you here.
Same notebook, right there.
I've had this notebook, I realize, for really 20 years,
the same exact notebook.
It's one of these notebooks where you can take the pages
in and out so you can reorganize it.
And you can see how I've done it here.
I've got a bunch of tabs on the front page.
Those are all the different things I have to keep track of.
Some of them are people that I have to coach and manage.
Some of them are projects I need to keep an eye on.
And then so I have a page for each one.
You see a sample page there on the right.
And look, I keep it really simple.
What a hot list is, it's not stuff I have to do.
It's stuff that I have to keep an eye on, that I have to remember to keep checking with
the team about.
Like, I'll see a thing and I'm like, ooh, those textures are ugly.
And I'll say, when are you going to fix those textures?
They're like, oh, no, no, no, pretty soon, maybe next week.
So you write down ugly textures, right, and you put a little note, next week, they say
they're going to fix it.
So that way, when you check in with the team, they're like, anything you want to check on?
I'm like, oh, yeah, those ugly textures, did you fix those yet, right?
So you remember to do that.
So having a hot list is very important.
I'm a paper and pencil kind of guy.
And so again, in terms of being organized,
one of the things I always say,
being organized is reaching for the catch up
and it is there, right?
So that's what organization is, right?
It's not like you forgot to get the catch up
or you lost it or anything.
So it's very important.
I need an eraser for this.
I know that sounds stupid, but I'm always,
you write things and then you erase status things,
but who has a pencil and eraser with them?
I do because it's taped in the notebook.
Right? It's always right there.
I can't possibly lose it. It's always right there.
I'm not saying you have to do that, but you have to come up with your systems, the systems
that are going to work for you.
You're going to think of things all the time, write them down.
Keep a notepad by the bed.
If you don't do that, oh my God, keep a notepad by the bed.
And why would you just keep it by the bed?
Like your shaving or whatever, why wouldn't you have one in the medicine cabinet?
You think of so many smart things then, you're like, oh, I'll remember that later.
You won't!
Write it down and get it in a notepad that goes somewhere.
And yes, yes, this is totally a thing.
In the shower one day I was like, oh my god, waterproof paper, that would be genius, I
should invent it.
Someone already invented it.
So keep a waterproof paper pad in the shower because you think of things in the shower,
you know you do really important things, write them down.
All right, so get organized.
You're like, ew, who does that?
A superhero!
That's who does that.
All right.
So another practical tip, running a studio,
it's so tempting to run around firefighting all the time.
There's Sharknado's breaking everything
and causing fires all over the place,
and you've got to help this, and you've got to fix this,
and you've got to fix that, and it feels so productive
when you're putting out all these fires.
But when you're doing that, you're not moving forward.
You're just barely getting by.
What you need is to find time so you can think ahead
of what happens next, what does the studio do next,
who do we need to hire next?
You need time.
for that. You need to get beyond firefighting mode.
Okay? And there's a lot of ways to do that. One of them is to make time
for yourself. On my calendar, every morning from nine to ten
is a block. It just says, important work. During that period, I am not allowed to
look at email. I am only allowed to do things on my to-do
list, which are things that are kind of for
getting out ahead of things. I can't, I don't always hit it every day,
but trying to have that discipline makes such a difference and makes things much
calmer.
Delegating is one of the hardest things for people.
You started your own studio
because you wanted to do everything.
You want everything to be perfect your way,
but you can't do everything.
And pretty soon your people are gonna start to hate you
because stuff's not getting done
because you're the bottleneck, right?
And you don't want that.
And you need to make time to do the important things.
So you need to start experimenting with delegating,
getting other people to do things,
and figuring out what are the tasks you wanna hold on to,
and what are the tasks you wanna give to others?
Another important one, keep doing what you're best at.
Now I know I just said no,
you can't work on the game anymore,
you gotta focus on the people.
Well of course, the people are your top responsibility.
But you're doing this
because you have some genius with games.
There's something you're super good at.
Don't give it up because you're still good at it.
Find a way that you can still do the parts
that you're best at.
Your team expects that from you.
It's your superpower.
It's one of your superpowers.
Your team expects you to bring that thing you're best at
and find a way to get that in there.
Being humble is super important.
It's real easy to pick up that sword and get real arrogant,
and it leads to a downfall every single time.
It leads to people not telling you the truth.
It leads to all kinds of problems.
And what do we call a superhero who's not humble?
Villain right you might be a super villain and you don't know it and no one's going to tell you because you're such an arrogant
Pain in the ass right?
And then that that's that's never good. So you want to be humble
Important, you're now gonna be super busy.
You're gonna be so busy, you're doing this job
60, 80 hours a week, whatever.
It can be easy to run yourself into the ground
and get a lot of bad habits.
You need to find your healthy self.
Find a way to kind of get healthy habits in your life
because everybody needs you to do that.
An unhealthy superhero, you know,
who's coughing and wheezing down the street
and hyperventilating every time something goes wrong,
it's like that's not gonna work for you.
And a phrase I got from Jeff Outlaw, one of the senior producers at our studio,
you eat last.
Okay, think of a situation, we're bringing pizza in, we're having a big brainstorming party,
did we order enough pizza? I don't know, probably we did, everybody's lining up getting pizza.
Imagine a situation where like you eat first and then there's not enough pizza for somebody else and then there you are, you know
Running the studio and you're eating pizza and other people are like, oh man, I'm sorry. I was late
I was fixing all these bugs that we only have because the deadlines were so short and
Like and what happens is people notice what you do
They notice, they're not always gonna tell you
that they notice, they notice what they do
because they expect more from you
than they expect from the other people they work with.
Because you picked up that sword, they expect more from you.
So you need to always remember,
like put everyone else first.
Because that's what superheroes do.
Okay, so there's some superhero tips.
So let's get to the alphabet of happiness.
We can do this, we're gonna go through these
and do these things.
Now they're hard, and I know they're icky,
and I know they're gross.
Do I have to do them?
Yes, you do, because you're holding a sword.
So who else is going to do it?
One way to think about why these are so important
and what's important about them for people,
anyone who's taken a basic psychology class
has run into Maslow's hierarchy of needs.
We often talk about it in terms of players and storytelling,
but you think about it in terms of the people
in your studio.
It's very, very relevant and valid.
At the bottom are your basic physiological needs,
and you say, well, what does that have to do with my studio?
How do you think people pay for food and water?
And when people crunch and they're not sleeping,
you're taking away one of their basic physiological needs.
And then after that, there's psychological needs.
And you're like, well, family, friendship, whatever.
What does that have to do with anything?
When you've got your staff working 60 hours a week, and
they can't maintain their family
relationships very well, they've got all kinds of
troubles and problems.
Because the whole point of this hierarchy is the stuff at
the top can't happen unless the stuff lower
down is taken care of.
And what's at the top?
At the very top, we have people achieving their full
potential and doing creative activities.
How are they going to be great game developers if the things underneath are like falling apart in their lives?
They can do it for a little while, but they can't sustain it.
And so you need to always keep an eye out for like, does everyone have all their needs fulfilled?
And even look at that level four, esteem needs.
Like if you're just barking at the team all the time and they're feeling like,
oh man, yeah, geez, I guess maybe we do kind of suck.
Like again, they're not going to be their best creative selves.
So, some concrete things that you can do.
All right.
A, adequate salary.
Well, that's kind of straightforward.
People need to get paid.
But the problem is now it's your job to figure out
how much is that?
How much should people get paid?
Here's my pro tip.
Ask them, right?
So, you know, how much would you be looking to make
at this job?
And they'll tell you.
And if you're like, oh, like we can afford that,
then you say, yeah, okay, that's great.
And if you're thinking, oh, no, we can't,
then you figure out, well, what can we afford?
And you tell them and they'll decide.
And that way, either way, they decided, yeah, okay, I'm doing it,
and then they'll be starting on a basis of some kind of adequate salary.
You know, it's a simple but important thing.
Second one, people need to believe in what they're doing,
especially in something like games.
Games is a passion-based industry.
and they need to believe in the mission,
not just the mission of this particular game,
like where's this studio going?
What are we doing after this game?
What is this place really all about?
I was working at a place once and I asked the boss that,
I'm like, what exactly is our goal?
And he's like, you know, I don't know, make cool stuff,
I don't know, and it was so unsatisfying to realize,
my God, he has no plan, we're just gonna drift around
from one thing to the next, that doesn't feel great,
I wanna feel like I'm part of something important.
Now, some people say, oh, really, I'm going to make a mission statement?
That sounds like the most corporate thing ever.
And yeah, if you make a crap mission statement, it is.
Right?
But you should, are you doing this for an important reason or not?
And the answer might be no, I'm not doing it for an important reason.
But if you are, you should be able to say what that is.
That's the mission statement.
Now, it takes some thinking, and it takes some work, and it takes some bravery to be
able to do it.
I really recommend reading this book, The Advantage, by Patrick Valencioni.
It is short and it is great.
It is all about that the main advantage an organization can have is to be healthy.
And he gives all these tips, and one of them is about coming up with clear mission statements,
clear core values, clear principles.
And so following the template of that, one of the things like we've done at our studio
is we have, you know, we have this little sheet right here where we have our clear mission
statement.
our clear core values, we have a bunch of principles,
I'm not gonna get into all those,
and you'll notice at the bottom, top priority right now,
and this is our current studio priority,
which we decided is protect and leverage our VRAR momentum.
Now you might say, one priority?
But like, yeah, you can only have one top priority.
That's how top priority works.
And so there I labeled everything and that's the thing.
And if you want to download these slides later,
you can check all that stuff out as a sample.
And but the important thing is that you have these discussions
with yourself and with the team to figure out what are we about,
what is important to us, and guess what?
You can change them later if you realize
that you picked the wrong ones.
You can do that.
It's okay.
But you need to be brave enough to step up and say,
this is what we're about.
And say it in front of everybody and get them to believe it.
And it's tough, right? Because people are scared to put these principles down.
Because this means, oh my God, what if I don't always do these?
This means I'm going to be a hypocrite and people will call me out.
Yes, that's right, they will. People will call you out for going against your own values.
You want that to happen. You want that to happen.
It's helpful. It hurts, but it's helpful.
Culture is really important.
Everyone that says culture is so important,
how do you engineer an excellent culture?
Well, you can't engineer an excellent culture.
Cultures grow.
That's what cultures do.
They grow from how people.
interact with each other. So that starts with you. How do you interact with everybody else?
And then how do they interact with each other?
That's all the culture is. And so focus on those interactions and you'll have an excellent culture.
It's not about, oh, we have jelly beans in the break room. It's not about that.
It's about how people interact with each other.
A big part of your job is removing distractions.
One of the horrible things, sharknadoes can crop up
inside the studio, they don't all come from outside.
You can get two people together who just don't get along
and suddenly you have chaos,
and that's your problem to solve.
So chaos can come from anywhere
and you have to keep an eye out for it,
you need to look for it,
and you need to find ways to deal with it.
People always say, oh, I hated working at that one place
because it had so much politics.
What is politics? Politics is one person wants to tell something to someone else, but they can't.
They're afraid to, they have this reason and that reason, they can't tell them, so they go and tell other people.
Oh, did you hear what that guy said? And this and that. That's when politics begins.
You need to look for that and weed that out and not let that.
happen. And of course it can come from you yourself and you have to watch for that.
Great advice from Ed Catmull, another excellent book, Creativity Inc., his tale of how Pixar
was created and formed and he has all these leadership lessons in there. A lot of great
quotes in that book. You have problems you know and problems you don't know. And realizing
this, realizing of course we all know we have problems we know and we're trying to fix those
problems. But acknowledging that you also have problems you don't know.
means you're going to keep an eye out for problems that you're like not even aware of
yet.
It's very important.
And the other phrase he uses, the good hides the bad.
When things are going really well at the studio, no one wants to tell you about some crappy
situation where there's a fight between the art and engineering department, because people
feel bad that they've got this crappy thing going on when everything's so good.
Because when things are good, when things are bad, everyone will talk about all the
bad things.
When things are good, the good things hide the bad things.
So don't fall under the illusion like, oh, everything seems to be going so well.
You still must weed out these hidden problems.
And a very important thing he mentions, only the leaders can remake the rules of the studio.
Sometimes you have rules, written or unwritten, at the studio that are broken and bad.
And most of the people in the studio can't do anything about it.
It's just they don't see it as something within their power.
It's only within your power.
Ed Catmull tells this great story about this really bad design table they had
that was long and skinny, and the people who sat in the middle of it
were the important people, and people on the ends didn't really get to participate very much.
And everyone knew it was bad, but no one would say anything
because they were like, obviously management likes this
because that's why they put this table here.
right? And eventually they had to realize, oh my God, we have to change this. And it
was a big deal. I had a situation on I Expect You to Die. We'd been very, very budget conscious
because we'd had a history in the past of sometimes going over budget on internal projects.
So we'd really clamp down on it. And we had rules about, you know, this is the budget
and that's that. The team came up with this brilliant idea to do this opening credit song
sequence.
And they were like, oh, this is great, but we can't do it,
because it's just not in the budget.
And no one even wanted to bring it up with me.
They didn't even want to say it, because they were sure I
would shoot it down.
And then I happened to see it, and I'm like, oh my god, this
is so amazing.
We have to do this.
And they're like, and so here I am.
I'm the head of the company telling them, we
have to do this.
And they're like, we can't.
I'm like, why can't we?
It's just the budget.
It's not there.
I'm like, we'll change the budget.
And everyone's like, wait, we can change the budget?
Right?
And so that's one of the things, when you end up in a leadership position,
you have to look for places the rules need to be remade.
People need to not just believe in their work and believe in the mission,
they need to be excited about it, they need to be enthusiastic.
And you're like, of course they are, they're making games, it's awesome.
Are they?
Really?
Maybe, maybe not.
You need to talk to people.
You need to ask.
Check in with people about how they're feeling
about the work.
You need to ask just in case.
People need to feel cared about.
It's important.
It's one of the things that really improves
their self-esteem.
And you might say, of course, you know, they get paid,
they get to make games, of course they feel cared about.
But is that really true?
Like, what have you done to really show you care
how they feel, right?
And a great way to do that is to ask them how they feel.
I like this phrase, I forgot to say I care.
And it's an easy thing to forget.
So the best way to do this is first
you have to actually care, right?
If you don't actually care.
You're going to have a hard time.
But first, you have to actually care, but that's not enough.
Then you have to back that up by doing things
that caring people do, and even that's not enough.
Then you have to tell people anyway
about that you care how they feel and that you want to know,
how do you feel about this?
I'm going to lump these next two together because they have a lot to do with each other.
Good feedback and helpful coaching.
This is one of the hardest things.
For me personally, this was really, really hard.
I think we still struggle with it a bit, but it was a turning point for me to realize how
important these things are.
that people really need excellent feedback
about what they're doing.
I personally believe 360 feedback,
where you collect feedback from people's peers
about each other, about what are they good at,
what do they need to get better at, is really important.
They can't give it to each other directly
because it's too dangerous.
It could cause too much tension.
So you create a situation where it has to flow
through studio leadership, where people say,
here's what I liked about this person,
and here's where this person needs to improve,
and then...
The manager as coach needs to kind of sit down with people
and say, you know, here's what people feel like you need
to get better at.
And so you need to get that feedback.
A thing you need to come to terms with, who are your A,
B, and C players?
Who are your people who are excellent?
Who are your people who are, yeah, they're OK?
And who are your people who are having trouble?
Nobody likes to face this.
You don't like to face the fact that, yeah, that one guy
is not really doing very well.
I'm just going to try and not think about it because I want
to avoid it.
you need to think about it because that person who's not doing very well,
you could have an A player in there instead and imagine how much better everything would be.
And their life won't end if they have to end up leaving the studio.
And maybe if you actually confronted their problem, maybe you'd help them deal with it and they'd get better.
Right? But ignoring the C players is just unacceptable.
Because people need to know where they stand.
They need you to tell them, like, how am I doing?
Am I doing well?
How do I, how do I, and if not, how can I get better?
And the C players, you need to find a way to get the better,
and if you can't get them better, you need to get them out.
And it sucks, nobody likes firing people.
It sucks to have to do it, but you have to do it.
And people's lives don't end when they get fired.
Often it's better.
They're like, oh, I was really struggling at this one place,
I got fired, and man, I found a place I fit in much better,
and I'm doing better work.
It happens all the time.
So, coaching.
You must make time for one-on-one coaching meetings.
It always feels like, oh, I don't have time for this,
we gotta focus on the game,
and I gotta focus on all these fires.
You need to make time to sit down with people and say,
how's it going, what's going well,
what do you need help with, what are problems that you have?
You need to give your people time
to talk through their problems
so they can get advice from you or from somebody.
And this really, as a leader,
this is your number one priority.
One-on-one meetings with.
the people you work with is the best thing you can do to help make them great.
And it's scary because you don't know the perfect way to do it,
and you don't know exactly what to say, and you don't have to have all the answers.
We've all had the situation where you go and you,
you go to somebody with a problem and like you talk through the problem
and then you realize the solution in your own brain just through talking about it.
Right? Just...
And the more you do it, you're just going to get better at it anyway.
And this is a great time for you to have your core valuables, your core principles and your
core values ready.
Like I always keep them on a little sheet of paper right nearby when we have these meetings.
So when someone did something really great, I can say, hey man, that's really great.
You're really embodying what we're about.
Or someone did something that's questionable, I can say, well, I don't think that was good.
Or I can say, hey, look, guy, principle number four, we've talked about this.
Why are you going against it?
Talk about it in the concrete.
way. And very efficient, help people coach each other. Make opportunities for people
to get together and just share their problems with each other. And just create those opportunities,
get them scheduled. I remember the first time I finally figured out to do that and people
were like, wow, I didn't know that we were allowed to do this.
Yeah, okay, right, no, it is really useful
and sort of obviously useful,
but no one ever said this was a good thing to do.
Two amazing books by the same people, by Stone and Heen,
Difficult Conversations.
This is all about how do you have difficult conversations
in a productive, useful way,
and related, Thanks for the Feedback.
It's a book about how to take feedback,
but in doing so, it's really about
how to give the best possible feedback.
And one thing I've been doing recently,
I totally recommend, get a tool for anonymous feedback.
We've been using this one called OfficeVibe.
It's expensive.
I'll put it out there.
We're in a little debate about, is this really worth it?
But we feel like it is.
And what this does is it sends little quizzes, easy little
surveys to people about how you feel about your project,
how you feel about your coworkers, how you feel about
your boss, just little simple things, simple, simple little
web things, just like one or two questions a week.
Real simple.
And then it collects all that data and it shares the data
with management in an anonymous way.
So you can kind of see the vibe of what's going on in there.
But most important, this is the most valuable part,
people can kind of, there's free form open boxes,
people can kind of type stuff in,
and you get it all, and it's all anonymous.
So it's like a suggestion box
of the things people are concerned about.
And here's the best part,
you can answer the questions anonymously.
You're not anonymous, they know it's you.
You're the boss, they know that.
But you don't know who asked it.
So someone's like, man, I'm really upset by this one thing.
This project got canceled.
And I think we're going on the wrong track.
And you'd be like, whoa, I haven't heard about this.
And you can say, hey, Anonymous, let me tell you,
I really think this is better.
And here's the reasons why it's so much better.
And sometimes they come back.
First, they're like, oh my god, my big, serious complaint.
The boss just got me a letter back.
And sometimes they're like, that actually made sense.
And they write back to you.
And they say, thanks for explaining that.
I didn't know.
I didn't understand.
I've had no other way to get information like that.
So like finding a tool for anonymous feedback is great.
You can check out my talk from last year.
It was all about information flow in the studio.
One of the great things in this Patrick Lencioni book, he uses a term that is super valuable,
overcommunication.
He points out that people can't read your mind, and as a leader, you must over-communicate
the things that are important.
You must say them not just once, you can't be just like, oh, I said it, they all know.
You need to say it again and again to the point where you're a little embarrassed, right?
Because a repetition of important things is helpful, because they're important, right?
So you should repeat important things.
you should be saying important things again and again,
in different ways.
Because it's better for people to hear,
you get the idea, but look how uncomfortable it is,
but I'm gonna do it anyway.
Important things, you should repeat them, right?
Yeah.
So.
A joint feeling of respect, right?
You want to feel respected by people,
people want to feel respected by you.
You want to look for these situations.
This is back to this notion of,
are you yourself good at making others feel respected?
And you need to look inside yourself
and make sure that that's really true.
Keeping communication comfortable, because when it's not comfortable, it stops.
And that's when politics begins.
One of the things as a game designer, I feel like my most important discovery is this reading
some psychology neurology paper and realizing that we have two different circuits in our
brains, that the circuits for avoiding negative consequences and the circuits for seeking
positive consequences are completely different brain systems.
And we see this in game design all the time, this moment when people switch from reward
seeking to punishment avoiding.
It's very important for game design.
It's also very important for your studio.
Why are people communicating with you?
Are they communicating with you because they have to?
Or are they communicating with you because they want to?
Everything will be different.
If you're the kind of person who's tough to talk to, and
they're like, ugh, I don't want to talk to that guy,
people are using a totally different part of their brain.
And how's it going in your studio?
How's the communication going?
When is it comfortable?
When is it uncomfortable?
People want to like their teammates, and I know that sounds sort of simple and sort of straightforward,
but it's true and it's important.
And when you interview people, you should be thinking about likability.
Who is going to fit in with the culture and how are people going to like each other?
And if you check out last year's talk, I talked a lot about the research evidence
that shows that likability is more important.
then how good somebody is at their job.
That sounds crazy, but it's totally true,
and you can hear the complicated story about it,
but you wanna focus, you wanna think about
making sure people like each other.
It's one of the main reasons people quit a studio,
is like I couldn't stand the people I was working with.
And the last part of the alphabet is measurable progress.
People really want measurable progress.
We know that we're game designers.
Oh my God, how do we not know that?
We do know that, but we so rarely design it well
into our studios.
And it comes from so many places.
It can certainly come from the project.
We're making great progress on the project.
I feel really great about that.
Raises are really important.
Did you ever think about why we have inflation
here on planet Earth?
Every nation has inflation.
Why should it be that prices and salaries gradually rise over time?
Shouldn't it drift up and drift down?
No, it gradually rises because human beings like progress,
even if we have to make it up.
Right?
So figuring out the raises that are going
to feel like good, measurable progress for people
is very important and very tricky.
People's growing responsibility and getting more and more responsibility is important.
And of course, you want to make it clear, measurably clear, letting people know that
like I'm now, you know, yeah, we're giving you these new responsibilities and we're looking
forward to you taking care of those.
One thing people talk about is the Peter Principle.
This is a famous thing in large organizations.
The idea that people get promoted, you know, you're good at your job.
We're going to promote you.
Oh, you're good at your job.
And when do we stop?
We stop when you suck at your job.
And what that means is ultimately you're going to have an organization full of people who
suck at their job.
And some people are like, there's nothing you can do about it, it's just what happens.
It's not true.
The way you do it is don't promote people until they've already been doing the new job
for a while.
Because if they do the new job and they suck, don't promote them.
But if they do their new job and they're great,
well, then you promote them and you avoid the Peter principle.
So job titles and figuring that out is important.
And I know it sounds silly.
Like, oh, really?
Just a name?
Just a label?
You're game designers.
Oh my god.
You know that.
You know how important just some bogus title
is into making someone feel good about themselves?
You know that.
Clear feedback, of course, about exactly,
are you good at your job?
Are you getting better or not?
And having your manager tell you,
yeah, you're really getting better.
I really see you getting better.
And being very clear about that is important.
And then, of course, watching a studio grow itself,
which sometimes happens with studios,
that can feel like progress to people as well.
So I'm gonna talk about some studio growth rules of thumb.
Just real quick here.
If you have more than five people,
that's at the point where you need a producer.
And you're going to need another producer for every 10
developers that you get.
If you have more than 10 people in your studio,
you're going to find you're needing sub-team meetings
to get certain kinds of communication to happen.
When you've got small studios, you
don't have to think about communication so much.
It just happens.
Everybody's just there.
Once you get more than 10, you have
to organize and plan the communication,
or it doesn't happen.
Once you get more than 20 people,
like coaching isn't going to happen so naturally anymore.
You need to assign formal coaching responsibilities.
Once you get more than 30,
you better get a full-time IT guy.
I'll just say that, it's important.
And you're gonna need one every 50 more developers you get.
Once you get to around 40 people, you're going to find you need departments of some kind.
A flat architecture is not going to work for you anymore, and you're going to need leaders
to lead up these departments.
And by 50, you'll probably need full-time HR, you'll probably need full-time accounting
and finance.
Once you get to 60, you're going to need two layers of management for coaching inside departments.
I heard when Media Molecule was formed, the guys who do Little Big Planet, they said,
We're, our plan is to not have to get bigger than 30 because we've had the best experiences
with no more than 30 devs.
So we're going to design games that only need 30 devs.
Now just look at the website, they have 51 devs right now.
So I think, what I suspect is they're pushing up against that 60 number.
They don't want to, they don't, they don't want a place where they want to have those
two layers.
And we're up to 105, I'm not really seeing
too many more barriers right now,
but I'll tell you this, once you reach 150,
and I've seen this again and again,
you hit Dunbar's number, this is an innate human thing,
you can read all about it,
and your organization will split in two.
It's just what happens with human primates.
Now, when should you get business development?
When should you get marketing?
I can't give you guidelines on that.
Some people start with it at day one.
Some people don't need to start with it till later.
But you're gonna need it sometime,
so you better figure that out.
Okay, back to the plan.
You built a studio, you protected the studio,
and now you're focusing a lot on optimizing the studio.
But you're still a little bit sad,
because I didn't really wanna think about people all day.
I wanna think about games.
That's why I did this.
I wanna think about games all day.
And I'll give you a secret.
The studio is a game.
And the people who work there are the players.
And everything you know about game design,
you can use to make that studio great.
And if you do that, you're going to make
a studio that doesn't just make games
and doesn't just make money, but is
going to create joy.
for every single person who interacts with it at all.
And it's going to be the hardest damn game
that you have ever worked on.
But I'm here to tell you, you can do it.
Thanks very much.
It looks like I use up all the time.
I'm happy to chat with people afterwards.
Please don't forget to fill out your surveys
and have a great GDC.