Hello everybody. Welcome to Offroad Trading Company and RTS
without guns. Before we get started, please remember to
silence your cell phones. All right. So, all right. There we
go. That's exciting. All right. So, this is, these are the games
that I've shipped, which shows that my main background is a
strategy game developer.
Oh my gosh.
And this is who I am now.
This is the project I've been working on
for the last three years.
Awful Training Company.
And in fact, this is a game I've wanted to make
kind of my entire career.
And so I was very excited I finally got a chance to do that.
And one of the things I want to talk about today is I really
feel that real-time strategy is actually an underexplored
genre. That there is a lot more possibilities out there than
what we see from the current RTS games. So, what makes an RTS?
Some of the things we often think of are not having a high
APM, actions per minute, a game where you're selecting a lot of
units, moving around really quickly.
have war, they tend to be, hold on, I'm sorry. There we go.
All right, they tend to be short games.
They tend to involve combat.
You know, this is what you think of as a traditional RTS.
However, if you dig a little deeper, what about Majesty?
That was a fantastic RTS game that had no unit selection.
You basically just put down bounties on the map
and the units kind of moved around based off of like these,
you know, you basically put down,
so if you attack this, you know, this works here,
I'll give you a certain amount of money.
and the units kind of followed around according to those wishes. Or, Adam's zombie
smasher, which is a game that had no fog of war. Or what about Sins of a Solar Empire,
which is almost like a 4X RTS. These games, a game of sins often took 3, 4, 5 hours. So,
what about a game with no combat?
and most importantly, I didn't just pick three random RTS games
to show that you can buck conventions. These are all
three classics in the genre. If you could only play four RTS
games, you'd be much better off playing each of these three and
just one from the first set of games I showed you.
which were StarCraft, Command and Conquer, Age of Empires,
Company of Heroes. They're all great games but to some extent
they're a little bit interchangeable because they
have a lot of the same parts. And kind of at a core level
they're kind of trying to do the same thing. So how can we make
an RTS without combat?
So this is what an operating company looks like. And it is
economic RTS. So what that means is the conflict in the game
revolves around the free market. There's a lot of resources in
the game. You know, typical RTS you might have two to four
resources. We have 13.
and each of them has a price. And the price goes up and down
depending upon player actions. If players make a lot of iron
and sell it in the market, it goes down. If players are
buying a lot of food, then the price goes up. And basically you
do well at the game by figuring out what are the resources that
are going to have, you know,
the highest demand and the least supply.
You look around, what's going to be worth a lot
in a couple days and what are my opponents
producing the least of?
That's how you're able to make a lot of money.
There's no direct combat and the game ends
basically with a hostile takeover.
So the aggression in the game is in the stock market.
The basic goal is to make as much money as possible
and then you eventually win by taking that money
and buying up the stock of your opponents.
So to talk about how I got here, I first want to talk about the
games that influenced me to get to off world. Because even
though off world is a pretty unusual game, there's not really
another, economic RTS is sort of a subgenre I basically invented
here. It actually has a lot of antecedents. Pretty much almost
every element of the game was taken from other games. Almost
everything in it is actually recognizable, it just hasn't
been together in this specific assortment.
So here's Belter. It's a very, very old hex encounter war game
from 1979. And it's a game I played as a kid. And it's what
first introduced the idea of going out, exploring,
discovering resources and them having sort of different levels.
So in Belter you would go from asteroid to asteroid and you'd
roll a dice and you'd discover if it had low or medium or high
iron or gas or whatever. And that's where I got the basic
idea for resources in Offworld.
Mule is pretty obvious influence on off world. That's
where I got the basic idea for claims. And mule had limited
claims which is really important. Like in a
traditional RTS, you're able to gather resources anywhere.
There's really no limitation on it.
where as in Mule you get a new claim every turn.
And that's really what makes the game interesting
because you have to make a tough choice of
are you going to invest in food or smith ore
or energy or whatever.
And I wanted that same mechanic in Offworld.
and I also borrowed auctions from Mule because it was such an
important part of the game. Our auctions work very differently.
They are much more like traditional auctions. But
basically after playing Mule, I knew that we had to have
auctions. It was such a cool thing to have.
Board games have influenced Offworld a lot, obviously,
for people who've played it.
They often, I often hear that, you know,
Offworld feels like, you know,
a board game that's on your computer,
it's like one that would be like way too complex to play,
but it still feels like a board game,
which is interesting,
because people don't necessarily say that
about other RTS games.
And I think, I think the reason they do
is because we really commit to transparency
in the rules in Offworld.
So here, for example, I'm showing you some detail of how
a steel mine works.
And it's showing that basically you put in one unit of iron in
one side and then out the other side comes half a unit of
steel. And all of the buildings in Alfa World basically work
like that. They're very chunky.
on the map there, you see those little cubes that represent
iron. You don't have to take a big jump to think of all those
sort of your games with little wooden cubes that you tend to
have. So we definitely wanted to give people that feeling.
Railroad tycoon is another huge influence on us. And that was
where I kind of got the concept of your shipping lanes. That
there's sort of a geographical element of, you know, you have
a base somewhere and then you go out and get your resources and
then you ship them around. You get iron from one place, you
take it here, you turn it into steel and you do something with
that. You get water from one place, you take it here, you
turn it into fuel, then you take the fuel and you turn it into
chemicals.
So indeed, you got to talk about this here, which is the
resource chart in Railroad Tycoon, which is another really
big core part of Offworld, is all of this arrangement, how you
turn resources into each one, turn one resource into another.
As an aside, I spent a long time online trying to find a resource
chart for the original railroad tycoon and the only one I could
find was in German. Which I think is very telling because if
you know Germans, the only thing better than a game where you can
turn wheat into bread is a game in which you first get to turn
it into flour and then you turn it into bread.
So this is their type of game.
And this is what the resource chart looks like in off world.
So actually it's almost the same number of types of
buildings and types of resources and conversions.
And some are a little more complex than others.
The electronics factory requires three inputs.
Some spit out two inputs.
The reactor takes water and splits it into oxygen fuel,
which creates some interesting dynamics in the system.
But here's actually the big one.
It's Age of Empires.
And specifically, there's just one building in Age of Empires
that has a huge influence on off world. And that building is the
market, which you can see here kind of on the left side of the
screen. In fact, it's selected, so you can see in the bottom
left corner of the screen there's this interface, which I
want to zoom in here. So this is the market building where you
can, there's four resources in Age of Empires. Food, wood,
stone, gold.
and using the market you can trade any of those resources at
any time for using gold. And the wonderful thing about this
system is that the prices are global. So...
you know, I start buying wood, I get wood, but the price goes
up for everyone. So if someone out there notices that the
price of wood has gotten really high, they can start taking
advantage of that. They can produce a lot of wood, turn it
to gold, and gold is really valuable in nature empires. You
can, you know, some of the most powerful units like knights are
made with gold. So they can really take advantage of this
sort of market inefficiency by turning basically something
worthless like, not worthless, but less worthwhile, less
worthy.
whatever that word is, taking that wood, turning it into gold,
turning it into a really powerful unit. So you can see
there's kind of a direct line here from the market in Age of
Empires right to our resource market in Offworld. In many
ways you can say that we made an entire game about just this one
building in Age of Empires.
and there's something interesting I'd like to note,
which is you see there's actually two prices there, right?
So you can sell wood for 76 gold,
and you have to spend 142 to buy it.
So they're actually kind of like,
they're hedging their bets, basically.
They're doubling the price to make sure people don't.
do too much trading. It's an interesting part of the game,
but it's just something to the side. It's a supplement to the
main game. They didn't want this part of the game to take over by
having those two prices, the buy and sell price, be too close.
And when I first made off world, I actually just adopted what
they did. I had the buy and sell price be, I'd have the buy price
be double the sell price. And
it wasn't really interesting. The game never really took off
internally when we were playing until I decided I don't know if
this is working. I just collapsed the price into one
price. So when you buy it and sell it, it's the same price.
And then the game suddenly became so much more interesting
because then there were so many new ways to get an advantage
off of the market. At that point it was all about arbitrage. The
market could change within a few seconds and you can make
you can make a huge profit off of something very quickly.
Where here, you buy wood for $142,
you're going to have to wait a long time
for the price to get high enough
for you to make sense to actually sell it.
You probably are never going to be able
to make money that way.
So, collapsing into one price made a huge difference.
All right, so but why build a game
around a free market at all?
And for me it comes down to,
what I call adaptive game play. Adaptive game play means you
are adapting your strategy to the current environment, which
is really the core of strategy gaming. There is not one choice.
This is an RPG. We are not letting you decide how you want
to play the game. The whole point is to see what environment
the game is presenting to you and then try to make the best
choice depending upon that.
that's adaptation. And I think all good strategy games have
that. And I want to kind of go into all of the things in off
world that enable that. And a lot of these things you'll see
come back to a free market. So, you know, number one, you got
the random maps. Right? And different type of train favor
different types of resources. So you might have some maps where
there's a lot of iron and very little water. Or you might have
another map where there's the reverse. And that totally
changes the dynamics in the market.
If you see a map where there's very little water,
then you want to make sure that you monopolize that early.
Maybe you try to grab up as much of the water as possible
because you know that by the end of the game,
the prices of all the life support materials
are going to be super high,
and everyone's going to have to buy that from you.
We have random events in the game.
You see on the...
On the left there, there's a fuel shortage and an iron
shortage, which is causing sort of like a temporary spike in
price for those resources. On the right, there's an oxygen
surplus and a chemical surplus, which is sort of doing the
opposite. So these are other things that can sort of mix up
the supply-demand ratio on the market.
we introduced random prices for when the game begins.
On the left side, those are kind of what you'd say
are the base prices for all the resources.
So you know, kind of the more advanced resources
like electronics and glass started out more expensive.
Things like water and...
iron and aluminum, things you can just get
straight from the ground, start out cheaper.
And so, at some point I was like,
well I feel like I really want to
have the game a little more variety,
make the game have a little more variety because
when the game starts with the same prices,
you kind of end up always starting with the same buildings,
you know, based off of that kind of dynamic.
And so I was like, well let's just roll the dice
and see what the prices are.
And so I did what you see there in the middle column,
whereas I just said, you know,
kind of prices all over the place.
And that sort of works at a high level.
It definitely made the game have more variety
because things were very, very different.
But the problem was there was too much cognitive load
on the player when the game began.
You know, they look at that chart of numbers
and it's just kind of like,
it's just a mishmash of numbers.
it's hard to process all at once. So what we did instead is
what you see in the right column, which is that we either
double a resource, the double resources price or half it. And
then we also give a little colored hint. So you can see
immediately when you see that, when the game starts, this is
exactly what the market is going to look like. You click quickly
and you're like, oh, there's four resources, or double price
and two resources are half price.
you know, and that can hugely affect, you know, how you want
to start. So here you see iron is green, it's 40 bucks, that
means it's double price. So you might want to grab two iron
tiles instead of one at the beginning of the game. Here's
another thing, random auctions. So over the course of the game,
you know, usually every 24 hours basically, you get an auction
comes up and that can be for a patent, it can be for a tile, it
can be for something on the black market. And that's an
interesting, you know, sort of
the game can throw at you because the players can't
anticipate what's going to come up. What you're seeing here is
some fan art that was made based off of a game that's become
infamous among our community. It was from a tournament where two
players both started the game where due to random prices,
steel was like I think double price and iron was half price.
So they both were going to be very clever and just build three
steel mills to take advantage of that, you know,
price discrepancy and just create a lot of steel. But
since they both did that, it basically drove the price of
iron up so high that then the steel mills became unprofitable.
And basically both players got stuck. They couldn't even
upgrade. They were both just sitting there kind of like
waiting like, well, what should happen now? And what the game
decided to let happen was suddenly auction off a high iron
tile.
and that was it basically.
It's like well whoever gets this tile wins the game I guess.
So the auction kept going up and up and up
and just for reference here,
a typical auction usually goes from maybe 20,000,
maybe 30,000 if it's something really desirable.
So it went up to 60,000, 90, 98, 128.
192 and eventually one guy got it for $224,000. And just for
reference, if you have in a two player game, if you have $400,000
you can probably just win the game at that point. That's
probably enough to win. So he got the high iron tile, but this
is what you call the winner's curse at an auction. He spent so
much that when you spend that much it goes directly into your
debt and his basically his stock price immediately collapsed to
$1. And...
and the other player won just by basically buying them out.
So the thing here is they just said
they had never been in this situation before
of like how do we value this high iron tile?
There is some correct price.
It was probably maybe 90,000 would be my guess,
but I'm not sure, you know,
it's just you gotta figure it out as the game goes, right?
And that's what's great about adaptive gameplay, right?
You know, you have to, you know,
this is this unusual situation,
you gotta figure it out on the fly.
So here's the black market. These are a bunch of items that can
basically mess with your opponents. Things like EMP
which knocks out their buildings or mutiny where you literally
steal their buildings. Dynamite where you blow up their
buildings. You get the drift. There's some positive ones here
like an adrenaline boost that makes your stuff go faster.
But, you know, like when we started out,
we had maybe six or seven, and that seemed like fun.
But it was like, well, we could push this more.
And so, you know, we eventually,
we ship with maybe like 18 or 19 effects.
And, you know, that's an obvious place
to basically mix things up each game.
It's like there's a deck of black market items,
and you draw up seven each game.
whatever comes up can greatly influence how you want to play.
If a game has no pirates, that changes the dynamics.
Then it's safer to ship valuable resources over long distances
because you know someone isn't going to be able to steal them
from you. But here's the really big one, which is opponent
decisions. The choices the other players make in the game, you
start at one place, but the game ends in such a different place.
We see a lot, you know,
our community has a bunch of tournaments that they run kind
of regularly. You'll often see these games where two players,
you know, very high level players go against each other.
The first game it ends very quickly in like four days with
majority buyout. The next game it's this huge long affair, goes
10, 12 days, ends with a bunch of off world markets, where the
most advanced buildings. It all kind of goes back to kind of
these early decisions that those players meant that made the game
spin off in these different directions.
So put all these together, there's a lot of things that are
different about each game of off world, which is how you get
such high replayability. And so talking about opponent choices,
one of the real big ones here is when you found your
headquarters.
which of the four headquarter types, which is kind of like
StarCraft, are you going to be Terran, are you going to be
Zerg, are you going to be Protoss. But one thing that one
of our testers came up with an idea early on in the project, he
said, what if you chose your headquarters after the game
began, right? So, you know, what if you chose your
And that was great.
That was sort of like a breakthrough idea
because it, going back to the opponent decisions,
you know, like that is such an important one,
like what headquarters can be,
because that radically changes the market.
And I'll get to that in a little bit.
But I just want to point out that,
you know, when you work in a genre,
sometimes you're not aware of the baggage you're inheriting.
You know, I never really thought about like,
well maybe you should pick your headquarter type after the game
begins because every RTS you've ever played that's something you
do in the set up screen. That's just sort of a given. And doing
it this way was great. I mean, it was like that idea came up.
You know, I implemented it that afternoon. We tried it right
away and like immediately we knew that was what we wanted to
do. So, the, what headquarters you choose is so important
because it really radically alters your relationship to the
market.
The first one here is the expansive. They are sort of like
the vanilla HQ. They just have a lot of sort of straight forward
bonuses. Makes them a good one for new players. But they are
not going to radically change the market unlike these guys,
the robots. They don't consume any life support.
and they ship, they use, instead of using fuel,
they use power for their vehicles.
So that's obviously going to radically change the market.
You know, you see there's a bunch of robots
coming into the game, well probably the prices
of food, oxygen, and fuel are not going to get all that high.
Here's another big one. The scavengers, they use carbon
instead of steel for their buildings and for upgrading
their headquarters. Most everyone else uses steel. And
steel is like the super key early game resource. When you're
at level one, you almost certainly want to build some
steel mills. And they kind of like, they're able to get around
that. They can just focus on carbon. They can basically
ignore iron entirely. So they're playing a game where they only
care about four resources, which makes them potentially really
powerful.
And then here's my favorite, headquarter type,
the scientific.
They're able to put their buildings
directly on primary resources.
So a farm, for example, turns water into food.
Right, so for the scientists,
they can just put their farms directly on the water.
They don't need a water pump to make the water
and then send it to the farm.
They can just do it directly.
So that changes the market too because they're not going to be
producing primary resources which often end up flooding the
market by the end of the game. So there's actually a bit of an
Achilles heel here for the scientists which is that if
you're playing them, they probably don't have any iron
mines, they probably don't have any water pumps. So if you're
their opponent, you can start producing some water yourself.
And I'm getting a little ahead of myself here because I'm going
to be talking about the hack array. But that's a building
artificially create a water shortage.
So you can drive up the price of water
and know you'll make a lot of money just yourself
because you know that the scientist
probably doesn't have any.
Let me talk about some of the more advanced buildings in the
game. This is the patent lab. This is the kind of like really
unique technologies. Things like teleportation, so you don't need
ships to move your goods around. Something like cold fusion lets
you use water instead of power. Slant drilling is a neat one.
It means you can get sort of the I drink your milkshake patent.
You basically get to use the resources in tiles adjacent to
yours. So if someone else got a monopoly on
you can get slant drilling and claim a tile next to silicon
and start mining his resource. It feels great. Each of these
has kind of like a really kind of strange interesting
orthogonal effect. I was like, oh, it wouldn't be cool. A lot
of RTS games have these type of things, these technologies that
you resource, that you research.
that change things about the game.
And I thought I was going to be real clever
and be like, oh, what if we make them patents
so that when you research it, only you get it
and everyone else is locked out from it.
And so there's this race to get these patents
and like, oh wow, I came up with this awesome
new game mechanic.
Except it sounds pretty familiar
if you play the little game called Civ IV.
Because I basically just re-implemented Wonders.
I actually didn't even realize it.
Someone just brought this up in a press interview.
I'm like, oh yeah.
All right. I guess you're right. All right. So here's the hack
array which I mentioned earlier. This is a really neat one. I
love this building. So I showed you there were the shortages and
surpluses that happened in the game. Those happen randomly.
There's just a little RNG thing in the background that kind of
rolls every once in a while and decides what's going to happen.
But with a hack array, you can basically trigger these things
artificially. So you can create, for example, an aluminum
shortage.
you find out that it's coming and then the aluminum shortage
happens. But the other players have no idea whether was this a
real aluminum shortage or an artificial one. The effect is
the same, but the trick is if you find out someone is
artificially shorting aluminum, they're probably doing that
because they bought up a huge stockpile of it.
and they're basically trying to drive up the price
to take advantage of that.
And so you want to basically take an action against that.
You either want to create your own aluminum surpluses
or make sure you sell your own aluminum,
drive the price down before they do.
But I don't know, it's just a neat thing.
Creates a lot of paranoia.
and we took it further in multiplayer so that when you put
down a hacker array, it's covered with a hologram, which
basically makes it look like another building. So you're not
even aware if your opponents have hacker arrays. So you get a
lot of people talking back and forth when the game goes, like
when you see a shortage, you're like, oh, is that a real one or
a fake one? And the gig gets sort of up when the same shortage
happens like twice in a row. Then you're like, oh, okay, he's
going for it.
So let's talk about the black market. So I said there was no
combat in the game. Maybe that's a lie because there's the black
market. There is a way to kind of like blow up people's stuff
and shoot down their blimps and do stuff like that. However,
what I say is when we started the game, we kind of like
We took out all of the zero sum combat mechanics.
When you have tanks and barracks and military stuff,
that stuff tends to dominate,
so we wanted to go to the other extreme.
But once we went there, then we're like,
well, maybe we can start introducing
some of this stuff back into the game,
but we just need to figure out a way
to make sure it doesn't dominate.
And what was neat about our solution was it actually
kind of fits as sort of like a free market mechanic.
Which is the idea here is you see each of those
black market items has a different price.
Like you see pirates there, the second on the left
is $6,000.
And so what happens here is if I buy pirates,
the price goes up, and it goes up for everyone in the game.
So if I buy it for 6,000, then the next person will have to buy it for 10,000, and then the
next person after that will have to buy it for 16,000, and then it'll be 25,000. And
eventually the price will get high enough that it just doesn't make sense to buy pirates
anymore. And that basically solved the problem, because you know each of these black
market items is only going to get used so many times in the game.
and it also has this nice side effect of when you saw the
price go up, that means you know your opponent just bought one.
So if you saw that the price of dynamite just went up, then you
know that he's probably going to do something with some dynamite,
which might change what you decide to do.
and we put in pirates. Pirates are a pretty interesting item on the black market because
they allow you to actually steal a resource from another player. And actually in the
In an early prototype, we did actually experiment
for a while with having pirates and that you could
move around a map and basically place on people's
shipping lanes and those would blow up their ships
and you get their stuff.
But then we're like, well, we need something
to counter the pirates, so okay, maybe we'll let you
build police ships and then we'll fly the police ships
over and the police ships will shoot down the pirates.
and you know, it's kind of like, once you go down that road,
it's kind of a slippery slope towards
just making a regular RTS.
So, and you know, without really enough benefit there,
you know, like we're not differentiating ourselves enough
and like that part of the game isn't ever going to be
as fully featured as a real RTS.
So eventually we just pulled it back to like,
let's just turn this into this high level thing
that you don't have to micromanage,
just fire and forget, you just basically hit.
click a tile, place down the pirates, they manage
themselves and they basically steal X number of units and
then they go away. And then it was, it kind of fit the game
again at that point.
All right, so another cool thing on the black market
are the holograms and spies.
So you put a hologram down,
and it basically makes your building look like
one of the other buildings that's adjacent to it.
And the typical building you want to hide
is the off-world market,
because that's sort of the most powerful building
of the game.
It's kind of the end-game building that you use
to ship resources off-world,
where the prices are very high,
and they're also constant.
They don't really go down from oversupplying the market.
you can sometimes you see in games people will oversupply
the market on Mars which will drive the prices down and then
the only way to basically end the game is to go off world.
So because of the black market you really want to hide your
off world market.
So you want to put a hologram on it right?
And then the counter for that is either you know watching the
other player really closely or you place down spies and the
spies will kind of reveal holograms within a certain
range so you have a little thing going back and forth
between how those two things work together.
However, I made a choice early on, as soon as I thought of the
idea, I was like, oh, that sounds great, but it will never
work in single player. Like people, because basically,
basically it's like a, it's a catch 22 for the AI. There's no
way you can write an AI to handle holograms and spies.
Let's say, first of all, you might just do a bad job. It's
hard to do. So you might just do a bad job writing the AI, which
is not good, obviously. But what if you do a good job?
If you do a good job having the AI be able to identify where
holograms are, and they're able to figure out where you tend to
put holograms and they're able to target your buildings because
they guessed right, people are just not going to believe that
the AI played fairly. I can tell you from years of experience
working on AI, that's exactly what's going to happen. So it's
a lose-lose situation. There's no way to make people believe
the AI. Players don't trust the AI and they find cheats even
when there aren't any.
However, I really like the idea, so I just said, well, let's just
try adding something that's multiplayer only. And it works
great in multiplayer. It's not a problem in single player. And I
guess maybe that's okay. Something I hadn't really tried
all that much before in other games I made were single player
or multiplayer, where we tried to make it basically the same.
Okay. I think the real crucial piece to make the whole black
market work. So black market was fun. Got in the game, people
were having fun with it. But there was still a sense of like
you know, I lost the game because I got EMP too much or my
buildings got mutiny at a key time and there was nothing I
could do.
once the opponent tried to hit me, there was absolutely
nothing I could do. So we introduced the goon squad,
which will protect you from sabotage. So you put a goon
squad on your off-road market, someone tries to dynamite it,
it's blocked. However, it's not just blocked.
the person you try to attack with the dynamite gets your
dynamite. And also normally when you attack someone with a
black market, you don't know who attacked you. That's a
hidden information. When you attack someone with a goon
squad, that information is announced for everyone. And we
found that humans are surprisingly very vindictive.
If someone blows up my off world market, or tries to,
and I find out because of a goon squad,
there's a pretty good chance I'm gonna take that dynamite
and hit that person back.
Even if that's not the best move for me to make,
it just feels good, and you just do it, and that's that.
But the real thing about the goon squad
is it's not actually, because there's only gonna be
so many goon squads bought in the course of a game,
it's price goes up just like all the black market items.
It's the threat of a goon squad that's important.
The fact that you know,
the player could put it down,
and the effects of hitting a goon squad
are so devastating.
So, it turns into this mind game.
Surely, someone wouldn't be dumb enough
to build a geotherm so early and not goon squad it.
Of course, then you're tempted to not goon squad it
because they never think you would not goon squad it.
Anyway, it's fun.
All right, I wanna talk about the stock market a little bit.
early on, the way it works, you buy into other opponents, you buy into your opponents and at
some point you have enough money to buy them out and you buy them out, you actually get all
their stuff. You get their headquarters, you get all their buildings, you get everything. And
that worked okay, but the problem was it was just too much for most players to handle. It was
just like I got all this new stuff, I don't understand it, I don't know how it works. And in
an 8 player game, it was...
absolutely insane. So we want to try something different. So we
try what we call a subsidiary system where once a player gets
bought out, they basically get taken over by a very
conservative AI that runs the company to make money and that
money is distributed to their owners. So in this case you see
the subsidiary here is King Morgan.
he's owned partially by blue and partially by green so his money gets split between them.
And that worked great. It also had the big advantage of buying out a player was no
longer all or nothing. We had this problem before where if there were two people A and B
were competing to buy out C, whoever ends up winning that battle, there's a pretty good
chance they're going to end up winning the game. Whereas here, both of those players were
aiming to get King Morgan, they both got half of them, they're both kind of like in a good
position to continue on to win the game.
Here's another thing that we introduced after that,
which was majority buyouts, which was this concept of
once the other players got to own six of your shares,
you're just immediately removed from the game.
And you immediately become a subsidiary.
This was important because there is sort of like
a king-making problem in the game.
We do support four-player, six-player,
eight-player free-for-alls.
If it's very clear a player is going to lose,
you kind of want them eliminated as soon as possible.
Because you don't want them hanging around,
buying things on the black market,
messing with other players.
You want to get them out of the game.
Also, this created, kind of on accident,
kind of like actually a rush boom turtle mechanic
in the game in that the majority buyout
is sort of like the rush.
you know, you're kind of putting in your money
aggressively to take something out early.
Whereas the total mechanic is you kind of buy up shares
of your own stock to protect yourself.
And then the boom is basically, I'm going to take my money,
I'm going to invest it in my own infrastructure
to hopefully make more money in the long run.
And it's funny how it just kind of worked naturally.
Which basically led to, totally led to the idea
of the locked shares, which is that once you get to,
once you own five of your own shares of stock,
they're kind of like all combined into one super share.
And so that's a real key point in the game.
You kind of want to get to those five shares,
then you know you're safe from a majority buyout.
this is masquerade mode. This is something that also came hand in hand with the black market
once it came in the game. Which was this concept of you play a multiplayer, you get hit by the
black market but there's a sense of like, oh, you hit me because you think I'm the best
player or you think I'm the most threatening player or you just want to beat me because I
beat you last game and that's not fair. So at any rate, what, and I actually wasn't a fan of
this. This was my team. They really wanted to get in. They put it in on their own and it
worked.
So, you know, that's great.
And the idea here is your identity is hidden.
So here you see me, I'm one of the players,
and then there's Clark and Herbert and Asimov,
and those are, I don't know who those are.
So you can't attack a specific player,
you have to just kind of like attack the person
who looks like him during the lead.
And anyone who's played board games knows
that this is a classic dynamic, you can get around the table.
Unfortunately, there's no way to hide people's identity
in real life, but you can in an off world.
So this is something we did here with multiplayer to kind of like, we're not, we don't have a huge user base, but the people who play multiplayer love multiplayer, so we want to do as much as we can to enable them to play with each other.
So we did things like, when you go to the main menu of the game, if someone is waiting in the queue, in sort of a rank play, to play with someone, we tell them, hey, there's a game available.
And you click on that, the screen on the left, it takes you to the screen on the right, and it says, oh, there's a match available for 1v1, or there's three players waiting for a four player.
So you really want to help.
bring people into the game, let them know that if they join
they can start a game right now.
Also, when you're in the queue waiting for a match,
we actually let you play single player.
So you can play a skirmish game,
you can play the daily challenge,
you can watch a replay file, you can do all this stuff
while it's waiting for an opponent,
and as soon as you find that opponent,
you'll get moved into the multiplayer game.
I think this has made a huge difference
for keeping our multiplayer community alive,
even with a pretty low multiplayer player base.
Yeah, so I want to talk now a little bit about early access.
And to start out with, I want to kind of give you
a sense of what our project looked
like throughout development.
So I started the game basically in the summer of 2013.
So that lovely shot in the upper left
is what the game looked like right off the beginning.
and then in January we started introducing
hex tiles and terrain basically,
and then you can see things slowly improve step by step.
The August 2014 is an important date,
that's when we had what we called our founders program,
which was you could come to our website, buy the game.
we actually didn't show people what the game looked like,
so they were actually buying it blind,
so I will be always grateful to people
who took part in that program.
But they bought into it, we sent them a Steam code,
they downloaded the game,
and then they were able to start playing it,
and this is what it looked like.
So it looked passable, right?
You could imagine that it could eventually become a game.
And this is the rest of the development.
The one in the upper left there is,
that's what it looked like when it launched in early access.
And then from there on,
It's interesting because we went up in early access,
we heard a lot of people say,
oh wow, this looks like a finished game,
but you can see clearly, just look at the cliffs,
for example, like they're, you know, it just,
there was so much more that we could improve in the game,
but it was really important to me to release it early
so that I could learn about the game from our players
while we still had time to do something about it.
So.
What I think early access is important is the most common
problem in the industry is waste. And that is people making
decisions and having to wait months or even years before they
know whether those decisions were good or not. And I learned
this lesson while working on Civ 3 and Civ 4. Civ 3 was made
completely in a vacuum. The only people who ever played Civ 3
before the game came out were either the people on the
development team or the testers. That's it.
and we shipped the game, it had a lot of issues. And the worst
part is a lot of the issues were fairly obvious. There's the
things that we should have caught and we could have easily
done something about if we just knew about them at the time. So
the CIV 4, I want to do it completely differently.
After Civ 3 shipped, I really embedded myself into the Civ
community, found some of the best voices in the community
and helped them guide me to know how to basically patch Civ 3.
So then the next step was, well, let's bring these people
on board, create sort of this private testing group where
they could play Civ 4 early.
And I mean really early.
They played it in the first half of the project.
it was, Civ 4 was about a two and a half year development
cycle and they played it at about the 12 month,
you know, 12 months after development.
So they played it when it was really early,
it was really ugly, but I think that's the key reason
why Civ 4 was really well received,
is that we had this great iteration time
with the fan community, you know,
with actual players who are outside of the team
and didn't have all the prejudices
you have inside of your team.
And we saw this immediately once we went up on early access,
that we were blind to certain problems in the game.
And probably the most obvious example of this
is the reveal map option.
So the way we had made Offworld was it has a scanning mode
when the game begins,
which is basically the exploration part,
and you just start clicking around the map,
revealing tiles slowly,
until you find what you think is a good founding location.
And that works great in single player,
but the multiplayer community
just found it completely unacceptable.
because basically you imagine two players,
one of them scans one direction,
one of them scans the other direction.
The person who went east finds a great founding location,
puts down their headquarters.
Person who went west feels like they lost the game
because they just randomly went the wrong direction.
we had game mechanics to basically balance that.
Of like, well, whoever found second,
you get extra claims and so on and so forth.
But the main thing is perception.
Like at that point, perception is reality.
It felt unfair to people.
So we tried something different.
And this happened like within a month or two
of early access.
We like, we know we gotta do something about this.
So I came up with the reveal map option,
which means that basically the game,
the map starts completely revealed
and you have basically kind of like a reverse auction
that you could found immediately if you want to,
but you're gonna have to take on $200,000 of debt.
And that price is just gonna get,
kind of like slowly ticked down.
I got this idea I think from Frozen Synapse,
they have kind of like a similar idea of like,
you know, show the whole map and then you kind of bid
on the different starting location.
But like, you know, basically the number kind of
keeps ticking down until it gets to the point
where you're like, well, I think the best spot on the map
is worth say $40,000 of debt, so you're able to,
you know, so you commit.
You're the first mover, you get it.
And then you find out if you made the right choice,
you know, over the course of the game.
And that worked. The multiple computer were like, yes, that's
it. That's the way they play the game, period. And if we had been
a traditional game where we didn't go through early access,
we would have found this out two months after launch instead of
12 months before launch. That makes a pretty big difference
because we then had 12 months to iterate on just this option
itself. It became a core part of the game instead of a hacky fix
that we had to do post launch.
Another thing that was really important is that I knew we were going to make major changes in
early access and there have been games in early access that have made major changes that have
really upset their community. And this is a hard thing. There's no simple answer here because
the community thinks they have one game, they're happy with it, so the game changes.
what, you know, like, and if they're unhappy with it,
it can lead to, you know, it can lead to some really
bad feelings, some bad reviews,
lead to controversy, basically.
We didn't want that to happen,
so what we did is anytime we had some major change
come through, and usually this meant something
on the stock market, like the majority buyout feature,
what we would do is we'd say,
hey, we got this new feature, but it's an option.
we would introduce as an option. When you set the game you can decide whether you're going to
use it or not. But what we also did then is we do the update, hey, the new feature is here.
Hey, and we're also going to host a community tournament. But if you play in the
tournament, you have to play using this new feature.
So which would encourage people to opt in because they want to
play the official Mohawk tournament. They want to win.
So it's not just the games inside of the tournament, but
people would start practicing using this option, of course,
because they wanted to get good at it. So immediately we get
all this great feedback on this feature. It's kind of like
using, by incentivizing them to try it out, forcing it on them.
I believe it's really important to get closer to your community.
This is my friends list on steam.
And you see these are some of the hardest core off-road
players.
You see people who have played games here for thousands of
hours.
And this is a sign that I'm really close with them.
They see something wrong with the game, they'll message me
immediately.
And we'll talk back and forth about it.
Twitch. I think Twitch is great. We stream on it weekly and we
use it for tournaments. And I think what's great about it is
it's just this public space where everyone can come
together. You start streaming the game, so all your fans start
to come there and it just kind of like snowballs from there
because they meet each other and then they make connections and
then they'll start streaming themselves. In fact, that's one
thing we did early with our tournaments is we basically
said if you're going to play in our tournament, you have to
stream your game.
which meant that a lot of our hardcore players
then suddenly became Twitch streamers
and then it kind of like, you know, multiplied from there.
So that's something that worked great.
Discords.
I don't know how many of you guys are using Discord yet for
games but I think Discord is going to become a really big
deal. It's kind of completely replaced. Our forums are dead,
our Reddit is dead, all of the action now is on Discord. And
it's because it's real-time interaction. And so in fact,
when you go into the game, we kind of point people to Discord
right away, like, hey, join our Discord channel. It's a really
friendly, healthy community. You'll often see people come on
there and like, hey, I'm new to the game. And people say, oh,
welcome, let me help you give you advice about how to play.
I really, I really, and also it's a place where,
you can see here, the channel I'm in is actually
like a feedback, a private feedback channel I have
for some of the more core players.
So like it's a way to also kind of like
bring them all together in one place
to talk about stuff that's coming further down the road
without having to expose everyone to that.
and here's one of the nice benefits about being so close to your players. We have a daily
challenge in the game. You play a single player game on the same random seed that changes every
24 hours and we have a replay feature where when you finish the game, you can see the
the replay gets uploaded and then you can,
all the other players can download and see how everyone else,
how did someone get that great time in the daily challenge?
So what I would do is I would come into the morning,
I'd open up the daily challenge,
see who got the best score, watch the replay,
and I'd be immediately like, oh, they're using this,
they're using this strategy against the AI,
or they're doing this thing,
or like they're using this thing,
and I think that's totally imbalanced.
So what I would do is like, I would then see what they did,
I would change the AI,
I would make a build, I'd push it to steam,
and then I'd contact that person,
and be like, hey, try what you did this morning again.
And then I'd find out whether I fixed the problem or not.
I mean, this is amazing, right?
This is like 24 hour iteration directly with the community.
I never dreamed of that, like working on Civ 4.
Even though I had players, you had this weeks of lag
between when you do something and when you find out
whether your decisions were good.
This is, it's amazing to be able to do this.
And you know, community extends your game, right?
Like we had so many people playing the game,
putting up videos that like within our release week,
we had a million and a half views.
Some of the super fans have eventually helped out with the
team, whether that means streaming or testing or Blue's
designed our last DLC that just came out.
You'll see people on Discord basically say,
like, hey, post your, you know,
for new players who are having a hard time,
post your replay, I'll take a look at it,
I'll give you advice.
It's just, you know, community is important.
I mean, people understand that.
All right, so.
probably some things we do differently about early access
if we did it again. One is we had basically a full QA pass.
We would do kind of a big monthly updates. Which meant we
kind of did a full QA pass because we wanted them to be
polished. And
that's fine but it's kind of grueling on the team to put them through that process. You're
releasing every month, we're a small team, we want to be moving quickly. So we did a couple
things to help ourselves out. We had a next version branch which is basically one we could
update whenever we wanted to without going through QA because you had to opt into it. So
that helped. But I think that next time around probably what I would do is I would just have a
build machine that automatically updates the public version every Monday.
and if there's a problem, just do a roll back or a hot fix.
Like, it's okay, I've found, you know,
if you're in touch with the community, like, it's okay.
Like, I think that they're generally forgiving of problems
if you're responsive.
I would probably also wait a little bit longer to go up in
early access. Be aware that your only free press hit comes when
you launch on early access. That's kind of like when the
press conceive of you as a new game. A lot of the big
YouTubers and streamers were only interested in the game the
first time around. When we had the final launch they kind of
had moved on basically. In some cases you have the worst cases.
We had one very prominent YouTuber viewer.
people ask when it came out in early access,
hey, are you going to review this?
And he said, oh, I don't do reviews of early access games.
But then when we came out for real,
he basically had forgotten about it.
So, you know, that can happen.
This is how I like to do early access.
Which is, the more steps you have from testing a game
internally to releasing it, the better.
You want a whole bunch of smaller incremental steps
to get to the final release.
What we did was this.
We had a private beta, and then we jumped all the way
to early access.
And I would really like to have two steps in between there,
at least.
A public beta, where we're like, OK, now we're
going to show our game publicly and let you buy it
through our site, the way a game like Factorio work,
for example.
And then the next step would be like an unlisted Steam page,
which is the idea that your game's up on Steam,
people can buy it, but only if they have
like an external link to it.
Kind of like one of those like private YouTube videos
you can only watch if you happen to have the link.
And your game wouldn't show up on Steam in like searches
or in the top sellers or it wouldn't be promoted,
that type of thing.
So that's a great way to kind of like have that stream
infrastructure.
There's a lot of players who don't want to buy a game
until it's on Steam, period, end of story.
So if you have this, you're able to pull in those players,
even if you're not kind of like getting the full on hit
of being up on early,
the full on pressure of being up on early access.
So this is kind of an interesting question.
We were $40 in early access, which was like,
made us one of the absolutely most expensive games on there.
And I think you can, if you want to,
charge less when you're in early access
and then raise the price, which is unusual.
You don't normally get a chance to do that,
but I think you can pull it off there.
But I'm not sure if we should have lowered the price
because although it did, having a high price
definitely hurt our review score on Steam,
but it definitely kept.
We didn't have too many players to deal with.
The players that we got during the early access
were really what I call high quality players.
They were ones who wanted to be part
of the development process,
and they were good to work with.
So I'm kind of unsure about this.
But this is kind of like my big general feeling about early
access and about games in general.
Eventually your players always understand your game better
than you do.
And being able to do early access means you're like fully
committing to that truth.
Like that's just the way it is whether you like it or not.
I also have some suggestions for what Valve should do.
As I mentioned, the unlisted store pages, as I understand,
I think this might actually be happening now.
I also think there should be an early access category for reviews.
Qualities of games can go up and down over time and it makes a lot of sense that a game
when it was early access is going to be better after release than before release.
So I don't see why you wouldn't want to just have a separate category for those type of
reviews.
And I also think there shouldn't be sales or refunds during early access.
This is a quote from a Subnautica developer and he points out that, you know...
When you lower the price, you get a group of people
who are less dedicated to your product,
and there's a pretty good chance
you're gonna leave a negative view,
because they didn't really research it.
They didn't really know what they were getting into.
And I'd say that the goal here
is actually to get fewer players.
You know, you want there to be kind of a bigger hurdle
for people to buy your game, Windows on Early Access,
so they know they're doing something different.
They're not just buying a game on Steam,
they're buying a game that's in development.
Like, so I would be totally happy with, you know.
kind of like a smaller group of players in early access that are more committed to the
development process. Also, be good to your early access customers. When we released, we
automatically upgraded them all to the deluxe edition. They started off immediately with
soundtrack and the DLC that we launched. These are your best fans. Treat them well. So speaking
of reviews, I want to mention a few things about them.
So here's a guy who left a negative review a long time ago.
We had a big UI change, he really, really didn't like it.
And our executive producer at Stardock,
very politely mentioned like,
hey, maybe you wanna, we've released the game,
made some changes, you might wanna check it out.
And so I think he, I can't, sorry for me to read,
but I think he came back like eight or nine months later
and was like, oh, this is great, you fixed everything,
I love the game, and changed his review.
So if you take the right attitude toward it,
I think that could be.
there's no harm there.
I mean, sometimes you find someone and clearly
they're just looking for a different type of game.
That happens to us sometimes.
It feels like sometimes people come to Offworld
thinking it's gonna be like Anno
and we're never gonna be able to make the game
what they want.
And so that's just, you know,
unfortunately maybe we need to just do our job
of how we're marketing the game in that case.
So here's a negative review of someone who found the game a
little bit like a chewing exercise. So he's not a big fan.
Here's one of the interesting things about achievements I
didn't expect. They're a great way to give context to negative
reviews. So I saw him and I'm like, I feel like Offworld is an
exciting, dynamic, challenging game. He doesn't. I wonder why.
I clicked on his profile and I found out, oh, he only played on the second lowest
difficulty level. And there's nine difficulty levels in off world. So the second level is
like, it's super easy. And so I don't necessarily know what I should do about this problem.
Like should we take away the easy levels? Should we push people to the higher levels more? I'm
not sure. But at least I have some context about the complaint. So here's another big
question. People often worry about going to early access. Do you get a second launch?
right? And I was very worried about this. I asked all sorts of
people who were up on early access what would happen when we
came out. And for us at least, we did. We actually sold almost
the exact same number of units our first two weeks of early
access as we did our first two weeks of release. And month by
month we've done better after early access than we did while
we were on early access.
That's what you see. Those are our lifetime sales. Those DLC
numbers are inflated a little bit because we gave a bunch of
DLC away to our early access owners. So it's hard to judge
what that would be without that. So maybe half those numbers
it's hard to evaluate. But at any rate, our DLC is doing well
and we've been able to introduce basically one every month or
two. And there's pretty good pick up on it. This is our
sales graph from the very beginning of early access to a
week ago.
I want to highlight a few points on it. This is early access
release. This is final release. You can see the curves look
almost identical which is really encouraging. That's nice to know.
These were our first major discounts.
This is the first time we were 50% off,
was actually during the early access phase,
and the first time we went down to 66% off
was actually pretty recently, a few months ago.
And those first discounts are a big deal.
You're gonna need a major spike there.
I think we actually probably should have waited
to go 50% off after release.
And so I would definitely do that differently
next time around.
These are capsule events, weekend deals,
or when we went up on Steam Workshop.
And those are a big deal.
I mean, that's the main thing on Steam is visibility.
You know, being on the front page,
that's where the sales come from.
These are the event sales.
The summer sale, Starduck has a sale basically every,
excuse me, autumn.
And then the Christmas sale.
And I found this graph really interesting.
This is our total revenue by price.
And so you can see that like 40% of our revenue
is basically at full price.
And actually it's definitely higher than that.
I suspect it's almost 50% because these numbers
don't include early access for whatever reason
the numbers I had were all.
post final release.
And on early access, we never went down below 50%.
But at any rate, there's a sense that
once after you release, you're gonna make
all of your revenue just off your sales.
And I think this shows that you're still making
pretty good revenue even just day after day
just selling at a normal price.
All right. So I do want to get to the end here. I think it's
important to always ask yourself, you know, beyond all
of this stuff about what the development was like and all
different random game mechanics, why do you make games at all?
You know, and so I often get asked whether off world is a
free trade game or an anti-capitalist game or some
other statement on the world economy.
And I don't think games should be trying to make broad
statements like, you know, capitalism is good or capitalism
is bad. It's just too simplistic. And also the game
designer has too much power to set up the rules to support his
or her own biases.
This is what I think off world is about.
The prices tell a story.
You know, in off world, if iron costs more than steel,
then something has gone wrong.
And you win by taking advantage of these discrepancies.
You know, that puts you in the shoes of a business person,
which is really sort of the best that a game can do.
You know, there's a reason why everything costs
what it does.
You know, sometimes that goes beyond supply and demand,
to government policy, and cultural factors.
But there's always a reason.
And if we don't like what something costs,
we should find out why instead of just complaining about it.
But more broadly, I made off with a trading company for the
same reason I make all strategy games, that they are
anti-ideological. In a good strategy game, the answer to
every question, what HQ is best, what resource is most
important, what should I research first, should always
start with, well, it depends.
The point of having to make tough choices
and to adapt to the environment is that
there is never ever just one right answer to follow blindly.
And I think that lesson is as important now
as it has ever been.
And that's it, thanks for coming.
time for maybe one or two. All right. Go ahead. What impact has
the DLCs had on your community? Did it fragment them or bring
them together? Um...
So we did a few things to basically make sure
that it wouldn't happen.
So like for example, we had a series,
DLC series as an asteroid,
as large as asteroid, the asteroid belt,
an alternate location to play at.
And then we were worried about like,
well, what would happen if someone has it,
one person has it, another person doesn't,
they wanna play a multiplayer.
And we just solved it by saying like,
if you have the DLC and you host the game,
anyone can join you.
Or in ranked play, it just comes up automatically,
even if you don't have the DLC.
like you'll still be exposed to it.
You just won't be able to play in a single player.
So, you know, you just do the best you can, basically.
Thanks.
Mm-hmm.
Hey, the game is so brilliant,
but it's so different from anything else on the market.
I'm curious, how did you approach
teaching players how to play the game,
since there's so little to look at from other games,
so little experience to pull in?
Yeah, so, and this is something I'm particularly bad at,
actually, is tutorials.
I just, I'm really bad at that,
but fortunately, my business partner and art director,
Dorian is, Newcomb, is very good at that.
He worked hard on the CIFI tutorials, which are amazing,
and he just, you know, like,
fully committed to that part of the project.
So, I'm afraid I don't really have a good answer for it,
because he's the one that does it,
and I'm just glad I'm working with him.
Hey, so when you put the game up for sale initially,
the one where you had no screenshots,
you also put up the rule set or like a design document
that read very much like a board game rule set.
Can you talk a little bit about that,
why you chose to do that?
Yeah, so we weren't showing a screen shot, but I felt like the most important thing was the
rules themselves. We were able to take advantage of the fact that the game had such a board
game feel. I don't know how many board games I have that I read the rules but never actually
played. So that is a phenomenon. People kind of understand what that's like. So I thought
that they're probably the players that we wanted to get were people who would be good with
that.
they'd be like, oh cool, there's a little bit
of a small rule book for me to read,
and that'll give me a sense of how the game plays,
and I'll kind of like imagine it,
and maybe I'll be off a little bit,
but that'll like make me kind of want to get into the game.
I mean, I wanted to give them something, right?
We're not giving them a screenshot.
We gotta give them something.
Go ahead, thanks.
So I want to address one thing, the question about tutorials,
one other thing we really focused on is in the UI,
we really focused on trying to give all the information
you needed when something happened.
You want to build a metal mine, you press the metal mine,
we immediately show a line to the iron,
we show a line to the aluminum.
Like, there's another half of it, which is,
we try to make sure we always give people
the information they need just when they need it in the game.
And so that's super important too, beyond tutorials.
you know, kind of more on the tutorial side. Did you feel like, you know,
because the tutorials felt like they told a story and they had the mission
segments to them. Do you feel like you got any pushback or lost any revenue
opportunities by not having an actual official campaign?
So the campaign is that we have an off world is dynamic and it
has what you call like a light story touch. There's
characters. There's not really much of a story. Part of that
is like if I had to write a story, it would be absolutely
terrible. This is just not what I do. And I kind of wanted the
freedom to develop a dynamic campaign that you could do that
was replayable.
doesn't match a lot of players expectations for RTS. But I was
already not matching anyone's expectations for RTS anyway. So
I figured I might as well go for it. I think it's just kind of
like we're a small team. We don't, seven or eight guys and we
have various things that we're good at. That was just something
that we absolutely were not good at.
I bet there's a lot of players who would get into the game
if we had a more standard story-based campaign.
It's just something.
And actually, I think it's something
that we're gonna get into.
There is a writer that we're working with now,
writer slash designer,
who I've worked with in various projects,
who designed the Patron and Patriot DLC,
which is a huge expansion of the campaign
and did have a lot of story content for the new CEOs.
And so we're probably gonna continue working with him.
He's gonna backfill a lot of that story into the game.
So.
It's great to hear.
Thank you so much.
Yeah, cool, thanks.
Do you have any plans to port the game to console, like PS4?
Uhhh...
No, not right now.
But it's always possible.
I mean, so I did actually did a mapping
to the console controller.
And, you know, it's okay, right?
But it's like it's an RTS.
It's really hard to pull off with a controller.
This is gonna like totally be a disaster
if we ever decide, mark a disaster, I just said,
if we ever have to sell it on the console.
But like, you know, doing, I mean,
it could potentially work, right?
Like you're not controlling units, right?
So you could make it work on a console,
you could make it work on a tablet, right?
I think there's good possibilities there.
I just think that you'd need to like,
kind of like rebuild part of the game from the ground up.
So yeah, I mean, I do think about it.
Like, it'd be kind of a neat project to take on.
But unfortunately we don't have anything happening right now.
So, thanks.
Thank you.
Over there.
Okay, yeah I was just wondering,
you created the game, this is your game.
Do you also help other people to build a game?
Are you for hire?
Wait, sorry, can you repeat that?
Okay, do you help other people create games?
Oh, do I help other people, you mean do I work on other teams
or consult or that type of thing?
Is that what you mean?
I mean, not very much.
I mean, I've written a lot about game design.
I do a game design podcast, Designer Notes,
where I talk to designers.
I mean, I try to spread game design information.
I mean, every once in a while, if there's a small project,
I mean, I have taken on, like,
work on something for a day or two
if someone just wants some feedback on the game.
So, I mean, I am open to stuff like that.
But when I work on a game, I have a hard time even,
I've never really even been able to work on two games
at once, right?
Like, I talk to people who work on three or four games
at the same time, and I find that amazing
that anyone can do that.
But thanks.
Do you attribute the success of the game
to being 3D versus being a 2D game?
I'm sorry, I couldn't help it.
The game is 3D.
Do you think that that was important
for the game to be successful?
Was the point of it being 3D?
So when I first did the prototype, it was actually 2D,
just because that was simple.
Well, it was like OpenGL, but like straight down,
but functionally it was 2D.
And you could make it just 2D,
but at this point I think the tools,
the best tools out there are 3D tools, right?
Like we use Unity.
which was great to develop in.
Basically because it has amazing art tools.
Like our artists were immediately,
I mean artists, I'm almost just artist, right?
Like the one main guy we had was able to become immediately
five times as more productive as he had been
before we jumped to Unity.
So, like, you know, 3D has gotten to the point
where it's just very easy to develop in 3D,
and if it was simpler to develop in 2D,
I probably would do 2D.
I don't think there's anything fundamentally about it
that would make it work one way or another.
My question is that with this game you're taking combat out of RTS.
Right.
You're playing with that notion. Are there any plans for Mohawk or you yourself to take on another genre and try to take out a core mechanic and see what you can do with it?
Well, that would that be our thing?
Once may be enough, it is a big challenge.
I'll say that.
Yeah, I mean, you know, I mean, to some extent,
this comes to the question of what you should do
as an independent developer, right?
Like, I love RTS games, but I'm never gonna be able
to take on StarCraft as a small team,
and that's just crazy, right?
So you have to do something radically different.
Right?
And so some of the games I showed you,
like Adam Zombie Smash was a great game of like,
that's an amazing RTS.
And you know, he just changed some of the basic assumptions
about how an RTS worked,
and was able to make a great game,
and he wasn't competing against anyone else.
And so that's the same basic idea
of what we're trying to do with Offworld.
So yeah, I mean, probably we'll always do that with games.
You know, like we're gonna have to figure out
how to make something that no one else is making.
I mean, I think that's what you have to do
as an independent developer.
Looking forward to the next experiment.
All right, thank you.
All right.
Whoops.
All right, looks like maybe one more.
Yeah, yeah.
Hello.
I figured out the question.
What do you think is the future of RTS?
The future of RTS.
You know, it's a hard question for me to answer
because I'm kind of done with traditional RTS games.
I don't really find them particularly enjoyable anymore
just because I play them so much.
So I hope the future of RTS games
is more games like Offworld, right?
Which are like, what I want is to play a game
that takes about 30 minutes,
that's strategic and competitive
and I can play with my friends, right?
That's what I want.
And Offworld delivers that in a way that's interesting.
And I don't want to do a Tank Rush anymore with my friends.
I want to do something different.
But I still love that format.
Just the basic idea of we're going to play this game over a
lunch break, and we're going to have this ups and downs.
And after the game, getting together and talking about
what happened is going to be amazing.
That's what I want out of an RTS game.
Is that going to happen? I don't know.
I think the traditional RTS is absolutely in danger.
And the big one there is because of MOBAs.
MOBAs have destroyed the traditional RTS game.
Because RTS games as they are, are kind of terrible.
you're asking a player to control 100 units spread all over
the map and jump back and forth and pay attention to what
they're doing and what all their opponents are doing.
And it's amazing those games ever worked at all.
Like MOBAs are just the micro aspect of an RTS.
And so that's why people are like,
oh, this is really fun because now I actually feel like
I can handle this game.
Off-world is just the macro aspect of an RTS.
You know, we dropped all the micro parts.
You don't have to worry about units.
And because, so we, there's two games in there,
they're just half of a whole RTS,
which is a sign of just how complex
and overburdened those games tend to be.
So yeah, I don't think there's necessarily a big future
for the traditional RTS, but I love the format.
like playing a strategic game with your friends, 30 minutes,
up to eight players, something like that.
So I hope to see more.
Yeah, I agree.
Thank you.
All right, thanks.
All right, thanks for coming, everyone.