Thanks for coming to my talk, a historian's guide to researching your historical game.
My name is James Coltrane.
I'm an assistant professor of history at the University of Nebraska, and I'm also a game
developer.
I'm currently working as a solo dev on a first-person narrative exploration game called Cassius,
in which players explore an evacuated plantation estate during the American Revolution to confront
our memory of the founding fathers.
and their relationship with colonial slavery.
The game is based closely on historical research,
and every plot point, environment, and object
is based on a documented analog from museums, archives,
and historic sites.
It's not yet formally announced, but if you're interested,
you can see some screens and a draft trailer on my studio
site at historiated.com.
Here's just a couple more.
shots of that.
Now of course historical settings have long been popular topics for games and recent years
are no exceptions.
So today I want to talk to you a little bit about how you might begin to research your
own historically themed games and I'll use some of my own examples but I'll also talk
about how thinking like a historian as you're researching might give you some really cool
and thought provoking ideas for your game narratives.
It's a lot to do in 30 minutes but you should at least have an idea of how to get started
once we're done.
But first, let's talk a little bit about the way that history works.
Sometimes we tend to think that the past is very set and established, only occasionally
updated with new discoveries.
But in reality, history is very messy right from the beginning.
If you look at any claim made in a normal textbook, the evidence often begins to look
more like this, a messy pile of garbage, which historians must then piece together to construct
a narrative of what happened.
So this leads us to some key principles about the way history works.
The first is that history is not the truth.
We are only following traces.
And even if we could get inside the mind of a historical witness, this still wouldn't
be the truth because other people would have experienced the moment differently.
Second, history is a discussion, and that's because every historian who looks at the same
pile of garbage is going to draw different conclusions.
Finally, history is always changing because each generation of historians will view their
garbage piles differently.
For instance, historians in the early 20th century would have rated Andrew Jackson as
one of our best presidents for his military victories and his role in expanding democracy.
while contemporary ones rightly criticize him for his slave
holding and role in the Trail of Tears,
leaving room for other alternatives.
There's Andrew Jackson, proposed Harriet Tubman $20 bill.
OK.
Let's talk a little bit about how to structure your research.
When you're choosing a topic, it's
important to lean on the work that historians have already
done for you.
There's no shame in focusing on topics
with accessible resources.
And historians often make the same choice
when we're choosing our own projects.
For instance.
I chose Eastern Virginia for the setting of my game, Cassius, in part because I could
draw on the expertise of the Colonial Williamsburg Foundation, where I had a research fellowship,
and learn from the restored buildings, an ample library, and hundreds of expert interpreters.
This is especially true for visual evidence.
If people have already reconstructed the settings you're interested in at museum exhibits or
for documentaries, this can save you a ton of time.
It's also important to remember that just like in other aspects of game design,
your research is going to be an iterative process.
So remember, you'll likely be skipping back and forth
between the next few steps that I'm going to go through.
And you're going to have new ideas, which point you to new evidence,
and then back to new ideas.
So if we're looking for a place to start,
getting your hands on a broad, accessible book
from a reliable scholar is a pretty good first step.
For instance, when I wanted an introduction
into Aztec culture for one of my history lectures,
this short, sweet book by archaeologist Michael Smith
succinctly covered almost every aspect.
But how do we know that what we're reading
is reliable and not absurdist pseudo-history?
Well, Good History works under peer review, where before publication, other expert historians
critique a draft, which offers some insurance against fraudulent or other unreliable interpretations.
Books from university presses are all peer reviewed.
And you can just see also if you have a book that's not from a university press, if it's
been blurbed or positively reviewed by working historians, or if it's connected to an established
museum or a government agency.
Once you've read broadly in a book or two, you should be full of ideas and also topics
that you'd like to investigate further.
So now's our time to start gathering sources.
Historians divide our sources into two types.
Primary sources, which are things like diaries, letters, records, interviews, maps, photographs,
but also artifacts, art, and architecture that come directly from the period that we're
studying.
For instance, this slave pass that featured in the research of my game,
and also this map of the area surrounding Williamsburg,
both of which were featured nearby in Virginia.
And of course, you're also going to use a lot of secondary sources.
These are things like books and articles by historians and other scholars
who interpret primary sources and draw their own conclusions.
And there are some things like a historical newspaper,
which actually qualify as both.
Secondary sources are pretty easy to come by via your book's bibliographies,
but there may be a lot to process.
So a couple of tips.
First, even just looking at the recommended books that come up on Amazon or some other site
can give you a pretty good indication of important books in your field,
especially if you're already starting out with a respected title.
Also, Google Scholar is a very useful tool because it can show you the most cited books
in your topic and that can give you a sense of both the reliability of the scholarship
and also how prominent the interpretations you're considering are.
Primary sources, on the other hand, are going to take more effort.
The most obvious place to find original documents
is to actually visit the archives and the libraries
that have the originals.
But that's a lot to ask of a busy developer.
Instead, you can start in your bibliographies
and see which manuscript collections were
used in writing the book and look up those archives online.
Many are going to have the actual documents available
to read.
And in some cases, this will be available completely for free.
So here's that pass that I showed again.
You can view directly on the Williamsburg website.
In addition, bibliographies will also show published primary sources,
like collections of letters, and even books and other print media from your period.
These are available in public domain and many of them complete online,
like this collection of Thomas Jefferson's letters.
Some great sites to check for these types of public sources include archive.org
and the Digital Public Library of America, and even in some cases, Google Books.
There's the Digital Public Library of America.
For Cassius, I found many complete digital copies of books that were actually owned by
George Washington and Thomas Jefferson, like this gardening manual, which was available
complete and for free online.
Additionally, you can search for modern primary source collections targeted to high school
or college students.
You also want to visit the websites of the relevant historic sites and museums for visual
evidence.
The online collections at the Williamsburg Museum have been invaluable for me in making Cassius,
and many incredibly important museums, like the Metropolitan Museum of Art,
the Art Institute of Chicago, and the British Museum,
have nearly their complete collections viewable online, sometimes with royalty-free images.
In addition to these sources, you're going to want to get help from experts.
So there are two broad categories of historians who can potentially help you.
Scholarly historians, like me, are mostly university professors, and these are people
who are actively trying to produce totally new interpretations and discoveries based
on original research.
So they probably won't be able to fact-check your game.
And in some cases, they may know even less than you do about some of your topics.
However, because academics are in the habit of extrapolating very large themes from their
areas of original research, they're going to be very good for helping you with things
like politics, economics, empire, religion, race, gender, and especially also debates
and controversies that may be happening in the academic field that you're going to want
to be aware of.
The other kind of expert that you'll be looking for are public historians,
and these can include archivists, museum officials, park rangers,
anybody else who's tasked with preserving and educating the public about history.
These are experts who are likely to be able to tell you about the everyday life in your period.
And these days, even bloggers, YouTubers, and Pinterest boards can be helpful,
and sometimes even pretty reliable.
For instance, Townsend & Sons,
a company that makes props for American Revolution reenactors,
runs an awesome YouTube channel on 18th century life and cooking.
And yes, this is where you can get all your pressing earthen ovens questions answered.
And even though he isn't a professional historian, he routinely cites peer-reviewed scholars,
primary documents, and also collaborates with public history officials.
Now a few pieces of advice when you're reaching out to experts.
First, do as much research as you can, especially about the expert in question, before you make
contact.
Look up their books and articles, and go on YouTube and see if they have any lectures,
so that if they give you the time, you're not asking about things that you could have
easily learned yourself.
Second, ease them into the idea of your game.
If somebody looks particularly cranky,
maybe don't even say game in that first email.
Lots of experts may not know how far games have come
as a serious storytelling medium,
and they may need a few quick examples
to know that you're not doing something totally trivial.
Also, keep in mind that the most famous experts may not always be as useful as young up-and-coming
scholars who may be more open to sharing and possibly be more up-to-date on recent discoveries.
You can find these experts by looking through your list of secondary authors on the websites
of public history institutions and also by looking through the faculty pages of your
local universities.
Finally, if you're a bigger studio, paying a small consulting fee can go a long way.
Also, be prepared and respectful if the expert isn't enthusiastic about your game, and make
sure to credit them, but only after you've allowed them to see the final project and
make sure they want their name associated with it.
Now one important way that experts can help you
is in dealing with cultural sensitivity.
And now of course, we don't have time in such a short talk
to adequately cover very complicated issues
like representation, diversity, and cultural appropriation,
but a few points of advice.
First, pitch your idea early to as many experts
from as many different backgrounds as you can
and get their gut reactions.
If they're critical at first, but you still feel really confident in your concept,
you can try again once you've put together mock-ups or prototypes,
but you need to take their advice seriously.
Also, it's really important to talk with people who have different sets of expertise.
Your game design peers may have very culturally thoughtful suggestions that...
for your game that don't actually turn out
to be historically accurate.
And while the historians should be able to help you
do justice to past subjects,
they may have game design ideas
that are either artistically unworkable
or even clumsy and offensive
when you actually put them into practice.
You'll need to get a lot of feedback from a lot of people
and use your own judgment to balance all of that input.
So now that you've gathered a lot of evidence
and you have people to help guide you,
let's talk about how we actually interpret that evidence.
First of all, no matter how silly or weird your game idea,
I always encourage everyone to read at least a little bit
from primary records of that period.
In my experience, nothing is going to spark
your imagination faster or show you the weirder side
of your topic quicker than reading directly from the past.
But we also need to keep in mind some principles
to help us evaluate what we're reading.
First, we need to remember that if our documents
are sometimes, that our documents are sometimes
going to contradict one another, or just not make sense.
And we're going to have to use our secondary sources
and our expert advice to try to figure out what they mean
or which are more accurate.
And when we consider a given document,
we want to think about the biases that every author has.
And not just whether or not they're being honest with us,
but broader questions like, why is the author even writing this?
Who are they writing it for?
What does that audience expect of them?
How does the author's identity affect what they're saying?
What societal pressures are on them
to say things a certain way?
There are also biases that are present in the documents themselves.
One is survival bias.
This means that the more likely a kind of document is to survive,
the more disproportionate influence it will have on our record of the past.
A great example of this is Neolithic cave art.
Most prehistoric people lived outdoors.
But because the objects they left in caves are much more likely to survive until today,
we give them such outsized attention that the public often refers to these people colloquially as cavemen.
Another important bias to watch is for document bias.
If the only records you have from a town
are from the church, you may be tempted
to overstate the importance of religion in daily life
because that's all those documents are intended to tell you.
Let's look at an example of an excellent primary source.
One of the most valuable kinds of documents for my game Cassius and for the history of
slavery overall are newspaper advertisements for escaped slaves, like this one placed by
Thomas Jefferson.
From these short ads, we can extrapolate all kinds of details that we wouldn't otherwise
have about enslaved people's daily lives, including their diet, clothing, health.
family structure, names, spoken languages, ethnic backgrounds,
personal properties, punishments, skills, and more.
But the ads are obviously subject to significant biases.
First, they're completely limited to only things masters knew
about these people and wanted to share in public.
But second, we also have a document bias,
and that's the generalizations that we make from them
may only really apply to slaves who run away,
rather than the broader group of enslaved people.
It's important for us to think about how we interpret evidence
because when we recreate a historical world in our game,
we're actually creating our own historic interpretation.
So let's talk a little bit about the issue of accuracy.
A lot of game designers get excited about a quote unquote
hardcore approach to realism.
This instinct is already common to war games and survival games,
and sometimes that mentality carries over
into history-themed games.
But while this might work for little details like sword
pommels or dress floral patterns,
these aspirations usually break down and prove insufficient
once we start trying to depict effectively larger
social and cultural realities.
And of course, complete accuracy is impossible.
And that should be obvious to us,
as shown in this classic Onion video,
satirizing a super realistic Iraq War game
where you sit bored for eight hours fixing trucks.
Thus, even the quote unquote super realistic games
have to make a lot of compromises
to be anything somebody is going to want to play.
There are also different kinds of accuracy that we can consider.
Sometimes it may make sense to choose accuracy in tone
rather than accuracy in detail, be it using an EDM track
for a decadent Roman feast instead of the possibly
shrill and unfamiliar ancient music that actually would have played.
or skipping the exhaustive Elizabethan pleasantries,
not to mention all the things we'd have a hard time depicting,
the accents, the cadences, the unfamiliar vocabulary
that might slow NPC dialogue to a crawl.
But that doesn't mean that we have to abandon
deep historical engagement just because we're
willing to make some sacrifices in the name of making
our games more playable.
Despite interdimensional travel and robotic songbirds,
Bioshock Infinite directly engages
with 19th century immigration, racism, and colonialism.
And even though there is a very, very fierce debate
over its success in dealing with these topics,
it makes much more of an effort than the supposedly sturdy
Oregon Trail.
which significantly overlooks the presence
of Native Americans, themes of colonialism,
and all kinds of other important elements.
More recently, the return of the Obra Dinn
mixed fantastical horror elements
with a great deal of pretty accurate daily life
from 19th century sailing,
including a really excellent portrayal
of maritime diversity.
Another way that accuracy comes into play
is when you're dealing with historical myths.
There are plenty of pop culture bubbles to burst.
Napoleon wasn't really that short.
Vikings didn't really have horns on their helmets.
And Paul Revere never said the British are coming
because he was the British.
Your commitment to accuracy will help you decide
whether you're going to affirm or dispel myths.
And some of these may just be fun to play with
with your audience.
You do, however, need to think about which tropes,
like, say, the common one of Columbus as a historic explorer,
may actually be covering up for historic abuses,
and whether or not it's desirable to perpetuate those even in a less serious game.
And of course, no matter how seriously we take the issue
of historical accuracy, your research
is going to provide you with a lot of rich content
to drive your storytelling and your design.
So let's take a little time to consider
how thinking like a historian can help your game.
Let's start with characters.
It's a common maxim to say that each character should
be the hero of their own story.
And heroes have goals that they want to achieve.
And while lots of human aspirations,
like love and success and family and creative expression,
are relatively universal, how your character seeks out those things
is going to be radically different period to period.
You'll want to know how common important modern categories of identity,
like race, class, and gender were expressed,
which sometimes may be very, very different than the present.
For instance, let me present you with a very manly portrait
of George Washington from the 18th century.
even though his curvy body, relaxed posture, and frilly clothing
might signal femininity to some people in the present.
In his day, manliness was expressed by the ease and grace
powerful people had when they had command over others,
including the people he owned, unfortunately.
You also want to pay attention to other categories
that may be more important in the past than they are today.
Depending on the area, this could include things like
religious identity, imperial affiliation, tribe, language group.
For instance, it may be hard to imagine a Baptist and a Methodist coming to blows today
over their theological differences, but that was a real possibility at certain periods
in the past.
Your research will also enrich the setting and the environmental design incredibly.
Two great questions to be asking over and over again as you learn about past spaces
are, number one, why is this here?
And number two, how did this get here?
The why is going to tell you not only about practical demands,
the way that societies manage resources and concerns
like water, transportation, shelter, security,
but also their symbolic priorities.
Why did they build in a particular place?
Why did they build in the style they did?
Why did they decorate in the style they did?
The how question is also very important
because it's going to reveal how things like agriculture,
technology, and economies work, but especially how money
and labor help produce spaces.
The secret pirate towns of Uncharted 4, for instance,
show a ton of attention to 18th century architecture
that reflects a lot of careful thinking about the why.
But the how is a little bit hardly established.
I mean, who in these secret pirate towns
is paying for hundreds of sculptors
to produce decades of work on all of these statues?
These pirates were very committed to public art.
Yeah.
So here's some of their statues.
In my own game, balancing the questions of scale, architectural style, natural light,
and other practical concerns in the design of the main house not only made my environmental
design more accurate, but taught me a lot about how the characters, enslaved and free,
inhabited and lived in this house.
Here's a little bit of that house exterior.
And of course...
What you learn about the past is going to impact a way
of what you think is possible for your narrative arcs
and plot threads.
I found a useful exercise to think about is
what sort of stories are only possible
in your historical moment?
For instance, think of a typical mission quest
in an open world game.
If your game is set like Assassin's Creed Origins
in ancient Egypt, could this same mission
fit into The Witcher?
And these are things like, find my dog.
Could it fit into Grand Theft Auto?
Or, when you think about the beliefs and pressures and priorities of your characters,
what sorts of stories could only happen in your period?
These may end up being some of the most interesting.
There are a lot of other questions we can ask.
People often critique horror movies and say that all of the tension would dissipate
in a particular moment if someone only had cell service.
What stories are possible in worlds that exist long before electricity or printing?
How does resource management in your game change
when a drink of water means a five mile walk?
How does inventory management change
when objects like silver buttons are relatively commonplace,
but paper sheets remain expensive?
Just by learning how to light a candle
using an 18th century tinderbox from my own game
had all kinds of ramifications
about how I might manage light,
which bled over into level design
and even elements of story tension.
And finally, while a lot of historical games concentrate on trying to reconstruct past events and spaces literally,
I think there's an exciting opportunity to start trying to represent past mentalities, worldviews, religious beliefs, and cosmologies.
That is to say, to try to make our players feel the way historical people did in a place,
or see historical scenes the way that historical actors did.
For instance...
We in the present may be tempted to view a medieval chapel cathedral as having a timeless
ethereal mystique, when period visitors may have viewed it more like this, thinking the
patronage was tacky or crass, to say nothing of how modern Assassin's Creed players view
it.
Or for another interesting example, consider the ancient Egyptians, who in using hieroglyphs
had no formal distinction between writing and art.
That meant to literate Egyptians,
this could be writing, as could this, but also this.
But even seemingly decorative items like this pectoral
from King Tutankhamun could also be writing, in this case,
incorporating the hieroglyphs from his throne name,
as you can see, both having the sun disk, the scarab,
and the basket glyphs.
This means that scenes that appear wholly pictorial
to a modern audience, some Egyptians would have looked at
and heard letter sounds and saw words
as they looked at these images.
And these are the types of very core cultural differences
that could be really exciting to capture in a game.
All right, to finish, let's take a scenario.
Say you wanna make yet another pirate-themed game, okay?
And you've done your research as we've discussed.
You have primary documents, manuscripts,
published primary documents.
You have some visual references.
You have some secondary sources.
You may have even found an expert or two to advise.
I could potentially advise a little bit about pirates.
And once you've gone over the material,
this is how your research findings
might compare to the pop culture reality of how
people think about pirates.
Here's a little research diagram.
So we have all these tropes about pirates.
Some of these end up being pretty accurate.
Pirates were often after Spanish loot, especially silver.
They really did use black flags in some cases
to signal that they were coming.
We have from pirate documents that they were often,
people in an argument were forced on duels,
especially on marooned islands.
They definitely drank a lot of rum.
We have evidence of eye patches and even a kind of a quirky
theory that healthy people may have used an eye patch to keep
one of their eyes ready for night vision in the below cabin.
Blackbeard was a real person with a lot of really crazy
stories attributed to him.
And we have evidence of some pretty crazy pirate towns like
Port Royal, where people wrote about there being so many
taverns that the parrots and the monkeys were often drunk.
We have lots of pirate tropes that are myths.
The yarrr pirate voice was invented by the actor who played Long John Silver for Disney's
Treasure Island.
And of course pirates were very diverse, so they would have had lots of other weird noises
if they were French or Dutch.
right? Um, we don't have any evidence of anybody walking the plank. Uh, certainly there were
people who lost their legs as pirates, but they're probably not going to be climbing too many
ropes after that. Um, and we have one instance of Captain Kidd in buried treasure, but this
probably wasn't a great place to hide your loot, right? In addition to that, this, we'd find
things that we never expected.
The life of pirates is often really unglamorous.
Sometimes when they take cities hostage, they would ask for things like food
because they were hungry, because they're on the run, they don't get to relax a lot.
A lot of pirate raids were less violent than you might expect akin to
a mugging where somebody quickly hands over their wallet because they don't want any trouble.
We have evidence of a lot of women contributing to pirate culture, including in some cases women
who disguise their gender to pass as men and serve on pirate ships.
There's a tremendous amount of ethnic and racial diversity
represented among pirate crews, a lot more religious influence
than we see exhibited in a lot of games.
And perhaps most surprising, a lot of pirate crews
operated as democracies, agreeing on a set of agreed
terms before they would carry out a voyage,
oftentimes having pretty equal shares of the potential loot.
And many of these agreements even
incorporated health insurance, something
that a number of us would like to see
included in our daily lives.
All right?
Now, there's lots of different directions that you could go with this material.
You could make a more silly game like Sea of Thieves or a more straightforward game
like Black Flag, but no matter your strategy, you're going to have a lot of potential resources
to draw upon and you're going to have a much better possible amount of narratives to draw
on.
because of your historical research.
So, I hope that regardless of your goals,
that you and your fearless crew won't be afraid
of another trip to the library.
So, thank you for listening.
And do we have time for questions?
Yeah, take a couple.
Ready, a little hard to see.
You talked a lot about accurately representing
certain visual or physical elements of an error.
But I guess I wonder about viable counterfactual outcomes.
So I'm a huge fan of historical simulations.
But of course, the player is the wild card
and will optimize and optimize.
And so often, these things that should
have been virtually impossible, as far as we know,
turn out to be very viable.
And so like, you know, like.
I guess I'm curious about your thoughts about making more likely or more common outcomes
actually more common in historical simulation.
Yeah, I think there's a couple of theoretical approaches to that.
One is with story.
A lot of times you may want to feature things that are based closely on historic records,
but obviously as soon as we have play and reaction, we do have a counterfactual,
so that's something that didn't happen.
And so I think a good approach to that is by using what I'm doing in my own game,
which is a composite historical fiction,
where it's a piece of original...
plot, but you're drawing from all these influences.
And then I think even though if we're allowing players to interact a lot, that that also
generates counterfactuals, that we can sort of think about accuracy in terms of modeling
a process.
So in other words, if we build a virtual pirate ship, no one with the name of our online player
ever actually sailed that, but we could try our best to sort of duplicate the mechanisms
of it and the other people that they encounter so that their input...
is receiving a similar feedback as a historical character
in that period might have.
I see.
Thank you.
Thank you for the talk.
I played a lot of Civ IV, and Gandhi was a Christian,
and he declared war on me.
So that wasn't very accurate.
How comfortable are you in breaking history in Cassius?
Or do we have to wait and see?
I think my particular goals in Cassius are really to address a lot of misconceptions
that both people get at historic sites when they go visit places like Monticello and also
that I get in my own classrooms.
So it's got a pretty sober tone and it's designed to really put the focus on the scale of enslavement.
You know, in a place like Monticello, if you go today, you'll see a restored house and
maybe a cabin or two and they're trying to improve that.
But in a lot of cases...
You know, you would have one white family living
in one of these houses.
There could be up to 1,500 people that are
working in the service of that.
And so, but that's my particular aim.
You know, if your particular aim in a lighter area of history
is to be really, really silly, you know,
I think some of those things can be productive.
And they can also get people thinking.
You know, when you play Siv and Gandhi is both a Christian
and kills you, that dissonance is in itself educational,
right, because you're noticing the difference from reality.
Yeah.
Hi, I'm a game designer and also a writer.
So I believe there's always a fantasy
about rewrite the history, especially
about becoming the hero who rewrite this history.
But we rarely see that coming to part of the gameplay.
I believe it's a really difficult design decision.
since people already know what happened in real life,
but if we have a rewrite the history at some point,
that opens the Pandora's box to some extent.
And especially that when we have that in the gameplay,
we find that it's not as impactful as we expected.
So how do you think about, what could you change about it?
Yeah, that's it.
I think it's just a really important thing
to know what your goals are
and also to manage that tone effectively.
So I think in all kinds of simulations,
you could have a very respectful tour
of a very serious battlefield
where a lot of people died
and you want people to have a somber tone,
but if you're able to jump up
and bounce on the gravestones like Mario
or something like that,
then that breaks that level of tone.
So.
I think you want to think ahead and account for the types of unexpected actions that people
might have.
But then again, like I said, in other cases, that sort of playfulness actually may have
its own educational objectives.
You just want to make sure that it's not sending kind of unfortunate or even misguided conclusions
in the experience that players are having.
Thank you.
So I think it's 4.20 now, so we're going to go ahead and
wrap up.
I will hang out in the breakout room if anybody else
wants to chat.
And thank you so much again for coming.