Who here has been to the MicroTalks before?
Awesome.
If you haven't, brace yourself.
You are in for something a little bit different
than a normal GDC talk, where we have 10 speakers
who are going to speak over the next hour,
and they each have very specific guidelines.
They each get 20 slides that play for 16 seconds a piece,
no more and no less.
They are set on a timer.
It is very emotionally intense to be up here.
And it's always under one overarching theme,
which this year is creative voice.
And I'm joined by the amazing Mike Jungbluth,
who's going to kick it off.
Hey, Mike.
Woo!
All right, here we go.
Hi, I'm Mike Jungluth, a lead gameplay animator at BioWare,
and I'm creator of the Animation Bootcamp
and the Animation Exchange.
So for the next six minutes, it makes perfect sense for me
to talk about the benefits of supporting a creative voice,
both your own and others.
The core of what we do as animators,
technical animators, and animation programmers
is support other people's voices
and help bring them to life.
This goes for both our teammates
and the characters in our games,
and that support is, well,
It's just so tiring.
I mean, when you've made so many similar combat and locomotion
systems from game to game that it feels like Groundhog Day,
summoning the strength to get excited
about another mashup of other proven game systems
and power fantasies can just get harder.
and harder. So, if I'm being honest here, more than some altruistic idea of supporting other
people's creative voices, this is really about what are we doing with ours? We all hit a point
where we sort of say, what the hell am I really doing with my animation and these characters that
I'm helping to bring to life?
Do I want to work on giant games with giant teams or do I want to work on a smaller team
and go the indie route?
After all these years figuring out the skills I need for the type of work I do now, can
I even scale that up or out as needed for the other type of work?
And who the hell do I think I am that I could even say anything that anyone would care about
to begin with?
Okay, imposter syndrome, what should I do?
I could go skydiving to feel a little alive.
There we go, ha ha.
That's the sweet adrenaline boost that I needed.
Maybe that can masquerade as confidence
for my remaining four minutes.
Four minutes, what have I been talking about
for the last two minutes?
All right, let's check my notes.
Okay, that doesn't mean anything, that doesn't help.
What, fuck.
Okay, support, supporting a creative voice, right.
Look at that bastard faking confidence on slide one.
Ugh, fake it till you make it, right?
We could easily waste our next three minutes
on if you ever stop feeling like a fake,
or if you can ever really make it,
and the very feeling of making it
leading to the tedium that got us here,
but let's look at the space between fake it and make it.
Knowledge and expertise are the bridge over the fake it to make it gap.
They're the reason we're all here.
They're why the bootcamp and the exchange exist.
The more you learn about a subject, the less of a fake you are.
And the more you can share how you made it, well, the better it is for everyone.
But.
that's really been largely focused on the how of the craft.
And while the how remains important,
the what you're saying and why you're saying it of our craft
now needs a lot more focus.
Otherwise, we've really just built a bridge to nowhere.
or worse, an unwelcoming forest.
Because the knowledge and expertise we needed to get here
is often separate from the expertise
required to pass through.
We need to become versed in sociology, psychology,
philosophy, economics, anthropology, archeology,
a whole bunch more ologies.
Sure, you don't need to know what all of these things are
to share your hot take on the what and why,
but we as creators should strive to engage
with everything in life to the degree we do our animations.
It can be your torch as you venture into that unwelcoming forest.
But if creativity is the spark that lights your torch,
knowledge of the subject is going to be the fuel that will keep it lit.
And like water to a flame, lack of knowledge will actually weaken your torch
until it's eventually extinguished, leaving you in the dark.
alone. And relighting an extinguished light is even harder than lighting a new one.
The amount of knowledge to cover the doubt you and others will have about your ideas and
approaches will make even the brightest of creative sparks feel dull and, well, lifeless.
So we need to make the forest less of that and more of this.
To help the people crossing the bridge of how
not succumb to instant burnout and cynicism.
Because like the bridge we built and maintain,
we now have a lot of forest paths to light,
which isn't gonna be easy.
So when you see people speaking about the what and why,
even if all you want is the how,
Listen, it can matter someday.
If you're thinking this isn't an animation talk, well I see you, but my remaining minute
can't be the end of this conversation.
We all need to be open and honest about what we know and what we don't know.
When you have a source of knowledge, share it.
When you don't, listen.
Then we can all know how much fuel we have and where to fuel up when any of us need it.
We need to then know our platforms that we engage with,
social media, conferences, our games.
They allow us to engage with different amounts
of immediacy, agency, and directness,
which can multiply the intensity of your light.
And each is gonna require different amounts of fuel.
Because the what and why are less objective than the how.
So we need to be better at balancing our engagement
with what we and others make.
Take care not to burn out your own torch
or to burn down another's path
when trying to light the way.
My hope is that this week we have a lot more what and why conversations on our path through
the forest because in the forest is a new world full of inspiring and unique creations
pushing all of us to know more about the craft and ourselves but also each other by honestly
supporting each other's voice.
Thank you.
Our work is never finished, only abandoned, or how to ship unfinished animation and feel
good about it.
Hi, my name is Kristen.
I'm an animator and I've been in the industry for almost 10 years.
In my career, I've shipped over 16 titles and have been credited on probably more than 20.
Doing the math, that's almost two games a year, or more than that if you take everything
into consideration.
Yeah, that's a lot of projects. This isn't a brag, I bring it up because it means I've dealt
with some very tight deadlines and when you don't have enough time or resources, you have to find
ways to ship unfinished animation and feel good about it. Shipping unfinished animation? That
sounds kind of embarrassing. Sometimes no matter how much time and energy you put into something,
it's not going to be good just because video games. It's up to you to dig into your creative
toolbox and tackle all the problems, expected and unexpected, that are thrown at you.
You know, there's the age-old problems.
Perhaps game design is at lockdown.
Perhaps some big opportunity arose
and you have to ship early.
Or perhaps you just never even had enough time to begin with.
And then there's the weirder problems.
Perhaps all your animations are sped up
to match the beat of a song out of your control.
Or your animations are shared
across totally wildly different characters.
Or you can animate your character's body,
but their heads are controlled by a avatared VR headset.
All real things I've had to deal with.
And no matter how normal or weird your problems are,
things happen and you just have to get it done.
Don't get me wrong, I'm not saying you should
death march, crunch your way through it,
but don't just give up and half-ass it.
Work smart, not just hard.
And real talk?
Focus on what's important and work on the extras if you have time.
Don't sacrifice your friends and family crunching on something that no one's going to notice but you.
Because players are not going to care that you stayed late to put that subtle offset in your character's fingers.
And that's who we're making these games for, the players.
On one game I worked on, I decided it was better to add animation variety than to polish a few animations to a perfect.
polish. I wanted the player to be delighted and surprised when
their character did something fun and unexpected. Always
remember who your game is for. And yes, that means for that
game, I didn't end up with many demo reel pieces. But that
doesn't mean the animation was bad. It accomplished what it
needed to for the situation and the players enjoyed it. You're
making a game, not a demo reel. And that's the point. Really
think about what's right for the situation. Sometimes a small set
of hyper polished animations is what you need.
or maybe variety is key, and sometimes things are just a mess and you have to be flexible.
And once you have decided on your direction, try to get animations in the game quickly.
Test them, throw them out, and make new ones. This is especially true when the design is
constantly changing. And don't spend time polishing something until you know things
are working as a whole. Once everything is roughed in and working, make a polish priority list.
Take the time to identify what animation is most important, even
Ah, and hit polish for them first,
even if they aren't your favorites.
Don't get caught up in the little details
and ignore the big picture.
And the next thing to do is to work in passes.
It gives you some leeway
when your team pulls the rug out from under you.
If you haven't focused on polishing animations one at a time,
you won't lose as much work if someone cuts something or changes the design.
You'll also know that everything is at the same even level of polish.
As a whole, it will be cohesive. And use the tools you have.
For example, use key pairs instead of stepped animation.
In an emergency, you can ship a blocked out splined animation, but you can't ship a
skipped one. You can also use animation layers and
state graph to create new animations quickly.
And speaking of state graphs, use them.
Being able to set up and integrate your own animations
is so powerful and allows you to get your things in the game
faster and test them yourself.
Waiting on engineering to integrate animations
is frustrating and often just bottlenecks to the process.
And about engineers.
bug them for tools to help you.
If you have an idea for a tool that will save you time,
then talk to your lead or talk to engineering directly
if you can.
Often something that will take them an hour
will save you days worth of frustration.
Your time is important too,
so work with your team to make your job easier.
And speaking of your team,
when somebody comes at you with an unrealistic request
that'll blow out your schedule, push back.
You're a team member too,
and your time and opinion is important.
Offer solutions and find a middle ground that's
appropriate for your timeline and your team size.
And if you know you have a difficult task before you,
don't panic.
Make a realistic plan and execute.
Go in with a clear creative vision
and identify, prioritize, and focus
on what's most meaningful for the game and the player.
If you've achieved that, then that's a success,
even if you're shipping with some unpolished animation.
And as a final note, putting your best effort
but not being able to finish things to a perfect polish
is not a reflection on you as a person.
A lot of the time, that unfinished animation is only imperfect to you.
To everyone else, the animation is finished.
And remember, you can always go back and polish your favorite animations for your demo reel
later.
Thanks everyone!
I'm Kristen, and you can find me at At Stuff by Kristen on Twitter.
Hi, everybody.
My name is Yusef Cole, and I'm from the Bronx, New York.
And this is the home page of my website.
There's a reason that it looks like a bad choose
your own adventure game.
It's because I claim very two different lines of work
as my profession.
Hold on a second.
It just broke.
Let's try that again.
I am a motion graphics animator, and I specialize in software like Adobe After Effects and Cinema
4D.
I animate shapes and typography for 2D screens, and I've been doing that for over a decade.
I've worked on projects for companies like Facebook, Nike, and so on.
And I'm also a freelance games critic.
I write essays about video games where I try and dig into
unexplored themes and how they reflect politics
and history in the world.
I've written for sites like Waypoint, Pace, Unwinnable,
and ZAM, which brings me to what I'm gonna talk about today.
Picking passions.
For years, I've done motion graphics as my main gig
and picked up freelance writing on the side.
Why?
Because as interesting as the process of animation can be,
a lot of the jobs I've taken haven't been
that intellectually stimulating.
There's a lot of creative potential in motion graphics,
but the content is usually a little hard to care about.
Snowflakes for a car commercial,
animating cute mascots for health insurance companies,
helping a social media network apologize for being shitty
before they then go on to be even more shitty.
So in August I started working as the head of animation
at Patriot Act with Asad Minhaj.
And this is a show, it's the first time in many years
that I felt truly invested in the end product
and the content I'm making.
I get to work with fun, brilliant people
coming up with fascinating topics
that I actually care about.
And this presents a problem for my side hustle, writing.
On many of my previous gigs, I was able to take weeks off
for research, brainstorming, and pitching.
Now my time is super compressed.
We make an episode a week from this start.
So I can't give this job just 75%.
But I still love to write.
So I've spent the past few months wrestling
with how exactly to do that.
That means squeezing in my passion projects where I can,
like on the train before work, writing at night
before passing out, waking up early to write,
never going to the gym ever.
Of course, there are some limitations to these methods.
Trying to finish an essay on my phone
in the middle of rush hour,
not getting to spend time with my partner or my cats
after work, being perpetually sleep deprived,
never going to the gym ever.
There's gotta be a better way.
A lot of the friction comes from trying to do
two totally different things at once.
It's really hard sometimes to switch gears in the brain,
especially when one of those gears is huge and overwhelming
and sucks up all of your time.
Here's how I attempt to invest both in writing unique, challenging essays and engaging more
fully in the creative process of the show.
If I remember to turn off my animator brain and to turn on my writer brain, I can apply
the ideas we came up with for the show as inspiration for my own work in the future.
So I think Karl Marx may have been onto something when he told workers to seize the means of
production.
What I mean in my case is how do you take something that doesn't belong to you, your
labor and your time on a job, and make it work for your own interests.
So some background.
I enjoy writing about culture and politics
and how they intersect with games.
Some examples are for Unwinnable,
I wrote about Cuphead and the racism
of the 1930s cartoons that inspired it.
I was able to dig into the history of minstrelsy
and American entertainment for this essay.
For Waypoint, I wrote about Detroit Become Human,
and I talked about the game's questionable analogy
between race, labor, and fictional androids.
I also talked about how the studio itself, Quantic Dream, is also plagued by labor issues
and how that knowledge infects the messages trying to get across.
So both of these essays were deep historical dives which required a lot of time spent on
research.
I don't really have that time anymore.
Luckily, Patriot Act is a show about historical deep dives, though, so the solution to my
lack of time then is to allow my main hustle to work for my side one.
Here are four of the episodes, some of the episodes
that we've done so far on the show.
One is about student loans, one's on Amazon, Supreme,
and Saudi Arabia.
Without spending too much extra time,
I can generate some really interesting pitches
off of each of these subjects.
Is it worth going to school for e-sports for student loans?
How scarcity culture affects the value of rare old games
for Supreme?
What Amazon's history of cannibalizing its competitors
means for its game publisher and games in the Arab world
and youth culture in modern Saudi Arabia.
I haven't written any of these yet, so you guys are free to.
One of the most important practices of a games critic is looking outside of games for inspiration.
Rather than seeing my day job as a slog, something that doesn't apply at all to writing,
I now see it as a creative goldmine with plenty of excess ideas and energy spilling out.
I'm daily inspired by being on a creative job that thankfully seems to have a lot of
parallels with my side hustle.
But the kind of job you have shouldn't matter.
The key is finding the right similarities and learning how to make wildly different
disciplines inform each other.
The result can be something greater than the sum of its parts.
Am I still tired?
Yes.
Time will never be on my side.
I still have to write in the mornings and on the train
and on the weekends.
But it's something I love to do and I will always love doing.
So I'm glad that I found a way to not only make it work
with my day job, but to make my day job work for it.
Thank you.
Hello, world.
So I am Heather Alexandra McIntyre.
I am a staff writer for Kotaku.com, a video game
website about video games.
And I have never made a PowerPoint since high school.
So here we go.
So we're talking about creative voice today.
And sometimes that means looking at games from perspectives
that we might not have considered them before.
So I want to kind of go through what
that might look like for a very specific thing in this case.
In this case, it's.
idle animations, I'm just gonna start with what's basically my thesis once the slide moves forward,
but the idea is that even the smallest things inside games that we love have really, really
strange and large implications that we need to examine. Lana, is this slide not moving?
I told you at the start of what I was talking about. Is it moving?
There we go.
So what's the big deal here?
So I'm gonna talk about idle animation.
So let's go.
So the goals of players
and the goals of fictional characters often align,
but there are times when players exert control over actors
and subvert their wants or desires.
Idle animations are places
where they're free from player tyranny.
We will get into that.
And you should treat them as these very special places.
So video game characters
are many different things at once.
This is Sora from Kingdom Hearts on the left.
He's in gameplay on the right, he's in a cut scene.
Video game characters exist
between very specific dipole states.
They're being tugged between two things at any given point,
and we should define what those things are.
They are both actors, by which I mean
that they are controllable persona manipulated by players,
and they're characters, by which I mean
individuals within a fiction,
but also like people in a world,
and we need to start treating them like actual people.
Because they're being pulled in these two different directions, there's conflict though.
What Raiden wants as a character in Metal Gear Solid 2 is incredibly different than what a
player might want for Raiden at any given time. And because video game characters are fulfilling
two roles, it's a problem. Here's an example of that. On the left, there is a YouTuber who
is making a compilation video of all the death animations in Resident Evil 2.
The objective here for the actor is to die over and over.
Claire Redfield's objective as a character is to live.
These two things are not compatible. That's super screwed up.
But, good news, these two things can align.
Solid Snake wants to sneak through a base, and he wants to complete his mission.
The player wants to not get spotted and get the highest rank at the end of the game. Great.
Things are in alignment.
But we need to be careful because players are tyrants.
I know we're supposed to say like,
players are the best in everything,
but players scare the shit out of me.
They control everything about video game worlds.
They can make these people, and I mean it,
these people do things that they do not want to do.
The implications of that are very scary. I think video game characters want freedom and thankfully there are places where they get it. Thankfully, yes.
Cutscenes is one place where they actually get to act as entities solely within their fictional world, by which I mean they just get to be people.
And then idle animations where they finally get to express, just for a moment, a little autonomy.
This is Sonic the Hedgehog.
This is very well-known idle animation.
This thing expresses a very specific tension.
Sonic the Hedgehog's objective is clear here right now.
He wants to move, but the player is a tyrant,
and they are not pushing buttons on the controller,
and so therefore we don't just learn something
about Sonic the Hedgehog's personality
because of that idle animation,
because look at him, he's a nice, fun guy.
He's like, oh, his buddies are smiling or whatever,
but also that animation starts to express something
about Sonic and his actual relationship
to us and players.
which is to say, you know, Arthur Morgan goes into town and he shoots like 50 people
because the player's like, I'm just going to be rooting, tooting and shooting.
But then when they stop, Arthur shakes out his hand when he's on his horse.
That moment is beautiful to me.
It's the moment where Arthur gets to exhale finally after being controlled.
Sometimes Arthur Morgan will pet his horse and in these moments we can ask us like questions like, what does Arthur Morgan value?
But we should also be asking what does Arthur do and what does he value before the player asserts control over him as an actor?
Those are the things I want to see when I return to Arthur.
Because small moments aren't.
these people, these entities are being controlled constantly by players, by tyrannical people. And so
the moments where they get to even express a tiny moment of themselves, even though those things are
being crafted by us, are important. This can happen in gameplay too. Here Mario is skidding.
This is not just about game feel. It's not just about having good platforming mechanics.
This is a moment where I'm reminded that Mario is a person in a place with weight and validity,
and that's really, really cool. Tracer is reloading her guns. Oh, wow, how flashy.
Those Blizzard animations are really great, aren't they, Lana?
But also, you can kind of cancel this animation by hitting melee,
but otherwise I will suggest to you that this is a moment where Tracer is free.
Good news, even better news, you can bake some of this knowledge into your mechanics.
So Arthur values his horse a lot, but we get a chance to pet Arthur's horse too,
because if Arthur values it, we should probably give players a chance to value those things too.
If Arthur values it enough to do it by himself,
bridge that gap and allow your players to do it with Arthur, because empathy is key.
You need to be treating the people that you are animating as people.
I keep on saying people because I mean it. These are entities.
And if you start to find the moments in your games where people can break away, that's great.
There are exceptions to this, like digital worlds are a huge exception because the bodies that we inhabit in digital worlds
tend to be a little bit more like extensions of our limbs.
So we get to sort of define the poses and idle animations in there, but otherwise...
Find the moments where your characters can break free from player tyranny and emphasize them.
You won't just have moments where your characters find relief, your players will find relief with
your characters and your games will be kinder. And I think that's something we all need right
now in this world is just a little bit of kindness. So there you go.
Howdy, everybody.
My name's Brandon Nason and I'm a 3D animator
currently working at Pocket Gems,
a mobile gaming company based here in the city.
It's about three blocks that way.
After nearly three years of development,
we recently released our newest title,
Wild Beyond, late last year,
and I'm now assisting with the creation
of new assets for the live product.
So by profession, I'm an animator,
but I'm also a landscape photographer.
I'm a Spartan racer,
I'm a leader of a nearly undefeated escape room group,
and I'm a very lucky boyfriend.
Now, you're probably asking yourself, why is this guy up here sharing these personal
details with you at a talk that's supposed to be about game development?
Because I believe that having a robust and enriching personal life outside the walls
of the studio can help you be a better game developer and artist.
I believe that our industry always has had this problem, finding the proper work-life
balance for its developers, and I'm up here today to make the case of why it's absolutely
vital that we keep this relevant in our community.
I believe there's a little bit of a sickness within our community where having a personal
life is at best seen as a nice perk and at the very worst a weakness.
There are vast creative and emotional benefits for balancing personal and professional priorities
and I would like to go over a few of those with you today.
I think that we often get a little wrapped up in finding reference and tree animation
a little bit too cerebrally sometimes.
We count frames, we analyze spacing, and we make these really embarrassing reference videos,
and we try our damnedest to get these massive tangles of sign waste to somehow create life.
But animators are also actors.
Need to animate a character falling in love?
Yeah, of course you can find a reference video on YouTube
about somebody falling in love.
But how much more well-informed would your decisions
and acting choices be if you'd actually
gone through that experience?
I believe that living boldly and seeking out new experiences
will help you develop a creative catalog
that you can draw upon while animating.
It also works for the physical realm.
Does a character need to rock climb?
Again, you can find video reference
of the physical mechanics of that.
But if you go rock climbing yourself
and experience the adrenaline rush and the muscle fatigue
when you get up to the top of the wall and you look down,
you'll be able to animate with far more fidelity.
You'll feel it.
I run Spartan races with my friends for fun, and I can't tell you how well that's informed my understanding of the physicality of body movement and weight.
Have you guys ever jumped over a fire, climbed a rope, thrown a spear?
Those are experiences that you'll never forget and help me each and every time I animate.
Now, why is that important?
I believe that knowledge gained from real-world experiences like these can elevate your animation from something that is merely functional to something truly artistic and nuanced.
That type of knowledge cannot be gained from sitting in front of your computer stuck in
the office crunching to meet a deadline.
So let's take a moment to talk about the emotional benefits of prioritizing your personal life.
So animating professionally can be grueling.
As amazing as this feeling as a career in animation can be, it often comes with a price.
We've all heard the horror stories, the rumors, even the news reports, especially over the
last couple of years.
endless crunch, low pay, living contact to contract with no stability and enormous economic
anxiety, substance abuse, even divorce.
If you aren't personally experiencing these aspects of our industry, you assuredly know
somebody who has.
Our passion drives us to work hard, sometimes with such force and fervor that burnout is
inevitable.
For the record, I consider myself extremely fortunate
to have found a company that values the employees enough
to make work-life balance a priority.
I know, however, that I'm the minority on this issue.
But for those of you who have to deal with some,
if not all, of the problems I listed,
I would highly recommend putting the time and effort
into cultivating your friendships.
I mean, just being able to go home in a rage
when things aren't going well at work,
to commiserate and even problem solve
with people that love and care
about your personal well-being is extremely important,
especially during times like crunch.
I know I've had to experience that from time to time.
When you're sitting in front of that monitor,
bleary-eyed from lack of sleep,
eyes shifting up to the clock on the wall,
dreading that looming deadline,
just knowing that you're not alone in the world
and that there are people out there that believe in you
can be the proverbial thing that keeps you afloat.
Both creativity and passion are not ever-flowing springs.
They're more like buckets,
pushed you hard and for too long,
and those buckets can empty or even start to develop holes.
It's important to have the self-knowledge
that allows you to know what refills those creative reservoirs
and to give yourself enough time
for you to fill them back up outside of work.
For me, planning on going on adventures gives me something to look forward to, which is
always nice.
Traveling the world and seeing new places with friends and loved ones leaves me refreshed
and ready to get back to work.
It can be different for everybody, but I challenge you to go and find your passion, find your
inspiration, and give yourself the time to enjoy it.
Being emotionally and creatively healthy makes you a better animator and an employee.
Who's going to do a better job?
The walking zombie of a human being?
Sleep-deprived and burned out?
Or a well-rested animator fresh off a weekend spent doing what they love with friends and family?
Creativity requires inspiration, epiphany, and hard work.
It also requires the state of mind to be receptive to those things.
Remember that at the end of the day, in spite of all the various programs we interface with
and the professional obstacles that we must navigate, we are artists first and foremost,
and as such we thrive off inspiration and personal experiences just like any other
artistic discipline. Note too that we are all only human and that we need some recovery time
and the solidarity of friends and family to get us through the tough times.
Each and every one of us only has this one life to live.
Jobs will come and go, your work will ebb and flow,
but your personal relationships and emotional and creative health last forever.
So get out there, make friends, call your mom, experience life,
and above all else, make sure you take care of yourself.
You'll only be a better artist and game developer if you do.
Thank you.
I call my mom, she's going to like that.
All right.
I was told to put this under my chin.
Is that working?
Hi, my name's Gwen.
I love this room.
My name's Gwen.
I'm an animator.
I'm an indie developer.
And the theme of this talk this year is creative voice.
So let's talk about how to be creative.
Let's talk about how do you actually be creative.
Science has already figured this out, thankfully.
It turns out that the way you be more creative
is to have constraints.
It turns out that having limited resources
forces your brain to work different
and will actually make you more creative, which is good,
because we have a lot of constraints in this industry.
We have constraints on bone counts, on frame counts,
on all sorts of things.
These talks are ridiculous.
I have constraints for this talk, right?
I have 20 slides.
The talk auto-advances after 16 seconds on each slide.
I have to work within these ridiculous technical constraints.
And I have other things too, right?
Like I've got constraints on my tone.
Because I give this talk, I've given it several times,
and every year I do like kind of maybe a quirky, funny sort of talk.
So now I've got an audience built up, and they expect me to do a talk like that.
And if I do something different, my audience will be mad about it.
Well, they just won't like it as much.
And then I have this other audience, just people in this room, right?
Like, look around. Everybody here is an animator.
You want to hear about animation.
You don't want to hear about, like, my book club, or Lana's haircut, or design, or comedy.
It's why you're here, right?
So I have to figure out what you guys want,
which is easy, because you fill out evaluations every year.
You fill out those evaluation forms, right?
And what you guys like is,
anytime you have a takeaway, technical talks,
things where you have something
that you can take back to your studio and use, right?
We know this.
You fill out the forms and tell us this.
But in spite of this, every year,
Lana, the person who runs this, says,
no, no, no, not for the micro talks.
This is different.
This is gonna be about culture.
It's gonna be about feelings, right?
This is how we end the day.
We're gonna do something cathartic.
We're gonna inspire people.
We're gonna do something really different.
My creative director is a whack job
who has a different idea for what this should be
than the market, which is also different
from what, honestly, what I care about.
If you really break it down
and you look at what I care about,
all I care about is this.
This is my indie game.
I spent my nights and weekends working on it.
I quit my job at the end of last year and I got it funded.
I've, it's going extremely well.
I've spun up a small team.
I'm bringing the game here.
I'm showcasing this game that I've been working on
for years in the Expo Hall.
this year at GDC and I'm over the moon about it.
It's all I think about, right?
This is my baby.
But it's not what you want to hear about.
You don't want somebody standing on stage marketing at you.
I know that.
What I care about, what's most important to me,
and sometimes you're gonna experience this in your career,
the thing that's most important to you
isn't necessarily what your audience wants
or what your creative director wants.
a lot of times you're being pulled in a lot of different directions and it's difficult to marry
them all, right? Like let's again just take a look at this talk. Like this talk has to be a little
bit funny, it's got to be about culture, it's got to be about animation so that you guys are happy,
it has to be about kind so that I'm happy.
And a little bit, it's got to be about peanut butter.
And I know that's going to be, sound unusual, but I've got financial constraints and I just
need you to bear with me here, all right?
Because I don't have a lot of money and I got this contract to promote peanut butter
and I don't really need the contract, but if I don't take this contract this year, then
I won't have one next year and I might really need that contract next year.
And so I don't really have a lot of time to do this other stuff with the peanut butter,
but I'm going to jam it in anyway. And why not? Because peanut butter is great.
Like, there's nothing wrong with peanut butter. I don't feel like a sellout by promoting peanut
butter. I don't think that diminishes this talk at all. Peanut butter is delicious. I would have
probably put the peanut butter stuff in here anyway. So anyway, if we're getting back to it,
this talk is going to be a little bit funny. It's going to be about culture. It's going to
be about animation. It's going to be about kind. And it's going to be a little bit about peanut
butter, which is fine.
All right, here we go.
This is kind.
It features a lot of animation smears.
So if you look here, you'll see I'm going forward.
And then when I undo, the smears are even more exaggerated.
I'm going to do it again right here.
I'm going to move forward.
And you see kind of a smear.
And when I undo, you'll see it really exaggerated.
The way I achieve this is I create several cylinders.
And I sketch traditional 2D smear frames on these cylinders.
These cylinders are bound between two bones
that I can kind of pull apart or orient
how I need to in order to make a certain kind of a shape.
When I start the effect, I spawn a cylinder.
And the cylinder I choose is, basically I have to create
a series of these for the ends of each character,
the extremities, and for the body.
I create three cylinders for each one
for the three different directions it could be pulling in.
So here we're looking at the cylinders for the T shape.
And in engine, I basically spawn this effect,
which spawns a cylinder.
You see it?
I leave one bone in world space, and I have the other bone
attached to the end of the extremity.
I also have a couple bones in the middle that it will push
out sometimes if I need to make an arc like this.
So that's the talk.
And it had some constraints, all right?
It's it.
I mean, did those constraints make the talk better?
I don't know.
They made it more creative, though.
I think we can all agree that science is right.
That talk was more creative because of it.
And I think that's a good thing.
So if you're ever pulled, if you feel
like you're being pulled in a lot of different directions
by your director and different people at your studio,
embrace that.
That's a good thing.
That's going to make you more creative in the end.
My name's Gwen.
The game I'm showcasing this year is Kine.
You can play it on the expo floor later.
I hope you enjoy the nut butters and the rest of your day.
Cheers.
Here's to you.
Thank you.
Hello, my name is Jon Paul Reinmuller.
I have been in the industry for about 10 years.
So I'm an animation specialist at Vicarious Visions,
and I've been a lead on eight projects
since I've been there, almost the whole time, actually,
which is kind of hard to believe.
But.
It should advance and it won't.
Before that, I had some experiences at Rhythm and Hues
as an animation lead.
And before that, I was in the military for eight years
and had some opportunities to lead there as well.
So why am I telling you this?
Why does this even matter?
Why should you listen?
Well, what I'm saying here is that although I'm an animator,
I've spent lots of my career as a manager as well.
Some of you in here may have had
completely different experiences,
and I don't want to act like I know all of them.
So this is from my perspective with some of my experiences.
So I've struggled ever since I became a lead
to find a balance of creating animation content
while helping foster creative direction within my teams.
So what's the problem with that?
Well,
Because animation is all I know and care about.
And this is what got me here.
So I need to be good at this.
I need to keep doing this.
This is all I have, right?
With that mindset, though, comes its own set of challenges.
because I have always been focused as an animator
with some leading involved.
It's like I have two pieces of my brain
kind of fighting over each other constantly
in battle to save the hearts and minds of,
I'm not really sure where I was going with that,
but oh yeah, that's right, my animator brain,
my animator brain, that's right.
So I don't always have time to take on the shots that I want.
So I take on some shit shots some of the time
so my team can stay passionate.
Games already operate on tight schedules.
It's hard to take those animations to polish.
Now tack on the duties of being a lead.
I just need to animate.
Boy, I suck.
I still need to manage the team with its own responsibilities and the project with its
own responsibilities, like tracking assets, career advancements, pipeline issues, outsourcing,
art directors, lots to think about and use energy towards.
But you all know how much energy goes into a single performance or a complex body mechanics.
There's so much new stuff to think about, all this added responsibility that was rewarding
in a sense, but also a bit tense since the same old question kept creeping in.
I need to animate, right?
To be a successful lead, I realized that I needed to reach out.
I needed to find this new brand of creativity that would empower my role as a lead rather
than distract from it.
I started to think back on all the areas I had the privilege of being creative and having
impact as a lead.
working with narrative and art leadership to help shape who these characters were in our games
through brainstorms, revisions, concepting, figuring out new ways to tell stories in games,
maybe sometimes the same story. This allowed me to challenge my own knowledge of what I thought
storytelling was. I thought about how my direction was impacting animation quality. It wasn't just
about holding myself accountable anymore. Understanding how different animators work
and learning from them. I had to learn how to manage them differently to get the best team
results in the end.
Learning how to give the best feedback for that individual
helped me understand better and more precise ways
to give feedback.
And funny enough, it actually helped me understand
the type of feedback that helped me too.
I didn't stop becoming an animator
just because I was a lead.
I needed to rely on them just as much.
Driving how to communicate a story through this process at an early stage and sell the idea
honestly felt like this creative break. I would get more excited about this phase sometimes,
and it taught me a lot about myself as an artist and surprisingly something I was passionate
about outside of animation.
I've stopped thinking about all the problems.
I've stopped thinking just as an animator and now a lead,
but more importantly as a game dev.
I learned how to contribute to many areas of game development
and not just animation, and I also learned
how this can influence animation at my studio
as we develop games.
I learned to grow leadership on the team.
Training and mentoring new leads is important
for the health of your department and your team.
And some people want the opportunity,
and being able to provide that support
helps foster an environment
where people can challenge themselves as well.
And yes, growing leads and leaders on your team
will allow me and you possibly
to still be animating content.
I have stayed strong against production
and told them that I will never give up taking shots,
but I'll take on shots sometimes
that aren't as intense on the workload,
opening up space for my team to stay passionate and engaged,
and the struggle continues to be very real.
I am still working on the right balance
because just like me, it has evolved.
I know now that I will be creative and I will have a voice.
It's just up to me to help define what that balance looks like.
And now with all of that out of the way, I can get back to making really important decisions.
Like on Fridays, it's donut and bagel day, so which one am I going to choose?
Finding your creative voice in what we do
comes with challenges and struggles, and that's okay.
I don't know which way to go all the time,
but as I look out at how I contribute
to the creative process of being a game dev,
it has become clear to me that leading,
like animating, is what you make of it.
The choice to find your voice in all of this
is what has empowered me to be creative.
Thank you for listening.
I'm John Paul Ryan Miller,
an animation specialist at Vicarious Visions.
You can link up with me on Twitter.
We're all week at GDC.
Let's hope this plays.
So my name is Akita Teraduke.
I've been animating for five years.
Four of those years have been in mobile games.
And more recently, my first year in PC console
in January of this year.
And I currently live in, reside in Orange County, California.
And I work at Nexon OC, so.
Okay, this thing doesn't wanna play.
Okay, I guess it's playing.
So...
What did I learn about my...
during my journey?
I learned that I have a lot of problems.
As you can tell.
First of all, I wanted to grow, but I didn't really know where to begin.
Am I considered a good animator now that I have a job in the industry?
I really have no idea.
But early on, I was struggling to make a connection with my job's subject matter.
Initially, everything was exciting.
I was just happy to have a job and be doing animation.
But over time, I got complacent and...
I began to lose my motivation.
Plus, my traditional approach to animation,
of diving right in without planning or researching at all,
wasn't really working for me.
So, I was really passionate, but it left me anxious,
and I had to figure out a way to solve all these problems,
but still make it an enjoyable experience for myself.
So, let's talk about growth.
It's hard to push yourself, right?
Settling on your surface ideas may leave you bored and be reflected in your work, and you
don't want that.
So embrace being a nerd.
Being a nerd lets you dive deeper into your research and help you find your voice as an
artist.
For me, being a freak encyclopedia of random facts and knowledge gave me the confidence
behind my artistic decisions and opinions.
There's a reason why they call them growing pains.
Finding your confidence can be a challenge for some, so maybe all you have to do is change
your perspective.
Speaking of perspective, I worked on Marvel's Avengers Academy, a mobile game.
I am not into Marvel comic books.
I know, please don't hate me, but I do have a healthy obsession with mythology and folklore.
And by reframing Marvel as a modern day mythos, I was able to take a look at character progression
like Thor, or characters like Thor, and take note of how his personality changed over time.
And just as an example, a Shakespearean actor that we...
all known love inspired by classic mythology in the first film to the more goofy and awkward
badass of the by the end of the third film. I want to talk about passion really quick.
Have you ever seen a shot that you could feel the animator was having fun with it? Well,
my friend Lindsay Lidecker animated this shot and she's incredibly funny and naturally animated.
I think that she was very successful with this animation by establishing a personal
connection with the character which led to other artists being inspired by her idea and
creating art.
on their own.
So if you can make a personal connection with your character,
you can make anything they do interesting, right?
Be it running around with a cardboard box in your head,
playing with a soccer ball,
or simply sitting down in a chair.
However, it's not enough to just be passionate.
I like to jump in and start doing things,
but that would often lead to frustration,
and that was just simply because
I just didn't have enough information.
However...
I discovered that YouTube has plenty of information, including summaries that I could listen to
without having to read the entire Marvel omnibus.
I was on tight deadlines and I had a really tight schedule.
I had to make do with what I had.
In the case of Moon Girl and Devil Dino,
I had no idea who either of these characters were.
All they had to go off were visuals
which often depict that Devil Dino's just a crazy dinosaur.
But getting to know the relationship
helped me focus on his playful puppy attitude instead.
And Devil Dino had more to him
than being just another angry dinosaur.
Even with all these strategies in full swing,
researching was still a pain.
I love comedy and working on Family Guy's quests for stuff.
But I learned I wasn't very good at comedy.
With a suggestion of my peers, I went straight to the source
and watched as much Family Guy as my brain could handle.
So like all of Family Guy.
I began to get a better understanding of the show's
style and really figured out where the characters were
coming from.
This also caused me to have more of a snowball effect.
And I ended up studying.
comedic icons like Buster Keaton and Charlie Chaplin on my own.
Turns out I was having fun.
And I used the same approach when tasked with dance animations.
I'm naturally a horrible dancer, so I got tasked with all the dance animations.
And it turns out that studying the complicated...
mechanics of dance was actually an enjoyable experience for me. So let's recap this mess.
Researching, first of all, helps you grow as an artist without noticing it. Fake it till you make
it only gets you so far. And I couldn't just keep firing from the hip. I had to learn to be
invested with my research, which grew my confidence as an artist and animator. Finding the interest in
assignments is going to be your responsibility. Shift your perspective until you can make that
connection. And...
The more you know about what you're animating,
the more informed your decisions will be in the end.
And finally, use creative ways to make research
and study fun for yourself.
If you're frustrated and it feels like a chore,
try a different approach.
Instead of treating it as a formality,
treat research as an opportunity to learn something new.
Researching ultimately is a friend and a powerful tool
in helping you find your artistic voice.
My name is Nikita Taranduke.
You can email me at nikitataranduke at dma.com.
Find me on Twitter at Nikita Taranduke.
Thank you very much.
I hope not.
All right.
My name is Nikki Roth.
I'm a tech animator at Google, and I'm
here to talk about confidence with confidence.
All right.
So let me tell you a little bit about my first career
in gymnastics.
I grew up as a competitive gymnast.
And as a gymnast, you are literally
judged on your confidence and ability to execute skills.
There was this one skill, the full twisting side gainer.
I remember spending an entire summer
training this beam dismount.
I practiced it and practiced it until I felt confident
I could perform it under pressure.
You can imagine how nerve wracking it is
to throw yourself backwards and upside down
on a four inch piece of wood.
Beam was not my favorite event.
It was more of a mind game.
but it was time to debut this skill.
So at the next meet, my coach gave me her pep talk.
She told me I could do this.
She reminded me how many times I've done this before.
And she went over the 10 different things
I should focus on, but what really mattered
was that she and my teammates were there cheering me on.
I went through my own rituals, the internal monologue,
all right, Nikki, you got this.
The drills that were now mantras,
lift, set, wrap.
and all the ridiculous mind melding it took for me to believe I could do this.
As gymnasts, we are taught to stand and walk with attitude.
So I strutted to the beam, I saluted, took a deep breath, and began the routine.
The moment came.
Lift.
Set.
Wrap.
The connection, the form, call me biased, but it was solid.
And when we gymnasts stick a landing,
we salute not with one, but with both arms.
If you break down a gymnastics routine
into frames like an animation, it's all about posing.
Strong lines, silhouettes.
In a single pose, we can recognize confidence.
In a single pose, we can read misery or mastery.
So if we frame this on my current career,
which is basically digital gymnastics,
I am still being judged on my confidence to execute skill.
And it's not easy.
It takes practice, courage,
and it really helps to have support.
I want to help my team do great things,
but I need to show what I can offer.
I need to own what I can do and own what I can't.
For me, I struggled with owning it.
It's hard to walk into a room with confidence
when you're not sure you have what it takes to be there.
Imposter syndrome is real.
Like gymnastics or anything else, it's more of a mind game.
You are there because you put in the time.
You are there because you want to be.
So be there.
Sit at the table, literally sit at the table.
You belong there.
Be present and engaged.
Listen thoughtfully.
But don't just listen.
Form your own opinions.
Your perspective and your experience is so unique
that you and only you can bring it to the table.
But don't just bring it.
Share your thoughts.
Say them and say them with conviction.
Speak up, ask questions,
amplify your voice and be part of the conversation.
We can read body language, but we can't read minds.
I used to be a chronic mumbler.
I was constantly having to repeat myself.
I would be interrupted or talked over.
But when you come from a place of passion,
you will energize the room.
If you are authentic in what you have to say,
others will care.
If you are transparent and show empathy,
Others will appreciate what you choose to share.
On the other hand, speaking up does not
mean being the loudest or talking the most.
Speaking up is about sharing your voice
and sharing the floor.
By including others around you, you
can create a dialogue and a space for everyone.
We all have different personality types.
We digest information differently,
express ourselves differently.
Not everyone prefers speaking in front of large crowds.
It makes us feel vulnerable.
When you are considerate of this,
when you empower others, it empowers you.
It builds a network of support and trust
that will absolutely help to build your confidence.
And allies can give you the courage to speak up
when you need to the most.
So, it's time to debut your skills.
Confidence comes with training, courage, and support.
I encourage you to practice sharing
and share what you practice.
Trust it, own it, and when you nail it,
salute with both arms.
Thank you.
Hi.
Wait.
Oh.
Oh boy.
Oh, there's water?
No, there's not.
Oh, damn.
Okay.
This is the last one of the day, right?
Last one of the day, last one of the day, this is it.
Hi, everyone.
My name is Lana Byszynski.
I am a senior animator with Blizzard Entertainment.
Hi, I'm Ryan Duffin.
I'm the animation director at Bioware in Austin.
Were you the kid who drew in class when it was against the rules?
Were you a straight-A student, troublemaker, or a fool?
Do you recall with joy or dread the promises admissions said?
So you spend all your money on an animation school.
You still think you'd argue that it should have been Henke
But you sacrifice for your dreams to make things move on Xbox screens
What's the price you pay to get in the game industry?
We scrub along life's timeline where others pitch we roll
When art school came
A normal life it has a path, for us it has a spline.
We chose to live our lives this way, one keyframe at a time.
Woo!
You graduate from college with a 50 grand degree.
But now you've got your first job with the decent.
The project begs for overtime, you're young and eager, this is fine.
When broken down by hour, you'd make more at Mickey D's.
You started on your second game without much introduction.
You carved your niche among an institutional dysfunction.
From step to block to polished blinds,
you've redone this whole shot 10 times
because your director's never heard of pre-production.
You scrub along a life's timeline
where others pitch we rolled.
We eased out from a life of cycles, loops, and olds.
A normal life, it has a path, for us it has us blind.
We chose to live our lives this way, one keyframe at a time.
You get a corporate job and now you're making better pay
By annual reviews and a 401k
But now you fantasize about an indie legacy
Your game a work of art made with love and integrity
But maybe it gets lost in steam and you'll have to file for bankruptcy
Corporate hours are no surprise at six months out you've worked all night. You'd think it'd be more organized
You've shipped a few titles, now you've done this for some years.
And there are options for you to grow, none of them are here.
Do you compromise work and life to not displace your man or wife?
Or sacrifice stability to further your career?
You put your heart and soul in it, you're driven to succeed.
It's a decade down the line, you graduate.
You've got your spreadsheets so tight you forget what Maya looks like
and spend your days in twice as many meetings as you need.
We scrub along life's timeline where others pitch we roll.
We chase mastery of the NARD instead of chasing gold.
A normal life, it has a path, for us it has a spline.
We chose to live our lives this way one keyframe at a time.
Now you're looking back over your successful career.
You've gotten some good and bad credits over the years.
But it's a fight to stay relevant.
Is there such thing as retirement?
In a couple decades, will there still be room for me here?
Woo!
We, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we,
we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we,
we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we,
we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we, we.
where others pitch we rolled.
And you can feel the frame rate change
as we grow tired and old.
A normal life, it has a path.
For us, it has a spline.
We chose to live our lives this way, one keyframe at a time.
We scrub along life's timeline.
We keep our layers clean.
Because we can't undo or load up a fresh scene.
A normal life, it has a path.
For us, it has a spline.
We chose to live our lives this way, one key frame at a time.
We chose to live our lives this way.
One key frame at a time