Hi everyone, welcome to the GDC Twitch channel.
My name is Brian Francis, the invisible voice inside your head, the person hosting your
game development adventure today.
We are here today checking out a game called MechWarrior 5 Mercenaries, which if you're
like me...
This series should be very familiar to you because it was a big staple of 1990s PC gaming.
In the last couple of years, we've also had the new Battletech game, which came from Harebrained Schemes.
But today, we're getting back in the world of mech piloting.
We are, as you can see right now, suiting up to get into a nice big stompy mech.
And this game comes to us from the fine folks at Piranha Games.
In the lower left-hand corner of the screen, Piranha Games CEO, Russ Bullock.
Russ, how are you doing?
Great, thanks for your interest.
I'm glad that it sounds like you like the game.
I think that's all any developer wants to hear.
Well, okay, they want to hear that the game is successful.
But one of the more rewarding things is seeing that the fans got what they wanted out of it.
I'm going over to the chat real quick and give a quick shout out to some of our viewers
like Unnatural Flavors who have shown up already.
For folks in chat, if you're not familiar with our stream what we do is we'll be talking
to Russ about the making of MechWarrior 5 Mercenaries and we're going to be taking your
questions so if you have questions about MechWarrior 5, if you want to know about mech design,
if you want to think about, have questions about balancing heat levels.
Ask him in chat. People like Veritas the Snazzy Dragon. Feel free to just ask questions.
We will pass them on to Russ, the ones that are on topic, and from there we will just hopefully
learn more about how this game got made. Russ, like I said, implied before, MechWarrior was
once a dominant PC shooter game. It's kind of a simulation game, shooter game.
Not just because it was a bunch of levels where you popped in a mech and shot things,
but also because you chose an array of mechs,
you managed your mechs in your hangar across a variety of missions.
And then around 2000, MechWarrior 4 was the last proper named MechWarrior game,
and the series kind of spiraled out for different reasons and just wasn't amazed anymore.
Your studio has been working with MechWarrior Online for a bit.
How did your studio get started working in the MechWarrior franchise?
And what are your origins for MechWarrior 5?
That's a lot of questions. I'm sorry about that.
It's okay.
No, I would say, well first off, I was a fan of...
I played all those original PC games, even starting in 89.
The original MechWarrior, which honestly might be one of the biggest inspirations for MechWarrior 5 Mercenaries...
So I remember playing that one, you know, begging my mom to buy it in the mall, and
then we had to swap out the CGA monitor for an EGA monitor so I could do those simple
new early graphics.
And I played all of them, and I guess even the last one, MechWarrior 4, anyhow, would
have been around even since we became a dev studio.
So we started our studio in 2000, and 2000 to 2002 was where MechWarrior 4 and up to
MechWarrior 4 Remerks was launched.
So this was a brand I always had huge interest in.
It was really a dream of mine to work with it,
and I always felt like it was almost certainly well out of reach.
But we, really long story short,
we started to form a relationship with Jordan Wiseman,
who had the original FOSA founder and creator,
who had sold FOSA to Microsoft,
but then he had spent some years there
and started a new studio and had licensed Arise back.
And in 2008 we started that relationship and
2009 we released this video, some people might remember it, it was our attempt to kind of
push for a new MechWarrior game.
And that never got off the ground, but by 2011 we had managed to license those rights
and started work on MechWarrior Online.
So MechWarrior Online was something we were extremely interested in, but it was also kind
of a step we felt like we had to take because either we weren't ready, or the market wasn't
ready, or...
A number of things just weren't ready for the next single player MechWarrior game yet.
So we kind of established both ourselves and our knowledge of MechWarrior but also kind
of re-established a foothold for the brand with MechWarrior Online.
We ran that for a number of years and then it was clear though the minute we started
MechWarrior Online that the fans were super excited and also in the next breath they were
like okay great but where is MechWarrior 5?
So we knew all those years that this is something we really wanted to get to when the timing was right.
Then it was early 2016, we started development.
So a full three years since we started some basic prototyping and production and ramping up to where we finally shipped it.
So it's really a long path, dream come true.
I'm super happy. It's great to hear about devs who get to sort of be inspired by games when they were younger and then get to follow in their footsteps as they build their careers.
I am going to go to the chat real quick. We are going to ask, we're going to pull Hammerzeit's question here.
How did it feel to make an entry to what is considered to be a premier PC series from
the 90s and early 2000s, and how do you adapt this genre to today's markets, especially
as a smaller studio?
I stand corrected.
That's a great question, Hammerzeit.
It is a good question, and it definitely identifies some of the challenges that we face, because
you know, it's not the same world and the same market and everything that it was in
the 90s when MechWarrior was at its heyday.
And so...
You have a lot of tough decisions to make early on in production.
It's like, do you want to attempt something radically different
that you think today's gamers want, will adapt to all of today's gamers,
and, you know, try to establish it in that regard?
Or do you want to give long-time fans of the franchise what they want?
And we chose the latter, and I think that's for some good reasons.
And it doesn't mean, of course, that MechWarrior 5 Mercenaries doesn't have a significant amount of modern updates when it comes to things.
And not just visually and graphically, but in the destructible environments, even in the controls and a lot of things that modern games do today.
But ultimately, what we decided to do was, let's update and give MechWarrior 5 Mercenaries fans...
The game they always dreamed of. The one that they...
When they were playing MechWarrior 4 Mercenaries or MechWarrior 2 Mercenaries,
and they loved it to death,
but when the experience was a little too linear and was over too fast,
and they were left wanting just after maybe 8 to 10 hours of a single-player campaign,
we decided, well, let's make something...
In those moments, you're always dreaming, like, well, what if?
What if you could fly anywhere?
What if you could take contracts anywhere?
You know, this, you could do this or that and had your own drop ship and can actually see your mechs.
And we tried to essentially bring what I felt like would be all the dreams of all those years playing those games to life in MechWarrior 5 Mercenaries.
And in doing so, we would meet the requirements and dreams of longtime MechWarrior fans,
but also by modernizing it to today's engines, technology, destructible environments, control schemes.
We'd have also a chance to reach out to, you know, maybe a new generation of MechWarrior fans as well.
So that's how we approached it. You could have gone a different way. You could have really radically
changed and revolutionized the entire thing and hoped that it would find an audience, but we
we stuck with, well, we started with our core audience, I guess, and
advanced the concept from there.
Right on. Hammerzeit also wants to say thank you for making something as great as MechWarrior 5 after 17 years of quote, twilight years.
I don't know if that's a specific reference to Battletech lore, but...
We are going to get to some other questions from folks in chat.
Zayde, Azmay, we do see your questions, but for now we're going to...
I'm going to lean in on some of the development focus questions that we've got lined up here.
Russ, the first one I have to ask is, I think some of the things that defines MechWarrior
for me and my love of giant robots is the sensation that unlike other giant robot experiences
in video games, this one is dedicated to make it feel like you're piloting something.
You have the system where you move the torso and the legs in two different directions.
The heat management, you and I were talking before the stream about our days playing this on joystick in the original series.
As a new, without sort of any code or assets from the old games to sort of boo you, which that's an assumption I'm making,
how did you start from the ground up making something that would feel like the old systems that was probably more meant to be played on keyboard and mouse since joysticks aren't as popular these days?
And get that piloting sensation even without the piloting peripheral.
Yeah, well, one of the huge advantages we had was that, you know, even when we started
MechWarrior 5 Mercenaries in early 2016, we had already been working on MechWarrior Online
for over five years.
So if there's people out there that know MechWarrior Online, there's, you know, we could talk
and debate about...
It is a game that has been around for 8 years in the free to play space.
There is one thing that everyone would agree on, I think, is that the mech combat is great.
It is the high point of the product.
We really did establish really great mech combat.
We were bringing that into MechWarrior 5.
We were starting with a strong know-how of how to create strong mech combat.
and starting with all the mech concepts and assets for all the battle mechs that we've spent,
well now, you know, the last eight years concepting and developing, which is also another
like top two strong point of MechWarrior 9 and Piranha Games' work on MechWarrior,
is really the establishing and or re-establishing of the look and feel of all the battle mechs in
the universe. Our artist, Alex Iglesias, has concepted out
almost all of them at this point. I mean there's still some we haven't got to, but there's so many.
Well over 100 chassis in MechWarrior 9 with, you know, four to five variants each, so we're up into
the, you know, over a thousand range. And people have really gravitated towards those, and it's
really become kind of a standard now. We license those art assets out to a harebrained scheme,
so you see the same mechs as MechWarrior 9 and as MechWarrior 5.
In Herobrine's biotech product as well, almost entirely.
They've done a couple, like the Hatchet Man,
and they have the new one in their latest DLC,
which is an original concept.
But for the most part, it's been the new mechs
that we've established here at Piranha and in mechWare Online.
So we were bringing these two real strong pillars to the table.
That was a lot of know-how that we had developed over the years
and had at our disposal.
And then, you know, we...
The rest... I think if you play MechWarrior 5, I think it also would be fair to say that
that remains a high point. Our strength would be the mission-to-mission combat simulator is,
maybe unsurprisingly, because of our history with MechWarrior 9, is the high point of MechWarrior 5
as well. But we had to develop other expertises in artificial intelligence systems and in campaign
and storytelling. I think those areas...
are good, but they're not as strong as some other areas.
And so, again, our strength are in the combat simulator.
And so I think that might get to most of your question,
or did I miss maybe a piece of that?
Yeah, well, I guess I'll zero in on the question
of what do you think makes piloting feel good
in a modern game space?
Like, what do you think your team did right
about the feeling of piloting?
Hmm, okay.
Yeah, well, the torso-twisting feeling, that is,
It's good that you're showing the tutorial of the game here because it is the type of game that still requires a tutorial.
Because there's a lot of people that have never played anything quite like this before.
And that's what makes MechWarrior so unique is that there is this concept that you're essentially a walking tank.
And that's where MechWarrior 5 is good because it has this really great third-person camera
which quickly explains to players that...
that
lower combat, then say like your average FPP shooter.
I think the amount of things that's going through the person's brain while they're playing
a game like MechWarrior is every bit as high or intense as any
Super Twitch FPS. It's just that because you're always making movements on your controls
It's that you're thinking ahead like five steps ahead. It's like well if I want to
Back up and get behind this building and get cover before that guy finishes turning around
Then I've got to start making those movements ahead of time to slow this giant mech down
Put it into reverse and turn and back around that corner before he can finish his turn
so although what's being presented on the screen is
I'm not sure if it's a better way to describe this than a twitch first person shooter.
I think the actions inside the player's head and the movements they're planning is every bit as intense.
So it's very satisfying that way.
You have the lumbering sounds, the turning sounds of your torso,
the reaction as you shoot your weapons or take hits,
the sparks in your cockpit when you take a hit,
as you lose bits and pieces of your mech.
in turn losing weapons.
There's just so many things that add up to a mech cockpit experience and
again I think that's something we have had now about eight years to fine-tune
between MWO and MechWarrior 5, so
the magic is in there and it's just a collection I think of
dozens of things that the guys have
learned and developed over the last eight years.
Right on. I'm going to jump to the chat real quick.
CyberAlpha05 asked if there was any collaboration with the Harebrained Studios BattleTech team.
I think you mentioned there that you guys have been licensing mech design to them.
Anything else from the fine folks at Harebrained that have helped you out?
Not much. There's not a lot between the studios in that regard.
We know each other well. We're friends of each other.
They come to mechcon and everything.
For BattleTech, we licensed artwork to them and they used that.
And it's pretty much the same thing this way.
The jump ship you see in the travel sequences is theirs.
That's the only artwork that I'm aware of.
But also they offered quite a bit of valuable help in the localization front
because they had already gone through localization at BattleTech
and I believe they shipped with the same languages that we did.
We shipped with... besides English we had...
French, German and Russian, which are strong languages for the MechWarrior brand.
And they had gone through the same process, so I know that our guys here in Localization
got help from a couple of individuals on their side, helped out a lot in Localization.
So, that's about it.
Each of our studios are just so busy with their own games.
There's not a lot of like...
You know, we're not talking about the campaign or the story, which...
with each other about each other's games or anything like that.
But just help out.
Oh, can we help you with Loke?
Can we help you with some...
Sure, you know, you can use our...
We'll use some of yours and stuff like that.
Stuff that would help with, you know, production time,
production risk, things like that.
The Loke thing is actually something I would super want to dive into
just because, you know, reaching new markets in any video game space
is kind of an important conversation for devs.
I am going to dive to one more question before I return to my questions.
However...
Veritas the Snazzy Dragon would like to know, would you talk a little about how the mechs ported to MechWarrior Online were overhauled to have new damage models?
For me, this is one of the most important and impressive parts of MechWarrior 5 visually.
Y'all are asking some good questions today, thank you.
Yeah, so we were able to bring over the mechs pretty much as is.
We didn't remodel them, which was really key to our design.
We're like, okay, we're only so big of a studio.
It's not like we can remodel, like, you know, six years worth of models.
So, good thing that they were still really great models that held up really well,
and we brought them over.
But we did know that we wanted to go significantly further with the damage state.
In MechWarrior 9, it looks great, but it's limited really to basically just arm removal.
Once the arms are blown off.
I think that's the only thing that actually has a model swap, if I'm not mistaken, in
MechWarrior Online, we'll model swap out the arms.
And so, of course, we thought about a lot of different ways we could approach this,
but we also wanted to be careful that we weren't overreaching into something overly complex
where you spend massive amounts of engineering resources just to end up with something that
looks kind of odd.
So we basically just went with kind of what we knew, but went a lot further.
So in MechWarrior Online...
You have the pristine paint.
When you get shot with a laser, you have the laser glow.
And then whenever you get shot, whether it's laser or anything,
you have the damage texture layer.
So it removes the paint and shows the pock marks and stuff
like you're taking damage.
And then that's kind of all the MWO does until a limb is lost,
like an arm is lost, and then you do the model swaps.
In MechWarrior 5, we have the damage, like the laser glow, and we have the damage texture.
But we went a little further, we said, okay, damage texture represents your armor, like you're still in, you still have armor left on your mech.
But when you get to internal structure, we're actually going to do a model swap.
And then, once the, once all the internal structure is gone, we'll do another model swap to the destroyed state.
And that's the case in almost every component, but obviously with the certain areas like
center torso, when you're done with structure, your mech's dead anyhow, but there's still
another model swap.
So what this turns out to be is you have two arms, two legs, two torsos, a center torso,
a head, and then even the rear torsos.
And you add this up, I think it's something like, what is that, two, four, six, seven.
7 times 3 and I think I'm missing some. You end up having something like between 20 and 30.
I'm a little rusty in this knowledge now. I used to have it all down perfectly, but somewhere between like 20 and 30
various damage dates per mech. And so it did, it was a pretty big effort. If you look here, like I guess your footage
it's recorded. You can't, you just walk past the centurion. You can see that on the screen. That's okay. They can see it.
So these legs, I think that right leg there is
destroyed. That's
You know, down to its base model swap out of structure, and then the other leg might be showing some structure left.
And so, it did take quite a bit of effort with every chassis in the game.
We had to model both states.
Both armor's gone, and now structure's gone, and we do swaps based on everything.
So that's how the system works, and I think for the most part it works.
I'm really happy with it. It shows tons of detail when you get back to the mech lab.
And that was part of the point too, it's like I want the feedback in real time in combat,
but when you, the whole point of MechWarrior 5 Mercenaries is coming back and being alive
in this hangar, and you want to see that damage persist.
So that was a main point as well.
And I would say we're like, I'm like 95% happy with it.
The only time it kind of trips up a little bit is in combat, because the model swaps
are so precise.
If you're very precise in your shooting and say you're just hitting one particular component,
like just the right dead center in the center torso,
you'll see all the model swaps happen there and it's a very distinct line.
So I think if we were ever to make any improvements, we'd try to do some sort of...
Bleeding out from that pristine line to make it blend a little better, but otherwise, you know really happy with with the overall
system
Brief shout out here to the voice actor behind this particular character spirits
It's the same guy who voices Adam Jensen and deus ex and I'm blanking on his name, but I love his voice
That's a lias to fix it. That's it
Yeah, and he was also in battle tech as the people channel would know he was yeah
bad guy red-haired bad guy
in the cinematics where you...
Spoiler alert, he's in that game as well.
All of this is super familiar stuff if you've been playing mech warrior for as long as some of the folks in chat have been
You know, this is old hat. How do you think?
You approached you and your team approached redesigning those features for this game and making sure it was still accessible
Even the players who didn't know that like hey, it's not a good idea to just kid up your mech with all lasers
Cuz then it overheats
Yeah, it's um, it's you're right. It's one of the key like pillars of any mech warrior game and it's also very
It's a big discussion point for a lot of people because there's so many ways to go about a mech lab.
In fact, as many numbered series mech games as there are, there's a different mech lab.
And those that know the intricacies will understand that.
For example, people might remember that MechWarrior 3 was a no-holds-barred, almost Franken-mech system
which had maybe a few fans, but some detractors.
MechWarrior 4 went with more of a size hardpoint system.
MechWarrior Online, not part of the numbered series, but MechWarrior Online has, without
a doubt, the most robust mech lab known to mankind.
I mean, it is out there.
It does everything.
And so we had that experience of having a mech lab like MechWarrior Online, which is
great for a PvP game, it allows people to do unbelievable numbers of different builds
looking for the min-max situation.
So we had all that and we could have brought that over exactly to MechWarrior 5, but we didn't.
And for a few reasons.
One is, it is way too much.
If we're trying to re-establish MechWarrior single-player games,
PvE, and be successful enough that maybe there's a MechWarrior 6 one day,
we needed it to be understandable and reachable to more than just,
you know, the most hardcore fans of the brand.
So that was...
a fairly big part of it, and of why we brought down the complexity somewhat.
But maybe the bigger element, and this is what I've expressed to the, you know, the
MechWarrior 9 community, and it is the bigger element, is MechWarrior 5 is not a PvP multiplayer
game.
It is a single player game that allows co-op play.
And for this reason, you're also managing a mercenary unit, unlike ever before, like
to a level of freedom that they've only dreamed about in the past.
In order for that to work, you really need all the various variants of the mechs and
the markets that you visit in the star map to all have some meaning.
With a mechware online style of mech lab, you can almost take any mech and the customization
level is so high that you can accomplish the same thing that other mechs do well, just
through customization.
We felt we needed to limit that quite a bit so that when you...
Customize your mech. It has meaning but you're also not
Overriding what other mechs would do so when you go to the market and you see mechs for sale
They're almost any everyone that's there has some meaning like oh neat. I haven't seen that one yet. I'd really like to buy that one
And have this free market system in this metagame really work and make sense
So there's a couple reasons, but still it's a very for a brand new player. There's still you know plenty of depth there
I mean you can still
swap out weapons, three different types of that.
So we have kind of a size hardpoint system as well like MechWarrior 4,
so there are some restrictions, but you can generally put smaller ones in.
But we just don't allow what's called hardpoint inflation,
where you can't, say, pull out a large energy weapon
and then put three small ones in.
So anyhow, I think it's an hour long conversation going to Mech Labs,
but it's core.
to any MechWarrior experience for sure.
And I feel like anyhow, and I've got some feedback to this, some of the most hardcore
MechWarrior Online fans might still long for the deeper MechLab, but I think for the most
part the feedback has been that we found the right balance for this single player experience,
you know, market driven game.
Right on.
I will get back to some chat questions in a second.
I wanted to ask about one more system and how you all approached it.
As you mentioned, this game is not just about piloting the mechs, it's about running the
whole mercenary group, taking systems to systems, contracts.
So it's a really neat metagame that fits in with the story missions, negotiating contracts.
I'm a super big fan of these systems because they help with that simulation aspect and they help you personalize the decisions you're making on not just a mech design level, but like a who is my group, what kind of jobs do we take on, how much trouble are we in right now.
I wish we had more time to dive into it on the stream, but we're just going through some
of the early missions here.
But how did your studio approach designing that one, knowing it would kind of be not
just the anchor for your single player mission, you know, not just the backbone for your single
player missions, but also where people will be spending a lot of time if they chose to
ignore the single player, all the main missions and just go run their companies?
Yeah, I think.
fairly early on and one of the messages we kept saying, I know I repeated it in a lot
of meetings, was, you know, where the game is lost, you know, out the gate if we can't
create a metagame experience in the front end that's nearly as fun as being out on the
missions or at least as, you know, addicting and engrossing to want to manage your company.
So that's...
I don't know if we achieved that entirely, meaning I still think going out on the missions
is the funnest aspect.
We did put a lot of effort into that to make sure that we tried to make that metagame experience
really meaningful.
So you touched on the high points.
First off, there's the ability to travel anywhere you want, but it's fairly expensive to hire
jumpships to take your dropship and your unit places.
Every time you travel...
You know, you're thinking about that, because, you know, there's 100,000 sea bills, 50,000 sea bills, that's a lot.
And the other, I think one of the bigger innovations that we did in our game,
that I don't think has been done before, is this notion that,
sure, you can repair your mechs anywhere, but when you're in the war zone,
it's more expensive to do repairs, and it takes more time.
So we created this because we wanted to try to bring the Star Map alive, where...
players were actively always thinking about the star map and where they do certain things.
And so we kind of went out of our way to, well for one, if a player wants to hire pilots
for their battle mechs, they're only available in the industrial hubs.
And then to kind of reinforce the industrial hubs, we also said, well, those are penalty
free areas to repair.
and you have to repair your mech, so they don't cost extra and it doesn't take extra time.
So now we've created a situation where there's a lot of motivations for the player to plan around
how long they're visiting the war zones versus how long they're visiting the industrial hubs.
And now there's a bit of pressure on you as a mercenary commander to
try to have enough functioning mission-worthy battle mechs and pilots that you're not just...
going on one mission repairing everything, going on one mission repairing everything,
but perhaps when you go to the war zone you're thinking,
well, you know, we have enough mechs and pilots to do two missions, maybe even three,
if we've got a good stable, before we need to incur those costs to fly out to do all
those repairs and whatnot.
So we did quite a few things like that in hopes of bringing, you know, more life to
the Star Map.
The View Intel button tells you which planets have which contracts and what mechs you might
encounter in the battlefields and so on.
So that's, I hope that answers the question, but it was definitely a big effort for us.
It wasn't just like, it's all about the missions when you go in here, there's nothing really
to think about except which contract you accept.
It's a little more than that.
You think about the contracts, but you're always thinking about where should I fly next
and when should we fly and stuff like that.
I like that answer. I especially like the part where you mentioned using the war zones as an incentive.
Like, hey, you can only be in this area so long, your funds will run out.
That's some good insight.
Yeah, and speaking of that, Aaron Sedrick-Arch says there's an incentive to fail at your mech stable for that reason.
I am going to go back to questions from chat for a minute.
These will be a little off topic for Dev, but you know, you guys have been great.
We'll give you guys some questions that are a little off topic.
Do you have any plans for mod support?
And if that's the case, or if it's not the case, can you talk about what it takes to implement
to support modders for games like this?
Yeah, we do.
We told the community quite a while ago that we plan to support mods.
In fact, we are preparing the editor for release right now.
It's, we told the community recently on our, the Discord channel.
So anyone who's bought the game at this point can get access to the
MechWarrior5 Mercenaries Discord channel, by the way.
And so welcome you to come in there.
And there's lots of good resources around joysticks support and just,
you know, a whole bunch of things.
There's a bunch of drop areas if you're looking for people to play co-op with.
But one of those things is mod support channels.
And we just let everyone know that our goal is to release the editor here sometime next week before we all break for Christmas.
I think there's a good chance that we're going to meet that goal.
And so basically we're going to release the editor.
And what that will do is it'll allow mod creators to get started.
We're still going to be lacking a kind of a smooth...
you know, end user experience for just, like, selecting and downloading mods.
And so we're going to be working closely with Epic on that.
I'm sure we're going to be one of the...
there's no timelines or ETAs yet on that aspect of it, but,
you know, they're adding that kind of functionality to the Epic Games Store,
similar to a Steamworks type of thing.
And so we're going to be right there with them, I hope,
being one of the first studios to support that.
But you won't have to wait for that.
The editor will be out soon and people can get started making mods.
And they can still potentially share them with each other through more old-school methods.
Like, here, take this folder, do this, do that.
All sorts of things like that.
And then we're going to be looking to get more of that end-user experience.
And as soon as we can, no ETA yet on that.
But there's the answer.
Right on, I also need to give a shoutout to Centron for asking that question.
I'm going to have questions about working with Epic in a bit.
But, let's see...
We can talk about co-op, questions like StarMix
StarMix says they're bringing in some questions from the NGNGTV
community stream, so shoutout to the folks at NGNGTV.
StarMacs would like to know if co-op players will be able to interact with the StarMac and MechBay in the future.
And I guess, what was sort of the challenges of doing a co-op mode in the first place?
Because, I mean, you know, take every problem you have making it for one player and multiply it by two.
And that's what it sounds like to me.
Yeah, I mean, even adding peer-to-peer co-op, it might sound simple.
And perhaps, you know, compared to the online infrastructure that is required for something like MechWarrior Online, it is simple.
But...
It still makes almost every programming task that you do in the game take twice as long.
Because almost everything you do you have to make sure is ready for a co-op player and that replicates to the player.
So it definitely added a lot of development time, a lot of complexity.
And things like he mentions, I don't know what the likelihood of stuff like that is.
Because you have to consider things like, well, it's not just technical requirements that we have to consider.
We have to consider.
The gameplay aspects like does your friend or person that you're playing the game with,
do you want him to actually spend your C-Bills?
Because in Instant Action, you know you, so it's not a limitation of technology because
in Instant Action, you know, you can edit your mech, edit your loadout, edit your paint
job, all that kind of stuff.
When it comes to playing in someone else's campaign game, you don't.
There's a different aspect there because they have.
certain mechs in their campaign, they don't have all mechs, and they have certain pilots,
and you come in and you essentially take the place of one of those AI pilots, so you become,
you know, naming AI pilot's name. It's like, okay, you're gonna be him, so play him for me,
and play this mech, and come out in my missions with me, and help out. So you don't bring your
own stuff in, and we also didn't think that we could allow the player to adjust and spend
the person's campaign that you're in, you know, because then...
It's going to open up a massive can of worms of like, yeah, well, we'll put in options to say if you want to allow it or not.
So everything's possible with time.
But, you know, we might have had to release December 2020 if we wanted to put all of that stuff in.
So who knows where patches or updates will go from here.
No commitments.
But I will be listening.
And we understand, you know, people are really enjoying co-op.
I'm sure there'll be a few, you know, there'll be some additions and adjustments, just as
long as we're being, you know, careful and just remembering that this is, you know, it's
not MechWarrior Online, it's a single player game that allows co-op play.
The majority of their co-op play will probably be in instant action, but helping your buddy
out in his campaign is certainly fun, but you just remember that you're in his campaign
and using his C-Builds and his equipment.
Right on.
I'm going to get one more question from Hammerzite, which, before I move on to some other questions,
what were the positives and negatives of experiences of developing this game?
How did it go transitioning to a new engine, and how was it, how was the transition to
working?
They said, Hammerzite asks...
How was it like transitioning to a genre where narrative was at the front and center compared to the multiplayer online, MechWarrior Online?
I would rephrase the question as what was it like transitioning to a single player campaign, you know, just kind of a campaign thing because
narrative may be, narrative focus may be not quite the adjective I would use.
But I guess, you know, I like his question. What were the ups and downs of making this game?
Oh my goodness.
In hindsight, it feels like...
Piranha Games is not a brand new studio, right?
We've been around now for 20 years.
However, even making this game was still a massive challenge.
It was very hard.
There almost was no aspect of the game that wasn't incredibly challenging.
I mean, the base, core, mech, combat, damage model system, everything.
That was challenging, but probably the one area that, you know, coming from MechWarrior Online,
that was, even though we felt challenges,
we knew where we were going and how we were going to get there.
But almost every other aspect from telling a story, which obviously MechWarrior 9 has nothing like that,
creating the AI systems, creating the procedure generated missions,
everything at one point in the project felt extremely challenging and,
oh my god, are we actually going to be able to do this?
So I couldn't even narrow it down, there must be a half a dozen systems that were very, very challenging.
There were moments during the development where you wonder if you're going to succeed
at finishing off that item, or if you're going to have to drastically change the way the
game works.
So we came through, and I believe every case.
Very challenging production.
I think that goes for a few reasons.
A lot of CEOs might feel this way about almost every game they make, but I do think there
was some extra challenge here, because even though we were a...
We're a veteran studio, we've been around for a long time, but we had been 100% in PvP
multiplayer games for the last 5-6 years previous to making MechWarrior 5.
So, yeah, a lot of challenges in almost every area.
I'm going to move on to some questions on my part.
Just a heads up for folks, we've got about 20 minutes left in the stream, so if you've
got some questions, get them in chat.
We're going to talk about some other stuff, but we'll grab more before we're out of here.
Let's talk about the Epic Game Store.
This is a big new thing for the game world.
It's been literally a year, almost a year to the day since it launched.
That might not be entirely correct, but it's been a year since it kicked off at the...
Right around the time of the Game Awards, Hades launched on Early Access back then,
and you all were able to choose to be an Epic Games Store exclusive for your launch, which is,
you know, I think that's such an interesting decision in a world where, you know, you say,
when you say, okay, our market is PC players, we're only going to launch on PC, and then to say,
right now, the best choice for us is to launch on the Epic Games Store and exclusively work with
them.
What's that process been like and how did it feel working with Epic as a partner?
Well, big question. I would say, you know, the jury's still out a little bit to say if, you know, 100% everything works out the way we thought it would or planned it would when we put it together.
when we decided to take the Epic Games Store deal.
We took it for a number of reasons, which I'll get into, but I think we still have some,
maybe even like a few months to go here before we can say if all of it panned out like we
hoped it might.
But the reason that we took it, there was...
I've known the guys over there for quite a long time, as a lot of developers do, because
they've been working with Unreal Engine at one time or another over long careers.
You get to know the guys over there well.
But we were already using Unreal 4, obviously we started development in 2016.
And we had been a kind of company though that, you know, with MechWarrior Online,
we've been self-publishing and selling our own games on our own portal now for years and years.
So we were developing MechWarrior 5 not really, just kind of intending that it would be sold everywhere,
including our own portal.
And that was the plan.
And there really wasn't any knowledge. I didn't even know that Epic was necessarily even doing these types of deals.
You just started to kind of hear about it.
Maybe I would say...
Even in early... What? Early 2019?
You know, first quarter 2019, you start to hear about...
I think Metro Exodus is one of the first ones I kind of heard about where it's like,
oh, there's a thing going on here, you know, like, yeah, this is making the news.
OK, well, this is interesting.
Still didn't have any, you know, really nausea.
We do something like that.
At any rate, I had a conversation with Joe and it probably wasn't until
April or May that we had our first real conversation with them
that this came up as like, oh, there's there's there's something to consider here.
You know, there's an opportunity. There's a.
Now, a proposal to become one of these games.
And so for us, as any small developer
would say, is like, well, what are the pros and cons?
And one of the major benefits, of course, was
we felt very strongly that we were going to be able to make a better game
because it was going to...
Just the nature of switching over to the other store,
changing how the co-op is going to work with the Epic Games store
and a few other things that, you know, we were going to be able to...
We moved our release date from September to December, which was going to make it the full
one year delay from the original release date.
And we just had a pretty good idea of just how much extra
quality we were going to be able to put into the game.
So that was really the number one thing.
And then there's other deal terms that I won't get into specifics here, but there's other deal terms that make
just add on top of that, where it removes a significant amount of risk for
studios that...
or perhaps even all the risk.
And it says, well, then it almost becomes just,
you know, a bad decision if you don't,
because we've got a situation where you can make
a better game and remove the risk.
And if I'm talking about the type of game that I'm making
and who I'm making it for,
this becomes a very easy decision
because I want to deliver
the best MechWarrior 5 Mercenaries game I can.
That's my number one priority as a developer.
And, you know, if you do that,
You have a lot of faith that the rest of it was going to work itself out, because all
that really matters in the end is quality.
People want a quality product that they can play, and they can play for a very long time.
So that really made it pretty easy for us, and we started to work on it.
And I think, in hindsight, that part has definitely worked out.
The quality of the game is significantly higher than it would have been with an earlier release.
And, you know, working with Epic has been good.
They've been very, you know, very, very responsive.
And they take care of the developers that work with them very well,
because they understand that we're, you know,
we're under some challenges when it comes to, you know,
the marketplace still adapting to some of the things
they're not happy with about the exclusivities.
And then also understanding that their store is,
you know, behind when it comes to features
compared to the big stores like Steam.
And so...
They work really closely with you to prioritize the things that you need for your game
and to, you know, just work hard to, you know, get, you know, updates as fast as they can.
So, I think it's worked out pretty well for us.
I'm not sure I've answered all the intricacies of your question,
but that was... that's kind of a gist of our story on it.
And I think, you know, for MechWarrior fans out there,
you know, at the very least, should be...
I think happy that the game got the amount of resources and development time that we
were able to give it, and some of that was due to us doing that Epic Games Store deal.
Right on, um, uh, we can address one thing that folks in chat are asking about.
Uh, you mentioned before we started the stream that you had a new update going out today.
It looks like that update has arrived.
Um, uh, folks are asking where the patch notes will be posted.
And I guess, I guess, um, what...
We talk about the nature of making games in 2019,
it's different than making games in 2004,
different than making games in 1994.
And one of the things has to be that games are not just a fixed product
that goes on the shelves and is done.
They have patches and notes and updates and expansions.
And how are you all thinking about sort of...
You know, this isn't a live game, this isn't MechWarrior Online, but...
A, I guess the first question is, to help the folks in chat out,
what's going on with this patch? And then the follow-up question is,
how have you sort of structured the studio to be able to keep working on MechWarrior after it launched?
Yeah, it's a good question, because we've been really reminding ourselves of that too,
you know, saying, okay, this is not MechWarrior Online.
It takes a lot of reminders, even for ourselves in that regard.
But quickly, so the hotfix that just went out, this one is very small.
The patch notes will be on the Discord channel.
They'll be pinned there somewhere, for sure.
And this one in particular is just a few small fixes to some of the HOTAS controllers.
In particular, there was a crash when, if you had your HOTAS joystick...
plugged in as well as having foot pedals plugged in all at the same time it would
cause a crash and some other like kind of related aspects so that was something
one get out right away without waiting on anything else so that's what is in
this hotfix now it's not as confirmed yet but there's there's a plan for there
to be another hotfix on another one this week it'll probably be on Thursday
Possible it could slip to Friday, but I'm anticipating they'll be more like Thursday around this time
And that one's a little bigger and a little more significant. It's got
Several crash fixes
Some other I
Don't have the notes in front of me, but the notes will be up on discord. But that one
It's even got it's got some other
fixes for the tutorial mission with some
Subs by www.zeoranger.co.uk
optimizations we'll call it as well as some crashes.
So there's fairly significant fixes for stability we wanted to get out into the game
before the weekend hit.
So look for those patch notes on Thursday.
So hopefully the larger playing numbers of the weekend will have a better time
for us pushing out a couple of hotfixes here before the weekend hits.
And then, you know, if everything holds, there's likely to be at least one more
patch next week.
The first patch is the one before we break for Christmas, target around midweek, maybe as early as Tuesday.
That one is probably bigger than the other two combined, but basically just a number of fixes, we'll call it, before we break for Christmas.
So, it'll be a total of three patches, and obviously the goal here is to just make sure that the game is in as good a state as possible,
because it's been a long three years, and we're all tired, and we hope...
We can get a nice restful Christmas break between December 20th and about January 2nd.
So our plan is to not be fixed in the game during that period, so we want it to be working well.
And as far as in general, we have to remind ourselves that this isn't MechWarrior Online,
so we're not looking to do scheduled patches every two weeks like we did for the first
several years of MechWarrior Online, and then every month after that.
That comes down to every little tuning of every little balancing because it was a PvP game.
This will live, you know, come the new year a little more like a traditional, you know, premium product.
We hope there will be, you know, that we'll be launching the sales. We're like a little over 24
hours here, so I don't think we know yet just how much of a DLC plan there will be. We'll kind of
be dictated by how things go over here for the next few weeks. I think that's, um...
You know, that's fair. People understand that's probably the case.
And so, we'll be watching and waiting and we'll be designing and planning our DLC plan.
And so, most of the updates will come through more larger DLC type situation,
but I'm sure there'll be several planned free updates, of course, as well.
Anything that's like a bug fix or whatever, those are going to be free updates, of course.
Right on, right on.
Um, yeah, uh, it's time about 1251 here.
Uh, this footage is only, uh,
only because I was able to play the game so much before we got here, so...
But, you know, we got time to listen, to take your questions and talk more about Metal Warrior.
Um, man, uh...
Hey, uh, Russ, um, I am going to pull one question from chat.
This is kind of granular, but Doom Machine would like to know if there's anything you looked at as far as sensor ranges and enemy spawns being so close to players.
If that's being looked into at all?
Yeah, well at the moment we're not looking into it.
It has been a matter that has gone through several iterations before we released.
It's not perfect, so I think we would say we would continue to look at it.
Basically, you've got a challenging situation where we need enemies to spawn in for the action,
but also, especially in these wave-based mission types,
but also we're trying to account for the fact that we have up to three co-op players.
And it's like understanding exactly where all the co-op players are and which direction
everyone's looking is kind of tricky to make sure we get our spawn.
So I think we have a system right now where like, you know, like 90% of the time it works great.
And then...
Everyone's been a while, you're like, oh, wait a minute, how did he get there that quickly?
Like, I was just looking that way, then I turn around, there he is, 200 meters away.
So I think it's something that will definitely go through more fine-tuning, so I think you
can, it's safe to say you can expect at least some more fine-tuning and systems like that.
Right on, and then one more question from chat, Grace3PastryChef would like to know
if more mission types would be coming along to help add variety to the game.
I think so.
I think that probably...
You know, just at first blush, you know, this early on is probably something that fits more
into a DLC type environment where, you know, we might have a DLC pack and let's say it
will add a number of things, maybe another mini campaign and perhaps, you know, more
mission types.
And then likely if that happens, those new mission types potentially could just kind
of proliferate, you know, throughout the inner sphere.
Those sort of things are not decided yet, those are design decisions that we still have to make.
Hopefully forgive us that we really haven't had a lot of time to think about DLC yet.
I think the big studios, the big companies, of course they'd have this dialed in 30, 60, 90 day and stuff.
So being a small studio we need to be a little more reactionary than some.
But hopefully it feels like we're...
We're very close, you know, within days of being able to really sit back and go,
okay, what's next? And there have been some of those conversations happening already in the studio,
some of the artists, some of the designers, just a lot of brainstorming, a lot of whiteboarding,
a lot of... but also there's still a lot of reactionary stuff for us to do, like seeing
what people are saying. So we're just now like a day and a half into getting an idea of what,
you know, the players feel like.
We are making decisions over the next couple of weeks and there is no shortage of great
ideas both internally and with the players.
I'm sure if the game and the success justifies it because I'm sure we could work on updates
for this game for a very long time.
Right on. I'll follow up on that question with, you was talking there about being a small company,
you've mentioned a few times, you know, being a 70-person team. As a CEO, I guess, like, how does
it feel, you know, to like be making, keeping a mid-sized company alive and afloat out there in
today's world? Is there anything you think you've done right by your team for like making them want
to stay there and work with you, like making them, you know, not...
Not scaling up to 200 people like what have you sort of learned like as a small shop?
Keeping keeping your doors open and stuff. That's a vague question. I'm sorry about that. No, it's okay. No, it's a good question. I
I'm sure it's a matter of opinion because I'm sure there's plenty of devs out there. Maybe that belong to very small
you know indie shops, and they're thinking wait a minute 70s on a small studio, but
From my perspective it really is you know, I've
You've been doing this 20 years now.
We have our, so December 20th is our launch party
and also our 20 year anniversary is our studio.
So we've gone through all the years
where we were 12 to 15 and to 30 to 40 to 60 to 70.
And it's interesting, you know,
back when we were like 40 or 50 then or 30
and the big studios were 70.
And now it's kind of the scaling of how much.
Bigger things getting done and what it takes to create games.
And now that we're 70, we really haven't climbed out of that small to mid-tier yet.
Now those studios are 100 to 120.
So I think we're still a small studio and I think the greatest accomplishment has been
that we have kept an independent development studio open for 20 years.
That is not easy.
And if you think it is, do me a favor, go start a game studio.
You know, have 70 staff and let me know in 20 years if you're still around.
It takes a lot to go right and a lot of hard work and we've managed to do it, which is grateful for.
So that's the part I'm most proud of is tallying up just the number of months that I've been able to employ people
and keep them employed and be able to make games that we all like.
So that's...
That has been a 20 year journey, and I'm not sure where it ends yet, but not yet.
We're going to be around for a bit longer anyhow, and we got a game to work on here,
so I guess that's all any independent developer can ask for.
Right on.
We are about to close up, but I'm going to get one more question in from chat, because
it's just such a good one.
Ziety1 would like to know, what was a big aha moment during development?
I almost feel like this is going to be like the other one, it's like, well we had about
ten of them and every one of them felt like, oh my god, an aha moment.
I'll take a little bit of a different look at this to answer it.
I'm probably going to, the way I'll answer this I think is like when we had a moment
where it was like, aha, you know, this thing is going to work.
You know, this thing is, it's going to happen.
This game is coming together and I think it might even be pretty good.
And I think that probably came, oh boy, maybe even as late as six or so months ago when
we put together this urban test environment, city environment, which finally for the first
time had kind of brought...
everything together both mechs, the mech combat, turrets, the vehicles, but most importantly
sort of a final garrison, city garrison environment where all the tall buildings and the fully
destructible city environment that you see in some of these urban settings.
And we were able to jump in there and we were able to play and I'm running around the city
walking right through buildings and chasing a light mech around the city.
As I missed, the bullets were obliterating the side of other buildings.
And I sat back, had a big smile on my face, and I was just like,
okay, this is gonna work.
This is really fun, and there's really nothing else out there like it.
And that was an a-ha moment for me to kind of give me a lot of confidence that
there was still a ton of work to do, but that we could bring it home.
Right on.
And everyone in chat, folks like Commissar Punk, Thronny Joe,
YourBloodMarauder, y'all are great, y'all are asking some great questions.
I would ask them all for you if I had the time, but I do not.
Sadly, time is a finite resource.
And, you know, wait, that got a little dark.
OK, we're going to we're going to walk away from that thread.
Yeah. Ross, thank you so much for joining us today.
I can see we've had some new folks join us in the last part
of the half and sort of last few minutes.
I would encourage you to go back and watch the earlier part of the stream.
We're going to archive all this for you to get some other questions answered.
For folks like Sprogue who are just coming in because of the new patch,
Russ has already explained that those patch notes will be available in the Discord.
Russ, is the Discord also a place where people can provide feedback
and ask some of the great questions that they're asking?
Yeah, there's a whole bunch of channels.
There's feedback channels, bug report channels, everything you'd expect.
Got it. So, uh, I wish, hmm, ah, I wish I had a link to the Discord handy I could drop in chat, but, uh, um, where's a place they can find a link to that?
Oh boy, um...
I'm the worst at these sort of things, um, all I know is, uh, the server name is MechWarrior5mercenaries, so...
Yeah, you'll find it.
Right on, I am, uh, uh, trying to...
I'm going to find a link, and I unfortunately cannot.
But yeah, let me see.
Yeah, with that, sorry for stumbling over my words there, we are going to wrap things
up for today.
Thank you all so much for joining us.
Russ, if they've got any questions for you, just like us devs, you know, moving away from
the fan questions, where's a good place they can reach out to you about that?
Best places, discord channel, um, you'll see us listed there.
I don't know how your success rate would be on direct messaging, but, um, Tina is a
community manager and, um, usually being able to, you know, talk to her if there's,
she can come directly to us and say, Hey, you know, here's something I think
that was noteworthy.
I got this question from somebody and she can ask us.
Right on. I was able to drop the Discord link in chat for folks who do not have it yet.
And with that, we are going to wrap things up for the day.
Thank you all so much for watching, and Russ, thank you for joining us.
You're welcome.
I forgot to do more of my closing spiel because I was so focused on the Discord link.
If you are yourself a game developer interested in game development, this is GDC, the GDC Twitch channel.
We are always here talking about the art and business of making games.
If you happen to drop by on Friday, we're gonna be doing a stream with the folks behind Age of Empires 2 Definitive Edition.
So I'm just spending this week reliving my 90s childhood apparently with PC games.
If you join us in the new year, we will have more streams from other great devs as we ramp up for GDC in March.
If you're a developer yourself, we'd love to have you out at the show.
And if you are interested in coming to the show, scroll down and you can get some info on registration.
If you click the follow button on this channel, you will get notifications when we go live.
And not only do we have those interviews I mentioned,
but we will have the Game Developers Choice Awards and IGF Awards ceremonies live at the show.
And so hopefully some other cool stuff too.
With that, I would like to wish everyone a happy Wednesday.
And that's it. Enjoy your MEX. Enjoy blowing stuff up.
Thank you.