SORRY YOU HAD TO WATCH THIS
**Philip sings the starry night away**
Good afternoon, everyone.
My name is Gary Scheinman.
I scored Bioshock Infinite.
I actually scored all three of the Bioshock games.
Bioshock Infinite, I guess, is Bioshock 3, in a way.
I don't think they want to call it that.
They've been fantastic games to work on.
I'm very grateful to have been involved in these three really,
really beautifully made games.
And I've really just been honored that they chose me
and that they appreciated my music.
got the gig because I did a game called Destroy All Humans.
And the audio director, Emily Ridgway,
went to work in Rational Games and said,
you've got to hire Gary Scheinman.
And so they did.
And so it's been a very important.
part of my career, these three really, really beautiful games.
But Infinite really was...
Bioshock 1 had its own unique style,
and Bioshock 2 also utilized the style of Bioshock 1.
It was really, it was a true...
It was set in Rapture, this city under the sea, in the same period.
So it really made sense to use the score, or the style of the score, from the original
Bioshock.
But when we got to Bioshock Infinite, everyone, including myself, did not want to use the
material from Bioshock 1 and 2.
It just did not make sense.
It was a completely unique game.
There are parallels.
And we'll talk a little bit about that
during my presentation today.
But really, we had a completely fresh game.
It was set in a different period, 1912,
in a city in the sky, almost sort of the polar opposite
in a way, 180 degrees.
And the bright, everything in Rapture
was dark and dingy and drippy and wet.
And everything in Bioshock Infinite
is bright and sunny and blazing light.
So it really was a different game.
I had.
I can't not mention the partners that I had in the game.
First of all, the entire team at Irrational Games.
Unfortunately, they did close their doors.
But it's a great development team.
Ken Levine, the creative director, is, I call him the Steve Jobs of video games.
He really is a creative genius and I love working with him.
Jim Bonney was the music director and Patrick Bothrop was the audio director
and all those guys really did amazing things to make this game,
this really, really wonderful game.
And I am a contracted composer, so they were in Boston,
and I was in LA basically throwing stuff over the fence
and saying, how's this?
When we first started, originally, I mean,
because Bioshock 1 and 2 had been successful,
there was no problem getting a budget
for an orchestra, a large orchestra.
But, and initially we thought, hey, this is going to be orchestral, you know.
What do you want?
Want to go to London?
Where should we go?
And it was like, okay, well, that's all cool and great.
But it didn't turn out that way.
A lot of things didn't turn out that way.
And I think for good reason, and I'm grateful that they didn't.
The first music, some of the first music I wrote for them was a...
Well, I wrote a trailer.
I wrote the score to a trailer, which was a big presentation trailer.
And then they had like a...
a press release conference, and it was a live, and they showed images from the game,
and they wanted me to write some original music. So I'm going to play a little bit of that, just so that
this was my initial early concept of what the score might sound like.
Find out more at open.gdn.com
And I don't know if any of you noticed it, but at the end you hear Mike country tis of thee in minor.
Which, because this is a dystopian world, and it's set in this city that's very American,
and everything about it is patriotic, and yet what it is, it's a breakaway city,
and it is really sort of a dystopian America.
What would happen if everything went horribly wrong?
So I thought that was appropriate.
And then we, I messed around with a lot of different approaches.
And it really wasn't until E3, there was an E3 the year before it came out, and they made a presentation there.
And they had this AI character called Elizabeth, artificial intelligence.
And she wasn't, she was...
an important character, but not the central character.
But the press, everything written about that E3
presentation had Elizabeth, Elizabeth, Elizabeth.
And it became really, really such an important part
of what people were discussing on the game
that it really had an influence on the whole creative team.
And they decided to elevate her character to really
your partner in the game.
And so this artificial intelligence
becomes your partner.
And it was at that point that I realized
that she was really important and that she
I ought to write a theme for her.
And so I wrote a theme, but I didn't want,
knowing Ken Levine, Ken really responds
to live performances.
So I said to Jim, I said, you know,
I don't really want to send this theme over to anyone.
I want to record it live.
And he goes, well, you know,
we really don't have a budget for that,
just to do mock-ups.
And I go, well, I'm going to come out of pocket.
I really want to record this.
So I recorded it with one cello and one viola.
We did some overdubs.
And so.
I did this really, really simple tonal triadic theme for her,
but it was an important point in the realization for the approach for the entire score.
You
Thank you for watching.
Ready?
One.
Get set.
Go!
So that simple theme, I sent that to Ken and Ken loved, I mean really loved it.
It really moved him and it became my realization that I had that okay,
this is the direction for the score. It's not orchestral, this is a really simple
score and this involves really, really
beautifully played, expressive solo instruments,
and it somehow expressed the sadness of this world
and expressed its, I don't know,
I didn't, this is the thing, all throughout the game,
they never told me how the game ended.
I was scoring the end of the game and didn't understand what it was exactly.
Because they were so secretive.
But I knew there was this deep mystery.
And so this simple music really was an epiphany for me and an epiphany for everyone in the
game.
So, the realization was...
Keep it simple.
Small string ensembles, not orchestral.
And the positive response to live string players
that Ken had.
And then I did something that I've never done before.
And it was really worked on this.
I don't know if it would work for any other project.
But what I did was I said to Jim, I said, look,
we have all this money.
We're not going to spend it.
I think I have a way that's going to really work for me and for Ken and for you.
I want to record my demos with live players.
And he said, well, let's try that. He was open to that.
So I did a couple of sessions with live players, and Ken was really digging the result.
When I'd mock things up, he wasn't digging it or understanding it.
When he heard it with live players, it was like...
Yes, that's it.
That sounds great.
And it was just a realization.
And I've never had more fun than working in that manner.
It was just fantastic.
I'd write the music.
And then a week later, I'd bring a string quartet in,
and we'd record for three hours.
And two weeks later, I'd have.
And eventually, it led me to the ideal string section
for the game, which was.
ten string players, three violins, three violas, three cellos, and one double bass.
And that seemed to be sort of like ideal.
Before that, I had as few as three sessions with string quartets,
string quartet and double bass, just all sorts of different ensembles,
and all of them with really great players.
It was done in L.A., it was done at AFM,
because it was grandfathered in from the old Bauschok game.
And it was just totally working for him.
And it was a really interesting way
to really generate really cool music.
And really, by the time I was nearly finished scoring it,
most of the score had been recorded and was done.
There was just an extra session or two
that had to be put together.
So there were several categories of this game
the music would fit into.
Now, there's also all the source music.
I did not write the source music.
Jim Bonney hired a bunch of really talented people
to do this fantastic job on the source music,
really, really brilliant stuff.
a barbershop quartet singing Beach Boy songs.
Just really cool stuff.
And if you play the game and you understand
how this game is sort of unstuck in time and anything
is possible because time interacts with it
in bizarre and crazy ways, they understand
how a Beach Boy song could appear in 1912 being
sung by a barbershop quartet.
But the scripted events, scripted events
are really essentially little vignettes,
little movie vignettes that are locked to time.
So you can score them like a picture.
And really, the player has free agency, could walk away from them.
And in fact, if you're playing the game for the fourth time,
you're probably going to walk away from all the scripted events.
But first time, you're definitely going to watch the scripted events,
because something important is happening.
And so most of these needed to be scored.
So I'm going to play.
This was a really interesting experiment initially.
And really, once you get up to Columbia,
the city in the sky, you end up in this little grotto.
And then you open the door, and there is Columbia.
And it's beautiful.
It's really beautiful.
It's like.
It's not a dark place, at least at this point.
I did not want the music to be scary at all.
And yet, I didn't want the music just to be happy-go-lucky.
So what I did was I combined...
I listened to Stephen Foster songs.
for a couple of days, Stephen Foster being the great American songwriter of the 19th century,
and maybe there's a little New World Symphony. And I wrote this really simple, pretty melody
with some simple chord changes, but then underneath it I added a chromatic, sort of slithery
second layer that I thought represented what potentially is going to come at you in the city.
thanks for watching, leading to this final video!
So, and I used the video you see here as what I composed to.
I just took that video and I thought it appropriate to bring that video.
So, I just thought I'd show you this.
I decided because I only had 10 players and because I wasn't sure how this was going to
work when I recorded it, I thought I need to separate the tonal part from the chromatic
part.
So...
Here just really is just a very simple,
with just sustained chords.
Alyssa Park was the first violinist
and she's just playing this really beautifully
sweet solo, poco vibrato.
And I decided to do very little with the accompaniment
with the tone part because I didn't think
the accompaniment, I thought if I made it busy,
it would be fighting the other chromatic part.
All right, so that's that.
And then here's a look at the chromatic parts.
So this chromatic part is actually quite complex,
but played pianissimo so that it didn't fight it.
But basically it's all strings.
I used a little celesta as well.
["Celesta"]
And I thought, as I was separating them, I thought maybe there's a spot, and one thing
to realize as a composer for a video game is that you never, there's no music, well
there's, not always, but a lot of music can get utilized in different spots.
So I thought, okay, I can deliver both of these to Jim, and he can use this in some
other spot in the game, and I think he did, I'm not absolutely certain of that.
So that was that experiment, and it really worked quite nicely.
That music won the Gang Award for instrumental music of the year last year.
So that was all very cool.
And then there was another interesting aspect to the score,
and that was there's these characters called the Lutece twins,
and they are sort of in on the joke.
They really kind of know what's happening
throughout all these different permutations of time and interactions.
And so they're sort of talking in what appears to be nonsense all the time,
which only makes sense when you get to the end of the game
and you realize that they know what all the different possibilities,
and that really in this...
alternative world, there's like millions, or perhaps an infinite, that's the term, infinite,
possibilities of how this, things can turn out. And in the end, it does, you know,
Booker, the Booker character, which you play, the solution is that he has to die. And that can,
that's the only way to end it from being a tragic story. But here's the test twins.
They... well at least she...
invented the technology that allows the city to flow.
Giant balls?
Quantum particles suspended in space-time at a fixed height.
So, not giant balls?
But the thing is, my book said they disappeared several years ago.
I didn't.
But I don't.
You sure that's right?
Something tells me they're not exactly what they appear to be.
I was going to have to go to court.
No.
That's injunctive.
That's not injunctive.
I don't think the syntax is important.
I'm not telling you what I'm trying to do.
A little bit of importunity there.
I'm just not allowed to go to court.
I know the syntax.
There she jumps in.
And the other woman is like,
You see, the Lichess twins are in all these different places that you cross, and you don't...
It doesn't make any sense until you understand that they're just completely unstuck in time and can do whatever the hell they want.
And then finally, I thought it was interesting.
This is the one spot in the game where the music in Bioshock Infinite
actually was similar to the original score,
because you end up in Rapture.
If you've played the game, you know you end up briefly in the city of Rapture
because Elizabeth has this power to open tears, literally tears.
She can open a tear in time.
And when in danger, you can kind of dive through it.
And they end up...
actually in Rapture and they take a ride in a bathysphere,
which is this submarine.
So I wrote a cue that kind of sounded like Rapture music,
you know, from my original score.
Thanks for watching !
And you notice this open fifth sound, which is something that's used in the listening
theme, became sort of a norm motif throughout the score.
God, how beautiful.
It's like the stars.
Are you going to open it?
No, it's not worth it.
Damn it.
I thought once we were here, I could fully control-
So that oar motif gets used throughout the game,
because to me it sort of represented the infinite.
There's something magical about a fifth
that's in relationship to the overtone series.
So that ostinato figure literally appears
in a lot of cues throughout the game
and worked quite nicely as tying together.
It's a simple, simple technique,
but it just worked really beautifully.
And then I wrote, they needed some mood music,
they needed some ambient music,
so I decided that I would write some,
use some extended techniques
and write some aleatory for this.
And I thought I'd show you just a few of the cues.
And these I handed off to Jim and said,
just use these wherever you need some mood,
just, you know, whatever.
And this is all done with small string ensembles.
If you think you need, and one lesson here is if you think you need a large string ensemble
to do extended techniques, you really don't.
A lot can be done with a string quartet.
just simple chords using quarter tone detuning.
It's just creating some mood.
I think up is the last one.
And as this moves along, they get more and more out of tune, quarter tone-wise.
The oscillation gets wider and wider.
But it was very effective and very helpful.
So combat music became a really interesting struggle.
in this game.
Because even though I'd found this idea
and that everyone seemed really pleased with,
which was to use these small string ensembles,
there still was the feeling that combat music
has to have large resources,
that we had to have an orchestra to really play combat,
to really make that work.
And so I'm gonna play, I did a few combat cues,
and it was really, the controversy was apparently raging
in Boston, little known to the rest of the country,
about whether this combat music had to be orchestral or not
and people were sort of like fighting Ken on it.
Ken was feeling that the orchestral wasn't working.
So I'm gonna play, here's a orchestral cue.
I know the video's very fuzzy,
but this is what I was writing to.
These are just samples because we didn't have to work with them.
We didn't deploy the support.
So hot.
All right, so I think, I mean, there's nothing wrong with that piece of combat music for
this chaotic combat sequences that were common in Bioshock, but Ken was feeling that it was
not unique enough.
And one of the, I remember from when I first started working on the original Bioshock,
Emily called me and said, okay, she goes, here's the direction for the score.
It can't sound like any other film, game, or TV score ever heard before.
A little intimidating, okay?
Well, sort of this is the same direction, okay?
Can't sound like any film, TV, or game show before.
So I started experimenting around with small ensembles.
What can be done combat-wise with small ensembles?
And I think it became actually a very interesting technique.
I've to be very careful here because theЯЯЯЯЯЯЯяяяёаааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааЊааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааааа
Alright, so, let's see what happens.
I'm just going to stop the stream.
Alright, now we get the idea.
It's very annoying, but it really worked great in the game.
It really worked great.
It really helped create this sense of things
are completely out of control.
This is really, it really facilitated
what we wanted to accomplish in this game
in terms of the combat music.
And there's several different genres of this,
but essentially what I did was I created
this really repetitive.
percussion ostinato figures, and I just kept them going.
I just, just relentless, they're just relentless.
And then over that, added these figures,
these aleatoric figures, sometimes rhythmic figures
using the strings, and I'm gonna show you
how I accomplished that.
And I played most, we did bring in a percussionist one day,
but I played much of the percussion,
and I didn't quantize it either.
I kept it very ragged, because my thinking on it was like,
like a drum circle at Venice Beach.
Any of you ever been to Venice Beach?
It's like a bunch of guys smoking dope, playing drums, okay?
And it's not necessarily quantized.
And I thought that...
I thought that that would be really effective here.
That it's almost like just a bunch of guys getting their nerve up
to go kill a bunch of other guys.
And I thought that that kind of worked.
So it was just me just playing this stuff in unquantized.
And every now and then I'd be so out of breath.
I'd nudge a note a little bit.
So that was also part of the approach on it.
So what I did was I wrote tons of little, short,
aleatoric, intense moments.
And I'm going to show you a few.
Just nails on chalkboard type of cues, you know.
And then there's another example using basically just taking all these little bits of aleatory
and sort of just massaging them together and making them work and overlapping them in any
ways that felt creative to me.
So it's really grating, but it really worked wonders in combat.
It just created this sense of complete chaos, and it's frightening.
And that was really what they wanted to achieve.
And it was all done, really, using these small string ensembles.
It really...
So I learned something.
I was fighting for the orchestral combat music.
Of course, I like to have an orchestra to record with too.
So maybe there was a bit of selfishness there.
But really, I really felt that you can't have combat
without an orchestra in this context.
But I was wrong.
And Ken was right.
And it is a lesson to be learned that very often,
your creative partners, the people you're working with,
They know their game better than you know their game.
You are a partner, and sometimes you have some good ideas,
and they'll totally recognize it when you come up with them.
But sometimes they know something.
Well, they weren't telling me how the game ended, either.
So, uh, but they knew something,
and Ken in particular is this just brilliant guy,
and he just is very intuitive.
He can't say, well, it needs to be aleatoric
with small string ensembles and a ragged percussion track.
He can't say that.
Because he doesn't have that musical knowledge.
But he can, he'll tell you when he doesn't like something.
And so it really pushed me to create these sorts of.
And here I am.
And these are just, and the interesting thing,
another thing that I learned was,
you would think if you doubled it,
it would make it more intense.
How many thinks it gets more intense when you double it?
Well, it doesn't, it gets less intense
because it takes all the jagged edges off
and it, because they're all gonna be,
you know, flamming with one another.
And, uh.
And so really it was a single pass that was the most effective.
And I would double these, and we'd listen back and go,
whoa, it doesn't sound as intense.
It's like really not driving anymore.
So it became clear that
these instruments play with this sort of dry intensity
like, I'm in this space,
and a single pass was much more effective
than just doubling and tripling.
I mean, I could have taken out 10 strings and made it 30,
but it wasn't effective.
Just write words like scream on top of the track.
And then let them tell, you know, scream.
So...
A couple more. Violent, intense.
So just really annoying stuff, OK?
The more annoying, the better.
And the players were a little annoyed by it, too, at times.
But it really just worked so well.
I think, um, so here's another.
Then there was another, uh, well, let me see.
This is a little bit, just a little bit
of some of those techniques.
You can hear some of the stuff you just heard.
And me just sort of creating a montage out of it.
And using them and doubling them.
And literally taking the audio, putting it into my DAW,
and just moving it around until it made sense to me.
All right.
And then there was another type of combat cue,
which was really sort of written out, sort of through composed.
And really, it involved using sort of like violent string
ostinatos.
So here's.
Again, though, with these repetitive drama Venice beach stunts.
I actually thought of going to Venice beach to see if I could get there.
But then I thought, it won't match temples.
The better of that I didn't.
I forgot my ask.
And Ken also said something, because I mean, the composer in me wants these types of cues
to be, to change and to do, to, you know, Jerry Goldsmith was one of my great teachers.
I mean, I didn't, he didn't study with them privately or anything, but just listening
to his music, and when he did comedy, he would just like all of a sudden go to something
quite different and do something else.
But Ken said, Ken didn't want that.
He really wanted what I'd call like musical meatloaf.
Like wherever you cut it, it's kind of the same.
Here, or there's sort of, you know.
So, and he was right, because he really felt like
if this music is changing too much,
it's gonna sound like you're catching things,
and he didn't want that.
Again, he knew his game, and he pushed me
to do some really brilliant things, I think.
And then there was just, the final is just layered combat,
because there's times, there were times in the game
when the character would be fighting these, you know,
game characters and he would, Booker would duck away,
you know, kind of get away from it.
So basically, just crossfade to a less intense version
of the same track.
And there are three layers.
There's active, passive, and then what Jim called turtling,
like a little turtle getting in a shell.
So here's just some example.
Here would be the active.
There was a lot of combat in this game.
And so then here would be the passive version.
much less intense.
It's completely in sync, tempo-wise,
but basically, so you can easily crossfade
back and forth between that track
and the other combat, the full active version.
A simple technique, but it worked well here.
And then turtling, in the turtling,
I added some tension strings.
because the percussion is almost gone, everything is almost gone.
So I just felt it needed some kind of tension.
So I actually added this extra layer of tension strings.
But again, totally in sync with the other two cues.
So you could easily ramp it up to the full active within a bar
and you're there.
So.
A couple of things that I would recommend in sort of like closing here and before I
take some questions from you guys.
I've always tried, when possible, to suggest music that I just somehow intuitively feel would be useful for the game.
I just have some sense that, hey, this cue, and thus the Elizabeth cue, which was sort of a realization that,
hey, this team has found the center of this game now, the Elizabeth character, now I have to write some music for it.
And that was an epiphany for myself,
in terms of finding the style for the game,
and also in terms of Ken really going, yes, yes, this is it.
This is the style for this.
And there was another cue I did that was called AD, which
is literally, originally, I was thinking, well,
maybe I need to write a Booker theme.
So I wrote this.
And they liked this music a lot, but at first,
they had nowhere to put it.
And then Jim says, I found a spot for it.
So he ended up using it in this moment.
where you find out really how Elizabeth gets unstuck in time
because she's going.
It's complex.
It's not worth going to, but if you played the game,
you know it's this really complex set of circumstances
where it only makes sense, actually,
when you go to Wikipedia and read.
No, I'm kidding.
It does make sense, but it is complex.
It's really complex.
And really, I had to read online like, oh, OK.
I see now.
It all totally makes sense.
Because it's a really, I mean, one of the things
that Irrational is and has been really good at
is this story, you know?
And so they created a very complex story.
But I just thought I'd sort of play the AD theme, which
is originally the Booker theme.
and
Okay, and I'll talk to you soon.
Bye!
This morning I told a story of something I read years ago that's always stuck with me
and it's always helped me.
And it was something that Stravinsky, Igor Stravinsky said.
And he said that, and he wrote at the piano.
That's where he didn't have any samples.
So he wrote at the piano.
And he said, if you...
to the piano and say, start writing,
is I don't know where to start.
I just, I have no idea. It's infinite.
No pun intended.
But if you play two notes,
I can start composing immediately.
And so, and that always struck me
as really critical,
and something that we need to think about
is whether any kind of creative aspect
of games or anything, really,
it's like, get started.
Find your two notes. Find something.
And then take that.
and then see where that leads you.
And so this is really how I found my two notes in this game.
And it was a fantastic experience.
I received the BAFTA for this score, which was incredible.
I wish I'd gone to London.
I didn't, unfortunately.
Because I didn't know if I'd win or not.
Actually, the end of that week, I was heading up to Seattle
to record a Shadow of the Mordor game.
So.
In any event, it's been all three of the games.
I don't know if they'll make another Bioshock.
I hope they do, but I'm not...
I kind of think Ken has gone on to different stories to tell.
So in any event, if you have questions,
I'm happy to take some questions from you guys.
And...
Great presentation.
Thank you.
With the smaller ensemble, you mentioned earlier that it can be, not intimidating, but it can be preferable to use a large orchestra for combat music.
I thought so, I thought.
Right. Was part of that transition in the way of thinking influenced by, in the games like Bioshock where you have so many different sound effects considerations with the vigors or plasmids, all the different weapon sounds.
I found that when I was playing Infinite, I thought that.
the music really cut through a tremendous amount because of the less that was going on
in terms of not as many timbres getting buried by a gunshot, etc.
Do you think that that...
I do think that that worked.
I certainly... I wasn't conscious of that because I was sending music to Jim
and Jim was implementing it and going,
yeah, this is working, or if there was a problem with it,
okay, it's working up to here, you need to fix it, and he'd tell me why.
And it is sort of like the contractor's dilemma.
I mean, you aren't in-house.
You're sort of doing the best you can from afar, but there is an advantage to being in-house.
as well. But yeah, I do think that that definitely was very effective in helping that. But again,
I mean, it's just always be open to a paradigm shift. That's another thing that I just keep
telling myself, because no matter how certain you are of this is the way something ought
to be done, you need to be open to the possibility that something that you completely different.
I mean, Mahler said, Gustav Mahler said, in his late 50s, is, I am always the student.
he's always learning something new.
So I learned something new in this,
and I learned it from the development team,
who, especially Ken, who just kept pushing
until he got what he wanted.
And then I'm like, yes, this is frickin' awesome.
This is great.
So.
Great, thank you.
Sure.
That was a great presentation. Thanks for sharing with us.
My question is, when you're writing this aleatory music that is so intensely emotional and dependent
on the performance, how do you cope with not knowing exactly how it's going to sound until
you get to the studio?
Well, I mean, you have to do a study of aleatoric music.
You have to have some sense of how it's going to sound.
If you've never written anything aleatoric,
or you haven't studied the scores
of the great aleatoric composers,
then you may, in fact, kind of make some mistakes
and find yourself.
with unsatisfactory results.
So I felt fairly confident that what I'd written
was going to be effective.
And then you're there.
You talk to the players, and you adjust.
If something's not working, you just go, OK,
let's try that down a fifth, because it's just not
quite working in that register.
Or can you give that any more?
At one point I asked that and then one of the bass players broke his bow and he just left.
He was so pissed. You know, he was doing Colenio and I'm just thinking, you know,
I mean, you should use a pencil for that or a piece of wood, but in any event.
So yeah, you adjust on the scene.
But I think you need to do some study of it
so that you are confident that you're not wasting your time.
But in this context, we had the money,
so if anything really didn't work,
there was lots of stuff that ended up on the cutting room floor
that just didn't quite work.
But we had the, you know...
We knew we were on the right direction.
So if every single aleatoric little vignette was not useful,
then so be it.
That's OK, too.
Hi, Gary.
Congratulations on a great achievement.
Thank you.
Actually, following up on the aleatoric element, a lot of us
would face the actual predicament
of having to have the music reviewed.
before going to the studio to record it.
So we would face the issue of having to try and mock up these...
This is the fix. Hire small string ensembles.
Yeah, but obviously, but, like, to have, even before you go to the studio,
to have the game director hear your music...
beforehand. How do you?
Oh, well, yes, that that is a challenge. If you haven't, I
mean, I now have a whole library of stuff that I can sort of
drawn to use as placeholders until it gets replaced. But you
know, you can you literally could go anywhere in the
literature and take snippets of music and use it as placeholder say it's this
is kind of what I want to achieve so I would say as long as it doesn't end up
in the game I think that's a perfectly cool thing to do as or or and they're
also like symphobia and other libraries do have
you know, pre-rendered, uh, aleatoric tracks.
Problem with those is that so many of them have been heard a lot on television
and used incessantly.
So I try not to use them, uh, even though some of them are quite good
because it just, they just feel.
worn out.
So, you know, and by the way, you can take traditional samples and you can do things
with them, detune them, and do some really creative things with them.
So, and if you just can bring in one player, bring in one player, bring in a violinist
and then overdub and create some effects, you know?
Yeah, it wouldn't sound even close to how effective that is when you actually have those
musicians together and they're like...
they're playing their instrument that way.
Right, but look, you have to wing it to some extent.
So you have to experiment and you have to really try to find
and maybe the answer is to find some things
from the pre-existing tracks and say,
this is gonna get replaced by something similar.
Okay, thank you.
Sure.
So one of the most effective elements of Bioshock Infinite's music for me was that the ending flourish when combat is over and all the enemies have been defeated.
And I thought you might get into this, but you actually didn't. So I was just curious, was that your idea? Was that something you talked with Ken and Jim about?
Like, how did that particular...
uh, flourish at the end of combat come about.
Wait, say, wait, wait, what, in which queue?
The, the ending, you know, when you, all the enemies are defeated
and there's sort of that dissonant, like, uh, I'm not, I'm not even sure.
Right, right, this, this gap.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, it's, it's, it's this very effective, just, I'm not a musician,
so I just, like, hear it, just, for me, it was an incredibly effective notion that,
okay, combat is ended, this.
like period of intensity has ended and now you're safe.
Um, uh, so, I mean, do, uh, do you recall what, uh, at that point in the game or in
that point in combat?
You'd have to play that for me so that I recall exactly what they requested there.
Yeah.
In that case, wouldn't that have been something that they requested then?
Yes, they would have requested that.
And Jim asked, sometimes he asked for stingers that he ended up using in different spots
that I wasn't even aware of.
So I created, I had literally probably spent an hour just doing stingers.
And I wrote tons and tons and tons of them.
you know, we recorded them and then just here, use them any way you want.
Okay. Well, it was very effective nonetheless.
Thanks. Thank you.
Hi.
During the combat music, I found a lot of it when I was personally playing that a lot of the percussive elements
and even
the strings in the way that they would interact with each other
Sounded quite a bit like alarms was that a conscious decision or was that just sort of a happy accident that you know?
It sort of sounded like an old firebell from that era or like the the old crank
Sirens that were on on fire trucks at that point that just it
the the choices made felt
Like they were conscious as opposed to just like oh great that worked
Well, I don't I wasn't thinking about that and I didn't actually use any old alarms. I certainly had some metal
percussion instruments that possibly
You know were what you were thinking of when you heard those and I would you know have them banging away
probably just me playing.
Although one day I did bring in a percussionist
and had him play all day.
And that was a great experience.
But it just turned out that I have a lot of percussion.
And the percussion was working.
And by the way, we really were fighting against not
wanting to have the big Hans Zimmerisch drums.
We wanted small drums and smaller instruments,
just like that some human being might actually
be playing in the real world.
Again, back to my Venice Beach sort of analogy.
But we wanted, like, they didn't need to be these giant.
As a matter of fact, those were too cinematic and too,
and, and, uh,
Ken actually would reject those.
So we went with smaller instruments, smaller drums.
And sometimes Jim would record some drum and send it to me.
He goes, I think this is really cool.
And I'd go, OK.
And I'd make a whole sample library out of it
and would use it.
And they were.
pretty they were pretty simple sounding it might just be a tom-tom like in a
basic tom-tom like from
Indian tom-tom or something like that, but there was just something cool about that that just was very effective. We just again we just
Upset the applecart and and went in a direction that was quite different, and and I thought it was very effective
Thank you sure
Hi. Very early on in the combat in the game, there's a sequence of events as Booker's firing his pistol.
First it's just a shot, and then it's a shot with a piano stab, and then the third shot is with like orchestral or string layers.
How did that come about? I think it's brilliant. It invokes fear at first and then empowerment.
That's, I mean, that's probably...
Jim Bonney just taking my material and using it in really creative, cool ways.
Yeah, it seemed to cross between being music and sound design and implementing.
Yeah, he was, I mean, that's the cool thing about having a full-time music director like Nathan.
You know, they can focus totally on the music and think about it sometimes for a year or two.
So, very creative.
solutions like that can be found.
And he was asking for a lot of different things from me,
some of which I didn't even know how exactly they'd get used
and didn't know until I saw them in use.
Cool, thanks.
Sure.
First off, I want to thank you for composing A Louder Than Air.
It's fantastic.
My question is one of inspiration.
I guess in sort of some unfair comparisons,
the combat music is like that of Johnny Greenwood.
And for me especially, it's sort of
that there will be blood score where that oil derrick is
burning down.
And I've seen that compared in a few articles.
And I know that Mr. Levine is a huge film head.
So in terms of inspiration, do you ever
look at anything like that?
Or do you try to keep everything that's been done before?
I like that score for Let There Be Blood.
I was writing aleatoric music before that score existed,
certainly, so it wasn't an epiphany for me
to hear that score, but I thought it was very effective.
I love that score, that Johnny Greenwood score.
Very cool.
Thanks.
Hi Gary, it's sort of similar to his question,
but I was curious for either the aleatoric elements
or the more tonal string writing,
did you look to any classical pieces for inspiration to?
Well, I listened to a lot of Stephen Foster
for the one cue that I,
and also the New World Symphony.
because I thought that had a very Americana vibe to it.
And also Charles Ives.
Oh, okay.
As well, because I thought, I mean,
Charles Ives really wrote a lot
of really cool Americana music.
So those were also inspirations for me.
That's great, thank you.
Sure.
Thanks for this.
You know, regarding the whole montage of aleatoric, these little aleatoric pieces, and you mentioned
putting them together in different ways, did you ever...
Did you ever have them or the music system actually sort of splice them in a random fashion or were they always
You sort of placing them together in the way that sounded best. No, I I really picked
I picked them out very specifically for their effectiveness
I don't think a music system would have put them together in a creative way
I mean, it's possible that they could if you program the hell out of it
you might find some really cool way to do that.
But that was not what was done in this case.
It was really me just overlapping and just finding something
that just really felt chaotic and crazy and effective.
Awesome, thanks.
Sure.
Hi. First of all, thank you very much for the music of Bioshock. It's fantastic.
So, when you approached Infinite, did you really want it to...
and I know that there was a level in Infinite that actually had Rapture in it,
but did you approach it sort of wanting it to feel like an extension of the Bioshock universe?
Like, did you want it to have music similar enough to the first one that it was relatable,
or did you sort of want it to be its own new thing?
No, I really, it needed to be, and I wanted it to be,
a completely fresh and unique score.
Because it's, other than that one cue
where you actually end up in rapture,
it really, as far as I was concerned,
and certainly as far as the entire team at Irrational,
it needed to have its own unique sound.
It really did.
Thank you.
Sure.
Hey, just a more quick question.
So I noticed you got a lot of crazy sounds out of the strings.
So were there any things that just kind of like came up in the studio,
just unplanned, that you just kind of kept in because you liked it?
What, say that again?
I know you said you planned out a lot of the bizarre string parts.
Yeah.
I was asking if there's anything that just kind of came up that you didn't plan,
that you really liked and just kind of kept going.
You get surprises all the time.
When you're recording live instruments, especially stuff like this,
you do get surprises.
And then you say, hey, whatever you just did.
Do that again.
That was very cool.
Yeah, and that is the beauty of working with real musicians.
I love that part of it, because you never know what they're
going to come up with.
You never know how they're going to take your music
and do some really cool, unique thing that you did not expect.
And I want that from the players, the live players
that I work with.
I want them to experiment and to try unique things.
But that's the best.
That's the most fun part.
Thank you.
Sure.
All right, well, thank you all.
Thanks for coming.