My name is Doug Sheehan.
I'm one of the lead gameplay programmers at Insomniac Games.
And we're here to talk about building traversal
in Marvel's Spider-Man.
So let's just jump right in.
So in the fall of 2014, I found out Insomniac Games
was making a Spider-Man game, and that I
was going to be assigned to bring his traversal to life.
This was not only going to be the biggest game in Insomniac's history, but it was also
using a legendary IP that had really heavily infested and rabid fan base, and it had an
unrivaled expectation of quality for anything that we'd ever made.
And as someone that, as a poor college student, holed up in bookstores and read Spider-Man
comics, the idea of making Spider-Man swing was super exciting and also at the same time
completely and utterly terrifying.
Fortunately, we had the game's vision statement as a starting point, which was, play like
a superhero movie feels.
So we kind of set upon our journey to, as the saying goes, make you feel like Spider-Man.
So what does playing like a superhero movie
feels even mean for Traversal?
Well, with Swingin' as our starting point,
we decided on a few core beliefs that would kind of guide
the feature's development.
So the first thing we acknowledged
was that we wanted to target a pretty broad audience.
Spider-Man has a really big worldwide following,
and we wanted as many people as possible to be able to play
and enjoy the game.
However, we knew that we had the issue that most gamers don't really have any muscle memory
for swinging.
Unlike, say, a third-person shooter or a first-person shooter, most folks don't have any brain map
for how to make swinging go and function.
So to add to the challenge, we start the game out by chucking you out a window, giving you
the control, and saying, all right, swing time, go.
So wanting that first moment to feel just right, we knew we had to get the controls
to a point where they were easy to learn but hard to master.
Next, we wanted traversal and swinging in particular to be rooted in physics.
This was vital to give players a sense of believability, that feeling that they could
actually swing through New York as a superhero.
Following that, swing lines had to attach to in-world geometry.
No questions asked.
This was extremely important in order to ground the simulation correctly, but we were mostly
terrified that a bunch of angry fans would tell us we were ruining their childhood if
we didn't do it.
So finally, we wanted to have a dynamic camera.
The look and feel of swinging needed to be fluid, fast,
exciting, and especially cinematic.
We needed a camera that helped translate
all that high-flying acrobatics and velocity
into a really visceral experience for the player,
something that they could just feel in their gut.
Today, I'm going to show you how we achieved those core principles by taking you through
the process by which we created Traversal.
The biggest key to our success is iteration.
For a lot of the elements I'll show you, not just what we ended up actually shipping, but
where we started, where we failed, what we learned, and how we got better.
However, knowing when you needed to improve isn't necessarily always obvious to you.
It came from a steady diet of playtesting and learning how players interacted with the
game and where it was failing them.
This meant we had to stay really flexible in our execution
and always looking to be greater.
So before we can actually swing, we
have to have something to attach to.
So as stated, we wanted swinging to be accessible.
And this meant that we needed to think a bit about attach points
from the player's perspective.
Namely, what is the player actually
going to be responsible for when it comes
to picking an attach point?
And what is the system going to be responsible for
and doing to help them?
So we first decided that we wanted players really
just thinking about where they wanted to go, rather than
where they were attaching.
This removed a pretty significant burden from the player and let them focus on additional
layers of gameplay, like chasing cars, dodging bullets, rockets, and the occasional pigeon.
The player would communicate their directional intent with the analog stick, and then the
system would take it from there.
So our first attempt at finding attach points
was to comb the environment using an array of ray casts.
This was designed to minimize the required effort
from design and environment and to ensure that we were actually
attaching to geometry.
But this presented a number of problems
that we just couldn't overcome at the end of the day.
The biggest issue is that raycasts simply didn't provide enough resolution for us.
Our line lengths would often exceed 50 meters, and even with a respectable density of raycasts,
we were getting these 20 meter gaps at full range.
This was enough to not only miss small objects that we wanted to swing from, like flagpoles
and radio towers, but it would completely miss large sections of buildings entirely.
Specifically, an additional issue we recognized is that corners were often the optimal swing
points and raycasts were just really bad at finding those positions because of the resolution
problem.
So a more obvious problem is that Raycast can't hit things that don't have collision.
This was particularly problematic with trees in areas like Central Park, and even if those
objects did have a little bit of collision for the trunk or something like that, we still
weren't going to be able to find them because of the resolution issue.
And finally, as we'll talk about later,
a lot of points require some additional fix-up
after you find that initial point.
Doing these adjustments via collision checks
could prove really costly in a performance hit
when processing dozens of potential attach points.
And they still might not really be what we want.
So with those raycasts coming up short, we moved on.
We decided to use a markup-based approach
by wrapping our buildings in box volumes that approximate
the shape of the building.
We could find those nearby volumes,
process them on a face-by-face basis,
and then only then perform a final raycast on that point
to get their true attach point on the geometry.
But moving to markup provided a number
of advantages that were absent when using raycasts.
First, point collection was really fast.
By using a kind of a cache-friendly sphere database
that was just our data, it significantly
helped with scalability in terms of being
able to have a lot of markup out in the world
and be able to process it quickly.
By using the shape information, we effectively now
had infinite resolution for point placement
on each face of the volume.
This allowed us to easily find edges and corners
and never have to worry about missing smaller objects.
And finally, by using markup, we were
able to afford designers a lot of additional control
over various gameplay aspects, like custom swing parameters
and where you could and couldn't swing.
So the main drawback with markup was placement scalability.
We had a huge world full of things that were
going to require the markup.
And placing all of this by hand and maintaining it
through production as environment
was constantly changing was going
to be an enormous amount of upkeep and potential bugs.
So our solution to that involved a couple of primary tools.
First, we had to handle the buildings.
Fortunately, we were using a system called Houdini
to help us generate the geometry for our environment
out of building blocks.
This software could also then be leveraged
to analyze that geometry and procedurally place volumes
to approximate our building shapes.
For objects outside of Houdini's operation,
we deployed our engine's prefab system.
This bundled up markup with all of those objects
that we'd place, and every time an instance was put down,
it would just bring the markup in with it
so we didn't have to worry about it.
So with our markup now populating the world,
we needed to actually do something kind of useful for it
rather than just stare at it.
And at any point, the immediate area
can be filled with just hundreds of volumes that
are all potential swing points.
And we needed to filter through all that to find the best one.
So in order to pick that final attach point,
we need to start with a reasonable reference
point as our ideal position.
Here we kind of have a top-down view of our hero surrounded
by buildings.
And the player influence over point selection
comes from the input on the left stick.
And as stated before, we want the player thinking only
about where they're going, not specifically
where they're attaching.
So the input direction really just kind of
provides a starting point.
From that input direction, we can then apply an ideal slope
and a line length to transform the input direction
into a position that represents kind of our ideal attach point,
where we would want to go if we had infinite attach
points all over.
And moving back to a top-down view,
we can then use that position to generate two more
points on each face.
First one is the point that's closest to our reference point,
and the next is a raycast point along our ideal line
direction, which is then just clamped to the volume bounds.
So we can then blend between those two points
to get our output point for any situation.
The closest point is most useful when
you want to swing along the face and swing parallel to it,
while the right cast point is most useful when you're
swinging directly at the object.
And then we can just kind of blend between those
based on what your input is relative to the face normal
to get one that's most appropriate.
So now that we have a point, we need
to refine it a little bit in order to make it more effective.
Our blended point can change the slope and the line length
a lot, which can lead to really long flat lines,
short and steep lines, and everything kind of in between.
So we really wanted to try and give the player
a more consistent rhythm with swinging.
And that meant that we needed to try and keep those lines
as consistent as possible.
So we wanted to move things around a little bit
to get closer to the ideal.
So this is an example of shifting the attach point up
just a little bit in order to get closer to that ideal slope,
which had gotten kind of overly flattened by the closest point
calculation.
By moving more towards this ideal slope,
you can see that we prevent the player from having quite
such an excessive drop during the swing, which will then
make it more consistent as they go swing to swing
and more predictable.
So now that we've generated this field of points
across a whole bunch of markup faces,
and we need to actually decide which
one's going to be our swing point for this frame.
So we do this by scoring each of the points
and taking the best one.
Our scoring algorithm is then geared
to fulfill that desire of translating that stick
input to a point that moves us in the desired direction.
So our first scoring element is how the face normal
relates to input direction.
As I said, you're trying to swing parallel
to the faces where possible in this case.
And so the input direction means that the player
will be able to swing along that surface
in the direction they desire.
Now, because corners provide the player the most control,
we do try and snap points to edges when they're nearby.
So we can then use the best normal available
on that entire sweep of the corner
to compare against input for our score calculation.
We can also give corners a bonus when
we're trying to turn if that corner is going
to help us make that turn.
When taking input into account, we
start with the angle between the input direction
and the direction of the attach point,
and then we score that delta.
And for range, we're looking for points
that match our ideal length, and then it just
falls off in either direction as we deviate from that.
And we apply a similar fall-off method for slope
as the angle moves away from our ideal.
And once we have all that together,
we can do a weighted sum, and the highest score
is going to win.
So here you can see it all coming together in game.
The blue boxes are our market volumes,
and you can see a little bit of debug info
about each point's score floating above it
that kind of helps us figure out when we try to debug
why one point is better than another point,
particularly if we didn't want that to be the case,
we can go adjust those weighting values
in order to tune swing to make it
so that we're continuing to get the expected point.
Now that we have our attach point, we can talk about what happens when you're actually
on the line.
As stated, we wanted to have a physics-based system that we modify the results of.
We're going to start with the physics and then proceed to mess with the universe a little
bit.
So the two basic forces involved in the pendulum
are gravity and tension.
As you can see here, the tension is
a factor of line length, angle, and gravity,
all in the direction of the line.
And it's kind of responsible for pulling
that bob of the pendulum in a circle
around the center of the system.
We also break gravity up into its two component vectors
here, one parallel to the line and one perpendicular.
The perpendicular portion represents
that kind of restoring force.
It's the thing that makes the pendulum
oscillate back and forth.
And the parallel portion is what's left.
And you'll see in our calculations,
we can actually cancel that out with part of tension
to simplify the math a little bit, which we do here.
So when actually calculating this in code,
we internally just set the mass to one
since we're not really dealing with a variable mass system,
and we can tune gravity how we want to.
And after a bit of simplification,
we apply the remaining forces of tension
and perpendicular gravity to our velocity.
Also, just for a little bit more accuracy,
we do four iterations each frame
to run the entire thing at about 120 hertz.
So when we're talking about how we wanted swinging to feel,
the number one thing that came up
was that swings needed to feel fluid.
This led to a couple of rules that
drove a variety of other elements
within the swing system.
First, we wanted to avoid slack lines.
We wanted to keep the player feeling like they were swinging,
not falling.
So by keeping the line taut at all times,
it gave the player a much more predictable experience
and prevented kind of bounciness and sudden change
in direction as that slack line goes taut from a free fall.
And this led to the need that once a line is shortened,
it generally stays that length.
We do look for opportunities to try and kind of restore
lost line length when possible, but doing so too quickly
feels really wrong to people.
And so we had to be really careful to do that
with caution.
So our first goal on getting a new line
is then giving the player a good experience of just getting
into the swing.
But the initial setup poses an immediate challenge.
The incoming velocity is almost always very, very different
than the velocity that's going to be tangent to the swing arc.
And we don't want to just snap it,
because that's going to feel like a sudden change
in direction and just give players whiplash.
So, however, if we just let the simulation play out as is,
you get something that looks a bit like this.
Because of our rule that we don't allow the line
to lengthen again, the velocity running
into the center of the swing arc
shortens the line up considerably,
and this can result in losing the entirety of the swing's dip
as well as causing a really rapid acceleration
in angular velocity that's hard for players to react to.
They just get shot up in the air
without knowing what happened.
So to improve, we blend the incoming velocity
towards the tangent direction of the swing arc
a little bit on each iteration.
This helps maintain healthier line lengths
and improves the expected behavior in the angular
velocity.
And the player can also now feel a lot more significant drop
in the swing arc compared to the previous motion path.
So now that they're into the swing,
the player is going to want to further mess around
with their motion in order to move themselves around.
So we do this with just a simple accelerated rotation
on the total velocity.
We scale that turn speed based on your max,
we scale that turn speed based on where you are
in the swing arc, so you get more control at the trough,
less up at the apexes, so you kind of come to a stall
that feels about right.
And we can also adjust the turn speed based on
whether you're turning with the attach point
or away from the attach point.
So when it comes to managing speed while on the line,
things are going to vary a lot from swing to swing.
The two biggest influences on speed for any given swing
will be the amount of speed the hero brings in,
as well as the gravity that's applied
during the swing that's going to accelerate them
throughout the swing arc.
So due to streaming considerations,
we also needed to stay below about a 10 second average speed
of 30 meters per second so that we could avoid loading stalls
and just get everything in as we're
hurtling through the world.
So we start by deciding what our horizontal terminal velocity
is for any given swing.
As a baseline, this is done by translating our fall speed
into a max speed while never letting it actually
slow you down so we don't cut your incoming speed at all.
So this ends up feeling pretty natural to players
because they're basically using gravity to help generate speed.
And it helps with streaming because in order
to generate fall speed, they have
to be just falling for a while, which
is going to have drag, which is going
to slow their horizontal speed, which
helps our average speed.
So, once they're attached, we let normal physics accelerate them up to the max speed, and we
go from there.
But to enforce that terminal velocity,
we do kind of a little bit of a weird thing.
We only cap the hero's horizontal speed.
And this can have a little bit of an odd side effect
in some cases, where you're actually slowing down
in 3D through the downswing,
but it does help you get through these really long
swing arcs a lot faster, get down to the trough,
get down to where you wanna be in a better way.
And the slowdown doesn't come into play too often,
and most players are completely unaware it's happening
due to a lot of other speed cues going on,
like camera rotation, environment motion,
motion blur, screen effects, everything else
that we're just throwing at them to try and sell.
sell that speed.
Now, on the other side of the swing, on the upswing,
gravity is going to be slowing you down.
However, we do have a few things
that we wanted to take into account on this side of the swing.
First, we want players to feel like
gravity is appropriately slowing them down,
so it needs to feel physically correct and natural.
But, with line lengths being highly variable,
it creates an inconsistent timing
to the various release levels, something we wanted
to try and close the gap on.
So we also don't want to slow the player down too much when they're near the trough.
We want to let them keep that hard-earned speed just a little bit longer
so that they can use it to fling themselves through the world.
And from there, we account for all this
by implementing a variable gravity upswing.
At any given point on the upswing,
your gravity is going to be determined
by a combination of your current speed
and where you are on the swing arc.
What this ends up doing is really helping swing timing
be a lot more consistent and allowing more swings
to move through the full range of release points.
So the player ends up having a much more predictable time
and can get those high releases even if they're not necessarily
moving that fast.
So.
With the basics all now in place, I want to talk a bit about our experience of refining the swinging mechanics over the course of production.
Again, we go back to our usability-driven, iterative approach, and per our initial goals,
we really wanted the player to feel the momentum in physics, but we also wanted swinging to be accessible.
So usability testing proves a critical element
in iterating on this accessibility.
This is because developers quickly become
their own worst testers, and I say this all the time
to people that I work with, because basically,
we just know too much about how things work,
and we're generally really quick to forgive ourselves
because our code is amazing,
and shame on you for suggesting otherwise.
So, we also tend to play the game in a very particular way,
the way we designed it.
Real players, however, will interact with the game
in a number of unexpected and sometimes confounding ways,
stressing elements of the system
that the developer may never encounter.
So finally, you need to make sure
functionality lines up with player expectations.
As a developer, we may have a perfectly rational explanation
for why something works the way it does put to a player,
it just seems weird, broken, confusing,
or just not any fun whatsoever.
So what did we find?
Well, players suck at managing physics.
So forces will often act against their desires,
attach points aren't really directly player-driven,
leading to a lot of variability,
and world geometry is complex and difficult
for many players to effectively navigate
while tethered to an attach point.
The end result was that players felt
that they kind of lacked control over the in-game results.
This was despite everything working just as intended
when we made the initial version of Swinging.
So how do we approach solving this problem?
We injected a number of assists into swinging
to help smooth out the experience,
giving them a few less things to worry about
and moving the system's behavior to be closer
to the player expectations wherever possible.
Our goal was to keep these as invisible
to the player as we could, and we found
that if you deviated too far from real physics,
players would notice, and often they would react
pretty negatively to it.
So our first major usability problem
was that players felt like it was basically impossible
to swing in a straight line.
The result of the simulation was creating a mismatch
between the player's input intent and the character motion.
And the results were confusing and frustrating
a lot of our players.
So the reason this was happening is that forces
were conspiring to move the character in a way
that it would settle underneath the attach point,
as you might imagine with a normal pendulum.
The tension force has this component that moves towards the attach point and gravity
just reinforces that to continue to pull you down.
So in this video you'll be able to see what happens when the tension forces are in full
effect.
The player is going to be trying to swing straight down the middle of the street here,
but they're consistently getting pulled sideways towards the attach point.
When they then try and counter-steer to get back to the middle,
their next attach point goes on the other side of the street,
and it just increases frustration.
So to top all this off, that zigzagging motion
also slows them down for their straight line speed,
and they just feel like they can't really build up that momentum that they're looking for.
So, how do you fight gravity?
Well, you cheat.
So we move the simulation pivot away from the wall
into a position that will help us swing straighter
while leaving the visible attach point on the wall.
We then can blend that pivot position back over time
or when the player is turning.
This makes sure that turns do pivot on the right place
and on the visible place, and that if you settle
underneath the attach point, you're settling
under the visual one, not the one that we've moved away.
This motion was detectable to players,
particularly when we A-B tested it,
but we found that most Veldt it actually worked more
as they expected, aligning their input desire to the results.
In this video, you'll see that pivot tweaking
is going to be fully active.
The player can maintain a lot more consistent center line
and build speed a lot more easily.
Their directional intent is transferred
a lot more cleanly to motion.
The next usability problem was that players
felt they weren't really able to get a swing line when
their body was at or near the top of a building.
This was happening because we required an attach point
to be just a minimum height above you.
And we do that because it prevents you from just flying
over the pivot point or requiring
that we just slam you straight down in order
to get you under it.
However, this rule was completely
hidden from the player.
And there was not really any reason for them
to expect or anticipate that it was there.
An additional reason this can occur is that players' perception of the character position for the world is pretty murky when they're in the air and all the buildings are pretty far off to the side.
And players are just frankly pretty impatient when falling and spamming that R2 button and trying to get a swing line.
So what do we do?
Well, once a cheater, always a cheater.
We secretly allowed the simulation attach point
to rise above the building edge.
This would raise the valid attach point ceiling
and let people attach a little bit sooner.
It also had this nice side effect
of improving lines that were previously good,
but not really all that great.
And so player awareness of this was actually almost zero.
It's actually pretty hard to notice
a vertical shift in the pivot point
when you're swinging underneath it.
So our next usability problem was our game director special,
which is that players were often oversteering
when trying to turn and clipping
into the edges of buildings.
And so our solution here is to do a number of collision tests
to scan the world for problem cases.
We'd send a cone of checks forward,
looking for things that we might run into,
so that we can nudge you just a little
to the left or the right.
And we would also send a series of checks
kind of forward and sideways,
looking for gaps in upcoming walls.
This gave us a clue that we might want to
dampen your steering values a little bit,
so that you don't oversteer when trying to make a turn
and slam yourself into the wall,
instead of clearing that wall and swinging into the gap.
So these two things combined to give players a hugely empowering feeling of just made it
without really noticing that we were the ones letting them make it.
So yet another consistent problem was that players would often have a line that was just
long enough to smack them right into the top of a building that they thought they were
going to clear.
And this was kind of particularly bad because players, as we've said, didn't have any control
over line length, so they were quick to blame us for all their problems.
So the solution, then, is to just shorten the line,
slowly but dynamically, in order to get it just short enough
to clear that building.
So we'd use collision to scan ahead for the maximum height,
and then we would slowly raise the player through the swing
until the new line length was just short enough
to clear that building.
So one final element to talk about
is how we shorten the line to keep players above the ground.
So we do this because our ground and rooftops
are so littered with cars and props and pedestrians
and squirrels and other things that trying to navigate
and swing through all that would be basically impossible.
We didn't want players face-planing
into the ground all the time,
and we also didn't want them becoming
just a bug on a windshield.
So, similar to clearing buildings, we'd use collision to get the ground tight and then
we'd scale that vertical motion on their downswing in order to keep them above the ground and
have kind of a swing floor so that they could get that nice street sweeping feel.
So once a player's time on the line is complete,
it's time for what ends up being one of the most satisfying
elements of swinging, flinging yourself off the line
across the world with reckless abandon.
So when doing so, we have two sets of data for letting go.
We have releasing and jumping.
Jumping gives you a lot more acrobatic motion, a lot more
height and more speed.
But just simple releasing has simpler animations
and allows you to take a follow-up action more quickly.
So players get to choose between the two based
on what they're trying to do.
One of the really nice gameplay features of swinging
when it comes to these releases is the inherent analog
nature of how release points translate into exit direction.
So a player can choose to release low to get more speed
or hold on just a little bit longer to get more height.
Now our first approach to swing releases
was very metric driven, something that was totally sane
based on Insomniac's platforming history.
So we defined a desired jump height
and a time to peak for various release points
and speeds along the swing arc,
and then kind of blend those values from those key points
to get one for any release point.
The goal was to make jumps feel predictable and consistent
so that players could plan ahead
and get their next move going.
We had this model for about two years,
and we were getting mostly positive feedback on it.
But there was always this kind of undercurrent pointing
at a lack of player satisfaction.
Players felt like jumps were too heavy
and that their momentum on the swing line
wasn't really translating to their jumps.
This was because the metric-driven approach
was changing gravity significantly
for any given release point based on player speed
to hit that jump height target that we had set.
Instead of feeling really rewarding with an expected amount of fling,
players' kind of physics feel was being violated,
and they felt that they were being penalized somehow.
We had this model in for the helicopter chase demo in 2017,
when a lot of people online were saying,
oh, the swinging looks slow.
And so part of that was this kind of heaviness to the swing...
excuse me, to the swing jumps.
So to fix this, we moved to a more free release model
that let go of all those controlling metrics
in order to keep a fixed gravity for each release point.
This was the only design factor into the jump,
other than your velocity on the swing line,
and as we wanted to remove anything else
that was gonna feel artificial.
So once implemented, this change created a much more
natural translation of swing speed to jump size
that better matched player expectation.
We saw an immediate increase in fun factor
as players were now able to fling themselves
across the world with just abandon,
which led to a greatly increased sense of speed and joy
and just general cohesiveness
of the entire swinging experience.
So stepping away from the simulation side for a minute,
I want to talk just a little bit about how
the animation for swinging is implemented on the code side.
So it's mostly going to be about the mechanics of how
we pick animations to play and then adjust them to more
accurately represent the underlying simulation.
So when we first started talking about swinging,
the gameplay and animation groups
laid out some high-level goals for how we wanted the animation
to look and feel.
This included having fluid animation
over the course of the swing arc,
having a clean entry animation from our air pose
through the sling and into the swing.
The character's body, obviously, wanted to align to the web line
so that it felt right.
And we needed to have this kind of well-timed kick
at the trough in order to sell momentum and for a player
cue as to where they were in the swing arc.
So our first iteration of animating the swing,
we approached the seamless animation through the swing arc
by actually just using a single animation.
The animator created an on-the-line animation
that started at the drop horizon
and went all the way through to the apex horizon.
In code, we would then drive the animation's time
based on where the player was in the swing arc
for any given frame.
So in order to get our clean entry animations,
we created separate swing intro animations
for different points along the swing arc.
These animations would end pose matched
with the full swing animation,
so that the blend to the swing would be seamless.
And when a player began a swing,
we would calculate where they were in the swing arc
and blend between those different kind of...
pointed animations in order to get one specifically
for that angle.
We would then continue to dynamically blend
that value during the entirety of that intro animation
so that we would get a nice match
for the final pose of the swing as they go into that swing
animation.
In order to get the body to align without having
to make duplicate swing arc animations,
we then deployed partial animations
to just kind of adjust the final body angle.
We used this on both the body to go side to side,
as well as the arms for kind of a final fix up
when those weren't matching.
So after iterating on this model for most of production,
we had some things that worked just as expected.
These included the entry animation system
working really, really well.
It allowed smooth entry and timing
into the swing animation.
And our adjustment partials did a really good job
at aligning the character to the swing line
with minimal amount of additional animation required.
Finally, the animation through the swing arc was fluid.
But the system presented a few limitations
that were capping the animator's creativity.
First, we had really limited variability in the swing.
Getting any variation in this model
required animating a brand new swing from start
to finish, one end to the other.
And if you wanted to do something different,
you had to make another one and another one and another one.
And so next we had very, very perceptible animation time scaling.
Line lengths and player speeds are highly variable, which was born out in highly variable arc speeds.
And with a fixed number of animation frames scaling over a variable time range,
we would get these really easy-to-feel time scaling artifacts.
And this was especially evident when we get these really slow, sluggish kick-throughs
that lacked any impact whatsoever on longer lines or slower swings.
So we had a couple of new goals.
Enable variety and reduce the time scaling.
We accomplished, we attacked these
by breaking the swing arc up into pieces
that we then animated separately.
We would animate the downswing and the upswing independently
all the way through the trough,
which let us kind of overlap the kick animation
wherever we wanted to kind of overlap that inflection point.
We would then continue to drive the animation time
as before on the up and downswing animations
as they weren't as susceptible to the visible scaling
as the kick animations were.
So once we were in a swing, we would estimate the time
to trough during the downswing so that we could trigger
that kick animation at just the right time
in order to be able to play at a full speed.
This instantly made our kicks feel a lot more
powerful and consistent.
It also meant that we could plug in a variety of animations
into the kick portion without needing to reanimate
the rest of the swing.
But animators be animators, and we weren't done yet.
They wanted more.
So by breaking the swing animation into pieces,
it allowed us to now have a lot more variety
in the way we constructed the animation for the swing.
We were able to introduce custom kicks and spins
with custom upswings.
We had hard catch variations of the downswing.
And all of these things could be played with or without
one another to get a whole bunch of custom swings
and unique swings that look different
as you went from one swing to the next
and add a lot more texture and flavor
to swinging in the game.
So this new iteration helped us solve our major problems
by allowing us to create a lot more animation variety,
and it also helped us eliminate the animation scaling
for the most notable portion of the swing.
So one final problem worth noting
was that with all of the various moves that Spider-Man can do,
he would often end up in poses that didn't really
play nicely with our swing intro animations.
We needed to either wait for the animation
to get to a point where the character could
blend into the intro better.
or live with really, really bad looking blends
as we tried to get into those sling animations.
So to solve this, Animation wanted to add
a lot more variety to swing intros,
but programming didn't really want to manage
each of those clips manually.
So to push that work over to the content creators,
we added a data-driven setup that allowed animators
to tell the game what the next animation would be.
from the current time in the active animation.
They'd mark up a section of a jump animation with data
that would point to custom sling animations,
and this allowed them to cleanly get out
of all these crazy acrobatic poses with custom slings
that made the traversal feel a lot more seamless
and the character feel a lot more dynamic.
So, kind of stepping away now from animation,
I want to talk a bit about our approach
to the traversal camera.
We knew from previous games that good motion and animation
only goes so far in translating the experience to the player.
The camera is actually often the most important aspect
in conveying elements of speed and translation
in a way that gives the player that kind of visceral
connection to the action that's on the screen.
So when we started out our top level goals
for the traversal camera, we came up with three main items
that we found important after early prototyping
with kind of a mostly static camera.
First, we wanted to minimize the amount of player input
was required.
This is because players would often
need to be using the face buttons
and we didn't want to require them
to have to switch between that and a stick input.
That was just a lot of camera management
that we didn't want people to mess with.
Next, we needed to accentuate the pendulum motion
and the forces on the line.
And finally, we wanted to communicate a sense of speed
to the player.
So we have a pretty long history of third-person games
at Insomniac, and we've generally
started with a follow camera model that
tries to have the camera looking in the same direction
as the hero's velocity.
So while successful in other games, in other contexts,
it did present a few problems for Spider-Man,
particularly at the high speeds that Spider-Man could move
and how much we had to let you see where you were going.
So the biggest issue was that when we tuned it effectively,
to where you were going, it was extremely susceptible
to these sudden changes in velocity
causing large changes in view direction.
The camera would just swing around incessantly on people.
This had this feedback loop with camera relative controls
where the camera would change a lot,
which would change your input a lot,
which would change your camera a lot,
and you'd just get into this death spiral.
So in order to fix the problem, we
moved to a model based on the player more
dragging the camera around.
This was done by we'd predict the player's position based
on their current speed, and then we'd
use that to calculate how it would drag more of a camera
boom and how that would change the rotation.
This ended up being a lot less noisy with velocity changes,
as the frame-to-frame delta was generally a whole lot smaller.
So with the camera now following us more appropriately,
I want to talk a bit about how we accentuate the pendulum
motion of the player through camera motion.
In addition to just feeling better, this also actually helped address two major usability issues
that a more static camera was presenting.
First, as stated before, players weren't really noticing the full extent of vertical translation
the character was actually performing.
Players were also presenting a really poor level of comprehension of where they actually were in the swing arc.
They were frequently hanging on for too long, releasing high,
losing all their forward momentum, and wondering what in the hell happened.
So the first thing we manipulate to help sell the swing arc
is the camera's pitch.
We try and roughly match the swing arc's pitch
in order to feel that motion through the camera.
As you can see here, we want to keep the pitch a little more
flattened on the downswing so that you
can keep your eyes on the horizon
and keep an eye on where you're going.
And then on the upswing, we tend to exaggerate the pitch
a little bit in order to communicate that rise more
effectively and let them feel like they're moving up
without getting too far into the upswing.
So the next element we added to help the player feel
the swing arc more was to move the character's position
and screen space down and then back up
over the course of the swing.
This created kind of a real-world physical tracking
response from the player that would reinforce
the in-game motion as they kind of looked down
and looked up with the character moving on screen.
So when it came to turning, we really
wanted to get players to feel that they were whipping
around a corner at high speed and bringing
that same sensation you get when you're in a turning
car leaning to the side.
And to get this effect, we apply a little bit of roll
to the camera when turning and scale it
based on the line angle and turn speed.
But a word of caution here, we did
have to be careful not to push it too far due
to motion sickness concerns.
And we did add an option to scale it down or turn it off
entirely for people that had problems with that.
So now that we have players feeling
the translation in traversal,
we need to make sure that they actually felt the speed.
So this means we needed to layer
as many visual cues as possible
to help sell not just the current speed,
but changes in speed.
Probably the most impactful thing to sensing speed
through the world is going to be field of view.
A wider field of view tends to elongate objects
in front of you, making it feel like you're
covering more ground.
And it also brings a lot of peripheral objects
into view that are going to be moving really fast by you
so you get a lot more of that relative motion feel.
In order to really sell the changes in speed,
we're constantly updating the game's field of view
while traversing.
To deal with sudden speed changes,
we rely more on actually adjusting the camera's follow
distance, as you don't want to bounce field of view
around too much.
It gets really weird.
We have certain kind of explosive moves
that create a spring action on the camera
so that it falls back before blending closer again.
This gives those moves a much bigger sense of impact,
like the character's boosting away suddenly,
leaving the camera in the dust, and then it
has to play catch up a little bit.
So here you'll be able to see all of that coming together to show the sense of speed.
There's a little bit of debugger on the side to give you a better idea of how the field of view and follow distance are changing as it goes through the action.
So the final bit of camera development I want to talk about is related to how the camera
is handled when we perform a variety of traversal moves.
So our first version of the traversal camera treated each move as its kind of special,
unique item.
This was driven by a desire to make every move as cinematic as possible with the thought
that if you string together a bunch of really cinematic moves, you're going to get something
extra special, super cinematic.
This presented a couple of problems though.
In this video from an early vertical slice, you'll see some of the issues with the
everything is a special snowflake and how that kind of breaks down. You'll see
that going from move to move would cause a change in framing and field of view
that could kind of muddle the perception of speed and rapid sequencing of moves
would create a very noisy relationship between the world, the character, and the
view.
So, how did we get better?
Well, we started with a more unified model
for all of our traversal moves
that had a speed-driven field of view and follow distance
that would stay consistent
across all of the different moves.
We also smoothed out any adjustments we were doing
to offsets to make those changes feel less aggressive
and not kind of upset the player.
So here, you're going to see that we ended up getting some pretty good results.
You're going to get a lot more consistent perception of speed when moving from one move
to another.
The camera ends up being a lot more predictable to the player, and one move flows into the
next without feeling like there's a major state change that the player has to suddenly
adjust to.
This proved a lot more fun and predictable to players, and gave an overall better experience.
Alright, so, as we started to get a full set of traversal moves in the game,
and playing with them more both internally and through usability,
we found that unsurprisingly, our first version was rarely good enough.
So this led to a lot of feedback that motion felt stiff and imprecise.
Players weren't able to navigate as well as they wanted,
a lot of moves weren't matching expectations,
and they were unable to actually land where they wanted to.
So we started kind of revisiting things.
So with wall run, our first pass was set up
to actually be locked to either be horizontal or vertical
with no in-between and no ability to switch.
The entry was based on a combination
of character velocity, input direction, the walls facing,
and it had a heavy bias towards maintaining
your current momentum.
So if you're going really fast horizontally,
you are really likely to get a horizontal wall run.
The single biggest problem we had
was that wall run entry direction
was really poorly mapped to player expectations.
They never really understood the concept
of momentum driving the entry direction
and how that overwhelmed their input.
And this was made even worse
because there was just no ability
to switch from horizontal to vertical
if they didn't get what they wanted.
And on top of that, the camera direction
versus a vertical wall was making input
to entry mapping even more confusing.
Can you tell me in this image, pushing up on the stick,
is that supposed to make you go forward or up?
A lot of players didn't really know what they wanted to do in that situation.
So players would often try to compensate for this by pointing the camera where they wanted
to go, but the system was paying zero attention to the camera, and so it wasn't helping them.
So with our big problems identified, we set out to make some changes.
The first thing we did was to add analog steering.
This created a lot more in-between values for entry direction, as well as giving players
the ability to adjust on the fly if they weren't happy with their entry direction.
Then we revisited our entry direction process as a whole.
We added a camera-driven influence
to help translate player intent to in-game results.
And we then significantly amped up the effect of player input
over momentum so that they had a lot more control
over the results and what happened on the output.
So these combined to result in a significant reduction
in player frustration.
So for in-air control, once they're off the line,
just flying through the air, we wanted the player
we had an initial approach that heavily favored momentum.
Again, we were looking at that momentum thing
over and over again in the first rev.
So this meant that in-air steering was fairly stiff
and players needed to rely on web moves
like swinging and web zip for rapid direction change.
The idea was that it would make your swing releases
more meaningful and consequential.
But this model presented a number of problems in play testing, much like everything else seems to.
First, swing speeds amplify small differences in angle over large distances.
This made it almost impossible to be precise.
If you tried to release off a line and you saw something in the distance,
little variations in that angle would cause big variations in where you ended up.
In addition, players were really just terrible at thinking ahead to manage their speed.
While there are tools to slow down, they generally go as fast as possible to their destination,
and only once they're there do they try and stop.
This usually ends up with the player kind of fumbling around and orbiting their destination
as they try and get closer and just having a bad time.
So finally, players were having a lot of difficulty reacting quickly to changes in situation or
geometry.
So in order to help solve these problems,
we had to put more control back in players' hands
and let go of some of our really strict momentum-based
concepts.
To start, we significantly increased the in-air turn
speeds.
This immediately helped players react a lot more quickly
to dynamic elements, and it also allowed people to more
effectively set up their next move,
increasing their ability to chain moves
and just basically use the full suite of traversal elements.
Later on, we massively increased the amount of drag applied
to the player when pulling back on the stick.
This let players feel a lot more precise
when they were reaching their destination
because they could go from 60 to zero in a very short time.
Overall, this led to a lot fewer instances
of players fumbling around their destination
and let people feel like they could stick the landing.
So the next thing we needed to address was our more specific
world interaction moves.
So when we started making the game,
we knew that we wanted to make the city feel
like a big part of traversal, and Spider-Man's interaction
with the world needed to be tangible.
And while swinging and web zip did require geometry to work,
you were still kind of mid-air and disconnected
when using them.
We wanted something that was a little more tactile.
So our first version was zipping through the legs of a water
tower with our web tunnel move.
This was really cinematic from a presentation standpoint,
and it really fulfilled the fantasy of interacting
with those specific objects.
But it did have a few shortcomings.
The first problem is that the move has a pretty rigid
directionality.
There wasn't a lot of room for players
to modify the direction going through the object
because it was a fixed structure.
And in addition, the entry angles were pretty limited.
You could only engage the web tunnel from a limited angle
range before it started to look really weird of getting sucked
in sideways and turning through this thing.
So in this case, we recognize that WebTunnel
had some inherent limitations that we weren't
going to be able to get over.
In addition, we liked having the move
as it was for certain situations.
That cinematic presentation was really
effective for certain things.
So instead, we created point launch,
a move where you could zip to a point on top of an object
and then spring back off instantly with a big jump.
We were able to get the desired world interaction
we were looking for with web tunnels,
along with a number of additional benefits.
First, the player could enter and exit a point launch
from any direction.
And because we needed just a point,
the opportunity for placement in the world
had increased dramatically.
So once point launch was implemented,
we started to notice that we had a lot of traversal moves
that we were treating as unique.
We had unique names for them, and we
thought they were all special.
But to the player, they all felt like the same thing.
In this case, that was go to a thing.
So as you can see, we had separate unique button
combinations for going to a perch, point launching,
and zipping to a wall.
To make things worse, point launch only worked on perches,
which were a special kind of point.
But we had a very similar move that
worked on perches and edges.
And ultimately, this led to a lot of problems
with the player's ability to mentally map
this variety of controls to what felt to them
like the same action.
So they'd fumble a lot, do the wrong thing,
and just generally get themselves screwed up.
So our solution was then to merge all of this
into a single input space using the triggers.
This helped to ensure that the button to action mapping
in the player's brain was a lot more one to one.
However, it's not just a matter of merging buttons,
it's never that simple.
It did require us to adapt some of the moves as well.
First, we expanded point launch to work on all edges,
which ended up being a win for the player,
and we merged it with zip to perch.
We then moved zip to wall to be an aim mode only action
so that its targeting didn't conflict with the other moves
that it was sharing buttons with.
So after iterating our controls by doing things
like changing buttons and adding moves,
there's a few major takeaways from this section
that I feel are pretty important.
First, if the player expectation and system designs
are not aligned, then your controls just fail
and the player experience is gonna drop.
We spent a lot of time giving long-winded design reasons
why our controls were the way they were when they started,
but ultimately, players will just never get the most
out of a system that they have trouble using.
And the next lesson would be that trying to add analog input
and behavior to our moves helped add depth, utility, freedom,
and flow to our moves and just increase the player's
experience.
So as we were getting towards the end of production
and our core mechanics were all in place,
we started to drive down to the next level of usability
feedback.
We found that players were still feeling
that they experienced a somewhat kind of stuttery rhythm, where
it would feel incredibly smooth at times,
but they were kind of consistently
getting these little snags and hiccups that
were breaking their momentum.
So, as we kept gathering information,
we found that most of the problems
boiled down to just a few cases across the city.
In response, we created a kind of small palette of moves
that would help maintain flow
to get around those rough edges.
Many of these moves were designed to be
a natural extension from the character's current action,
so they didn't require any input.
One of the players who feel like
they were expertly executing these moves
that would often require unnatural reflexes
if they wanted to execute them manually.
So my first example here shows one of our biggest issues.
You'd clip a corner, causing a short wall run that would then
eject you sideways.
The sudden change in direction would often surprise players
and would frequently create situations
that were difficult to recover from as they were exiting
at a high enough velocity they'd often
get clear across the street before they knew what
the hell happened to them.
So we kind of fixed this by adding just a small little move
to redirect you parallel to your incoming velocity
if you were only wall running for a really short time.
This very quickly got the player back in action
with a consistent reference direction
and they were able to just get right back
to what they were doing.
So the next example looks more at a case
where players didn't really have a tool
to change direction easily.
If a player was wall running up a building
and wanted to corner over it,
they would have to clear the building
and then figure out what their next move was
once they could actually see what was above them.
This led to kind of this gap in flow
while players processed that view
and caused a lot of stall for them.
To fix this, we added a move that the player could trigger before clearing the wall to
get over the edge and redirect their velocity all in one shot.
This added a little layer of skill, which was nice, and it added some depth while letting
players a lot more efficiently navigate over these buildings.
So a lot of our additional moves centered around
trying to traverse through space near walls
and how that conflicts with our art team's desire
to have a lot of stuff sticking out of those walls
and into our play space.
The biggest factor here was fire escapes.
It just didn't feel like New York without them,
but they were basically the total arch nemesis
for the traversal team the entire production.
We ended up making a lot of vaulting moves,
both from the air and from wall run and from swing,
to get around these, as well as completely custom ladder
climbing web move to kind of climb them like a ladder
up a fire escape stack.
We also needed to deal with signs hanging out of buildings,
particularly in places like Chinatown,
and a lot of small little outcroppings and changes
in wall contour that were too small to just wall run over,
but they were too big to just wall run over,
but too small to actually run on entirely.
So.
And today, that wraps up our journey
that we went on with creating Traversal for Marvel's Spider-Man.
We had a whole lot of fun along the way
working with such a great character,
but there are definitely a few key things
I believe any developer can learn from our experience here.
First, in creating mechanics, start with a simple implementation
and then add complexity only as you uncover new problems.
By keeping things simple early,
we were able to avoid going too far down a path
that our players wouldn't respond to,
which in many cases kept us from wasting work.
We ended up with a system that had a whole lot of features,
but many of the additions were things
that we could never have anticipated needing
or wanting ahead of time.
Second, you have to stay flexible in your approach
to creating mechanics.
We were initially really resistant to some
of the best changes, because we had all the design
reasons listed out why it was working
like it was supposed to.
And clearly, it was the feedback that was the problem.
By allowing the game to evolve, we
came to a final product that was far superior to what
we thought was the right approach earlier
in development.
And finally, you are your own worst tester.
And in some cases, the rest of your dev team
quickly catches up with being terrible.
Developers know exactly how their systems work
and they're just, and the way they're supposed to be used.
So when you play the game, it will often work
exactly as you expected.
Different players will play the game
in wildly different ways.
and you'll never know where the real problems and edge cases
are until you let them loose in your game.
Even with external play testers, you
should always challenge yourself and others
to try to play the game in different ways
and try and have a different experience
in mapping what your controls are into the game.
So that's it for me.
Thanks so much for coming.
And it looks like we've got about 10 minutes for some Q&A.
I'm going to start over here.
Hello.
So the problem space you're working in
seemed like it required a ton of different skill sets
to effectively solve these problems,
like cinematography, physics, game design,
a whole bunch of others.
What was the composition of your team like?
And how did you effectively organize
around these different skill sets to solve these problems?
So we have what we call the traversal pod,
which consisted of a couple of programmers,
a handful of animators, a designer,
as well as just everybody else
looking at traversal in general.
So we'd have effects people that would come in
and help with effects, our animation director.
would also kind of be looking at things
from a cinematography standpoint,
as well as the animators in the Traversal Pod.
And so it was really just getting,
it was an extremely collaborative environment
and getting all the different people
from all the different disciplines with eyeballs on it
and everybody looking for ways to give input
on how to improve things.
Thanks.
Was any inspiration drawn from Spider-Man 2's web-slinging mechanics?
Early on, we definitely played all of the games.
Spider-Man 2 did a lot of really great things, so did Ultimate Spider-Man,
so did Web of Shadows, so did ASM2.
Those were all teams that had a lot of really great ideas that they executed in different ways.
We definitely took things from them.
The biggest thing we got through the history of Spider-Man games
was your web's better darn well attached to buildings.
But...
When we took it from there, we ended up at the end of the day wanting to make something
that was also kind of our own.
And I think we sort of hit that by having a traversal system that layered a lot of different
moves together to make you feel like you had a wider palette.
Thank you.
What were some of the challenges and solutions you had with swing-heavy combat situations
such as like the final Doc Ock fight, which was on a rooftop?
Yeah, so that created kind of a lot of weird things.
And we actually had the ability to basically have a config
data set that kind of parameterized
how swinging worked.
And so one of the things we were able to do was make a
duplicate data set that was entirely re-parameterized for
different situations.
So when we were inside GCT, inside Grand Central,
or when we were in a combat arena, like a boss fight,
we could sit there and basically just change
all the parameters for how swinging worked
in order to make it fit that space a little bit better.
We didn't want to deviate too far,
it needed to be kind of, make sense to the player,
but it did let us make sure that we weren't
kind of overshooting things, when you weren't getting...
When you're outside, it's these big, huge swings
that give you a lot of height and a lot of stuff like that.
If you're inside or in a boss arena,
that becomes a problem if you're constantly
getting yourself flung up in the air
with nothing to swing from
and just have to free fall for a while.
So that re-parameterization really helped us
to make things fit whatever situation we were dealing with.
Thank you.
Hi, thanks for the talk.
Really, really excellent.
So I have a question about
What you said earlier where you would do animation blending to correct the way Spider-Man was facing during Swing.
But with all of his cool poses and so on, how did you prevent that blend from creating like strange artifacts during the animation?
I'll give a lot of credit there to our animation team with Elliot Grossman, who did a lot of
the animation work, and to our core engine programmer for animation, Johnny Garrett.
They made a sweet animation system and a bunch of sweet animations that did really cool stuff.
For the most part, the blending ended up...
We just made sure to control where those things go,
and we made sure to control when we used them
so that they didn't get too far outside of what we needed.
We also had the side effect that when you're swinging,
you're kind of out in the air.
So, unlike if you're on the ground
or somewhere where you have to really
hand plant on things and touch things,
if there was a little bit of drift
from those partials and stuff,
it didn't really matter as much for swinging.
And so it gave us a lot more freedom
to kind of play with that stuff.
We just had to make sure that visually
you were lined up with the line
and it felt like those forces were correct,
and at that point we were good to go.
Alright, thanks.
Yeah.
Hey, it seems like throughout development you're changing like gravity settings, adding
new mechanics that Spider-Man can use.
How did you like work alongside the level design team like during this process to make
sure that all their work isn't like thrown away as soon as you change like a huge fundamental
setting or something?
That was one of the biggest challenges we had.
You know, working on...
not necessarily a new IP to us.
We didn't really have all of the mechanics locked down
until we were well into production
before things started to get locked down, which,
as you said, creates challenges for the design team.
A lot of it came down to the designer in our pod, Josue,
basically did a lot of work of trying to maintain things
consistently.
He actually built the metrics for the entire city.
by himself, and then it was done.
And then we actually generated the geometry
after that through Houdini.
So we got a lot of consistency in the open world
by just having that go through one person.
For interiors and stuff, we just tried to set up some metrics
and go from there.
I would say that kind of swinging on interiors
is something that I think we didn't make as good
as we would have liked because it was such a big move
and we didn't have the time to really focus on that.
But we were able to use that re-parameterization
to make it work for most of the spaces that we needed it.
Awesome, thanks.
Hi.
Excellent talk.
Thank you so much.
Great game.
I'm definitely stealing all your math.
I noticed in this talk about traversal, you didn't really
talk about the wall climbing at all, like the walking around.
I'm assuming it might have either been outside the scope
of this talk or not super relevant.
But that's a system that I've actually messed around with
for my own game.
And I'm curious if it was ever supposed to be a bigger
element of traversal than it was, and then you clamped it
because it was too complicated.
or any edge cases like that?
So wall crawl was really, you know,
it's really identifiable with the character,
but it has this problem for games,
which is when you do it, you can only go so fast
or you look like a weird salamander.
And usually when people are on a wall,
they want to interact out from the wall.
There's nowhere to put your camera except for inside of you or something.
And so it creates a lot of these gameplay problems.
Our designers in some ways had trouble figuring out how to use it.
Our buildings had a lot of complexity to their geometry
that added a lot of complexity to the wall crawl stuff.
We actually had Ross McIntosh, one of our programmers,
was working on it for.
probably a couple years working on some wall crawl stuff.
And it's a really, really complicated problem
to deal with all of that geometry.
I noticed that you hard clamped it
to go around corners of specific animations
so it didn't actually have to deal
with artifacts and stuff.
Yeah, so we tried to kind of scope down
in places where we could to take some things
that were really hard problems and make them into...
little bit simpler problems.
And so we did that wherever we could with wall crawl.
We still wanted to make sure and fulfill that kind of
fantasy element while having most of the game focused on
this big, fast speed traversal.
And so we just chose to have wall crawl be something that
we implemented as well as we could, but didn't try to
over-focus on.
Makes sense.
Thank you so much.
Hey, amazing talk.
Totally loved it.
We tried to build a Spider-Man game as one of the prototypes
and really, really failed to do it.
So one of the things I had a doubt about
was you mentioned that we used box volumes for collision
detections.
And so how do you decide which objects in the scene
to go to?
Was it applied to everything that he could attach to?
And if so, how did you maintain the performance
as to where you detect the collision occurs?
Does it happen in a particular area, and how so?
So, sorry, was your question like,
how do we decide where to place markup and where not to?
Yeah.
So, for the most part, we wanted to,
in the open world, we marked up everything.
Like I was saying, we used our procedurally generating
system Houdini, well, it's not ours,
it's not worth any license, but,
to place a lot of that stuff, so it was kind of everywhere.
For interiors and things, we would just decide if the space was in metric,
and we would place or not place things based on whether it was in metric for that.
And other than that, we would just find other things that we wanted to attach to,
like treetops and stuff like that, and just place markup there.
That's where we could use our prefabs to say,
okay, this object is always going to come bundled with this markup,
so every time it gets out there, it's populated with that markup.
So it really just came down to anything that, as much as possible,
anything that looked like you should be able to swing from it,
we tried to get markup on it.
Did you have any performance issues in trying to find out which place to attach to or like
whether anything you had to optimize to do that?
We had a few things.
We went through a number of iterations on that.
We ended up getting better by, like I said, using kind of a sphere database and some search
querying to kind of pack all the data in as much as we could.
Really helped us kind of speed things up.
We ended up being able to move it off onto a job on kind of another thread so that it
could happen in the background.
And so it ended up taking, even in an area that was highly dense,
it ended up taking, on the PS4,
probably in a dense area, about 2 milliseconds
to process and chug through everything.
So it wasn't necessarily cheap,
but it wasn't too untractable either.
Cool, thank you.
Hi. Thank you for your impressive session.
So I'm making a swinging VR game,
like Spider-Man.
So if you will make VR Spider-Man,
so what do you change spec or game design?
What was your question?
Sorry, I didn't catch it.
Sorry.
So what do you change for VR game like Spider-Man?
What do we kind of change to make a game like Spider-Man?
go through the town and swing with rope.
So is it kind of how do we have to change the city to make swinging work?
Yeah, you're right.
Gotcha. Okay, so it's actually interesting.
We had a lot of tests early on talking about how wide the streets needed to be.
If you actually take full New York width streets,
they're actually really terrible for swinging
because your line angles end up being like too far to the side.
So we did a lot of tests to figure out what the right widths were for the streets,
a lot of metric tests early on.
And so we had to kind of play around with all of that really early.
in order to find what the right distances were
before we kind of populated the entire city with stuff.
So it was kind of just progressing things a little bit,
a little bit at a time in lockstep
as we were kind of iterating on the design side
and on the world construction side,
iterating on the swing side to make sure those two things
kind of work together in a really nice way.
Thank you.
Cool.
There's other questions?
All right, I think we're out of time.
Thanks guys.