Hello. My name is Jonathan Banks. I'm an environment artist with Telltale Games. Thank you all
very much for coming to this session today. I just wanted to remind a few of you right
now that we don't want to record anything, and also to fill out your evaluations after
this. That would be great. So, I work for Telltale Games. I've been there for about
four years now, and I help define the visual art style for The Walking Dead.
for the Mature franchise.
So how many of you have played the Walking Dead game so far?
Awesome.
Very cool.
For those of you who haven't, I'm going to start by showing a trailer that showcases
the visual art style we achieved.
Rated M for Mature.
Message one.
Oh my god, finally.
I don't know if you tried to reach us.
All the calls are getting dropped.
I want my parents to come home now.
I think that might be a little while.
He's bitten!
We gotta throw him out!
I'm gonna kill him, Kat!
You wanna get violent, you old fuck?
Well, come on!
I don't know who you are or what you did, but you better become a better liar.
All right. So today I'm going to be talking about the art of The Walking Dead and the
approach we at Telltale took to make it happen. The Walking Dead IP is about survivors living
in the aftermath of a zombie apocalypse. It's originally a comic created by Robert Kirkman
with illustrated works by Tony Moore and Charlie Adlard. Telltale's The Walking Dead is based
on the comic book universe.
So typically, most post-apocalyptic games on the market are gritty and realistic.
If you look up zombie game or zombie apocalypse online, you get something like this.
With the exception of Plants vs. Zombies, it all looks pretty much the same.
The imagery is bleak, desaturated, and muted.
Before The Walking Dead, Telltale is a company best known for comical, lighthearted adventure
games such as Tales of Monkey Island, Sam & Max, Puzzle Agent, and Back to the Future.
So going from games like these to The Walking Dead was a difficult task. So how did we do
it? Pre-production.
The general consensus during pre-production was that we wanted to create a unique-looking
game that was familiar to the comics, but also had that strong illustrated style seen
in most telltale titles.
Looking at the comic, we were inspired by its bold compositions and classic comic book
art style.
We really felt that the hand-painted textures and stylistic lighting would be a really good
fit for this franchise.
Inspired, a few quick concepts were made.
These were some of the only concepts made during pre-production.
To move the production forward, we decided to create a 3D environment based on one of
these concepts.
We used the morgue concept as seen here because it visually represented what we were looking
to achieve and was the most graphic.
The end result was this.
This art stayed true to the illustrated concept,
drew inspiration from the comic,
and worked well within the Telltale engine.
This art inspired the team and excited the company.
Most importantly, it moved the production forward.
At the time, I was working on Jurassic Park and Puzzle Agent,
so I did a lot of this during my lunch break.
And this is one of the first pieces of art that was created for the game.
The fundamental techniques that were used to create the environment art were then passed
on to the character department in order to create our first zombie.
Sharing and evolving the artistic process utilized by both the character and environment
art allowed us to create a cohesive world that fully immersed the player.
This was really important to me.
I really wanted all assets to really seamlessly fit together.
After showing this work to Robert Kirkman, he was super enthusiastic with what we were doing, and excited.
With a few assets to work with, our Cinematics and Design department put together the following prototype.
Someone else is here? Thank God. You didn't leave them to us, did you?
No. No, I don't think so.
Look, we need help here. She's having a baby.
Wait a minute. Where'd you come from?
I was looking for medical supplies.
This guy in my camp, he...
Shit! Behind you!
Maybe they didn't hear that.
So I hope one day you'll be able to see that whole prototype in its entirety without it
being cut down. But one thing we learned from that was that
we could tell a mature and engaging story with stylized art.
We also learned that the environments and the characters fit cohesively together.
The art process. Every major element in the game started with
a concept. This included both character art and environment
art.
These illustrated works would then be translated into 3D.
So you can really see how true we stayed to these concepts.
We really tried to recreate what we saw.
This was the first screenshot we ended up sending out to the public.
It was during Comic-Con, and I was a little bit nervous at first.
I wasn't too sure how the public was going to respond to this.
But it was insanely positive.
In fact, I didn't see one negative comment.
The only thing I saw was people started complaining about
the banner ads that had surrounded the articles.
So this positive response is really inspiring to us.
We knew we had created a unique and beautiful world that got
people excited and wanting to see more.
In some cases, there really just wasn't time for a
concept, so we looked to the comic for inspiration.
Herschel's Farm was an example of an environment that we did
not get a concept for at first.
So we looked to the comic.
This is a scan from the comic, and you can see how it was
recreated in 3D.
Stayed really true.
And even though we didn't have a concept at first for this environment,
we still were able to create something really beautiful.
Breaking down the art further,
the following techniques provided solutions
for visually striking real-time art.
These included handcrafted line work,
colorful textures, and atmospheric lighting.
Handcrafted line work.
Working on the Puzzle Agent series, and having developed the 2D techniques used to create
Graham Animals' unique style in 3D, I wanted to take a similar approach to the art creation
for The Walking Dead. In Puzzle Agent, all line work was painted
directly onto textures and then applied to models.
No procedural techniques were used. So this was all done in 3D.
And looking at what we learned from this, we were able to apply it to The Walking Dead.
So as you can see here, the line work was painted directly onto the models.
And I hope these turntables really show you what handcrafted line work looks like.
We kept our line work loose because it more closely resembled that of the comic and could
be easily adapted by all artists in the studio. So this is how it's applied to characters.
And you can see how it's also applied to environments as well.
Later into production, we got a new shader that showed what procedural line work and
shading looked like.
However, it felt too computerized and took away from the player being completely immersed
in the Walking Dead universe.
Therefore, we decided not to use it.
Now, I thought that was a really good approach.
But lately, we've actually had a little bit of time to experiment.
We took basically the best of The Walking Dead,
and we took our procedural shader,
and you can see right here, we just released this yesterday.
This is our new franchise that we're developing.
And the reason I'm showing this is because everything we do at Telltale
is really an evolution of what we've learned from our past products.
So, working on various projects like Puzzle Agent and Jurassic Park,
really learned a lot about the art style for that.
That was also applied to The Walking Dead.
And you can see where we're taking it now.
But that's the future.
Colorful textures.
Unlike the flat colors in Puzzle Agent,
The Walking Dead really needed to have another dimension to its palette.
So as you can see from these textures,
there's an incredible amount of saturation and detail.
There's also what I'd like to call crafted imperfection
into each one of these textures.
And that's really because The Walking Dead deals with
imperfect characters, with imperfect paths,
placed in imperfect situations.
So we wanted to reflect a little bit of that in our textures.
You can see how it's applied to one-offs and also characters.
So breaking down some of these textures even further,
you can see first we used illustrative techniques
to really define highlights and shadows.
We kept this very loose. Then we would add color variation by overlaying watercolor textures
or just painting this directly into the maps. And then, of course, adding line work.
As you can see, when it all comes together in an in-game screenshot, it really helped
our model shine. Atmospheric lighting.
So one of the most important techniques that glued the entire canvas together was atmospheric
lighting.
Using the cinematic lighting techniques we learned in making Jurassic Park, we pushed
it even further with The Walking Dead.
Really Jurassic Park was the first game where we explored cinematic drama.
And we took what we learned from that and applied it to The Walking Dead.
So as you can see here, there's an incredible amount of mood and atmosphere with the lighting.
We have bold use of silhouettes that really give our lighting a noir look to it.
There's a lot of high contrast in here.
You can see how it's applied to some of our other scenes.
Really lighting where we wanted the player to focus their attention.
So we wanted every game, every scene in the game to be unique.
Therefore, we created color-keyed concept art that could be effectively translated by
our 3D artists.
This was also a really great way to see where an episode was progressing through color.
As you can see, if you take one of these color scripts and blow it up, you get something
like this.
And now you can see how it would be translated in 3D.
You can see how close we came to reproducing some of these color keys.
So breaking down a few of these scenes even further, this is just a scene with models
and textures. Then we would light it based on color key
concept art. You can really see just what lighting does
to a scene. There's an incredible amount of mood already.
And then once After Effects and Final Art Direction were involved.
So we didn't have too much After Effects to work with.
Basically what you're seeing here is the addition of depth fog and a color overlay to help basically
pull together some of the colors. We also had, used alpha flats in order to
showcase glows or light beams. And here's the motor in, just models and
textures. Once it's lit.
And then with After Effects and Final Art Direction.
And one of my favorite scenes, St. John's Dairy.
In some cases, you can see some of these textures are gray.
We ended up colorizing them in the engine with lighting.
And then with fog, After Effects, and Final Art Direction.
So you can see there's a tremendous amount of mood and atmosphere
that we were able to put into our scenes just with lighting.
Technical constraints.
So in order to ship on a wide range of platforms,
the following technical limitations were imposed.
Environments had a modeling budget of 30,000 verts.
This was so we could add more characters on screen.
A big part of The Walking Dead is the characters,
but we didn't want the environments to be bare flat.
So basically what we did is we resorted
to low polygon modeling techniques
and used camera-facing flats where appropriate.
At first, we had screen-based ambient occlusion,
but that was removed, so we ended up baking that into the lightmaps.
Vertex lighting replaced perpixel lighting.
As I went over earlier, we had limited post-processing effects.
HDR was removed.
And we had reduced lightmap sizes.
This was the big—this, I think, had the biggest impact on the game.
Basically, we had a new compression algorithm,
and our lightmaps basically went from being very sharp and graphic
to a little bit soft.
However, we didn't let this get to us.
We really just focused on what, with the resources we had,
and we were still able to create some really beautiful art.
This was further, we had our first play test,
and the art received basically some of the highest scores.
Production.
So we ended up creating these style guides
in order to keep the art consistent and production efficient.
This is really a great way to provide new artists tutorials
on how to adapt to the art style.
And within these tutorials, it showed how...
Within these style guides, it showed how to create textures,
outline modeling constraints,
and include brushes that can basically be easily shared
throughout the entire art department.
In some cases, there were some tutorials
that basically showed how to create assets very quickly.
You could use this train as an example right here.
Once it was modeled, line work could be easily applied to it,
and then we could throw on a few base textures
and move it down through the production pipeline.
Later, if time permitted,
we could basically paint over these with a polish pass.
As you can see,
the train now has gone through a polish pass.
It has increased contrast, weathering, and details.
So the information in these style guides
really allowed for quick iterations
and the rapid creation of assets.
Because of this, the art could be iterated upon when changes to the story occurred without
severely affecting the production schedule. This was critical in order to give our writers
the freedom they needed to tell the story they wanted to tell in the time that was given
to them. So in about a year and a half, we created
78 environments, 45 characters, 2,316 textures, and a few more.
275 objects, 77 effects, and a zombie factory.
At one point, the entire company worked on the project, but the core development team
that created the majority of this art consisted of about six artists.
The final product.
Using the resources available to us and embracing our constraints, we created art that successfully
aided in the telling of a mature story.
By merging the look of the comic with Telltale's familiar illustrative style, we created a
beautiful and commercially successful zombie apocalypse.
If there's one thing I learned from working on The Walking Dead, it's this.
Trust in what you do best as a studio and let that shine through the product.
Thank you.
And we have time for questions, so if anyone has any, feel free to ask.
Great work, really love it.
And I had a question.
You commented a little bit about how the final 3D
environments were really driven so much by the concept
art, the style of the concept art.
Could you talk a little bit more about if there were other
areas where the concept art team was interacting with the
modeling team and the texturing team?
Because it almost seems like.
As opposed to normally when there's a painting and it might translate to photorealistic textures,
here it seemed like there was a lot more overlap.
Mm-hmm.
There definitely was.
And even in some cases, they would actually create concepts based on what we had gray
boxed.
At times, you know, they would actually fill us in with a few textures.
They'd come up with some ideas, and that was really cool.
We could kind of bounce off of each other in order to create some really beautiful work.
Great.
Thanks.
One of the things I love about the game was that the characters were very stylized but
still very emotionally expressive, which I think really contributed to how emotionally
mature and dramatic the game was and how much everyone liked it.
Can you speak to sort of using those very stylized faces to convey these very heavy
and serious emotions that were maybe not...
So, that's really what we invest a lot of our technology into.
So, what do you do?
Well, there's, you know, there's basically, they are able to create style guides that
showcase various emotions, and it's really not my department as far as how that is acted
out.
But it's pretty cool what we're able to do at the company.
When you were creating the art, I've never tried to do a visual style like that.
Which maps do you use?
Was that all diffuse only and an emphasis on the line work?
It was.
Yeah, so we didn't use any normal maps.
It was all diffuse based, no specular maps, basic Lambert shading.
Wow.
Yeah.
Very cool, thanks.
Where will you be this Sunday night?
I've got a date, actually, so...
Yeah.
Good choice.
Oh, five?
Okay.
Hi, you briefly mentioned how...
Why everyone's looking at me.
Um, you briefly mentioned how...
As the episodes would progress, there would be a color progression.
Are there any other ways that you progressed how the story and the place in the story,
not the physical location, but like the temporal element of the story,
like where the story is progressing and how the characters are feeling,
like how that plays into the environment?
Can you repeat the question again?
Yeah, so how does...
And what ways does the tone of the story affect the environment in other ways other than just
the color progression in the episode?
Okay, yeah.
So I showed a slide earlier that was like the slaughterhouse right in the back of the
barn.
Yeah.
And so, you know, it wasn't like we would basically, that's a scene that we really wanted
to be scary.
So we added a lot more mood into that.
And that was reflected really in the concept.
Basically, the concept artists would basically see what was going on with the story.
They would get a pitch from there.
Then they would basically be able to do what they do best and concept some art out.
It should have a lot of mood to it.
Where you see sometimes, like in St. John's Dairy.
You could see that it was just in daytime,
and you could see how that progressed as the night came.
We had a lot of rain and atmosphere.
And in some cases, it just evolved that way.
I know when we were first making that specific scene,
it wasn't going to have any rain or any lightning
or anything like that.
But as we started making the game,
we saw that that was just going to add to the scene
if we added all that contrast in there.
Thank you.
Hi. You mentioned earlier that the art is based off of the comics.
But I wanted to know, did you take anything either during the project or personally from
the show at all? Like, while making the environments?
We looked at the whole IP. Okay, cool.
And there was also a few other things we looked at.
I'm just not allowed to talk about them here.
Okay, that's fine. Thank you.
But I love the whole, yeah, the whole series is amazing.
Hi, so my question is a bit about the modularity, I guess.
So I saw that I played the game, and the environments,
they look really, really good and really different.
And I noticed that the colors change a lot.
So I want to know, did you guys reuse many things?
Because I know, since most of the things
were in the textures, like the other guy's question asked,
did you guys reuse a lot of the props?
Or was it totally unique?
Because the environments, they do look,
you can really feel the difference in the pacing.
So yes, the question was, do we reuse anything?
Okay, and yes, we do.
The trick is to not make it look that way,
and I would say that lighting played an integral part with that.
One thing that I did was actually create an asset library.
And that was, that you could easily,
see most engines have this basically,
where you can, you have all your different assets
and you can easily populate a scene.
And that was actually really helpful with everything we were doing.
Especially once we reached like episode four and five.
And we, you know, our schedule got crunched.
And so really setting up some of these techniques
that we could create environments and scenes
really quickly was essential.
And then using, you know, we had a little bit of tech
where we could take textures and shift the color around.
And then, of course, with lighting.
It's amazing what you can do with lighting
to cover a lot of that up.
Thanks.
Speaking of lighting, could you tell us how many lights you needed on average in a scene,
and what kind?
So, well we had per-vertex lighting, but that was all real-time lights, and that was mainly
on the characters.
For environment specifically, we could use any astronomical number, basically, because
it was all baked lighting.
We did use ambient occlusion as well where appropriate.
So it didn't really matter when it came to baked lighting.
In some cases, we were able to override some of the baked lighting with real-time lighting.
And that's usually about four point lights that we have access to.
Sometimes less.
Depends on if it ships on, like, iPhone or not.
Yeah.
All right.
Is that it?
Thank you all for coming.
Really appreciate it.