Welcome all to this talk about product discovery
and integrating citizen science into EVE Online.
Just to kind of start you off, please, you know the drill,
turn off your phones and fill out the survey
and all the nice things.
My name is Berkut Fynboson.
People call me Berkut, like hamburgers.
It's much easier.
I'm a senior development manager at CCP Games in Reykjavik.
And I'm Ottila Sonner, I'm the CEO and co-founder
of Massively Multiplayer Online Science.
And exactly a year ago during GDC,
we launched a new project, codenamed Project Discovery,
which later became one of the biggest
citizen science efforts in 2016.
This is even more remarkable if you consider the fact that none of the parties involved
had a track record in citizen science.
So how did we manage to make this work?
Well as a teaser I can tell you that video games and gamers play a substantial role in
the success.
But to tell you the whole story, I have to start with citizen science.
Citizen science is the crowdsourcing of scientific data analysis or data acquisition, but I believe
it's much more than that.
It has a very strong educational aspect.
And also it's an invaluable tool in scientific outreach.
It's paramount that we understand what scientists are working on,
even if it may be on a superficial level.
And what would be a better tool for that
than to actually work on the data that scientists work with?
So citizen science, I believe, is very important.
Now, you may have heard the term citizen science,
and I'm pretty sure you met some of these projects
in citizen science, like the protein folding game,
where we try to find native structures of proteins, or...
Zooniverse slash Galaxy Zoo, where we classify galaxies captured on Hubble deep space images.
Actually this project became so successful, so popular, that a whole platform grew out of it,
and now they're hosting like more than 50 different projects.
Another good example is the Phylo,
which is a project from Canada,
from the McGill University.
And here researchers are trying to solve
DNA sequence alignment problems.
And finally, a final example, iVIR,
where we have to map the visual neurons in the human brain.
All of these projects do an amazing job in citizen science, but they have a major problem
to tackle, and that is user engagement and retention.
So that's where our story started.
Three years ago, with a friend of mine, Bernhard Revers,
we had an idea that instead of creating standalone citizen
science games or citizen science gamified experiences,
why don't we take these problems and integrate them
with the most engaging form of entertainment of today, which
is unquestionably video games?
integrating them with major already existing AAA titles,
and integrate them as a seamless gaming experience.
And our hypothesis was that if we managed to make this,
managed to create this experience,
managed to match the visuals, connect the dots with the lore,
with the reward system, with the game mechanics,
and ask the pros of the game industry
to create an engaging experience,
then we might be able to transform a tiny percentage
of all the time that we spend with gaming.
to do something good in real life.
And that tiny percentage would be a virtually limitless
human computation engine to serve science.
So that was our initial concept.
And first we contacted researchers.
We tried to validate the idea.
We got very enthusiastic responses,
and we met with Emma Lundberg.
She's heading a research group in Sweden
at the Human Protein Atlas.
They're building a big open database of microscope images.
And we immediately knew that this kind of material
would be a perfect raw material for a first project.
She has a quarter million images, beautiful ones.
The task of the gamer was to find or localize the green markings on the image
that mark the location of a certain protein.
This was one part of the job, this was actually the easier part of the job, we had a lot of friends in research.
But the harder part was to get in touch with the gaming industry, with you guys.
And when we had this idea, I immediately knew that EVE Online would be a perfect match for the project.
So we started to work on that, and after a couple of months,
I got an email from Andy Norgren,
she's the executive producer of EVE Online,
that this sounds intriguing, let's have a Skype.
So, she immediately became a huge supporter of the project,
and around 2015, November, we already flew to Reykjavik,
and we're presenting this concept
to the stakeholders at CCP.
So integrating citizen science into a AAA-established computer
game is no easy task.
Like Attila was saying, the EVE dev team
was super curious about this idea and about this project.
And for those of you that don't know EVE Online,
EVE Online is a single-seat, massively multiplayer online
game where hundreds of thousands of players
fight over power, wealth, and fame.
And in EVE, players decide their own fate and write their
own stories.
But, you know, product discovery and EVE Online.
Why?
Well, first, because of science.
There are all huge science buffs at CCP.
And for myself, my kind of first interaction with
crowdsourced science was this beautiful thing called
SETIatHome.
I think this was like back in 1999 or something.
And me and my best friend used to sit and watch this
for hours, looking for aliens in faraway galaxies.
We were actually on dial-up modem,
so his mom was not happy when she got the phone bill.
But hey, science.
But the thing, there was no interaction with this.
This was just something you watched,
and it just kind of chucked along.
We kind of, you know, while we were looking at this,
we were kind of, you know, we were talking about it,
and we were kind of role-playing this whole thing.
And, you know, of course, playing, at that time,
a lot of XCOM apocalypse, I think it was, you know,
because we had to prepare for the invasion.
So it had kind of been, you know, stuck in my mind
for quite some time,
long before I started the gaming industry.
It's like, how can you actually merge these two together?
So when Attila called, I was super stoked.
And this is a...
This is a really interesting game design challenge.
And we really look at this as an opportunity
to take part in something much bigger,
and who isn't up for a great challenge?
And we also believe that, we also
hope that our example sets the stage
for many other successful collaborations between science
and gaming to come.
So yeah.
There were a lot of unknowns when we dove into this.
And we really enjoy unknowns at CCP.
And it was everything from technical unknowns
to legal issues, very, very, very interesting legal issues.
And also, how in the world we're going
to design and build this thing.
But we set four main design principles
to guide us on this journey.
The first one was we wanted the science to be of real world
purpose and altruistic nature.
So drone strike analysis bad, cancer research or mapping
human proteins, good.
It had to be aesthetically fitting and thematically
adoptable to fit the EVE universe.
And so we didn't want research data with images of giraffes
or rhinos.
Or we didn't really want any street signs from planet Earth,
since New Eden is very far from planet Earth.
The task had to take consistent length of time to solve.
We didn't want to create a moment where
some things are like two seconds,
and then you get like a 15 minute data set you had to
solve.
And the research needed a high volume of tasks.
So a quarter of a million tasks fitted the first research
data quite well.
So as you've seen, the data from Human Protein Atlas is
really beautiful.
And actually, to a point where our director thought we had
tinkered with the data before showing it to him.
Thematically in-game, the in-game science faction,
Sisters of Eve, are actually researching tissue samples
they've gotten from the mysterious drift arrays
in the game.
They're trying to kind of make sense of these drifters.
The Sisters of Eve research group
is led by Professor Lundberg
and calls upon capsuleers of New Eden
to take part in solving this scientific challenge
through the Project Discovery interface.
And this is really great, because you
have Professor Lindbergh in game and then
Professor Lindbergh in reality.
So you're kind of merging, kind of playing with merging realities
here.
On time to complete, we knew that this was not
the easiest task to understand, mapping these proteins.
So we spent a lot of time balancing and tweaking
and working, testing the game out on our test servers
and getting a lot of great feedback from our players.
And yeah, there was a lot of tweaks in the first month
of testing.
And as I said before, the Subcellular Protein Atlas
had around 250,000 samples.
So we thought it was a great kind of start project
for PRODISCOVERY.
Our preliminary calculation gave us around two to three months
to reach full consensus on the data.
And we were proven wrong, but I won't spoil it.
I won't spill the beans for Attila.
He will have something fun for him to talk about.
So actually, how did we build this thing?
We partnered up with Reykjavik University, the computer
science department at Reykjavik University, to work
with us on this.
And we thought it was a great opportunity to kind of
strengthen our ties with universities in Iceland.
And kind of, you know, it's.
kind of goes a full circle then.
So this is the first version of Eve Citizen Science.
This was a web browser version we showed at FanFest.
I think it was 2015 when we showed this.
Yeah, so.
And yeah, we showed the first version at EVE FanFest 2015.
Got a lot of great feedback there.
Then took it to EVE Vegas and launched it
on CC, which is our test server.
And then launched it exactly a year ago.
kind of the core idea of ProDiscovery is that CCP provides the framework and then MMOS
provides the content. It's kind of the link between us and the scientists and the scientists
or the science partners provide the content for this frame. This makes the whole kind
of dependency chain really interesting because due to legal issues we are not allowed to
host a lot of the data that's being shown here.
And so there's a really interesting challenge of giving
away, kind of having to depend on a third party
for your content.
Which is always a super scary thing when you're a game
developer, because if anyone has tried it, time to penis
is very short.
So how does it actually work in game?
While you play EVE Online, you can launch the Pro Discovery
window and play.
And this is because of the time to complete is relatively
short, it's a great thing you can do while doing things that
take a long time, such as mining, or when you're
traveling between places, or just hanging around in
stations chatting to people.
So it's kind of a good side project to work on.
So when you open the interface, you get an image of a cell sample, and your task is to identify where the green-marked proteins...
Yeah, where the green proteins sit.
For example here, it's in the nucleus, I think.
Yeah, nucleus, probably.
Now someone called me out.
So yeah, you pick the categories on...
you're right, and once you kind of feel confident,
you submit your answer,
and the answer is analyzed against
all the other analysis submitted for that sample.
That then gives you feedback on your submission.
In this case here, we picked the correct answer.
You can have multiple answers, which makes this exponentially
more difficult. But to actually calculate accuracy and to
reward you, there are around 15% of all tasks in Pro Discovery
are what we call pre-solved or gold standard tasks that we use
to, yeah, judge your accuracy.
and reward you accordingly.
When you reach a new level, so you basically level up slowly.
You gain experience point and level up slowly.
And when you reach a new level, you
get something called analysis credits, which then you
can spend to buy some awesome rewards that you can't get
anywhere else, but while you play this thing.
So actually on the gold standard, what's quite interesting is because we can't host any of the images,
the gold standard tasks are balanced by the scientists.
So that creates a lot of really interesting back and forth between us as game developers
and the scientists and kind of talking about game best practices.
And I think the HPA guys are, you know, they're becoming like super game developers slowly.
And so once a sample reaches a significant level of agreement,
we can say with some certainty that it
has reached a consensus.
Yeah, so the sample actually lives in a database until that consensus has been reached.
And this can mean anything between 15 to 50 submissions of each sample.
So the dataset, you know, even if the dataset is 250,000 images,
it's actually 250,000 times 15 to 50.
So it's a relatively big, big task.
And I thought to get our hands a bit more dirty
with technical details.
We created a platform that on one side
standardizing the data and the problem types that
comes from research, and the other side,
it provides an API for game developers, which is important
because.
You can focus on creating the user interface and an engaging experience for your players
and you don't have to be swarmed by the details of the citizen science process itself.
that is very important that this part of the architecture
is performance, so it can handle heavy load.
And also from a business point of view,
it's interesting that we're a neutral party,
so I think that way it's easier for other game developers
to hop on board and be part of this.
Now, I really hope that at this point you already see how cool
and important and fun this project is, but I really want
to show how easy it is to integrate.
So basically there are two things that you have to do.
This is roughly the code that you have to call to get a task.
From our servers, we provide you with all the information
that you need to visualize this task.
And then when the player is ready, you submit the task.
Again, relatively simple.
And our API provides you with all the information that is
needed to show the results screen.
We give you an accuracy score that you can use to hand out
rewards for the players.
So it's as simple as that, other than that you can really
focus on building an engaging experience and connecting the
dots with the lore and all the in-game mechanics.
So the results.
After all this preparation, you can
believe that we couldn't wait to see how players reacted
and what's coming out of this.
And it was way beyond our wildest imaginations.
This is the numbers from the first day.
We had around half a million classifications,
and almost 15,000 images reached consensus.
This was along with about three or four hours of downtime.
I was here at GDC.
I couldn't come to GDC.
I was in the hotel room with not the best internet trying
to keep the whole thing alive.
So it's quite interesting.
And another nice metric is the Sisters of Eve combat suit,
which is kind of the ultimate reward in Project Discovery.
And we thought that it would take at least a couple of days
to hand out one of those.
We had to hand out 45 in the first day, which was pretty unbelievable.
I don't remember, you had the number of how many hours we estimated?
It was 16 hours and 17 minutes to hand out the first one.
And the second one was like two minutes later.
So that guy, like if he wouldn't have had a toast, but rather just like dry bread.
You would have won, so tough luck.
Yeah, we could call it a draw, I think.
Yeah, we could call it a draw.
So it was pretty amazing.
We thought that we had a quarter million images to analyze as the first batch.
We had an estimation of two or three months.
Again, we were very wrong with this.
Players have gone over the whole first batch in three weeks' time.
And since then, actually, we put the same data set
for the sixth time in the system for players to analyze,
which is really interesting from the citizen science point
of view to see how the different consensus, what
is the relation between time and the different consensus
that players are creating and so on.
So in itself, it's really interesting research
in citizen science.
And as of today, we have more than 25 million classifications
in the system, which is pretty amazing.
From the scientific side, where researchers are still
working on to analyze the data, there is one thing
that Emma already published, is this.
This is a very special protein structure
called rods and rings, for obvious reasons.
And players have identified around 100 new protein
candidates that play a part in this structure.
So it's already really nice.
From a game designer point of view, I think.
it's even more interesting how the community reacted.
And we can say that the community embraced the project.
They were very active, they created a lot of content,
Wiki pages, tutorial videos.
These are some quotes from e-forums,
which show how strong the educational aspect
of the project was and how a great experience
CCP created around the problem set.
One of our favorite thing is this poetry competition.
Which was about project discovery and I love this almost classic tubular red nucleus is blue
But it's only the green that matters to you which actually describes perfectly what you have to do in the project
From the researcher side, as Berggruen mentioned, we created an avatar for Emma.
But it's not just that, but they were really active in the whole process.
So they were communicating with the players, they were active on the forums, they were coming to FanFest.
And, for example, they were giving a streaming lecture.
about proteomics in Yves University,
using the same material that they used in Stockholm
for university students to teach proteomics,
which was a really nice crossover.
Also, one of my favorite stories
about how committed they were is that
two years ago when we, at Yves Vegas,
where we showcased the first prototype,
Emma actually cancelled her appearance at the Proteomics Conference where she was supposed
to speak about her research and opted to come to Vegas and talk to players about this.
And then we had a live citizen science tournament
in Reykjavik last week.
It was a lot of fun.
And actually Hilmar mentioned it in his closing speech
as this being the next eSports,
which was of course a huge exaggeration,
but it was really nice to hear.
And then we had a lot of articles about the project,
both in high profile scientific journals.
Actually, the journalist who wrote this article told me
that this is the first time that I published a screenshot
from video game, which is nice, I think.
And also in mainstream media.
Of course, this was very good for CCP, this was very good for us, for Human Protein Atlas, for the project,
but I think having that much attention from the general public, from non-gamers,
having such positive messages in the media is very important for the whole gaming industry.
Now a couple of words about the future.
So we are, of course, trying to work with more and more game
developers.
One project that I can talk of is Gearbox.
Two years ago, I met with Randy Pitchford here at GDC,
and he became a
a very big fan and supporter of this whole project.
And I don't know if you've seen his presentation.
He showed some images and videos about new artistic styles
and techniques that they're experimenting with.
And we just can't wait to see how citizen science can
be integrated with that titles.
Another thing is this, we realize that from a higher
perspective what we're doing, we're trying to find
already existing, established, active online communities
and try to kind of tweak their activities a bit
or smuggle a little bit of science in their everyday life.
And so we thought that why don't we approach MOOCs,
which are these big open online courses
with tens of thousands of very enthusiastic
and motivated students,
and why don't we bring real life scientific data
for them to analyze.
So in that effort, we are working together
with the Geneva University,
and we try to bring exoplanet research data
into their course on the subject.
And they are a very prestigious institute on that,
because Michel Mayor, who is a professor of the university,
is actually the researcher who found the very first exoplanet.
So that's very interesting.
And of course, a very important part of our future plans
is to have new projects together with CCP.
So with the human proton atlas project,
it has run its course.
So we have decided to sunset it and start
focusing on all the research.
And it's actually quite great, because now we've
built this framework.
And it's now a matter of trying to find new ways to visualize
new types of data.
And I think they're interesting.
creative layer. So kind of the four principles that I talked about earlier,
what we actually learned, you know, since we wrote those is that, you know,
looking for a new project,
kind of the most important thing that we found is that we don't want to devalue
the project as it is today.
We have set a certain expectation standard in ProDiscovery.
And it's not only the altruistic nature
and the seamless connection
that kind of pulls in the community,
but it's also the complexity and the depth of the research.
Kind of a caveat here,
the EVE community is very open and willing to take on
like very difficult challenges.
And you know, they kind of,
I don't know if you've played EVE,
but EVE is kind of a hardcore game.
That's, yeah.
It's kind of a,
maybe a
light, yeah.
But of course, there are plenty of simpler research projects
out there, so you don't need to worry that you need to teach
your players to fold proteins or something.
So after going through a few different data sets and
narrowing down, we managed to narrow it down to something
that felt really close to home.
And we were actually going to work with the University of
Geneva.
to search for exoplanets.
We were going to announce it at GDC,
but then NASA announced TRAPPIST-1 last week.
And we were like, hey, that's kind of the same thing
as we're doing.
And they're also working with University of Geneva.
So let's join up.
So for those of you that don't know,
exoplanets are planets orbiting suns outside our solar systems.
All the stars that you see in the sky are.
in simple terms, suns.
Yeah, the data set is extremely big.
I mean, it's almost as big as the stars you see in the sky.
But at the same time, there are some limiting factors
and issues.
For instance, the gold standard set
is limited to the amount of exoplanets that we know about.
even, you know, that kind of takes the gold standard set down to a few thousands.
And even like, you know, if you want to get data sets or gold standards data in the resolution
that we're looking for, it actually limits it even further down.
And so Professor Lindberg will actually pass the torch over to Michel Meyer,
who is going to be the ambassador for this new project.
an avatar in game, which is pretty cool.
And almost as cool as him getting a Wolf Prize this year
in physics, which is also really cool.
But yeah, like Attila was saying,
Michel found the first exoplanet back in 1995.
So we're really excited of getting him on board.
And he will actually be coming to FanFest this year,
giving a talk, a super scientific talk
about exoplanets.
So the data that we're receiving from in this phase of ProDiscovery is
are kind of these light curves and this is basically
in simple terms this is almost like a time lapse of a star so
you have a telescope and it takes snapshots of the star over a period of
time and when you kind of plot these up you
get these beautiful light curves.
And what the players are looking for are actually dips in this
light curve.
And that's basically when something goes in front of the
star and blocking the light from it.
In science terms, this is called a transit.
So players would be looking at transits.
And here you see a better representation of transits.
These are like multiple transits.
And of course, you know this thing.
you know, by now this is the TRAPPIST-1 light curve.
And yeah, this is, this is, this is, these are the seven exoplanets that were
announced last week by University of
Lice in collaboration with NASA and
all sorts of cool, um, you know, yeah, scientific.
universities and stuff.
But what's actually nice is that the University of Geneva
holds the prestigious last position in the Nature article
that announced the find.
So we're super happy that we're working with them.
So why can't we use algorithms to find these exoplanets?
Well, we somewhat can use algorithms
to find these exoplanets.
There is a box-fitting algorithm.
used to search for periodic transits in the light curves.
This method is called BLS or box-fitting least squares.
I hope that's correct.
It's more or less like a periodogram
looking for periodic events in the light curve
and computing the power as a function of the frequency.
And then the algorithm folds the light curve to find,
to the highest identified peak in the BLS.
But, there are some issues with it.
It's great when you have like a single planet.
This works great when you have a single planet,
but this starts to break really badly
when you have multi-planet systems like Trappist-1,
and when you have...
circumbindary planets that you see here, basically, systems
with two suns, monotransit events, and transits that are
masqueraded by strong stellar activity, so if you have a lot
of activities around.
So humans are actually outperforming the algorithm.
So there is still some hope for humans, which is great.
And there are also a lot of interesting challenges here
that we're working through with the students
from Reykjavik University.
They're both really interesting technical issues
with how in the world do you render
ridiculous amount of data points in a graph in E1 line?
How do you fold these light graphs
and how do you actually mark them?
And then how do you mark multiple transits?
But there's also a lot of really interesting game design
questions.
And since we only want to host one project at a time,
one really interesting challenge is how do you sunset the Human
Protein Atlas project, and how do you do it gracefully,
and how do you store the data and store the prestige
that people have managed to create for themselves?
Another interesting challenge is that exoplanets are really,
really, really, really, really rare.
So how do you make an engaging experience searching
for a needle in a haystack?
So that's definitely a fun problem to solve.
And then we also want to create opportunities for mastery,
and that's super important.
So a couple of takeaways from this lecture.
And this was actually a super fun project to work on.
Even if it's considered a serious game,
it's still entertaining.
And it is entertainment.
And I mean, I think the game is fun.
But what's actually also really great
is that we managed to connect people that usually don't talk.
I've probably never googled as many words from emails in my life.
I've learned a lot of words that I can never use, but again,
but my Google searches are very interesting now.
I mean, we were kind of one of the reasons why this project, I think, worked really well with us,
is that we have a really engaged community, and they're really engaged with this project.
They actually made their own subreddit about ProDiscovery that kind of blew up.
It was amazing and there was a lot of people like non-scientists that,
non-EVE players that participate in this community.
So that's really, really great.
Like I said before, I mean, this was a huge leap of faith, you know,
trusting a third party to provide content.
for a game is a very, very, very scary thought.
And it's something we talked a lot about in CCP.
If it's like, this is like one of the big blockers
for the project in the beginning.
It's like, how can you make sure that like,
how can you make sure that we can press this person?
And, but it, you know, it was unnecessary scare.
I mean, the project has, you know, not, yeah, it's been up.
Yeah, it's very little downtime.
And it's really good content.
And we managed to kind of emerge the content fairly
seamlessly with the game and the whole game experience.
And kind of apart from this being fun, we found that there
are two main reasons why that kind of drove people back to
Pro Discovery.
The first one was that there was a big group of people that
looked at Pro Discovery as a
almost as mining, so there was exclusive rewards that you
couldn't get anywhere else, and you could sell it
for a good profit.
And then there was also a very big group of players that are
just doing it for the science, and are doing it for the
greater good.
And it's actually amazing the amount of people that have
ridiculous amount of analysis credits and are not spending
it, because the reward is doing science.
And so that's really great.
And also, Huw and Proton Atlas did a fantastic job
embracing the community.
Everything from communicating with people on Twitter quite
actively, to opening up their wall to send along people into
the wikis, and giving university lectures in the
in-game university, Eve University.
So we definitely want to, this is one of the things that
drove us and Attila to.
investigate MOOCs and allow players to dive as deeply as
they want into the subject at hand.
Yeah, and also, like what I said before, what MMOS is
providing is not limited to cell images or exoplanets.
It's really easy to kind of imagine how this could fit into other games.
I mean, here is something that's super straightforward.
I mean, these are not actual projects.
This is just like sketches, like bad Photoshop, producer Photoshop, like I call it.
I mean, here you can see like, you know, us, Zoo, Zoo Universe kind of analyzing
images, animal images from webcams.
like automated images or, you know, even cooler, like,
if you could, you know, use your pip in Fallout 4 to cure cancer.
I don't know. That would be awesome.
Anyone from Bethesda? Bling, bling.
But all in all, I mean, now we have the infrastructure in place
and we can really start to kind of weave the core storyline
of the game with Pro Discovery.
giving us more tools to deepen the experience and blur the lines between the reality of EVE Online and the reality that we live in.
And by doing this we hope to set an example,
we hope that our example sets the stage for many more successful collaborations between science and gaming to come.
So yeah, Citizen Science begins with you.
Any questions?
I have a question actually, yeah.
Yep, there's a mic in the center.
Sure.
It's been a little while since I played Eve,
but you guys do have a lot of sort of,
for the Bartles type players that don't want to do combat,
but want to do exploration and research,
there's a lot of options for that in the game.
There's like the probe ships that you can get
that are sort of more specialized towards exploration.
How much did Project Discovery bleed
into that sort of exploration play type?
Like were there ships that were better at pulling in data
that were like research ships or anything like that?
So we wanted the project to be something for everyone.
And we wanted the barrier of entry to be as low as we could,
because analyzing proteins is actually
a fairly difficult task.
So for this initial project, we did not
tie it into any of the core systems.
But this actually served us as great PVE.
And it's actually great exploration content in an odd way.
It's a really cool project.
I just want to congratulate you guys on the success so far.
I think I heard you said something,
you had like 250,000 protein samples.
I was just wondering if you could elaborate
where those came from and how they were collected.
They were coming from the Human Protein Atlas.
And it's a 10, 15 year research project.
And they're building an open database
of microscopic images.
So it was them who acquired these images.
They have a state of the art technology.
They're acquiring, I don't know how many images per week.
But it's growing, growing continuously.
I think it's super cool that your players actually were the ones that created that subreddit
And I'm super hoping that they're that the scientists on the team did an AMA that we all can read
But my question is how did you initially communicate the the real-world?
quality of this this
Project or minigame to your players like they clearly know what's going on and why it's important, and what did you how'd you tell them?
and
That's a good question.
We had no idea how to communicate it.
We're really good at communicating
in-game, in-lore type of communication,
but this tie-in between real science and in-game content.
There was a lot of debate like, hey, how much should we?
downplay or upplay the real science part,
because in a way, you don't want to break the immersion
of you're playing Eve, and when you're playing
Pro Discovery in Eve, you're actually doing science
for the science faction.
So there was a very delicate balance,
but then it just spun out, and people kind of started
writing whatever they wanted.
I mean, you guys have such a good community
that I figured you did something on the forums
or something like that first.
You didn't do that?
No, we did like, I mean, we had like a webpage and we have forums and video blogs and on our own kind of in-game news network and yeah, so multiple channels. Awesome.
Hey guys, amazing talk and project and I was wondering if you can shed some light about how will you turn the Exoplanet stuff into a gameplay experience?
Yeah, so I mean we are kind of in the initial steps in making it, but there is a really...
So you're basically looking for these transits, and when you're looking for these transits,
they should happen in a certain rhythm.
So what you're looking for, you're both looking for the dips, and then you're also looking for the rhythms of those dips.
So there is some really cool tools that you have to use
where you're kind of overlapping the light curves
on top of itself, and then aligning,
kind of using the power of the dip,
you try to align the transits.
There's actually a second state that will kind of look like.
the curves kind of, you know, they have,
usually have somewhat of a sine wave.
So, you know, you need to also normalize that.
So there is a, you know, multiple kind of tools that you use.
But it's, I mean, it's one of the things
that we are debating a lot right now.
And what extra things we'll add into it.
But yeah, you are looking for a needle in a haystack.
So there is a lot of data that has nothing in it.
So there is, yeah, there is an interesting mastery element.
Okay, okay. Thank you.
Hey. When you pick the game, you mentioned that you want a
consistent play time. So it doesn't sometimes finish too
fast or too slow. Is that because of the gameplay or more
for rewarding? Because for City at Home you mentioned, right,
they had no problem dealing with different kind of CPUs because
we can always weigh all the outcomes and reward fairly.
And even if the rewards are not different, I mean, people are apparently buying crates, trying to open them in CSGO.
So I suppose even random chance of different rewards may not be a problem.
So is that more from gameplay's perspective to make it more interesting?
Yeah, it was definitely from a gameplay perspective.
You know, we want to, when you open up this thing, we kind of want you to have the feeling that...
you know what you're getting yourself into.
Like, you don't want to,
we don't want to create a feeling of you, like,
not knowing if, you know, you will do like two
and that will be like five minutes,
or if you do two and you will do like, you know, 30 minutes.
So we just, the consistent time was more to,
yeah, just kind of create familiarity
and not scare people away.
Okay.
Thank you.
Hi there. My name is Brandon. I'm a grad student at the University of Utah. I make games that
heal people. So hearing this talk from you two is really inspiring. Yeah, what you're doing is
making a huge impact.
really, really exciting to see.
So one of the things that kind of stood out to me
is really important for making this work
is the partnership between the university and CCP.
So I was wondering if you could maybe elaborate
a bit more on that, like what value did
the university see in collaborating with CCP
and vice versa too?
I'd love if you guys could elaborate on that a bit.
Sorry, what was the last thing?
Just elaborating on the partnership between the two,
and what value you each saw in each other.
Yeah.
I mean, it's working with universities.
I mean, the good thing about working with universities
is you get just a much more academic approach to the issue,
rather than us game developers,
and we've been groomed in thinking in productions
and production cycles, and like, oh, this won't work.
But.
So kind of research is sometimes organized to the bottom
when you're in production, sadly.
So we've learned a lot from working with the university
and just kind of their approaches to the issue
and how they kind of deal with and dissect the issues
at hand.
Kind of a bonus from that is that we've actually found
awesome developers.
through these projects that are now working with us.
So that's also just kind of helping,
I mean that's helping the tiny island of Iceland a lot
because we have, it's sometimes tricky
to lure people to move to Iceland to work.
Wonder why.
So, no, it's been really good and there's a very,
we have a very healthy relationship
with universities in Iceland.
Yeah, and I don't know if you care to share, Attila,
any about that relationship, too.
Well, I think one thing which was really interesting,
and probably Berger should talk about that,
we had a presentation with Andy,
One big obstacle in the very early stage of the project is how to justify it.
Both inside CSC and both for the gamer community.
This is something that needs a bit of focus, so it means that other things will lose a bit of focus,
and players always have things that they want to improve.
And so she had to justify all this.
And this was a very lucky setup that we
can say that a lot of the work was
done by external students or interns in the company.
So we could communicate that there is not
huge loss of focus in CCP.
So I think that was a really interesting approach.
OK, thank you.
Hi, thanks for the talk first of all.
And I just want to ask, I think it's great what you're doing
because while the human brain is great at pattern recognition,
even to the point where humans can recognize patterns
where there are none, did you take any steps
to avoid fake data from people seeing patterns
where there are none?
Yes, we did.
So one of the issues with crowdsourcing and crowdsourcing
science is...
are like trends, and you know, if things go viral.
And we had the thing go viral very early on in the project
where people like started to, I mean,
they started to spam one of the protein categories
called the cytoplasm.
And we had to react really quickly,
and luckily it was, you know, really early on
and we managed to kind of deal with it right away.
So we had to, we kind of changed
our reward structure a little bit.
But this is always one of the top things you have to worry about in any crowd sourcing thing.
It's like if everyone decides to press A, then A must be the right answer.
That's kind of the issue. It's one of the downsides of crowd sourcing.
But I don't know. I think we're getting really good data.
The accuracy is relatively good when you compare it to crowd sourcing.
gold standard and analysis done by scientists.
So.
So just to add a little bit more on that,
in the beginning we used two ways
to benchmark players' performance.
One was gold standard.
That was pretty straightforward.
And the other way was when we reached consensus
on a certain image, then we retroactively
adjusted the scores of players.
And that was a small point where players
could actually exploit the system if they wanted to.
Plus, cytoplasm is a location in the cell
which appears more often,
and it's kind of a judgment call in many cases,
whether you mark it as a class or it's there,
but it's not really a signal.
Putting all this together, we had this thing which we called
later Cytoplasm Scam, and then we quickly, quickly really just
removed that kind of
thing in the system where we retroactively adjusted the scores and we now just use gold
standard. Which is actually, it's interesting because in many classical citizen science
projects they actually use this approach to benchmark users' performance. But you know,
games are a bit different.
Yeah, great. Thanks and keep up the good work.
you might have just answered this question partially with
that response. But with project discovery, you talked about your
accuracy being measured against all the other submissions from
crowdsourcing. You guys blew up pretty quickly within the first
24 hours, so maybe this wasn't at the end of the day a problem.
But did you have any concerns or considerations within the first
few hours or the first few days on not having the database to
base your samples against?
Actually, the first few days, the only consideration
was to keep the system running.
We didn't have time to analyze the data quality.
But I think already at that point,
we knew that it's going to be very successful
from the perspective of activity.
so it gives us more space to maneuver.
So that's why we focused on first to find the glitches
in the system and the bottlenecks,
and then it took like two weeks,
and then after that we could focus on the quality.
But this Cytoplasm scan was so obvious
and so everywhere in the forums, as far as I remember,
so actually that we corrected in the first week.
But I mean this is also where the consensus of the consensus was quite interesting
So we could see after after the first three weeks when we reached consensus when we got the second consensus
We could basically look at the two data sets together and see hey, you know how much offset was in the initial spike
And you know how much?
Badness or goodness, you know was the initial spike, but they were relatively consistent
at least the first three consensus.
Yeah, it's really interesting because in classical citizen science platforms, they try to optimize
more or less the usage of citizen science resources.
So they try to use algorithms so that you can reach a consensus for a relatively low
number of votes.
Whereas here now we are improving a platform that we can kind of automatically...
put on the queue the same task that has been solved because
it's an interesting thing. Of course we try to optimize the
solution of one certain task
but then
you know, it's not possible to change, like,
research project in a game from one day to the other.
Whereas on the classical platforms,
you just close the project and you choose another.
Here, we have to keep it running.
So here, even if they solved it in three weeks,
we have to keep it running for half a year.
So that's also an interesting specialty of this approach.
Yeah.
Thank you, guys.
Thank you.
All right.
Well, thank you very much.
Thanks for coming.