Thank you for all of you for coming out to Reign's Game of Thrones, the Song of Fire and License.
I want to first introduce us three panelists. I'm a semi-moderator, but also going to be chiming in as a panelist as well.
Just starting with myself, I work at Devolver Digital. My name is Nigel Lowry, and I work at Devolver Digital, the publisher of Reign's Game of Thrones and the Reign's series.
And hopefully we'll be able to lead this conversation.
Yeah, so I'm Francois Haliot.
I'm the designer, developer, and author, writer
of Reigns Game of Thrones and the other Reigns, too.
In various capacities, I'm the developer.
Hey, I'm Jeff Peters.
I'm the VP of licensing and retail at HBO.
My group is in charge of basically all the consumer
products for HBO's television shows, which
extends out to digital games.
We were the team that worked directly with Devolver and Nereal to create this collaboration.
And so there's a lot of people behind that work at Nereal, at Devolver Digital and HBO that worked on this.
But we're the three that kind of pulled our teams and talked about what we wanted to kind of get out there about the story of this project.
So the goals and the takeaways is a very brief chat.
The first part is a very brief chat about licensed games and the relationship to brands.
That's kind of how this started. I wanted to speak about licensed games at first.
Originally it was going to be a larger panel with a lot of people that worked on a variety of licensed games,
but in talking to our mentors at GDC, they thought it was best, and I see why now,
to tell the full story as much as we can about Reigns Game of Thrones is a little more focused,
and about our experience, so hopefully it will be helpful to the audience.
You guys look into licensed games or have a licensed project proposed to you.
The bulk of this conversation is to be a discussion of Reign's Game of Thrones, the game.
I list here as an unreproducible case study that hopefully can provide you guys with some action items,
some insights, some stories and anecdotes that, again, if you guys have an opportunity to work on a licensed game,
this will be of service to you.
I say unreproducible, and we'll get to this again later.
A lot of games, a lot of success, and a lot specifically in this project you'll see
is a matter of timing, things coming together, and a lot of luck.
I don't think people should be ashamed of admitting that success is a large part of
luck and I think that's a lot about what we'll talk about today.
And then finally, question and answer session.
Jeff would appreciate it.
I would not actually, but Jeff would appreciate it if you didn't ask about Game of Thrones
spoilers.
If you can get something out of him of substance, I will give you $100.
My wife and I would be appreciative.
You can't.
We'll see.
You do.
So, very quickly, and again, start chiming in whenever you have some thoughts.
The whole thing, like I said, is framed around the idea of licensed games, and it's this intersection of art and IP.
I've always found it fascinating that there's an established brand, a licensed movie, a comic book, a breakfast cereal, and someone makes a game out of it.
In some, sometimes successful, sometimes monstrous ways.
This has changed a lot over the years. I went and did a little bit of research and looked into it.
And I think Jeff would probably agree and Francois too, in your experience in playing games, you've seen a lot of different licensed products.
Most recently, Spider-Man was a huge success that took that brand to new places and probably was one of the now
tentpole entries in what that brand and the IP is about. You also have things like AdWord Gaming, which I'm strangely attracted to.
Cool Spot was a video game for 7-Up.
There's a fucking video game about 7-Up's icon and people don't really care about it, but it was a way of marketing for them.
The Witcher, a lot of people probably don't think about or realize that The Witcher is based off a book, and there was a licensed property.
And then even this week, we saw Nintendo giving their license to an indie developer, of great note of course, and great success,
but they're putting out Cadence of Hyrule, which blew everyone's mind.
So a lot has happened with licensing over the past few years, and when looking at this,
and Jeff and I and Francois talked a little bit about this prior to the session,
we kind of talked about it being a spectrum.
This isn't a judge of quality by any means. It's just of how the game relates to a brand maybe.
So you have the standard section, again, it's not buckets, but these are games that take a brand,
make a video game out of it. They can be very high quality, like Aladdin for example,
if you ever played it on the Sega Genesis, the Super Nintendo.
Super Nintendo was the superior version, in my opinion.
But they're basically merch. Not a bad thing. It's not a bad take on a licensed game,
but they're merch. They're translating it very directly.
Where we move over into complementary, we see video games as a support product, right?
These are something that may do something with that brand, that story that extends it out.
An example being Enter the Matrix, which again, it's a personal one I love.
It took two characters that would wander off screen in the second Matrix movie,
and this game would tell you what the fuck did they do when they wandered off screen.
And it was really cool. As a big fan of the Matrix, and Matrix 2 and Matrix 3, I will defend them all,
that it was really neat to see how it rounded out that series.
And then, thank you Jeff for the final section.
He named it and it's a really cool name, Exemplar.
These are the games that take it so far,
and this is a very sliver, a small sliver of, I think, licensed games,
take something so far that they almost,
that game actually becomes the most important part of that franchise.
As I mentioned, The Witcher before, if you walk through the halls here,
I bet 95 out of 100 people would associate it first with the game,
and most people would have no idea that it was a book series.
It extends these brands into absolutely new areas, things that they never expected to go and are very hard to come by.
But when done well, they're outstanding.
Do you guys kind of agree with this spectrum that we talked about?
Yeah, you know, it's definitely an interesting kind of way to break these things down.
When we're talking about this as a brand holder, you know, so HBO owns the IP for Game of Thrones.
You know, it's actually probably worth just taking a little step back and
sort of explaining our attitude toward licensed products and licensed gaming.
You want them to be, you know, more than just a logo slap where you're taking
Game of Thrones and putting on something, you know.
You can do that on a coffee mug or a t-shirt and get away with it.
But when you're talking about a game,
those kind of things are not really that fulfilling, you know.
And we take a lot of care to make sure that the projects that we want to embark
on are bringing more to it than.
That sort of standard approach.
You get into the complimentary tier,
and that's really what interests us.
We're looking for ways for our brands
to be enriched by a game.
And that Matrix example is a good one.
It's basically a side story, content within the world
that goes in a new place.
We've done some games like that.
Reigns is a similar thing.
We allowed the characters into the universe of Reigns.
And let the narrative take them places that aren't happening in the show.
The exemplar thing, when we were talking about this last week,
is to me it's a really interesting thing.
That really is kind of a holy grail.
Where if you can create something that is so powerful
that it's almost like putting out new content altogether
in a new part of your brand.
That's just a really attractive thing as a licensor
and as a storyteller, as a brand holder.
It's hard to do.
And I would say there are probably very few examples of that actually happening.
I actually couldn't think of many more, to be honest with you.
I mean, you could argue that Spider-Man was so big, but still, I mean, there's movies,
there's the comic books, so it's hard to really push it to that point of something so singular,
like The Witcher.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think, indeed, also we sort of naturally tended to go towards the complimentary kind
of position for Rang's Game of Thrones.
Because with the size of the series and the books behind the series Game of Thrones, it's
such a very large landscape of a universe, if you want, and they created a very, very
strong visual universe.
And our game could not at any point be like a substitute for that universe, and it's really
something that adds.
something that lets the player use his memories and his visual artifacts that come directly
from the show and turn them into something else that's not related necessarily to what's
told in the series.
So very like an extension.
And let players play while they wait for the new series,
while they prepare for what happens next in the show.
And it's really in this way that it's a complementary kind
of approach, I think.
And so I think there's a whole other GDC panel on licensed
games, because I think there's some really interesting things
being done, both historically and modern day.
And I think we really are in some golden age of licensed
games.
Which brings us to Reign's Game of Thrones, an unlikely but obvious pairing.
Just a quick history, this was a collaboration between HBO and Nereal.
This game came out, if you're not familiar with it, it did come out the end of last year
on mobile and on Steam.
It'll be coming out three days before season 8 starts on Nintendo Switch.
Good timing.
Yeah, we planned that out remarkably well.
That's seemingly the publisher's smart ideas, I think.
It's a case study.
The reason we're here is it's a case study on how a small developer, a small development
team can work with a global brand and how it can, much to honestly our shock, work out
super smoothly.
Again, a lot of luck and the people involved as we make this happen, but it was a story
that I think was worth telling.
Again, like I said, it's unreproducible.
And by the way, unreproducible and irreproducible are both words and I changed this three times
in this presentation.
But unreproducible luck.
is contributing factor. So it's hard to replicate and I don't think you know this doesn't sound like
sounds real self-congratulatory. It's not. It's really an attribution and nod to the fact that
this is a lot of luck and timing involved here. So there's some discussion points walking through
everything from collaboration to release and then learning. And in the interest of time I just want
to jump right into the collaboration. I'd love for you guys to tell the story from both your sides.
How did this collaboration come into being?
Yeah, so why don't I start with my little anecdote.
Um, this, uh, the, this game kind of hit our radar.
Um, you know, I've got some folks on my staff who are over here who are kind of our game team.
And they, they knew about Reigns.
And, you know, the, the original game got some really great love.
And, uh, for, you know, well-deserved it.
And, and so it was sort of on our radar.
It's like, that's an interesting game.
And you guys at Devolver had been trying to kind of figure out how to have a conversation with us
because you were thinking...
You know, maybe there's something there with that, you know, that mega show Game of Thrones.
You had made contact through a third party that we both work with
and somebody knew somebody who called somebody else and eventually an email ended up on my
in my inbox. And we had a very quick
back and forth exchange saying like, this could be interesting. So, two or three
days later, I don't remember exactly how long, we got an email from Dan Weiss
who's one of the creators of Game of Thrones. And Dan said,
We're over here in Belfast shooting, I think they were shooting season seven.
Have you guys heard of this game Reigns?
Like, we're obsessed and we're playing it all the time.
Could we do that for Game of Thrones?
Could you guys make that happen?
And, I mean, talk about making me look good.
We were able to just literally, like say, oh yeah, we know those guys.
No problem.
We'll, you know, we'll hook you up.
And so it was, I mean, it was the ultimate, like, you know,
smooth moment for me professionally.
So that was great.
But then, you know, knowing that they were really into this.
You know, it was an immediate like, yeah, let's see if we can make this happen.
You know, and then we'll get deeper in after that, but that was kind of our like little kismet moment.
And then getting from there to getting a game done is the whole rest of the story that, you know, there's some interesting twists and turns along the way.
And Francois, do you mind, I know, I mean, because I'm involved, I know the story of when you first pitched the original Reigns to our team.
Yeah.
So yeah, that was in 2015, December.
And I sent a pitch to a developer
because I didn't do any eat before that.
So that was like I was starting as an indie, if you want.
Very much indie, like the proper one who was scrubbing.
Anyway, so I was a send a mail to Frank Parker saying,
OK, I got this great concept.
It's a mix of Tinder and Game of Thrones.
And that's how I sold the game to Devolver in a way.
And then, yeah, I remember afterwards,
we were like, remember the brains, or sorry,
Tinder, Game of Thrones concept, but that's how you pitched it.
What if we could do that?
Yeah.
And I was a
I totally didn't expect, even at that point,
even after the success of RANKS, to actually make a...
So we got a deal done, right?
Well, we started on a deal. How did you, this is questions for Jeff,
how did you push this internally? Like, if you have the producers,
but how did you work through HBO? Because I kind of think that's important.
Yeah, that's definitely worth mentioning. Every company is different,
obviously, but from our, with our process,
there's several rungs of a ladder you have to climb.
You know, on this one.
And Dan and David are one of them.
They kind of, we hit that rung early
because they wanted to do this.
But then, you know, we, the next step was, you know,
to begin talking to you guys about a business deal.
What is the deal here?
And, you know, it's worth noting that when, you know,
when we do a deal for, for example,
for a big free-to-play game,
that's a much bigger financial opportunity,
which comes with completely different royalty rates
and guarantees and all these things.
We looked at this, we couldn't hold them hostage for a gigantic minimum guarantee
because that's just not how the business works.
Also we don't have a gigantic minimum guarantee to give you.
Right, it would have died on the line right then.
Right.
So we're lucky that we can come with some flexibility in that sense.
And so we began thinking about, well, what could we accept?
What would make sense?
We immediately pitched this internally to the executives
that have sort of a check mark for us.
as a Halo game, as something that is going to bring, you know, it fits perfectly with the show.
It's got this really great point of view and a stylistic view that we really like,
and we just had this vision. We actually asked you guys, I think, to mock up what Tyrion would
look like and what Daenerys would look like. Yeah, there's some examples, early examples here on the
screen of like, they needed to have art to show. Yeah, so having some art was excellent, because
it's, you know, it's one thing to just say, yeah, it's a game where you swipe left and right.
But being able to show what it's really going to look like was helpful.
We also have to take our digital deals to George Martin, who's the creator of the books and the universe.
So we have a close relationship with him on gaming in particular.
And so we had to be able to pitch his team.
And we worked pretty closely with you guys to help hone that.
It took a while. It was probably a better part of a year.
That was one thing that, you know, if they could teach about...
make a point about is it's the one thing that will not change.
I bet most licensed games whether you guys or any other license or is it just takes so
much time and you actually have to build that obviously not into like I want to get this
approved but the process in general is it's not going to turn around a license game very
quickly because there may be you know to me I'm talking to Will and Dustin and Jeff.
But then there's a lot of people that I've never talked to or never see
that have to approve these things. And it's kind of mind-blowing to think about.
Because we as a company, and I know Francois' company,
we're pretty quick to turn things around because there's only a few people.
But you have to keep in mind how many people have to approve this.
And then, I mean, we can talk about now or later,
but the casting thing I didn't even think about.
I had no idea about how casting works and the talent.
Yeah, and I think overall the...
The making of the game was nine months,
and signing the contracts was a year.
So that was longer than making the game.
But that's totally fine.
But you made Reigns for Majesty in the meantime.
So that was fine.
Yeah, exactly.
I made another game in the meantime.
That was actually really helpful,
that you guys had something to work on.
Yeah.
Yeah, we were on a series.
Definitely.
It's definitely that internal approval process,
but it's also legal.
We are big corporations, and we have.
Very rigid legal department, so we had to negotiate an agreement with you guys and go through that.
Doesn't happen overnight.
Um, you know, it's uh, it, it, it, I will say as a, you know, a testament to you guys, you hung in there with us all the way.
You know, and we're there and, and, uh.
We weren't doing anything else really.
Ha ha ha.
Just hanging out.
Yeah.
But, uh, it's, that's an important thing, you know, if we're speaking to folks who maybe, you know, want to have an idea to do something like this with a licensed property.
You know, I would say just from our perspective, some advice is you do need to come with some flexibility and,
you know, perseverance and, you know, and kind of patience.
And we try to be really communicative on our side.
Like we try to keep you posted.
And I always say I never really mind when people bug me saying like, do you have an update?
Do you have an update?
You know, I'll be happy to tell you no, we don't have an update.
That could be different with a different licensor.
You know, you have to probably gauge that.
Like what's the back and forth like?
It is a process and it's going to be different for every project.
We had to think about things like our other digital game projects that were underway.
How do we launch this one?
What time does it go out?
You know, you're talking about marketing, you know, and user acquisition.
You know, if we've got one other game that's out there in the market buying ads
and doing a big spend for Game of Thrones, it's not a great idea to put out a second one
so you're both competing and you're just driving up the spend rates for everybody.
So we try to be very organized with that and kind of put things out, like an air traffic controller.
Got a bunch of planes to take off, how do we do it the right way?
And that's all a part of the internal discussion.
So that leads me to a question for Francois, because there's this big machine working,
and obviously you have this, I think I say here, cultural phenomenon at Game of Thrones.
What were you and your team, what were you thinking? Were you scared of this?
Yeah, I think...
I think we were very proud because I'm a big fan of the book.
I can show you my 1996 edition of Game of Thrones and of the series that we watched
a couple of times before.
So that was a huge thing as a fan to be able to touch this and play with it and make something
with it.
So that was, I think, a big responsibility in a way.
And also, yeah, all this process that sort of, we sort of inherited like a year of discussing
this deal and stuff.
And so we, the production phase couldn't fail, you know, yeah.
We had a certain pressure to make things happen in a continuous and...
with quality, but with the aim of getting somewhere in the time that we defined,
because that made sense for your air traffic control.
So we couldn't actually postpone like I would have done for another project.
We couldn't postpone the thing too long, I think.
And then the final part of the collaboration,
you've mentioned a little bit of this.
This is for Jeff.
You know, it's still surprising to me, even to this day.
And we appreciate it, but
was there pushback on a small team,
small team working on a pretty, I don't know,
different kind of game for
your flagship IP at HBO, I assume?
The pushback is maybe too strong of a word, but it is.
That was something that I had to basically have an answer for
when I went up to my executive team.
I had to say to them, look, this isn't, you know, this isn't EA.
But this is why we think it's an interesting opportunity.
I hate to interrupt, but I think that you guys are known, you have a bunch of very successful,
free to play, I think, Game of Thrones games, right? And bigger games.
But was there concern, I mean, did you guys go in and say,
look, there's a pretty limited financial gain to be had here, comparatively?
Yeah. Yeah, that was definitely part of the analysis.
And it's always one of the questions, well, what are we going to earn?
The, again, so that, that feeds into the presentation and I, you know, I, I feel personally at HBO,
I have a luxury of being able to say, we want to do something because it's a halo product.
This is something that is going to be, you know, it's, it's going to get some shine.
It's not just putting out something to crank out royalty checks.
That's not always the case.
Some licensors, some companies really aren't,
they're not that focused on that.
They're much more about mass plays
and really maximizing earnings.
So that's sort of how we position it.
And we've done this in many other things,
like jewelry and sneakers and other things like that,
where we maybe aren't gonna earn a ton,
but the attention you're gonna get,
the fan reaction, the surprise,
and all of that is valuable to us.
So this was really positioned that way as this is a game that just makes so much sense.
When we put it out there, yeah, we're not going to, you know, fund a new season of a
Game of Thrones spin-off on the royalty checks from this project, but the value is going
to be there.
And we were right, you know, the reaction to this game was fantastic and it's exactly
what we did it for.
Awesome, thank you.
Yeah.
So I'm going to move on to the concept production.
And we've kind of gone over a little bit of this already,
so this is going to be a flowing thing.
But I think that first question for Francois.
So you mentioned you obviously read the books since 1996,
watched the show.
What was your, I mean, what kind of research did you do?
Did you go back because it seems like a pretty overwhelming,
like I'm still amazed actually myself of the detail,
you know, what kind of research did you do before you started?
So, yeah, I did a lot of research and that's where the fact that you play with a universe
and not just a single IP that's not very well known, is that you got like a corpus of information
and of...
But that's very, very detailed and very afford, like you got like the canon, you got...
fan theories and all this is very, very clear.
There's like a continent of information you can go through
that's been criticized and reviewed by people.
So you can very easily find information about everything.
From the on of winter, if you take some sort of details that are just spread out in the
series, to very obvious things like the wall and so on and so forth.
So you can really easily, and that's really like three things for me.
That's the Tibris series, the first things that we really looked into and researched,
the books and the fan site.
But that's always interesting for us, especially because our game, in a way, is a bit like
a fan fiction simulator, in a way.
This is, in the end, what we sort of created.
We wanted the player to be able to tell himself, to bring the story where he could imagine
it to go.
That was really what we wanted to do, and that's what fan fiction is.
So that was relevant to look at that material, and it's a very extremely detailed material
on the Internet for Game of Thrones.
So one of the things that I think surprised me in the process, and this is what I wanted
to ask you guys about it, and I think maybe would be helpful for the folks watching here,
is this idea of an approval process versus a collaboration.
Because I went into this...
Honestly thinking again big scary corporation that I didn't know yet that it would be approval process
You send something and they tell you to know to X things, right?
And then you have to go back and do it
But what was surprising I think probably to I know to you and I was that it was pretty collaborative
Yeah, so can you guys talk a little bit about the process?
Maybe how in general you do it as a licensor and then you know Francois maybe about how it worked with Game of Thrones
Yeah, yeah
so
We have a lot of approvals that we have to do.
We have to really think as the brand holder,
anything we put out there public has to be on brand.
It has to not create a headache.
I would wake up in a cold sweat in the middle of the night
thinking, oh, did we put out something that somebody's
going to be pissed off that we put in it?
So we take good care to make sure we're really
doing something that's, one, going to do the brand proud,
but two, work in our universe.
Talent likeness is a big thing.
Right.
Again, a lot of, every company is different in this case, but for Game of Thrones, our actors have the right to approve those illustrations.
And so that requires us to get the drawings, send it out to their representatives, they'll look at it, they may request changes.
I think mostly in this case-
And this is the talent themselves to clarify, like-
Correct, the actors.
Yeah, the actors. I mean, some of them their agent does it for them or their manager, some of them, you know, the actor themselves.
Peter Dinklage is all, you know, you'll just write your right back.
That's cool.
Yeah, yeah.
But the, you know, that's a whole other process. That's something we had to work in.
The story was very much a concern for us, because this is a very narrative driven game.
We're putting it out in between season 7 and 8, and you know, the finale is coming.
And we had to make sure we weren't putting in something that was going to be, you know, wrong for the game.
And so we had to really take care and think about that.
You know, you guys would submit.
outlines and narratives and my team would just pour through them
and make sure something wasn't incorrect.
I remember one specific thing, I think it was Cersei,
it was about Daenerys, but something that Will, who's sitting up here,
was like, well, no, her braid is usually over here, and her part is here.
It was something so specific, and there's things I didn't think about.
I was like, that just looks like Cersei, right?
There's a lot of details that the actor and then the brand holder is going to want to get right.
Yeah, and I would say, you know, one of the reasons why we get really specific like that is because
Game of Thrones in particular, there's a fan base out there that notices those things and doesn't like it.
You know, they want it to be on. So we're really careful on all that stuff.
I was going to say, to that point, I just realized, sorry, but I just realized looking at this.
On the left is the pitch, right?
It's the pitch image.
On the right is the final image.
And that's how long, we were talking
about how long the deal took.
A lot happened at Xerces between that pitch
and when the game came out.
She rose to power and also got a haircut.
Yeah.
It's also in the final image, we decided
the setting, which was around season seven.
So yeah, we had to stick to how she looked at that point.
So talk about, sorry to interrupt,
talk about the approval from your side.
I think the approval.
And especially at my level, the collaboration with Will, who is a Vervarian, was very interesting
also because it's not just like some sort of censorship process that just cuts your
thing or tells you, no, you can't do that.
He never said that.
He said always you should do that instead.
It's more like a collaboration, since he always was always bringing something new to
the game that was adding value to it.
I can, because I looked at a few discussions we had,
and that's a very interesting way of explaining
how we made the game better together.
That's not, it's where the collaboration with the license
was interesting.
So for example, I had this card, okay,
a delegation of archmasters from the Citadel is here.
They are asking you to select the next Grand Maester.
So we'll say, I don't think this set of cards works.
The maesters are pretty much an apolitical organization,
and the grand maester is selected by the archmaesters,
not by the ruler of Westeros, which was totally true
and totally right.
So to this I answer, and this is where you see the discussion
and where we come to something that's a bit better and more
interesting.
I answer to that, yes, you're right, but without choice,
we need cards.
like that to recruit a new maester if need be.
If you killed the maester and you need to recruit a new one,
how do you do that?
That's me as a game designer who say, I need this in a way.
And his answer is very interesting
because that's how we put things forward if you want.
They could be executed in a more devious way.
I think it's reasonable that the king-queen will want to influence who is appointed Grand
Maester, but we should not make it as simple as speaking like this.
So you see how the discussion sort of brought the design forward and made the game better
in the end.
And we had that sort of thing on the 1,600 cards of the game, if you want.
So that process was very much a process to bring quality to the game and not just say,
you can't put that.
If I can't do that, what do I do?
He very much understood the way I was designing my thing,
if you want.
That's very important.
Another one, because that's a funny one.
So it's like, so one of the card was,
dragon is afflicted with an acute lethargy.
I'm unable to cure.
Do you wish to see him?
So that was one of the card.
And we'll say to this, can you remind me,
what is the story with dragon being asleep like this?
Like, don't fuck with my dragons, you know?
So, yeah.
So we had a lot of, but always in a tone that was helpful
and not just saying, don't do that.
It's not going to work.
That's just, yeah.
An example of collaboration.
And the last thing I wanted to ask about, I mean we've kind of talked about it a little
bit, but what was a surprise to me, and again I would love to communicate to the audience
here is you get blessed with this universe, right, to work with, but you don't...
Business reasons will prevent you from being able to work with all parts of it, right?
So, for example, the casting.
We just mentioned the approval process, but
we can't put 400 individual actors in this game, right?
Right, yeah, we have some limitations.
And again, this is all unique to our business, but
there's only so many actors we can put in a thing before too much.
And they participate, they're paid out of our royalties as they should be.
And so we have a cap, we only have so many we can put in.
And that was difficult because I remember, Francois, you had sort of this archetypal list of,
we need somebody to, you know, because we're melding in your existing game engine.
We need all of these characters. How do we do them?
And so we had to come up with things like, well, all right, you're going to have to have just like,
instead of Lord Janos Slint, the captain of the City Watch,
we have to have a generic captain of the City Watch.
And let's write it, let's craft a different name for that guy.
We had to be a little flexible on that stuff.
Generic, stark soldier instead of a guy that you know from the show, that type of thing.
Yeah, that was a little surprising to me, I know.
Yeah, I think also one good thing for that particular range of approvals,
which are the visual approvals for the talents,
the good thing about Rangs is that you got one portrait of Cersei,
one portrait of Jaime.
Although difficult it is to do Jamie, that's another problem.
One portrait of each of the characters.
So you don't, we don't have like eight months of production to get to the point where we
got all the visuals of Tyrion, if you want.
And that makes it, that's very useful because we were able to work in priority on these
visuals at the start, in the first three, four months of the project.
to be able to submit them to approval, and it takes quite a long time.
We were a bit worried at some point.
And just to be able to, in parallel, work on the story,
because the story, we don't need the approval from the license
team, but not from Tyrion on what he says in the game.
So this is how we manage the overall process
of the production.
It's like we had to prioritize a few things
to get the approval in time for the release, if you want.
I also, this reminds me of a key moment in the game design,
where the original Reigns game and Her Majesty,
there's one monarch.
It's, you know, he gets a new name
every time he's regenerated.
But we, when we started talking about this,
we said, well, who is sitting on the throne?
Like, are we really gonna pick one?
Right.
You know, like, can we really pick one?
I don't know if we can.
And that, you know, the design twist on that was,
okay, well.
These are visions that Melisandre's having.
We kicked around several different ideas on both sides
and had a really long back and forth, how do we do that?
How do you have different Game of Thrones characters sitting
on the throne who don't belong there necessarily?
And when we did finally land on that visions in the fire thing,
it was like, aha.
And that also then influenced, well,
which actors do we need to put in this thing?
And it was all a really complex kind of...
Yeah, I remember that very precisely.
There's a lot of talk about that.
Yeah, we spent a lot of time...
Because the first idea we had was to imagine, you know,
at some point Daenerys ends up in the Tower of Warlocks in Qarth.
And that could have been all the visions she got at that point.
And that was in season 7, so that was...
Or 6, I don't remember.
That's season 2, man. That was a long time ago.
That was actually a big fan.
That's the reason why we didn't.
That was our complaint.
We were like, that was season two.
It was very long ago.
Yes, yes, true.
But yeah, so that would have been an interesting way to mix up,
explain that we got visions in the game.
But the idea of Mlissandre was interesting,
much more interesting because she's got...
She failed a bit with Stannis, so she's looking for the new king or the new queen to follow.
And that gives a very interesting motive to the game that really vibrates very well with
the series.
And her fallibility, which we've seen in the show, like she's certain she had the right
guy and it wasn't true.
That worked perfectly in this thing, because we figured, oh, well, every time you regenerate,
it's her being like, oh, no, that wasn't it.
Maybe it was Sansa.
Maybe it's Jon Snow.
It worked out really well for this.
And that's what I guess the goal of this particular section is.
If you're working with somebody, and we're obviously very fortunate,
but if you're working with somebody on a licensed game like this,
the collaborative process versus just the simple approval process is ultra important.
So it makes a, maybe from the standard thing that we talked about,
to something more complimentary.
Because you're doing something that adds the experience of your fan base to your fan base and the license's fan base.
We don't have time to really delve into it. This was part of the discussion, but
Francois shared this. This is the, if you pull the hood back on any Reigns game,
it's an effin' spreadsheet, right?
It's just thousands of choices that can be made and where it goes.
Yeah, and these would be dumped over to Will to like home to approve.
So yeah, so that's just a shared spreadsheet if you want.
And the whole process was good for this is that we had one single shared spreadsheet.
I was not sending text to approve.
It was sending it back with a red pencil.
No, so it's not like that.
We had a full process, and it could
change the status of each line.
And we come back, we read it, and this
is how the game was made.
And you got 1,600 lines like that.
And the last little bit of the actual game
was the marketing release.
I do work with a lot of the marketing at Devolver Digital.
And so, you know, one of the things, and I want to hear Francois and Jeff's take on it,
but one of the interesting things is, okay, when you're getting ready,
the game was very close to completion before we announced it.
I mean, there wasn't a whole lot left because it was a lengthy approval process.
We didn't want to announce it and then just kind of shrug our shoulders while we're waiting.
So when we did announce it, one of the interesting things that, you know,
you have to take into account versus your own game or your own project.
is obviously the existing fan base.
And with this particular one, there's certainly lots of expectations.
As Jeff alluded to, there's people looking for hints.
They want answers.
And so,
one of the things, the first prompt I have up there is,
you know, what was important to communicate to fans of Reigns,
Reigns Game of Thrones, and between the two franchises.
And one thing that was ultra important that I guess I didn't anticipate until right before really doing it,
is making sure that people understand you're working with a licensed game and there's some expectations.
It's getting better, but there's expectations that this is just a skin job
and it is putting the, you're slapping Game of Thrones maybe on Reigns.
And we had to really avoid that. We wanted to communicate that this was, in fact, a full-fledged standalone game.
It's a sequel. However you want to put it, it's not, you know, did you enjoy Reigns?
What if we just slapped these characters on there? Because that's pretty common in licensed games. You see this.
And so I don't know, you know, when it comes to my questions to you guys is how did you think about managing those communities, those expectations?
What was it that you sought to be the most important thing from your side when you were releasing it?
Yeah, you know, that is it's always top of mind for us, right?
Like we we are nothing without our fans, you know, like there's no show without an amazing rabid fan base.
So it's it's very important to us.
We we take.
You know, very seriously, and make sure that the things that we put out there aren't going to be deemed like that, where it's just a cash grab or a logo slap.
Have you had that happen? Have you had any, I mean, without maybe giving too specifics, have you had things that were just a huge blowback when you announced them?
Or any kind of particular angst, sensitivities that fans have?
We've had a few things that kind of landed with kind of a little head scratch reaction, but nothing too terrible, because we take really careful care to do that.
But no, it's definitely important, and it had to be seen as, you know, as complimentary
to the brand and additive to the brand, not, you know, not taking away from.
There's also, you know, the other things that we think about a lot are about timing and
all the other stuff that's going on, not just for products, you know, not my department,
but for the show itself.
So is there going to be a teaser trailer that's dropping the day before we announce this game?
If so, we don't want to do it that day because everyone's going to be talking about that teaser.
They're not going to be talking about this product.
You know, is there, do we have some other, are we talking about a, you know, our deal with Adidas that day?
Like we need to, you know, we need to get breathing room in between all these things.
That's an interesting point you brought up.
I remember specifically in a conversation was we were releasing the game in between seasons.
And I kind of, of course, like your natural expectation is, why don't we just release
this alongside a season?
How great would that be?
But I think you made the point that everyone's trying to do that, whether it's, you know,
whiskey or shoes or whatever it is, they all want to be tied in.
Ours is a narrative kind of thing that could really satiate a fan base in between.
I spend a good part of my work day telling people.
You don't want to be right next to the new season of the show,
because all anybody's going to talk about
is what's on TV on the show, and they're going to miss you.
It is a fire hose of Game of Thrones content right now,
and more so in four weeks, three and a half weeks.
And you don't want to be-
Plug.
Yeah, plug, plug.
Tune in.
But it is very much a concern of ours
is that you need to do these things in a way
where they're going to have room to breathe,
and they can get lost.
Also, one thing that is important is, I think, as a licensor, we got the sort of expectation,
but when you think about it, like, five seconds, you understand it's very long, that when you
work with, like, the Game of Thrones IP, you got a bit of Game of Thrones marketing.
But it's not that at all.
And it's very important to understand that you still have to sell your game, and although
you use the IP and you use the universe of Game of Thrones, you won't share the marketing
plan of the series, okay?
And that's super important because that's exactly the sort of thing you want to avoid
actually, to be on the same sort of level.
Because it won't work for your product, to be very clear.
Yeah, that was... We talked about that at length, I think, right before the release of it.
And this is, again, another thing that hopefully can communicate, or at least take away,
is it's still on you to market your game.
You have the benefit of an IP, but it's definitely on you to market your game.
Because these brands, and in our case, Game of Thrones,
they have their own strategies.
And they have strategies that don't necessarily...
You're going to accept the small indie mobile game.
They're not putting ads in between Game of Thrones and V for this game.
We can expect a tweet and some social support or things like that.
Sometimes.
But it's really on you.
And so it was on us on the publishing side to really work with Apple, Google and Steam
and other partners and PR and things like that to get it out there.
Because it's not that HBO wasn't helpful.
It's that they have a lot of things.
And they can offer a little bit to you.
The input, you know, they told us and they're right, it's still on you to sell your game.
So that was a good piece of learning that I think I would definitely pass on to someone working on a licensed product.
Don't think of it as an easy street, like you got this, you can go.
This is where, you know, licensing is different from code dev.
You know, I mean, there's the other model where like, you know, we might take a whole bunch of money and pay someone to make us a game.
Right.
And then.
We market it.
We would be doing it.
But let me know if you would like to do that.
No, we would not.
But that's actually not how we approach things.
We're just not set up to.
A lot of other studios and TV networks do that more often.
But that's one of the wrinkles of this, which is very
valuable as a takeaway for anyone that's thinking about
doing this.
You have to have your own marketing strategies, and you
have to bring that in in your pitch and explain how you're
going to do it.
How do you acquire users?
What does that mean?
You know, does it mean blanketing Facebook with ads for your game?
I need to know that because I need to go to my social media team and explain to them this is going to be out there.
These guys are going to be buying against Game of Thrones.
Are you trying to do the same thing in that same window?
Should we be careful?
You know, it's a lot behind the scenes that you have to really think about.
And it's in 2019, you know, that is a real concern.
That was another thing that popped up in the marketing that was interesting to me is
that App Store was our primary place to sell the game.
And when you type in Game of Thrones in the App Store,
you're not going to be first if you're a small game. Like there's a lot of other bigger things out there.
So you had to, we had to work,
you know, we make sure we talk with Apple making sure that, you know, it was all set up properly
and things like that. But you're a competing, you're not the only licensee out there.
And that was a an eye-opening thing too. It worked out fine for us.
We got promotion and things like that from Apple and Google and whatnot, but
You know, when people are trying to organically find your game,
if you're one of many, that was something that you just got to keep in mind.
In the interest of time, I just want to ask one last question
before we open it to questions from you guys,
if you have any, that aren't about Season 8.
What, in general, would you take away from this?
What was the personal, professional highs and lows of this project?
And that's for both of you.
You go first.
I think...
I think what we take from this is very much the fact that the licensed game needs to be
connection between the license and the game.
And you can't have this unbalance.
I think the bad licensed games are either you've got big brands and a weak game you
put behind that because you need to have some sort of gameplay.
And another bad game is when you've got the license is just like a layer on top of a very
good game mechanic.
That's just it.
It's like you're risking your game.
So this is very important, I think.
And that's the main takeaway for me as a designer,
is that makes sense when you use the license to make
the game better, and you use the game to enrich the license
in a way, or explore what I say about explore the universe
of Game of Thrones.
And when you got that connection, that makes it work,
that makes it worthwhile, and you bring something
to the table, I would say.
And I think we start to see that,
and I'm very, very excited to see Indies starting to do that.
And I think that's also an interesting thing that's
happening that's, in a way, starting with us, I suppose.
That Indies, like working with big IPs,
is something very, very strong.
If it makes sense, if the game play makes sense,
it's super strong.
Like, so you were talking about cannons.
Cannons of Hyrule.
That's a huge thing, and I think it makes so much sense
because...
You always add in the Zelda game, the Zelda IP,
you always add this sort of very strong connection
to dance and music.
So you got a lot of things around that
in the Zelda franchise.
And the crypt of the Necrodancer gameplay
is so perfect.
It makes a lot of sense.
Both thematically and mechanically as a game design perspective.
Jeff, what did you get out of this? What did you get out of your relationship with us?
Except, I mean, other than meeting you guys.
Well, that's obviously a high point, but besides that.
You know, we get a lot of shine off of this, you know?
Like, when you talk about, again, that dynamic of it's not going to earn us, you know, the most.
But we've gotten accolades.
We got amazing reception.
People reviewed this game and loved it.
I mean, the general reaction to the announcement was,
oh, hell yeah.
Like, that's exactly the reigns of Game of Thrones.
It's perfect.
And I mean, talk about a sense of fulfillment from that.
That's exactly what we all were excited about.
The collaboration, the collaborative efforts
that we've talked a lot about were very fulfilling.
And to me, it's a testament to the two teams.
And the big win on this is like it is not Halo.
And it feels like an additive experience for our fans
where we created something that we're
giving this new little world inside our world to play with.
And that's really, really gratifying just professionally
and personally, too.
Great.
Well, thank you guys for answering
the questions and chatting.
I'd love to.
And that's it for the.
The presentation itself, if you guys have any questions,
we're happy to answer them.
First, who wants to know the end of Game of Thrones?
All right, don't call on any of them.
Sorry, dude.
I think there's a, if you need to talk over the microphone.
Thank you so much.
It was very interesting to hear the insights
of this experience.
I missed the first maybe two minutes,
and I didn't hear a.
This was the first game you did with IP,
or you had any previous experience on doing IP games?
I don't think you have.
No, I didn't.
OK.
I've worked on, we did something for a game called
Broforce and a movie called The Expendables called
The Expendabros.
But that was a free promotional thing,
and it was a much smaller project.
OK, I played that one.
No, OK, good.
Yeah, it was very good.
It was free, so why not?
Yeah.
So my question is, when you had to deal with the IP owner,
and you have to set the terms of the contract,
and there's not much information around what are good terms,
like what is a reasonable MG or marketing stipend?
Or I don't know, how much the license is worth for the revenue share.
I can't tell you that to be honest.
I mean, Jeff could, I don't know even how much he could speak to it.
That's a really good question because I didn't know that either going in.
We had no idea.
But I think in my, at least my limited experience and from what I've heard from others,
it just, it depends on the IP.
And the licensor too.
And the licensor.
Some people I think are pretty aggressive out there.
Yeah.
So, I mean, we're pretty flexible in my shop.
Like, we're open to discussing all that stuff.
So it's hard to say, you know, like, come with a million bucks or you're not going to get in the door.
Like, that might be the case some places.
Royalty rates are often more important in a, in a, for a smaller project like this, you know, like,
if you can't offer a huge amount guaranteed, like, maybe you can share more on the royalty side,
which can help, you know, make that case that, well, if, look, if it does really well,
then our cut is, is better, you know.
Yeah, okay. Thank you. Because it's very difficult to understand because probably all of the licensed games have NDA, so nobody can share the information.
But I really look hard for information about it. There's nowhere to be found anyone who tells, hey, this is regular, this is okay.
I'm not sure this is regular. I think that's probably what I've learned from it. It just depends on sometimes there's an overinflation of value.
You have no idea. I wish I could answer. I just know our deal, which I obviously can't talk about.
But I think, you know, the best way to do it is just to ask. If you have a target, go ask them.
They'll probably be willing to say, this is what I'm going to need.
Okay. Thank you. Yeah, thank you.
Want to go over to that side? Yeah, sure.
Hi. Awesome talk. And I just want to ask, do you have any advice for someone who wants to get close to a company to make a licensing game?
I'll tell you, Jeff alluded to this earlier.
When we started this, I had no contact at HBO.
I had no idea how to get a hold of HBO.
I went to my HBO Go and screamed at it and did nothing, right?
I basically looked and I thought about who they might be doing business with
and then worked down the ladder onto someone I might know.
So it was a three or four person chain before we get to the idea of,
okay, this is someone that may know somebody at HBO.
So if you have a target you're going for, I'd suggest looking who they may be working with currently,
and then kind of working through those avenues.
Because that's basically how I got it. I have no other avenue to get to talk to anyone at HBO.
There is an organization called Lima, which stands for licensing industry,
some merchandising of America. I don't know what Lima stands for.
So that's the licensing trade organization that most of us belong to.
You can probably, I mean, it doesn't hurt to call them.
They've got a website and just say, who do I contact at HBO or Sony or Warner Brothers or whatever.
Like they might be able to help you out that way.
And Google, you know, like Google it up.
We get a lot of cold calls that people just kind of find our details out there online.
And just one quick question.
Who do you want to get the Iron Throne?
Ah, that's a hard one. I've actually said this publicly before, so it won't come back to haunt me.
But my favorite character is Tormund, Giant's Bane. So, yeah, I want to see Tormund on a throne. That would be dope.
All right. Thank you very much.
How's it going? Hi, my name is Ashley and I lead marketing for Activision and Blizzard Consumer Products.
Never heard of them.
I know, a little tiny company.
I think we spend a lot of our days in the same way,
talking to partners about marketing.
So thank you for that.
I question, either for you specifically, Jeff, or for you guys, how you navigate confidentiality.
So wanting to make sure that you are servicing the fans and giving them what they want in
regards to programs that might be day and date, etc.
But obviously dealing with extremely sensitive materials and timelines.
Any interesting anecdotes, if you guys could or wanted to share?
To answer the first question, we're very serious about it.
Like, we don't often like to do NDAs ahead of having a deal
because it's just extra paperwork to do.
So we don't share anything.
And then our license agreements have full confidentiality
clauses with complete ironclad requirements.
That said, we actually don't let anything,
we didn't tell them anything.
Like, when we had things where we were like,
oh, you can't have that in the game.
Because it's.
potentially going to be, you know.
We found ways to communicate that to them without saying,
take that out, it's going to be in the final season.
We're pretty careful.
Yeah.
So if I can add to this, we had some sort of a
a way to circumvent, even getting closer to doing spoilers and stuff,
or potential spoilers, because we can also accidentally find them, you know.
So basically what we did for Game of Thrones, for Reign of Game of Thrones,
is to just do all the possible spoilers.
So it's like everything that can happen in the series
will happen in the series.
Sada.
No, no.
So it's like, it's really, but it's maybe,
but that's also related to the fact
that we make a narrative game, so we have to tell stories,
you know?
We can't just mess around.
But the fact is that because of frames
and because of the lack of the light.
the probabilistic system we got behind that just creates stories with whatever happens
to the player and you can have ranks that you can have millions of possible ranks if
you want.
So that just creates like a potential things that can happen with the Game of Thrones.
I talk about like fine fiction simulator.
It's like we just embrace the possible scope and we never tell you.
We can't.
And of course, we don't.
You guys don't even know.
We don't even know.
So we can't tell you this is the right answer if you want.
But maybe we have it.
In a couple of months, he's going to see some things on TV that he's been like, oh yeah,
that's right.
Son of a bitch.
Thank you guys.
Thank you.
We only have a couple minutes left, so just quickly, we'll get both of them, but just if we could be quickly.
Yeah, I'm curious. So I'm sure you guys at HBO get a ton of pitches
from different mobile game companies. Would you say that getting the email from
Dan and David is the thing that set the project
above the others, or was it going to happen regardless, do you think?
It certainly helped, and again, it was one of those that made us look good. But we really
liked Reigns, and were interested in it anyway, and probably would have
you know.
So we're just pending the conversation with these guys to make sure there's actually something there.
We probably would have pitched this up, you know, to them.
But, you know, so it doesn't require that, right?
And it's very rare that that would be the case.
It's much more likely that, you know, your producers, your showrunners aren't sending...
So you think it would have happened regardless of that?
I think so, yeah.
And Dan and Dave are really unique in that they are really,
they love the licensed product and the merch,
and they're really engaged with us in that,
and often say, like, what about this, what about that?
Hey, I got a quick question. I don't know if you can disclose that, but is there a reason why Game of Thrones franchise hasn't been breaking like the triple A game stuff?
Like I've seen, we see Spiderman, Star Wars games, all these big brands, and Game of Thrones is kind of like the biggest PC game I guess is like the Telltale series.
So we haven't really found the right opportunity to do that, and we've looked at things and we will continue to look at things.
It's a, I'll tell you what, from a licensor standpoint,
knowing what it takes to build a AAA console game,
$100 million and then a couple more million.
Don't look at me, I don't know.
I mean, a couple more hundred million to market the game,
you know, like that's a massive, massive investment
from the studio and the publisher and all of that.
And it has to be right and it has to be fantastic and good.
If you look at the track record,
we talked about this a little bit in the beginning about...
The history of licensed gaming.
There's a lot of roadkill out there over the years with licensed console games.
And we began looking, when we first started looking at,
we called them video games.
This was like 12 years ago.
We should do a video game.
No one calls them that anymore.
I do.
But we started looking at that.
And we did some research and we looked at case studies.
And the Spider-Man game from this year has been...
revelatory in that sense. But, you know, I always look at Avatar, and if there's anyone here from, I think, Sony, you know, no offense.
But Avatar was the biggest movie in the world. It set all the box records. It blew the doors off of everything.
They put out a console game, and it was a complete dud. And that's our nightmare.
Yeah, right. But there is, well, if you look at the modifications for some of the games, there are some pretty good ones.
Great, Game of Thrones mods.
So there's obviously some marketing.
Unlicensed mods.
And Game of Thrones is a licensed mod.
Game of Thrones has like this certain adhesive
with some of the games because, you know,
the way the franchise works.
Yeah.
Yeah, no, it's something we are looking at.
We've heard pitches, and for the right opportunity,
I think we totally would.
You know, it's also the other part,
it's a four year dev cycle too, right?
So it's a commitment.
It's a bear to take on something like that.
I imagine.
Yeah.
Well, thank you all very much.
Thank you for the question, and thank you all very much for coming out.
Appreciate it.
Thank you.