Oh, hi.
I'm Lucas, and I'm a senior concept artist at ZeniMax Online Studios, and you just caught
me finishing up this key art illustration for The Elder Scrolls Online.
Okay.
Obviously, that's not really true.
This is actually just a print of a painting that I finished about a year ago.
The truth is that I really only work digitally nowadays, and in part, that's because the
conflicting demands of key art necessitate a very iterative process, which wouldn't
be realistic within the constraints of traditional painting workflows.
At GDC 2019, I'm going to talk more about those demands and the actual workflow that
I use to address them.
You see, marketing key art lies at the intersection of disparate interests which all have an influence
on the outcome of the finished product.
And the real skill in successfully executing narrative illustrations like these is based
on the artist's ability to navigate the demands imposed by competing stakeholders while still
arriving at a composition that manages to tell an engaging story.
So for more, join me at GDC on Thursday at 5.30pm for my session,
Illustrating Tamriel, Creating Key Art for the Elder Scrolls Online,
where we'll talk about those issues in greater depth.
I'll also pull back the curtain on my rather idiosyncratic painting process
and show in-progress images and alternate compositional sketches
that previously haven't ever been seen outside the studio.
I think it's going to be a lot of fun and I hope to see you there!