Hey, everyone.
Good afternoon.
I'm going to talk to you about my specific process of how
I go about immersing a creative world into a game user
interface.
My name is Steph Chow.
I am a UX UI consultant for games,
and I'm really excited to be here.
My first GDC was back in 2014, and it
was such a great experience to attend these sessions.
And the fact that I'm standing here giving my own talk
is truly unbelievable.
So I really hope you folks get something good out of it today.
To give a short background on myself,
before entering the game industry,
I worked in the field of graphic design,
primarily with branding consumer products for entertainment.
I then joined the game industry back in 2012 with Disney Games
to help out with art direction and UI UX.
And even after my time at Disney,
I was able to work on other big brands
with my consulting work for both new and live games.
And so I've had the opportunity to work
with really terrific brands that revolve around unique worlds.
And for today, I have a couple goals
I hope I can achieve with you.
I hope that at the end of this talk,
you will have a knowledge of the impact
UI can have on your game's overall branding.
You will have learned a method of how to go about
producing creative UI elements
that complements your game's world.
And last but not least, an understanding of the balancing
act required between your narrative UI and usability.
So with my history embedded in working with art direction
and UI and UX for games, I learned a lot of what it means
to work on games backed by great IP.
And as I worked on these games, I grew to realize
that one of the reasons why players play these games
is not just because the game is fun itself,
but it's because of the world these IPs stem from,
that fans grow to love for years
and sometimes even their entire life.
And when I say worlds, I mean the fictitious universe
created from mediums like film, games,
and have their own individual culture,
visual rules, and aesthetics.
These worlds are the things people fall in love with
because of the unique perspective they present
that isn't of our world.
And when it comes to games,
and when it comes to games,
the entire screen is an opportunity
to help immerse a player in that world.
So within a world, there are so many different visuals
that one can take reference from when developing their game
and their user interface.
It's with the details that go beyond character art
and environments like typography, iconography,
color palettes that help keep a player immersed
and engaged in a game.
And in my years of working on interface,
really what I've aimed for with Art Direction for UIUX
is a branded experience.
Creative worlds presented in games can make for a game's holistic brand vision and journey.
And that's what you can achieve within a game's world and experience.
A truly creative and exciting experience that through visuals, but also through functionality.
While we often talk about user experience through via functionality, this player experience along with world immersion
becomes defining of a great brand experience.
Take for example Bioshock Infinite Game by Irrational Games.
Yes, the game is a first-person shooter
set in the early 1900s,
but while you're not shooting up enemies
or engaging in psychokinetic powers,
you're still able to be immersed within the world
while navigating crucial UI that enables the game
to be played by the player in the first place.
And that brings me to an important point.
Just as important for a game to be visually immersive,
games as interactive experiences need to be usable
and easy to use.
We want as little friction to happen
so the player can enjoy the game's world
because it plays into the bigger picture
of defining a great brand experience.
A pretty game is nothing with a bad user experience.
So it's imperative that you focus on creating a UI
that is simultaneously usable and immersive.
Even with the Dead Space series by EA,
the team successfully created a diegetic user interface
that had yourself and the main character
immersed in the same world and seeing the same UI.
There is still, though, a simultaneous focus, however,
on how everything is laid out and designed
that enables the player to frictionlessly
navigate the game's content.
So when we talk about immersive elements with your game,
which equals out to the entire user experience,
UI has the same capability to immerse a player
into a world just like characters,
visual effects, and environments.
UI is an opportunity to reflect your game's world
and strengthen your game's visual branding
through narrative, graphics, and of course, usability.
So in a compact amount of time, I will discuss how to embed
a game's world in its UI via these three phases,
research, exploration, and iteration.
So step one, let's create the foundation,
power up and research your world.
What is the world you are presenting to the player?
What is the world influenced by culturally?
What visuals, patterns, textures can you take on
with your UI?
This is a time to seek out the visual elements
that make your world distinct.
And it's quite possible that the same references
your game's world is inspired by
can be the same references that your UI can be inspired by.
But there's so many different places
your UI can get inspiration from.
UI can be inspired by history,
most notably how the Bethesda's Fallout series
took inspiration from American 1950s post-war signage
and technology interfaces.
The Fallout series has a remarkably branded image
through its UI.
Typography, color, textures, all of it plays a part
of keeping your universe immersed into the game.
The UI evokes a powerful brand,
while the player enacts with contact
in a way that allows them a fun experience.
UI can even be inspired by nature,
as seen here in King's Paradise Bay.
You can see how the button's color palette and treatment
is reminiscent of oceans and natural rocks.
UI can even be inspired by, say, a subculture,
where it's very clear how games like Nintendo's Splatoon 2
gets its inspiration from punk and urban references.
While this universe is out of this world,
their UI draws actually from very familiar,
fun color palettes that you will see often in graffiti
and other fashionable punk patterns.
So big picture, UI doesn't have to just be
a bright, juicy green button.
There are plenty of ways to dress it up.
So in a natural way that fits with your game's narrative
if you desire it.
Now all those games that I showed were already live,
and for example of myself with this process,
when I was working on Moana's Island Life,
I had spent hours researching myself
in the Oceania culture,
which is what the movie itself is based off of.
And when you are researching,
you start to not only find keywords that define your world,
but you start seeing inspiration for your UI.
You start to see how icons can be designed,
how silhouettes can be used,
or what even kind of color palettes or typography
you can dot to these three key words.
And that is going to allow you to start researching
handful of fonts that can complement your world,
start developing a UI color palette
that guides the user naturally
while still maintaining a branded experience,
or even provide inspiration
of what kind of pop-up container shapes
you can house your UI content in.
So after researching your world,
picking up visual cues and palettes,
you can then take this all into exploration
for a couple of sample screens.
And by doing so, you can see what portions
of your research is going to work
and maybe not work so well.
My suggestion would be to apply this exploration
with something like perhaps a main game HUD,
a character screen.
So to recap, within research that acts as your foundation
for your UI immersion, I would recommend
looking into reference visuals and their details
that inspire your game's world.
If you can do that beyond Google by, say,
watching movies, museum visits that
are similar to the world that has inspired your game,
that makes for even better reference.
And finally, once you have all this research,
you can then start taking it to the exploration phase.
So then when we go into the exploration phase,
this is our chance to build out our UI
on perhaps a couple of key screens.
And we want to answer the question of
how do you immerse the world into your UI?
And it's exciting, because all you have to do is just explore.
I think this is a great opportunity
to be able to explore all different kind of spectrums
of visuals when you're setting out for your UI direction.
To me, it's almost like, let's say, baking a cake.
There's so many different ingredients to play with
that not only influences the way that your cake tastes,
but also how it looks.
There's an endless amount of variations
that you can proceed with,
but this is a time with the range of UI elements
for your game that you can think about
how your player will enjoy the most.
But what's important is that you explore the spectrum
offered by your ingredients.
These UI ingredients can allow for immersion,
but within each one, there are different spectrums
you can experiment with during your exploration.
For example, diegetic UI or non-diegetic UI.
Which one will work better for your game?
And as a quick recap, diegetic UI is interface
that is included in the game's world.
For example, it can be seen and heard by the game characters.
Non-diegetic, however, is interface
that is rendered outside the game world,
only visible and audible to the players in the real world.
So with diegetic, you're able to gain
a fully immersive narrative visually.
It's great when the narrative is very natural,
like let's say looking at a map
the same way that Campo Santos Firewatch does,
or even in Dead Space, because you and your character
are in a spaceship, ultimately,
you're looking at the same heads-up display.
But there's also risk to diegetic UI.
If you have a lot of information to show,
there is a chance that crucial information
can get buried due to the narrative UI.
Complex tasks in the game may have a lot of friction
due to a heavy cognitive load required by these tasks.
And when you commit to a diegetic look,
you're committing to preserving the fourth wall,
which could prove later difficult,
depending on your player's task in the game.
And non-diegetic shouldn't be considered a loss of narrative,
as it's there to help guide the player through complex tasks
and strategies.
And as you see with even games such as Riot's League
of Legends or Atlas' Persona series,
the two keep to non-diegetic because they
have complex tasks and content that
should be clearly separated so the player can easily
play the game.
But of course, the risk of non-diegetic
is depending on how it is laid out and designed.
Because the way, if it's badly laid out,
you can risk further complicating your complex task.
And if it's not designed correctly,
then it will distract from the world being presented,
in addition to just breaking the fourth wall.
So, how do you explore the decision
to have a UI that is more diegetic or non-diegetic?
Well, it depends.
Both can be narrative.
This should be more of a decision based
on your game's mediums and mechanics.
For simple mechanics or console games,
you may not need a non-diegetic UI
and can project through characters
or other diegetic methods.
But perhaps your game is significantly complex
with strategy that creating that UI layer
in between the player will make
for a frictionless experience
between a player and a game's world.
So depending on how you pursue via diegetic
or non-diegetic UI,
there are still several other ingredients you can play with
that immerse your world into the UI.
Skeuomorphic UI creates a sense of familiarity
by emulating materials,
while flat design stays true to its medium,
often feeling minimal and utilitarian.
But for Blizzard's Hearthstone, the developer commits to a skeuomorphic UI
that enforces their narrative for a player literally playing with cards
in this tavern that's in the game.
The game is a card game, yet through its UI elements,
we are kept in a world that preserves such a narrative
that feels tangible to the user.
And while flat design stays true to its minimal style,
it can help focus the player on what the bigger focus
of the world is in the game.
For example, Nintendo's Pokemon Go
solely wants to focus on the Pokemon.
So they aim to keep their UI rather minimal and flat
in order to focus consistently on the Pokemon.
And then you have things like our games like Nintendo's Zelda Breath of the Wild
where the minimal flat design allows the player to focus on Link,
to focus on his inventory, which plays a huge part of the adventurous world within the game.
And while these few examples are extremities,
you often see many games will adopt almost a mixture,
but they do so in a way that tries to complement the world in a consistent manner
and to not look fractured within their UI.
So when going through your exploration,
even testing out designs through a similar visual scale
can help you create a wide variety of choices.
While I tend to do this specific exercise
just with one layout, even different layouts
are worth exploring as well when looking
at the visual scale of each design.
Layout as well has the ability to promote easy usability and world immersion.
Within Nintendo's Fire Emblem Heroes, the way they lay out their gacha feature
plays in line with their narrative of using magical stones to summon heroes through a
mystical gateway. The layout of the orbs is not only easy to interact with by simply tapping,
but they're also able to clearly explain the benefits of each orb and what kind of hero
you can gain while summoning the stone's hero.
Another fun example is with Dragon Ball Z Dokkan Battle.
When you're about to go into battle,
not only is the screen laid out
in this exciting action-packed manga-inspired layout,
but it also clearly communicates
who you are fighting against.
Or even the way that they decide
to display their characters,
that even though it's just about communicating basic stats,
they do so in mimicking
a traditional trading card layout style,
which is very familiar to the brand's long history
of selling trading cards.
And then if we even go beyond just static visuals,
but animation, animation of your UI
can still keep the player immersed within the world.
Here in Quantic Dream's Heavy Rain,
the developers clearly develop an animation UI
that helps communicate timing urgency of specific commands
that were pinned to their related actions,
such as punching and dodging.
And even with EA's Mirror's Edge,
the team was able to use animation with their UI
to not only direct the player in the right direction,
but simultaneously promote the game spirit
of being a fast-paced action game.
So, in short, there is so much you can explore in these phases
with just using these four UI elements.
When you're trying to figure out how to immerse a game's world into the UI,
just know that variety is king in this phase,
and exploring different varieties of each ingredient
will provide for a wholesome building process.
But then once you've built out these UI options,
how do you pick?
In the iteration phase, you get to decide the balance
between narrative UI and its impact
on the overall user experience.
You've done a bunch of exploration of what your UI can be,
but at the end of the day, we need to remember
that UI needs to enable interaction with the game's world,
not distract from it.
Sometimes this decision can be very clear,
but I have found that focusing on these four main elements
often help me edit, revise, and decide a solid direction
when it comes to critical UI visuals for a game.
Readability.
Am I sacrificing readability for style?
Am I looking at the game's info or the info's styling?
Consider the risk you could be over-designing your UI.
Perhaps due to color or more visual iteration
in a decoration.
You could be distracting the player
from the content you're presenting to them.
Personality.
Can I see my world's keywords when I look at the UI,
even without the visual support of characters and environments?
What's important to see is in those games,
brands or keywords are visually implied in the design.
So visuals have the ability to stand on their own,
but still reflect the game's brand.
Implication.
Are interactive elements distinct
from non-interactive elements?
How much can I edit down to a more essential core look?
Your UI doesn't have to be literal to your references.
Perhaps color palettes and light iconography
is enough to communicate a brand in a world.
Also, I need to make sure that the player can tell
the difference between interactive objects
and non-interactive objects.
And finally, scale.
Does the visual UI language have legs to expand to other UI elements?
Can I scale without breaking the memory bank within the game?
Can I possibly scale this distinct look to even perhaps marketing or community assets?
You may find that perhaps some of your ideas, while looking really cool, have a really heavy
memory load or can't even scale, let's say, from a nine-slicing perspective.
So when you look and start to iterate your designs,
you just need to be judicious about these four categories.
You need a balance between narrative impact
and player usability.
Remember, during our process,
how good UI should enhance and promote
a frictionless experience for a player
and the world they are interacting with.
UI is just one of the many visual elements
that can be included in your game.
To enhance the game's world,
and once you have chosen a UI direction,
likely you'll need to keep iterating on it too.
And when that happens, it's always good to keep some key principles in mind
to make sure your UI's narrative isn't jeopardizing usability.
As I am creating UI for an entirely new game,
I will always refer to these 10 usability heuristics
provided by the Nielsen Norman Group to help me revise my immersive UI.
And...
Even though a lot of the examples I had
were very much console or mobile-based,
I just wanted to give some thoughts on, as well,
of how I can see UI immersion continuing on
with some new mediums within games.
So for AR and UI immersion, I think
there's going to be a very interesting balancing act.
Since AR's focus with games will be based on the camera
and real world interactions,
I feel like the user interface will be kept to a minimal
to balance out with the camera visuals.
Especially if the intent is to blend a player's environment
with game visuals such as characters,
a focus on that experience
would require minimal interface on your screen.
And when it comes to VR,
I think that there's a huge opportunity for a diegetic UI.
With VR, the additional access to haptic audio
and animation features that provides good player feedback
mechanisms can also be considered for world immersion
opportunities.
And you'll also likely need to still
have some kind of visual interface, like type
or perhaps even buttons for accessibility.
But there's going to be some really exciting stuff that
goes on, I think, between VR and immersion for UI.
So to conclude, it's really crucial during the entire process
that you keep a very open mind of how you can inject story into your UI.
There are visual ways both diegetic and non-diegetic to do so.
And by doing so, you're going to keep a player immersed in a game's world,
which will be beneficial to your overall brand.
It is just your job as a UI UX designer
to make sure that this UI does not distract from the world.
And you can do that using heuristic principles.
And this is just even more important because we live in a time in a market
where not invest investing in your U I's ability to add on to your brand it to
pass up on that opportunity is a mistake. There are so many user interfaces that
are generic and can be mistaken for any other let's say sci-fi game or even any
other farm building game your U I is an opportunity to be as unique as your
games world so take advantage of it.
So if you only take a smidgen away from today's presentation,
here's a few things to remember.
To acquire a well-designed immersive UI,
split your process into research, exploration,
and iteration.
And then during your exploration,
make sure to test a design out with a variety of designs,
a variety of layouts.
Think about how animation can play a part in your UI.
And then finally,
When you want to decide that balance between your UI's immersion and usability, you can
use these four elements to iterate and improve your UI.
So that's it for me.
Thank you everyone for listening, and hopefully I can take some questions.
First of all, thank you very much for delivering this incredible speech.
Now, with regards to diegetic and non-diegetic UI,
I know that there are games that do it fully on one end or the other,
and then there are games like the Metro series that kind of have a balance
between that in terms of stealth and objectives for diegetic,
for in-game objects and things like ammo counts, for instance, being...
Non-diegetic, do you think that there's a risk of a conflict between immersion, readability,
and all those aspects that you mentioned when you try to strike a middle ground?
So your question is, is there a risk in going for a more diegetic UI
and risking usability for immersion's sake?
basically if immersion is going to be impacted somewhat if you try to go in the middle, if
you try to incorporate components from both ends.
I would say if you try and strike a balance that's in between those two, you have to do
so in a consistent manner.
And pending on the user task, whether it's something that's really complex, the more
complex a task is, diegetic UI may not be...
Diegetic UI is useful when it feels very first nature to the player.
And so if it's a very complicated task that a user doesn't, say, experience in the real
world, it will be tough.
But you should always explore if you can.
Thank you kindly.
Hi, Steph.
I'm Kevin.
I'm a UX designer at Google Maps.
I love what I do, but I'm really torn when it comes to in-game navigation UI.
And one of the things I've always found conflicting was reaching your destination or seeing in
an abstract, simplistic 2D view of your goals or enemies on the map, and sometimes that
would break immersion.
And sometimes I would actually play games very differently,
turning off the UI entirely.
Games like Far Cry, Assassin's Creed Syndicate.
My first experience turning off UI was the Radar in Metal Gear Solid 2,
and it completely blew my mind.
I was curious as to if you have any insights,
the balance between reaching your goal and objectives
versus immersion in nav UI.
Right. So in regards to you said Google Maps.
Yeah. Um, so for Google Maps,
I would just turn to the user for your, your answer.
Why is your user using Google Maps?
It's because they're trying to get somewhere.
They're not necessarily looking for an immersive experience,
like let's say with games.
And so I think if being able to optimize for that process of for them,
the experience will be much better if it's.
more clear to them, just like,
I just want to get from point A to point B.
But then it's always thinking about,
I guess you would say, the user's intent
of why they're doing that task.
Okay, cool.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Hi, so you mentioned a few times about animated UI elements.
I was just wondering if you had any specific methods or tools
for kind of communicating the intended animation
to developers or clients when you're kind of exploring?
Right, yeah, I mean, it really depends on your resources
at that point.
Sometimes, depending on your games team,
you have people who are naturally animators.
Sometimes you have only resources,
let's say, like PowerPoint, right?
And I say that.
from, it really depends on your comfort level.
Sometimes even for myself, I will just use
like a quick keynote, pending on the animation,
just to demonstrate, okay, this UI element
should move over here once I acquire this goal.
So I would say it really depends on your resources.
Yeah.
Thanks.
Do you recommend any
practices or pieces of work that new UX designers should try and add to their
portfolio if they're just trying to get into the industry?
Right, I would say...
That's an interesting question and I would say from that perspective, I think the best
thing you can do as a UI designer starting out is just to create your own projects and
to do so in a way that I think what's always a lovely demonstration.
is when you show something like a game HUD
and a character profile screen
because that demonstrates your skill of layout,
your skill of colors and typography,
and you wanna be able to tell them
that you can balance in between screens
that have a lot of information that needs to be digested
versus very minimal information.
Thank you.
So does localization ever play a factor?
I know in my personal experience, I have artists
pick great fonts that fit the world, and they don't have any
European characters, so we can't localize.
And maybe on the flip side, you need to do something like
an IKEA manual that there's no text at all, but that might
fit the world.
That's a really good question.
So in terms of localization,
I think from an exploration perspective,
you should be, when you're creating these UI screens,
it should be very inspirational.
And so from that perspective,
you should try and find fonts that feel true to your brand.
But then, and then afterwards,
you can take that as kind of your goal
and then look at fonts that are.
that are able to be like localized for your game.
And so I would say for your research and exploration part,
you just look at what you feel like is the best font.
And then after that, you go into localization fonts
and then work with your font vendor
to see which font will match closest to it.
Do you have any, like, ideas or guidelines or recommendations for, say, user interfaces
and user experience in games or immersive environments where there isn't necessarily
a fourth wall?
where instead of playing a character, you are more or less the character in something
that is either slightly augmented reality or an alternate reality that is still making
callbacks to the current reality.
A lot of what I like to do is in those situations where there is a little bit of a blur between
game reality and reality, so UX and UI there for me gets a little...
confusing because I'm not quite sure what to do because there's not really a
fourth wall and the only information presented to you is entirely separate
and also the same as the character as you are the character
Right, so in that respect, I would say that it depends on your game's nature, right?
If it's a very story-driven game, then I think that you want to not necessarily, like UI is important,
but then you want to make sure it's not distracting as well from the main experience.
So especially if you're doing something like mixed reality, augmented reality,
I would say that you want, if anything, you want user interface at that point to be very minimal.
In terms of resources, I would say just being able to...
Really being able to, I think, research about just like any other games that have been working on it,
just seeing their findings as well would be a good idea.
Because especially with AR, there's going to be new usability issues that
you're going to be finding yourself. So it's a whole process, I think.
Thank you.
And I think actually we're out of time right now.
And so I'll be just on the side if you have more questions.
And thank you so much for listening.