We're going to go ahead and get started.
Thanks everyone for joining us today for the Storytellers of Esports panel.
I'll go ahead and talk a bit about the panel and then we'll do introductions and we'll
get right to it.
So, the Storytellers of Esports panel is, we're going to talk really quickly about why
storytelling is such a critical component of esports alongside having a big prize purse
or having a huge stage.
So having a lot of awesome players competing in your game.
So I'm Tim Young, I'm going to be moderating this panel.
I work at Twitch as a partnerships analyst.
And we'll start with introductions here on the right.
So I'm TJ Huckaby, I'm a writer and game designer behind SC2VN, which is the StarCraft
2 visual novel.
My name is Travis Beauchamp, I produce the Smash Brothers, which is a nine-part documentary
miniseries on professional Smash Brothers players.
And right now I'm working on a follow-up to that.
My name is also Travis, but Travis Gafford. I am an e-sports journalist. I was with GameSpot
and CBS Interactive recently, but just recently, about a month ago, helped launch Yahoo! e-sports.
So that's my whole thing.
I'm Damian Echada. I do video production for Team Liquid, and we just built out a company
called 1UP Studios, which does video production for a range of developers, other companies, etc.
I'm Brittany Brown, I'm a community program manager at Twitch, and I've previously worked
with CBS Interactive, Zubu, Red Bull Esports, ESL, various different companies as a host
and on-camera personality.
Oh, awesome. Thanks you all. Thanks everyone for joining us today.
So, to get this panel started, I'll just go ahead quickly and ask.
So, like, right now there's a huge spotlight on eSports right now.
2016, sports stadiums literally packed, you know, with eSports fans.
So why do you guys think that storytelling is such a critical component next to having, you know, a huge league or a really big prize pool?
So we'll start with Brittany.
Yes, so storytelling I would say is probably the top priority that you should be focusing
on as a game developer or even an org owner.
within the scene. I think Thresh was a really good example. If you were here previously
in the last panel, he talked about how he really catapulted his career off of a story
that was told about him and that's when he really knew he was a pro gamer and became
a pro gamer. In general, storytelling is really important just because it's kind of, it's
a link to our past, present, future, as well as a connection to humanity.
So as we watch stories, or tell stories, and watch stories, or listen to stories, and see
stories being published, we therefore feel connection, feel some sort of empathy, or
whatever it is, to that person that's being published.
being shown within that story.
Not only that, stories inform, educate, inspire, motivate a list of other things that then
contribute to both change and growth within any scene.
And I think for eSports specifically, with so many people coming into it and it being
under such a huge spotlight right now, it's really important that you tell those stories
effectively so that we preserve the culture that has been made previously in the past.
What was really interesting for me is I actually started off not being a competitive gamer
and I played games like Mass Effect and other RPGs.
I was not invested in League of Legends, Dota 2, Counter-Strike, none of that, right?
Then one of my buddies picked up the Dota 2 beta and we started playing a little bit.
I was horrible at the game.
But I got really invested because he started telling me about this narrative between Navi and Alliance and like that whole lead up to TI.
And it blew my mind because my entire life I had never understood why my family would always get like super excited over...
I'm from California so like the Angels or the Dodgers or the Lakers and they like scream at the TV and jump up out of their chairs.
I had like zero clue what any of that meant. I just, I legit thought that they had a problem.
And that they were overly invested in all these Kobe's and whoever's.
I was like, I don't get this. It makes zero sense to me.
So my pinnacle moment of understanding, at least storytelling in eSports,
was I'm sitting in this Buffalo Wild Wings during TI, I think it was 4.
Dota fans could shoot me if I'm wrong for this.
But it's Na'Vi versus Alliance, and it's the final game,
and the TPs are canceled, and everyone in the bar starts erupting.
You know, like, the event ends and, like, I'm just sitting there in this Buffalo Wild Wings
realizing, like, I finally get why, like, my grandpa screams at the TV when Kobe misses
a shot or when he makes a shot or when, you know, the Angels do something insane because
it's like you're invested in those players and the organization storylines and, like,
the lineage of certain brands and it was a pretty interesting experience and that's kind
of how I got started into my eSports career, so to speak.
So I actually, sorry Travis, I actually answered the completely wrong question, which will
come later on.
But my start in esports was actually from my sister Sam Brown, some of you may be familiar
with her.
She works for Twitch as well as a community program manager.
She introduced me to eSports back in 2013, and it was from her college's eSports club.
And she would just be like, this is phenomenal, you should come check it out.
And so every weekend I would go and hang out with a bunch of people that were really into
eSports.
I thought that was really cool and from then on we attended Season 3 Worlds for League
of Legends and that's when I really knew it was something that I wanted to get involved
in.
I've always been really competitive in traditional sports so when coming into this field I was
like completely, I don't know, astounded by the competitive play and how...
these players were, and for me it was all about telling stories like my entire life,
so I wanted to go in and really learn about these pro players that were playing at Season
3 Worlds, and I couldn't really find as much information as I wanted, so I thought that
it would be really interesting to go and dig myself. I would then reach out to them via
Twitter or just through press releases and things like that to...
I'm here about their story and then from then on I was like everyone should be hearing about this
so I started my own podcast at my local community college, which
Actually did really well and that's when Travis came into my life and thought that us working together would be really awesome
It was okay. It was ultimately okay. No, it was great.
Yeah, I mean, it's funny, I think, especially with these two, a very similar story for me,
where I, you know, kind of got into, was never a traditional sports fan,
got into watching StarCraft II competitively because I really liked the game,
but eventually found myself playing way more League of Legends than I did, you know, actually play StarCraft II.
And for me, at some point in time, there was a question that was asked of, you know,
League eSports had started to become a thing. There wasn't really much going on there, but it was way back in the beginning of this whole thing.
And I asked myself, you know, I'm playing way more League, but I care way more about StarCraft II as an eSport.
Why is that? And the answer came to me that I was actually really deeply invested in the personalities and stories in StarCraft,
but I didn't really know anything about what was happening in League,
because at the time there was just not really very much content being made in it.
My favorite podcast at the time was one called State of the Game by J.P.
McDaniel. Really great podcast that featured different pro players talking
about the game, the story lines, the drama oftentimes. Crazy drama. And
For me, I realized maybe there's an opportunity here to create something in League and both
educate myself and educate the fans and try to replicate what I loved so much about StarCraft 2.
And so that led to the creation of State of the League, which was just a shameless rip-off
of his show.
And that was when I started to realize, you know, actually one of the big goals for me
in e-sports from that initial show and still to this day is I really want to provide a
People who care about League or are interested in eSport, the opportunity to become a fan of a player or to hate a player even, right?
That's, I think, for me, what people are, what gets them into the eSport.
Seeing those big moments of somebody, you know, break down on stage or hearing some crazy story about a player.
And so that's what drives me forward today is telling these stories.
I mean, I agree that having a league and having a huge prize pool kind of brings legitimacy,
but people really get excited about the stories of the players and the teams.
It's like Brady versus Manning.
For me growing up in the Bay Area, it was the 49ers and the Cowboys.
That kind of got you excited.
And I think it's true for eSports as well.
If you take those players and team stories out of either sports or eSports, you're just
left with the game.
And the game is interesting.
Games can be, you know, but it's ones and zeros.
It's like the ball and bat.
The real interesting stuff is the people playing the game expressing themselves through the
game that creates story lines and that drives interest.
Like I said, working on a follow-up to the Smash Bros. project.
And, uh, you know, one of the protagonists is Mango.
And he's a...
He's by far probably the most popular, most well-known Smasher.
And, uh, the way he plays the game is so instinctual in the moment.
It's a very unique play style.
And I was interviewing a local...
And he was talking about Mango saying that it almost didn't matter that it was playing
Melee.
It could have been anything.
It's just for Mango, the way he would talk about it is like, oh, he was a buster.
Or I got in his head and I wrecked him.
And I think that kind of gets to the heart of it.
It's about player-to-player interactions.
That's the interesting part of sports and e-sports.
So if you ignore that, I think it's really to your detriment.
I think if you were to take even the top level StarCraft II tournament or whatever that you
stream and would normally have 50,000 views, if you were to take away the casters, if you
were to take away the player name plates and just show this high level game, you probably
wouldn't get nearly as many views.
It's really when you have these two forces, Huck and Idra, the bad boy and the pretty
boy that's always smiling, making hearts on the map.
That's sort of what is driving this fan support, not necessarily the high, high top level play.
It certainly helps, it augments that story line, but it's really who these two people
are because you're going to be pulling way more interest because people are interested
in these two people specifically, not just who's doing the best at any given game.
Yeah, great answers guys.
So a common theme I kind of saw across
what you guys were talking about is like
storytelling was a way that you were introduced
to your specific communities.
So maybe Travis, can you speak more about like
what has your experience been about
drawing new players into a specific community
you were putting a spotlight on?
Sure, I mean, you know, for me I feel like
you know, the
I myself got drawn into Melee haphazardly.
I was living with my brother at the time.
I had played 64. That was my game.
I went to college, played 64, and wrecked everyone.
My brother got a GameCube while I was away at college, and he played Melee.
So when we started living together, that was the only game we had,
and he just destroyed me at it, consistently.
One slightly inebriated night I was very frustrated and he showed me like you know these videos
and stuff of these pro players and that kind of sparked me to really you know get excited
about it and I wanted to kind of share that feeling of seeing this game and you know it's
yes it's ones and zeros and it's this very clean sort of universe it's very separate
from like a dirty field of like you know when you're playing football or whatever but
When you see these guys play at a top level, it doesn't feel that way.
It feels like they can bend the rules a little bit and just sort of make it their own.
It's like they're, of course, talking about Mango.
It's like a Neo going into Matrix and making it their own.
In that sense, it's almost more human in some way than sports.
But, and that's kind of what I wanted to share
and bring people into with the Smash Brothers.
Kind of explain that aspect of it,
but with the stories of these people
and kind of bring them into that.
Yeah, awesome.
I mean, you touched on it just a little bit,
but like the comparison to traditional sports,
and I think Damian talked about it too,
is like there are storylines in traditional sports,
but both of you guys seem to feel like
there's something a bit different about eSports
compared to traditional sports storytelling.
So, Travis, do you think you can lead us
into that discussion?
Yeah, I mean, it's really interesting for me. I find myself maybe confronting this more
than I ever have before because, you know, for those that don't know, Yahoo! Esports
is now under Yahoo! Sports. It's an initiative of that, right? Whereas before I was working
at GameSpot and we were coming at it from the game coverage angle.
Some of the people that I'm working with now are executive producers who have produced, you know, Olympics coverage and traditional sports coverage for a long time.
And so the kind of conversations that we're having are questions around, like, where are the differences?
What do we focus on? What can we learn from on the traditional sports side compared to esports?
And one of the things that I've quickly kind of realized, you know, I've known it for a while,
but I think putting it in this context has helped me think about it more, is that...
And hopefully I don't get slaughtered by traditional sports fans for saying this, but I feel like
eSports, maybe more than traditional sports, is so much about the personalities and about
the stories.
I think there's a lot of different reasons for that, but one of it is just that
It kind of came out of this grass roots thing where there's no kind of like filter, you
know, these guys are not, they don't always have a ton of press training and even beyond
that, you know, this all came up after the rise of social media.
So you have
A ton of stuff that's happening where players immediately after the game are putting their
opinions out on that on Twitter or Facebook. Even, you know, just a personal thing that
happened yesterday was a ‑‑
I guess it was two days ago. Doublelift, who is a friend of mine and also one of the most
prominent players in League, lost in a very, very embarrassing fashion to one of the worst
teams and he immediately unfollowed everyone that he followed on Twitter and only followed
his teammates and sort of made this like statement. And it's one of those things where it's not
something that was said in an interview, but it very clearly tells the story of where he's
at right now with the team.
And I think there's just so many of these opportunities where
You know, we have discussions about how much should we focus
on a match highlight versus how much should we put video
resources into doing a feature or something about a player.
And again, I think maybe in traditional sports, a
highlight goes crazy.
Whereas in e-sports, there's so much draw for that post-game
interview.
I'm obviously very biased because that's what I do.
But I think it's just one of the big differences.
I think another big difference is what we talked about at least in the last panel was
how different games can kind of come and go within eSports as we've seen with StarCraft
2, StarCraft and everything, but I think that storytelling really allows those professional
players to create their brand and to go on social media and be able to do things like
Doublelift has done.
and for people to become fans of them and then therefore then go on to future careers
within the scene and not just go into whatever game that they're going to be playing as a
professional player blindsided by what's going to happen next.
Storytelling is really a foundation for them to be able to figure out at least the time
that they're being a pro player what the next step is for them and to use storytellers
as a way to be able to build their brand and to be able to have a future within the scene.
So TJ, you actually have a really interesting contrast to everyone else on the panel, kind
of focused on video content.
You actually shipped a game about eSports, Starcraft 2 visual novel.
So when you're drafting a story, more or less even a fictional story, what are the compelling
elements are you looking for to talk about this community you're covering?
Right, right, because I chose to write about eSports, you know, I'm not like having to just follow players from day to day.
So it's like, what, what, why did I come to eSports and what was it so compelling about it?
And to me, you know, if you're going to tell any story, no matter what kind of story it is,
it has to have some sort of human element.
And so a lot of the times that you see in eSports is like these teenagers or 20 somethings, you know,
they are devoting a huge amount of time and effort and passion to this game.
They're sacrificing a whole lot.
And for what?
And for a lot of the time, it's for nothing.
And that story right there of someone chasing everything and going after it and really not
ending up with anything in the end, there's a story there. And I like to tell that story. I
think that a lot of the time what we see focused in eSports storytelling is the story of the
champion's rise and how he made it. But I think something equally beautiful is the guy who is
just playing these online tournaments day in and day out and he finally wins one. He's been up
all night and he takes that $100 that he just won and he buys the first steak dinner he's had
in three months. I think that
As long as there is some sort of human element there that eSports provides a rich landscape
to tell whatever sort of story you want.
I think Travis especially does that really well.
Me Travis?
Yes.
Awesome.
Thanks a lot.
You touched on it just a little bit, but it's about, you know, you're working, and Travis
you talked about it too, you're working with people who don't have a lot of press training,
who are like teenagers or 20-somethings, and they can be hard to work with sometimes, or
maybe they're really quiet, you know, their personalities, they play games all day, and
they won't, you know, they're not very extroverted, so I think we talked about it a bit at dinner
last night, like how do you get sometimes these guys to open up, or like, you know,
to tell their story of how they got where they are?
Well, you know, it's funny. I actually, I was thinking about this as we were talking.
I feel like, you know, the difference between sports and eSports, you have this tradition.
You know, eSports is just organized video gaming, really.
And video games have historically been this, you know, pastime of...
that dispossess, you know, the geeks and the nerds and the weaklings and stuff, you know,
people who are, you know, not in the mainstream.
It's always kind of been, like, looked down upon.
So that's kind of slowly changing, but I feel like that, because of that history and because
it's still a little bit true, you have these storylines that might be more internal, more
emotionally driven.
And like you say, more, you know, more people are kind of, like, withdrawn or can be withdrawn.
I had a great interview with a guy, I think it was the best episode out of all nine episodes I did, Isaiah.
He's this really shy guy who's just incredible, has this amazingly fast, aggressive Captain Falcon that he plays.
And he refused to get on camera because he was very camera shy.
So I kind of said, okay, what if we just sit down with an audio recorder?
And I'll go take you to lunch and we'll just talk.
And so we sat there and talked for hours.
We found that it was at Apex 2012,
this big tournament, and it's very loud.
So we went up to this, found this perfect little quiet room
and we just sat there and had the recorder
and we just talked for hours.
And from that, I got, he just opened up
and was able to really kind of talk about issues
with his self-confidence and things that.
He definitely would not have said on camera if I'd forced him into this position he was
uncomfortable with.
So I think you have to respect these players, you have to respect their individuality, and
sometimes you don't get people to talk at all, but that's how it goes.
I think you just have to be open to...
Telling stories differently.
However you can.
Yeah, I mean that's really interesting because you actually kind of got him into his natural
element.
But it's interesting, everyone on this side of the table works with players who are thrust
into the spotlight more or less.
So maybe in your case, if you're doing a post-game interview, and someone's not really opening
up, how do you kind of get them to tell their story or do you kind of carry that weight
on for them?
I'm happy you asked that, Tim, because I was about to answer that.
You're already a better panel host than Nick Allen, my friend, who hosted the last one.
So we're off to a great start.
It's fun for me. I benefit a lot from the fact that I get to interview these guys every weekend.
And, you know, obviously I don't interview the same guy every weekend, but with the format for League structure,
I predominantly cover League of Legends, I'm at the studio every single weekend doing interviews with the teams.
And one of the benefits of that is that over time I have the
opportunity to start forging these personal relationships. So
you'll have oftentimes a new rookie that will come in. They
have never done an interview. And it's funny because you might
see them interacting with their teammates and they might seem
really energetic or whatever. And then of course whenever you
put them in front of a camera they start to feel really
nervous.
I'll sometimes get criticism for my interviews being too
casual or too silly and oftentimes that's because, you
know, especially when it's with a new guy, I'm fine opting for
the kind of like let's just joke around about how your teammates
So I'm going to try to snore too loud or something like that for a little bit to get whoever it
is I'm talking to really comfortable. Because that means that, you know, at the end of the
season potentially if they win, they're going to be much more open and candid about sort
of their path than, you know, if I hadn't really talked to them or if they're so set
with this idea of like I only give like the professional PR answer, like, yeah, we're
just going to try really hard. We tried really hard. Our effort was really … ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ??
you know, there today. I think just sort of forging those relationships and really allowing
the players to feel like, you know, they're able to showcase their personality, they're
able to show who they are. That's sort of how you get sometimes that really golden moment.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think Damian and I worked a lot on both
me doing interviews just like Travis, as well as behind the scenes documentary style pieces.
And a lot of the time we made sure to take the time that we were creating the best story
as possible, not just the story that we saw from the outside, but stories that we have
learned from just getting to know the players themselves.
So we would spend time with them.
If we can, or just have them become comfortable with us before we even went in and tried to touch the story,
I think making sure that you have the right message,
and knowing the person personally, or the subject that you are trying to tell a story about,
is going to be way more effective than just going in and telling a story about a pro player that you know is very good at the game.
It's important to really get to know them prior, so that you can show the audience what you see is so special about them.
Yeah, so when we're looking at the landscape of eSports right now, there's a ton of different
games, right?
So like Dota League, Starcraft, Hearthstone, Rocket League, it's going to be crazy.
So these games span across a ton of different designs, and you're not going to know how
to play every single game.
So Damien, you've worked across a multitude of games, how do you take the story that comes
from a variety of backgrounds and makes it palatable for everyone to enjoy?
So for me, I do a majority of documentary work.
So I try to find a touchpoint with a player that I can relate to, and then maybe if it's
not something that I can directly relate to, something that I have a friend that's very
similar as.
But finding the human element in someone is probably the most important part, and figuring
out how to...
Talk to the player about their gameplay as well as what makes them tick.
So, for example, for me, when I started doing the series on Team Liquid last year, we had a player, Phoenix, who no one knew who he was, really.
He had played top lane in Korea, but did a horrible job, got brought to America, had little play.
And we had to replace one of our star players with him.
So it was like fighting the community against this,
like, who is this guy, get rid of him,
bring back your old guy.
Like, the community was already just disposed to dislike him.
And especially adding the fact that he was Korean
and didn't know a lot of English,
I had to figure out how to get a North American audience
to care about a kid from Korea
that everyone from Korea said was bad,
and no one in America wanted him to be there.
So I spent a lot of time with him and with our manager, just
kind of like trying to figure out who he was. The day that we
picked him up, I actually, his previous name was Miso and we
were going over names and I was the one that named him Phoenix.
So that was just kind of a random interesting point where
me and him kind of built a relationship off of that. So
like I'd always go out to eat with him and any time that they
would do like an activity I would make sure to kind of be
there.
And obviously from a documentary standpoint, that's something that I was able to do.
Maybe not everyone's able to do that, but to like what Brittany and Travis said, building
the personal relationship with the player and getting them comfortable with you is probably
one of the most important things when telling their story.
So, you know, when you guys are crafting your stories and, you know, you're coming from
a very complex game that, like, a lot of mechanics, a lot of strategy behind it, how do you guys
decide, like, what parts to leave out?
Like, especially in Super Smash Melee, it's just insane amount, like, textbooks and textbooks
amount of knowledge you have to know to understand, you know, what's the best game.
So how do you kind of decide what gameplay or knowledge to leave in and what story elements,
you know, to keep out?
When I started approaching the project, I sort of did it with the assumption that
if a potential audience member didn't have at least a little bit of love for games,
that I wasn't going to care about them.
If they didn't have that base level of...
If they had any respect for games or interest in gaming, then they could essentially fuck off.
But I've realized, in retrospect, that's probably a short-sighted kind of perspective,
because King of Kong, one of the most successful gaming documentaries of all time,
and I think still the best, had hardly any specifics for gameplay.
It had maybe five minutes worth of screen time devoted to the actual game mechanics,
and the rest was just these...
players and their emotional journeys and their interactions and stuff.
So I think for the most part, you can sort of just leave out the specifics for the gameplay
and concentrate on what victories and defeat mean for these emotional stories.
Like, Rudy is a football movie.
Sort of.
It's, you know, Rudy plays actual football for like one tackle at the end of the movie
and that's it.
And the rest is just, you know, those emotional kind of progressions.
So I think you can, I don't want to say you should leave it out entirely, but if your
goal is the widest audience possible, then I think gameplay always kind of has to take
a back seat.
I mean, you should try to always have a universal story.
Like, someone that doesn't know anything about the game, if they watch your interview or
you're part of your documentary, they can walk away with something that they understood.
But I would say that don't bury what you're doing in jargon, but you don't ‑‑ at the
same token, I don't agree that you should have none, because it provides some really
nice flavor and authenticity to what you're telling about.
Yeah, and a lot of the times, like, the players' personalities are, like, interwoven with the
gameplay.
And, like, that's what you did in the game, right?
Right.
So, what you wanted, well, what I did specifically, at least, was that if you have a character
who's pretty hot-headed or whatever, they might play, like, a hot-headed style.
Or if you have someone that's pretty laid back, you know, they play very passive.
And games are, you know, you can sort of sometimes see that, like, in boxing, Manny Pacquiao or
whatever, versus Floyd Mayweather, people would say that, you know, Floyd played lame.
But...
In games it lets you really, you can really get into that because there's so many, at
least in most games, have so many ways for players to express themselves.
And I think that the best e-sports, the ones that are most watchable, have lots of ways
for players to express themselves.
The danger is, of course, it's a little abstract.
Like you have, let's say there's a theoretical movie,
like an e-sports movie, and it's double lift
at the end of the movie, like pulling off
this amazing pentakill, and CLG wins the day or whatever.
And it's climactic, and everybody's happy and stuff.
But the act itself is sort of abstract.
He's sitting there at a computer.
And then over here on a screen this character does these things and kills these other characters
and they win.
And I think because of that, because in contrast to regular sports which is just played with
a human body which everyone has and can understand, you know, you as a content creator have to
kind of...
explain and synthesize all those things that are really cool about the game so that we
as an audience can feel like, you know, we just saw an amazing catch by Jerry Rice when
Doublelift pulls off this pentakill.
We have to be taught ahead of time a little bit why a pentakill is beautiful, just like
an athletic act.
Yeah. So obviously all you guys have worked across a lot of, you know, really, you know,
professional players, really popular players. But for anyone who's like trying to get into
the space as either like a developer or even a storyteller, you know, the landscape of esports
has changed, you know, dramatically in probably the span that all of you guys have been working.
You know, how do you guys still find access to players? I mean, you guys, you know, go to LCS
every weekend, but do you have any advice for people who are just looking to, you know, start
this on their own or like start interviewing on their own or telling stories on their own?
Yeah, it's really hard. As the scene evolves, it gets more difficult to get access to the pros.
I mentioned earlier that I did a show called State of the League where I
had three or four different pros on every week.
That show I can't do anymore because these guys are just so busy, even more so than in
traditional sports, e-sports athletes are spending a tremendous amount of time practicing,
competing, fulfilling sponsor obligations, you know, trying out their new coaches, strange
athletic.
a training program, who knows, right? And so it can be very difficult. I think that,
you know, it depends on what you're really looking to do. If you just want to start telling
eSports stories, there's some amazing games that are coming up right now, and those don't
have any stories being told yet.
And you could be a part in creating the rise of this next big title.
And that can be as simple as just going up to a tournament.
And what I used to do is just stand next to the stage,
and whenever the team was done, they'd win or lose,
and you'd just ask a player, do you want to do an interview?
Sometimes they'll say no, sometimes they'll say yes, and that's an opportunity.
I think as you look at some of the bigger e-sports publishers and tournament organizers
are starting to really understand what ‑‑ how important it is to have documentary crews,
media, press cover their stuff. Because, again, as you look at the stuff as
a sport, the analogies are there, right?
There's a reason why traditional sports media exists and why
these guys have been creating stuff. So I think shout out to
Nicola who is in the audience right now from Riot PR. She does
a really good job of not only accommodating the folks that
have been in the scene like myself for a really long time
but also, you know, we have people at the LCS every weekend
that are brand new faces that are coming in as part of like
the teams that are trying to learn how to do this stuff and
get better at doing interviews.
And so I think that there are opportunities in both areas and you just kind of need to figure out what approach you're going to take.
One of the most interesting things that I noticed over this last, I'd say, two years is last year I was a full-time content creator with Team Liquid and then TSM also had a guy.
And now, I don't know, maybe half the teams, right? Something around that, now have in-house content creators.
Maybe they're part-times, some of them are full-time.
It seems like a lot of organizations are picking up in-house content creators and a lot of
those people are just found by, they create content.
Maybe you want to do documentary pieces but the only stuff that you have access to is
in-game footage and maybe some of Travis's interviews, right?
But you could still build the narrative about Doublelift with some highlight videos plus
some interwoven Travis things and climb the ranks on Reddit and then all of a sudden Team
Liquid's asking you to come and be their intern for the summer.
So I think there's a ton of opportunity in entering the scene, you just have to actually
do stuff, right?
Because I could sit here and talk to you all day about all this content that I want to
make, but if I don't have anything, there's nothing to look at.
So once you finally grab the players, I think a good job that all you guys do is keeping
the story really authentic.
Like when people watch, say, the Smash Bros. documentary, it's like, oh my god, I really
understand the Smash community now.
Or when people watch any of your pieces on League or Smash, it's like, oh my god, I really
kind of understand these players and this team.
And it's interesting to me because both of you guys...
So, you know, not too long ago we were non-eSports fans and now you're really capturing the essence
of these teams and these players.
How do you guys kind of keep that authenticity?
For me, kind of just driving back to what I said earlier, it's really identifying with
the players.
So I come from more of a player side or an organization side.
So one of the things that we did with our first season of the series Rebirth that I
made is we were just really honest about everything that was happening.
So we'd gotten a player from Korea, Piglet, who was like, you know, some people consider
maybe...
a
reason why he was benched. Like, people knew that he had, you know, a difficult attitude
to work with and that we were working with him to get him to a better place so we could
We cooperated with the team better to where we could understand one another.
And I think we were pretty honest about that whole process in our show.
And that was, I think, a bi-weekly at that time sort of series that we did.
So for me, keeping the authenticity was not trying to sweep anything under the rug as
an organization, but just being very forward with the players' best intentions at heart.
I definitely have the same strategy as both Damian and Travis when I'm going into, let's
say, an interview, an on-camera interview, or an on-stage hosting type interview.
I definitely want to make sure to sprinkle in those little elements that this is maybe
a 16-year-old who is going through some rough patches back at home, and that could have
translated then into his gameplay.
I think things like that are really important to notice and acknowledge within both either
an interview or a documentary style piece because that just then again adds the human
element and allows people to be able to relate to that person rather than just kind of kicking
them while they're down because of a loss and just a fan being upset because their favorite
pro player couldn't play up to par that day.
So I think sprinkling in those little human elements are very important.
Cool.
So, for this next question, it's actually really interesting we grouped you two guys
together because I want to talk about how developers can empower the content creators
to tell their stories.
And I think both of you guys have a really interesting perspective on both ends of the
spectrum, right?
Yeah.
So, I finished SC2VN and I was like, I want to put this on Steam.
Oh, it's Starcraft, like actual property with some of their actual music on it.
What's it going to take to do that?
And I think that three years ago, there's no chance that Blizzard would have done this.
It's way too risky.
It's crazy to let some fan project on Steam with your IP.
But you know, they heard us out.
They vetted the project, and they were like, okay, you can do this.
So I think that just goes to show how they understand how important it is to be empowering
your people who are telling stories about your players who are showing that StarCraft
isn't just a game.
It's actually way more than that.
It's like a sport in South Korea and has been for 15 years.
It's like a force of nature.
It's not just some game that kids play.
And the more people that understand that, the more staying power that StarCraft has.
Slightly different for you, I'd say.
Yeah, Nintendo.
They're a hard nut to crack. I feel like for the most part, I mean, you do have to do this
little dance around with them. It's kind of well known how they approach content on YouTube,
specifically speed runs and stuff like that. And that's ‑‑ it's something that was
always in the back of my mind. For the time being, I mean, I have so far had no contact
from Nintendo.
And that's fine.
I'd be happy if they just never, you know, kind of had to step in and say anything.
I would like to see a point where they evolve a little bit as a company
to recognize the power that empowering their fans could have.
You know, these... Nintendo is an institution.
Like, you know, so many people grew up...
on the consoles, myself included.
And it's part and parcel with my childhood.
So to have this company be so standoffish about letting us
tell their stories or letting anyone, even like getting
streaming rights and stuff to just show the game at a
tournament, I think it has to change eventually.
They have to recognize that eventually they have to be
more open.
acknowledge the fact that it's the 21st century now.
But you know, I, we'll see.
We'll see what that timeline is like.
And for you guys, I mean, we talked a lot about League and you guys go to LCS and like
Riot does a really awesome job about like building up their players.
But actually, you also cover like a bunch of other games as well.
So have you seen, you know, everyone, you know, rightfully so, uses Riot as an example
of like what they do right.
But are anyone, is anyone doing anything differently that helps you guys out?
I mean, I primarily work with organizations that have put on the tournaments, so like
ESL and things like that.
So I work with them in my line of work when it comes to reaching the pro players and
Making sure that I have press access to any story that I really want to talk about.
When it comes to working with a game developer, Riot Games has always been really good to me.
They're the ones that I'm most familiar with, like I said, or like even Travis said.
If you are looking to get into...
into eSports and you want to go down the Riot Games path, which obviously right now is the
most developed game developer that has the most successful eSport right now, I would
say just even contacting Nicola, she's in the audience, or someone at Riot.
Sorry Nicola, I know.
That will allow you into the press room, and they're very good about it,
on weekends when it's not so busy for you to just get a better understanding and to learn about it.
Or even if you're a game developer that are trying to figure out different ways to allow
these press to come in, I would say following that sort of path of just allowing these people
to come in and tell the stories, or allowing the right people to come in and tell the stories,
that you have faith will tell the stories effectively, would be the best approach.
Yeah, I can also speak to working with Blizzard a little bit. So obviously they're spinning up
here as a storm. They'd really like that to be considered an e-sport. And just the enthusiasm
that I've seen from the press team over there in trying to ‑‑ what I appreciate is that they
recognize that there's a lot of value in having not just, you know, your own company telling the
stories of your players, but also having third party media in. And they have been really good
about trying to accommodate.
You know, journalists coming in, documentary people coming in,
and just, you know, how can we make this happen?
How can you come?
Like, when does the schedule align for you?
How can we get you access to players?
Who do you want to talk to?
That stuff is so great to hear from them.
Conversely, you know, I had a friend who went to TI recently
and explained to me that it was much, much harder to get access
to players for interviews.
And I think...
Yeah, I mean if you are holding a tournament and you have your players like behind an iron curtain and there's no way for anybody to get access to them, surprise it's going to be a lot harder for people to tell stories about your players.
Might be accurate.
No comment.
So, do you guys feel like there are any missed opportunities the developers aren't doing right now to empower you to tell stories about their players?
I mean, again, sort of what I was hinting at varies from
developer to developer, publisher to publisher.
I think that there are some that are obviously really
great about trying to get you art assets and resources so
that you can showcase gameplay footage in your stuff.
There's people who are great at trying to match you up with a
player or even just giving you a place to work at their event
that they're holding up.
I think that stuff goes a really long way.
To kind of spin this off, I think, again, I really hope that developers and publishers
understand the value of people telling the stories for your stuff.
I know that's kind of the whole point.
We're just reiterating this a ton.
I think developers and publishers understandably when they're thinking about their game, they think about it in the context of, oh, this is the game we've spent years developing, this is the balance team we've put together to make this so when people come and watch a tournament, it's not just about the
They're going to be watching and see that big play or talking about how balance update
changes stuff. But you know what people really going to talk about? When you strip away the
meta and strip away those big plays and all that stuff. At its core people two years from
now might not remember why the team won this thing but they will remember that that player
who got second in every single tournament for years leading up to this finally won and
was able to walk away with a trophy. And in that moment that's what they'll remember.
And so I think that's what we're going to do. And I think that's what we're going to do.
For me, those opportunities, I just hope that developers and
publishers really recognize that that is something that is
just organic and that they can't force and that they
really need to provide opportunities for those stories
to play themselves out.
Because you can throw like a million dollars into a prize
pool, but guess what?
People aren't going to keep caring about your sport or your
e-sport if nobody knows why they should care about the
players that are competing in it.
I agree.
Oh, sorry.
So, kind of on the day-to-day, like how often do you have to interface?
I mean, I'm sure we're going to get a lot of diverse answers here, but on the day-to-day,
how often do you interface with these developers to gain access to players or tell different
stories about their game?
Well, I mean, I maintain email contact with people at Blizzard's PR department, you know,
trying to work on other projects going forward.
It's pretty simple.
They're very accessible.
They're like, ah, text me, call me whenever you want.
They really try to make it as easy as possible, specifically.
Yeah.
Absolutely.
I would say, like, just, at least when I used to do this more full time, my week-to-week
was more so just making sure to respect the game developer, the publisher, contact them
way ahead of time to make sure that they know that I'm going to be coming in and telling
a story, and if they have any advice or anything, or want to help me get a pro player to do
an interview with.
then those are the sort of things that we would plan out way ahead of time.
Or like making sure that if I do know that these are the stories that I want to cover,
these are the things that I know people are going to find appealing,
do that research way beforehand and have that ready so that when you do attend the event
and you've already talked to the publisher or the game developer,
That they know that you have this game plan and that they know that you're ready and you want these specific pro players.
And you go into the event hoping that you'll get those pro players, because obviously it doesn't always happen the exact way that you expect it to.
But you go in and you have kind of this set plan and schedule and a day-to-day for those pro players to then feel comfortable and know that you're doing your job right and that you're just more professional in that sense.
So we have time for just one more question and we'll just toss it over to Q&A.
So really quickly, so instead of giving advice to future content creators or future storytellers
who would be interested in doing this, what advice would you have given to your past self?
Because a lot of you guys have been doing this for years now.
Do your own thing. Don't follow what everyone else is doing. If
you go on Reddit or whatever on our Starcraft and you read, I'm
going to make a YouTube channel where everyone is casting
something. You can automatically know that this person is going
to fail because they're bringing nothing to the table that day
nine didn't five years ago. So find your niche, find something
you're good at and hopefully it's a niche and just go after
with passion and hopefully if you work hard enough it will
happen. That's just how it works.
I think my advice could apply to other content creators as well, not just myself.
But I think that you find, specifically the authentic storytelling and stuff,
and creating something that's meaningful,
you find that that person has an interesting story, at least on its face,
and you can see creating a story around them.
But I think it's a little counterintuitive,
but I think you have to become an expert at fictional storytelling
because...
The way we perceive reality in a very real sense is sort of a narrative process.
We go through our day-to-day lives, we have overt goals, we have subconscious goals, we
have antagonists in our lives.
We are the protagonists in what we do.
So that's not surprising why the classical Western narrative is the most popular form
of story and has been for a long time.
So if you become an expert at that storytelling structure, you are so much more empowered
to when you see the interesting story that you want to tell with your eSports guy, you
can take those elements and see where they match up and learn how to tell that in the
way that will be most impactful and most meaningful to your potential audience.
I think I would probably tell myself to, while it's good to
listen to community feedback and criticism, you should take
it all with a grain of salt.
One of the things that I have tried since I started,
basically because I started off of Reddit, is to interact
with that community constantly.
Anytime I have content go up there, it's hang out in the
comments or listen to Twitter or whatever.
And I think that's allowed me to really iterate on the
content that I'm creating and make it better.
On the other hand, it is true that I've probably let that stuff get to me sometimes whenever people are very critical of something.
And there's been moments in time where that sort of emotion or the feeling that comes from that will work to make me not want to do something.
Or I'll shut down an idea early on because I'll think,
I'll get blown up for doing this or what if it's not the quality bar at the gate that I pride
myself in and so then, you know, people will say that I suck. And so I think just being prepared
to like do it anyway and have people tell you that you suck or whatever and then do it again and
have less people do that, I think that that's something that you just have to kind of steal
yourself for.
I actually agree a lot with Travis, the other one.
I think learning proper narrative structure was really important.
I learned that probably around this last six or seven months is trying to figure out how
to tell a character's storyline properly to where an audience can digest it.
And that kind of breaks some of that barrier of like, I don't understand eSports, but what
is a story?
The majority of people will understand like a...
traditional narrative structure and so it helps a lot where you can see like, oh, this is a conflict, this is a protagonist, this is an antagonist.
And then also I would have told myself to work with Travis sooner, because we did a great doublelift three part series.
Doublelift and Nikola are the stars of this panel, if you guys haven't figured it out.
My advice would be to, I guess, follow more with this, Travis.
Going into it, I was extremely nervous.
The community that I was mainly focusing on was the League of Legends community,
and I was warned beforehand that they can be toxic at times, just like any other community.
But, I guess also going into it, being a female within the scene was a lot of pressure, I felt like, originally.
So, I think...
Beforehand, I was very nervous about how I presented myself, both on camera and off
camera, as well as the comments that I was going to be receiving.
However, now I realize that that's not...
The base thing that I should have been focusing on, the stories that I was telling was about
the pro players and about the games themselves.
That's where the focus was and it had nothing to do with me and I shouldn't have even been
nervous or I guess I can guess myself in any way because I was really just trying to tell
the story about them and that's what the audience ultimately wanted.
So I would say focus on...
So, I guess this goes with Damian and the other Travis, making sure that you have the
correct elements and components to create a really compelling story for the audience
to come in to then become passionate about not only the game, but the players themselves,
I think is huge.
All right.
Awesome.
Thanks, guys.
So, we'll open up to Q&A, and I think there are two microphones over there.
So we'll start to my right.
Where am I?
How do you balance stories about,
sorry, how do you balance deciding whether to tell stories
about individual players or about teams and franchises?
And how to sort of...
Yeah, so the question is how do you balance
telling stories about a player versus a team
or a franchise or anything like that?
I think I always go with player over franchise. I don't know if Team Liquid would want me to say that.
I always find it more interesting from a personal player perspective.
And actually a lot of the pieces that I work on travel back in time to players when they were on previous teams.
It's also very nice to talk about a franchise and its lineage and the owners and what it's based upon.
But ultimately at the end of the day, for me at least, I connect with players a lot more than I connect with brains.
Thanks.
Hi, thanks a lot. You guys touched on a little bit about what developers and publishers could do to facilitate storytelling.
Looking for more from an actual feature perspective in an eSports game, are there specific features that you guys are missing in current games that facilitate storytelling?
Observer modes or things like that that we could build to better facilitate that.
Thanks.
So the question was what features can developers provide to enable storytelling?
So I have a free to play was a documentary that valve did about
their Dota 2 game. And some of the most immersing slash like
interesting things that were done in that is they had like
these insane like CGI kind of renders but apparently it was
all captured in game.
Not sure if that's true, but a lot of this like really immersive sort of like quick cuts of action that showed how intense a moment was
For me as a League of Legends storyteller, that's not available
so that was probably the most frustrating thing over the last couple years is that
I couldn't go in and watch a team fight from a different perspective.
There was a couple episodes where I attempted to recreate what happened in the game.
Didn't work out very well.
But kind of almost worked out well.
So having a replay system or being able to download the game files and pull full HD renders
of everything is really nice as opposed to trying to blow up 720 to 1080.
So just having a lot of access to the game at least at a bare
minimum level of the game files and on top of that having access
to move your camera around in some sort of free roam state is
really good not only just for the bare bones highlight reels
that you see people put together with sick plays but also from a
narrative perspective to get a different view.
Great, thank you.
All right, thanks for the question.
Over here.
Hey guys, I'm Steven.
I used to play professionally in the past.
And one thing I was going to ask you
from an interviewer perspective
and also from a documentary perspective,
you have a high level of access to players
and that may be coming down as we professionalize more.
But how do you deal with the emotional intelligence
of understanding a player right after they play
and you want to interview them to get them in the moment?
How do you handle the emotional intelligence part of that
when you're speaking with a player?
So you're speaking to after a loss or something or after a win, how do you deal with that raw emotion after?
Yeah, I mean, obviously, that's a great time to interview anyone.
It's fantastic to have someone get that kind of raw energy in the immediate moment.
It's funny because, of course, the immediate question you want to ask is,
How do you feel? Or, how does it feel?
which is maybe not a very good one. But I don't know. It's an
interesting challenge every time. It's like you have so much
energy coming off of this person and how do you really
encapsulate that moment for people who are at home to watch.
I think there actually I can give a pretty good example.
There was a moment after CLG won and knew they were going to be
making it to Madison Square Garden last year and I
interviewed their bot lane and they were just so happy.
And normally you're like, okay, cool, they're going to celebrate, they're going to talk about how they're finally like where they think that they've needed to be as a team for years.
And all they wanted to do was, excuse the language, but fuck around.
So people can go see this interview, it was with Aftermoon Doublelift, and they just troll me the entire time.
And I'm like, you can see like in the first five minutes I'm
like, well, I'm like trying to get it back on topic and
eventually I just gave up and let them have fun. I think
ultimately realizing that, you know, it's at that point in
time like their show to steer and to run, just letting them
have that runway to just say whatever they want to do or
whatever, I think that's really the path forward.
Cool. Thanks for the question.
We might only have time for one more but I'll try to sneak
another one in.
So as a publisher developer kind of doing our own thing and hoping to break into the eSports world
What kind of stuff could our marketing team do internally that would
differ from what say a player created or influencer created YouTube content?
that they would provide.
So what could we do that would help, I guess, facilitate or foster an esports community
opposed to what a player could do better, essentially.
So the question is, as a publisher or a developer, what can your internal marketing team do that's
different than what a content creator provides or an interviewer provides?
I think it's really important to put your players on a pedestal, so to speak.
So like, say for example, if, I think it was...
SMITE, they put a lot of their content creators and like players up to the forefront and that
was really interesting when I was learning about that. But just like any new game developer
I think if you have a player let's say streaming your brand new game right and this is like
a pro player from a team or a player that you think might go pro, like sort of blast
some of that stuff out on social media and like give them the platform to show off your
game more than they might have normally.
And you can do that in game too by offering a one button click.
You can now spectate your top players just from the main launch screen.
That's a pretty decent example, I think.
If we go super quickly, we actually have time for two.
So we'll start over here.
So most of you guys work in well-established gaming
communities, but what about communities
where the viewership and the money is not quite there?
And so the common response I get to certain communities
where I say, where's the content, where's the narratives,
is that there is no narratives to be told, which is,
what would you say to people like that
that are discouraged from writing
in those type of communities?
First off, sup, Tafo, how you doing?
What's up?
And second, I think there's so many stories everywhere.
Like, I was actually, I've been, when I wait for renders and stuff,
and I'm editing and things, I only have time to play a really quick game.
And I'll play TagPro often.
And it's this really simple game.
It's kind of a small community.
And you wouldn't necessarily think that there's a lot of stories there, but my imagination
runs wild with like who are these characters or these people behind these like dots that
are running around on the screen.
Agario is another similar kind of game where it's just like dots moving around.
And I think because it is so ambiguous, you know, sort of the graphics and stuff and not
knowing anybody behind there, you know, you just
You just have to dig. There are stories everywhere.
There is no one telling him. It's fertile ground. No competition.
Go for it.
Last question.
This is actually a question about the Smash Brothers.
You had a bunch of the top players in but you didn't have Armada.
I'm curious why you chose not to include that story.
He is briefly in as a doubles partner for Mew2King.
I'm curious how you made that decision.
It was a tough call. I actually, part of me was like hoping that I would get the chance to do
something else with Armada and that ended up happening so I'm very happy about that.
But I had to sort of truncate it, you know, I was like these are the guys that I want to tell
the story about and, you know, there's only a certain amount of resources that I had. Like,
I was, I had quit my job at the time and like I was eating ramen and
Eventually I was like, okay, Evo is coming up. We just got into that. That would be a great
capper to seal the whole thing. We're back in the spotlight kind of thing. So I kind of saw
that as a proper way to end it. It was a little bit like Armada is in it at the very end of the
last few episodes. But it's almost like I set him up as a pin for Mango to knock down and that
was the end.
He definitely gets different treatment in this movie that I'm producing right now, but
that's, that was kind of, sort of arbitrary I guess.
It's like, same reason I couldn't really give an episode to Chewdat, who I think probably
deserved one.
It was just that, you know, I had to be ruthless in my decision making.
All right, thanks.
Thanks everyone for coming and thanks to all the panels for showing up.
Thank you.
Be sure to fill out the survey.
And also, I think some of us will be hanging out outside, right, to answer more questions?
Yeah.
Right, cool.
Thanks, guys.
Cool.
Thanks.