Hi and hello to the people in chat. This is very cool. It's like
dual purpose presentation and very, very hyped for this.
And I am also, good segue, very hyped to talk about
Among Us' TikTok strategy with you,
which I have seen some people go like,
TikTok is my nemesis, and I understand,
and I understand there's a lot of social media platforms
out there, so this is going to be a deep dive
into one of them to hopefully kind of
help you navigate everything.
So as a brief introduction, my name is Victoria Tran.
I'm the community director at Innersloth.
We make the game Among Us and the Henry Stickmin Collection.
And at any point and afterwards, you
can find me on Twitter at the VTran, usually around there,
as many of us really are.
And before I kind of get into like the in-depth portion
of Among Us' TikTok, I do have a confession
that at this point I'm like a serial instigator,
creator, content maker for Indie Game Studio TikToks.
Among Us is not the only one that I've worked on
and I think that actually gives me a lot
of really nice context and contextual.
context and info when it comes to other kind of game studios and other genres. So as a really brief
overview of what I've done. I initially started the Kitfox Games TikTok account in February 2020
and they did amazing. I did not get them to 25k followers like you see here. I think I got them
to like 10k and they've done an amazing job with it and they obviously had a bunch of different
games and also was interesting in that it was a studio account and not just a singular game.
And then in July 2021, I worked on the unpacking TikTok account,
which by the way, they're doing amazing.
They're like up for awards.
I'm very proud of them.
And that did super well that I think got to 170k
until I left in December 2021,
because that was just a side thing that I was helping them out with.
And then finally, we reached the Among Us TikTok account, which is my main thing,
and I started that in December 2020. So, yeah. So, I've worked on a bunch of different genres,
a bunch of different games, different kind of context when it comes to game studios.
And as much as Among Us is a very huge TikTok account, I think there's a lot of lessons that
I learned throughout all three of them that can be applied to whichever kind of TikTok account you
have.
OK, so let's kind of get started a little brief intro,
all that kind of stuff.
So this is a study that was done by TikTok.
conducted by material.
So just a heads up that, you know, there might be some bias there.
But according to the study that they did, TikTokers are one point
five times more likely to immediately go out and buy something or wishlist
something they discovered on the platform compared to kind of other platform users.
And this is sort of the big thing of why everyone keeps talking about TikTok.
It's just that the discoverability for it in terms of other social media platforms is quite good in terms of their algorithm.
People continually learning something new. So learning more updates about your game, learning more about your game.
That's a huge part of it. And of course, just being inspired.
And there's a lot of really great indie games out there and, you know, AAA games out there that it's really.
interesting to see the ways in which they inspire other TikTok users and really make it into the
cultural zeitgeist, I suppose. So really briefly, again, I'm going to go back into Among Us,
again, a little more in-depth about it. So we launched, as I said, in December 2020.
We got a ton of followers within the first six months, which is very, not actually, not that
rare in terms of TikTok. Okay.
That's a lot. It's a little bit, it's rare in terms of TikTok growth to have that many,
but you will often see like when a lot of indie games or a lot of other studios kind of talk
about that the amount of follows that you get on an account does kind of exceed the rate in
which you would see on like Twitter or Facebook, if you're using that, or Instagram, that sort of thing.
And for context, I am the person who's currently working on all the community and marketing side
stuff in Among Us, which means that I don't get as much time as I would like on it because I have
so many other things to do. And the goal for our Among Us account, which might be different for
your accounts, was brand awareness, engagement, and sustainability. So sustainability of our
community because at this point, we had really good discoverability. So that wasn't one of the
goals for the Among Us account.
And of course, huge caveat, Among Us already had a huge player base.
By the time I launched the TikTok, I don't really take credit for all the growth there.
And in terms of effort that I put into it.
So for the Among Us account, I put in about one video per week at minimum.
I would love to do more.
But as I said, it's a little bit difficult because I have so many other things to do.
So at my frequency, I go once per week.
And I did that.
for the same thing for unpacking, where I did one video a week and Kit Fox was around
two videos of a week if I could swing it. But again, there's a lot of things going on,
so I often couldn't do as many as I wanted.
I honestly consider the effort that you have to put into TikTok quite high.
So unlike like a tweet where you can just type it out or something,
creation for me takes around 15 minutes to one hour per video,
depending on how magnificent you want and how much editing you're doing.
The trends can take one to two hours per week in order just to like scroll
through it and read and watch.
all the things that are going on.
And also I put in like an hour per week on engagement.
So that could be like going through other videos
and liking them and commenting on them,
going through our own comments and commenting through them.
Basically personality and cultural understanding
of TikTok has to be quite on point and engaging with it.
So it is quite a high effort social media platform.
So I just wanted to warn you about that.
All right, so.
I will soon get to the case studies, but I really want to go over building a brand identifier
on TikTok.
This kind of goes through a very social media general strategy, but there are some unique
considerations I put into TikTok structure.
So the first thing is like, you really want to talk...
Think about how you want to be recognized on TikTok
because that's a huge thing.
It's so visual, right?
So the first thing is style and tone.
So how you want to sound on TikTok.
Do you want to be quirky, wholesome,
relatable, calming, competitive?
I usually pick three big adjectives
that will describe your overall content.
And then everything kind of trickles down from there.
So what lighting we'll use?
How polished will things look?
What kind of content will you create?
How do you want your audience to understand you?
Then you go for consistent brand elements. So it's really beneficial for a TikTok account
to have one person or character continually and distinctly appear in videos.
So scrolling through videos is really quick and not everyone checks the username and profile
pic. So having a distinct face someone can immediately associate with your TikTok account
really helps people identify your content easily. And it's very common for people to
have only 1 to 2 people actually appear in a TikTok when it comes to their own account.
If you don't want to use your face, totally fine.
Just use consistent elements.
You can have certain lighting, a distinctive mark, an object,
a color palette, a video game character.
Unpacking, for example, didn't have any characters whatsoever.
So we really went with really distinct elements of it.
Hook, the first one to three seconds of a video is extremely important, as with anything.
I'm sure you've heard the word hook so many times now.
But you do really want to front load your video with the most interesting thing possible.
And it doesn't even need to be visual.
It could be a question like, how did I make feet move in my game?
Or times I use the Among Us account for my own personal gain, and everyone hates this
task or something like that.
Basically pose an idea and use the rest of the video to expand on it.
And then you have trends and this is a beautiful way to keep engagement, right? TikTok is known
for its viral trends and hopping onto that in a timely manner is really nice because if you
can't think of anything or if you want people to stick around for something, they'll tend to do it
if there is like a trend that they know like a hook or some punchline is coming.
And a lot of people think, like, does creating a brand voice
really matter, especially if I'm indie?
And it does, I think.
And according to the Sprout Social Index,
some of the reasons why brands stood out more than others,
according to consumers, was things
like memorable content, personality,
or distinct personality, and compelling storytelling.
And a lot of times with social, we're not gunning for like a one-hit viral thing.
We're really aiming for sustainable, practical, practical community engagement.
And we can create content that is memorable and keeps us at the top of mind.
All right, so I'm going to go a little bit more in depth into the actual Among Us videos that we've done.
So there are kind of five content types that I found really helpful for me when it comes to Among Us.
Those are things are game updates. So these are ongoing updates about the game, whether it's bug fixes or huge announcements, personality, TikTok.
So videos hopping on trends or having fun with the community.
Behind the scenes things, this shows off more developer focused looks at the games and what
goes into making it.
Gameplay, so videos that focus on game content that is already out.
And miscellaneous things, so this could be reactions, we have merchandise, so I use merchandise,
that sort of thing.
And game updates by far get the highest engagement and share rate for Among Us.
This isn't really a shock.
The difficulty here is really to make a game update interesting sometimes,
especially when you know you don't have much to show for it
or you need it to keep people informed about things like bug fixes,
which is a little bit difficult.
But I do try to keep these as short as possible. Generally, people always recommend to keep
these as short as possible, like any TikTok as short as possible, just because the looping
is really good for the algorithm. But it all varies. Anyways, so when it comes to the actual
game updates, some things that I've done that have worked really well is really focusing
the TikTok, right? So we've had like Among Us updates where it was like, hey, these are
all the things that are happening. And instead, I just broke it apart into
bit by bit pieces. So for example, we had an update on June 30th that introduced a bunch
of new things, but the one standout thing was we had a new task that was vent cleaning.
And then part of, you know, really understanding your community and knowing what makes them tick
and really what like makes them laugh or makes them excited is to.
know what they talk about. So a lot of people talked about vent cleaning being a kind of joke
task in Among Us or a joke excuse. And we actually implemented it. And so when I put it into the
TikTok, that was the only thing that I focused on. And I didn't talk about any of the other things
that we had. And I was just like, hey, we have vent cleaning. And that made it more interesting
than just like a casual bug update, a casual update full of fixes and stuff like that.
There was also another time where we updated the game,
and I'm sure many of you have been through this before,
and it just broke the game.
Like, it wasn't working.
And the hard thing on TikTok is to really communicate,
especially when you have a big community on it,
is to just communicate,
hey, we're working on bug fixes,
because you can't just tweet out.
hey, we're you can't just tweet out on TweetTalk. Hey, we're working on bug fixes and do a quick
status update. So, for this, I kind of hopped onto a trending meme at the time, which was like
a song which you can't hear and the gesture. And I really made fun of the fact that we
completely broke the game, which people took really well and we got a lot of software developers
relating to the video, too. And it really successfully conveyed information about
keeping the game updated and that we were aware of the problems that people had with a meme.
So, that's cool.
So these TikToks that I'm going to talk about next are the personality-based TikToks.
These are super varied in terms of our virality, but that's okay though.
The point of these TikToks aren't necessarily to get big numbers, though it's always nice,
but to solidify our tone with the community and create that connection as an indie studio.
And these videos can often be longer.
All right, so the one that I'm kind of focusing on here
is that at the time of posting TikTok,
the only question I was getting in comments
was stuff about where the new map was.
And you can get this too.
You can be like, oh God,
like everyone keeps asking me when the release date is.
Everyone keeps asking me if it's coming out on mobile,
that sort of thing.
And hopping onto a trend and really like.
not being afraid to be honest with your TikTok community is one of the things that they just like love the most.
Even more so than like a lot of other social media platforms I found that they've just really latched on to this kind of self-awareness.
Next, we have behind-the-scenes videos.
These, honestly, for me, are the worst performing ones.
And I think it's because I'm not very good at them.
I've seen other indie studios do so good with them.
And I don't know.
It could be because I'm making it wrong.
It could also be because the majority of our community
really cares about new items and not really old ones.
But that's OK.
The videos here tend to be longer
and aren't necessarily a target for the For You page,
for me anyway.
They're usually more just to get our community engaged.
So for example, you can answer questions from TikToks,
like in the TikTok comments and respond to them.
And that could be a way that you talk about
more behind the scenes stuff.
Here, it probably would have been a better hook
if maybe I'd like shown a little more
of the actual Among Us character, but that's all right.
It's one of those things where you can kind of learn
from videos that don't do as well.
And also just like, you know, reading the comments
and being able to respond to them.
Next are the gameplay videos.
These focus on gameplay.
It takes content straight from the game
and plops it into a fun little video.
And these tend to do relatively well,
but they definitely vary due to the fact
gameplay can cover anything from difficult tasks,
gameplay styles, looking at game details, that sort of thing.
And, again, it's really important, I think, to really hone in on one part of the gameplay
aspect. So, for example, we had an update for Among Us roles, and the actual trailer
that I put onto the TikTok account didn't do super well. But this video that I just
talked about focusing on the shapeshifter kill and showing it in the game did way better
in terms of views. So that's a really interesting thing.
Miscellaneous stuff, merchandise, reacts, interactions,
Among Us has plenty of other things to talk about,
and you may too.
So whether it's duetting videos
or showing off new merchandise,
I find it just really fun to be able to talk about it.
One of the things that I will say
is that it does much better than I thought,
but you have to be very careful
about not straight up being like, buy this thing,
because I feel like the algorithm
or like TikTok on the back end
doesn't really like the whole like, buy, buy, buy thing.
So instead, what I usually do is just literally show off like the product.
Don't even say honestly, like where they can get it.
You can put a website maybe in the comments or something or like respond to people.
But otherwise, people just really like looking at cool stuff.
And merch, for sure, is one of those things that is big on TikTok.
All this to say is that I've shown you videos that have a lot of views,
but it is still a learning process.
You can see on the top left, I have a video that had 100K views.
And that's not as much as the one right below it, which is 12.9 million views.
It really is one of those things where I...
No, don't. I wouldn't trust anyone who just guarantees that you can go viral all the time.
It is definitely just working and figuring out what content works with your community
and continually kind of testing it. And that's really important, I think, when it comes to TikTok,
but also when it comes to any social media platform is really testing and keeping track
of what works and what doesn't work. And how do we actually measure success?
So this is a very rough overview.
This is just like a snippet I took out of a spreadsheet.
But this is the kinds of ways that I track,
like how well is something actually doing?
What is our engagement percentage?
Because that's something that's really important to me.
And from this, we can determine things
like personalized TikToks get the highest engagement
compared to other categories, particularly
in the number of people commenting.
However, game update TikToks usually get the most visibility overall.
So it's like, what am I aiming for?
Am I aiming for visibility?
Am I aiming for engagement?
The most shareable content was the water bottle video, which makes sense because people probably
wanted other people to see the merch and to buy it.
That really happens quite a bit.
And the second most shareable content was usually anything involving game updates because
people would tell their friends, like, hey.
let's play this or they share it with their communities.
Behind the scenes videos are things that I probably shouldn't post a lot of or I should
really change what I do because it is not doing as well as the other categories.
And gameplay is more like solid middle of the road content.
And the For You page is obviously the best place to be in for visibility.
But once people are on your profile page,
having content that interests them will really help boost stats.
It's really all about thinking like, you know, what are your goals for TikTok?
Is it just views that hopefully convert to wish lists?
Do you want engagement on the platform? Are you aiming for shares?
Overall, pay attention to what's happening with your content
so you can better prepare for success on the platform.
All right, so this is another chart.
Shout out to SystemChalk on Twitter for this,
who is an amazing economist
and really helped me out with this.
We plotted this Among Us data on a graph
that measures engagement
and found that overall engagement percentage
doesn't actually really shift based on the video length.
So if you consider success to be people watching
to the end of something, then shorter videos are better,
but we didn't really see anything
that indicated longer videos
were hurting engagement measures.
We also did a plot for length and views.
And while it does show a negative trend,
it's not a very strong relationship.
I'm not saying completely irrelevant
because the three longest videos are also
the bottom three for views.
And the TikTok algorithm does reward videos
that get rewatched over and over.
But it's fair to say that at least part of the connection
is that we just have more success in the short video
club.
None of this really counts as a breakthrough, by the way,
or anything.
really, especially considering how small our sample size is
with the Among Us account,
but as in like the number of videos we have.
But we were just curious about the length
and was a little surprised to see how stable
the engagement measure was
no matter how long the video was.
And this is what it looks like for Among Us,
but it's possible this graph might look different
for other game audiences.
As with any content, things really vary from game to game.
And all of this is to say, people getting excited and informed about your game is never a straight line.
It's really this infinite loop that again, TikTok put out.
It's about discoverability, consideration, review, and participation with your videos.
And according to the study, 44% of the daily TikTok users did want branded content to be fun and entertaining.
Again, it's just it's this loop of figuring out what people want,
what people are responding to.
And I wouldn't be discouraged if it doesn't work out all at once in the beginning.
And I'm going to really briefly go over the community
and being part of it because some initial warnings
if you haven't been on TikTok before,
expect to see two comments the most.
Will this game be on mobile and is it free?
Don't forget TikTok is a mobile only app basically.
So obviously the users will be prioritizing their phone
but also many are used to free mobile games being the norm.
This isn't to discourage you to say TikTok users won't buy
or wishlist your game on PC or console.
Definitely the opposite. It's just that I want to warn you and like any platform,
there are biases and types of comments you may see and, you know, just be aware. Don't take it
too much to heart. People do care about your game even if they ask if it's free.
And it isn't always easy, right?
So to be perfectly clear, initial viral TikToks
that I got on the Among Us account
were just inundated with dead game comments.
Any big game you can see, they just
get so many dead game comments.
That isn't to say you have to give up on the platform,
though, when you do get negativity.
At least engaging with it really helps people pay attention
to who is reading and who is engaging with the comments.
And again, why?
It's because it's not just about going viral.
It really is about building a sustainable, long-term community
for your studio.
And if you hate going on a social media platform
or your studio hates going on a social media platform
because the comments are really bad,
that's not a great place to be in.
So really leaning into it can, if you
have the mental capacity, change the sentiment, create fans,
and highlight those that are already in your corner
and create a healthier space for your team.
And really analyzing the negativity.
Is it bugs?
Is it lack of updates, a viral thing, et cetera?
It's something that I really went into where
after a period of honestly me being like, I hate it here,
I started responding to more comments.
Because I know how lovely TikTok can be.
So I started responding to things
and actually as among us, just not punching down on people,
but trying to be like, hey, I appreciate you're here.
Or hey, I'm just reading these comments,
even if it's a joke, right?
And it actually started working, right?
So we can see here, people started being a little bit nicer about things.
And then on the left, again, another example of me
just kind of responding to a very negative comment.
And the thing about TikTok comments is it doesn't like really or I don't know
how they order it.
But some things will just like pop up at the top, even if you respond,
even if you don't respond to them, even if you do respond to them,
just because it's getting a lot of engagement.
So often at the times at the top, we'd see like dead game comments.
So I just make sure I respond to those because you can see my reply below.
And then on the right, you can see kind of the sentiment
start to change where people were like.
hey, why are you actually, why are you saying this?
That's kind of mean.
And again, it's one of those things where
being an indie game studio doesn't really help with this
and just being a person that is responding to it
and people understanding there's a person behind the count
has really helped.
All of this to say is basically to make an effort
to be a part of the community that you post in.
Understand and pay attention to how the community
interacts in the space, the language they use, even emojis.
All right, so we're almost near the end.
And then I can take questions because I
know there are a bunch of questions in chat.
And maybe there are a bunch of questions in the audience.
I'm not sure.
But this is important.
Why have I kept talking about TikTok, about social media,
that sort of thing, especially when you maybe
have heard it's not super great in terms of conversion,
in terms of all social media platforms?
So this is a study by Hootsuite's Digital 2022
report.
And the interesting thing about this graph
is that it measured the percentage of internet users
who use each channel as a primary source of information
when researching brands.
Though, keep in mind, this is not game-specific or anything,
so there's some messiness here.
And we can see on the lower part of this graph, from 35
to 64-year-olds, is as we expect.
Find a brand on Google, any search engine,
for more information about the brand, its offerings,
and what it's like.
The interesting part is the youngest age group here, 16 to 24 year olds.
And the younger we get on this graph, the more we see social networks are actually the
places people go to search up a brand.
And this group is the one that does it over a search engine.
And I'm not 16 to 24.
However, I can confirm that actually I have started using social media.
I will type it in, in like Instagram or something when I want to find out more about
any kind of product because honestly, it's just easier for me that way.
And this isn't to say SEO or anything isn't important. It's just that as you know,
we kind of build a culturally relevant brand, it means we need to engage with culturally
relevant platforms. And things are always changing. I understand it's really stressful.
There was a MySpace. Now there is no MySpace. Facebook. I don't even know what Facebook is
doing. And now we have TikTok. And we have so many other things. And there's probably
more and more things coming. And it can be really stressful.
I understand, but there are reasons to which, you know, we want to engage with these platforms
as studios, as games, as people, whatever.
And again, this is what works for Among Us,
and this is how we got all this data with experimentation,
a little bit of flexibility, agility.
All of these are super important for our constantly morphing
platform like TikTok, where the trends are driven
by users and internet memes.
And working with data alongside cultural interest in the space
is key to making a successful brand in a space like this.
Engage with your community.
Remember, it's not just about numbers going up,
but having a healthy and thriving long-term player
base.
And then as bigger the player base goes,
maybe you can depend a little less on social media platforms
if that's not your thing, if that's not what you like.
And as I said, you really want to engage with the platforms
to be a culturally relevant continuing brand,
but also be a brand that engages and is conscious of the world
that it's a part of.
Hopefully, you want to make a good mark wherever you are too.
And every brand success measures by far are very different,
but merging quantitative and qualitative data
will take you very far.
Thank you for listening to me babble on for quite a while.
I guess we can start doing questions.
I know there is a lot in chat, but for people
who are attending in the audience, I don't know if.
Maybe I'll answer a question in chat while the audience can.
Okay, questions? Let's see.
How does marketing on TikTok differ from other social media systems?
Is there anything you found that's significantly easier or harder on different platforms?
That's a very big question.
I think a lot of social media platforms, if you're talking about marketing,
if you're talking about like paid marketing or something, that could be very different.
As with anything, I think with TikTok, the thing that a lot of people struggle with
is just how organic TikTok needs to feel sometimes.
And especially when you're if you're making like a sponsored or an ad on TikTok,
a lot of the time, like you will automatically scroll through it if you can see that it's a clear brand.
But if it's like someone who's like a little more, I've seen people like use like influencers on TikTok,
like just like kind of talk about a product more organically, but still have the ad thing.
That's something I think is one of the things that people are struggling with.
I hope that was your question.
Do we have questions from the audience?
in person?
Hello.
Oh yes, hello.
Hi.
Hello.
I'm a huge fan and yes, so this is kind of a two part question.
We were actually both finalists last year in the GameHers for Best Community Manager
Indie so I would love to be your friend if possible.
And also, what do you do if something is failing and the studio is freaking out?
How do you pivot or react to that?
Is there kind of a panic plan or do you have any tips or advice for something like that?
When something is failing.
Like let's say on social you kind of have a,
not the reaction you were hoping for.
Maybe you've done kind of a troll post or a meme post
and it's kind of getting maybe canceled
or something like that, kind of the worst possible.
And you're getting a lot of really negative,
negative response.
Do you have any tips for that on TikTok
or really any socials?
Yeah, so I hesitate to kind of give super blanket response answers to this,
because I'm like, what are you? What did you post?
Right. So it's right.
So it's one of those things where it's like, well, I mean, there's only so much
firefighting you can do depending on how severe the community thinks it is.
Like if you made like.
a joke and they're like a silence brand because I don't know, it was a really old meme and whatever,
then it's one of those things where you can just move on from it. Like again, people's attention
spans and remembering of things super fast. I would just keep posting. Maybe, I don't know what
it is, feel free to DM me on Twitter, I don't know what's happening. But I would say when it comes to,
it's just.
being honest with whatever your studio and understanding that sometimes things don't
take up well with the community or at least like responding to the comments in there and being like
you know what you're right that wasn't the greatest joke we could have made
gonna fix it or I don't know again I don't know what happened.
But I would say like really taking note of what the community is saying and making an effort to
like respond, engage with it. Like I took like almost like a day just going through comment,
dead game comments and responding to it. So hopefully that helps.
Thank you so much and thank you for being here.
Yeah, no, thank you.
OK, I will switch to a chat question.
Is there an ideal video length that you
found drove the most engagement?
Yes, under 15 seconds, always.
Well, OK, most engagement, no, because as the graph kind
of showed, it honestly was pretty consistent.
If you want the views, though, then under 15 seconds.
All right.
In-person question.
Hey, Victoria, it's Jared.
Ooh, it's hot.
Oh, hey!
Yeah, thanks for always being willing to share
everything that you've learned
from all of these games that you've worked on.
I was wondering, for discoverability of a game
that, let's say, is relatively unknown,
like you did with Boyfriend Dungeon or Unpacking,
what would be one big point that you'd give advice
for discoverability of a relatively unknown game on TikTok?
Yeah, so, okay, oh God, one.
It's okay, so it's a mixture of things.
The biggest thing is always just like the hook
of your TikTok content.
So the first video that ever blew up on Kit Fox Games
when I was working on it,
that like got like the first like,
the first video I had like maybe like over 100,000 views.
views in, or maybe over 10,000 views, and it's been a long time, sorry, I'm stalling,
is one where I was basically talking about dating your weapons or something. It was just
something that was kind of, if you heard it for the first time, you were like, wait, what?
So having people really
have like a wait what moment is usually quite helpful when it comes to like discoverability.
Like the weird like so if you go on TikTok there's like a weirdness to it there's like a little bit
of a chaos to it and that really is something that hooks on quite a bit and when it comes to
unpacking oh I also sorry I also meant to say having like three to five hashtags usually pretty
good um please make it relevant but.
some people like just look at the hashtags other game studios are using and kind of learn from that.
And for unpacking the first one that kind of went viral was honestly just talking about the joy of
I think talking about organization because so many people love organizing things. Like TikTok
has like organization TikTok, there's book talk, there is game talk, there are so many like sub
TikTok genres is that really honing in onto one genre that you like, you really want people to
discover is usually the way to get more discoverability.
Oh, okay. We're over time, but oh no. Okay. I was gonna say,
but they didn't tell me to wrap up yet, but they totally did.
I just ignored it, sorry.
Thank you for being here.
If you have any more questions, and I
know there are a lot of questions in chat
and I'm sure in person, please feel
free to message me on Twitter.
It might take me a little bit to get to it,
but I will try to get to it.
Or just tweet at me so other people can see the question
too.
Yeah, thank you so much for being here.
I hope it was helpful.
And have a good GDC.
Stay safe if you're out there.
OK, bye.