Hi, I'm Hannah Nicklin from Degoutte Fabrique.
I've tried to adjust my slides,
because I'm gonna be sitting here
in the right hand side bottom corner of your screen.
So I've made some slight adjustments.
So anything that you can't see,
just trust me that it's not that important.
It's just sort of like a background setting.
And otherwise, if the slides seem a little bit unbalanced
in terms of design,
it's because I've had to move things around a little bit
to make this work.
So I hope it still gives you somewhat of the experience that you would have got had you been listening to this talk at GDC.
So I'm Hannah Nicklin, I'm from Die Güte Fabrik, and my talk is called Kill the Hero, Save the World.
I'm the narrative designer and writer for Mutazione, which is a mutant soap opera where
small-town gossip meets the supernatural, that's our tagline, which was released in
September 2019 on Apple Arcade, PS4 and PC, and I'm now CEO and Studio Lead of Devuted
Fabric.
Before transitioning to video games as a main practice, I also worked as a playwright and
theatre maker and I have a PhD in the spaces between games and theatre and their uses as
anti-capitalist practice. That might sometimes colour my perspective here a little bit, but
hopefully it's a useful perspective. I've been practising as a writer and game designer
therefore for over a decade.
So I want to just take a moment to shout out the other talks which would have happened
by other members of the team. Nils Denneken was going to lead a talk on the visual design
of the game. Christopher Holngard and Oscar Lusada were on a panel on the dialogue UI.
And I was also super stoked to be on a narrative innovation panel with a whole host of awesome
people working in narrative design and writing. I hope that they can submit their talks too,
but in picking up the workload of a cancelled GDC, it's hard to find the time to record
a talk.
We've lost a lot of expertise this year and I know that our team are especially sad that we can't mark the many years of hard work that we put into Metassione.
Solidarity with everyone affected across the world.
A final aside, while I was the narrative designer and writer, my work was obviously deeply influenced by the skill and practice of other members of the team.
Metassione is the work of many hands and hearts and minds over almost a decade of on and off production,
so if you have a copy of the game,
please take the time to look at the credits. So this talk is called Kill the Hero, Save the World
and because I'm a writer it has a fairly predictable double meaning there. I think
that killing our heroes might produce better narrative worlds and games, that's one meaning,
but I also think there's something fairly politically urgent about destroying
the narrative of heroic exceptionalism, that it allows us to tell better, more relatable,
truer stories about how we live together in the world, and which begin to think through
the qualities of the problems of our contemporary lives. I think one way to do that is to kill
the hero and consider the ensemble cast.
And that's what my talk is about.
But don't worry, I'm mostly going to concentrate on the practice of ensemble cast storytelling
rather than the polemic or the politics of it.
There'll be a little sprinkling of that towards the end.
So I'm going to talk first in more general terms about what ensemble casts are.
and how and why telling stories with them is different to telling a hero's tale story.
And then I'm going to talk in depth about specific decisions and examples from Metassione to
illustrate how I specifically went about it in writing for and designing Metassione's narrative.
Okay, so kill the hero for better narrative worlds.
Why do I want us to think about alternatives to the hero's tale?
Let's first set out what the hero's tale is. The hero's tale is also sometimes called the monomyth
or the hero's journey and is a basic template for storytelling that features
a hero who goes on an adventure and overcomes some kind of
obstacle, before returning, forever changed or transformed.
And it's the basis of a bunch of storytelling.
I think we in particular gravitate towards the world revolving around one character in
games because a lot of the language of games is borrowed from film, which loves the hero's
tale.
Although it's worth saying that the hero's tale is as old as Aristotle.
Film loves to dive into single timeline psychologies, and it's really good at exploring these.
You have a discrete amount of attention, 90, 120 minutes or so, and you can carefully construct
every moment to pressure and expose that hero in transition.
But I think we need to interrogate whether the aesthetic and formal assumptions built into that tendency to use the language of film is actually useful to us in games, or at least if it's always useful to us.
So, in order to do that, we have to understand how they work, why use them, and to take the time to ask what if there's something better than the hero's tale out there?
So let's set out some of the qualities of the hero's tale.
Typically it revolves around one central character.
In a patriarchal society it's usually a man, it's usually a white man, it's usually
a white, cis, het man etc. And that central character begins
naive. They are called to a journey, they face
challenges and they return change which means that
all the other characters in the story serve this forward arc.
It becomes this, typically, man.
versus the world, versus characters, versus environment,
which are all there to serve their story.
Victory is inevitable, especially in games when using the hero's tale, because when
we build the player's identity into this hero, giving them room to fail as film more
often can, giving them that room to fail is less possible because honestly it's not
fun to fail and the mechanics of games, whether it be puzzle solving or fighting battles,
tend against it, leaving aside experimental practices here.
This results in, more often, false jeopardy.
The feeling like, in the end,
you never really had anything at stake.
The hero's tale works when the psychological focus
on one individual is served by a specific structure.
For example, a short time span and a director's eye,
which can focus on their psychological journey.
So I'm asking what if the heroes format prominent in games, taken largely from films, is not suited to a lot of game stories, especially those that intend to run longer than two to four hours?
Two to four hours is the length of a film or a long piece of theatre.
A perfect unit, typically the content of the human bladder, how long you can hold yourself
before needing the toilet, that is the… well, okay, films these days, think Marvel, etc,
you kind of need a toilet break. But in general, this 2-4 hour length is a perfect unit in which
to hold the attention of the audience or the player and to explore the inner workings of a
single character as they're put under pressure, changed in the heat of whatever kind of story
that you're trying to tell. When we're talking…
longer than that single unit of human attention, everything changes.
You need new structures and foundations to make your story stand up.
As people are able to, in games, explore a world rather than follow a directorial eye,
as players choose their own camera angles and pacing and characterisation is shifted by player choice,
focus can become dissipated.
It's hard to provide the focus and interiority that you need to explore a single psyche,
and the hero's tale begins to feel thin, interrupted.
We also often pad out this single unit of storytelling with filler to make it longer,
whether that be convoluted plotting or tasks that don't move the story or the characterisation
forward, which can in turn begin to make the story feel like it's decoupling from the
mechanics and that the world is there to occupy you rather than enthrall or move forward.
That's not to say that it never works, but unless you have the resources to make an open
world that is as delightful or thrilling to engage with at the level of something like
Breath of the Wild, where actually I'd argue that the world itself is the hero, I think
we could be looking more often towards ensemble casts rather than heroes in order to build
engaging, convincing and compelling open story worlds in games.
So it's time to back away from the films, my friends, and try some other media.
So I come from this experimental theatre background.
This means I'm a really big fan of interdisciplinary thinking,
learning from other art forms, collaborating with people from other art forms.
And I think there's a big lesson out there for game storytelling
to be found in the ensemble cast template employed by long-running TV shows.
You see, I'm not even going all arty interdisciplinary on you and explaining how we need to learn
from contemporary dance or experimental live art. Not that we can't. Ask me about that
in another talk. No, I'm just asking us to look to television.
So the Ensemble Cast TV Show template focuses on a group of characters rather than one central
hero style character. In this story template, it's the interplay of community rather than
the victory of the hero which is the focus of the story.
So here are some qualities of ensemble cast storytelling.
Ensemble cast storytelling focuses on a group of characters, giving many of them the same
importance. It means that you're looking at a community rather than an individual under pressure.
The drama arises from the community in context, either with their environment or each other.
You can play with much more variety, whether that be different characters, locations,
and that means that you can tell longer, more complex stories.
You can play with different tones, comedy or drama,
without making it all forced through one single character.
You can switch through different plot levels in order to give the pacing a break and a shape.
conflicting points of view can arise when you have an ensemble cast.
So rather than one true truth belonging to one person,
several different people telling you different things can leave you guessing
about the ending and provide more genuine jeopardy.
And the jeopardy at stake is something much more recognisable to our daily
lives, where often there's no ideal action,
no fully informed position, just people trying to do their best.
So the ensemble cast can also examine cause and effect over longer periods, over generations,
as communities often carry with them the consequences of past actions in a way that can be more
naturally exposed through lots of small clues, rather than one hero having to lore-dump their
whole psychology on you.
Okay, so let's look at a concrete example of ensemble cast storytelling in action.
Imitaciones.
So I would define Mitassiene as an ensemble-cast-driven story.
When I joined the team nearly four years ago, it was being described by Nils Deniken,
the creative director, as a soap opera. And that was a strong part of what appealed to me
about writing for it. Because soap operas are ensemble-cast-driven, and I think this
ensemble-cast format is massively underused as a template for game storytelling.
By the way, if your instinct is to turn up your nose at soap opera, I would invite you to examine that reaction.
A few reactions to the game online have focused on that soap opera label as wrong because they think it's a good game.
I mean, thanks for thinking it's good, but I would say that rom-coms, soap operas,
they share that they're typically seen as feminine or domestic forms of storytelling.
They often centre female characters and experiences, and therefore somehow lower quality, less
concerned with the big themes of life.
But I'd argue that soap operas are not low-quality television.
They are, to my mind, more neutral than that.
They're defined by being long-running, character-driven, ensemble-classed slices of life.
They share a lot of their qualities with situational comedies,
except they tend to be drama rather than comedy-driven.
The soap bit of soap opera is just referring to those domestic concerns
about a community in a place.
Rather than using a journey to shape the drama,
it's their past, present, and future context which is the heat of the storytelling.
So let's take a look at some of the useful tactics of ensemble storytelling
and how they can be used to build a story world using my work in Matassione as an example.
And real quick, I'm not saying we did this totally right.
With more resources, we would have liked to have been more elegant about fleshing out the world of
the game. One particular key thing would have been interesting to us would be to allow you to
play as other characters on different days in the game. But this is what we did with the resources
that we had available, i.e. game dev.
Okay, so first a little bit about the game, which you can find trailers and links to at
metassionegame.com if you don't know how to spell that, it's written in the corner.
That's how metassione is spelled and it's pronounced like I'm saying it.
You can give it a bit more of an Italian flair, it's an Italian word if you want to.
that's my best impression. It was named by Nils and our long-time collaborator and incredible
composer and musician Alessandro Coronas who lives in Sardinia so it's got sprinklings of Italian
all throughout the world. It's a 2D adventure style game where you explore a community over
a period of time. You can also gather seeds from the wild, talk to people, overhear conversations
and grow gardens with the seeds that you've collected.
In Mitassione, you explore the community as a 15-year-old girl called Kai.
Kai sets out at the beginning of the game thinking she's heading to the community to
care for her dying grandfather.
He thinks he's going to train her as a replacement spiritual leader for his strange and isolated
town of Park Mutants.
And by the end, both of them discover it's all a bit more complicated than that.
The answers are in the community itself.
So Mottesione is this world of weird and wonderful flora and fauna,
and a community cast of characters of many shapes, sizes and colours.
There are beautiful landscapes to explore, full of Mills's incredible art, and the great animations of our two animators.
Please look up the credits as before.
And there's this magical musical gardening mechanic at the heart of it, where you can create gardens, which are procedural music engines,
where every seed you plant adds to the composition, and where each garden represents a step towards healing a fractured community.
It's also, as I said, a soap opera.
It's interested in the mundane as much as the sublime.
It's about a community of people who live alongside
the consequences of the past,
as well as the actions of the present.
There are love triangles and old wounds,
band nights and communal barbecues.
So that's a little bit about the game.
The following is how I employed some of the tactics
of ensemble storytelling in this fantasy-tinged
alternative world of Mattassione.
So I used a variety of characters and locations.
We treated days in the game like chapters or episodes,
and had special events and different characters
to focus on in each episode.
Varying the characters and key locations
helped us keep the storytelling alive, engaging,
and to use different characters to vary the pacing,
meaning that we didn't have to generate
relentless jeopardy in a single character arc.
We were dipping into other characters' arcs every episode.
While Kai is your way into the themes of Mitassione, it's only how the ensemble casts begin to build a
sense of time, place, and presence that the themes and problems of the game begin to emerge.
You discover that this is a community dealing with intergenerational grief,
and that by bearing witness to stuff people haven't been able to speak about,
by being the catalyst as a new person in the community, the community can begin to process it.
The story builds like a collage.
not at a point. And the gameplay rewards you in understanding this. So I design the narrative
to work with what I call multiple middles. One of the first things that you're often
asked about interactive narrative is how important are the choices? Do they matter? And I'd
like to think that all the choices characters make in a game matter, but the amount of control
you have over them and what they in turn affect is often seen as the sum of how complex or
accomplished a piece of narrative design is.
A lot of games discourse tends towards judging the accomplishment of games on how close they
get to the real world of choice and consequence, but sometimes abstraction is more valuable
than simulation in helping us reflect on the world.
When asked this question with regards to Mitassione, I like to talk about the game having multiple
middles rather than multiple endings.
In conversations in the game I very much used the Kentucky Route Zero model of choice,
colouring how the character responds to the situation but not letting you choose who the
character is. Are you attempt to be articulate Kai or are you diffuse the situation with a bad joke
Kai? Either way you're still Kai. The conversations branch, you might access different reactions,
memories or stories but they come to the same place in the end.
Instead, there's a great deal of choice in terms of which B, C, A plots you dig deeper down into,
who you make deeper connections with, and how much the complex and thoroughly plotted history
that you uncover. Multiple middles. This means you explore widely. This means that the game
rewards you for meandering, for exploring the context of the moment and uncovering the
interrelationship of past and present.
De-centering Kai by not making you control her and her character allows you to see the whole ensemble cast on the same level.
This allows conflicting points of view to emerge.
Following and developing several characters instead of one allows for much more subtle exposition and conflict from which insight can emerge, again like a collage.
Not making the player invest everything in one character means that they can see a balance of points of view,
contrasting and highlighting one another.
It allows for the player to feel like they're choosing a way through the narrative,
unpicking a mystery in a way that is cheap in terms of narrative design of interaction,
like I'm not having to plot hundreds of thousands of branching paths,
but it's rich in terms of player experience.
In a hero's tale version of Mitassione, your grandfather would have been your guide in the game.
and would have given you unbiased and true information.
The other characters would have things
that you needed to harvest
in order to proceed along your quest.
But in our ensemble cast template,
as Mattassione progresses and your conversations begin
to paint past conflicts and mistakes into the picture,
you realize that not only is your grandfather's account
unreliable, but that the discontents in the community
are not as soluble as he claims.
The choices we give in dialogue don't affect the outcome of the conversations.
They're more about revealing Kai's character than altering outcomes,
and about uncovering the community through discourse with them.
It's meant to de-centre her from being a conventional player heroine.
It also encourages the player to listen to,
rather than solve, other characters when you spend time with them.
The big structural lesson when thinking about learning from long-running TV series is the
A plot, B plot, C plot, and the Er plot.
So the Er plot is what I'm calling in TV the series-long plot.
Not all ensemble shows have these, especially not slice-of-life ones, but having a central
theme or narrative problem
that the plot of the series returns to can be a pleasing and useful underlying rhythm.
Sometimes in like monster of the day style long-running tv shows,
there'll be one main bad guy that they keep on returning to throughout the whole of the season
and that's a good example of an ur-plot.
Another good example, and a TV show which I return to a lot in writing the game, is
Star Trek DS9, a great example of ensemble cast TV formatting, that often uses season-long
er plots for the big historical shifts in the world and the wider Star Trek universe,
but develops the characters and the community through A, B and C plots. They put community
in context. Politics becomes practice.
The ABC plots happen within episodes. The shifting focus of an ensemble cast allows
an episode to deal with one big theme or problem, whilst also varying the pace and levity with
smaller subplots. Again, not all placing it on a hero, where shifts in tone could feel
unbalancing.
The A-plot is the driving theme or problem of the episode.
In day five of Mitassione, that might be,
go on a boat trip with Tung and Miu
and discover that you should grow a garden
to help Tung with his boat making.
B-plots are the secondary stories in an episode, often lighter, comedic, or contrasting thematically
in a way that reflects on the A-plot, all of which makes the A-plot more compelling
when you return to it. In Day 5 and Mitassione, B-plots include following upon the events
of the night before, when it was revealed that Spike the bartender has a long-running
crush on Tung's mother, Claire.
C-plots are the smallest unit and might resemble empty side quests, but the difference in an
ensemble setting is that you care about the characters because of the previous investment
that you've put into them, which means that these details can be dealt with lightly but
also used to add to your satisfaction with the completeness of the universe.
In day five of Meta-sione, a sea plot would include the sausage folk.
If you haven't played the game, please do.
And you'll find out all about the sausage people.
They're plotting a new scheme, which this time will definitely make them all rich.
I should add that Meta-sione is a non-monetary economy,
so that gives you some sense of the levity of that plotline.
So in Meta-sione, I make a conscious decision.
plots, contributing to that er plot, mandatory. In each time of day, you have two or three
conversations or actions that, when completed, will move time forwards. We always mark the
mandatory conversations with clear clues in a journal, and in the world, with a symbol
that tells you when the last conversation will move time forwards.
whether or not to move time forwards,
or to explore the many other hundreds
and hundreds of conversations
that you can have throughout the game.
In Mitassione, each day in the game has an A-plot,
which contributes to the E-plot,
these mandatory conversations or actions.
Then there's a great deal of choice
in terms of B and C-plots,
which you can dig deeper down into.
with characters you can make deeper connections with, and you can choose therefore how much of
the complex and thoroughly plotted history that you uncover. It gives play a choice in terms of
breadth, in terms of exploration. That's why I talk about multiple middles, not multiple endings.
So I therefore made narrative design decisions that focused on the characters as complex,
rich, and I also made them a little bit different for the smallness of their community.
I wanted getting to know them in this broad, exploratory way which rewarded
the player for digging deeper, I wanted getting to know them to reflect this central musical
gardening mechanic, which was so wonderfully devised by Douglas Wilson and Alessandro Coronas,
to feel like coming across a number of new plants you've never seen before,
watching them grow, tending to them where possible, and allowing them to surprise you.
I set out to build narrative design that would allow the player to choose their own pace,
to push at the central plot, or to meander, wander, and grow the story at their own pace.
The themes of the story are tough in places. Among the everyday, it also deals in trauma,
colonialism, infidelity, aging, and illness. But in reviews, the game is often characterized
as gentle, I think because of the opportunity that the player has to pace their own experience.
Hopefully, as you play Metasione, none of this narrative design will feel visible.
Instead, it'll feel like you're making your own way through a community full of life.
A community that's lived long before you and, all being well, will live long after you leave.
The Ensembl-Kast template allows me to imply this complexity and depth with a variety of voices,
plotlines, and a form of player agency which reveals layers of the onion skin
the more and more deeper you dig down.
Finally, in the last couple of minutes, I'm going to touch lightly on the political implications
of ensemble cast storytelling. All acts are political. All storytelling contains politics.
The choices in any piece of storytelling or design hold within them political assumptions and affordances.
So as a last note, I'd like to say a little bit about why I think we should care about writing for ensembles rather than heroes,
beyond the fact that it can help you tell a long-form story in a more compelling way.
We live in a global society.
My actions today in Copenhagen, what I choose to buy or eat, can have a material impact on people
I will never meet in China or Maui or the Democratic Republic of Congo. Climate crisis
demands every country on earth take action. People die and are dying because of the fictions we draw
on the world like borders and nations. We are connected. I wrote these words a month ago.
before I'd ever heard the words novel coronavirus or COVID-19.
I considered whether or not I should turn them down in the context of a
global pandemic and I assure you I don't mean to
instrumentalise people's anxiety or suffering but
this is just true. That's it.
We were always connected, but now, more than ever,
we can wield our connections far more dangerously,
and I think it's time we start to tell stories
about the world that explore that,
that do away with the hero,
that begin to work on the challenges that emerge
when we ask how we live together as an ensemble,
that paints the people we touch with our lives
as more than just non-player characters
placed there to further our quest,
or that says that we just need to wait for a hero
to get us out of this mess.
That's why I think it's not only useful for longer form games to tell stories with ensemble casts,
but also, I think, urgently relevant.
So, really quickly, key takeaways I'd offer to people thinking about telling an ensemble cast story.
Make sure the ensemble cast characters reflect and shape one another.
When you write a hero's journey, the character has to change beginning to end.
When you write for an ensemble cast, think about how they all change.
Think carefully about the player's presence in the world,
and therefore the narrative design. Be diverse.
In characters, varied identities, voices, backgrounds, perspectives.
Make it rewarding to dig into the world.
don't define characters by their difference.
It's an easy and slightly lazy mistake to make
in building a diverse world
to make characters defined
by the ways that they're different.
But when characters live together in a community,
they'll have a lot of similarities as well.
Make characters surprising, complicated.
Watch TV, but also operas and 24-hour durational theatre.
Read detective novels, get to know the affordances
of all of the forms and genres and the relationships
between audience and storytelling that exist out there.
And keep track of it all.
Your world, your universe, the past,
the complicated present, how you conceptualize the story
and storytelling and plotting, planning, and programming.
Somewhere there is a 24-hour long presentation I could give about the spreadsheets and narrative
design systems in Mitassione. You're not going to get it today, but think in a connected way
between all departments about how you're going to tell the story, how you're going to manage time,
how you're going to present characters, and what player exploration means in this world,
what choice means. And get rid of the hero.
Keep examining your assumptions about what storytelling is and how those assumptions shape
your view of the world. Look to other cultures and forms, historical and contemporary,
especially outside of the Western tradition, and build your teams in a diverse way. There's
no better way to write diverse stories than to build a team made up of diverse peoples.
So, thank you so much for your time. I hope this has been valuable to you.
You can find me at Hannah Nicklin, pretty much on all of the internet,
and Guta Fabrique is who you should follow
on Twitter if you want to hear updates on the game.
I hope that you're all well and safe and in these complicated times
I wish you the strength and solidarity of good community.
Thank you.