Good morning, everyone. My name is Brian Francis.
I'm a community manager with GDC and a contributing editor at gamasutra.com.
If you need to refer to me in the third person, my pronouns are he, him.
I am joined today by Shell Games VP of Game Design,
Harley Baldwin and speedrunner Utsu.
Harley and Utsu, would you please introduce yourselves?
Hi, I'm Harley Baldwin.
As you said, I'm the VP of Design at Shell Games.
And many years ago.
16 years ago. I was a senior level designer at LucasArts and had the great good fortune
to work on Republic Commando. I haven't ever seen anybody speed run it and so this is going to be
fascinating experience for me and I can't wait.
My name is Utsu. I'm the speed runner.
I picked up this game a few months ago just because I always enjoyed
Robocommando as a game and as I looked in the run it looked more
and more interesting especially since a newer bug got found a little while ago.
And so I basically picked it up and
it's been fun to run ever since and if you need to
refer to me in the third person my pronouns are she her.
Roger that, thank you Utsu. So for folks who've been watching our last couple speedruns,
I mentioned the last couple days that speedrunning is this incredible art form that sort of brings the
the play and video game closer to the development of video games.
Today we are, obviously as people mentioned, we're running Star Wars
Republic Commando, a LucasArts game from 2005. Republic Commando is one of my
favorite shooters from my teenage years. It's a Star Wars game without Jedi.
Its cultural relevance is still felt today as its heroes Delta Squadron were
featured in Star Wars Clone Wars, the TV show.
Karen Travis's books kept Love for the Clone Commandos alive and
sort of brought built out the commando.
group in the popular eye for a number of years.
And just this year, Lucasfilm announced another upcoming
series about clone soldiers, Star Wars The Bad Batch.
While Republic Commando isn't the only reason that fans have
fallen in love with the clones and the different nicknames
they give themselves and the roles they occupy in Star Wars,
it's definitely a big reason for it.
It's why we're here.
It gave birth to Karen Travis's books.
From a game side, Republic Commando captures a particular moment in game design that's a halfway mark between classic shooters like Doom and modern shooters like Fortnite, Call of Duty, or Apex Legends.
And we're lucky to be joined by Harley, who, as she mentioned, she was a senior level designer on the game, to talk about what it was like making games in that era.
Also, we are here because there are some particular ways that Utsu will be breaking this game that I really want to see how she reacts to.
With that in mind, really quick I'm gonna look at chat. We have folks like Taylor D, Alex Jacobson,
Heath Close, thank you all for joining us. Ryan Lippert wants to say this is one of the most
overlooked and underrated Star Wars games. This was a huge part of their middle school gaming days,
mine too. Folks in chat, if you have questions for Harley or Utsu, if you're a...
And we're gonna ask to keep it on topic.
I know we've got some runner fans in here
and I appreciate having you here,
but we're Game Developers Conference, we gotta keep it.
game development. If you have questions for Harley about working on this game, feel free to ask him.
If you're a developer and want to know about speedrunners and speedrunning games, feel free
to ask them for Utsu and I will grab them. With that, I think it's time. I believe the battle in
the Geonosis Arena has kicked off. The war has begun. Utsu, take it away.
And you want me to start from new game?
Start from new game, please.
All right.
Oh, I've got chills.
I was just rewatching Clone Wars and Tan Wei was in a bunch of episodes that I featured
in.
I love the design of these creatures, you know, they're influenced by the Greys.
Episode 2 does a great job with like 50s sci-fi aesthetic and importing it for a new world.
Yeah, this whole sequence was basically done by animation and technical art when we realized
like, oh yeah, we need a little bit of a tutorial just about how to use the twin stick shooters.
And they got together and essentially skunkworst this.
uh, to a pretty, pretty final level of done.
Um, it was, it was really amazing when we came in.
Oh, look, this is basically already been handled.
Yeah.
It's yeah, it's kind of not a level, but it is like a brief, like, you
know, it's in the narrative space.
It's not a, it's not a cut scene.
Cause it's not pre-rendered and it's not a, um, level of just
the player doesn't move during it.
Although there is a brief, like, yeah, this part, the tutorial.
Like, this is really neat.
I actually personally referenced this.
I was running a Star Wars, we were running a Clone Wars RPG session
using Fantasy Flight Games RPG system, and we had a bunch of new players
who'd never played with the system before, so I was like,
right, Clone Wars handled, Republic Commando handled this.
We'll just pretend we're on Kamino doing a training session.
Yeah.
Real quick, let's go to chat and start taking some questions.
Here's one from Big Law Big Law for Harley.
What's the most interesting hitch you had developing this game?
I think the most interesting one that we had as a team overall
was that originally the commandos were indistinguishable from one another.
They were clones, right? We figured they were clones.
And we were working in the context of the movie.
in which clones are clones are clones and so we had all four of them using essentially the same
voice or voice of lights and it became clear that that was difficult to know who was doing what,
there were gameplay implications that were a problem and when we showed it to George Lucas
he felt that it would be a stronger story if
the clones were differentiated and lent his support behind the idea of giving each clone
a personality. That stuff actually came in pretty late and it was only through the amazing
gargantuan efforts of the writers, the artists, etc. that we actually managed to get the four
distinct commandos in and to give them personalities and just everybody. It was an amazing...
new feature and new conceptual feature that sort of came in without a hitch, but if I
was on a game where that level of change came in at the late date that it did now, with
the experience that I have, I never would have tried to pull something like that off.
Could I, not to interrupt, but if I ask a quick question, is there a way that I can
mute the Zoom audio feed?
That's a good question.
Because I'm hearing the game twice and it's a little distracting.
If our tech team, is there a way to mute that through Zoom?
While we go ahead with the run, while this cuts in still modes, let's see here.
It sounds like we just killed the audio, that's fine, we'll be okay.
Uh, Utsu, what's your favorite level to run in this, to do in this run?
Uh, like individual or like section?
We'll go ahead for the sections because there's only three levels if you look at it at the top level.
All right.
Um, my favorite one is the Republic Assault Ship.
Um, my very favorite is the part, is the...
First, technically second hangar that you clear in the Republic Assault Ship.
The one where you have to like set up for the incoming droid dispensers.
Yep.
Alright, with the run beginning, let's go ahead and watch our first hack take place.
Just a little jump over the wall, which I think actually might be allowed,
but then Uchi's about to do something that when we were testing this,
was already just like, oh no, that's not how you play this game.
There we go.
Little behind the geometry there, nice.
We, I have a fun fact about this level.
The goal for the first part of this mission
is to hunt the Geonosian General Sunfack.
Sunfack has actually been, he's still kicking around.
I play the Fantasy Flight Games tabletop game,
X-Wing Miniatures, and now that they've introduced
the prequel factions.
They've released the Geonosian Starfighter and Sun Fac is the most powerful.
He gets to be a character in that game because he's just riding around in the Geonosian Starfighter.
Also, he sucks. He's such a pain to deal with when other players use him.
So, something you probably just saw me do there is you probably saw the load bar go twice.
It's because I quicksave and I quickloaded during the load screen.
Which, doing that...
From what I understand is the level triggers spawn after your character spawns, and if
you quicksave and quickload before the character spawns, it messes up the triggers.
So here I can tell 6-2 to hack this console before I'm even told to hack it.
Thanks!
I didn't even notice that when I was watching this one before.
Harley, I noticed watching this run, you know, a lot of interactions are slowed down by the
force timers on using, you know, interacting with doors or ordering the clones to interact
with doors.
Were those sort of meant to pad out the game a little bit?
They do, like sometimes it's very clear that they're meant to make things feel tense.
But I'm curious what some of the philosophy behind that was.
So.
Partly it was because we knew there would be places where you might have, you know, a threat on this side of the door that you have to deal with, you're trying to get through on the other side.
I don't think there was really any desire to pad out the game so much as there was to give level designers tools to create that feeling of tension, right?
We discovered early on that if you don't really have to depend on your squad...
then you'll just leave them behind, you won't pay attention,
and it's not gonna feel like a squad game.
Okay, and now?
Since that was-
Like, yeah, like-
Yeah, like you are now.
And I suspect that there's gonna be a lot of that
in this playthrough.
It was really, it was a pillar of the game
to try to do that, so.
I also noticed, though, you don't need your squad
because you're skipping a lot of triggers
and that kind of stuff, so you've got a lot of AI
just standing there, waiting to be told it should wake up.
Again, a thing I think I'm going to see a lot of today.
So this is going to be the most confusing part.
So first, I quicksave and quickloaded here.
And then if you press the walk button, the shift button,
while you go down a zip line, you don't go down the zip line.
So I get to just be up here, which lets me do this.
Oh, no.
Which lets me walk by the glass.
Nice, because there's no collision up there to keep you to do it, because nobody would ever be up there.
Yeah.
Usually, once you shoot the glass, you gotta go through this whole cutscene where you open up that door and then
O7 has to shoot down a thing. But because I quicksave and quickloaded,
I can just come over here to the exit door and leave.
So I quicksave with a mouse button during this, uh...
I have to do with a mouse button during these,
or I have to somehow press start before it fully
loads to quick save.
And doing that lets me quick load.
And I can walk around in this cut scene.
Oh my goodness.
I do love getting to look at these armors from this angle
in this cut scene.
You can really get to see how the, I love like the hologram,
you know, like the, like all the ways that like,
it gathers and orients people in the scene,
you know, like everyone gathering around waiting for orders.
We were talking before about how the personalities for 07, 40, and 62 got added late in the game.
I've heard Brett DeVille, a friend of the show, who helped make this happen, shout out
to our guy.
I've heard him talk before about how that's sort of the reason that even though each clone
has a specialty, those specialties aren't really reflected in the gameplay.
I play like Seb, if I have my rules remembering right.
Sev isn't really any better at sniping than any of the other clones.
That sort of sounds like it came from the same place, right?
That late arrival?
Well, it did, and it also, like, we did do some experience trying to figure out if we
tuned them differently, would it make a difference?
What we found was that there was so much cognitive load trying to figure out who to put on what.
that it actually frustrated players.
And so we went with conceptually, you know who you want to use things, and players who
want to opt into that can, and players who don't, won't.
We didn't publicize that there wasn't any difference, obviously.
In fact, it wasn't really well known or widely known until pretty late.
It was still, like I had people walk up to me for years telling me, you know, I really
like using Sev on the sniper positions, etc.
Because your brain just convinces you that that's the way it is.
That is certainly not unique to Republic Commando, the idea that you can let the player's expectations
fill in features that might otherwise be actually problematic to implement.
Yeah, Gabe Paftr in chat wants to say that I,
Brett DeVille's oral history stream is great.
Highly recommended.
Also, yeah, I watched that stream too.
And I picked up a few facts that are in my note sheet
from it, because he was nice enough to grab some guests
from, he grabbed some of his former coworkers.
I don't remember how they view on it,
but that was a lot of fun.
I think that was like back in 14 or 15,
because I remember watching it in my old job.
I wasn't on that, I was on the most recent, he and Tim Longo did a Dev Game Club podcast
very recently where they played this game and interviewed a bunch of the people who
were developers on it, and I did get to be on that one, it was great.
I highly recommend it if you're interested in the game generally.
Yeah, Mariana McQueen wants to say that they love these skips, and so do I Mariana.
Um, uh, Heath Close would like to know, was there a significance behind the names 0740162?
Uh, not that I know of, definitely 38 though. Um, oh yeah, there's a, there's a tradition at LucasArts,
well there was a tradition when LucasArts existed, of naming characters and rooms and
things and robots and whatever you could after, um, THX 1138, which was...
an early and seminal movie for George Lucas,
in which a lot of the techniques that he used
to create the Star Wars franchise
generally were explored early.
And we all had, I think, a deep fondness for the movie,
so reflected it as much as we could.
By the way, if you're a person who loves Star Wars,
but hasn't checked out George Lucas's film American Graffiti,
I finally watched that late last year and I was blown away.
God, like what a and it's funny because there's a there's a one.
There's an 1138 reference in that movie, too.
And I'm so a you get to see Harrison Ford, you know, right before Han Solo
and be such a wonderful movie, like such a straight like
it couldn't get made today.
This is what I felt watching it.
And it was so wonderful to watch.
Oh.
Gabe has another good question. Does the AI have a preference if they point us at a snipe point and all the squadmates are available, does the game default to Sev over others?
I don't think so, but it's possible. I mean, the AI programmer who worked on this, John Hintock, he spent the entire...
development cycle of the game working on it. And that could be in there, and I honestly wouldn't
know. The level of craftsmanship that he put into the squad AI was truly mind-boggling.
And it's certainly possible. It's also possible that you just think so, because your mind's doing
confirmation bias every time you see Sev walk up to a snake point, right?
Yeah, you only remember those times, not the other ones.
Yeah.
The load-save hack, or the quick-save hack, is really interesting.
I mean, it's certainly standard practice in game development
to figure out what you think your most airtight level load and save scripts are.
And once you've got that, you replicate it all over the game, right?
So if somebody finds a way to hack that,
they've essentially got a backdoor into the entire game,
which is what you're using right now.
Something that I wanted to say back there is that if you didn't see it,
So following props, if you quick save and quick load,
will just be frozen in air where they
where they were, the quick save happened
until they're interacted with again.
So that let me skip to a bomb planting portions.
What that also did is it displaced this this bridge here.
Oh, no. Oh, so.
So if I try to go the correct way, the intended, like walk through this way.
Oh. Yeah.
So to get past that, you have to do this.
Excepted. Oh my goodness.
Go where the bridge was.
Oh, fascinating.
Yep.
Right, and that would have been
that would have been
an optimization of physics
because back in those days,
having any kind of physics simulation
in your game was incredibly expensive.
And...
So we had to find ways to turn it off as soon as we possibly could, you know, if the player's not looking at it, etc.
Uh, from chat, uh, Big Law Big Law says that's goofy as heck. I agree.
Harley, I have a question for you while we roll ahead.
Utu, feel free to just interrupt us if you have a great hack or skip to show off.
What other games from the time of development were you sort of inspired by as a level designer?
Oh, well, I mean, you always start with Half-Life, right?
But everybody does.
Uh, we were definitely looking at, uh, at early, uh, multiplayer squad games.
Um, uh, definitely looking at, um, at other, uh, uh, sorry, I'm the, the
repeat of that makes me feel like I'm in the, in the matrix, uh,
and kind of hijacks my brain.
Um, uh.
this hard. I struggle with this so much and I don't know why. So what I'm doing here is,
you can climb through this window but I can't remember the, I can get this, but I just can't
remember the correct angle to go at it. It's a little hole in the in the collision somewhere
that you can just hit. Yeah, I got a
This is something we discussed in one of our earlier runs,
is how sometimes these hacks,
because you're burning so much time elsewhere,
it's okay to run these hacks over and over again.
Right, right.
Yeah, this one I can't really afford to just not do either,
because it saves so much time.
Yeah.
You just tap that to...
I should have access to unlock doors
once a link is established.
It's so interesting.
The way that you play this game
is not at all about trying to create a sort of coherent narrative, and I don't mean the story
of the game, I mean the narrative of what you're doing as the player, as the character. It's really
about creating a narrative of how the game was built and how you have sort of packed insight
into the way the game was built.
I feel like watching speedrunning is a thing that people who want to get into game development
should do because it just shows you so many of the secrets of how we do this stuff.
Yeah, Harley, you didn't work on Junos specifically, we're going to see your own Minecraft levels
when we get to Kashyyyk, but you were helping other designers work on these early levels.
Do you have any memories about, obviously not about...
Obviously not about trying to make sure players didn't do this,
but do you have any memories of helping your teammates figure out
what this game should feel like in its early stages?
We did have a really...
We spent a lot of time on the bridge,
the falling bridge that you skipped earlier,
because it was so much about establishing place,
establishing enemy,
establishing how useful sniping could be.
You know, there's a...
sort of half tutorial half cut scene early on with the bridge where you're supposed to
snipe a geonosian um and um uh just restarting the whole level just in case that's good yeah
that's fine because we were learning so much about
establishing place and character of a level.
We spent a lot of time as a level design group
looking at that and discussing it and playing it and giving feedback
and seeing new iterations and stuff like that.
It was a very early level to come forward, you know.
The way that essentially the development on this game worked was that
One level would be running out ahead, trying new things,
trying to meet new goals,
whether those were technical or experiential or whatever,
sometimes tools, to make sure that that would work
for other people so that everybody didn't get stopped
by a, oh, nope, that's not gonna work moment later on,
that you'd already had time to work that out.
And so this was one of those levels, right?
We also knew that because it was the very beginning
of the game, we were going to need to be able to,
build it, then build the whole game, then come back and make sure that it was supporting
what it needed to support, both in terms of tutorial and story, narrative context.
So it got a lot of that stuff.
Taylor?
Also, I think one of my follow notifications went through my OBS.
Oh, interesting.
Really quick, Taylor D. first wants to say you got this, Itsu.
So you got some support.
Taylor would also like to add in from a longtime speed runner.
Watching speed running has to be done with the proper mindset.
If you're a game dev, we often like not having these types of tricks patched out.
And in their experience, devs will often use runners as free QA, which isn't fun.
Both of the other developers we talked to this week
definitely acknowledge that, like, you know, they see a bug
that shows up and runs and they do their.
they actually go out of their way not to patch those out
because it doesn't interrupt the main player's experience.
And they definitely did that,
but I also could see some dev watching GDQ or whatever
and being like, oh no, we have to eliminate that bug
for some reason they feel is valid.
But I understand where Taylor's coming from.
Yeah, yeah.
It's interesting what I have taken away from
from things like this is, well, okay,
so sometimes a buck comes up
and it's in the player's favor, right?
But it's going to be rare
on some kind of a vanilla playthrough.
For me.
Like, I mark those will not fix, and I do it with a kind of a joy, because I know that
a curious player might find that, and it's not going to break anything else that they're
not interested in having broken, and they get to walk away feeling like they've outsmarted
the developers.
That being said, I absolutely am not claiming that we find all the bugs and decide not to
fix them.
Certainly, speedrunners find bugs that we haven't found.
It's also true that probably every game you speedrun has a few of those little
love letters to curiosity, sort of, in the game. It is our job to make things that people enjoy.
And it is also our job to keep a wide variety of player types in mind, right? Yeah, you can make
some games for a very narrow player type. Only people who, whatever, like to collect everything
or whatever.
There are situations in which that can happen, but especially when you're talking about AAA
games, you have to appeal to a wide variety of player types because you need those sales.
So I always look at bugs like that and say, like, do we have to fix this if people who
are sort of just playing through without looking for stuff like this won't find it or be bothered
by it, but people who really, really value it might find it and have a great time with
it?
Utsu, I'm not asking this from a hurry-to perspective, but I just want to know, would it help you if it was okay if we skipped ahead?
Like, as much as I want to see this hack, I also don't want you to feel bad if you pick someone to do it.
See, the issue is I don't know if I can just skip it.
Oh wait, yeah, I can. Let me give it like five more tries.
This isn't that hard. I have literally no idea why it's this difficult.
It's just not cooperating with me.
Yeah, hey, look, in these uncertain times,
we just sort of have to roll with the punches, yeah.
As I've said 20 times this season.
It's entirely possible that I'm the one who put the bad geometry here.
You know, at the end of any dev cycle,
once you've done all of the creative stuff...
A level designer spends a lot of time just going and trying to put in geometry to keep
people from doing stuff like this.
And if you're a tiny bit slapdash or your verts aren't snapped or whatever, it leaves
a hole.
Yeah.
Gabe would like to know again, did the team explore multiplayer with AI squads like in
single player?
If not, why?
If so, why?
If not, why not?
Or if so, why didn't it make it into the game?
Yeah.
We didn't, and the answer is actually really simple.
With the hardware that we were running at the time,
both the PCs that people had in the home
and the original Xbox this game released on,
there wouldn't have been a way to make
a decent-looking multiplayer arenas
and still optimize enough
to have all of those characters in the game.
Oh no, oh no.
Yeah, and so-
You just fell through a lot.
I just did the bug where you stop a zipline and that whole ship isn't solid so I can just jump through it.
Nice.
That's faster than I thought.
Sometimes when you watch it you're just like, oh no.
Like, oh no, my brain.
I just progressed to the next mission which is literally right after that level.
What you missed was me jumping through the window, dropping down to the very last bomb plant,
and then jumping over a gap and walking to the end of the level.
There's kind of a weird hack with these turrets too, right?
Like you just walk by one.
I've seen, like I mentioned, I think there's a hack.
Oh yeah, the turrets in Fur actually a tiny bit here.
Gotcha.
These later parts look a little bit similar.
You know what's kind of funny about this is
this looks a lot like what it looks like
to see a level designer play their own level.
Some of these, it's not like we deliberately leave
exploits in for our own use.
But you look at them and you're like, well, nobody's going to find that, right?
I, it's only, it's, it's only something I can use because I know it's there.
Um, uh, and so when you, when you're doing what we call a smoke test, where
you're just checking to make sure the thing you just changed didn't break
everything, you know, this is how you run your, your level really.
Yeah.
Um.
Harley, did you want to add anything else about the conversation before Gabe's question?
Sorry, I cut you off.
I'm sorry, I can't remember what we were talking about, so if you'll remind me, maybe?
AI for multiplayer squad, like putting squad in multiplayer?
Yeah, no, it wasn't something we ever would have really been able to consider just because
of the optimization requirements and wanting to have good-looking arenas.
Yeah.
There was a long, long time when the reality was you could have about
five characters on screen, maybe up to eight if they were really optimized, and that was
going to be it.
And so with the numbers of players in the arena, it just wasn't going to work out.
That's good.
Speaking of optimization, what was it like, like you've been involved for a long time,
what was it like optimizing this game for the original Xbox and then later PC?
I forget if it was simultaneous or not, but you know, the original Xbox is sort of what
I'm curious about.
Yeah.
Versus compared to your experience helping your team optimize their games now.
Oh, well, so we developed on PCs that were built as close to the original Xbox config as possible at the time, if I remember correctly.
And so we, it wasn't until pretty late in the game that we had it on the Xbox.
Mostly everything fit and worked okay.
There were a few, there were a few problems in terms of textures, texture memory, I remember being a real problem,
and that we had to sort of...
and Scrooge-specific textures that showed less down until everything else fit, and that was a long process.
Geometry wasn't too bad.
The thing that was a real surprise, I think, was...
I mean, it was a new console, so you just never know.
I've seen this happen with other new consoles as well.
It was the problem of streaming.
You know, this is Unreal 2, I believe, and its streaming capabilities are one of the
reasons we decided to use it, without having to write our own streaming engine.
But until you're on the target hardware, you can't really know how fast you're going to
stream in and out.
And there were some places where it was like, oh, no, we are not going to stream that fast
enough.
We are going to have to figure out a way to tap dance right here so that things have a
chance to stream in.
the Kashyyyk tree as you go up the tree, you'll actually see some of those and
and uh yeah there are a few of them where
where um we weren't supposed to have a chapter break
but we had to have some kind of break or the it wasn't just gonna just wasn't
gonna be able to do it. That makes sense uh looking back at chat
uh Heath uh says uh from the from the skip from a few
minutes ago, they can't stop moving in their seat to
to help you get uh once we get over that rock.
Coltzone Games just wants to say hi.
Hey Coltzone, I've seen some of your tweets on GDC Summer this week.
I hope you're having a good time.
I think you are, so I'm glad you joined us.
Gabe is throwing great questions one after another.
One of the things they remember desperately wanting when they first played Republic
Window was a level where you operate the turret on airborne transport.
Was anything like that ever prototyped and would similar optimization constraints apply?
Yeah, we did some early prototypes about a variety of different things where you might be on a moving platform vehicle, etc.
But at the time, the state-of-the-art and the level of physics simulation we could do,
it was so prohibitively expensive that we weren't able to make that work and make things like enemies work.
You know, these days it would be pretty...
pretty simple to do. But he was asking a lot of the machines we
got available.
I love I love when you consider the technical limitations of any
art actually, whether it's film, music, or games. And you dig
into sort of how the art is informed by the technical, you
know, by those technical limitations, you know, like,
think
how lenses physically morph the look of film,
or how games, depending on how much memory was available,
could only ship certain features,
even if something may have been executable
on the perfect machine, but not on every machine.
I love it.
I love thinking about games like that,
because it's always like,
once you understand the restrictions,
you sort of understand the art, I feel like.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's also really interesting how in any console's life cycle,
early on you get a bunch of games that are trying to take a big swing at what this new console can do.
As teams get really good at pushing the console to its very limits,
you begin to see some really amazing stuff.
And then with the next console life cycle, that stuff is all just de rigueur.
And now you've got teams pushing new stuff.
You know, there are conversations that happen at the end of that five years
that are conversations that would have been completely shut down at the beginning,
because like we just don't we just don't have the time to do that.
Oh, we've learned this and this and this and those three games.
We can put them together and make make something possible.
PlayStation two was very much the apex of that
because it had such an incredibly long life cycle.
You know, you had you had.
That team is fully dedicated to making games on it for 10 years straight.
And people really, really knew at the end of that console's life cycle how to put it
through its paces and make it do stuff it was never actually meant to do.
Oh, that skip over the rock there, too, was incredible.
That was really fun to watch.
So something I didn't mention is, so you saw me get on and off the turret.
What that does is, for some reason, I don't know what exactly causes it, but getting on
and off of a turret just...
makes you invincible to everything but explosions.
Yeah, I know why that is.
It's because we couldn't make the turret's
collision impervious to shots
because when you want to take somebody down
by shooting them on the turret,
and you can see past the shield or whatever,
you want that shot to hit as a player, right?
But if you're on the turret, you don't really have the same situational awareness.
And so they can just run up behind you and shoot you, and you can't know that that happened.
And that turned out to be a huge feel-bad in playtesting.
And so I'm sure we just made it so that, no, if you're on a turret, you have to be able to see
the threat, and that threat is going to be something that will explode.
So.
It was essentially a way to make sure that the player experience matched what their perception was while they were on the counter-total.
That's so cool. I just love the little, you know,
okay, we solved this problem, it's good.
And then years later, runners are like, hey, wait a minute.
Yeah.
We're going to go to the chat again while we open this dial.
Big Law Big Law wants to say that there seems to be a recurring measure with PC releases
around 2005.
One release in particular, Enter the Matrix, has vehicle speed locked to the clock speed
of the CPU and as a result modern PCs have the vehicles move far faster than they should.
Taylor D says that there's a lot of runs like that where frame rate is tied to physics and
that unless it's emulated by the game, unless it's emulated, the game is absolutely broken.
Gabe says, sorry for spamming questions.
They just love this game
and the chance to hear from the dev is amazing.
Gabe, don't feel sorry about spamming questions.
We're just trying to make sure everyone
gets a chance to ask questions.
But yours are great.
I'm glad Harley can answer them
and I hope Harley's having as much fun as I am.
This is gold.
This is just chef's kiss every five minutes.
How many times do you use the turret hat?
Three times.
Also, something you missed there was,
there's a whole section where you wait
for a bridge to extend for about a minute,
but you can jump off of the console,
around a corner, onto some collision,
just walk over to where the bridge is supposed to be.
Oh yeah, I just leveled.
I saw that when I checked the run out.
You aren't actually supposed to get up there,
but if you use that console,
then you can get up high enough.
Yeah, I mean, speaking of optimizing physics,
Absolutely, the cheapest way to do physics is to have collision where the player will
be able to walk later and have things animate into that space, right?
And I'm sure we did that a great deal here.
I'm trying to think of a place that I'm sure that we actually used simulated physics to
change the path.
I might be able, when we get to the levels that I actually put together, I might be able
to find one, but...
Oh, I am, I cannot wait for us to get the machine.
Let's just say that.
So here's something kind of neat.
This Geonosian Elite cannot hurt you if you enter this hack
from an angle.
Fascinating.
Also, something I've noticed about some
of these demolition charges, some of them hurt you,
and some of them don't.
Some of them, like, you can be right up close to,
and you'll only lose a tiny bit of shield.
Some of them, like that one, you'll
explode it, like, right up to it, and it'll just kill you.
Interesting.
So the ones that you see me back up from, those are the ones that actually do damage.
The ones that I just shove my face into, I don't care about.
Sounds like some inconsistent parent-child relationships in the prefabs in Unreal.
That's funny, I know that that's a technical thing, but you're just like,
oh, it sounds like some inconsistent parent-child relationships,
and I'm like, oh boy, I've been there.
Well, I've both as a parent and a child.
Yeah, so one of the things that I did on this game besides level design was help set up the
technical art pipeline for the maneuvers, including the door breaches and stuff.
When you have assets like that that are used over and over and over again,
heal things, etc.
The way that it's built in the engine is very hierarchical, so that you have different elements that you can add onto the model to make it work.
And if people copy that for some reason, because they want to make a broken one or whatever,
you can get into a situation where people are using very slightly different versions,
and then you think you've made a decision about, this is the final version, it will or won't kill people when it explodes in front of them.
But you can certainly get into a spot where...
Unless you're extremely careful with what is deployed to the level, because I received
that in different versions available.
Going from chat, Utsu, we have a question for you.
Alex Jacobson would like to know, how well do you know the process around how a lot of
route skips are found in Game Freakies?
A lot of what skips?
How well do you know the process around how a lot of the route and skips were found?
I know next to nothing for this for how they were found in this game since I showed up again only a
few months ago when um all of this stuff was already found there's been very little found
I think the only thing recent that's been found since I showed up which again the the community
isn't very like together
in like the sense of like there's uh there's one singular discord where like
everybody is a big community and everything there's just one gigantic star wars discord
that uh oh dear um so it actually took me a while to actually even get resources for
learning this run i don't even remember if i knew that you could shoot those containers down
when i played the game
Okay, I'm gonna do something for my sanity.
I was gonna say, I wonder, I was like,
are you actually playing on easy difficulty?
I am on easy, but I think something might've gone wrong
with me hitting new game.
Because usually runs are started just from a save
just to skip the intro cutscene.
Oh, I see.
And it's felt like this whole time
that I've been taking just way more damage than usual.
Yeah, I was noticing that,
because I watched, like I said.
I was like, hmm, that's more than I saw before.
Going for questions in chat again,
JD4 would like to ask, it seems like there's so much going on
in terms of action gameplay and level complexity.
Was it difficult to address narrative pacing?
That's a question for you, Harley.
Um...
Sometimes. I mean, we...
The way the levels were made, right,
we essentially did a block out of the level first and said,
okay, here's where we're gonna fight and here's where we're gonna...
narrative stuff and here's where we're going to have a rest. And I know that as we got deeper
into the development, things like door breaches, you know, sometimes we deliberately put them there
so the players would have a chance to take a break and rest and or so that your squad members could
say things that contributed to the narrative. So most of that stuff is pretty well blocked out
before you end up.
uh, hooking up, you know, the bulk of the action gameplay.
Uh, there are certainly times when it doesn't work,
and you've got to figure out what to do then.
Um, those aren't usually bugs so much as it just feels really weird,
for example, to go from this great big fight
into this sort of quiet introspective cutscene or whatever.
Um...
And sometimes, you know, you do things like, okay, well, let's try routing the player around.
And in levels like this, where the hallways are pretty modular, and it's not super hard
to take the modules you have and build a new hallway or reroute a hallway, you can do stuff
like that pretty easily.
But not late in the game, once all the scripting has hooked up.
Because the scripting gets extremely, extraordinarily complicated.
You want to know all of that stuff pretty early on.
Utsu, I've seen you do this hack with the spider droids a couple times where you manage to get into their spawn point before they emerge into the proper combat area.
Would you be able to describe that hack for us?
Well, that's not even really a hack, it's just walking towards it before the game intended for you to even be there.
Yeah.
It's the simplest hack, walk in the door and act like you belong.
Josh Dua would like to ask, were there any constraints in Unreal Engine 2 that limited
the team's vision for level design?
Um, yes, absolutely.
I mean every level has constraints that limit the vision, right?
The first thing a designer asks themselves is not what grand vision do I have, but what
are the constraints that I actually have to pay attention to?
And this one certainly was no exception.
Trying to think of specific stuff...
That version of Unreal, and honestly, just the hardware that we're running on, again,
it was very difficult to have a really big arena,
and also any of the connective tissue to the rest of the levels.
So you'll notice that we very often have a short hallway, and...
and you know that there's the the hallway takes as long as it takes to load door closes and you can
never get through that again right that's that's all um uh you know and given our druthers most
level designers would prefer not to have arena hallway arena hallway gameplay but it's pretty
difficult um to do that when that's sort of the way that the uh software wants to be run um uh so
There are a lot of different tricks that we use to make it feel less like that.
But certainly it does come up in this game.
Next question, Michael Gibbs would like to ask Harley,
what made you want to be a level designer?
It seems like you get to wear multiple hats of programming and art in gameplay.
That's basically what made me want to be a level designer.
I started out as an art tech in the industry, and I really liked art teching, you know, it was...
I really liked the system design aspect of it, the technical aspect was fun, the team aspect was great,
but I saw level designers getting to take portions of every discipline and put it on a plate and
arrange it in a beautiful way to serve up to players, and that's what I wanted to do.
Um, and...
You know, there's something about the crux of your gameplay being architectural rather
than systemic that just really appealed to me.
It made me think about places in a different and deeper way.
And having been a level designer at a reasonably large portion of my career, I still think
about places in a different way.
in a different way. It's affected everything in my life, honestly, from the way I set up
my house. My house is set up with systems for optimized efficiency in a way that I think
few people do. They're thinking more, is it pretty? And I'm thinking, how many steps does
it take to do this or that, or et cetera?
I think also the fact that I had a strong technical background as a technical artist
and a strong art background because I went to school for photography really drew me to
something that let me integrate all of those things at once.
And then also you get to be in the play tests if you're a level designer and being the person
who actually gets to be there live and watch people.
Not necessarily do this, because you rarely get a speedrunner in playtesting, but watch
people be the first people to enjoy the game or hate it.
It has its own kind of gravity.
Roger that.
I think it's interesting, Utsu does this a couple times in the run, where she chooses
to be the actor that's interacting with the big, the tense making of the game.
timing thing where you have to hit the terminal for like a minute.
And it's interesting to watch her do that as the player instead of doing what most players
do, which is, hey clone, go do it.
Now I'm down in a clone, I have to juggle my soldiers as I sand the situation.
As a designer, what's it like to sort of watch a player make that choice to like look away
from the combat and look away from all the spaces you've built and just stare at the
wall by themselves for a minute?
Well, I mean, it's watching somebody who's gone through the looking glass, right?
So much of making a game like this is smoke and mirrors, right?
And so if the player chooses to put another squad member on that thing,
you want to have essentially a play unfold in front of them that they get to engage in
in terms of defending that person on the console.
But if they are on the console themselves, you definitely don't want them feeling like,
I just got shot in the back a hundred times and that was no fun.
And so watching somebody make that choice in this game is,
oh, you understand how there are times
when we're essentially doing a stage play,
and there are times when we're actively doing
what combat that you as a player engage in,
and you've been able to perceive the difference
between those times.
Does that make sense?
Yes.
Something that I compare that whole one-man hacking section
to is a...
the scene in the amazing spider-man where stan lee is a librarian and he's just kind of
dusting off and cleaning books while all the action is happening behind him and he yeah
yeah i do so three is just hacking away and behind him it's just explosions and
robots dying i was like i'm hit and he was like oh there's the codes cool yeah
Utsu, this section of the game is interesting.
We're going through a whole level that is just the clones exploring an abandoned Republic
capital ship.
And the interesting thing to me is that there's a lot less skips in this section.
At least I noticed a lot less when I was watching a previous run.
In part because for a while you're separated from the rest of the clones and you can't
send them off to handle something while you stand by the door.
What are your thoughts as a runner about how this part of the game feels compared to the
first and third sections?
I like this level, this is my favorite level a whole lot more because in terms of the run,
it feels a whole lot more true to the intent of the game.
I've always said that every level has a theme. Geonosis has the like rubble climbing and hopping over things.
This game is just, this level is just a full-on organizing your squad.
Just making the best use out of them as you possibly can.
It's really interesting to hear you talk about the themes as...
as basically player verbs rather than narrative themes
or sort of higher level interactive themes.
It's fascinating that the lens you bring to it,
which makes sense given what you're doing.
We love to talk about lenses when we're around shell games
because that's what Jesse's whole book was about.
Jesse's shell, the shell of shell games.
We're gonna go to chat real quick
while we let this area begin.
Uh, Misha, uh, sorry, I'm far away from my screen.
Misha Samorodin, uh, would like to say it's funny how level design can apply to real life.
Um, Taylor D, uh, back again, would like to say that speedrunners make excellent QA, by the way.
Uh, they know that Naughty Dog hired, uh, Oven Donkey, an uncharted runner, to QA test Uncharted 4.
We actually had Dave actually pop the question for us yesterday.
We were speedrunning on Nucleolian and he was there.
Just wanted to like, you know, discuss about getting into QA.
Harley, what are your thoughts for like runners who want to get into QA?
Or anyone in general.
Like who want...
For people who want to professionally...
play video games all day and every QA person just tried to shoot me from afar
from wherever they're sitting. What are your thoughts about getting in and
succeeding in that field? So I do think that there are some real
strengths to being a speedrunner if you're looking for a gig as QA, right?
You've already proven that you can successfully
reproduce games and reproduce bugs and you know
what those reproduction steps are.
it's super important to be able to communicate that in a way that devs can understand,
and to be able to represent what's important to the player and what's not. And again, right,
you've got that wide range of player types that you've got to be able to represent for.
But I wouldn't...
I wouldn't think it unreasonable to, if you're trying to get in as QA and you haven't held
that position for, you know, to sort of, rather than showcase a whole speedrun, show how you've
found and made reproducible above in a company's game, and then written up those steps so that
they can see how you would go about communicating about that.
you know, even how you describe the bug and its impact is important there.
So, yeah, I can totally see companies being really interested in that,
especially if they've got a game type for which that matters, right?
There are game types that doesn't matter much.
It seems viable.
Yeah. Heath, while on the subject of career,
Keith Close again would like to ask,
what are the most important skills to have
when looking for a level designer
or wanting to become one?
Oh, the most important skills.
Probably the first one is communication.
A level designer is the person who takes
and showcases the work of every person on the team
on screen in front of the player, right?
And so you have to be somebody that the whole team.
can trust and can talk to about the situation of how is their work going to look and how
is it going to be showcased rather than made to look weird or strange. That's the number
one. Second, I would think, is a pretty decent understanding of architecture. You need to
know how people move in space and how they expect space to move around them in order
to do level design well.
less so if it's mission design, you know, you get a space shooter, architecture doesn't come in that
relevant. But architecture is super important. Some kind of good understanding of dramatic
rhythm, whether that's, you know, having a background in playwriting or understanding TV,
Because you're not only setting up the action, you're also setting up the storytelling, right?
You don't build the cutscene, but you make sure that the cutscene is produced for the player in
its optimum way, and from the perspective where they walk in the room, they can't miss it,
and also it doesn't feel weird, right?
We've all walked into a room cutscene and it's like,
oh, this isn't quite feeling right,
or you moved me 10 feet to the left
and I understood, whatever.
Sometimes you're forced into that,
but the more you can take care
not to have stuff like that happen,
the more your team is going to appreciate
how you're showing them work.
Yeah, I just realized something else.
These turrets are not really hurting you too.
So uh no no they aren't so uh something that uh I want to show off so you saw how I walked in this
was just a whole big battleground cutscene yeah well I'm just gonna go and do that quick save
quick load bug and it doesn't happen anymore oh my goodness that nice it it just kind of
something in the code just never goes through to spawn everybody and engage the battle so you just
kind of get to walk through these guys spawn just fine but not uh
not anything else that's fascinating um yeah different set of triggers no it's all right
interrupt any time yeah we want we want to we want to celebrate the like i said we want to
celebrate the the line between what was intended and what what what's there um
Harley, I have a, before we get back to chat, I have a question that we can talk about this
level.
Rewatching this run, I appreciated how the setup for this level is to give this spooky
feel.
Gabe in chat mentions that separating you from your squad adds to that, you know, that
nervous feeling, that tension before going into a space.
It's interesting where this level goes from there because there's kind of this mystery
about, you know, why are there Trandoshans here if you're a Star Wars renewer like me?
the Trandoshans are a lizard race that's really into slave trade.
that do not appear to be aligned with the droid army at first,
although this level certainly shows they are later on.
There's kind of like an ambiguity to the whole start of it that sort of
doesn't feel like to me as a player, like that ambiguity never has
like a big reveal or anything, the droids just sort of make their way into the story.
What were sort of your thoughts, do you remember anything about what the team was discussing at the time with this level
and playing that ambiguity into...
into the game.
Also, I appreciate how this part of Utsu's run
is just waiting for everyone to walk in.
They got to spawn, right?
You can't just spawn them right there.
So, yep.
Yeah, so this, you're absolutely right
that removing the squad was a big thing.
And like, they had just done a level
in which having the squad have your back
was super important, right?
So having that feeling of being sort of out alone
was important to the tension.
The question of the Trandoshans, it really comes down to this was an interstitial plot point in our minds between two movies, right?
And we wanted to make sure that you were able to discover something that maybe is obvious in the second movie,
but that you were there for understanding that.
when those two factions ally.
We wanted it to feel like,
oh, well, yeah, you started out just as a clone
and you're just running around doing your thing,
but you stumble into a sort of conspiracy
of enormous proportions.
And so this is the beginning of that.
Like, these guys don't belong here
and what are they doing overall?
Doesn't make a lot of sense.
The reveal might be...
a little bit extended.
You know, the environmental storytelling in this level is just so good.
I remember the first time I played it, I was like, this is just great.
And I played the game again recently, a couple of months ago,
and I had exactly the same reaction.
Both in the moment, saying...
the environmental storytelling in this level is so good.
And also remembering that feeling of,
wow, the environmental storytelling is so good
and this is how to do it.
We'll get back to some questions in chat,
but I'll just finish off with another
kind of Star Wars nerd comment.
Yeah, I actually didn't sort of fully realize
that there's kind of an interesting thing
because this whole game winds up in Kashyyyk,
the through line, which is, at the time was,
like it had made in a lot of Star Wars
the thing with material was.
how the Trandoshans were sort of the mortal enemy of the Wookiees and they enslaved them
and that leading to Kashyyyk which is a big set piece from episode 3, Revenge of the Sith
and just as a natural flow from Geonosis through this Trandoshan encounter on the ship to Kashyyyk.
I didn't fully appreciate that before.
Something that I really like about this level is this part here.
Yeah.
An elegant weapon for a more civilized time.
Oh, I missed that every other time.
You just let me turn right and there it is, and he references Episode four.
The only lightsaber in the entire game.
I was looking up trivia and it mentioned that you can find one of the games
somewhere, and I was like, Oh, I wonder where it is.
It's actually kind of funny.
This is the same kind of ship.
Just to give a shout out to the devs at Respawn.
This is the same kind of environment that
Spoilers for those who haven't played Jedi Fallen Lord.
Three, two, one.
There's a level where they flash back to Order 66
and it takes place on a ship like this.
And you get to, the way they navigate that space
and make that feel, you know, a very orderly space
suddenly feel like threatening to a child.
Mwah, like chef's kiss.
I just keep saying chef's kiss.
Let's go back to chat because y'all are here
to chat with Harley.
I'm just taking a page.
Oh, go for it.
Actually, so first of all, you saw me,
quicksave quickload at the very beginning which let me blow up a wall before I defeat the big guy
and something you've been seeing is I will press the reload button with a full mag and it'll cancel
animations so I can come up to these which usually you have to blow up and just...
here it comes
nice
So that works, but I guess it is how it works.
40 is just going to be yelling at me like,
don't worry, keep holding them off.
I'll be through soon.
I'll just be here like, like, yeah, yeah, I, I, I gotcha.
I don't, don't worry buddy.
That's awesome.
Let's go back to the chat.
Cause like I said, I'm just, I, every,
if I nerd out about Star Wars, I nerd out about Star Wars.
Gabe would like to know, did the holographic HUD elements
present interesting rendering or tech challenges?
Um, probably, but I wasn't super involved in setting that up.
Um, by the time they got to me, um, it was really just these are the assets that you're hooking up
to the to the prefabs in Unreal, um, and making sure that everybody knows which prefabs to use
for which situation. Um, uh, I know that it's, I mean, it's...
You'd think that we wouldn't keep remaking these, but you know, you need to with every
new console generation.
The holographic stuff in Star Wars is such an important and iconic IP element that, you
know, it's...
In some ways, it is a really tempting...
thing to use as both UI and a way to guide the player and etc etc.
And so from a game design perspective, one of the things that it, one of the
challenges it can often pose is you initially overuse it because it's
such a great way to give the player information atop the world.
But if you overuse it, the players can't tell one part from another, and they, again,
when the load gets really high, you're essentially spamming them with information that they can't
process all at once, and so you have to hurt back.
But yeah, the temptation of, well, it's just an overlay on the world, you can put all the
information you need in the world, it's easy to lead yourself down that path.
Kind of interesting because it weirdly like it's a faux augmented reality experience,
even though I'm sure if you pop the camera from the player point of view,
they would still be there.
But it's that's sort of a yeah, I'm sure.
I'm sure actually for people doing augmented reality design like that's something worth considering
because it's a faux there's a weird overlap there.
Yeah. Yeah.
I mean, and that's exactly like that.
There is a great deal of care and craftsmanship
that's gone into the whole idea.
Like this whole HUD, conceptually in the game,
is the helmet's display, right?
It's not, it's real in that it's AR in the game.
And, you know, just took a great deal of thought
and iteration from,
the UI designer, but also a huge amount of input from both the rest of the team and playtesters.
I will point out before I get back to questions from chat that we did see a few minutes ago Utsu
using the turret hack again, and it's interesting how the speed up component there is by eliminating
the damage kit variable, Utsu's just able to roll ahead and start completing objectives
while the transitions are running around kicking 3-8's shins.
Something you saw right here in that little area up there is if I quicksave and quickload and then
immediately push W, D, and crouch, I can sort of clip through an invisible wall and let me walk
through which lets me skip a door blowing up sequence which also skips I think a lot of
enemy spawning and turrets turning on.
which lets me immediately rescue 6-2.
And to go off of the helmet thing,
there actually is an option in-game
to just turn on a sort of helmet HUD.
Yep. Ooh. I forget if I played with this.
Oh, I feel like I did, yeah, because I had the ...
I recognize this health bar.
Yeah, this is ... That's how I first played the game,
but as I tried to run it more,
it just kind of got more in the way.
It makes sense. Especially if you really are trying to understand everything in the level as you move through.
If the helmet was stationary, it'd be a bit easier, but it just kind of gets annoying shaking around as I move.
Speaking of UI, Alex Dudman in chat would like to know,
what was behind the decision to have the ammo represented on the weapon itself as opposed to a HUD element?
Which I think a lot of games were experimenting with this at the time.
You can see on the shotgun right now, the 24, and there's like a light counter down there.
But the other weapons that the commander uses have little indicators of how many shots are left.
Yeah, absolutely. I mean, the reality is that a first-person shooter, very often,
the character that you're playing from your own perspective is your gun. So the more you can have
your gun reflect the state of your character right now, the better, right? And it was as
simple as that. We just really wanted people to be able to, without having to look at the HUD in
any way, understand what gun am I using.
What state is it in? Does it need to be reloaded? How much ammo do I have?
Especially in a game like this, where you're essentially scrounging ammo all the time.
Knowing how long it's going to be before you need to make sure you break off combat and go scrounge ammo is incredibly important.
Josh Goode would like to say that a Blocktober seems to have become a popular outlet for
demystifying the celebrity of level designer, so that we so often see attributed to players.
Do you feel that the deconstruction of level design to its most basic components has given
both existing and prospective devs a common ground for evolving the profession?
Yeah, sure.
I mean, as an art form, it doesn't advance unless people deconstruct it and put it back
together.
We don't get fresh blood to have new ideas in level design unless people are finding new avenues into it, right?
So, yeah, to me it's as simple as that.
Now, to be fair, it's been years since I actually did level design,
and the moment-to-moment and daily concerns of a level designer are no longer mine.
I try to use my best memory there, but it's a little bit...
It's a little bit like trying to remember younger versions of yourself.
That's such an interesting sentiment.
Chat seems to really gel with the comment you made about how the gun is your character.
I guess, you know, with the knife popping out every now and then, you could...
First-person shooter characters are secretly just like a pair of arms sometimes.
They pretty much are, yeah.
Optimization-wise...
If you pulled this camera out, you're definitely not gonna see a character, right?
Because you can't afford to be animating and rendering a character that the camera doesn't see,
especially when you're pushing everything to its limit, which we definitely were in this game.
Something I'm gonna do here is, so I just quicksave.
I'm gonna quickload again, which lets me move in this cutscene.
But my favorite thing about being able to move in this cutscene is you can kill the advisor.
Oh no. Oh no!
Oh no!
Oh man, my- oh no, my brain broke.
But yeah, so
for this whole, uh, dialogue that they're explaining to you like
what the Trandoshans are doing here and stuff and uh, what you need to do next
you're just kind of
running to your next objective.
So
you basically cut the time of the level in half.
Alex Jacobson would like to know was there any thought in playtesting QA or even with yourself Harley about finding skips within levels like the ones that Utsu's done?
Oh absolutely. The numbers of skips, I mean that's 90% of a level designers job once you've got, once you're at the point where you're only fixing bugs is QA goes in and finds skips and they show, and you just can't believe some of them right?
It's just a huge, enormous part of that process.
Some of these, I find myself wondering,
and I can't tell if this is the developer's bias
or if this is a possibility and it's real.
I find myself wondering if difference in processors
and clock speeds and hardware made things possible now
that weren't possible on the machines
we were running at the time.
And I honestly don't know the answer,
but I want it to be true.
Because we worked really hard to get this as bulletproof as it could be, and some of
these are just a little bit like, oh, come on, we would have found that.
I think we would have found that.
We should have found that.
Gotcha.
Let's see here.
Uh, da da da.
Walter Giannuzzi points out, wasn't that a premise of early id first-person shooters
that you didn't have to render the character?
I'm not super familiar with some of the design history of id's early days, however, John
Romero did a talk about the early programming principles of id and you can, if you have
a conference pass, you can still go watch it because it's archived here on Swapcard
for a little bit.
You can just pop in, watch it, it's like you were there.
Uh, let's see, um, Alex Dudman is replying to Gabe that, uh...
It's programmed that the you know, the advisor shows up in the game as a hologram
But they're still treated as a character by by the game itself
Yeah, that's obviously the very simple explanation for that. It's just very funny to so so there you saw a little bit of my
Squad organization I put o7 all the way back there on that sniper terminal. Yeah, so that I could
Tell him to hack a console that was basically right next to him
Mm-hmm
Yeah, I love the forethought about,
if I've got him there, then he's right next to it kind of stuff.
That's why this is my favorite level in the entire run.
Just overall, the assault ship just has a lot of that,
like playing the game in the way that the devs
truly wanted the player to be experiencing these clones.
Yeah.
I'm gonna actually put something up this level. This is levels of detention area
which the clones joke about like is the translations of the heat. This is also a
level that visually maps itself to the aesthetics behind A New Hope and the
intention area on the Death Star. Harley I'm sort of curious because I know that
like some of that is also the art team and you know how they choose to make it
make an area look after you all gray box it.
Where, when you're working with an IP like this,
like how do you navigate these opportunities
when you sort of realize like,
hey, we have the opportunity to draw
from an existing art style or an existing space
to help players contextualize it?
Oh, and I guess you drop into a garbage chute too, duh.
And what's sort of your thought process behind that?
I know you didn't directly work on this level,
but I'm sure you were, saw some of it.
I mean, before you sit down, hopefully,
before you sit down to even do your paper map of the level at the very beginning,
you understand the area that the level will be in,
so that you understand the sorts of architecture that you can use to direct the player.
We absolutely knew that this was going to be a detention area.
I do remember some discussion about whether it was cool to actually go down the garbage chute,
but, you know, it wasn't.
The reality was, the conversation was about,
is it cooler to be able to actually experience that?
Or is it more tropey and maybe would make people feel like,
oh yeah, here's another garbage chute.
And we made the guess that it would be cooler
to be able to experience that.
And it was absolutely borne out in playtesting, right?
But finally getting to do what Han and Luke and Leia do
at the beginning of New Hope.
Yeah, yeah, everybody wants to do that, right?
We were all, we were all eight when that was,
oh yeah, no, right,
and now here the real adventure begins, so.
Yeah, it's where the movie becomes a creature feature
and not just a running gun.
Right.
In terms of how you navigate that stuff generally, like when you're working with a known IP,
the more recognizable your areas can be, the more players who know those IPs are going to be able
to navigate your level design, again, your architectural, you know, they'll be able to
make sense of your architecture without being super confused by it. If this room didn't have
that great big open to space window out there so that it reads as a hangar.
you wouldn't know where to look for the guns in case an enemy ship comes in, etc.
So all of that, all of those contextual clues are things you can draw off of in a known IP,
and especially if you're talking about an IP that's likely to have fans playing the game
because they saw the movie, watched the TV show, read the book, whatever, and they already have
innate knowledge about the function of a space. That's everything you want. That's just gravy
where your players get to walk into a space and feel clever.
in a way that you would have to work really hard for otherwise.
I really appreciate the hangar example and another point is because it's a big wall of
space, even if you're not a Star Wars aficionado and you're just here because you like a good
Xbox shooter, it's a wall, right?
It's just a wall.
If you walk up to it, you're not going to get sucked down into the vacuum or the force
field won't go down.
Careful, she might do that later.
Also, this level I'm playing now, this is my absolute favorite portion of the speedrun.
And it's not even that fast, it's just really nice to just sit through because it's so optimized.
But something that just happened there that I have no idea why it happens, when you go
down that little ramp into that little chute, for some reason your squad will always shift
into search and destroy.
for some reason, and I have no idea why.
I can tell you probably why.
I'm not 100% sure that I'm right about this,
but I'm pretty sure I'm right.
One of the earlier you asked,
why, what were some of the pivots
that you ended up making when you made the game?
And putting the squad,
defaulting the squad into Search and Destroy
was one of them.
We had a playtest where we had pretty much everything working, pretty much all the levels put together.
You know, there was polish and stuff to do, but we understood what the game was generally.
We had a playtest, and we had a team playthrough, and some of the feedback that we got that was pretty concerning at the time was,
it doesn't really feel like a squad game. Like, I can hear them, but I never see them.
and I don't really feel like I'm part of a squad.
And the directors, they would, maybe not every milestone,
but periodically they would do a sort of a half day off site
where they'd take feedback like that
and they'd really think about it and hash it out
and come back and like, okay, here's the plan.
They took that feedback away.
They came back and they said,
we think we have the right answer.
We think the plan is to just,
basically every time you move into a new section of the game,
to default to search and destroy, so that they'll run in front of you,
you see your squad do stuff, you remember they're there, you remember to put them on
the maneuvers, etc. and it worked beautifully. It was an
incredibly simple code change, and we had been discussing some very
complicated solutions, but it really did the trick in terms of
reminding you you're in a squad, showing you what your squad can do,
putting you in context of what they're going to do. This is my favorite level,
this map level, this section is my favorite section of the game.
Yeah, so the reason why this is my favorite is because you pop a uh one of the mines on one of
these things here over there so at the moment that the normal droids come out of there they um
they blow up all four of those and immediately kill their own drop pod. You position these guys
here so they're just in as far away as they can be and then you put someone else right there so
that they're right next to the
the force field power generator so at the moment it's available you can just
tell him to blow it up and then he'll just be right next to it.
Yeah, that's playing like the level designer, like absolutely.
It's so nice and choreographed.
But it's funny, that's my favorite section of the game as well but for
totally different reasons. I love the fact that I have to plate spin
for what it feels like forever and just not
mess even one thing up in order to get through it.
That was a boss by the way, he was so hard.
little environmental storytelling is running away. I love how this is the part of the game where you
start to notice like there's actually like when you're in those hallways there's like these lines
at the top of the camera um because they're right above the character head that like leads you through
the space um and they just feel they feel like almost like they're yanking you forward uh there's
such an interesting like psychological like if you're watching when you're watching someone else
play this it'll be real and not playing it yourself you realize that there's psychological
things that pull people around um yeah
your brain factors onto even if you aren't consciously grabbing onto it.
Yeah. I wonder if it'll be relevant. I want to chat a little bit about
way back there you turned right and you saw
a dead Jedi with a lightsaber. One of the things that reminded me
of is that
job description or when they put up a job rep for a new level designer at LucasArts,
part of the job description was always, do you know why players always turn right instead of left?
It was a very specific, and I honestly don't know if it's true, but I still believe it because it
was just, it is known amongst the level designers at LucasArts that people always turn right instead
of left, and then, and so you have to put an end of a hallway there so that they know.
to hang a left which is why we put that there we knew everybody would see it because that you know
conventional wisdom was they're going to turn right oh that's so fascinating uh because uh a
because um i was talking with um
Bill Gardner of 2K a while back about T-sections in level design and his thoughts about those.
I know that when I turn right as a player I'm often like,
okay, well that's the way forward, I need to look for the goodies.
But I feel like that might just be like a follow-up reaction to what you were designing at the time,
which is a response to what players were doing before goodies were being placed in that sense.
It's certainly possible. I mean, you put a goodie at the end of a thing so a player knows that there's nothing else there, right?
It's not necessarily to make sure they have enough ammo, though. You do have to do that as well.
So I don't know where that loop is. It's a little bit of a chicken and egg question.
Do players turn right because they know there are goodies there, or do we put goodies there because we know players are going to turn right?
Yeah. Oh, my brain just broke a little. Oh my god, that's like...
It's like you said.
It's like on the Wish Came First, chicken or the egg.
Yeah.
It's like you said, secrets of the universe.
No, Dave was not saying yesterday secrets of the universe.
You were saying from the looking glass.
If we're going game development terms, I guess we've crossed the magic circle.
Good old turret hack coming up again.
Chad is also...
Oh my goodness, yeah. Dave has an interesting consideration question.
Is it true in the UK and Australia where turning left on the car is easier than turning right?
I don't know if anyone's from the UK or Australia.
I don't think we can adequately answer that, but I guess, I wonder if that has something to do with our perceptions of left and right across different countries.
Yeah, I don't know the answer to that, but it would be interesting. I wonder if you could get a grant for that study.
Funny enough, this tank that's coming up right now, popping up on the elevator, I have a little Lego, I have a Lego one of those down there on my left, one of the, I think it's the first one they released from the Revenge of the Sith quite a lot.
It's missing a few pieces and it got beat up in the moves that we had to do.
But this game is just such a visual feast for like,
I remember when this was my obsession, when these things were what I loved thinking about.
Yeah.
Is this the only full-size... I don't know if this is the only one in the game.
I don't remember. You might be able to see them from a distance.
Sheep and maybe...
I know that on Kashyyyk you see like the Torrent fighters for the first time.
It's so interesting to see them rendered because they show up in the Clone Wars TV show so
much now.
Like, you know, there's like that, the way they look there is burning my brain.
It's funny to see the same silhouette.
But just, you know, like rendered in UE2 as opposed to the animation of Clone Wars.
Like all the little details like that where it's like,
oh, we made this one asset for this one scene,
and it looks this way,
and it clearly looks like the thing that's in the movie.
I actually now don't even remember.
So I know this game would have shipped right,
you know, in between the two movies.
And now I'm just having a Star Wars nerd out moment.
I don't remember if the Torrents were in episode two,
but I do remember that they were in the
first animated TV series that aired on Cartoon Network
with like the little short micro episodes.
So now I'm just having a whole bunch of like, wait, when was this?
When was this show?
Yeah, I can't go that deep into that nerd rabbit hole.
I'm sorry.
It's okay.
I'm in the rabbit hole by myself.
Yeah, sometimes you end up there.
Oh, JD4, were there any elements in the level design ladder,
or excuse me, were there any elements in the level design,
like the ladder on the tank where you had to extrapolate from the cannon,
or from what Lucasfilm handed you, to realize it in the game world?
Because that ladder is definitely, he's right, the ladder that you climb up into the tank
is definitely like a, oh, of course there'd be a ladder.
Right.
But it's not something that I think is shown elsewhere.
I mean, yes.
I hate to generalize so much, but in some ways that's what level design is, right?
Here's a room with a function, now let's put a fight in that room, and how do we use the
function of the room to give coherence to the fight, right?
Here's an object with a function, etc.
The one that I think, in my memory, was the one that really...
I had to think about a lot was the elevators in Kashyyyk.
It seemed really weird to me that Wookiees would need elevators,
but we're not Wookiees, and we have to get up and down some way, right?
And it didn't necessarily feel like it was going to be a great choice to have a huge amount of shoe leather
in order to just go up.
By shoe leather, you mean like ramps and stairways?
Well, yeah, just a lot of walking and running, right?
Yeah.
Shoe leather is...
Like, unless you can fill it with action, nobody wants to walk forever, right?
Yeah.
And so we ended up with elevators, and it works out fine, and they actually work as
a pretty nice progress bar through that section of the game.
Okay, going up another elevator, going up another elevator, ooh, I'm going up another
level.
But initially, I remember being convinced that wasn't going to work.
Yeah. Bradley Ellis would like to know, when you designed levels, what was your philosophy for designing cover? That's a great question, and I love it.
Me personally, it was give the player enough agency that they can do what they want to do with their squad, right?
We had these mechanics where you could essentially have three extra guns going at once.
And I didn't just want to have, well, here's three cover spots
where you can put your three squad members,
and that'll help you.
I wanted players to be able to really choose
how they were going to take on different challenges.
That was partly because I had the advantage
of getting to play nearly complete levels before I even
started making mine, because I came onto the team.
I wasn't on the team during pre-production, I came on as production started.
In terms of the player being able to use cover, I at the time tended to be a real run-and-gun
player where basically my play pattern was find all the ammo and use all the heal stations.
So I probably actually...
In terms of philosophy, probably my philosophy was don't put enough cover in to keep people moving.
That may also, that feels like sort of a remnant. Games changed a lot in this time. Cover got a lot more important
compared to the Doom days where cover was
cover? Doom? What? No, you- you- it's rip and tear, baby. Um, we're coming up on Kashyyyk,
uh, for folks in chat, just a heads up. We still have a little bit of time left in the run, but
we will be coming towards the end. I suggest start asking questions. Um, uh, Harley, when we talked
before, uh, the show, you- you- you told us that Kashyyyk, uh, the camp that's coming up and then
the- the tree at the end are the areas you built by hand.
So feel free to just go in and start telling stories if there's anything you want to tell us about making this.
Sure. Getting this barbeque creature was a major coup for me.
I really wanted to show that Trandoshan's relaxing as a way of letting you walk into this space and be relaxed,
so that we could do a little bit of ramping up the excitement.
But it was late, and there really wasn't a lot of budget or scope for Trandoshan food.
But somebody did me a huge favor and made me that barbecued lizard creature,
for which I will forever be grateful.
I always think about that when I'm interviewing devs about games,
because I'm always keeping an eye on it now after hearing a story from TJ Fixman about Insomniac,
about how something that, if you think about it like a physical object,
yeah, sure, we could probably like...
make a fake Trandoshan creep, you know, like just a bit of barbecue or something, like some gross meat.
Like, yeah, we can whip that up in 30 minutes.
In video games, in ARK, you want me to do what? From one thing? From how much?
Yeah.
Yep.
That was a- that was- that was a carefully crafted ambush, which you basically skipped most of, as you can see.
Oh, that's why I got so excited when I watched...
I'm just...
What this run looks like on Kashyyyk is so different from the...
Kashyyyk is the most, uh...
We don't care about your effort, we want to go fast level.
I keep wondering why that is under the hood, like, why does the gunship,
you know, why does the capital ship have such linear sections versus...
Kashyyyk has open ones, but I don't want to speculate, uh...
I probably won't do that.
I'm kind of thinking it's mostly just due to the open nature of it all.
The ship is kind of closed in so there's nothing to really climb on while this has a lot of
hills that you can climb and stuff like that.
Yeah, we definitely wanted to change the feel so that you felt like you were outside and
so some of that stuff comes from needing to be able to do that for sure.
That's one of those explosions that hurts you.
I wasn't back far enough.
Oh yeah, I love how giant the Wookiees are in this game.
Yeah.
They look like bodybuilders.
You don't get to stand next to a Wookiee very often.
You want to make it count, right?
Hey, go to Galaxy's Edge when it's safe to again, and you can do that there because Chewy won't drown.
Oh yeah, so something fun I'm going to do in this next level, for the longest time they could figure out how to get the...
Press the walk button to make the zip line stop moving you to work on this level.
But once this... Oh, dude, get off me.
Once this... Once the quicksave quickload thing was found...
They finally found the way.
And now you can just kinda... pop.
And you know, through this level you kinda go all the way around rescuing Wookiees from...
from their...
their cages.
You just, uh... walk through.
Yeah.
This is my carefully, carefully crafted...
uh, BSP.
Wow.
Well, at least you get to see that the entire level is actually spatially coherent, which
is a little bit rare, and that it all fits in the space that it's supposed to fit in,
in real space.
I'm gonna say it cheerfully.
This is also another fun thing.
I'm actually gonna run through this in the intended way, just to give viewers at least
a perspective for how much this is skipping.
So, oh yeah, so we get to see, yeah.
Thank you, thank you, it's really nice of you.
I actually, absolutely, oh, that's so close.
I absolutely love the noises
that the Wookiees make in the sound.
They always sound so sad.
They sound like, oh, why is this happening?
I was having a good morning.
So here, I'm gonna quick save.
What you're supposed to do is just come to this window,
see Grievous, and then you blow this up.
been spotted get down there or general kenobi hello there the amount of time that i spent making sure
that you had to see grievous before you could continue on you would just be flabbergasted
but yeah so so you do that you come through here you know there's that guy there so you
see tar fall and you know you you blow this up where are they taking him
I can't get over the Wookiee sounds, they just...
They sound in such distress.
Sounds so sad.
They're being, uh...
I mean, I wish the sound... I know, um, I remember Brett got the sound team on, uh...
Some of the sound folks on his run, and, uh...
they were talking about some of their work.
And I'd love to know which of these were pulled
from the LucasArchives, from Ben Bird's work,
and which of these were cooked up or inspired by it.
Because it's always interesting to mix.
So you do all that.
But what you do for the run is you do not look at Grievous.
It is very bad to look at Grievous.
Don't look at Grievous.
Don't scare Grievous.
Do not look at Grievous.
Just kidding.
Jump over here.
Don't verify Grievous' presence on Kishi.
Yeah.
You acknowledge Tardhole exists.
You walk back.
You come through.
Then you look at Grievous.
Yes, of course you do, because it's the cutscene of Grievous.
You tap that on there.
You throw that.
And then...
And then these guys just stand here and let you spam them.
Not usually. You have to use the shock grenade to stun them.
Which is interesting because the shock grenade, it's also damaging you, right? Or it's supposed to be so you don't want to stand by it?
It is, but it's pretty insignificant compared to the effects that it gives.
Just this thinking of how I would have played this, I don't stand by the grenades I throw where I try not to.
I mean, I do in Apex Legends, who am I kidding? I blow myself up.
But runners and other fast- oh god, the fighter has no collision.
It actually does.
Oh, right here in the center, yeah.
It's fascinating.
I can verify, I'm pretty sure that's an honest hack that shipped in the game, having been
the one who tried to set that up to be bulletproof.
Yeah.
It was.
These scavenger droids are the worst to deal with.
Now this section was not my level. I did help a little bit with bug fixing. I don't think I helped with optimization at all.
Gotcha.
So there are parts where I'm like, yeah, I know this part really, really well because I ended up, you know, painstakingly doing a thing.
Oh, now I feel bad.
But not most of it. Most of it, I'm just gonna be able to enjoy it without the...
without the... no, don't feel bad, right?
Like, we do this because we want people to have fun,
and fun means different things to different people.
It's all good.
Um, JD Ford in chat, uh, says,
watching someone just slip through your meticulous design
must be equally frustrating and morbidly fascinating.
I mean, I just want to go back in time and fix it.
That's all.
I do. Oh, God. Yeah.
Gabe wants to know if you can kill Grievous with that pack.
No, you Grievous does not have a health bar or anything like that.
Yeah, Grievous is just a he's he's the moving equivalent of a prop.
That's right. Hey, that's true in real life, too.
In the movies. Grievous is is horribly pathetic
in the movies and the Clone Wars compared to his 2D Clone Wars variant.
Yeah, I remember.
I believe 2D Clone Wars was out about the same time as this.
Oh, hello, Army.
Good to meet you.
Was out at about the same time as this.
And so seeing Grievous was like, oh, shoot, it's that guy.
Oh, man, we better be careful around him.
And then he came out for three in the, oh, that's going to hurt.
For three in the Clone Wars.
Everyone's just like, he's not as scary as he's supposed to be.
Okay, I need to deal with these guys.
Gotcha.
Setting up the Grievous Guards was one of the most fun things
for me as a level designer.
They were just so fun.
They were unlike,
they operated unlike any other level in the game.
And for me, that stuff is always really interesting, right?
Take a new ingredient and try to blend it in
a dish that's already being served as it were.
The Magna Guards are such an interesting design component because they're not Jedi characters,
but they use Jedi-ish weapons, but they're droids, so they're melee, but they're melee
fighters and this is a gun game, so watching different games, like, try to figure out how
to put them in.
There we go.
Oh no.
Uh oh.
Nice.
We're off the map.
You have to know where you're going.
Um, I think sound to navigate.
No, I'm using this wall here and I, I wasn't hugging it quite as well as I should be.
Gotcha.
Here we go.
Um, uh, Alex Jacobson wants to weigh in with a lot of glitch hunters within speed
running communities actually have a lot of knowledge about how games work, whether
it's dev experience, QA experience, and how that's how they find a lot of exploits
is wondering.
I wonder if someone forgot to stop this.
At least that's to Alex's knowledge,
it's obviously not true for all runners.
Absolutely, right?
And even if you haven't worked in the industry,
once you've found a few of these,
you start seeing the kinds of ways that we think
and it opens up new horizons.
I'm sure this isn't consistent across the discipline, but in my experience, a lot of level designers are super organized thinkers because you have to be able to manage huge amounts of data.
And you have to be aware at any time of like, what is the player's objective? What tools do they have? You know, what do they know? What do they not know, etc, etc.
And so that's going to lead you to setting things up in a specific way that people who have.
uh... who have less of a tendency to organize stuff in that way are going to
be able to exploit
you're going to leave holes in the way you've got stuff set up
uh... uh...
let's see
uh...
i'm looking at chat uh... matthew's
oh no go for it
so there you saw me do the quick save quick load to be able to skip the zipline portion
and here i'm actually using the
I didn't do that right. I'm actually using the game's physics to skip hacking this console here that has the crane move.
I did that too early.
So you just shoot this.
And as they spawn, release it.
And then it drops it onto him.
rather than mean to come over here and hack this, which you can still hack this and still
move the crane despite there being nothing on it anymore.
Right.
That's good implementation right there.
Chad is discussing uh how come the clone advisor was killable um but Grievous was not um uh um
Kisan Kisan Kian George I don't know if it's Gorge or George.
Keon Gorge says, uh, they think Grievous is different because he's unique in the game
and there are plenty of clones of health bars and hitboxes elsewhere in the game because they
obviously interact with, uh, the droids in some combat scenarios. Okay, we're just walking through
the lab again, I see. That doesn't even save time or anything, it's just fun for messing around.
This level is what I call a whole W level. A what? A whole W level. You just hold the forward key
because...
There's no skips or tricks, just kind of walking through it.
I hold out the pistol here because it just doesn't use ammo.
Gotcha, yeah.
And the most combat I do is against little scavenger droids.
I guess the pistol also, it uses less camera time,
so if you're trying to keep an eye on the environment.
Yeah, I thought at first they did it
because it makes you move faster, but no.
I kind of wish that was the case, though.
I feel like a whole lot more unique movement
would also come into play sometimes
with just pulling out the pistol.
Um, Harley, I don't know if you remember anything about the cell.
We can jam on like, like the pistol game.
I remember games from this era were very like, okay, you have your general gun.
You have your situational guns, uh, that play your, like maybe guns of higher
skill uses that can then be used more broadly, um, like this game, sniper
attachment, um,
But the pistol is always the fallback for when you run out of ammo.
And that convention has changed a lot.
But it feels like a leftover thing from Doom where the pistol was just sort of your little backup if you could not find ammo and you needed to do something.
Yeah, absolutely. In some ways it was.
It's also worth remembering that this game was a game that was intended to be...
reaching a Star Wars audience, not necessarily a shooter audience.
We expected to include shooters among them, but there were a lot of Star Wars fans at the time,
especially new Star Wars fans that didn't necessarily have a really sophisticated shooter
skill base. And so we needed to make sure that if Push came to shove and they had
wasted all their ammo or used it on something...
that they had a way to try to get to the next ammo drop, to try to get to the next load,
etc.
And so, you know, as you do when you're making games, you look at existing games and you
say, how did they solve that, right?
We did not think we were going to be able to solve it just with the knife thing coming
out of your hand, because that's actually a pretty difficult skill in and of itself,
and there are enemies that it's pretty hard to kill that way.
as you've proven today, Lister, can kill anything that way if you know how.
Speaking on something about designing shooter stuff, something I was paying attention to
on Utsu's run actually weirdly lines up with an experience I have playing Respawn's Apex
Legends right now.
I'm just giving awful off to Respawn.
Oh yeah, this is bad.
This is something.
Yeah, you can just climb up here and...
I don't feel like playing this level today.
I don't like this one.
Something is happening where every time I'm about to bring up the very specific question I'm about to ask,
Usu's just like, okay, let's break everyone's brains visually.
Yeah, that's a lot of these levels, unfortunately.
There's just no real time for breaks to make.
You'll notice I'm leaving them behind a lot here,
despite there being nothing really that would affect them going forward.
That's because I need them to be at full health.
It's very important that they're at full health.
Aha! Fascinating. Interesting.
For the upcoming bridge section that they keep bringing up.
Yep, that bridge section is the hardest in the game, I think.
So yeah. We'll see how you break the last level.
It's actually really difficult. It's got a lot of finagling and strategy to it.
Yeah, it is.
Here you'll see.
You really have to have the whole picture for this bridge level.
I'll be fascinated to see how you take it on.
it's it's very choreographed uh and if and it's really frustrating sometimes because uh
sometimes uh droids don't go the they don't dance the dance so you're just like you you're not in
place what are you doing
I'm gonna bring up my question really quick while we get going on the bridge.
When you watch Utsu zoom in with the assault rifle or aim in on the assault rifle,
you see like a pretty significant muzzle flare there.
And I've begun to notice in shooters when the flare is so bright that I actually have trouble seeing my opponent,
especially in a PvP game.
Harley, do you remember any discussions about that, that animation effect,
when you were working on Republic Commando?
I don't necessarily remember anything specific to that.
We played...
The team played the multiplayer portion every Friday for like the second half of the day.
We needed to make sure they were, as they say these days, eating their own dog food.
I don't think that's what we called it back then.
And we gave a lot of feedback about how stuff that was working in the single-player portion of the game
might be getting in the way in the multiplayer.
Most people on the team were pretty avid multiplayer shooter players.
But I don't remember that one specifically.
It might have been because I think we had a tendency, and this will not surprise you,
knowing how much love we put into O7's story, we had a tendency as a team to be either sniper
or whatever the heavy, I don't remember what that thing is called, anti-armor.
The DC-17.
Yeah, yeah.
And so I'm not sure that that would have gotten the due diligence that it really needed to get that level of polish, if that makes sense.
That's good. I actually know some, spoken to some other developers, that muzzle flare is often tweaking it as an intentional thing sometimes.
But yeah. Bradley Ellis would like to know, was there an enemy that was hard to design around based on their difficulty to the player?
Yes. It's a surprising answer. I think I'm the only level designer who got to use every enemy
in the game in a level because of the last level. It's basically an old home week for enemies.
And honestly, the hardest one to design around were the Geonosian young things that come out
of the eggs. They're surprisingly hard for players to hit.
They move fast and they can do a lot of damage, especially if you've got more than one of
them, surprisingly quickly.
And so being able to put enough of them in the room that they feel creepy enough to commensurate
to the amount of damage they can do to you very quickly actually turned out to be quite
a challenge.
Something I remember, now we're past the bridge, we sort of just rolled past it, but the, uh, something I appreciate in the way that sequence plays out is that, you know, you go to blow the bridge,
you click the button, the charge doesn't go off, and everyone panics, and that feels like one of the most authentic, uh, you know, everyone from the clones to the advisor panics.
Um, and I feel like that broad spread, like, wait, what do we do, is one of the neatest.
Games in general, I love it when they're like,
oh, you complete an objective, but something went wrong,
and now you have to upend it.
Like, it's just such a good tension-raising thing.
I definitely really like the dialogue in that part.
I was actually just thinking about that as it happened.
I really like how just genuine 38 sounds
when he's just like, what, misfire?
Who packed that charge?
Who is the idiot who did that?
Yeah, Mike Stemmly, who wrote a good portion of this game's dialogue, really did just an amazing job.
When we came to him and said,
Okay, so we have this huge challenge where we had essentially a character that was one character,
but now has to be differentiated, and you have to feel like you're part of this brotherhood, blah blah blah,
can you do it? And you don't have very much time.
Just did an amazing job.
you know, as a level designer, you come up with,
this is the function of this line that I need.
As you go through your level, you send it off,
you get it back.
And I can remember so clearly getting my lines back
and being like, this stuff is great.
I absolutely love all the dialogue and just the voice.
I love just clones in general.
I think clones are way cooler than stormtroopers.
I think they're cooler than rebels.
I think they're cooler than droids.
They're just my favorite military form.
the entire series.
I remember hearing a Disney infinity designer saying it ran
into a really weird problem when they were making a Star Wars
Disney infinity product, which was
they hit a weird age gap between how some players approached their levels, because obviously,
depending on which line of Star Wars they're making content for, you were shooting Stormtroopers
or you were fighting with clones, and they hit a point where younger players who grew up with
the prequels and the Clone Wars, so people slightly younger than I think me and Utsu,
were struck, were not as, they didn't view white armor as bad guys by default.
I forgot the full context of the quote, so I'm paraphrasing, but I was like, that blew my mind
because I was like, you know, to me, white armor is by default evil and it's not like, you know,
when the Clone Wars came around, you know, but like that, like the link between these friendly
clones and the Stormtroopers was something I appreciated but didn't, you know, internalize.
But if you go up with the Clone Wars and like Captain Rex was like your action figure or
something, that's, that's different than what I had.
Yeah, yeah, visual languages. Go ahead.
I'm gonna skip a trigger that makes it so I don't have to blow up that door.
Nice!
Because I quick-saved and quick-loaded.
Uh-huh.
And I'm coming up on some really fun just parkour that skips a little bit of fights.
Which, the jumps look really, really hard, but they're actually surprisingly easy.
Mm-hmm.
It's interesting because he's not like jumping.
I love that high jump, jump kick the Wookies just did.
Yeah.
All right, go ahead.
Wookie martial arts.
But here we go.
Oh my goodness.
Nice.
And here it goes again.
La la la la la.
Yeah, just these droids are like, all right, let's get this club.
What is he doing?
Where is he going?
What?
These commandos are weird.
I always like, I always think of game AI as sort of being like,
you know, like a working schmuck in a way, because they're always
they're like, OK, we got to pretend to do the thing.
Like the very Wreck-It Ralph, like, you know, showing up for a reboot,
the Canadian animated show.
And that, to speedrunners, especially like, like just a player
who is absolutely disregarding the setting and fiction.
And it's amusing.
It kind of makes me wish a little bit that this IP had allowed us, uh, fictionally to do Bloodgates,
but it wasn't a thing. I mean, a few places we did with hacking consoles and stuff, but, um,
you know, it doesn't really make sense very much in the IP.
Uh, Bloodgates. Do you mean, like, the keycard hunting of Doom?
No, I mean, basically, like, we're just not gonna let you out of this room. We're not gonna
let the exit be openable until you've killed everything in this room that needs killing,
right?
Got it, yeah.
I thought of more.
That's it, yeah? Like you have to gather the resource from the enemies to kill them?
Yeah.
And it just puts a cap on that.
Yep.
Oh no.
To your comment about white stormtroopers being evil or not evil, those are the kinds
of details that...
But usually an IP gives you an advantage on, right?
Everybody knows the visual language of this thing.
And so you don't have to teach your players
to shoot the guys in white or not shoot the guys in white
because they all know, they all saw the movie.
But when you talk about a movie that has a history,
or an IP that has a history that spans
that many changes in the universe
and people being more or less familiar
with different time periods,
it's really hard to get a shared context
so that you can take advantage of the IP in that way.
And it's interesting because if you think about it from like a writing and thematic standpoint,
like everything that happens is so functional, but like the movies also aren't free from, you know, relying on visual language.
They need you, the audience, to understand, you know, morally or thematically what's going on.
And there's conversations about what the prequels, you know, sort of do well, do less well.
And the fact that they did, you know, get a generation of kids to sort of...
attached to these characters. It's, um, culturally, uh, if you go on what's Star Wars TikTok and you
watch like kids even younger than the prequel kids, you know, learning about Star, you know,
who growing up with Star Wars and making their videos and jokes and references, A, they're
hilarious. Um, B- I love that such a thing exists as Star Wars TikTok. Yeah. Um, so sorry to
interrupt but, uh, so here I'm doing something kind of interesting where, uh, I'm jumping over
a trigger that spawns super battle droids. Uh-huh.
Um, so that Tarfful doesn't die.
And I'm also making sure my, uh, my troopers don't, uh, don't come in.
So they also don't hit the triggers because, uh, clone troopers can hit.
The, the squad can hit trick.
This is not this hard to jump over.
It wasn't with me.
Um, leaning, trying to get you up over it.
I want to see, I know this isn't that hard.
I know you can't see it too also, but sometimes when you do a thing that I did a hundred times
or you don't do a thing, I'm like doing this, like, especially when you trigger an explosion
and you're right up in front of it, I'm like leaning away from the screen.
So yeah, so you skip the trigger.
Tarfful can't hit the trigger that spawns Super Violet Droids.
Oh shoot, I didn't click save.
Let me do this again.
Okay, there.
I remember watching this section and seeing how difficult this whole thing can be.
I mean, at least it's not a bug you can just stumble into. You've really got to want it.
Yeah, I feel like those ones are more forgivable. Like the ones that you really have to force. There we go.
Yeah, so Tarfful can't hit triggers.
So, you come over here. You jump around this.
and you can just kind of skip this room a little bit by just shooting this a lot.
Oh boy. And it just destroys it. Oh boy.
And Harley, I'm pretty sure those those barrows were just meant to say to players,
don't come over here, don't come over here. Pretty much. Yeah right, you'd have to come in and some...
But now you're getting triggers.
These Trandoshans have a lot more health than normal Trandoshans.
I don't know why they have so much more health.
I don't either.
Probably to make this a little bit of a mini boss fight with the Grievous Guard there.
The first time I saw this enemy, you know,
I think I had not been believing we were going to be able to pull this off.
So, I mean, it still had a lot of bugs and a lot of work to go, but the first time I saw this
anime with what the animators and the AI programmer had managed to do, I was just so excited. I
couldn't wait to make this guy hoppity-jumpity-flippity around my levels.
Watch, I love how Utu, like, in the record run that Utu holds,
you can watch her try to get this guard to actually jump down.
Because, oh, I don't have record at all.
I have fourth place.
That's it. That's it.
So my recent playthrough, which is on the same difficulty,
I just looked it up right before we did this, is eight hours.
Now, to be fair, I am a very slow player, right?
I like to look at everything and I go around.
I can't stand it if there's any ammo that I didn't pick up, etc.
That's just my playstyle.
So this is less than a quarter of my playthrough on the same difficulty.
Yeah. You saw me there go to the menu and just load the chapter,
because that spawns me with more ammo, and it puts my squad at full health.
Yeah.
Right, and that's a dev cheat, I believe, right?
Because we needed to be able to just pop in
and try new stuff out and have your squad be healthy.
I think at some point we actually had to ask
for a dev cheat to give a sort of random amount of health
to your squad so that we would know what it was like
to play through the sections of your level
if you had done more or less well
in terms of keeping them healthy.
Was cooperative play ever something
that you experimented with in this game?
Not really.
Uh...
Yeah, I don't...
Yeah, I didn't think so, but...
Yeah.
It was just kind of something that popped in my head, like...
And credit to Chad. Chad's actually been asking me about co-op for a second.
I just sort of... We kept getting on other topics.
Sure.
There's talk of the sequel, which I believe has been discussed,
that a sequel was considered and then cancelled for this game.
and people in chat were asking,
oh, would the sequel have had co-op?
And it's like, well, it never got that far.
So that's not a question we can really have an answer for.
You know, the sequel could have had,
it could have had lat commando sections
where you're riding in the gunships
and shooting things for all we know.
I would so love either a sequel or a remake.
A remake with like modern day mechanics
would be really cool.
Yeah, like there's been a lot of interesting remasters
like Resident Evil and Final Fantasy
that have been revisiting old.
I'd love to see this with like,
a sprint feature added, maybe some stuff from the new Battlefront that Commandos are in
now.
Yeah, the Commandos have made the journey to EA's Battlefront 2, Harley.
The folks at DICE, DICE does those?
DICE EA?
They're still, they're keeping your boys alive.
I'm so happy that the creators of Clone Wars loved Delta Squad so much that they made them
canon before Disney's declaration of non-canon.
Yeah, the reckoning, the splits, the Legends creation.
I appreciate that as a Star Wars fan, especially when they were heading into an era that the
books had tread over so thoroughly.
I appreciate that they just needed to come out and say, we can't maintain this, guys.
This is really hard.
We need to start over.
You know, like I know Delta, Republic Commando isn't canon anymore, but that's never gonna stop the fun I have with it.
Well, Republic Commando now is canon because, um...
because of them being in the Clone Wars TV show,
which thus, by connection, makes this game canon.
I believe, oh God, I don't want to do more nerd discussions right now.
I believe, like, officially, like, this is Legends
because the events of how Kashyyyk, the Kashyyyk battle started,
had been rewritten over.
It's like how if you, um, but you know, Halo has the same problem.
They made a whole book about Fall of Reach,
and then they made the Reach, Halo Reach, the video game,
and they play out in drastically different ways,
even though I actually really like the Fall of Reach book.
It is really hard to keep a universe consistent over time, especially a long one.
I just want to insert very quickly, you're back at my level and I'm so, so glad to watch
you grinding your way up these ramps the way that I hoped people would have to do, even
in a speedrun.
I haven't been managing my ammo well, so I'm actually not taking out these super auto-droids
as efficiently as I could.
Yeah, you really want heavy armor for those.
I noticed in the recorded run that you rely on, you're constantly like, it's interesting
to see where you burn time to go back and get your grenades, you know, like you efficiently
manage the grenades and stuff, Utsu.
Like there really is a beauty, if anyone here, I found Utsu's run on speedrun.com, if you
want to watch Utsu, like really just like show what's going on, there's obviously other
runners in there you can watch and appreciate too, I just don't know their names.
But the balance of like and like the weaving between them,
you know, the skips, but the the ammo management,
like there's really every runner we've had on this week.
Bubbles, Delphoi, Go, Dave Stereo, the work,
like this is a skip and I've been treating this
like this is a skill.
This isn't just like I'm coming asking someone to come on
and play a game.
That's how I've been thinking and I've been appreciating
that this whole time this whole week.
It's been such a blast.
Watching you walk up and stab that droid dispenser to death is like, you're just stabbing me in the heart.
LAUGHTER
Harley, do you have any other memories about working on this particular section?
So, this whole section, what I really wanted, like, after this, not the next step, but I think the step after,
you finally get to see the sky again, right? And I really wanted it to feel...
Essentially, I was drawing a little bit on...
on Lord of the Rings, I wanted it to feel like this is the section under the mountain
where you're just really slogging through and then it opens up again.
And also it's late game, so I wanted it to be really hard.
The space wasn't really there to put as many maneuver options as I wanted in.
in order to get all of your squad on screen firing um it was pretty difficult
gotcha so so there i just jumped over a sugar that spawns march and oceans oh yeah i wonder
what was going on with these little um uh the little like jumps over the barrels and the rocks
because when i watched you run i didn't fully understand it yeah that is uh that's just 100%
making sure that more enemies don't spawn this guy
Yeah, this guy likes to not get flash banged.
I don't know why that is.
Yeah, I don't know why.
He just kind of doesn't sometimes.
Which is really frustrating because you throw that
and you're going fast
and then suddenly your back is full of bullets.
Yeah.
And you're just kind of like, excuse me?
That's interesting because it hits the normal player too.
You know, who might be trying to rely
on flash bang grenades.
Yeah.
I wonder if he might be inside some...
collision initially that, you know, a few more seconds it would be fine, but he's inside
collision and so from his perspective he's not getting hit by the collision of the grenade
when it goes off.
Harley, we have a question from chat, Dave Packers back again, how does it feel to watch
people, I mean you sort of said this when they're melee cheesing the droid spawners,
but how does it feel to watch people melee cheese other enemies like the super battle
droids or the droidekas?
I mean, sometimes, especially when it's a thing that I'm like,
oh man, I know exactly what I could have done to fix that.
It's a little bit hard, but mostly it's just great to watch people
taking this bit of software and finding new ways to have fun with it.
The idea that somebody would care enough about a game that you made
to spend as much time as you would have had to spend to just gain the knowledge, let alone the
skill to do this, is pretty great, right? Just imagining the many, many hours of somebody working
to get this far. We are now in the heart of the Citadel, which I believe makes for moving closer
and closer to the end of the game.
We've got a little, we have officially 23 minutes left in the schedule, so just a reminder,
but I don't quite know how that relates to where Utsu is in the run.
Reminder for folks, if you have questions for Harley, questions for Utsu, throw them
in chat, we are still grabbing them, even if Utsu and I stop every five minutes to geek
out about Star Wars, because you can't stop me.
Gabe throws in that the droidekas in particular have an exploit where if you run up to them,
they can't shoot you because the guns stick through your body.
Ew.
So that wasn't working correctly, so I'm loading just an autosave real quick.
A lot of things just haven't been working right in this game.
I don't know why.
Look, it's GDC Summer, it's every unexpected thing that can happen will happen.
It's GDC 2020.
This is how we do GDC this year.
It's everything going wrong in these uncertain times.
We are all learning to be the most flexible versions of ourselves.
There we go.
Oh, I know what I was doing wrong.
I was quicksaving, pressing E, then quickloading.
When I need to press E, then quicksave, quickload.
So...
Is this a hack or a fighting game combo?
So this...
I'm...
So, Geonosian Elites are supposed to spawn here,
but they don't.
I don't remember exactly the reason.
I was told the reason once,
but I don't remember the reason why.
But yeah, so this is hacking,
and also I'm not holding E.
This is just going.
Nice.
Nice. Let's take a break.
I will be, I'll be 100% honest with you.
This room is my least favorite room in the game.
So the fact that you figured out how to skip it,
It's all good, man.
Yeah, so the Geonosians don't spawn, but when you finish this hack, it gives the Geonosians
a death command.
So what happens is the game is just like, here you go.
You're like, oh, thank you.
I didn't get to say this earlier, I appreciate whoever on the LucasArts animation team modeled
this and animated this gun, because the little fingers, they're just like clicky right there.
When I played this game, there's something satisfying about having that weapon out.
I was wondering what those were at first, and I learned that those are actually like,
this gun runs off of like Geonosian blood, so what it's doing is it's trying to stab
into your arm and take your Geonosian blood, but you don't have Geonosian blood.
That's why they run out and you can't just put more ammo in them.
That's, uh, that's... yeah.
And that's why Geonosian elites can just kind of keep using them over and over again.
You're like, when are you gonna run out of ammo?
When...
I kind of wish there was a mechanic where...
I understand this game was made in 2005, so I doubt there was even a thing thought about, but...
It'd be kind of cool if there was a mechanic where, like...
The more they shot at you with it, like, you'd see their health, like, slowly going down or something.
Um, it's pretty good narrative and mechanical resonance there, honestly, that little detail.
Um, actually the game was made in 2003-2004. I think we were basically done by 2005.
Right, right.
Yeah.
Jules Blumenthal says, even though we commented on how, you know, things have been going...
It's 2020, things go wrong.
Many things have gone right though on this run.
Utsu, that's a big thanks to you, and I know I'm going to thank you profusely again at the end,
but I just want to hope folks in the chat appreciate...
You know, we got some speedrunners out there in chat, so I know they appreciate,
but from the development side, I hope folks appreciate that Utsu...
What Utsu's been showing off today is something that took a lot of practice and time.
We appreciate having her with us.
Are you usually in a position where you need to talk and play at the same time when you're speedrunning in Tsuu?
Uh, not if I'm not, like, wanting to.
Yeah.
Uh, my current, uh, personal best, uh, I was quiet for.
Mm-hmm.
So...
That doesn't surprise me.
We stream games on the GDC Twitch channel and we do so while interviewing developers and I have...
After a couple years of doing it, I have a process now where I check out the game first and check out how intense it is.
And depending on the intensity, I will either grab a co-worker to help run the interview or I will pre-record my footage for the game because...
I've played games while interviewing the developers before, sometimes very intensely, and after every time the developer goes,
man, like, we have to, you know, like, when we're doing press interviews at E3 or whatever,
and people want to interview us while we're playing the game, it's impossible. I don't know how you do this.
And I'm like, yeah, I don't know either. I don't remember the interview.
Yeah, totally. I, I, very early on in my career, I realized I have to say,
look, on demos or whatever, I can either play or I can talk. I can't do both.
Oh yeah, this Wookiee has to die.
Oh, sorry, Wookiee. Oh yeah, I re- aww.
He has a rocket launcher and we need that.
That's mean.
Yeah.
That's mean, but he should have just given me that rocket launcher to begin with.
Fair enough.
It's interesting because you probably, um...
Harley, were you working on this solo again?
Yep.
Yeah, which means you probably put him in there like,
oh, let's give the player a friend to help make this fight feel authentic.
Yeah, I thought he was probably gonna get killed,
but I didn't think he was gonna get killed by the player.
Okay, I'm gonna kill my own squad, too, unfortunately.
Yeah, but they can be revived.
Right. As long as you're still alive, that's all good.
It is like, God, this is just one of those moments that feels like, um...
These Grievous Fires just aren't cooperating.
Like, they're bouncing around and out of position.
Yeah, usually they're all supposed to cluster up, like, around there.
and then uh and then they'll um i'll be able to lock on the rocket launcher and kill all three at
once but they just weren't having any of it yeah fascinating uh going to chat real quick
alex jacobson would like to say they've never had a chance to get this much insight into game
development as a speed runner so this is a cool opportunity as a runner and they're watching
their friend run a cool game oh thanks alex thank you for joining us
Matthew Miller would like to say, every time someone interjects a chat comment, they expect to hear about donations, then they remember it's GDC and not GDQ.
Game development done quick. Which, as Dylan Watson points out, is just a game jam.
I will say, I think GDQ is going on later this month, and I hope folks who have the opportunity to do so can check it out and donate to that event, because it's a neat event.
And without them organizing things, you know, we wouldn't have...
I don't think we would have found each or the other runners we've had.
Oh, we have a question. John Kruchowski would like to know, how were the levels coordinated
with the story team? Were the levels made first and then story tacked on, vice versa,
or a mixture of both? I bet it's a mixture of both. I'm interested to hear how that played out.
A little bit of a mixture of both. Mostly though, the story team led by Tip Longo,
who is the creative director.
wrote the story overall and then split the story up into gameplay parts and handed those gameplay
parts to us saying okay your job is to make it fun with gameplay and also make sure this part
of the story gets told. So we're we're coming up with a final level here on the tree part yeah the
tree climbing yeah the tree part where i if you thought i was wait what do you mean my squad's
unavailable they're already right behind me huh no oh that's that's not what i want i'm gonna load
that's a different kind of speedrun bug
Um, but uh, oh wow I'm all the way back here, interesting.
All right, I will remember the auto save, or quick save.
Um, but uh, this is, next, the last level is probably going to
hurt you a lot if simply destroying these uh, droid
dispensers does hurt you.
Because I know the last level is supposed to, like, you drop off your squad at the turrets
in reverse order of the way you got them and stuff.
And you'll see what we kind of do.
While we get back to that section, Gabe, Paf would like to ask,
did the LucasArts team ever get any pushback on concepts
like back to in-planetary weapons based on them not fitting with Star Wars?
Which I think is just a good springboard for conversations
about how you work with IP holders
and how you try to build a good partnership with them.
Yeah, I mean, I was at LucasArts for seven years
and worked on a number of games.
And for every one of those, there was always a negotiation with IP for stuff, right?
Because we were always wanting to and trying to push game mechanics sort of through.
a narrative sib, if you will, right? And so we'd come up with like, oh, well, we could just make
this happen. And so, yeah, there were always intense negotiations about that. In terms of
this particular one, I don't remember that there were any particularly vivid conversations.
I know that we spent a lot of time mechanically working on how do the back-to-tanks work,
and we started with just regular health pickups like minigames did and do at the time.
And I don't exactly remember why we arrived on this, because we really wanted you and your squad
to feel like you needed to help each other out health-wise. And it didn't make a lot of sense
to be trading...
health you are doing a look at trigger thing aren't you
yeah um this is kind of finicky at all it's a little bit of rng so
i know what's about to happen
i think that's good
Sorry, you've hijacked my brain.
I was probably in the middle of a word and I can't.
Oh, no, no, no.
I actually hardly I would appreciate if you watched this part, because I have to.
Yeah, I have to restart.
Actually, I have a hard save, so I can load that next time if I don't get it.
But yeah, this this part is a little bit of RNG
since the barrel has to
it has to fling in a way where I can both get on top of it,
but it's also high enough for me to get somewhere.
Oh, that's the wrong kind of... that's the wrong kind of nade.
Oh whoops, okay here, let me load my hard save.
Also these, uh, textures are so just...
Low, uh...
Low graphics that, uh, it's...
Hard to line up sometimes, cause I'm just kinda going off of a...
Vague smudge.
Here we go.
I'm gonna try to get this by a hair.
No, that's not gonna work.
This is the most finicky part of the run,
but the skip is very much worth it.
Yeah, again, hardly, like I said, I went in,
I was like, oh, she worked on these sections.
I watched these sections.
Uh-oh.
The textures are actually probably lower res
in this part of the game.
even on the same objects than they are in other.
Yeah, I think this will work.
This might work.
Um, here we go.
Here we go.
Let it go.
Let it go. Nice.
So you walk up here and hold it back anymore.
And a lovely look at all that Unreal Engine 2 goodness.
Yep.
Bradley Ellis would like to know,
what was your favorite level to design, Harley, and why?
I think it was this one.
I got to play with every enemy.
I actually didn't start out as the level designer for this.
Kevin Schmidt actually did the paper design
and had worked with the artist to get the layout.
But then he transferred over to be the lead level designer
and brought me in to finish it.
And so I had this whole thing where I wanted players to face every enemy they'd faced with the squad,
but to be able to use what they knew about the enemies to face them.
So 6-2 is over here now, but 0-7-40 are still back there.
I'm gonna quick save here because this egg here in particular
will sometimes fall on your head as you're trying to run through.
Or that one also will land on your head as you're trying to run through.
Oh no!
Gotta look up.
I'm just trying to make the most straightforward path through here because
you don't kill all these eggs until the very end of the hallway.
Yeah, and that's how I played this game as well when I was doing it.
yet interesting because it's kinda like it's not like you're cutting the whole
room into a to be enough to use your area of effect
actions
to handle them as opposed to grinding straight through and dealing with all the little swarms
yeah if you do that you're just gonna use up all your ammo and be really sad
so is it a different feeling
uh...
oh well actually we're at the key part of the game here so I'm gonna let this play out
sorry Alec we'll get to your question
I have a question about this turret.
Yeah.
It's fire rate feels so inconsistent.
Does it have like a set fire rate or anything or ammo count or anything?
Because sometimes it feels like it takes like five seconds for it to start firing again
after a burst.
And then sometimes it feels like if I wiggle my mouse it starts to shoot again.
Yeah, I don't know the answer to that.
It doesn't have a set ammo count because we needed people to be able to shoot this thing until it was done
because this is the end of the game and you can't finish the game until it's done.
You like my awesome destruction there?
Yeah.
And that was nothing like the last time.
That's it. That's when the run ends.
Oh no, because you have to do an evac, right?
Yeah.
You blew it up so hard there's not a trace of it.
Oh, hey Scorch.
Nice.
If you look on my ally counter, you'll see now that there are two 40s.
because he's got two arrows because uh 07 and 40 are still back at the beginning of the level
but it also spawns a 40 and a 62 as if they are rendezvousing with you.
Oh that's funny. I haven't I haven't remembered trying to script the um changes in the HUD
up until now. We wanted to show uh yeah. And time would end there. Yep.
Yep, and now we have the epilogue where sadly Sev gets left behind.
Oh man, yeah.
I believe canonically in Legends Sev survived.
I think Star Wars Galaxies patched him in as an amnesiac clone or something.
That's it.
That's the end of Star Wars Republic Commando.
Utsu, thank you so much for doing that run.
Yeah, I had a lot of fun. I missed some stuff that I wasn't expecting to miss, but it's all right.
I mean, it was awesome to get to see you do it, to get to talk to you while you did it.
And yeah, I know how hard it is to play and talk, so I think you did an amazing job.
Before we get out of here, we have a couple minutes left in our session,
so we will take some questions from chat.
First one is from Alex Jacobson.
Is it a different feeling, like seeing a skip of a level you made using a bug
that would have been a mistake of a different part of a team?
So I guess it's like, if you worked on the level, but then the bug is someone else's responsibility,
does it sort of feel different versus you going, oh, I did that myself?
Yeah, it does. I'm much more inclined to forgive somebody else's bug than my own, right?
So there's...
You know, earlier I said I wish I could go back in time and fix them.
That only applies to the bugs that I know I left in there.
And Heath Close would like to ask, you mentioned paper design,
what steps did you take to approach a level around this time?
So, I mean, I think this is probably still true across the board.
Paper design is a really important step, right?
it helps you understand the scope of the game, it helps you have conversations with other disciplines
about the efforts they're going to need to put in. I think that I did paper design for the levels in
this game in Excel because early on I discovered that I would get really particularly fussy about
making things look pretty given a tool that would allow that to happen and that that
was just an unbelievable time sink for me.
And so I started using Excel
because you could use little draw tools in Excel
and there was no possible way you could make it look pretty.
And so I could let go of that need
and just really focus and iterate on the concepts,
the ideas, the layout, the architecture, et cetera,
of the space.
And I kept using that trick for a long time.
That's one of the downsides of having architecture interest
is that.
you know, architectural drawings are gorgeous and there's really no reason to spend the time to try
to make your drawings that pretty, unless you're a trained architect, in which case it comes naturally.
Right on.
I'm going to start wrapping things up then.
For folks who watch this, thank you so much
for joining the speedrun of Star Wars Republic Commando.
Thank you to Utsu and Harley Baldwin for joining us.
Utsu and Harley, if people want to follow you,
like learn more about what you're doing now,
Utsu, your other runs, Harley, your work at Shell Games,
where should they follow you?
Where should they find you online?
You can find my Twitter.
It's is at UtsuMade.
And.
my someone else followed my dummy twitch what the hell um
and then um i'm actually gonna just stop that stream now um and then uh
what is it um you can find my actual twitch is a twitch.tv forward slash utsuwu i would
definitely for the folks who followed who somehow found the dummy account i guess probably because
we're one of
two accounts streaming Republic Commando right now.
Maybe.
I didn't think of that.
Make sure you follow Utz's main account, Harley.
Where can they find you?
I'm MsHarleyBaldwin, M-S Harley Baldwin, on Twitter.
And yeah, all of my shell games work and also some of the stuff I'm playing and
struggling with and etc.
You'll find it up there.
Right on. Thank you so much to chat for watching. Please make sure to rate this session. Give any
feedback you have, whether it's about the sound, the video, the audio, what was discussed, do it.
Thank you, Dylan, for noticing my psycho masks behind me from Borderlands. Normally I would try
and show off my cats, but I had to change cameras and this one's actually on a narrower angle.
Um, uh, with that, um, I think that's about it.
All I'll say is, um, uh, this is our last speed run for the week.
Uh, we're wrapping up GDC summer today.
Thank you all so much for joining us.
We sincerely like we've, we've worked so hard to try and make something fun for
you, something informative and seeing all these comments talking about how much
people learned from this game really makes me feel better.
Um, uh, uh, all I'll say is that other than that, um, uh, I really do feel like,
like.
we got to see something special here today with Utsu and Harley.
And I know I sort of did this partly to torture whatever developer I could get.
I was like, oh, I want to see break their game and see how their face goes.
But at the same time,
like I said, this is speed running is where the line blurs.
It's where players approach a game literally as the software is implemented,
not figuratively as the developers intend. And
I hope it's not our original idea.
Double Fine and IGN and other folks
have done runs like this.
So please go check theirs out as well.
And I can only stress enough, like, thank you.
This is cool.
This is special.
And yeah, this has been a lot of fun.
That's it.
Thank you all.
All right.
Take us home, everyone.
Bye.