I'm Hannah Nicklin and I'm really delighted to be part of this narrative design panel.
Really well curated thanks to Clara and everyone involved.
I'm the narrative designer and writer for Mutazione, which is a mutant soap opera where small town gossip meets the supernatural.
That's our tagline.
and it was released in September 2019 on Apple Arcade, PS4 and PC.
I've also been CEO and Studio Lead of Degood Fabric since GDC last year.
Just to give you a quick overview of the game,
we call it a mutant soap opera because it's very definitely, formally a soap opera.
Some people push back on that a little bit, which is interesting.
As a writer, I have to look at form and genre as quite neutral.
I wouldn't say that...
action movies are always bad, I wouldn't say that soap operas are always bad, you know, they have
qualities which you might expect from them in terms of storytelling and Mettetione is very much
considered with both the dramatic and the domestic and it's an ensemble cast story so it's very much
a soap opera in those terms and the mutant bit is fairly clear from this cast picture which you can
see here. It's a 2D adventure game mostly focused on exploration, conversations,
and with this really beautiful, magical, musical gardening mechanic folded into the story.
So in Matasiona you explore a community as a 15 year old girl called Kai. Kai sets out
at the beginning of the game to head to the community in order to care for her dying grandfather.
He thinks that he's bringing her there to train as a replacement spiritual leader for
his strange and isolated town of Park Mutants.
And by the end, both of them discover that it's all a bit more complicated than that.
And the answers are in the community itself.
So Mitassione is this world of weird and wonderful flora and fauna and a community
cast of characters of many different shapes, sizes and colours.
There are really beautiful landscapes to explore and this magical musical gardening
mechanic where you can create gardens which are procedural music engines, essentially.
where every seed that you plant adds to the procedural composition
and where each garden represents a step towards healing a fractured community.
It's also, as I said, a soap opera. It's interested in the mundane as much as the
sublime. It's about a community of people who
live alongside the consequences of the past
as well as the action of the present. There are love triangles and old wounds,
bands nights and communal barbecues. There are big life-changing events and
small
inconsequential ones. So that aside, I'd like to talk particularly about one aspect of the
narrative design with you today, something which I took to calling in conversations with the team
and in the press as I've talked more about the game in public as multiple middles. So
let me go to the next slide. Some nice gifts for you all.
Multiple Middles is how I'm articulating the narrative design structure that I used in
Mitassi and I to support that soap opera ensemble cast community-driven dramatic story. So at the
same time as providing a linear structure and experience which chimed with the more sort of
conventional tv and film intentions of the creative lead Nils Denneken, i.e. that there's
one single story that every player experienced, one history which you're going through,
whilst giving the player lots more room to discover more besides that main history.
So how they encounter and build their sense of that history, of what's gone before and what's
being written now, is very much down to their agency through exploration. The more that they
explore, the more they're rewarded with more time in the community which helps them understand it
better. One of the first things that you're often asked when you're working in interactive narrative
is how important are the choices or do they matter?
And I'd like to think that all the choices characters make in a well-written game matter,
but the amount of control you have over them as a player, and what in turn
that effect is on the rest of the game, is often seen as the sum of how complex or
accomplished a piece of narrative design is. So a lot of games discourse can tend towards
judging the accomplishment of games and how close they get to the real world
of choice and consequence. But sometimes abstraction rather than simulation or linearity
is useful. Sometimes things don't have to be branching in order to be rewarding as a piece
of narrative design. We have to think of these things as tools that we use. In my opinion,
when working with any form or set of expectations, the craft is to consider the quality of the
materials that you're working with. In this case, writing for interaction, like working with or
against the grain of a piece of wood. It doesn't really matter what you do as long as you do it
with intentionality. You can work with it or against it.
but neither of those approaches is wrong if you understand the quality of that decision and why you're doing it.
So when I'm asked this question about choice with regards to Mitasiyene,
I've taken to describing the decisions I made in the narrative design as the game having multiple middles rather than multiple endings.
So in the individual conversations in the game, I very much use the Kentucky Route Zero model of choice,
colouring how the character plays the situation, but not really letting you choose who the character is.
So are you Kai attempting to be articulate?
Are you Kai trying to diffuse the situation with a joke?
Either way, you're still Kai.
You're still a version of Kai,
depending on whether she might be in a good mood
or a bad mood that day.
The conversations branch,
but they do always close down to pretty much the same result
at the end of a conversation.
You might have accessed different reactions,
memories and stories,
but they do come to the same place in the end.
So the player agency is instead found in exploration.
Let me go to the next slide.
So why did I design it like this?
Well, as a writer and narrative designer,
coming to the project of Metassione,
which was, you know, I came to about four years ago,
but the game and the story world itself
had been in Nils' head and been developed for,
you know, five or so years
before the point at which I came to it.
As I came to it, I said, what is the story?
What is it to you?
Ann Nils said it was important that it was driven by this ensemble cast of characters.
People were using the term soap opera to talk about it, so I did my homework, I made sure I
understood what that meant formally, and it was centred around a theme of looking at a community
that was a little bit differently aligned with nature. So they'd had this disaster in the past
that had changed them.
and they'd built their world a little bit differently.
So I wanted to show what that meant domestically
as well as dramatically.
And it was also built on this really clearly defined
pre-existing story world and plot.
So I had those things to work with.
And the decisions that I therefore made
about player choice were driven by these considerations,
which could be translated as needing room
to develop many characters journeys in tandem.
drama-driven, slice-of-life setting, that's how I define soap opera in this context,
able to examine the interplay of community because that was very much,
there are so many stories in there, the only way to tell them was to give an
ensemble cast approach. And I really wanted to contrast usefully with this
sort of fantasy tinged setting that Nils had so beautifully built in order to
to give a depth of storytelling that belied their sort of cartoonish appearances.
I said that would give a really interesting contrast and make the world feel really rich and alive.
So for these reasons it made a lot of sense for me not to give the players a different means to
affect the outcomes, like multiple endings. I don't want the player to fail because failure
means sort of destroying this community or allowing them to continue suffering,
which doesn't seem ethical to me when designing a piece of narrative.
So to not allow the player agency to exert on the outcome linearly, i.e. to make it branch,
instead I wanted to invite them to shape their experience of the story laterally.
I wanted them to explore sideways, multiple middles as opposed to multiple endings.
This is something that really opened up a lot of references to TV style storytelling and there is
another talk that I have delivered digitally for GDC called Kill the Heroes Save the World about
ensemble cast storytelling and how that those choices that I made in order to tell the story
of all of the community well were very much drawn from the influences of long-running TV shows.
A, B and C plots.
is very much an approach which I took to Mitassione and its multiple middles also.
So the player choice in Mitassione is exploration rather than conversation focused.
It's not about branching, it's about whether or not you ever experience this conversation or that conversation
or if you move the story forwards and decide to never see those.
It meant a lot of careful planning to make sure that those mandatory moments in each time of day
encouraged the player to discover B and C plots,
and no matter which kind of pace you took it at,
or no matter how much you decided to explore
in one time or another, it still felt rewarding.
And it also gave characters well-shaped journeys.
So it meant that every character had to sort of dip
into the mandatory A plot or a plot,
as you might call it in a sort of TV series length
kind of context.
every character that I wanted to develop over the time, they had to dip into the mandatory stuff
in order to bring you out if you wanted to continue following their story. So do check
out that other GDC talk that I gave for more context on that stuff. But just some examples
of what like an A plot, B plot, C plot is. As I looked at multiple middles, I considered the A
plot as the driving theme or problem of the game.
we split it up into chapters, so I would think about this on a chapter by chapter basis,
as well as that sort of Ur plot, whole game length context. So for example in Metasianian on day five
you have to go on a boat trip with Tung and Miu and discover that you should grow a garden
to help Tung with his boat making. And that's really important to move the story forwards,
to bring in the gardens for that day, that has to happen.
B plots are not a thing that you have to do in Mitassione, but they will be really
sort of keyed up in previous episodes, mandatory plot points, or hinted at in
those mandatory plot points in that day particularly. So they are sort of the
secondary story if you're talking in TV terms in an episode, they're often
lighter, comedic, and they contrast thematically in a way that reflects on
the A plot really usefully, or gives you a different tone to break off into.
and then when you return to the A plot it's hopefully more compelling.
So in day five of Mitassione, B plots include following up on the events of
the night before when it was revealed that Spike the
bartender has had a long-running crush on Tang's mother, Claire. So there are
hints of that in the A plot and if you want to you can dig more into
it. C plots are the smallest unit and
in a more linear form of storytelling where you have a lot of control
over outcomes, multiple endings.
These kind of C-plot style things, they tend to feel a little bit empty, a little bit like side quests,
without much purpose because they don't move things forward in that real punching linear way,
but in a multiple middles kind of explore as much as you like sideways,
C-plots become a really nice place to develop characters, to develop light relief,
and to just add to your satisfaction with the completeness of the universe.
So in day five of Mitassione, a C plot would include the sausage folk plotting a new scheme,
which this time will definitely make them all rich. By the way, they live in a non-monetary
economy, so that's never going to happen, but that's why it's fun. So the only mandatory path
is the A plot. The multiple middles are the choices you make each time of day to dig into
B and C plots. Hopefully that makes sense. A big part of making this work was in making time
transparent.
because one of the ways which I made it feel like a universe
which is happening whether or not you are there,
which very much chimes with the sense of building
a really convincing story world,
was that if you move time forwards,
you would never be able to access
those conversations again.
That meant that I had to work,
I co-developed a bunch of narrative design details
along with game designers, UI designers, the whole team.
in order to really give you a sense of what your decisions meant in terms of time.
So we have details such as the journal, which is a diegetic means of setting out which conversations or actions are mandatory.
These that you see here, the black text, that's the prompt that you'd get and when you complete an A-plot,
when you complete a piece of mandatory plotting or with an action or a conversation, you get a follow-up in purple.
So once you've completed all of the mandatory actions or conversations for a time of day,
so this is Tuesday night in this picture here, time will move forward. That last action or
conversation will have a timer symbol marked above it. So you choose that knowing that it's
going to move time forward. You can choose not to click it and to explore elsewhere if you feel like
you've not got enough of that time of day yet. It allows you to make an intentional decision as a
player.
They also gave the many characters habits and routines, constructing plots as you progressed,
whether or not you'd found the first or second conversation added to the sense of this pre-existing,
alive story world in which you are not the only protagonist,
which was one of the core values of the storytelling.
And the slice-of-life aspect of the soap opera genre.
I was able to serve that by interweaving lots of plot lines and allowing the player to discover
histories and participate in different dramas, past and present, and to work that into this
ensemble cast to use it to develop them as characters because there's not room in the
A-plot for everyone to have meaningful journeys, but in this way the player gets to choose who
they like and who they're interested in and to try and intersect with them in most times a day
and see how they're doing.
It's still player choice, but it's choice through exploration rather than branching pathways.
So this allowed me to build this drama-driven, domestic life characteristic,
which is very much aligned with the soap opera genre.
And that soap opera setting of personal dramas and everyday routines,
and the choice that I made to draw characters who are very naturalistic,
contrasting with the fantasy setting,
I hope that it gave weight to this mutant world that otherwise could have come across as a little bit glib.
There were some really big themes in the plot as it was originally presented to me,
including the trauma of losing your kids, of being betrayed, of death,
and it was very much hanging over the community from all of these past events
which are described to me when I joined the team as a writer.
Multiple Middles style storytelling.
allowed me to build characterisations which were rich and complex, meaning that the full
ensemble cast felt real and part of the texture of the place, and it gave me room to explore those
themes more delicately, more carefully and more naturalistically in a way that did them justice,
I hope. And I also worked carefully in the dialogue to imbue each character with a distinct voice,
from cadence, idioms, style and manner of speech, all of those things.
My playwright training very much came in there.
The idiom is that you should be able to cover the lines,
the names of every person in a script
and just looking at the way that they talk,
tell who they are.
I very much used that naturalistic dialogue style approach
to the way that people talked.
Again, building characterization, building nuance
and building journeys that I hope feel real
and rewarding to dig down into.
So in being transparent about time and combining this with the freedom to explore Nils's wonderful
environment, I hope that the narrative design was able to reflect this theme of this closeness to
nature which was part of the original brief and also build in the main piece of mechanical gameplay,
the magical musical gardens so beautifully composed musically and programmatically
respectively by Alessandro Coronas and Doug Wilson.
I made narrative decisions that focused on the characters as complex, rich and a little
bit different for the smallness of their community.
I wanted getting to know them to feel like coming across a number of new plants you've
never seen before, tending to them, watching them grow and allowing them to surprise you.
I set out to build a narrative design that would allow the player to choose their own
pace, to push at this central plot if they wanted to, but also to meander and wander
and grow their story at their own pace.
because the themes of the story are tough.
It deals with trauma, colonialism, infidelity,
aging, illness, but actually when you read reviews
of the game or people just talking about it,
they often characterize it as gentle.
And I think it's because of that multiple middles approach
to the storytelling, which gives you the opportunity
to pace your own experience,
your own journey through the story.
So when I talk about multiple models, what I mean is exploration focused, lateral narrative design,
which opens up a community of characters rather than linear choice and consequence style storytelling,
which focuses only really on that hero's journey and how their weight of agency affects the world.
That's a perfectly acceptable way to tell a story, but it's not the way that was going to
be best useful in telling this particular story, which I was given a brief of telling.
So in this context it enabled me to build characters that had routines and habits in
the physical space of the game and that made exploration easier because you sort of knew
where people were going to be. I also worked to allow you to choose which characters or subplots
you're more interested in, allowing you to find the natural ebb and flow of different times of day
and altogether giving you more of a sense of natural pacing of really existing in this world.
It was quieter in the evenings when everyone had gone to bed, for example, or some characters
were always up early and some didn't get up until later.
These things really gives a universal sense of place.
I also worked really hard in the narrative design to be transparent around time, really
giving the player a sense of control and agency around their own pacing, and that was key
to really enabling multiple middles and making it feel rewarding.
So that enables characters to feel like they're living full and well-rounded lives,
and that the player's presence in the world feels situated and grounded in the context of a quite
fantastical setting. This enabled me to talk more effectively about community as well, because the
community was not there to serve the player's journey, rather the player was being rewarded
for exploring and listening to it.
tending to the story rather than applying pressure to it.
To take general principles from this talk, like as an author
of what I learned and what I think people could learn more generally,
I'd like to advocate for the consideration of
player agency as a quality and not a virtue
of writing for games and of storytelling in games.
Restricting agency can be a useful tool in helping you tell your story more
effectively, more intuitively.
and in a manner which allows you to explore
maybe more complicated themes more sensitively.
Multiple middles, as I've described it here,
style design allows for player agency through exploration
rather than changing outcomes.
And I think that this is a thing that you develop over time
is a sense as someone, as you develop your craft
as a narrative designer and a writer,
you start understanding that genres don't have virtues
They have qualities, the same with form,
and the same with this structure of player interaction.
They are all tools with which we need to really consider
what will serve our story best.
One of the most meaningful dialogue options
I offer in mutazione is often the option, stay quiet.
When someone is talking to you of their grief,
or their sorrow, or their regrets,
sometimes the most powerful act is not to act, but to listen.
we can build narrative design that supports the telling
of that kind of act of listening.
And multiple middles is how I personally attempted it.
Thanks very much for listening.
And I know that we're all doing this virtually,
so I'm really stoked to watch the other contributors
to the panel's videos on all of their expertise
and what they've learned from what they've been working on.
Thanks very much for listening to me.
Take care.