Hi everybody.
Thank you for coming to an hour long session
on the last day of GDC at 10 a.m.
I appreciate it.
I'm supposed to say, they told me to say a thing,
fuck what do I say?
Shit.
No.
We are off to a really good start guys.
Don't use flash cause it scares me.
Turn off noise making things.
All right.
Hi.
I'm Leighton Gray, I'm the co-creator, co-writer, and art director, and I guess head daddy of
Dream Daddy, a dad dating simulator, the dating sim where you play as a hot dad, and your
goal is to meet and romance other hot dads.
And today, I'm here to talk to you about something that's really serious and very important,
and just really close to my heart in a sentimental way, and that's...
Oh boy.
Don't ruin my gag. No. And that's memes. Or more specifically, how to write and market
games for the internet without embarrassing yourself too much. Step one, don't do this.
Let's talk about why.
Dream Daddy was a product of the internet and there was a lot of intentionality in how
we wrote, designed, and marketed it towards online communities like Tumblr, Twitter, and
YouTube.
And while we were working on the game, we were kind of making all of these creative
choices in a vacuum, unsure if these ideas we had seeded in the game to get people to
share it would actually work or not.
And when we announced the game and subsequently released it, we finally got to see what worked
and what didn't, and we were thankfully largely successful.
We landed ourselves at the top selling game on Steam globally on launch day,
and we were named the third most trending game on Tumblr for 2017,
and knocked Overwatch off the top spot for the first time in months,
which was exciting.
And I don't know about you guys,
but it was pretty much impossible to go on any social media
without seeing a ton of posts about how much people wanted to kiss these dads.
So in this talk, I'm going to break down
how we engineered the game from its inception
to be as shareable as possible,
and how you can apply these same principles
to your work as well.
And to understand what gets people to share,
let's begin by talking about what really, really doesn't.
You may have seen this internal Google document
that was leaked a while ago called It's Lit,
which covers what the cool teens think is dank and on fleek.
And if there's one thing I know about cool teens,
it's that the only thing they love more than the Beatles
and Coldplay is bowing down to our corporate overlords
by relying on brands to shape their world.
As the kids say, SMH.
And because companies follow clueless internal documents
like this one, they do stuff like this.
And this is a whole Twitter account
that just collects brands being horrifically out of touch.
a bunch of grown people sat at a table and were like,
this is our marketing strategy, we're doing great.
So obviously nobody likes it when a 35 year old PR dude
tells you that it's on fleek to buy a roast beef sandwich.
And another big issue here is that when brands
do stuff like this, it shows that they're hearing consumers
but they're not actually listening.
And with an ever increasing awareness of and skepticism
towards transparent marketing ploys and pandering,
it's more important than ever
to have a deep working understanding
of the community your game is for
so that you don't get endlessly dunked on
by an army of 15 year olds on Twitter.
And we talk about this in Dream Daddy for a little bit
when you ask your teenage daughter to explain memes to you.
There's Eggie.
So Amanda says, dad, it's complicated.
See, memes are inside jokes shared by a bunch of people
that get less funny the more people do it.
So the problem is that by the time a meme gets to you, dad,
all of us youths have already done the joke to death.
And what's worse than that is that movies and TV
and video games will try to jump in on a meme train,
but just based on how long it takes to make them,
the meme will be long dead by the time it comes out.
So it just dates it and isn't funny.
And then of course you say, oh shit, what up?
Because we're hacks.
So if trying to incorporate memes into your work is the kiss of death, how do we effectively
write content that exists adjacent to internet culture without directly referencing it?
And how can we take concrete steps to encourage the organic spread of our work?
And to answer that question, I'm going to talk about every game developer's favorite
topic, art history.
Yay.
And if it's not obvious from literally everything about me.
So modernism was the first major art movement
of the early 20th century.
It came in on the heels of the Romantic movement,
which was all about aestheticizing intense emotion,
and it was extremely melodramatic and lofty.
So in response, modernism focused on defying
the traditional ideas of the 19th century,
and this also coincided with the Industrial Revolution.
This movement encouraged artists and writers
to try new things and explore unorthodox ideas
with enthusiasm and to question everything.
Artists like Picasso, Duchamp, Kandinsky,
and writers like James Joyce and Marcel Proust
are perfect examples of modernism.
They were all doing things nobody had seen before.
And as we approach the mid to late 20th century,
the reaction to modernism was postmodernism.
While modernism was more of an art movement
than anything else,
postmodernism was just as much a philosophical movement
intended to critique society and culture
as it was an art movement.
And as a whole, postmodernism can be defined by a heavy sense of cynicism and irony towards
everything.
There's a huge emphasis on nihilism, the idea that truth is a subjective construct,
and it made things like parody and pastiche popular.
And a big element of postmodernism was intertextuality and references to other media.
For instance, Scream is a really great example because it repeatedly references and subverts
horror movie tropes.
For postmodernism, just imagine a bunch of artists in black turtlenecks chain-smoking
and generally just being miserable.
But remember postmodernism because we will get back to it in a minute.
Because a lot has changed since the postmodern movement started.
And one of the biggest changes has been the advent of the Internet.
Postmodernism doesn't really give us the tools that we need to meaningfully navigate a relationship
with current content because the Internet has had such a huge impact on the way that
we create, consume, and share media.
And so much of an impact that we're currently experiencing a huge cultural shift from mass
media to social media.
We've gone from a top-down model of distribution
to a participatory culture where consumers are not just
consumers of static, unchanging content.
They're people who are reshaping and remixing
the context and meaning of media.
And the language that currently exists around content
that becomes successful on the internet
unnecessarily mystifies this entire process.
When we say something goes viral,
we're robbing both the content creator
and the audience of their agency.
Like we're passively infecting each other with content,
which is not how it works.
And consulting, marketing, and PR firms
will dangle this concept of going viral above your head
to get you to give them money
and to intentionally muddy the process
of what it takes to create a successful product.
And we can even track where this kind of thinking originated.
The term meme was introduced in 1976
in Richard Dawkins' book, The Selfish Gene,
as the cultural corollary of the gene,
the idea being that a meme propagates itself
in a way similar to genes.
And I kid you not, he uses the phrase meme pool,
which is a pretty fun mental image.
And this sort of biological metaphor is a big reason
why we oversimplify this process down to virality.
And of course, memes have been around a long,
a long time before we had a name for them.
Humans figuring out how to start fire is a meme.
It did not necessarily look like this,
but it is still a meme.
And I'll have you know that I worked really, really hard
to get this as artifacted as possible.
Idioms are memes.
Metaphors are memes.
Tropes in media are memes.
A meme is just an idea,
an idea that can spread and mutate and be improved upon.
Even with classical paintings,
artistic movements are defined
by a certain collection of memes.
Like, guys, I hate to break it to you,
but even the great masters were just doing, like,
really exceptional Jesus fan art.
Like, all it's missing is the flower crown.
And in the 19th century, women's scrapbooking culture
revolved around cutting interesting tidbits
out of books and newspapers and collecting them
in a single place so they were easily shareable,
which is pretty much just old-timey Pinterest
down to the weird obsession with mason jars.
I mean, one could even say that it's uncanny.
You guys love blasphemy, but you won't stand for dad puns?
Okay.
You came to the dream daddy talk.
Did you really think I was not gonna?
All right.
My point is, the internet just accelerates behaviors
we were already doing, and we as members
of a network community choose to share content
that's meaningful to us.
So instead of placing the onus on this seemingly unknowable
magical phenomenon, virality, it's more productive for us
as game developers to analyze how we can imbue content
with the kind of meaning that will compel people to share.
And this idea to counter virality is called spreadability.
The intersection of qualities that optimize content
for sharing through social media.
This model recognizes that the driving force
behind what we share comes from a social place
and that our lives aren't defined by brands.
Rather, we use the media we consume
to facilitate conversations that we're already having,
just like humans have always done with all forms of art
from the beginning of time.
Which brings us back around to art movements.
How can we tap into this collective culture
and figure out what will make people share
when internet culture is so nebulous and ever-shifting?
I mean,
You ever go without checking Twitter for a couple of days and then you come back and
you're like, what the fuck is everybody talking about?
Like it's a daunting task and I can often feel like you're trying to hit a moving target.
But by understanding the art movement that we're currently on the cusp of, it can take
some of the guesswork out of it.
So on a sliding scale of sincerity and cynicism with modernism being very sincere and post-modernism
being very cynical.
What does that mean for the current state of art and philosophy?
How could we possibly describe this emerging culture of media born from the Internet?
I don't know.
That's the talk.
Bye.
I will tell you in a second.
It's metamodernism.
This is the part where I die on stage.
which in a nutshell is a movement defined
by ironic detachment with sincere engagement.
The Metamodernist Manifesto was written
by artist Luke Turner,
and the man, the meme, the legend himself, Shia LaBeouf.
Here's a basic rundown of the core tenets of metamodernism.
It acknowledges that prescribing exclusively
to either solely modern or postmodern ideas
limits our ability to tell robust, complex stories.
and that the best storytelling comes from oscillating between two poles,
primarily sincerity and cynicism, but also a highbrow and lowbrow,
optimism and doubt, relativism and truth, etc.
Like, it reflects real life.
Our lives are not just solely one thing or one thing.
Like, it's kind of a mixed bag.
And this is where the meta prefix comes from,
not in the sense that something is self-aware or self-referential in a meta way,
although it can be and often is.
It comes from the word metaxy, meaning an in-betweenness.
It also aims to collapse distances between disparate groups of people.
It acknowledges the layered identities we present both online and in real life.
And finally, it embodies a sense of radical optimism and self-love in the face of decades
of postmodernism's unbridled cynicism.
One of the most notable things about metamodernism is that the parameters are extremely loose.
Media doesn't have to ascribe to all these tenets to be considered metamodern, and this
idea is commonly referred to in metamodern texts as an affective feeling, since metamodern
media often borrows, mutates, and remixes elements from modernism and postmodernism.
I like to compare it to early 2000s fashion, but just with less of whatever that is.
You can combine and pay homage to many different tropes and feelings to create something totally
new that doesn't feel as tired as a lot of postmodern tropes do at this point.
To put all of this in perspective, let's look at some games that I would consider postmodern
versus a few I think are firmly metamodern.
Hello, this is Shia LaBeouf.
I'm actually gonna talk about Shia LaBeouf first.
That's what's happening now.
So Shia LaBeouf has done a lot of really,
really interesting things with meta-modern media.
If you'll recall, a couple of years ago,
he did this performance art piece that was called
I Am Not, or, hashtag, I Am Not Sorry,
where he sat in a room with a bag over his head
that said, I Am Not Famous Anymore.
And if you recall the way that the media
kind of reported on this, it was very much like,
Oh, look at those wild celebs, they're at it again.
And what actually happened is that people would go in,
you know, expecting it to be something silly like that,
and they would come in and they'd take the bag
off of Shia's head because it was a very...
high art kind of thing where he's just sitting in a room
and you could kind of do whatever you wanted with him.
So they take the bag off of his head and he'd be crying.
And then this person who is only ever known
about Shia LaBeouf as like this celebrity, this symbol,
suddenly has this like very real moment with him.
And a lot of people would start crying themselves
and they would like hold his hand and try to console him
and actually have like a much more meaningful experience.
And I highly recommend that anybody go check out Shia LaBeouf's other work.
He's done a lot of really interesting performance art pieces aside from getting arrested for
public intoxication in Savannah, Georgia, which is a...
For a place with open container lots, that's hard to do.
Anyway, now let's talk about games that are postmodern.
The Stanley Parable and Portal both deconstruct traditional ideas surrounding player agency
in a game like Sonic Dreams Collection, Lampoon's Sonic fan culture in the late 90s.
And all three of these games are pretty resoundingly cynical and feature varying degrees of subversion
in their respective genres.
Postmodernism.
Progressing past this era of postmodern work, we have games like Undertale and Doki Doki
Literature Club.
The distinction here is that both games are deconstructions of deconstructions.
Undertale is particularly notable in this sense because it plays with RPG tropes in
several different ways.
The fact that the player is constantly faced with choosing between pacifism and violence
and then has to live with the consequences is very metamodern because, again, it's that
oscillation between those poles without totally reconciling them.
And then you have characters who are aware of your previous actions and comment on them
and breaking the fourth wall by making direct appeals to the player.
So doki doki literature club.
Sorry to leave you guys hanging.
Is on one level a deconstruction and commentary on a lighthearted dating sim and all the trappings
of the genre.
Your childhood best friend, a blank slate male main character, takes place in a high
school.
Anime titty.
And then as the game starts to take a darker turn, it starts playing off of horror tropes
as well and then becomes extremely meta once Monica addresses the player directly.
The game manages to be simultaneously cutesy, sweet, and endearing, while also just absolutely
horrific.
It allows the player to hold both ideas at once.
And I believe that it's no coincidence that these two games have enjoyed a lot of success
and have garnered massive fandoms.
Because ultimately, metamodernism is the source of all Internet culture and it informs the
sensibilities of some of the most popular media right now.
Such as Rick and Morty, the music of Childish Gambino, Bojack Horseman, Bo Burnham's standup,
Black Mirror, and Homestuck, which I put in there because apparently it's 2012.
So let's break down what each of these core tenets
really mean and how we utilize these ideas
to make Dream Daddy a success.
So sincerity wrapped in cynicism
is the really, really big one
that if you remember one thing from this talk,
remember that.
The guiding idea of metamodernism
is pretty well embodied by this Jerry Saltz quote.
I know that the art I'm creating may seem silly or stupid,
that it might've been done before,
but that doesn't mean that this isn't serious.
And by wrapping a sincere story in this cynical exterior,
you're basically Trojan horsing meaning into your game.
I kind of like to think of it like salted caramel,
like you get the salty and the sweet
and they both bring out the best in each other
and now I'm really hungry.
But a perfect example of this in a game
that Dream Daddy would not exist without
is Hottiful Boyfriend, the Pigeon Dating Sim.
Yes, I know you like kissing birds, thank you.
And what clearly looks like a very silly game
where you play as a human girl dating birds
has been pretty widely regarded
as one of the best dating sims out there.
Players praise the surprisingly well-written story
and sprawling lore.
So this is a particularly effective technique
that also worked for us.
Setting the player's expectations low
with the promise of something silly or weird,
dating birds, kissing dads.
And then doing a bit of a bait and switch with a story that's actually meaningful.
Cuz let's face it,
it's really hard to just tell a serious story at face value on the Internet.
We have to steep it in a few layers of irony so it's palatable because
the Internet has ruined all of our brains and just turned us into
whatever fucked up sense of humor the Internet has done to us.
I really don't understand it.
But if Dream Daddy was instead just called like favorable fathers and was a straightforward
story about the experience of being a single dad, it would have been seen as a little overly
sentimental.
You know, you got to put daddy in the title.
Gets them in the door.
And because people unfortunately already tend to have low expectations of dating sims as
a genre, we were able to pleasantly surprise players with a story with hidden depth.
Because one second you're hanging out with the goth dad who loves shopping at Hot Topic
and writing his own smutty narrative fiction that he then gets.
leather bound, and then the next,
he's giving a monologue in a graveyard
about how death helps him appreciate his life more.
And even though the game is about dating dads,
it's also pretty heavily about the experience
of growing up in a single-parent household,
and that resonated with people.
Next, collapsing distances.
I'm gonna collapse the distance between me and this water.
Hydration is important.
Because the internet is an incredible tool
for connecting us with people from all walks of life
from all over the world and then yelling at all those people
from different walks of life for having opinions,
metamodernism places a heavy emphasis
on exploring not only our differences,
but the things that we have in common.
This is where what I will lovingly call
hashtag relatable, hashtag content comes from.
Because at their core, internet memes
are just super condensed storytelling
to communicate a universal truth.
Like.
We all do the thing where you stand in the shower
and then you fill your mouth with water
and then you spit it out like you're a water fountain.
It's a feeling of like, me too, I do that.
And also most memes that get really popular
kind of boil down to the same format.
Like thing you should be doing,
thing you should not be doing,
thing you should be doing,
thing you should not be doing
but you're gonna do anyway.
Ha.
And, you know, this one.
And if you want to go like really Freudian with it,
what this is really expressing is this.
So what I'm saying is that memes are gonna enter
the literary canon as works of high art someday.
Anyway, further extrapolating that kind of meme-y thing
into a video game narrative is as simple
as writing truthfully and authentically.
I know that sounds kind of obvious,
but your best writing is going to come
from a place of vulnerability,
and that authenticity will always shine through.
Dream Daddy has been pretty widely praised for having a very genuine and heartfelt story.
And I think so many of the most touching moments in the game came from some deeply vulnerable
places for me and my co-writer Vernon.
And we touch on a lot of serious subjects like alcoholism, imposter syndrome, toxic
masculinity, etc.
Like by allowing yourself to be vulnerable with players that can connect with you more.
Like for example, whoa, guys, holy shit.
I'm up here, I'm doing a talk, we had technical difficulties,
I spent the last hour freaking out, I have not had breakfast,
I hate public speaking, it's really stressful,
I'm having a bad time.
Anyway, we're back.
Thanks, thank you.
But this is exactly what I'm talking about.
By choosing to be vulnerable,
you guys hopefully feel a little bit more connected to me
as a person.
And if you don't, then just act like you are.
I don't know, work with me.
I was vulnerable with you, don't take advantage of that.
Anyway, one of the things we did post-announcement
were these character introductions,
which were actually modeled around tag me memes
like this one.
And if you've never seen one of these before,
they're typically a bunch of simply drawn characters
with these brief descriptions.
I always end up comparing them to horoscopes.
Like there's these sets of traits
that really could be applicable to anybody,
but the idea is that you tag the one that you're most like
and then you also tag your friends.
And so we did these, and following that,
people really related to these descriptions
of the characters, and even if they didn't exactly,
they tagged their friends who did,
which is another entry point for new players.
And so we decided to post a blank version
for people to put their own Dadsonas onto,
because people were sending us
so much fan art of them anyway.
I mean, like, look at those good boys.
And what actually ended up happening
is that people kind of turned it into a meme.
It was just this for a very long time.
We kind of had to like not check the notifications
because you guys are some memers.
So you can definitely draw inspiration from memes
without clumsily shoving them in places
where they don't belong.
And another example of this happened
when I got some of the early sketches of Joseph Sprite
from our wonderful character artist, Shannon Pei.
I had passed off my designs
and when she showed me this pose, I was like,
That looks really familiar.
Why does that look so familiar?
And then I realized, oh, oh,
he looks like, you know, I had to do it to him guy.
I should get her to change that.
And then I thought, no, I should not,
because that creates an opportunity
for people to make that connection on their own,
to speculate whether it was on purpose or not,
or to just make jokes about it.
And sure enough, we got a ton of tweets like this.
I'm thrilled.
This is exactly what I wanted.
So, metamodernism also stresses the understanding
of other perspectives, which goes hand in hand
with inclusivity and diversity.
And when I was submitting my pitch for a talk,
I considered doing one about writing inclusivity,
and then I realized that that talk would be 60 seconds long
because all I have to say is, just fucking do it!
Write diverse characters,
represent diverse groups of people,
and if you're not sure how to write perspectives
that are different from your own,
Find someone who does and give them money.
It's that easy.
And if you've never written a song before
and you don't know how to read music
and you don't know how to play any instruments
and you don't know anything about music theory
and also you've never actually even listened to music before
are you going to set out to create the entire soundtrack
of your game recorded from scratch in your basement?
No, you're gonna hire someone who knows what they're doing.
It's the same thing.
And obviously neither Dream Daddy's co-creator Vernon Sharai are gay dads, so we were constantly
talking to a lot of gay men, trans men, actual fathers, and other members of the LGBT community
to get feedback, and the game is so much richer for it.
And I really do not want to hear that writing perspectives that are inclusive is some kind
of niche topic that won't make money, because if the success of Dream Daddy is any indication,
there is a huge demographic of people that is starved for content that represents them.
I know!
I'm a member of that demographic.
And these people deserve to feel included.
And further, not only is putting together a diverse cast
a wonderful step towards inclusivity,
it's just more realistic.
Diversity is just good storytelling.
And also I'm gonna advocate for doing your research.
I am a huge nerd and I love reading a lot of books
and you should too if you're a writer.
So like do as much research as you can
and keep a running notebook of what you're learning.
Creating a vocabulary of knowledge
that you can draw upon as you're writing.
is gonna make your work so much better.
And when you get stuck on story,
you can always go back to those notes for inspiration.
And when we started writing Dream Daddy,
I checked out a bunch of books from the library
on pretty much.
anything even tangentially related to the story.
Being a dad, being a single dad,
the cultural ideas wrapped up in patriarchal societies,
being a gay dad, the history of the gay man in America,
et cetera, and we learned so much
that we otherwise never would have touched on.
Just read more, read more is my point.
Also, if you enjoyed Dream Daddy
or like my brother's husband,
please read Does This Baby Make Me Look Straight
by Dan Bukitinsky because it's fantastic
and really funny and it made me cry a lot.
And obviously we're going to talk about layered identities now.
The way we present ourselves varies based on who we're talking to.
The way you tell a story to your parents is probably very different from the way that
you tell a story to your friends.
And similarly, the way that you present yourself on Facebook is probably very, very different
from the way that you present yourself on your private vent Twitter.
Don't act like you do not have one.
I know about the anime shit posting.
It's okay.
We're all friends here.
And one of the cool things about metamodernism
is that it encourages us to really explore
how we express these different facets of our personalities
through not only social media, but video games as well.
I know I'm not the only person in this room
who spends an inordinate amount of time
on character creators.
There's a community of people who I think
really want more gaming experiences
that let them explore themselves
and games that can teach them something about who they are
or give them an opportunity to explore their sexuality
or gender identity when they might not be able to do so
in real life.
And there's no better testament to how underserved this community is than the popularity of Dragon Age and Mass Effect, among young women and queer people especially.
The fandoms for these games are vibrant and thriving, and most of the fan content revolves around exploring the relationships between the characters and creating work about the players Shepard, Warden, Inquisitor, Hawk, etc.
And while these games are of course amazing
in their own right,
I think that the robust character creators
combined with very well-written friendships
and romantic relationships
really encourage this type of extensive engagement
beyond playtime
because it creates a deeper emotional investment.
I'm so thirsty, literally and figuratively.
Trying to play off of this,
our goal with the writing player dad
and designing the character creator,
was to give people lots of options to customize their dad.
Making sure to include a wide variety of skin tones,
facial features, body types,
options to have a trans dad,
as well as more androgynous and feminine options
to choose from.
And I would include all the tweets from people
thanking us for having a character creator
that actually represents them,
but I did not want to start weeping
in the middle of this talk and be unable to continue
if you went to Tyler's talk earlier this week.
You got to see us both cry.
It was great.
You also make some decisions in the first five minutes of the game in regards to the
gender of your dead spouse, as well as whether Amanda is your biological child or if she
was adopted.
And these choices had very little effect on the rest of the game aside from changing a
few variables, but they proved to be really meaningful to people in how it dictated their
characters' past and sexuality.
Oh, God, excuse me.
They give you the lapel mic and you can't even lean away.
It's like you're just going to hear all of it.
This is who I am.
What's wrong with, no!
And full credit again to Dream Daddy's brilliant director
Tyler Hutchison, who's sitting right over there.
At least I hope it's Tyler.
A bunch of people look the same
when the lights are really bright.
That's you, okay.
And you know, it was also his idea for the binder bods,
and he gave the amazing talk earlier this week
about how you as a straight white dude
can take small steps to make a world of difference
for players, which if you missed,
please check out on the vault.
It was wonderful.
Anyway, one of the major things that compels people to share things with others on the
internet is whether the content communicates something about the person or their relationships
with others.
So creating an opportunity for players to express themselves, especially through a character
creator is something that is pretty much guaranteed to be shareable.
I mean, do you guys remember when Miitomo came out and Twitter was just only Miitomo
for a long time?
Everyone just wants to show everybody else what they look like in cute cartoon form.
It's a universal thing.
It's what brings us all together.
We love cartoons.
And finally, we have radical optimism.
And I like to describe this recent shift
over the past couple of years
as the progression from the popularity of Me IRL memes.
which are about hating yourself and being depressed.
These are all fun.
These are relatable.
And we went from this to wholesome memes,
where you want to support your friends and pet dogs
and just be kind and positive.
And right now, I think people are really craving stuff
that's silly and fun and uplifting
because, boy, things are kind of dire in the world right now.
And as you can see from this highly scientific line graph,
depression memes continue to be popular,
but wholesome memes are slowly rising up and taking over.
And this little spike right here that kicks it off is,
what do you know, 2016 election, yeah.
And if you take a look at the kind of content
that fan communities create,
which we can assume is what people really, really want
out of their stories.
Time and time again, for every fandom that I looked up on AO3,
what could possibly be more popular than angst, blowjobs, and anal sex?
This is a real thing that I wrote into my talk and I regret it a little bit now.
Anybody want to guess what it is?
It's fluff!
And for those who have never read fanfic, and first of all, yeah, okay, sure.
Fluff is just comedic, silly, sweet fanfic with little to no substance.
It's like the wholesome equivalent of a lemon or a porn without plot.
And at this point, I think we're all pretty burned out on cynicism in characters who don't
talk like real people do and stories that are just grim and gritty for the sake of being
grim and gritty.
And I'm not saying that your game should just be sweet and simple, but people seem to respond
really strongly to stories about characters who genuinely care about each other and may
want the best for each other.
And when we were writing the game, it was also really important to us that none of the
humor punched down, so to speak.
We tried really hard to keep everything positive
and again, inclusive,
because jokes that punch down hurt your players.
And with comedy,
your jokes are going to create in-groups and out-groups.
And by punching down,
you're tightening the radius of that in-group
smaller and smaller and potentially alienating players
that would otherwise really enjoy your game.
Plus going for the low hanging fruit
is just so done and creatively bankrupt at this point.
I mean, look at Ricky Gervais.
Can he chill?
Can he find some chill?
And by not punching down, you're actually going to force yourself to be even more creative
and your writing will be better.
This mentality also extended into the approach that we took for our social media accounts.
We always tried to come from a place of positivity and support, which ranges from how we responded
to fan art to how we responded to angry players reporting bugs.
It's sort of like when you go to Disney and you ask, they can't tell you the park closes
at 8.
They have to say the park is open until 8.
So we adopted the voice of a supportive, proud dad on Twitter,
and people responded really well to it.
And the coolest part that us being positive, in turn,
got the fans to be supportive and kind to each other as well.
So you really have the power to set the tone
of how people interact with both you and other players.
So now that I've gone over the core tenets of metamodernism,
which are, again, sincerity wrapped in cynicism,
collapsing distances, radical optimism,
and layered identities,
let's talk about how you can utilize these principles
to create a product that's very spreadable.
So the moment that we see a piece of content
on social media, before we're even consciously aware of it,
our brain is already making decisions
about its shareability.
A 2011 study by a group of psychologists at UCLA put a bunch of students through an fMRI
scan as they were exposed to different pitches for a variety of fake TV shows and instructed
to role-play as interns and to take note of the pitches that they would potentially want
to share with producers.
The psychologist determined that the moment a group of students role-playing as interns
were first exposed to an idea that they would ultimately decide to share with the producers,
this area in the brain called the temporal parietal junction would light up, and it's
the area between the temporal and parietal lobes oscillating between two areas of the
brain metamodernism.
So the temporal parietal junction is actually a part of the outer layer of the brain called
the mentalization network.
Mentalizing is the process of understanding how other people think and feel,
and this entire network is engaged when we see something that we might potentially share with others.
And this is the same part of the brain that theoretically would have been engaged
when ancient humans dragged fresh kale back to their tribe.
We're deeply wired to want to share things of quality with those that we care about.
And even though the TPJ's connection with social media
is still being pretty extensively researched,
we can actually use this information to our advantage
by looking at the kinds of rapid fire questions
we're subconsciously thinking
when we see an interesting post on social media.
Namely, is this content worth engaging with?
Is it worth sharing?
What's the best platform to spread it through?
Might it be of interest to specific people?
Does it convey something about who I am
or my relationship with others?
And does it reflect the values of my community?
And some questions you'll want to ask yourself
in your design process to make sure that the answers
to all of those questions are a resounding yes.
You want to think about, is it portable, quotable, grabbable?
Is it available when and where audiences want it?
Is it easily reusable in a variety of ways?
Is it relevant to multiple audiences?
And if so, who?
Is it a part of a steady stream of material?
And because so much of the way people interact with games
now takes place outside of playtime and fan communities
and on social media,
encouraging this kind of engagement is essential
for ensuring that your game is spreadable.
And there are a couple of different things
that you can do to create a game
that leaves room for people to sink their teeth
into the work and run with it.
And with the way this participatory culture works,
you as a dev need to be okay with relinquishing
a certain amount of control over your IP.
Think about it like this.
You hand somebody a finished novel.
They'll read it and they'll have a good time, sure,
but what if you handed the same person a Mad Lib
and told them to fill it in?
And then you hand hundreds of other people the same Mad Lib
and they're all gonna have different ways
of filling in the blanks and then they're gonna fight
each other over how they filled in the blanks,
but they're gonna be so much more engaged
because they get to decide what this story means to them.
And some things that can create these little Mad Libs gaps
for players include tapping into shared fantasies,
humor, parody references and intertextuality,
unfinished content, mystery, timely controversy,
and the dreaded discourse, and rumors.
Going in depth into each of these
would be an entire talk in itself, but as one example,
I mean, we didn't end each of the dad's date paths
essentially at the beginning of a romantic relationship
just because we.
didn't have forever to write a sprawling epic of a dating sim.
It was partially that.
But by leaving the endings ambiguous and open-ended, it created an opportunity for players to decide
for themselves what happens next and has spurred a ton of fan art and imagines and fanfics
and memes.
And I know that it can be really difficult to relinquish some of that control.
But giving people room to remix, pay homage to,
and meme elements of your work
not only creates a community
where everyone feels more invested in a property
because they're able to help shape the context of the work,
but it also creates a network of entry points
for people to be exposed to your product.
Traditional marketing and PR avenues are still very important,
and we definitely did our fair share of spreading press releases.
But as you can see, grassroots rallying from fans casts a much wider net
that is not only going to reach a much wider audience,
but people are so much more likely to be interested in your game
when it's being endorsed by someone they know or respect,
rather than it just being hawked at them by an advertisement.
Because, let's face it...
Nobody wants to be marketed to, especially while they're playing a game or just trying
to read their friends' hot takes on Facebook.
And the same demographic that responds positively to the principles of metamodernism consists
of a bunch of young people who hate all of the trappings of late-stage capitalism, so
you kind of need to be tactful about it.
And marketing should not be your last step.
It should be your first.
It should be an ongoing conversation
throughout the development process.
Understand who your game is for,
what that community values,
and how your game can facilitate, subvert,
or reinforce the conversations people are already having.
Going back to this slide,
I want to talk about portability
because I think that's arguably
the most important point on this list.
A big part of getting an idea to travel on the internet
is by really optimizing its portability.
This often boils down to nailing your elevator pitch,
but not the stop at every floor
waiting for people to get on and off elevator pitch,
and honest to God, under 30 seconds elevator pitch.
What is your game about?
Dream Daddy co-creator Vernon
calls it compressible content theory.
The more easily and concisely you can explain an idea,
the further it will travel on the internet.
Dream Daddy, a dad dating simulator
is exactly what it says on the tin.
The dating sim where you play as a hot dad
and your goal is to meet and romance other hot dads
while raising your teenage daughter
who's about to leave for college.
Someday I will get it to the speed of like side effects
for medication and commercials, but today it's not that day.
And even the acronym for the game, DDADDS,
communicates what the game is about.
And I don't think I'm ever gonna be able
to do anything better than that acronym.
Like, I can't live up to that.
I've peaked.
Further, when I was designing the characters, there were a few guiding principles I tried
to keep in mind.
Because fan communities can create so many new entry points for new players, it was important
to me that the dads could be easily recognizable down to their simplest elements.
And even recognizable just based on color scheme.
It was also important to me that...
I know, I love it.
It was important to me that all of the characters
could be cheaply and easily cosplayable,
my hope being that you could walk into any thrift store
and walk out with most of the items
you would need to pull off a decent cosplay.
And not only is it just an indescribable joy and honor
to see so many people's takes on the characters,
these cosplays also bolster the spreadability of Dream Daddy
and can act as yet another entry point
into the game's world for the uninitiated.
And I feel like both of these things are kind of the visual corollary of compressible content
theory.
So the designs are still readable, whether it's cosplay, really cute chibis, dogs, or
ponies.
We also tried to create what we called screencapable moments.
Moments that we engineered so people would want to post a screencap to Twitter or Facebook
or tell their friends in a group chat.
And a lot of these ended up being absurd jokes.
Wholesome stuff.
Relatable content.
or thirst, and speaking of thirst.
I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I shouldn't have done that.
But the end goal with all of these
was to have players share a screen grab,
and for that to get people to ask,
what is this, what is Dream Daddy?
And this even applied to our Steam page.
This Tumblr post by a random user,
not affiliated with us at all,
thank you, this person.
And it was just a screen cap of the Steam page.
It got 200,000 notes.
And this sort of thing works really well.
You just have to be very intentional about it.
Because what all of this boils down to is that when you create a piece of work that
aligns with metamodernism and spreadable theory, you're maximizing the shareability of your
game because it shows that you're not just hearing your community, you're actually listening.
So to round up, now that you understand the concepts
of metamodernism and spreadability,
I hope that you can start spotting elements
of metamodernism in the media you consume
and start incorporating those principles into your work.
And remember that when you create content
that exists adjacent to the internet
without directly referencing it,
that makes you the most on fleek bae of all.
Thank you.
And if you're interested in reading more about metamodernism, spreadability, or just checking
out some of the sources I mentioned in this talk, here's a link where I've, it's just
a ton of books, websites, interviews.
There's like a shorter version of this talk if you want to share it, it'd be great.
And you know, follow me on all the stuff or don't, because it's not great.
And also follow my dog on Instagram.
She's really cute.
And please fill out the speaker evals
that you will be receiving
because I would love to come back here
and just fumble my way through yet another talk.
But we have, oh, I finished really early.
We have a lot of time.
People ask questions so I can feel less bad
about finishing so early.
There's mics.
Any questions?
Hufflepuff, what's up?
Yo, so I was wondering, so usually a lot of content
for like, you know, metamodernism stuff
is like more appealing towards like millennials basically.
I was wondering how do you work with trying to like
relate this to like other people of other generations,
I suppose?
That is a really interesting point.
I think Dream Daddy is a really.
extremely targeting millennials and Gen Z kind of game.
And that's not something that I've really thought about
because the approach that you would need to take
to appeal to potentially people who are older
would involve different social media
because I feel like there's been this mass migration
away from things like Facebook for people of a certain age
because they're like, my grandma's on there.
I'm like, I don't want her to see my anime posts.
So that's a really good question that I.
Talk to me afterwards and maybe I'll say something more articulate.
Thank you.
Good scarf.
Anybody else?
Wow, we're just getting like non-stop looks here.
Is that a vaporwave skirt?
Yeah, it totally is.
It has like the doot-doot skeleton on it.
It's like, seriously, we're talking memes here.
Where is that from?
We can talk after.
Okay.
All right.
I get it.
You don't want to share your fashion secrets.
It's fine.
What's up?
can any of this backfire?
Constantly and all the time.
Always, I think, you know,
knowing to not put memes in your stuff
can reduce the possibility of that backfiring
because if you look at social media for like,
any major brand, which is really what spurred this talk
of like, Denny's Twitter, Wendy's Twitter,
like they're kind of doing okay, but I feel like.
There's only so long that we could get away with doing this
before everyone kind of catches on
and it's like, oh, the jig is up.
I think the thing that you should focus on first
is make a good thing before you try
to make a spreadable thing.
And if it's good, I don't know, cream rises
and people will see that it is good.
Yay.
Oh, there's other people at that mic.
Hi, what's up?
Choose your first.
Oh, no problem.
Okay, so you have to fight.
Well, just to follow up on the Twitter thing, I'll go ahead.
You mentioned you chose a voice for your Twitter and you made sure to present as a nice dad
and your audience responded.
Who was in charge of doing that?
Was the writer involved or did you guys just come over?
Oh, here's a good one.
This is what we would say.
It was Vernon and I and we were doing a really great job
of doing good dad jokes because, I don't know,
I feel like it's really easy to just be like,
take care of yourselves.
I'm your dad.
And then I guess we went out for cigarettes
and never came back because we don't really tweet
on the account anymore.
Thank you.
Yeah, so that's all us.
Okay, you know.
Yes.
Speaking of the Internet and Twitter, as soon as I realized that this was not just about
embarrassing yourself on the Internet, or not embarrassing yourself on the Internet.
Oh, there was plenty of that.
And realizing that it was about Dream Daddy, I immediately tweeted at Erica Ishii saying,
in a talk about Dream Daddy and about how not to embarrass yourself on the interwebs,
thinking about you, Erica Ishii.
She said, I know that first thing, and the key to the second thing is not to feel shame
like a normal human being and just go for it.
And for anybody who doesn't know, Erika Ishii is the voice of the daughter in Dream Daddy.
Precious Amanda.
Also, hey, yesterday was the two year anniversary of when we started working on Dads, and it
was also Amanda's birthday.
So happy birthday, Amanda.
Play her last name.
Yay!
Clap for the fictional character.
Thank you, yes, Erica is wonderful.
You were just gonna read a tweet?
Well, no, just that, kind of, but yeah.
Okay.
No, I agree with that.
This has probably been the most human talk
I've been involved in.
Thank you, I did it.
You did it, yay, you did great.
Yeah, I think the same thing is like also,
if you are terminally online, like I am,
you kind of just have to step away from it a bit
and just not listen to the hot takes
of like every 13-year-old who's like,
you suck and you should die.
Like, you just gotta step back and like go outside sometimes,
which seems like a very reductive take,
but sometimes it's what you gotta do.
You.
Okay, uh, I didn't understand 50% of the first few minutes of your talk where you were
memeing at me and I genuinely laughed at your dad pun. Should I just sort of stay away from
this, uh, trying to do what you've done here?
Well, I don't think you have to.
I think it's just the understanding of like,
lost my train of thought.
I don't know.
I don't think you necessarily have to understand memes
because the whole point isn't, you know,
don't try to directly do memes.
Why didn't I go longer?
I don't have good answers to questions.
I'm sorry.
Thank you for your question.
Oh God.
Hi.
Hello.
Well, the point was don't use memes, right?
The point was don't use memes, right?
Yeah, that was it.
That's what the talk was about.
Good talk.
Thanks!
Do you have any examples of dads
that didn't fit this criteria
and were scrapped dads?
Ghost dads?
Hmmm...
I don't know.
I think...
I think I wanted to do like a surfer dad,
like a real beach bum,
like just kind of hangs out in the beach house dad,
but that there would have been like no conflict there
because I just would have been like,
hey man, let's go surf.
And I think there was actually like Brian originally was going to just be like the sweet cinnamon roll dad who was just nice
And then we started writing that we're like hmm
If someone's just a cinnamon roll there is no such thing as conflict in this game. It's just not a 130,000 word
coffee shop AU so
We ended up like I was like shoot
I really wish that we had a rival dad because I just want like a dad another dad knew to duke it out and we're
like
I'll just scrap Brian's path,
like let's make him the rival dad, sure.
We have the assets, we're not changing it,
we're just gonna rewrite it.
So Brian was once a very sweet boy,
and now he's still a sweet boy,
but beneath the rival exterior.
Cool, thanks.
Thank you.
Okay, thank you.
Hey there, brilliant talk.
So actually, the gentleman over there
actually brings up a good point.
So as we as creators age, one of the things
that I'm I guess fearing is that we're getting
further and further away from exactly,
from the conversation itself that's happening
around the internet.
So like one of us might be using on fleek
when we're like 40 still for some reason.
So my question is like how exactly do you keep yourself
in the conversation as you age?
Um, higher younger people would be an answer to that one.
But I know that it can be really difficult.
And that's also just like following the right people on social media.
Like if you're just following people your age, like you really kind of want like a
scattershot from all age groups because
Yeah, but going back to the other point is just like,
make sure your thing is good,
because if you do a thing and it's just like,
oh, I own it, and I'm not implying
that this is what you're gonna do,
but if you're just like, I just won 100,000 retweets,
like, it's not gonna go so hot.
But yeah, just quality first, and then memes.
All right. But not, but not that.
Quality first, but also not, perfect.
Thank you, what he said.
Hello.
I mean, I just got to this one.
You could do those guys.
Oh.
Hi, hello.
I like hit, the lights are so bright.
You guys are just like indistinct blurs.
So, hello blur.
So with regards to writing and narrative design,
I was curious about how,
when you have characters that you're writing
and also you have visual representation.
And then with voice acting as well, delineating, like basically how specific you go with each given character.
As far as, you know, because like as soon as you start voicing a character, then that actually kind of closes off
what that character can be to a player.
Is that making sense?
As far as like...
No, that 100% makes sense.
That's why we did not do fully voiced things, because we pretty much just have dad grunts.
And even that I was a little nervous about doing, because I think so much of game culture
right now happens as a result of Let's Plays, and half the fun of a Let's Play is seeing
what kind of voice the Let's Players choose to do for the characters.
And so we just wanted to keep it really minimal
while still having some fun cameos from people
that hopefully players would enjoy hearing
make a lot of weird dad noises.
Did you find that there was a wide disparity
on how people voiced certain dads
or was it fairly consistent?
So you know how stressful it is when you write something
and then you have to read it in front of a group of people?
Imagine that, but then you look at the view count
and it's like three million and then you're like.
Okay, I can't do this.
So I've watched maybe like one episode of one Let's Play,
so I don't know.
Thank you.
You were waiting.
Okay, so.
I haven't played Dream Daddy, but I went to both your talks and they're both excellent,
so now I have to play it.
I wanted to ask about process.
I wanted to ask about research.
What were the most difficult things to research and how did you take some of the things that
you mentioned in your talk, like couching brain fart.
Sincerity.
Sincerity within cynicism or within silliness.
How did that inform your research?
cynical, like...
Yeah, I think with writing a comedy game,
the first thing that we figured out
when we were making the big flow charts of like,
here's how the narrative works,
and this happens and this happens,
like, along with figuring out like,
okay, here's the basic character arc,
one of the first things we nailed down for each character
was like, what is the emotional core of this story?
And then just layering lots and lots of jokes on it
and just making sure that like, it's a gradual...
path down like if you date Robert who's the bad dad like I mean you guys just run around
and like eat pizza in an alley and then he makes a joke about like this is where I come
to masturbate and like you whittle and all that stuff but then like his story gets kind
of like dark and sad later so it's just more of like a gradual you got to wade into it
I think but with the research.
I think the research ties itself to the sincerity because you are finding what the truth in this story is.
And it was really interesting reading the books. Like I read one book that was written by like a
heterosexual father and then I read that does this baby make me look straight and like does this baby make me look straight?
It's the sweetest like those are the most thoughtful parents and then reading this straight dad book. It's like
I'm threatened by my son, even though he is eight years old,
and my wife's authority threatens my masculinity.
It's like, God, dude, pull it the fuck together.
So yeah, it's also just like picking and choosing
what works for you and what doesn't,
because obviously we did not wanna have a dad
who's like, I'm a big, strong man,
and I don't need to have feelings talks with my children,
because that threatens my identity.
Yeah.
Thanks.
Thank you.
We got five minutes.
What's up?
All right.
Thank you first because I didn't realize I needed to see AO3 in a talk until now and
it was great.
I got you.
Yeah.
And when you build a game for inclusivity and you build your Twitter for any, your outreach
for inclusivity, how, what is your mentality when people still feel unincluded?
Like how do you reach out to those people and what's your general approach there?
there is no such thing as perfect representation,
but that doesn't mean that you shouldn't strive for it.
You just kind of have to accept that some people are,
it's just, I wish people could, on the internet,
could learn the phrase, this is not for me.
And that's okay.
And that can be a really difficult thing because you can really try your hardest and be taking as many steps as possible
at every single step of like, okay, is this inclusive? Is this inclusive?
We have all these consultants and you can still fuck up real bad.
And I think another important thing, especially in regards to social media,
is never, ever market your game on the inclusivity.
Don't do it. It is the bare minimum.
Not a thing you should get cookies for.
And also people will come down on you so hard
because it's super transparent of like,
well, we put fat people in this game,
so give us a pat on the back.
That's, sorry, sorry, no, that's not a dig.
That's not a dig.
It's a thing.
No, no, no, I'm laughing because that's hysterical.
Yeah, okay.
But yeah, just because people,
like the moment you say that you're inclusive,
like people are gonna be like,
well, how inclusive is it really?
And then you will get call out posts.
But yeah, just do it because it's the right thing to do
and it's good storytelling, not, you know, whatever.
Thank you.
Your experience and sharing it was really valuable.
Yay. Hello.
Hey, hi. So I came to the talk thinking that it was about how
to put your game out there without being embarrassed,
but I think what I understood was the opposite.
It was like being embarrassed is the way.
Yeah? All right.
Yeah.
My entire brand is just how fucking ready I am to get off of this stage.
Who?
Alright, so my question is if I understood it right.
Seems like, yeah, thanks.
Oh, yay.
Alright, okay, nobody, no, we're done.
Thank you.
You guys did great.
Yay!