Hello everyone and welcome to the Animation Microtalks.
We're so thrilled to have you join us here today with a quick show of hands, who here has been to a Microtalks before?
All right, all right, quite a number of you.
That's fantastic.
Well, welcome back.
It's great that some of you already know what you're in for.
For those of you who don't, let's start off with an introduction.
My name is Brandon Mason McConkey.
I'm a senior animator on the Overwatch team at Blizzard, and I've been involved in the Microtalks either as a panelist or a co-host for the last four years.
Each year, we choose a theme that guides these talks in order to make sure that they are cohesive in narrative and structure.
And yet, despite our best efforts, they still tend to be pretty chaotic.
We've had deep dives into bat facts, diatribes against crutch culture, and one year we even closed out with a musical number.
But you know what, that's part of their charm.
Unlike the other sessions you might see at the Animation Summit, the MicroTalk series isn't meant to leave you with trade or technical secrets.
You won't be learning new animation layer workflows or how to untangle the noodley mess of your state machines.
Instead, these talks will focus more on the culture of animating in our field.
Experiences, observations, rants, wild musings.
Our goal is to offer insight into the aspects of the industry that aren't often discussed, and to do so through the individual lenses of our panelists.
So, what unifying theme did we choose this year?
Well, that's actually pretty tricky.
Generally speaking, we like to keep three things in mind when crafting them.
First, it should be broad enough so that 10 speakers can create unique presentations that don't all discuss the same ideas while still providing enough focus so that they don't all talk about the same thing.
Secondly, the theme should be topical enough so that it resonates with our audience.
So ideas like, how the rumble pack changed my life are probably a non-starter.
And lastly, we want our themes to be affirming, inspirational even.
Ideally, we'd like each of you to leave this session absolutely stoked to engage with this community.
With this in mind, I turned a bit introspective in search for an answer.
What's something that's provocative enough to generate interesting ideas?
What shared experiences would be worth exploring?
And what challenges do we face as a community?
And you know what?
One idea, one sentiment, kept bubbling up to the surface.
And that was that this industry can be a real shit show sometimes.
which is not the theme of this year's Animation Microtalks, but I think it might be something that we can all relate to and have encountered at one time or another in our careers.
I know that I personally experienced this, and you know what?
It starts at the very beginning.
As a student, the barrier to entry into the industry felt almost insurmountable.
Not only does it require thousands of hours of work to learn the craft and refine our skills, but it also has the added bonus of sometimes costing an ungodly amount of money as well.
Finding that first break is so vitally important, but the path to get there can be hard to navigate.
And once you do get your foot in the door, finding a job that values you as a person and artist can prove difficult.
Our passion for making video games is often used as a tool to overwork and underpay us, and it's easy to become jaded about the industry as a whole.
Layoffs, studio closures, cancelled projects, this field can be brutal.
Not only that, but the job itself is hard.
I've never once sat at my desk at the beginning of a project and thought to myself, well, this is going to be a piece of cake.
When people say every ship game is a miracle, man are they not kidding.
And as game developers, every day represents a new challenge that we have to overcome.
So why do we do it?
If it's that hard and that stressful, why would we put ourselves through it?
Because making video games is frickin' awesome.
And honestly, I think we're an optimistic bunch.
I think we have to be in order to be good at what we do.
In order to create something out of nothing, we have to have the ability to look forward and see the potential in ourselves and what we're creating.
We have to have the unshakable belief in vision that allows us to be able to walk into a conference room, stand in front of some extremely important people, and say things like, I think a giant, uh, sentient space ape who eats peanut butter and shoots lightning should be the face of our game.
And then we have to defend it.
We are a community of problem solvers.
It's what we do day in and day out.
Challenges don't scare us, they excite us.
There's just this spark of joy that happens when you tinker with a problem for hours, if not days, and everything eventually clicks.
Something ephemeral, but compelling.
Those times when you delete a single frame and it fixes an entire shot.
Or when you hook up the right node in the blend tree and all of a sudden that one annoying pop disappears.
Even when you can't solve the problem on your own and have to turn to your colleagues for help, the collaborative problem solving involved can still be upon it's health.
And it was this collective sense of optimism in the face of the trials and tribulations that are so deeply ingrained in our industry that eventually inspired the theme of these micro talks.
Because if there's one thing I admire most about this community, it is the drive to make this industry better.
To push boundaries and test limits and to always look towards a new horizon.
Yep, New Horizon checked all the boxes, broad but directional, hopeful in tone, and left plenty of room to explore topics that would resonate with all of you.
We've recruited an incredibly talented panel of speakers for you this evening.
They come from all across the industry and more than likely have touched at least one or two of your favorite games.
and they put a ton of work into these talks.
For only being about five minutes long, the microtalks are some of the most challenging of the Animation Summit, largely due to the format.
Each speaker gets exactly 20 slides that auto-advance every 16 seconds to make their case.
No more, no less.
Timing, as always, is the most important thing that we do, and I know they're gonna knock it out of the park.
I'm so excited for you folks to finally see what they've been working on, so please, sit back, relax, and enjoy the final session of the Animation Summit 2023.
Once again, my name is Brandon Nason.
These are the ways to contact me if you should feel so inclined.
Hey, everyone.
My talk is, Are You Not Entertained?
How Flirtious Gags and Easter Eggs Benefit Players and Devs Alike.
I love finding Easter eggs in games.
I think it's because by their very nature, they're like a little gift you didn't know you were going to get.
But did you ever realize they can also be a gift to those that make them?
My name is Danish Syed.
I'm a principal UI visual designer at Respawn Entertainment.
I have a pretty diverse background and degrees in computer science and animation.
I've worked in film, TV, and games.
And I always love finding new ways to entertain myself, which, as you'll see, is a pretty useful quality to have when making games.
There's a great quote about development that says it's like playing chess against a formidable opponent, but where you have to commit to all your moves in advance.
I don't really remember who said it, but it stuck with me because it does a great job illustrating how difficult and complex it really is, and how much thought and planning is required.
I think most developers would agree that we have dream jobs, but that doesn't mean we can't get buried under that which we love.
There's always a ton of work to do and not enough time to do it in.
And as we all know, art is never finished, only abandoned.
We all want to polish our work to perfection, but often have to move on to the next task.
Yet, sometimes it's important to take a break and do something for yourself.
Something pointless or silly.
Something to give yourself a creative boost to make it through production.
There's lots of ways you can do this.
I'm going to cover a few methods I've used over the years to give myself a fun diversion and inject a little more life into the game along the way.
The simplest and easiest is the flourish.
Take an extra bit of polish, a fun addition, a small Easter egg, taking your task beyond what's necessary and doing something that gives you a real sense of satisfaction.
It's the kind of thing fans won't miss when it's not there, but will notice when it is.
For example, in Mortal Kombat 11, fighter customization was a key feature of the game.
In addition to full body outfits, each character could equip three pieces of gear.
I designed and choreographed unique animations for every gear piece for every character to not only highlight the item, but also express their personality and move set.
So when it came time to do the Joker, I thought it'd be funny if we broke the fourth wall and had the camera itself be afraid to approach the character.
The Joker would then egg you on to get closer and scare you when he got close enough.
And, of course, laugh at you for falling for it.
In another example, I wanted to treat his gear like an infomercial, where he's trying to sell you the item, complete with on-screen graphics.
New and improved Joker products, of course, a reference to the classic 1989 Batman film.
In both of these examples, I broke the template of what we were doing with other characters and tried to have a little extra fun.
Another example in MK11 were the friendships.
I designed a lot of typography for the game, but for the friendships, I wanted to do something a little extra.
And something as fun and light-hearted as the animations themselves.
I even threw a little extra star if you get a flawless victory.
The next method is a little bigger, the side mission.
A task that's maybe not part of your normal responsibilities, but something you really enjoy doing.
It could be something you might chip away at over a longer period of time between tasks.
Almost like a personal project, it just happens to be part of the game.
In my case, I have a background in motion graphics.
And my previous job was designing and animating title sequences for film and television.
So I never missed the chance to leverage those skills and craft some cool titles for a game.
We could have easily shipped without it, but for me, it was really fun to do, and it was good for the game.
Finally, we have co-op mode, recruiting collaborators to grow your gag into something a little more ambitious.
It's basically feature creep, so use sparingly and be mindful of others' time.
Now, the iconic handshake you see here is not just a visual metaphor for this category, it's literally what we did.
The Predator was a guest fighter in MKX, and so I worked with a handful of other developers to put in an Easter egg that recreated the famous handshake.
You son of a bitch.
The interesting thing about the handshake is that it opened the door for our characters to interact with each other on the select screen, something we hadn't done before.
We built on that for Injustice 2, having the entire system based around character interaction.
You can see our first prototype here.
Something that may not have happened had we not proved it out previously at MKX.
And here you can see it in action.
One character attacks and the other responds to the counterattack as we go into slow-mo, creating a cool visual tableau.
Each character has a variety of attack types to keep things varied, an uppercut, a side hook, a chest strike, and each character would have all three animation reactions to play accordingly.
With this new template firmly established, we had time to have fun with it.
The flash was the perfect candidate.
As the slow-mo kicks in, the flash enters the speed force, and we see him react to his slow deployment, a wonderful gag that has its roots all the way back to the Predator handshake in MKX.
It's important to remember you don't want to inadvertently make things harder for your fellow developers.
In the last example, everything was planned and approved.
As features begin to grow, you have to be aware of downstream effects in QA time.
Pick your moment and keep everybody in the loop, and don't creep.
Unless everybody's on the same page.
With all said and done, these little gifts to yourself will make it out into the real world, and players will notice no matter how small they are.
Even the tiniest details will spark joy in those that see them, and they'll want to share that joy with others.
Creating a game is a long road, the end of which can easily be lost over the horizon.
So we should do what we can to keep ourselves invested and engaged throughout.
While you work hard to make fun for others, remember to make some fun for yourself.
Thanks.
Hello, my name is Hayden Cooper.
I've come from the world of ViewModel animation.
I'm here today to talk about why InSpec animations are one of the coolest things in ViewModel.
So, tap your mags, push your forward assists, and strap in.
What is an inspect?
In the inspect is a V model animation in which the player is viewing their weapon in first person.
They're able to see the details and mechanics of their weapon and all of their glory.
So what is ViewModel?
ViewModel is first person.
If it's hard to explain to your friends or family what you do as an animator, add on the extra layer of saying, I work with only hands and a weapon.
They're sure to understand.
The inspect is a nice-to-have animation.
It is not a necessary sequence in the same way that a reload, a draw, or a fire animation will fit into your gameplay design.
It's not responding to a specific event.
inspect animations are a really cool opportunity for us view model animators to step on stage and demonstrate our knowledge and skill by fiddling with all the bits and bobs on these weapons.
And it really helps to kind of show off the assets or tie the room together.
So why are inspects a thing now?
I think they're situations for us to really define and set the mood.
Pretty romantic.
In situations outside of gameplay where the player isn't just running around and shooting anything they see moving.
But not all InSpecs are made the same.
There are three types of InSpecs that I'm recognizing.
There are player-initiated ones, where a player presses with a hotkey, and there are extended idles, and smaller moments known as fidgets.
A player initiated inspect.
This is when the player presses a button to start the inspect and they have full agency to stop them.
I'll say that these are more common nowadays.
And depending on how fancy you can get, it can lead to some pretty cool gaming clips as you see here.
This is me, by the way.
Next are extended idles.
These are incorporated near the end of the idle animation, and these can be just as flourishy as they are seen in older games where they didn't need a dedicated hotkey.
Lastly are fidgets, which are smaller moments of readjusting the weapon that really show how heavy holding this weapon up can be, or after gripping it for so long, how sweaty they can get.
So it's a little readjustment, just a little, sorry.
Majority of the time in a first person shooter, your attention isn't on the weapon, but it's on the battlefield.
You're scanning what's ahead of you and InSpecs are going to break that.
By bringing the peripheral into your foreground.
Creating opportunities for acting.
Who is holding these objects and weapons will vary from game to game.
Some will be full of gritty, mil-sim operators.
Others can be rosters chock full of varied personalities with distinct characteristics.
There's a lot of world building that can go into it.
A grounded shooter is the perfect place to reflect shooting doctrines or training of that era.
Such as this example, the operator is pulling the slide back, doing a chamber check to ensure that this weapon is 100% loaded or unloaded.
If the world you're building isn't as grounded and heavy as lead, you can get away with some pretty ridiculous stuff.
As seen here.
Stuff like this shows the game will be a wild ride and full of fun.
Weapons and objects in your game are going to vary.
A pistol will feel lighter and snappy, while rifles like the sniper here are really going to feel the force that it takes to operate it.
Also because it's good just to take another moment to see it.
or maybe there are bits and pieces on a weapon that you've been looking at the entire time you've been playing.
And so did the animator, who has worked on it for many, many hours.
So perhaps you've thought about fiddling with this little bit.
Those tactile experiences are really important because the worlds and levels first-person shooters are in are set up in pretty rigid ways and for many different reasons, but I'll let level designers talk about that.
So, InSpec animations really help flesh out the world that you're playing in.
InSpecs as we know it haven't always been around.
They've evolved to what they are because of weapon customization.
Extended idles and fidgets are what have paved the way for player-initiated InSpecs that we have now.
Those InSpecs today are a work of art.
It is a showcase of a team's talent across disciplines.
It's more than animation, it's modeling, it's audio, and it's visual effects.
All of these are on stage performing together and going absolutely ham.
I'd argue that we are in a renaissance of view model animation, that these InSpecs in particular are the epitome and peak of the craft.
I like to assume that we're just scratching the surface when it comes to this kind of stuff.
So I just want to say thank you for letting me gush and ramble on about InSpecs today.
My name is Hayden, and I hope everyone here has a fantastic rest of their time at GDC.
Take it easy.
All right.
My name is Jean-Paul Reimuller.
I've been in the industry for about 13 years now, this year, three in film and the rest in game development.
I'm an Associate Animation Director at Blizzard, currently working on Diablo 4 in Cinematics.
It's easy for many folks who stay in this biz a long time to get stuck in their ways and can often dig their heels in instead of letting themselves learn, grow, and evolve in this ever-changing industry.
So I found an analogy with how we approach eating food with my son.
I know, makes perfect sense, right?
We always ask our son to try a new food once before saying no, and this has led to him enjoying foods that he never thought he would.
It's called his no thank you bite.
If he doesn't like it after that, then we don't need to push it on him, and at least he tried it, and now he knows whether he likes it or not.
Hopefully, that will help him make a more informed choice next time, right?
Seems simple, right?
So if we as animators and artists can stay open to just trying something new once in a while instead of digging our heels in, just think about how much we can learn about ourselves and others while pushing into new horizons.
Starting out in film, I always considered myself a high-functioning animation machine, right?
And my only real goals were to continue to grow my skill set and to take on whatever challenges were put in front of me.
As I transitioned to game development after a few years, that notion was challenged for the first time.
For the first time, I had to understand the functionality of what I was trying to create and how it fit into everybody else's idea of what works.
Not all individuals were concerned with the quality of my animations, but more how it felt and what the player experience was.
I started to question my choices, my skill set, my goals.
I got real feedback about who I was as an individual collaborator and not just my skill set.
So I questioned.
Did I make the right choice to transition to games?
I also felt inspired at the same time.
So what the fuck is going on?
I was getting opportunities, though.
Opportunities to take some bites out of something new that challenged this way of thinking.
Challenges that at the same time felt like it was taking focus away from my goal to be this high-functioning animation machine.
As my career went on and I worked on different projects, I began to take on more challenges.
Leading wasn't something I was initially hired to do, but it was presented as an opportunity.
I was scared shitless and many times I felt like I had no idea where to begin.
but I tried it.
And even though the experiences I have had are not always what I intended them to be, I learned by just saying yes to something new from time to time allowed me to become a better collaborator, a better teammate, and ultimately a better developer.
It wasn't, isn't that what we all want?
An environment where we can challenge ourselves, fail a ton, learn, and ultimately grow?
Doesn't this lead to success in many areas?
Well, not always the way that you would think.
Now, some of the areas where I have said, sure, I'll try that out, gave me opportunities to gather new perspectives and skills.
but when it was over or near the end, it also helped me find out what I was really passionate about and where I ultimately wanted my career to go.
Transitioning to an art lead was one of the most rewarding moves I ever made.
Did I see it at the time?
Hell no.
It was nerve wracking and I just took a chance.
I was way outside of my norm and my comfort and I felt like I was failing all the time in the early stages.
But what I did realize is that with the support of my team, my leads, mentors, I was able to push past that on most days.
And I was able to hone in where I was needed in this role rather than force myself into areas that the team didn't need me or that would have overcomplicated things.
And at the end, when asked to be an art lead again, I was able to say no thank you with confidence and continue my journey where I knew I would be happy in, in animation.
Without those experiences, I would have never had that perspective and confidence in the next horizon.
As our careers move on, I have found that opportunities are there, not all at once and not all the same, but they're there.
The question is, will opportunities still be there if I don't take some of those bites?
Moving forward from here, how do we foster this simple concept within ourselves so we can help our co-workers, our family, you all, to try something new, to take that bite?
The perception that we can't change habits to help build opportunities can sometimes hold us back from pushing ourselves and others.
I've been coming to GDC for almost seven years.
Look at all those faces, right?
And in the audience, look around you.
Some I met way back then, some I met just last night.
You will have shifts in your career that you may not be able to influence.
Company changes, project shifts, a pandemic.
If we can find those small bites though and say yes, even if it's just a few of them, you may walk away with a much different experience that you will have along the way.
Look at my son.
Now this week, GDC will give you plenty of opportunities to take a bite before saying, no thank you.
It is in those moments that I think about the excitement each year, the passion that I see here, and the challenges that everyone faces when I discover that I'm not alone.
It gives me courage to go back to my studio to challenge myself and my team to continue to push towards those new horizons.
I'm John Paul Ryan Miller, Associate Animation Director at Blizzard.
Stay engaged, stay connected, thanks for listening, and I'll see you in Sanctuary.
Hi, my name is Yuna, and I'm here to talk about existing productively and professionally on the internet.
So we're going to open this one with some audience participation.
Raise your hand if you've ever felt that horrible cringe of seeing an old post that you made two or ten years ago on the internet.
Feels pretty good, right?
So for my first GDC, my teachers told us to print physical business cards.
So imagine my surprise when people asked for my Twitter handle instead, and that being online seemed like a social requirement for the industry.
However, I'll now list what scared me about putting myself online.
I'm an introvert.
Going on the internet means being perceived.
People could be mean to me, and I can have the emotional fortitude of a newborn puppy.
People I admire and potential employers, they would find me and they would judge me.
So how did I start putting myself out there?
Well, as someone looking to break into the industry in 2018, this was the only thing I could do.
So to give myself the courage to start, I came up with a structure for curating a more professional online presence.
This was a chart I saw as a student and my instructors told us that people like working with these people way more than those people.
I wanted to telegraph myself online to be around here with a healthy dose of kid who's got lots of spunk and lots of potential.
So, for me that wasn't quite specific enough to get started, so I made this Venn diagram to spark some positive introspection and to define the pillars of my desired online presence.
I decided I wanted to present a good work ethic, that I learn quickly, and that I'm passionate about animation.
And at the time my content strategy mostly hinged on the Anim State Discord and on Twitter.
Now, some stuff about Twitter has changed since the year I started using it.
I'm not going to talk about that stuff, but take the Twitter-specific language I use with a grain of salt.
So, how did I communicate my pillars on Twitter?
First, I almost exclusively posted work in progress threads of personal work.
This was super scary, especially when using industry hashtags for more views, but they showed the game dev community my work ethic, that I could learn quickly, and that I could take and implement feedback.
Second, I kept it professional and engaged only with industry-related content.
And third, I tried to keep my tone professional and kind.
Being a dick on the internet gets you nowhere, especially in a small industry like ours.
I also jumped into the AnimState Discord at around the same time and I mostly kept my rules of engagement the same.
The strength of AnimState is in the direct accessibility to professionals and the sheer concentration of industry knowledge, so I was mostly active in the feedback channel to practice asking for feedback and to practice giving constructively critical and actionable feedback to others.
My biggest rule was to treat everyone on the server like a teacher and potential co-worker, and now an enormous part of my early success was rooted in taking online animation courses.
I didn't go to art school, I got my undergrad degree in biochemistry, and I actually took the MCAT before deciding on a slightly different career path.
These online courses were how I learned animation, and a lot of my social media posts were actually class assignment progressions, so these classes gave me both the structure to learn animation and content for my online job-seeking presence.
I genuinely can't recommend these classes enough.
Not only were my instructors incredible teachers, but being coached by industry veterans on how to specifically better present myself was invaluable.
So now, five years later, I've gotten jobs, I've been able to grow my industry community, so now I mostly use the internet to post pictures of my cats.
So what worked for me may not work for you, and I'll leave both current job seekers and industry professionals with some suggestions about connecting online.
So to job seekers, do your research.
Have someone's details correct before you ask for their time and attention.
Do make the effort to come up with specific questions and make it easier for us to help you.
Do be excited.
We all love animation and games and so we're starting from common ground.
Don't assume the worst if you don't hear back.
People are busy.
And don't be a dick if you don't get what you want.
and to the professionals out there, do take the time to respond, especially if you recognize genuine effort.
When I was starting out, I had absolutely no clue how to learn about the industry except for cold emailing folks.
and the pros who made time for me back then were able to steer me in the correct direction and that turns out pretty well.
Here I am.
So you all know who you are.
Thank you so much.
And just also don't be a dick.
Absolutely nothing comes out of discouraging the future talent of our industry and they could be your coworkers tomorrow.
So in conclusion, just on the internet, be thoughtful, have fun, and don't be a dick.
that is my talk.
All right.
Hello, everyone.
My name is Emily Katzke.
I'm an animation lead at Bungie.
And I have a confession for you all today.
I sit at my desk like a pretzel.
I know, I know, it's terrible.
For those of you who are 30 and under, you may or may not understand the full weight of that confession.
But for those of you who are 30 and over, I know you get how bad that is.
Y'all just felt a chill run down your spine, okay?
Now, truthfully, I have had this problem since as long as I can remember sitting at a desk.
I was never taught proper desk posture, and even if it was mentioned in passing, I never took it seriously.
I remember these pains starting as early as high school and getting worse and worse as I made sitting at a desk my job.
Now, I have tried so many things to fix my posture.
I have tried those elastic bands that you put your arms through and they tighten, and they're supposed to get you to sit upright.
In reality, they just pinch your armpits.
I have also tried that, like, buzzer necklace thing that you put on your back, and it's just a buzz to remind you to sit upright.
In reality, it just makes you feel bad every two minutes out of your eight-hour workday, every day.
And then finally, I tried just good old-fashioned working out your back and your core muscles to have the strength and stamina to sit upright.
In reality, I just had my typical desk pains with the added post-workout soreness on top.
Now, I know I am not the only one with this problem.
I have seen you shrimpies out there.
I have seen the goblins.
I've seen whatever this thing is.
My point is, I am not the only one, okay?
Now, I am not here to fix our posture, obviously.
But what I am here to do is to tell you how I completely eradicated my desk pains, and that is through stretching.
Now, I'm going to ask for some audience participation.
I'm going to need all of you to stand on up.
Put yourself down and stand up, and we're going to stretch together.
Let's do this.
All right, y'all.
So, what you're gonna do is stand with your feet shoulder width apart.
You're gonna have your back straight, your shoulders down.
You're gonna make sure you're mindful of your neighbors.
I know it's packed in tight, but you should be good to go, okay?
You're gonna keep your shoulders down.
And then, you are gonna be mindful of your own body.
If you feel any pain or discomfort, please stop, okay?
Be smart.
So, we're gonna start with good old-fashioned wrist stretches.
You're gonna put your right arm out,
talk about
make it good, and relax.
All right, we're gonna do your left arm.
Same thing, left arm out, palm up, grab your fingertips, and pull back and down towards your arm, and relax.
Left arm out, palm down, grab at your knuckles this time, and pull, this is the last stretch, make it good, and relax, shake it out, shake it out.
Okay, so next up, we're gonna do back stretches, just a good old fashioned, stand up straight, you're gonna put your arms out in front of you,
grab one hand with the other, and then you're going to reach out and all the way up.
Make it good.
I think about going like behind my head a little bit.
Put your back into it.
One more.
And relax.
Shake it out, shake it out, shake it out.
Okay, I'm going to talk you through this last one, and then we're going to do it, so just hear me out.
The next thing we're going to do are neck rolls.
Your head is a nine-pound bowling ball, and we're going to make it do all the work for you, okay?
So you're going to think about sitting up straight, keeping your shoulders down, and what we're going to do is drop our head forward, roll to the right, back, left, forward, left, back, right, forward, deep breath in.
and we're done, okay?
So, let's do this.
Stand up straight, shoulders down, drop your head forward and slowly roll to the right, to the back, to the left, and forward, and back to the left, to the back, to the right, and forward.
You're going to take a deep breath in, sit up straight, and exhale.
on
So what you're going to do is follow me on Twitter if you like this because I'm going to post so much more there because I feel so passionately about how this changed my life.
I'm talking desk stretches that you can do at work and people won't stare at you funny.
I'm talking full body stretches that you can do at your home, the gym, anything that involves a little much for work.
And I'm even going to do targeted stretches.
So if you're like, I just care about my neck or my wrists or my lower back, it's all going to be there.
So thank you all so much.
And frankly,
I hope these stretches help you as much as they've helped me.
Hello, my name is Josiah Haworth.
I've been a game developer for around eight years and I am currently a senior animator at Riot Games working on the first-person shooter Valorant.
And I have traveled all the way from Los Angeles, California for my very first GDC to tell you all that I am an idiot.
Don't laugh too hard.
But in all seriousness, I would like to share a personal journey that led me to game development and hopefully help you avoid the pitfalls that I fell into.
But in order to do that, we're going to need to take a step back and get a broader view of my mistakes and how I spent almost six years of my life chasing a job in film when I should have realized where my heart truly resided.
In storytelling, a hero's journey is usually initiated with a call to action that forces or convinces the character to embark on an adventure.
During this journey, the character conflict often arises when a character's wants are misaligned with what they actually need to grow.
We see this a lot in animated films.
In Kung Fu Panda, Po wants to fight like one of the five masters, but what he really needs is to embrace his own unique fighting style.
In Princess and the Frog, Prince David wants to marry rich and live the high life, but what he really needs is to find true love.
And just like those characters, it took me a while before I realized what I really needed.
Growing up, I wasn't obsessed with the Godfather or the latest Spielberg movie.
I was obsessed with trying to figure out how to catch the secret Mew in Pokemon Red and Blue, or chasing down rumors on how to get the Triforce of Power in Ocarina of Time.
But animation captivated me.
And after watching a DVD of The Incredibles at my retail job for the 100th time, I decided I wanted to animate for a living.
However, it never dawned on me that games needed to have animations.
Like I said, not the brightest.
I applied for the animation program, but was only accepted into the game art major.
This was my first hint.
However, after accepting, instead of taking the hint, I was actually disappointed and felt that I had failed.
For a brief moment, I was actually on the right track, until a spot opened up and I switched majors to animation.
All through college, while others were using their free time polishing up their filmmaking skills, I always spent mine playing Team Fortress 2 and hosting Enemies of the Dark Descent Horror Nights in my dorm.
I was studying film, but I spent all my free time playing video games.
After graduation, my first job was at an AR company that wanted to make their own games.
It wasn't a film, but I thought I could potentially use it as a stepping stone towards feature animation.
I continued to have near misses with game development until I got a call back from Blizzard Entertainment.
And I cannot stress this enough.
I am so foolish that even after joining Blizzard, my main goal was to use it as a point on my resume to go into feature.
But my time there changed me, surrounded by the most talented, kind, and thoughtful people I had ever met in my career.
People that I had so much in common with.
I resonated with my co-workers, and now fellow devs, in a way I had not experienced before.
We talked similarly, we could have long conversations about games we found and what we hoped to make.
And from this, my heart began to truly open to game development, and I began to learn.
From World of Warcraft, I learned that technical restrictions breed innovation and critical thinking.
It taught me that keeping the goals and limitations of a project in mind, and how to work within them to get the best performance possible.
And most importantly, that ideas in animation are king.
From Overwatch, I learned that with great power comes great responsibility.
In a system and game where everything is possible, keeping the game design and scope in mind was key to success.
It taught me restraint, but also had to mesh character fantasy with their ability to design.
And since Valorant was my first launch title, I learned how gritty and organic the pre-launch period can be.
How trust and empathy are vital at such a formative stage of the development cycle.
And also how to take tight game design restrictions and infuse it with character fantasy.
and slowly but surely the bubble of stupidity surrounding me broke down.
It took almost 10 years to realize that what I really needed and was truly hungering for was to be part of making the games that I enjoyed so much.
Game development is a beautiful collaborative mess.
It is truly a job where teams are stronger together, where collaboration and mutual respect are key to success, and where the goal is for every craft to plus the work that was put before it, all in service of the player.
Nothing beats the feeling of having players notice that little extra touch you add to the game, because those are the moments that I remember when gaming.
And being able to do that for others has made me realize more and more that working in games is what I needed all along.
But please, I'm begging you, learn from my stupidity.
Don't dismiss an opportunity out of hand simply because it may not tick all of your boxes.
Don't lock yourself into working on a specific project, or a specific studio, or even a specific game type.
Not every job can give you what you want, but you can learn things that you need from every project.
It's been some time since I realized that being a game developer is what I needed, but seeing players be surprised and delighted by the work that I do only strengthens my love for games.
My name is Ryan Duffin.
I'm the animation director at Undead Labs.
When I was asked to sub in for another speaker, I started thinking about the zeitgeist of 2023.
Two things jumped out at me, AI and feedback culture.
Brandon told me the talk should be uplifting and inspiring.
And I was like, yeah, you got it.
No problem.
So in flip-flopping between the two and my own non-committal nature, I found a common thread, so I'm going to try and squeeze in both.
Here's the real title of my talk.
The first one is bait.
It's worth mentioning that I'm not an AI expert.
If I say anything insightful here, it's regurgitated from people who are smarter than me.
However, the removal of the need for human expertise is thematically appropriate when we're talking about AI, because it makes no secret about that trajectory.
The discourse among professionals and professional creatives seems to be either angry shouting that this shouldn't exist, or casual acceptance that it's just another tool on the inevitable march of progress.
Whether you think it should exist or not, it does.
And yes, it's no secret.
It's a tool, but it advocates
Its advocates have made no secret that democratizing is a nice-sounding word for cutting out expensive experts like us.
Six months ago, some of these mid-journey prompts might have been paid artist work.
AI advocates freely admit that with potential comes threat, but for game dev, we also need to consider testing, so the machine doesn't fill our games with dicks in Hitler, and the legality of training models is still in question.
We can't ship things we can't verify the source of, and AI can be cagey about sources.
And I don't want to be the woke police here, but every human that MidJourney produces is pretty hot.
Nobody's average, nobody's ugly.
Unattractive means not a model.
Apparently stockbroker means bodybuilder.
These are two prompts I fetted.
I did not specify white or male.
Whatever your thoughts on diversity, that's a blind spot to reality.
It's just a tool is pacifying language.
You have to remember that not every tool is created with ethics or consequences in mind.
Some tools change the course of human history.
Some tools destroy entire industries.
It is a tool, and I'm not saying it's one of these.
Only time will tell.
That bait title was generated by chat GPT.
To anyone who buys or sells the self-aggrandizing bullshit of some of these conference talks names, this is fucking gold.
And it makes me wonder, is it the machines that are impersonating us?
The scary thing is that AI regurgitates things that exist in novel ways.
And that shouldn't be scary to a room full of creatives, but it is.
In AAA, we creators, through our mergers and market research, organize media into formulas and tropes that are predictable and reproducible.
Even if AI is just some kind of fancy auto-complete, how many of our interactions or entertainment really challenges our feelings or emotions?
Games can be beautiful, fresh and original, but a lot aren't.
We're up to our eyeballs in retreads and clones, dosing us up with enough dopamine to not notice.
Of course we're at risk of being replaced.
We make ourselves replaceable when our entertainment is banal and derivative.
AI is creating content, AI-created content is here,
and the lowest hanging fruit is junk food.
Are you saying pretentious artsy fartsiness is the only way to save our industry?
Not everything we want to consume needs to push or provoke us.
That's fine.
Tropes exist for a reason.
Sometimes you just want a cheeseburger and a lot of us are cheeseburger makers.
The robots are going to figure out cheeseburgers before they figure out duck pate.
The advantage we meat sacks still have over the machine is we can imagine, we can critique, and mindfully iterate.
AI can produce, but it cannot judge and it cannot feel.
Great art can move us, but we can't make things great if we can't talk about them critically.
Maybe you've heard the term toxic positivity, but you've definitely experienced it.
It's a pretty simple concept, the idea that a positive attitude is everything.
Don't point out problems if you don't have the solutions, and silence all negativity.
And to some people, any critique sounds like negativity.
I was down on time to drink in these, so.
Does this make sense in a professional environment?
We're lucky in games that lying to ourselves and each other, when something's bad it just means delays, cancellations, layoffs, or mediocre games.
Would you take a cruise or a flight that's managed this way?
Do you want a pilot that doesn't want to hear about the engine fire?
Positive attitudes have become a sort of prayer, but they don't cure cancer, climb mountains, put out fires, or plug holes in ships.
And there's quite a bit of evidence that suggests the opposite.
They can make us totally oblivious to our problems.
this lack of self-awareness isn't so different than the AI.
Artists and animators learn critical analysis as part of our trade, but game dev culture is having a harder time with this type of communication as our industry matures.
It's largely on us, the creatives, to help lead people toward a culture of constructive feedback.
To make things good or great, we need to be honest about the fact that they're not there yet.
Of course, open feedback is not an excuse to be aggressive, mean, or disrespectful.
We criticize the work, not the worker.
You've maybe heard the term radical candor, usually in the context of someone making excuses for being an asshole, but it's definitely, it's defined as saying what you think while giving a damn about the person you're saying it to.
A life-changing concept for me was when Brene Brown explained the difference between guilt and shame as what I've done versus what I am.
Every animator in this room has made a bad animation.
It's fine.
It's how we get better.
We're professionals because we make more good ones.
Despite all effort to monetize
Sorry, this is a last minute talk.
Despite all effort to structure, produce, and monetize, we are still a creative industry.
If we're going to compete with this new technology, we're going to need to double down on the things that make us and our work human.
Creativity, passion, self-awareness.
The opposite of love is not hate, it's apathy.
People who speak honestly about problems still care.
They're invested in making things better.
Now more than ever, we need to embrace the tools we humans have that these new technologies do not.
Computers don't know what is good, what is great, what is appealing, moving, or meaningful.
That's what we're for.
To do that, we have to push ourselves harder to be better, and we have to be honest with ourselves and each other when we're not.
If this talk didn't suck, it's because I have good friends who gave me good feedback.
Thank you.
So, unfortunately we had two speakers that had to bow out last week, last minute.
Silver lining of that, though, is that we get to close out with another musical number.
Yeah, so, okay, so the talk, I was a substitute, JP was as well, and he was dignified enough to not complain about it like me.
So yeah, it was I think in February.
And I was really busy.
And even like a week afterwards, I was like, do you really need me to do this?
Because I'd rather work on my car.
And I was told yes.
And so I went for it.
But then as I was stressed out and finishing the talk and all that, I thought it'd be funny because we did a song the last time we were here.
I was like, I'll have Chad GPT write a song.
And it was okay, like it was an okay song.
And I'll try to keep the story, the short version.
And if you're at the bar later, I'll tell you the long version.
But here's what I have in my notes to describe this.
So after GDC 2018, Mike, wherever you are, I don't know where you are.
Anyway, Mike Jungbluth said, you should do a musical microtalk.
And I said, OK, but only if Landa does it too.
We wrote a song called One Keyframe at a Time.
We played it at GDC 2019 as a surprise.
I don't think we're going to top that, but I've been thinking about doing another one since.
So I had ChatGPT write one about how it's going to steal our jobs.
And it did, and it was OK, but I thought maybe I could do better.
First, I was trying to edit it into something, and then I just wound up shit canning the whole thing.
writing something different.
That was on Wednesday and I finished it on Friday.
I think on Thursday night I messaged Brandon and I said about 70 percent chance of this happening and then it happened.
So the video you're going to see here was done by on Saturday lunch.
Simon Unger is supposed to be here unfortunately he couldn't be but he was going to be second guitar.
Can we get it a little louder?
Thanks.
Or a lot louder?
They say they democratize but they
It can take a famous face and put it somewhere compromised It'll take a politician, fill their mouths with different lies A coalition forced to hell, also will have more junk to sell
Hello.
Sorry for the technical difficulties