The first talk of the day, as you can see,
is Steve and Nina here from Fulbright
talking about level design in Tacoma.
-.
So I am a level designer at Fulbright,
and obviously I worked on Tacoma.
Tacoma, for those of you who haven't played it,
here's a screenshot of it.
It's a first-person 3D exploration game
set on a space station in the near future.
It's about a woman named Amy who's been sent
to retrieve an AI from a space station called Tacoma
that has been recently evacuated for a reason
that you as the player are not fully aware of
in the beginning of the game.
And you play as Amy and sort of discover what happened with this crew that left and why the AI is still there and all this stuff.
So the game is really about exploring the station to learn about what happened there recently.
And the story is communicated on multiple levels throughout the game, both mechanically and through the environment,
which is what...
sort of this whole topic is, because it's all sort of relating back to level design
for us.
So we'll explain what some of our design goals were, how they relate to level design specifically,
and what it was like actually implementing them throughout the development of Tacoma
from the beginning to the end, basically.
So I'll pass the torch along to Steve, who will kick off our little discussion.
Peace.
Thanks, Nina.
Let me see, can I angle that a little bit?
No, I can't.
So, yeah, I was the co-story lead
and kind of the creative direction force of the game.
And I come from a level design background.
So, like Nina was saying, Fulbright, Fulbright.
in the Level Design Summit is a piece of level design jargon.
So like the name of our studio is a level design term.
So we have a very like level design centric
kind of founders syndrome about how we tell stories
and what the focus of our design process is
and how we relate to the player.
So on my side of the talk,
I'm gonna talk a little bit about the kind of top down.
direction and player experiential intent behind the game,
how we got to that from Gone Home
and what we were trying to do with Tacoma
and how we worked together to put that on screen.
So yeah, our first game at Fulbright was Gone Home,
which there's a screenshot of up here,
which was a game about exploring an empty house,
well, empty of people house,
to find out about what happened
to the people who lived there.
It was a story exploration game,
a walking simulator of early vintage.
And it really focused on just the environment,
the objects in it, and what you could learn from that
and finding audio diaries that explain the story within that.
But going from Gone Home to Tacoma,
we wanted to expand on what we do
with these kinds of games mechanically and work.
more on how the player is involved
with the moments in the story
and how they engage with finding the story actively
in a way that we didn't in Gone Home.
We wanted to bring the player closer
to moments in the story as they happened,
while also allowing them to have the full freedom
to find every detail they're interested in
like they had in Gone Home.
So as part of that, we were really heavily inspired
by immersive theater productions like Sleep No More,
where the audience shares the space with the performers
and follows them through the performance space
and kind of chooses their own path
through these scenes that are happening.
Something that is, I'll talk a little bit more
about Sleep No More, it's a performance
that's been in production for like, I don't know,
like six, seven years now in New York.
and it takes place across three floors of a converted hotel,
and I think it's actually a converted warehouse
that they made look like a hotel.
But basically, you as an audience member in this space,
and there's a lot of performers that are moving through it
along their own paths, and you as an individual
can only follow one, you know,
you can only be in one place at one time.
So the performance is an hour long,
but it loops three times over the course of the night,
and so you as an individual can say like,
oh, I followed.
these performers into this scene
and then follow that guy last time,
I'm going to follow the lady
that was the other side of it this time
and see more of the total,
but you're kind of building up partial information
about what the entire performance is
through what you choose to observe.
We wanted to take that core experience,
which we felt is really unique and valuable,
and convert it into a form that felt native
to a digital experience.
And so for us, what that meant was that since this is a
digital game, instead of it just looping and you choosing
what you're gonna do on the next loop,
we could give you the ability to fast forward and rewind
and pause and be in control of both the performance
and your experience of it instead of just your experience
of the performance.
So we wanted to give players the tools
to understand the story as it happens
by actually being able to have hooks into it
and what they are seeing of it and what it's doing
along with being observant.
Basically to be a more active observer
than we had in our prior games.
But we didn't start from this as our set of core mechanics
when we started working on Tacoma.
When we started, we had a bunch more traditional
progression style.
We started with a story and progression structure
that was very close to Gone Home.
Here we have the first thing you do in Gone Home.
is move an object and find a key and unlock a door with it,
which is extremely traditional.
We do have some locked doors and stuff in Tacoma,
but it was more at the center of what we were doing
in our first rev of the game.
This progression style is derived
from classic audio diary-based level design,
so I worked on the, multiple people at the studio
worked on the Bioshock series before we worked at Fulbright.
And I kind of learned how to tell a story
in a level from those games.
And I was very familiar with how you stage out spaces
to place story breadcrumbs to have the player
kind of move through a story as they move through a space.
And in a lot of ways, I was probably too familiar with it
because we said, we should do that again.
And that's fair, right?
Like, I don't know.
it's a legitimate way to make a thing.
But as we started to do it,
we kind of realized that it wasn't speaking fully
to what we actually wanted to do with the game.
In a mostly linear story game,
you use audio diaries to match the player's flow
through the space.
In Gone Home, you're discovering this story of
a young woman named Sam who's a high schooler
and kind of what's happened to her
in the year that you've been away.
She moves to a new house,
which is the house you're exploring,
goes to a new school,
meets another young lady at the school
and they fall in love.
And so, you know, in the game,
this is the first part of Gone Home.
This is the entry and the West Hall of the house.
And so, you know, we arrange the plot points
in the order that you'll most likely encounter them.
And it can feel non-linear,
it at least is player-driven and self-guided,
but it still is saying we're going to send you
on a reliable path through these spaces
that tell you a linear story.
And in its original state,
Tacoma followed this same design approach.
The spaces were laid out kind of as a string of pearls,
and each point in it contained an isolated
section of the story or a plot point or a moment,
and you moved through them and they were basically spent
and then you continued on your way.
And our first pass included these AR projections,
these 3D recordings that ended up being the core
of the finished game, but they were much more isolated.
They were essentially visual audio diaries.
I think that we've seen these a lot in games,
where you kind of are playing a sci-fi game
and you walk into a room and a hologram shows up.
you don't really need to look at it usually.
It's just, you know, it's visual flavor for an audio diary.
But as we were doing that,
we realized that, yeah, it wasn't really different.
It wasn't really, you know,
something that we hadn't done before.
It was just a sci-fi version of here's your audio diary.
And so, you know, with that version of the game,
we basically, it showed us what we wanted to do
with this, you know, element of what we were doing.
because it showed us what it wasn't doing.
So, you know, the fact that these AR characters
actually fit in our kind of stayed level design process
showed that they kind of weren't having enough impact
on the game, because they didn't force us
to design it differently.
There were one or two places in the original version
of the game where these AR scenes kind of spread out
over more space and showed us the potential of like,
oh, okay, this person leaves the room
and you can either stay in the room or follow them
and you're kind of doing that piecing together.
But it still was localized.
It was still on the scale of just like,
you know, kind of a 20 foot radius
or 40 foot radius or something.
But it showed us that we could do more with it.
if we thought about level design differently.
Our levels needed to be reshaped
to embrace nonlinear interconnected AR scenes,
which means they needed to be designed for those scenes,
not be designed and then we put the scenes into them.
They needed to be just larger and more complex,
have more going on in them.
The scenes needed to be longer,
they needed to cover more area,
and the kind of area they covered needed to be different.
It basically was the thing that forced us out of our traditional, you know, shock game,
audio diary level design territory, which is good, but it also meant that we had a lot
of new problems to solve, which is also good.
except when you're trying to ship a game,
because it's hard.
It takes a long time.
So, you know, our AR scenes turned from these points
where you would kind of encounter one character,
a couple of characters, and either two webs.
They had multiple characters
that all had individual threads
that were running parallel to each other
and that, like Sleep No More,
you couldn't see all of at once.
In fact, you can't see all of any of our central AR scenes
unless you.
pause and rewind and move through them a number of times.
Pardon me.
And we leave that to the player to determine
how deep they want to go into seeing
the content of these scenes.
But that was also good because that is in line
with what we wanted the player's relationship
to Gone Home to be, which is to say,
there's a house here, there's a bunch of stuff in it.
find all the stuff, it's because you wanted to find
all the stuff, not because you felt like you had to
or you're checking off a list or whatever.
And so similarly, at the point that we expanded
on what our AR scenes were, it reinforced
that central player experience in a totally different form.
So that's good.
But it took us a while to get there.
It took us a first version of the game
that we were like, oh, this isn't what we're doing
to realize what that was.
So now when you play Tacoma,
you see our version of what it means
for these AR scenes not to just be visual audio diaries
but to be the central mechanic of the game,
the way that you discover the story
and what the rest of the game is supporting
as opposed to being a supplemental part
of the overall experience.
So.
That was our direction, right?
We worked together to discover the mechanics
and what the requirements were
for that central player experience.
But then the question became,
how do we actually build those spaces and build the scenes
and do the work to support the player
through that entire experience in the details,
not just at the high level.
And so Nina's gonna talk a little bit
about that process of putting it on screen.
Wow, nice job, Steve.
I'll be back later.
I'll clap for you.
We'll clap for you every time.
One thing I want to add to what Steve was just saying,
which wasn't in my slides, but now I want to say it,
is that people, other developers, might find it interesting
that in that process of going from more of a string of pearls
approach to this interconnected AR scene approach
with the rewinding and fast-forwarding that we ended up with,
We had a whole full version of the game that we had built
that we just basically completely threw in the trash.
And that was over a year of work, maybe?
Sometimes you do pre-production on purpose.
Sometimes you realize you were doing it afterwards.
Yeah, exactly.
You spend a year on pre-production without realizing it.
So this was all a big learning experience for us, I feel like.
And yeah, we really did kind of end up
starting largely from scratch when
we found the actual mechanics that we felt inspired by.
So maybe just a little nugget that people
might find interesting.
So I'm going to talk about paper mapping and gray blocking
and all that sort of implementation stuff.
So what I knew when I started paper mapping,
which I think it was like me, Steven, tied in,
I did a lot of it though,
what I knew was that from this earlier version of Tacoma,
the thing that was inspiring us,
that made us want to change the game so much.
were the scenes that were taking place in these more open, interconnected spaces where
characters in our scenes could walk around from room to room and sort of like pass each other
in a natural way. And that felt like a pretty good structure for our AR scenes, and I'll get
into a little more detail about what that means, but I came into the paper maps knowing that.
And I knew a little bit about the AR scenes that Steven Carlo were developing and I knew that each part of the station
would serve to house a specific character with a specific job
And thus would need the realistic facilities to support these functions. So with that in mind I focused on creating
nonlinear spaces that would support both the future AR scenes and sort of the more utilitarian aspect of like
Who are these characters?
And what are they actually doing there?
What do they have to do to realistically fulfill their job
in their section of the station?
So it's like, we have like our botanist
has like his botany wing, sub wing,
and then we have like our engineer has like her area.
So it was sort of like job based sections of the game
that I was paper mapping early on.
So here is some text and not the paper maps because that's the next slide.
Let's see.
Oh, it's because I didn't hit the button correctly.
Okay, so to get more into paper mapping, here are some actual paper maps.
I want to talk about why I think sort of our initial approach worked so well with AR scenes
that were eventually built with these.
And these are two of the early admin paper maps.
So the administration wing is like sort of the first big wing that you encounter in the
game.
And it contains the operations facilities and the personnel, the admin and operations
facilities and it's called the personnel wing.
Sorry.
So the earlier paper map is the one on the left,
and then the one on the right is sort of closer to what our final, like, gray block ended up being
and what the final level is now in the game.
So while I was paper mapping and working on that one on the left, which is the early one,
I'd ask myself how the rooms would be laid out
and what order they would be laid out in, sort of in the space,
such that the people who live there could actually use them realistically.
So I think this is especially important because Tacoma is about a bunch of characters that
are living and working on a space station like in isolation with this small group.
So they're like literally living in their workspace.
And so how do I design a space that seems like it would actually be tolerable to someone
who is in this sort of extreme situation?
So one of the obvious questions for this is like where does the bedroom belong in this kind of space?
Where do the personal spaces belong in this like primarily?
Workspace oriented station, you know, yeah, I interject. Yeah
So something that as far as the paper map goes something I think is a couple things. I think are probably interesting are a
So Robert has done a blog post at some point about sort of like the stages of being a good
level designer basically and how there's sort of like complexity and interconnectivity of
space that you learn over time.
And I think that you'll see that.
The one on the right is a much better version of that
than the one on the left.
And it both supports our scenes better
because the spaces kind of have overlap
the way the scenes do,
but it also just naturally makes it feel
like a more believable place to be.
Especially on a space station,
it's like they want to have a conservation of space.
So as far as the fiction driving what we do,
we were like, also we should bring it in
so there's not wasted space.
It's up.
The other thing that I think is,
hopefully
I don't know, it's interesting to me,
is that Nina, before she worked at Fulbright,
had only made smaller 2D games,
and so this progression is also Nina learning
to be a 3D level designer as this process was going on,
and I think kind of like,
it was very interesting to me to see.
your paper maps evolve as you kind of did a lot of revs
of like, I'll paper map it, then I'll gray block it.
Oh, I can see why that isn't really what it was going for.
I'll paper map it again based on that.
So some of the progression, I think, of the spaces
was also like your learning process
as kind of becoming a level designer, which was cool.
Yeah, it's hilarious.
I was looking through all my old notebook of paper maps
and I looked at the first one and it was just like a box.
Like I divided the box a couple times.
Gotta start somewhere.
It was so bad.
I didn't put that in any of the slides.
Too embarrassing.
But yeah, I did a lot of paper maps
and one of the things we did focus on was yeah, like
cutting out stuff, like cutting out as many hallways as possible
and just like making our spaces as compact as possible
to also support the realism and the utilitarianism of these spaces
because like you wouldn't...
it doesn't make sense to have such a sprawling space station.
That wouldn't make sense for the company in the game
to build such a huge space with a small amount of people
who have, as we explore in the game, crappy jobs.
So it's a small, very compact space.
And the paper map process was super iterative.
So the time difference between these two paper
maps are pretty wide.
We did a lot of iterative paper mapping,
especially in the beginning.
So.
Like I was talking about the bedrooms.
So when we're thinking about like where a bedroom would go
in like a workspace on a space station like this,
you probably, when you think about it,
you probably don't want it near the entrance of a wing
because that doesn't feel very private, right?
You also don't want to put someone's bunk
right next to their office
because like who wants to sleep next to their office?
Like you probably don't want to do that.
And even though this is like a corporation building it,
I still don't think they would even do that.
That would be really evil.
We could have gone that direction.
So we wanted to make sure that there was a clear separation
between public and private spaces on the station,
given the fact that the station was built
for long-term postings on it for these people.
So I iterated on these paper maps with this concept in mind
and came to a decision that our levels should have
the sort of hub and spoke structure.
So for example, admin's hub is the dining room.
So you can see it's sort of like that central space
where all the other spaces branch off of it.
And each space that branches off the central hub is separated to a different degree based
on whether it's a workspace or a private space.
So most workspaces branch directly from the hub without much space in between since they're
meant to feel more easily accessible by multiple members of the crew who might need to use
them for work.
So the conference room is right next to the dining room.
I have it circled right there.
And that conference room even has a window looking into the hub
because the conference room is like an extra public space
where like they're having meetings
with many different people on the station.
And the conference room is also like, it's also sort of like associated
with the dining room because it's like these sort
of like public gathering spaces.
And this wing is really like dedicated to that because it's
like administration.
This is where people come.
to meet with their supervisor, Evie, to have meetings with her,
to go to the conference room, to eat.
And so it kind of makes sense to have these places closer
together for us.
And then sort of the opposite of that is the private space.
And in this wing, I have circled here
where the bunk is for Evie.
Evie St. James, she's the station administrator,
so she lives in the administration wing.
And her bunk has this sort of nice hallway
that's connected to that hub space.
But.
it has the separate hallway unlike the conference room
which literally just has a door and a window
separating it from the hub space.
So this is like an example of how we're like
separating private space more deliberately.
And this kind of approach with the hub and spoke structure
and separating private spaces really deliberately
works super well for AR scenes
because you can have conversations.
that intersect and break off in a natural way.
So for example, you see a lot of conversations in Tacoma
intersect in the hub space of a wing
where the characters would naturally
be passing by each other.
So like say there's one part where it's like,
Evie like comes out from her office
and she's walking through and then she ends up
in a conversation at the dinner table
because she's like naturally moving from a private space
to a public space and encounters a group there
and stops to talk to them.
And then like.
with these more public spaces, it makes sense
that they would be gathering there
to hang out with each other, right?
So the open interconnectedness of these spaces
worked super well because of that natural flow of people
through them based on how they would be
living their lives naturally.
So I have some more examples of this.
So we have Sarah right here who's at the pool table
in the administration wing talking to Odin
who's the station AI, and she talks to Odin a lot,
and it's great.
And so she's in this open space that the dining room overlooks.
So she, you can see sort of like there's an upwards ramp going up,
and there's a dining room above, and then she's below with Odin.
And soon enough, she's like, she's sitting there playing pool,
and then Nat actually comes over to the railing,
which I have her little yellow arrow pointing to Nat,
and she like calls Sarah over for cake, which is happening.
upstairs. This is kind of a neat moment because it's like you're maybe as a player you're focused
on what Sarah's talking about to Odin and that's your full attention is focused on that
and then suddenly you hear this voice you know Nat calling out like hey like look over here
and you as the player will like shift usually and like look up see Nat calling to Sarah.
and then see another group of characters
gathered up around the dining table.
And then that gives you a lot of information about,
oh, okay, so there's another part of the scene happening.
While I've been paying attention to Sarah,
maybe I should rewind and go see what Nat
was talking to those people about.
So that's sort of a nice moment
where the hub is really a space
where you can kind of like see multiple
nodes of conversation happening
and be made aware to go check out
another part of the scene later.
It's kind of nice.
You guys want to hear a dorky level design thing about that?
It's a scripting thing, actually.
So you don't want to be able to hear everybody from everywhere.
Something that I think most developers don't really, well,
anyway, in this kind of game, it's
not very common for you to have to really worry
about a lot of overlapping conversation.
But we did.
So it was like, how do we make it
so you can hear people a little bit from far away,
but it's not just stepping on each other?
Some of that is our programmer, Hannah,
put in a system where if you're.
looking at a character, they're louder,
which is nice if you look away from somebody,
they get quieter.
But that doesn't really speak to something
like someone literally calling
all the way across the space.
So you could do something smart and programmery to do that,
or you could do like we did,
which is when she yells,
we script her voice range to be twice as far,
and then we put it back to its normal range
when she's done.
Yeah, we do that in a bunch of spots.
With the like, yeah, the far away conversations
where people are like, hey.
Yeah, so don't overthink it sometimes.
Just turn it up.
Yeah, so this worked out really well.
And also if you think about it,
it would have felt sort of,
I think it would have been less rewarding
given our mechanics if we had, for example,
had this playroom where Sarah is separated
by a hall and a door from the dining room
because then Nat would have had to walk down the hall
to get Sarah and the player wouldn't be able
to see the crowd at the dinner table.
Right, so this sort of hub structure where the spaces are interconnected and
looking into each other gives us the opportunity to make these moments where
you can see things in the distance like that.
Which wouldn't work as well with too many very separated rooms that don't look
into each other.
So, obviously not every AR scene is going to have conversations that are always interconnected
like this and flowing in and out of each other.
Sometimes there's going to be very private moments that we want to isolate, or that the
characters would want to isolate themselves.
The screenshot I have up there is when Evie goes into her office, which is a private space,
and she takes something out of a drawer.
You can look at it, it's a photo of her sister, and she has this sort of private moment.
So it's for these private moments where characters are being more introspective
or having like a one-on-one conversation that it's useful to have the private
spaces be separated like we did on purpose sort of for the utilitarian aspect.
It also helps us sort of design scenes that can have private moments because we
have specific parts of the level that are designed to sort of make that possible.
We dubbed in some of the sound of constructing these levels
into the background of the talk for your pleasure.
Yeah, the dub.
The construction dub, not subbed.
So we found a lot of useful ways to design AR scenes that
made good use of the hub and spoke structure.
And there were still, wait, why did I?
I love it.
I love PowerPoints.
So, like I was saying, we found these useful ways
to design levels that supported AR scenes
that could have both interconnected moments
where characters are talking to each other in groups
and flowing in and out of conversations,
and also the private stuff that happens
in these more private spaces.
We had found all these ways to design the levels
to support that stuff, which was great.
but we still had some elements of the level design
that had to adapt to our AR scene specifically.
So Tacoma is a station where people live.
So for example, there's a lot of tables and chairs and beds.
and various objects that the characters would naturally
have to interact with while they're going
about their daily lives.
Like, wouldn't it be weird if no one ever sat in a chair?
Like, that's just something people do,
so you would expect it to see
in these daily life scenes, right?
So we're a pretty small studio with one, one, one
full-time animator who animated almost all of it
with some help later on, which was awesome.
but she did a great job and but it meant that once the AR scenes were animated
there couldn't be significant changes to like what the animations were because she was making a lot
of animations and had to keep going so we could you know ship the game so we want to stay on
schedule and if a character sits on a rock like Clive does in the screenshot
That rock can't move.
The level designer put it there at one point,
Noelle animated everything specifically
to line up with it.
If we move it, like, she's not gonna update the animation.
That's on us.
So we had a lot of animation dependencies like that
that were in communication with the level design
and that we as level designers had to work around
and be aware of.
So here's an editor screenshot.
If I was placing or moving objects or architecture,
I'd know that they were labeled as animation props,
animation-dependent props, so I would know not to move them.
And sometimes you would also just watch a scene
to make sure you weren't placing something
in an awkward position that...
a character was already moving through.
Like if I wanted to do some set decoration,
I would have to make sure like,
don't put this like pile of garbage, right?
Where Evie's like walking,
because why would she walk through that?
She would trip over it.
So we had to be very careful about stuff like that.
Because these AR scenes were being animated
sort of simultaneously as we were like building these levels
and placing a lot of stuff.
So it was all happening in parallel, which was.
a lot. It was intense. So sometimes we actually took advantage of this effect. Like I was
talking about not wanting to place the garbage where Evie would clip through it while she's
walking through it, because that would be weird. Sometimes we actually took advantage
of that for narrative reasons, which was fun, because seeing a character clip through something
could give the player some information about the time when that AR scene actually took
place.
So...
Basically, it could help the player understand the timeline of the narrative through observation
of what objects were moved after the events in the AR scene occurred, or perhaps objects
that had not moved since the AR scene had occurred.
So, for example, in Botany, here we have Sarah's leg clipping through the hose right at the
bottom there where her foot is.
And later on in the scene, you actually see Andrew setting up that very hose as part of
the scene.
He's sort of doing some maintenance to help the oxygen situation on the station.
So you can see him in this screenshot stepping over the same hose that she was
formerly clipping through.
So while for the most part we tried to prevent
AR scene characters from clipping through stuff
in ugly ways, sometimes it was fun to provide
this kind of narrative detail where you could have
the situation, because if you think about it,
every level's always in cut scene mode,
but a lot of the environment is static like this hose.
So if you're watching it carefully,
you can kind of catch these weird moments
where it's like, oh yeah, this was moved during the scene
and I can kind of see that.
and what is the thing Andrew is actually touching.
It's kind of fun to show the player, like,
this is an actual object that this character
really did touch at some point.
So, the environment really needs to be in conversation
with these animations in both time and space.
based on this example I just gave.
So while the level design of the floor plan was done before,
like the paper maps and stuff was done
before these animations existed,
we were still able to have our AR scenes
be a narrative conversation with the environment
using like set decoration moments like that
that were placed sort of later after the paper mapping
and gray blocking was done.
So that was fun.
So I want to go a little deeper into this time and space aspect of AR scenes,
being in conversation with the environment.
Because one of our big challenges was guiding players
to these things called AR desktops, which I have circled up there.
AR desktops are the characters' computer desktops that they'll open from time
to time at specific points in an AR scene.
And when I say desktop, I mean like literally like their computer
with their emails and stuff on it.
Like you can...
Frob, you can click whatever that thing,
the button in the air, and it opens their desktop
in your vision.
So, given the spatial nature of AR scenes,
this means an AR desktop is only accessible to a player
during a specific window of time during an AR scene.
So for example, Nat only opens that desktop
for like 30 seconds a minute into the scene.
and then she'll close it after it being open for a couple seconds.
Because that's the amount of time she takes in the scene to check her email or whatever she's doing.
So, early in development we found that players were frequently missing out on these error desktops
entirely during playtests. They would just miss them, not see them,
maybe be near it in a scene but be facing the wrong way for example, and just totally whiff on it.
and then would move on and just have no idea
that there was all this extra story stuff
for them to discover, which is a problem for us.
So AR desktops often contain some
really great narrative beats,
so we wanted to fix this issue.
We had to learn how to guide the player to an AR desktop
at a specific time in a specific part of the level.
because otherwise they would just miss all the stuff.
So here is an image of one of the early era
desktop button iterations in our editor.
And because the first approach we took to this
was just like by relying on the buttons visuals.
And we were like, maybe if we make it eye catching enough,
like people will just see it easier,
which is like kind of funny that that was our first approach
now that I think about it.
because it didn't work because the whole problem was like sometimes people would just be in a
different part of the area or like not looking at it at all. So no matter how eye-catching it was,
they still weren't going to see it because they needed to be in a specific place
at a specific time. It wasn't an issue with the button being not obvious. It was an issue with
place and time. So we realized this and it was a key realization because
We looked at the AR desktop timeline, which I have like,
this is actually our first sketch of this idea,
which is funny, from our whiteboard.
And that playing bar is like a rough sketch
of our AR scene timeline that appears
at the bottom of the screen that you're using
to fast forward and rewind.
And we realized that had a lot of free space on it
that wasn't being used to convey any information.
And we were like, oh wait, we could give the player
like some kind of hint on the timeline
as to when the desktops are appearing.
So we are gonna switch to the next slide.
Here I've circled the AR desktop again.
And I've circled this time the pips,
which are what sort of came from that realization
that the AR scene timeline could be used
to convey this information.
So we tutorialized this early on and stuff,
but it actually worked out really naturally.
Most players pick up on it right away,
where it's like when you're scrubbing through the timeline,
those little bubbles will like inflate
and turn to their associated character's color
when the desktop is active in the world,
and then they'll like deflate when the desktop is closed.
So players can kind of use that to be like.
okay how long is it open for, what character should I be looking for,
we didn't just rely on color, we have the characters
job icon on each one also to like double up on that information.
And so yeah that was a really great solution to be like
here's a way to give the player a hint but not actually like
give them like an in-world like quest marker or whatever where they're like
looking for it in the level like
they just have the information of the timing
and then they do the exploration themselves to find it.
So that worked really well.
Another challenge we faced early on in Tacoma's development
that's related to the AR scenes
is that we wanted AR scenes and desktops
to be tied to progression in some way,
but we didn't know what that would be at first.
So we wanted to do, we tried some like traditional,
ah, no, I hate it.
Sorry.
We wanted to do some traditional progression at first
involving keys and locks,
because that's kind of what we were used to.
So we tried that first, and then through playtests,
we quickly learned that.
people would find keys in desktops.
We put them in a lot of desktops early on.
And once players learned about that,
their whole goal was just to look for desktops.
And they would just fast forward through the whole scene,
not listen to anything, and just look for desktops,
because they were like, the keys are all here.
If I just find all the keys,
I can progress through the video game,
and that makes me feel good.
And we were like, that's great,
but we want you to pay attention to our AR scenes,
so we have to change how we think about progression.
to help the player actually want to engage with AR scenes in the story while also feeling
like they're making forward progress by doing that.
So basically I pitched this thing called the Sync Device, which is, this is what it actually
looks like in the game.
And I was like...
So these AR scenes, narratively, are this data that's been left over on the station,
like this kind of security camera-esque footage of what...
these people were doing there.
And we also have this concept of going to retrieve this AI,
which would probably involve some sort of download.
So I was like, what if in each wing of the station,
you basically have a USB drive type thing
that you're plugging into that wing
and syncing with the data there
as part of your mission to retrieve the AI?
You have to sync with each wing
in order to access the AI in the end.
And this I pitched as sort of like a.
a progression system based on something that we understand from our real lives.
So like people playing video games are probably familiar with downloading stuff or using a
USB drive so they know when they see this plug into the wall and it starts ticking away
with its little percentage meter, players actually, we thought this wasn't going to
work but then it did.
Players mostly are like, yeah, I see that download going, I'm going to go do other stuff
because downloads are slow.
and we make it go slow on purpose
and don't give the player a clear understanding
of what exactly is making it tick.
And they just assume it's gonna go
and they can come back later and it'll all be fine.
And this actually works.
And we're really.
surprised and happy about that because this sort of gave players the room and
time to move through space and counter the story while they're sort of like, okay that downloads going so like I guess I'll just chill and
learn what's going on with these characters.
So the sync device in Tacoma creates this illusion for the player
that the data is
is being synced.
And we don't have the sync device actually,
like if you stand in front of it and look at it,
it looks like it's ticking away steadily,
but it's actually under the hood not.
So the device's completion percentage,
which goes from zero to 100,
is boosted every time you recover
or completely finish an AR scene.
whenever you walk into a new room.
And there are a couple of other smaller factors
that make the percentage go up a certain amount.
But we don't, there's nothing pinging the player about this.
This is just happening purely under the hood.
So the boost based on player actions
helps those who explore it,
because they're exploring and then they come back
and they're like, oh, it's at 50% now.
That's cool, I guess I'll go check out this other area
and it'll probably be done by the time I'm back,
because that seemed to go pretty fast.
It was also really important to us for the sync device to be located in a physical space
that was outside of the wing.
We talked about having a tracker.
So like the characters in the story, Amy, who you're playing as, also has her own AR
desktop that you can pull up at any time and you get messages on it and stuff.
And we talked about having a tracker that you could check on your desktop and we did
not do that because we knew that at that point...
It's interesting to make a progression system
that is explicitly about being opaque
and not knowable to the player.
And so if you could be like, oh, it's at 10%,
and then I recovered this scene, and now it's at 20%,
oh, I see, so I should just go game this
and find all the stuff to, then, again,
it would be like when people were just going
into desktops to try to find key codes.
you would say, oh, okay, so now how do I touch everything
to get this filled up as fast as possible?
Whereas when you actually have to walk down a hall
to a space and start exploring it
and then disengage from that to go back
and check on what the progress is,
it both makes it less clear how to game it at all
and it puts it out of your head until you're like,
I think I'm done here, maybe I should go check that thing.
And then it gives you something to do
to progress of your own volition
without there being like.
achievement unlocked, achievement unlocked,
just like popping up on your desktop as you play.
Right.
And our sync device isn't very strict about this stuff,
so for most players, just by like going to each area,
like it'll just go to 100% without too much effort.
So we wanted to make it sort of also easy to do,
while still requiring some amount of like exploration
and engagement with AR scenes.
So yeah it it was sort of designed to support these non-linear levels cause the sync device
doesn't really care what order you're encountering things in it just says engage with the
environment I'll take care of the rest. So that worked out really well for us.
There's the sync device again.
And now we have some hilarious, horrible art from me
that I drew of it when I was pitching it.
So just some fun stuff to show you
sort of where we started with this.
We wanted to like, we like did think about
how would Amy carry this around?
That was kind of fun.
And then Kate, our environment artist,
drew lovely concept art of it, which is great.
So that's kind of what.
our initial design was for it. So yeah, that's sort of my end of things. And I'm
gonna pass it back to Steve and he's gonna talk more about stuff. Thanks.
So you're doing a pair talk is great. You get so much more
applause. So, you know, I think what Nina was talking about is, you know, from
our
perspective, all of the elements of what we were doing
were really in conversation with each other.
You know, the spaces are connected
to the fictional function of the station.
The AR scenes are connected to the shape of the spaces.
The player's HUD markers and the design
of the progression mechanic are connected
to how the player engages with the AR scenes
and how they direct themselves through each area.
And all of these elements support each other
and they loop back into each other, right?
Like the.
space determines the progression and the progression tells you something about the
setting and the fiction and what your job is and that, anyway. So you know, this is,
none of them stand on their own and they're all reinforcing each other. So from a
creative direction and player experience standpoint, that's really good. You know,
we're talking about unifying all of these disparate elements and making them feel
like they are a cohesive whole. And you know, this level of deep integration
between all the parts of the story and the environment and the mechanics,
it also presents a lot of its own production challenges.
So let's talk about the writing and recording
and the implementation of an AR scene.
Something that was interesting, I think unique,
about how we worked is we had to have our gray block layouts
of the station locked down.
before I could write the story.
Because the playable spaces in the station
determined what would happen in each scene.
The scenes are about these characters
moving through these spaces.
So I needed to know the kitchen's over here,
and the conference room is over here, and the dining table
is here, and the pool table is there before I even
wrote a scene about how Nat was going to call down
to Sarah at the pool table at this point in the story.
Pardon me.
And I don't think that there are a lot of games
where the level layout being locked
is a dependency on starting to write the story of the game.
But that meant that we had to iterate early
and feel confident in, okay, these spaces make sense
for the function of the space
and for an explorable space,
fictionally and from the player's perspective,
and feel confident in that.
Because like Nina was saying about the animations,
having a dependency on just a prop being placed somewhere,
the story had a dependency on the level design
not changing very much.
So up on screen is the paper map that Nina showed earlier,
the kind of final paper map of this section
of the admin wing, and then.
Next to that is a couple of pages from my notebook,
writing the game.
I always write all my stuff longhand in notebooks
and it can be really useful to, you know,
see revisions and see how things are connected.
You can see a little bit of highlighter here.
Writing this game was...
There's a lot of stuff that we did on this game
that we really didn't have any examples to look at,
for the most part, so we just kind of had to figure it out.
So in Tacoma, the game is about there being
these sections of scenes that branch off
and happen in parallel and then come back together.
So there were parts where I would be writing a scene
and then highlight like.
the blue part is this sub scene,
the green part is this sub scene,
they're happening at the same time
and then they come back together.
So the level design and the writing were really of a piece.
And you know, at that point,
yeah, we kind of had to just like stick with it.
We had to go from there.
Five minutes?
Well, I'll be goddamned.
All right.
So because...
As noted, we had to lay out the space, write the stuff,
and then we had to go record it.
And we recorded Tacoma ensemble style.
There's Mike Suricks.
I see him right there, our voice director.
Mike Suricks is here.
We felt it was really important
because all of these scenes were about
characters being in a room together
and having discussions and being face-to-face
and having these intense moments.
for us to record the game on a sound stage
with all the actors present performing the scenes together,
which was fantastic.
The actors were really excited about it
because in games mostly it's one person in a booth
and another person in a booth
and them being able to perform this
basically as a stage play,
them being able to react to each other's energy
in the scene and everything was really exciting.
But it also meant that we laid out the levels,
wrote the story, flew down to LA,
got six actors together for two days
and recorded the entire game.
And we weren't gonna do that twice,
so that had to stick as well.
So we had, for people who have shipped larger games,
voice recording on Tacoma was locked
14 months before we shipped.
Because our animator Noel had to animate
the fucking game based on those.
reads, so like, we could've done pickups,
you know, like small pickups, but we couldn't be like,
you know what, this scene should, we should do,
this should be something different here,
because then, you know, Noelle had to wait
until we had the final recordings to even really start,
you know, she could block out these scenes,
but to actually animate them, again, another dependency
on this whole stack of everything
being related to each other, which is, you know,
part of what Nina pointed out, but.
Something that we were really happy to be able to have is that
because
Like Nina was saying that we're basically in cutscene mode all the time
It meant it meant that the the animations could be very conversant with the environment. So we did a lot of
the characters touching the world.
So in all of these screenshots,
you can see Andrew's leaning on a rail
and Evie runs her hand along this railing
as she goes up the ramp
and Nat is sitting on the edge of a thing.
And that's, at that point, another place
where the gray block influenced the story
and then the story influenced the animations
and then the animations were touching a railing.
So if that railing was, for instance,
gray blocked in when the animation was made
and then we put the mesh in,
the mesh had to match the gray block
down to the centimeter.
or else the hand would now be floating or clipping
or blah, blah, blah.
And that went all the way down to things
like placing this mug.
So at some point, we were like, we're
going to have a jazz mug in the game
because we had a jazz mug in Gone Home,
and that's important to us.
So Noelle, our animator, was like, oh, OK,
so this mug is here.
So how about Clive is carrying this mug and drinking from it
during the first part of the scene,
and he puts it there during the scene.
And so we were like, cool, that makes sense.
And then at some point, we were play testing,
and we noticed that Clive puts the mug, like, he like.
puts the mug down and his hand just goes through it.
And it's like, there's no way for us to move the object
in such a way that he wouldn't just do that,
just knock that mug over.
And so that was one of those points where it's like,
we do need to update that animation
because it's no way that it makes sense
for this mug to be here.
But, you know, like,
so, you know, it's something like this where,
I guess the screenshot's a little dark,
but we had a bunch of angled walls in the game,
and, you know, those were gray-blocked in,
and then it was animated for Eevee to be leaning on this wall,
but when the wall mesh came in,
if the angle was a few degrees different.
So those are these, like, little things where...
we intended to build an experience
where everything was talking to everything else,
but that meant that everything was talking
to everything else.
The geo talked to the writing,
talked to the recording,
talked to the animation,
which then once the animation was in,
it talked back to the geo
because the geo had to make sure
that it was consistent with the animation
once it existed.
So when you're starting out, you should try to fully consider all of the dependencies
that are involved in creating a unified design as early as you can.
Not because you shouldn't do it, but because you should know what you're signing up for.
And as I noted, we didn't have a lot of precedence for what we were doing, so we discovered a
lot of this along the way, but I think there is valuable space for people to work in that
I think is easy not to do, which is the...
mental projection of if I do this,
what are the five steps later,
and what's this gonna touch?
It's easy to be like, if we do this, it'll be cool.
Or if we do this, it'll touch this one thing.
But really kind of trying to do the visualization exercise
of like, what is this going to lead all the way to?
I think it'd be valuable even just so that you can
expect those things before they happen
instead of stumbling upon them when they do.
So, one minute.
That's good. Because I'm on my last idea. So we're talking about doing a lot of stuff that
hasn't been done before. We're talking about doing, you know, getting away from a
traditional lock and key progression. But that said, we also did rely on those
traditional hierarchy of information or hierarchy of value approaches in
supplemental information. So the central space is very interconnected.
They're based on these AR scenes,
but we also wanted to encourage and reward players
to fully explore all of our spaces,
including the side spaces that Nina was talking about.
And that totally goes back to stuff that we've done before.
We have keypad doors that lock off optional areas,
and it encourages the player to say,
how am I going to find this keypad?
and when you get in there we have to reward the player. In a more traditional game that might be
like some rare ammo or upgrade points or something in our case it was just extra
information that tells you more about the story because you did the work.
to find it, but that isn't central to the player's experience,
but that uses a very traditional approach to hiding keys,
making blocks be clear, rewarding you for doing the traditional level stuff
to get in there, but we have to think of it in terms of, again,
the writing goes back to, like, what part of the story are we going to put in here
that it's okay for the player to miss, but that they'll actually be excited about finding.
So, you know.
For whatever you're working on, stuff that is traditional,
I think, is worth relying on as appropriate,
even if it's not the new, fresh, exciting thing.
Thank you very much.
Vernina, Steve, Tacoma's gonna be in the IGF pavilion
if you wanna play it.