I'm Laura Hall. I'm a game designer, artist, and writer. I live in Portland,
Oregon, and I make a lot of stuff. Right now my focus is escape rooms, but I'm
also really involved in like alternate reality games and art installation work.
These are some of the things that I've worked on recently. The Amazon Echo
Escape at New York Comic Con. There was a national tour of a Resident Evil game
that I helped work on.
The Silence in Room 1258 was an installation piece in London in 2017,
and the piece that we'll be discussing today mostly is Spark of Resistance,
which was the first ever escape room game that I made.
That one, it was in Portland, it doesn't exist anymore,
but that was a spy drama set in an alternate universe, kind of Cold War-era dystopia.
And today I'm going to talk about the design principles
of how I make deeply narrative and immersive escape rooms,
in particular the lessons I've learned
and the mistakes that I've made to learn those lessons,
and why those games work best when all of the work
that goes into them is totally invisible to the player.
But to kick it off, I want to define some stuff first.
And can I ask, how many people have actually been
to an escape room?
Yes, that's great.
That makes my job a lot easier.
So like a quick overview, they started out as
these point and click flash games in the early double aughts.
Someone pretty quickly had the idea to translate those
into actual physical spaces.
But the earliest you're seeing those is around that time.
So this is actually still a pretty new genre,
even though it draws from things that have existed
for hundreds of years.
When I'm talking about escape rooms, I'm referring to the specific physical space, people buy
tickets to visit it, they may or may not be locked in, it's usually against fire code
these days to actually lock the door, so that's fine.
There's generally an hour to play the puzzle, sometimes it can be as little as 45 minutes,
sometimes up to 90.
And often you're not actually trying to escape anymore, they're usually goal-oriented.
As an example, more often than not, it's defusing a bomb.
But it's a relatively new genre, and it's part of what we refer to as immersive entertainment.
So some definitions of that.
No Proscenium, which is an amazing resource for this kind of thing,
puts it as an experience that physically and usually narratively
places the audience in the same space where the action is occurring.
And Sarah Thatcher, who works at Disney and is amazing,
she defined it as something without a frame around it.
There's no proscenium, no screen,
it's something that's happening in space.
That also encompasses things like theater, haunted houses, theme parks, live action role play, installation work.
They draw upon a lot of principles that have crossover in user experience and video game level design.
And so while this presentation specifically deals with escape rooms, there are lots of design principles that I think are, and I wish were, universally applicable.
These are some of the dimensions of immersion
that you get either in a physical space
or in interacting with a screen.
So you're enjoying your time there, hopefully.
You're mentally engaged in the process.
You're feeling a sense of spatial presence,
whether that's in relation to a game controller
or the environment around you.
And the ultimate goal is to feel transportation,
so you're immersed in a narrative.
To me, that feeling of transportation is key
to all of the work that we do.
And then this is a basic spectrum of where immersive works
tend to fall.
It's developed by Rachel Pendergrass.
So is there a cohesive story,
or is the experience largely about setting a mood?
Would the performance work if there was no audience
participating, or is it entirely reliant upon participation?
There's other questions about people's ability
to move through the space, or whether they're stationary,
whether or not there is a fourth wall,
or they're able to engage directly with the actors,
for example.
Or whether the narrative is set and it can be influenced by the people doing those interactions.
And you can see that escape rooms fall upon the audience dependent line and the atmospheric line.
So lots of theming and it can't take place without the people in it.
And then also, I'm going to break down some of the elements of our game,
and there may be other ways that you personally define these,
but when I'm speaking about it, this is what I mean.
The narrative is the story told by the world.
The set, the objects, everything is speaking to whatever the story is that you're inhabiting.
versus the story or the plot.
And that's the action that's playing out over the hour
that people are inside the game.
And then there's another layer, which is the game flow.
That's the puzzles and interactions
that people are progressing through
that is driving them forward.
So when we set out to design these, we're facing three challenges.
We want to tell a story that's entertaining while people are under a significant physical
and mental stress.
We want to tell that story in a physical space in a cinematic way.
And we want to use puzzles and interactions thoughtfully to make it fun and reinforce
the themes of whatever they're going through.
And so again, I want to draw your attention to...
the place where escape rooms fall on here
because it is different to what my goals are.
My goal is to drive it fully into the narrative side.
I have never seen an escape room reviewed
like a theater performance before,
and so that is what I'm working toward.
I want it to be taken seriously as art.
But because it is still emerging,
you know, there are people who are trying to do that,
but generally not so much with the story stuff.
So, our first challenge, telling the story while people are under significant physical
and mental stress.
When we think about these designs, our first step is narrowing in on what's happening to
people's brains in these spaces, and cognitively there's a lot going on.
And this is really easy to see when people step inside a theater or a haunted house.
They both have visitors crossing a threshold into another world.
The lights go down, the music starts, people's hearts speed up a little,
their eyes are like adjusting to the light, and they start darting around,
and they're keying into what's happening. But that's actually the brain entering
a kind of survival mode. And once that switch has been flipped,
We're then asking people to solve puzzles or take in information or interact with characters.
And it's a real challenge to communicate directly with the player's brain when it's in that
state.
So I'd like to talk for a minute about what is happening to players mentally when they're
in that escape room.
They're in survival mode.
They're excited.
You know, we've used lighting cues in design
to bring them into a flow state.
And so I want to show you a video.
It's really important that you follow the instructions
on the screen very carefully.
This is an awareness test.
How many passes does the team in white make?
The answer is 13.
But, did you see the moonwalking bear?
So that's more generally known as the invisible gorilla experiment.
It's a great example of how the brain and the body are doing weird things in concert
when they're in stressful situations and when you're asking people to focus on particular
things.
And you see that play out in escape rooms all the time.
In our original room.
We had a klaxon that blared any time we were delivering a hint to people, and people would
be standing right next to it.
This is a loud klaxon.
And they would totally miss it because they were so deeply engrossed in whatever they
were interacting with.
And that's something that we just have to keep in mind for basically every single part
of the story that we're trying to convey.
Another funny kind of lizard brain survival mode thing is that we love to look for patterns
in stuff.
Does this sink look worried to you?
In an escape room, you can see how that becomes a problem
if you need people to find only the specific patterns
that you want them to find.
So this is what's happening in people's brains.
They're deeply focused to the exclusion
of most other information.
They're quickly searching and processing
to try and make connections between the game elements.
And they're getting mentally and physically exhausted
by what they're seeing and doing.
Ignoring the physical element is something
that you also see a lot,
but people become so wrapped up in these games
that they forget that they're standing
on a hard, cold, concrete floor for an hour.
And afterward, they're like,
why do my legs hurt so much?
Well, we know.
So, the lessons for that are to eliminate red herrings and extra junk wherever possible,
to be mindful of how players are able to take in information, and really to lean on the
world building.
Understanding that, I think, is respecting the player.
We also avoid putting in text unless it's absolutely vital,
because again, they really will not absorb it.
They will process it as quickly as they can for puzzle elements,
and then it gets thrown to the side.
So it's a really poor way to deliver any kind of story.
Since this is part of the narrative summit,
I'm not gonna get too deep into how we go
into the world building, but this is like a summary.
There's a huge difference between what the player
actually sees and processes and what we need to know
in order to make a world that feels cohesive.
Honestly, that could be a whole day-long summit in itself.
But so Spark of Resistance, it's a spy drama,
but from another perspective, the players are terrorists
instead of freedom fighters.
We chose to set our story in an oppressive world
full of censorship, and we knew what we wanted to say
about that, which guided everything that we put into it.
But from a player perspective,
you're just kind of going on a fun adventure.
In Spark of Resistance, that game, this is the lesson in action.
Players are told that there are secret agents who have been activated to investigate the
office of a spy who is deep undercover.
That person had missed a check-in and we assume the worst, like they've just disappeared.
We need these players to go in and figure out what's happened.
So this is how it plays out.
Their first puzzle leads to a tape recorder,
which says, if you're listening to this,
I'm in big trouble.
Then the players send a key card
through a built-in message tube system.
And in the game flow,
that is the first time that that character,
which is not a real person,
but that's the first time they become aware
of the players in that space in the game world.
The spy then sends them back a note,
which is written on another puzzle.
and they use that information to distract a security guard
and it displays a video of the spy evading the guard
based on the information they've just sent.
The spy then speaks directly to the players via a camera
and it's a betrayal.
So from that point on, the players are on their own.
They have to complete the mission and save themselves.
Each of the puzzles moves them forward in the task of investigating the office and helping
the spy.
Each one grants them slightly more knowledge about the dystopian world via an increasing
amount of security clearance and access to information.
And this is all done with, like, two lines of dialogue, a short video and that handwritten
message which you can see.
So for each of those moments, we boiled the plot and narrative stuff down to its very most essential message
because we knew that people would not be able to process anything more than that.
The environment, the object design, and the puzzle mechanics carry the burden of the rest.
So our second challenge is telling an engaging story
in a physical space in a cinematic way.
Knowing that players are not gonna take in that info,
how do we turn, well, you can imagine
the big scroll from Star Wars.
How do we turn a huge wall of text
into the single evocative image
which is what kicks off A New Hope?
It's a tiny.
Starship flying against a huge inky black sky,
and then a massive star destroyer.
You don't need or really remember that text
because you know exactly what the dynamic is
from the first image that you're presented with.
Show, don't tell, right?
In my experience, when you show up in an escape room, it's all about that sense of anticipation.
You don't really know what's about to happen because you want to avoid spoilers for yourself.
You probably don't know what it looks like inside because places generally don't place
photographs of their rooms online.
You're maybe a little excited, maybe a little bit scared.
So you show up and then the first thing that happens
is that you're handed a letter
or you get a really long speech about the world
and what you're supposed to be doing in it
and it's just a hype killer.
So nobody remembers any of the story
that is presented in those moments.
But thankfully we don't have to reinvent the wheel.
There's best practices for moving people
through physical spaces.
from LARP to theater to theme parks.
They've also undergone the stress tests
that escape rooms as an industry have not.
You know, they're putting thousands and thousands
of people through these spaces every day.
So if we look to them for the best practices
of how to convey story in those environments
where people are moving through them quickly,
we can really learn a lot.
And I also have to call out environmental storytelling
is like a legitimate meme at this point.
Joking about the way that video games place little vignettes
into levels to tell you, you know,
whatever has just happened, but something's happened here.
But the reason it's a joke is because it's so obvious,
right, like ideally you're using the level layout
and the affordances of all of the objects and interactions.
But being obvious in this manner stops the progression of the plot while you look at
it and in an escape room where there's a taking timer, that's a huge problem because you're
deliberately wasting the player's time.
So the lessons there.
Use elements from architecture, LARP, theater, films to set the tone and the design for specific
emotion and avoid and eliminate frictions that yank people out of immersion.
Like when you think of what an office looks like to you, you know, it's probably like this top photo. It's messy
There's fluorescent lights. You can see that reflected in media like office space or the office
But when you start looking at more stylized versions of offices in film
Also set in sort of dystopian era stuff. You can see where our influences were taken from
So our third challenge, to use puzzles and interactions thoughtfully to make the game
fun and reinforce the themes.
And I have to step back and talk about why we actually like puzzles because actually
maybe we kind of don't.
People solve puzzles because they like pain,
they like being released from pain,
and they like most of all that they find within themselves
the power to release themselves from their own pain.
I love that quote, but escape rooms
are like a kind of funny niche right now,
and I think people self-select out of them a lot
because they feel like it's going to be difficult,
but these are behaviors that we see
in the real world all the time,
whether that's from video game grinding and farming,
like those are terrible terms, that's not fun.
as we would define it, but all the way up to marathoning and rock climbing.
That's the type four kinds of fun where it's not necessarily fun while you're doing it,
but you're kind of glad you did it.
What makes a good puzzle?
Tells you how to solve it inherent in its design.
You don't have to have any kind of explanation.
You also don't need to rely upon outside knowledge like literature or film trivia.
And a good puzzle is also adjustable by adding or reducing the information in it.
Like this puzzle is obvious what to do in this,
and this guy is really enjoying doing the obvious thing.
So the way to implement that is through the use
of diegetic objects, eliminating busy work,
only including puzzles that are gonna propel
the plot forward, and elimination of friction,
and we'll discuss friction in a minute.
This is an example from Spark of how these principles
were put into action.
Players were presented with a shelf of library books.
If you are familiar with how a library works,
you can guess that the stickers on the side
refer to the Dewey Decimal System of cataloging,
and putting them into order forms a sentence
that directs you toward a page inside one of the books
where you find a library checkout card
that you overlay onto a page.
It's a really solid design because you can solve the entire thing without any other elements.
If you know how the books work, it's easy to do.
But actually the player base is now aging out of using libraries, so it's maybe not
a great puzzle anymore because it does require extra outside knowledge like typewriters,
VCRs and cassette tapes are the same.
So everything I've described is about crafting
an illusion for people.
They have the illusion of agency,
and they have this feeling that they're propelling
themselves through a very carefully crafted puzzle path,
but actually nothing that they do is accidental.
Every single thing that they maybe are,
we would consider like emergent play,
is something that we have planned for.
Because we very carefully avoided creating friction
in the design, people are totally immersed
and everything is flowing easily.
They have no idea how much work has gone into making that experience fun,
because they have been totally transported and are able to live in that moment.
And I think that's something really special.
I think that The Greatest Sin is promising to deliver that gift of transportation.
You know, for an hour or however long you're engaging with the work.
and then doing something that causes reality
to come screeching back in.
Like if you think about the pattern recognition
with the face in the sink,
like it's natural human instinct
to want to peek behind the curtain.
So that's something that people, players,
look for without even thinking,
and it's our job as entertainers to keep that curtain drawn.
Friction can come from a lot of places.
and mostly it tends to do with accessibility
in escape room games.
Lots and lots of puzzles rely on color changes, for example,
but that totally eliminates the experience
of anybody who's colorblind or in any way sight limited.
Considering accessibility of motion,
of hearing, and of movement is also a big one.
So, experiences in games are a gift
that designers can give to our players.
You know, we've done a good job
if we can help those players enter the magic circle
and have fun in the worlds that we've built.
But if we can help them to not only experience the world
in a new way, to feel a bit of magic,
transportation, and heroism,
and then carry that new way of experience
in the world with them when they leave,
that is success to me.
Thank you.
We can take questions, I guess, at the mic.
We have about 10 minutes, yeah.
Hi.
I was wondering if you have any best practices for developing narratives that adapt to different
players' skill levels, like with the escape room, it could be a room full of 12-year-olds
or a room full of 32-year-olds.
Sure.
So, the question is about adapting the game dynamically for the level of the skill of
the players in it.
comes down to hinting generally.
Hinting is a very specific skill
because you want to point people in the right direction
but it's like having somebody scratch an itch for you,
like it just doesn't work.
They need to be able to scratch it themselves.
So it's just about providing enough information
to set them on the right path.
But also generally, 12-year-olds are sort of in a gray area for
being able to enjoy most escape rooms.
They don't tend to have the level of concentration necessary.
So part of that is just only allowing a certain age group to participate in
the first place.
I wanted to talk about time limits and escape rooms in virtual reality. I'm working on a
virtual reality escape room game right now. And having played other competing games in
that space, I actually personally feel like time limits don't make sense in that capacity
because it's inherently extremely unfun to play through again. Failure doesn't feel good.
And because there aren't real people or a real space that you need to kick people out
of that doesn't...
serve the player outside of creating that stress, which may be worthwhile in and of
itself.
So I kind of wanted your opinion on that.
Sure.
So in the games that we do, actually, this is kind of a secret, but I would be absolutely
happy if 100% of players got out, there were three minutes left on the clock, and they
also felt like they were the only players to ever escape.
But that's again, that's crafting that illusion.
It's an entertainment component, right?
I think that in VR in particular,
you have to watch out for the physical fatigue.
So having a timer in that situation might just be a way
to make sure that people aren't experiencing time dilation
and forgetting that time is passing.
But you're right, it could just be a totally untimed thing
as long as there's enough structure
to lead people through it.
Thanks very much.
Thank you.
Hi, wonderful talk.
Is there a resource for other disciplines?
We're all here to feed the narrative.
I'm an audio person, so it's part of my responsibility to support the narrative.
Is there a resource to learn better communication, whether it's a book or online, to learn more
about the vocabulary?
Yeah, so No Proscenium is an amazing website and newsletter that is listing physical experiences
generally and they have a corresponding group on Facebook called Everything Immersive and
it really is for everything immersive and I would recommend starting there.
We actually have started an immersive book club,
which we're running.
If you look at immersivebook.club.
So that's one of our ways of attempting
to break out of the silo.
Because yeah, there's best practices for UX
and there's best practices for theater
and then they don't ever really cross over.
So that's something that I think is really important
just as an industry and it's a new industry.
Cool, thank you.
Thanks.
You've made a lot of escape rooms.
Do you have advice for people who are new to that?
How much work does it take and how do you start small
so that you don't boil the ocean?
To make escape rooms?
Yeah.
Oh man.
In 30 seconds or less.
Sure.
So, first of all, I would say escape rooms ultimately are a ticket selling business.
The fun part of doing the design is over very quickly.
And there's a lot of real estate stuff involved in them.
So I would keep that in mind before sort of venturing down that path.
But if you're really determined, playtesting is by far the most important thing.
And there is a skill that you have to develop
in watching people try and fail to solve puzzles
because if they're failing at it,
it's your fault as the designer
and not really their fault as a player.
So learning to be able to see that,
to hold yourself back from intervening and doing that
is really the best lesson.
And I'd say playtest like three to five times more
than you're doing the design.
I think he was next.
Sure.
One of our talk, you spoke about world building and we authors love to world build and players
never get it, but sometimes players, they will see these bits of lore and story and
they'll just gloss over them and this can bore them or disengage them and they in turn
will disengage other players and it's like a negative feedback loop.
How do you best determine a dose of worldbuilding or story lore for players to avoid this?
I mean, I think it depends on the type of player you're creating the lore for, right?
Because I'm somebody who wants to dig really deep into all of the secrets of something,
so I will read all of the material that a lot of people probably are just moving past.
So if you're designing that thing for me...
having it there and then making it easy to pass by totally makes sense.
But if it's something that's meant to benefit all of the players, I mean,
I would start asking like what is actually necessary.
If it is something that the players are deciding is not important to the experience,
then it might either be conveyed better in some other manner or just taken out.
Okay, thank you so much.
I know it's in a sense almost the opposite of what you do, but I'm particularly interested
in meditative spaces, and I could also see how it's very similar in certain ways.
I wondered if you had any thoughts about engaging design for meditative spaces.
I mean, me, do you remember the game Myst?
Yes, I wouldn't be standing here if it wasn't for Myst.
I used to peel off on the side of that little island and just hang out with the dappled
sun coming in, and finally the game would just say, are you going to do anything?
Yeah. So I would actually say like the sort of opposite coin of the work that I make is
untimed, like experience-based stuff. The Now Play, this thing that I highlighted at the beginning,
is situated in a desk and it's supposed to be the experience of reading other people's letters.
And I consider that a game. And it's something that you participate in, you feel everything,
you're looking at it, you're reading between the lines, but you personally decide.
when that experience ends, when you have enough information,
or when you're satisfied.
It's something that her story used really well,
I think, as well.
So there's definitely a place for it.
But yeah, for me, the opposite of the escape rooms
is stuff that's entirely reading, and is untimed,
and is deeply personal and not team-based.
So yeah, there's definitely space for meditation.
Just in your talk, I'm excited to see more of your work.
Thanks.
Hi.
Do you have any insights on how to make people not feel left out in some part of the games?
I always feel like that in escape room games.
Every single player, even on successful teams, says something like that.
They say, oh, I didn't do anything.
And like when you're watching through the cameras, you're like, no, I saw when you picked
up that thing and you made this connection.
The way to do that, I think, is through a sort of debrief afterward, which is something
that LARPs really nail.
It's something where you walk players through
and then you specifically call out,
like you did this and you did this
and you ask somebody, you know,
what did you do that with this thing?
There's also a thing from LARP called froth,
which is a collective myth making that occurs
when you're sort of,
when the players are telling the story,
so they're sort of world building after the fact.
So just making room to encourage that
I think would be really helpful with that feeling,
but everybody feels that way too, so yeah.
Yeah, that ties very much into my question, because I usually have a similar feeling after doing a room escape game,
and I feel like, man, I'd really enjoy doing this with one or maybe two other people, instead of five, six, seven, eight,
and we're all just looking at different corners and shouting at each other, like,
did anyone find that combination yet? And like, oh, you solved that? I didn't even see that part of the puzzle.
Yeah.
puzzles solved by groups where you don't necessarily get to see the whole picture,
like sit down with the letter and put the narrative together in your head quietly in your own time.
So that's kind of where the cinematic moment stuff comes in.
We usually try to have people branching off into different areas and spaces,
but when there's some sort of story thing that we need them to see,
we drive them together.
That's something that you see in theater like Sleep No More, for example.
For the big major scenes, all of the actors all converge physically on the same space
and something plays out.
So you can choose to not participate in that,
but you're also missing a huge part of it.
So, yeah, it's just very tightly structured in that way
to make sure that there is always something
for people to do.
I'd say the sweet spot is generally eight people as well
for an hour long game, so.
Thank you.
You had mentioned wanting escape rooms to be taken as seriously as theater,
and I'm trying to figure out the intersections between theater and gaming.
And one of the things that even something like Sleep No More doesn't have,
that games have, is a fail state, which escape rooms have.
And so I was just wondering your thoughts,
as something that I've been trying to figure out myself, of like,
how do you make a fail state still narratively satisfying?
For our games, we try and get everybody
to at least a particular part in the story,
which I'd say is about at the 80% mark.
So they've seen everything there is to see.
In Spark of Resistance, that's where the turn happens.
Like they've been betrayed,
and they're tasked with setting off an EMP device.
So whether they set that off or not
is sort of beside the point.
They've already absorbed everything.
And it is really a lot of work to get players to that point
if they're sort of not enjoying the rest of the game.
But I would say check out Strange Bird Immersive.
They're based in Houston, Texas,
and they do a seance theater experience
that's sort of built around an escape room.
So it's a literal integration of theater into a game.
So I think whether or not you succeed in that game
sort of doesn't matter to the story
that's on either end of it as well.
So that is a potential structure to look at.
Awesome, thank you so much.
Hi, thank you for coming here.
I'm creating my own mixed reality game in immersive theater.
So I feel your talk is super helpful.
I wonder if you can talk a little bit about the strategies
for how do we balance the player's free will
and the limitation our game rules set.
Because usually if a player wants to do things
the game designer doesn't intend to,
that will ruin or create distractions, that experience.
I mean, that's part of what the playtesting is that we do.
I would say in our rooms, players never do anything that we do not want them to do, even
if they believe that they are secretly.
Because at a certain point, doing what they want to do in a physical room means they're
going to get hurt.
It's probably different for mixed reality, I'm sure.
But I would say, instead of trying to prevent them
to do that, to build space for that to happen,
sort of a side note, I took a trip to play Escape Rooms
for a full week in Malaysia, and the address for that
is up here, it's every game in this city.
And in one of the games, it was set in a classroom,
and we were each given name tags.
for each of the students.
And so, the first group in our cluster that went through it
like role-played as these characters
that they were just making up.
Then they created roles for the next group
to take on with secret roles
that we weren't allowed to communicate to the other players.
So like that emergent behavior that we came up with
made that game something really, really special.
So I think just like creating the opportunity for that
and then not stepping on people
when it's starting to happen as long as they're safe
is probably a good way to approach it.
Thank you.
Hi, so I am a narrative designer.
I'm currently working on a couple of historical ARG projects
that are creating a story and a narrative game
around real world artifacts.
And I'm wondering if you have any advice
for creating this sort of narrative space
when the boundary between what is part of the game
and what isn't is not as clear as a room.
For alternate reality game stuff,
I think probably players are gonna read
10 to 20 times more into it than you've intended,
which is kinda nice as the designer
to not have to do that work.
So I would just say, again,
it comes down to play testing.
You're always gonna be surprised
by what is emerging from that,
but if you practice enough in advance,
and I know that's really difficult
for ARGs and live events in particular.
But the more that you can anticipate, the better it's going to be on the other side.
But also maybe don't worry about it too much because they will come up with all sorts of
like fun facts and connections.
Then I would work those into the game in a way that feels rewarding as if you had been
doing it on purpose the whole time.
Thank you.
Sure.
Hi, thank you for the great talk.
Oh, sorry.
We have to wrap it up, but I'm going to go to the lounge over
there if you two want to follow me over.
We can keep chatting.
Cool, thanks.