Hi, everybody.
I'm Zach Johnson.
I'm the creative director of Asymmetric.
We made a game 15 years ago that some of you
might remember called Kingdom of Loathing.
It was a browser-based multiplayer role-playing game,
stick figure art, a lot of goofy jokes.
And a couple of years ago, a couple of years ago,
a few months ago,
Forgot how long it's been.
A couple of years ago, we started working
on a follow-up game, West of Loathing.
A few months ago, we released it.
It's a lot of the same team in common.
A few new people brought on to make this,
but yeah, that's who I am and what we're doing.
Because talking about comedy
is one of the least funny things I can imagine doing.
When they asked me to do this talk,
I kind of didn't want to,
and then the more I thought about it,
the more I didn't want to.
And then in February, I got lucky because Tim Schafer
accidentally wrote my entire talk for me in this tweet.
And that's pretty much the secret.
We decided when we started making this thing
that it was going to be a comedy game.
It wasn't gonna be an adventure game
or an RPG with comedy elements,
but it was going to straight up be a comedy game.
Instead of a game with jokes in it,
which happens all the time,
this was sort of a game made out of jokes.
we didn't like consciously arrive at a bunch of bullet point
lists of how we were doing this, right?
We, when it came time to write this talk,
we were just like, wait, how did we do it?
Like, what was our approach to this?
And we kind of started with the fundamental basis
of all of the writing that happens in the game
is this relationship between the narrator and the player.
Because it's a Western RPG.
in both senses.
The character, we wanted as much as possible
for the character to just be a kind of a cypher,
an avatar of the player.
We didn't wanna have,
they didn't have a real strong character,
they didn't have strong opinions about things.
Like, we wanted to write them as the way
that you wanna write, or the way that we wanted to write it,
which was sort of neutral and friendly,
and like, you can make some assumptions about them,
like they wanna be here, you know, they like their parents.
they don't like being annoyed or beaten up or whatever.
But for the most part, just let the player
kind of inhabit that character.
But the narrator, and so this is nothing super novel.
I think if you looked up narrator in the dictionary,
it would probably just say this,
but the narrator is me and Riff, the other writer,
sort of talking to the player.
But what's cool about that is that it allows us
to just kind of treat the narrator as a character.
And because we've been doing this for so long,
it's a character that we've been developing for 15 years.
And having the entirety of the sort of non-spoken text
in the game be a dialogue between us and the player
in the form of the player character
has a lot of advantages in.
in terms of being able to just cram jokes
into literally everywhere.
Like, every piece of text you see in the game,
whether it's in the options menu, item description,
exposition about what happens when you open a door,
or whatever, it's all this character that you get used to.
And so, literally every piece of text
becomes the opportunity for us to at least try to be funny.
It's a real quantity over quality kind of approach.
But it works because it, you know, if you have a game with four jokes in it and one
of them is bad, your game is only 75% funny.
If you have a game with a thousand jokes in it and 250 of them are bad, then your game
is 75% funny.
The narrator as a sort of like honest character, an honest reflection of who we are as writers.
also lets us be a little self-deprecating about stuff,
which is a fantastic way to cover up
fundamental flaws with your game,
act like they're on purpose and like they were,
we meant to do that because isn't that funny?
You don't wanna overdo it, but.
Honestly, because of the way the game looks,
people come in with a set of expectations
that is not, this is gonna be this amazing,
sweeping, epic thing, right?
And so it's okay to be a little goofy about it
because it is a little goofy.
Like, it's not about being the biggest video game
that it can be.
It's about sitting around with us,
having a fun conversation.
Having the narrator talk to the character
as its own character lets you also,
you don't want to tell the character,
you don't want to tell the player character how they feel,
right, but what you can do is say,
wow, that was pretty scary, huh?
that the saying you know what if that happened to me I would be pretty angry
right now how do you know how you feel about that and it lets you it lets you
convey emotion and opinions about stuff without undermining the players ability
to inhabit the player character and the other the nice thing about that is when
it's so silly it also doesn't have to be consistent like if the narrator likes
catch up if when it's funny for the narrator like catch up they can not like
catch up later if it's funnier for them to not like catch up depending on what
you're trying to do with catch up.
Typically, in interactions between the player
and the narrator, we have the player
as kind of the straight man, and the narrator just
sort of messes with you, and you push back against it,
and that's where a lot of the humor of that interaction
comes from.
Every once in a while, and I think I do this a little bit
more than Riff does, I like to give the player the opportunity
to be the sort of annoying kid brother that just kind of
repeats everything that the narrator says
until the narrator gets really aggravated,
and you move on from there.
But for the most part, when the entire game takes place in this kind of jokey, buddy cop
sort of conversation between the narrator and the character, just the default means
of exposition for what's happening in the game becomes an opportunity for comedy.
And also sometimes, so there's a moment in the prologue of the game where we introduce
the
sort of minor equivalent of a morality system we have where there's this guy
sleeping outside of a outside of a cave that you're supposed to arrest some dudes
in and you can decide whether you want to just kill him while he's sleeping and
the narrator kind of pushes back against that because we don't want it to be easy
for the player to get into this sort of like well I'm a cold-blooded killer
because
We didn't really want to write a lot of stuff
to support the player as a cold-blooded killer,
because that's less funny.
So you get a lot of opportunities
to be talked out of murdering this kid.
And the thing that I noticed, which was weird,
is that when we were demoing this at PAX and stuff,
every time somebody went through that,
they did it with this huge grin on their face the entire time.
And I'm just sitting there at first thinking, no, I don't.
I thought we were going to remove this from the game because this is not funny.
This is like trying to warn you that the stuff that you are doing is not on tone with what
we want you to do, but people just loved it.
And so I think as a result of that, we ended up doing a lot more kind of stuff where the
narrator argues with the player and just sort of tries to get in the way of stuff.
It's hard to tell when to stop doing that because it's gotten annoying, but we're usually
not there when people are playing, so we don't really care.
It also allows you to break the fourth wall without it being super obnoxious.
Like, we try to do it sparingly because it's, you know, you just don't want to get too...
We don't want the player to constantly be acknowledging that they're in a video game.
We don't really want the narrator to constantly be acknowledging that it's a video game, but
sometimes it helps.
There's the kind of in-fiction way where...
So there's a series of spittoons in the game that are really gross to get into, and...
I remember I wrote that I set the first one in there and I and I told ref okay
right this there's going to be 6 or 7 of these and they should get grosser and
grosser as the game goes on and he wrote the first one so gross that I had no
idea how he was going to move on from there but what he did was a thing that
turned out to be one of the things that people like the most about this which
was that it turns into this weird series of kind of arguments between the player
and the narrator where the narrator
gradually just starts acknowledging,
like, look, I don't want to save this.
Like, I don't want you to do this.
I don't want to have to describe this stuff to you.
And it's cool just because by the time you get there,
you've gotten used to the voice of the narrator,
and so the fourth wall breaking becomes,
you know, just like a little bit of a surprise.
The thing that I like about it,
and this is not funny at all,
but it also lets you do things like
there's a hat that you can find that's kind of hidden in the prologue that
unlocks a really hard combat mode and you can't get away from it and the
narrator can just tell you that and the thing that I sort of feel like was the
the best use of this was at the end once you've finished the main storyline of
the game and you can click the thing to like get the ending cutscene it just
tells you
this is not going to change anything about your character or the state of the
world. You can just watch this cutscene and then you can leave and do something
else and come back and do it again. Like you don't you don't need to save.
You can't save. But I wish games sort of had the confidence to let you know
stuff like that because there's nothing more annoying to me than getting
40 hours into some RPG and then not knowing that I'm about to do something
that means I should have saved or I have to revert to an hour ago.
Biggest advantage is that when everything that we write in the game has this voice that
is trying to be funny, writing it is not a chore, because it's great.
We just get to write jokes all day, and what could be better than that?
Obviously it's work. I mean, you make games, you know that even the fun parts of it are work.
But it is nice that essentially everything that we do becomes, at worst,
a puzzle that we have to solve to figure out a way to make some boring thing funny.
How do we make the graphics quality options funny?
And then that was another thing. It was like a few minutes of work and then people loved it.
It also, the fact that we had to do it this way
sort of talked us out of the idea of having
some kind of codex that you would unlock
encyclopedia entries about stuff.
We were sort of worried moving from
Kingdom of Loathing to West of Loathing,
well this game has animation and the combat
is like stuff's moving around.
We're not gonna have enough opportunities to write stuff.
We should add some structures that let us
just put a bunch of text in front of people.
And I'm really glad that we didn't do that.
Instead, we found other little cracks to put it in.
And I don't think anybody's going
to criticize West of Loathing for not
having enough writing in it.
So that's it.
So this is going to be longer because there's
a lot of stuff we don't do.
the game is made out of comedy,
the reward for the player for doing everything
is more or less just gonna be more jokes.
Like you walk into a room,
you see that it has five objects in it,
you know that you can probably click them
to at least get an attempt at something funny.
Maybe just a pun, whatever.
We don't want the systems of the game to get in the way of that.
We don't want to make you feel bad by blocking you from finding this stuff.
So I mean, we did stuff like putting really good gear in all the spittoons,
which are not hard to find and they're not hard to get through, right?
We just kind of wanted the...
we had one of the game to not be particularly challenging we added an
optional hard mode just in case but
it we needed to stick to the core this game is made of jokes and so
we don't we didn't want to do adventure game kind of puzzles where
if you with essentially decided
well
We didn't start out making an adventure game, actually,
because none of us really like adventure games that much
because of this kind of stuff.
But it gradually dawned on us that we were accidentally
making an adventure game.
So then we were kind of stuck in it.
And so we decided, all right, if there's a puzzle that
requires a needle as its solution, we don't want the
player to live in a world where there is only one needle.
And if you didn't find it, you can't get past the puzzle.
So we just decided to put a needle in every haystack.
There are occasional hard puzzles, right?
There are some math puzzles, there are some weird
Morse code and Braille stuff hidden in some of the stuff
that Kevin put in, but they're either so out of the way
that people aren't gonna feel bad about missing them,
or we put in some kind of just brute force,
like you can eventually get a stat high enough
to just skip this and it's fine.
I had a brief aside that I'm gonna skip.
Combat.
The system, like this is definitely
the weakest part of the game, and we all know this, right?
And if we didn't know it, a bunch of reviews told us.
The system is great and flexible,
and it's capable of doing a lot of cool stuff,
but we kind of just didn't,
we ran out of time and we ran out of money,
and so we ended up with combat not in fantastic shape.
And we decided, well, given that there's not really any way
to make this super funny just on its own,
and we don't have time to make it super satisfying,
let's just make it really easy.
People will like that.
I thought that would be a happy face at the end there,
but it was a sad face.
But, and it's important when you find something
that contradicts everybody and makes you feel better
about yourself that you put it in a bigger font.
I think that making the combat easy and just getting it out of the way really served our
goal of making the game be a game that is about jokes.
In a video game like this, there's going to be a bunch of stuff that you have to do over
and over and over again, and moving between areas on the map in this game is a thing that
happens all the time.
And so one of the things that we had to do was write a tremendous number of random encounters
so that that stuff didn't get repetitive.
And pretty early on, we realized that the scope of what was going to happen in random
encounters had to go way down so that it was essentially just writing.
We had thought that maybe random encounters would be like a room that you went into with
some stuff that you could interact with, but that got...
that would have taken way too long.
So we ended up able to cram like 200 of them in there
because a lot of them were somewhat formulaic,
but like three different crates that you open
with three different jokes, that's three different jokes.
It's a game about jokes, so that counts as three encounters.
Segway, it's important if you don't have a segway
to just say segway, so you know
there's supposed to be one there.
And I'm doing another talk about our tool chain
and the design post-mortem for West of Loading tomorrow
in the main conference,
so I'll get way more into this there.
But the tools that we built on the back end
and the engine that was built on the front end
were really optimized to just let us cram
as much stuff in there as quickly as we could.
And that was very important to avoiding repetition,
to being able to get all those random encounters in there,
to being able to just maximize the text.
so that there were just as many jokes as possible,
so that one of them was funny, then we win.
Colorblind mode is a joke
that a bunch of reviews picked up on,
a bunch of people just, you know, thought was funny.
And what was cool about that is that
the amount of work that it took
to add that option to the game was literally typing this.
into a text bucket that we had, and it added the option.
And every system in the backend of the development tools
for this stuff was like that.
Everything just made it as easy as possible
for us to do stuff before we talked ourselves out of it.
Another important axiom.
And what I mean to say here is that because the game is about jokes, often a joke is better
than a good thing that's harder to make than a joke.
We had two sort of big towns in the game,
and I wanted there to be gambling mini-games
in both of them.
And I didn't really have a good idea for either of them,
and so like the poker game in the opening town's saloon,
like I agonized over it, and I put it off,
and I put it off, and I put it off,
and then I did all this work making this system
that it just...
It's not bad exactly, but it's just not good.
It was a bunch of work.
It didn't, I probably could have just omitted that room
from the saloon and nobody but me would have known
that there was ever supposed to be anything there.
And I didn't even know what was supposed to be there.
So it would have been fine to just omit it,
but it was a bunch of work and it resulted in this thing
that was not particularly,
not particularly interesting to anybody.
Just, it's, nobody talks about it.
I knew from the exhaustive research that I did watching HBO's Deadwood several years
ago that in Deadwood, Pharaoh was a card game that was more popular than poker.
So we decided in the Breadwood camp that we would have a version of Pharaoh.
I especially didn't have an idea for that.
So what I ended up doing was like, what if this is just a game where you name as many
pharaohs as you can and how you do is determined by how well you can lie to the other people
that are playing.
That works, right?
That is actually kind of funny.
And the poker game was like 268 lines of script,
not funny at all.
The pharaoh game was 89 lines of script.
And we also ended up with this random pharaoh name generator
that I'm hoping to license to Campo Santo
for in the Valley of Gods.
They haven't gotten back to me yet.
So Rif, the other writer, he's the one who does
almost all of the NPC dialogue,
because when I write an NPC, it's usually me
with some sort of weird vocal technique,
and an errand they're not willing to run.
So I asked him, hey, pretend you have a list of things
that you do when you're writing an NPC
and tell me what those things are
so that I can put them in this talk.
So first thing he talked about was the voice of the NPC
and what they would sound like if they were talking.
Like, do they have an accent?
Do they drop H's?
Do they clip G's at the end of words?
Do they say um or uh or er?
Going on further from that,
how much of that can we put in
before it becomes too annoying to read?
Does it even work in text?
Because one thing we absolutely were never gonna do was VO.
So we needed to make sure it wasn't annoying
to actually like.
be able to imagine what the character sounded like.
For major characters, we had these really short,
and it's important in presentations
to have a lot of text on a slide.
That's one thing I've read.
We wrote these sort of short Bibles
about what kind of, like, what's this character like?
What do they sound like?
And doing those early,
because these were like the partners
that you can take with you,
so there were gonna be hundreds of conversations
with these guys.
Another thing to determine about them is generally just a mood, which determines, like, all right,
what's the sort of overall flavor of the jokes that you're going to get from these guys.
An important thing about them that I would never have thought about actually
until riff pointed this out was
like essentially how much of the players B s is this character willing
to put up with because that kind of determines whether the humor of the
interaction comes from something that's funny about the NPC
or some or the sort of resistance of the NPC
to what the players is trying to bring to the table.
Few other random things like you know imagine what they look like
and then it's easier to imagine them saying stuff for us that's easy because
it's just a very, it's very abstract, right?
Like they don't, they look like stick figures
and so in our imagination,
they can look like whatever they want.
What do they want?
Maybe it's something stupid.
That would be funny.
Maybe it's something weird
and then you can ask them why they want that weird thing
and then maybe there's a funny reason for it.
Why don't they already have it?
Maybe they're afraid of something that's not scary.
You know, maybe they're too drunk or too lazy
to go get it themselves.
That lets the player make fun of the person a little bit.
What are they doing when you find them?
Especially for random encounters,
this is where just a lot of the sort of,
the stuff that I remember most as funny moments in the games
is these things that I would encounter
when I was play testing that Riff had written
and I had never seen before.
And so it was cool to just find these weird characters
in different parts of the world doing weird stuff.
How do they feel about you interrupting them?
Another source of like, either them being annoyed with you
or them being annoyed with you is funnier
than them being grateful to you,
so we probably erred on the side of that a little bit.
If you have just a one-off interaction with somebody that doesn't need to have any mechanical effect or anything,
you can often just do, like, a real easy thing, like,
maybe it's funny because they can't hear you and you keep having to repeat yourself,
or maybe they have a weird accent or aren't from around here and so you have a hard time understanding them,
or maybe there's some, like, outrageous thing about the environment,
or some outrageous thing about them, sort of Saturday Night Live character, and you can lean into that for...
the duration of a short conversation,
or maybe they're really bad at their job
and they don't understand that they're bad at their job,
and that's funny, like Monty Python is funny.
Doing this makes it kind of hard
to hang anything important on the character,
but it's pretty easy,
and if you're just trying to make a lot of them,
then it's a nice way to make kind of a fun interlude.
In...
In writing jokes on the internet for 15 years,
we've had a lot of chances to look at stuff we wrote
a year ago or five years ago or 10 years ago
and see how they hold up and see how we feel about them.
And so we've kind of learned.
And there are a lot of examples of all of these things
that I'm about to say that we don't do
in Kingdom of Loathing, don't at me.
We try to avoid topical stuff,
like this happened while we were making the game,
and it's funny and everybody likes it,
but it would be nonsense if the game,
which came out in August, had a thing that was about this
and required you to understand this, right?
Like there's just.
you never know which things are gonna last.
And it's like some joke equivalent to this from 10 years ago.
Maybe we'll put in a thing about it
and if you get it, you get it.
But we try not to, we try in general with references
to not make it such that it would just be nonsense
if you don't get the reference.
Like it's okay if it's a little weird,
but it shouldn't just be like,
hey look, this is just, remember this thing?
Just using somebody else's joke verbatim.
Like this was funny once.
And now it's just like nothing makes me groan more than just
kind of, yes, OK, all right, all right, yes, that
was funny when they did it however many years ago.
Something that we, as we got older, gradually
got more and more, felt more and more strongly about
is that we just shouldn't be mean, right?
Like there's no reason to.
The tone that we established with Kingdom of Loathing was basically we didn't ever want
to make fun of anything that somebody didn't choose.
Like we can make a joke about, you know, he's a hippie, he smells bad or whatever, but we
kept religion out of it, you know, but we obviously, it's pretty easy to not make jokes
about race when everything is a stick figure.
But that said we did say well we're making a Western.
There are some problems with this genre that we don't really
have anything important to say about right and so we were a
little worried that by just completely omitting the genocide
of Native Americans from the from our game that we would
catch some heat for maybe whitewashing it.
But then it turns out when you make a dumb comedy game.
Nobody seems to care about that.
So
I guess we dodged a bullet by thinking about that more than anybody else ever did.
When, and this is just a little rougher in general,
and I couldn't quite figure out what I was going to say while this slide was up,
and I still don't know, so I'm eager to find out.
We kind of determined in Kingdom of Loathing that...
we're not making fun of things that people didn't choose.
And we're like, well, people don't necessarily
choose their religion, and people don't necessarily
choose their politics.
And so what I like to think of is, say, a 17-year-old kid
raised in a conservative household
playing a game that's warm and funny
and comes from a place where we all
think of ourselves as right-thinking progressives.
But.
So does this kid.
This kid doesn't know.
And then suddenly, he gets to some specific political thing
where we say, hey, kid, turns out you're an asshole.
And he had no idea.
And now the entire message is just kind of wasted on him,
as opposed to just being like ambiently the right stuff,
as opposed to actively sort of aggressively aligned
against the wrong stuff.
That said, this is a very cowardly approach to politics.
And I.
kind of just have to own that.
And that also was a very bad choice for where to end the talk.
So you might have questions like about the cake, for instance, and whether it's true
or not.
Hi, I just want to say as a comedy writer,
I'm really excited to talk to you
because just a year ago, my comedy partner accused me
of stealing the name of my killer guitar
from his stab bat from Kingdom of Loathing.
But I was wondering about,
I write games that are not funny, but I put funny in them.
What kind of feedback do you look for?
Do you even look for when you're play testing?
How funny is it?
Is it, you know, does anybody say,
that's not funny and you take it out?
Yeah, the question is how we deal with
and how we look for feedback
about the actual comedy aspects of it.
And, you know, we kind of don't.
Like we've been doing it the same way for so long
that like our voice is what it is.
the players are kind of either here for it or they're not.
And it's like, it's like if somebody comes up
and criticizes the graphics,
like I don't know what to tell you, buddy.
Like, like you either, you can either put up with this
and see it for what it is or you can't.
There, every once in a while,
there will be some internal argument about whether,
like I will, it's usually me.
I will put in a joke that says,
that's something that doesn't make,
kinda doesn't make any sense, and so many people will report it like thinking it's a
typo or a bug that Kevin will just constantly exhort me to change it.
When you drink a cup of coffee in this game, it says, like let's say your character's name
is Susan, it says, you drink the cup of Joe, and your reply is, my name's Susan.
which I think that's funny because the insinuation is that you've misunderstood
what the narrator is saying and think that the narrator thinks that your name is Joe,
but then if that's the case, then why did they put it in this weird sentence that...
And it got reported as a bug a bunch of times, but I just sort of insisted...
Yeah.
Right?
Because it just looks like a typo, right?
If you don't...
And it's not like a totally reasonable joke to get, right?
Like, what you're getting about this is that it's just sort of a weird thing that doesn't make a ton of sense.
But I always ended up sticking to my guns on those things.
I don't think we changed a single joke as a result of feedback in all of this.
So, uh...
So I noticed in the podcast you whenever some player asks like to ask you guys to make a joke like a clothing pun
you guys iterate and
Try and try again to find the right one. So how do you guys know when you're you find the right funny?
Either you get tired of looking or you find one that we just all sort of agree, like,
okay, that's it, we're done.
Like it's usually pretty clear if you found a really good one, and it also becomes clear
if you're not going to find a good one, so you just kind of stop, basically stop wherever
you were when you realize that.
You know, might have been better to back up a couple to a slightly funnier one, but who
has the time?
So you mentioned in the talk that you shouldn't let gameplay
get in the way of humor if you're trying to make just a
straight-up comedy game, and also that you sort of made the
combat easier to not make it get in the way of the comedy.
Do you think there are any notable experiences in your
time developing games where the gameplay or the mechanic
worked extremely well in service of the humor?
That's hard to say, actually.
I, seems like the kind of thing I should have an answer for,
but I think I don't.
You know, we just try to make that the default mode,
but it doesn't ever, I don't think there's any moments
where the game becomes really transcendently a comedy game.
Like something like, like Jazz Punk is another game
that I would say is just definitely a comedy game.
Given that they are a first-person shooter,
I think it is easier to turn tropes upside down
than our thing where it's just,
like, it's always gonna be you're walking around in a room
having conversations about stuff.
So it's really more just,
here's a bunch of standard delivery for jokes
than it is like.
we did something weird and expensive on the technical side.
But, you know, I mean, I guess like the Norton,
when he throws the antivirus into your eyes
and it messes up the screen, like, that's a thing, right?
That's like, oh, now everything looks really annoying
until I figure out how to solve this quest.
But I'm reluctant to draw attention to that
because while I think it's funny,
that's kind of a joke on the player
rather than a joke at the player.
So, yeah, I don't know.
30 minutes.
Thanks, everyone.