Hello everyone, welcome to our presentation.
Thank you, thank you.
You know, animation is the best way to make a video game alive.
Then, we'll be talking about our work on Rayman game,
and more specifically, all the technology helped to keep face
with the artistic vision for the animation in a game.
we will see how Rayman's world comes to life.
Hi, I'm Anaïs Dussautois.
I'm an animator on Rayman Origins and on Rayman Legends.
I'm going to talk to you about the technical part of this presentation.
And I'm Christophe.
I'm the artistic director of animation
and character designer on Rayman Origins and Rayman Legends.
I'm in charge of the artistic part.
So first, we will start with the spirit of the Ubisoft
Montpellier studio, and how that way of life influences
the spirit of the game.
Then we're going to travel in time to go back to the
origins of Rayman, and we'll see how the artists work with
the Ubi art framework, or technology.
Then we're going to tell you the story of GenAnim,
the UBI framework animation tool.
And then we're going to finish if we've
got the time with a small demonstration about that tool.
Cool.
Woo-hoo.
I'm not stressed at all.
Everything's fine.
Can you see me?
It's OK.
Not small.
Um, I'm going to try to imagine you, all of you, naked.
And it's going to be better.
So let's talk about the Ubisoft Montpellier Studio spirit.
We think that the ambience and the atmosphere at Montpellier
Studio contribute to our creative success.
So we are working in a very pleasant context.
Well, in the south of France, we've got the beach.
It's a sunny place.
Got Morito's bikinis and all that stuff.
We design creative projects, like From Dust, Beyond Good
and Evil, Rabbids Go Home, Roman Origins, Roman Legends,
of course.
We surround ourselves with a talented and passionate team.
And I to the team, by the way.
team is made of really hard workers.
They're working together in a very good team spirit,
and they are really involved in the final quality of the project.
And we also develop innovative tools,
and I think that the fact that we are creating innovative tools together
make us understand the constraint of the other's job.
We have to leave our comfort zone and communicate a lot,
and it contributes to have a good team synergy.
But for now, I invite you to discover the villa, the place
that we work, with this small video of the team
that I have made.
It's homemade, so let's see that.
Yeah.
Adios
Really look very happy. Thank you for them
They deserve that.
Really, really.
So now, let's back to the origins.
To understand the art and the philosophy of Rayman,
how we did the connection with the Rayman origins
and Rayman legends, let's jump to the past.
So who's the character of Rayman?
Rayman's character with no arms, no legs,
and a really weird haircut.
But yeah, it's a little, ah.
But most of all, it's a very iconic silhouette.
But who's the best place to speak about Rayman
than his creator, Michel Ancel?
So let's see a small interview about that.
My name is Michel Ancel, and I'm the creative director
on Rayman Legend and Rayman Origin.
The creation of Rayman was really, in fact, very simple,
because it was something that I did when I was
around 20 years old.
And it was really the character I wanted to make
to experience the games I was creating.
Rayman is a very simple and direct character.
He's not talking, it's really about action.
So he's really made all the animation and the design.
is made so that you can understand the character just by looking at it.
It's not just storytelling and things like that.
It's really a direct connection between you and the character.
First, it was designed in pixels, and when you don't have a lot of pixels, you are forced to have very strong characteristics in your character.
And I think even now in 3D, because sometimes the character is far away, you still need a character that you can identify very easily.
We started with 2D games, because a long time ago it was easier to do 2D games.
And then we moved to 3D, and the games became more complex,
interesting, but really different in terms of gaming,
of gameplay, and from what we started with.
Coming back in 2D is really a way
to go back to the roots of video games.
Phew.
Cool.
That's my boss.
Huh.
So the question is, why to come back in 2D?
Since the beginning of the industry,
and particularly the advent of the 3D games,
there has been a race to create more and more
photorealistic games with more and more complicated controls
and cameras.
So we tried to back to the basic,
keep simple controls, a visible game space,
to come back to an affordable way to play together.
We tried to make a game for the hardcore gamer,
but also for the casual gamers.
And we tried, the purpose was to make them play together
in one single room.
So the first three men.
the first one, the 20 years old were man,
still the favorite of the franchise and its top seller.
And we believe that has a lot to do with the accessibility
of the 2D graphics and gameplay.
That means more familiarity for everyone,
and also the promise of old classic gameplay
that platformers fans adore.
We try to keep the magic and the fantasy of the first Rayman,
and we mix it with the HD quality and the new technology
that we can access with the new tools that we create
to form a contemporary vision of this universe to all of you.
So the gamers, non-gamers, everybody.
At the beginning, the team was focused
on inventing a more efficient, flexible, and creative approach
to build 2D games.
So we started to develop the UbiArt framework.
At the beginning, it was an idea of Michel Ancel.
And it begins with a small team of artists and engineers.
They work together to create all those tools.
So it's designed to all small creative team.
to produce high-quality graphics and gameplay rapidly and efficiently.
With it, you are able to animate a large style of animation, like cut-out paper, drawing,
paintings.
Can I say modeling past?
Yeah, modeling past.
Clay?
Yeah, clay.
Okay.
Thank you.
Sorry, I'm French.
So it's built to fit with the needs of the artist in 2D.
On Rayman Origins and Rayman Legends,
we wanted to fit perfectly with the vision of the artist.
So we developed a tool that allows
to put directly the drawing of the artist, the concept
art, into the game.
So we don't lose the essence of the primary art concept,
and we keep the energy on the artistic part
to stay focused on the creation.
As we modified the classic pipe to fit with the old 2D
concepts.
We saved lots of time and energy to product a great variety of universes,
great variety of assets,
to build backgrounds, platforms, create different worlds,
life elements,
characters,
that give to the game its own personality.
So, to...
To be more clear, I'm gonna show you a small video
about the artistic pipeline
or the artist work with those tools.
I'm Jean-Christophe Alessandri,
I'm the artistic director of Emanuel Jones.
The graphic creation on A Man's Legend starts with a preparatory work
based on sketches and concept art.
Then we go through a validation stage with the creative director
and the different managers of the other trade corps
to then arrive at a prototyping phase, especially on the framework.
We work in a very organic way, and the framework allows us to do that.
It allows us to be very flexible, to make several iterations from a design.
What is also interesting with the framework is that it is the concept art that we will put in the game in the end.
We are not in a heavy production pattern, but on the contrary, we are in a very reactive logic
that really allows us to test as much as possible all the ideas that can fuse in a team
Between animations, level art, level design, game design, concept artists,
all these people can really create in the same way.
I like to take a look at the concept art that's made for the worlds for the game from the
artists themselves before actually building something in the level because I think when
I make something for the game I want it to be visually coherent with the actual overall
vision for the final product and so even if I'm making something that's purely gameplay
oriented I like to know that it's going to fit with the direction that the artists have
for the final product.
And also what I end up doing when I'm looking at the concept art is I have a tendency to be inspired by even small things like a fallen tree that the player is walking through in the picture.
And it makes me want to use that kind of geometry in my level.
So then I do that and sometimes it leads to the creation of interesting gameplay elements or terrain properties that we wouldn't normally have.
And so I like to be inspired by the art before actually proceeding in my area of expertise.
But I also like to make sure that my work is just consistent with the overall vision.
What's interesting is that we have a template frieze.
So that have no graphical content, just a basic mockup.
So we can build the level using this mockup frieze.
They already have the constraints for visual things,
but by themselves they don't have a particular visual,
so they can be used in any circumstance.
But they already have the constraints for the collision and everything,
so we don't build things like we want.
We already have constraints to work with.
And we already know that when the artist will find a visual for the freeze
and a visual for every element,
It will fit with the collision we put so we'll not have to work a lot on top of that.
When the level is built, when the gameplay element, the situation are done,
we'll make a new review with the artist. We'll say
what intention we have, what was the
idea of the level.
And with that, they will be able to build a world landscape.
Easily, normally they don't have to touch our work, we don't have to add new constraints to their work.
And so they can build the level on top of that, graphically speaking.
We developed some small tools, including the Atlas Editor,
which allows artists to gather many graphic elements in a single texture,
and to cut the mesh directly by drawing them by hand in 2D.
and to be able to re-apply them in-game and make sure that we optimize as much as possible.
It also allows to add volume and animate these objects
with a simplified interface that allows you to go very fast.
I have a lot of fun with trying to bring a lot of life and things happening on screen,
lots of wow moments.
And I think that the tools that we have, but also the concept and the game and the gameplay
mechanics really mesh well together with this kind of philosophy of creating levels that
are alive with lots of things happening.
And it makes for some very exciting results and it's always fun to see people playing
these levels and reacting to such.
animated worlds and
Just the fact that they enjoy them so much when stuff surprises them, you know, it's not predictable
It's just wow and amazing and they always want to come back and experience something new. So it's really cool for me
Thank you, thank you
So now let's approach the character design
And how it influence the style of animation.
And how we made the transition between Rayman 2,
The Great Escape, Rayman 3, Oodlemavok,
and the new Rayman in 2D.
Michel Ancel is a fan of Joan Sfar, Jean-Louis Marco,
that kind of French book style.
So we decided to adapt the character design.
from a comic book named Roscoe le Rouge.
At the beginning of the project, we didn't know what the animation tool was capable of.
But we knew that we wanted for the animation something easy to do, a simple process, something
cool to look at, something punchy, and not just a simple cut-out animation.
And we asked the engineer to implement scale, stretch, and squash.
Then the character design made its step into US cartoon style.
To make the animation more efficient, give more opportunity to optimize the action line
with a strong and clear pausing and more snappy timing.
And we wanted the game to look like an animated cartoon.
That means a sophisticated painterly style
for the background, a celluloid look for the characters,
more extreme poses, and to have some wacky situations.
OK, it's clear that the style of the character design
impact.
the style of the animation.
The more your design is realistic, and the more you need drawings to make the animation
subtle, and the more it's difficult to step to reality.
That process could be long, especially for cut-out animation.
But the more the design is stylized, graphic or cartoony, and more it will be easy to adapt
the animation to cut-out style.
And our reference are Tex Havry, Chuck Jones, and Bob Glumpet,
of course.
But we were more influenced by some more recent cartoons,
like Cats on Dance or Ranald Snippy.
And cartoon snappy style is very fun to draw and to animate,
too.
But it's very practical for all kind of games.
Now let's talk about the pipeline of creation.
In order to create a strong character design, there is one very important rule.
Form follows function.
That means
the player got to identify the nature,
the dangerousness of an enemy.
the function of a gameplay element in one single look
that's got to help him to stay reactive and to keep the flow.
That means we got constraints
that we got to take care when we are designing a gameplay element, an enemy or any characters.
That constraint is given by the game design, the level design, or the environment.
An example.
About the design of a gameplay element in a food world.
the constraint for designing a gameplay element.
It took place in a kitchen.
It was a very...
environment.
The gameplay constraint included the fact that
the gameplay element threw dangerous things.
It was two meters high.
It needed to move right and left.
And the playable character died if he touched it.
So, okay, let's find some ideas like the dangerous things could be a fireball.
But what kind of enemy, for example, could throw a fireball?
Could be a dragon.
But a dragon in the kitchen, yes, why not?
But if we dress him with a chef's hat, an apron,
he's going to look like a cook.
And he needs a weapon for the near attack.
So no problem, he's going to have a fork.
And it's done.
And that's the easy part in Iron Man.
That's an easy, crazy world.
Almost everything is a joke, you know?
So now the character designer can start to work.
He makes some sketches.
One is approved.
And on that stage of process, the character
stays a rough sketch.
He could be colored, or stay in black and white,
or very simple color.
After that, different parts of his body are split apart.
The animator makes the setup.
At the same time, the technical director
makes the animation tree.
Then the first animations are made with rough assets.
And the gameplay programmer uses it
to improve artificial intelligence.
The timing to test his prototype,
that's the same for the LD, the level designer.
He can test his map with a rough asset, the same.
And after some iteration, when the map is approved,
we can clean the character up.
The character designer make a contrast on Photoshop.
We replace the rough asset by the clean one,
directly on the TGA texture.
No need to change.
The name on any asset or animation, no need to modify the setup.
The new clean character works in the game directly.
To illustrate the pipeline process, let's take another example with a playable character.
We had already created the animation for Rayman and Globox.
And we wanted to reuse the animation tree
to create the Teensy.
I said before, when we are designing a character, the way in which it will be animated is always
kept in mind.
We must be able to separate each part of the body of the character.
For example, eye, mouth, legs, body, etc.
This method has an impact on how the character is designed, for sure.
A well-designed character means a minimum of number of assets, like you can see there,
for a maximum of amount of animations.
With the TenZ, with only one texture, we created like three...
three hundred and fifty animations.
And on Romano Regis, the animator in charge of this character,
made about 250 animations in like two weeks.
So it's really fast to produce animations.
And he was very smart, but the way
that he used the few elements that he's got,
he reused elements like different arms or different.
or the nose to be, if you want to take the tinsy
and put it in a front view.
It just deforms the nose to pretend that it's a new asset,
but it's not.
So we've got a few examples in this video.
So it's only done with one squared texture
and with no new assets.
So thanks for him.
Thanks for them.
So it's an important part of the work of the animators.
You know, we are not God creating life.
We are kind of cheater, nice cheater, like a magician,
something like that.
And if we succeed to do great animation, it's like you take
part into the magic that we create.
So it's cool.
To work on characterization, it's probably the funniest part
between us.
Emma's character designer, and me as an animator,
we had to work very close together.
And it's really, really cool.
And it's very good for the game, too.
One thing make our production very efficient,
especially at the beginning when the team was very small.
is a multi-talented profile of the collaborators and the animators.
To make the ideal crew, we thought it would be smart to recruit animators from a French
animation school.
In fact, in school they learn a lot of different school, they learn traditional animation.
3D, and they learn to use a lot of different software.
So, our animators are very multi-talented.
That's right.
Most of them are character designers, too.
They can cut out a character, make the setup.
Some are also storyboard artists, color artists.
That means we have a complete small crew able to work on gameplay animation,
make a cutscene from the concept to the final.
That's very efficient and practical.
And to illustrate, we have a video.
The last one, but...
The animators.
Let's see that.
For example, for Blue Box, I try to go on trips with Rupi, Bardet, Deception, all those things,
the sleeping side but cool at the same time.
There was already a Globox made on Rayman 3D, so we had to remake a Globox a little bit weird.
We had to do something a little bit different from the usual crazy Globox, where you're just messing around, doing stupid things in every way.
We had to do something a little bit more groovy, so to speak.
It was interesting because we had to remake a character that already exists and that we've seen a lot.
We tried to see where we could put some fun, for example.
on things like a walk, jump, attack sequence.
As the space is very limited to do an anime,
we're not going to be able to express ourselves as much as possible.
So we're going to try to make a distinct pose appear, a bit crazy.
And we're going to try to put the fun there.
And if not, to really let go, poses like wait or stand,
where we have a beach of time, not unlimited, but much wider.
There, we can express ourselves and do crazy things.
The inters are managed by GeneAnim, so you just have to set your own pace,
put some good pausings, and the machine does the rest.
The idea of Genanim comes from Michel.
Throughout the creation of the tool, throughout its development,
we tried to keep it simple and intuitive,
to be able to iterate quickly and easily.
One of the main advantages of the Genanim chest
is that it allows no intermediary between the drawing
and animation. There is no interpretation between the two.
The animator will directly animate the drawings of the concept artist.
This makes it possible to be very faithful to the original concept.
We take the picture and we extract from it a mesh.
But it's a mesh that we can deform to make the movement.
So we can take an arm and we put points on it.
And after, very easily, we can deform,
we move really the picture to create the animations.
Every time an animator needs a special feature, we discuss it with our DT.
My work with U3 is to evaluate improvements that could be made
to facilitate the work of the animators or to optimize the performance of the characters in the game.
It allows you to have directly what you download in the software.
It's cool.
So we jump into the technical part of this presentation.
What is GenAnim?
GenAnim is a UBI framework animation tool.
It's a customizable tool created at Ubisoft Montpellier
for Rayman Origins.
And we reuse and upgrade it for Rayman Legends.
It's done principally by Philippe Vimon and Yossri Salas.
It's to, uh...
to some tool programmer that they work very close to us.
So it's really cool if we need to improve some tools
as animator.
We just ask them to improve the.
one particular tool, and they just do it.
And in like one week, we've got the new tool
at our disposal.
So it's made as all the technology.
It's made to fit with those specific needs in 2D.
So we can put directly, as we've seen before,
the drawing of the artist.
And here is the drawing of the character artist
into the animation software.
So we can keep the essence of the drawing, and there is no long skinning or rigging to do.
And we save a lot of time to work on the characterization of the characters.
And this adds a lot of fun into the game.
It's an intuitive to use tool.
The animator, like me, I can quickly transform any drawings
to an animated character.
I can do my own actors set up.
I can upgrade it with new drawings.
If I start an animation and I need some new assets,
I just have to ask Christophe to draw them,
and then he send it to me.
And I can implement that into my actual animation,
into my actual setup, with no long time,
no long technical stuff to manage.
It's really easy to use.
The animations are done faster, so we
can product many original characters
in a very tiny time of production.
And that's why Rayman is a rich and immersive 2D platformer
with a lot of funny characters.
It's a simple to use tool, but it's powerful.
We have additive animation for the gameplay needs.
We have inverse kinematics to facilitate the animator's work.
We've got polyline collision to fit with the gameplay collision with the punch, the hit, and all that stuff.
We can add event on the timeline to trigger effects, sounds,
to separate the animation between transition and loop to help the gameplay programmer.
And the optimizations while tinkering too.
We can practice.
When you create a character, you have...
several different textures, different assets,
different arms, different legs, different bodies.
And we create like one, two, three, a lot of textures.
And we have a tool that just brings
all the assets in the textures and brings them
into one single texture with the space optimized.
So it's really cool.
We don't have to.
to take care really about that at the first time
when we're doing animations.
We just take care of that later.
And the optimization is really good.
That allows us to put a lot of assets into the game,
because we've got the space to do it.
We can also reuse the animation of a character
by changing his skinning.
It's great.
So I can make, if I want, a different look of Freyman
or some bosses that we've made that are a gabary.
They have a shape and a.
I can't just talk too much about that, because it's not really allowed.
You know, Rayman Legends is not out, so you'll see when you'll buy it.
It's okay.
And the easiness to use GeneAnim means that we can produce fast and a lot.
And to make move things, it's a better way to make it alive and rich.
And of course we have characters like playable, enemies, bosses, fairies, different costumes
like you said, or skins for the same characters.
For example, the fairies in the Oreman origin were one skeleton in a different costume.
We can animate platforms, breakables, groups, backgrounds, UI and interface,
crowds, plants, mechanics with a different system of animation.
We use GNAnim for gameplay animation and for cutscene in-game videos.
Everything needs to be animated.
So, we're gonna see...
I'm just gonna move...
So we're going to see a few examples of how we bring life
into the Rayman's world really easily.
And it's a low-cost character that we call life elements
that we can put on the foreground or on the background
to bring life to the game.
So here we work with a simplified.
simplified version of O2.
We just.
We don't keep the information of the bones, we only keep the information of the miges, the drain.
And so we can make a lot, a lot, a lot of those things. We can put them into a level and we still have 60 frames per second. It's great.
Then we can animate effects too.
And this technique is really different, kind of.
It's just like a sprite animation,
but we put it in GenAnim so we can add deformation
to that sprite animation.
And with that one single texture, it looks like a drawing.
Old-fashioned style.
Yeah, old-fashioned style.
That's it.
So now it's time for the demonstration.
I'm going to work a bit on the genanine,
and we're going to see how it works together.
So I got to just get out of here.
So we prepare a character, Kristoff Drozd.
This small character looks like a testicle a bit.
But it's OK.
I'm going to animate it.
Fine.
We can make anything alive in Roman origin, even a testicle.
So I'm going to do like if I was in my workspace.
So I'm maybe going to skip some parts, because we are a bit
late.
But I'm going to try to do an animation really quickly.
So first, when you open GenAnim, you've
got nothing inside of it.
FaceUp sends me the drawings, and then I cut it out in few parts.
And I just had to drag and drop the TGA textures that I created
to start the setup of the character.
So I was talking about cheating.
Obviously, I'm going to cheat here.
I'm just going to show you how we create easily a bone
that we can rename.
And this bone is not ever attached to the visual.
So I had to create a mesh.
That's it.
Easy.
So I'll create mesh around each element.
I'll create bones to control them.
And here I've got some templates.
I'm going to create one template per element.
And cheating.
OK.
And we just do all the elements like that.
You've got here the template names
that we can rename to find ourselves easily
in the animation process.
Then with those bones, I'm going to copy them and put that
into the skeleton edition.
to connect the different parts of the body.
Like, OK, the arms to the body, the mouth to the body,
to the testicle.
I'm going to copy that.
It's really not fast.
It's really not.
It's easy to do.
to do the setup, and I've done it yesterday night.
And it takes me like half an hour to just doing the setup
and then creating the one animation.
I think we're going to have no time,
if you want to have some questions to ask at the end.
So stop speaking and start working.
Thank you.
the bone of the body.
There is no visual attached because we
are in the edition mode.
So the mouth is there.
You can attach them with that.
You can see that with the blue line, they are connected.
I'm going to do that for all the bones.
It's going to be more faster.
It's a bit scary to animate just in front of you.
It's an encouragement.
Woo!
Oh.
All right.
Thank you.
Yeah.
OK.
There exists.
It's a kind of old version of Shendanim, so there is not really an interface or something like that.
Oh... Okay...
Cut to math...
Just hit one...
Okay, so the arms are left.
Okay, this way.
So all I'm doing is just connect
the different parts of the bodies together.
So now when I move the body bones,
all the things come with it.
Now I connect them to the root.
OK, now I have my bones down with all the influences.
Now I can start to animate something.
Woo, my favorite part.
So I'm just going to call the visual on the bones.
So I call those templates.
Okay. Eyes.
I forgot the eyes.
Can I sing a song?
So I'm going to bring all these elements in the animation mode.
OK, so it looks like that for now.
And I need to refer to the drawings of Christophe
to see how I'm going to mix them together.
So I can control the z function to put an element in front
or in the back.
So now the mouth is in the front.
The eyes are in the front.
I'm just going to stay in France.
I text the same visual for the right arm and the left arm.
And I'm going to just symmetrize them to bring some less
space in the database.
The same thing for the foot.
For the feet.
Feet, feet.
Okay.
And...
It's...
Is it okay for you?
Yeah.
Okay, I approve it.
We've got the pair.
Right.
So now, all I had to do is just put, let's make a jump.
Okay, jump.
So I can deform the scale in different axis,
like X, Y, and it's still 10 minutes,
so I had to do that really fast.
Okay.
So I'm going to scale axes in X and Y with the deformation
to do something like that.
Yeah, I use a special thing that allows me to deform all
in the same time.
That makes me.
I'm gonna win some times with that.
That's my keyframe.
Not done, ever! Thank you!
My boss look at me when I work, and I'm not sure I appreciate that.
That's pretty sure.
Maybe I'm going to be fired at the end of this presentation, so I have to do the best that I can.
Okay.
So I can copy past different keys.
It's not going to be a subtle animation, but...
It's just going to show you the power of the tool.
So I can play, but it's going to be really fast.
Blah, blah, blah, blah.
So I can reduce the speed just to see if it works.
Seems pretty good for a two-minute animation.
And then.
I'm going to do the transition.
So I insert frames between the key frames.
You can't put any at all?
Huh?
You can't put any transition at all?
Yeah.
Almost done.
Wing wing.
We've got no overlap here, but it's a start.
It's a start.
We're not going to develop that so much,
because maybe you've got some questions.
And I want to answer that if I can.
So OK, I'm going to just.
do a few resume, a few summary about what we've said in that conference.
So, if I can take you, give you advice.
Just communicate a lot with your team members and leave your comfort zone to be more efficient.
It's very cool.
For my part, I work a lot with the gameplay programmers and it helps to put a lot of life
into the game because they've got the conscience of what I need and I've got the conscience
of what they need.
If you reinvent an iconic character,
be sure to remember where he comes from
and where you want him to go.
Use tools that allow you to fit the best
with your vision of your game.
If you want to create any characters,
just remember that forms follow functions in the video game.
It's really, really important to not losing the player.
And if you want to do a good characterization,
keep your silhouette very recognizable.
Don't lose the fact that it had to stay
visible in the game space.
And focus on strong posing.
That's it.
So thank you for coming.
It's the end of our presentation.
Woo!
Thank you.
Thanks.
Thanks a lot.
A bwing, bwing, bwing.
So if you have any questions, I need someone to translate because my English is not so fluent, as you can see.
I call Gabrielle Schragers, she's the writer on Rayman Origins, actually.
So, big applause for her. Thank you, Gabrielle.
And just try and help these guys if you have any questions. So, please, ask away and I'll translate.
Hey, first of all, big fan, well done.
It was an amazing job.
But then also, you have this amazing game on console,
and you moved to an amazing game on iOS.
Can you talk a little bit about the iOS game?
Was it the same team?
Did you guys use the same engine at all
when you made the iPad iPhone game?
Ah, so we used the same tools to do on all the iOS for the sharing.
Is it the same tools?
Yes, exactly the same tools.
Same engine, same tools.
Same pipeline, same tools.
Not on the tablet.
Alright.
Yeah, it's another engine, but for all the consoles for PC, for the Vita too.
I think that's the same engine and the same tools.
Yeah.
And from art directing the work on the iOS game,
the tablet game, Jungle Run,
were you art directing it, or was it outsourced at all?
Man 2 speaking French
No. No. No.
It's another team.
It's another team, but they were using all the assets,
obviously, that were created for...
They reuse the assets that we create on Rayman Origins, so they keep a lot of the same animations.
Fantastic, thank you guys.
You're welcome.
Anybody else?
Don't be shy.
Not shy, just short.
I don't have a question.
I gotta run.
But I just want to say, you guys are like, Rayman is the reason I'm in the industry.
I've hopped around to a lot of really stylized studios.
So keep doing this rad stuff.
This latest game is amazing.
You guys are fantastic.
So thanks for inspiring a veteran.
Continue, continue.
That was a really easy question.
Thank you.
That was not really a question, but thank you.
OK.
It's all you.
Did you also have any technical artists to help you with the particle effects, the special effects, or was it all done in 2D?
The question, I should translate into English, is whether or not we have particular tools to create the special effects in the animation, or whether it's the same tools as we're using for all the other animations?
If all the effects and the particle was all draw, or if someone did a specific job on that using other tools or technical artists.
Thank you for translating for yourself.
We have...
Okay.
On Roman Origin, we have tools for the FX, of course,
but we have two FX artists.
One comes from the traditional animation.
And the other is more technical and use a procedure more specific for procedural stuff.
For the particles?
Yeah, particles and stuff like that, yeah.
But they were all hand drawn, were they not?
You don't like, did they see me?
Yes, yes.
Oh yes, yes.
They were all hand drawn.
Okay.
Go ahead.
Bye.
Thanks for coming, great talk.
That Gen Anim tool looks really amazing.
I was wondering if you guys had any plans
to distribute or sell the tool to other companies.
I will show you a few questions.
So the question is if we're going to sell the tool
or share the tool.
I think we...
We want to share the tool, but I'm not sure about the position of Ubisoft at that point.
So it's over.
OK?
It could be great to share that tool.
We had to do a small modification
to make it a lot more user-friendly.
It could be great, but I'm going to ask my bosses
and post something on the Facebook page of Rayman
or something like that to answer your questions,
because I really don't know what.
strategy.
For the moment.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Sorry, I just found out that we actually have nothing
in here next session, so if you wanted to QA a few
more questions, you're more than welcome to.
Cool.
Additional time.
I can stay one hour
longer then.
Thank you.
Hi, I was just curious how you handled the lighting on the characters because it seems to bend and not just wash over the flat 2D.
So how did you handle that?
He was asking how you handled the lighting on the characters because it was 2D, 3D...
If you ever see a French rapper, you'll be like...
On Roman Origins, there was no dynamic lighting.
It's like a cartoon.
It's like an animated cartoon.
No dynamic lighting.
It's just like a traditional cartoon lighting.
Hi, yeah, I was wondering, as an animator,
was there like a learning curve to using the actual polygons yourself?
Does that make sense?
Did you say a learning curve? I'm sorry.
Yeah, to defining the polygons when animating.
as opposed to it just being a square.
Is there a curve to make it square?
No, it's not just a square.
I didn't show you that because I've got no time,
but you can deform the mesh to adapt it
to the shape of the assets.
And when you do an articulation tool, as you can see,
as you have seen in the video of the animators,
you can replace the, you can move the points.
to be close to the shape of the arm.
And you can also move those points,
like to make a...
a plieur.
A fold. You want to create a fold.
If you want to create a fold more stronger or more smooth,
you can modify that to answer your question.
Yeah. Yeah. Cool. Thank you.
Oh, okay. Go ahead.
How long did it take you to develop the tool?
All from creating the animation system and developing the 2D background, you know, layering.
How long did it take you to develop the GeneAnim tool?
So when did it become functional, was it a two month window, three month window?
Oh, from...
It was very, very quick.
And Michel worked with a very small team of artists and engineers to do that.
And it took about six months to get it up and running, basically.
Awesome.
Thank you.
Beautiful stuff.
Cool.
Other questions, other questions,
there's questions everywhere.
I just wanted to compliment you on how intuitive
the Genonym tool seemed, and also you showed a video
with the level editor, appearing to be just as intuitive
as the Genonym tool.
Is it all part of Genonym, and maybe if you guys,
if Ubisoft.
sells it, will the level editor and how intuitive that looks
be packaged with it?
That'd be awesome.
Yes, so the level editor is not genanime,
but it's part of the framework package.
Yes, it's another tool.
Yes, that's right.
Yes, framework, it's part of genanime,
is part of the framework engine.
So it's included in the package.
And yes, the level design tools are incredibly intuitive.
And the level designers love to work with them.
So yes, easy tools.
Hi, it's a question about art direction.
Can I ask it?
About animation.
I was wondering if you had an artist that
unified all the style of the different levels,
since all are painted.
Or if each artist managed to keep the style consistent
through the game.
The question is, do you have an artist who is in charge of unifying the style throughout the different levels?
It's like in many productions.
Michel Ancel, on Reman Origins, is an artistic director.
And each concept artist and each level artist
is able to work on any level, any world.
So you're saying Michel Ancel, as the artistic director of the project,
obviously does the...
makes sure that there's the coherency throughout the world
and every one of our artists are capable of working on any of the levels
and adapting their style to whatever his creative and artistic vision is.
As we said, of course, artists have a...
Sometimes they work more easily with organic material,
with life, living organisms,
and others have a preference for working with more metallic
and structured architectural elements.
But so they can choose also which universe
works the best for them.
Okay.
Well, obviously, great team and great games.
Thanks.
Thank you very much.
Hi, this is also about the artistic direction of the levels actually.
So one thing that struck me was that the levels of Rayman Origins were really imaginative
and they felt they really popped in a way.
So I was curious about how did you go about creating the particular style of each level?
Was it like somebody wrote a story for it or was it up to the imagination?
Yeah, that's part of the creative process of working with Michel,
who will come in every day with a great story to tell about,
which are all sort of micro-stories,
so little stories of what happens in the food world.
And then together, the team bounces off his ideas
and makes character designs and backgrounds,
and then iterate.
Every day, every day, every day, there is new stuff that pops, that appears and disappears,
depending on what Michel, what pops into his brain, and how much the rest of the team embraces
each of the levels. So that's, yeah, that's why there's so many unbelievable variety, like 70
levels with, I don't know how many, completely different environments. Yeah, and that's part
of the fun, and that's what makes Rayman. And it's because we're in this completely iterative
process constantly.
That's so much stuff, so much creativity just goes out.
And probably as much as you guys have seen on screen,
also gets lost in the process because we
can't keep everything.
Thank you.
That's it.
OK.
Go to lunch now.
It's better.
If you've got any questions, we're
going to stay outside a bit.
Thanks to you.
You've been great.
Thank you very much.
Thanks.
Thank you for coming.