Okay, so
So in physics, there's this idea, this idea that reality is like two different things happening at the same time.
On the one hand, it's a world of particles, and objects, and events, basically the everyday phenomenal world that we live in.
But at the quantum level, of course, it behaves more like a wave function, a field of possibilities, or overlapping potential realities, or what any Marvel fan knows as the multiverse.
Now, Dr. Strange might have his own definition, but for our purposes, a multiverse is a good way to think about the nature of interactive story design.
Because in a branching narrative game, we use logic and structure to create a sort of multiversal story tree that defines all the many possible paths through a narrative.
But the story can only ever be experienced along a single path at a time, and it's these individual story branches where we give meaning, emotion, and value to the audience and to the players.
So this talk is about how we do both of those things together.
Using the left brain to create meaningful narrative structures, while using the right brain to tell a powerful and emotionally resonant story that satisfies players, no matter what branches they pick through the game.
And I'm going to do that in the context of six principles that we followed when we were making As Dusk Falls, along with examples of how they show up in the game.
Six principles for growing a tree in the multiverse.
OK, so before we dive in, I'm just going to tell you a little bit about me and about the studio.
I'm Brad Kane.
I got started in the late 90s as a journalist covering what were then called story games.
I worked as a producer at Pixar Animation Studios, as a screenwriter, designer, and narrative director on a bunch of different games, including some of the former Telltale, a few AAA titles, some live action projects at Netflix.
And I spent over four years creating As Dusk Falls along with the talented team at Interior Night in London.
The company, for those who don't know, was founded in 2017 by CEO and creative director Caroline Marchal as an independent studio dedicated to making cinematic narrative games.
And our first game, As Dusk Falls, is a six-chapter original interactive drama about two families from different backgrounds whose paths cross at a motel in Arizona in 1998 and the events leading up to and in the aftermath of that one fateful night.
Now, it's specifically a branching multi-protagonist story where player choice and player action determine how the narrative unfolds.
It's what some people would call a choose-your-own-adventure game, where players can't see everything in one or even three or five playthroughs because there's just a lot of different paths to take through the story.
Here's our launch trailer just to give you a sense of the tone and the look of the game.
The thing about shadows, you can't escape them.
You just learn to keep them behind you and look toward the light.
I represent some business acquaintances of your father's.
You help me take care of my family, I'll help you take care of yours.
You swear it won't happen again?
We can make it through this.
On the ground, now!
You're making a huge mistake!
Daddy, don't go!
All you had to do was keep your mouth shut.
What are you doing?
Improvising.
I'm not just gonna abandon you.
Family means sacrifice.
All right, so we developed It's a great trailer
So we developed the game with Xbox Game Studios, and we released day one on Game Pass last July.
And the reviews were generally pretty positive.
We won Games for Impact at the Game Awards.
We've had writing nominations at several of the other award shows, along with various noms for directing, acting, music, and so on.
So now when we started working on this game in 2017, we had a very specific goal in mind, which was to move the medium, the narrative game medium, away from like adapted games, adapted IP games and adventure games, towards something closer to prestige television.
We were inspired by, and we're still inspired by, shows like these.
These are shows defined by great writing, great storytelling, great characters especially.
A lot of them are crime dramas like our game, but really it's about a certain creative bar.
Our goal with this game was a TV-style experience for every player, whatever choices they made along the way.
And that meant we needed to focus on things such as the inevitable technical glitch.
such as having a great screenplay, priority number one.
Choices that actually matter, not just the illusion of choice.
Original stories, original IP, consistent pacing.
Narrative game design is traditionally quite slow, and like I said, we were going for something closer to a season of television.
Manageable production complexity, which for us would mean we could offer a wider choice field and have more flexibility for iteration and rewrites.
An experience where all playthrough paths are valid and good, which is really important to us and I'll talk more about soon.
And we also have a major multiplayer component in the game that I'll touch back on toward the end of the talk.
So why does any of this matter?
Well, at Interior Knight, we believe that branching storytelling is not a gimmick, but it's actually a medium.
And that when we create these games in a deep and approachable way, they can have mass appeal for gamers and especially for non-gamers, because people everywhere love good stories, they love games.
People really like experiencing these things together socially, and they really enjoy learning about themselves and each other in the process, which is something that we offer through our games.
So that was our starting point.
Let's dive now into the creative process that led to the game we shipped last summer.
And I just want to give you guys a spoiler warning.
I'm going to be giving out a lot of them.
So if you haven't played the game and you're really excited to experience the story firsthand, you can leave now, and I won't be offended.
There goes Carolyn, creative director.
All right, so like I said, there's these six principles.
And the first is what I like to call no McKee, break McKee.
Be a master of story structure so you can destroy it.
Who is Robert McKee?
For those who don't know, McKee is probably the best-known teacher of story structure, specifically cinematic story structure, meaning for movies and TV.
People tend to either love him or hate him.
He's very polarizing.
But he knows his stuff, and a lot of screenwriters, especially when they're starting out, will take his three-day workshop or read his book, Story.
It's kind of like a fundamental one.
And there's lots of other great screenwriting teachers out there, too.
This is just a sample of them.
But what they all teach in one form or another is story, and specifically the art of story structure.
So when we talk about structure, what do we actually mean?
Well, it's this thing we all learned about in school that most people in this room probably understand, that stories have a beginning, a middle, and an end, that we can divide them into three acts, that there are inflection points like the inciting incident, the midpoint, the lowpoint, the climax.
And the reason that story has this, looks like this, this shape, is that the shape itself is what creates emotional engagement.
It's something that comes from deep within our psyche.
Shape is like how we understand and make greater relevance of an emotional experience.
It's why entertainment tends to look like this.
And yet, it's really common for trained screenwriters to come into this medium of branching games.
And they're ready to exercise their structure muscles that they learned in Hollywood.
And they're surprised to hear narrative designers tell them, hey, your outline doesn't work, or that story is ignoring the player, or you're putting the story on rails, all these ideas.
And everything they've been trained to do kind of fails.
Spanner in the works, of course, is player agency.
The need for the player to be at the center of the experience.
So writers will then think, OK, well, I'll just create a screenplay, but then I'll insert some choices in between the turning points and kind of choice-ify my script.
But these are the moments that don't really matter, the ones in between the turning points.
And so you get choices that don't feel like they matter either.
You get the illusion of agency.
Players can see through that, especially these days.
We've had a lot of good branching games, and so there's kind of some knowledge around that.
And everyone sort of throws rocks at the game.
So what do we do?
How do we solve this?
Well, we have to break McKee.
But not all the way, right?
We have to know classical structure well enough to know what you need to honor and what you can adapt in a game like this, what you can afford to lose.
It won't work to skip an inciting incident or have a story without a climax.
That would never feel good.
It won't have the engagement we're looking for.
But if the instinct is, in story terms, Jane starts the story lonely, and she begins to trust Clara at the midpoint.
They face a final problem as a team, and they wind up friends for life.
That kind of model of things might be a little too rigid for what we do in these games.
We have to break that a little bit.
So let's look at an example of how we do this in As Dusk Falls.
This is Vince.
He is a former airline mechanic who, in book one of the game, is moving cross-country with his wife, his daughter, his father, to start a new life when they have to stop for the night at a motel in Arizona on Route 66.
And that road trip is the starting point of the story.
We can represent it as the first point on a story graph like this.
It's the little yellow dot in the bottom left, if you guys can see that from back there.
Now, if this were a movie, the inciting incident would typically happen at about the 10-minute mark.
That's what the numbers are along the bottom.
They're a reference point for film.
And in this case, it's when Vince, who we now understand has problems fighting for what he cares about.
It's like his character flaw.
He gets taken hostage with his family at the motel by the three Holt brothers.
Now, in the movie, the story might continue something like this.
At the 30-minute mark, which is usually the start of Act 2 in traditional structure, Vince's worst fears are realized when his wife, Michelle, gets shot.
And at the midpoint, when he can only send one hostage to safety, he kind of gets to be the one to decide who, he insists on sending her out, of course, but it means his impressionable young daughter, Zoe, is left inside with the gunmen.
At 75 minutes, which is often a sort of false ending moment in story structure theory, it seems they're about to get rescued,
But then the corrupt sheriff recklessly assaults the motel, putting everyone inside in danger.
At our crisis or low point, Vince and his daughter get trapped in the burning motel.
Things could get no worse for them.
But at the climax, Vince finds his courage, fights off the bad guys, and ultimately sacrifices his life to save his daughters.
Now that's a nice shape to the story.
This curve looks nice and curvy.
And it's going to feel pretty good if it's well written.
But in a narrative game, it's not enough.
We also need the choices.
And just as we can't offer meaningless choice, we also can't offer choices that do this to the story shape.
Because in that blue path especially, what's happening is the choices mattered.
They've really changed the shape.
But the story doesn't have really a recognizable shape anymore.
It's not going to feel engaging or satisfying in the way you want it to be.
So instead, what we have to do is we have to map the choices onto the inflection points of the story in a way that preserves enough of the structure to keep it meaningful.
In the Vince example, it's going to be things like whether his wife gets shot or not.
That's a variable in our game.
She might never get hurt at all.
And in that case, their story becomes more about how they work together in a crisis with the kind of marital problems that they have going on.
which hostage he sends to safety.
Like I said, that's actually a choice.
He might choose his father or his daughter.
And the back half of the story takes on a whole different context, depending on what he picks.
Instead of fighting the Holt brothers at the climax, he can choose to be their ally, fighting against the corrupt sheriff instead.
Whole different path into the climax there.
And there's lots of ways that book one can end.
Vince can be dead or alive.
He can be free or kidnapped, and so on and so forth.
So here's a second curve, story curve, made from those same choice moments we just looked at.
And it looks kind of similar to the shape of the first yellow one that I put up.
But if you superimpose them, they're different enough that the choices matter, but the experience and the shape still remain meaningful and engaging.
It's still a story.
Now, a classically trained writer might argue that there's always going to be one set of curves that's a little more perfect, a little more McKee.
I think McKee would probably say that.
And he's right in the context of a film.
But what we get in the bargain here is player agency.
And that is the compromise we have to make and that we're happy to make for a good branching game.
Sip of water.
OK, so principle number two, characters as questions.
That title is a little misleading, because most characters in most stories are questions, actually.
What will Walter White sacrifice in his quest to take control of his own life?
Can Elizabeth II preserve tradition as the world around her modernizes?
Can John Snow, a bastard from the North, save a world that doesn't care about him and hardly wants to be saved?
These are all central story questions, which is to say they not only drive plot, but they also convey theme.
And themes, as we know, are often binary.
Things like fate and free will, nature versus nurture, the good of the many versus the needs of the few.
Binaries lend themselves well to narrative games, of course.
And in most movies and shows, the exploration of theme is closely tied to how characters arc.
So this is a character arc example, rags to riches.
We're all familiar with character arcs, I assume.
Usually a character starts with one value.
In this case, it would be rags and ends up somewhere different, riches.
But that could be anything, selfish to selfless or shy to confident.
The key is that they're diametric.
They form two poles.
They're not always super diametric, but there's a change implied in the character arc.
Now, in a branching drama, we have character arcs also.
But we tend to need to start our characters not at the initial point of a journey, like with the whole arc ahead of them, because agency.
So instead, it's more like in the middle there, beginning in the center of the curve.
So the story can kind of go either way, rags or riches.
And therefore, so can the meaning.
In this example, maybe it means the protagonist starts out with a low-level corporate employee job, boring but stable salary.
And the question is, will she make millions or will she lose everything over the course of whatever that story is?
And here's the key.
Each answer implies a very different thing about what that story meant.
after you've seen it.
So like in A Breaking Bad Game, for example, Walter White might have turned himself in and worked with his cousin Hank to take down the cartel, making it a sort of redemption story for him.
Or in The Crown, the queen might choose to abdicate in the 90s, making hers a story about the triumph of modernity.
And Jon Snow might have chosen to rule in tyranny with Daenerys, or even taken the Iron Throne for himself, turning his story into a tale of corruption and probably a better ending.
So how about As Dusk Falls?
We're going to look now at how we built a story tree for the second main character, Jay, that took into account the variability of theme.
Now Jay, for those who haven't played and didn't want to leave after the spoiler warning, is the youngest of three brothers who try to solve their family's debt problem by robbing the corrupt sheriff of Turok.
But it all goes to hell when they get holed up at this motel with half a dozen hostages and the sheriff outside basically trying to kill them for various reasons.
His theme question is, can Jay escape his toxic family without becoming just like them?
Here's a short clip just introducing the three Holt brothers.
You're always out skulking in the woods, climbing trees and all that.
We all know you're good at it.
And you want to help the family, right?
You know I do.
Then here's your chance.
Okay, so those are the Holtz.
And each episode typically has one or two major branching moments that relate to Jay's theme about his family identity, how he feels about that.
Chapter one starts off pretty low stakes, because we're early in the story arc.
And the question is just, does he get that money from the safe that they're talking about, or does he fail and disappoint his brothers?
In chapter two, he's not actually playable in this one, but his story is still evolving and the stakes are still rising for him.
Thematically, it's about whether his family is scraping by through a difficult night or are they kind of shooting hostages, making things a lot worse.
It's kind of building toward where his story is going to go.
In chapter three, Jay either sides with Vince or with his own family in a certain dilemma, further testing everything he believes about himself and his relationship to them.
And then in chapter four, which in our game is the beginning of book two, and it properly kind of becomes Jay's story at that point, now the stakes kick into high gear.
Does Jay fight with his family until the bitter end, or does he abandon them and run for it on his own?
In chapter five, his story is mostly about his relationship with his close friend Vanessa as he's kind of trying to get to the border and escape.
But thematically, the stakes are getting huge for him because she represents his last best chance at personal redemption.
So does he lie about his identity knowing that he could be putting her at terrible risk, or does he tell her the truth and face losing his only friend and ally?
And finally, in chapter six, the stakes could be no higher, the font no bigger.
Does Jay escape to Canada at the expense of another person's life, or does he surrender to save his own soul?
So those are the questions behind the story tree.
And there's, of course, a lot of ways to cut out a branch that answers them.
In this path here, Jay's journey is mostly one of safety and loyalty, you could say.
He's staying loyal to his family.
He's loyal to his friend.
But in a final twist, he actually kills an innocent person.
to gain his freedom.
And so the answer to his theme question could be said to be something like, you might escape a toxic family, but the toxicity lives on inside you.
Whereas, in this version, totally different path, his journey is a lot more turbulent along the way.
He abandons his family.
He deceives his friend.
But in the end, he makes a very noble choice, and the answer to the theme question becomes that real freedom is about personal integrity.
And of course, there's other paths, too.
It's not always black or white.
But you always get the experience of exploring a theme and deciding how that character resolves, how that arc will go for you.
And again, McKee would probably say that characters have one right ending because it's intrinsic to what their flaw is, who they are, must determine how they resolve.
And again, maybe he's right.
But for us, it's more interesting to let players explore that and figure out what it means to have that flaw and decide for themselves
how it resolves and whether it resolves.
Okay, on to principle number three, agency and consequence.
So we talked about major inflection points and how you can manage choices so that you keep an overall dramatic structure.
But in any given scene, there's still always this push and pull between story and design.
It's kind of like the inherent conflict of these games.
Story wants to tell a good tale.
Design wants every choice to matter.
Sometimes we have to find a balance, somehow.
Somehow we have to find a balance.
Now, not every choice can be world-shaking.
Sometimes it's going to be more about probing the different sides of a character or adding flavor to an interesting moment.
But at least once per scene in this game, we wanted a piece of meaningful, impactful agency that would really matter.
And we called these, in our game, crossroads choices.
In real life, when you reach a crossroads, your choices have ripple effects.
Sometimes those are short term, sometimes they're long term.
In episode two, for instance, chapter two, Vince has that key decision I mentioned about which hostage gets sent out of the motel to safety.
He's got his wife, his father, his daughter.
They're all inside.
They all, for different reasons, need to get out.
And depending on previous choices, the game presents the two best options for who that could be.
It's a binary, determined by other things that have come before it.
and that choice has consequences.
Consequences that are immediate, consequences that are delayed, you could say, and then consequences that are quite long term.
So immediately after the choice, there's three different scenes that play out depending on who Vince is escorting outside for the hostage exchange.
For instance, if it's his wife, then the act of saying farewell forces them to kind of face this issue they've had in their marriage.
And they either kind of decide they're going to work on it and try to heal it, or that they're going to dissolve it and that this is probably a kind of goodbye for them.
Then there's delayed consequences, consequences where the ripple effects are felt in later scenes or even into the next episode, say.
So if Michelle was shot and not rescued in that scene, she actually, spoiler, dies at the beginning of the next episode.
Whether that's a painful death or peaceful death is still variable, depending on agency on the player's part.
And if Zoe also wasn't rescued, meaning if Jim was the one who was sent out, then Zoe witnesses that, and it's hugely traumatizing for her.
And then in our game, there's actually these kind of longer term consequences.
For example, 14 years later, our story kind of spans quite a long period of time.
Michelle, if she lived, can be married or divorced.
And Zoe, who is now 20, she has either lost Vince, or she's lost Michelle, or she's lost both of them, or she's lost neither of them.
A lot of different states for her.
And Jim, too, the father, he has his own set of immediate, delayed, and long-term consequences.
So it all kind of like ripples out.
And all of it, in this case, links back to that one choice from Chapter 2.
Now, the key to all this is that even as you accrue different levels of consequence, you still want to keep things interesting by layering on new crossroad choices, even as your consequences build up.
This is Vanessa.
She's that friend that Jay makes during his escape to the border.
And a lot of how his story plays out toward the end depends on how his crossroad choices kind of intersect with her fate.
This is not the most exciting visual aid you'll ever see, but it's super useful.
We do a lot of these.
It's like a two-by-two story matrix.
It shows how two earlier sets of choices combine into a later scene.
So along the top, it's this moment at the end of chapter 5 where Vanessa either stays with Jay for the duration of his story, or she's going to go her own way on player choice.
And down the left-hand column there, it's a moment from the start of the next episode when Jay either bluffs his way past a police roadblock, or he kind of fails to bluff and he ends up being essentially chased by the cops on his journey north toward the border, toward Glacier National Park, in fact.
And the one there with the blue, this one is subdivided again by another slightly minor variable.
So there's really five states going into the final act of his story in that episode, which is cool.
It's cool to have five states.
But that's still all consequence.
We still need to have agency.
So each of those five ranches has its own crossroad choice in the game, which further subdivides into a total of 10 outcomes, which is the light blue boxes there.
So even though not every choice can matter, you just can't make a game where every choice matters.
It's not going to probably be affordable and run into problems.
But even though that's the case, if you keep on introducing important choices into your consequences that you're building up, you get a sort of layering effect where the choices constantly feel like they matter and players feel ownership over the story, which is really the goal.
All right.
Principle number four, A story and B story.
So we wanted from the beginning with this game to do something a little different with points of view and non-linear storytelling.
Almost all TV shows and films use some kind of A-B or A-B-C structure, with usually one main story intercut with one or more side stories.
For instance, in Better Call Saul, it's definitely Jimmy McGill as the main character.
But almost every episode, we spend a good chunk with Mike and his dealings with the cartel.
It's the structure of that show.
House of the Dragon uses an ensemble.
The Wire cut back and forth between the cops and the criminals.
And I put Lost up here, even though it's old, because their AB structure was usually the same character at different points in time, kind of jumping back and forward, which is kind of close to what we did in this game.
Our idea was that every episode would have an A story and a B story where the B story takes place at some point in the past and affects the future as seen in the A story.
Now sometimes that B story would be an hour in the past, sometimes a few days, sometimes months, and in that one episode it's 14 years.
What's cool about that is it's much more epic and responsive and you get a real sense of scope out of the story.
The challenge is the logic.
because we see parts of the future before we get to parts of the past.
So we can't, for instance, conditionally kill a character that we know is going to turn up later.
We have to know what we can affect and when we can affect it.
So let's look at how a story tree can shape up, factoring in everything we've talked about so far, including this time dynamic.
So, okay, Chapter 6 starts in 2012, in the future, as it were, with Zoe, who was a kid at the motel, and now she's a 20-year-old woman.
And we know she's tormented by her past.
We set that up in the episode.
And she's paranoid about a mysterious something that we don't yet understand in the present day.
She's got some problem.
And like we said earlier, she has multiple substates, depending on things that happened earlier, whether her parents are alive or dead, and so on.
But essentially, she's a young woman dealing with years of varied trauma.
So we tell a bit of that story, and then we cut back to 1998.
And now we're with Jay again.
And it's late in his story.
He's on the run.
He's trying to get to Canada.
It's that scene from the blue story matrix.
And this is basically just a visual version of that without the fifth case, two by two matrix.
He's got those two main variables in play.
He's either pursued by the cops or not.
And he's either with Vanessa or he's alone.
Now, cutting back to 2012 again, at the end of a subplot between Zoe and her grandfather, we discover that Zoe has been receiving letters from Jay.
And she's been hiding them in a box up on a shelf.
And we see the letter.
And the letter is worded in such a way that we know Jay must survive his story to be able to send it, but not whether he'll escape or get caught.
We can't reveal that yet, because the player hasn't determined it yet.
So back in 98, we have the climactic scene of Jay approaching the Canadian border over the mountains.
And again, that part of the scene is really modular.
There were four ways up the mountain.
There are three or four totally different kind of climactic scenes based on different variables.
There's multiple outcomes for what happens to Vanessa.
And ultimately, it all funnels into this one key variable for Jay, which is, does he get caught or does he jump to freedom?
So now, back in 2012, this is where that's all finally going to come together and all pays off.
We learn that the reason Zoe has been struggling in recent days is because she's been debating whether to go see Jay face-to-face.
And for the final scene, they have this long-fated encounter, one-on-one meeting together.
But the nature of it is radically different, depending on what happened in the previous scene from 1998.
If Jay escaped to Canada, Zoe's visiting him at his hidden cabin in the Canadian wilderness.
The central question of the scene is, does she agree with his feeling that he didn't deserve his freedom?
Now players decide that, and it leads to multiple endings for Jay and Zoe.
They can reconcile, or she can finally turn him into the authorities, and so on and so forth.
But if Jay was captured, then the 2012 scene is very different.
Zoe is visiting him on Death Row in Arizona prior to his execution.
And the final question now is, in light of everything that's happened, will she be the friend he needs and be there for him on the day of his death?
Players again decide that, which leads to further endings for Jay, either redeeming him, condemning him, and so on.
And that's about our maximum branching complexity, by the way.
So there's two major branches times two variables.
Each with a crossroads choice leads to roughly eight to 10 outcomes.
It sounds like the same structure from the other scene we talked about.
That's because that's kind of a natural limit for us.
We find that if we get much more subdivided than that, what you've got is complexity for the sake of complexity.
Players don't feel it.
It's kind of not worth doing it.
So that's typically where we cap it.
And part of why that's true is because of principle number five, which is no game overs or bad branches.
That any branch we make, any story we tell, we're committed to making it feel like that's the best branch you could have gotten.
Again, this is like a prestige TV experience.
You want all playthroughs to feel like a great piece of content.
Now, not all games take that approach.
In, like, The Walking Dead, the zombies can get you, you die, and that makes sense for that IP, right?
Or in Hidden Agenda from Supermassive, it's possible to finish that game without ever solving the mystery.
And again, that's kind of by design.
Or in some of the Netflix shows, including ones I've worked on, you can just pick the wrong path and fail, and it tells you you have to rewind and try again or else you turn off your TV.
Those are your options.
But our model was Prestige TV.
And there's no Prestige show where this happens.
So for us, the show always goes on.
If you fail a QTE or you make a terrible choice, there will be a consequence.
But that consequence doesn't affect the format of your experience.
It just changes the story.
So early in the game, we're more forgiving about what that means.
The most damage you can do in episode one, for instance, is you get a sheriff's deputy killed when he swings by for a seven.
Make it sound like it's not a big deal, but poor guy, right?
But once we get to episode two, choices start leaving a more permanent mark on the game.
And from there forward, major characters can die in almost every episode.
And when that happens, the story has to adapt.
Partly, we do that with an ensemble cast, like I talked about, like allowing the POV character to swap over.
Partly, it's just how we structure the episode when we allow consequences to happen.
But it's not trickery.
We don't write a dead character out of the story.
The fact of their death becomes a defining theme for the survivors and the people who love them.
And that story just kind of adapts from there.
Now, not every major event is life or death either, by the way, especially in a game like this.
Again, maybe in The Walking Dead.
But at a couple points in the middle of the game, it's possible for Jay to get arrested.
and his journey doesn't end there.
That wouldn't have felt good.
It would just feel like a bad branch.
And we also didn't want to tell a story from inside the prison system for three episodes.
We could have, but it wasn't the story we wanted to tell.
So we needed a way to adapt the story to be responsive to what happens without tying our hands creatively.
And we knew Jay would have to escape custody, so we didn't focus the agency on that.
It's not about what clever way do you get out of the office, because ultimately it wouldn't have mattered.
He always escapes.
So instead, it's about what happens during that arrest.
And there's this conditional scene that plays out where he's being interrogated by an FBI agent pretending to be on his side, played by the wonderful Brian Bovell.
And whether players figure out that he's kind of playing him when he's not on their side determines whether Jay sort of confesses on tape.
Let's watch it.
My son's a linebacker.
Got himself a full ride to ASU.
Do you like football?
Not really.
Well, he does.
He's out there pursuing his dreams.
That's what I want for you, too, son.
But here's the problem.
Forensics has you at the sheriff's house.
Witnesses have you at the motel.
To get a deal, a way out, you need to give up something the DA doesn't already know.
There's only one thing big enough, and that's who made you do what you did that night.
See, we had a lot of bodies inside that motel.
Four police officers dead at the scene.
Another two on life support.
You weren't just a witness.
You were part of it.
So tell me, who put you up to it?
Tyler.
He gave the orders.
I just did what he said.
Make a note.
Suspect has confessed to multiple murders at the Desert Dream Motel.
And to being an accessory in the murder of Victor Gray.
Wait.
That's not what I... You can discuss the finer points with the judge.
You said... You said you'd help me.
I am helping you.
You're gonna feel a lot better now.
What about pursuing my dreams?
Like your son?
That isn't my son.
This isn't even my office.
Yeah.
So Jay's always going to escape this room.
But that confession variable gets stored.
And much later, if he's on death row and if he didn't confess in this scene, he can't actually get a reprieve.
So it's a small touch.
It's just an example of how even a failure, in this case the failure of getting arrested in a different scene, can be used to tailor the narrative.
OK, so I started the talk on the idea of trees and branches and left brains and right brains.
And a lot of what we've covered so far has been the left brain, really, the design.
But the moment-to-moment quality of any story comes down to the writing, which means, as a writer, you have to know how to take all these branching principles and just sort of completely forget them and flatten yourself down into a single branch as you write.
So in terms of our writing process, we used all the same tools that a writing team in television would use.
From the beginning, we got together in TV-style writer's rooms.
We worked out the story on boards and post-its with a lot of fidget toys.
We created a pretty extensive story bible with characters, locations, world building, elements, which we regularly updated throughout the project.
We also like working with character maps.
This game is about relationships between characters and between families of characters.
And especially with the AB structure, we needed to understand how everyone was connected to each other.
In fact, for all the branching complexity of the game, and it is complex, this character map came before any of that, before any of the branching got figured out.
Now where it starts to get unique to this format is that we use specialized tools to outline and write in a way that lets us focus on the story while also still paying attention to the considerations of branching structure.
We looked at a lot of branching dialogue tools before we kind of got into the meat of this.
But we decided to go with a modified version of Microsoft Word, which sort of shocks people, especially writers, when they hear that.
But it's actually a really customizable tool.
It's especially good for collaboration.
There are other custom tools out there with various strengths and weaknesses.
I could talk about more afterward in the wrap-up if anyone's interested.
I'd strongly recommend against trying to write in a flowchart tool like Articy, Romero, or ArcWeave.
Those are great tools, but they're not so great for writing.
But it's ultimately up to what works for your team and for you.
And then it's just about writing pages.
I think our final script was about 1,200 pages long, writing them and trying to make them as good as possible.
And the thing with the writing is it's just this tricky balance where you need to bring in all the skills you have as a screenwriter, focusing on character and emotional authenticity and the flow of the scene, and write as if there's only one branch, the branch that you're in at the moment that you're writing it.
while at the same time remembering that moments can sort of weave in and out of each other in a very non-linear and tricky way in this format, and that there's things like feeders and choice responses and moments where the dialogue dovetails back to mainline, which do have special status within the screenplay, and they have to be written with the tree in mind.
Which is why it's really a cross-brain exercise, bringing it back to this image.
Some writers work with a separate narrative designer.
Some studios are set up for writers to work with a separate narrative designer.
And they communicate back and forth a lot.
They have to work very closely together.
Otherwise, you just have to get very good at moving back and forth across your own corpus callosum and kind of doing both.
But in either case, this is where I'd say the two sides of the process really collide.
It's all about this weirdly zen idea of having to remember the tree and forget the tree at the same time.
And then even when we think we're done, we're definitely not done.
We went through multiple rounds of UR feedback on this game, and sometimes they radically changed the story, too.
For a long time, Vanessa always came with Jay at the end of into Chapter 6 in one of three different emotional states.
But we got feedback that some people wanted to leave her behind in Chapter 5 for her own sake.
So we got into the truth of that.
It was a good note.
And we came up with a pretty last minute storyline for what happens if Jay is approaching the border by himself and without the cops on his tail.
Because prior to that, that was the source of the drama.
So we had to kind of figure out something else.
Which is how we ended up at this character of the park ranger that Jay meets, who's sort of like a much older version of himself, like a reflection of who he could become if he goes the right way in his journey.
I'll just play you one last snippet here so we can see it.
You know, I've seen a lot of crazy things up here.
Forest fires, avalanches.
But I always wondered, is it really necessary that we carry these?
But we are border patrol.
In the rare event some criminal makes a run for it, we need to be prepared.
Look, you seem like a nice kid, but we got a stolen car down at the trailhead, which State PD says belongs to an 18-year-old who shot up a motel in Arizona, and was last seen headed north.
Now, you got no water bottle, no headlamp, and I sure didn't see a campsite further down the trail.
So, what's the deal here?
Michael?
Please, let me keep hiking.
Oh, son.
I can't do that.
I've got a responsibility.
Can't you just help me?
Look, it's no kind of life running from the law.
You'll be living with that shadow over you forever.
Let me take you down the hill.
I've never once fired this thing, and I sure don't want to start now.
So I'm going to let it hang there.
But out of curiosity, who would have surrendered?
Nice.
And run.
Interesting.
So yeah, that was a scene born out of necessity.
But in the end, it gave us a really nice piece of character-based storytelling.
So, let's get back to why all of this matters, why any of it matters.
So, branching narrative games, they let us tell these, like, fractalized, multiversal stories that are both emotionally deep and approachable, where players have a major role in shaping the journey.
This is one of the insight screens from our game, which sort of collates the player's choices and play style into a personality assessment.
I show it because these games can also reveal something about players in a way that linear TV can't do.
They're a kind of mirror.
They show us what we value and how we respond under pressure and how we differ from other people in that regard.
I mentioned multiplayer.
At Interior Night, we do believe these experiences can be shared.
And a big part of the game was seeing how people respond to these problems as a group.
You can actually play with up to eight people locally, and there's a network mode, too.
This is an area where the design team really pushed the medium and tried to figure out how we could offer something brand new and different for players.
Now, another reason why this all matters is what the future of content looks like.
We've seen explosions of original prestige shows across the streaming services.
I mean, we've seen the streaming services themselves explode too, of course.
And those same streamers are now getting more and more involved in funding and distributing games.
It's all kind of converging.
And pretty much every game IP is now considered a possible transmedia property from almost the second it comes into being, which all points to a future where really good stories told in unusual ways will have an audience.
And like I said, branching stories aren't just a niche or a moment.
They're another type of entertainment, and that factors into the publishing equation.
So there's a lot of opportunity out there if we take the medium seriously and let it really be about that creative bar, which has been our take on it.
So as designers, we do that by learning to see the tree, the multiverse, by being everything everywhere all at once.
Well, as writers, we have to be completely in the moment and in the truth of the characters, because that's where a great story comes from, and that's what ultimately makes your audience care.
So, thank you very much.
I think we have time, so let's open it up to questions.
Hey, I have like a million questions, but I'll try to just pick one.
On a practical level, when you have so many different states and so many different scenes, how do you keep the entire team engaged with this multiverse?
Whereas the writer can have the multiverse living in their head, but the rest of the team, they're building individual scenes.
So how do you make sure that everyone is
aimed at the right vision for a given scene amongst, you know, 14 other options.
Yeah, so I'm going to repeat the questions for the camera.
The question is how do you kind of keep the whole team kind of in the vision of the branching game, because it's quite complex.
And it's true that as writers we have more of that in our head, like as designers.
I'd say that for us a big part of that is that we have a pretty small team.
I'm
We work in Word, but then we also use Articy.
So there's a visual representation of the game for design and production teams.
And we also do things like table reads.
We continually work with the team on it.
So the short answer, I think, is that we do it by doing it.
It has to happen.
Everyone needs to be in the loop.
If someone doesn't know what's going on, they're going to get on Slack and ask a question or talk to their director or something and kind of make sure they have that knowledge.
Great.
Great talk.
Thank you.
Hello, thank you for an amazing talk.
I'm super interested, because you mentioned that you wouldn't recommend using RTC as a tool for writing, right?
And we actually did that on a game called Game Deck, which also involved a lot of branching narrative.
And we also weren't happy with it.
So I would be super interested to learn a little bit more about your writing pipeline, because you mentioned that you
approach writing as a normal screenplay writing, right?
So how does that pipeline of writing and then using RDC work at your company?
Yeah, it's tricky.
I mean, it's first worth saying that we developed our format having previously worked in proprietary branching tools.
Like we all came from different companies that did this type of thing.
So there was already some internal knowledge on like what we would need to do in a
in a Microsoft Word format.
It could be very complicated otherwise.
So we figured out how to organize it in Word.
And then it's definitely a pain point for us getting into Articy, and especially with revision and iteration, because those tools don't speak that well together.
If we make a change, there needs to be this kind of manual update process, and it's something we've been looking at.
talk
here.
And it's something that we're also exploring tools and trying to figure out how we want to improve that.
But having people there to navigate that bridge was just a big piece of that for us, and it let us kind of get the creative.
We'd love a speech on that someday.
Interesting.
OK.
Note taken.
Hello.
Thank you for the excellent talk.
I'm curious, for people who are looking to do smaller, maybe solo branching narratives, or just who wouldn't be working in a team, how would you recommend estimating the scope that you can feasibly accomplish?
And kind of following on the last question,
What software would you recommend when you're not writing across a team?
I assume proprietary software is easier to use in that circumstance, but I'm not actually sure.
Something like Twine?
Yeah, so let me repeat the question.
I forgot to do that on this one.
So it's about firstly managing scope on a solo project.
And I wanted to just ask, when you say manage scope, do you mean for yourself as a writer, or do you mean like the complexity going into production from the script?
I'd say just like the complexity of the actual script, like how much can I, like if I'm writing my own branching narrative and it's just me, how do you do a reality check on like this is how much I can feasibly accomplish as one person?
Yeah, I mean, so on the writing side that's going to come down to how, I don't know, how prolific you are I guess, you know, I mean,
be ambitious
So yeah, you kind of just have to, I think, try it a bit.
The other side of that question, which is what can you produce, I think is a whole other matter.
It's useful to know what your ratio is.
There's usually a ratio of how much material you've written versus what a playthrough is.
These games are often something like 2 to 1 or 3 to 1 in terms of how much gets produced versus how much gets seen by the player.
There's a whole bunch of different ways to look at that.
Yeah, budget's going to factor into that, and time.
If you're doing it on your own time, maybe you want to take bite-sized chunks and make sure you can accomplish something.
Versus if you're out to be the Brandon Sanderson of game writing, and you've got 15 volumes in you or something, then more power to you.
And then what sort of software would you recommend for an independent?
Yeah, software for independent.
I'm probably not the best person to answer that.
I know people use Twine.
But are you talking cinematic or interactive fiction?
Interactive fiction.
Yeah.
I mean, I think Twine's what they use, but there's probably other people who know that better because we're very specifically focused on cinematic.
So it's very much like screenplay style for us.
But we could chat about it more in the wrap-up area after if you like.
OK.
Sounds great.
Thank you.
Hey Brad, great talk.
I got two questions for you.
As you were in the midst of pre-production and production, how often did you play test as a team and have to go back to the story bible and realize, oh we need to refine this or flesh out this detail.
How often did your team review the story as it was developing?
Yeah, well the team is constantly in the game.
How often the writing team saw the game, I think that the answer to that is we need to do more of it.
We were, you know, there was a lot of exploration and experimentation and figuring out the, you know, we have a unique art style and understanding how that was going to work in the format was a long process.
And so there was a period where it was like better for the team to kind of work that out without us being like, you're not
You know, facial expression doesn't, you know, there's a lot that we could have, like, been obstructive on.
As we got further along, we played it more, and I think that we definitely, it's something we've talked about, we want to keep increasing that, because you, there's, like, the, it's super valuable to always be playing the game.
It's just about knowing when your notes are useful, because, like, there's a point at which the cinematics are just bad.
Like, it's just their first pass, and everyone knows it, and the last thing you need is a writer coming in and being like, I feel like you're not accomplishing my,
Did you notice any sort of communication tools or strategies that really helped working between the narrative and the other disciplines on the project?
on
you know, just shooting a message to each other, jumping on a call, but communication always, you know, a quick call solves things better than 100 slacks, if you know what I mean.
So that's my five minute warning.
Yeah, okay, so one or two more questions.
Hi, I had a question about the crossroads decision points.
I know that in the game those decision points require player alignment, but I'm wondering, like, what was the rationale behind revealing that those were, like, major choice points to the player versus obscuring that?
It makes me think of, like,
In Telltale, when it's like, so-and-so will remember this, or Intel Dawn, where there's like the little butterfly, what do you think is the value of saying this is a big choice versus not letting the player know when that's occurring?
Yeah, it's a good question about how, about why and when you make big choices transparent in these games.
And I think there's a reason that these games all seem to land on, like you're saying, different ways of communicating it.
at
You play the Netflix stories and you don't see a tree.
You don't typically know.
And that's fine.
But I think we just feel that it's a value add for people to know that this is an important moment.
And it helps convey that certain moments are going to be impactful, and especially in a multiplayer setting.
It adds stakes, like you just feel in the moment the tension of that, and we're all sitting there going like, oh god, what's going to happen?
And it's also part of the maxim that choices should matter.
We're saying your choices matter, and this choice is especially going to matter.
We're being upfront about that, so please take your time and think about it.
Our timer mechanic actually works differently on crossroads choices.
They're typically untimed, because we want people to just sit and talk to each other and figure out, honestly, what's the right move here?
Because there's going to be consequences.
So it's a design decision, and I'm definitely interested to see a game that goes either way with it that was the one we made for this game.
Thank you.
Do we have time for one more?
Yeah.
While he's looking at the time, go for it.
Thank you for the fascinating talk.
My question, naively, if you have a branch, every time the players make a choice, you end up with your branches doubling each choice.
So I recognize that you need to recollect them into a limited number of branches, such as he's in Canada or he's on death row.
However, funneling players into one of two branches might reduce the feeling of agency and make them feel railroaded.
How do you prevent combinatorial explosion while at the same time preserving players' feelings of agency?
Yes, so the question is how do you prevent combinatorial or exponential branching and keep agency?
And I think the brief answer is like I was talking about the 10 rule, like how we didn't go past that level of nuance.
And it's for that reason.
You can't go bigger than that without spending more than you want to spend on these games.
But if you go less, it does feel railroaded.
So it's a balance, honestly.
That question you're asking is kind of
one of the central questions that we face in designing these games.
Because like you say, you do want people to feel like their choices are mattering, but you can't do a sub-choice on a sub-choice on a sub-choice, or you quickly, you know, you really do have a tree at that point.
And maybe in the text adventure game of that, you can afford to do it if all you're spending is writing time.
But when you're shooting, and you've got actors, and you've got voice, and you've got an art team, there's got to be production constraints.
So that balance is a big part of the process, honestly.
And that's kind of the art and science of it.
And that's a good question, by the way.
I'm happy to talk about that and other topics at the Alcove.
I think they're going to kick us out right now.
I just have a post-mortem question.
Did you use telemetry to analyze how many players took which path or if there are branches which was maybe taken by really few players to learn from it to see for the next game maybe this was a bad decision or something?
Yeah, good question about telemetry.
The answer is yes, we get telemetry.
Before release, there's like UR feedback telemetry, so we could see what people were doing in playtests, and we did make some tweaks based on that.
And then after the fact, we also get telemetry.
We don't do post-launch updates or anything.
We're not changing the balance, but we do see that stuff.
We'll do that for the next game.
Yeah, it's good to know.
I think even if it's just for the pleasure of being like, oh, the choice was balanced, or whoops, everyone chose to run, whatever it is.
But yeah, it's nice to be able to know what people are picking.
Thank you.
So thank you, everyone.
I'm supposed to remind you to fill out your thingy that you're going to get emailed.
And if you want to talk more, there's a little alcove that way.
I'm happy to chat with people during lunch.