Hello, everybody.
My name is Sean Krenkel.
I'm the co-founder of a game studio called Night School.
We're down in Los Angeles.
And we started in 2014, like the middle of 2014.
And we've put out two games.
The first one is a game called Oxenfree,
which is sort of like a supernatural,
coming-of-age adventure.
And then we also did a game in the middle of the year
last year based on Mr. Robot, the TV show,
and that's sort of like a...
paranoid texting thriller.
Somebody likes that game.
So this is a picture of me and my co-founder, Adam Hines,
who is also my cousin and is also sitting right there
and is mortified.
Yes, that little sweet potato wrote all of Oxenfree.
So when Adam and I were little kids,
we just always cared about story and cared about games.
something that we, as we started the studio,
that was really the thing that we thought
we could focus in on and make something really special.
And so, for us, the story-focused games that we make
are all about kind of letting players
push and pull at narrative in ways
that they haven't seen in games before.
And so today, I wanted to talk about
how our team has been approaching that,
just specifically with Oxenfree.
So we'll go back to 2014.
We were there, crammed in a little 600 square foot box
in Glendale, California.
And there are obviously no shortage of amazing dev teams
who are doing really great storytelling in games.
And so we knew we would have to do something
really different to stand out.
Because again, I'm sure half this room
is making extraordinary story games.
So the thing that we started to really come back to
over and over again that we were observing
was this idea that most games really kind of treat
gameplay and story in these very siloed moments, right?
So you would have a mechanics-driven encounter,
then you move to some storytelling,
that storytelling is either something that tells you
what you're going to do next
or is there for emotional impact,
then you go back to the mechanics-driven encounter.
And so even in the best stuff on the market,
that works well, but we thought as a small team,
something that we could try to do is make a game
where the mechanics only serve to push the story.
And so every decision that we made in the game
then would focus on that.
And that was really sort of the foundation
for the studio and for Oxenfree.
So, you know, in the very beginning,
we only had a really basic idea
of what Oxenfree was going to end up being.
You know, we had some pretty specific references
for what we wanted the feel to be,
but we didn't know what the story would turn out to be
or the mechanics.
You know, I mentioned it before,
but it was like supernatural elements
we thought were really cool,
coming of age we thought was really cool,
and if you look at all these different movies
and books and shows that are,
referenced up here, they all have this really underlying
vibe that is frankly pretty well-mined territory
in movies and other media, but you haven't seen
a lot of it in games, and so you kind of keyed into that
and went, oh, this could be a really interesting space
to play in for a game.
So Oxenfree's basic story came together really quickly.
It's about this girl named Alex and the game takes place
on an overnight party where Alex and her stepbrother,
Jonas, go off and...
right after the first act they end up unwittingly opening this crazy ghostly rift and
They then have to kind of uncover the mystery of the island and what they've just unleashed
And we also unpack a fair amount of trauma in Alex's life
Rooted in issues with her her older brother Michael who had passed away
So usually, and I'm sure a lot of folks in this room
would think maybe we kind of got ahead of ourselves
because even for us as a team,
we'd historically like to find a set of mechanics
and then build the game around that set of mechanics
and build the narrative to support those mechanics.
And we were a little kind of nervous about that.
We were falling in love with this story
and maybe a little bit too early.
But because we were loving where the story was headed,
decided to kind of keep pushing and let that story
drive all of our mechanics choices.
So I want to take a step back for a second
and talk about the what versus the why.
And that's really, for Night School,
that's a guiding principle of all of the games that we do,
is having a clear understanding and delineation
of the what and the why.
So what is the player doing,
and then why is the player doing that?
Because hopefully there's a meaningful connection
between those two things.
And I'm sure I'm gonna butcher this slightly,
but in film, the what is the plot,
and that is the sequence of events that take place
over the course of the film.
And then the story is the why,
because it tells us why the characters
are on the journey they're on,
and how that series of events happens.
In games, games are primarily a what medium
because they're interactive.
And so the what is typically the set of mechanics
and encounters, and then the why still remains the story.
So I'm sure this isn't a new concept to anybody in this room,
but many games treat their what as a toy, right?
So you've got like running and jumping,
or aiming and firing, or flinging,
or katamari-ing, whatever that is.
And these are all these really fully developed toys
that are fun to interact with at a very primal level,
because games really excel at the what, right?
Like that's so much of the purpose of why we all love them.
But then a toy alone, no matter how fun it is,
can get boring kind of quickly if there's no feeling
of progression or escalation.
So that's where games traditionally introduce things
like challenge or changes to how the toy works,
or adding new variables to impede your ability
then to use that toy.
So, you know, in games, story is usually just a catalyst,
then, to the real game of what you're doing.
And so we were finding ourselves in this dilemma
of how could we make a story-focused game
with no overt challenge be mechanically satisfying?
Like, what mechanic would best represent the story
that we were developing, and how could we escalate that
over the course of the game?
And we kept coming back to communication,
like being that central piece.
So if Alex's story is why you play Oxenfree,
then communication and how we communicate just as humans
would become our what.
So, kind of quickly just breaking down like,
what was, what is Alex's why,
and what is Alex's what in the game?
So, her why before these kids open this crazy hell gate
is basically just like overcoming awkwardness,
you know, the typical kind of teen stuff
that you would expect of a senior in high school,
and allowing you to define her as a character or.
kind of role play and be yourself as Alex.
And then after the gate opens up,
you're forging bonds with friends and your new stepbrother,
but in a very kind of mortal way,
instead of the sort of teen BS way that happens
before the gate opens.
You're coming to terms with these deep-seated issues
regarding your brother's death,
and you're uncovering the mystery
of the island's inhabitants,
so that you can bring peace to the island.
But then, if you break that down into the what,
it's actually super basic.
It's essentially just like exploring and communicating.
So instead of escalating challenges to what you are doing,
we would escalate the stakes of why you do it
through story.
So we set a very core rule set for movement,
navigation, communication,
but we would then tweak elements of the story
over and over and over again to sort of escalate it
and give that feeling of challenge.
So every creative decision we made then was intended
to smooth out story interactivity.
And where that ended up putting us was,
you know, we kind of looked at it as three different buckets
for our main kind of creative decision making process.
Exploration, which is pretty straightforward,
communication, and then the visual design
that needs to house those prior decisions.
So from an exploration front, how can we make exploration
more conducive to storytelling?
So the first decision we made was that movement
has to be contiguous through the whole game.
Like we never wanted there to be a cut scene,
so there's never a cut scene in the game,
and it was crucial to us to say,
we're never going to take control away from the player
at any time, and always they have the ability
to have some form of input and move.
And that was a big key thing that became a massive,
had a huge ripple effect and big design challenge
both from a writing perspective and a design perspective.
The other piece of exploration that we thought
would be important for us was.
to make it more of a big screen, kind of lean back
experience and not a point and click game.
Like you can play it that way, but we wanted to make sure
that the foundation of the game was still
something that you could play with a controller
and feel really kind of natural and fluid.
So more importantly though, probably most importantly,
is really the kind of bucket of communication, right?
So if we're gonna make communication
the nucleus of this game,
the act of choosing dialogue for us
needed to feel like an ability.
And that was a big distinction
that we wanted to make up front,
where dialogue is not a set of menu choices
that have right or wrong or good or bad or.
morally gray or whatever, it really needed to feel like
an ability and an extension of you.
And so that meant that in the writing process,
Adam, as he was working on it, needed to think through
a wide array of options that I'll kind of go into in a bit.
So another kind of quick aside,
I had never heard of this term a pre-mortem before,
that you guys might know this term,
but I did not know it at all,
and I was looking up how not to freak out before a talk
because I knew I'd be up here slightly freaking out,
which is basically happening,
and I found this TED Talk,
and this guy was talking about
you could stop a stressful moment before it happens
by doing a pre-mortem,
and a pre-mortem...
is it's like a business concept where at the beginning
of a project you look at the end goal and the product
that you're going to build and you play out in your head
every possible scenario that could go totally wrong.
Like just be super imaginative and think of the worst case
of everything and then you work, whoops,
you work your way backwards then and now you've ideally
sort of covered off on a majority of these scenarios
and you're prepared for them before they come.
it calms you down, and that's the type of thing
you could apply to yourself in your everyday existence.
And so what I thought was really interesting,
while looking that up just for my own
non-freaking-out reasons, was that
Oxenfree's writing process was essentially a...
big pre-mortem, because the way Adam approached
writing Oxenfree, as often as possible,
the player needed to have dialogue choices
that they would naturally want.
So again, it's not about good or bad, or light or dark,
it's just like, what would they naturally want to say?
And so, and our goal internally,
even as we were playtesting it, was to make sure that.
One of the big things that we did in all of our playtests
was go, was there ever a moment you were left
wanting to say something?
Did you feel like Alex didn't have,
you know, queued up in the chamber
a line that you would want to say?
And that went, we went back and did a lot of rewrites
based on elements of that.
So Adam then, you know, had to read players' minds
basically in advance, and that is why
the script for this four or five hour game
is 1,800 pages long.
Sorry, Adam.
So another big thing for us, you know,
when we think about communication as a mechanic
and as an ability.
was to ensure that Alex would never talk
unless the player makes her.
This is something that we thought we could put
another kind of big stamp on where we would go,
you know, if other games you have these moments
where the player character,
even maybe the player character gets to choose a line,
but then immediately thereafter, the NPC says something,
and then there's kind of a ping-pong back and forth,
and you wait for a discussion to end
so that you can then jump in and say something.
we said, no, we want it to be every time she talks,
it's because you make her talk, right?
So there's never a moment in the game
where Alex will say something
unless you decide to initiate that.
And that was really crucial in making it feel
more like an ability and less like a set of menu options.
So that also had a pretty insane ripple effect
in terms of how the game was designed,
because one, now the players can be super just weird
and mute and run through it and not say a word.
and there's an achievement for that,
so I don't know if anybody ever got that achievement,
but you can play the game totally silent.
And then the other thing was that, like in real life,
if you've got multiple characters around you
and you don't say something,
the other NPCs have to be able to pick up that conversation
and keep it moving, right?
So it was really our goal to make it feel that fluid,
where if the player decides to just kind of lay in the cut
and not say anything, they can,
because the other characters will continue talking.
You
So, and then even, you know, when it comes down to
the supernatural abilities in the game.
This is something that we started to let
get the best of us very early on.
Like we initially were like, we gotta have a ghost gun,
or we gotta have some sort of Spectro 3.
We literally had something called the Spectro 3000
for like a week.
It was so stupid.
I'm really glad we didn't keep it.
And so we killed that.
And we killed all these other mechanics
that we were starting to think through and prototype that.
didn't have to do with communication.
Like that was, if that's the core of the game,
we wanted the way you interact with ghosts
to also be rooted in communication.
And so, that's kind of where the radio came from.
Like the radio in the game is this analog, creepy,
semi-familiar, but also really weird mechanic
that allows Alex to talk to the ghosts
and also allow the ghosts to talk to her.
And the other thing that started to feel really special
or interesting about that from a player character perspective
was that now they were wielding.
what would be a weapon and something else,
but they were the only one that could kind of open gates,
talk to the ghosts, and not be trapped
in the sort of tropes of Alex is the chosen one.
It's more like she's just got a radio in her pocket.
So all these design ideas then needed to manifest through a
simple visual design.
And every decision that we made on how the game looks and
feels was intended to serve those design choices that I
just walked through.
we had early on. We decided we wanted a really far back camera to let you see the player
character, to let you see a few NPCs at once, to let you see where you're exploring and
kind of searching for different objects of interest. And also to encompass all the dialogue
bubbles that come up. And so that was really something that I think
before we even landed on a lot of
where the story was going to go,
we knew we wanted the camera to be this far back
to feel like, essentially,
whenever you're looking at the game, it's a shot,
like a very defined shot.
Yet, at the same time, we didn't want it to be
locked in, you know, very scripted cameras.
And another thing that we sort of came upon
pretty early in the prototyping phase
was our talk bubbles and how those talk bubbles function.
We kept going back to like, if in other games,
you are wielding a sword or a gun or whatever
and these are these things that let you
interact with the world,
how can we make dialogue feel that way?
And those talk bubbles are positioned the way that they are
because we didn't want players to have to
look up or down or look at sort of subtitles
that are on the lower left upper corner or whatever.
We wanted them to feel as connected to Alex as possible
so that
while you're playing and deciding what to say,
your eye is not moving around the screen.
Your eye is looking at the character firmly the whole time,
and if you decide to look away,
that's only because you're exploring.
It's more of a choice for the player
rather than having to kind of dart around.
So we really wanted those talk bubbles to be,
again, like an extension of Alex.
Oh, so another kind of result of that then became,
now we have these talk bubbles, we've got these characters,
we've got this really zoomed out camera,
well how fast should she be moving around?
Because early on we had her just sprinting
and jumping on stuff and she's having these
tear-jerker conversations about her dead brother
and that felt super weird and kind of mixed up
and then we're like, well should there be a run button?
And then we're like, well what does a run button
have to do in this game?
we tried, I don't even know, we spent months on these things
that now feel to us, we kind of forget them,
but we spent months trying to sort this out.
And where we ended up landing was,
whenever Alex is talking, she slows to either kind of a jog
or almost like a pretty brisk walk,
and then when she's not talking, she speeds up
and she can navigate that way.
And we, hopefully that was something
that's invisible to players,
but it also let them cover ground
when that would be the interaction that they'd want to do,
but.
observe and talk and not be, you know,
having these crazy conversations
while running through a forest.
So a lot of these early decisions then
ended up starting to push back,
where at a certain point the mechanics
and visual choices that we made did push back on the story.
And I'll give you just a couple of examples,
but yeah, this was a little bit further
into the development of the game.
We started to go, there's some key moments in the game
that now that these mechanics are truly solidified,
let's tweak bits of the story for it.
So the first one, which has been, I don't know,
sort of controversial even in our own team,
is this very deliberately paced first act.
So the first act of the game, about 30, 45 minutes,
is you're walking and talking and hanging out with people.
There's no ghosts, there's no crazy.
over-the-top supernatural stuff happening.
It is essentially a microcosm of people's
typical senior year in high school.
So you've got things like,
you've got these heightened versions of
you're meeting somebody that you really want to impress,
but there's other people there who know.
some dirt about you, or you know that your friend
has this massive crush, so are you gonna choose
to help him or just like totally expose him
and make him embarrassed?
And so, you know, for us, the reason why we made
this decision was that we wanted people to get
really familiar with Alex as a character and the movement.
the core relationships with these friends
before the ghost shit hits the fan
because then when said shit hits the fan,
it just feels way crazier and more over the top
because you're really familiar with the character
and sort of the systems at play in the game.
And then this one, I'll try to, it's not too spoilery,
actually it won't be spoilery, I'll speak in code.
The conclusion of the game became the sum
of all of our communication mechanics.
So there was a point where like after alpha,
actually after beta, I don't know, it was bad.
We were late in the game, and we were trying to sort out
the conclusion, and we had these elaborate puzzles,
and we were like, again, kind of ham-fisting new mechanics
in at the end, and we went, this just doesn't fit.
It like, even intellectually, where people should be
at the end of this game should be more about Alex's
and their emotional journey, and they shouldn't be
learning how to like, fill water and things,
and move blocks around, and do all these things
that have nothing to do with it.
we ended up going, okay, with the mechanics
that they've already learned, let's let them
either jettison these ghostly creatures
back to the strange place from where they came
as a single sort of organism,
or you can kind of negotiate and treat them as individuals
and bring elements of them out by peaceful means.
But it's all done through the radio
and things that you learned earlier in the game,
not through introducing new mechanics.
So all these decisions came together to make a game
that our team is super proud of.
I mean, we're beyond grateful to have this community
of players now who have connected with Alex both inside
but also outside of the game.
Like it totally blows us away every time
we see any of this stuff.
And we, you know, I think we feel that we're pretty sure
that the community is connected with her.
Because they can feel that when we were making it,
we were always more worried about why Alex would do something,
why she would make a decision,
why she would put herself in harm's way,
as opposed to anything else.
Like that was the most important thing,
that was the guiding principle for the whole game.
And we feel like it's really sort of paid off
in making something pretty special.
This slide makes me laugh when I'm looking at it.
This is, you guys have probably seen this kind of
classic quote from Pixar founder and Disney CCO,
John Lasseter, where he talks about kind of the interplay
between art and technology, right?
And so for those guys, the art.
challenges the technology and then the technology
inspires the art and for us we've kind of like
morphed and mutated that kind of basic idea
where for us we want to continue to approach game making
through this lens of story inspiring our mechanics
but then we will build mechanics that empower players
to tell their own stories.
So I hope this talk has given you some interesting ideas
to explore as well and thank you.
Do we have Q&A time? I don't know how long I've been up here. Sweet. How do we do that?
Can't see. Just hurdle questions. There we go. How's it going?
My name is Odette. I'm also a point and click adventure game designer, developer, indie.
I'm very interested in learning about the prototyping, playtesting, early stages,
because this game, when I played it, it felt like the voice acting and all that
was a very strong part and I'm curious how did you do that in early stages of the development?
So it was pretty funny, we would record scratch audio
in our bathroom at the office, and we would come up
with these really just ridiculous small scenarios,
none of which made it into the game,
and Adam would write these scripts that would be like.
okay, here is a challenge to overcome,
and here's a lot of branching options,
and let's test out basically all those systems
that I was just talking through.
And so, we did that for a while.
Like, we did not do any casting or any of the real,
you know, solid, solidified writing
until we had gone through that prototyping phase.
But early on, Brian, who's also here,
who was our lead engineer, was working on a tool
that was intended to be a very...
visual, simple design tool that ideally any designer
or writer who's not hyper-technical can get into
and use it's a visual kind of node-based thing
so that you could even play something out
without dropping it into a full scene.
We, to be perfectly honest, it all came in way too hot.
Like we were halfway through the game
and some of the core tools were still getting built.
The story was changing for a long time.
So I'd like to say that we, in the first three months,
had this like,
Yes, here it is moment, but we were at alpha still like crapping our pants
So it was but yeah, I mean for us. We were kind of doing two or three things at once
There was a lot of art tests happening
That we're not taking into account a lot of the dialogue
And then there were a lot of like script tests happening based on the tool set that Bryant was building and then we would just
Let people play it that was pretty much it. Thank you sure
All right
Since most games kind of take control away from the player,
lock the camera, etc. to force the player to view the story,
did you guys have issues with playtesters walking away from conversations
and missing out on parts of the story or the delivery of certain voice lines
that kind of took away from their experience?
all the time.
Like, yeah, the earliest versions of the game,
we wanted to let you go anywhere at any time
and be able to backtrack, go wherever you want,
and have a lot of conversations be location agnostic.
And we ended up having to kind of hone that in.
I think for our next stuff, we'd still like to find ways
to improve more of that and let important conversations
sort of happen anywhere.
But yeah, the biggest challenge is we're like,
how long should a scene be?
How long should a chunk of dialogue be?
Because if a character is moving,
if a player is moving too quickly
from one waypoint to another,
they're going to trigger the next conversation too early.
Or are they going to run along
and then there's just a long, dead stretch of space?
or are they going to go backwards
and not be able to talk about anything?
And so, all credit goes to Adam
and his maniacal writing process
for finding ways to fill in
and kind of shave off the edges of that,
but there was never like a magic bullet for it.
It was just a lot of play testing
and finding where people went and how to guide them
and how long scenes should be.
Okay, thank you.
Sure.
So awesome game. The timing I think is really crucial to the dialogue mechanics in Oxenfree.
Like how long the options stay on screen or how long the conversation pauses while the system is waiting to see if the character is going to reply.
Was there any science that went into choosing those numbers or do you guys just sort of feel it out and watch playtest?
That was another just duct tape and a prayer thing.
Early on we did want a science and a consistent thing for it
and it's something that response wise to the game,
some people really love exactly how it was timed
and other people are kind of pissed off about it,
but ultimately.
most of those lines and how the interrupts work,
sometimes you cut somebody off right in the middle of a line,
sometimes they say their whole line
was all just hand tweaked basically,
because it's like maybe a line
has some really crucial information
that an NPC might be saying something that you need to hear,
so we're going to let that whole line play.
But if it's more just a feel thing,
as often as possible,
we wanted you to just cut people off, no matter what.
So that would be the perfect world version,
but half the lines are not that way
because they're just for subjective reasons.
Quick follow-up question. Did you ever measure that like cutting off other characters and did that ever feed back into the relationships between the characters?
Not the cutting off. No, but thank you. We're gonna take that idea
Please do
Thank you
Did you systemically deal with interrupting?
Conversations or were they custom every time when Alex chose to speak or not?
Sorry, could you say that again?
So, other characters are speaking, Alex responds in the middle, cuts people off.
Did you have to systemically deal with then resuming or how to deal with all of that?
A lot, yes. So again, crazy writer Adam down there.
There's, we, as often as possible, we'd like the NPCs or Alex to be able to pick up the conversation.
So if you cut somebody off in the middle of any line, we don't want it to just like awkwardly...
jump back into the conversation.
So there's a lot of lines in the game,
hundreds of lines where they'll be like,
okay, back to what we were talking about,
or things like that.
So yes, there is definitely a system
for all of that in place.
Cool, thank you.
Thanks.
Hi, my name is Molly. I'm an artist, so I have a lot of like art questions for you, but
I'll keep it to just a mechanics question. The radio idea is really interesting to me,
and that mechanic is like fascinating. How did you guys come up with that? Like what inspired it?
So early on, it actually became like an offshoot
of another idea.
Early on we wanted to have a tape recorder.
And that tape recorder, we were going to let you
record a bunch of stuff in the world
and run around with that.
And then, and Brian still wants it,
and he's bummed out that it's not in the game.
And it got totally crazy, and we went,
no, what are the elements that we really like about it?
Back to that communication thing, we thought,
what is something that's familiar, and radio is familiar,
and what is something that's creepy?
So we thought about radios and Silent Hill
were a really big piece of that,
that feeling of the static and that feeling of like,
I'm getting a very guttural piece of feedback from the game,
but it's also not direct.
You don't know what it means all the time.
And so we thought it could be this really
kind of cool coded thing.
So for us, early on, the radio,
we kind of looked at it as
aesthetically like the Silent Hill radio,
and then mechanically we wanted it to be like the ocarina,
an ocarina of time, where you can have sequences
of things that you can plug in, like a puzzle,
or tunes, or things like that.
And so it kind of became both of those, essentially.
We wanted it to be, the other big piece was that
we wanted players to have some form of analog expression
while they're playing, and instead of just choosing
dialogue choices, so being able to bust that radio out
whenever you want.
and pick up little secrets and listen to other stations.
Just felt pretty cool.
So it was kind of all those things,
but it took a long time to get to it.
That's awesome.
Thank you.
I was just told, I'm so sorry sir,
I was just told that was the last question.
But I'll talk to you out there.
Okay, thank you guys so much.