So welcome to how to talk about games today.
Hopefully you're in the right place.
And we're going to talk a little bit about how
to talk about games.
All right.
Oh yeah, I'm supposed to tell you to silence your cell phones.
I'm supposed to tell you to please fill out
the evaluation thingy.
You can fill it out now.
It's going to be a great talk, so there you go.
So on and so forth.
And with that, oh, and at the end,
if you like or are interested in some of the things
that we present and you want more information,
we have little cards up here with a URL
on the back of them of stuff that we've put together
so that folks, they look like this,
so that you can go get more stuff if you want it.
All right, so why does this even matter to you?
So a lot of the things that are happening right now
around games and the way that we talk about games
in the public sphere and the way that folks are concerned
or interested in their effects and the way
that they're consumed in society.
That can result in a number of different things.
So one of the things that can happen there
is that the legislative and political bodies take
a look at something and they decide
that they're going to make new rules around to fix
what they perceive to be as a problem in that space.
It also forms part of the cultural basis of why and how the general public thinks about games.
So when you go home and you talk to your mom about video games, what do they think about video games?
What do their friends think about video games?
How do we as a society think about games in general?
And what does that mean?
And when certain issues hit the mass media, when they hit the newspaper, when they hit
the talk shows, when they hit the news cycles, etc., that can start to sway public opinion
this way, that way, what have you.
And then last but not least, all of that discussion influences, you know, we're raising kids,
they're getting mixed messages from the media in and of themselves, so how do they think
about games and how does that sort of inform the next generation around what they think
about games?
So we were all talking about this sort of behind the scenes with each other, because
we're usually friends.
Usually.
Yeah, I know, right?
And we were having a discussion about it.
We said, hey, maybe we should throw together a panel on this
because it's fairly timely right now.
So we did.
These are my esteemed colleagues and panelists.
They all have a great number of fancy titles
next to their names.
They will probably introduce themselves
as they get up and talk so that they'll
cover what their fancy titles actually mean.
But in the background of all of those fancy titles,
There's a lot of organizational leadership in the folks that are sitting up here right now.
We've got a Canada research chair that used to be president of DIGRA.
We've got leadership in Global Game Jam.
We've got leadership in Higher Education Video Game Alliance.
So on and so forth.
And so just a wealth of experience in different ways
that these issues have impacted some of the organizations
in and around games with that.
So what am I actually talking about when I say these issues,
stuff like that?
And I'm sure that you can all name them.
But just to sort of put a point on it,
so the games and violence debate.
The games and addiction debate, right?
Games are addictive now, and we're gonna classify that
in the health organization.
Games and health more generally, right?
Games and their effect on society, so on and so forth.
One of my personal favorites was the one where
we don't, you know, the problem with unemployment
is because we make video games,
and so young men don't want jobs anymore.
I found it particularly interesting.
All right.
So why are we here? So this session is about understanding the background of some of these recent discussions and then a call to action for developers to start to have a voice in and around some of these debates directly as somebody that knows something about making video games rather than not being a part of that engagement.
So with that...
Okay. Good afternoon. My name is Lindsay Grace and I'm going to be talking about moral panic
and misunderstanding. So last year I wrote a couple of articles for CNN and some other
venues, Associated Press, and also sat on a panel around discussing the new World Health
Organization's classification of games addiction and this debate around games and violence
and whether or not shooters are somehow inspired by games.
So what I'm here to do is to actually help you understand that we've actually been here before.
So the first place we'll start is comic books.
So in the last century, comic books were considered the source of much debate.
My favorite quote of the era is from Frederick Wortham, who wrote the book Seduction of the Innocent.
And Frederick explicitly claimed to Senate that he thinks Hitler was a beginner compared
to the comic book industry.
And this is in the context of 1940s U.S.
So basically, it was widely debated as to whether or not comic books were the source
of juvenile delinquency.
Book burnings commenced, and this is one of them, and generally comic books were considered
dangerous, the same comic books that have inspired lots of contemporary media.
At some point, what you'll see in the history is that all leisure seems subject to moral
panic.
So we'll go back to the Puritans to start.
This is a great little article from Sports Illustrated
and Robert Doyle basically describes
and highlights the Puritans supporting
of the burning of the Book of Sports.
If you're unfamiliar with the Book of Sports,
it was basically a 1600s era guide
to Sunday sport and recreation for after church.
It was publicly burned in England in 1643
because it was dangerous and evil.
Later, if you go through the histories of the Industrial Revolution, for example, you
could read Cunningham's Leisure in the Industrial Revolution, you'll learn about the fact that
class, religion, and ideology, ideological tensions, existed around things as trivial
as tourism.
So for example, there are discussions about how travel, music, and racing, the new leisures
available to a middle class, were actually part of an anti-social culture.
And then there's Dungeons and Dragons.
So if you don't know about the Dungeons and Dragons story,
I've got to tell you.
So the great, I like the way they described it,
there was the great 1980s Dungeons and Dragons panics.
There's a great little BBC magazine article
you can read about it.
And explicitly, D&D, Dungeons and Dragons,
was accused of inspiring suicides, occult activity,
being aligned with rape, prostitution, sadism,
sex perversion, all kinds of things.
In fact, it was actually linked to a murder by a man, the man who committed the murder was Darren Molitor in 1985.
And Darren wrote a letter that helped feed this moral panic.
In the letter, and I've just highlighted a few things here, he explicitly talks about how Dungeons and Dragons inspired him to be violent,
and he described it as possessive, addictive, and evil.
So D&D was once addictive and inspired violence.
You'll start to see a trend here.
So the founding of an organization called
Bothered About Dungeons and Dragons,
inspired by MAD, Mothers Against Drunk Driving,
was founded by a woman named Pat Pulling.
And in 83, BAD went out and set forth
to help people get away from the addictive properties of D&D.
One of the things that this person did,
Pat Pulling actually created a book called The Devil's Web,
where she talks about the intersection
of Satan and entertainment.
And she became the director
of the National Coalition on TV Violence.
The National Coalition on TV Violence
actually earned the support of the US Surgeon General,
at the time it was C. Everett Koop,
who did believe that TV was part of the problem for violence
which brings us to television.
So if you think about television,
In the history of analyzing TV and its effects on aggression,
we actually have more than 40 years of data and analysis.
One of the claims that was proven in a study,
like this study, is actually that third graders become
more violent from watching TV even 10 years later.
This is a study published in 72.
And we also, that there is a clear, rather,
positive correlation between TV violence
and aggressive behavior.
This is from another study published in 94.
So of course, you must be asking,
science proves that television fosters aggression.
Except, after 40 years, some people are still saying no.
So in this example, which is a study from 2008,
it does not, their understanding of the relationship
indicates that they do not correlate properly.
So, there are lots of publications
and lots of peer-reviewed, high-quality research
that actually says there's no link between violent and TV.
Then there's the next one, television addiction.
So one of the best, I think,
quotes from this Scientific American publication
that the famous Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi and Kubi
actually wrote together,
is that most of the criteria for substance abuse
or substance dependence can apply to people
who watch a lot of TV.
What do you think about how pervasive television is
in many modern cultures?
And I actually did some quick research.
So there's an OECD publication that
talks about how people use their leisure time.
And at this point, across the 19 countries that were surveyed,
it's about 39% of our leisure.
So when you're not working, you're almost a 50% chance
that you're watching TV.
And we have some results, some research
that claims that.
If you look at meta-analysis, or you look at the different previous studies,
you'll find that there's actually a smaller effect of violent video games
than television violence,
which I think is an interesting observation,
given how much society is not worried about TV.
So, that brings us to games.
If we talk about games...
I think one approach, theme of the presentations
that we're all giving, one way to talk about games
is actually to remind people of our worldwide political past
with leisure.
So I gave you these references, right?
Point them to the moral panics that have occurred before
when people were worried that if we allowed people
to go and be tourists, they would lose their connection
to religion, or that we were burning books
because we thought that they were dangerous,
or that we really did believe in Dungeons and Dragons
being a very dangerous and addicting experience.
And then also point them to the people who misled us
to the detriment of the people they were looking to help.
We wanted happy, healthy children,
and some people had some approaches that seemed questionable.
So, remind people and really highlight this idea
that there is a dangerous game of pitting leisure
against morality, and that leisure itself is political.
Attacking leisure is an opportunity to chip at culture.
and enforce your own culture.
It's a little bit of a culture war.
So, as scientists, politicians, and journalists
claim the detriments of comic books,
that they would drive innocent children
into the clutches of juvenile delinquency,
others actually highlighted the fact
that comic books attracted a high quotient
of creative people who thought of,
basically got access to a more,
but a new publishing venue.
So it really offered them opportunities
that other modes of publishing didn't.
So attacking games kind of mirrors the past attacks on leisure that we've seen historically.
And in an era of declining leisure,
where in the US workism is becoming the new religion,
and work may even be killing us,
maybe we should not attack leisure.
We should ask about the root of these discords, of this discord.
So like TV, no matter what, it's going to be a long time.
If we can ever make these links, it's
going to take us a long time to do it.
But I remind you, as people at GDC,
that games don't need to be burned to be erased.
Erasing our cultural contribution is much easier.
And if you'd like, we're going to give you
a bunch of links to some things that
help you understand how all this works together.
Thanks.
That's all I have.
Yep, there we go.
Thanks, I drew the short straw
and got to talk about games and violence.
I'm Mia Consolvo, I'm the Canada Research Chair
in Game Studies and Design.
Yeah, there's, I'm just basically doing a deep dive
into what Lindsay was alluding to in terms of the research,
mostly the social science research on games
and their links to violence and aggression,
that kind of thing.
And I would point out also that this is one of the most
like heavily scrutinized areas of research
that you will come across.
You know, if I did a study in this particular field,
I would be scared to death to publish it
because you're just immediately jumped on
and everything is just.
As it should be, it should be carefully reviewed,
but there is a ton of people looking at this research
and seeing if it is up to scratch.
It is not just research about games and violence, though,
that's been problematic or called into account.
If you pay attention to the news,
you may notice social science research in general
has been having a rough time.
You may hear the word replication crisis being used.
Basically what happened is,
especially a lot of research in psychology,
you remember, like at university,
and like those sophomores,
they get called to do, you know,
for extra credit, you do the research.
And some of those early studies
that had like very influential findings,
people are finally getting around
to replicating some of them,
and some of them are not holding up to scrutiny.
One of the biggest examples is the marshmallow test.
So if you remember, this is the one where you put a kid in a room with a plate of marshmallows and you're like
I don't know exactly how you do it,
but see how long they can wait,
and if they can avoid eating the marshmallow,
and it's all about grit, right?
And if you can avoid eating the marshmallow,
then 10 years down the line,
you're gonna get into Stanford, right?
And your life is gonna be cake and wonderful.
And what the replication found was that,
well, no, actually, it's more about your background
and your socioeconomic class
that leads you to be able to resist the marshmallow
rather than some inner grit.
So, yeah.
A lot of social science research you really just need to take with a grain of salt and
see is it standing up?
And also, as Lindsay was saying, this is culture.
People are changing and our culture is changing and so we can't just say if we found something
once in the past it's necessarily going to hold up.
To games and violence, however, if you
are looking for an actual book to read on this topic
and you're not allergic to academic prose,
I would highly recommend Barry Gunter's 2016
Does Playing Video Games Make Players More Violent?
I have the title in the handout on the website.
It's 280 pages.
I read all of them.
The panelists know because I've told them this repeatedly.
I think reading the book at times made me violent
more than a video game has probably made anyone violent.
But it's a very thorough accounting
of hundreds of the studies over the past
looking at games and violence.
So this is a big block of text, but what he's basically saying here is just that video game
playing doesn't occur in a social vacuum, right? Like, it's a part of our culture and our daily
life. We have, you know, a socioeconomic background, we live in certain places,
we have different educations, we have different genders. All of these things play a role.
And as he says, going one step further to differentiate
between the effects of violent video games
as distinct from those of violent movies,
you know, and watching in a movie theater
or program scene on TV is even more challenging.
It's so incredibly hard with people to like,
pull out one particular thread of what they do,
you know, to say how does this, you know,
affect the whole rest of their life?
How can we hold every other element
of people's lives constant, you know, to see?
You know, so that's like a really key thing to think about.
And again, placing this in context, Lindsay did this,
so I'll just go through it quickly,
but there have been studies, you know,
and it does relate to moral panics,
but people worried about movies,
people worried about television,
the cultivation model in the 80s basically said
if you watch a lot of violent TV,
maybe you wouldn't become aggressive,
but you would think the world is a mean and scary place,
much more than it actually was.
And a lot of the early research, even on violent games,
tended to link violent media together
in terms of when you studied populations.
And so you can't even pick out, like, how this, you know,
did games do something?
Because it was just, this is like people
who watch violent TV and movies and that kind of thing.
When you get to the research on games themselves,
there are three types of studies that you see.
So there are surveys where you're having children or adults
fill out detailed questionnaires about their media use,
their backgrounds, their personality type,
that kind of thing.
You have naturalistic observation where perhaps
you go to playgrounds and watch people play
and then try and infer that and maybe talk with them later
about their media diet.
to see if there are any correlations.
And then you have experiments where you set people up
in a lab and you have them play a game
and then take a survey or interact in some way.
So there are problems associated with
all of these types of methods.
So for surveys, you can't actually prove causality, right?
The most that you can do is actually find a correlation.
You know, people who.
play a lot of Grand Theft Auto,
are also maybe arguing a lot with their teachers,
but you don't know.
Maybe they argue a lot with their teachers
and then they go play Grand Theft Auto, right?
Like there's no one way that you can see
that the evidence is pointing
that one necessarily leads to the other.
If you're observing people in a setting,
you have little control over the actual setting.
It's not a population sample.
This is just a very convenient sample,
and you can't control the variables.
And with experiments, it's an artificial setting,
so you're having people come into a lab
and play a video game,
and I mean, it's just completely unnatural.
But also in terms of effect time,
because maybe they're having them fill out a survey
or react to something,
so you might be able to say,
oh, they got a little angry 15 minutes after my test,
but you don't know necessarily did that,
maybe then they got over it a day, a week, a month later.
So it's really hard with experiments
to show anything beyond.
immediate effect.
Other
critiques that people have made of some of the research on violence in games.
Studies can examine these, these seem kind of similar,
but they're actually very different things that people are looking at. Violent thoughts, violent feelings, and violent behaviors, right?
They're not all the same thing. If you have a thought about what
you might do to somebody who cuts you off in traffic,
that doesn't mean that you necessarily go
and do the thing, right?
The thought and the behavior,
even though you'd really like to, are not equivalent.
The feeling, you may have rage directed
at the person who cut you off in traffic,
that does not necessarily mean you're gonna do the thing.
So you have to look at what the studies
are actually studying.
Studies use different measures and definitions
of what aggression actually is.
Some have tried to standardize over time
and they have standardized personality tests
or definitions like they carry over
from one study to another,
but especially a lot of the early research
varied wildly in terms of what they said about them.
And there are ethical concerns about using and testing
actual aggression, right?
You can't just say, I'm gonna have kids play this game
and then I'm gonna have another kid go up
and punch the kid to see if he punches him back, right?
Like, ethics review boards really don't like you
to do that kind of thing.
And so you have to develop substitutes for what an aggressive act might be.
So a really common one is the noise blast.
You're playing with somebody else and you want to punish them and it's like, how loud
a blast of noise do you give them?
And that's like a substitute.
Is a loud noise blast really the same thing as punching someone?
Another substitute is hot sauce.
You know, you want to punish somebody.
How much hot sauce are you putting on, like, food that they're being given?
Culturally, this is really weird to me.
You know, I'd be like, more hot sauce, please.
Like, you just don't like me. You didn't put much on there.
If you go through again all of this literature,
there are two major theories or approaches
in terms of trying to figure out these links.
There's the general aggression model, the GAM,
which Craig Anderson is one of the leading researchers on.
which is mostly focusing on thoughts,
is installing scripts for behavior
that you play these games, and you're learning reactions,
like, and that's gonna influence then what you actually do.
And then in CounterPoint, the catalyst model,
which is Chris Ferguson, Chris Ferguson has been like
one of the most active opponents of the GAM
and their research and calling out their methods.
And he says that, you know, their findings are just suspect.
And he looks at things like personality
and environmental factors.
Everyone does agree it's not a simple issue.
Gosh, thanks, it's complicated.
But they'll say things like,
it depends on a player's neighborhood,
their family history, their school performance,
their friends, personality, social history,
immediate diet, gender, mental health,
and so on and so on and so on.
And so what they all do at least agree on
is that what you're looking for are risk factors associated.
But again, figuring out, and they argue about
what those risk factors might be
and the best ways to do them.
You'll also hear people talk about the meta-analyses,
you know, the big studies that take all the studies
and say, well, maybe if we cram them all together,
we'll see if we learn something as a result.
The problem here is that if you take crappy studies
and put them together, you just get a really big,
really crappy study.
This is my whole talk, Mia, is meta-studies.
You're just killing me here, you're killing me.
So, yeah, another problem.
Thank you, Roger.
Another problem with these meta-analysis is a lot of them focus on research that has been published.
There is a publication bias many times. If you do a study and you find like no significant results,
a lot of journals don't want to publish it because it doesn't seem very exciting,
even though in like violence research no significant results might be important.
And so you're leaving out those studies and their lack of results.
Scientists have different ways of interpreting the results,
what one might consider a moderate effect,
one might consider a minor effect.
And so again, there's just no clear-cut consensus.
Some are very convinced of their truth,
but there is no complete consensus overall.
I'm kind of over time, so just getting really nitpicky.
Not all games are violent.
People don't always play them just for the violent parts.
The research tends to conflate research
on little kids, young kids, 17-year-olds, and adults
without separating them out
and how they might be different.
Some of the studies don't really mention
our women and girls involved.
A few do, but not all of them,
so we don't really know conclusively about gender.
And just to close up, another way to approach this
is to ask, what do people do with games?
How are they using them in their lives?
What are they taking away from them?
What are they bringing to them?
Rather than asking, what do games do to people?
Thanks.
Perfect.
Thank you, Doc.
Appreciate it.
I'm Roger. It's nice to see everyone here.
I collect titles.
I work at Queensland University of Technology,
Entertainment Arts and Engineering at Utah,
and all sorts of other fun things.
I like that workaholism.
I'm a lucky guy. I get to work with talented people and talented students to make games.
Sometimes they're for entertainment and sometimes they are for health.
And so we have a lab that we work in where we're making games in a hospital
to sort of help people with all sorts of different things,
ranging from helping disabled people ski again and or sail again.
to doing all sorts of things with medication compliance and things like that.
So I sort of have a vested interest in this notion, just to put all my biases out there,
about games as an industry and prepping people to work in a games industry,
and then also games as medicine, and that games are good for you.
In fact, I have done a lot of talks when I first started doing work in medicine
on are games good for you and how can games help people out.
People love talking about the negative aspects of games.
I think that came through in the previous talks,
and there's been lots of it.
I think if you just, if you Google games are bad for you,
lots of fun stuff pops up, right?
So there's like no lack of it.
But oddly enough, lots of good stuff pops up as well.
And I think this is one of the shifts
that we're starting to see,
that you would be surprised who is writing
about the positive impacts of games, right?
and the kinds of things that they're asking about.
So like, for example, on the vegan article,
they're talking about games are good for you,
lots of reasons why games are good for you.
A call for responsible play,
so this emphasis on personal responsibility,
that's an important shift.
And we're gonna talk about that a little bit,
how we stop looking at the stimuli or the thing itself,
and we start looking at behavior
and responsible behavior, right?
I mean, of course, the same concerns
that everyone always has,
but it's an interesting shift to see what happens.
It's already been addressed that there is negative,
there is great academic work on games
on sort of both sides of this debate,
if you believe there are two sides.
Really, there's just a lot of thought on there.
It's kind of hard to boil it down into two camps.
And on addiction, though, we're seeing a shift
in the way people talk about addiction.
So in the beginning, people liked to talk about media
in the same ways that they would talk
about addictive substances.
So you would talk about games the same way
you might talk about a chemical substance or a drug, right?
And certainly they could point to lots of negative things
that happen around games.
And I think it's important for us, when we talk about games,
especially when we talk about games in the press,
not to sort of sweep these things under the rugs.
Whether it's through academic study or anecdotes,
people have stories about negative things
around game play, right?
Just as we laugh when we talk about negative things around driving, we don't have to hide that.
We don't have to say driving is good all the time.
That every time you get behind the wheel of a car, it's a delightful experience, right?
Mia wants to kill people apparently when she gets behind the wheel of a car,
so I'm going to add that bullet point to this slide, right?
And I think that when we talk about negative aspects of leisure or negative aspects of games, in particular, is leisure,
We're not alone in this.
So one of the things that we don't hear much about
is exercise addiction, right?
And exercise addiction isn't a new thing.
This is something that's been studied since the 70s.
There are places where you can be treated
for exercise addiction.
There are lots of great articles on exercise addiction.
Being an exercise addict is a very serious condition.
It can affect your body in tremendous ways.
It reduces your longevity.
It can compromise your immune system.
There are all sorts of terrible things that happen.
But when we talk about exercise, this isn't what comes up, right?
We don't talk about exercise addiction when we have general conversations about exercise.
And the reason for that is because exercise is good for you.
This is known, right?
Even though it is addictive, even though people get hurt by it.
Even though some of the cultures around where we do exercise are very complicated and under
debate right now, the idea that when we talk about exercise, if I were to say, hey, let's
talk about exercise, none of you are going to say, oh, that's terrible.
Exercise is the worst.
It's addictive, and you might be exposed to toxic.
cultures, and oh my god, exercise, don't get me started, right?
No, because you walk with the assumption that exercise is good for you.
And so we can actually have conversations about those things and not worry that we're
going to get rid of exercise and start having gym membership burning parties.
I mean, I don't even know what that would look like, right?
So what if instead of always apologizing for games, we started with something else?
What if we started with games are good for you?
What if that was the assumption?
And so to get to this notion that games are good for you,
we might have to start talking about the things about games
that are good for you,
not just the right to be entertained,
that is a valuable thing,
or to engage and lead your time.
But are there things about games that are good for you?
There are lots of great individual studies
on this kind of stuff, both from social scientific
and medical research.
This, for example, is a single study on the game Bejeweled
that shows that it has the impact that playing Bejeweled
for 30 minutes a day three times a week
has the same impact on state and trait anxiety.
State anxiety is what we all experience
when you get stressed out when something bad happens.
Or trait anxiety, you just deal with generalized anxiety.
It has the same impact as low dose benzos.
So low dose Valium or low dose Xanax, right?
And that it's a wonderful study
because they do all this biometric stuff.
It's a good study.
And they sort of show that unlike a lot of things
that are prescribed,
Like people don't take their medications
when they're prescribed to them.
When they were prescribed to video games,
they took them more than the recommended dosage.
And so they were prescribed a half hour of play.
Average amount of play was just over 40 minutes.
So get your bejeweled on.
But rather than looking at a bunch of individual studies,
Mia already alluded to that meta studies and meta reviews
are wonderful and extraordinarily useful.
And there's just never anything to critique about them.
We looked at each other's work, I swear.
But in reality, though, this is actually a great place to start when you want to start
looking for research, our meta-reviews.
So a good meta-review, like this is a report that was sponsored by a center in Australia,
and they looked at 200 different articles.
on well-being and children and games and sort of extract themes from it, right? And so it's a good
place to sort of start the conversation. Clearly, these things are never definitive, right? But they
looked at a lot of research, like we said, over 200 peer-reviewed published articles,
again, with caveats for all the things that Mia mentioned.
And they sort of talked about positive emotional impacts
of games, the healthy relationships that come
from games, and social capital.
Social capital is sort of the things
we use in life to exchange with one another
that aren't monetary related but are cool.
So you could say, hey, look at.
I have a really cool mount or I'm really high level and wow.
And other people might say, oh, that's really great.
So that's social capital that you can exchange, right?
And then the impact on self-esteem,
the positive impact on self-esteem.
The citation for this will also be on the website that's
on that handout if you need it.
But when we talked about the positive emotional impact or when that article talks about it,
they sort of looked at mental well-being with video games, that it's a good way to relax,
it's a good way to not feel stressed out.
These are things that you might already believe, but there's research that talks about this,
that people who play games tend not to have depressed mood as much.
Oddly enough, a lot of the research has a horseshoe-shaped pattern, meaning that those
who don't play games and those who play excessive amounts of games have depressive mood problems.
But those that play moderate games have less of this than people who don't play games.
Right?
And we actually see this with obesity as well.
that there's arguments about obesity in games and that those who don't play games and those
who play excessive games are more likely to suffer from childhood obesity than those who
play moderate amounts of games as well.
So that pattern seems to emerge a lot.
That in terms of healthy relationships, that people who play games tend to have less risky
friendship networks, high levels of family closeness, and that people in games like WoW
are sometimes they find this a safe space to discuss things that might be difficult
for them to discuss.
interpersonally, right?
And so the use of avatars, the use of the game
means that they can sort of talk about things in their life
that they might be uncomfortable talking about IRL.
This is actually true in other studies as well.
So with adults, with adults who have returned from war
and are suffering from PTSD, there's been great work
that some people are more comfortable talking
to a virtual counselor than a real counselor,
that they can be more honest and more forthcoming
with an avatar than they can another person in the room.
In terms of self-esteem, we sort of see that a lot of players feel they can express themselves
more.
They feel empowered and confident to express their sexuality, their appearance.
They're not afraid of these things.
And that virtual worlds can sort of give people a break from this stuff.
This is not the only meta review on this.
There's lots of them.
This one is pretty interesting, though,
because it was published by the APA, the American
Psychological Association, in their premier journal,
American Psychologist.
The American Psychological Association
has a complex relationship with games.
They've come out on the other side of this games addiction
debate in the past.
And so you might have seen news articles that say things like, American Psychological Association
has concerns about games addiction.
But at the same time, they are publishing work on the healthy benefits of playing games
in their major journal, which is pretty interesting.
So this is another article that sort of analyzes
dozens of other articles.
And instead of saying, what are the social aspects of it,
it says that there are cognitive benefits to games,
that the types of things that we learn,
in fact, they do a really interesting analysis
of articles about first-person shooters
that show that playing first-person shooters
teaches you spatial reasoning and other skills
at the same level as taking high-level college courses
in them.
that they're good for motivation,
that they're good for emotional health,
and that they're very social.
So it's a great review of these kinds of things.
But the point of it isn't these articles
that I'm talking about, it's that we
don't have to dismiss that maybe some people who play games
have bad experiences or that bad things happen to them
around games.
We would be lying if that were the case, right?
No one hates love, but clearly people have been hurt in love.
There wouldn't be a pop music industry
if people didn't get hurt in love.
But that talking about the positive aspects of games
might get us to a place where we can say games are good for you
and still have honest conversations about everything
else.
And that just because some people have a bad experience,
it doesn't mean that's a defining characteristic
of the thing itself.
Um, that's all I have for you. You feel free to email me any questions you might have. Thank you.
Yeah, all right, so now I got sucked this panel with the the joy of going right after Roger
It's always interesting so my name is Andy. I also collect titles
I'm a professor of human interface technology at Canterbury, which is a Christ Church
I'm also a professor of art and design at RIT
I'm a game scholar and resident at American right now.
And probably most relevant to this particular talk,
I'm president of the Higher Education Video Game Alliance.
And I became president of the Higher Education Video Game
Alliance about mid-2017, around Thanksgiving time.
It was really nice.
My very good friend and colleague
was the prior president, Constance Steinkuhler.
and we were kind of discussing as a board
like who was gonna take it on next
and she talked me into it,
as she has a way of doing.
And she said, well, I just, I wanna tell you, right,
like, you know, I think you're gonna have
a pretty smooth sailing here with your tenure with HFGA,
like it's not gonna be that big of a deal
because when I, she used to be assigned
to the Office of Science and Technology Policy
at the White House, and she said,
when we were there, right, Sandy Hook happened.
and we got called to a meeting in Joe Biden's office
to talk about video games.
So if that doesn't happen to you,
like, you know, like you're gonna have an easier time
of it than I did, right?
So it's gonna be okay.
And so that was fun.
And then it got to be about January
and we had another school shooting
and the president of the United States opened his mouth
about how that was the fault of video games.
So it took three months.
Great.
That was really super.
I particularly do enjoy the fact, though,
that his tweet was actually from 2012
that everyone referenced in response to that debate.
It was pretty great.
So pretty much then, everything old is new again again.
That's what happened in Washington
in the wake of the shooting in Florida.
And so what was interesting and a little bit different though was I got a bunch of folks in the industry saying
It'll blow over
This always happens
like we shouldn't worry about issuing statements and you know coming out on on these sides of these issues and and this that and the
Other and and then eventually right like Trump said no
we're gonna have a meeting in the White House and we're gonna make the game executives show up and answer for this and that that uh that
and then they had that meeting and basically everybody yelled at each other
and nobody was you know it wasn't like I mean the optics of having a meeting at
the White House sort of means you're gonna yell at each other because that
makes for a better news story. But that's
you know kinda what happened right except that
in the background of all of that
There's some really interesting things that happened.
So one was that issue got referred
to the Commission for School Safety
that had to issue a report back to the president
over the course of the next year, the School Safety
Commission Report.
I'm willing to bet that most of you have not read it.
It's pretty dry.
Got to be honest.
One of the things that's interesting about that,
though, is that it specifically calls out the Motion Picture
Association of America and their rating systems as inadequate.
but it does not call out video games.
And one of the reasons for that is that there was a bunch
of sustained advocacy behind the fact
because organizations like mine, like the ESA,
like the IGDA were making those articles
that said the research is not conclusive, right,
that violent video games causes school shootings, right?
And so that was a very necessary point of advocacy
to continue to protect this medium that we love.
And I just talked over my next slide.
So how does this affect you?
Well, it affects you because if they decided that it did,
we could all be legislated out of making
certain kinds of content pretty darn quickly.
We have a really great precedent with the Supreme Court case.
from a few years ago about games being first-person projected speech and all of that. I don't
know if you've noticed this, but the balance of the court has shifted a little bit since
that was tried. I'm not willing to go down the road and say it'll always be upheld. You
never know. And then, okay, so that was like my first three months on the job.
And then we had this.
Winning.
So then the World Health Organization
comes out and says we're going to have a classification
around addiction in games.
And I watched a bunch of my academic colleagues
who just did the very same thing that we kind of did
with games and violence.
It said the research is not clear,
that the studies are this and this.
You know, it's going to take a long time to figure this stuff out and this kind of research
is very difficult and it's not definitive and so on and so forth, right?
And I was sitting here on mailing list watching colleagues that said that those very things
about violence turn around and say, yeah, but man, kids can't stop playing Fortnite.
Like, we got to do something about this, like right now.
And you're like, but, but the.
You know, if you're really into that particular issue, right,
there's a, I would tell you there's a really great panel
discussion at Games for Change in 2018.
And the woman in that's very dark on there.
is Kelly Dunlop and you should check her out because her work in this space is probably some of the the most
down-to-earth and reasonable
Around what addiction you know addiction is a really loaded word, right?
There's a medical classification for it
But the way we use it popularly has very little to do with that
And so that's an issue. Behind the scenes, if you're in and out of D.C. the way I am, the way you have been,
one of the things you will notice is the standard age of the American lawmaker.
And there are some big generational divides
regarding attitudes about games.
So we all love these little stats, right,
that's like, everybody plays games, right?
There's, you know, like 97% of everyone ever plays games
and we've been playing games since the dawn of time
and all this kind of stuff.
But we play very different kinds of games
based on our age a lot, right?
We classify a lot of things in American politics
as this left-right debate, right?
But the real debate...
is old young, right?
And so this was a really interesting article
that just came out not too terribly long ago
about the eligible voters and their age.
And what you see is that there are some really,
really big generations that are, you know,
in like early retirement age right now.
And that's not going to phase out until like after 2045.
Right? So the way that we talk about media,
kind of there's some issues there.
The other thing that I think is really interesting is that we're all at GDC and we're all developers
and we make games and we know how games are made and we know some of the motivations behind
them and what the industry kind of looks like a little bit and so on and so forth.
This is how most people think games get made.
Right? So there's an idea person and then elves and then game.
Right? Just talk to like freshmen that come into games programs.
Right? They're like, I want to be the idea guy.
Right? Like, you know.
Right? So there just, there isn't this public narrative about how games get made.
And yet when you think about film, right?
like a three-year-old knows that there's actors and a script
and that gets turned into a thing, right?
And then you say, well, how does a game get made?
I don't really know, right?
Something with a computer, I think, right?
So it's no wonder that they're trying to,
that there's a lot of fear and moral panic
around what these things do to us
because they don't understand how they're made,
what they are, and how they're being consumed,
and thus their effect.
We've talked a lot about some big national examples,
but the way this trickles down, it can be state by state,
it can be local district, it can be how games are perceived
by the librarian at your local library, right?
It can be like Vermont just tried to ban the sale
of violent video games independently.
just as a state legislature action.
And that fortunately died on the governor's desk
because there's really no way to enforce it presently.
But it was an interesting piece of legislation
to see just kind of float right out there.
There's some efforts right now to legislate loot crates
starting out of Hawaii, so on and so forth.
So what I would say to you is that if we
profess to really care about this medium,
to aspire to games as art.
and to hold ourselves to the highest academic
and professional standards,
then that also means using the knowledge that we have
and the passion for this medium that we hold, right,
to defend it, right?
It means not being silent, right?
And a lot of times we're silent because like,
well, if we say the wrong thing,
like it's gonna go on Twitter
and then bad things happen and so on, right?
But if you don't say anything, right,
you're seeding a void for other people
to fill in that discussion.
I think Roger probably did it better than I did, right?
But let's just remember that games have done some awesome things along the way for culture,
both in education and just purely as a form of entertainment.
So in conclusion, beware the media rumor.
please, okay?
A lot of popular press articles will take some
of the academic work that like Mia was citing
or that Roger was citing and pick out what they think
would be a really nice headline,
even if it doesn't exactly match what the study says, right?
And then that gets condensed into a social media soundbite
and so on and so forth, right?
And so there's very little meat sometimes
to what that looks like.
And so remember that we've been here before.
in our history of moral panics, particularly in this country, but also in others.
Beware of unpublished or preliminary research,
or research that had a particular sponsor with an agenda.
You see that sometimes in this space. Most importantly, I think, is to seek some
empathy with the motivations of parents.
right? Because really I mean they just want their kids to be okay, right? That's the point,
right? And so you know they're scared sometimes reading some of these articles or they're
scared that schools are getting shot up and you know this kind of stuff and so they're
looking, they're knee jerking for answers that are easy that they think they have some
control. Remember that you are an expert on the creation of games, right? Most people
have no idea how they're made.
Our relationship with games is complex.
A lot of times the research is less clear than any headline
will ever allow.
The way we talk about games influences
a lot of what is said about them and where the future research
is targeted.
So whatever the public debate around games
shapes the kinds of research that's
going to be funded the next time that money is allocated
for research funding to look at this stuff.
So what we say actually matters because that influences
the things that we're going to be able to go and explore
and hopefully find out.
And you make a difference when you speak as a games creator,
as a researcher, or as a professional.
And like I said, a lot of the information
that we packed into the panel is on this little website
that we made, which is on the back of that card.
And I'll also tweet the link after the talk and stuff.
And with that, we get to the good stuff.
So it's Q&A time.
Do we have Q&A time?
We have Q&A time.
10 minutes.
So we have short Q&A time, and so we would actually
really appreciate it.
And we do have a wrap-up room, too.
Yeah, we have a wrap-up room.
In 204.
If you would ask questions rather than giving comments
or micro-speeches.
And so everyone will be so much happier if you do.
And in fact, the best question gets a bag of kangaroo meat.
So hop on up and ask a good question.
All the way from Australia.
It's from Australia.
Here you go.
97% Australian.
97% from Australia.
I'm more spicy sometimes.
What was the first question?
All right.
So one topic that wasn't breached here is VR.
And VR, I think, is fundamentally different
because it strives to be ultimately indistinguishable
from reality.
It strives to replace sensory input of reality
itself with something synthetic.
And in that case, something violent
is you carrying out a violent action.
It is not through a proxy or through make-believe.
There is no, ultimately, in its ideal form,
no awareness that it isn't real other than the memory
of going into VR.
So the CNN editorial that I actually wrote addresses this succinctly because there was a Stanford faculty member researcher who had the same opinion and raised the fact, he actually made design suggestions, like if we curve the bullets, then at least we're not training.
All right, that'll be good.
Yeah.
So I have a full response to that.
And I don't think that increased realism drives us to be the kinds of people who would do heinous acts.
But the question wasn't increased realism necessarily,
but the distinctional difference between something
that happens in a rectangle and something
that you have a first direct experience of with your senses,
the way reality interacts with your senses.
I guess I would argue though that it's not just about senses.
Human beings are more than just a response to particular stimuli.
There's a contextual awareness about what you're doing.
So unless it's the Matrix where you don't know you're in the Matrix and you're being
powered by batteries in the background, like you knew you put a VR headset on, you knew
that you're engaged with...
a fantasy environment that is not in present day reality, so on and so forth.
So the contextual understanding of what you're doing and why you're doing it and the motivation
behind that is still wildly different than the physical act of what would happen in,
say, like soldier training, where you know that, in fact, you're training for a real
life scenario.
where you are going to be shot at or are going to be shooting.
So it's again, right, there's, you know, we can, a lot of people will point to the graphics,
will point to the realism, right, but the behavior, right, is something that we don't really,
you know, it's much stickier than that.
I sympathize with what you're saying because we frequently speak out of both sides of our
mouth on this kind of stuff where we say like for training, for surgery, it's just like
being a surgeon, right?
Or for what it is to have the refugee experience.
It's just like the simulated empathy machine, right?
So I get it.
But at the same time, I think that if you look at play and make-believe
People have been role-playing all sorts of experiences
with various levels of realism,
with and without computer mediation.
There are live-action role-playing organizations
that rent ships and all dress in authentic gear,
but they never stab each other, right?
Like when they're, and they feel like pirates
or they look like spaceship Star Troopers
or whatever the thing that they're doing is,
but...
you are you because you play that thing we're good at differentiating that people are good
at differentiating that and when people can't differentiate reality from fantasy um there there
is there's actually a disease for that right um and so i don't know that technology is the problem
with this um uh the separation between those two things we'll happily talk to you out in the
hallway with a little more if you'd like all right if that's cool thanks
Hello, I'm I come from parallel industry. I'm working for as
medical operations. So we are doing board games. And have you
have you ever like within your research where they were this
topic of analog games were covered? Can I can I look for
something interesting?
Has there been any work on analog games and violence?
Like, or game violence?
I mean, D&D, of course, yeah, but then...
Not that I'm familiar with.
D&D is a good example, but right.
Yeah.
And something other,
because we are funding this kind of research,
and if someone is interested, I would like to share.
I think one of the...
A challenge that also researchers face is,
you know, like I have colleagues who say,
you know, like when you're getting grants,
like, why don't you approach the game industry for funding?
And I'm like, ha ha ha.
They're not going to give me money.
But also the sense that I want to be independent.
Because if I say, this study was sponsored by EA,
people are going to give me the eye.
How independent were you really?
There are plans for conferences and this stuff.
Yeah.
For example, we just launched a document for how games manually are helping people with Alzheimer's disease.
So this kind of stuff we are looking for.
I would love to talk to you afterward. There's a whole world of health games researchers that I think would be super interested.
Thank you.
Hi. So I've actually had conversations in this vein before,
where talking about publications and kind of the biases that can go into them
and the publication stuff. And we, during the conversation,
the thing was brought up of these positives articles.
And somebody who was talking for the other side says,
why can't you say all those same things about those?
The bias, the fact that it's sensational
to say these are good.
And we had an interesting conversation about it.
I'm curious what you would say would be a good response
to saying like, if you apply those arguments
back towards the positive articles.
I need help with the question just a little bit more.
I'm sorry.
So basically for like a lot of the sensationalist ones like old books about D&D and stuff like that
There was a lot of there was kind of the moral panic
There's some where it's like this is a very punchy headline that was convinced down
God, so when the same thing is said about like all these being positive like all the good things games do yeah, okay
I got it. I got so because because to be perfectly honest there isn't like on the
no one's really arguing against those things.
So as Mia pointed out, where there might be studies
and we go back and forth over a period of time
of are games addictive or are games not addictive,
we're not seeing articles showing
that games don't reduce anxiety.
We're not seeing articles that show games
are not reducing self-esteem or increasing self-esteem.
Right, and so they're actually,
there aren't,
other articles to go back to that say these things aren't happening.
And so it's kind of like there are lots of debates where everyone wants to believe there's two sides
to the debate, but it's like exercise, right? It's like there are no articles that say that
cardiovascular activity in a regular healthy person can't be a wonderful part of their life,
right? There's no anti-cardio, I mean there are some silly things on the internet, right?
But there's no anti-cardiovascular activity study group at Stanford, right? And the same is true,
the pro-social aspects of games.
Can I just jump into and say that I would agree
that I think that all the research
should be strictly scrutinized,
because, yeah, it's like if you're gonna critique
one set of studies, you should be critiquing all sets.
It's just that, honestly, when you come up with,
you say a nice thing, most people aren't ready
to jump on you and be like, prove it!
Right?
You know, like, I don't think that's true!
What's your methodology?
Is it a population sample?
So that's definitely true, and I would argue
In terms of the broader concerns, I mean, yes, games do impact people.
They can impact us poorly.
They can impact us in positive ways.
It's just far more complicated in terms of how they do that, right?
And I think that's true of the positive impacts as much as well.
Yeah, and I think, too, there's, you know, like, to me, in some of the work that I do
and the way that that translates into things like policy proposal and legislative action,
you know, there's either action or there's not, right?
And so to err on the side of not.
you know, increase, of not creating more legislation,
of not creating new policy, of, you know, letting sort of,
you know, free market just, you know, kind of go and do it,
you know, its thing, right?
I think there's the, you know, so, so.
to me, right, like what's the harm in having a good think piece, right, that makes everybody
feel good, right, but maybe it wasn't completely accurate.
Well, yeah, I mean, we should strive for accuracy, but who got hurt?
right there, whereas on the other end, right, you do that and then, you know, that biases
public opinion and that creates a, you know, a call to action and we start, you know, passing
laws about, you know, what we're, you know, going to allow to be seen and not seen, right?
I think that that's a very slippery slope. And so, you know, I would hold a piece that's
trying to skew public opinion in that way to a high standard, I hope, right? So.
On that note, I think we're going to conclude here.
We'll answer questions in the wrap-up room.
We strongly encourage you to give us your feedback via the
forms that you now are able to access through mobile phones.
And also to take these things if you want them.
Hey, guy with the good hat, you can have it if you want it.
You had a great question, and that hat is just amazing.
You seem like the person that deserves this.
All right, thank you.