Hey, my name is Nick Sutner. I'm an independent writer, designer, and consultant.
And before that I worked at PlayStation for a long time doing business development and finding and signing a lot of the bigger indie titles.
And then I worked at Oculus for a while after that.
And in my time spent at those big companies, I realized just how critical it is for any game release to have champions fighting for your game on the inside of these big platforms.
Or at a publisher, or in the press.
So I'm doing a talk at GDC called Platforms are People to the Importance of Finding Your Champion.
And I'm going to talk about that.
And I'm going to go more into detail and talk about just why it's so important and some of the internal machinations of how these things work, to understand why it's important to have people on your side fighting for your games.
I really believe that any sort of positive promotion or placement or anything good that's done for your game is done because someone, a person genuinely cares about your game and wants to see it do well and share it with more people.
And I think it's important to internalize that and then also know how to find those people.
So I'm also going to walk through that in my talk. So please join me. I think it's going to
be helpful if you're someone who is planning to commercially release a game and make it
sustainable for your studio. Thanks.