Cool, I'm up on my box now, and all of maybe five-four,
so I think I'll go ahead and get started.
So my talk today is Don't Call Them Whales,
Free-to-Place Vendors and Virtual Value.
If you don't know me, I'm the CEO and co-founder of Kongregate.
And if you don't know Kongregate, it is a, to start with, a browser, a web platform for
browser games on the web.
So think YouTube for games.
We get just a ton of content, about 1,300 new games.
per month, 95,000 games total across a really wide variety of genres.
And this gives us, with that ton of games, it gives us some interesting opportunities
to do.
a lot of interesting research.
And I am a big data geek, as you will discover quickly
in this talk.
So I think that's really fun.
Most of the data in this talk will be from the web.
But about 18 months ago, we started
publishing games on mobile.
And we've published about 15 games in that time period.
Now that's not sort of the reach and breadth and depth
of data we have from the web,
but we've gotten more than 35 million installs
and a bunch of titles in the top grossing.
So there's a lot of interesting data there too.
So,
give you a concept, give you,
I'll be using both in this talk.
So one of the dirty secrets of Congregate
is that we depend very heavily on 2% of our players.
In 2000, we launched our virtual goods in-app purchasing
on our platform.
about six years ago at the end of 2008.
And since that time period, 2.1% of accounts active
have purchased virtual goods.
And those 2% buying have brought in 75%
of the revenue on Congregate.
The other 25% comes from advertising.
And that split has increased over the years.
So in 2014, 85% of our revenue came from virtual goods.
and just 15% from advertising.
And if you look closer, it's actually much, much more
concentrated than that.
So this takes a look at our buyers since 2008
on congregate.com.
And on the left-hand chart, it splits them out,
splits all the spenders out by the amount
they spent lifetime on the Congregate platform.
So you can see that about a little more than 50%
have spent less than $10.
And about 4% have spent $500 or more.
On the right-hand side, and did I get my left and right confused?
Because that sometimes happens to me.
No, it's right.
On the right-hand side, you've got the same split
looking at the percent of revenue coming
from that category of buyers.
54% who spent less than $10 represent exactly 1% of our total revenue in the last six years.
And the 4% of people who have spent $500 or more are 72% of our revenue.
So if you multiply 4% by 2%, that's 0.1% of our player base is representing half of our
revenue.
If you look at individual games, it's the same story.
So this is the top eight grossing games
on Kongregate during 2014.
looking at their revenue distribution
by spender category.
So that same chart on the right that I looked at
from the previous account.
If you can't read it, the bright green,
it represents the revenue from spenders
who spent more than $500.
And you can see that six out of eight games
get the vast majority of their revenue
from people who spent more than $500.
and all eight get the clear majority of their revenue
from people who spent $100 or more.
On mobile, the pattern is similar.
Here are our top five grossing games on mobile broken out
the same way.
The spend is a little bit more distributed
for a couple of reasons.
One is that the games haven't been out as long.
And the longer that you're out, the more
that you're going to get concentration of spend.
and people who are playing for a long time.
But the other factor is genre.
On the web, our top grossing games
are pretty dominated by MMORPGs and collectible card games.
And on mobile, we've deliberately
diversified a little bit more beyond that.
If you look at the same games, quite a few of these games
we have on both web and mobile, and their distribution of spend
on the website and on the mobile are so close
that it's difficult to tell the charts apart.
Fundamentally, how people are spending in your game
is going to be the same whatever platform that you're on.
And with the exception of one game,
the vast majority of our games are getting their revenue
from people who are spending $100 plus or more.
And it's not just Congregate, and it's not just our games.
This is normal for the industry.
So Swerve, which is an analytics and A-B testing platform,
did a report back in January of 2014.
where they looked at everybody playing and spending across all of their games using their services
and found that one and a half percent of people active that month spent,
and then when they broke them into deciles,
they found that the top ten percent of spenders represented half of the revenue.
0.15% of active players were half the revenue,
a little bit more diffuse than Congregate,
but not meaningfully different.
And this is with a lot of games that
didn't have where the highest thing that you could buy
was $19.99.
So while this is totally true of the industry,
it's also something that we're really uncomfortable with.
So let's see.
OK.
There, now I'm on the right slide.
So whenever I mention that our top spenders on Congregate
have spent $50,000 to $80,000, people nearly always
react with kind of this mix of awe and horror.
And there's a lot of criticism for free-to-play games
and ethics.
And one of the things that they quickly jump on
is the amount that the biggest spenders are spending.
And they start questioning.
Are these people sane?
Are developers some kind of predator
that's ripping money from these people?
And it's not just ethical concerns.
People worry that free-to-play games
are too financially dependent on just a few people.
So much so that Zynga listed it as a risk in their IPO perspectives.
Now, from my perspective, pretty much every business is dependent on good customers,
so I don't think it's much of a risk, but Zynga certainly thought so and publishized it.
So to better understand what's going on here,
I think it makes sense to take a look at who's buying.
This chart shows average revenue per user, or ARPU,
on congregate.com by the reported age of the user
at registration, or the birth date reported at registration
and whatever age they are.
now. So, young users spend very little on average, with spend rising gradually through
college age, rapidly increasing after they graduate, and then plateauing through middle
age when disposable income is at its highest. There's some weird little sharp dips at 25
and 35, and that's probably driven by people putting in fake January 1, 1980 and 1990.
birth dates, because those are exactly 15, sorry, 25 and 35
years ago now.
There's also an issue with people
with the ages over than 57, because our registration form
anchors at 1940.
And everything from age 57 or older is immediately visible,
so probably has a high portion of people who are just
putting in random ages.
But just looking at the core data from 13 through 57,
you can still see a really clear trend
and in terms of what's going on.
You can see a little bit more of what's going on
if you decompose ARPU between percentage of buyers
and the average revenue per paying user or ARPU.
Is that my computer?
OK.
The youngest players generally don't have a way of paying,
no credit cards or PayPal accounts.
But the percent of players who are buying
rises rapidly with age and independence,
and then plateauing.
through the 30s before just starting to decline in the 40s.
I suspect that people in their 40s now are kind of the first generation that grew up
with video games, and so familiarity and comfort with video games is a little bit lower past
that age.
The increase in ARPAPU, though, is much more gradual
and peaks in the late 40s and early 50s.
Again, ignore most of the data from age 50.
That's distorted by the registration process.
What is clear, though, is that spending
grows first with the ability to pay and then the means to pay.
This chart shows US disposable income
by educational attainment and age.
And if you look at sort of the angle of this chart
and the growth of disposable income over age,
it really mirrors the ARPA-PU growth very closely.
People are spending what they can afford to spend.
So this chart is,
delving a little bit more granularly into our big spenders and takes our top 20 spenders lifetime on Congregate.com
and sorts them from youngest to oldest. The youngest is 24. The oldest is 68.
Both the average and medium age of big spenders is 40.
The older big spenders all come from the US and Western Europe,
while the few younger spenders come
from more assorted countries.
The little red flag with a flower is Hong Kong.
You can also see Brazil and the United Arab Emirates
and Sweden are the people, are the spenders who are under 30.
And our customer service team has spoken on the phone
or emailed with.
every single person on this list,
both to check that there was nothing fraudulent going on,
and then to also help them with various
in-game customer service issues
and issues that arise when you spend that much money.
And they say that every time they talk to them,
they're sort of impressed by sort of the politeness
and reasonableness of all of these top 20 spenders.
A lot of them own their own businesses.
Some are engineers.
There's a doctor with the CDC and CPAs and similar.
These are sort of older, competent, professional people.
The columns also show how much they spend
and then breaks it out into what games they're spending it in.
So that first blue part is their main game
that has the most spend.
The red is their second game.
And then there's a few more colors for other games.
And one of the things that you can see really clearly here
is that most of these players are spending
most of their money on one game.
They may be buying in other games,
but they're really concentrating their resources in one game.
The phenomenon of a serial big spender
who's going in and dropping significant amounts of cash
in game after game is really rare.
I think there's only two, maybe three people out of this 20
who show that pattern.
So now I'm going to jump into a different look at the data and start looking at one
particular game.
Because once you start looking at gameplay patterns, it makes much more sense to look
at an individual game.
The next series of slides are all going to be data from Tyrant Unleashed, which is a
game we publish on mobile and web from Synapse Games.
And thank you again Synapse for once more letting me share a lot of your data.
So this chart, it takes a little while to look through,
but it shows the average number of sessions
per daily active user by the day they are in the game.
So from one year, day of install in through.
a year and a half in, and then breaks it by the eventual spend category that they reach.
So if they eventually become a $500 plus spender, then they're in the line in green.
If they've spent less than $500, they're red.
Non-spenders are blue.
And what you can see is that from day one,
that the biggest spenders are much, much more active
than anybody else in the game.
Over their lifetime, they're averaging around 20 sessions
per day, whereas lesser spenders are averaging around 12,
and non-spenders around five.
The longer they're in the game, the more it comes together,
but the pattern of big spenders are twice as active
as lesser spenders and then twice as active again
from non-spenders is pretty consistent.
And most people who spend a long time in this game
do end up spending.
So by about a year in,
two thirds of all active players in the game have spent.
But non-spenders aren't driven out
because that still means a third of people
have played the game for a year and a half without spending.
Most of them spend, some people spend pretty quickly.
About 18% of people make their first purchase
on the day of install, and about half
have made their first purchase within a week
of installing the game.
But after that, it takes a long time to go up.
And at a month in, 30% of the people
who are going to purchase have not yet purchased.
And even six months in.
These graphs are not yet at 100%.
People are still making their first purchase,
even people who are going to go on to spend $500 or more.
As you would expect, the biggest spenders
do spend a little bit earlier and a little bit faster
than lesser spenders.
But there's not really a big difference.
People are, a lot of big spenders
are taking their time before they
make their first purchase.
And they're spending gradually over time.
So this breaks all of the spenders out into deciles
by the average amount that they've spent,
and then looks at their spending by time in the game.
And you can see, especially the first and second deciles,
that their investment in the game is really, really gradual.
They're spending kind of the same amount every month
steadily.
It's a little hard to see what some of the lower deciles
are doing here, just because the top ones are so big.
So here in this next slide, I'm taking away the top two.
And you can see that that gradual investment is still
happening just at a slightly less steep angle
and with a lower amount.
The only groups that don't rise significantly over time
are the bottom deciles, where people are spending $20 or less.
And most of those are just making one purchase and done.
So how do you spend $5,000 in a game?
Now I'm gonna look at one individual case of a big spender.
This big spender is a 40-year-old Californian
whose primary game is an action RPG.
It's single player in a social environment
with a lot of skill-based leveling
and multiple class paths that give him
a strong feeling of progress.
There's guilds and co-op multiplayer,
PVP and tournaments that they participate in.
And they play four to six days a week,
play more than 1,000 times lifetime.
And they play and spend in other games.
But 90% of money and time is going into just this one game.
So you can see that that fits the sort
of prototypical stereotype of the big spenders
that we've talked about up to this point.
What do they actually spend on?
So in 2014, they spent about $7,500,
$2,200 on consumables, $1,800 for skill upgrades,
some miscellaneous things, and then
the bulk of their money going towards competitive multiplayer,
tournament skilled wars, PVP, that kind of thing.
So a little bit more about this big spender.
It's me.
And a little bit more about this big spender.
I'm not spending it on a game.
I'm spending it on figure skating.
So how does that work?
Well, believe it or not, there's actually
an amazing parallel between the structure
of competitive figure skating and a game.
This has been the structure for the US Figure Skating
Association since like 60 years, 70 years.
But they may as well have invented gamification.
So.
It's a single-player sport in a social environment.
So, individual sport done in a shared session.
So, I skate at the Yerba Buena rink that's kind of right on top of the conference center right now
with other people who I get to know well and become friends with.
If this makes me slightly cooler, one of them is occasionally Brian Boitano.
who is a very nice guy.
There's skill-based leveling, multiple class paths,
so there's five different classes in which you compete
and can test up and level up.
I'm progressing along the moves in the field,
basic skills tests, as well as singles, freestyle.
And I am...
I've tested through three levels on moves in the field
and on two levels on freestyle and working
to level up on both.
And I do this by learning new skills, achievements,
and then testing in the test session.
So, say, an example might be a sit-spin or a flip-jump
or something like that.
There's guilds and co-op multiplayer.
So I'm a member of the skating club of San Francisco.
I'm also a member of a synchronized skating team.
And believe me, there's nothing cool about that.
That's the picture of me in that red sequined vest
with something really strange in my hair.
That's my synchronized skating team.
There's also ice dance in Paris, but I don't do that.
And there's competitive multiplayer.
So there's frequent competitions
organized by age, level, and mode.
And points are also tallied for clubs and rinks.
And that pressure is actually very real
and very significant, and is the reason why
in that picture there to the right,
I'm dressed like a B-52.
We were hosting a competition at my rink,
and the rink manager wanted.
all of the good skaters to compete in as many events as possible so we would earn more points.
And she made me do this group routine in this particular outfit.
And the good news is that we did win that trophy and she was happy.
So, what, you know, I gave all these sort of game equivalents to my spending.
So, the consumables was my ice time, so just going to my daily session costs about $11.
I do that almost every day. That adds up.
The skilled upgrades are my private lessons.
I take a $135 half hour lesson every week.
That ends up being about $1,800 a year.
There's some miscellaneous costs for equipment and costumes.
But the big bulk of money is going to competition fees
and travel to get to competitions.
And even with $7,500, I definitely
haven't hit my max spend.
I'm actually participating in relatively few competitions,
because I have to travel so much for Congregate already.
And while I'm naturally thrifty, I'm happy to spend this money.
I love skating enough that a 10% increase in my skills
is worth 10x the cost.
When I make this comparison, people
will often dismiss it as being fundamentally different
because skating is exercise.
I can resell my skates, et cetera.
Skating is good for my health, but you can see here
that most of my spend is going to skill progression
and competition, and that's exactly the same things
that you spend on in game.
Nothing, well, except for the actual ice time,
nothing that's listed here has any resale value
or does any good for my health.
Even the equipment is really services
like skate sharpening and my locker.
And my larger point here is that games are hobbies,
and people spend a lot on their hobbies.
So an example would be a weekly golfer
could easily spend $10,000 a year on greens fees,
and golf clubs, lessons, going to the driving range.
somebody's an amateur guitarist, while they might not spend much day to day,
the few that I've known tend to obsess about collecting guitars and, you know,
will go visit shops that have guitars that they like that they can't afford
just to sort of touch and see them.
and usually end up spending more than they really want to on guitars.
Going to eat in restaurants adds up very quickly if you do it weekly,
especially in San Francisco.
And baseball fans, season tickets, a visit to spring training,
that can be 5,000 between them pretty quickly.
Even something like your aunt does, like quilting.
Materials get expensive pretty quickly,
and it's nicer to use nice materials,
so people will spend on that.
A really good sewing machine is going to cost $5,000,
and if you're doing it all the time, you're going to want that.
Even something that seems like it would be really cheap,
relatively like running.
somebody who becomes a competitive runner is likely to start spending money.
You're going to go through shoes pretty quickly,
and at $100, $150 a pop,
you can spend $500 on shoes and clothes quite easily.
Especially once you start competing, race fees and travel to races,
it adds up just the way my figure skating does.
So how did I get started on this path?
And I think looking at sort of the long term pattern
of my spin kind of explains a lot about
sort of the psychology and how things work.
So I started skating back in 2004.
looking for an alternative exercise,
immediately fell in love, started taking group lessons,
and I bought skates.
And in 2005 and early 2006, my spend was accelerating.
Then in June of 2006, my brother and I started Congregate,
and suddenly I had neither money nor time.
We were going without salaries.
And so there's about a two-year period
where I was barely skating and barely spending at all.
things stabilized by 2009.
And I went back to sort of the trend line
that I'd been on before.
In 2010, we sold Kongregate to GameStop.
And I used some of that money to buy custom skates.
And then they're made by the same people who
make them for Brian Boitano.
So again, they're very cool.
And I'm still using those from five years ago.
It was a good investment.
And then I started competing and joined the SYNC team.
It jumped a lot last year when I went to compete at my first nationals.
It was in Massachusetts in April.
I'm probably the only person who has ever combined a trip to PAX East and adult skating nationals.
And this coming year, I expect that I'm going to spend even more.
guesstimating somewhere around $12,000.
When I turned 40 last year,
my family gave me a really, really lovely gift
of a trip to the Dorothy Hamill Fantasy Skate Camp.
It was awesome, and I'm likely to go back and spend a week with great coaches skating for a week again.
And I could really easily see spending, say, $20,000 in a year if I did both adult nationals and the big international competition in Germany,
work with a choreographer, do things like that.
So I don't know that I would do that sort of regularly,
but I can very much see that happening
and feel that it would be rational.
You know, the choices that I'm making here
may seem a little unusual,
but they've been gradual, thoughtful investments
put to something that I love.
I'd rather spend money on figure skating
than almost anything else.
So I'm lucky enough to have the means and disposable income
to put towards skating, especially
as I don't have kids.
But that's not true of all skaters or all gamers.
Here's a friend that I skate with on Facebook posting
about her decision not to go to nationals this year
because her husband has lost her job
and they need to budget and save.
And she's saving, but she's putting the money goes
to the mortgage first and then health care.
And then she's saving for her nephew's wedding.
But she's still finding enough money in the budget
to skate and take lessons and do the base case.
And then several other people are chiming in
about their decision making.
again deciding it was too expensive to go to nationals.
The point here is that even avid fans
are making rational, thoughtful decisions
about how they're spending.
Now, not every skater or gamer is
making their spending decisions totally rationally
and within their budget.
There's always a spectrum of human behavior in any group,
and there's always going to be some people who
are trying to fill unmet emotional needs
in unhealthy ways.
But we don't blame department stores
for the occasional compulsive shopper.
And we shouldn't blame either figure skating or games
for the occasional compulsive spender.
And it's not just figure skating,
and it's not just games.
Other industries have similar dynamics.
For example, the music industry.
So if you start with a base of radio, which
is a really mass audience, and streaming, and piracy,
most artists are getting very little money
from these sources.
But they're getting a lot of exposure to a broad audience
in the hope that a smaller percentage of them
are going to go on and buy either a physical or digital
copy of their music.
And then from there, a smaller percentage than that
is going to go on and buy a ticket to go to a concert
and maybe buy a t-shirt.
And then there's going to be, in the last few years,
as the amount of revenue from the amount of people
buying physical and digital copies of music
has gone down with piracy and streaming,
artists are getting more clever about putting together
packages, VIP packages.
to sell sort of expensive experiences
to their very highest fans.
So what you see there is that overall,
millions of people may be seeing,
listening to an artist's music,
but the artist's revenue is heavily concentrated
in the 12% who spend 20 to $500
to go to concerts and buy merchandise.
And even within that, it's probably concentrate on the repeat concert goers who are maybe
traveling to get there, the people who buy every album, even the bad ones.
And then, again, the people who are buying VIP packages.
I'm showing a screenshot here from one that U2 is doing.
That's $1,500 for a ticket to the concert, a hotel room,
and premium access to merchandise,
where you can spend again, and just the possibility of a drawing
where you might get to meet the band.
So, like a really low percentage chance that you might be anywhere near the band.
And that's $1,500.
And again, it's a little closer to home as well, in terms of the concentration.
If you look at console games, the dynamics are more similar than you would expect.
So GameStop, our parent company, is a very hefty percentage of the US market for video
games.
And they've reported publicly that 20% of their customers are members of PowerUp Rewards,
which is their loyalty database.
And 70% of their revenue is coming
from those 20% of customers who are loyalty members.
And even within that, it's more densely packed.
So there's two tiers of Power Up Rewards membership.
There's the free one, where you just
kind of give over your information,
and you get an immediate discount.
And you're earning points that you can potentially
redeem for things in their loyalty store.
And then there's the pro version, which costs $15
and gets you a copy of Game Informer Magazine,
larger discounts, and double the points.
As you would imagine, anybody who's going to spend $15
on a membership is a really good customer.
And so the people in the basic free tier, on average,
buy from GameStop three times a year, spend $160.
The people in the pro buy 10 times on average and spend $570.
And that's just their spend within GameStop.
They're probably spending on Steam and other places.
Now the number, the breakout between
Basic and pro on power up members is not a public number, but you can make a guess that it's got to be
you know less than 10% of the GameStop audience and somewhere in the 40 to 50 percent range of
total revenue
So if this kind of distribution and this kind of setup
is totally normal, why are we so uncomfortable with big spenders
in free-to-play games?
So uncomfortable that we quickly jump to mental illness
and bad behavior on the game developer's part to explain it.
So I think there's several reasons.
One is data.
Before free-to-play, we really didn't
know how much people were spending.
It was scattered across multiple sources,
and those sources were generally retailers
and platform holders.
Until recently, I doubt that the retailers themselves knew.
I worked in data analysis and marketing
for several retail companies before we started Congregate.
And at that time, we knew almost everything
about customers who were buying through catalogs and web.
But if we wanted any data from the store,
it was always just anonymous transaction data.
And there was no way to figure out who
was purchasing again and again.
An individual store manager might
know who their big customers were
and what they were spending on average.
But it took loyalty programs, which really took off
in the last 10 years or so.
for people at the retail level to really understand
and collect this kind of data.
And even once they had it,
they were probably reasonably comfortable with it,
because this kind of concentration is normal
regardless of what you sell.
I have a funny story about Larry Ellison
from a previous company
that I probably shouldn't tell publicly,
but if you ever catch me nodding at a podium,
I will tell you what it is.
So reason two is that spend is more concentrated,
and we should be honest about that.
It's more concentrated, and the biggest spenders
are spending more.
So this table shows off the dynamics
of mobile and web markets, starting with a base case
of a paid mobile app.
These numbers are all made up, so don't read too closely
into them.
But I have enough data that I feel
like these are pretty plausible as sort of above median cases,
but way below actual real successes.
In the current mobile market, it's really hard to get much of anyone to buy a game.
There's just too much free content.
When you go free, installs can explode, but conversion goes down
and lives in a relatively narrow range.
So what ends up mattering is whether players keep playing
and keep spending and drive the average amount spent up.
And that's why free-to-play is generating more revenue than paid.
It's not because more people are getting into your game
and having a chance to convert.
Generally, you're going to have fewer buyers
than you would have otherwise.
But I think people think that that's what the dynamic is,
that you're getting more people in who might buy.
The total number of people buying is almost certainly going down
because the more casually interested are not going to pay unless they have to.
The reason that total revenue is up is because the most invested players
who in a paid world spent the same as everyone else
now have their spend uncapped.
So some people who would have spent before enjoy the game for free
and the most invested spend much more than they would have.
essentially subsidizing a free experience for everybody else.
Reason three is that we don't value digital games very highly.
So I've put together a chart, again, with some good numbers
from MPD and some really, really shitty numbers
for paid PC games that are
somewhat made up but somewhat plausible after talking to
PC developers. So take it with a grain of salt.
But the range of prices
and sort of the...
the general dynamics of total market size
are probably pretty accurate.
So console games have better graphics and more content
to play through than most PC games or definitely
most mobile games.
But the average player only plays a small portion
of that content.
Completion rates on even the best games on console
tend to be lower.
to be around 30%, I believe.
Well, some mobile and PC games are quite short.
Monument Valley is pretty darn short, for example.
The delta between play times is likely a lot less
than the delta in price.
Is a new console game really worth four to five times
the average PC game, 20 to 25 times
the average paid mobile game?
I'm biased because I'm in that space,
but I don't really think so.
And the other thing is, again, these numbers are rough,
but the market size of each of these genres,
or not genres, platforms,
marches roughly in step
with the average sales price of a game.
Though in theory, mobile and PC should be larger
than console games because they're platforms
that have much broader reach.
Almost everybody has a computer,
almost everybody has a smartphone.
So why is price mattering more than the number of possible players?
And that's because I believe demand for games is fundamentally inelastic.
So what inelastic means is that when the price drops,
the total amount sold increases, but not enough to account,
to make up for the drop in price, so total revenue is lower.
And I know you're thinking, OK, that
doesn't make any sense at all.
If that's true, why do PC game developers
make so much more when they're part of Steam sales
and Humble Bundle?
Clearly, price is dropping and their revenue is going up.
But when you think about it, that's what's going on
is a sale and a special event.
And they're getting a lot more promotion.
If you drop the price without giving them
a lot more attention and putting a perception in the mind
of the player that they're getting this amazing limited
time deal, the revenue for these games
wouldn't go up at that same price.
They would go down.
Steam sales help draw more people into play PC games,
which increases the sale for that category overall,
and exposes consumers to a lot broader range
of games and developers,
which overall is really good for the industry.
But it's probably mostly cannibalizing revenue
that would otherwise have gone to console.
So pricing studies have consistently shown that we make our decisions based on our perceived
sense of value rather than price alone.
And interestingly, price itself is a signal of value to most of us.
So we assume that if the price being charged is higher, the item must be better.
So
If you see a higher priced wine, your default assumption is that it's better wine.
You don't have really any way to know that, but the price is giving you that signal.
If you go into a drugstore and you see a brand name like Aleve right next to the Walgreens Naproxen sodium,
Those are exactly the same things, and yet people,
and this includes me, have a tendency to go reach over
and buy the Aleve because it must be better
because it's more expensive.
But it's really the same thing.
So on mobile, we have anchored our perception
of value really low.
How much for them J's? $1,000.
Sold.
Yo, you gotta get some app.
It's free.
What?
No, no!
So we're all familiar with the terrible race to the bottom
on paid game pricing that happened on iOS a few years back.
There was no retail or platform who cared about
the total sales to organize and control price wars,
and the going price for games was quickly pushed down
to 99 cents.
Games that you can play for many hours are priced at or below a cup of coffee, or the
cost of renting a movie that lasts 90 minutes.
A few games can come in at higher prices, like Minecraft or Final Fantasy Tactics, when
their value has been anchored high on another platform.
And prices are slowly creeping up again.
$3.99 is more common.
$4.99 is more common.
But for paid games to be viable for more developers,
prices need to rise a lot, among other things,
so that sale events can be more meaningful.
A $0.99 drop may be 50% on $1.99 game,
but it's not going to get a lot of people excited.
So that's why free-to-play is so strong in the mobile market.
Free-to-play games set their own value.
In a free-to-play game, nobody can
sell a good that's useful except you, which makes
your game a little monopoly.
It's an insecure monopoly, though, because the player
can leave at any time.
And if you piss them off by pricing things
in weird and aggressive ways, they are likely to leave.
There's no point price shopping packages of gold between games
or the value of any kind of premium currency.
The other game's items have no meaning in the game
that you're playing.
The more compelling and engaging the game,
the more that players care about their status and progress,
and the higher the value of the goods in the game
become to the player, and the higher you can set your prices.
Which comes to the next reason that I think
is affecting our perception of big spenders, which is that we
don't value virtual goods.
Our brains easily pin value on physical objects.
Part of the reason console games have been able to continue
to anchor their value high relative to digital versions
is that disk.
But that disk has been a tiny percentage
of the cost of selling a console game for a very long time.
It's the development, it's the retail share,
it's the marketing.
That's what's driving the cost up on just about everything.
But even out of context, physical goods
are always perceived as having value.
But out of context of playing a game,
virtual items have no meaning.
They're incredibly abstract.
And therefore, it's almost impossible for us
to value something that we've never interacted with
and never imagined.
A physical good, we always assume
it has a value because it had a cost to produce.
So I think this is a large part of the success of Skylanders,
for example, is that it bridges that gap between physical
and virtual value.
So a parent can go into a store and buy something
that looks like something that they understand
and give it to their child, who then converts it
into a virtual item that has a lot more meaning to them.
So another example is that spending $5,000 to $10,000
on a specialized PC gaming rig that improves your skill
and your competitiveness in a highly competitive game
like League of Legends can easily cost $5,000 to $10,000.
And it's fundamentally the same as spending $5,000 to $10,000
on.
skills and other things in a virtual game
that would improve your competitiveness.
But I bet you all find it a lot easier
to contemplate and accept.
If you walked into this room,
you're much more likely to say, wow,
than what were you thinking.
But if the same person had spent that same money in game,
you would be a little bit more concerned.
For the person who's spending in game,
these items have context and they have equal value.
And just because you haven't experienced it
doesn't make it less valid.
So reason five is that I don't think we value games
equally with other hobbies.
Here's a lovely anti-game and slightly misogynistic quote
from Ray Bradbury along that topic.
And we don't value it not only with other hobbies
or even other forms of entertainment.
A few weeks ago, I was looking for a comprehensive history
of games going back to ancient times.
And I was surprised to find that one does not
appear to have been written.
Most universities have entire departments
devoted to studying literature, film, and theater
with virtually nothing about games.
But we've been playing games back to thousands of years BC
and playing and spending just as much time on them.
And yet, we don't give them any credence
in an intellectual way.
Games are a waste of time, games are for kids, games aren't art.
All of those things are sort of this sort of backbeat of culture.
It's not hard for me to talk about my obsession with figure skating with non-skaters.
People generally think that it's kind of quirky and charming, that I care about something
that is a little strange.
Caring about sports, even unusual sports where you're wearing sequins and makeup and play
music is broadly accepted.
But if it were a game that I was spending that much money on, I think I'd be more defensive,
especially with non-gamers.
The bias against games is so insidious that even within the industry, we've internalized
enough that we question someone with means spending tens of thousands of dollars on a
game, especially when you combine it with the low value we place on mobile and PC games
and especially virtual goods.
And so people jump to explanations like mental illness or evil games manipulating players.
when the real explanation is that they are rational, wealthy people
who are dedicated fans of a particular game and investing in their progress in it.
So please don't call them whales.
Call them hobbyists, call them super fans,
call them something else.
To call them whales is to dehumanize them.
To talk of catching them suggests
that they're blundering into your net
or somebody else's net, rather than choosing
to spend their time and money in a game.
And if we as developers don't respect our players
and the value that we create, who will?
Thank you.
Thanks.
A lot of people helped me with this talk, so thank you to them.
I will post this talk and I've posted most of the other ones that I've done and other
ones from congregate people on our blog.
We have a booth in the expo this time so if you would like to talk to us, please stop
by there.
I'm happy to talk to people afterwards.
You can follow me on Twitter, and I'm happy to take some questions now.
The cost of the individual items for the hobbies is clear.
So if you go to the sporting goods store, you know exactly what the cost is of your skates.
You go to GameStop, you know exactly what the cost of Call of Duty is.
Do you feel that it changes the model when there's an obfuscation of cost
where you're using hard currency or gotcha,
where it becomes much, much harder to know what the actual value is of the things that you're purchasing?
I don't think it changes it that much.
For one thing, most of these spenders are
sort of very rational, careful optimizers.
Ubisoft did a good talk last year
where they did a lot of sort of social science research into.
their biggest spenders in one particular game
and found out that they were very careful,
thoughtful people who were maximizing certain things.
It makes the, with gotcha boxes,
the individual result of a particular poll may be uncertain,
but the sort of total value of what you
are likely to get at the end of it is pretty clear.
and people who are spending that much are thinking it through.
And, you know, I would say that, you know, when I got into figure skating,
I had no idea how much I would spend.
And even the first time going into nationals,
there were all sorts of sort of hidden and unexpected costs
where I had to, you know, suddenly pay for warm-up time and other things.
I think, you know,
every time you're making a choice,
you're looking at it on the face of it.
And while you may be playing a gotcha box
with the intention of getting one particular item,
if the game is doing it right,
then every time you pull it,
you're getting something that you value.
So you should be feeling like,
I got a good deal with this gotcha pull,
even if I didn't get what I wanted.
I think that sort of framework
of how we think about designing free-to-play.
is actually part of sort of the humanized idea
of spenders and spending.
That if we're thinking about everybody
as sort of rational and thoughtful,
then we should be thinking about
how they feel immediately about purchasing
and doing it in a way where it feels right every time.
I'm not saying that that's exactly
what's happening in every game,
but for somebody to keep spending again and again and again,
they must be feeling that they're getting a good value.
What about variable ratio reinforcement?
That's a hook that does keep people going,
because it's a compelling feature that's
hard to step away from.
That's what makes video slots work so well.
And the top five of the top games in the top 25
are straight up.
So what I would say is you're buying an experience.
If you're enjoying that experience, then
you're getting the value of it.
So I don't think saying something.
An element that makes it more enjoyable for you to play,
and enjoyable to spend, that's making the game into a spend,
is part of the entertainment of what you're doing.
And we should trust that that is,
that the person is making that decision.
and enjoying it at that level.
Again, as I mentioned,
spend tends to be extremely even across time periods,
which shows that people are having
sort of controlled reactions
and thinking thoughtfully about what they're spending.
Do you think it makes a moral difference for the games that purposefully try to get those really top-end spenders to make more purchases,
like psychological things in the game sort of try to pinch them in and try to just almost force them to buy something to continue for those really high-end spenders?
I think the games that do that are driving away their big spenders.
I think that the feeling of being forced to do something is sort of one of the most unpleasant
ways that you can go about monetizing.
And that games that do that are probably, actually don't have the highest number of
spenders.
Like, you want positive incentives.
competition to drive spending.
I don't think pinch points are not, from my perspective,
not a terribly effective way of monetizing and not really
directed at big spenders.
I think pinch points tend to be about getting $5 from everybody.
Like you get to a certain point, and now we're
going to get that first $5.
you can leave.
And as you saw, somebody spending $5 or $10 once
doesn't add up to very much in the long term.
And so I think that kind of monetization is a mistake.
All right.
Hi.
I was wondering if any of your data
shows that if a similar genre of game
was introduced into your market?
if there was a siphoning of spending towards that new game,
or if there was some sort of loyalty to a game
that was already invested, like people were investing in?
There's intense loyalty.
So when we started, we have this broad platform
where we're advertising a lot of games,
and when we first started having games be successful,
one of our concerns was
If we show somebody another game,
are we going to just cannibalize sales and move them across?
And what we find is that our sales have increased really
steadily over the years, because people find the games that they
really care about, and they spend in those,
and they stay in those.
And it's relatively rare to shake them from that loyalty.
Again, you saw that in that big spender data
that most people had one game that they spent on.
The situation where that's not true is where a game isn't being supported and new content
isn't being released, the event cycle has died, there's not any new features.
At that point, there is a vulnerable point where if a good new game in that same genre
comes in, then you will see a bunch of people jump over.
But generally, if somebody is spending a significant amount in the game...
They're not leaving. Thank you
Thanks Emily great talk
So you mentioned that in the games you have the the ability to really anchor
Your own prices
But as we see more and more games of the same genre coming out with the same types of purchases going on
Do you think that's gonna put at risk that that like the competition can now anchor the price say of like your hero or something?
I think it may influence it for that first purchase.
And certainly I think we've seen it most in card games,
where cards are amongst the easiest things to sort of understand buying and to compare.
We'll see card games that come out that are pricing cards at more like $7 and $10,
and then there'll be the complaint, no, so Magic prices it at this, et cetera.
But those games still do well.
Essentially, what happens is then if you're price comparing,
you're already probably not loving the game.
and by the time that you have spent more time in it,
again, you value that card more than that other game.
I do think that it's important to keep prices,
there's sort of like a careful happy band
between high enough that you're not just
sort of giving away money because things are.
inelastic, but you also don't want to,
you never want the player to feel that they're being
taken advantage of or that they're being,
they're not getting good value.
And that's what you should always concentrate on
is that feeling of value and you probably want to keep
things more at like, you know, $15 or $20 to spend,
but you get a lot of stuff and you feel really great.
Like, to me, that's how it should be working.
Cool, thank you.
So lovely talk, thank you. I am curious, I suspect I know where you're headed with this, but your thoughts on the paid incentive advertising, such as some of the services that the mobile publisher I was with would use, and whether you think that's a good concept from the advertiser's standpoint as opposed from the company making revenue from it.
No, I think well executed, they're great.
I think it's important to design them in ways that they're not competing directly with what
you would actually spend in-app purchase on.
We've done some A-B tests and seen where
if we made our offers more prominent overall
and we'd see an increase in offer revenue
and then a total decrease.
But I don't think it has to be that way.
One great example is our most recent game,
Adventure Capitalist.
I don't know if you've played that game.
But most of the in-app purchases are sort of speed-ups of, you know, 3x permanent speed-ups.
But you can get a 2x 4-hour speed-up just by watching an ad.
And I go into that game and it's just part of sort of the optimization that I do every time is that I watch an ad.
I'm really happy to see it.
We get lots of complaints from players saying,
oh, my ads aren't working, because they really
like the system.
But at the same time, we're seeing really good results
on the in-app purchases.
So I think if designed well, they're very complimentary.
But it is important to think about the relative value
of one ad versus somebody spending $2 or $3.
Great, it's three o'clock, so I have to get down anyway.