My name is Whitney Clayton, and I'm the art director at Compulsion Games.
And my talk is about how we created the art direction for We Happy Few,
and how we realized this art direction with our procedural generation technology.
Uh-oh. Sorry.
Okay.
So, We Happy Few is a first-person roguelike survival game.
It's set in 1960s dystopian England,
and it's about this society,
the Society of Wellington Wells,
and they're addicted to this drug called joy.
And they take this drug in order to forget
this terrible thing they did during World War II,
but also to be happy all the time.
So you play a downer,
so somebody who has willingly gone off of your joy.
And as a downer, you're a threat to the society.
So your objective is to survive long enough to escape, but also to understand kind of
your role in the society and how it got to where it is.
We Happy Few happens to be procedural.
So for us, this means that each time you play the game,
the road layout is different, the streets are different,
and where the gameplay locations are all different.
But before I get into that, I'll just give you
a little background about myself.
Before I was an art director, I was a concept artist.
And before I was a concept artist, I was studying painting in university.
So, I like art and I don't like math.
And when the studio head asked me how I felt about doing a procedural game,
I was like, sounds great!
Because I had no idea what he was talking about.
And the whole thing has been way more challenging than I could have imagined.
But we've come a long way and it's been really exciting and interesting process.
So creating a rich and expressive art direction is challenging enough.
We have our own artistic rules to consider.
So design, composition, lighting, all that.
But with a procedural system, everything is a hundred times harder.
And that is because it puts constraints on the artist's tools.
So one of our biggest constraints is environmental composition.
So here you'll see...
A bunch of buildings lined up, but there's this big random gap
in between the buildings.
And if this was a handcrafted area,
we definitely wouldn't leave this gap there.
But this was a problem with the system,
and we had to live with this visually for a long time,
which was pretty painful, considering
that if we were building this by hand,
we would just close this gap.
It's also experimental, this technology.
So there are, sometimes it feels like it has a mind of its own.
So this was a bug that we had for a while where five buildings were showing up in a row.
And again, if we were hand crafting this space, we definitely wouldn't do this.
And it's not until we playtest the heck out of this game that we find issues like this.
But this is where we are now.
So it's taken a long time to get here,
both on the art and tech side, but we've learned a lot.
And it's really exciting to see it coming together.
So in this talk, I'm gonna go over pre-pre-production,
so how we kind of came up with the core themes
for this game and how this led to our choice in setting.
Pre-production, so how we took this setting
and created our own unique world from this.
and production, so how we realized this world
with the procedural generation system.
So very early on in the project,
there were a few key concepts we knew we wanted
for the next game.
These were kind of concepts that we would use
to build kind of the building blocks of our foundation.
So we knew we wanted to try to do a procedural game.
Our first game is called Contrast, and it was a
handcrafted game.
And after about two and a half years of production, we had a
game that was about four hours long, and players were just
blowing through it.
So we knew we wanted to make a larger, richer environment.
with more that would encourage exploration.
But we had the same size Indy team.
We also had some very strong tech minds on the team.
So we thought that if we could pull off procedural
generation, it would be worth the risk.
We knew we also wanted to try to do a survival game. It seemed to work well with the concept of
procedural generation because you die a lot. But also we just have a fondness for survival games.
We thought an interesting take on a survival game could be urban survival. So if you're
surviving in a city rather than in a wilderness setting. And this would lend itself to kind of
unique threats and challenges.
So if you're surviving in an urban environment, your
biggest threat would be the society itself.
So we thought it was really interesting, this idea that
you were kind of this sane outsider in this obscure
world where you have to learn the rules of this world in
order to blend in and conform to this society.
We also like the idea of, we also like the idea of, sorry,
my timer stopped working, so, of doing a dystopian alternate
history, so we love the idea of doing a dystopian, so where one
event changes the course of history and creates kind of a
parallel history.
with its own unique rules.
Doing a dystopia seemed exciting because it
would lend itself for us to be creative and kind of create
this fantasy world.
But we also like the idea of working from history.
I personally like this a lot because I
like building off of material from history.
I think it gives us kind of a lot of interesting material
to work off from.
But we didn't want to do a.
sort of bleak, authoritarian, dystopian,
one where people are wearing work suits and marching around
because this has been done before.
I also didn't want to necessarily be in a world
where it's very bleak and depressing.
So we thought it would be much more interesting to do
something more like Brave New World.
Maybe it's a society that's kind of done this to themselves.
It's kind of ambiguous whether it's a dystopia or a utopia.
And Brave New World is much more stylish than 1984.
This is what inspired the idea that maybe this society is
kind of repressed by its own happiness, which kind of led
to the idea of the mask.
So the mask is kind of one of our most iconic
elements for the game.
This was the first concept I did for the game.
I was really trying to get this feeling of somebody who's repressed by their own happiness
or maybe conforming to a world where happiness is very valuable.
So I was designing the mask to be kind of like
to look like the person's face, but it
pushes the corners of their mouth up into a smile.
And I was trying to get this kind of contrast
between the look in this person's eyes
and the smile on their face, and kind of give them
this sense of kind of obliviousness
or like running on autopilot.
But it turns out that this actually existed.
So in Budapest after World War I,
there were these people and they called themselves
the Society of Smiles.
And they made these super terrifying masks
to try to motivate each other to be happy.
And I have no idea what they were thinking
because these are horrifying.
And I think they're way less convincing than our masks.
But so it happened in real life, but we didn't know that.
So after deciding on these early concepts,
I knew we needed to kind of pull core themes
that we could use to inspire what our setting would be.
Doing this is important because it creates
a really clear foundation and something
that we can always go back and look at.
and refer to.
So these core themes were conformity.
So this is a place where everyone cares about fitting in
and adhering to social rules.
Paranoia and suspicion.
We wanted the player to be the only kind of sane outsider
in this suspiciously perfect place,
and to give you a sense of paranoia when you're playing
that you will be caught as that outsider.
And a feeling of suspicion from the people around you
that maybe you don't blend into this world,
or you're not part of this world.
Happiness, so this is a place that values happiness
above everything else.
and denial.
So their obsession with happiness
is causing their society to crumble apart.
And they're kind of in denial of the fact
that this is because of their own choices that they've made.
They're kind of being willfully oblivious of the fact
that this is a collapsing society.
So all of this led to Britain in the 60s.
This seemed to fit all of these settings pretty well.
It's a very kind of fun and iconic setting.
And I'll just tell you a little bit about how we came
to this conclusion.
So when I was thinking about a place that kind of values
appearance in society, I was reminded of this show
that I grew up watching called Keeping Up Appearances.
I don't know if anyone has seen this show.
But it's about.
a woman and her name is Hyacinth Bucket,
but she tells everyone it's Bouquet.
And she's from a lower working class family,
but she lives in this upper middle class neighborhood
and she's determined to prove to her neighbors
that she's part of the upper middle class.
So it's all about rules and etiquette
and appearance in society.
So this was actually the first inspiration for the setting.
So people are like, oh, were you inspired by Bioshock?
That was actually this show.
And then I was reminded of Hot Fuzz.
So we knew we wanted you to be this kind of sane outsider in this suspiciously perfect place.
And that's pretty much exactly what this movie is about.
So it's about this cop and he goes to this very quaint, perfect English town
and people are disappearing and he starts to wonder what's going on
and then they become suspicious of him figuring it out.
And this idea of kind of a village or a small English town that's perfect but it has
like a deep secret.
This is a pretty common theme in British media, so the
prisoner is another example.
And that's something we've pulled from a lot.
There's also an episode of The Avengers that
touches on this subject.
So Britain seems like a good choice.
So now we have to pick a decade.
And if we're going to choose a decade that symbolizes
happiness, the 60s is an obvious choice.
So Winston Churchill had died, and he had marked the end of
this kind of war-torn area that was ruled by the upper
class, and Harold Wilson became prime minister.
And he was all about change and reform and progress.
And so there were a lot of great social reforms that
happened at this time.
But the kind of Austin Powers swinging 60s that we think of
was really only in a small part of London called
Carnaby Street.
So England wanted to kind of project this idea that that's what England was about,
but really most of England was stuck in the 50s.
However, because of this kind of commercialization of pop culture, such as the Beatles,
there was this social shift in values where people all of a sudden started
caring about image and fashion and hedonism more than they had before.
And then modernism, which is kind of the key aesthetic movement of the 50s and 60s.
And we like the idea that our society is kind of rejecting their history
and rejecting their environment for this kind of delusional idea of their utopia.
And that's very similar to the modernist movement, which
was kind of a rejection of history and the environment
for this fantastical vision of the future.
And this was inspired by technological progress
and affected everything from design and fashion.
But one of the most obvious examples
is brutalist architecture.
So you had kind of, um.
architects plowing down historic town centers
and building these giant space age buildings, right,
surrounded by old Tudor buildings.
And they weren't designed to help people
or to be comfortable, but under this kind of fantasy
that houses are machines for living in.
So it's very kind of delusional idea
of what the future should be
that's very disconnected from reality.
So this seemed to fit the dystopia
that we wanted to explore.
So, 60s in England seems like a good choice.
At this point, we all start brainstorming.
So our narrative director goes off and crafts this very
elaborate back story of what our world's going to be.
The designers start thinking of mechanics.
The programmers start working on the generation system.
And I started concepting.
So this was the first concept I did for the game.
And for based off of these, the first kind of environmental concept.
And I was really trying to get this feeling of an old world England
with this positive regime of happiness blatantly kind of layered on top of it.
So.
They have these old crumbly Tudor buildings,
which left these kind of nice canvases
where people could have painted colors on them.
They painted the roads.
They have kind of modern sleek elements
like the tube televisions lying in front of them,
creating this really nice contrast.
And then you have like the traditional English things
like the bunting and the awnings.
And then I wanted the sky to be kind of this sickly, off
pudding green to kind of make it feel a bit uneasy.
And then our tech director and I also were doing a lot of
research on road planning and layout and how the generation
system should try to mimic a real village or city.
We knew we wanted a couple different types of
environments in this world.
We researched London and how that's laid out,
and British villages, which really have no logic
or patterns or anything.
So we kind of have these building blocks.
Now we, sorry.
So now we need to kind of establish the building blocks
as to what makes our own world unique
from England in the 60s.
So one of the things that in our art direction we always think about is this idea of retrofuturism.
So I talked a lot about modernism.
But because this is a dystopia and it's a fantasy,
modernism isn't really enough.
So I think of retrofuturism as kind of an extension of that.
So we like this idea that the society is running out
of resources, but they've spent their money
on this kind of expensive, fancy, useless gadgets
that are very much a fantasy.
So I did a lot of research on old kind of
retrofuturistic designs, and they very much are based on a
fantasy even in their designs.
So they have no visible parts, sleek curves in plastic.
So this was a lot of fun to research.
And this is an example of one of our pieces of retro technology.
It's called the compliment machine.
And its only purpose is really to compliment people
and to make them feel good about themselves.
So again, kind of simple shapes, clean plastic, black seams.
It's very kind of sophisticated, but totally useless.
Another important thing that we always think about
with the art direction is style.
So what I mean by style is like lighting, shapes,
color, composition, design,
and how that affects the kind of meaning of the environment
and the type of environment that you're in.
So we have kind of two main worlds
that maybe you guys know from either playing the game
or seeing trailers.
We have the garden district and the village,
and the garden district is kind of this historic area
that has been neglected since the war,
and it's totally bombed out.
And this is where people who've had a bad reaction to the drug
get ostracized.
So it's this very kind of depressing area full of people
who are not stable.
And it's war-torn.
But it also represents real history.
So it's kind of the honest area.
So it was important to me that while this area is kind of sad
and tragic, it's also kind of beautiful and
welcoming and organic.
And then on the other side, you have the modern area that
people of Wellington Wells live in.
This is like a location from that area in a bridge.
And it's very happy and stylish, but it's
very kind of cold and disconnected
and almost kind of off-putting with how kind
of shiny and artificial it is.
Here's another example from the Garan District.
This is a hermit house.
And again, it's very dilapidated and wonky.
This guy believes he's a secret agent
living in this tree house.
But it's also organic, and it's cozy.
And because it's England, and there's rain all the time,
there's flowers everywhere.
And this is from the, maybe you guys have seen this
from the intro, this is the office.
And this kind of symbolizes the epitome
of society and bureaucracy.
So very stylish, but very clean and slick
and artificial and cold.
This also applies to character design.
So on one side you see a wastrel.
So this is somebody who had a bad reaction to joy
and has been kicked out of the village.
you know, she's mentally unhinged,
but you kind of feel for her.
She's a real person.
And then the other side is a welly,
so somebody who wears the masks and takes the drugs,
and she's very vacant and frightening.
So style also applies to lighting.
So in the game, you can take joy, which is the drug that
everyone takes.
And you can see the world for how they see it.
So it was really important to push the contrast between the
world off of joy and on joy.
So off of joy, it's England.
It's cloudy and rainy and overcast.
But then on joy, it's clear and bright and sunny.
And the idea is that when you take joy, you blend into the
society a bit more, because you feel like how everyone
else feels.
But you can also kind of empathize
with why the society is addicted to this drug.
So, another thing that we always think about is environmental storytelling.
So, this is storytelling through the world and not through dialogue.
It's been a bit tricky to figure out what reads.
We're trying to tell the story of our own specific world.
We want to be clear, but not too hand-holdy and not too on the nose.
So, this is an example of a statue in the game.
It's the statue of happiness, clearly selling the idea that that's what this place cares
about over everything.
Back to brutalism.
So we do use brutalism in the game, but mostly for these
kind of checkpoint bridges between areas.
So I talked about brutalism being this rejection of
history for the future.
And in our game, it literally separates the historic area
from the modern world.
So it's very symbolic.
And it prevents people from crossing
between those two areas.
So the area that's been refurbished is mostly still
full of old architecture, but they use new modern elements
and they layer that on top.
So we do a lot with signage, kind of motivational signage
to spell out the regime.
So we have these kind of plexiglass posters everywhere
to kind of keep people perked up.
And then we have Uncle Jack.
And he's kind of the local celebrity of Wellington Wells.
And he was inspired by BBC news anchors.
So before 1964, there was really only one channel,
and that was the BBC.
And he's the only channel of Wellington Wells.
And he's an entertainer, a news anchor.
And his primary goal is to keep everyone motivated,
keep them moving on.
But if you listen closely to what he talks about,
you can learn a lot about the history.
And he was a real actor that we filmed on a set.
And that was really, really exciting and
really interesting.
And we were a little worried about how that would blend
into the world.
But because we put all these effects and film grains on him
and make it black and white, and because we're using Unreal
and we can get really high fidelity, it actually doesn't
clash as much as we thought it might, doing this kind of
mixed media thing.
So this has been really, really fun working with an actor.
So now we have our world of Wellington Wells, and we have
to realize this with our procedural
generation technology.
So the first thing we had to think about was what we wanted
to make procedural and what we didn't want to make procedural.
So we had to be really critical of this, because it
doesn't benefit everything if everything is procedural.
So the things that we decided to make procedural.
Oops, sorry.
Ah.
Oops.
So the things we decided to make procedural were like the
road layouts, the houses, where the houses fall on the
streets, the island shape, the island size, the decals, the
props on the sides of buildings.
All of this was done with the intention that if we can pull
this off, it will encourage exploration and make the world
feel different every time you play it.
And then there were things we chose to not make procedural.
So interiors to buildings, well, the buildings themselves,
parks, plazas, the lighting, props.
None of this seemed to be beneficial to be procedural.
By doing this, it would give full control
to the artists and designers,
and we wouldn't have to be working around this system.
We actually did try to make interiors procedural,
but it was just too much of a headache for everybody,
and it wasn't giving us any kind of visual benefit.
And the designers were going nuts with that.
So this is an example of our street, which is procedural.
So how this works is that the artists build plots and assets.
And if it's a road tile, they give this to the many things
they give to the programmers, which they implement.
Or if it's kind of a plot or a
gameplay or narrative area, that goes to the LDs before
it's implemented.
So artists create all the assets, and then it gets laid
out in the system.
And a really oversimplified way of describing how it
works is that it lays out the road map, and then it puts
kind of the key narrative and gameplay locations that we
know we need on that road map in the world.
And then it fills out the space in between, and then it
layers over that the decals and assets with our decorator.
And
The programmers have created tools for the artists, so the
artists can control the decorator and the
dispersion of props.
So we can go in and control things like how high up the
signs are on the buildings, how frequently they show up,
where the decals and puddles fall on the streets, how far
away the mailboxes are from the road.
So we do have control over those kind of elements.
And then this is an example of a handcrafted space.
So these are interiors from our village.
We tried to push composition and push
all of our artistic tools in these spaces
and also push narrative and design and everything
we have control over.
So here we were really trying to get
across the strong kind of mid-century,
modern, stylish interior.
And we can kind of go crazy with lighting as well.
So now I'll just give you a really rough timeline for how we
created the village area with the procedural system.
So we started with the concept.
So here's the concept that I showed you earlier.
This is based off of this area I had visited as a kid called
the Shambles in York.
It's full of these very old Tudor buildings with lots of
character, and we thought that this would be a very iconic
British type of architecture to try to build.
And then we do layout research to figure out.
how these places should get laid out and what kind of
roadmap this should be.
And then our tech director does crazy super magic that I
cannot describe to you at all how that works, because I'm on
the art side.
And unfortunately, he's not talking here.
But it is very complicated.
And it works.
So this was really, really exciting.
So we made these temporary buildings that are very simple,
but we put them into the system, and our tech director
was able to get curves in the street, and it actually feels
like an actual English village.
So this was what was reassuring to the fact that we
can actually make this world with this system.
So then we had to make the real buildings that we would use.
So I went ahead and designed what we call filler buildings.
So these are facade buildings.
They're just like blocks.
And we use these to bridge between interactive gameplay
and narrative buildings.
So the point of these buildings is that they are
kind of forgettable without being ugly, because we don't
want them to detract from where you need to go as a player.
So I made them very flat and very muted.
But we put them in the world, we built them, and they were just like way too flat and ugly
and killed any sense of composition in the space.
And then we added our gloomy overcast lighting and it became this like really yucky, drab,
flat place.
But we got the decorator system working, so you can see there is a tree in the middle
of the street.
But yeah, we had to do something about these buildings.
They were just too boring.
And we also didn't know which percentage of the world
they would take up.
So this was in the beginning of the project.
And we didn't know how many design locations
we would have in this world.
But we kept them for a while.
And we added atmosphere to see if that would kind of fix it.
But now it's feeling very sickly green.
So not only is there no composition,
but it's very kind of sickly looking.
But we were able to get the decorator to spawn these
buntings going across the different buildings and kind
of arrange the props in a way that makes sense.
So it's starting to feel a little bit better in that
sense.
So we dialed back on the sickly green and made it a bit
more clear and blue.
But now it was really contrasting with the joy
mechanic, or sorry, it wasn't contrasting enough with the
joy mechanic.
So when you take joy, you wouldn't really notice it
because you're already in this blue sky.
But then we got a height variation.
So this was really cool.
Having height variation really helped with the feeling of
composition.
But then we were getting issues where you have two
buildings showing up next to each other and these kind of
weird, awkward.
a staggering of buildings that feels very unnatural.
And this was the worst, these giant random gaps everywhere
that are totally not in the real world.
And this is for the very obvious reason
that we have square buildings fitting into curved roads.
So they would create these negative spaces
that were very unnatural.
we had to re-look at how we did the filler buildings, which
is great, because it gave me an excuse to redesign them.
So we created what we call our filler system, which is
creating different buildings of various widths that, with a
high enough texture resolution, they would deform and kind of
squish to fill the gaps.
So I went ahead and designed some new filler buildings.
And here I was really trying to push.
the silhouette in the buildings, and to see how interesting we
could make them before they detract from the gameplay
spaces.
And then our environment artist went ahead and built them
and gave them.
We always tried to push for this kind of stylized realism.
It's very much inspired by stop motion.
So he gave it this really great kind of spindly quality.
So they have way more character than they had before.
And then we put them in.
And
It works and this is really, really great.
So now it actually feels like a real English village and we
don't have these weird unnatural gaps everywhere.
We tried to tweak the lighting to be a little less sickly, but
it's still pretty gloomy.
And for some reason, our decorators stopped working.
So there's really nothing in the street anymore.
But the fillers are working and this was really great.
And so we tweaked the lighting to be a bit cooler, a little
more purple.
And here you can see that the fillers are not detracting
from the gameplay spaces that you need to go to.
So this was cool.
We learned that you can push silhouette and shape, but as
long as you don't put lights on it or bold colors, it won't
detract from the gameplay spaces as long as there's
enough glowing lights on those spaces.
But then the height variation was causing all these bugs,
which was bad because we were trying to get the build stable
for early access.
So we had to dial back on this because we just couldn't have
these issues in the build for our early access release.
And then the curves in the streets were creating this
problem where filler buildings were eating.
other buildings.
So we also had to dial back on the curves.
So now we're kind of back to flat buildings on a grid,
which is bad, because we never wanted that.
So what did we do to try to make this a little more interesting?
We put a lot of love and energy into the places that we could control, so our kind of custom plots like parks.
So this is an example of a place that we have control over.
So we pushed the lighting and the composition and the story in these kind of areas. So in this park there is these
toys that you can go play on and if you play on them you can kind of blend in
temporarily if you have a mob on you.
And then we added vistas.
So I know these are quite simple vistas,
but in England, vistas are very kind of low and rolling.
So this would help a lot
with bringing composition to the space.
But we put them too close to the world,
and they totally gobbled up the world.
So I came into work one morning and played the build,
and the vistas were just engulfing the whole world,
which was really startling.
But we moved them back and they're feeling good.
And we tweaked the lighting to be a little more purple,
which was nice because it still felt like overcast
and didn't detract from joy,
but wasn't completely miserable to play in.
We added coasts.
We did a lot of research on English coasts
and what those look like.
And we added foliage.
And now it's finally coming together.
And the artists are putting lots of love
into gameplay spaces and really...
kind of going nuts in them, which is great.
But then we get this bug where decals or props are blocking
gameplay spaces so you can't actually access them.
So this is an example of another kind of unpredictable
bug that would show up.
And unless we play test the crap out of this game, we
just miss this stuff.
But we created a rule to prevent this from happening.
So now this doesn't happen so much.
And then to add composition, we just had to think a lot
about how we could kind of block the line of sight.
So we put these big arches in that go over the streets.
And that really, really helped kind of fill out the street.
And the more kind of the props we added
and the more things we used to block the line of sight,
the more kind of rich and dynamic the world felt.
So this is where we are now.
So it's feeling good.
The architecture is working.
The streets feel alive.
But we don't have height variation.
We don't have curves.
So what is the next step?
well, to bring back height variation and curves.
But we also want to create specific sections of areas.
So in order to create more variation in the world,
instead of everything being very homogenous,
we would like to try to have specific commercial streets,
residential streets.
And in order to do that, we need to create rules.
So this is an example of a concept I would do
to give to our programmers, to be like,
can we...
Can we create these different areas and can we use these
types of rules to kind of...
dictate what these areas will be like.
So if we have commercial streets, maybe the buildings
are all three to four stories tall, and they have dense
alleyways behind them.
If we have residential streets, maybe the buildings
are all one to two story high, and there's always a garden
behind them, separated by a path, and another garden.
So we kind of have to reverse engineer the way a village
looks and create a bunch of rules.
But we're working on this, and this is the plan.
And I think this will really help give a sense of realism
and variation to the world.
And then on a macro level, we would like to.
create variation with how the entire world is designed.
So right now, the world is just these kind of flat little
crackers all separated by bridges.
And we would love there to be different types of land
formations in between these areas.
Maybe the areas are separated by
pinch points instead of bridges, maybe they're in valleys,
maybe they're kind of on top of mountains.
And if we're able to add this kind of variation to the world,
then it will really feel like a different place
each time you play.
So this is another thing we're working on.
So that's it.
Thanks for coming.
I hope you learned a lot.
Does anyone have questions?
I don't know how much time we have because my timer didn't
work.
Nobody?
OK.
Thank you very much.