ready? Let's do this. Okay. So before we get started, I have to do the essentials. Turn off
noise makers. Especially beepers. If you have one of those, just chuck it outside. Because
that is just a problem. Anyways, you'll also be getting evals at the end. Excellent is
recommended. Good is okay. But definitely excellent is what we ask you to give.
So let me introduce myself first.
I'm Grant Schonkweiler, as you can see,
commander in Schonk at Schonk Ventures,
because when you start your own company,
you can make up your title, so that's pretty cool.
I'll be your moderator and timekeeper,
which you don't have to worry about the timekeeper,
that's more for them.
Before Garth gets started here, though,
I wanted to introduce the talk.
And it is a talk, it kind of looks like a panel,
kind of looks like micro talks, whatever,
but really, it's one cohesive story
told by four different people,
these amazing people right here.
And you may have read this, you may have seen this
in the guide or hopefully you read it,
that this is more about the feel portion of being a producer.
You know, we all know about Agile and Scrum
and Kanban and all those things,
but what we wanted to talk about is the feel portion,
the soft skills of being a producer,
the one-on-one relationships that you have
with the people on your team.
So that's what we're gonna get into today.
Oops.
Go slide.
This is that awkward part?
Okay, so, but we are producers, right?
So we need to have some sort of agenda for our meeting,
I mean, talk today.
So Garth's gonna come up first.
He's gonna talk about For the Love of the Video Game.
Oxana will then talk about Building Team Culture.
Chuck Charles will talk about creating thriving teams,
and then Brian will close us out
with conflict in the workplace.
So yeah, I'm gonna introduce everybody,
and then get ready, there's an interactive portion of this.
So don't fall asleep, I know it's Thursday.
Just stay ready.
So let me introduce Garth first.
He is a senior producer at Fraxis Games, overseeing the XCOM franchise since 2010.
He began his career in design on XCOM Enemy Unknown in an IGF student prototype called
Winds of Orbis.
In a previous life, he was a VP at a large financial institution before pursuing his
Masters of Entertainment Technology at Carnegie Mellon.
Garth was instrumental in coming up with the format and session idea for this a few years
ago but wasn't able to make it because he's working on a little game called XCOM 2.
So we're super happy to have him here this year.
Alright Garth, take it away.
So yes, we're gonna talk about trust mechanics.
I'm very excited to be here today to talk about
the harder part of our job, which is the soft skills.
So, this will not be a talk about Agile, Waterfall,
Scrum, Kanban, Lean, Six Sigma,
or any other hybrid approach that I'm sure you guys
are using in some form on your projects right now.
But there is no silver bullet,
as evidenced by our repeated post-mortem mistakes
that we all share with each other.
So, process is important, I wanna make that clear.
But what if when it comes to enabling a culture for a team to find success,
we've been focusing a little bit too much on the wrong area?
This is a quote from Pixar president Ed Catmull.
He's created a few hits that I'm sure you guys are aware of from his book, Creativity Inc.
You can't manage what you can't measure as a maxim that is taught and believed by many
in both the business and education sectors.
But in fact, the phrase is ridiculous.
Something said by people who are unaware of how much is hidden.
A large portion of what we manage can't be measured, and not realizing this has unintended
consequences."
Now, I love this quote, but I would not recommend you guys bringing this to your boss if you
need more time on your project.
But there's a snippet in this quote that is critical.
It's being unaware of how much is hidden.
So after choosing a process that makes sense for your team, then the trickier part begins.
You have to have an acute awareness of your team's dynamics to empower them to uncover the hidden
within this vast dark cave when you start your project.
Usually the magic in a project is in all the nooks and crannies and you have to help enable them to find a light.
So, how do we do it?
I have no idea on XCOM. I really don't.
But I can give you some two, with two very simple key takeaways that stayed true throughout XCOM.
And also...
Keeping them upheld throughout the project as well is part of it.
And those two keys are trust and love.
Now, you guys all came to the video game industry probably because you have your own love story
with this awesome interactive medium when you were young.
So that to me is the easier part.
But the trust is more what I wanted to focus on.
And when I was sort of given the opportunity
to go from level design and sort of this
junior production role into lead producer,
the very first thing I wanted to do
was sit down with each of the leads
and ask them simply, how can I make your job easier?
I didn't want to prescribe anything to them.
And frankly, I couldn't, because I wanted to learn
from these very awesome senior guys.
But I think that helped set the tone with them
that this is an environment where I want to support you.
And I want to have an ongoing relationship
with you guys to have an environment
where we can find success.
together. So the trust mechanics are not something that I knew about when I
started out on this franchise back in 2009, but looking back in it, sort of in
retrospect, our process has changed a lot. Those process elements that I spouted
off at the beginning of this, we've tried little tidbits of each of those, we've
tried, you know, poker planning and agile fall and anything you can think of, and
we're still experimenting today. That's always going to change as you talk to
your team.
But there's a few elements that have stayed true
throughout XCOM's production.
And I sort of see this as a machination.
These are gears and cogs that work together
in the different elements.
You want to love the vision.
love your support structure, and hear your community.
So we'll talk about each one of these a little bit.
If you do these things, I think success will follow.
Of course you need individual hard work,
but these are the dynamics holding the team together.
So trust mechanic number one, love the vision.
You guys all know what a vision is.
You must have a vision.
Our vision, like most, took.
some time to find.
This is our shell screen, I believe in 2007, 2008,
with one of our early gameplay prototypes.
And if you guys went to my art director's talk
on Monday, Greg Furch, he did a really, really great
deep dive on this initiative that he and the lead designer
worked with 10 artists before they had any engineers
to sort of find what the gameplay
of XCOM Enemy Unknown would be.
Greg, I apologize for this screenshot if you're here.
I didn't get that approved by you, but I'm trying to make a point that the vision can
be murky up front sometimes.
If you look on paper, this looked like a really poor production initiative.
We're sinking dozens of man months into something that we know is not going to ship.
But what in fact it allowed them to do was to make mistakes early and to uncover the hidden,
to start finding things.
So the fog of war change, the visibility system, the camera logic,
how the soldiers worked with the UI and the action points,
all of these things were found in a relatively cost-effective way up front
that would have been catastrophic on the back end.
And it allowed the team to sort of find their way.
As we rolled on into production,
these are two screenshots of our glam cams.
And we took elements from that gameplay pre-visualization
and actually executed on them in the game.
You would think once that vision starts getting found,
then intuitively it's easy to maintain,
but you always have to keep that trust
between disciplines going,
because you're gonna have some problems
when actual implementation happens,
where it's not as beautiful as that gameplay previs.
And the rubber met the road quite a bit.
We often fell back on a studio-wide mantra when we were having conflict between disciplines that,
you know, I say conflict, but they worked so well together because they understood what was driving our community.
At Firaxis, for all our projects, we think gameplay first, or gameplay experience first.
pillars on XCOM 2 that Greg and our team drove was making a strategy game feel
more action-oriented, but when that presentation layer started stomping on
the gameplay mechanics and the understandability of the depth of our
mechanics and the interesting decisions and what was happening, which is what our
community wants, then he was able to work with design and find that happy middle ground.
So the second mechanic is a multi-cog approach.
This is love your support structure.
And I say support structure because you have your team,
which everyone knows about,
but then you also have your external partners.
And that can be an investor, that can be a publisher.
And I think it can really be understated
that you want to have a very strong relationship
with the people funding your vision.
We're very lucky to have a relationship with 2K Games,
and it started out on an excellent footing
because they believed in a turn-based strategy game
and giving it AAA support.
which is critical.
And then day to day, we have had a completely
transparent relationship with them
when design changes are happening,
when they need to see where we're at with the schedule.
I often hear stories from colleagues in the industry
where their instinct is to hide information
from an external partner.
And they're doing that to protect the team,
but to me that's indicative of a longer term problem
where you want to have an open, transparent relationship
and make them understand the reality of game development
and 2K has been phenomenal with that.
So the next cog is your team.
And this can be sort of its own presentation,
but we don't have a ton of time.
So these are the guys and gals that execute on the vision.
And I wanted to just show a few pictures.
Before I joined for Access, I was at Carnegie Mellon,
like Grant said.
And our advisor, Jesse Schell, would often
say the success of a student project
could be reflected in their joy and their interaction
in a candid photo.
He said there was a direct correlation between that
and then a project team that looked like they
didn't want to work together.
We made this roughshod.
Terrible student prototype that blossomed into an IGF winner and you can see we really enjoy working together
We still like go to this picture every year and talk about hey
We need to reunite
There was a lot of trust and love between us and we wanted to get our get each other's backs
We were terrified of letting each other down
And I'm lucky to sort of have that microcosm from CMU
and see that blown to a studio-wide culture at Firaxis,
where every single project there is this high standard,
and we have teammates that don't want to let each other down.
These are pictures from the team back in the mid-2000s,
and all these folks are still with the company.
I think we have over a 60 percent attrition rate
on the XCOM team from one inception over a decade ago,
which is great in any industry, let alone game development,
and it's really indicative of the culture that we have there.
Sometimes conflict happens, but hey.
You gotta tough love your teammates once in a while.
So not everything is always gonna be hunky-dory.
Of course, you'll have team members get lost,
and they'll lose sight of the vision,
and it's the producer's job to champion that
and get them back on track.
That happened often on Enemy Unknown,
and we did some non-publisher-driven milestones
to get levels back on track,
and then we parlayed concepts like that into XCOM 2
with this idea of goalposts.
It's essentially epics in producer speak,
but what we did was we made them
very, very visible and transparent.
We laid out over the course.
sorry about that, of multiple years on our War Room whiteboard
what the content team was going to drive towards.
And not only did they hit it, but they exceeded it.
We actually shipped an entirely new environment set
than what we had planned.
And we got a lot of feedback from them after the fact
that they liked how visible these were
and that these were not buried away in some backlog
that only a few producers would see.
So it was really a good initiative.
It didn't work as well for design and tech
because the acceptance criteria there is a lot more murky
and nebulous and prone to change.
So we had one-off design cabals with them
to help them find their way,
to have more actionable items quicker,
and then we would grow those into playthroughs,
which I would highly recommend using.
You have to use them conservatively, though,
because there's key times in the schedule where it's...
It's appropriate to use them as all the systems are converging and all the content's coming in.
It's going to be buggy and messy as hell up front.
And you want that team to feel a little bit of that pain, so then you can see day over day,
it improves and you guys sort of uncover the hidden together and find the fun.
Okay, I'm gonna make this a little bit shorter,
but this is a topic I'm really passionate about.
Crunch is big in the industry as producers
and the owners of the time were responsible
for the outcome of that if you do crunch.
Xcom put in a lot of extra hours,
and I'm not gonna say we didn't crunch,
but we did want to respect what drives others.
I've talked a lot about vision, about vision execution,
and I think those are the most important thing,
but they shouldn't come at the cost
of spitting your team out for dead.
You have to be aware of the team health
and figure out how to manage that.
We had some ways of doing that.
I'll be happy to talk about with people afterwards
where we had sort of a tailored extra hour approach
where we got the buy-in from individuals
after we balance loaded.
We made them aware of the why we were asking for more work
and managed it that way.
So the last trust mechanic is community,
and community is everything.
They're your pillar beneficiary,
the recipient of everything that you've worked to build,
and you want to maintain a relationship with them
after you ship, especially in this day and age now, too,
where there's more ways to communicate with them.
You want that community to grow.
But if you notice, I say hear your community and not listen to your community.
It's very easy to design by community.
And we want that information.
After Enemy Unknown, we actually aggregated all of their feedback that was trending on
the top forums and the top reviews.
And we made design aware of that feedback, but it did not drive our design pillars for
XCOM 2.
It was just part of the informational process.
So, these are XCOM's trust mechanics.
Love the vision, love your support structure,
and hear your community.
These are ultimately what allowed us to light up our cave
with a thousand bonfires.
How will you light yours?
Thank you.
Thank you, Garth.
All right, so we're gonna do something
that may be a little awkward for some of you.
This comes from Scott Crabtree.
By the way, he has a talk tomorrow at three o'clock.
I recommend you go to, because he is amazing.
Nice plug.
Okay, so if you're willing and able, please stand up.
That's now.
This is the part where you stand up.
I know it's Thursday.
If this was Friday, I would not ask you to stand up.
Find your nearest partner and talk for 30 seconds each
about what you just learned from Garth's talk.
That was excellent.
Thanks man.
Let's do the thing with your hands where you're talking.
Last year the photographer came in during this part and we got amazing pictures because
we're all like...
Blah blah blah.
Alright, alright, alright, alright.
Everyone sit back down.
Don't worry, don't worry.
Stop talking.
You in the back.
Time's up.
Don't worry.
You'll get to talk to each other more, I promise.
I promise.
And now you have new friends.
You can go to the bar later and talk about this even more.
I promise there will be more time to talk.
But next up, we have Oksana.
She's going to talk to you about.
Oh, that was the wrong thing to say.
Anyways, she is the development director
at Riot Games, heading up the platform group.
She has 10 years of experience in the industry
as an engineer, and five years in production,
so she made a pretty cool switch, so Oksana.
Hi guys.
Hello.
Thank you.
Hi.
How awesome, I love this.
All right, so I'll be talking about
high performance team culture,
and I'll give you four tips today.
These are the tips that actually come from
my own experience, something that worked for me in the past.
I find those to be very easy to understand,
but very effective.
And so I'll jump right in.
And the first tip, the first tip of the day
is start with the why.
When we talk about high performance on teams,
we usually talk about motivation.
So what drives motivation?
What drives people to perform highly?
And it's an interesting question.
I remember when I was interviewing at Microsoft
about like five years ago, I think,
the interviewer asked me,
like how do you motivate teams through crunch time?
And I was just switching to production at the time
and I thought about it and I'm like,
well, I buy pizza and donuts
and I hope they feel better about it.
So my interview didn't go well.
But my thinking evolved since then,
and so I read the book by Daniel Pink about drive.
And in that book he says there are three primary motivators,
two primary drivers for motivation.
And it's purpose, autonomy, and mastery.
Purpose, autonomy, and mastery.
And so the sense of purpose
is probably the strongest way to motivate people.
And the way I mean this is when you have a team comprised of individuals whose sense
of their own internal purpose is aligned with your why for the team, it's a very powerful
combination.
I'll give you an example of how this works on my team.
I'm heading a platform team.
And we're doing stuff that's generally
considered not very sexy.
I personally think it's sexy.
But it's like installers, patchers, servers,
localization, all this stuff that is not the actual game
development.
And so when I try to motivate people to work on my team,
it sometimes is hard.
But I have this guy on my team, his name is Michael.
And I talk to him about why he works on my team
and he gave me this story.
He actually used to be a teacher
and he one day noticed a kid in his class.
The kid was like super unhappy, he was very shy, very...
Like, nobody would even talk to the kid.
And Michael decided to help him.
So he sat down with the kid, and for the next couple of
weeks, he showed him how to make a game.
So they made this little game together.
And then this kid brought it and showed it to the classmates.
Overnight, he became from like a total pariah, somebody who nobody would even talk to,
to the most popular kid in the class.
And so Michael changed this kid's life by helping him with making this game.
And so when Michael works on a platform team,
he actually does that for other people,
help them focus on building the game and creative side of it
by taking all of this other stuff away.
And he does that because it aligns
with his own sense of purpose, what gives him fulfillment.
So I don't have to buy him donuts
to convince him to go and work hard on my team.
He does that because he wants to.
So that's the tip number one, start with the why.
Make sure you have very clearly articulated why
for your team, but then make sure that your people
on your team actually align with that sense of why.
So that's number one.
Number two, define success.
A while back my boss gave me a book,
it was called something like On Leadership,
How to Build Successful Organizations,
and it was written by this guy.
How many of you know who this guy is?
Okay, a few.
So this is a basketball coach.
At the time I looked at the book and I'm like,
I don't wanna read this, I'm not into sports,
like why would I even read this?
And so I looked him up.
So this is Coach Wooden of UCLA Basketball.
And this guy, his team won 88.
consecutive games, 88 in a row.
So it's win after win after win after win,
continuously, nonstop.
He won 10 national championships in 12 years,
with a record seven in a row.
Previous record is two in a row.
So if anyone knows about performance, is this guy.
And so, I'm like, okay, I'm gonna read this book.
And in this book, he defines success like this.
So I'm gonna read it, because it's very important.
I know you all can read, but I'm gonna read it anyways.
Success is peace of mind, which is a direct result
of self-satisfaction in knowing you did your best
to become the best you're capable of becoming.
So, understanding this had a profound effect
on how I motivate my teams,
and how I set the goals for them.
it's very easy to set the goals that are like external KPIs
or metrics or targets.
You know, your game must perform to certain Metacritic score
or you must ship by certain date.
When you motivate people by those external kind of outcomes,
they don't necessarily have control over that.
And so it may drive like wrong kind of behaviors.
I don't know if you guys know about,
Wells Fargo recently fired like 5,000 people
because they were creating all these shadow accounts
because their KPI was...
how many accounts they sell in a given time frame.
So you don't want that kind of behavior.
What you want is your teams to continuously
and relentlessly compete against themselves.
One of the probably most weird conversations
I had at Riot when I joined,
when we were talking about releasing some feature,
And I said, well, we should look up
how the competitors do it.
And the guys look at me like, competitors?
We don't compete against people.
We're actually focusing on trying to do the best thing
for the player right now.
And so that just blew my mind.
But that's a really good way to motivate teams
to focus on continuously improving
and competing against themselves.
And so my tip number two.
Tip number three, we talked a little bit about trust.
We all know that there is no high performance
without trust, right?
And in fact, Patrick Linceoni, in his book,
The Five Dysfunctions of a Team,
says that absence of trust is probably the most foundational,
the most common dysfunction on team.
By the way, if you haven't read this book,
please go read it.
It's a foundational must read for every producer out there.
But building trust, it's easy to say,
of course we've gotta build trust,
but what does it mean?
It's a hard thing to do.
And I'm here to tell you it's not a hard thing to do.
I'm an engineer, I love formulas.
I'm gonna give you a super simple formula
to build trust on a team.
You ready?
Yes?
Yes, okay.
There you go.
Done, boom.
So, trust equation.
Trust is credibility, reliability,
intimacy over self-orientation.
Credibility is you have the experience
and the knowledge about what you're talking about,
so I can trust you on a subject.
Reliability is I can trust you
to do what you say you're going to do.
Intimacy is I can trust you with my secrets
and that you're not gonna tell somebody else
about these secrets,
or you're going to kind of use them against me.
But all of that is charmed by self-orientation.
If I for a second believe.
that you're acting in your own interest and not in mine.
I will not trust you, no matter how credible,
how reliable, or how trustworthy you are.
I will not trust you.
And this works, this is a super powerful formula
that works from a team, individual level,
all the way to organizations.
On a team level, it works like this, it looks like this.
An engineer goes, hey, I really like this system.
I really love this system and I wanna work on this,
but my team needs me to focus here.
So I'm going to put this down, my pet project, my love child,
and I'm going to focus on what the team needs me to do right now.
And so he's sacrificing his own self-interest for the interest of the team.
And then when other people see that, they start doing the same thing,
and the next thing you know, magic happens.
And the same thing works all the way
to an organizational level.
So at Riot, we made this our fundamental principle.
The mission of the entire company
is to aspire to be the most player-focused company
in the world.
And that means that we have players' trust
because no matter mistakes,
and we make a lot of mistakes,
but the mistakes we make, players know and forgive us
because they think and they know
that we have their interests at heart first and foremost.
And it has to be genuine too.
So that was my tip number three.
My tip number four, and the final tip,
is distort reality just a little bit.
What does this mean?
You, you know this guy is pretty famous
for distortion of reality.
But what I mean here is it's going back
to that sense of trust.
It's when you walk on the team and you want to build this high performance culture, you don't go and tell them
Hey guys, we're gonna be high performing team. So let's all focus and do this instead
What you want to do is you want to act and talk as if they're already there
You pretend, but then you believe in your mind deeply
that your people are the best people you have,
that they're bright, that they're brilliant,
and they can and will get there.
And then you just talk to them that way.
There's this very funny kind of experiment that was done.
I was really surprised by the outcomes of this.
So they took a set of rats, same kind of rats,
and they separated it into two sets.
And they gave one set to one set of experimenters
and the other set to another.
Said, these rats are stupid, these rats are smart.
and they had them run the rats through a labyrinth
and measure how fast the rats would finish.
The people who believe their rats are smart
actually had much better results
than the people who believe their rats are stupid.
Same type of rats, so weird.
And so they looked into it and it turns out
that people who believe their rats are smart,
they actually treated them a little bit with more TLC.
They gave them little snacks,
they encouraged them a little bit more,
they petted them, and so rats perform better.
Like holy shit.
And now, if that's how it works for rats,
imagine what it does for people.
When you genuinely believe in your people,
just imagine the results you can accomplish.
And that's the distortion of reality.
And so, this is the recommended list
that some of the books that I use in this talk.
But before we go, before I go,
I want to use the distortion of reality on you guys.
Okay, are you ready?
Everybody's taking pictures.
One second.
Okay, so I'm gonna use the distortion of reality on you.
In this audience, we are all, of course,
the type of people that fill out GDC surveys.
So when we walk out of here,
when we receive our results back,
we will have 100% completion rate.
Yes?
Yes, thank you.
Thank you.
Thank you, Oksana.
Well.
my friends, it's come to that time again. Clearly you all enjoyed this. So once again, stand up
and chat about what you've learned from Oxana.
No, it's amazing.
Come on, man, you do it.
I'm gonna be alone next time.
It's not too late.
We should.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
I realize that...
I forgot one thing.
I should have had Joel give me three points
and a funny point.
We did the Petra Kutra stuff on Monday and we had where you're from, what your hobbies
are outside of games, and something that your high school friend would be amazed to know
about you.
And I heard from Mr. Mikos that one guy was like, I sew better than my wife, and another
guy was like, I dropped out of high school, have a GED.
Yeah, it's amazing.
Awesome.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Yeah, you guys are making me feel so weird.
We're really good on here.
How are you feeling physically, hanging in there?
We're at about 28 minutes.
So, I don't know.
That's good.
Alright, alright.
Alright, alright, alright.
That's why you're back there.
In the back of the room.
Alright.
Calm down, you crazy animals.
Thank you. Thank you. Maybe I should announce La La Land as a winner. Maybe that'll get
everybody's attention.
All right, cool.
Up next is Chuck.
He is the CPO of Shell Games.
He can tell you what CPO means, it sounds fancy.
His background is in architecture.
He worked on Sims 2 EP Team,
and now works on theme park attractions
such as Disney Toy Story Mania,
which I got a high score on, just saying.
To cutting edge VR and AR such as I Expect You to Die.
Also, he is an adjunct faculty at CMU
teaching production and leadership.
All right, Chuck.
I like finding sage wisdom inside of Jira.
Well said Atlassian.
So I've been making games for a while, or what feels like a
long time anyway.
I've worked on dozens and dozens of games.
And I've seen a lot of them do really well and succeed.
And I've seen a lot of them crash and burn.
And I'm sure most of you in this room have gone through
those observations on different projects you've
worked on or projects you've seen out there.
And after a while, you start trying to figure out what the
difference is between those really successful teams and
the ones that fail, what the impact is that informs how
those teams are going to do.
So what I want to talk about today a little bit is teams
that thrive, and kind of our quest at Shell Games to figure
out what enabled those teams to thrive when others didn't,
and trying to replicate an environment to have very
successful teams.
So I actually had a hypothesis going into this a few years
ago, and the first was that very successful teams had much
higher morale, were happier with their vision, believed in
their project more, and were generally
happier working together.
And certainly, when I say that, I mean all else being
equal, right?
There's plenty of things outside the team that
contribute to the success or failure of a game that
sometimes you don't have control over.
But when we look just at the teams, I certainly posited that
happier teams did better work.
And I had a second theory that most of the teams that we
experience in the game industry have a very similar
curve of morale over time.
Maybe something like this, where we start off really
early at the beginning, and there's tons of potential.
We have the world in front of us.
We have a prototype that feels really good.
And then the reality starts setting in about what we have
to build and all the crap we don't know about.
And it gets really scary.
But then we get really good at focusing in our scope, and
the possibility space narrows in.
And morale starts to lift back up.
And you get to a really good spot, and things start to come
together, and you ship your game, and you feel really good
about it.
And I'm sure there's slight differences in this, but I
really felt like over time, a lot of projects followed this
same curve.
And I kind of wondered, if we could map this curve, if we
knew this existed for multiple projects, as a studio, can we
head it off at the past?
Can we anticipate these dips and valleys so that we
continue to boost the morale of the teams from the studio's
perspective so that we can reduce the
impact of these valleys?
So we did an experiment.
And for two years, every three weeks, I sent a survey to
about 12 teams in our studio.
And I asked three big questions.
The first was to rate your project's chance for success.
Then we asked people to rate your overall satisfaction at
that given day.
And then we asked people to select any number of emotional
indicators that they wanted.
And this is the graph we used.
So on the vertical up and down are positive or negative
emotions, and from left to right is kind of the intensity
of these emotions.
And people could go through and pick and choose.
So I'm going to show you if I can get the mouse over here.
Maybe.
Yeah, all right.
I'm going to show you what that looks like over time.
So while this is playing, I'll just explain it.
This is just a subset of the data,
but here's some examples of four or five teams.
The vertical axis is their satisfaction on the project.
Horizontal is over time.
So there's a motion graph showing
the duration of these projects.
And actually, the size of the sphere in this example
is related to the joyful quadrant
of those emotional indicators.
So we got a lot of data over two years.
So what did that show us?
Well, not a ton. It wasn't actually that useful.
The first thing, our first hypothesis, did seem to be correct.
When we look back at our teams, we saw ones that were
consistently higher in morale over the lifetime of their
project were generally more successful.
So that was cool.
That was kind of useful.
But man, there was no relationship with teams.
That fictional curve did not seem to be replicated across
different projects in any way.
It was really shocking how little projects
looked like each other.
And what was kind of crazier is they didn't even seem to map
to big points in the project.
It wasn't like, oh, we had a big cut in scope here, or a
big shift in decisions here, or priority
changes from the client.
It was like teams with really high morale were consistently
pretty high, and they ebbed and flowed seemingly randomly.
And teams that were lower kind of did the same thing.
So a lot of our realization from this was we could
look at the team's morale, we could track it,
but any interventions we tried weren't super useful
or impactful on that morale over time.
And we realized that team morale and happiness
wasn't something that we could impose on the team,
it was something that really needed to come
from the heart of the team, from its people.
I like how we all randomly picked like four lessons
for everybody to learn.
Producers here.
I always love this quote by Peter Drucker, right?
That culture eats strategy for breakfast.
And when we looked at teams that really thrived at RStudio,
it wasn't because of process or schedule or best practices.
It was kind of these cultural norms on the team.
And not just the team leadership, but the entire team.
And when we tried to replicate those,
we really looked at the teams that were doing really well,
and we found kind of these four common cultural traits
for these thriving teams.
So I'm going to share those next and some concrete steps
about how you can maybe apply those to your teams.
So the first that we noticed was our thriving teams were
really ones that were willing to buy into a decision fully
and then just move on.
So one of the strategies we saw time and time again is people on these teams were willing
to be convinced of different points of view, but more so than that, they would tell each
other specifically what would change their mind, right?
If Garth and I are in a disagreement, it's one thing to acknowledge that I have a particular
viewpoint.
But these teams elevated that and were actually open with
each other about, yeah, I don't agree with you, but
here's some things that would get me to agree with you.
And these may be big things, right?
It may be building a prototype.
It may be answering really challenging questions.
It may be data or information that you don't have.
But going through this process made it really clear to people
on the team that there's a culture of being open to
changing your mind, and people were very
willing to be convinced.
The second kind of almost powerful phrase
we saw these teams reference a lot
is one called disagree and commit.
And these were teams that were really focused
on building consensus, like that was very important for them.
But on larger and larger teams,
these teams acknowledged that that's not always possible,
you don't always get everyone on the same page.
And that's kind of fine, that's normal,
but we saw teams that were much more successful
focus in on if you can't build consensus,
at least commit to the group, commit to the team.
And by doing that, a lot of times they were able to eliminate a lot of the,
well, I told you so, right, out there in the future, or people sabotaging the team
because they didn't feel like they ever bought into the decision.
So people that were willing to acknowledge and say their disagreement,
but then commit to each other as a team, were much more powerful teams.
So the second cultural attribute we noticed a lot
was the teams had really good strategies
for cutting through complexity.
So just as an example here, this is
a what we call a propaganda poster
that these teams use in our studio.
And this was for our recent VR title, I Expect You to Die.
And lots of people use things like vision statements and pillars, but when we saw teams that were really good at cutting through
complex decisions
And understanding how to simplify down to what was really important
These were teams that would essentially actively market their vision in their team
They wouldn't just write it in a Google Doc or bury it on Perforce.
They would make posters.
They would hang them up in the team areas.
This became a marketing or propaganda effort for them to
get everyone bought into that vision, which allowed a lot of
really strong conversations of just, we have a lot of complex
options in front of us, but how does that match up to our game
pillar?
Another really powerful phrase we noticed a lot was the term
or the sentence, basically, what problem are
we trying to solve?
And Oksana mentioned earlier, starting with the why is
really critical.
And we found this is a really useful tool.
And teams leverage this a lot on really successful team
cultures, because it kind of cuts through a lot of the
complexity to focus on the actual core of the problem
you're trying to address.
And a lot of times that problem isn't obvious, may
have not been agreed to.
or is really challenging to get to.
But teams that were able to use this phrase
were able to kind of get down to the meat of the conversation,
get everyone on the same page with the problem
we're trying to solve.
And it was much easier to move people through solution spaces.
So our third one here are teams that were most successful
were willing to be very vulnerable.
And part of this involved them not punishing mistakes.
And one side of this coin is being willing to admit your own mistakes or screw ups, but
that set a lot of strong team culture as an example to the rest of the team that mistakes
were okay.
People were willing to hear them.
They were willing to be vulnerable in front of each other.
Because guess what?
If you punish mistakes, it's not like they go away.
You just don't hear about them anymore because people are afraid to tell you.
Another thing these teams did in their culture was a lot of
transparency, which a few people have
mentioned already today.
And I remember actually from my background in architecture, a
lot of architects build houses with these giant-ass glass
windows, right?
And people always think it's for the view or for the light
in the house.
But really, architects do that because you'll keep your house
cleaner.
It changes the culture in your house to be transparent.
If anybody's familiar with Frank Lloyd Wright, I remember one of his philosophies.
He'd do a lot of houses for clients, and he would refuse to put garage doors on garages.
He would only make carports, because he knew if he put garage doors on there,
people would just fill their garages with crap.
And he didn't want people to do that. He wanted them to have simpler, cleaner lives.
So he would build in transparency into their homes, even if they didn't want it.
So it's kind of interesting to think about.
I think a lot of folks view transparency on their team as
something they need to navigate or negotiate, either
with their clients or partners or within their
organization.
But transparency on your team can actually be a real benefit
or transformation for the culture on your own team.
And last, number four, folks on these teams were excellent
at resolving conflicts.
But man, the thing that stuck out was how swift and rapid
they were able to do this.
When we look at the best examples of this on teams, these are people who are resolving
conflicts within minutes of them happening, not hours or days or weeks.
So they had essentially zero hesitation in approaching each other to resolve conflicts.
And I'll share another kind of key or powerful phrase.
And this one's kind of funny.
This actually circulates around our studio and has been
kind of a key phrase at Shell Games for a long time.
And really, in my mind, it goes back to valuing the
understanding of other people over just being right.
And that phrase is, tell me more about that.
And we've kind of built a strong culture around people
using that phrase when they disagree with someone or when
someone says something that they
immediately recoil against.
And it's kind of funny.
About three weeks ago, we were sitting in a meeting and
someone said this to someone else.
And Jesse Schell, our CEO and founder, started laughing in
the corner of the room.
We're like, what's so funny?
And he's like, I don't think you guys realize where I stole
that from.
He got that from a chatbot named Eliza that came out in 1966.
And Eliza had such poor AI that she wouldn't really function
well when you chat with her.
So to kind of trick people around this,
they found a phrase where if Eliza didn't understand what
you were saying, she would simply write back,
tell me more about that.
And it's kind of stupid, but it's an incredibly powerful phrase,
because it really, it does two things, right?
It signals to the other person that you really value understanding them.
And to yourself, it reminds you that there's a lot more to understand
to get to the why, to get to the real understanding
of why someone is bringing something up.
So it kind of lowers your initial, if your gut reaction isn't defense
or countering someone's argument, but it's let me hear more
about what you're trying to get across.
Man, people don't change until they feel heard.
And this is a good, kind of powerful phrase
to remind you to hear other people.
So everything we talked about today
in terms of teams that thrive and teams that are successful
and teams that have really high morale,
all of this from our observations
boiled down to essentially how people treated each other
on the team.
You know, success was never based on a strategy or a process.
It always ended up being part of the culture,
and that culture needed to be built bit by bit
by every single person on the team.
And if you haven't noticed already,
those four items we just talked about,
those aren't things that your team can do.
Those are things that you can do.
Because culture made strategy for breakfast,
but you get to make the culture.
So while you're here at GDC,
I would certainly challenge everybody
not to get too swept up in focusing
on how to improve your teams.
Focus on improving yourself.
Be the best example of what you want your team to be.
Be an exemplar for them.
That's where your best value is going to be, and that's
going to give you the best chance of
making a thriving team.
Thanks.
Alright, alright, stand up. We're gonna do something a little different this time.
So last year... stand up still, you still have to stand up.
So last year's version of this talk, the prequel if you will,
Michelle Ducker talked about stress and dealing with stress
and one of her ways of dealing with it is to scream.
And I like to do this because it really messes with the people on both sides of us.
So what I want you to do is I want you to take just a few seconds, close your eyes,
and think about what makes you stressed this week, what makes you stressed at work, the
things that you're kind of thinking about now instead of just being present and being
part of this, and then on the count of three we're all going to scream as loud as we can
and get that out.
Okay?
Ready?
Okay.
One, two, three.
Ahhh!
Perfect.
Okay.
Now, do the normal thing, turn and talk to each other for a few seconds and we'll get
that going.
I think I'm stressed about this.
This.
That's fun.
You have 15 minutes.
You're the only one outside.
Don't take 15 minutes.
I don't actually.
Don't take 15 minutes, but you have 15 minutes.
Someone produced this.
Well done, Grant.
And created a story, a narrative.
You're right, it's almost like that.
Yeah, it's not quite enough.
Alright, alright.
One more to go, and then you can
talk in the hallways forever.
You can spend as much time getting to know each other as you want.
All right.
I just want to like McConaughey.
People in the back.
Everybody in front of you is sat down.
That is the indicator that we are ready to move on with our lives.
Alright, last one, here we go.
Brian over here is game director at Backflip Studios.
They're based in Boulder, Colorado.
He constantly is going to Red Rock and sending me pictures and making me angry.
He's worked on a bunch of games, Paper Toss, which is one of my favorite, Ninjump, Ragdoll
Blaster franchise, along with Dragon Bale, and his personal favorite, Army of Darkness
Defense.
Alright, Brian.
What I just screamed about was this moment.
What are you most stressed about?
About 12 seconds from now.
So forgive me for being a little raspy.
In my lifetime, I've been an algebra teacher, a wrestling coach, I was a bartender, I was
a pastor.
That didn't stick.
I was the lead singer in an 80s cover band, which is what that picture is.
I'm not crying or hungry, I'm singing.
And this kind of crooked path through a bunch of different jobs and careers and weird things
Has helped me realize that no matter the job no matter the scenario
Whether it's a sophomore who's retaking algebra because he failed it once already and hates you on day one
Or maybe it's a really fiery debate about the nature of magic and dragons with your lead artist.
Being able to communicate in the midst of conflict is a skill that will help you everywhere, always.
Right?
So, it is a little difficult talking about soft skills, feely things,
and having it not feel like a poster hung in your kitchen in your game studio, like,
hang in there.
Um...
Because it can feel like platitudes, right?
What is a concrete thing that we can do from soft skills?
And that's why they're called soft skills, not so concrete.
So, but my aim today is to target a few scenarios
that you will inevitably find yourself in.
at different points in your career, provide you some resources.
Oxana and I picked one of the same books.
She shares some examples from my life,
so that hopefully my failures can enlighten you,
or at least you can laugh at me, which is fine.
But my intent is not to give you a bunch of crap for motivational posters,
although that might end up happening.
So, I wanted to do... Here's some books. These are good.
You should read them, except for the third one, because it's not out yet.
It comes out in like two weeks, but Kim Scott gives a bunch of talks about radical candor.
And so, the whole point of this is, this is difficult conversations having to initiate them.
It's receiving feedback.
The five love languages is a bit churchy, as a heads up, but understanding what motivates people,
getting to the why, is an important thing.
And this does a really good job of understanding what motivates different types of people.
And then the five dysfunctions of a team,
Oxana's right, go read it now.
Maybe not right now.
So I think it's important, you were talking about,
who was talking about this?
Chuck.
Was talking about conflict and how it got resolved quickly.
Conflict isn't failure.
And this is important to know.
Conflict is not failure.
If I worked at a place with only clones of myself, first of all, that is damn terrifying.
The beer fridge would be well-stocked, though.
But I would still have problems.
I get mad at myself, arguably more than Goody does.
Arguably.
Um, conflict is the surest human interaction with a group of people over time.
My own equation is people plus time equals hostility.
It's inescapable.
Um, and so, uh, and this is also just like a really good lesson to learn.
I think a lot of producers, a lot of leaders like to be liked.
And it's super important that you just absorb this now.
Some people won't like you.
And that's okay.
We're not for everybody.
Everybody's not for us.
Some people won't like you.
That's all right.
I mean, that's not like a badge to go around
and be like Captain A-hole firing off all the time.
Some people just don't like me.
That's not, right?
It's not an excuse to run roughshod and be a douche, but I am saying it is okay.
Some people won't like you.
So here are the three types of conflict you will undoubtedly have in your life, work,
things, always.
When members of your team are not getting along and you have to mediate that.
Sometimes people don't like each other.
Chuck and Grant, tough to tell sometimes.
Or sometimes there is conflict
and they're not great at navigating that.
Sometimes you have to be the person
who initiates a difficult conversation.
You have to say something to someone
that you are relatively certain is going to be unpopular.
And then at some point in your life,
you are going to have to be told something you don't love.
And knowing how to be able to do that is important.
So, how to handle when folks aren't getting along.
So, step one, have them try to do it themselves.
I know that sounds lazy,
and it sounds a lot like conflict avoidance,
and the opposite of what I'm talking about
for the next five minutes,
but if you can trust them to figure it out themselves,
trust them to be adults,
I think you guys can figure this out.
You girls, you can figure it out, figure it out, right?
But you have to monitor the situation, otherwise that actually is just laziness.
Because what happens in a lot of conflicts is one person feels fine.
I have been heard, I feel fine.
And the other person, not fine.
And if you ask somebody, hey how are you doing?
Fine.
How are you doing?
Not fine.
You gotta be able to manage and understand that.
So what I try to do is bring people together,
I put them in the same room and purposely mediate.
My wife's a therapist, so I get lots of practice.
She specializes in adolescence,
which is how she puts up with me.
She married a giant man-child.
But what I find when you put people in the same room
is their complaints get a little less hyperbolic.
It's not, they never listen to me.
It's always this way.
They treat me like I'm stupid.
It's, I kind of don't feel listened to.
There's a difference in how people communicate
when they face their accuser.
But having people in the same room is helpful.
And it's also important to know that there's a difference
between somebody who needs to vent
and when it's time to mediate.
Sometimes somebody's just gotta be able to come in,
close the door and go, what the fuck?
That's an important thing that needs to happen sometimes.
And then, I think we just got the adult rating, sorry.
And then there's a time where you're like,
okay, that wasn't just a vent.
This is a persistent issue that we're gonna have to handle.
So here's a few things that I like to do in these moments.
I like to remember that conflict arises
out of passion, not apathy.
Usually conflict happens because people believe in something and they believe
different things and their ideas are problems, right? Um,
I loved, tell me more about that. Tell me, tell me some more about that.
What I'm hearing is what does that feel like?
What does resolution look like to you? What does this, here we are,
we have a conflict. What does the solution look like to you?
Asking, do you feel like you're being understood?
Giving somebody the opportunity to go,
no, I'm pretty sure you're just talking.
I do that sometimes.
And then one of my favorite,
it was actually Clint who sent me a list
of 31 powerful questions,
and one of my favorite ones was,
if you could go back and do this over again,
what would you do differently?
It's a really good way to get somebody
to analyze a conflict situation and go,
Yeah, what would I do differently?
And it puts it on them, what could they have done
to improve this scenario?
So that's step one.
So you have to tell somebody something
that you think is going to embarrass them
or make them feel bad about themselves.
How do you do that in a reasonable way?
Maybe that's you have to give like the hygiene talk.
Has anybody ever had to give the hygiene talk?
And not to like too broad a strokes, but it usually starts with, dude.
Not always.
Maybe you've got to tell someone on your team that their work isn't meeting the standards
that you've set.
You're not hitting the bar that we've decided on.
There's kind of two scenarios here.
Sometimes it's simply helping someone
see something they're oblivious to,
like lettuce in their teeth.
And sometimes it's,
they'll make an observation about themselves
because they've got a sneaking suspicion they're not great.
And they will say,
oh, I just don't think I'm doing a good job.
And a lot of folks are gonna try and say,
no, no, you're fine, you're fine.
Nope.
You have a responsibility, you have a moral obligation
as a leader to be able to say,
man, I think you might be right.
Things don't feel awesome right now.
What can I do to help you?
You're right, it feels like things are a little off.
What can I do to help?
I think that's super important.
All right, getting to that time.
When you have to receive a message that you don't love.
Don't just cover your ears.
So for me, I'm going to tell a bit of a personal story.
I know we're getting close to the end of the time and this is helpful because then I won't
get emotional about it.
I had a tough conversation that stung and I had a tough time hearing it.
I will say...
It led me to meditation practice actually,
and thank you to Brian Sharp who gave a talk about that
and really kind of changed my life.
But a couple things here.
When somebody, these are just kind of very practical things.
If somebody tells you something
that you don't think you're gonna love,
understand the truth, understand their truth,
hear what they're hearing, not just what you think.
Find the nuggets of truth in that,
even if you don't agree with the entire message.
Remove the buts, right?
You're gonna be like, well yeah, but that,
it's not about them.
It's about you.
Take that.
So, how to do this quickly.
Imagine, let me paint a picture for you
that could be viewed two different ways.
You're in a meeting, you're a person who's
slightly intimidated by the person leading the meeting.
You're a bit quiet, you're worried your feedback's
gonna get shot down or dismissed.
The leader senses that and asks you to speak.
You fidget uncomfortably, you stammer,
you don't do a good job presenting your idea.
The leader presses you again saying,
it's your job, speak up.
In that moment, you feel vulnerable and a little humiliated.
Your leader seems like a bully who cornered you
and kind of made you feel dumb.
Or, you're the team lead.
You're having a discussion about an upcoming release
for your game, it's a relatively healthy group discussion,
but your designer hasn't chimed in.
You ask them for their thoughts,
they kind of muddle through it,
you push them to clarify,
they say they'd prefer not to comment,
and you remind them that it is literally
their job description to have opinions about this feature.
Guess which one I was?
In this scenario, without knowing it,
I was a total bully.
I didn't know it.
I didn't mean to be.
Like I didn't, I think of myself as a rather gregarious dude.
I kind of try to be a little,
my wife calls me intensely laid back.
I thought I was the pretty girl in this picture.
I was not.
I goaded someone who was being quiet.
I prodded them when they felt intimidated.
I didn't allow their truth of intimidation to exist
because I didn't mean it.
It's like when I was little and my brother would hit me,
and it hurt, and he's like, I barely hit you.
We were both right.
He did barely hit me compared to what he could do,
but damn, he's four and a half years older than me,
he's like six foot two in the military, he's mean.
He hurt.
But it wasn't my intention, but my behavior that mattered.
And in their moment of vulnerability,
I met that with aggression and snark.
So I got pulled in by the founder of my company
and the HR manager that I was being threatening.
Phwoar.
Dude, that hurt.
And I wanted to make excuses,
and I had all the buts,
but it's his job, but it, but, but, but, no.
Somebody felt threatened by me.
I had to.
I had to feel the truth of that and think,
I'm a fucking bully.
And that hurt.
But I had to see that truth of it,
and I had to understand, and I had to process that
because it was important to how I treat people
and how I lead now.
This was an important thing for me to hear,
and I didn't love hearing it.
I'm going to leave you with some little snippet to remind myself to not be emotional about this anymore,
which is when you get into a position of leadership, the same discussion that you have,
the same words with the same person changes context and you have to be aware of that.
I wasn't aware of that and it's why I was being a bully essentially.
I would be able to have a discussion with somebody and go, that's kind of dumb.
Why would we do that?
Sometimes that would almost be like
a healthy conversation starter with your peers,
not so much when you're in charge.
Hey, that's dumb, sounds really dismissive.
Don't, I mean, don't do that anyway, but still.
So,
if you have the final say,
don't speak first.
Thank you.
Alright, so we're actually pretty much out of time.
I want to thank you all for coming and joining us
on the journey of production,
working on the Heart of the Team Part Two.
Maybe there'll be a Part Three,
because you're all going to give us excellent reviews.
So thank you for coming.
Also, thank you to the awesome CAs in the back,
George, Autumn, Chris, William, for working our shit.
And Eric and the rest of the AV crew for providing AV.
If you have any questions, we will be around.
Thank you very much for coming.