Hello, welcome to this ask me anything session. I'm Alex Waro from Gamasutra and I am joined today by
Take This executive director Eve Creviche. Eve, thank you so much for joining us.
Thank you, Alex. I appreciate it.
We were joking just before this started that you were going to introduce me as take two
director and you managed it.
I didn't even joke.
It was so close.
I was like, hmm.
Now the important thing about this session is that these fine folks in chat are going
to get to ask you questions about your work and your role in the industry and sort of
where you see it going.
So folks in chat, please drop questions in.
Use the question feature to upload stuff and we are going to serve up your finest questions.
I'm really excited.
And with that, I'm also going to mute Slack,
because of course, these are the things
we need to do these days.
Yeah, I probably need to mute a couple of different things.
As you go about clicking all these buttons
and muting all the real things, why don't you,
as you feel comfortable, sort of fill us in
on what you've been doing at TakeThis recently
and sort of how you got into the industry.
Yeah, absolutely. So I've been at take this for two years now. And in that time, I really focused the work that we do on health to be to to be on root causes. So what are the things that
um that cause mental distress and what are the the factors that can that we can change that can help
people experience better mental health in the game industry um as they play games and in
communities that surround games and in streaming environments and so we think a lot uh about what
are the things we can do to create systemic change and what are the ways that we can
normalize a conversation about mental health.
and mental well-being and self-care so that people understand that it's, one, okay and
normal to not be okay, and two, it's really fantastic to get help and seek support from
communities, from mental health professionals, etc.
So we want to work to normalize the conversation from the individual level, and we also want
to work to change the conditions that make mental wellness more possible in games.
Right on, yeah, it's a it does the organization.
We've already got some very good questions here in chat.
I'm just going to throw them at you if you don't mind.
Awesome. Yeah, please do.
Nice. We have one here from Danny.
They want to know, are demographic splits a serious consideration
when tackling mental health and games or are most concepts and concerns
universal among all players?
Oh, that's a great question, Danny.
Yeah. So there are there are both really substantial cultural differences in the way people understand and talk about mental health and mental well-being.
And then there are also differences in outcomes and the experience that different demographics have with mental health care in particular.
So you have.
culturally and geographically really dramatic differences in the way people
understand what it means to have mental well-being
and how that is treated or talked about culturally.
And take this really functions best in a European,
Western European and North American context because that's
what our version of mental health is. That's what we're familiar with
culturally.
The other thing, yeah, and then in terms of the demographic differences in the experience
of mental health care, you know, there's a lot of really good history, documentation about the
specific ways in which Black people have been pathologized.
through mental health care in really awful and prejudicial ways. And so there's historical
distrust and history of mistreatment of Black people in mental health care, for example.
So yes, the answer is yes. Yeah, that makes a ton of sense.
Frustratingly, in a conversation like this, we could then go for another 20 minutes, I think, just talking about strategies to deal with that.
But there's already a bunch of other fantastic questions in here.
Do you want to sort of jump over for a sec as we sort of expand the topic and look at, let's see, Tamla here had a good question.
How do you address mental health and alarm based chat in your workplace?
I guess sort of so how people are beginning to discuss feeling strain, feeling mental unwellness, that kind of thing.
How do you.
How do you address that kind of conversation in an office environment?
Hmm. Yeah.
Especially since quarantine and since the pandemic has started,
that's been a really big deal and something we've we've created.
Some workshops that we've offered to a couple of places
and we've created a lot of resources.
We have actually a whole series of articles on our website,
TakeThis.org, on coping with workplace stress and stress in general.
Yeah. I mean, the short answer is yes.
The longer answer is that the game industry
is prone to burnout. It's a really major problem, and that's caused by the high levels of uncertainty
that people experience in the game industry and the cultural norms in the industry that relate to
kind of passion, this myth of passion, where you come and you put all of yourself into your work.
And you have very little separation and very few boundaries.
And that leads to burnout and stress and anxiety, which
and so so it's really it is the responsibility of supervisors
and company leaders to have their pulse, their eyes on the pulse
and to understand where and be able to recognize signs of burnout and stress
and to to mitigate those.
And there's responses that are kind of personal and individual.
And then there's responses and mitigation efforts
that can happen at a company or structural level.
In terms of what's happening specifically in the pandemic,
there's a really major increase among managers in and out
of work while exhausting.
in terms of providing support to the team.
I agree. I hadn't really considered the new burdens being placed upon folks for communication
and sort of maintain team morale.
On an individual level, for folks who are logging in from home now
for months and months at a time, logging into this conference,
maybe this one we can dig in there about this Nathaniel.
The first thing is that after a data convention like this, I already feel overwhelmed and
a bit depressed.
Is there any way to help with dealing with this?
I know we don't want to dig into specific strategies, but as people who are logging
in from home and either feeling very isolated or overwhelmed or perhaps both.
What sort of suggestions would you have for how to deal with that?
Yeah, I mean this is a very non-technical term, but FOMO, right?
There's a couple things going on when you engage in a really intense experience,
like an online conference. One is you feel like you have to see it all,
and you have to catch it all, and that's too much.
Right? So if you are feeling overwhelmed at the end of today, that means probably that you've
done more than you needed to do. You don't have to catch it all. All of this is recorded. All of
this is going to be online, download, you know, or most of it. And that's okay. It's okay to miss
things. It's okay to take breaks and step away. And that's, in fact, quite healthy. We as humans
don't have the capacity to just keep going and going and going and going.
In the case of this particular experience and in the case of work in general, we do better when we take breaks.
That's why crunch is so harmful, because it actually, we are less effective when we work too much.
Our brain stops functioning at its normal level and our body as well.
So taking more breaks and allowing yourself to miss things.
And also video interaction and online interaction taxes us emotionally.
You know, I'm talking about this emotional labor because we don't get the same type of interface with people.
And so we have to fill in the blanks a lot.
And so our brains have to work harder.
And that is.
taxing. And so just knowing that we are having to correct for a suboptimal experience in this time.
Yeah, for sure. And also, you're not alone. That's a normal experience right now. This is a very
strange experience. And those of us who've been to GDC before, we know that this is not GDC that
we're used to, right? This is a very different experience, and it's a little bit disappointing.
And that's okay.
Absolutely, yeah.
There's a bunch of great questions, of course, but I don't want to let one slip by.
It was asked a little while ago by Matt, and I think it's important.
A lot of people have voted it up.
Matt wants to know, do you happen to have any experience with veterans,
and gaming as it pertains to the mental health of veterans?
Mm. Well, I would actually refer people to a great organization that we partner with
called Stack Up. And they're a fantastic organization that works specifically with
veterans. The issue of mental health for veterans is really a major one, and it's a real challenging
one. And take this, we don't specialize in working with veterans. That's a very specific
set of needs and population and culture that's very particular. You know, we
Take This prides itself on being game literate, or veteran literate.
And so I would say, you know, there are some great organizations out there that
do know how to respond to veterans in a very particular way, and StackUp in particular comes
to mind. Yeah, I think that's a great recommendation. And relevant to Take This' work,
there was a question here from Danger who wants to know, how can a psychologist or
a licensed counselor get involved to support Take This' mission?
Oh, awesome question. We love to have more people get involved.
Right now, actually, we're recruiting for our first ever AFK Online.
So our AFK room is a quiet, supportive space at conventions that we provide.
And it's staffed by clinical and non-clinical volunteers.
And we're spinning up for PAX Online.
First ever online AFK room.
We need volunteers.
If you go to our website to our contact us page,
you can get in touch with us.
And I or one of my colleagues to you in short order.
All right, let's jump back to the thought
of mental health and game companies specifically.
Josh asks, some companies have been introducing
mindfulness training as a form
of encouraging mental health awareness.
Do you feel this is an effective strategy
towards opening the larger discussion
of normalizing mental wellness?
Hmm, that's a great question.
So, mindfulness is a really powerful tool.
And it's a tool that's used in a couple of really great therapeutic approaches.
But it's just one of many tools.
It's one that's kind of easily accessible, especially because there's all these mindfulness apps out there.
Headspace comes to mind is the biggest one, right?
A lot of people know about it.
And it feels like an easy add, I think, for a lot of companies.
I don't think, I think it's a great idea, but it's like, it's not a panacea, right?
It's a starting point. And it's one of many tools.
And for some people, it may not be the right tool,
or it may not be the right delivery mechanism.
So other people need other things.
But mindfulness, you know, mindfulness is super powerful.
I have found it personally extremely useful.
It's been transformative to me.
But but it's this is, you know, mental well-being is a very personal
individual thing, and everybody's on their own path.
And so one size fits all approach is never going to work for for everybody.
Yeah, I completely agree.
There was actually another question sort of relevant.
I think there was Nathaniel asked a little while ago,
how can companies and game companies specifically go about presenting?
issues regarding mental health in a way that helps people understand how they might feel.
And I assume that's sort of a general empathy and understanding of the, yeah. What do you think?
Yeah, so that's a great, that's a really great question and a really powerful one too.
There's a couple of bits to my answer.
One is that games themselves tell stories
and create metaphors for the way we understand the world,
and they both reflect society and can shape society,
can shape culture.
And so we have at our disposal in games
an extraordinarily powerful tool
to shape the conversation around mental health
and mental wellbeing in general.
There's some amazing games that have come out
in the last few years.
that either represent self-care in a wonderful way or show a really accurate example of mental
illness or help to kind of walk people down the road of what it looks like and feels like to be
in a certain state. Some of the ones that we've highlighted recently are Celeste and
Stardew Valley and Gris and Sea of Solitude and of course Hellblades, Senua's Sacrifice.
And so the good representation of mental health in games is really important.
The other piece that I think is really important is to talk about how we use communities
and the culture and norms inside game communities,
like in-game interaction and like...
community around games to shape the way we talk about ourselves and to help
people understand how they relate to each other and what's good so we can
change the norms to reflect positive support for mental health and well-being.
and positive interactions. Victoria Tran actually earlier today gave a great talk on
creating positive community environments. Her work at Kitfox Games is just fantastic,
and there are many others who think about this work as well. There's many ways that we can
use our power as shapers and creators of community.
shared online spaces to set norms around positive online environments. We have, Take This has
streaming ambassadors who do that in their streaming environments. They're moderators and
they themselves are really well trained and experienced in creating positive environments
and in shaping spaces that promote empathy and demonstrate empathy inside their communities.
That's super cool. Yeah, it's really cool.
We kind of already addressed this question, but I wonder if we can dig into it a little more.
Daniel asked a little while ago, when building online communities,
what is the best way to approach harassment and mental health?
They've already talked about the actual players themselves.
But I wonder for, you know, since you do so much work with game companies
and game makers, for people who are working on online games,
who are embedded in online communities and maybe.
How do they deal with and how do they regulate the levels of harassment and
kind of just mental drain that they are often subjected to in a role like that
where you're public facing inside a game company?
Have you seen any experience with that?
Have you?
Yeah.
We, um, yeah, we've actually worked with a number of companies to help, um,
help their community teams.
Uh,
Either navigate, learn to set boundaries and learn, develop some skills around that so
that they can better protect themselves.
And also to understand better how to support people who are experiencing harassment.
Yeah.
Right.
But, but ultimately, the experience of dealing with toxicity and harassment, which is endemic
to the industry and a major problem.
Um
is the responsibility not of individual moderators and employees, but of companies
to develop structures that address it directly. And that means really strong technical solutions,
but also creating and being really steadfast in creating zero-tolerance harassment policies and
positive communities. There's a lot of good research out there that you can teach people
empathy by
Introducing them to community environments that promote empathy and that you can change people's
behavior by bringing them into a community in a positive and constructive way. And that only
happens when the community is intentionally designed. And that only happens when a company
is intentionally designed.
And so the issue of toxicity and harassment does not start at the community design level.
It starts at the company dynamic and leadership level.
Because if you have a company that accepts as its premise that harassment isn't okay
and is unacceptable, and that we want a positive space for our,
and a welcoming space for everyone who wants to play our game, then you can design for that.
And only when you design for that can you get to the place where it's possible in a community.
That's a long process, but that's where it starts.
Yeah, it does seem like, you know, especially with recent events at Ubisoft and elsewhere, like if you don't have buy-in and significant
interest in enacting change at senior levels, that it doesn't, it seems like very challenging to enact serious, you know, company-wide change.
It's, I would, I would actually, it's not very challenging.
It's impossible.
Oh, fair enough.
Yeah, absolutely.
Yeah.
There is a question about this that I want to get back to real quick.
Here we go.
Austin recently asked, do you know of any proven practices you can recommend that a
development firm can implement to foster a culture that's supportive of those living
with or suffering from mental illness?
Mm. Oh gosh, that's the whole time, but proven practices.
What do you think?
Proven practices. Gosh, I mean, that's a
it's not it's not proven practices.
It's it's a culture that emphasizes humanity.
That recognizes people's needs as people.
That is highly transparent and that provides respect to people.
That provides the space and good boundaries to allow people to undertake good self-care.
So good boundaries means good work hour limits, good boundaries around how much of your life
is involved in your work.
good boundaries around when you can walk away completely.
So it's about an orientation towards balance and wellness.
And a support for that at the company level,
like an active advocating for people to leave,
to take breaks, to understand what's going on,
to feel empowered to participate
and have their opinion heard.
Yeah, yeah, there's a whole series of things like that.
Yeah, that sounds, those all make a lot of sense to me.
And it's, it sounds like it really depends
on the environment, the team size,
and sort of what kind of, you know,
whether it's an indie or a big company,
I mean, that kind of thing.
Yes, yeah, it shifts dramatically at a large company,
especially a large company with, you know,
public companies, I think, are in a very different position
than private studios, privately held studios.
Absolutely.
Yeah.
There was another question here about a specific person's struggles.
Here we go.
Someone asks, Leah asks, what suggestions do you have for someone with a diagnosed mental
health issue who wants to reduce stigma around it through visibility, but also doesn't want
to cause discord with teammates who might not understand?
How do people who have unique needs and who struggle with mental health express and make
those struggles public and visible without detracting from the team, I guess?
Yeah, that's a tough one because there's enough stigma about mental health and mental illness
that people get really afraid when you start talking about it. The recommendation,
so this is something actually we're actively working on and we've got our second annual.
a game summit on mental health.
It's called TIGS.
And I work in partnership with Mark Chandler on this.
And we are we are in October.
We're going to be sharing stories of people in the game industry
with mental health, mental illness and
and talking specifically about that so that we can reduce the stigma.
And it's really about sharing as many of those stories as possible.
But but one of the ways to do that is to
Bring as much data to the conversation as possible.
So when you talk about your diagnosis, also describe what it looks like and talk about
what accommodation looks like and what you don't need.
You know, I don't need sympathy or I don't need you to feel sorry for me.
I need, you know, specific accommodations or just...
I need you to know and I need you to be able to look at me and see me as the full person
that I am.
Yeah.
You know, it reminds me of, you know, we spoke briefly before this about the myth of passion
and how it can be sort of turned against game developers to sort of burn them out and that
kind of thing.
I wonder, do you have any thoughts on how workers in this industry can sort of avoid
being...
You know, like, you know, pulled by the by the by passion and by the call of their collaborators to work beyond their limits or to push their mental health into sort of unhealthy states.
So this is this. I'm not going to sugarcoat this one, because it's a tough one to answer. Because if you're in a company where the expectation is that you work and you work too much,
and you put all of yourself into your work, and your supervisors and seniors do the same thing,
it's going to feel like if you don't, you're going to lose your job.
And if you're stuck in that job because you need it and can't leave and can't move out of it,
that's a tough place to be in, right? Because
What managers do and what leaders do sets the tone for the whole company.
So if you are a manager and a leader, even if you tell your employees that they don't need to work, you know, 50, 60, 80 hours a week, and you do, you are putting pressure on them to do that.
Right.
So and when I say when I speak to managers and leaders right now, I say you even if you think you're not pressuring your employees.
If you do that, if you do that bad thing, they will think they have to, and that is bad.
So you need to be good about setting limits and being an example,
because that only comes from the top. Full stop.
And I have to, as the executive director of Take This,
I have to check myself, too, in that I have to stop.
I have to articulate that I am leaving my desk,
that I am walking away, that I am disconnecting,
so that I know that my employees,
and so that my employees know that they can, right?
But in,
The other thing is to really cultivate in yourself a lot of other passions and other
ways to enjoy yourself, right? Even if it is still related to games, as long as it is
explicitly not your work, but it's something slightly different, that's great.
Giving yourself explicit ways to leave and shut off will give you the energy and space
to reenergize and take care of yourself.
That's really important.
I think I answered the question.
Yeah, I think those are the things that are pertinent.
Absolutely.
Yeah.
That's something we've been talking around this whole conversation is.
It's those kind of challenges.
Something before, we have about five minutes left.
So if anyone wants to get your questions,
please get them in quick.
There was a good one here about 10 minutes ago from Thomas,
but it's still a good one now, and I want to get to it.
Thomas asks, how do we as an industry create real change
in scheduling deadlines, launch dates, et cetera,
while keeping things like mental health, burnout,
and so on in mind, without fear of being replaced
by the newer, younger generation
who haven't hit these walls yet?
Is that a thing you regularly deal with in your own work, is sort of the aging problems
industry has where older workers seem to have a hard time getting employed when younger
folks don't?
Yeah, it is. Although there's some evidence that the population, the game industry population,
is actually aging a little bit, which indicates there's maybe a shift around that now.
There is a lot of burnout, which definitely chases people out of the industry
pretty quickly, on average around 10 years in.
which we are concerned about.
But I would say the answer to this is that there are good models out there for more transparent
and more participatory scheduling and planning processes that help to kind of mitigate these
issues.
We're working on some tools and resources in partnership with the IGDA that hopefully
we'll be able to talk about soon.
around this stuff. It's about training. The industry is an interesting place. It's not
actually that old of an industry, and so it's kind of still catching up to itself in terms
of professionalization and skill building around management, planning, forecasting, etc.
And so it's time for the industry really to mature around that stuff. And I hope to be part of the
positive push towards that in the industry.
Yeah, I hope so. I mean, I hope you're a part of it for a long time to come.
Eve, thank you so much for joining us today.
It is my distinct pleasure.
I'm very happy to be here.
And I really encourage people to reach out to take this or to me directly.
You know, we do better when we are part of a large community
and we work together.
So would you recommend for people who want to learn more, get in touch, go to the website or is there somewhere else you'd rather get in touch?
OK, take this dot org.
You can also find us on Twitter at Take This Org.
And I'm at Eve Krebachet.
Nice.
And there was an event coming up, right?
Did I remember that right?
Are you guys working on that for this year?
Is that as far as you can tell?
Yeah, we have an event coming up
the 7th and 8th of October,
the International Game Summit on Mental Health.
Yep, that's one we partner on.
And we've got a lot of other stuff in the works
over the next few months.
I'm just really looking forward to it.
So keep an eye on us.
Yeah, no, absolutely we will.
Thank you guys so much
and enjoy the rest of your GDC summer.