Hello folks, welcome to GDC 2021.
This is a live fireside chat,
Gina Davis and Mithu Khandaker
on masculinity and video games in the gaming community.
I'm Joel Couture, editor-in-chief of Indie Games Plus.
My pronouns are he, him,
and I'll be the moderator for this session.
Now I'd like to pass things over to Gina
so she can introduce herself,
in case you somehow need an introduction for her
and her tremendous amount of work
in all kinds of media industries.
So Gina, please take it away.
Oh, thank you so much.
Thanks for that.
And thanks for everybody for being here.
I'm very excited to be a part of this today and very
excited to get going and talk about this, this topic
that we've done a very extensive
study about.
And so, yeah, looking forward to all of this.
All right, and next we have Mitu.
Could you say a few words
about your own impressive body of work?
Because you're pretty impressive as well.
Thanks, Joel.
Yeah, just really honored to be here.
So hi, I'm Dr. Mitu Kandeka.
I'm a game designer and engineer.
So I'm a professor at NYU Game Center,
and I'm also CEO at Glow Up Games,
which is a diverse mobile game studio.
And I've been in the games industry for around 14 years now, so I've been coming to GDC for about
that long as well, so really thrilled to be here to welcome Gina to her first GDC. So I've been
lucky as well to be on the advisory committee for GDC for the last six years or so on the advocacy
side, so I'm here to represent the game developers' perspective.
Well, it's great to have you both here. I'm just going to jump right in with some questions. So
let's talk about this study. Can you tell us a bit about the study and how everything worked, Gina?
Yes, absolutely.
We we looked at both the games themselves and also
the the players that that people watch play
and took a survey also to find out people's
impressions and and ideas about it.
So this is a very, very extensive study, and we believe more extensive
than any that's been done previously on on gaming and what messages it sends.
Okay, what sort of specifics were you looking for in the study?
Like what did you were you hoping to find from watching what people watch play?
Well, we wanted to find out we wanted to find out what,
like I said, what message the the games are sending and
and found particularly strong results
in what the male characters represent
and the the the impact of violence
and hyper masculinity in
in these in these games that are that are being played.
and trying to see what kind of impact that has and how it can maybe be improved moving forward.
The study indicates that many elements of the gaming ecosystem reinforce something called
the man box. Can you tell us a little bit about what this man box entails? Because that was a
learning experience for me because I'd never heard this subject before.
about. Right.
Tell us how video games connect to it
on many different levels.
And how is this building a very specific vision
of the world and what is acceptable behavior
through interacting with the medium of games?
So that was a mouthful.
Right, right.
So the MANBOX is the seven pillars of the MANBOX
is a concept that was developed by our partners at Promundo.
And it refers to a set of beliefs that are communicated
by parents and family and the media and peers.
and other members of society that place pressures
on men and boys to be a certain way.
And these pressures include telling men
to be self-sufficient, to act tough,
to be physically attractive,
to stick to very rigid gender roles,
to be heterosexual, to have sexual prowess,
and to use aggression to resolve conflicts.
And we found in our study that
masculine norms are very strongly upheld with four and five male characters displaying at least
one of these pillars of masculinity. For example, seven to ten male characters are shown engaging
in stereotypically masculine activities like
taking risks, engaging in violence, getting angry.
Nearly one in four male characters actually express anger.
And violence is also a major component of this man box.
Sixty three percent of male characters
enact violence in the in the in the games.
And 84 percent of that time, the violence is directed against other people.
And the leading motive for violence from male characters is personal gain compared to the small
proportion of characters who are perpetrating violence for a more noble motivation, protecting
a stranger or protecting society. It kind of alters like your players, the game players'
visions on kind of what reality is or what is acceptable behavior through their kind of
interactions with these games.
Right, yes, hyper exposure to to these kinds of tropes is is
very impactful and will definitely you know what we what
we're exposed to over and over becomes a sort of reality for us
and
media and games and the things that we see in our popular culture have a tremendous impact on
shaping who we are. So as you can imagine, watching, playing these games over and over
or watching people play these games can have a significant impact about what you think is
is the actual way that men should be or what masculinity should look like.
Yeah, exactly. Seeing these kind of reinforce
from like hearing what the boys hangouts
or seeing the reinforce in the games they're playing
can kind of feed into, this is right, this is real.
This is how people talk and act to each other.
Right, right.
That's your point.
Mitsu, I'm gonna bug you.
Can you suggest some ways, no matter how small,
to kind of break away from these man box elements
in game development,
or how developers can kind of steer away from that?
Yeah, I mean, I think firstly to speak to that, like this was the first time I was lucky enough
to sort of get a peek at the study ahead of time. And I think firstly to speak to the man box,
like I think the thing I love about that definition is the way that it talks about how
it is limiting, right, for both cis men and folks of all genders, right? So,
like the ways in which these representations kind of box people in.
in certain ways.
And I think the other thing as well,
before I sort of get to your question directly,
is that I love about the study,
is that it is very intersectional
and that's something I care a lot about.
So there's a lot of, in addition to sort of looking at...
gender representation.
It's also sort of, you know, there's some groundbreaking
sort of new findings through the content analysis
to do with race representation, to do with queer representation
and like looking across all of these different intersecting axes,
which is a really important perspective to take.
And so and those are sort of all things
that we should be thinking of kind of together as game developers like.
you know, taking this very intersectional approach.
I think, you know, to speak to sort of ways
that we can intervene in these kinds of representations,
I think it's like several fold, right?
As these things often are,
because you look at this sort of,
I think I have like, you know, three distinct sort of ways that I think about this.
Because firstly, there's the business perspective, right?
And if we're looking at...
Because I know the study looked at sort of the top five streamers
and what games they're playing.
And so the reasons for...
And often those are sort of AAA games, etc.
And the reasons why those games are often sort of perpetrating
these types of, you know, these types of tropes, etc., is because
you know, the games industry, as we know, we sort of, it's very like, most designs are very sort of
iterative, right? Like, we take sort of what's worked before and innovate on it slightly,
because, you know, games are kind of, making games is inherently risky in a lot of ways.
It's financially risky. It's also really, really hard, right? Like, as we know, as game developers.
Games can run into all kinds of...
It's just an inherently tricky sort of technical and design
sort of undertaking anytime you're making a game.
And so often the things that...
So innovation can often be difficult in that context, especially...
So I think the thing I'm getting to is that...
It really takes studios to hold values around wanting to break free of these tropes, right?
It really does need to come from the business perspective, studio leadership, wanting to really take a stance and
and innovate on these types of representations. And part of that as well is, you know, something
I'll get to again more, is like who is in positions of decision making around what goes into a game,
right? Like who is being represented? Because as we know, often it is, you know,
the games industry is overwhelmingly represented in leadership positions by
cis white men and cis white straight men.
So we need to disrupt that.
And the last thing I'll say,
I think from a design perspective,
you know, it's not that we don't have ways
to think about better representation
because there are plenty of developers out there
who are doing that work.
And often those are folks
from marginalized backgrounds themselves
who have perhaps, you know, smaller studios
or they're...
doing work by themselves or in like tiny teams, but they need the opportunity to sort of have funding
to really have their ideas pushed forward. So we need to sort of, you know, this is a
wide-ranging problem and it's a structural problem that we need to disrupt.
I definitely agree that this goes all the way through every level of like game development,
like requires management to take a lead on this, requires like...
people in like your position in like leadership positions to take care of things,
handle things much better than they've been handled before. And it tells different stories,
and it shows different types of like gameplay elements and risks. And yeah, it's risky,
but like it also will broaden what this industry can do and say, reaching out to folks who are
normally represented here.
Gina, I want to bug you about some more stuff.
What trends are you seeing in kind of the characters
represented in video games?
You touched on it a little bit,
but sort of in who gets represented
and how they're being represented.
Right, right. So male characters outnumbered female characters four to one,
and white characters outnumbered characters of color three to one.
Unfortunately, LGBTQ disabled and large body type characters are nearly
non-existent. White male characters are twice as likely to carry a weapon
as male characters of color and are much more likely to be violent.
particularly carrying a gun.
And then when we look at the top 20 streamers,
they are all men, only one is a man of color
and only one identifies as LGBTQ.
And there's often a 10% of,
streamers use homophobic or transphobic language, or that language appears in about 10% of segments,
no disabled characters, and then streamers often use ableist language in nearly half of the gameplay
segments, like some kind of variation of the ableist language, crazy in one in five game
segments. So there's just a lot of that sort of...
negative stereotyping and violence and hyper masculinity going on in the characters that are
being played. You've also touched on what's the study revealed about the sexualization
of women as well because that was another thing that comes up quite frequently.
Oh, yes. Well, yes, there's definitely a few female characters.
There are they are they are tremendously
sexualized, hyper sexualized.
And, you know, this also has a tremendous impact on
both the concept of women feeling comfortable to join in
and play these same games and and how.
Women are viewed from a sort of hypermasculine lens that sees them more as sex objects rather than equal partners.
Female characters are 10 times more likely to be shown in revealing clothing than male characters.
Definitely a large problem.
Um, what effect are we feeling this is having on the audience receiving the game?
I imagine it's similar to what violence that effect has on like the males
who are receiving these games.
That's hoping to kind of open up both of you.
I mean, I can field that one.
You know, in terms of, you know, just the experience,
we know across like all kinds of media,
and this is obviously, you know,
this is why it's so exciting to have Gina here
to like talk about this,
because obviously the work that you've done across like
other sort of types of media representation
also shows this, like representation matters.
We know that.
I've felt that in my own life.
you know, being a little brown girl growing up,
playing video games from as long as I can remember,
you know, you sort of learn, and especially, you know,
and this is why I was, as I was saying,
like intersectionality is important.
We need to look at gender representation
together with race representation,
because often, you know, for someone in my position,
like for instance, taking, I don't know,
like Street Fighter as an example,
just because I remember playing it when I was young,
and, you know, seeing that classic dilemma
that I think a lot of us faced of like.
oh, are we the female character, are we Chun-Li?
Or in my case, am I Dal Sim, the one,
like, you know, the Indian character,
which is not great representation, right?
And so it's like, oh, who is close enough
to how I feel like I'm represented?
And I think the thing that I often say about this
is I actually, even though I was making those decisions,
it didn't actually hit me for the longest time.
that that was a decision I was making. Like I didn't, when I was like young and even in my
teens often, like playing video games, I wasn't like, oh, you know, if only I could see myself,
because that wasn't even represented as, I wasn't even presented to me as an option, right? And so
when you're sort of taught over and over that you're not going to be represented,
you sort of internalize like, oh,
maybe I'm not, maybe I don't deserve to be represented.
And that is sort of this really, you know,
it's something that a lot of us carry.
And it's in the work that I'm now doing
through my company, Glow Up,
where we're explicitly setting out to rectify that,
you know, like myself and my co-founder,
Latoya Peterson, you know, as women and women of color,
we, you know, we think about this a lot,
like we've had these experiences.
And so that's why we want to, you know,
we want to do better.
Yeah, I think it's important to be able to kind of see yourselves in these play experiences.
And it's important for the cis males to also see other people out in the world.
Like it gives you this closed world view to see no one but the same white males doing the same
white male fantasy power fantasies all the time. So they're limited in kind of what they even
accept of the world or see of the world. They don't see that these people even exist out there.
So I kind of want to ask from the development side,
Mitu, how does this affect developers
who are creating these kind of sexualized versions of women
or these nasty stereotypes and things like that?
Because I feel that must have an effect
on a development team that spends months and years
crafting something, frankly, gross.
Well, I mean, I think the one thing I want to speak to is the experience of
marginalized folks at these companies, right?
So whether you're women or, you know, non-binary or, you know, from any other
marginalized access, underrepresented access within games, often, you know, folks.
do want to be, especially if you're a big team
where you don't have that decision-making power.
Like, you know, this is, none of this is stuff
that developers don't already know, right?
But what will often happen is folks in leadership positions.
will just cut certain, even if you,
I've got just countless stories of friends, et cetera,
who've worked on games where you start including
more diverse representation, but then as soon as,
as games often do, as I said, making games is hard.
So they come into, you run up against time and budget
and all these things.
And often because of the values of folks
in leadership positions,
the first thing to get cut is those diverse representations. And I think that is the thing
that has the effect on folks, because they're being told like, oh, your experiences don't matter.
We can also take that further, right? Like today is, as we were talking about a little
bit before this Joel, like today is a really interesting day to be.
having this discussion, because, you know, as Bloomberg reported, the lawsuit by the
state of California against Activision Blizzard for the sort of alleged, you know, as they
call it, the frat boy culture within that space, like, the experience of being a marginalized
person within games is often a traumatic one.
And that's something that we also need to rectify.
And if you're thinking of reading this in the audience,
like looking at the articles in the lawsuit,
please, please take care of yourself.
It is probably one of the most awful ones I've read
in a good long time in this industry.
So please take care before you read it.
All right, uh, we'll just shift over a little bit.
The findings in the study indicated popular stream games often promote
hypermasculinity through violence or personal gain and aggression like you
said earlier. Do we have any suggestions for
developers on how to better frame their game experiences to move away from this,
better shape their characters to move away from this behavior even if
violence is kind of the focus of the game?
Right, well, it would be important, I think, for developers to consider examining,
do the male characters have to be aggressive all the time
and repress their emotions and to fight anytime they feel threatened,
which then results in more violence and more risky behavior.
you know, perhaps they can think about what are ways that the characters can face these challenges
in the game more creatively? What other more creative and mentally challenging ways can
they address these problems or more clever things that the characters can do rather than just
shooting guns?
and therefore, you know, acknowledge that they have a role to play in reinforcing positive
ideas of manhood, and I think that's very important.
To jump in on that as well, yeah, I think, sorry, I guess that's what you're going to ask.
I think that, I think that, you know, there is such a rich landscape of types of
of types of game design that have yet to be explored and to be funded as well,
because these are types of things that lots of designers I know have sort of experimented with,
etc. Looking at ideas of vulnerability among male characters, like looking at...
There was a wonderful talk by the developer Brie Code a couple of years ago at GDC
about sort of tend and befriend mechanics in games.
So that's an area where there are folks doing work, but we need those ideas to be given
the platform and those ideas to be pushed further.
So I think that, yeah, and to speak to what Gina was saying about what other actions can
there be.
as a game design teacher, so when I teach game design at NYU, you know, one of the lenses we
have for thinking about game design is thinking about verbs that characters have, right, like,
or that you can do as a player. So what are the verbs that
you know, like actions, like doing words that characters or the player is able to enact
within a game that aren't necessarily just, you know, combat related.
So there's, you know, there's, yeah, there's all kinds of things that we can be sort of
exploring further through games for sure.
you know, the idea of like friendship mechanics, the idea of the, you know, just exploring more
vulnerability. And I think, you know, part of that is also thinking about like pro-social design,
right? So a lot of game design is often competitive or a lot of games, you know, in terms of the sort
of subset of games we're talking about, there's, you know, like competitive gameplay versus
like thinking about like, oh, how do you design for sort of more pro-social interactions between
players? Like how does the game design actually help bring that about and reward those kinds of
behaviors? So I think that's kind of what I found really interesting about the study is that it
points to the sort of necessity of creating these spaces.
for players of all genders really, but especially for those who are sort of affected by this,
like, or limited by this man box idea. Yeah, there's definitely some proof out there that
shows like different experiences in games, like not the hardcore pure violent shooter is like.
they're not the most popular things. They're still immensely popular, don't get me wrong,
but these other experiences that push us to be more social or that can bring a little bit of fun
together or less focus on like harming other human beings and like more different styles of stories
are starting to gain a lot of like power or power may not be the best word but they're getting their
audience, they're getting their audience, people are seeing them and they're starting to be made
like there is some different stuff finally coming out there.
Yeah, there was some wonderful stuff.
We were talking a little bit earlier, Joel,
about the IGF Awards last night, right?
So we can see within that space,
the sort of plethora of interesting,
like new types of games that are popular
and that are being made, of course.
Yeah, and that talk about community kind of like brings me to my next question for you, gang.
Research has indicated that many males find game to be a connection with peers and community,
like so even we're seeing it there, like they're finding there's a connection with those Twitch streamers
or with their friends. So, and they're also saying according to your study, Gina, that it's a place
that can be their true selves. Gaming also seems to connect these players with too many damaging
stereotypes and visions of masculinity. So
What sort of work do we feel game developers can do in trying to use this feeling of connection and community to build something more positive?
Will we build on that natural, like, that desire to be together, but like, if this, like, and to build a better true self?
Right, right. Well, we found a tremendous evidence for how important the connection with
with peers and friends and community is to people who game. Our survey showed that
in the gaming culture, 91 percent of boys and 86 percent of men say that playing video games
is an important way for them to connect with their male friends. But unfortunately, young gamers
experienced a tremendous amount of bullying and harassment in online gaming.
And older respondents said they routinely witness homophobia
and racism and online gaming.
So the the culture is providing valuable human connection
and certainly a space to do that.
But the ongoing concern is that the culture often normalizes violence and hate.
And so the thing to think about is, since there's such a positive aspect
that you can gain.
from developing community and sharing time,
special time with your friends through gaming,
how can we make it a more positive experience
and subject you to less bullying, harassment, and violence?
There has to be positive things that
ways to make the experience more positive and creative.
And, you know, we know that what happens in the fictional world
does have a real life impact and.
the online gaming provides incredibly important opportunities
for boys and young men to connect,
but we need to make it so, as you said,
they can feel like they're being their true selves online
and not having to reinforce toxic prejudices
and toxic masculinity.
Yeah, your study brought up,
they mentioned true self came up a lot.
I wonder how much true self is,
um I I this is me without rules not this is is this who I really am or is this who I am when
the boys all want to be bad and I want to be bad together like does it just feed that kind of nature
and do the males just kind of assume that's their true self because this is what I am without rules
and when it thinks of me like I hope
I know you're saying this is just me.
This is just me speculating.
But but but you do have to wonder, can they be their true selves
when there's so much emphasis on being hypermasculine and
and embracing violence?
You know, is is some of it posturing, especially with young boys?
You know, are they really feeling that?
Or is that or do they have to emphasize hypermasculinity
in order to feel like they belong?
Yeah, it's definitely a problem.
And I mean, like you said, with the bullying being an issue
and all the homophobia slurs getting thrown around,
like, are you being your true self
or have you been kind of cowed into this position?
So it's feeding a lot of like negative stereotypes
to your point.
So I think just to jump in on that as well, it seems like, you know, one of the things
that the study, you know, seems to point to is like, yeah, just these spaces being opportunities
for male identifying folks and cis men, especially like being able to connect, right?
you know, and I want, and to some extent it's because like the parameters that the rest of
society is set is like, oh, these are the ways in which you like, number one, can connect,
you know, in this, in this like very limited kind of, in this very limited kind of way.
So that's kind of one part of it, like, oh, if there's sort of, if there are sort of other types
of, um,
sort of like more pro-social environments, which, you know,
which, and this is like, this is beyond a games problem,
right, because this is again, like, this is what the,
this is like a societal problem writ large, as we know,
as many things are.
So I think that's, that's sort of one part of it.
The, the other thing that I thought was really interesting
about like the study to speak to that kind of power fantasy
element of games is,
and I think you touched on this earlier, Gina,
when you said,
that in terms of sort of representations of like aggression, etc.
It's white male protagonists who are enacting those without
without sort of like other reasons.
And I think one of the things that I found interesting about the study
is looking at like, oh, when there are characters of color
who are also being.
being violent in some way or being aggressive in some way,
often it's for this larger social good,
which is sort of like a trope in itself, right?
But it's just interesting.
Like, I just thought that was an interesting finding
from the study.
Definitely a little piece that came out of it.
Sorry, I was talking to you.
No, I was just going to say, I did find it very interesting that that
white characters were so much more violent than than characters of color.
It's not like we say, hey, let's make it equal.
Let's get the characters of color more violent.
It's let's get the white characters less violent.
All right.
So I know we're kind of we're heading towards the talk about management, but I wanted to ask,
and maybe this is unfair to ask me too, but what do you feel that individuals working at
game development companies like all the way down the ladder can push and do to help like work for
better representation and deter toxicity sexism and those things? And I mean we've seen again
those gross allegations go all the way up the ladder. We've talked about how it's that change
really needs to come from up top. But I mean what can...
your white guy in the office do, like, what do we need to do?
Yeah, I mean, yes, oof, again, what a day to be.
Yeah, I think this is, I think we need to talk about it today.
Absolutely. And, you know, and I think that, firstly, you know, just
reiterating that ultimately, these problems go up to leadership, right?
Like that is ultimately like, it's these things start from the top.
So companies and leaders need to have values where they care about these issues.
And often, you know, and the way that I look at it, and often, yeah, it's
it can be complex as well, because it's not to say that.
Folks from marginalized backgrounds can't also, you know, if they've bought into these
hegemonic ideas, they can't also perpetrate this.
But I think, you know, it really does come from a question of values from the top, because
that's also like, who gets you listened to at the company?
Who gets supported at the company?
What is the overall culture at the company?
So that's definitely one part of it.
In terms of sort of every, like, you know,
just folks who are not in leadership positions necessarily.
I mean, firstly, you know, we as an industry
need to support marginalized folks
being able to get to leadership positions because.
It's not just a pipeline problem.
This is what I say.
And you know, I'm lucky enough to be like a,
if then STEM ambassador, like I do all kinds of work
to sort of help get more folks into the industry.
But the biggest problem is that once they're there,
they're not being supported and able to stay.
And that's because they're not.
you know, it's at the least worst end of the spectrum, it's because they're not being listened
to. And as we've seen in the worst end of the spectrum, it's, you know, stuff like what's
coming out in the allegations, which is like, just sort of the tip of the iceberg in a lot of ways
in terms of like the what really is going on. So one of the last thing I'll say about that is that
it is incumbent upon allies, often like cis white men, allies to
step up and intervene when they see these things happen. There's all kinds of things that can be
said about that, but the burden shouldn't be on marginalized folks to drive the change,
and often it is us who is doing it. So that's another thing where, again, who gets listened to?
Where is the locus of power in the industry? So that's something we need to disrupt.
There's definitely a lot of marginalized folks literally just thrown into the wolves for
a claim of diversity when nothing is actually changing in management.
Maybe I'm just speculating on this point, but perhaps some of that community feeling
could be of value.
Because like, Gina, to your point, like the males feel there's a sense of community and
working with that.
But there's...
The people in power who cause these errors feel they're all right in it.
I mean, this is perfect.
This is, again, this is just my speculation.
So meeting those walls of like their peers saying, hey, no, this is not right what you're
doing uses that sense of community and games to show them, no, this behavior is not acceptable
because when we're silent, I think everything's fine.
All right, so let me tell you, you smashed through my next question.
Oh, sorry.
No, it was perfect. It's like, shoot, you're doubling up on my questions. All right.
I got another one on, let's say,
like the platform holders for like Twitch and that,
not just, Twitch just came for a moment,
it's not the one I'm specifically calling out,
but like streaming platform holders.
Do we feel they have some responsibility
and who kind of, who gets pushed to the front
as their popular streamers
and you know, what we can kind of work with there?
Gina, do you have any thoughts on that?
So, so say it again.
Sorry, I phrased that really funny.
Do we wonder if streamers, like stream platform holders,
like where you're getting your footage for your study,
if they have some responsibility they could possibly work
or tools they could possibly work with
to kind of promote more positive representation?
Well, right.
They would have to be creative about it.
In other words, they would have to sort of...
maybe talk about the limitations they feel the game has,
or maybe, you know, it'd be helpful if they talked about
ways that they could creatively think of changing,
getting away from as much violence
and getting more creativity and cooperation in the games
and less stereotyping and hyper-masculinity.
I mean, they're certainly incredible influencers,
so it seems like they should be part of the conversation
if they would like to help impact the industry.
And yeah, so jumping on that as well.
Yeah, I think if your question is like,
do platform holders have responsibility to shift the picture of representation in the industry?
My answer is absolutely yes.
doing more and some platforms are starting to do this and certainly the conversations around
race that started last summer definitely pushed more of these platform holders to
have those conversations and push marginalized folks in terms of who gets featured, etc.
you know, we exist. Like, there's, you know, there's, there's plenty of streamers out there
from, from, you know, from diverse backgrounds. And I want to shout out to communities like
Black Girl Gamers, Brown Girl Game Code, you know, the Noir Network, like there are just,
you know, there are communities where, you know, you can find all kinds of, you know,
all kinds of other voices to profile and to sort of give a platform to.
So if we want wider systemic change, that is a really key part of it.
It's vital for those platform holders to take a hand in it.
Gina, do you feel there's any aspect of the study I haven't touched on that you kind of wanted to push forward or talk about?
No, you've covered a lot of it.
You've done an excellent job so far.
I can't think of. I'm sure I hadn't missed any important kind of elements of it.
Right. Right. So
is the study going to become available publicly anytime soon?
Yes, it is. It's it's available on our website, which is CJane.org
S E E J A N E.org.
Yes. It just got released today, right?
Yes. Yes.
which is exciting.
So, like I said, I got to have a sneak peek at it.
So yeah, excited for other folks to see it as well.
Yeah, it's very exciting, very interesting.
Yeah, has anyone been requesting the study
or like, I guess, what's your next step from here?
Well, do events like this promoted
and bring it to attention,
hopefully be in some articles about it.
And...
you know, move forward, you know, we really value our relationship, our partnership with Promundo,
so we can intend to keep working with them on this type of thing and see if we can make some progress.
Sounds great. So, we're really looking at kind of management as being a central issue here.
So, and we're pushing, we would like to see more marginalized people in positions of management.
This is a difficult question to ask, but how do we think that can happen?
Is there ways we can see the industry, like the bigger giants in the industry,
like help make that change?
So I think from my perspective, it's, you know, it's, it's, there's multiple facets to it, right?
As I was saying before, it's creating environments where marginalized folks are not leaking out of
the industry, right? Like there is a huge leaky bucket problem, as we call it. There's the old
adage that within games, if you've...
If you've had a career longer than five years, you're deemed a veteran because the dropout rate from the industry is so high.
It's high for anybody because there's such a burnout culture in many ways, but then that's especially true.
you know, for marginalized folks.
So that aspect, absolutely,
like allowing folks to survive in the industry
long enough and thrive, you know,
let's just not survive.
Let's like, let's create conditions for people
from marginalized backgrounds to thrive in the industry
such that they can reach these positions
of leadership and management.
So that's definitely one of them.
And I think secondly, in terms of, because, you know, one of the things that I'm lucky enough to see
through the work I do as an educator and just, you know, just being able to
say shout out to organizations like Game Devs of Color,
where, you know, there are lots of sort of up and coming marginalized devs
who like have like amazing games and amazing ideas, etc.
But they need.
access to resources and funding.
And that is something that needs to also come from the top
because one of the things that we see
in terms of like indie studios that get formed,
often the ones that get funded
are the ones who've come out of the big Activision blizzards
and the riots and like all of these other places.
So allowing access to funds for folks
from more kinds of backgrounds
is gonna be super important.
Are there any good sources of funding that exist now?
that you're aware of?
Sources of funding.
Yeah, of course.
So, well, it's, you know, this is something I could definitely speak to,
but, you know, there's, I do want to shout out to things like WINGS Fund,
which is something that I'm, you know, on the advisory board for as well,
which is a fund specifically funding folks from marginalized backgrounds
and marginalized genders.
There's also, shout out to Galaxy Fund, which is run by some of the folks who started Glitch.
which is another sort of newer sort of source of funding
who are very interested in sort of pushing forward
the landscape for underrepresented developers as well.
So yeah, I mean, you know, there's just not enough.
And that's the thing, and we need to, you know,
disrupt like who, from more traditional sources of funding,
because like, again, those organizations
that I shouted out to,
it's marginalized folks setting those up often, right?
So, you know, but we need people who are in,
existing sort of seats of power within the industry to also make those changes and hold
those values. Yeah, like we keep saying it comes from up top. Not that, oh, I'm barely hearing
things. All right.
You two are too quick. You literally burned through three prepared questions.
So we are in uncharted territory here.
Gina, I noticed in your study that there has been a little bit of growth over the years.
You notice between your study and I think there was another one done.
What was it, 10 years ago? Or it was quite a bit older.
Oh, that we did or?
Yeah, or at least some of the numbers have gone up very slightly,
but they have gone.
There has been some positive change.
There's some positive change.
OK, sure. Yeah.
I don't have I don't have the old numbers in front of me, but
but yeah, you know.
The change is too glacial, you know, obviously at this point.
This has been, I mean, we could have said all this about games
10 and 20 years ago, the same problems showing themselves.
So it just it needs.
I guess it just needs some enthusiasm to rethink this and see how
how can we really make it
a more positive influence on society, you know, and
and make it even more fun and more interesting and challenging and
and a place to feel
not only welcome, but more supported and safe and inclusive.
Yeah.
So we're seeing any sort of like little, like to Jean's point, glacial changes in positivity,
treatments of like marginalized folks and.
Well, there's yeah, I mean.
Yes, things are definitely moving forward.
You know, there are more, again, you know, there's more marginalized
folks coming into the industry than ever before.
But again, reiterating we need to create the systems of support
to be able to keep them there.
There's the work that we're obviously doing at Glow Up Games.
which is, you know, just a, we're a, we're proud to be like a really diverse studio ourselves,
like I said. So, and you know, we've, we fought hard to get there as well. We're, I think the
first, the first studio of our kind, like the first all women of color founded mobile game studio to
have raised over a million dollars in seed funding. So, you know, there's, there's, there's
change is, is happening slowly. Just, we've got to,
there's a lot of fighting to do to get there and that's something that you know so many of us are
working to change. Yeah I didn't want to imply that there was a we're good now because things
are doing great now we're getting slightly better but no like it's to Gina's point again
change is glacial that we're seeing and as we're seeing in places like the
allegations that Activision Blizzard it's not actually happening probably at all so there's a
lot of
That's stuff that kind of needs to get dealt with at the moment.
Yeah. Well, I have. Oh, sorry.
Go ahead. I was going to say that I would also encourage
people in the industry and create us to to use our research.
You know, it's available to everyone and has some valuable insights
in there for everybody.
So I think it'd be important for for the community to look at that.
I have a question for Gina, actually, if I may.
So I'm curious, because you do so much great work
in sort of other types of media and film and TV
around representation,
what are the sort of similarities you're seeing
and what are the sort of differences you're seeing
between those spaces and, you know,
as you've sort of set your foot in looking at this
in the games industry as well?
Right. Well, yeah, our first
the reason I started the Institute and the and the original
object was to impact on screen character representation
and what kids see, because I felt that there were some
negative messages coming through, especially about females and a profound lack of female characters
in what was made for little kids and why are we teaching children to have unconscious bias from
the beginning. And we've had some really very good success in making a difference in the 15 years
that we've been doing it.
And it's really been through the research.
The research has had the most impact for us
in that a lot of times people aren't aware fully
of what they're making.
They see it one way, but when the research shows
that it's actually another way.
So just learning about what they're actually showing.
helps them realize they need to make a change.
And so we can hope that the research will inspire change
in the same way, sorry, in the gaming industry,
where they say, wow, we didn't realize that that was the case
and how poor our representation is of people of color
and with disabilities and LGBTQIA+.
So let's try making some changes.
So, I mean, that is a hopeful outcome for this.
Yeah, there's some difficulties coming up for,
well, I imagine there are,
with showing people data and having them face
what these unconscious biases.
Right, right.
It's an incredible, you know, powerful,
incredibly powerful unconscious biases
where you literally can't see what it is you're making.
And it was,
It was so eye opening to people when we had I mean, I suspected that
that people weren't adding female characters
because they didn't realize that they weren't including enough female characters.
They thought they were doing right by girls and
but pointing it out to them and helping them see what they're actually making
made all the difference.
And we've actually now the most exciting goal that we've achieved
is that lead characters
being
for lead characters in both children's television and movies made for children,
we've now achieved parity between the male and female lead characters.
So this is monumental.
It's never happened before.
And it's a huge change since we started 15 years ago.
So so dramatic progress can be made.
People just have to be aware that it needs to be made.
Yeah, I love that because, you know, to speak to one of the reasons why I started
Blow Up Games, my company, is, you know, feeling simultaneously inspired by but then frustrated by
the positive state changes that we were seeing in like film and TV, with creators of colour
taking the helm more and more, and more creators of colour.
starting their own production companies and being able to get like have those opportunities,
but then realizing like, oh, like that same change just isn't happening in the games industry. And so
wanting to really sort of step up and, and, you know, try and bring that change into effect. So,
yeah, you know, for, for example, you know, creators like Issa Rae, who, you know,
and we're at Glow Up, full disclosure, we're,
we're working on a tie-in game for her hit TV show, Insecure.
So, you know, just, but that to us, like, speaks to that difference, right?
Between, like, the changes, as you're saying, Gina, that have happened in, you know,
in film, in TV, et cetera.
But, you know, the games industry basically just has a long way to go.
Gina, we really appreciate the work you've put into giving us some hard data
to show the developers.
Like, that...
this needs to move, this needs to change.
These are the, this is the ugly truth on paper.
Like these are the actual numbers and percentages.
It's undeniable.
So thank you so much for putting in that work.
Well, yeah, and that's our goal is to take our study
to all the leading game developers and companies
to share it with them privately
and see what we can encourage to happen.
I want to thank you both for coming out.
And this was a fantastic talk
and I think an important time for it.
Gina, thank you very much.
My pleasure, thank you.
Thank you so much as well for coming out.
If you have anything in closing to say to the audience,
I mean, feel free.
No, just that I love gaming.
Every day, every day I play games far too long.
People say, oh, you're so busy.
I'm like, really, is that why I have...
such a high score on Candy Crush.
So it's a it's definitely probably a mind beat.
I yeah, I love I love playing games and it's important to me.
And so so this is all really fun and and important to me.
And I have two boys, teenage boys.
So, yeah, it's all very important to me.
Yeah, I think that's the vital thing. We all love games and we want them to be better.
That's really what we're asking for at the end of the day.
What folks, Matu and Gina, you're trying to do here. I think that's fantastic.
Yeah, thank you.
So again, thank you so much for coming out today to have this talk.
Thank you to the GDC audience for watching us. And please enjoy the rest of your show.
Thank you. Thanks, everybody.
Thank you. And thank you, Gina.
Great to have you at your first GDC.
Thank you. Thank you.
All right. Take care.