Okay, here we go.
My name is Asher Vollmer.
I made this game called Threes, it's up there.
You might have heard of it.
And most importantly for this talk, I went to USC,
one of my favorite universities.
Yeah, good.
I loved it, I learned a lot for context.
I started in 2008 and I graduated in 2012.
And I've been coming to GDC all those years,
which means that this is my 10th GDC.
And that makes me your resident dinosaur.
Thanks.
And I'm full of wisdom.
OK, so I've got a lot to say.
I'm going to stop talking slowly.
I've got a lot to say.
I'm just going to jump straight to the point.
Here's my number one tip for going indie after college.
Don't do it.
What are you doing?
This is a crazy idea.
Later up, Jenny and Ted are going to talk as well.
And they're lovely people.
And they're going to pump you up.
But I'm on stage right now, and I'm going to be a big old bummer
about the kind of realities of being an indie game developer.
First off, first lesson I wish anyone told me when I was in school
is that game development is super slow.
It's a very, very slow process.
And this was a revelation to me because I had done a million game jams,
and I loved game jams, and I was like,
oh, I can make games at like a million miles per minute.
But that's not really...
what was happening.
A game jam game is usually about like 10 minutes of gameplay, generously, a pretty title screen,
and some music and sound effects, and that's like, oh my god, I made a cool game.
But that is not releasing a video game.
That is making a game jam game.
Releasing a video game looks more like this.
There's playtesting, QA, art, platform integration, reaching out to press and platforms, deciding
when the right time to release, deciding who to give free keys to, getting a lawyer, making
sure all the contracts are signed.
all the stuff and making time to make marketing materials.
Marketing materials take forever, don't forget.
And so that takes forever to do.
And then you'll look back, and you're like, wait a minute.
I only have 10 minutes of gameplay.
Maybe I should think this through before I start
committing to all of this.
Maybe I should spend more time making the game better,
which makes the game development take longer,
because the real main marketing material you need
is a reason that anyone should care about your game at all.
And it's really hard to do that when your game is tiny.
Tom Francis earlier this week, a very smart guy, made Heat Signature and Gunpoint,
proposed this timeline to me earlier this week, and I really like it.
The first step to making a video game is to fully understand your game.
And this will take roughly five minutes to infinity years. Somewhere in there.
And then, step two is to release your game, which will take about a year after that.
So your game will take anywhere from a year to infinity plus one years.
So good luck with that. Also, it's game development.
is incredibly expensive.
Cool thing about college is that it's free,
totally free, no strings attached.
Yeah, not true, but when you're in college,
you have a lot of permission to be in college
and to learn things and to experiment.
And you have this blanket understanding
that you should be enjoying your life
and trying new things and learning and growing.
And as soon as you get out into the real world, all that turns into guilt.
And all that time turns into, like, oh god, money.
Rent is obvious.
Food is obvious.
A lot of you might be thinking, I don't need health insurance.
And that is the worst thing you could possibly think.
Get health insurance.
Oh my god.
And it costs money.
I'm sorry.
But you're young.
It's cheaper than me.
And also, random, annoying junk also costs money.
So life costs money, but also the game itself costs money.
If you're lacking at some talents,
maybe you're not so good at art,
maybe you're not so good at music, whatever,
you wanna make sure that you're collaborating
with people who can do that,
and they're gonna need to get paid somehow.
So that costs money, and also we live in a cool era
where software is subscription now a lot,
and if your game is taking infinity years to make,
that's infinity dollars to have any software.
So games are super expensive.
And also, my next slide is very scary.
And I'm sorry about it in advance.
Here it comes.
You're not going to make your money back
after you release your game.
Sorry.
This is a really sad, scary slide.
But it's just sort of something you
have to accept when you're going into this.
Businesses move in cycles.
Earlier this week, Jeff Vogel of SpiderWeb Software,
who has been an indie game developer for 24 years,
longer than probably a lot of you have been alive,
has actually seen this happen to the game industry.
There was a huge peak very recently with Steam,
making games make tons and tons and tons of money.
But now we've experienced the glut of indie games,
and now we are in the contraction.
So games are making less money than recently.
So just be aware that games are expensive,
and you're not gonna make your money back.
Also, game development is emotionally draining.
I'm sorry, there's so many of these.
I'm emotionally drained giving this talk.
So in college, you have all these amazing support
structures.
Teachers are your mentors.
Classes give you deadlines.
Extracurricular classes give you tons of inspiration.
And then your friends are within a mile radius
to give you critique.
And cool thing is that when college is over,
all those things go away.
Sorry.
And those things are important when you're in college,
because they help you grow as a person.
But surprise, here's a cool fact, is that you're never actually done growing as a person.
So what your job is going to have to be, in addition to making a game,
is also getting all those support structures back into your life somehow.
Which is hard, but possible, but hard.
A quick example is, in the four years since threes,
I've made probably 30 different prototypes, some of which are up here,
trying to figure out who I am and what kind of games I want to make.
And most of these are in some form of abandoned
because I decided that they were not worth my time, which
was a decision that was made.
Anyway, so to recap, game development
is incredibly slow, incredibly expensive,
and emotionally draining.
Are you scared yet?
Because you should be.
Anyway, this is me being a jerk.
Sorry about that.
But I'm here to be real.
And I kind of wish more people would have been real when I was in college
and been up front with this stuff about me.
So if you're looking at these and you're still thinking to yourself,
well, I can't really imagine anything else I'd rather be doing with my life.
Well, good. OK. Cool.
Then you might have a chance.
You might even be up for this crazy challenge.
And here are some coping mechanisms for dealing with all these things.
Because life is one big coping mechanism.
Here's some quick tips, quick life hacks.
How to cope financially.
Eat out less.
You're all students, we all eat out at the time.
Stop it.
Stop what you're doing.
Learn what food you love to eat out the most and learn how to make it.
And then you can buy all the products in bulk,
and you'll save a ton of money, and you can be indie for longer.
Also, use your freezer.
This is a huge look up Google how to use your freezer
effectively.
This is a huge thing.
It's going to save you a million dollars.
And bike instead of using a car.
Oh, and also, rev share if you can't pay people up front.
But make sure that you're doing it ethically.
Always pay people for their work.
Make sure that they can support that.
That's coping financially.
Here's how to cope emotionally.
I'm running out of time.
I'm sorry.
Make time for people. Like, cool, you're making a game, it's your whole lifeblood.
If it fails, you fail. I'm sorry. But make sure you have time for the people in your life,
because you will feel so isolated otherwise. Make time for exercise. Another cool life hack.
Instant, like, you feel better when you exercise. Who knew? Take classes. Like I said,
you're never done growing. Improv, pottery, doesn't matter. And finally, reevaluate regularly
how you're doing. How is the process? What's it like?
Has this been good?
Don't reevaluate daily, hourly.
That's a mistake.
I've made that mistake.
Look back on the week or the month and be like, was this a good plan?
And then make a new plan and then stick with it.
And here's how you cope with the passage of time.
You don't.
Sorry.
Be young, I guess.
You did it.
Anyway, I just want to apologize one last time for this talk.
I've been a terrible person, but my goal is to help you find some way to cope.
And look out at the indie life and see that it is a very rough road ahead.
And if you are still somehow convinced that that is the right thing to do, there are ways
to do it.
Anyway, thank you, and good luck.
Can everyone hear me? Yeah? All right. Oh man, I'm so tall. Okay. Hi, everyone. Thank you for coming to my talk about going indie after college.
My name is Jenny, and I go by Qdork on Twitter and Instagram, and I graduated from the NYU Game Center's BFA program for game design last year.
During my time as an undergrad, I collaborated with AP Thompson,
another graduate from the MFA program,
and we worked together on a couple of games together.
We submitted our games to festivals like the IGF,
Fantastic Arcade, and Indiecade, and MPD Design and Programming,
while I mostly contributed art to these projects.
Together, we made this game called Stellar Smooch.
It's about kissing and loneliness in space.
Stellar Smooch got an IGF nomination for Best Student
Game in 2015.
The following year, we teamed up again to make BeGlitched,
a pastel match-three roguelike about insecurity
in computers and ourselves.
BeGlitched won best student game at the IGF in 2016.
So those are a couple of games AP and I worked on together.
I also like to code and design games on my own,
so here are some projects I made solo.
This is a game I made for a class
where you have to put on your makeup in 10 seconds or less.
It's called Morning Makeup Madness.
And here's another game where you have to put this noodley-limbed avatar through a series of challenging workout poses.
For my capstone project, I started working on a personal game about dieting.
It's called Consume Me, and it's still a work in progress.
While I was in school, I posted my work in progress and game development to social media, and that helped me get my name out there.
It all led to awards and getting opportunities to give talks about my work.
By a lot of people's definition of success, they might think I'm successful.
But you're also thinking, hey, maybe she just works really hard
and put in a lot of effort to get to where she is.
Well, I think we know that's not the entire story.
Has anyone heard of survivorship bias?
Here's a comic which pretty much sums it up.
So survivorship bias is a cognitive bias that
occurs when someone tries to make a decision based on past successes
while ignoring past failures.
Popular media often tells us the story of this determined
individual who pursues their dreams and beats the odds.
There's much less of a focus on the many people that may be
similarly skilled and determined but fail to ever
find success because of factors beyond their own control
or other seemingly random events.
And this creates a false perception that anyone can
achieve great things if they just have the ability and make
the effort.
Hard work and effort do matter, but there's more to success
than just that.
A lot of people are going to talk about their success,
but not mention the advantages and privileges they have.
So here are some that you may have never realized I even had.
First of all, I don't require any food or sleep.
I can pull all-nighters, and I just
happen to be born with an unlimited resource of energy,
talent, and creativity.
I have never, ever felt depressed, or sad,
or hopeless in my entire life, not even in a single day.
And I'm the life of the party, both online and offline.
I've never felt lonely, and I definitely don't have social anxiety or anything.
Finally, I'm also undying and perfect, the alpha and the omega, the beginning and the end.
So, if you haven't realized it at this point, basically, success is something you're born with.
And if you weren't born successful, I'm sorry, I can't help you, you better just leave this talk.
Okay, that was a joke. I hope you got that it was a joke.
But here are some real disclaimers I'm going to mention.
Yes, I worked really hard and put in a lot of effort to get to where I am, but I would
be nowhere without these privileges and advantages.
I graduated from a great university without student loans.
I didn't have to worry about my living situation after I graduated.
My parents lived in the city and I lived with them during part of my time at NYU.
I got to collaborate with some pretty fantastic people.
My school gave me access to a lot of good resources,
like professors and friends, and I
couldn't have made any of these award-winning games
without AP.
BGLICH gave me a safety net.
It made me enough money, which meant I had some time
to experiment and continue making my own stuff.
And to reiterate and put everything into context,
I got to do what I do because I graduated school
without this pressure of finding a job
and supporting myself financially immediately.
So just remember to put success into context when you hear other people talk about their
success stories.
Stuff that worked for me might not work for you, and your path to success might not look
like mine.
However, it doesn't mean that you can't succeed.
This advice is probably going to be more useful if you have certain similar circumstances
to mine.
However, you still might be able to take away some of these points, even if we don't have
a lot in common.
Because at the end of the day, success still ultimately
boils down to luck, like winning the lottery.
And though I can't tell you how to win the lottery,
I can give you advice on how to buy some more lottery tickets.
So a lot of you who want to go indie might have this mindset.
I want to pour in the next five years of my life
and all of my savings into making this one game.
And you better believe it's going
to be all worth it in the end.
My first piece of advice is don't
try to make that ultimate game.
Your thesis project won't be the end-all, be-all.
It's a common mistake.
Making The Ultimate Game was the reason why I wanted to go indie.
Konsumi was my capstone project, and I was doing everything on my own.
I was coding, designing, and doing art.
I wanted to take Konsumi and finish it by myself.
But I had a lot of trouble being my own boss.
I didn't know how to work on a big project by myself.
I struggled with planning out a large, ambitious game,
with time management, with setting deadlines
I could follow through on.
I constantly felt like a huge disappointment to myself.
At the same time, I also had to deal with burning out.
The transition to life after graduation was hard for me
because I felt alone and hopeless a lot of the time,
which made it extremely difficult to solve big design
problems and to really make any progress at all on my game.
So this is how I felt a few months
after going indie after college.
So to reiterate, don't try to make that ultimate game,
especially if you plan to work on it by yourself
and don't have a lot of experience doing it.
Instead, assume that you're probably going to continue making games after you release the current one you're working on.
So it's time to scope down.
Smaller projects let you explore your ideas in a less risky way.
Think about spending one month on exploring one design idea versus five years. One month is way less risky, duh.
And each project you work on and release is like buying another lottery ticket.
However, the more tickets you buy, the better of a chance
you have to end up successful, because unlike gambling
or winning the lottery, you aren't starting back from zero.
You're gaining skills and learning from mistakes
with each game you ship.
All of this will make you a better developer,
and you can apply every single one
of these valuable lessons you've learned to the next project
you choose to work on.
So here are some examples of small projects
that let me experiment with different stuff.
I got commissioned to make each of these games
after I was finished with school.
Here's Bredna, help Bredna clean her room.
It took around one month to make it, and I collaborated with AP again, and he programmed it.
It was for PlayNYC, and I even made a plush controller for it.
Hungry Buddies, a game where you have to feed your friend the food they're hungry for.
I'm in this game for the Luge Vipo arcade in France.
And finally, here's Pip Squeak.
Pip Squeak's a goofy dog who likes walking around and eating eggs.
There are 20 levels.
It's the biggest project I made mostly by myself.
It was part of Fantastic Arcade's bundle last year.
Anyway.
These smaller projects not only let me explore new ideas,
they also taught me how to scope better
because I am definitely a person who needs external deadlines
to get things done.
They also gave me space from consume me,
which I needed so I could approach my design problems
with a fresh and new perspective.
Just remember, making smaller projects
doesn't mean you can't make a big one someday.
Smaller projects can let you test out a design or concept
without investing too much time and resources
if it turns out to be a crummy idea in the end.
Maybe someday you can turn that idea into your big ultimate dream game.
Also, you can't, remember, you can't continue buying lottery tickets if you're burned out or dead.
So I've definitely been close to that there, and it was really not a good place to be in.
Dealing with burning out in isolation were really hard challenges for me,
and I honestly still struggle with that stuff today,
but I do think I've come a long way from where I used to be.
So please be sure to take care of yourself.
Those are some of my tips for buying more lottery tickets.
Remember to look at others' successes in context.
And even though success relies a lot on luck,
you do have the ability to increase the odds.
The most valuable thing about going indie for me
was definitely getting the chance to make my own games
and also my own mistakes and learning from them, of course.
Anyway, whatever you decide to do,
I wish you the best of luck.
Thank you for your time.
Okay, we got 10 more minutes, let's try to make this work.
Hi, my name is Ted Dinola.
Here are some of the things I've worked on
and some of the places I've worked,
but I'm not really here to talk about that,
I'm here to talk about you guys, so let's get on with it.
Many of you are still in school, that is awesome,
because school gives you a lot of unique opportunities.
Asher alluded to some of these earlier,
but there are some things that you can be doing
that'll give you a better chance of success,
both now and going forward in your career.
First off, the game industry is an industry.
It comes down to shipping games and making money,
but in college, you have the freedom to not make things
that need to be commercially viable
or widely distributable.
You can make things that can only be played
with one weird controller, like thread setting,
emotionally challenging games that can only be played
with one person or in one place, like Deadbolt,
or reveal bits about your life and are hard to swallow,
like N2.
Something like Bad News, which is that game
in the bottom corner there,
Literally it requires someone to be manning it full-time as well as a full-time actor and it's one player at a time
So I've never gotten to play it, but I watched for hours as they coordinated this amazing simulation
Jen Sandercox edible games in the top corner stairs a game you literally eat
And then down there in the bottom corners coffee. I'm misunderstanding a live-action play
So these are some really weird stuff and you have the freedom to do it
don't just you know use your projects as a way to like make things that you
think are kind of cool and simulate games you love, make weird stuff as much as possible.
One way you can do that is participating in Game Jams.
There are literally hundreds of these all the time.
They are online, they are local.
I strongly recommend if you have one nearby, go physically and work with people.
But definitely participate in any way you can.
It's a great opportunity to experiment, try out different mechanics in a really safe space.
Some of those ideas can turn into bigger things.
All of you here are really ahead of the game,
because you've come out to an event,
and you've been meeting people and talking to folks
and building those connections.
But find local game meetups in your areas.
If you don't live near a major city,
there's still independent game development organizations,
a great one, and you can find folks to talk to.
If they don't exist in your area, think about making them.
But definitely meet up with other developers
and talk to them and find out what they're doing.
That kind of brings me to networking.
You know, we've all heard about networking.
Very important to making connections.
But this is a really, it's not a bunch of cogs and gears.
It's not a transactional thing.
It is about making friends and appreciating what they do.
This is a title by Porpentine, by the way.
And if you're not familiar with their work, you should.
It's all of our job, though, to connect with each other
and build each other up.
Specifically.
All the people in this room right now,
you're all in similar positions.
Make friends, keep in touch, find out what you're doing
because in five or six or 10 years,
you will be able to help each other,
you'll find needs for folks.
And it's our jobs to boost each other up together.
Similar to that is mentorship.
Mentorship is like networking but cross-generational.
There are several people without whom
I would not have been able to have such a successful career.
It doesn't have to be a formal process,
it's not like Johnny Tremaine.
working at the silversmith.
It can be something as simple as just keeping in touch
over emails, showing your builds out,
messaging someone at 3 a.m. because you have a job offer
and you're not sure if you're gonna take it.
But it's incredibly valuable.
Feel free to shoot us all emails and Twitters and stuff.
We will try to help you out because it's really scary.
But that said, let's talk about going indie after college.
You may remember Asher's slide.
This is no surprise.
Don't do this to yourself.
At least not.
full-time. I'll get to more of that later, but here are some reasons why you really shouldn't.
Kind of expounding on what these two talked about. You guys don't know how to work. And I don't mean
that in like the old man way of like, young kids are shiftless and they can't work and they're
lazy. I mean you will work yourselves to death. And that is not something you want to do. This
is a slide from an amazing Twine game, and I do not know the maker of it, but it is called Retro
by the aptly named Starving Indy. There are a lot of things to consider and you
haven't really had experience with them yet. You have a whole lot to learn and
there are things you can do to enable that. Working by yourself in a vacuum
with singular vision, that can work sometimes and there are several
folks who have had really great success but working with a team allows you to
learn a lot more and much more quickly and most importantly it allows you to
avoid
Really bad habits. Just as one small example here,
this is a material graph from an Unreal game on an amazing tumbler.
There are a lot of easier ways to do this, but if that's how you've been doing it for years,
you're, you know, good for you. You're spending a lot of time.
Of course, something that we all know about is this industry is incredibly volatile.
This is a chart I'm sure most of you have seen.
This is Steam games released by year.
Ooh, look at that.
So in 2012, there were 403 games released total on Steam.
There were over 7,500 released last year.
Many of you may not be familiar with this corollary chart.
This is median copies owned per game.
So if you were releasing a game in 2012
and had some modicum of success,
you could totally run a business off of that.
230 is not a small number.
But 5,000 last year is not something that's sustainable.
Also note that Steam Spy includes keys handed out, so this number is inflated.
I'm going to talk real fast about two games that I released at different times in my career,
and why they were kind of successes or failures.
This first one was a game with balls.
You probably haven't heard about it, and that's totally fine.
It was a kind of a cash grab iOS thing that did okay.
We set this game up for success.
We developed it on a really short cycle,
budget was super low, we made deals with Amazon
to have them featured on the Android store,
but things didn't go so great.
See, 2010, Amazon store was new on Android,
they didn't have filtering, so whole bunch of folks
with OG Moto Droids downloaded the game.
I don't know if you've tried to run a Unity game
on an ARMv5, but it doesn't really work at all,
so that was one start to death.
On iOS, things were a little bit different.
We had pretty solid sales for the first three to four days,
and then suddenly I noticed sales drop off
and unique user count skyrocket,
because we had been picked up by this amazing store
called Appulous, which gave games away for free.
And so we pinned a lot of our success as a company on that,
and it just did not pan out,
because you can't predict these things.
Let me fast forward, though, to a couple years later.
I had been working, actually, for a bunch of really, really large mobile social studios
like Zynga, making exciting stuff, and I'd gotten sick of that, so I decided to take
the money and the skills they had given me and go make an independent game with some
friends.
Breed Only Memories, we originally planned to take like eight months to make it.
We realized super early on that content is very, very, very time-consuming to make, and
so we re-scoped about two years out.
And during this time, none of us were really crunched except near conferences.
Most of us had savings to live off of because we weren't getting paid actively.
And we made something that I really value.
Now, at the end of the day, this, to me, is a successful game.
That said, I've not gotten much money from it.
It sold pretty well, 273,000 copies, I think, on Steam alone.
But that money all goes somewhere.
We had a huge number of folks to support.
We had a lot of development time.
I got to make this and be very happy with it, and now I work at Oculus because that's
how it works.
You make a thing out of love, and then you release it.
Shameless plug, by the way, this is coming out on Switch soon, so feel free to check
that out.
Anyways, some caveats here, because I don't want to end on a down note.
And hopefully, like you guys, if you've been reading into these things, it's not really
a down note.
There are things you can do still.
Definitely make games in your spare time.
You should be doing that all the time.
You should definitely be participating in jams
to do that as well.
Make games in between jobs.
It gives you a sense of regularity and purpose,
and it lets you polish your skills.
But also, more importantly, it gives you something
to show to future employers.
It was actually a very early version of a game with balls
that landed me my first gig.
And I think that you should definitely
be doing that for folks.
This is my content information up here.
Feel free to take a picture of that or anything.
And if you have any questions.
Reach out to me. I will help you or if like if you're like I have a really are specific question
I will get you in touch with someone that has gone through that same path
Also, there are lots of programs that can help you out if you've made a VR game before
We have a program called oculus start that's if you just google that you'll have all the confirmation
We can get you hardware. We can get you support tickets
It's really great, and I'm doing this because I believe in all of you and just like you I want to power us all up together
And I ran a little bit fast, but thank you so much