My name is Michał Staniszewski. I came from Poland.
I was active on the demo scene since 1997.
I was presented there by a hand with a bonsai from Plastic.
Today I will talk a little bit about the creative process of making our recent project Bound.
So I will show the trailer of the game so you will have like,
you will know what I will talk about later on.
Okay, so who is Plastic?
Plastic is a small studio in Poland specializing in making really experimental stuff, different experiences.
We have roots in the demo scene since 1997 and we've made a couple of demos that were nicely received in Europe.
And then Santa Monica Studio External contacted us in 2006
and asked us to make an interactive something for PlayStation 3
because they wanted to create a digital community on PlayStation 3
and asked several groups, Temosin groups, for help.
And we made Lingering Shadows.
Some of you may remember it.
And then we've made Datura, which was another experimental production
designed for PlayStation Move.
And at that point, we were having tiny experiences with very early virtual reality.
And it was too early for that game, for that time.
Okay, so after Datura, we were thinking what to do next.
And we've made Godzilla to refresh the engine.
So the thing is that we are really a weird studio that
makes an engine for each of our projects, which is pretty
crazy, but it actually works.
And we're thinking that what we are good at, and we went
back to the productions from the demo scene.
And we were still looking for a new direction.
We knew that we were good technically.
We could make a lot of stuff on screen dynamic
without too many problems and fighting with the technology.
But at the same time, Journey was released,
which was a great emotional game,
maybe more an experience than a game.
And I always wanted to make a game
with a strong female character, like in Miyazaki movies.
But most importantly, my son was born.
It was six years ago.
And this got me thinking into a family theme.
So at first I called it Equality.
And the code name for it was The Princess.
It was a narrative, it's supposed to be narrative, not game with a fragility of the family as a main team
presented in a form of metaphor.
But it was like a very ambitious on paper, so actually it also contained persistent multiplayer world
with structures based on a lot of iterations from different players.
But we also were thinking about speedrunning element,
because we were working with different digital communities.
We were working with Demoscene.
We were working with Katsila, which
is the overclockers community.
And right now, we wanted to work a little bit with speedrunners.
But the most important thing was the concept
of showing the story in a way that the players will
have a different view on it and they would judge on its own.
So, in the family problem presented in the game,
we didn't want to show anyone from the family as particularly bad
and leave the interpretation to the player.
So at some point we had the first working prototype.
Like I said, we are rewriting engine for every project.
So we had those design blocks and tools
written from the scratch.
So these are like simple shapes with physics and working camera
around the character, like the TPP camera,
the events that change the camera.
But the thing was that I...
For the 3D platformer, I needed more depth and visibility,
so I asked one of the programmers to add me a lighting.
And we got the first look of Unreal World.
I always wanted to have in this project the red sky
and the ocean of cubes that would cover the distances between the architecture.
The Red Sky is inspired by a demo scene production from 2002 called Chimera by Halcyon.
And it's a very, very important production because it's a milestone in terms of dividing a moment
where the demo scene was not mostly about competing programmers and competing artists, but...
the demo started to,
they wanted to present some kind of content
and some kind of meaning, and to became an art form.
And Halcyon was done by, in 2002,
it was supposed to be shown
on one of the biggest demos in parties,
but it was disqualified because it was too abstract
and organizers didn't feel that it fits into the category.
The interesting thing about Chimera is that the music for it, like the ambience, was done
by Jako Izalo, a croaker, and he's one of the original authors of Angry Birds.
So he designed the characters in Angry Birds.
So you can start with such design to go completely different places.
And the Ocean of Cubes is inspired by a 64K intro, Texas, from 2008, made by Keyboarders.
It was the first production on the Demos team that used geometry shaders.
We had lighting in Unreal world, but we were still thinking that what will be the actual look.
We were at this point thinking about those as not the actual graphics,
but we knew that the long shadows are very important for a production.
On the other front, I was trying to design a mechanic.
that will cooperate with the story where the character wipes away her memories
and thus making the world disappear.
So this concept was pretty unique, actually I felt it was unique,
but later on I discovered that 3D Mario World has exactly the same mechanic
in the more difficult levels.
But this kind of look didn't...
I asked for showing it in a different way and we've changed it to dividing the cubes
that we already have.
into smaller chunks, and actually we were surprised that it worked so well, and it was
pretty simple.
So the thing is that we didn't have any kind of physics in there, just mathematics that
just displays the blocks if they are more distant from the character.
No physics was used because the maths are just faster and we could show a lot and a
lot of those chunks.
And we were iterating on those elements and we got inspired by modern art.
I will talk about it later on in the talk.
But we had to design some extra mechanisms, like control zones,
who tell the designer what parts of the world are more visible.
And there was tons of parameters.
But in the end, we've managed to shrink it just
to the minimum and maximum distance
when the displacement happens, and minimum and maximum distance
when the scale happens.
But we also had zones to maintain the architecture of the Unreal world if we wanted to show some
kind of buildings in the distance.
And also we had a scripting, a simple scripting of the destruction so we could use it in cutscenes
and completely hide them or to reveal them or simple things.
But our game also is about memories, so we started to write another piece of code with
the fragments that come together when you get closer, so you could see what's inside
the memories of my character.
The funny thing about it is that it was running entirely on GPU,
but together with the gameplay mechanics.
So actually, GPU, we've checked on GPU which chunks got into their places,
and based on that, we've opened the door to the next parts of the game.
The chunks were pre-processed, but it was very, very fast, so...
Whoa.
Thank you.
And we had to iterate more on the memories because black and white was like grayscale,
was really hard to read by the players and we've added diffuse lighting so the characters
could be seen as different.
The overall design of the memories is mostly influenced by Gone Home.
So environmental storytelling works best when the items are placed in the places where they actually should be.
But it was still hard for the players to read what's happening in there.
And we ended up going back with the textures that have pre-baked lighting.
and to make the characters more distinguishable from each other.
We had to use the standard uniforms for kids, so blue and pink,
change the haircuts so players will exactly know that this is a boy and there's a girl.
And we had a lot of work with balancing those memories,
so none of the characters would be felt that it's always bad,
or at some particular moment that it's like domestic violence is happening.
Okay, so we had the first solid prototype,
and it had like an animated character,
and the Unreal world was mostly working.
We've changed the name of the equality project
to Yorkingdom.com.
So it took us around 20 months to get there
with three programmers and me.
Okay, so right now I will talk a little bit
about the modern art.
So, for that prototype that you have seen, we had a biggest problem of that the world
was looking mostly constantly the same, and we decided to explore the modern art since
at some point it was based on the primitive shapes.
And we found that Piet Mondrian's work
would work great because it's based on the squares and there are just five colors, red,
white, yellow, blue, and black, and it worked.
So if we used those colors in the Unreal world, it was really working nicely.
But the thing is that, more importantly, we had those elements that reminded me of the
paintings from Suprematism.
These paintings are really interesting because they have a special way to do them.
So the thing is that the picture needs to be looked at as a whole and not as some fragment
elements.
So if we had in this middle painting a red line...
Normally, your eyes would go in that direction,
so it's balanced in a way that there are added black squares in the bottom.
But the most important thing about the suprematism is not actually the painting itself,
but the idea.
So it's a form of conceptual art that arised,
and like Kazimierz Malewicz was saying,
it's the supremacy of pure artistic feeling.
So I will concentrate a little bit on that,
because I know there's a lot of people that have problems with modern art
because they think that it's just simple
and why they should be excited about the black square on a white background.
But actually, to understand the modern art and conceptual art...
You need to look at the context.
So in case of supremacy, you need to go back to the whole art that was created by man since
the cave ages and understand that the human was trying to reach the realism.
And when he finally did it, he knew that we as a human race can do it, and we can deconstruct it.
And then the Impressionism arrived, and then Cubism.
In the end, the Suprematist was created, and this is the context for that.
But in Bound, we were mostly concentrating on how it looks.
So, except for the paintings, we were looking at the modern art,
like Bauhaus for architecture.
And we discovered that the modern art museums
are made from the shapes that can be recreated in the game.
And actually some parts of those museums are in the game.
You can try to search for them.
But we still had this problem that those blocks looked similar and similar.
So we've implemented a simple decal projection system that was putting little paintings on
those shards in Unreal World, and it was implemented in such a way that when the shards got dissolved
and displaced, the painting stayed on them.
So for each of the levels, we decided to make a tribute for modern artists of 20th century.
So for example, Laszlo Mahalinaš, in one of the levels, he was using simple geometric
shapes involving transparency.
But Laszlo has a lot of great works in conceptual art.
For example, think about this.
One of his performances.
involved calling his friend on the telephone
and telling him to draw a painting.
And when the painting was done, based on his descriptions over the phone,
he asked if the painting was actually his art or his friend's.
Think about it.
And next is August Herbin, for example.
He was like concentrating on triangles and spheres and mixing them, inverting,
and they got into one of the levels of the game.
But also Yayoi Kusama, who is also a great conceptual artist,
and she is in love with circle shapes and polka dot patterns.
So, the implementation was very simple.
We had those kind of simple paintings stored in an array of texture with colors and transparency
and we projected the coordinates and stored in a vertex attributes of those flying shards.
But now I will go to dance, which is another part of my presentation.
The princess in the very beginning was not a dancer.
The design was made by Jakub Jabłoński from Platycimic
and she was presented as a runner.
It was a part of the story of the game.
I will spoil it if I will tell why,
but if you will play the game, you will understand.
So we were iterating on the designs of the character
and we decided to choose the delicate direction.
And at first we wanted the princess to go through her life
and portray as a woman,
becoming stronger and faster.
But in the end, because of...
production.
We didn't want to make all those animation sets
and all those characters,
so we decided to have just one,
but she was still a runner.
And we hand animated her.
And all animation system is written by hand.
It doesn't involve any blend shapes, blend trees,
because I thought that they were not needed
and I felt comfortable with such approach.
And at this point, Santa Monica sent us their feedback
and it was pretty devastating.
So designers did not feel like the character
was expressive or felt like a female.
We need to amp up her animation
so that she feels like a unique character.
So the character felt like a game character
and we were making a game after all.
Thank you.
And I was lucky because one of my friends sent me a movie with a dancer, with a contemporary
dancer, and she was having those kind of emotions in her dance.
So I had to do a super fast curse.
Luckily, I was training dance with my wife for a couple of years and it helped me a lot.
So I started to study on ballet, contemporary dance, gymnastics, and even ice figure skating.
I started from ballet and Tchaikovsky was a best start.
Swan Lake and Nutcracker are the obvious ballets to watch.
But ballerinas have a rigid classical set of moves.
They are very rarely doing floor parts, actually, if you watch it closely.
So it's easy to show the beauty of motion with ballet,
but it's really hard to present emotions.
Those moves were designed during a lot of years,
and they are really strict.
But they have a good glossary because of that,
and it was easier to communicate with the choreographer.
On the other hand, contemporary ballet has a lot more emotions into it,
and dance is presented in a more literal way.
And finally, contemporary dance, there's a lot of references on YouTube,
and it's easier to go through them.
And I found a lot of great, let's say amateur dancers,
or dancers who were in a contest like So You Think You Can Dance,
like Lydia Phillips, Megan Branch, Olga Kurajeva, many, many more.
And at some point I was understanding the dance to this point that I could predict who will win another season of Surfing Who Can Dance.
But there were problems with glossary, because it's really hard to find it on the internet
to show exactly what move is which one, and it was harder to communicate with the choreographer,
so I had to cut those moves into tiny pieces and then use a tablet to show what I'm talking
about.
But I was also going through gymnastics and this was like a very interesting time.
From gymnastics I wanted to take the cartwheel move and I discovered that the balance beam
motion is really, really interesting.
But there is one thing, the gymnastics from the 80s were great, like Olga Korbut and her
performances during the Olympics and also Nadia Comaneci.
So those gymnasts from the 80s were adding a lot of graceful motion and balletic moves
in between the figures.
And right now, it's just the points and figures, so I actually didn't take anything from current
gymnastics performances, and it's really sad.
On the other hand, ice skating is really great, and especially for me, Julia Lipnitskaya.
And from that I took the motion in the middle.
So going back to the game, the first attempt was like adding dense figures to the character
motions.
I still was using a hand-written system so I could add procedural elements in there based
on an overbroad presentation by David Rosen so the character could look where she walks.
This is how the ballerina walks, if you can see.
So the thing is that when it's really hard to find a running or walking ballerina,
and they usually go more like this to enter the stage.
And this is the one moment when you can see them without making actual dance movements.
So like I said, the character was still hand animated, hand programmed.
And this was the first prototype of dance that we did.
It was very, very rigid, but it was promising.
So from that point I knew that there would be a responsiveness and the beauty of motion
and they don't work together.
So if we want to have a responsive character, then I would have to cut down the blending
between the poses and if I would like to have a nice movement, then I would need to take
off the responsiveness.
And I decided to go with the beauty of motion.
So we were iterating on this and we were finding new poses and trying to animate them by hand,
but at some point it was really, really hard.
It was hard to find the reference of a dancer, for example, walking on a ledge, or a dancer
walking on a ladder.
So there are things on the Internet that are still not there.
There are still some things that you can't find on the Internet.
And we got more and more feedback from the players that they wanted to dance.
So if we will give them possibilities of dancing, then they will just dance in a game.
And it was great.
So it was like the best decision that I did during the project to finally contact the
real dancer and choreographer.
So we wanted a dancer that knows classical ballet, modern contemporary dance,
and would be flexible enough to perform all those cartwheels and gymnastic movements.
And we have chosen Maria Udot and choreographer Michał Gural.
It was like the best pick.
And the first motion capture session was really good.
The dancers were preparing in the hall with mirrors
for one week based on the materials I provided.
And after that, we were performing the session.
It was the first session that we did as a studio, so I was a little bit scared.
And also, it was the first day at work for our new animator, and he didn't work with
motion-captured animation before, so I was double scared.
But in the end, it was really, really superb.
And it was so good that we decided that we need a second mock-up session.
And we decided to change everything.
So all the hand animation that we got in the project was replaced with the motion captured ones.
So including jumps.
But also we recorded cutscenes and they were hard to perform actually.
So what we wanted to have is that in cutscenes the character would behave in a balletic way,
like in an actual ballet stage.
And it was really hard to mock up because we had only animatics,
but thankfully we also had the choreographer,
so he was looking at the animatics and in fly he was like showing up the moves to Maria, how to do them.
And also we recorded full 25, 30 second sequences.
So for players to play with them in a fun way.
And those sequences were different for each of the levels.
And now I will go to the next stage of my presentation about emotional design.
So this is the part of the game that I'm mostly proud of.
So emotional design.
At first we had the first design doc, which was called Equality and was 56 pages long.
And there was everything. Like I said, it's supposed to be a multiplayer game with a persistent world and so on.
But from that design doc only 10% landed and was implemented in the final game.
And the next design doc was just 11 pages long.
We changed the title to Your Kingdom Come.
And we had also an art guide, which
was based on Vimeo stuff pics that I was collecting.
But at this point, we didn't have ballet and modern art.
And the third design doc was the actual presentation
for the pitch at Santa Monica.
And we discovered that.
Probably the VR was the thing that got the biggest attention.
But back to the emotional design.
So the most important thing,
you probably know about it already
if you go to the other session,
and it's good to tell it more and more and more,
is play testing.
When we were doing Linger in Shadows,
we didn't do any play test at all.
You can believe me that we shipped the game
without testing it with any player.
And it's because we were coming from the demo scene,
and on demo scene, you didn't show your demo to anyone
because it would ruin the competition.
So actually, it was element of surprise
that could make you win the competition.
And that's why you're not supposed to show it to anyone.
And we delivered that in Shadows, but by our surprise, people still enjoyed it.
But Datura had only two playtests, and we made the first playtest when we had like 80
or 90% of the game, and when we did it, we knew that it was a disaster.
So the second playtest didn't change anything at all.
So in Bound we decided that we need to playtest from almost the beginning when we had the
working prototype and we had around 50 of them.
But it's important to make it properly.
So it's not in a way that the whole team stands in the back of the playtesters.
Of course, you do it in a normal playtest, like during the jams or during the showcasing
your game.
But when you make an emotional game, it's really important that the tester is alone
with the game.
Because every single joke, every single word, and every single explanation will break the feeling of the game.
So it's good to prepare a playtest room.
So this is a room from Santa Monica, but probably if you're a small developer, you will not be able to use it.
But you can just have a single place, like separated place, and use private streaming to another place where you can review it.
It's super easy on PS4, it's also very easy on PC, and I encourage you to do it from the start.
And also a good thing is to prepare a questionnaire in a networked form, so you could have those answers and send them to your team.
And during this playtesting, during the last ones, we managed to notice that actually the
game started to work.
It was very late in the production, but this is something that we wanted to achieve and
it started to work.
So basically we divided the players into two groups.
Those that were emotionally connected and those who were emotionally disconnected.
So emotionally connected people were those who had similar life experiences like our
character in the game.
And from this group we've extracted a group of players that had cathartic emotions at
the end of the game, for some working in a therapeutical way.
And players from that group
were not playing the game, they were not playing the princess.
It was princess that was playing their lives.
That was known from the beginning that the main character,
she's a kind of ballerina and modern dancer at the same time.
But the story I got to know when I arrived here,
just before we started working,
and also the story is a bit touching to myself,
is about the woman.
who wants to go on with her life and solve her family issues with her parents.
Her father left the family and now she has to decide if she wants to see him
or she wants to continue be with her mother or other way around.
So I have it myself, my parents unfortunately have separated as well.
An inner fight is quite close to me, also in that age when I'm trying to make decisions.
Whose fault was that and what should I do with it?
I think it's nice also that the people who are going to play the game, they will have them to make their own decision because it's a big decision.
In the beginning I had a chance to see myself put into the skin of the character.
It's very funny to see something else moving like you.
It's a bit abstract, I would say.
But at the same time, we have a very similar body.
She moves as I move, so I make it.
It's going to be looking really cool.
Okay, so in the next part of my presentation I would like to talk a little bit about Bound in VR.
So, with VR we had a very first Morpheus prototype.
It was Santa Monica Studio who sent us their prototype and it was really nice,
but I broke it like in five days.
It shattered in my hands.
But it was enough for us to play the game and run it.
And I've seen that the camera system works for a third-person perspective.
You just need to make it static for those that are experiencing motion sickness.
And because the game was showing the actual performance of a dancer,
we made the camera in such a way that you can get close to the character.
But the game was PSVR compatible, it was not PSVR exclusive, so it was really hard to deliver
that message with the players.
They were mostly prepared that the game is VR or the game is not VR.
And we've made the trailer for the PSVR launch, but we didn't decide to show that trailer
because it actually looked like a normal 2D game, but with a shaking camera.
Take a look.
But, like you have seen in the very last cut of this video, we've made the princess to
look at you when you look at her.
So basically in VR you don't feel like you are the character.
You feel that you are a third person around her.
and you have a visual connection and you can feel the presence.
And when you have a performing artist,
you can feel the presence of the artist in a very close distance.
So this is an important find because normally when you go to a ballet or opera,
you can see the performer in a long distance.
Or maybe if you have a very good ticket.
Normally you sit in a distance and it doesn't feel different like a TV screen, but with
better audio.
And during the motion capture session, we felt that it's really great to be so close
to Ballerina and we've managed to represent the same emotion inside the VR game.
And players really love that.
So, like, this is a comment, the VR mode in this game is incredible and elevates the experience
leagues beyond the 2D mode of play.
But I've also discovered, like, recurring messages like this, in VR it's almost a religious
experience at times.
So what's happening?
Like, what happened?
I was thinking about the presentation of Genova Chen a couple of years back on GDC,
when he was talking about the spiritual feelings inside a game.
And when we live in a city and see a lot of human creations,
it's really hard to get this spiritual feeling.
So it's easier to get it in the mountains,
where you can't see any kind of human-made structures.
Or in a space station,
where you can see the Earth from a distance.
And in Bound we have a word that is based on pure mathematics, so maybe it worked such
way because the mathematics is the language of nature.
Okay, so if you have some questions, then you can use the microphones.
Hi, great, great talk.
Nicole's are from Z design.
I was curious on the emotion palette, the other emotion architecture, the profile,
what were the emotions that were easiest to get in that great combination between
the, you know, the character and the, you know, the environments.
You mean it's like emotions to evoke in a player?
Yeah, I mean like were there... did you...
Actually, that might be just the question itself, it's like...
Did you have like a list of specific emotions you were trying to target and then you...
Did you make adjustments to, you know, to get towards that?
So, in terms of like...
Emotions in dance, I really started from the basics, like the movement.
And we were expanding this, but the choreographer, Michael,
was like, enlightened me about it, how it should be done.
And actually, we didn't design those emotions.
They were there after we got the performance captured.
And yeah, so we were not concentrating on that.
So it's like emotion in terms of the expression of the character, not necessarily going after
fear here or joy here or curiosity there.
Yeah, we had just a couple of places where, for example, fear at this point and so on.
And also we got those elements where she was fighting with her fears.
And this is something that we designed actually,
and then it was made by the choreographer.
So for example, when we had the pearls
that represents one of the fears of the character,
then the motions contain those kinds of movements.
And for example, another one has the paper plane,
so she was hanging her arms.
So yeah, I think that that actually answers your questions.
Thank you.
Absolutely beautiful game. It's amazing. Thank you.
You said when you were playtesting that you found that there were some people who felt attached to the game and some people who felt detached.
Is this kind of like the attached ones liked the game, the detached ones were giving negative feedback of the game?
Yeah, it's a really good question.
So, those that were emotionally connected and based on their life experiences,
there was a part of players that really liked it,
and there was another part that really hated it.
Because, I don't want to spoil the ending of the game,
but there is a decision in the end,
and some of them already did that decision in their life.
And we asked them to make it another time.
And that's why they hated it.
But those who didn't make this decision,
they've seen it in a game, so they could make the first step.
And then they could try to do it in real life.
And like I said, we made a questionnaire.
And in this questionnaire was something like,
what decision you made in the end?
And they were answering this, but another question is,
why did you make this decision?
And this is the moment when they revealed
what they felt about the game and their true feelings.
Do you feel like...
I would imagine it's a bit of a controversial game in the sense that it's not a gamey game with enemies and points and respawn and all the usual things that people sort of demand out of games.
And when you kind of like divide your
response groups into like the likes and the dislikes, you just discard the dislike?
Yeah. Or are you saying like, how do I get more of those dislikes into the like pile? Or you just say, good
I've identified who doesn't like the game and I don't care about them anymore.
I have to make the game for those who have, you know, who I'm, they're kind of on my side.
So the thing is that that was one of the biggest bad decisions that I made in the game to make this kind of polarized audience, one contained with players that are real players, hardcore players like those speedrunners.
and those who just want to experience the audiovisual feelings and emotions in the game
and they don't want that game mechanic at all.
And the thing is that...
So, what I was thinking, if we will deliver things for the players and things for non-gamers...
then they will find their path.
But the problem is when they were crossing paths
and those who don't usually play games
went to a moment when it required some skills,
then they got frustrated.
And those who...
just want to play a game and didn't find those places where it actually needs some skill
were also frustrated because they thought it's like it's easy game without the mechanics
at all.
And there's like a big mechanic for speedrunners because the game can be passed in 120 ways
and one of the ways is the fastest.
And we got like a very tiny small speedrunners working on that.
and they've managed to beat the game in 27 minutes
and it's nicely designed because they drop it like a couple of seconds more and more.
It requires a lot of work and they spend hours in the game
and they are really happy that they discovered that and they think that it's a game.
But in VR mostly, people enjoy the audiovisual,
like the presence of the game and they concentrate on the story.
Even though those players... so VR works differently on real players.
So you say, are you actually concerned about the parts of the game that require a skill
mechanic?
Is that actually fighting the intent?
I guess where have you decided to land?
Who is your perfect player?
Yeah, I was thinking that if we'll manage to get most players from different sides,
it would be the best, but I think I would go in the direction where those players seeking for
emotional narrative storytelling without any skills, because they are already tired of solving
puzzles, fighting and so on, and just contemplate on the audiovisual and story side. I think that
these are our players.
Great, thank you very much.
Thank you.
Hi. Could you talk a bit about the final locomotion system that you put together after you got
the mocap session and how it was informed by your aesthetic understanding? Like, does
the technical implementation, like, was it influenced by your aesthetic understanding
of ballet and dance and do you have a specific example of that?
So the locomotion system is actually really easy, but we...
We motion captured everything, including the walking, running,
and so on.
We just needed to add the loops for it.
And it's really, really simple.
I mean, we are just blending one animation
to another without any sophisticated tools.
We don't need blend trees because we
have one single character without any items.
We don't divide the movement between hands and legs.
So in this term, it was really simple, but still.
What I wanted to do is to have a maximum flow of blending those animations, including when
you walk on a ledge or jump.
So this was what I was concentrating on.
But as for implementation, it's really a black box.
And you wouldn't take anything from that implementation.
It's just like writing and hard coding.
And if I would do it one more time, I would do it exactly the same.
Okay, interesting. Thanks.
Thank you.
Okay, so if there are not many more questions, then thank you.