Let's tell the people about online features for indie devs and programmers without network experience.
So this is a crash course, your first hit, an introduction to the net.
I'm Claire, that was Pixel, and your title will have online features.
You don't need to be a pro to add them.
Even single player titles will plug into Steam and PlayStation servers.
Range of zero upkeep platform services are there for you to use and abuse.
There's some quick wins, naming and shaming the hard stuff, pitfalls that'll lock you back months,
building servers is easier and harder than you think, compression's your secret weapon,
your takeaway, know what you don't know about networking, what fits into your game,
and what you need to google and read up on. Online features for indie devs and programmers without...
oof
oh
It's going to get one more take.