Hi everybody, well that was unexpected.
Welcome to sunny San Francisco and the first day of GDC 2019 and the third State and Future
of Board Games panel which I'm very excited to present this year.
I'm Paul Dean, I'm one of the co-founders of Shut Up and Sit Down, I'm also a writer
and a games journalist.
a wannabe games designer and so many other things, but more interesting than me are three
other wonderful people on a panel who have agreed to appear this year.
Starting as far away from me as possible, I'd like everyone to introduce themselves
because this year we have a particularly awesome panel.
I'm Jen Sandacock. I make edible tabletop games, so they're games that you actually have to eat.
So I've put 13 different games into a cookbook which is part recipes, part rules, and yeah.
Jonathan.
Hi everyone, I'm Jonathan Ying, I'm a game designer.
I've worked with, I've done a lot of game design for a number of different games, including
Star Wars Imperial Assault, Doom the board game, Game of Thrones trivia, and more recently
Power Rangers Heroes of the Grid, Nickelodeon Splat Attack, and Sonic Dice Rush, which is
coming out very soon.
I didn't know about that.
Yeah.
And I've also done games independently, a game called Bargain Quest, which was covered
by Shout Up and Sit Down.
And yeah, I just do a lot of game design.
And Susan.
Hi, I'm Susan McKinley-Ross, and I'm a toy and game designer.
I've licensed over 40 products and over a dozen games.
The most popular is Quirkle, which
has been described as Scrabble with shapes and colors.
Quirkle won the Spiel des Jahres in 2011.
And another game I designed that's done really well
is called Hoot Owl Hoot.
It's a cooperative game where children
are trying to get the owls back to the nest
before the sun comes up.
And because of my toy background,
I'm mostly in the family games market.
Thank you all for coming.
I would like to ask, oh, by the way,
I should tell you all the format for this
for the last few years has always been,
we'll talk about a few topics together on the panel
for about sort of 30, 40 minutes,
and then we'll open up to the floor.
Please come at us with any questions you like.
We have such a diverse range of people this year
that I think you could touch on anything
and someone will have something cool to say about it.
We actually started an hour early in the.
Thank you.
in the speakers lounge by accident just talking about stuff we're excited by.
Can I ask you all what in the last 12 months
has excited you most in tabletop gaming? What do you think
is most interesting right now?
We're going to start down this end, alright, sure.
I mean, we'll just do whatever we want.
I think for me, some of the stuff, I mean, other than like personal successes,
I think some of the stuff I'm interested in is seeing
much more wider recognition of a wider range of tabletop games.
They're not all quite hardcore games.
There's a lot of stuff for families, or light games.
And there's a lot of food-themed games, which I like food-themed games.
I don't get why.
Well, let's see.
There's a couple of things that I've been finding
really particularly exciting.
Some of them are just games,
technology is continuing to evolve,
like manufacturing technology, particularly fantasy players.
There was a talk earlier today about Key Forge, right?
The first unique deck game,
which even like a year ago would not have been possible
to produce just because of the limitations
of digital printing.
And like they've created a whole new method
that have opened up a huge range
of new possibilities for design.
And a lot of that kind of innovation is happening right now, and I'm just super excited to see what's coming down the pipe.
The other thing that I'm really excited about is that there's a lot more multimedia board game stuff going on.
Things like Renegade Games has T-Dragon Society, which is both a board game and a comic book.
and they were working with Oni Press on that, and I just found that really charming, because
a lot of games have wonderful worlds and awesome artwork, and we don't often get to explore
those worlds in the same way that we might explore Star Wars, which exists on every single
possible level.
Oh my goodness, yes.
But if a franchise starts as a tabletop game or something like that, I mean, I guess we
have the Clue movie, but, you know.
And what a fine movie it is.
But yeah, I think those are two things that I'm super excited about that have been coming out this year.
Similarly, I'm really excited about the scope and the variety of games that are available right now.
I feel like there's more interesting mechanics, there's more interesting themes,
there's more interesting materials being used in games like food or toys or water or air.
People are doing new and novel things that I don't think would have been happening five years ago.
I didn't go to Toy Fair this year, but I watched the reports from a website called The Game Isle,
and basically she took photos of...
all the cool games that were coming out and I was looking through them and I was
getting that ping of
oh I wish I designed that and that's an excellent feeling when you're looking at
the games coming out and
and they inspire you to to make things so I'm really excited about the variety
of things that are out
on the market right now.
Well we touched on this briefly before the panel started about is the market going to
saturate at any point because it was, last year it was something like three and a half
thousand new board games came out, which works out about ten new board games a day, which
is too many for me to play.
And Jonathan, you said something like four thousand this year?
Yeah, what I've heard reported is that about four thousand games have been announced or
are already in production this year.
Like, by now, right?
How is that possible? How is there a market for that?
Turns out there's a lot of people, is the other thing, with a fair amount of income,
and also board games are spreading, right?
Like, more and more communities are having access to board games or are learning about it.
I mean, I think we could definitely credit things like Critical Role
for making things like Dungeons & Dragons feel much more mainstream.
And just like the market is continuing to grow when people are finding more and like people are still finding success
You know going for it, and I'm personally a little bit nervous about like how how far we can stretch this
But it's so far
It's continuing to you know trend outward and trend upward and more products and more people buying these products, and it's been crazy
It continues to be crazy
I think as a designer and a gamer, I'm excited about the saturation.
I think the market is saturated.
If I were a publisher or a manufacturer or a retailer,
I'd be much more worried about it because how do you
stock what's going to sell?
How do you know what's going to work for your store?
Many harder choices at that level.
But as a designer and a gamer, it's very exciting.
And I also am worried about the short-term future.
Is this sustainable?
But I think there's some hope that we could eventually
get to a book model.
where there are lots of people who read a wide range of books,
and there will be a lot of people
who play a wide range of games.
And I'm hoping that that's what can happen for our industry.
And then the other thing is, I'm a gamer
who had a game night this weekend,
and Puerto Rico got played.
And Puerto Rico's old.
It shouldn't get played anymore at game nights.
But it's a good game, and it ended up getting played.
And I think we're
There are gamers evolving now who are only going to play games once or twice.
They're not going to keep Puerto Rico on their shelves for years and years and play it over
and over again.
And that's more like the book model.
That's more you read a book once or you buy a book because you're interested in it.
You don't necessarily get around to reading it.
I'm hoping something like that can help the level of market situation that there is.
Yeah, I do feel that this is having an interesting effect on people attempting to create lifestyle
games.
Like, you know, I'm not sure we'll ever get, or it'll be very challenging for another game
to be like Magic the Gathering, where it's like that is the only game some gamers play.
Or like, you know, there's just so many options out there and it's so hard to make it.
your one hobby is following this one game
and all of its expansions.
Now it's like, oh, here's a game I like,
I've played it a couple times,
and if an expansion comes out,
maybe I'll break it out again.
And that is becoming more and more of a thing,
but usually for people who are financially stable enough
to use games as a leisure activity.
They are still, games are still a luxury product,
which is, yeah, has continued to be true.
And they're just becoming a more and more popular luxury product, which is also exciting, but I think we should pay attention to that.
Accessibility is a big deal in board games right now, and as games become more...
more popular, we also want them to become more accessible
to bring in new players.
Because, you know, this is not,
there are a lot of players out there,
but not all of them are interested
in exactly the same themes or exactly the same mechanics.
Some people, you know, want to play games
while having a snack.
I was gonna say, I mean, that could be someone's entry
into tabletop gaming, could be edible games.
That could be this bizarre but fascinating vector
of that spreading.
Yeah, I mean, I do feel like somewhat I've tried to target bakers as well as gamers.
Most of my games aren't super hardcore games, so if somebody is a hardcore gamer, they probably
will bounce off my games a bit, but people who are like, oh, I want to do a fun thing
before maybe I play a hardcore game, or I really love baking and I want to show off
all my amazing baking skills, there's games for that in the book.
So, sort of reflecting on that then, what makes it interesting to be a board games designer now in 2019?
There's a lot of people at GDC who are more and more interested in board games.
Loads of people prototype things on tabletop if they're thinking of going into digital games design.
Why should they stick with board games? Why should a person be a board games designer?
I think partly like Kickstarter is still like there are a lot of games on Kickstarter but
if you have a genuinely good idea it will
come to the surface and people will find out about it.
Because I think there's generally in the tabletop space,
there's people who every week check Kickstarter,
what are the Kickstarters out right now?
And so people are consciously looking through that system.
And so I think if you are able to come up with something
that's able to stand out from the hundreds of games
that are out on Kickstarter at any one time,
then there's a chance for you.
And that feels good that genuinely good products
can still stand out and be noticed.
I mean, sort of part and parcel to the fact that we're getting so many more games coming out, right?
The systems for actually manufacturing those games are becoming more and more accessible, right?
We're having websites like GameCrafter now allows you to do custom punch-outs,
which they weren't doing a couple of years ago.
And all of these things will allow people to make even really small print runs of games
just for themselves, just for their hobby.
And once you have that, maybe you're going to try and like...
run a Kickstarter or maybe you're going to try and pitch it to a publisher.
And that, you know, the barrier for entry for board games is lower than it's ever been,
honestly.
And the ability for people who have access to the internet to create a game that looks
nice and that feels professional really kind of fuels that dream and that desire to make
money.
something cool and to put it out there.
And even as big as the board game market is growing,
people are hungry.
People want, like, with all these games coming out,
players are having a harder time finding exactly the game
that suits the thing that they really personally want, right?
And there was a long time when in video games,
where like people weren't making adventure games, right?
Yes.
And then once, and so no one was serving that market
because that market was considered a niche market.
I think a similar thing is happening in tabletop.
right, where we are able to now make games that are more targeted at a specific group
of people or at a specific audience that is currently underserved or that just like, you
know, they want a new thing that fits their paradigm for their type of gamer.
Yeah, that's fair.
Well, then, I mean, with that in mind, if Kickstarter exists,
if all this infrastructure is appearing,
is Kickstarter the place that independents should start?
If there are people here who want to make their own board
games, where would you tell them to go?
Should they be pitching to big publishers?
I think you're going to get a range of answers
to that question, so we should each take it, yeah.
Yeah, I mean, I think.
I think there are opportunities on Kickstarter, but I was looking over Kickstarter earlier
this week about what's available right now, and I am constantly looking at what's on Kickstarter.
And it does feel like the games that are successful are people who are not first-time creators.
So it does seem like it's very, you know, unless you have something that really stands
out, it's very difficult to...
get started. It's better than probably digital games I would say still
to be able to get in. The barrier to entry is okay but it's not easy.
So when I started my business I had been a product developer and a product designer and I started my company with the express purpose of product design.
I'd done product development, I know how important safety, packaging, advertising, shipping, all of it is.
And I knew that that's an expertise that wasn't what I wanted to have, I wanted to focus on the design part.
And I really, I didn't have the opportunity for Kickstarter when I started.
But I wouldn't have gone that route anyway because I really like having a partner.
who has that expertise and takes over that part of the job.
Angie Holmstrom is the wholesale manager for Mindware
and she sells Quirkle all over the world
so much better than I can.
And I'm so glad that I have a team doing all of that
and working on my behalf on the game all the time
when I'm working on the next game.
So for me, having a publisher and having the eyes of a publisher and the polish of a publisher
and the expertise of a publisher is my preference as a designer,
but I recognize the financial incentive for Kickstarter can work much better for designers,
and if you're willing to put in the extra work that Kickstarter requires,
you can really maintain control of your game in a way that you might not necessarily be able to with a publisher.
Can I just say though, like on the Kickstarter front,
I feel like you can't ever get enough money
to be able to make it, to be able to pay yourself at all.
You can get enough money to make a product.
Like if all you're doing is trying to get your dream
out there, Kickstarter will do that.
But like, I think like having the other person
to look after a bunch of stuff,
it really takes a lot of time to do all of that.
And the nice part of having the publisher is I designed Quirkle in 2006.
I'm continuing to design Quirkle spin-offs and expansions because that's what I've been asked for.
But I'm not... they're continuing to work on it and grow it and I can spend my time on other things.
So it's really nice having other people invested in the growth of something you're working on
and you can move on to the next design project. I really appreciate that.
Yeah, I feel like as a platform, Kickstarter has changed a lot over the years.
It's become a little bit more, in some ways, much more stable.
Like there are a lot more sort of orthodox ways of running a Kickstarter, which is both
good and bad because there are all these rules that people follow.
Like one of the fascinating things is like the rule of thumb is like launch your Kickstarter
on a Tuesday.
And that's like, that's the idea.
But, but here's the thing, right?
Everyone knows that, right?
And so now every Tuesday, like 900 Kickstarters launch.
And where's yours?
It's in there, right?
Like, it's in, it's,
unless people are getting that in their feed,
it's much, it's challenging for them to see it.
And, you know, with all of these rules, with all these new setups where it's like play, you know, Kickstarter backers now demand, like,
we want to see a gameplay video. We want to see reviews ahead of time. You should send it out to all these reviewers.
We want to see, and which means you have to make prototypes for every reviewer before the game is done.
We want to see how the game looks. We want to see near-final artwork on this Kickstarter, like.
Used to be you could run a kick starter with like a couple of our pieces and a really good game idea and you know be really earnest right when I did the bargain quest kick starter originally.
One of the piece of advice I got was like hey do the video yourself like do you have to have you know use your laptop camera or whatever and just sort of.
talk about your game and what you're trying to do.
And that really worked, that worked alright at the time.
But these days, people want trailers for their board games,
for them to do crazy money.
They see a human face, like, who's this? What is this?
This doesn't seem professional at all.
Which is a weird expectation to have for Kickstarter,
but it's one people are increasingly having.
Yeah.
and they're becoming a lot less tolerant of mistakes along that road as well.
If you, you know, they're like,
all these Kickstarters have already happened,
and clearly we expect you to operate as good as the best Kickstarter.
And I would say, I mean, first of all, that doesn't sound like the work of a single person anymore.
And secondly, I mean, what was it Simon said, was it the end of last year?
I mean, they've had apparently all this Kickstarter success, but maybe the profits aren't quite there
because they are investing so much money in this marketing and making what they are.
The creator of Scythe posted like a really wonderful series of articles about,
like you can look at the Stonemaier Games website, but they posted a series of articles about like...
why I don't put my games on Kickstarter anymore, right?
Like, why the platform no longer works for my model.
But they also posted a series that were like,
but if I did make a Kickstarter,
here's how I would do it now.
And they were, and then by the end of it,
they were like, okay, maybe we'll do another one
because they have, but you know,
they have to play the game super differently.
And it's a really intimidating prospect for new designers, but I mean, I wouldn't necessarily
say don't go for it, but there are community expectations that like might need to be researched
and you need to set your expectations, right?
Like you can't expect to make Gloomhaven money every time, you know?
But fans will expect you to deliver Gloomhaven quality correspondence and Gloomhaven quality
like graphic design or what have you like a lot and it can be intimidating.
being that available to fans.
There was a really good talk earlier today
by the people who made Dream Daddy
about being constantly available,
which is a thing people don't think about about Kickstarter.
Sorry, I'm starting to ramble a bit.
But when you run a Kickstarter,
you are also on the hook to correspond
with every commenter, every single person
who has an idea about your game
or has an opinion about your game.
And if you go quiet for like more than 48 hours during a Kickstarter, people start to ask questions and get upset.
And that is stressful.
Generally, if you manage social media for a popular brand, or what becomes a popular brand, which isn't always even in your control.
Based on this then, I mean, I would like to ask all the panel, how did you personally start?
Where did your initial success come from?
And based on that, what advice do you have for...
you know, future aspiring designers, how do they become a success now that everything is constantly changing?
Okay, well, so, I mean, my start in the industry was incredibly orthodox, right?
Like, I applied for Fantasy Flight Games' game design position for an associate game designer.
And, you know, that application was very much, it felt like applying to college, right?
It's like, here's, you know, an essay section, and here...
like write the rules to rock, paper, scissors,
that sort of stuff, and then standard interview,
and then I was in a salaried game design position
for a while, which is really not a job that exists.
I mean, it does, but it's not one that is readily available.
It is a hard job to find, and most companies
don't keep game designers on staff in that way.
From there, after I was at FFG for several years, and then I
left to go independent, partly at the behest of Tim Fowers,
who has had a lot of success with Kickstarter,
with a lot of these things.
I think for any new designer, I think definitely reach out to creators that you know and that
you like who have products similar to yours because the industry is still kind of young
and it's still not like super, it's not so crazy.
Like Tim is so excited when new designers want to talk to him and he will answer any
question that you have.
I mean same here, just feel free to reach out to me on Twitter or whatever, but like most designers that you know
will be thrilled to talk about how they're doing and like give you advice and give you suggestions about what's
You know what worked for them
Because we want this industry to grow and want you know kind of to see
One of the big things though is that we are not always publishers.
I get a lot of people who message me and say,
hey, I have this game idea and I'm like, I'm not a publisher.
That sounds like a great idea, but like, or like,
I probably shouldn't look at it legally, but like, don't do that, right?
But you can reach out for advice on like, you know,
so what did you do when you were running your Kickstarter?
Are there any things I might want to avoid?
And some of them will be too busy to answer you,
but some of them will be thrilled to, you know, to talk and to...
give you advice of like pitfalls to avoid.
So, based on that, would you recommend the orthodox approach if you apply to a large company
and sort of cut your teeth there?
Uh, I...
For me, I was very privileged. I was in a...
I had some amount of savings saved up that I was able to say, move to Minnesota from California,
which is not something everyone could have done.
Also, I know at Fantasy Flight they also offer an internship
and several of their employees were former interns.
But that internship was not a paid internship.
It was like they work very hard to,
we work very hard to teach the interns
and like to give them a valuable experience,
but it's not a paid position.
And so only the people who could do that
were people who could afford to basically take
like three months to just come into a studio every day
and just kind of learn, right?
Like it's almost like going to school.
I think absolutely when you see these job openings, you can't lose anything by applying,
and half of the applications are really good exercises.
Write the rules to rock, paper, scissors coherently is a great thing to do.
Even if I had never gotten the job, it helped me in my technical writing.
So Susan, is that the best way to become a games designer?
I have no idea.
My own experience was I knew I wanted to create something
and you were asking why be a game designer earlier
and it's because you have to make something.
You're just driven, you're compelled,
you wake up in the middle of the night
and you think about it.
That's the reason you become a novelist
or you design jewelry or wallpaper or anything.
You're just compelled.
And so I knew I wanted to design something but I didn't know what and I worked at a toy and game company and they gave me the opportunity to turn in ideas and I went a little overboard and turned in 200 ideas.
And they said, okay, we're going to move you to the product development department and teach you how to do this.
I was super lucky. I was at the toy and game company because I wanted to make something and they made things.
And then when I started, they moved out of the area and I was looking for another job
and I couldn't find anything I liked as much and my husband encouraged me to start my own
company.
I had the blessing and the privilege of having a partner who had a full-time job in insurance
and I could start a company with the ability to fail and that was a great gift that not
everybody has.
But I started in toys and toys have in-house designers.
Toy companies design things in-house.
They're much less used to working with out-of-house designers.
When I switched to games, I found game companies are much more open to working with out-of-house
designers.
That's their model.
So they're much more approachable, they're much more willing to look at things,
they're much more willing to work with people who don't have as much experience.
So it's really, Kickstarter is one way to get in,
but game companies are much more open than a lot of different industries are.
And I think that's a really nice thing about it.
And what you said is true also.
I know many designers who are happy to answer emails
and respond to requests about information.
It's still a very friendly...
friendly industry. And advice, as you're designing games, I try to remember this myself,
write your instructions early and often. You can do yourself no harm by starting to write
instructions as soon as you possibly can. Edit them, stay on top of them, keep them
current with your current version of the game. It will just help in the end because instruction
writing is one of the hardest parts of this job. And the sooner you start, the easier
it is.
Can I ask how do you get 200 ideas for games?
I have like two.
They weren't just games, it was toys and games.
So it was 200 different products that I could see
in this company's line and I was young.
I didn't sleep for a month.
I was so excited about having one of these
become an actual product.
I think of those 205 became actual products,
which was not a bad ratio for someone
who had no clue what they were doing.
And I got to work on two of them and turn them into products.
And when you get to hold them in your hand,
you're like, I made this.
It's really exciting.
So Jen, is that the secret?
Don't sleep.
No, I like sleep a lot. I like sleep a lot. Maybe that's why I'm still like, I don't feel like I have
financial stability at the moment in my life. Like I've done a Kickstarter that did very well for most people's expectations of a Kickstarter
but it's not really an appropriate salary. I luckily have a partner who is able to support me
as well, so
Yeah, I kind of come from a digital games background,
which also isn't very stable,
but feels a little bit more stable than tabletop games
in terms of being able to have a career or a job in it.
So yeah, I'm not sure what I'm gonna be doing
when I ship my Kickstarter,
because I don't feel like doing another Kickstarter
is gonna be financially viable for me.
Have you found your experience making video games
is something that has transferable skills though?
I mean, yeah, definitely.
I mean, to me, game design for digital and game design
for tabletop are very similar.
And I think even more so for me, making edible games.
Because in most tabletop games, the things that you have on the,
like, you know, the pieces that you have,
they're not, like, consumable for many games.
Obviously, there's legacy games.
But, like, in digital games, people can destroy stuff
all over the place.
And so because I'm making edible games where stuff is going
to be...
eaten, it's basically destroyed. So my digital games really helped with my design for tabletop.
a topic that has come up on this panel several times now, but it feels
increasingly intense, I would say, over the last year. There's been growing discussion of
cultural appropriation in games, insensitivity in board games,
conflating cultures, poor and offensive
attempts at representation sometimes.
Is this a serious problem in the industry?
Is it something that we need to address?
Last year, I would add, one of our panelists last year,
Anna, was mentioning that she did not
feel that board games was nearly as representative or equitable
as video games for her, having worked in both.
I have a hot take.
I have a take on this one.
I definitely agree that tabletop games are not there yet, but I also feel that you kind
of have to be bad at something before you get good at something, and we are currently
bad at a thing, but it is, I think it is still a sign of...
the industry moving towards more games that even try to represent different cultures,
even though they are sometimes failing in their execution or failing in their ability to consult these cultures that they want to show off.
But like, it's kind of... there is an element that I feel like kind of refreshed to see a greater variety of themes than like
Western military history or...
Western military history or Western economic history, but there's so much of it. Yeah, I know right
But you know as we get a greater variety and as we get more themes that are differentiating themselves people are finding like oh, hey
How do I?
Set myself apart. Well, let's start doing things that people haven't done
And then sometimes they'll execute on those things less
less than appropriately
And I'm really hopeful that the industry will be taking these as learning experiences.
There are a lot of cool websites that are analyzing games via accessibility,
and doing all these things that are gaining a solid traction in the community, which is nice.
I am, I have some nervousness about call out culture
and it's a larger conversation about how
internet discourse is done, but I actually feel remarkable,
like I feel more optimistic than I had in the past
that we will get there, although I also feel very strongly
that we are not there, and that we are not doing
as good a job as we can be representing various cultures
and identities and yeah.
I mean, I would say my experience of meeting games designers,
and hanging out with games designers, and interviewing games designers,
is a lot of them look like this.
How do we change that? Can we change that?
Yeah, I mean, I guess some of it's just...
I know sometimes going to board game conventions,
I walk into a room and it's just full...
Yeah, I should make sure I talk into this.
Yeah, you go into a board game convention
and it's full of people who I don't...
I'm like, I look at people, I'm like,
I don't know if I identify with you,
I don't know if I'm gonna be able
to have anything in common with you.
And I think there's a lot more of a range of different board game conventions out there
that now are much more inclusive and anybody can turn up.
And I think that helps with the funnel of trying to get more voices in there.
Like, if you're not even able to go to a convention space and feel comfortable playing those games,
then you're probably not going to try to design board games at all.
So I think that's part of the step.
I mean, I think we've discussed that financial stability is very important and there is a cultural element to financial stability.
There are more, you know, wealth gaps, pay gaps, all of these things are true depending on, you know, kind of.
where you exist and that will affect whether or not you can
succeed or you feel comfortable attempting to succeed in the industry.
We are, you know, there are people who are doing a lot of work trying to foster
more inclusive behavior among
players which will lead into more inclusive behavior among, you know, within
the design scene as we get more people
who are enthusiastic about games in general.
I'm very heartened to have found out recently that the winner of the most
recent
the new game, Key Forge, which we had talked about.
their biggest event, the Vault Tour, was won by a female gamer.
And that is not common in competitive card game scenes.
And that's kind of a heartening event to happen, even though it took a while.
But, yeah, I think there are barriers to entry that companies are working on,
and that we as a culture are...
Struggling with and it will take time and it will take people who are in positions of power
Making active decisions and making choices that are like, okay
Let's see
I want more marginalized voices in my game where I think this game would be more interesting if
We can have like this culture represented accurately and we can serve like this either community or this, you know
present this thing that we don't see often effectively and that will usually require a more diverse set of creators like that is
I think, you know, we live in a capitalist society, and currently, diversity is kind
of where the money is.
Like, a lot of games that are being produced that have more diverse themes are being, are
being, people are responding very well to those.
You know, we're getting more, even in the digital space, right?
Like Overwatch is incredibly diverse with its cast, and not consistently successfully.
There are some issues.
But those characters have really struck a chord in a lot of communities that a competitive
shooter would almost never have hit otherwise.
You don't see Call of Duty showing up on Tumblr.
I mean you do a little bit, but that's a small...
I haven't spent enough time on Tumblr.
We're talking about social spaces or game spaces.
Have all of you spent some time in a board games cafe?
How many folks here, quick show of hands, have been to a board game cafe?
Yeah, okay.
This seems to be a growing scene.
This is really only a thing that I started doing over the last couple of years.
Do we think this is going to be permanent?
Do we think it's going to help the industry in general,
help the marketing games, and maybe also help change the atmosphere?
I've enjoyed a lot of board game cafes more than I've enjoyed some conventions I've been to.
I feel like there's, like it feels like often that it's like in one city there is a board
game cafe and people are kind of forced to do whatever style of board game cafe that
is. I feel like I've tried to go to a few different board game cafes and some of them
They feel a lot more inclusive in terms of the range of games that they supply to people
and then the sort of events that they throw.
Some of them I think, I mean, the tabletop industry is very broad
and it feels like there should be more cafes that are across that broad ability.
So there's some that are for more hardcore people who want to be playing Key Forge or whatever it is,
but then there's some who just want to play with their kids and more casual games.
I would love to see.
you know, them specializing a bit more.
Two things. In my own
experience, anecdotal evidence, Quirkle had
a really unique experience in terms of contacting digital media
and
board game cafes. My husband Chris was really good at sending
out copies of Quirkle when it first came out. And he sent one to W. Eric Martin who at that point
was running Board Game News.
and he declared Quirkle his game of the year in 2000,
I think 2007, that's when he got it.
And he was really excited about it.
And he had a friend in Germany, Jeffrey Allers,
who said, will you please bring it to Germany?
I want to try it and play it.
We're going to meet up at this board game cafe,
Spiel Weiss, which I think was one of the very first board game cafes.
and I'd really like to play it there.
So Eric brought Quirkle to Germany
and played it with Jeffrey and Michael,
who owns the cafe, and Torsten Gimler,
who is the publisher at Schmichtbill,
and Torsten is the person who ended up licensing Quirkle
for the German publisher.
So for me, and then Quirkle went on to win the Spiel des Jahres,
so for me, board game cafes, super important,
and reaching out to different forms of media
and letting them know about your game, super important.
That led very directly to...
to the publisher Quirkle ended up with in Germany.
And also, I think in that case, Quirkle
found a stronger foothold among gamers
because we did that outreach than we expected.
I think if we hadn't been reaching out
to different content reviewers sort of people,
Quirkle might not have had that.
might not have found a home among gamers that it did.
It would have just stayed in the family game market
and it spread from there.
So very personal experience of value of board game cafes.
And then the other thing is,
one of the things that I think is super exciting
about games right now is the growing base of gamers
are people who are excited about learning new games.
And I think American gamers for.
a long, long time, I don't know how long, have been afraid of learning games. Families
have played the games that they grew up, you know, parents played Payday or Monopoly or
Scrabble or Parcheesi or Sorry. They played those games growing up.
And when they have kids, they buy the same games
because they don't want to learn new games.
And it's been a huge barrier of entry for American gamers
to learn new games.
And right now, I think in part because of board game cafes
and in part because of all the videos teaching games,
we're experiencing this spread of people
who like to learn new games, which is totally different
than what we've had before.
And I think there is going to be a driving force,
even though I think we're headed towards a problem
with oversaturation of games.
I think creating people who think learning games is fun is going to change our market
entirely.
People who think that it's fun to try something new and introduce their friends to it and
they're going to do it at board game cafes and they're going to do it by watching videos
and learning games that way.
I think that's a really strong force in our market right now.
I think that's a really interesting point. Do we think that digital content creators
are part of the reason that the hobbies exploded so much? Because there's now so much learn
to play stuff. There's so much in terms of board game reviews on the internet. And when
people speak to me about discovering a board game, they often say, I didn't see it in a
shop. I definitely didn't see an ad for it anywhere. I watched a review of it or something
like that on YouTube.
I think definitely similarly on Kickstarter people are also courting content creators
to like get the word out about their games and I think part of that is just
because the internet is, it is the most powerful like marketing tool anyone can have
and YouTube is huge, right, Twitter is enormous and those,
like as those tools get more powerful, like everyone wants to use those
to market whatever their product is whether it's board games or anything else
and so we are seeing a benefit from that.
There are even some concerns about like, you know, oh, if I want to learn to play this game, I'm not going to go to my local board game shop.
I might just go on YouTube and see a really excellent, very concise how to play video that I won't have to like drive downtown to enjoy.
Yeah.
And like, I think definitely we're seeing a lot of that in the fact that new designers are often trying to court those people with those audiences, right?
Because...
We can't afford, like a lot of us, you know, creators, we can't afford a huge marketing budget, right?
We're not going to put up a billboard in Times Square.
But we can reach out to someone with a very good following and be like, hey, here's a copy of our game.
If you, you know, you are looking, they are often looking for content to cover.
And if they enjoy your game, maybe they'll put out a piece of content that people will
hopefully enjoy and then they'll spread the word.
It's sort of a nice symbiotic relationship, theoretically, between developers and digital
content creators.
I think certainly that is probably going to become more and more of the status quo.
particularly as apparently we as a society get more and more into these digital celebrities,
right, like Twitch streamers and YouTubers.
I mean, I'm on the older end of millennials at this point, so I'm not sure.
So I hesitate to make any grand predictions about the future of digital technology,
but certainly in the moment it's a very powerful tool that people are working very hard to figure out how to use optimally.
Yeah, and I mean with digital content producers we also have, you know, digital production
like Game Crafter and we also have digital distribution like Amazon where people don't
go to their game shop to buy something, they just buy it on Amazon.
And I think, I love brick and mortar stores like for the same reason we all have discussed
and I...
I am a bit worried because having looked behind the curtain at the economic incentives, you
move so much product on Amazon.
People move so much product.
Honestly, just Amazon is enough to put a lot of places out of business.
And it is only through this diehard dedication.
We are in the same position that bookstores were in when borders collapsed.
And yet, like as we had discussed, book sales, physical book sales are going up this year.
There are more physical books being produced this year than previously,
which is not something I was expecting with the advent of Kindle.
So maybe board game shops will...
I strongly suspect they will survive in some fashion.
I don't know if they'll become huge.
But I don't think Amazon has it in them to kill them at least.
Sorry, I guess I moved back to that previous discussion.
But do you have any thoughts on YouTubers?
I mean, I suddenly noticed, like on my Kickstarter campaign, the influence of like, you know,
shut up and sit down, did a review.
And I think it was like a quarter of my backers came from that.
So I can't remember if that's the exact number, but it was a really large number of my backers
came because of that review.
And so like, you know, and I purposefully like I knew they had, you know, I, you know,
quartered basically, because I knew it was important.
And yeah, it was.
I mean this is also assuming that it goes well with that content creator, right?
Like a negative review.
Although honestly I've heard like people like a lot of people if like say Tom Vassil posts
like a review like I didn't much care for this particular game but they'll still talk
about it.
That still gets it in front of eyeballs, you know?
A lot of people are like oh I don't like games that Tom likes, maybe I'll like this.
I have found that if you don't like a game on the internet people will correct you and
explain how you're wrong and buy it anyway.
Getting into the conversation, it really does seem like that, you know, any news is...
There's no bad news, there's no bad publicity.
Yeah, there's no such thing as bad publicity, which I don't think is true,
but bad publicity can still create positive results.
There's one more thing I'd like to quickly touch on.
We did discuss a bit about counterfeiting board games in the panel last year.
Is that something that has affected any of you this year in any way?
I mean, not really for me.
I mean, I've recently been sending out some of my chapters
to some of my backers who I call play tasters,
because I like them.
And yeah, I mean, I guess particularly
with the sort of games I'm making,
people have to make it at home.
So it's kind of like a print and play game,
but I'm encouraging people to make their own.
So I'm somewhat encouraging people to like counterfeit
and make their own edible games
and maybe adjust my edible games if they don't like them.
So not so much for me.
A few years ago there was quite a spat of knockoff quirkles available on Amazon and
that was interesting.
There was some bad reviews because they were poorly produced and they were selling and
there was no way to tell if you were getting a good copy or a bad copy before you bought
it.
and my publisher worked with Amazon and got those cleaned out,
but the reviews are still there of these bad copies of Korkul.
This is a case where I'm really glad I have a publisher.
They're fighting counterfeits on multiple fronts.
And I know Russia is one country that particularly has a counterfeit problem.
We've had counterfeits in Canada. We've had counterfeits here.
So it's an issue and it's something that as a designer I don't have any idea how one controls it or what to do about it,
but I know it's a growing problem in our industry and can affect lots of different games.
Amazon actually, I believe there's a recent article, Amazon is actively cracking down
on their sellers and they're making it a point to make sure that hey, if you want to sell
a game on Amazon you have to be a registered seller and have, they're basically cracking
down on the accountability of people who produce these products and make sure that hey, people
selling these Asmodee titles or whatever have gotten their games from the appropriate channels
in a lot of cases and that otherwise you will, they.
They're categorizing them more and they're sort of cracking down all these little shop fronts which are often fronts for counterfeit games.
And they won't just automatically kind of just bundle them all together and be like,
ah, this is the product and we'll ship them out piecemeal.
Which has been a big, which is probably a big get.
And this is probably the best way that we have to fight counterfeiters in that way.
And the more current problem, I think, is it Alibaba?
That's a bigger problem right now, because that is so easily
counterfeit products available there.
So excellent that they're finding out ways to make it
work better on Amazon and crack down on the problem there.
Another way for counterfeiters is broken out.
And I was reading an article that was talking about how
the counterfeiters, they have these fantastic ways
of figuring out what price point they need
to sell the product.
They'll sell the most product,
and they're better at figuring that out
than the publishers.
They've got it worked out so that they can sell it
at that price, and that's what they'll sell the most.
And it's really interesting to me
the amount of work they also put into their products.
Crime is big business.
There you go.
Yeah.
So if anyone has a solution to how we defeat, I don't know,
piracy is not going to go away, is it?
Can someone solve crime for us?
Yeah.
Please step up.
We have a microphone that is just
waiting for your questions on anything
that you would like to reach out to the panel for.
Hello.
How are you?
Hi, I'm good.
I'm a college professor, and I teach game design.
And one of the experiments I tried to do is I was like,
I'll make my own card game.
I went through Publisher, I went through all that,
and I actually got it published.
Reviewed by Dice Tower.
Congratulations.
Thanks.
Reviewed by Dice Tower twice, made top 10, made GGcon.
How do you, and...
And my game didn't do as well as far as sales are concerned.
But I'm starting to see this trend of all these solid games,
but they just get drowned out by the massive amounts
of other games that are just waving right over.
How do you deal with Cult of the New?
I mean I guess I'd say you've got to like, I think it used to be with tabletop games
you just needed to have a good game to be able to stand out and I think now you've got
to have something that's got a big hook that's not just a good game but it's like just captures
people right, like as soon as they almost hear the title or see the box they're like
ooh.
So I think you've got to do more.
There are absolutely amazing games that slip under the radar
every day, you know, like, I mean.
Yeah, I totally agree.
Yeah, 10, you know, what was it, Paul?
Like 10 new games get made every day, basically.
I think that's Susan having 200 ideas.
That's true. Yeah, I mean, it's hard and if there was a recipe for guaranteed success,
then I don't think we would need conferences like this.
Yeah, I think one of the things is, you know, dedication and it's possible that it's the theme that didn't work.
It's possible that it's, that you didn't have the right marketing push at the time.
But people will start and try and like, you know, print copies, multiple iterations.
I mean, when Bargain Quest first came out, right, we had a very modest Kickstarter success.
I think we printed like 2,000 copies.
And I think it's entirely possible that might have been all we would have ever printed.
If the game didn't, if we, you know, didn't put in a lot of legwork like submitting it to, you know, different shows and like submitting it to different people and like just sort of going places and showing it off and putting in a huge amount of work and even that, we, we, and even then we got lucky, right?
We got, uh...
you know, we got positive reviews from Shut Up, It's Down, which really gave us a huge social media boost.
And that allowed us to kind of move forward, but not everyone has those opportunities.
But I think pursuing them is basically the only move most, particularly small devs, have.
But hey, good games get rethemed, good games get reprinted all the time, like, and, you know, it's not your only shot.
And...
Yeah, all I can say is you should definitely don't give up on it, but it's hard and don't think of it as a personal failing of your game or your product.
Oh no, I've learned a lot. I mean, I've learned that you need a team, there's a lot of dedication. It's insane. But I really appreciate your insight, thank you very much guys.
And based on that Susan, did you know with all these different ideas, did you know Quirkle was going to be the one that would take off?
Quirkle came later when I had my own company and I was designing toys, I wasn't designing
games but I'd been hosting a game night for a very long time and Quirkle came to me in
a dream.
almost fully finished and I got up in the morning and said,
that looks really cool, that was really neat in my dream,
I gotta go make that.
So I did and it worked out super well.
And since I was already a toy designer,
I had already pitched to Mindware, the toy company,
and they had turned down a bunch of my toys,
but I was like, yeah, this is gonna fit their line,
I need to send it to them and I did
and they accepted it immediately and went really well.
I did not know Quirkle was going to become so popular.
I had no idea that it would be so well received.
I was ready for it to be a middling success.
You know, I thought it was going to do well for a few years
and it just continued.
Continues to grow and thrive and I'm just super bused by it
But I did not know that it was going to be my best-selling product
Wait, you're telling me that you can design award-winning games in your sleep
Literally, I need more naps
Yeah, yes next question
It's rather a commentary. I'm Christophe from rebel game studio. So as money Poland
I just returned from Reno
trade show
Gamma trade show in Reno and what like topics here?
Covered were covered two years ago on retail and distribution
conferences yet
In my opinion, what we were talking at GAMA, it's about overabundance, over saturation,
and how to help brick and mortar stores to survive.
And the other topics were consolidation of the market and some companies going under.
Last year was the hardest year for many European publishers and distributors.
So, and probably you know that's a kind of domino effect.
We won't be buying new titles from new developers and game artists if we won't be prospering.
The topic for you here, to understand, I want to share it.
It's not, we are no longer looking for new good games.
We are looking for games that we, that...
that the games that are already evergreens, that have their solid place on the shelves,
that we can put new instead of them.
We are no longer willing to expand our catalogs or portfolio.
That's why these old games are still going strong, because it's for us.
It has better rate of interest to invest in promoting the games that we already have.
than to introduce new ones and start earning money in the next two years or something.
If we solve the problem that's currently on the distribution side, then you probably can
avoid the problems that we are now experiencing.
That's what we are now trying to solve.
So keep on with good work.
But your competition is not only this.
900 games on Kickstarter currently are all all these bestsellers and evergreens
that you have to be better than.
Yeah, so I think we're down to seven minutes. We should get moving.
Yes, the next speaker, please.
Yes, hi.
Just wondering, how do you think that global availability is affecting the hobby?
For example, I'm from South America and it's pretty hard to get most board games that I guess
it's easier to come by either in North America or Europe. So as you're speaking about, you know,
market saturation and how the scene can continue to grow, do you think that there is, you know,
something to be said about that you're not actually serving the whole available population
that is into the hobby?
Yeah, there are absolutely markets that we are not serving actively, partly because distribution can be very difficult in those regions currently and there are other like, you know, broader infrastructure reasons or a lot of publishers don't want to be the first one to dive in and invest heavily and take a risk in a region that
isn't proven, right? As things get bigger, people become more risk-averse. I think this is
possibly a big advantage to things like print and play, so that we can get more and more easily
accessible games in those kinds of regions. But yeah, it's hard, particularly when you're running
a physical product that requires things like translation and physical shipping of a 2kg box.
Can I just say, I don't know if it's just that.
Like I grew up in Australia, and sure I haven't lived in Australia for a while,
and board games have got a lot more popular since I've left,
but they were very expensive in Australia.
Australia speaks the same language as in the US,
it's quite a similar culture, like sure Australia's different,
but even so it was very expensive to get.
So I think there must be more than just transport and the things,
I mean, I assume Australia's getting better, but it's still really difficult.
There's also just taxes based on governments, right?
Like being able to figure out, OK, what are the import taxes for this region?
And yeah, some smaller publishers just don't have the bandwidth
to be able to run the import taxes for every single country, which
is unfortunate, but will hopefully get better as the industry gets
bigger and more successful.
And there's the problems of you can't just sell to one store in a country.
You need a base.
So usually you need a partner in that country who has a distribution channel
and can sell it to a lot of stores.
So it's a real investment each country you move into
finding someone you can work with and figuring out
how you're going to sell your container of games
that's going to be specific to that market and going to be shipped there.
Who is going to take those games? You can't just do a print run of a thousand for them
they're going to take a print run of 10,000 in a container and
You need a partner who's going to help you get through all those so it's
Unfortunately it makes it so much harder to move into different countries because of that
Less hard than it used to be but still it's a real challenge. I think we have time for maybe one more question
I hope this is worthy of being the last question, but I'll try.
We're starting to see a trend in bigger retailers of doing
exclusive games for them.
Walmart was the exclusive distributor of Fog of Love.
Target has a couple of games that are only
available through them.
Do you think this is a positive thing for the industry?
Do you think it's a negative?
Do you think it's just a flash in the pan?
Can I immediately say, speaking as a chap who lived in Vancouver for quite a while,
when something's available in Target, which is not even in your country, that's quite
frustrating.
I think it's absolutely a positive sign that, like, these, you know, cap-giant monoliths
think that games are valuable enough, that they want to have exclusivity of certain products
like this, that they think that they want to, that that is a valuable thing, it's a
good sign.
I do think it's bad for all of the accessibility reasons that we've mentioned, you know, leading
into this, right?
a game being exclusive to only one kind of store
means it's harder for people who don't have access
to that kind of store, or people who have ethical issues
with, say, how certain stores run themselves,
or what have you.
Well, and the industry as a whole is balancing
between the friendly local game store,
the specialty store that is supporting
and growing the game in the beginning,
and then Target can come in and take that popular game
and make it available on a much wider market.
but they didn't necessarily do the work of building that.
So as a publisher, you have to struggle
with these two different competing merchants you're
dealing with, the specialty market and the mass market,
and how to service them both and honor both of them
for the different things they provide for your game.
So exclusives in Target are a tricky, interesting, positive
sign, but not necessarily.
the best way to... I don't know. There you go.
And I know that actually happens a lot with the Target exclusive.
I know less about the Walmart exclusives.
I know that they are often limited time, and then they become available on a wider basis.
Yeah. To put it on the recording, yeah, some publishers will give exclusivity for a short
time before letting that run.
But that's also a big contract issue, right?
Like, as a designer, oftentimes I may not get a say in whether a game goes exclusive to one
company or another, because that's a business decision, right?
And, yeah, how long that exclusivity lasts is a huge component.
And, yeah, I think, I don't know, personally I'm not crazy about it,
just because I want everyone to play all of the games.
But, yeah, it is, we live in a society with market forces,
and that is how, if that is how they want, if that is how they will carry the game,
that is how they'll carry it, you know.
That's just, we play ball.
I think we have about half a minute left, so I just want to say thank you so much to
my panelists for agreeing to appear this evening.
You have been terrific.
Thank you, all of you, also, for coming and for your questions.
I should mention that this talk and all the previous ones are available online in the
GDC Vault or on YouTube where you can leave comments, where you can tell us what you think
about them, which is always helpful.
But more importantly on that topic, I am always told every year,
please fill in your evaluation forms, tell us what you thought,
tell us what you liked, tell us who you're excited about,
because that feedback is incredibly useful and it guides us to what we do next year.
Thank you very much, panelists.