Hello, I am Tyreek Plummer.
I am a game designer and artist.
I'm going to be talking today about 2D animation,
which is maybe my second favorite thing in the world.
If you're interested in animation but don't know where to start, or are struggling to get things to look right,
or if you understand some of the basics but just feel like you could use some tips in applying the principles,
hopefully this will be a helpful screed.
I also hope this will be helpful to people who work with animators and other non-artist people who make project scope decisions,
to provide some common language, things to consider, things to watch out for when assessing animated objects and assets,
and some tips for working with artists.
I've worked as an animator in games for about 12 years now on titles like Thor, God of Thunder,
Epic Mickey, The Power of Illusion, Adventure Time, Explore the Dungeon Because I Don't
Know, and Cadence of Hyrule, Crypt of the Necrodancer featuring the Legend of Zelda.
A lot of games with colons followed by long subtitles for some reason.
I'm also the creator of Catacomb Kids, which is a platformer roguelike that I've been working
on for going on 300 years now.
I mostly work in pixel art, but I don't think that'll color this talk too much because really
animation is animation and the fundamentals don't change all that much from one medium
to the next, even if specific techniques and tools might.
And this is going to be a talk largely about the fundamentals of animation as they apply to game art.
I will also preface this by saying these are all just things I've gleaned from my own personal
experience working as an animator. I'm not like any kind of super authority or anything,
it's just something that I care deeply about and I have a lot of opinions about what happens to be my
second favorite thing that I also happen to do for a living. Which is to say, please also learn from
other animators and people who are better than me, there are a lot of them and I'm sure they all have
opinions that they think are right too. That being the case, let's start off with some general
considerations. Before you even begin working on art for your game, there are some things
to consider with regards to 2D art and animation.
Like most aesthetic decisions in life, a lot of a lot of it comes down to what you want to communicate, what mood you want to impress upon others, what story you're trying to tell.
But you also need to be aware of the kind of game you're trying to make on a technical level and the challenges associated with your medium of choice, because any aesthetic decision is going to be a technical one as well.
If you're going to need to sprite, if you're going to need every sprite to have 12 fully animated facing directions and hundreds of kinds of fully rendered equipment that will be layered and animated and mixed and matched, I feel like at that point you might be better served by just using 3D assets to save everybody time and migraines.
Or if your art style isn't incredibly detailed to the point where drawing a single frame is
equivalent to a full day's work, maybe be aware of how that's going to impact the quantity of
art that can be made and plan around keeping any animation to an absolute bare minimum.
Or opt for a skeletal system where each highly detailed bit needs to be drawn only once or twice.
But of course, that'll come with its own set of challenges.
Or you could simplify the style to better fit within the limitations
of traditional frame by frame animation.
These are all valid options,
but they're things that need to be decided upon early and trust artists
when they tell you what's reasonable and what's not.
Nobody likes working for hours, days or weeks to make something
that ends up thrown out because the limitations of their medium
weren't properly considered early on.
2D animation can be very time consuming and if you don't account for this in your design,
you're going to have a bad time. A very long, crunch-filled bad time.
So let's say you've made those considerations, you've picked a style that works, you understand
the implications and you have decided you're going to go for it. 2D art, traditionally animated,
nice. So when you're animating, when you're breathing life into these still images,
making them act and react, what is it that you're actually doing?
Well, animation isn't just make thing look good,
although that's definitely usually a part of it.
Animation is communication,
communication of ideas through motion.
A character's idle animation can communicate volumes
about their personality, their mood,
their status in the world,
the way they interact with objects,
the way they walk, jump,
the way they flinch when they get hurt.
These are all means by which to communicate
to the viewer information that might take paragraphs
to describe otherwise.
If a picture is worth a thousand words,
then a sequence of images is like,
it's gotta be like an essay or something, I don't know.
But honestly, that communication aspect
is true for most animation,
whether it's for games or not,
communicating personality and individuality
through the motion.
But animating for games has an additional concern, which is communicating the game's state.
Not only must you convey the nature of the world and the characters in a broad sense,
you also have to present a clear message of what's happening right now and why,
and how the current game state will flow into the next and how its logical conclusion
of whatever the previous state was.
And you have to fit all of those matters of character and personality into that context.
You probably won't have a full solid 60 seconds of animation to convey that our reluctant hero
is feeling uncertain of their ability and in over their head. You might only have 8 frames
of a run cycle, 6 frames of an attack animation, and a single hurt frame to get across those ideas.
Moreover, that attack animation also needs to convey,
here's where the hitbox is.
These are invulnerability frames.
This is the cooldown time.
It can be a lot to keep in mind in addition to the meta objective
of make thing look good.
But this communication aspect of animation is one that I see frequently
misunderstood or outright ignored by animators who are just starting out
and the non-artists who are making requests of us.
What is the actual relevant information here?
What is the game state that you're trying to get across?
What is the character that you're trying to impart?
Good animation is effective communication.
It doesn't matter how cool that backflip looks
if it also takes away the player's ability
to accurately read the situation.
Another thing to think about is the fact that motion can be kind of an aesthetic in and of itself.
Like, of course, the way things move enhances whatever visual style is already present,
but it is possible to have an art style that looks great in stills, but if it's animated poorly, it can really kill the whole vibe.
It's also possible to have a visual style that looks very simple and unassuming at a glance,
but that moves with a clarity and precision that elevates it.
This is specifically not to say that you should go ahead and base your visual style and just absolute trash
Just because it could in theory look cool in motion. Although I mean feel free but
remember all the stuff I said about keeping in mind the limitations of the
medium, if you do pursue that. Rather,
what I mean is that animation is an important pivot of aesthetic.
It's an important pivot point within aesthetic that can elevate or diminish
other stylistic design decisions without being too reliant on them.
Honestly, this fact is kind of one of my favorite things about animation in general, the fact
that I can look at, for example, a child's drawing and envision a reality in which for
all the naivete and lack of finesse of the still image, I can envision a reality in which
it's animated in a way that lends credibility and intentionality and makes it look good
and cool when it moves.
I can look at this image and imagine the ways that I might animate it in a way that makes
sense and has weight and feels right, but that still doesn't rely on changing the underlying
aesthetic, whether it's worth doing or how easy it would be is another matter.
But my point is just that good art can have the principles of animation applied poorly
and what would traditionally be called bad art can have the principles of animation applied
well.
The form that the style takes does not dictate the quality of animation that is possible.
Also, I mean, it would be pretty cool to have an animated game that looks like a
child's drawing. Someone, somebody done that? Somebody's probably done that.
So with those considerations in mind, let's look at some of the more
technical details of what makes good animation.
First off, with a few definitions that I'll use throughout this talk that you should probably
understand, you may have heard these terms before, but in case you haven't, covering my bases.
Keyframes. These are the frames that show the key positions of whatever it is that you're animating.
The ones that tell the story of what's actually happening.
Just looking at the keyframes, you should be able to tell what the action is.
In-betweens are the frames, logically, that come in between the keyframes,
the ones that smooth out the key poses into a cohesive, fluid motion.
Spacing refers to how much an element moves in between one frame and the next.
And smears and multiples are techniques to show motion
by stretching an object across time
or making it appear multiple times within a single frame.
And then there are the principles of animation.
There are 12 of them.
Some guys at Disney wrote them down back in the eighties,
based on work that was done in the decades prior to that.
They aren't the whole of what makes good animation because art is subjective or
whatever, but they're an important foundation.
If you're just getting into animation,
these principles are
the jumping off point for understanding motion and developing an analytical eye as you consume
the works of others. And if you work with animators, these are concepts that may be
handy for you to have in order to more effectively communicate your ideas to them or
understand what they're talking about.
Sorry. But like I said, these principles were written by Disney dudes,
and so some of them are a bit less relevant to games animation than they are
for film and TV and such, and others are just kind of.
not super relevant to the intent of this talk. For instance, staging is a matter of composition
and scene setup, how you guide the viewer's eye, that sort of thing, which while it can still
apply to games, might be better explored through level design or something. And solid drawing is
also one of the 12 principles, but it basically just means be good at art, which isn't the most
helpful advice in my mind, so we're going to ignore some of these.
If you really want to get good at animation, though, I highly recommend
actually going and reading about all 12 principles and whatever other resources
you can get your grubby little hands on.
But I'm specifically trying to cover things
that might not be touched on in other places and things that are specific to games.
And a lot has been written about these principles already.
So we'll check out the seven principles of animation that
that we care about in this context for the time being.
So we're going to start with one you might already know about squash and stretch.
It's when you push a rubber ball down and it gets flatter and wider.
When you pull a rubber band and it gets longer and thinner.
It's the quickest, easiest way to give something a sense of life.
And you don't need to limit yourself to only affecting logically squishy things.
The classic animation example of this is to draw a bouncing ball,
but adding a bit of squash. Sorry.
but adding a bit of squash on just about anything is an easy way to increase the
impact of collisions or some stretch while an object is moving can impart a
sense of speed and give it an obvious directional heading.
Again, it's about communication.
Squash and stretch can look good and also tell you what direction
an impact has come from or what direction an object is moving in and how fast.
It's important, very important that you maintain the volume
of the object and character mass that gets sucked in along one axis
has to spread out on another.
If you aren't careful about maintaining the subject's volume,
it quickly stops reading as squash and stretch and becomes.
a transforming thing and what was supposed to have impact might end up having less because
it changes from a matter of perceiving force to a matter of perceiving malleability.
So be careful with keeping, maintaining the mass of the objects that you're animating
when you're applying squash and stretch.
You can see here some characters, a character that I did for for Epic Mickey and another
that I did for Cadence of Hyrule. And see how she, Impa, sort of squashes down
before popping up into the air. And same for the Knight Dude.
Next on the list is...
Anticipation. This is the pre-action, the moment before a thing happens that lets you know
what's about to happen, that something is about to happen. Usually it's a motion in the opposite
direction of whatever is about to follow. A slight shift to the right before you move to the left,
a dip down low before you leap upward. Anticipation can be big.
big sweeping windup before an enormous punch, a laser that pulls in on itself and shakes like
crazy in preparation to fire, or like a low twisting crouch where the character tenses like
a spring before a super jump. This is another character from Epic Mickey, Razul, and you can
see kind of a few different moments of anticipation within this.
So first of all, there's the most obvious,
which is the flourish that leads into the crouching position
before charging forward.
Like that crouching position can be considered
like in anticipation of moving forward,
but there are also some other ones
that might be a little less obvious.
There's a dip before the actual charging,
like he's in the crouch pose
and then he dips backwards before charging forward.
That's anticipation.
lifting like the actual spinning of the sword and putting it in the hand that can be considered like
an anticipation you can see it's moving in the opposite sword come in the opposite direction
coming up before going down and being held in both hands and there's also a little hop towards
the end of the charge that sort of prefaces the stop of movement where he like hops up before
sliding down and crouching a little bit lower.
But notice how each moment of anticipation is largely in an opposing direction to whatever action it is that follows.
Anticipation can also be very brief.
If you're making an action game where reflexes matter to any degree,
you probably don't want your player character to have to wait a half a second before their
input comes to fruition, no matter how cool it looks.
Unless you're making a Soulsborne or some such.
You might have enough room to add one or two frames of windup before it starts feeling laggy.
For many games, player actions don't even have any frames of anticipation, but they still manage to
look good because they still manage to feel good. Remember, animation in games shouldn't
override or betray the gameplay. It should serve it. It should bolster it.
So in a lot of games where you need that snap, that instant action,
sometimes there's no wind up at all on player actions,
but usually you can fit like a frame or two in there.
This is Impa again from Cadence of Hyrule,
doing a bit of wind up before, before spearing out.
A bit of anticipation.
Importantly.
Anticipation not only prefaces what's about to happen, but it can also tell players how important what is about to happen is through contrast.
Frequently, contrast is spoken in terms of color and brightness and that sort of thing.
But there is also contrast in motion.
If something that was moving is suddenly still or that was still is suddenly moving, you'll notice large motions draw the eye, rapid motions draw the eye.
And so.
You want to be absolutely sure the players can see what's about to happen.
You want to draw their eye, their attention to the important thing.
Don't just make the anticipation longer and give them more time to see it,
because again, that's not always going to be an option.
Like it has to be subservient to the gameplay.
And that's where like all this timing and stuff comes into play.
But. As opposed to making the anticipation last longer,
you can make it divergent from the norm, from whatever.
From whatever the usually is, whatever the thing is that's doing the anticipation,
that's doing the wind up, change its silhouette, change its color, make it vibrate, make it
smaller or bigger. Tense it like a coiled snake, fill it with potential energy.
Give the player's eye something to latch on to and it will.
So here we have a Wizzrobe from Cadence of Hyrule.
You can see there are a number of things going on to sort of
give visual attention to this to this charge up before the attack.
The silhouette changes.
You can see that that for the normal version, he's kind of like rounded.
But as he's charging his hat and other elements become much sharper,
much pointier, much more aggressive feeling.
There's also like a bit of vibration that that that kind of motion
can can attract the player's eye.
The silhouette changes completely.
The scarf comes off and begins flapping as another point of interest.
So yeah, there are a lot of different elements
that you can tweak to provide contrast
between one animation, one motion, and the next.
Next on the list of principles of animation, we have timing and timing is pretty much what
it sounds like.
It's how long things take to happen.
It's where the beats are.
It's the cadence of things.
If an animation is a sentence that describes an action, then timing can be thought of as
sort of where the punctuation is.
This can be very important in game art because game elements, especially characters...
Sorry. This can be very important in game art because game elements,
especially characters,
tend to have fairly discrete states and how animations are paced is frequently
tied directly to the transition between and within these states.
Timing informs how readily these state changes will be parsed by the player in
active, moving, changing, and visual environment.
And timing is also an essential part of conveying character.
To continue the metaphor, if timing is the punctuation,
then it stands to reason that different characters
would have different cadences to their speech.
They have different dialects, different patterns,
and so too will they have different cadences
in their motion.
So you can see here two different characters that have the exact same
frames, nothing about the actual frames themselves has changed except the
timing. You can see on the left,
the characters tend to have like a more steady
pace and the ones on the right have like definitive beats to their movement,
the big demon night guy like steps and pauses after each step.
It makes it feel a little more weighty while the one on the, on the,
on the left is,
is a bit more constant and kind of lacks a bit of a,
lacks a bit of focus on any particular pose or moment.
Same goes for the high knocks again from Cadence of Hyrule where the one on the
on the right, like, very definitively has a few poses that he holds that hold
focus. And there's more weight and more character to these motions, as opposed to
just like spinning around and chucking the thing, spin around, hold, build that
that that potential energy and then continue onward.
Ease in and ease out, also called slow in and slow out,
are sort of specific applications of timing.
Easing in and out is basically just another way
of saying that objects have inertia.
Things take a bit of time to get up to full speed or come to a complete stop.
When you ease in, you kind of start with your frames spaced closely together
and they get further apart as the motion progresses to represent like acceleration, you know.
Ease out is the exact opposite.
It's something coming to a slower halt.
It's this easing in the easing is essentially a measure of how spacing
changes across time.
It's worth noting that sometimes these elements that that easing is trying to
represent are handled by actual game
logic, you know, things like inertia, acceleration, deceleration.
Sometimes like that doesn't need to be coded into the.
the animation itself that you're working with,
because that's like the thing that the code is doing,
is handling all the acceleration and deceleration
and inertia for like, you know,
entire entities for characters and that sort of thing.
Which brings me to the point that a little bit of a break
from the 12 principles,
these animation principles were written
while operating under the assumption
that the animator would have complete control over
all elements of the scene, essentially, that there wouldn't be any outside variables
actively changing what's happening on screen as it occurs.
Obviously, that's not the case with games,
which isn't to say that these principles aren't still incredibly useful,
but rather that it's important to understand
when and where they apply in the context of of.
games and alongside game logic and consider where the game logic might be
interacting with these principles of acceleration, deceleration, anticipation,
all that sort of thing.
Not just not just in the way that I mentioned earlier, where anticipation on
player characters can be short to avoid visual lag and sluggish input like
that's that's one example.
But also in the sense of like.
you need to know like what exactly the character is doing in the game when
you're animating for it. You know, like, like if, if your character,
if you're animating an attack animation that can be played while the character
is either still or moving,
that's something that you need to know and take into account because if you
animated as, as if they're standing still,
there'll be like sliding around whenever you attack.
And if you animate it as if they're only moving,
they might look like they have
more motion than is reasonable for for attacking standing still.
So and. I've
I've definitely had this happen before, where I've animated something
that I was pretty pleased with and ended up being a little.
displeased because it didn't look great in context because the game logic applied motion that I was
not expecting to. And it was something that I could have accounted for had I known that that
would have been the case. Anyway, let's get back to the principles. That was just a brief aside.
The next principle is that of arcs. The idea is things tend to move in arcs, just
as a general observation. Objects like to be in rotation around a focal point and if they aren't
then they're usually being acted upon by by some kind of force that that pulls them in a direction
or one direction or another either by gravity or because of a literal.
physical attachment limiting directly linear motion, like a shoulder, how, you know, your
shoulder limits the motion of your elbow, which limits the motion of your hand. These
are all things that move along arcs, they're moving at fixed distances between one another.
And uh,
The pivot points for these arcs can be themselves moving along arcs.
I mean, if you think of it, humans were basically just a collection
of pendulums strung together.
So it can help if you're working on an animation
and it isn't looking quite right to check the arcs
and make sure they're moving along an expected trajectory
without any strange jumps or sudden deviations, jitters
that make the timing or spacing uneven, that sort of thing.
Next, we have follow-through and overlapping action.
Follow-through is...
sort of at the opposite end of anticipation.
If anticipation is communicating what's about to happen,
then follow through is communicating what has just happened
and how it continues to impact the subject.
Follow through is the way your arm continues for a bit before settling,
after throwing a ball,
or the way a long coat comes to rest a bit later than the rest of you
when you stop running.
Nothing ever really stops stone cold when it's finished moving,
and follow through is a reflection of that.
Similarly, overlapping action is the notion that different elements move at different
rates as some parts lead and other parts follow.
This is just an animation I made a few years ago just for fun, not for any particular game,
but you can see that it has a lot of elements of follow through in it.
The sleeve, the sleeves kind of dragging behind, the lantern swinging, coming back to the notion
of arcs, the lantern swinging in an arc.
The shorts also kind of lagging behind the legs,
the flames being kicked up in front of the boots.
These are all sort of elements of follow through
and overlapping action.
I want to say something about how follow through and overlapping action are important in games
specifically because XYZ, the delayed elements, can help clarify information, etc.
And I do think that's true, but more often than not, it just communicates that something
has happened and it's finished now.
Follow through can be subtler than other moments of motion as it kind of tends to be a state
of energy being lost and things coming to settle or returning to a more neutral state.
But...
follow through, it tends to ground motions
and make them look more believable and weighty.
Just classic tool to make thing look good.
And you can see Makoto here.
I did not make this one.
But you can see her,
similarly a lot of the cloth,
like sweeping behind, following the motions before,
kind of leading the eye.
to an understanding of what has just occurred.
Um, overlapping action can also help communicate patterns of motion similarly to how
stretching a character along the axis of its motion. So squash and stretch can inform as to
its heading and speed. So too can a lagging scarf or tail or something, uh, inform to player as to
what direction something is moving, clarify what's about to happen by showing what has.
come to pass immediately.
Especially in high-speed games and environments, having some kind of visual anchor to demonstrate the recent past
can be the difference between parsing a situation and becoming lost in a rapidly changing visual landscape.
And lastly, we have exaggeration. It's not literally lastly,
there's still like five more principles, but like I said before,
we don't care about those.
So lastly of the ones we're going through is exaggeration.
This one might seem
Like a bit of an odd one out, a lot of the other principles focus on aspects of animation that are grounded in a more
physical understanding of the world as viewing physics from the perspective of an artist. The gravity,
centrifugal force implied by arcs, the inertia conveyed by follow-through and overlapping action, the
potential energy generated through anticipation.
But exaggeration is no less important than any of these exaggeration of both
form and motion can triple the size of a fist mid punch
just for that extra impact, just for even just a frame.
You might not see it, but you can feel it
break someone's spine beyond logic to get the get them to twist
the way you need to for that extra like wind up that extra anticipation.
You can have the hero do a full front flip if their attack misses because their momentum
just carries them into it and they go head over head over heels.
Anticipation is frequently exaggerated just by its very nature because if it weren't it would be
easily missed. People just don't move that way.
Like if I'm about to do something I'm not gonna have a big motion.
you know, to show you that I'm about to do something.
And this is kind of the advantage of the medium, that we can freely deform
and make ridiculous all the things we need to as readily as anything else
in order to get our point across.
If the other principles of animation are the groundwork laid
to keep things believable and grounded, then exaggeration is the means
by which that believability is made to matter.
Exaggeration can be thought of as almost a modifier that can be added to the other principles to enhance their impact.
Exaggerate the squash and the stretch. Really push that anticipation. Fling those arcs like yo-yos.
I've been pushing this idea of animation as communication, which might make it sound kind of utilitarian and technical, but...
That's not what I'm saying. If animators are communicators, then our communication is poetry.
We are afforded the ability to play with form and time as much as a poet might play with rhyme and
meter. Now, now we're going to talk about some common mistakes that people make when animating,
not just in general. Firstly, and importantly,
More frames is not equivalent to better animation.
Buttery smooth motion is not a requisite for good animation.
And in fact, adding more frames to smooth things out
can sometimes actively harm the idea you're trying to convey
by making things seem a little sluggish
in addition to creating more work for yourself.
I sometimes see people who are new to animation
trying to smooth over errors of timing and readability
by adding more in-between frames
in the hope, I guess, that it'll...
click together at some point once the motion is completely fluid. It's not really how it works.
Even worse is the notion that adding more frames is an inherent improvement,
or that a lack of frames is somehow a sign of poor animation.
in general. Like somehow the dream is to have all 2D animation be 60 fully rendered frames a second
and then it would be perfect. A philosopher's stone of animation. That's also not really the goal.
Far more important than having silky smooth frames that detail every moment of an action is having
strong readable poses that lead logically from one to another and timing that reinforces the action.
If you have a frame of someone with a sword raised in preparation and then immediately after a frame of them with their sword having
slashed forward, that's still animation and if the poses are strong and the action is readable,
it'll be better than poorly made keyframes that are tied together with 100 in-betweens.
No amount of in-betweens is going to fix poorly timed, poorly posed keys.
Say what you will about the animation of the CDI Zelda games,
but their issue is not that they don't have enough frames.
More often than wanting to add more frames to animations I make,
I find myself having overdone it and I need to delete some to add back
in some snap to the animation, make the motion feel cleaner.
One of the first professional gigs I ever had was for a game called Amour, the Unicorn Keep.
Yet another game with a colon and a subtitle for some reason.
It's been there since the beginning.
And it was a small mobile game. I was the only artist.
It was a good early job though, because all the animations in the game were like two to four frames.
This is, by the way, not a measure of my current skill. I'm much better.
Now I can do much better under the same constraints.
But it was a great early exercise in readability of motion
under very strict frame limits. And to this day, I don't really think any of these,
any of these animations need to have more frames than they, than they do.
Other than, other than maybe the bow.
I think the bow could probably use some follow through,
but everything else is two frames, four frames. It reads.
You don't need any more than that.
So, if we're not going to add more frames to smooth out the motion, how do we ensure
that motion reads as smoothly and continuously as we want, especially for fast moving objects
and things?
Oh, that brings us to our next common mistake or misconception.
Smears and multiples.
As mentioned briefly before, smears and multiples are techniques used to show the motion of an
object across time by distorting it, and they are my favorite thing. I love them so much.
I want to use them everywhere. They are so fun to draw.
This is another animation I did for Epic Mickey, and it is my favorite frame that I have ever made.
Somebody pay me to make a game that is nothing but smears, please. I will do it in a heartbeat.
But I think smears are often sadly misunderstood.
Your first inclination upon seeing these smears and multiples might be that they
represent speed,
that they're used as a means to communicate this thing is moving quickly.
But that's not entirely true. Smears and multiples,
despite how strange and abstract they often end up looking,
are tools to clarify.
They are the result of an object moving so quickly
that a frame needs to contain additional information
in order to properly connect the previous with the next.
Smears aren't used to convey speed, but rather they are the result of speed.
And this is something that I think a lot of new animators
don't really understand, because I see.
A lot of times I see smears and multiples and just blur, motion blur,
being used in the exact opposite way.
An object that is moving slowly enough to be easily read
is given a streak behind it that because, well, that's what fast things have.
And so if I add what fast thing has
to my slow thing,
I'll make it seem fast. That's.
not really, it doesn't follow.
The logic doesn't work.
Because remember, it's about
communication and clarity of events,
readability of motion.
You don't add a smear to indicate
speed. You add a smear to
address the loss of information
when something is moving too quickly
to follow otherwise.
And also because they're hilarious
to look at and fun to make.
So you can see here
the actual context of that smear from the previous slide.
Pete is hammering his fist down,
but you can see the middle one,
that's what it looks like without the smear,
that's the frame in between.
And you can see that the smear is very directly connecting
those two very distant points of motion,
trying to fill in that
that lack of information, that void that would otherwise be just lost.
Another thing to be careful of is over-animating.
having too much animation in a way that goes beyond communicating the action and instead
begins to obfuscate what happens or contributes to visual noise. And this isn't just a thing that
beginners do. I've actually mostly seen this from people who are relatively decent animators,
but maybe get carried away with making a thing move in a fun animated way while
losing sight of the context.
I'm not ragging on anyone specific, it's a trap I fall into on occasion as well.
An animation can look cool in isolation, but when put into context, you might suddenly realize,
wow, that animation, that idle animation has a lot going on and it's
kind of exhausting to look at for hours at a time.
Or you might make assets that look fine on their own,
but when put in context of being on screen all at once,
suddenly begin to fight for your attention
because they're all moving and drawing your eye.
Remember contrast.
Remember how it applies to motion as well.
If your idle animation has as much motion in it
as your run, as your jump, as your attack,
then
The contrast between these different states is diminished,
and when an important state change occurs, it can be harder to distinguish
if they all have like the same amount of motion going on.
You want to have breaks somewhere so that your eye can
have a bit of a rest and assess what's going on.
The next thing to be careful of is thinking you know things.
You don't know things. I don't know things.
There's a lot of things I don't know.
And that's fine because things exist and we can look at them.
I'm saying use references, uh, even for things you think you understand,
use references, browse the internet. I hear there's all kinds of videos on there.
Uh, you have a body, I assume, uh,
probably a phone with a camera, film yourself.
Act it out, use props, take note, not just of the motion, but of the sensation of
moving. Where do your muscles tense and stretch? What is uncomfortable to do?
What position is comfortable to do?
Is there a more natural feeling way of doing whatever you're trying to do that
this character could be moving that you hadn't considered?
You won't know these things all the time.
And that's fine, because it's nice to have an excuse to act
like an absolute fool in a professional capacity. I've been
paid to swing a plastic sword around in my bedroom. It was
research. My plastic sword broke last year. I'm still sad about
that I need to get another one. It was an incredibly handy prop
I recommend. I recommend animators to have props, plastic
sword, real sword, maybe, maybe, maybe a little dangerous.
But really, use references not only because you'll have a better idea of what you're working
on in the moment, the thing that you're actually referencing, but you'll be building a mental
library to pull from, which will be even more helpful on the next thing you animate or whenever
you finally get to the thing that you need to animate.
that doesn't have a direct analog that you can just look up,
you will at least have the collective knowledge of everything,
of all the references you've gathered, of all the things that you've seen,
and the ability to put them together in new and interesting ways to depict
whatever action you're trying to get across.
Lastly, don't be too precious with your work.
I mean this generally, but I also mean this very specifically in the sense that
I sometimes see...
see newer animators who they seem afraid to redraw frames.
Like I see people draw a single frame of a character
and then instead of drawing the second frame, they take their one pose
that they've made and are happy with and just kind of shift, shift things around
and rotate bits here and there, maybe redraw things in piecemeal.
And more often than not, it ends up looking like an obvious Frankenstein variant of the
one frame that they drew that they were happy with.
Sometimes sometimes you can do that and it will be fine.
Sometimes shifting stuff around is a completely valid way to save time and not redraw things
that don't need redrawing.
But
Being able to do that and do that well, and more importantly, being able to know when that is a thing worth doing is a skill.
It's a skill that you develop and the sense that you have.
But sometimes you just got to draw six to 12 wholly unique frames.
And. And you should.
I promise it'll be worth it.
You'll improve so much more quickly
if you just embrace the opportunity to make new mistakes.
Mistakes such as not keeping an object's mass
and proportions consistent throughout the animation.
This is for real the last one.
This is one of those things
where that old principle of animation that I glossed over
is gonna kind of come back to haunt us a little bit.
Solid drawing.
that I mentioned and kind of dismissed earlier.
Being good at drawing.
The best way to keep your animations from turning to jelly
as you work and losing the mass and proportions
is to practice and train your eyes so that you can
spot when errors crop up.
Hone your eyes to falcon sharpness.
Also, do construction and rough out your animation
beforehand so that you can catch those errors early.
Construction in art refers to the creation of simplified forms to help in understanding
the shape of more complex forms and the employment of those simplified forms as a foundation
upon which to build more complex forms. So as an example, you might draw a person's limbs
as a bunch of cylinders to understand proportion.
without getting bogged in and trying to accurately capture the musculature of the arm.
In animation, it can be similarly helpful to use simple shapes
just to make sure you're keeping things consistently sized and spaced
without getting too hung up on the details.
You can see here, uh, animation of a bear boss for, uh,
for catacomb kids, uh, the rough version and the, uh, the final version.
Uh, I didn't personally do these, but, but, uh, they're a good example of,
of how you can just use blocked out shapes to, to, uh,
to test the motion before you lock yourself into any kind of rendering and spot spot issues early.
Here's an unfinished animation that I just started working on a few weeks ago.
I haven't made it much further than this yet, but it's a death animation for one of the
boss enemies in Catacomb Kids.
You know, the one that was just on screen previously.
I know for a fact, like just looking at it, as I was working on it, I was like, oh, there's
a bunch of size inconsistencies and proportion issues.
some stretches of time with you know I haven't figured out what the arms are
doing for the entire time yet but I'm not worried about it because the point
of the rough is to get the motion right and the timing right and see where the
problem areas are so that I can catch them and address them before they become
larger issues.
If you jump directly into animating and rendering at the same time,
you're going to be pretty sore when you run into a big error
in the very premise of the action that you're trying to convey.
You're going to be reluctant to address it
because that would mean throwing away a lot of the work you've already done.
Ask me how I know.
But, you know, it's like the old saying goes, measure twice, animate once.
So there are a few other miscellaneous things I want to touch on before I call
it a talk. Um,
there aren't quite mistakes or principles or useful jargon or anything,
but they're just things I've come to understand and value over time.
That might be handy tools in your bucket of tools.
First of all, I think I should mention 2D skeletal animation.
I should talk about that for a bit.
Skeletal animation is when you have a character composed of
predetermined bones and joints that are rotated on pivots
rather than having each frame be drawn as a completely separate
and unique image or frame.
It's like how 3D animation works, but, you know, one less dimension.
And skeletal animation is great. I like it a lot.
It's I use it in my game Catacomb Kids for all the humanoid characters
because it's important that they be able to change their visual appearance
in accordance with their equipped armor and weapons and such.
And I knew from the start that I wasn't going to have.
the wherewithal or patience or longevity of life to hand animate the dozens or hundreds
of layers of equipment that would be needed to represent all the possible combinations in the game.
And that's really one of the great benefits of skeletal animation.
You can reskin bones, attach things to them on fly in-engine to reflect aspects of the game that
would be otherwise extremely difficult or time-consuming to create if you were
doing things in a more drawing-oriented fashion. Skeletal animation is also
kind of a requirement if you're going to be doing any kind of procedural animation,
which is animation that is done on the fly either partially or entirely by computation rather than
being strictly handcrafted, in order to be more reactive to the events in game and the environment.
The skeletal animation also makes it easy to blend from one pose or animation to another
smoothly without having jumps in the animation from going from one frame to another, changing
pose.
Of course, skeletal animation, 2D skeletal animation is just as subject to all the previous
principles of animation that I mentioned as frame-by-frame animation is. And it can be harder
to implement some of these principles in a way that feels naturalistic and good if you're not
careful because of the way skeletal animation often relies heavily on automated interpolation
between key poses. It kind of comes back to the idea that
more frames does not equate to more quality.
In the same way I mentioned earlier
that good in-betweens can't save bad keys,
the same is true in reverse.
Strong keys don't automatically lead to good in-betweens
or good timing.
So if you have good keys in a skeletal pose,
you still have to often really finesse the timing
in the skeletal animation to get it to work well.
It's not a set it and forget it type thing.
Um, also in skeletal animation can be tempting to make your key frames and just
save your time, the effort of doing all the in-betweens.
But that's again, it's not a set it and forget it type deal.
That's, that's, that's an easy way to have your good art look bad.
It's an easy way to have your, your, uh, as I mentioned earlier, uh, good style,
uh, strong style, uh, can still be animated poorly and does disservice to
everyone involved.
Uh.
Skeletal animation can also be a limiting factor to some degree and the kinds of
actions that characters can pull off. All of those aforementioned benefits come at a cost,
which is that if you want to make an animation that really pushes the action with lots of
twists and flips, like whatever the heck this guy is doing, it'll probably end up being much
harder to pull off using skeletal animation than it would be to draw out the thing that
you want to happen frame by frame.
And I also want to mention something that kind of irks me in particular that I see in a lot of 2D skeletal animation, which is a lot of times the hips and shoulders are neglected.
I see a lot of skeletal animation where the hips don't sway, the shoulders don't shuffle, as though those joints are pinned in place at their respective corners of an unrotating torso.
And these are two vitally important parts of the body for establishing the motion of the entire
body and pose. And they're central to the importance in creating forces that drive
human action. And I mean, I kind of get it. If you make the hips and shoulders rotate,
then you might have to then make a variance of the torso sprite to reflect the rotation
and swap that out mid animation. It's a little more work. But I don't know, maybe it's worth it.
I admit I kind of have it easy in Catacomb Kids, which is where this green guy is from.
It's Grumble from my game. I kind of have it easy because the sprites are so low resolution
that I don't really have to worry about torso rotation. You can't really tell. It's just chunky
pixels. So maybe I can get it away with a little easier than others. But if you're going to be
making a game using skeletal animation, it might just be worth considering, keeping in mind.
what would need to happen to make, you know, to make the movement a little more naturalistic
with the swaying of hips and shoulders. And I know Maxwell from Scribblenauts is kind of a
silly comparison because he's obviously very deliberately puppet-esque and cute and cartoony.
It's just, this is just an example of what I'm talking about just to get the idea across. I'm
certain Maxwell is a fine lad with upstanding character. Another thing to consider is this.
We're making games.
Presumably, we've got an engine that can handle certain aspects of motion and visual clarity
for us.
Image transformation, scaling, coloring, rotation, etc.
So you can save yourself some work and leverage those tools where you can.
Squash and stretch as a visual effect is relatively simple to implement in code.
and is generally useful enough effect that you might just want to say,
screw it, I'm going to just make a single frame for this thing
and let the code do the rest.
If your character has a long scarf or hair that trails behind them,
maybe you don't need to animate it by hand.
Maybe you can slap some physics on that element and have it flow
and follow them in a way that both makes it more integrated
into the rest of the game.
It also keeps you from having to animate a scarf.
Effects like weapon trails and particle effects can also be used and sort of offloaded to the
engine side of things to better integrate them with the world as opposed to having
a lot of things baked into animations. So just something to keep in mind.
And while we're on the topic of engine stuff, I also want to request
of the people who are making the tools and pipeline for games with traditionally animated art
to consider supporting variable frame durations for animations. The ability to have animations
not play at a constant set speed of just one single frame rate the entire way through
and to change the duration of specific frames mid-animation is incredibly valuable
for creating impactful timings.
I'm going to bring back the Hinox just so you can see what a big difference it can make.
The one on the left is playing at a constant rate.
You can see the smear.
that, you know, as I mentioned earlier, you know, smears are meant to clarify,
clarify motion.
But in this example, you're not really supposed to notice it.
It's it's supposed to just be like very brief, just there for an instant,
supposed to impart a feeling rather than being
like a detail that anybody can see.
But the constant frame rate version, that frame has just as much time given to it and weight and importance as all the other frames of the animation.
And, yeah, I don't like it.
So please, please make your animators happy by letting us have variable frame rates in our animations.
That's it. That's all I'm going to say on that.
Apparently that's all I'm going to say on anything.
Um, yeah, that's me.
That's, that's been my talk about animation and stuff.
I hope it has been helpful and useful.
Um, this is me for a bit Friday.
Uh, if you have any questions, say what's up.
If you're going to yell at me, don't.