Hello, everyone. Nice to see you here. We are very honored to give this talk at the
GDC. Our topic is hair art in games, aesthetics difference between Eastern and Western. Thanks
for coming our speech. So first, let me introduce the speakers.
I am Nora Xiaoying Fu, is currently the lead character artist in Justice Mobile project
and the character specialist in Justice Online project at NetEase Thunderfile Studio.
I used to work at Digital Extremes as a character artist in Warframe project
and at EA Mobile Canada as a 3D artist.
Hi, I'm Hao, and I'm now currently a senior research
researcher at NetEase Thunderfire UX department.
Recent projects I have worked on includes Justice Online,
Mobile Duel, Uno Mobile, and Naraka Playpoint.
Nora will give the first half of the speech,
and Luo will give the next half.
Thanks for coming.
So let's start.
Yeah.
Yeah, okay, let's start our speech.
So as a media art loved by people all over the world,
games show different art styles.
When we make next generation games,
we often pay attention to the effects of characters
and the hair is a very important part of it.
What's interesting is there are many aesthetic similarities
and differences between Western and Eastern themes games
based on cultural background.
I'm fortunate to have worked in different game companies
in Canada and China, and have participated
in games of different art styles in different game fields
from East to West.
Here, I have collected some experience.
I have collected some working experience and find some interesting points to share with you with my partner.
There are many points and this talk will focus on the aspect of the hair.
So first, let's review the trends of hair design in video games in recent decades.
With the development of the technology,
especially the hardware improvement,
the game performance have been rapidly developed.
Therefore, artists are all allowed
to present their design more freely.
So hair has been shown very differently
at different historical stages of the game development,
becoming more refined and diverse.
We can see this changing trend from the tumble ride in 1990s
to the metal gear solid in 2000s
until the recent last of us.
In the games of 1990s,
since the hardware can only support very few triangles,
the hairstyles are also very simple
without the texture of hair.
With the improvement of hardware, in the 2000s,
the games have been able to support
a small number of haircuts with transparent hair textures.
And now, the hardware have been able to support
very high triangles and a large number of alpha test
and alpha blend transparent maps.
So artists are also better able to design and create
more complex hairstyles.
The same changes have been experienced in the Eastern game
industry, from Audition Online to Nalika Blade Chop Point,
and Justice Online Mobile in development stage.
The hair design is becoming more and more complex,
and the details, both on the texture
and its dynamic performance, are increased rapidly.
So, games have accompanied many players since their childhood.
We can see that in most games, the hair designs are mostly derived from hairstyles used in people's
daily life, extracting the elements from reality and using it for characters.
Whether in the early games like Resident Evil,
or the games released in recent year, such as Cyberpunk 2077.
The hairstyles of the characters are very common
in real life, which makes the players feel
that these characters are the people living around them,
looks familiar in appearance
and creates a sense of immersion.
At the same time, the design of character in games
is not only extracting elements from real life,
but some special designs are also affecting
the public aesthetics.
In 2000s, when Audition Online was the most popular game
in Chinese market, many stars have the similar haircuts
with Audition Online style.
Similar hairstyles can often have been seen in street,
becoming a very fashionable style of the era.
Today's gamers have more requirements for game quality.
They not only want to customizing the face
and the body in the game,
but also matching the different hairstyles
with their temperament.
Therefore, hairstyle art is very important to highlight the personality of the character.
Take Natty's Nalika Blade point as an example. In this game, players can not only customize the
character's face, but also can choose different hair colors and styles to increase the sense of
immersion.
And some games, such as NetEase Tianyu Mobile,
go a step further to providing more diversity,
such as custom sub-regional dyeing function for hair color.
Many players are willing to spend much time on it.
In terms of hair styling design and production,
there are many interesting similarities and differences
between Eastern theme and Western theme games.
Next, I will use several games produced by our net ease
as representative of the Eastern game
theme to compare with the game cases from Western theme.
Let's look at the similarity first.
In terms of art design, hair style design is implementable in game.
Whether Eastern or Western, the designs are all extracting from the elements of actual hair styles in life.
Then we are creating, like blades and short hair.
In the ancient Chinese theme games Justice Online,
which background is in Song dynasty a thousand years ago,
there are also some design elements
extracting from daily life, such as the blades
and the curly hair.
The examples go on and on.
From above, we can easily feel that whether it's
Eastern or Western, the design of hairstyle
are not rhythm or baseless, but created
with elements in real life.
Moreover, the biggest similarity in game industry
is the application of technology.
No matter which project, the main way to make in-game hair is haircut method.
With the improvement of the hardware, some game developers also use dynamic hair simulation to present better dynamic effects.
The hair cut method is a mostly wide use practice
in the game industry.
The vast majority of in-game hairstyles
use this technique to create hair.
Hair cuts can make very rich and complex shapes.
At the same time, especially combined
with a close simulation or dynamic ball,
it makes the movement of the hair more natural and smoother.
So let's take a look at this video for our Justice Mobile project first to see how it works.
Come on, little tiger, let me tie a knot for you.
In this real-time rendering video,
the cat's fur and the girl's hair
are made with hair cut method.
In combination with Unity cloth simulation,
which achieves a natural motion effect
when hair touching the body.
And the calculation amount is also very slow,
making it easily running on the mobile phone.
Another method is dynamic hair simulation,
best known as AMD Tracefax Hair, an Unreal Engine hair
rendering and simulation system.
Use a bundle-based workflow to rendering each hair
with physical accurate motion.
It enables the creation of hairstyles
to be simulated in real time, rendering hundreds of thousands
or more of the realistic hair.
In this video, the hair is used AMD Transpax technology.
Although the technology is the same,
when making different hairstyles in different themed games
between West and East, the focus on hair design aesthetics
and the gameplay in the game are different.
So what is the aesthetics difference
between Eastern and Western hairstyles?
Before showing the case, please allow
me to extend some Eastern and Western differences
in traditional painting.
I believe that everyone who has visited
a Western classical painting
and an ancient Chinese painting in a museum
will find that there are great differences between them two.
It's two completely different systems.
Relatively speaking, Western classical painting
focus on lighting and shadow,
perspective and anatomical structure,
which tend to present the reality in painting.
Whether figures or landscapes,
Western classical painting express
the material world and the reality.
So to speak, Western aesthetics mainly focus on creating,
recreating and attaches great importance to realism.
In contrast, the Eastern ancient painting
are not more about describing the real world,
but a kind of expression of personal feelings.
Take ancient Chinese painting as an example.
This is a part of China's national treasure,
a thousand miles of rivers and mountains
from Northern Song dynasty more than a thousand years ago.
When we feel the beauty of the, we can feel the beauty of the landscape
from painting, but the landscape are completely
inconsistent with light and shadow, perspective and structure.
This is the most important point of Chinese painting.
Feeling expression.
Realism is neither needed nor value
in Chinese traditional painting.
In fact, you can't find such a mountain like that at all.
And this blue color on the top of mountain
is also impossible in natural reality.
But we can still feel the same feeling
as when the author painting.
That is beauty.
Due to this difference in Eastern and Western aesthetics,
the difference between reproducing reality
and the expression emotions, the difference in hair design
aesthetics is caused.
And it is also the difference in players' acceptance
of hair aesthetics between Eastern and Western-themed
games.
Therefore, Western themed games focus on realism,
restore the shape in real life,
and pay more attention to the sense of reality,
such as the main character's hairstyle changing
during the fighting process.
Taking Last of Us 2 as an example, the shape of the hair is consistent with reality.
The hair roots are distinct. The material is very realistic. The surrounding broken hair is
clearly shown. And some shorter hair are struggled after the battle,
which is very realistic and physically true.
When seeing this, players will price the sense of reality.
On the other hand, many Oriental-themed games
consider the styling and the production of hair
from another direction, and will pay more attention
to the silhouette, outline, and the beauty of the styling,
while sacrificing part of the realism and the rationality.
Take three Chinese style games produced by our NetEase Thunderfire Studio, for example.
They are Justice Online, Narca Blade Point, Wangchuan Fenghua Lu.
So whether it is a realistic art style or a two-dimensional art style game,
The hair design tended to pay more attention
to the beauty of the silhouette, shape, and the line,
sacrificing part of the realistic feel.
In Justice Online, on the left, her hairstyle
is using lines to form a silhouette.
But if it's in real life, shouldn't it
hand down under the influence of gravity?
Narika played in the middle as another example.
So many decorations look so heavy.
Isn't she afraid that her precious golden accessories
will falling off during a fight?
How can the hair accessories be insert
from the bottom up against the gravity?
and Wang Chuan Feng Hua Lu on the right.
In order to create the silhouette,
the hair is floating in the air,
which is completely against the physics.
These designs are completely non-realistic,
but who can deny they are beautiful?
In fact, these hairstyles are widely priced
in players' group.
Through the feedback from various social media and questionnaires,
we draw a conclusion of our games player. Players don't care much about whether the hairstyle is
realistic and reasonable. They care more about whether the appearance is beautiful or not.
Therefore, in those projects,
Artists make a choice, giving up part of the reality of haircuts when we designing and producing hair, which is different from the realistic style in Western game.
After brief.
After briefly talking about the similarities and the differences mentioned above,
let me introduce how we design Oriental hairstyles.
As mentioned earlier, both Eastern and Western games have one thing in common in terms of aesthetics.
That is, many hairstyle elements are based on the extraction of hairstyle elements in life.
But in oriental-themed games, many hairstyles can hardly be found in real life.
Many shapes cannot be restored in real life because of the antigravity.
So how do we find elements?
This goes back to Chinese painting.
We pick the specific elements from historical painting
and then recreate to our works.
The traditional Chinese ink painting
is formed by one stroke.
Due to the characteristic of the brush,
there will be different thickness changes in one stroke.
The line drawn with the tip of the brush is thinner
and the line drawn with the brush obliquely is thicker.
At the same angle, the grass ratio of the falls different.
The lines are completely different.
The rhythm of ink painting is also drawn
within a single stroke.
Therefore, the line is the most important aesthetic element
of Chinese painting art,
and it is also a watershed
between Chinese and Western painting.
Changes in the thickness, shade, lightness, speed,
dryness, and wetness of a line under the stroke
can express emotion, ups and downs,
convey feelings, show character,
and publicizing individuality.
With the concept of lines, when we design and make hairstyle,
we will consider each strand of hair is a line
and pay more attention whether the lines of the hair
are smooth and whether each strand of hair
has a reasonable thickness change.
and whether there is enough tension in the outline of the styling that the hair strays out.
Take a look at this hair as an example.
Here is a haircut created in the collaboration between Nalika BladePoint and Justice Online.
Each strand hair in this hairstyle has ups and downs,
through the change of the thickness
and the shade of the silhouette.
The character's gritty personality is clearly shown.
Women's hairstyles are different from men's,
although they are using the curly lines as well
and have thickness changes.
In women's hair styles, we will pay more attention
to whether the curvature of the curve is soft or not,
and whether the falling strands are distributed
in a rhythmical change rather than an even distribution.
Through the changes of the outline and the silhouette
of the line, as well as the changes of the curling radium,
a completely different temperament can be reflected.
Curly hair and curly lines not only mean soft and feminine,
but also can show the power and the flamboyant personality.
This is the magic that lines bring in.
Therefore, when we make hair, we're
concerned about the beauty of the line shape,
the thickness change of hair strands,
the shade change of the hair pieces
shows on the UV distribution.
and the change of the curved radium
to the outline of the silhouette.
In addition to extracting design inspiration
from the lines of ink painting,
we also extract elements from traditional painting.
For example, this picture is a painting
of Tang Dynasty 1,300 years ago.
We're extracting the main hairstyle elements,
panhandle.
and the big peony flower,
combined with our understanding of the curve
to design this style.
Although it's kind of against gravity,
how can the hair pieces on the left
not fall down in the real world?
But it does not affect the beauty of this shape
in the game at all.
From perspective of aesthetics, hairstyle
is a very important part of the character
appearance of a certain era.
Hair can act as a gateway to bring us back to the old time.
In a way, hairstyle can connect our imagination of the past
with real tradition, forming bridges
across the time and the generations,
and reach thousands of households
through films, games, and other works.
After talking about some aesthetics discussion,
we then entered the focus on our speech.
It's also a summary from our teamwork experience.
how we can better achieve interesting and beautiful hairstyles in the game,
and what we can do. Next, we will summarize four key thoughts about hair design in video game,
as well as our understanding of design methods.
The four key points are history experience.
The game hair design in line with the character era
will give players a better sense of immersion.
In this part, we will talk about the historical immersion
of hairstyle through a series of Eastern and Western artworks
and games.
Part two, diversity personality.
From perspective of user experience,
we discuss how to present a diversity and a personality
by haircuts, as well as how to bring players
a variety of hairstyles design,
when allowing using their creativity.
Part three, contrast memory.
Although the main purpose of most hairstyle
is attractive appearance, some hairstyles
could express very strong personality characteristic.
We will discuss how to create some strong memory points
by creating hairstyles contrast.
Part four, label breaking, universal value.
We will discuss how to break the design concept
of labeling character with hairstyle labels
and try to use game art exploration
to convey universal value.
In addition, the work we have done
to realize the ideal of label breaking.
The third and the fourth part
will be introduced by my partner, Luo Hao.
So let's start with a brief review in the history of hair design.
In many cases, it's easy to identify the background of the character's era without
looking at the character's clothes, just by styling his hair.
The first one, Ancient Greece hairstyle.
The middle one is Baroque hairstyle.
And the last one is Qing Dynasty, China.
hairstyle.
Hair can symbolize person,
hair can symbolize personal identity,
status, cultural identity, and so on.
The study of these ancient hairstyles
can go in many directions,
from history books, statues,
frescoes, and ancient painting.
that have been passed down to the present.
We can get information about how ancient people dressed up
in the era when they lived.
In game design, we can make full use
of hairstyles with historical characteristics of the time
to better tell stories.
The hairstyle design in the game that
is in line with the character's era background
will give the players a better sense of immersion.
Here is a character from TV series Qingping Le in a collaboration with our Justice Online project.
Even if the audience have not tried this game or watched the TV series,
they can easily locate the historical background through her hair.
ancient China, and her identity, a well-educated woman
with a higher status, and so on.
The beautiful accessories on her head,
which is not over decorated, shows
that she is very rich, but with a restrained personality.
The hair was neatly combed back, indicating
that she has the habits to control her appearance, which
tell us her social status.
In fact, this woman is a queen in the game and TV series,
who dislike luxury and has reserved and quiet personality.
Another example, in this case,
through the hairstyle we see
and a sweet young girl in ancient China,
the accessories on her head are exquisite.
many small flowers and peels, showing her gentle and soft character. She is keeping Ben's hair
in front, looking neat and cute. In fact, this girl is a lovely princess with a tragic love story.
The right hairstyle can tell a story.
It can also allow players to evolve in the game
at the beginning with a good sense of immersion, experience,
and they will not feel inconsistent and strange.
In the game Total War Three Kingdom,
the developer has restored the historical background
in a high degree, and the reboot's unique hairstyle
is impressive.
The sense of historical immersion
is not only well represented in Oriental-themed games,
but also well reflected in many other culture themes.
As soon as a hairstyle in Assassin's Creed Oranges
is displayed,
Without any text introduction, players
know that the background of this game is ancient Egypt.
Similarly, as soon as this hairstyle comes out,
even people who have not played the God of War series
can know that the story takes place in ancient Greece
and a total warm Rome.
Hairstyling is used to express the background of the history.
To sum up, the hairstyle design in the game
that is in line with the character's era background
will make the players have a better sense of immersion.
Part two, diversity and personality.
After finishing the previous part,
let's talk about the diversity and the personality
of hairstyles.
This image is from Fallout 4.
I'm quoting this image here because it
fits my point of view.
We can change hairstyles in our daily life,
just like characters in games.
When people change their hairstyles,
sometimes the temperament is also changed.
The variety of hairstyle provide more display
or personality and temperament.
Therefore, in the game, as in daily life,
a variety of hairstyle options to change at any time,
providing a feeling of freshness,
as well as a deeper sense of involvement.
On the other hand, the specific outfit of some game characters shows a strong personality.
People remember those who impressed them with personalized appearance.
For example, Tagami Takayuki in Lost Judgment with a unique hairstyle which impressed people
easily.
This is a strong memory point that the feature of the haircut
brings to the player.
In another category of games, this
provide games with a greater variety
of different customized looks.
It can give players a better experience
and increase users' sickness.
In addition to the diversity of hairstyles,
individual customization can also
be improved through adjustments such as hair color dyeing.
Diversity and personality are two sides of a coin.
Whether it is a personalized design or diversified design,
the main purpose is to better provide the players
with memory points.
a sense of immersion, and a better game experience.
So what's NetEase Games did to provide the players with hairstyle diversity
while it's generating personalized and impress the character?
The variety of hairstyle highlights the richness of the game character.
At the same time, the personalized hairstyle design shows the special characteristics of players in the game.
Take Nalika Braid Point as an example.
Could you feel impressed when you saw this character for the first time?
If so, are you curious what elements make it impressive?
This comes to personalizing designs
to enhance the character's traits.
So what kind of personalized elements
are used in the design?
This hairstyle that combines a very muscular
mohawk hairstyle with long curly hair, that is family.
The designer combines two completely
opposite temperament hairstyles,
and they design the shape match the male face,
which have a very strong memory and personality.
Make one remember this look at a glance.
Different hairstyles in the game show different personality.
These three characters have the same facial feature,
similar clothing style, and are decorated
with similar bead necklace on their chest.
Sorry.
But because of the different hairstyle,
they show completely different personalities.
The one in the left feels tough and strong.
The one in the middle is more gentle.
And the one in the far right is between them too.
Why do people feel so different?
This is because the short, sharp line
gave people a sharp and strong feeling
with a certain aggression.
While the long curly lines show a certain gentle
and a mild natural.
The characteristics of the line are applied to the hairstyles,
which brings the character attributes unique with the lines
to the character.
It's also a good way to show personality.
If it is matched with different facial features, skin color,
and clothing, the character's shape
will have a more distinct personality.
After this other way to enhance the aesthetics richness
of character other than the personalization of the design,
of course, we can provide a more variety of hairstyles
in addition to personalized styling.
In the Tianyu mobile game, players can always find their favorite hairstyles to show their personality.
But within the same personality temperament, hairstyles can also be changed in different ways.
For example, the player's hair in the picture is a very cute and sweet one.
In the category of cute and sweet hairstyles, there are still varieties of haircut designs.
So diversity is also provided in personality.
In the same category of personality and temperament,
with similar hairline elements, different shapes
can design to better provide the players with rich diversity.
The same long hair curve shape through the different design
can also provide rich diversity in the category
of mild temperament.
The decorative items on the head are also
extremely important part in hair styling design.
Developers will design a lot of hair accessories
to provide more choice.
Some small accessories can make the player's image
in the game much more personalized,
such as cute fox ear accessories.
and the design of hairstyle and hair accessories
can better increase the beauty.
Below is a brief overview of the variety
of hairstyles and accessories.
In Justice Online, diverse customization
of traditional hairstyles gives the game
more possibility of better richness of characters
and the player space.
So let's take a look of the hairstyle and the decorations.
I am finishing my part of the speech, so let my partner Luo Hao introduce the next part of the speech to everyone. Thank you.
Thank you, Nora.
Hi, I'm Hao Luo. Thanks for listening to our speech. And I will be presenting the next two parts. So let's dive into the third part, which is about contrast and memory.
So most hairstyles are designed for beauty as the main purpose,
and the good hairstyle design makes the game character look with basic stylistic guidelines.
However, some hairstyles themselves have different characteristics, such as strong temperament.
For example, a long curly hair is naturally associated with a feminine and gentle temperament.
When looking at this curly hair, it's normal to think,
okay, she's probably a female.
Maybe because many women choose to keep long hair,
although they all have their own choices.
But if a male character keeps a big beard
along with the long curly hair,
it will conflict with the stereotype in our mind.
and it will definitely be impressive
because it brings a strong point for audiences to remember.
And the audiences or players will immediately feel
that this is a character
who has an interesting background story.
Let's take a look at this picture.
What kind of imagination do you have when you see it?
you probably would think she's a lovely girl
with gentle characteristics.
And she might be a gentle character in a game,
but that's not always the truth.
With the same hairstyle, he can also be a strong warrior.
So different face gives a different interpretation
of this same hairstyle.
But which one do you think is more impressive?
Looking at the picture in the middle,
the long hair matches the feminine feature
and looks totally part of it.
But the hairstyle impression in people's concept
conflicts with the character's temperament
in the third picture,
making it extremely impressive to most people.
Compared with the middle one,
audiences will more look forward
to the subsequent story content
brought by the character on the right.
We have not entered any maps with this character
with big beard and long hairstyle.
His image makes us eager to discover more about his story
and know more about his journey along the way.
Let's look at another example, a star in China.
What is your feeling when you look at this picture?
Her temperament is relatively mild, tender and soft.
And this used to be her daily hairstyle.
And it's beautiful, but maybe less memorable.
The middle one and the right one both changed to short hair,
which conflicted with her own soft looks and temperament.
The visual impact immediately make people
memorized so the star in reality actually keeps short hair for the most of the time
and we probably want to know more about her story and how she's doing when we see these two pictures
and when it comes to games
This is a boss from NetEase game Justice with a bald plus braided hairstyle design,
which has a strong memory point and fits the evil character aura that a boss should have.
By the way, this hairstyle also can be obtained by the player when you defeat the boss.
So if in this game, the player's customized face is relatively mild and soft with the evil hairstyle,
he will not only no more have evil temperament, but becomes a little funny to some players.
So that players around him feel very impressive.
and that is how you become a person remembered by everyone inside the guild or a player community.
Some players will use this hairstyle which cannot be purchased in the game
to communicate and to socialize with other players.
And there will even be players who have this hairstyle
and they will customize the color of this hair
to get a much more different effect.
In this way, he's also naturally remembered by other players
and this is exactly the effect
of having a huge constructing hair design.
And another example is in Naraka Playpoint of NetEase.
Some players will also customize their characters
with various hairstyles.
At the same time, they will also combine
the game's face customization settings
to make their characters into unique images.
Why do they do this?
The answer is that it is easier to be remembered
by other players.
Of course, in the process of hair and face customization,
players can enjoy the fun of their own creations.
But ultimately, they get more sense of accomplishment
because the very recognizable and constructing image
stays in people's memory.
So after talking about contrast and memory,
I will be moving on to the fourth part, which
is about label breaking and the universal values.
So in many cases, games artists and designers or directors
of movies often use hairstyle to directly define a character
and even his or her personality.
which has been mostly successful
because hairstyle leave players
and audiences great impression
and they just remember the character.
However, sometimes such a design
can have some unwelcome effects.
The reason for that is because
using a specific hairstyle to define a character
will make the game or film lack of variety.
A certain personality or characteristic should match only a certain kind of style.
If you think so, you have to find the person or the character with just a simple label.
But this character can also have a lot of other rich and varied hairstyle designs.
And through other aspects of character design to highlight the specific characteristics.
Therefore, sometimes it needs to be transferred to not using certain hairstyles to get characters labeled easily in-game,
and not defining a certain character or background with just a specific hairstyle,
because it bans diversity and discriminates.
And we can see that certain hair styles also have certain impressions in people's minds.
For example, this slicked back hair gives people the first impression that
they are related to gangsters or mafia. This is actually a natural label added to such characters.
However,
In fact, this kind of hairstyle used by some people reflects just cool characters
and has nothing to do with their occupations.
This kind of stereotype should not be labeled on a person or a character so easily.
And let's take a look at these pictures.
What do you imagine when you see them?
So these dirty braids give people the first impression
that they are related to street art, hip hop,
or other cultures, or cool new trends.
Just like this guy.
He can be a popular rapper.
But in fact, some dirty braids or dreadlocks
are connected with mysterious religions in some places.
Among the ethnic minorities in China,
there is a religious belief of Buddhism,
and the hairstyle of believers
are actually very similar to dreadlocks.
They do not represent street culture, hip hop art,
but rather a faith and reverence for the Buddhism.
Underneath these labels we just saw,
there actually lies a very different truth.
So for these two pictures, which one is more impressive?
Or which one makes us expect more stories behind it?
I think the answer might be the left one.
If we break the stereotype and add some other rich features
to the specific characterization,
for example, the old and devout believer
will be more storytelling than the features of the hairstyle
itself.
We can use this method of peeling off
those labels in game design to give the characters richer
and fuller information.
and it will have a more impressive impact
than just designing a defined hairstyle label
for a certain character.
And such character appearance designs
as an overturn to the traditional stereotype
may give players more memorable and impressive points
as well as greater impact to them.
but how to peel off or break these labels in game design.
Here, I would like to share what NetEase have done with you.
Firstly, we developed and applied a diverse headwear system.
We know that in a specific historical context,
Game designers are prone to labeling when designing character hairstyles.
For example, the golden hairpin for rich people and the helmet for warriors.
However, if you have a various and varied hair decoration system,
the effect of labeling will be largely reduced.
Why?
Because bringing a...
A lot of different hair accessories for players consequently reduces the stereotype that a certain character should have a certain hairstyle or wear a certain hair accessory.
In this game Justice Online, which is a big title of NetEase, we designed and implemented a diverse hair wear system.
As you can see in this video, the character has a rich variety of hair decorations and a wide variety of hair accessories that allow players to have many different combinations, even based on the same hairstyle.
And players can choose from many more other hairstyles to change combinations.
In this way, it's much more difficult to say,
in terms of hairstyle and hair accessories,
to give him a specific label, because the character is not
only limited to a certain hairstyle appearance.
On the other hand, it also enhances
the richness of the character, so that other players have
more desire to.
um, explore the story behind the character or to communicate and
socialize with the player behind him.
So we can change many decorations, Henny and headwear in this video.
And secondly, a creative hair shape customization system
was designed and implemented also,
according to the historical background of the game
and the characteristics of roles.
As mentioned before, we don't want
a game in which the warriors are only bald or with short hair.
The hairstyles can all be customized by players freely.
This kind of experimental function also allows players to be more inclusive about characters'
appearance, rather than limiting their perceptions to a certain character should only have a
certain hairstyle.
And some more examples can be found in Naraka Playpoint of NetEase.
So long hair of this regional culture,
the ancient Chinese updo, and the adjusted Western style
Mohican hairstyle, also use the male warrior in this video.
In this way, the male warrior is no longer exactly equal
to the bun or short hairstyle.
The game instead provides players
with more different options and collocations
so as to overcome the stereotypes.
And thirdly, what we did to break those labels is the design of the hair coloring system
based on diversity and high aesthetics.
And this has allowed netis to make some other achievements in breaking the stereotype as
well.
For example, in the Araka Playpoint,
it is also possible to use the hair coloring system
to match any hair color you like,
allowing players to create freely
and to be remembered by others.
Male characters should not die red in traditional concept.
Such inherent stereotype have been formed by so many people,
but in Araka Playpoint,
we have no such traditional stereotyped images.
In Tenryu Mobile, we give players more hair color customization options,
including highlighting parts of their hair as they like,
dying in gradient color, and some other options. Of course, the game
also provides the most basic coloring function,
which provides a variety of colors for players to
to choose from.
The player chooses this lovely young girl with two ponytails as his or her character.
And it's possible for the player to avoid a specific label by dyeing her hair into a favorable color.
Force
When designing games, based on the premise of conforming to the time background,
we try to do cultural integration and multifaceted display of different cultures.
And this means a lot, and we will continue to do it, because cultures and civilizations all
over the world are the heritage of the development stage in human history.
And if those cultures can be integrated into games, that's an awesome thing to do.
So here is an example.
In Naraka Playpoint, we have incorporated
the characteristic hairstyles of other regional cultures
and allowed players to create their own faces
in character face customization,
either Western or Eastern style.
And everything is possible.
And this game is not only to match the tastes of players from different regions in the world,
but also to achieve the integration of various cultures into the game.
This is also reflected in the design of hairstyles in Naraka Bay Point and some other games of Nereid.
So I think that's all what we want to share in terms of this topic.
And please allow me to summarize a little bit here.
Firstly, every background in game design is important
and do consider player experience and how to make them immerse more.
Secondly, get players into your hair design process, if possible,
and try to listen more to them.
And thirdly, while providing diversity and remember to allow freedom for personality.
Fourth, cultural blending can get you fans of different backgrounds.
And finally, sometimes it is worth to try label breaking and let's do more about it.
That's all. Thank you for listening.
Thank you.
And if you guys have any questions, we would like to answer these.
Okay, we're sorry that there's no time left for questions maybe.
And thank you guys for coming to our speech and bye. Have a nice day.
Thank you. Have a nice day. Bye.