All right, here we go.
So the name of my talk today, Get Your Game Out of My Movie,
Narrative Design in Mass Effect 2.
So I want to talk about the title,
because actually a lot of people have been asking me about this
and what it kind of means.
And really, for a Bioware game, we really
don't differentiate between game and story.
They're pretty much the same thing.
We start with story and we add gameplay,
but really they're.
they're symbiont to each other.
We don't really differentiate between the two.
And really, I think the title itself kind of
just encapsulates what we believe the rest of the industry
is really struggling with right now,
which is the fact that we have story, we have gameplay,
but we're really trying to merge them.
So what this presentation's going to be about
is how we solve those issues for Mass Effect 2.
So who's this guy talking to you?
Well.
My name is Armando Torrice. I'm the lead cinematic designer on the Mass Effect franchise.
I've been with the team for about four and a half years now,
and I've been running what we call the cinematic design department.
And cinematic design is really kind of an odd thing. It doesn't really exist in a lot of places.
And we just kind of...
Sorry, Frank.
So, yeah, that would be a good one for later on.
Um, so what is cinematic design? Well, we're narrative designers, um, uh, first, and we're
cinematic artists second. And what we really deal with is the how of interactive storytelling
and the how of interactive narrative. We provide the writers with the tools and the processes
to create the interactive conversations that are in the game. And when we talk about the
interactive conversations, we're really talking about the main way that we're communicating
with the player. It is the main device in which we, um, we, um, we communicate with
get story to the player and have them understand
what the intent of the writer
and the rest of the narrative design team is doing.
So, really, what are we talking about here today?
Well, we're gonna talk about a couple of things.
First thing is story perspective.
And if there's any writers out there,
they understand that story perspective
is a very powerful thing.
And it even gets even more complicated
once you add the player to the mix
of protagonist and antagonist.
And we're going to be addressing some of those issues.
that we encountered in the many role-playing games that we've made at Bioware.
The second is the agreement.
And the agreement is really the rules in which we deal with interactivity in the cinematic space
and how we apply those rules to what we're trying to achieve with the role-playing experience.
And, you know, we all know them, don't know if we all love them, but QuickTime events.
We've added QuickTime events to conversations in Mass Effect.
I'm gonna, we're gonna go through kind of what the process was in designing those and
making sure that they, they're a part of this agreement.
You know, they fit into our narrative design structure.
And we're gonna have some Q&A at the end of this, so you can ask me all types of great
questions.
So firstly, a BioWare game is composed of what we call the pillars of design.
And really they're story, exploration, progression, and gameplay.
So...
We have this concept of activity chaining,
which happens between these four different quadrants
of the player experience.
And the one we're gonna be concentrating on today is story.
But that's not to mean that the other parts
don't have story, like they obviously do.
But in terms of referencing and framing
this discussion today, we're going to be talking about
this interactive cinematic space.
And this is our product.
This is the conversation system that hopefully a lot of you got to play.
And we're going to be talking about the mechanics behind Story and how we navigated the minefield
of different player choice and agency.
So firstly, let's try to define what we call a conversation.
And the first thing that I think of, really, is that it's a narrative tool.
It's a way for us to communicate with the player.
And there's lots of narrative tools that we use.
We use ambient dialogue, we use video screens,
we use codexes, we use a myriad of techniques to communicate.
But this is our primary narrative tool.
And secondly, it's a game system.
It is a massive, massive thing that we develop at BioWare.
And it allows us to coordinate the content from disciplines
like art and writing and animation.
and level design and bring it all together to make these great interactions.
And it's also a philosophy. When we talk about conversation in Bioware, we're talking about
this character interaction, this emotional
storytelling that we're really trying to achieve. So this is something we're always
working on, always trying to evolve.
And this is the scary part of a Bioware game.
This is the conversation tree.
And I know a lot of people have a lot of opinions about conversation trees and
and you know whether or not they're a good way
to do interactive narrative and interactive dialogue.
But it really works for us.
We really have spent many, many years refining
this particular way of communicating with the player.
And you know, and it's the one thing that's very common
to all Bioware games.
We all use this basic technology.
Everything from Baldur's Gate to the new MMO
uses this technology and this design principle.
But if you look very closely and very deeply into this crazy web,
you'll notice that there's one thing that's inherent to what we're trying to achieve.
And it's the idea of choice.
And choice in cinematics is something we take really seriously at BioWare.
And it's the culmination of all the animations, the cameras,
the scripting, the dialogue, the VO, and we bring it all together.
And what we're trying to do is just really make sure that the player understands,
hey, you know what, this is your story.
This story doesn't belong to the writers.
This story belongs to the players.
And we really try to imbue everything we do
with that kind of sensibility.
So in order to frame this discussion,
we're gonna be talking about perspective.
And when we talk about perspective,
we're talking about a couple of different things.
We're talking about the point of view
in which the player interacts with the story.
And in Bioware games, it really comes down
to two different types of...
of categories. One is subjective and one is objective. So subjective, we have a huge history
of doing these types of games and I'm sure you can recognize a lot of them up there.
And really what a subjective game is, is a traditional computer role playing experience.
It's the one that we've all known for many many years where you are the avatar or the
playing character.
Dialogue responses that you make are verbatim.
There's no interpretation.
What you say is what your player says.
There's uninterrupted agency, which means that my character doesn't act without me actually telling him what to do.
He doesn't act on his own.
There's always a level of choice that happens moment to moment between me and my avatar.
And it's really great.
It allows us to quickly empathize with the avatar
in order to get into his head.
And this is really the design of, you know, this is you.
This is not someone else.
This is you playing the game.
But there's a couple of things that happens
and that we're going to be looking at right now.
And the first is really some of the side effects
that happens from the subjective point of view.
And it's temporal distortion and really lots of dialogue.
So temporal distortion happens when choices are being made.
or your player says something and we usually say,
oh, your player's silent.
But no, your player's not silent,
we just sped up time really fast.
And we just chopped out that time
and we went straight to whatever the response was.
And really, what happens is, in that type of situation,
the NPC has to hold up a lot of the dialogue on their own.
So there's a lot more exposition needs to happen.
So we're gonna take a look at a clip here
from Knights of the Old Republic.
in which we use this subjective storytelling technique.
Back again?
Is there something old Garuk can do for you?
Or did you just come to chat with a lonely old man?
So once again, this is the distortion that happens
when you're making a choice.
That's why I'm giving up the gambler's life.
But I think I can still manage
to answer some simple questions.
And again, some more distortion when you make a choice.
We're saying time has stopped at this point
and you are now contemplating your next choice.
So, and forgive me for the choppy video.
I'm running this thing off my little laptop here,
so just forgive me for that, please.
So here we go.
Now we get into the objective story.
And this is kind of what some of our newer titles are doing,
especially for the Mass Effect franchise.
And it actually brings along a lot of new challenges.
So when we talk about objective story, it's really counter to the traditional role-playing model.
You are not the avatar. So when people say that, they get kind of weirded out, because they're like, Shepard's me.
But you're not, no, it's really not. And I'm going to explain why most people feel that way about Shepard.
But you are not Shepard. Shepard has his own motivations, he has his own voice, he's an actual
character. He's more akin to Kratos than anything like on Dragon Age or any of the other titles.
So Avatar has his own voice and motivations.
The player is now voyeuristic to the whole experience.
And this is when we get into what we call
the interactive movie model,
where you're very objective to what's happening
and you're kind of watching things
and then trying to control it through your choice.
So there's a lot of reasons why we try to do this.
Really, it's this idea of real-time narrative environment
that actually removes a lot of these temporal distortions
that we saw with the previous clip.
And the temporal distortions being when you make a choice or you're waiting for a choice
So this allowed us to really break through and add drama to these interactions
Which is something which our project director really wanted to do and this is really the breakthrough in interactive storytelling that we made with
Mass Effect
so we're gonna take a look in Mass Effect and
We're gonna be we're gonna see this real-time
environment in action
What are you looking at?
The man who damn ugly.
I'm not looking for trouble.
Maybe I am.
Maybe you better get out of here before I find you some.
Alright, alright. I've got stuff to do anyway.
Come on, let's get out of here.
and a lot of cool stuff just kind of happened around you and it really feels like it's real
time and it really feels good. It feels very cinematic at that point. But I'm wondering
if a lot of people out there who are very traditional notice something very odd about
what Shepard did. And so if you can take just a little quick guess at what I'm trying to
allude to. Let's roll the clip again and let's take another look.
The man who's damn about to ruin it.
Ah, I'm not looking for trouble.
Maybe I am.
Maybe you better get out of here before I find you some.
Alright, alright. I've got stuff to do anyway.
Come on, let's get out of here.
So, um, I wonder, did anybody catch it at all?
He, uh, he expounded on the choice of the game.
Oh, nice, exactly.
So, what it was is, auto-reply.
So Shepard acted on his own without me telling him to do something.
I didn't want to say that.
As a player, I'm like, okay, well what if I wanted to turtle?
What if I wanted to make another choice?
You know, Shepard just did something.
Maybe I didn't want to.
Like, you know, am I disconnecting from this roleplaying experience?
My agency has just been interrupted.
Like, so, you know, what's going on here?
Was it lack of choice?
Was it an anti-roleplaying design?
And really, with so many of these traditional rules broken,
why is Mass Effect such a successful RPG experience?
And really, it comes down to what we call the agreement.
And the agreement is something that we have with the player.
It's a set of rules that binds us to the player
and the player to the designer to make sure
that their role-playing experience is always expected
and is always in line with their expectations.
So, what is the agreement?
Well, it's a covenant the designer makes with the player.
It's a set of rules that governs choice and expectation.
And we'll be getting into these in some detail.
It binds the player to the role-playing experience
and allows the player to access the avatar.
So it allows us to have this very fluid,
very first-person, very subjective role-playing experience
while still maintaining this objective
point of view in the story.
So what is the agreement we made?
Well, every time we're writing things at BioWare or at Mass Effect, we always come down to
some certain principles, which is a litmus test for us to say whether or not this is
a good role-playing experience or not.
And really, these are them.
And we often describe them as the covenant.
This is something, to us, is very sacred and something that we always come back to and
something that's just so important for us to maintain that role-playing experience.
So first...
Interface for choice is always predictable.
Choice produces results the player expects.
Give the player the choices they want,
and hopefully when they want to make them.
And the last one is the player story.
Like I said before, the story doesn't belong to the writers.
The writers give you this great multi-path narrative,
they give you this probability space to play in.
But you make your own story.
So let's look at some of these things.
So interface for choice is predictable.
And what are we really talking about?
Well, it's the conversation wheel.
The conversation wheel is a GUI interface
that we introduced that replaced the list system
that we see with a lot of the subjective narrative games
that we produced.
And really, it was in response also to the high-def era
and the fact that we didn't have the black bars,
the letter boxing.
to put words in.
So we needed something that was very slick and very intuitive.
And also, now that we moved to this different model,
now that we're objective to the experience,
we didn't have to write out the whole response anymore.
So we came up with a slick little interface,
which actually ended up becoming a very core component
to our narrative design.
So if we look behind this interface,
it's the dialogue tree, which we saw.
And really, when we look at the blue responses
These are all Shepard's responses,
or his potential responses, for that interaction.
So we're taking this and we're mapping it
to a nice simple GUI that a player
can easily interface with.
So we know what the conversation wheel is.
It's a dialogue navigation interface
which allows the player to interface with the story.
And we get all those choices and we map them
to these various points of the radial.
And we have an indicator that we move around
and we can make choices.
And it's pretty easy breezy.
It's a very simple kind of interface.
But we're gonna look deep into it
because even though it appears to be very simple,
there's a lot of mechanics that run behind it
which allow us to keep that predictability
that I was speaking of.
So firstly, we talk about the behavioral player.
And when we talk about behavioral,
we're talking about.
The different parts of the wheel actually mean something different to a writer or to
an interaction.
For example, if you look where it says Paragon, every time you pick the upper right, it's
a Paragon response, regardless of what it says or what it does.
It has a subtext or it has an emotion that's attached to it.
In this case, Paragon means do the right thing in the right way.
Whereas neutral is, you know, it's very kind of bland, usually ends the dialogue.
Renegade is do whatever you want, like do what you have to do to get the job done.
Friendly and hostile, pretty self-explanatory.
And investigative is always give me more information.
So we have this kind of interface now where someone can just be flicking the stick around
without getting into a lot of detail and really get whatever they want out of that interaction.
If they're playing as a paragon or if they're kind of mad at the guy,
they can switch it to renegade, and they don't really have to read too far into exactly what's
going to happen. They don't have to read too far into that role-playing experience.
So obviously this is the first layer of predictability. So it allows us to shape the narrative according
to the behavior of the player. Mapped emotional reactions, and reaction is exactly it.
Most of the time people who play this way don't really wait for the scene to end.
They're just, as soon as the wheel pops up, they're just making choices.
And they're getting rewarded with a very fluid cinematic experience at that point.
And one of the things that it does, it also, the direction on the wheel also colors what
is going to happen.
And we'll get into that on the next slide.
But really, it adds a lot of subtext to what's going on.
And I'll explain that in the next slide.
So the cognitive player. The cognitive player is the role player. It's the person who wants
to really read into what's going on, wants to make a careful choice and be very exacting
on what's going on. So we add these things called paraphrases. And paraphrases are really
small, I think it's 32 characters that were allowed in a paraphrase. But they're a condensed
version of what is going to be said next.
it's really sometimes it can even be described as what's in the player's head right before
he says it as well.
So when we look at this, we have several kind of choices here.
So we're going to be looking at the first one here, second layer of predictability,
sure.
We're going to be looking at this first choice here.
So when we look at this choice, which is I'll look into this, we understand it to be in
the paragon section of the wheel.
So when, as you can imagine, that line can be said or interpreted in so many different
ways, but because it's in a paragon section of the wheel, we understand it to be something
that, you know, Shepard's going to do the right thing in the right way.
So in this case, it gives it a dramatic coloring, which is now we understand it to be something
very positive, like, you know, Shepard's going to, he's going to look into this.
He's not just doing it flippantly or whatever.
It allows us to really narrow down the interpretation.
of what that choice means.
And also, if we look at the investigate, abusing suspects,
my expectation here is that I'll be getting more information
about who's abusing suspects.
So, like I said, there's two layers here,
and that's the big takeaway here.
There's the cognitive and there's the behavioral,
and they interact with each other
to allow us to have predictability
in the role-playing experience.
So, the next one.
is choice produces results the player expects.
So this is pretty self-explanatory.
If you make a choice, you expect something to happen.
If, as a designer, if I don't meet that expectation,
your role-playing experience is now busted.
So we're gonna look at something here.
We're gonna look at a dancer on Ilium,
and we're gonna use what we learned
on the predictability of the interface here,
and we're gonna move around just one little aspect of
the narrative design and just see how much of a change that makes to what the player expects.
So, as we ship the game, when you talk to this dancer, you can tip her and she'll dance for you
and all that. So it's in the paragon position, which is like, okay, well, the subtext can be
interpreted as, you know, Shepard's tipping her. He, you know, maybe he liked the dancing and
gives her a tip.
And really that closes my expectation.
Like, you know, it's like, wow, that's cool.
And I can move on.
I'm not really expecting much more.
So let's take a look at that interaction.
So at that point, the player's like, oh, okay, that's cool.
It's a very light interaction.
It just happens in one of the clubs.
And, eh, okay, that's fine.
But what happens now if I move the tip
to the investigate portion of the wheel, right?
Now it's kind of like, okay, well, what's next, right?
So let's take a look at that one
with the subtext of there's more information.
So as you can see, nothing happened.
Like, I made a choice and I got kicked out back to the first choice and nothing really occurred, right?
So, really, at this point, the player could feel really cheated with this interaction going,
okay, well, do I have to keep tipping her for a plot to open up?
Is there something else that I need to do?
I'm very confused at this point.
So, really, that would be an error in design,
in narrative design right there,
where we don't meet the expectation of the player.
So, once again, what if we moved it to the Renegade?
Well, you know, use your imagination.
It could be pretty much anything at that point.
But, you know, as you can see,
by just changing positions on the wheel,
we're adding subtext to just a word that says tip.
and we're adding that predictability to the interface
and we're trying to meet expectation whenever possible.
So the last one, or third I should say,
it's one more after this,
is give the player choices they want.
Now, and I often preface this with
when they want to make them, which is also very important.
So one of the things that we're gonna be looking at here,
is another video clip.
And this video clip is of an interrogation sequence
that happens.
Now, Shepard's interrogating somebody.
So, you know, if I'm a player
and Shepard's interrogating somebody,
I expect Shepard might get rough with him.
So, as a designer, if I don't put that interaction in,
I'm not meeting someone's expectations
of what an interrogation should be.
So that's exactly what we did with some interrupts
with this interaction.
I wanna see my advocate.
Your advocate hasn't arrived. We're trying to find him.
I'm not saying a damn word until he's here.
You two are in way over your-
Pay attention, Mr. Kellum.
That wasn't a good idea, kid. That is gonna cost you.
Control your temper. We wanted to talk.
Sorry, my associate gets a little... excited during interrogations.
Hit me again, asshole. Every punch is another credit in my pocket.
Works for me.
to you when I get out of here. Keep it up, tough guy. You'll leave in a bag. Go to hell.
I think Female Shepard rocks, by the way. So, what happened there? So the VO and the
situation all kind of supported and focused the player to have this interaction which
allowed them to hit them. So, you know, while he's saying it and you're like, wow, this
guy really sucks, like, God, I wish I could hit him. And bang, that thing pops up.
And you're like, that's fantastic.
I really feel like I wanted to make that choice,
and there it was.
Other kind of examples of that would have been
on the game when Tali's dad's kind of dead there.
Spoiler alert.
But, and she's crying, and most players are like,
wow, you know, I wish I could just hug her.
And then the interrupt comes up, and then you can hug her,
and it closes that loop on expectation,
and you feel really great and good about that interaction.
So we're gonna look at the opposite now,
where, you know, maybe things don't go good,
like there's a lot of stuff in this game, right?
So we're gonna look at somewhere where choices
are kinda weird and kinda didn't work.
So in this one, we're gonna look at a shopkeeper
on the Citadel.
Good day, my friends.
Welcome to the Citadel.
So we're given a choice, which is like a cuse of classism.
And it's just like, okay, well, you know,
there was no setup, I have no idea.
She just said welcome.
So let's just see what happens if I press this button.
You know, for a bunch of cheap touristy crap,
your prices are pretty high.
I am sorry you feel that way.
There are many stores on the Citadel.
Perhaps another would be more in your price range.
So you're saying I'm poor?
Just because I'm not as well off as you doesn't mean
you can hold yourself above me.
What?
No, I.
Hey, everyone.
This store discriminates against the poor.
Please, calm down.
As an apology, I'll let you have my station employee discount.
Is that acceptable?
Well, alright.
But you still have my field.
Please, enjoy your shopping experience.
So...
And we all really love that interaction.
But it actually doesn't really work.
Because it's like, okay,
accuse of classism, make a choice,
and kind of sit back and watch and...
really I don't really have any agency and Shepard's talking and I can't say anything.
So it breaks a lot of the rules of the agreement. And that's really a great example of where
things go wrong. And ways we could have fixed it could have been we gave a little interaction
with somebody right before we stepped into them, maybe we give her some lines, maybe
some ambient stuff. Like there's things we could have done to repair that situation,
but with times constraints the way they are, some things have to slip.
So really we have these two ideas of choices you want
and results you expect.
And really, it really is a cycle that happens
when we're dealing with this objective narrative.
So when we talk about choices you want
and results you expect,
and that's always being constantly reinforced
as you're playing,
we get what you call role-playing flow.
And you're really in the zone at this point,
and you're getting what you want,
and you're making choices,
and it's really awesome.
But really.
you're not, this is not a real traditional role-playing experience.
This is like, you know, like I said, this is not you, this is another character.
And, you know, through fantasy fulfillment, through this idea of, you know, keeping people
in the zone, we can still maintain a lot of the characteristics of the traditional role-playing
experience in this new model.
So,
One of the other ones that we got here is it's the player story and this is something that we really take seriously
At Bioware and you know what sometimes it backfires on us like you get into a lot of situations
When it's like wow you're ready to go to endgame and everything's really awesome
And you know you got your love interest, and it's really good, but then you stop by the citadel by fish right
It's just that
It's this idea of absurdity that can happen in the narrative.
And if you ask writers and traditional cinematic artists,
they all go kind of crazy and they're like,
no, no, no, but drama and this and that and the other.
But it's all emergent.
It's the idea that you can do whatever you want
and you're building your story.
It's unique to you.
And that's what we're really trying to push with Bioware.
So let's talk about the player story for a second.
And kind of one of the biggest things that we did.
with the sequel and what we're planning to do with Mass Effect 3 as well is this idea
of importing your save game. And this is something which was obviously very technical to try
to do on a number of levels, but it really illustrates our commitment to making sure
that the actual whole story is yours, you know, this is something which is unique to
you and you can tell your friends and compare notes and go wow, you know, like
I had this experience and that experience and it really just becomes about you at that
point.
So what is it?
It's your continuing story for Mass Effect.
It allows us to get some plot threads and bring them forward and it really is the uber
feature of the Mass Effect universe.
We are story driven games.
BioWare is committed to making the best story driven games in the world.
So features like this really fall in line with what we are trying to achieve.
So how much actually came across?
And I see a lot of things in the blogosphere and the rest
about it not being, there's not enough choice,
not enough things came across.
But in reality, we had 700 different hooks
that came across from ME1 to ME2
that changed the narrative based on choice
you had from the first one.
And what we found really is it's the small things
that matter.
It's the small things that make it.
your story. Obviously with a second title it's really hard to branch the narrative in
some gigantic way. You know, scope gets out of control. You know, it's just not practical
to do. But what can we do? How can we make this your personal story? So I'm going to
show you some examples of things, just real small things. And if you can imagine the next
thing kind of, you know, multiplied by 700.
you can get an idea of what we've been trying to accomplish with this particular feature.
So here's a shot of a really ugly shepherd on ME1.
And I don't know if anybody remembers this.
This is the big choice, save the council, let the council die, let the council live.
So we let the council die.
You know, they weren't much use to us and they were kind of off-putting.
So we're going to take that choice and we're going to bring it forward to Mass Effect 2
and give you some examples of things we did with that.
So we have these advertising kiosks on the Citadel and they did allow us to do some really
cool things and what we're going to see here is a movie that someone made of your exploits
on the Citadel for Mass Effect 1.
and there's a lot of things that change about that movie
based on your choices and actions on the first one.
So we're gonna take a look at The Council is Dead.
This began with an attack on a human settlement
in the Traverse, but Saren won't stop there.
So, there's a couple of things in there. It's a fall release. It's not a summer blockbuster.
You know, Shepard's actions were there. It was male Shepard in the ad. So, let's see
what it looks like, Council is Alive, but this time with a female player.
settlement in the Traverse. But Saren won't stop there. His guests aren't going to stay on the fringes of Citadel space.
So, Summer Blockbuster, fantastic.
So, what we saw there was really four different permutations
to one interaction that could happen.
You know, council's dead, alive, male, female,
and this is a very simple example of something that we do.
Pretty much everywhere in the game
in order to make your story.
So, the last topic here, I'm gonna try to get through it.
I know everybody's, we're running a little late here.
So the idea of quick time events, and you know, these things got a real bad rap over
the last little while, but we're gonna, we're gonna, I'm gonna show you how we kind of took
the idea of quick time events and integrated it into our philosophy of the agreement.
So what are we trying to solve for with, with, with interrupts?
Like, you know, if we're gonna add a feature, we gotta be solving some sort of problem.
So this is what we were trying to solve for.
So...
okay
looking at somebody
is getting uncomfortable
so
we still have problems with temporal distortion.
And really it's a side effect of adding interactivity
into the cinematic space.
So the idea of quick time events,
or really this idea of adding these interrupts,
or these very visceral quick time events
that would allow the player to take control of situations,
and really allow them to steer the narrative
in a real time way.
So this is our first sort of foray
into the real time character interaction side of design.
So when we talk about interrupts, we're talking about a couple of things.
We have these renegade interrupts.
We have paragon interrupts.
But we never have both on the screen at once.
And it was one of the design philosophies we had is the fact that, okay, well, making
a choice, and we had to make these very binary.
We found that giving people too much choice in this real-time space confused a lot of
people.
It was just too much.
So really, we just ended up making it one choice or the other.
This moment was either renegade or paragon.
But there was a lot of interesting things that came out of that.
And one of the interesting things that we found is,
if you're playing as a paragon and a renegade moment came up,
people were very conflicted about whether they should take it or not.
Because, man, if they see a flashing icon, they really want to take it.
But...
that's not the way I'm playing.
And like, you know, and if you look at some
of the biometric readings on this stuff, man,
it's just all over the map and they haven't done anything.
Like, you know, it's like they're just sitting there
and they're just really getting conflicted
and having some internal conflict.
So not having, not making a choice
was actually very powerful.
So we kind of kept everything very constrained
to that sort of design philosophy.
So let's apply the agreement to this and see how it lands.
So firstly,
Interface for choice is predictable. Sure, there it is. It's Renegade, it's Paragon,
it's left side, it's right side, it's pretty easy. When it comes up I can train the player
to always take that one and, you know. So I would say, yeah, okay, that makes sense.
Give the player choices they want. Well, as we saw with the interrogation scene, you know,
it really depends on the writing and iterating with the writers to make sure that they do
give you choices they want. It's the player's story.
Like I said, sometimes not making an interrupt can be more powerful than taking one.
So yeah, you know, I'd say it's a player's story.
Choice produces results the player expects.
Well, this ended up being a little hard for us because it was a real-time interaction.
We didn't have the ability of getting any of the cognitive sort of paraphrasing into
this space.
What do we do?
You know, on the first implementation,
it was really a lot of broken role playing,
you know, people accidentally shooting
other people in the face.
It was like, it was all over the place.
So we had to really come up with a different idea
of how to implement it.
And what we came up with was this idea of telegraphing,
which is really just a visual paraphrase.
It helps predict the specific action
that's going to be made,
and lets the cognitive player make a meaningful choice.
So I'm going to show you some examples of what I mean by a visual paraphrase.
So we have a situation where Shepard talks to a suspect and then Shepard just attacks
him.
So if there was an interrupt there, you would have no idea that, like, yeah, you know it's
going to be a renegade action, but there's so many shades of grey there.
If he could slap him, he could shoot him, he could push him, he could do, he could talk
mean to him, like, you know, there's just so much there that it really doesn't help
with the predictability.
of the role playing. So let's take a look at what that interaction looks like without
a telegraph.
Yeah, yeah, I told you, I ain't saying nothing.
Fine, we'll do it the hard way.
Oh, God, Dave, help me.
So, you know, in that case it's like, okay, well, I didn't want to push on this poor kid.
Like, you know, you have to, like, people have a lot of really strong feelings toward these digital actors.
Like, you have to really respect.
So, it's like, wow, you know what, I didn't want to do that, my role playing's broken,
Bioware, I hate you, it just goes on and on.
So, we add this idea of a telegraph.
So, this wouldn't work.
So, oh, fine, what do we do now?
So, we add another shot to the sequence where Shepard starts to crack his knuckles.
and this allows us to say hey you know what this I have now I have a really
good idea not only do I know that it's a renegade action
he's cracking his knuckles I bet you he's gonna hit him
so let's see what that looks like now
but you can't for me you gave another drill instructions for an assassination
who's the target? I don't know I didn't ask
because the people I work for
We don't have time for this.
Ow.
God dang.
So the cinematic designer there very cleverly just put a small little knuckle crack animation,
which now made the role playing experience what people expect.
So we would consider that very successful.
So in conclusion, I just want to hit a couple of really powerful points here.
Interactivity is a very potent narrative device.
Putting activity into cinematics is something we should all be looking at.
Really the idea of the linear cinematic has been around for a long, long time and hasn't
really changed much.
You know, yes, we get into facial mocap and a lot of the crazy stuff to make the fidelity
up, but we're forgetting these are game systems and what they do really well is be interactive.
The other is perspective is powerful, so making sure that when you start writing your game
you choose your perspective very wisely.
and discover your agreement and whenever you can stick with it.
Thank you very much.