Hello and welcome to day five of GDC Showcase.
I'm Gamma Sutra's news editor and associate publisher
and your host for this AMA, Alyssa McAloon.
I'll be moderating today's session with Brian Horton,
creative director at Insomniac Games.
We'll be taking your questions throughout the chat.
So feel free to drop those in the questions tab
in the little chat box on the right side
of your screen throughout.
Kind of keep things geared towards game development
as we are GDC here,
and we'll try to get your answers throughout the show.
So.
With that, let's introduce today's AMA guest.
Brian, hello.
Would you like to introduce yourself?
Hey, thanks so much, Alyssa.
You know, it's an honor to be invited at GDC to talk about Marvel's Spider-Man Miles Morales.
My name is Brian Horton.
I'm the Creative Director at Insomniac Games.
A quick bio for me, I've been a developer for about 26 years
and a Creative Director at Insomniac for the past three.
Great to have you.
Yeah, thanks.
You know, I'd like to answer some questions.
I'm really excited to do that.
But I'd also like to provide some context
and a short story overview
and the pillars that helped make our game happen.
So does that sound like something we can do?
Yeah, all for it. Let's go.
All right.
You know, I would say working on Spider-Man definitely has been a career highlight,
because my love for this iconic web-slinger runs deep.
Like most kids from the 70s, I watched the Spider-Man cartoons every Saturday morning.
My mom made me homemade Spider-Man outfits when I was a kid, and I rocked them on Halloween.
And of course, I poured through all my classic Spider-Man comics.
But years later, I rediscovered my love for the iconic web slinger in Miles Morales.
Brian Michael Bendis and Sarah Pacelli brought a fresh new energy to the franchise,
and it was a huge influence on the Insomniac team.
We fell in love with Miles, and it was essential to make a video game,
Origin Story, that was special experience.
And it started with our first game, Marvel's Spider-Man.
Miles is an Afro-Latino teen born and raised in Brooklyn.
His passions include science, playing ball, mixing beats,
and his favorite hero, Spider-Man.
And in our story, Peter is an older and more experienced
hero.
And this provided us a unique opportunity
for a new take on the origin story with Miles.
So when he was bitten by a genetically engineered spider,
and discovered his new powers, it
was destiny that Peter would be his mentor
and show Miles the ropes to become a hero.
So this brings us to the beginning
of the game in Marvel's Spider-Man, Miles Morales.
It's a year later, and it's the first day of winter break.
Miles' skills will be put to the test.
When Rhino escapes a prison convoy carving a path
of destruction across Manhattan, Peter is injured in the battle,
and Miles must protect his mentor.
Bioelectricity will surge through his body.
An explosive new power helps him to defeat Rhino.
But after this harrowing encounter,
Miles learns his mentor is leaving town
for a couple of weeks.
And this huge responsibility weighs on Miles.
But he's not alone.
His best friend, Genki Lee, knows his spider secret
and will support Miles while he stays
with them over winter break.
The Morales family recently moved from Brooklyn
to his mother's childhood apartment in East Harlem.
It's a vibrant and multicultural community
made even more beautiful by the fresh snow
and holiday decorations.
But all isn't well in Miles' new home.
Roxxon is days away from opening a new power plant
in the heart of Harlem,
powered by an experimental energy source called Nuform.
Rio Morales, Miles' mom, runs for city council
to fight Roxxon's push into Harlem
and to protect the people and neighborhood she loves.
And like all great Spider-Man stories,
Miles' personal and hero lives collide
when his mother's rally is attacked by the Underground,
a high-tech criminal army led by the Tinkerer
who steals Roxxon's new form.
When Miles tries to stop her,
his powers destabilize this experimental energy source.
resulting in an explosion that destroys Braithwaite Bridge,
only deepening his doubts as a hero.
So that's a little bit of a primer of our story,
but ultimately this is a game
where Miles must rise to the challenge
to become his own Spider-Man, overcoming his fears
and mastering his new powers to stop the war
that threatens his new home.
And we built this game on three pillars
that are an evolution from the first game
while taking full advantage of the power
of the PlayStation 5.
Our first pillar is to become an explosive new Spider-Man.
Our second was to protect your home
from two warring factions.
And the third is to play a seamless cinematic experience.
So in our first pillar, Become an Explosive New Spider-Man,
we wanted Miles to play differently from Peter,
with new combat, traversal, and gadgets
that reflect his unique powers, bioelectricity,
and optical camouflage, and his unique personality.
So when you see Miles swing through the city,
he has his own unique take on how he is a web slayer.
So these powers are gonna grow throughout the game
as Miles and the player become more experienced.
In our second pillar,
protect your home from two warring factions,
Harlem is ground zero for a two-sided war
between Roxxon and the underground.
And Miles must defeat these threats
to protect his family, friends,
and all the people of Harlem.
In our final pillar,
play a seamless cinematic experience.
We wanted the player to have an uninterrupted journey
from beginning to end,
eliminating loading screens
to keep the player engrossed in the story and gameplay.
So Insomniac Games' mission is to make a positive and lasting
impact in people's lives.
And Miles lives up to these ideals,
earning the name Spider-Man by embracing those unique powers
to save Harlem.
So it was an honor to work with PlayStation, Marvel
Games, and the talented actors and amazing developers
at Insomniac Games to bring Marvel Spider-Man to life.
And I really want to thank GDC for inviting
me to talk to you guys today and answer some of your questions.
So with that, I think we should just go ahead and wrap up.
Ask away.
Yeah, they've been flowing in.
So we'll just go ahead and get started here.
Coming from, let's see, this is kind of going to mix
a question from Tremaine in chat
with a question from Emilius in chat,
talking about how Miles Morales differs from Peter
as like a protagonist mechanically.
So Tremaine wanted to know,
they noticed that Miles is not as strong
or can't jump as high or as far as Pete.
Was this a conscious decision made from the start
or was this made for balancing with Miles' other abilities?
Yeah, I think we really looked at ways that we can offset
the power set between Peter and Miles.
And one of those was, you know,
some of the distances strengths that he has as a character.
He's not as experienced as Peter, he's not quite as strong,
but what we do have to compliment against that
is the power of his bioelectric punches.
And with that, with bioelectricity,
he's also able to dash and go across large distances.
So when you're swinging through the world
and you have a venom,
bar available, you can actually dash using Venom Dash to gain more speed.
So we found that our new powers was a way to offset and create some of the dynamism
that we may have pulled back from from the first game.
Well, that's kind of flows right into what Amelis was asking here,
saying that as Peter players would.
Oh, no, it scrolled. It scrolled. Where'd it go?
Sorry, this is live chat here.
So as Peter, the player would progress and earn new abilities via suit upgrades.
Miles, on the other hand, already has a few abilities at.
Naturally, most of them render the ones Peter had redundant if transported to this game.
Can you talk a bit more about the creative choice to remove all suit abilities and replace
them with passive mods? Maybe also a bit about intertwining his abilities with key level moments?
Yeah, the passive mods was something that we came to as a really exciting way to give the players that mix and match capability of new powers and really to start chasing those suits.
People love getting new suits. So we are still getting a reward for each suit that you could craft.
That said, we wanted to balance that against the powers.
So when you had suit powers before, they were like these really.
amazing OP skills, which were a lot of fun.
But what we wanted to do instead was leverage
all of Miles bioelectric attacks as a way to get some
of that spectacle back and balance the suit power.
So by having the suit mods, we think that was a good way
to still encourage suits and acquisition of suits
to get new things, but also lean more
into Miles inherent powers and abilities.
Awesome. So I'm going to take another question from Joaquin here in chat,
but I'm also going to hijack it a bit with my own.
These are all great questions, by the way.
I want to say these are wonderful.
There's so many more in here that we're going to get to that are incredible
and keep them coming throughout.
We'll get to as many as we have time for.
So the next question here is, how are you guys able to plan and schedule
the development length for this kind of smaller Spider-Man adventure?
And I'm also curious personally about doing this during a pandemic.
If you could kind of talk about your development for the whole game.
Schedule wise.
Yeah, we knew we had the fantastic foundation of Marvel Spider-Man, which I had the honor to work
on with Brian Intihar and the whole team. But so we had a lot of the core key systems from the
first game, which allowed us to really quickly iterate. And our focus was how do we make Miles
feel unique? That was the first thing we did. So we spent a lot of our early pre-production time
just developing Miles.
unique core skill sets. And also we were developing a whole new cast of enemies. So the underground
posed a whole new kind of level of threat and we wanted to make sure that their powers worked
specifically against and was a nice ballet between venom bioelectricity and their programmable matter
weapons. So we spent a lot of the early development developing those systems and also Miles' unique
traversal style. So that's where we spent a lot of our pre-production and we're able to roll into
production.
in a very short amount of time because of the foundation of the first game.
So we did build our game in vertical sort of slices.
So we had multiple slice productions where we work on portions of the game
and that brought them up to a quality that you could play the whole game from beginning to end.
We also developed our story very early on and tested it all along the way with storyboards.
before we went to the mocap stage.
And that goes into the final set question,
which is how we dealt with the pandemic.
Luckily, we had a lot of our cinematic shot,
but we had a number of story revisions that came after alpha
that meant that we needed to get new data.
But with a pandemic, we couldn't go to the stage.
So our animation team did an amazing job adapting old data,
getting new data either from a remote access safe location,
or they even recorded some of their own data themselves.
to help assemble these scenes in a very unique way that we've never done before.
So I just wanted to give a really big shout out to our animation team for being so
ingenious during the pandemic.
I've talked to a couple developers at this.
We did a GDC podcast episode
with the Jackbox folks a while ago
and talking to people about the pandemic.
It's so interesting to hear where the timing works out
for like where it hit in this part.
These projects we're kind of like seeing now
and saw a few months ago,
just how like everything was torn asunder
towards the end in the middle
and how it does adapted to it.
So thank you for sharing that.
Let's see, another one from Harris here says,
it was revealed a couple of years ago
how much technical wizardry was, excuse me,
was cleverly concealed by the direction
of the opening cut scene of Spider-Man in PS,
or Spider-Man, the first one.
Is there any moment in particular in Miles Morales
that comes to your mind as achieving seamless parody
across the technical and the creative sides?
Yeah, so we really took on our third pillar,
play a seamless cinematic experience.
Even a step further from Spider-Man,
there are no loading screens in Miles Morales
on the PlayStation 4 and the PlayStation 5.
So that was a big goal for us.
So we start our game in the subway with Miles Morales.
And as soon as you hit start,
You seamlessly enter into the city and begin the video game with no loading screens.
So there was a lot of trickery we had to do to think about how do we get into
Miles' apartment without a loading screen and then out into the world.
All of those were innovations that the team worked on together
on Miles Morales to make that even more seamless and more immersive.
So kind of bouncing off those pillars there again, Z in chat wants to know, can you tell
us a bit about the pillars from the first game for comparison and how they changed the second game
to distinguish the experience of Miles Morales?
Yeah, the pillars in the first game was really,
it was driven off of the idea to play
like a Marvel movie feels,
the idea of getting this bombastic, amazing sense
of cinematic drama that you'd get from a Spider-Man
and bring that to responsive, fast gameplay.
So that was a guiding principle that I think,
Brian Anterhart and the team really drove towards
that brought...
a level of spectacle and fun factor to the Spider-Man franchise. So that is still a foundation
of what we build on. These pillars were additive. They were just a way for us to really be super
specific about Miles' character, the story he had, the threats, and our theme of Miles
learning his new neighborhood, his new home of Harlem, and how he was going to let that be fuel.
to learn how to become a new Spider-Man.
So that's, I think the biggest change
was being very specific about how this was going to be
a Miles Morales experience versus just,
versus a Peter Parker experience.
I guess let's talk a bit more about crafting Miles as a character.
There's a lot of comments coming to chat here about seeing diversity in a video game,
seeing like a deaf character or even like Miles's family or like LGBT inclusion.
So we'll start at the top here with...
Tremaine's question got uploaded very quickly.
So they say they're all about diversity and love the game.
So when it was decided that Miles would get his own game,
how did you go about making sure that Harlem and its residents were properly represented?
Some studios failed to get the properly part, but you guys nailed it.
Authenticity was one of our key ingredients
to across the whole franchise.
When we talk about his new home of Harlem,
a lot of that started with research.
Our team did exhaustive amount of research
to ensure that the city itself felt authentic,
the people within it as well.
We actually did...
We actually went to Harlem with a group of people
to talk to the residents of Harlem
and to show them early builds of our game,
to get an idea of like,
hey, does Miles' apartment feel correct?
And we talked to people with mixed ethnicities
to ensure not only is Miles as a black American,
but having Puerto Rican roots.
Those cultures and those different aspects
of his personality.
and the culture being represented correctly.
So we actually made a lot of,
got a lot of amazing data and made some informed decisions
how we can get better representation across the game,
not only in the way the world looks,
but the people themselves.
And a big shout out to our narrative team,
Ben Arfman is a lead writer,
Mary Kenny as a senior writer.
Mary Kenny worked very closely with Evan Narciss,
one of our story consultants,
to ensure all the people of Harlem,
the quest givers, felt correct.
So Haley is one of our, you know,
we're so proud of bringing Haley to the game.
It really is just a powerful community organizer,
but also just the next level of representation
by showing authentic ASL between Miles and her in the game.
That was a huge innovation for both story and also animation.
So yeah, we just feel like research and asking questions
and working with people outside of our team
to help ensure that everything we did on the screen
was authentic and correct.
So Angelica in chat here has a question about ASL.
They say that they love that ASL made an appearance in the game.
Can you talk about the decision to bring that into the game and
kind of what kind of challenges the team had to do to make that
as successful as it was?
So it was Mary Kenny wanted to create a deaf character
in the game and Haley was born,
but that came with a number of technical challenges.
Like how do we correctly capture ASL in the game?
So we actually hired ASL actors, Haley specifically,
and even Miles who is played by Nanji Jeter,
we had someone who spoke ASL or was fluent in ASL
to do the mocap and we created brand new technology
at the capture stage and with our animators.
to ensure that all the finger movements were captured correctly. So there was a lot of work
to ensure that this was going to be done right. And we actually brought a consultant in as well
on the day of the stage to ensure anything that we wrote in the script, if there were any words
or anything that needed to be unique or sorry, that was not authentic or correct, that we would
make those adjustments on the stage, including the fact that Miles is actually not as experienced
with ASL. So his version of ASL is very different than Haley's.
as a beginner versus someone who's more experienced.
And like, it sounds like that having that kind of technology
and taking the time to go through those steps
and establish like workflows for that
is makes it easier for including that stuff
in the future too.
100%, I think it was an innovation
that we'll be building on in the future.
All right, another question here from,
another one from Tremaine, thank you.
Can you walk us through a typical day
as a creative director for Insomniac?
What are your responsibilities, pressures,
and what do you enjoy?
Well, one, Insomniac Games is just an amazing company
to work for.
It's, we have a philosophy
that great ideas come from everywhere.
So anyone on the team is contributing on the core
of what makes Spider-Man or any game we work on unique.
So it's about finding and pulling
collecting the ideas from our team and trying to come up with a vision that allows people to contribute ideas.
So if I think about my typical day, it starts first very early on.
to make sure that there is a clear vision and goal.
Once we have that, then it really just is a matter of,
on a day-to-day basis, working with the team
and helping steer to the final result
that we're trying to accomplish.
But it is, a day-to-day usually is a lot of conversations
early, working very closely with Cam Christian,
the game director, Jess Reed, the head of production,
and other leadership group to make sure
that every single person that is...
leading this effort has a clear direction and goal of what they need to do.
And then, you know, throughout the day, it's a lot of meetings. It's a lot of playing the game
and asking questions and hopefully providing some direction that's going to get us
to the next level. And then, you know, we do it all over again every day. So it's a really
fun and collaborative experience. Just kind of building on that,
obviously you didn't like wake up one day, join the game industry and suddenly be a creative
director. How did you kind of get to where you are now? And I guess what lessons did you carry
forward from other roles you've had?
Yeah, I've been very fortunate.
I went to art school, so I'm trained as an illustrator
and a painter, and I got my first job at Disney Interactive
in 1994, right out of college.
And then from there, I've just progressed.
from different companies. I worked at DreamWorks, I worked at Electronic Arts, I worked at Crystal
Dynamics on Tomb Raider, and that was where I really learned a tremendous amount of that
AAA video game development before going.
to Infinity Ward and eventually coming to Insomniac Games.
So yeah, across 26 years, I've picked up a lot of things.
But one thing I will say is working at Insomniac,
it is a mixture of excellence
and really taking care of the team,
the wellbeing of the team.
That's something that we really are priding ourselves on.
And actually making a positive statement in the world
that our mission to make a positive, lasting impact.
To me, that's a reason to want to make video games,
is to say something important.
So yeah, I've been very fortunate to sort of grow
from an artist to a lead artist to an art director
and eventually into game direction and creative direction.
And that's been a gradual experience.
I guess speaking of jumps from one thing to another,
PlayStation 4 to PlayStation 5
for Marvel's Spider-Man versus Miles Morales.
Gonna grab a couple of questions on that quick,
but we'll start off with Brian's here.
It says, hey Brian, can you talk about
Insomniac's engine evolution from PS4 to PS5
and what you were able to achieve
with the new console high tech?
Yeah, we have an amazing core team who works on our engine.
Abdul, one of our senior programmers,
created our ray traced reflections for the PlayStation 5.
And that was one of our huge innovations.
And what that really means is to make sure that every,
you know, if you think of New York City,
it's a city of skyscrapers made out of glass, right?
So if every single surface can reflect correctly,
and you can see the characters in the world reflecting, the world just becomes that much
more rich and realistic looking. The other area that we focused on is allowing options of how you
play. So you can either play at 60 frames per second at a near 4k, or you can play at a hybrid
60 frames per second at a lower resolution that's upscaled, or you can play at 30 frames per second
with full ray trace.
full ray tracing.
So we had all these different options
to give the player more choice on how they played the game.
But any mode that you play on the PlayStation 5
is definitely the most superior Spider-Man experience
you could have.
It truly is amazing to play the game in 60 frames per second
with ray tracing in our hybrid mode.
So it's been a really amazing progress.
To see our technology grow from the PlayStation 4,
which already looked amazing.
into the PlayStation 5 on launch day,
that was a huge accomplishment.
And kudos to our tech team.
So of course, Miles Morales is available
on both PlayStation 4 and PlayStation 5.
Can you talk a little bit about kind of developing
for these two different kinds of technology
with different capabilities
and making those experiences like good
on both sides of the fence?
Cause it'd be easy to go forward and be like,
well, here's all these cool PlayStation 5 features
and have the PlayStation 4 version left out.
But it seems like you guys achieved a balance.
Yeah, we wanted to make sure the PlayStation 4 consumer is going to get a Spider-Man experience that they were accustomed to.
the same level of fidelity of art and storytelling
and characterization, all of that,
all the gorgeous graphics,
all of that that we saw on the PlayStation 4 is represented.
But we wanted to make sure we had this upside,
this idea when you did go to the PlayStation 5,
these other ingredients would really help contribute
to the overall experience.
And in addition to the visuals,
we really did enhance the 3D audio in the game.
We wanted to make sure that the haptic controller was getting maximum use.
So when you do play with haptics, it really does add another level of immersion.
So I think that's the big difference is the tremendous pieces of hardware like
the controller, the 3D audio, in addition to the capabilities to run at 60 and
with ray tracing, those are the big differences.
I think like Miles Morales was the first game I played
that had the adapter trigger functionality in it.
So like that was like my first moment was like swinging
and being like, oh my gosh, this is so cool.
It was a great way to showcase that tech.
We're not here to talk about what I care about.
Oh no, I think that's great.
Thanks for playing the game, by the way.
Yeah, I'm bad at it, but it's incredible.
Ellen in chat wants to ask if you can talk a bit
about the animation challenges your team faced
to show how Miles is more inexperienced
with web slinging in combat compared to Peter.
Sure, I'm just gonna give a big shout out to James Hamm.
He did a lot of the principal animation and traversal
that it gave the personality of Miles Morales
versus Peter Parker.
As soon as you play that first moment
where you web swing as Miles Morales,
you can feel that it's a different character.
And a lot of that came down to
James putting himself into the idea.
He started as amateur parkour and he loves movement
and he's a big fan of the character.
And he wanted to bring a different personality to Miles Morales.
So that was a big part of it is like, how do we get his web slinging feeling unique?
And you're going to see a little bit more of out of control, but also a little bit more style.
We put a lot of effort into additional manual tricks, so he's going to have fun.
He's like a younger, new Spider-Man.
We wanted the player to have this sense of joy when they swung through the city.
augmenting that with more performable tricks.
So that was a huge part.
And then when it came to the combat,
we wanted a little bit more desperation and clumsiness,
but also this tremendous power
when you see him performing
all the different bioelectric moves.
And then the other thing that's really exciting
is the fact that Miles has this optical camouflage.
he can now scare people by going invisible
and redirecting into different places.
So that also informed a lot of the way he moves
through the world.
So, and then I'd be remiss not to see Najee Jeter
who has done such a great job bringing life
to the character and every cinematic
and all the VO you hear that informs a lot
of who the character is as well.
There's a second part to Ellen's question that I accidentally did not read.
They're curious about while you're going through those animations
to make them kind of distinctly miles and a little bit more unexperienced.
Was were there ever concerns about it becoming unclear
what the player was doing or kind of like
an inexperienced on miles side,
making the player feel like they might be doing something wrong?
Yeah, we wanted to balance.
the flair, like him, like, like sort of like arms, you know, in the air, legs, the bicycling
that might happen with his legs, all of that is flair, but not necessarily to make you
feel out of control.
So anytime you wanted to go up to a place, it still had the same accuracy of Spider-Man.
But what we wanted to do is on those in between things, provide a level of animation that
that just gave him a different personality.
So we didn't want to mess up a lot
of what made Spider-Man great,
which was that accurate and fluid traversal
from the first game.
You got me scrolling questions here.
There was one that was very good about I'm so sorry, I'm going to paraphrase
because I can't find it in the drawing list of questions
talking about kind of getting that cinematic experience you talked about before.
Can you talk a bit about maybe the technical kind of like tricks
that you guys use or experiences from past games that you've drawn on
to kind of make this like seamless movie like experience
where the player still feels involved in it?
Yeah, I would say the bridge sequence was one of our big places of innovation in addition to going in and out of interiors, which was one thing.
But as far as like on the sticks, we wanted to have these micro cinematic moments that led into interactivity.
And every time you did what we called exotic abilities, let's say like webbing up a bus, you're still using all of your web.
buttons that you would use in gameplay,
we would just make sure we framed the camera in a way
that looked more cinematic.
So whenever we could, we'd make these little
micro cinematic moments that led into an interactive moment.
And we tried to keep the QTE amount down
by making you feel like anything that might've been
considered a QTE was not abstract.
It felt connected to the buttons and inputs
that you would be used to in the game.
So the bridge sequence is probably
the best expression of that.
I found the questions I was paraphrasing that was half something Liana asked and half something
Thomas asked in chat here.
So credit where credit is due.
Just to build on Thomas's a bit more and kind of what you just talked about, what was the
key to delivering chasing and escaping experiences so successfully?
Can the same concept slash ideas be applied for less cinematic and more player-controlled
experiences?
Yeah, absolutely.
We're always trying to put as much control in the players' hands whenever we possibly
can.
And a lot of it just comes down to how can we bring more.
cinematography into gameplay itself.
So I think that's a big push for us going forward,
is continuing to evolve that so we never lose control
and try to put all actions in the player's hands,
but still try to find opportunities
where we can play with the camera.
Um, you're gonna have to stop me if you're, I don't know how much you can talk about this one.
It's always a great way to start off a question. Um, I guess working with an established IP,
can you talk a bit about kind of being creative in that space when you're working with a character
that has so much like history and established lore? Yeah, what's wonderful about Miles is he
has a little under...
10 years of lore, right?
So there was a lot of room for us to grow.
But as a franchise, Spider-Man has over 60, right?
It has much larger history.
But I think what's great about Marvel Games
is they're so willing to work with us as partners
to build on the established norms.
So you'll see a lot of things that we did in the first game
and things we did in the second game that
deviate from the comic books.
But that's all built on trust and conversations
that we have.
to say, does this still feel in keeping with the character?
And that's what we always have to ask ourselves
when we make a change.
Like the Tinkerer, for instance, being female and younger
and a friend of Miles Morales.
That was something that we innovated for this game.
And kind of building off of those story beats,
you can subvert expectations in a fun, exciting way
as well, which is always fun to see unfold.
That's the hope, right?
We have 24 seconds here, and there's
so many more questions in chat.
Oh, I'm sorry.
It's the nature of time. It's unforgiving.
So I guess if anyone wants to reach out to you about more kind of like Spider-Man development questions,
can they hit you up on Twitter or email?
Yeah, at Brian Horton Art, you know, hit me up and I'll be happy to answer as many questions as I possibly can.
Awesome. Thank you to everyone in chat for all your wonderful questions.
Thank you for making Spider-Man Morales with the rest of your wonderful,
or Spider-Man Morales with the rest of your wonderful team.
And have a great rest of your showcase, everyone.
BEEP BEEP BEEP BEEP BEEP