Welcome, everybody.
Very happy to have you here today about my talk,
Why Forums Can Be Great for Indie Community
and Discoverability.
A quick intro, I am Philomena.
I am the co-founder and game designer at Strayfawn Studio.
We are an indie studio located in Zurich, Switzerland,
currently consisting of 10 people.
And we concept and develop and publish our own premium PC games.
So we're an indie game studio which tries to make the games that they love
and also try to push them out and see if the world is actually interested in them.
So we released two games so far.
The first one is called Niche, a genetic survival game.
And the second one is called Nimbatus, the Space Drone Constructor.
And both of these games are very much focused on procedural generation and our simulation games.
So this allows us to focus heavily on community-based development.
So we always like check in with people, what they would like to see added next,
and what feedback they may have, and what should be improved.
And today I want to tell you about forums and about community hubs in general.
What you will take away from this session is what community hubs are currently popular.
I did a survey with 100 indie studios and like small teams from all over the world to
see what they are currently using as a community hub and what are the benefits and the problems
with these hubs.
And I want to tell you the story on why all of these options our studio actually in the
end went with a forum.
And once you have that forum, how to bring people in,
like also for other community hubs,
but especially with a forum,
that's probably the biggest challenge
when trying to build that up.
So let's start off with some numbers
and what indie developers have said about community hubs
and community building.
So the first question was, is community building actually
relevant for a game's financial success?
And you can see 96% I was surprised by this number.
96% of people actually said yes.
They believe that if a game has a community, that can actually
impact your launch visibility and your financial success
with the game.
I wanted to know if people are running their community hubs around their game, around their
studio or both.
You can see that usually studios are focused about communicating about their game.
Some had it about their studio and a couple had it about both.
And now we wonder, what are those community hubs actually?
So where are people currently bringing their fans
to interact with them?
And you can see that, not surprisingly,
Discord is like almost 50% of the people.
Discord is currently very, very popular.
It has spread like wildfire in the last half a year or so.
Basically half of the indie developers are using Discord as a community hub.
You can see that for the people that are developing PC games,
Steam forums are also a very big option.
Facebook groups are still around, not so much anymore,
but still quite a few people use Facebook groups.
And some people have other options,
and quite a couple of people actually don't have a main community hub,
but have different ones.
So they said they don't have one specific hub.
What I found a bit odd in the survey was,
like in this gray part, there were quite a few people
who said Twitter is their main community hub.
And I was like, is Twitter even a community hub?
because for example with YouTube and with Twitter it looks more like this,
like you are the developer and you tell people about all the cool things you're adding to your
game and they're just basically listening to you and maybe interacting with you but not so much
interacting with each other because the only opportunity they have to do that is like in the
comments of your tweets which doesn't give them enough space kind of and the community hub should
actually be a place where
people are interacting with each other and can share what they have created for your game and so forth.
So if Twitter is your main community hub, maybe consider moving to one like Discord
where people can actually interact with each other better.
So then I wanted to know why do you use this community hub?
And for Discord the answer was that it was very easy to set up and use and also free.
People already have accounts so you don't need to bring them to any site and they don't need to set up a new account.
platform independence.
So if you only have your game on Steam,
Steam forums is fine,
but if you also have it on like PlayStation 4
or like another PC store like GOT,
people don't want to come to your Steam forum,
so it's great to have a Discord
because it's platform independent.
And they really appreciate the chat feature
so that people can both with the devs
and with each other like communicate very quickly,
which for example for bug reports helps a lot
when you can just like.
chat back and forth until you figure out the problem together.
And people really appreciate bots about Discord.
So especially things that you can apply roles to people
or also run giveaways way more easily than you have to, like,
do random numbers and figure out who actually is the winner of the giveaways.
You can just do it with a bot.
With Steam, people said, yeah, you have it automatically
and it's free, and you have to maintain it anyways,
because if people are posting bug reports in the Steam
forums, they expect you to come and reply to them.
And it may influence the purchase decision of a game.
So people may are not sure if they should buy the game,
and then they go to the Steam forums
and read a bit what the general mood is in there.
Are people liking the game?
Maybe they ask a question, and if they get a good reply,
maybe it influences if they will buy the game.
And with Facebook groups, also again,
people already have accounts.
And very interesting here is that compared
to all the other hubs, for example, with Discord,
you just have like your set community size
and you can never like extend it.
You can never like make a post
and then it goes viral into other Discords.
But with a public Facebook group,
if you make an interesting post
and a lot of people share it,
you have the possibility for it to go viral,
which is not the case with the other hubs.
And also because people are very familiar with Facebook,
both devs and users,
and they just like hanging out on Facebook.
And then the question is, what other use,
what other hubs do you also use alongside your main hub?
So we can see quite a lot of people also,
like as a side hub, also use the...
Steam forums, again, because you have to, kind of.
Facebook's also still very much in use,
and people say that often they have started
their community building there,
and they have just, they have moved on to Discord,
but they still keep their Facebook page alive
because it still has some decent traffic going on.
Here, for the first time, we see subreddits.
So people think that, or a lot of developers think
that their target audience is actually there,
and that they should go there in order to reach them.
A few people also have Discord as a site, Hub, and a few have forums.
So we have seen forums are not that popular, at least not that popular anymore, and I wondered
why that is, and if people have even considered forums as an option, and you can see that
a lot of people say, no, it doesn't really fit our needs, or...
A lot of people also say we have actually never thought about that as an option at all.
A few people have a forum, some are thinking about it and some had one but closed it
because they found that it doesn't meet their needs anymore and doesn't keep up with the more recent options.
So why not have a forum?
So people said, it doesn't really
make sense for small games and small studios
because you have to bring in all the traffic by yourself.
And all the needs are already fulfilled by Steam Forums
and by Discord.
It's very hard to opt in.
People need to make an account.
And it's hard to gain traffic.
And it's also, it costs something usually.
And it's an effort to maintain it,
like if somebody does a spam post and so on.
So very high maintenance.
There were also some voices that said, yes, forums are absolutely great,
because they're the best structure for long and in-depth discussions.
I don't know if you have had that, but in Discord, if you're actually trying
to find a specific conversation somewhere, it's sometimes quite hard.
And then like two people are discussing
about something and then just somebody else jumps in and say,
how are you doing today?
And then suddenly the conversation shifts
and the in-depth discussion is maybe interrupted.
With a forum you have full control and you can apply your own rules.
Many people say it's the best way to collect user feedback and bugs,
and not only that, but also to archive it so that you can look it up very easily again.
And people said that it makes sense if the studio is big or the studio has more than one game,
because then it can cross-promote each other.
So these were the voices of 100 indie developers,
and now I want to tell you our story of why we actually
decided to go with the forum.
So our studio was just working on its first game, which is called Niche.
And at the very beginning, when it was just a prototype, we opened up a Facebook group
because we thought, yeah, that's the place our audience is.
And then we said, yeah, maybe also let's add a Twitter to reach more people.
And then we went to events and started gathering email addresses.
So let's also have a newsletter.
And then we did a Kickstarter, and then, yeah,
we also have to update our backers about all the new things
we're doing now.
And then we did Steam Early Access launch,
and then the Steam forums were also a new channel
we had to communicate on.
And then people opened the Discord
and kind of expected us to drop in from time to time.
Then we opened a YouTube channel because we
had regular videos whenever we did an update.
And then people opened a subreddit,
and it expected us also to check in from time to time.
And we did an Instagram, because everybody
said Instagram is cool.
So why not another one?
And after that, we started also working
on our second game, which is Nimbatus.
And there, we basically started with a Twitter.
It's the whole story all over again,
but just a bit different.
So here we thought a subreddit is better,
because it fits the target audience better.
Then the Discord happened.
The Kickstarter happened.
the email list happened, then we also started like posting an image, like kind of a dev insights,
whenever we had like a new update with the early access launch came the steam forums, youtube,
you see, so at least
At latest, after your second game, you will have a lot of places where people are actually
expecting you to communicate and to react to them.
And we were a bit overwhelmed by all of this and thought, yeah, maybe we can do this studio-based
community thing, right?
So we don't have, like...
accounts on everything with every game.
So we looked into all of this huge pile of stuff
where we had to communicate and thought, OK, which ones can
we actually do studio-based?
And we found some.
So OK, Instagram and YouTube, we can do those studio-based
and just use it for both games and upload videos and stuff.
We can kind of do the newsletter and the Kickstarter
studio-based, but we still have to communicate something
specifically for each game.
And yeah, now that we're actually building up a presence for the studio,
we actually also need a Twitter account for the studio and a Facebook account
for the studio and the Discord for the studio.
And you can see that in the end, it was just even more community hubs.
And then we decided to try and solve the problem.
by adding even more community hubs.
So we decided to open up the forum,
but the approach this time was planned to be different.
So we wanted to basically have the forum
as the main community hub for everything
where people knew if they wanted to reach us,
if they wanted to chat with us,
if they wanted all the infos,
they have to come to the forums.
And like, just...
manage the expectations that we will not be online everywhere and reacting within 24 hours on all these other platforms.
So we looked around a bit and
found a forum software called InVision.
Actually, we decided on this one also because like the guys from Kerbal Space Program
were using it and the guys from Don't Starve, so we thought,
huh, all the big guys are using this software,
so there must be something cool about it.
And we looked into it more, and we
saw that it has a lot of options for plug-ins
and a lot of cool features, which I will get to in a sec.
And yeah, then we kind of were, yeah, are we really doing forums over like Steam forums,
Facebook groups and Discord?
And at this point, Steam forums were not really an option anymore because we were also selling
the game on GOG.
So we had to kind of have a place where these people could come.
that dropped out as an option.
Facebook groups, we felt that not all of our players,
so especially with the second game,
even have a Facebook account.
And some said, no, I don't really want
to hang out on Facebook.
And Discord is great, but I'm also always a bit afraid
that how long will these things last?
So with a forum, you have a bit of a stability
because you will have people's email address
and if they, for example, have a bug report.
you will be pretty sure that you can reach them again because you have their email and you can reach out through that and
Yeah, with Discord it suddenly popped up and I'm not sure will it still be there in a year or in two years
maybe but maybe they also like decide to do something else with the company and then I will suddenly not have access to
my community anymore which sucks and then I cannot like bring them to another place very well, maybe
And also, the other big reason was that we now had two games,
and we kind of wanted the people to mingle a bit.
So if they played one game, many people played one game
but didn't know about the second game,
also because the target audience was quite different.
And we thought, yeah, maybe if we bring them in one place
together and they chat with each other a bit,
maybe they will also take a look at the other game
and ultimately become fans of the studio.
So after opening that forum, it basically went from very loud and we had to be everywhere to this.
Like completely quiet, nobody is online and that was probably the biggest community management
challenge or build-up challenge that we ever had compared to a Discord which is open it,
here's the Discord, oh there's a hundred people I can chat with now, that's nice.
And how did we actually try to make sure people visit the forums?
So we were very happy with the features that the forum offered.
It was exactly the place where we wanted our community to be
and we thought this will make our lives so much easier
if they are actually here and use all these features.
But how to actually get them there?
And one important thing was just relinking.
So in the Steam forums and on many other community platforms,
we basically just had this little note that said, yeah,
hi, we sometimes come here and chat with you a little bit,
but we're actually mostly only in our own forums.
Yeah, we come here and check out your box.
But other than that, if you want to chat, come over.
We're online almost every day.
And that was a very big relief to me,
because I felt like.
Okay, now I don't have to reply to every question that is posted somewhere.
And yeah, people can just, if they really want to chat, they can just do that extra step and come over to the forum,
and then I will take the time and chat with them over there.
And then we needed to make sure that people actually know that.
So whenever we sent out a newsletter, we said, yeah.
And if you want to discuss what we should add to the game next,
click on there.
Join us in the forums.
Chat with us there.
or whenever we released a new YouTube video with new content
that we had just added to the game, we made it like a little overview video
and said, yeah, if you want to check out the full list of patch notes,
you can just do that in the forum. So always incentivize them to
at least come check out the forum. You don't have to make an account, but maybe
take a look at it.
I think one of the most important things was a cool feature that a forum has, and we're
kind of trying to, like, we have seen all these different community hubs have benefits,
right?
So, with Reddit, for example, you have this very cool feature that you can up and down
vote things.
And we saw that, okay, the...
Basically, the forum has a very similar feature
that we can use as this.
And then we told people that if they have an idea for the game,
they have to come to the forum, post it there,
and we will then look at the top 10 ideas
from the last month or so.
And this was also a big relief, because previously we
had received emails that were this long with an idea.
I was like, I could read feedback all day,
or I could actually work on the game.
And now I could just tell them.
If you want your idea considered, please post it in the forum and make it appealing so people will vote for it and then we will check it out.
And so people also like started doing little doodles for their suggestions, so they get a lot of upvotes and that made it so much easier to like see what people are actually interested in adding to the game.
Another thing that is cool about the forum is that you can show who is actually online.
You can also do that with Discord, but for example in the Steam forums, people don't
know if you're actually around or not, or if you're asleep.
So people knew, okay, now Philo and Micha are online, and we taught them how they can
tag us.
And they even learned who is responsible for what over time.
So if they have a gameplay question, they maybe tag me.
If they have a bug, they maybe tag Micha.
And so I could just like every morning come online and check if I was tagged somewhere and if not, okay, everything is fine.
They're busy.
We also have a couple of moderators and they try to answer people's questions
and if they can't find a solution then they tag us and we always know basically if there's somebody in need of our help.
And yeah, not only that, but people, yeah,
started to get to know us a bit more as people
because they tagged us with our names.
And also in the forum,
you can have cool customization features.
So we made all of the developers into emojis.
that people started using and suddenly everybody knew,
ah, Marcus does the art and ah, Claudio is the game,
is the sound designer.
And so they started to know us and our roles
and our character a bit.
And you can also do like a lot of customization
with the sub forums and people like really appreciate it
when the things are like very much designed
towards the game.
And I think to this extent, I mean, you can even on Discord, you can have some customization,
but not as much as in the forum. With the sign up process, we try to make that easier with
sign up plugins that you can like use your Twitter account or your Steam account.
and even more useful plugins.
So trying to bring all the best things
from all the different community hubs.
So for example, in Discord,
people really appreciate those roles, right?
So we looked around, is there maybe a plugin?
And yes, there actually is one.
So now we could, for example,
give people the roles of Nimbatus tester.
And then...
if we had like a testing session coming up that was like urgent so we have to test this
by tonight and see if it works then we can just do at Nimbatus tester and they even get an email
so that's even stronger to like trigger them to come to the forum than it would
be on discord where they get the discord ping.
So that's great.
And there's also some cool plugins, for example,
for your newsletter.
So with MailChimp, when people sign up to the forums,
they can just check the box.
And then they're also automatically
added to your newsletter and get all the latest news.
So other things we try to get the community going
a little bit is we try to run a lot of giveaways.
So every couple of weeks, we said,
like on our other social media platforms, like on Twitter,
we posted, hey, we're running a raffle.
in our forums, so come on, make an account, post there,
and we will give away a Steam key randomly between everybody who participated.
And this actually got a lot of people to make an account, which was nice.
And then it's easier for them to come back.
and check in again because then they will already have their account.
So this helped a lot with bringing in new people and some then sticked around
and looked at other things that have been posted and became members of the community.
So we still do that pretty frequently.
But it doesn't really matter how many people you bring in.
In the end, it's really about how many people you can make stick around.
So people that really want to stay in the forums and chat with people.
And I think the best way to do this is to help people become friends.
So in our forums, for example, for our first game, we have a lot of people that draw their characters
and they have an art section and then they give each other tips on how they can improve their drawing skills.
So suddenly the forum is not just about the game anymore, but has a completely new kind of value.
So suddenly it's about improving your art.
Or other people started a beauty contest of their creatures.
So they posted screenshots and were judges of each other's breeding.
And it was kind of like a cat show and they did it every month.
And that was very cool.
And I was very happy when people started picking up
like random topics in the forum, because if they are only
talking about your game, there's only so much
they can talk about, right?
So if you haven't released an update in a long time,
maybe there's not so much to talk about anymore.
And now they're just talking about Hamilton the musical
and interesting biology stuff.
So because they have met people that they enjoy chatting with,
they can just now stick around and visit the forums
and talk to their friends.
So to sum this up a little bit, I have some numbers.
We opened the forum around six, seven months ago,
and so far around 3,700 people have registered,
and about 1,000 of them also signed up to the newsletter
with the plugin, which is nice.
And around like 15 to 16 people are usually online at a given time of the day.
So now people actually have somebody to interact with compared to the very beginning of the forums,
even though it was quite a bit of work.
Now it's actually quite consistent and we don't have to do so much anymore to bring in the traffic
because people are just stopping by to chat with their friends.
So all in all, I would say it was a good decision,
but I agree with the pros and contras
at the beginning of the talk,
that it's not a good idea
if you're working on your first game
and it's still very small,
and it will be very hard to also bring those people
over to the forums.
But if you have an already existing community of some size,
then it might make sense.
It made really a lot of sense now that we have two games,
and people are really mingling and exchanging experiences from both games very well.
For us, it has basically just made things so much more comfortable,
and I enjoy our whole community management a lot more,
since we have the forum and can check in there.
I can really recommend it.
So I hope you will keep building and growing your communities
and have a lot of fun with them.
Thank you.
Do we have any questions?
I run a rather large forum using the Zenforo software, and you mentioned you had done some research and ultimately settled on InVision.
So I was wondering if you could speak to some of the advantages that InVision offers over the competition.
Yeah, the question is why Envision is actually a nice software to use as a form software.
I think because of the features it has inherently.
So with the whole up and down vote feature and also the back end is like very easy to
use so you don't have to be a programmer to set up like your different chats and whatever.
And yeah, there were a lot of plugins,
and the plugin developers were quite active for it.
And I also really like the basic design
and how the site is structured.
I think it doesn't look so old-fashioned
as other forums do.
As a matter of the appearances,
isn't that a matter of a front-end design?
Isn't that something that you could customize
regardless of the base software?
Yeah, you can customize a lot of it.
But for example, I was in charge of it,
and I'm not a web programmer.
And so I saw that I would save a lot of work
if I would go with this approach where I can just set up
everything in the back end.
But yeah, we sometimes do small changes.
For example, we try to really make the forum look
like part of our website.
And then we had to have the website header programmed
into it, and then we had to tweak some things there.
Yes.
Thanks.
So if I have some extra time,
I can talk a bit more about community building.
That's a thing I really like to do.
One thing that I really enjoyed is building up developer communities.
I think that a lot of developers are still seeing each other more as competition
than actually as beneficial relations.
And for our first game, we built up basically a community around people
who make games about nature.
So we have a shared website with 30 games that are all related to nature
and a shared chat.
And it was really great, like, cross-promoting each other with that.
And I would love to see more developer communities, like, resolving around a specific topic.
So I would love to see, like, a space developer community and, like, if people like space games,
they just have to go to that website and then they see, like...
50 different games and then you can sort them by genre or whatever thing you think is important
or is it single player or multiplayer like as a
discoverability benefit for developers. So if you haven't considered that, please do and
I think we are done. If you have any questions, feel free to reach out to me at any time and
please fill out the survey that you will receive a mail of in a couple minutes. Thank you!
Oh yeah, sure.
Go right ahead.
Sorry.
Let's say you have a decently sized community.
How do you keep it, how do you kind of keep all those
members engaged kind of constantly when it seems to
maybe be dying down a little bit?
So for us, the most important thing to keep people engaged,
even if we are not pushing updates very often,
is just the fact that they can discuss what
should be in the next update.
I mean, for the first game, we only
release a new update every six months.
But in between, they are very busy chatting with each other.
So the devs only have this much time, so we really need to come up with small suggestions
that would be really great, and they spend a lot of time doing that.
And also, if they can talk about anything else than your game, then you don't really
need to come up with new content all the time.
Thank you.
You're welcome.