Hello everyone.
My name is Koushi Nakanishi, director of REGNATIVE 7.
Thanks for being here, but I can't speak English.
You are speaking English now!
So, here's Peter.
Thank you very much, Koshi.
My name is Pete Fabiano.
Some of you may know me as the guy who doesn't do ADR.
Others in the room will know me as Pete Fabiano,
Senior Manager of Global R&D.
My team and I handled a bit of the production
for this project, but that's not what we're here
to talk about today.
Today we're here to discuss, well I'm here speaking
on Koshi's behalf to discuss the vision
and approach we took with RE7.
So as most of you are aware, Resident Evil is known as biohazard in Japan.
So for this title, we consolidated the names and made the western name Resident Evil a
subtitle in Japan and vice versa overseas.
Internally, we nicknamed the project Harawata, which roughly translates as entrails or guts.
It also happens to be, however, part of the name for evil dead in Japanese.
So, quick show of hands, who in the room has actually played Resident Evil 7 in some form or another?
Wow, oh wait, me too.
Okay, well then most of you know what we're getting into.
For this series we took a new direction, in part by changing the camera to first person
and keeping a strong focus on survival horror.
And we're not just saying that, we did actually try to do that.
I'd like to start by playing a brief clip to help set the stage
and visually demonstrate what we accomplished.
What the fuck?
What is that?
What the fuck are you talking about?
So we weren't really sure how all this would be received.
As developers, we wanted to keep true to our creative vision, but how would fans and the
public respond?
Overall, we were pretty pleased with the public reception
from industry, media, and customer feedback.
Players were happy with the overall direction we took,
and we got positive commentary on the atmosphere
and the world that we tried to create.
So let's go back to the beginning, where it all started.
Osaka, 2014.
So how do you iterate on the RE franchise?
Well, you get two seasoned RE veterans, Jun Takeuchi and Koshi, to my left here,
who would ultimately act as executive producer, that's Jun Takeuchi,
and of course, the director here, Koshi.
This is when we first discussed the new direction
and started early stages in building the team.
So Takeuchi delivered his general vision for the title.
I mean, how are we going to take the brand forward?
The answer? Horror.
Yeah.
Sure. Could you be a bit more specific?
Yeah. So here we have the four mandates that he established.
Tone along the lines of Evil Dead.
First person perspective to keep players more immersed.
And we coupled that with photorealism to give it more of a realistic feeling.
And no co-op.
He felt that we should keep the experience more personal.
and thus make it single player.
And finally, references to past characters, etc.,
should be kept to a minimum or subdued.
If you're into horror,
then I'm sure you're familiar with Evil Dead.
So what did we extrapolate from that film?
Well, first off,
we wanted to keep the number of characters to a minimum.
We settle on about five main villains.
We knew that we were going up against other AAA blockbuster titles,
so we needed to be efficient in our approach
in order to keep budgets in check and still maintain a high level of interest and quality.
We kept the feeling of confinement by limiting the majority of the game to an old home.
This helped us to keep set pieces narrow and feeling semi-claustrophobic.
In addition, this all contributed to the way players would approach the game
and help capture the mood.
You can think of the RE series almost as a series of trilogies.
One in three had fixed cameras in gameplay,
and that created a feeling of helplessness or challenge
to keep players scared or anxious.
Four through six changed focus to third person,
and they gave us new types of enemies
to match the new direction in gameplay.
Now with seven, we wanted to keep
the tradition of adapting certain elements and direction
to make things feel fresh.
Two major components in this approach were photo realism and first person.
As we mentioned, our focus was to be on the player experience.
In this case, one that focused on horror.
To accomplish this, we brought the game back to single player and moved away from familiar series characters.
In order to concentrate on the horror aspect,
we needed to keep the scope of the game somewhat narrow.
We didn't want an expansive playing field
or to have too much clutter
around the single-player experience.
The team agreed that we needed to keep away
from a focus on the main characters.
In other words, we didn't want this to turn into a game
driven by the protagonist's story, per se,
but more so on the player experience itself.
So going back to Takuchi for a moment,
he gave us a very simple vision for the project.
Make the game scary and fun.
Really?
Seriously?
Yeah.
So yeah, something tells me Koshi wasn't quite as cavalier
when he heard the news, but he thought to himself,
no way, you're gonna let me run with just that?
But he was certainly up for the challenge.
Truth be told, this wasn't something
that came about spur of the moment.
As a company, we had been throwing around ideas as to where to take the franchise.
This came after careful consideration, especially regarding the next phase in the franchise
life cycle.
Koshi himself had been doing some soul searching.
He knew we needed to redefine the brand.
And now we had the general direction that we needed to take and he got now finally the
ability to take it there.
With that in mind, we had to go over brand identity.
What makes Resident Evil, Resident Evil?
I mean, how do you describe the game to people?
For us, it was fun, atmospheric, scary.
We needed to make sure though,
that RE differentiated itself from competitors.
So staying true to our newly defined vision,
we set out to begin planning and designing
and putting together a design document
in order to reach our end goal.
Probably most important focal point
was attempting to achieve the same impact or feeling
that players had the first time they picked up
and played the original RE.
Particularly the first one
and its iconic atmosphere and imagery.
So what did we have in the original RE that defined it?
Well, you had unfamiliar surroundings.
Where were you?
Everything you encountered was new,
and neither you nor the characters knew what was going on.
Interesting enemies.
Everyone remembers the first time you see the camera pan
to what appears to be a zombie, and it turns towards you.
Were you fighting with the undead?
Players didn't know who they were.
Sure, you heard the stars' names, but the characters weren't that developed.
They were new, and you didn't know who to trust.
Would you ever even make it out of this place alive?
You'll notice the goal here was to tie in a lot of unknowns.
Who, what, where, how.
All this contributes to giving off feelings of anxiety
and ultimately, fear.
For the new direction, we wanted to create that same sense, or create a sense of unknown.
So we chose a setting, a new setting in Louisiana, with an unfamiliar main character and a new mystery.
The sense of new and unknown continues with our enemy design.
With photorealism, our characters could display vivid expressions.
We could have them perform unexpected and grotesque actions.
And this leads to psychologically taxing situations,
a sort of psychological roller coaster.
Not knowing what to expect kept situations tense
and players often trying to keep their guards up
and sometimes failing.
With RE, level designs focused on enclosed areas
where you collect ammo and solve puzzles,
all with the intention of opening up new areas
and moving forward.
This was accomplished with either linear, or what we call tube style design,
or through more Metroidvania like progression.
We kept this for RE7 as well.
Welcome to the family everyone.
Since we wanted to keep to four or five main villains,
the less is more approach, we thought a good way to bring it all together
would be to make them a family.
Now we had some of the general ingredients we needed.
So we needed to review some of the issues we felt existed with making a horror game.
One of the main problems we discovered is that people get used to being scared pretty
quickly, especially if you can guess what's coming.
We thought that in RE, players overcame their fears by laying waste to enemies.
This is the catharsis point.
Once the unfamiliar grows and...
and then it becomes familiar or common,
people adapt and learn how to overcome their fears.
So we decided to shake things up a little bit.
We incorporated elements of the horror sub-genres
into each of the family members.
There's a multitude of categories here,
so without going into too many details,
we can say that Margaret, or the mother character,
for her, we took elements of body or natural horror.
Limbs exaggerate as she mutates.
Centipedes emerge from her body.
With Jack, the father character, we included elements of slasher films.
Lucas, a slice from psychological horror, and so on and so forth.
We still needed to overcome our perceived issues with horror, though.
And the easiest or simplest, at least in terms of theory, not execution, was immersion.
How do we make players feel like they're in this world or situation?
We already mentioned first-person and photorealism,
but adding to that we wanted to have a level of believability,
while limiting the characterization around the main character.
And of course, one final piece to the immersion puzzle was to include VR.
So what are some of the things we actively removed or chose to avoid?
To keep our overall vision of scary and fun while staying true to the defined RE identity,
we felt that we needed to exclude familiar characters, action elements, co-op, zombies,
any type of over-the-top blockbuster type film.
Including these would run counter to our goals or at the very best make them difficult to
achieve.
Now we are finally starting to get closer to actually building something.
We got our direction, our ideas, our definitions,
but what do fans like about the series?
So over our 20 years with the franchise,
we've gotten feedback that tells us
what the fans have liked across the timeline.
You've got characters, story, a sense of fear,
foreboding, puzzles, taking down enemies,
particularly in co-op, zombies, creatures,
all of the stuff that comes with RE and fixed cameras.
But not all fans are created equal.
And most importantly, you can't have it all.
So here's something Koshi believes about creating or building a commercial product.
Complete with visual references of what you get when you pack everything together.
As you can see, making something no one hates
means also making something that no one loves.
You'll remember potentially that Simpsons episode
where Homer made a car for the everyman,
and it ended up being for everyone
and no one at the same time.
Here's a little bit more philosophy.
Deciding what to do means also deciding what not to do.
And so with that, we completed our game design doc
and moved forward.
Which takes us to presenting that to you.
The guy seated in the front row, maybe.
Marketing, yeah.
So how did they respond?
Well, all companies and publisher-developer
relationships are different.
Some are contentious.
Some are friendly.
For us, when we presented it to them,
we didn't get much pushback.
However, it was very easy to come up
with reasons for failure or risk.
This was especially true as we were going
through the approval process.
From our perspective, marketing liked our design and direction.
Their major concern was determining where the brand fit into the market.
After all, we were trying to make something old, but new.
Lucky for our devs, however, our chairman, Big T, lover of baseball,
puts a lot of trust into our teams.
He truly believes that they're capable of making something good
and encourages them to do so.
He didn't actually say that.
No, he did.
How did the team react though?
I think that's a point that we need to explore.
Well, we took a lot of criticism to heart.
We knew we needed to appeal to our base,
so we needed to look more into the details of our approach.
Wanted to have something as fresh and memorable
as the Christopher Nolan Batman films.
However, the important point to consider
is that we didn't want to reboot the series.
We wanted to move it forward in its next natural stage.
So following through with our aims,
we broke down our targets and wanted to ensure
that we were making something
that our fans would be happy with.
It's all theory and data,
but at least it helped us to create goals
and move towards them.
One of our other goals became moving towards action via gameplay
rather than the shooting mechanics.
But there are already some great games out there that are scary.
Again, we needed to differentiate ourselves.
We needed what the Japanese refer to as the fifth sense of taste.
The umami.
So Koshi asked the teams to write up some mock reviews.
What would people say about our title?
Here's a general summary of what they wrote.
Excuse me for a moment.
Resident Evil 7 trades the massive scale and unrivaled variety of the previous installments
for a return to the magic of the original Resident Evil.
Though the game's theme and plotline hint at classic RE tropes, RE7 has largely discarded
its ongoing virus-centric story and familiar characters, which might be a disappointment
to some fans.
However, the development team should be commended for meeting and exceeding the high expectations
of the current market, and we were left with high hopes for the future of the series.
so they were trying to predict the future and be hopeful.
And with that, we finally started building.
We had to get in the right mindset.
We couldn't make something scary
without feeling or knowing fear ourselves.
So like it or not, he and the team set out
to find urban legends, watch horror films,
head to haunted mansions, et cetera, et cetera.
Koshi heard that the Uncharted team, though,
they got to go to a desert while making their game.
We only got to drive 30 minutes
to an abandoned location nearby.
Something tells me we got the short end of the stick.
Except he forgot that we actually got to go to Louisiana
and film quite a bunch of stuff for reference.
We got some wonderful stuff out there.
We got to travel to plantations, to museums,
to all sorts of locations that really helped
to capture some of the realism that we were going for.
Except that I think he forgot about that
because unfortunately he was at home building the game.
Anyway.
While doing all of this, something happened.
Some team members, they just didn't get Evil Dead.
They couldn't understand what made it interesting or fun.
So Koshi had to put things in perspective.
It was kind of like this.
It's a classic film that Sam Raimi made on a low budget.
Think about that.
Be Sam Raimi.
So we managed to set the mood and the mindset of the team.
Now it's time to create.
Internally, we decided to go with our new engine,
ultimately what came to be known as the RE engine,
but it wasn't ready yet.
So we started building our gray box in Unity.
Here's some samples for you guys to take a look at.
We didn't really care too much about making things cohesive or organized.
We just wanted to see our ideas come to life during the look dev process.
So when building out the gray box, we had a few basic mantras.
No lengthy docs.
Any interesting idea was valid.
And anyone and everyone should have the opportunity to realize their ideas.
It was important that everyone consider the game as a whole.
So we tried to remove any type of segregation or barriers
and encouraged people to expand beyond their official roles.
It didn't matter whether you were the audio director
or the art director or whatever,
you were free to discuss design.
During pre-production, we employed agile development,
we broke teams down into small groups,
we wanted to make sure that goals were defined,
and we created an environment where it really felt
like a number of individual indie teams
working amongst the larger team.
We took things a step further,
where we divided them into father, mother, brother,
and grandma plus, meaning anything else
outside of the grandma.
Kind of all to strengthen teamwork and bonds.
Because we didn't have a fleshed out story or scenario,
we were able to create some interesting pieces
that we actually used in the game.
Unfortunately, this did not come without its drawbacks.
Because we didn't have that,
Some things were left straying off course, confused.
Some members didn't respond to this well.
And in Koshi's words, sometimes it was just utter chaos.
But as it says here, passion is important.
And let me play you a clip of one of the things
that was a result of what we did in pre-production.
It's fucking hard!
The scene early on where you get your hand cut off
was the result of our art director lamenting over the fact
that there wasn't enough punch in the early scenes.
So Koshi thought that we'd certainly
make things interesting,
but how would players come back from that?
Then he remembered something that the author
of the Death Note series said.
Take your hero into a situation
that even you can't figure a way out of,
and work from there.
So the team ran with it.
The art director also had another idea.
He wanted to have the character lose his lower half
and start crawling his way towards one of the safe rooms.
Yeah, we didn't use that one.
So finally, we made it into full production.
All right, we've got our engine
and we're ready to do this for real.
Why did we make the engine in the first place?
Well, since it was customized with the ARRI in mind,
we of course needed to make enhancements in photogrammetry.
But we also wanted it to push what we could do,
not only technologically,
but also make our teams be able to produce more
in a more efficient way.
This would make things easier for all of us.
We couldn't continue doing things in full production
in the same way we did in pre-production.
So we made a few key changes.
Reviews would happen early and before we implemented ideas.
We moved to a waterfall system and carefully thought
about how we would incorporate the good ideas
that were born out of pre-production,
like what I just mentioned.
The overall dev process worked something more traditional,
like build, review, revise, iterate,
rinse and repeat kind of stuff.
So Tal Gujasan's back, this time with some ominous yet encouraging words.
He wanted Koshi and the team to really push things, make something special.
Except there's one other thing that he really, really wanted them to do.
Not delay the game.
So ship dates would not change.
With that...
We started to change things up and try to make things interesting.
We wanted to actually bring things forward even more.
So, what could we do?
One of the ideas was the split paths with Zoe and Mia.
Keeping with the scope of less is more,
and our fast approaching deadlines,
we wanted to have something that made players feel
like they were making a critical decision,
but also something that wouldn't be so involved
that it would delay the project.
We settled on having the decision affect part of the story,
even though the outcomes led the player
into more or less the same direction.
The chainsaw battle with Jack was another example
of a design decision that would be a challenge,
but also something that left a strong impression.
Knowing our limitations helped the team
to get more creative in their approach.
We kept things positive and set our sights on the goal.
So Koshi felt the need to sometimes ignore common ideologies
with regards to level design.
Take the jack character, for example.
In traditional design, you would have a learning curve,
carefully teaching players how to use weapons.
Though with our jack battle, players are given a chainsaw
and expected to fight immediately.
In another battle, you have a knife and a gun,
and both are fairly ineffective against him.
So your last resort is to get in a car and try something there.
Jack himself, both physically and gameplay-wise,
transforms.
And the only consistent piece is that he's still just batshit
crazy.
Getting this to work was a very arduous process.
And Koshi is indebted to the team
for doing their best to work against the conventional
wisdom.
So were the devs scared?
Yeah, yeah, we were scared at first.
And then we got numb to it, and then worried.
And then we tried changing stuff
because we thought it wasn't good.
And then we got stress, and more stress.
So what was important was to do constant user testing.
We had to make sure that it was objective.
We needed to know that things were scary
and we were starting to get numb to it,
so it was important to get an extra set of eyes.
See, these are some of the other things that we looked at with user testing.
It was important to keep the balance between that sense of anxiety and fear
and also the sense of calm.
You didn't want too much of one or too much of the other.
Also, the periods of stress.
You didn't want the player constantly stressed,
but you also wanted him to feel that sense of fear.
And of course, balancing the timing of procuring items,
or ammo, or guns, that needed to be all balanced out
so you didn't have too much and it was too easy,
or too little and making it too hard.
And very, very important as well,
was motivating the player to make them feel
like they were achieving certain goals and moving forward.
But after all of that, what's the most important thing,
or at least in terms of what we think
is the most important thing?
having fun while creating.
I know it sounds cheesy, but it's true.
And yeah, it's important that we laugh a lot.
Right now, the team is back at home, hard at work,
working on some extra DLC,
and trying to implement new ideas into that as well.
We want them to stay as creative as possible
and try new and different interesting ideas.
Next thing we have coming up does use a legacy character.
Hopefully we can turn it into something
that the fans will enjoy.
Oh, and for those of you that didn't raise your hands
at the beginning of this, this is a very important map.
You'll notice it's got a GameStop on it,
and our location, it's about a seven minute walk.
I don't know what I'm saying right now,
but the map is important if you didn't play yet.
And right before we get back to Koshi, we'd like to present to you with a parody video
that we used during our launch party.
This was to really get the devs amped and feel good about what they had done over the
years.
And it's a parody of a Japanese documentary-type program.
So it's about five, six minutes, so please bear with us while we go through it, but just
keep that in mind.
Osaka, Uchihirano.
Here, a team was working on a project to make Capcom's Shoun.
Team Harawatato.
This is the record of their development, full of hardships.
With the aim of thwarting the threat,
the tests showed repeated failures.
Unity was selected as the test environment.
The scene inside the taxi, which is considered as the introduction of the story.
The grand idea of chatting with the driver for 15 minutes is, of course, a sin.
The man with the glasses.
Later, he became Jack.
Hey! Hey, you!
What are you doing here?
Please, help me!
What's wrong?
I don't know.
You're too much, old man!
As an actor, he sometimes...
...takes his own body.
The legendary Chapter 2.
A challenging concept just for walking the field...
...was crap after all.
Reach the Moon.
Finally, a new engine has been rolled out.
The name is RE Engine.
Tragic system changes,
Isolate View,
PSVR response,
All of them are a sign of fear.
Is it really okay on this route?
Against all their worries, the team hit clocky Scrap-and-Build battles
and kept fighting the journey they believed in together.
That's how we met each other in June 2016.
America's men, 5300.
I could feel the audience's applause.
I could do it.
After I felt the response, I just had to run.
Oh
That's right, sir.
I'm gonna buy you plenty of...
Ha!
Sir!
So in closing, I'd like to leave you with a few words from Koshi himself.
This time we will have translation.
So as all of you have hopefully played, and if not, like Pete said, please go to GameStop and pick up a copy.
But we have successfully launched or shipped our title.
And as you just heard, and with confidence, I can say that we have achieved our vision.
Before and after the release of 7, I think we were able to change the way the franchise was perceived by the public.
Above all, I think we were able to raise expectations for the next development.
So if I could say there's a period before Resident Evil 7 and now that we've released,
after and the future, if I look into the future, I think that we're able to change the perception
or franchise and brand sort of image and we can now take this and carry it into and hopefully
carry it over into whatever comes next for the franchise.
Looking back on the development, the key to success was the simple vision, the team's
dedication, and passion.
And what's important is to have a very simple vision.
Not only that, but to be very faithful to your commitment, the team's commitment, and
also the team's passion.
I would like to thank all the people involved and all the fans.
I feel a sense of high speed right now.
Myself, as for myself, as the person who led the project and as a developer,
I have a great sense of satisfaction and what we were able to achieve.
As you just saw in the video, but it is a parody, please keep in mind.
It's not all fun times with happy faces and smiles all around.
I'm sure you guys have experienced similar things, going through very tough times and challenges.
But I hope you do agree that when you overcome those tough times challenges
with your team and to have this kind of result or to make it to your goal, it is all worth it.
And that feeling of overcoming these tough times and challenges,
and times when you don't think you can make it to the goal,
is very similar to what you experience in the game itself.
Thank you for listening.
Can I get the mic on?
So we have about 20 minutes, and we'll open it up to Q&A.
We have two mics, one on each aisle.
So if you could come up and ask the question into the mic.
Is it on?
Here we go, hi.
My name is Dory, I'm from Paradox Interactive
over in Sweden, thank you so much for the presentation,
I really love the game.
Just a question, I know you're in no position
to share any numbers or any of the
not so sexy budget stuff.
But I am curious, assuming the return on investment for a project such as this one is better than for a very, very large project such as Resident Evil 6,
what does that mean not only for this franchise, but for maybe all of Capcom's franchises going forward?
I don't think we can tell you the exact number, but...
I think we can give you a rough idea.
If we compare the number of people who participated in the project with the number of people who participated in the original project,
I think the number of people who participated in the original project was much higher.
What are your plans for future projects?
The mic is over there.
Oh, it's not the mic.
Well, as you said, I'm not in a position to give you a specific price.
But as I explained, this project includes the engine.
So it's not a simple comparison.
But in terms of development, it's certainly more compact than the 6.
Speaking of the future, after we finish building the engine,
we can focus on the game more deeply.
I think we can make better games.
So you're right, I am unable to share any numbers or figures here.
However, one thing to keep in mind for RE7 is that
sort of inclusive of the engine development cost is what we're looking at.
And so it's hard to compare. It's like comparing apples and oranges. So it's hard to say.
But the development cost, you're right, it was a lot more sort of compact in the sense of if you compare just purely numbers, seven versus six.
I can add to that. I mean, as I said in the presentation as well, I mean, we tried to be as efficient as possible.
So we tried to keep things within the budget that we were given.
Here's your answer.
Thank you.
Is that OK?
No, it's fine.
Hi, I just have one quick question
and one a little longer question.
But the first one is, was Texas Chainsaw Massacre
an influence at all?
Because I see quite a bit of that in the parts of the game
anyway.
Was Texas Chainsaw Massacre an influence at all?
Because I see quite a bit of that in the parts of the game anyway.
Well, as I explained earlier today,
The first game I'm going to talk about is Evil Dead.
There are many elements in the game,
and as I said, Texas Chainsaw is one of my favorite games.
There are many other games that I can use as a reference.
So first and foremost, you saw on the slide too, but I guess if we were to call out like the main vision or motif goal that we went for is Evil Dead,
but that doesn't mean that that was the only reference material that we went by.
So obviously Texas Chainsaw Massacre and everything else that you can really think of,
there's a whole sort of wide variety of elements that we pulled inspiration and influence from.
We're huge fans, period.
So there's a lot of influences.
Yes, so, this is a scene from a dinner party.
Actually, the reference video we showed to the team
was not from the Texas war, but a long-term dinner scene.
So, horror movies are the first of the Texas war.
There are a lot of dinner scenes of aliens that we've seen in various movies.
We collected a lot of dinner videos from all over the world
and chose the one that was most suitable for Biohazard.
So to add to that, that whole table dining scene,
the first video or the first scene
that I showed and shared with my friend, I mean my team,
is from Long Turn.
And we referenced a lot of very similar scenes
from a wide variety of film.
and probably non-film references from,
and it doesn't have to be anything that's from modern days,
everything old, new, from East and West.
But the very first scene that we showed to the team
was from that.
Yeah, it was really the table scene that made me think of it.
But sorry, the real question I wanted to ask was...
Oh, okay.
Well, I decided not to make that to be such a thing.
But I was just curious, was VR always part of the plan?
And if not, because I know you made a comment about
you just had to keep a schedule and didn't want to ship late.
So I was just wondering if VR was in the plan early,
and if it wasn't, how did you manage to get that in
without the schedule changing?
Yeah, I'm sorry.
This is a question I get asked a lot.
Well, as I explained today,
I heard from Takeuchi first,
and I thought,
VR would be a perfect fit for it.
So I included it in my first GDD.
But I actually started developing it
after the main game
was released,
a little after that.
So yeah, when we got the mandate from Takeuchi,
I thought in an instant, okay, this is meant for VR.
It would be the perfect fit.
But in reality, when we started really working on VR,
it wasn't until a little bit into the development period.
Yeah, in the original design doc,
he had included VR as well, but it wasn't necessary.
We didn't actually start building it out immediately.
Thank you. Thank you. I know.
I do see people lined up on this side too,
so let's take one from that side.
First off, I'd like to say that I really enjoyed this game.
It was really nice to play a Resident Evil game again that really encapsulated the horror
that the genre and game series has been trying to keep alive.
You mentioned how they kind of progress in a sequential order, like 1 through 3 is the
third person, and then 4 through 6 is more action-oriented.
Are you planning on going with that approach with Resident Evil from this point on as well?
Is there going to be 8 and 9 following 7's approach?
Or are you up in the air about that right now?
Good question.
Yes, as I said before we made 7,
but as for Survival Horror,
So, yeah, it was in the slide, and prior to 7, we can sort of group them into threes.
However, with this genre of survival horror, mystery and suspense is key, which means
who knows what's going to happen.
Okay, okay. I have two questions one is for the VR mode. They use a sort of locomotion which is
Continuous locomotion and up to now many games that use this type of locomotion people got sick
So did you try out also other types of locomotion with?
Teleports and so on and when was it that you were safe that this type of locomotion didn't make people sick
Japanese Interpretation
Yes, that's right.
Some of you may know this, but the first VR game to be released in Japan was Train E3.
We were pretty confident, but we got a lot of negative feedback that we were going to become too emotional.
And then, Sony told us that we needed to do more.
So, we tried a lot of things before the release,
and we actually used dozens of staff in the company for the test play.
I'm really sorry to everyone, but there were quite a few people who got drunk because it was a test.
We tried a lot of different patterns and were able to control it quite well.
That's how we were able to go with the current specifications.
So the very first time we showed off VR mode in semi-public trade was last year's E3.
We came in with a good amount of confidence to E3, but the result was that we did hear
a lot of people who said that they got sick.
we did have some negative feedback.
And so really, it was only after post E3
that we really, really started looking into
how we can improve and make it better.
We also got advice, very important and valuable advice
from the Sony team.
and worked very hard.
They encouraged us to do better,
and that we can do better.
So, and then prior to sort of mastering up or pre-release,
we did a lot of user testing within the company.
Several of our staff.
and personnel had tested the game too.
And I feel bad because I know that some people really got sick.
It is a test, so a lot of people probably were in for a little bit of a surprise.
But that's when we started tweaking and fine-tuning and a lot of trial and error
and really got to find the right kind of zone where we landed.
And second question is, you said part 7 would be more suspenseful and scary, and the first half of the game really is,
but the second half is more action-oriented, the final is very much gunfights and so on.
Was that a compromise to don't set off the fans so much, or was it planned, and would you do it otherwise,
taking it the scary way and the slow way all the way to the end the next time?
take had heard of this and what it wants.
So he thinks, there's still a mean arrangement,
and it'd be best if he raised all of that,
or is it something that our guys that want it
are at the outside trying to do forward?
Is that what you set in your mind,
or would you like to go transition
with a conclusion that's consistent
with your discussions previously?
So as a result,
as we now go back to the discussion
we think that there is motion
I wanted to make the level design so that players can understand the mystery of the game in the latter half of the game,
and when they have a hard time, they can beat the enemies and go to the goal.
I wanted to make an escalation like that, so I made it into the current level design.
So it's fair to say that even ourselves now post-release,
we can perhaps view it in that manner too.
So I don't disagree with that.
However, from a level design perspective,
the aim that we had there was that in the first half
of the game, you're now.
solving mysteries, you're finding out more, right?
And so towards the end of, or the latter half,
is that now that you're stronger
and you have a lot more of these mysteries solved
and you've uncovered all this,
that you can take an approach of maybe, you know,
trying to be in a position where you can go out
and really defeat the characters, defeat the enemies.
So that was really more the intent.
that you uncover, but then as you're progressing the game,
that you would use that to your strength.
Thank you.
Hi.
Actually, that was sort of my question,
but now I made something up on the spot here.
On one of the slides, you had some influences
of what horror could be, like you showed amnesia
and Outlast.
So that kind of progression of horror games turned into a lot of more indie developers.
I feel like there was a lot of influence from them.
Was there any kind of reaching out or kind of just sharing or collaborating of ideas with those indie developers?
Also, I know you have the exclusive right to decide what you're going to use and how you're going to show the film
but mainly the players have the freedom to decide what they're going to use for the movie
There's also the circle of gods
So, you have this exclusive right that allows you to have conversation with your co-workers
I wonder if you have ever experienced those kinds of ideas that came out around you?
Well, we do play a lot of indie titles, but we don't have that many in Japan.
So we haven't had that much experience.
a lot of the developers that make these games,
they're not really physically located in Japan.
So it's not as easy for us to have maybe some communication
or meeting up with them
and just having casual conversations.
So we haven't had the opportunity to really do that.
Thank you.
Thank you so much for your wonderful presentation.
I've been a big Resident Evil fan for a long time, so...
And I've been very receptive to the different directions that the series has gone in over the last 20 years.
However, a lot of people who I respect would say things like...
you know, they really miss the action elements of Resident Evil 4 through 6,
and I even had one person say that
he'd rather RE7 didn't do so well, so you guys could go back to
that more action-oriented direction, and...
Thank you.
Takahashi-san, I want to know, what would you say to a person with that kind of mindset?
And how do you get them to like the direction you took the game in?
I think it's okay to fail.
I think I explained it in today's presentation,
but I think it's difficult to make all the fans satisfied.
If you've played a lot, you'll know,
but the Baradar series has made a lot of spin-offs.
So, Capcom doesn't want to make action-oriented games at all,
but we want to focus on the concept of the project and make choices and focus on it.
So, simply put, please look forward to the future development.
Yeah, so there was one slide that we or Pete had shown. It says we can't fit this all in one package.
And so the meaning behind that obviously is that, you know, not all RE games are going to be 100% enjoyed by all RE fans at any time.
And as you know if you've been following the series there's also, besides the numerical REs, we've had some spin-offs.
And so we're not saying that Capcom or our RE team is not going back ever to action-oriented RE games.
I think that the simple sort of...
vision and owning up and committing to that and keeping focus keeping true to that is what we are trying to say here today for
RE7 and I think you guys you know can look forward to what we may come up with in the future
Thank you.
Okay, a little bit more.
And this is, sorry, we're out of time, so this is going to be lost.
So I actually, I also worked on Revelations.
So just to give you an example, you know,
it's not just the numerical titles that I worked on.
So I enjoyed, you know, basically kind of controlling
and giving life to Chris and Jill for that.
But in this, like, let's say if we had Leon
and then like he opens up the pot and like,
oh, there's cockroaches, like that's not something that.
I don't know if you guys would enjoy that as much.
So, you know, there's a certain focus that we just stick to.
And that just happens to be what we did for RE7.
Can I ask one last question really quickly?
Okay.
I love the game and I really liked your art director's idea
that you could get sliced in two and then have to crawl to the safe room.
Was there anything else that you rejected because it was too disgusting?
I know that you have a lot of ideas, but do you have any other ideas that you want to share?
I do, but I might use them next time.
I'm sorry, I can't say.