Alright. Wow. Okay. My name's Scott.
Um, I... well I started out with an um. Right now.
Um, there's no um. Okay.
So, these are the games that I've worked on.
I started at Lucas Learning, and, uh, but I'm here to talk about these games mostly.
Probably not Costume Quest as much, but, um...
I've also done a lot of comics and gallery shows.
And, what else?
Illustration. Children's book illustration.
That's kind of the spectrum of what I do.
But today we're going to talk about some of these guys.
You guys.
Okay.
Psychonauts.
I feel like I should be really dramatic with all you guys.
So many of you.
So yeah, you guys, Psychonauts.
Raise your hand if you have, just so I could...
Okay, cool.
Yes.
Okay, I won't go into that much detail about it then.
It's basically a psychic kid who goes to a camp with all these, like, psychonauts, which are very, you know, an epic kind of, um, secret agent group sort of thing.
And they all have psychic powers, like telekinesis, and they can lift things and throw things with their mind and stuff.
And he uncovers a secret plot, and...
It's really exciting, you guys.
So, um, but these...
The main character...
I'll talk a little bit about what goes into it.
Because today, I'm going to assume all you guys know how to draw a little bit.
And you know all the basics about like, yeah, you know, you know how shapes,
certain shapes make certain, like, characters feel a certain way,
or look a certain way, or act a certain way.
You know basic drawing and life drawing and stuff. That's cool.
But today, I'm going to focus mostly on, like, getting pumped about it.
And finding the meaning behind what you're doing.
Maybe the back story and the character.
You know what I mean? Like everything that you put in there is it could be a story
You don't just put a bunch of belt buckles on a dude and a bunch of like swords or something
Which is fine, too
But if you have a reason for that like the dude is really into swords or something or he's really into belts
but
Otherwise, don't do that as much. You know what I mean?
You have a reason for it, because everything you put in a character has a story, you know?
So, for the first game, for, um...
um...
D'Artagnan was the name of the main character in the beginning.
And he started out being really inspired by, um...
Like, he escaped from a traveling circus, like a group of gypsies in a caravan.
He was very acrobatic. That's how he can do all the acrobatics in the game and everything, you know?
But he's really into the Psychonauts, so he had to be very, very stern about it.
And so Tim was always... Tim Schafer is the... You guys don't know Tim.
Anyway, he's really into the backstory of all of his characters and writing that all out.
And he has an idea for this guy, the new Legend of Shaolin kid right there.
is kind of who we wanted to be like. He wanted to be kind of tough like that and really
serious about being a psychonaut.
So this is what he looked like after a million drawings. This is what he looked like
at that point.
And this is the first character that we designed for the game, which is probably a bad idea.
I'll tell you later why that's a bad idea.
So this is what he looked like. So we put him in the game and we started animating him.
And he had a real big head as you can see.
you know? And we put more of the characters in the game and as the style started kind
of becoming a thing together, like a cohesive style, he became more and more weird looking,
you know? And ultimately when we focus grouped it...
again. So then we went back and kind of started thinking about like what would
be like really what he's about you know like he's really serious about the
Psychonauts and the Psychonauts were always something that you like you get
comic books for and you'd send away for like special goggles and the decoder
ring and stuff so he's like a real fan but he's also serious so maybe he would
have some of those elements but then he would also be wanting to be like one of
the most popular Psychonauts which is this guy Sasha Nein.
So he would maybe start dressing like him, wanting to be like him a little bit.
You know, so that's kind of why we started, maybe he had some of these elements in there,
like some goggles and some things he sent away for that he thinks would help him out,
jumping into a mind and stuff.
And then, or maybe he starts dressing like Sasha a little bit,
maybe a little bit more Bauhaus-y, gets a little nicer.
And I thought I'd put a cast on him, it's like, oh yeah, asymmetry's cool.
And then Tim's like, oh, why has he got a cast?
We've got to write a story for that.
We have to, why did he break his arm?
And I was like, I wasn't even thinking about why.
So we didn't do that.
But ultimately, this was the design that we came up with.
And that was like millions, like hundreds and hundreds
and hundreds of drawings for this guy.
And one of the things that I have.
One of the things about, for me, as far as creative blocks and trying to get past certain things,
I blame a lot of stuff on maybe the tools I'm using. I'm very superstitious.
So there's times that I'll be drawing with pencil and paper and it's not going anywhere,
I can't come up with any good ideas, and I go to Tim, like,
this is pretty good, and he's all, eh, pretty good.
And I'm like, oh, and then I go back and I'm like, oh man, this pencil sucks, probably.
So then I go back and I grab all my markers and I'm like, and I start using markers and I'm like,
oh, right on. And then I get a couple good designs with markers.
Moments in the markers and I'm like, okay, I'm going to use paper bag and draw on paper bag for a while.
So in the beginning, I was doing a blaming that for a lot of stuff.
So that's why ultimately, I, after this, after I got this guy on paper bag, I was down paper bag for a while.
So.
And you know, and you gotta try out like drawing the characters in all the different positions and like not just drawing them in a pose
but then like trying them out like doing some of the things that you want them to do and see how the character works
and if it tells the story of who that person is. Like, this is She-
As you can see, I wasn't very organized with my character sheets there.
And then other times, certain characters are inspired by actual people.
Like Sasha was inspired by Kyle MacLachlan.
And Bobby Zilch was the bully in the game.
And he was inspired by Farkas.
So it was really angles.
But it was inspired by.
You pull the vibes from these guys.
You're not copying them.
You're pulling the energy from these dudes.
So he's a lot of weird angles.
That doesn't look like Farkas, really.
Anyways, and this is another one of the orderlies,
and he was inspired by Steve Buscemi.
And he put little notes on there to make sure they know
that he has very greasy hair.
Because you've got to give the modelers a lot of...
so maybe you can work together on shaping how the character is and stuff.
And if the programmer needs to have greasy hair tech,
then that's what needs to be done.
Okay. So here's the next game we're going to talk about.
Brutal Legend.
I wonder how many...
Okay, you guys are great. I'm really excited you're here.
So basically, Brutal Legend was a story of a roadie that's pulled back in time to the age of metal.
Which is, basically, it's a very...
It doesn't look like how it does in... Which is, of course, the Middle Ages, right?
But it's not how we think Middle Ages look. It's basically what all the album covers look like.
That's what the Middle Ages look like. Like, chrome volcanoes...
It's grown out the environments and stuff. It's just nuts because that's what's on on these covers and stuff. So
So that was so the elements that we need to pull from from this was a very different style so
so we definitely were looking at like current Frank Frazetta and
Just hot rod culture itself and just you know rock stars and all that all that jazz
tough jazz actually not jazz but
So these are all the things that we were kind of pulling from.
And in the beginning of a project, you want to surround yourself with as much reference as you can, like in the world.
I mean, I'm super addicted to the reference to the point where maybe it's a procrastination tool for me.
So we have a room at Double Fine where it's in the back
and we just cover the walls
with whatever we're getting pumped on.
And so in the pre-production phase for this,
we just cover the walls with,
Tim brought in his record collection,
we put in all these images from Nordic landscapes
and Frank Frazetta and all these barbarian things
and just amazing hot rod stuff we found.
And kind of just thought of what would be
in the heavy metal game
and just surrounded ourself with it.
Just surrounded every square inch.
And you sit in it.
And you take it in.
You take in this amazing room you created.
And this amazing world that you kind of...
And then you start kind of maybe making lists.
Because I start with making lots of lists.
And we all make lots of lists of just stuff that you would see in a crazy world like this.
You know?
So...
And then we had the basic...
The basic rule of putting...
If you design something like...
Yeah, it's a cool alligator or whatever, but what makes it specific to this world?
What makes it unique to this world?
And we had a blueprint of stuff because of this heavy metal and this amazing backstory that Tim wrote.
This huge, huge lore that starts from the beginning of time
when it's just a world covered in mud and writhing creatures.
That's like epic backstory.
That's not just like, my mom grew up here, you know?
It's crazy.
So he had all the reasons why this world was how it was, and why the world was growing
exhaust pipes, and why it had oil that you could, you know...
Well, actually, I guess we have oil we could mine.
don't we, fossil fuel?
Anyways, there's more badass versions of that in this world.
So the test was always, you put it on a heavy metal cover,
and if it will be cool enough for Motorhead
to put on their record cover or something, then it's cool.
If you don't think those guys are going to like it
on their record, then it's not a good design.
It's one of our rules, you guys.
So in the beginning, we kind of just threw out a lot of drawings,
and it just existed.
I didn't do this cartoony one here. This is Raz Madeline, who's amazing.
In the beginning, we were trying to go the extreme of figuring out which, what style we want to push, like these characters and everything.
So we were just drawing tons of crazy stuff.
And one of the lessons that we learned with Psychonauts was you don't start with the main dude.
You start with the cast of dudes and the cast of ladies and kind of get your style there and get your world there,
and then see who would work as a charismatic lead, you know?
So that's what we did here.
came up with all these creatures and put them together in groups and we're like,
okay, this is gonna be great, we're gonna,
this is gonna be how the world is gonna be, you know?
And then we're like, okay, now who's gonna be a good leader
in this group? And
the roadie
himself,
that character, Tim was always basing it
on this fellow right here.
Which, his name is Lemmy.
He's, he was based on him because he's the most respected dude in metal, he's like...
a real legit dude. Because he started out as a roadie
and then he became a rockstar after that. So he's just very respected, people are like,
dude,
he knows everything about everything. You're like, dude, well I don't know if he knows everything about everything, but
you trust him to take care of you, man, because he knows his stuff.
Because look at him. He's cool, right? And he always wears the same outfits.
Because he knows those are cool outfits.
So in the beginning we were kind of trying to have it be inspired, the main character inspired by Lemmy, you know.
So, and we were trying to pushing the proportions and see how stylish we wanted it, how realistic we wanted it.
And I did a lot of design work in meetings and stuff, so that's why there's a lot of binder paper ones.
And we kind of were trying him out in the things that we'd need him to do, you know, the situations.
Like he would need to be a respected roadie, on one hand.
You know, tell him dudes what to do.
And then he'd need to command demon armies with his demon wings.
Also. So he has to be able to do both those things, you guys.
And he looks pretty badass, right? Doing this?
These paintings are cool. Yeah, nice.
Let's take him in for a sec, you guys.
Okay.
But as we were kind of trying to figure out how the game would work and how you'd tell the story...
you kind of like, you're thinking like,
the main character comes back to this world,
it's like, you as a character,
you as a player, want to play this person.
You have to want to play this main character
experiencing this new world.
This is a new world that's amazing.
This is a fantasy world for any metalhead,
you know, any fan of metal.
But we kept on thinking, the more we were kind of,
we wanted to be, there should be a little bit of emotion
in this guy, the main character.
And as much as we wanted it to be like Lemmy,
he just looked like he's almost too cool.
to experience it like we would all experience it.
Like if he saw a volcano running down a monster back that's like,
you know, has
metal shards pouring out of his insides,
like he'd be like, dope.
Like we'd be like, that's crazy.
But it seems like he'd be like, oh yeah,
yeah, that's what's happening there, I know that, that's real.
And it's like...
And that's like no fun to play a guy like that, really, you know?
Because you want to kind of get excited.
That's kind of why Harry Potter is so rad.
I'm a fan of Harry Potter.
Because he goes into this magical world,
and you as a reader, you're reading along with him.
Everything he sees is crazy,
and he's getting excited about everything,
and you as a player want to feel that.
So it's like, and not only that, but he's the most important dude in that world.
That's like Fantasyland, you know?
And the same with Luke Skywalker.
You know that guy?
So anyways, so that's kind of like what we wanted.
So then we started looking more at Jack Black,
just because he would get pumped on it.
But he would kind of try to hold it in,
but he would also show that he knows his stuff.
He's a connoisseur of metal,
and he's actually badass at metal.
At playing it, performing it.
So we kind of went back towards that kind of vibe.
So that's kind of where we went more towards that,
and then kind of...
came up with this dude. Threw a little Danzig in there with him.
And he made him a little buffer than Jack Black.
And that's cool. We tried him out with some other characters.
He worked out pretty good with some of these other guys hanging out.
And then we put them, we did these these paintings to show off like how the
gameplay might work and what situations you might work in.
And it works good. There he is, riding that dude.
Let me see how...
I've got my trusty thing here.
Oh.
Okay.
What?
Okay. Sorry, you guys.
Back behind the scenes.
Um...
So I think we need to...
I need to kind of get... move on pretty quick.
I'll go by this really quick.
So one of the... some of the other characters in Brutal Legend that were...
were like, uh...
We're actually... what time...
What time do we got?
Forty minutes.
Fantastic. Okay, then we'll just skip this stuff.
Hey, I'm doing some rambling, you guys. I didn't see my thing here.
But anyways, this is another character, Ophelia.
She was...
Anyways, we'll skip Ophelia.
Here's some of the drawings of Ophelia, you guys.
I mean, basically, we were trying to make her gothy, and she sacrifices herself in the
Sea of Black Tears, and she rises up again as a phoenix.
So she would need to fly and command armies, too.
So we were trying all these elements on her, and then we decided that the sea itself would
kind of create her outfit, rather than create all these nice outfits.
That was the special thing there.
And then for the hair metal dude, he had to also fly, and it would make sense to have
his hair, because it's such a big part of his character.
That's the big part of flying.
Okay, so really quick, I'm going to go through this really quick.
Because we've got to get to drawing.
So this is how I work.
So I gather lots of reference.
By the way, this is one of the characters from our new game.
yeah, a broken age, you guys, where I would just collect like
photos and just crafts
and any paintings and anything that would make me feel a certain way and feel really good
and relax to start drawing and coming up with ideas and stuff. Because I just want to relax myself
as much as possible.
this is not from that game, but
this is what, typically what, like
how I come up with ideas, I just make
lots of lists, and I just jot down
stuff, and I just kind of let things flow
however, you know, the list could be about anything, whatever
you know, as long as I'm able to relax
myself, and I use Xerox paper
in order to kind of relax myself, because I
sketchbooks kind of stress the quality of it, it makes
it, makes me relax a little bit more, so
so I do, so I do this
sort of thing, and just kind of let it go, let it go
and then
Gestures out of like how?
Shapes might work and I don't know like I try to just pump a million of these out
So not one of them is really important
You know like you're kind of just trying to get get the just ideas and the feelings out
So so these are just kind of ideas for this main character. She's she's in this village
These are also doubles villagers at this point. Yeah
And then we start to close in on some of the some of the characters and then
scanning them in and just putting some value in there and some letters so people can kind of point out the ones that they
Like and how what elements they like and then we could start to mix and match and put them together in other ways
And then start putting them in situations
you know like that they'd be in the game maybe and see how they'd work and
Narrow them down to a few and do some color ruffs
And this is when you kind of maybe I put a little bit more time into it, you know
And then we choose them, and then we choose one.
And then we kind of push that a little bit more, you guys.
And then I make a character sheet.
As you see, it's a really rough character sheet,
but you just get an idea, you guys.
Just get the gestures, because they're making it, right?
Some head stuff.
And this is how she turns out.
This is what she is like in the game.
All right.
So that's the talk portion.
Now we're going to do some drawing together, you guys.
And I have these three assignments for us.
And by the way, we'll do questions at the end.
I think I was supposed to say something else.
Oh yeah, turn off your cell phones.
You're going to get an email evaluation after the panel, so just, you know, give me lots
of good feedback.
Cool.
And for Q&A, we'll just come up to these mics, but we'll go to that later.
Okay, let's go back to the assignment.
Get out your drawing materials, everybody.
I've never done this before, but I think it'll be fun, right?
Woo!
It will be so fun.
So, these are the three assignments.
So, the first one is draw a sad creature that lives under a rock or in a hole.
The creature helps the player get past a raging river, somehow.
The creature has a weapon.
Sometimes this is as much information as you get, guys, on a character.
Number two, draw a scientist.
A scientist that is discovering an amazing, earth-shattering thing.
A very excitable person.
Longs for the world to experience the new thing.
Oh man, so excited.
Okay, and the third one is draw a sneaky golem.
An old, ugly dude that has no friends except for his collection of rocks.
And I've taken it upon myself to...
Gather a little bit of reference for each one.
This is my reference for the sad creature in their zone.
This is the scientist's reference.
And this is the golem reference.
So, who would like to do number one?
This guy here, sad creature.
Who would like to do the scientist?
Oh boy, this is going to be a close one.
And who wants to do the golem?
I might need some help figuring this out.
Please, dude, help me figure this out.
I can't figure...
Cheer.
Cheer?
Yeah.
Oh, that's a good way to get pumped, right?
Who wants to do this one?
The sad creature?
Sounds good.
Who wants to do the scientist?
So far, that's winning.
Who wants to do the golem?
Sounds like gong?
Yeah, that's hard too.
All right.
Let's do the gong, you guys.
So here's my drawing materials.
Oh wait, let me switch.
Oops.
Move over here, guy.
Move over here.
Oh, this is my spot.
So we're going to go back to this.
Here's my drawing utensils.
I usually just use this one though, you guys.
Right now. This is my feeling good one.
This is my 6B pencil.
Okay.
Let's get pumped.
Maybe I'll, okay, yeah, let's put on some music for us
to relax to.
Not so quiet.
Eh, eh.
Okay, okay.
Oh.
Join!
You guys are awesome.
Play my music...
If you don't like this music, that's too bad.
So I have this weird thing, see this is why I'm superstitious you guys, I have this old sketchbook from when I used to work at Lucas, 15 years ago or so.
And for some reason I like to draw on top of it.
Instead of the table.
Okay, let's get started here.
So we're doing the Golem right? Is that what we're doing?
Okay guys, I'm gonna go back and forth. This is how we're doing it.
This is what the reference looks like.
And this is me drawing.
Boy, am I procrastinating right now.
Okay.
So, there's this guy.
By the way, you guys are welcome to talk amongst yourselves too.
It's okay, that's what happens in the studio.
This is the biggest studio of all time.
So, SneakyGone, he's an ugly dude, and he has no friends but his rocks.
I decided he's going to be a rock dude already.
First thing I do, is do some copying.
So I can relax a little bit.
Oh, is this the mic?
This is a sad guy.
I don't know if this dude in the corner...
Oh, you can't even see him.
The dude in the corner seems like kind of a weird...
kind of a weird bearded golem.
I don't know, he doesn't really strike me as a golem, but I'm enjoying him anyways.
So, okay.
Maybe these are some of the rocks he can dig.
Some other stuff.
Probably put in lots of geodes.
Those are cool, man.
That's where you put your little pew direction figures in.
This is a geode.
Maybe, maybe he lives in it.
That's pretty cute.
He's sad, but he wouldn't mind a visitor.
Yeah, I know.
Just because he's gotten new friends and he's sneaky doesn't mean he's a bad guy.
Yeah, he can be sneaky and a good guy.
Right? Right, everybody?
Maybe he's in his jailed.
He likes crystals too. Maybe not.
He seems like more of a stone dude.
The light works.
That's how it goes.
It's just the idea of phase.
Sometimes, maybe in this world, light works different.
We don't know. We don't know, you guys.
Is that a dude?
It's made of rock.
See?
I'm just kidding, I'll probably scan all this in and try to use some of it.
I usually just scan this stuff in and if I like how a drawing looks, or a dude looks,
sometimes it's hard to reproduce it, I'll just scan it in and trace it.
I'll blow it up.
That looks a little...
Maybe that's him.
This is Rock. This guy likes crystals.
There's also this guy.
You guys know the dude on the top right, right?
From that movie Gollum?
Derek Gollum, I think it's called.
It's that silent film.
It's cool.
Check it out.
What I always think of that dude,
and he has this amazing shaped head
that I'm not going to rip off.
Oh man, I'm glad you guys chose Gollum. This guy's cool.
But he's sneaky though, so maybe he's...
You guys drawing? Who's drawing?
Yes!
Who's excited about it?
You guys are good at cutting off exactly the right moment.
By the way, I don't wanna get your guys' hopes up.
We're not gonna see a finished, amazing character today.
We're just gonna get some ideas out.
Because usually I would probably just scan it in
and try to make it amazing.
But you know what?
Why sell myself short?
Maybe it's gonna be amazing.
I'd love to see the ones you guys do later.
Also, if we can figure out how to do that.
This is how you know he's made of stone.
You gotta put the stone stuff.
Cracks.
Otherwise he's just a gnome.
Okay.
Yeah, cause he's sneaky.
Hm.
Music's nice.
Let that music relax you guys.
How do you do that on top?
Cool.
Music.
This guy seems sneaky.
Okay.
I'll let you guys look at this for a bit.
Checking you guys out.
Alright.
I'll let you guys look at this for a bit.
Checking you guys out.
Heaven is in your eyes
Brighter than stars you're under
Right, I'm gonna switch it back.
I'm doing the list, again.
Just places you might be hanging out.
Over the night, forget it
I'm in the mood
What I like to do sometimes is make a list of just things that...
just kind of riff on words that might remind me of the other word in a way.
Because then that could... it's like an improv thing.
I do improv as well, you guys.
Which is a really good thing, tool, creative tool for people to write and illustrate.
But, um, if you...
If you let yourself stream of consciousness,
like write down words, and start with some that,
and some of them might have something to do
with what you're designing,
and some of them might not have anything to do with it,
but you're just kind of flowing,
because you don't know what this list might bring you to.
You know what I mean?
Like it might bring you to an idea
that might be cool or something.
Or to keep in mind these elements
as you're drawing a dude, you know?
That's works for me at least, you guys.
Might not work for you.
I'm just gonna write that word for me to feel good.
Okay.
I'm really stuck on giving him rocks to hold for some reason.
What is?
So this guy might have been a boy that was turned into a rock, I'll call him, and he's cursed.
Hmm.
That's all there's about to lose here.
Maybe a skin.
So what's the deal with golems again?
Wait, are golems like a cursed dude or is it a dude like a Frankenstein?
It's like Frankenstein, right?
Made out of clay.
Dude, interesting. I should research that one.
What?
Yeah, man. That's good. So they're made out of clay...
And they're like a Frankenstein dude.
Okay. I was going more with made out of rock than with cursed.
Hey, that's cool.
Teaches his own right in the world of Gollum's.
I like it. Do some chatting.
Five minutes trying? Okay.
As you can see, this is all just coming up with ideas, you guys. That's all.
I keep getting all the same things.
I don't know what to think about that.
Oh, it's from that? I don't know if it's from that.
I know these guys are really sneaky though.
Maybe he's wearing an algae shirt.
Because I wrote that down.
On a list.
Does that give me much more than that?
It gives me so much more.
Maybe he's wearing a rock hat.
Where's his collection?
He's wearing it.
Alright, well it's not an amazing design you guys, but hey, it gives an idea.
I don't know what I'm reading right now, okay.
So this is considered just the first pass, you guys.
First pass, if you get like an assignment like this,
this is how you just kind of get in the zone.
And you scan all these in.
See, I'm just, I'm quantiting up quality at this point.
Because it doesn't matter, just like, we're just trying to get some stuff out.
Oh, here's what this guy looks like.
Um.
And then you kind of do that pass and you scan these in and kind of try to arrange them nicely.
And maybe put a little bit of shading in there so people can think I put a lot more work into it.
And then send it to them and just kind of bombard them with stuff.
And then there's a second pass, third pass, fourth pass, fifth pass, six, seven, eight, nine, ten, maybe twenty-five thousand passes.
Perhaps. That's how it works sometimes.
And sometimes, maybe just once.
But almost never.
I have only nailed a character once in my life.
Right away.
Do you know who that is?
It was because it was the first...
Only because we...
Tim wrote a character based on this guy.
It was one of the first drawings I ever drew.
When I started at Double Frame.
working at Cyclone Ops, the first character I ever...
only one that nailed in the first drawing was Dogen.
I drew a character that looked like this character, Dogen.
This guy with a cap on his head.
That was like one of the first drawings I drew.
And he made it into the game exactly like that.
Only time in my life that a character is the first drawing.
I think.
This dude's probably blind, right?
Yeah, maybe he has a tail, I don't know.
Looking good.
All right, we'll do a couple more sketches and then we'll do some questions and chatting
together.
Continuing through the North, South and South subscribing to slavery.
Fatality is the biggest crime in history.
To get out of depression and go into sex work is detrimental.
For more UN videos visit www.un.org
I don't know what that is.
Maybe he's a...
There he is, he's moving along.
Hi you guys.
I guess this GOM I'll just make this GOM be him.
Give him some algae.
Um, anyways you guys, I think, I think we'll uh, oh here's the full thing.
I think we will...
Conclude this part and then maybe have some questions. What do you think?
That sound good?
How good is it sound?
Nice.
Most exciting one ever.
Okay, so thanks you guys for hanging out.
We'll do some questions now.
If you guys can, like, cruise up to these two mics,
and we'll just go back and forth or whatever.
Probably the easiest, and then everyone can hear your questions and stuff.
So, feel free to make your way up there whenever you want.
At your leisure.
And you can give a question about anything.
About drawing, how you do it.
Hi.
I'm Elise.
I guess that also involves a little bit of creative block.
I'm sorry, say again?
Maybe speak a little bit into the microphone.
Sorry.
I'm Elise.
I'm talking to a lot of people. Hi!
Thanks for being the first one. You're the best.
Yeah.
Oh wait, here's a consolation prize. You can have one of these for being the first person.
Oh, thanks.
So you briefly talked about creator's block and how you tried different materials and one of them was the paper bag.
Yeah.
I was also wondering if you could talk about further from that, like, discouragement.
Like, you're really working hard and you just can't get further.
You know what? It's weird. I think, like...
Let me turn off this music. I don't think we need this anymore.
Okay, I think... I don't think anyone really knows.
I think everyone hits writer's block and everyone struggles through it and no one knows exactly how, but you just try different things.
Sometimes if I'm hitting a block on a character
and I can't get past it and I find myself drawing
the same shapes and the same things
and I'm just getting so frustrated
because there's elements that I want to keep
that was approved other times and stuff,
sometimes I'll just get away from it
and come at it completely different.
I draw a completely different design,
think about it completely differently
just to shake my mind away
from that other thing that I'm married to.
Like that's something that oftentimes helps me out.
And then other times you just have to keep the faith, kind of.
Because you're just going to, sometimes you're just going to get...
I've had many times where I get pretty depressed
trying to design a character and it's not going well.
And then you're just kind of...
But then when you finally get something that's awesome, then it's good.
So...
Yeah, thank you.
Oh, wait, here, you can have one of these drawings.
Have one of these drawings.
Go ahead and choose one.
Oh wait, choose one, choose one.
You gotta choose one.
Just in case I want to give, just choose one.
Oh, just pick one. Oh, okay.
Whichever one you want.
Can I make lists, too?
Yes.
Hi, my name is Rebecca.
Thank you so much for this talk, it was really inspirational.
I had a similar question, so I came up with another.
Have you ever been in a situation where you've had to draw something completely outside of your usual style?
How do you find the motivation to switch styles?
Maybe not necessarily on the fly, but having to do something that's outside of your usual scope?
I think that's why in school, you're supposed to really study all types of drawing and be able to draw realistic.
I went to school to draw X-Men. That's what I wanted to do.
and draw fantasy paintings like Frank Frazetta and stuff.
So I was really into drawing realistic and really sticking to that.
But after that, being exposed to different art through friends,
I kind of enjoyed seeing how other people interpret stuff.
So I guess it's getting the basics down and then seeing,
just being really versatile, you know, being able to do it.
Like after Psychonauts, that was basically like my style
that I'd normally work in, but...
Fruital Legend, like everyone had to switch to that very Frazetta style.
And when you're working in a game company or a film company, you have to be able to,
you just have to be able to do it.
So, and if you're not pumped on it, you just, you gotta find what makes you pumped about it.
Because there's gotta be something about it.
Something. You put a little, little, little logo in there.
A little touch-up.
Put your initials, I don't know.
Yeah. Alright, thank you so much.
You're welcome.
My name's Byron, and the question that I have is,
when you run into a specific problem,
like something that your training hasn't covered,
and you need a technique to get around it,
where do you look to find the answers?
I'm sorry, say again?
So, like, let's say you run into a material
that you need to render that you've never done before,
so, like, a building made out of glass
or something like that.
Where would you look to find the techniques
to achieve that goal?
to achieve a design for something I don't know much about?
I mean, that's always what I do before I do any drawing at all, is just start to do tons of research and stuff.
I mean, I get, I pull a lot from Google image, you know, search, and then like sometimes those will take you to other web pages,
and you can find more images, and you can read about it and stuff.
So, I mean, I, there's, sometimes I do it for a whole like three, four, five days before I start any drawing.
I'll just do that for a while to kind of get a feel for it.
Is that one, In Cold Blood, where Truman Capote spent like...
nine months before writing a word or something like that.
Like he spent nine months just researching and getting ready
and his publisher's always like,
do you have anything to show for it?
He's like, I'm still getting, you know,
I'm getting and taking it in, you know?
So sometimes when you got a deadline though,
then you need to kind of speed that up.
Thank you.
No problem.
Hey, how's it going?
There's some other people over here too, just saying.
Say again?
Oh, there's some other people over here.
Oh, dude, sorry.
You can take her first.
I'll go back and forth.
Yeah, you guys, okay.
Okay, you wanna go?
I can.
Hi, Scott, my name is Fiona.
Hi, Fiona.
Hi, I was just wondering if you could talk a little bit
about the process of working with a director
to create a character.
Working with a director?
Mm-hmm.
Yeah, okay, sure.
I was fortunate enough to work mostly with Tim Schafer on these things, and he's just
the most amazing person ever to work for on that, because he cares so much about the character
and the backstory and just the overall character arcs of these characters. And he has great
taste. He has great taste in visual things as well. And I was kind of fortunate enough
to work with him, because we jived a lot, and we were able to...
you know, make each other laugh and have a good time.
So I guess in that sense, but whenever I found myself
like wanting to make him feel good and laugh at my drawings
or get pumped or punch the air or something.
And it's the sort of thing.
There are certain assignments that suck. There are certain assignments that you kind of have to like go for it.
And I would just go into his office and be like, oh dude, look at this.
And if he's ever like kind of lukewarm on it, then it's like you could use that.
But you know that he's just not going to be pumped on it.
So I just want to  I love the editing process. I love redrawing things.
And to a point.
I love redrawing things, and I love,
because I want it to make it good, you know?
I want to make it, I want everyone to enjoy it,
and I want to reshape things and make it really good, so.
And that works well with kids' books and stuff, too,
because the editing process,
a lot of artists go in just from art,
and they're like, dude, this is what I draw.
This is what I do.
You know, you don't tell me what I'm awesome at, you know?
And they don't take editing process well,
and that's kind of what is exciting to me, I don't know.
So I love working with directors, personally.
Thank you.
Oh, okay.
Hey.
Sup, man.
Super weird.
So my name is Vincent.
Thanks for the talk, Scott.
I'm just wondering because your work's really humorous
and always really funny, and I was just wondering,
like, do you use that, like, the humor lens to, like,
when you're designing something that's not really funny
or serious, like, is it more of a challenge for you
to design something like, maybe some of the stuff
on Brutal Legend, or even things like props
that aren't really, don't really have character.
Like, how do you use that in your work?
Yeah, well, I mean, I don't know, I guess, um,
I guess there's always a little bit of humor in there,
but there were times in Brutal Legend that it was,
I was researching some pretty terrifying stuff,
and drawing some pretty terrifying stuff.
Um, I felt like during that time,
my outside work, my paintings,
got cuter and cuter,
the more deeper I got into this terrifying world a little bit.
So, it's just like, finding ways to balance that stuff, you know?
Um, but I think, I don't know.
I like scary movies. I don't like sad movies though, I'll be honest.
Cool, thanks. Thanks man.
Hi. Oh, there's one over there too? I'm sorry.
Maybe you guys, if you want to come to these two, maybe you can make it easier on me, but let's do this one now.
I'm doing good. Psychonauts is one of my favorite all-time games, and part of it is because the visuals and the story just combine wonderfully together. I feel like if you change the element of either the tone of the story or the visual graphics, it just wouldn't have meshed quite as well. So how much did you work with the narrative team on creating that game, and how did that work out?
That was art director on Psychonauts.
So I was just, and the,
so I was working very closely with Tim,
but Tim creates a really amazing environment
where he could like, where he kind of welcomes everyone
to kind of brainstorm together.
And so the, you know, the designers and the game designers
and the artists and himself and the programmers,
even everybody kind of gets involved
and kind of get to have ideas to throw around
and just kind of, it's like a think tank there.
So it was in tandem. It wasn't like you created the characters and then somebody else was creating the dialogue for that character.
It was all kind of happening at the same time.
It usually starts with like a little snippet of information that Tim has or the game design people have.
Like for, we need a character like this here, you know. And then I'll start doing some drawings.
And then Tim might start writing a story around it or he'll write a story.
Some of you guys might know the story of how the camp kids were created the opposite direction.
Because Tim and I would always go to each other and be like, dude, like, you know, write
something first.
And he's like, no, just draw something.
And I'll write something to that.
Like, there's like a little bit of like back and forth that kind of sometimes.
kids in this camp, a whole bunch of different kids, and he was creating kind of their backstory,
and what he decided for that is, like, he, I just drew a bunch of kids, and he laid them
out, and he was like, one of his deliverables he had to come up with, like, a way to write
all these characters out, and he was getting frustrated doing his stuff, he's procrastinating
by going on Friendster back in the day, Friendster is the thing, and, and what he just, what
he, what he figured out was a way to use that to his advantage, and he put all the camp
kids into Friendster.
and then he wrote their personalities
and he had them comment on each other's posts
in a way that kind of let their characters rise up
and become more apparent and stuff.
So it really goes back and forth.
I mean, that process is really a back and forth thing
and you never know when the story element
will come out of drawing something and vice versa.
Okay, thank you.
Yeah, thank you, you're welcome.
Thank you.
Okay.
That was totally my question too.
Wait, that was your question?
Oh, sweet.
Thanks for coming up here.
But I feel like I worked that, I mean, I feel like one of my first lessons I learned in the entertainment industry
was I started working at Lucas Learning, which is like a small
part of LucasArts, and our first game
that I worked on, I was excited. It was a Star Wars game, it was great,
and I was just like, my first job, and it was only a year process for this game, and two weeks before it ended,
they canceled it.
And I was like,
totally heartbroken. I was like, dude, I put so much energy into this. This is crazy, you know?
And then that was just like the first lesson on how things sometimes go.
You can't be married to something that much, you know?
And sometimes you might love something, but then it's just not exactly right.
It's not exactly right for what the situation calls for in the movie or the game or whatever, you know?
It's just, you know, so even though you love it,
maybe you could use that to inspire a slightly different design or use it somewhere else or something.
But like, you kind of just have to...
roll with those punches.
Have you ever felt like it was really right and that the other person was wrong and
you just kind of swallow it?
If I'm the art director and I think it's the best and it's someone maybe that is like
if it's Tim deciding that, then yeah, Tim makes that decision. But maybe I can make a few more decisions
as art director.
But if I'm just designing something, you're designing something for
the greater good, you guys.
You can't get too married to that stuff.
Because, you know what?
You're going to draw amazing stuff all the time.
In an hour, you can't be married to this one thing.
Like, this is my crown jewel thing.
I shall never create anything as amazing.
It's not going to happen, you know?
And it's kind of not a good way of thinking about that.
Thank you.
No problem.
Thank you, man.
Oh, I didn't catch your guys' names.
Say your name too so I can hear you.
Hi, my name is Samantha. I was just asking about like you said you use a lot of reference and you gather a lot of reference.
Have you ever gotten an idea during creating a character that you go outside of your reference?
Say again?
Oh, well you gather a lot of reference when you make a character.
Has there ever been a point where in any of your character designs that you go outside of the reference that you gathered for like a good idea?
Well, I guess gathering references is an ongoing thing.
I guess it comes from anything.
I mean, you gather it from the internet, but you might be working on it and then you watch
a movie and you're like, damn, that kind of inspires you.
So you kind of just keep adding to the pile of stuff all the time.
It's not like it's a set time, like this day is my reference day.
after this day, no more reference.
Just keep adding to it.
Keep adding to it and have more stuff,
whatever works for you.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Hi, I'm Adam.
Great talk. Thank you.
I was just going to ask you about your process
when you're designing characters
in the initial phase.
Do you find that when you're drawing you find one character or design that you really really like and you instantly know or is it a process that requires a lot of deliberation to land on the right one?
Most times, yeah. I rarely am just like, this is the one. And if I do, it's just like, you know, I'm not married to it. As we've discussed.
That's my experience as well. Thank you.
Oh, cool, man. Good.
All right.
We're at time?
Yeah.
Right now?
We were trying to go over.
But if you want to ask more questions.
Okay.
You guys.
Sorry about that.
And thank you.
Okay.
Thank you.