Hello, everyone.
Just as a reminder before I start my talk, turn off your
cell phones and fill out the surveys that they
give you through email.
And so I'm going to get this talk rolling.
So I'm going to be talking about single player versus
multiplayer level design, and the paradigm shift that kind
of occurs when you're thinking about
designing between each one.
First of all, who am I?
My name is Elizabeth Beinke-Schwartz, and I'm a
level designer at a company in Austin, Texas called
Certain Affinity.
and I got my start working on the MMORPG,
Lord of the Rings Online, the Minds of Mora expansion pack.
And since then, I've worked on a bunch of different
single player and multiplayer titles,
including Bioshock Infinite, Mafia III and Doom,
and Call of Duty Modern Warfare Remaster.
And so what I will be covering today
is what is based on my own experience
coming from a single player,
highly narratively linear background.
designing stuff like for Bioshock Infinite and then
moving over to working at Certain Affinity and designing more multiplayer levels, especially for a first-person shooter design like for the
new Steam game that came out. Certain Affinity helped with
with some of the multiplayer for that and so
I came from a very narrative-heavy single-player background,
and I was very surprised when I started designing levels for multiplayer
about a lot of the differences.
There are some similarities, but there was a lot of things
I was used to putting a lot of time into in single-player levels
that I didn't need to in multiplayer.
And comparatively, things where I found out need to be paid a lot of attention to
when you design for a multiplayer level
that you don't really need to think about as much.
when you're designing a single player level.
So this talk is based on my own experiences,
kind of a, if you're gonna switch in between the two
and learn what similarities there are
and what differences there are.
So first of all, when you are starting to design the layouts for a space, obviously,
you need to plan for the size of your level.
And in single player, the things that go into figuring out how you're—
the size that you're going to design for is, you know,
how many combats are you going to be supporting in that space?
What are the sizes of those combats?
Are there going to be any big narrative set pieces in that level?
any traversal conversations, like for example if you need to support
smaller narrative moments where maybe, for example on Bioshock Infinite,
the player as Booker is talking with Elizabeth and they're walking and having a conversation and you're learning narrative moments
and so you want to think about designing a space that's a quiet moment.
where it doesn't intersect into combat or other elements like that.
And so thinking about the sizing there
and any additional side quests or content that you might want to add in there.
Whereas in multiplayer, the biggest thing when you're thinking about the level size is obviously
what is the game you're working on, how many players does it support,
are you designing for like a 2v2 level or a 64x64,
and also what is the intended time until engagement.
Is the game you're designing a game like Doom where it's almost immediate interaction and combat
and you just go, go, go?
Or are you designing a level for a smaller, slower, sorry, larger, slower-paced level
where you want to have a bit more space before the player encounters another enemy
so that they can get a sense of the battlefield and their options and a bit more of a tactical feel?
And once you've had a general idea of how big you want to
make your level.
There's a couple differences between the things you have to think about when you are designing
and framing and composition of the level overall.
So the biggest focus in single player, especially if you're working on a very narrative level,
is storytelling.
Storytelling is really important.
As some of the previous speakers talked about, trying to find any little moment that you
can tell the story in the level is really important.
and also supporting any gameplay objectives.
Steve touched on this a little bit about making sure the player knows
where they're going, like where they're trying to get to,
and making sure that's clear for the player is really important.
Whereas in multiplayer...
the biggest things isn't really storytelling as much,
and that was a big change for me.
Coming from working at Irrational,
it was all like, story, story, story,
how can we put story into every little bit element
of the space, whereas in some multiplayer games
do have a bit of story, but it's not as important,
and it's almost a waste of time to spend.
spend your time working and thinking about that element.
Whereas the more important things in multiplayer are more,
what are your player routes and paths
and options for the player to move around the space?
And also, something that's more important in multiplayer,
but not as important in single player,
is tightening up all the sight lines
and making sure that you fix any and all exploits
that you can before it gets out there live.
And so I'm gonna kind of break this down a little bit more.
So when I was talking about telling a story,
and using any opportunity you can to tell a story,
is you need to identify or create situations that really
frame narrative moments.
And so think about when you are designing a level that
doesn't have cut scenes.
what are the times where the player will definitely
be looking at a certain location and identifying those
and making sure that you use the crap out of that moment.
So some examples of this would be like in the image here,
when the player is exiting a room,
you know that the player is going to be looking at that door
and putting all this narrative moments.
around the door or say you're exiting the door, what do you see when you exit that door?
And some more examples of this are if the player is stuck in an elevator moving up or
down, maybe they are climbing up a ladder and that moment where they exit the ladder,
what will they see?
Identifying those moments is really important when you're designing a level.
either creating those moments or using those moments.
Also, when you are designing the space
to support narrative moments,
thinking about using things like a T-junction
to have an opportunity to show narrative.
bits to the player. For example, here, this is a T-junction where the player has entered
and they have the option of going left or right, and so putting the narrative elements
right at the base so the player will see it no matter which path they choose is a better
option than putting it in one area or another because you don't know whether the player
is going to see it or not.
And besides narrative, also making sure gameplay objectives are clear is super important in single player.
There's this idea that was coined by Walt Disney called weenies.
It's based on the concept that his dog used to follow him around when he had a hot dog or weenie,
and he noticed that the dog would follow him around and it would...
it was a way to guide the dog to certain places he wanted to.
So he used that terminology when designing theme parks,
like for example, Cinderella's Castle in Disney World, etc.
It's this visually distinctive thing that you can see,
and you can use that as a point of reference.
So in this example from Infinite,
you are exiting this small space.
the first thing you see is this statue of an angel,
and you know from past knowledge that
the young woman, Elizabeth, is in that tower,
the angel tower, and that's where you need to get to.
But you don't really, might not know how to get there yet,
but at least you know where you're going.
And on the image to the right,
it gives you an idea of the fact
that you can kind of see this angel statue from anywhere.
you are guided towards that space.
And so making sure you identify moments
like exiting rooms or things to display relevant narrative
or gameplay objectives is super important in single player.
Whereas in multiplayer,
framing is still really important,
but you're kind of framing different things.
You are thinking about
Making clear the player path options that they have so that players when they're running around the space
They can make split-second decisions of where they're going to be going and also it's really important to
guide
To make clear where the paths are going to be leading
Some some multiplayer levels you you might turn a path and you think you're going a certain direction and you get frustrated
Because it leads you somewhere else where you don't intend and that's not really the best
design of a space when you're designing a multiplayer level.
But for example here, this is an image of Zanzibar from Halo, and on the bottom right
you can see that there's a path framed on the side with the sand that kind of leads
up.
giving you the impression that you're going into the second layer of this building here,
but you also know that you can see the path up on the left coming out from the building,
so you know that somebody might be coming into the building from that left upper path as well.
Making sure that the options the player has to move around the space and strategically
where other enemies will be is the most important thing when designing a multiplayer level.
And the biggest change that I had to think about when I started designing multiplayer levels
is really paying a lot more attention to sight lines.
In single player, it can be kind of fun to find that teeny little spot where you can get an advantage
over an NPC and they don't see you and you feel like...
It's rewarding and fun because the enemy doesn't have feelings.
But in multiplayer, the enemy you're killing has feelings, they're a real person, and they
get frustrated if they don't, they die and they don't understand why.
In a multiplayer game it's important to understand why you died and...
feel like the players should feel like it's their fault that they made a mistake that they died and
not that there's some gaming of the system that feels unfair and so watching out for untimely
sight lines is super important and I have an example here of one of an early level I had done
and there was a small room.
where you could enter from either door,
which is the brown blocks there.
But if you enter down from the bottom
and walked up the stairs around those hexagonal pillars,
the player could have an unattended sight line
where they could look in between the two pillars
and get this teeny little sight line out of the door
and just snipe or shoot anyone
who was running around outside the door.
And the people who are running around outside were like,
what the heck?
Where did I die from?
I don't know.
And because the people outside can't really see in, and they
don't really see that there is an enemy in there.
And so I had to adjust this to block off that sight line.
And so a lot more time goes into really nailing down these
sight lines when you're designing a multiplayer map.
And once you have the base map designed,
obviously you want to start thinking about optional
or more advanced player routes.
And so in single player,
the additional routes can be used to.
give additional story elements to the player.
For example, this is a small basement
in a bar in the level Finkton,
and it's very out of the way,
but what happens is there's a guitar that's...
on a chair and the player can interact with it.
And what happens if you interact with it
is the player Booker starts playing,
strumming a guitar and Elizabeth there,
she starts singing this kind of melancholy song
about how the circle will never be unbroken,
kind of talking about like the chain of oppression
and people being poor and it being really difficult
to get out of that situation.
And she...
takes this orange and gives it to this little kid here.
And so it's a really poignant little teeny side moment
that a lot of players might not see,
but it can be fun to design and add these little elements
in your game.
And it can feel very rewarding as a player
to find these teeny little tidbits
and support additional narrative initiatives
or the feel of the level.
But you also have to think about what happens if the
player misses this.
Do we have the money and the resources to
support these moments?
Because in single player, at least more linear single
player levels, players often only play once.
And so is it OK if players miss this content?
And that's something that you have to think about a lot more
than when you're designing a multiplayer game.
game level because people will be playing those over and over again.
And obviously you can also use additional areas
in single-player to additional loot or other narrative elements as well.
Another thing that you have to consider
when designing a single-player level
is will the AI play nice if you add different types
of ways of interacting with the levels.
So it's great in single-player and multiplayer
to design spaces that support multiple play styles.
Maybe you want to design for stealth players
or you want to design for run-and-gun.
just go and shoot everyone, action folks, or sniping,
but you have to think about,
will the AI play nice with that?
So an example I use here on the left is Deus Ex,
where you can go in the vents and run around
and use those as a stealthy way of getting around.
And it's appealing to add these additional routes
to support stealth gameplay,
but you have to think about,
is the game you're making, will...
that support this type of play style,
because what happens if you shoot the enemy
through the vents, but the enemy can't get to you?
What happens then?
Is that okay?
Is your game, is your levels supporting
that kind of gameplay style?
And on the right side over here,
I'm using this example from Far Cry 3,
because this is something that,
when I was playing through it, I,
felt kind of frustrated at.
There are these defensible areas that you have to go into
in the map and try to take them over.
But once I got the sniper, I would just sit on the ridge
and shoot every enemy before they could even get to me
because the AI didn't really play nice with the sniper
because the combats weren't designed
with AIs having snipers.
And so I had an advantage over them.
And the AIs would try to run towards me,
like in the path that you can see kind of in the back left,
there's like a route up.
But they have to take so long to get to you
that you just have so much of an advantage,
it's not really fun anymore.
And so when you're thinking about
adding sniper vantage points,
trying to restrict the spaces
that the players can have those sniper moments,
or thinking about how the AIs
will respond to those moments accordingly.
So when you're designing optional routes in multiplayer,
it's pretty much a necessity that you have to design more
than one route.
Because if players encounter each other, the same route over
and over again is really boring.
And because players are playing these levels over and
over again, you need to provide multiple routes and
options for the player.
And so I have a couple examples here.
The player can jump up on that platform and then double jump
onto the platform.
platform on the right, or they can just run straight on the ground and then
jump and then ledge grab up onto the right, or an even more advanced player
could jump onto that platform and then do a much more difficult jump to get to a very small side ledge and
have a different
angle and advantage over the players, but it's a lot more difficult
for players to get onto that ledge without falling off.
And so providing both simple and advanced ways
for players to get around is really important
in multiplayer.
Now, when you're thinking about pickups
in single player and multiplayer,
in single player, oftentimes you can design the level first
and add pickups later,
weapon placements or power-ups or
ammo to replenish
Any anything that you've lost
Which often is designed so that that happens after a big combat scene or right before a big combat?
The good thing about in single-player is you can use pickups to tell stories
You can instead of just plopping them anywhere thinking about okay. How did these items get here?
Who was here and you know?
Why are they gone now?
And using those to tell stories
and to support the overarching story of your game.
Whereas in multiplayer, you pretty much
have to design pickups at the same time
that you are designing the layout.
So pickups in multiplayer like a power-up or a power weapon
or something.
Like in this example in Doom here,
there are these things called runes
where they appear randomly after a certain amount of time.
in a level and players rush to it and once they the first person to pick up the rune turns into a
giant demon who has a lot more power over everyone than just an individual player would and so
the thing to consider when you're placing these is that they will change how the space
that the pickups are in and how they play. They will be both a draw
where a lot of combat will happen around these pickups and a lot of different angles
will need to be supported for entering to get to those pickups and
to support a larger combat space than just this teeny little teeny little location
And exploits is probably one of the biggest things to think
about when you're designing a level for multiplayer.
In single player, it's not super important.
If the player finds an exploit, besides people posting
silly videos and then it getting on Polygon or
something, there are pretty low consequences.
And sometimes it can even be fun to get those teeny little
exploits.
But in multiplayer, especially if you're designing a level
that might possibly be used for.
for competitive gameplay someday, it's critical to fix and it's super high consequences.
Players will find any exploit, it's just a matter of time and it's only fun for the individual,
but frustrating for everyone else and unfair for everyone else involved. And so a lot more time
and play testing needs to be taken to find and fix these exploits.
And now we get into playtesting, because playtesting for a single-player level
and playtesting for a multiplayer level are pretty different.
So when playtesting for single player, you really,
especially if it's a narrative linear game,
you only get one shot.
Each playtester only gets one first impression
of your level and how they initially react to things.
And that's very applicable to the fact that
players in the end game
The final product will only play at once and so you need to find more people to play
But you need to take more time to polish your level before you show it to anyone
Because a lot of playtesters
you know, normal gamers don't have the skill set to extrapolate earlier levels
into a more polished state, so they might get distracted by little elements,
and taking more time to polish a level before putting it in front of a player
will make sure to see if the subtle, nuanced level design structures,
or lighting, or framing, etc., will lead to them understanding...
what they're doing and why and the narrative of a level.
And so keeping them as pure and untainted as possible
is really critical.
I mean, one way to get around this is to find
find other devs on your team,
especially other level designers
who are good at extrapolating.
So if you need to, and you should,
get people to look at your level early,
then you should find those people who have the skill
to look at the base bare bones framework of a gray box
and being able to imagine what it's going to be
in its final state and not get distracted
by all the nitty gritty details
that don't really matter at that stage.
And so overall, when you are playtesting for single player,
you should make sure that players should
know what their motivation is, and they should always
know where they are.
They might not know how to get to where they are supposed
to be going right away, but they should always
have a frame of reference as to where they're going and not
get lost.
And so if players are lost, then you should probably fix it.
Whereas when playtesting for multiplayer, you really need
to playtest often and iterate often.
It's really necessary to get loads and loads of playtests
done, preferably every day if possible, get people in and
just playing through it.
You don't really need to spend as much time on polish as
compared to single player, because the biggest thing in
multiplayer is the layouts themselves.
And so you can get people in earlier on.
play testing. And the earlier you get players in, the more players can have the opportunity
to experience your level over and over again, because that's going to be closer to what the
polished end-shipped game is going to be like, where players are going to play over and over again.
So for multiplayer, first impressions aren't a huge deal.
If players aren't really sure where they're going, or if
they're slightly lost, or they aren't able to make a mental
map of the whole layout of the level, it's not a huge deal
because most.
A well-designed multiplayer map will guide players to the combat anyways,
and so as long as players initially encounter other players, it's fine.
And if they don't have the skills the first game that they play
to understand what the layout is, they'll get that.
They'll get that after playing it many times.
And so in singleplayer, it's a big deal to fix if players are lost,
but not as much in multiplayer.
So in summary, the biggest things to think about
when you are designing for single-player
and multiplayer levels, and where you should put
more of your time and your priorities.
So in single-player, you should really make sure
to sell the narrative, whereas in multiplayer,
narrative is generally low priority.
I got, this is one of the things that I had to unlearn
when designing for multiplayer levels.
I was designing a level and I,
I like to, when I first design a level, to think about a space of what is it?
What is the structure?
Who was there before the player got there?
What is the whole history of the design of the space and what was it being used for?
And in multiplayer, I got really bogged down with thinking of all those teeny little details
that don't really matter and don't have a huge impact on the end result.
Not to say that teeny little narrative elements can't add a little bit to a level, but
you don't need to spend much time on that in multiplayer. But in single player and multiplayer,
they do share a similar element that they both need to make sure that they frame, you know,
optional routes and gameplay objectives.
And in single player, you need to design optional routes
to support any rewards that you give the player,
whether that's a narrative tidbit, or a pickup,
or something like that, and support optional play
styles as well.
And in multiplayer, you also need
to support multiple play styles, and that's even more important.
and make sure to design routes for more advanced players
so those advanced players feel a sense of progression
and that they're not just playing the same level
over and over again, but they can find additional routes
to evolve through the level
and get a fair advantage over players,
not like the sightline issue I was showing earlier,
but fair and visible advantages over other players.
And when you're playtesting single player, you playtest
less and polish more in between.
And in multiplayer, you playtest as often as possible
and make sure to repeat your playtesters.
And most important, fix exploits and sightlines
in multiplayer, because in single player,
they're pretty low priority.
And so these are a bunch of the things
that you have to think about when
you are designing for different experiences
in single player and multiplayer.
And a lot of the skill sets you learn from one
are applicable to the other, using a lot of
architectural and framing techniques that you've learned,
or thinking about what makes a fun layout in space.
And those can definitely be interchanged
in between the two, but there's a lot of
slightly different things that you have to think about
in terms of where you place your time
in thinking about them.
So thank you.
So we have like three minutes, so.
So yeah, if there's any questions,
might get one or two in.
Hi, that was a great talk, thank you.
I was just curious how you think of
cooperative level design,
because this seems focused mostly on multiplayer.
So I'm thinking, would you place cooperative
closer to single player or multiplayer?
So I haven't personally designed any cooperative multiplayer
levels yet, but I imagine that it probably takes into account
kind of both of the elements that I was talking about in
single player and multiplayer.
Obviously, you're right.
I was designing.
I was talking about specific examples, and there are a lot
of multiplayer experiences or single player experiences that
don't fit in between the two things I was talking about.
But cooperative play.
Yeah, there's definitely some similarities, like there might be framing objectives and maybe narrative moments that the cooperative team wants to experience together.
Those would be important to design and frame, but you don't have the issue of a single-player level where you only get one chance to understand what's going on.
Thank you.
Hi, thanks for the cool talk.
I would like to stick with the single player levels right now.
Before you're going to start with, I don't know, basic block out, whatever environment you're working on,
how much story, in terms of the storytelling-wise,
how much story do you need to start working on the level you're thinking about?
It really depends.
I would say the biggest thing to think about is...
what is the space.
Obviously, you might have varying amounts of data
as to what the story will be in the space,
but at least thinking about,
instead of starting out with just plain shapes,
thinking about what are those shapes and structures
and building small stories based on that
that might support the overall theme
of the game you're working on.
And so even if you don't have the full idea of what the story is yet,
you probably have a good idea of the general theme of the game.
And I mean, single player, you're going to rework your level multiple times.
And especially if it's a narrative game,
you're probably going to remake a bunch of the levels
to support new narrative elements that get put in.
And so you're just going to have to start somewhere
and then add stuff in later when you get more data.
Thank you so much.
Hello. Thanks for the talk first of all. I wanted to talk about multiplayer level design.
I guess my question is what's your opinion on asymmetry in multiplayer level design and
how you like handle giving players different advantages in a situation or would you rather
have like a completely symmetrical map where both teams like have no advantages over each
other? So I think symmetrical multiplayer levels
are, I don't prefer them because players can get easily mixed up and confuse us where they are.
But asymmetrical multiplayer, I hate using the word asymmetrical because they still are
symmetrical in terms of balancing. You need to figure out, like if you give advantage on one
side, you need to figure out a different way to give a similar advantage on another side.
provide locations that give advantages that are equidistant between the two players
and maybe supporting, like, maybe one route on one side is more stealth-oriented
whereas the other side is more open, direct combat.
And so, I prefer more asymmetrical multiplayer levels.
Thank you.
I think that's all the time we have, so thank you.