Hello.
So first I've been asked to have you silence your cell phones.
And then we can start.
So I am Eric Dodds, I am the game director on Hearthstone and I'm going to talk a little bit about
10 things that while we were developing Hearthstone we found to be very very useful
sort of as high-level design things so I'm going to talk a little bit about the specifics
of the things we did and also sort of why those things are important.
And so here are the things that I'm going to be talking about.
As you'll see, there's a whole bunch of things crossing a whole bunch of different ideas,
and they're all pretty big topics, so I'm not going to be, you know, deep diving into any of the specifics.
It's going to be more just talking about a couple of examples,
how they related to Hearthstone and sort of the ideas behind them.
So, the first thing that worked out very, very, very well for Hearthstone is that we
were able to iterate fast.
And that's certainly something that you will hear over and over if you go to GDC talks,
it's not like rocket science or anything to iterate fast.
And certainly on Hearthstone we found that...
we had tons and tons of bad ideas that we needed to try and then not do and so
that quick iteration let us not do all of those ideas and I guess the
interesting thing is is perhaps how we did the quick iteration so to start we
had a lot of pure design time and what I mean by that is me and Ben Brode the
other designer on the project spent a lot of time before anything else really
happened trying to figure out what the design of the game was
And I would love to say that that was planned, but accurately what I can say is that instead
all of our engineers were moved to another project for a while to help out with that project.
And so we got a lot of inadvertent pure design time.
And for us, it was very, very important
for a couple of reasons.
The first reason why this design time was important
was of course because our engineers
were not asking us questions
and bothering us asking those questions
so we could focus on design.
Actually one of the big reasons it was important is because if we had had engineers to ask us those questions
We would have answered their questions, and we wouldn't have had enough information
to actually know what we were going to do in the final design.
And so we would have told them things that later on would have kind of hosed us
because we would have later on said okay here's our design now and they would
have gone you know a year ago when you told us
that you wanted it to work like this well we implemented like this and then
it would have made it much more difficult or impossible to do the actual
design that we sort of wanted to to follow through with.
And in this pure design time, since of course we had a couple of designers and we had our lead artist as well, but no engineers,
we spent a lot of that time doing paper design.
And it works of course very well for our game because our game is based and comes from the physical collectible card game genre, that's its basis.
But I actually think that there's a lot of games that could end up doing...
more paper design time than they otherwise do.
And certainly I can say, as far as game development goes,
one reason that it was super useful for us to do this is because,
strictly from an expense point of view, I mean,
having two designers working on stuff,
doing paper design is a cheaper thing to do than having a full team rolling.
I can talk a little bit about this specific design.
So when we were working on the game, we were trying to solve a whole bunch of different
design problems.
And this specific card or idea was trying to solve the problem of the heroes feeling
really powerful.
Because when we were working on Hearthstone, one of the ideas we had is we wanted heroes
to not just be a punching bag, but to be this powerful character that actually interacts
with the environment and isn't just something that gets beat up.
And the issue we had with that, or sort of the reason we went in this direction is we decided,
hey, maybe we can make a really powerful hero who doesn't show up until later in the game.
So there's a fortress that you have to smash your way through before the hero leaps out.
And then once the hero leaps out, he can actually be powerful,
and we actually had a whole system where you spent points buying super cool weapons and armor and stuff for him.
But there ended up being a number of problems with this model not the least of which being that you
Generally didn't destroy the enemy's fortress you just built up a huge army
Waited till you had overwhelming force and then crushed their fortress and hero at the same time
But it was very very valuable for us to try things like this discover
They were terrible and and move on just in a paper format
Another thing that worked out very very well for us is we made a flash prototype of the game.
This is a picture of the game sort of in the middle of our flash prototype ideas,
not very early, but not towards the end.
What worked out well for this is that we got to try a whole bunch of the ideas in the Flash prototype,
and our final Flash prototype mechanically actually looks almost identical to how the
game looks today as far as mechanics. I mean it doesn't have the pretty 3D world and a lot of
the cool effects and all that kind of stuff, and some of the cards are certainly changed,
but the game field itself and the basic interactions and mechanics and UI were all
ready and done.
And what that meant was when we finished with this Flash prototype and we were ready to start building the real game,
we pointed to the Flash prototype and told our engineers,
hey, we're just going to sit around for a few months, why don't you just make that thing that's this game right here?
And it let the engineers make the back end of the game exactly how it was going to end up being design-wise,
so we didn't have to later on make changes and get in trouble because there were engineering problems behind the scenes.
So it was a huge advantage for us to build this Flash prototype.
And of course it also meant that we got to very quickly try a whole bunch of ideas, put
them into the Flash prototype, not worry that it was junking up the code because we knew
we were going to throw it away in the long run.
So another very important thing for us in Hearthstone was sharing the vision with our
team.
Certainly everybody on our team is going to be participating in making the game.
If you've ever been on a game where everybody on the team is not making the same game, it doesn't go so well.
And yeah, there's a lot of ways of communicating what the game is all about.
You can communicate it via, you know, just talking a lot about it or showing some example games
or sharing design documents which normally make people fall asleep.
But what we did is we had a set of six stakes in the ground and these were the
basic ideas that we used to communicate both to ourselves and and to new people
who are joining the team and pretty much all of the people who are involved in
around the game what the game was all about.
And so that at a high level made sure that everybody who was making the game
was making the same game and had these same high-level ideas.
Yeah, these are actually two of the the six stakes in the ground and I'll
certainly be talking about some more of them later, but these stakes were just
critical for communicating to the rest of the team what the game was.
and the reason why that ended up being so important, or I think it's important really in all games,
is that certainly on the Hearthstone team, everybody on the team is a designer,
and I think this is really just true across all of game development,
that all of your engineers and artists and pretty much everybody involved in the game
is making design decisions, large and small.
and there's a couple of ways you can go about sort of designing the game and the way we decided to go about it is that on the design side we sort of said here's the big way we want this idea to work, here's sort of the big picture idea behind whatever the system is that our engineers or artists or whatever we're putting in and then the engineer or artist has
both the knowledge because they understand sort of the the big vision and
also the the
on the ground knowledge to make the right implementation choices there because
There's often going to be a lot of small details that the person who's actually doing the implementation
You know the engineer artist or whatnot is going to notice that's going to be hard to notice up front
You, of course, could handle this as a designer
by putting out a design document that
details every little detail.
But I've had bad experience with that in the past,
because design documents end up being outdated about two
seconds, usually, after you send them out.
And you can't really cover all the details.
So sort of along the lines of this,
one of the things that was very important for us,
and I certainly recommend, is making sure
that everybody on your team has what
I think of as designer brain.
and when looking at somebody to be on our team,
I'm much more excited about an engineer
who is a good engineer, who has designer brain
and sort of can think like a designer
as an engaged in the game,
rather than an amazing engineer
who's not really into the game you're making,
they're not really interested in playing it,
they're not really, don't have strong designer brain.
So it made a world of difference for us on Hearthstone
that sort of everybody on the team
was able to make those design decisions
and let us move forward together sort of as a whole.
So, simplifying Hearthstone is probably at a high level our biggest goal from the very
beginning.
I mean our thought about Hearthstone as a whole was we wanted to make a game that took
what's cool about collectible card games and made them accessible to a lot more people.
Collectible card games in general are pretty complicated beasts that are pretty intimidating to get into
and so we wanted to make sure that we made a game that everybody could sort of understand and start playing immediately.
And one of the things that that meant was we started questioning the basics of what it meant to make a collectible card game or for something to be a collectible card game.
So for instance, there's a lot of collectible card games that have a lot of specific different turns and you have to understand this phase and this phase and this phase and what can be done in each of those phases.
And we decided, okay, we're going to rip all of that out.
The only phase, there's only one phase, the time you get to do stuff, your turn.
And during that turn you actually can just do whatever the heck you want to do in any order.
One of the reasons ways that turned out very well is because it actually adds some tactical depth
and one of our general rules when we're looking at simplifying a system is can we simplify that
system without removing sort of depth of play and in fact in this case as we removed sort of
the turn order in a lot of ways it added depth of play.
Another basic thing that we sort of thought about and challenged when working on Hearthstone
was the traditional collectible card game resource model, which traditionally has your
resources being cards that are drawn, that are part of your collection, just like your
creatures and spells and that you build your deck out of them.
for a whole bunch of different reasons we felt like it was pretty important for us to simplify the game in that area and to make it so that the
resources were in fact a thing that you got automatically every turn rather than a thing that was a card in your hand
and there's a bunch of different reasons for this
certainly one of them is as a new player of a collectible card game
and I actually can even say for myself who is a very experienced player of collectible card games
whenever I look at a collectible card game and go what
percentage of mana or resources or whatever I should put in the deck I generally go online
and look up something because it's just very complicated to figure out how you should build
a deck.
And also putting resources in your deck is not nearly as exciting as minions and spells
so if I'm putting together an awesome deck I want to go, I'm going to put fireballs and
giants and dragons and...
resources is just it was not as exciting. And lastly it actually helped speed play
which was really important to us for Hearthstone to make sure that the game played pretty fast
and normally in a collectible card game I have two choices at the start of my turn I go
am I going to play a resource or which resource am I going to play and then I choose to do the
cool thing which is playing my spell playing my minion you know that sort of thing and so
this speeded that up as well.
Another thing, this is sort of a geeky thing that makes me happy, but it's also a good example as well,
is that we were able to effectively remove the idea of exhaustion in a lot of ways.
And to me, why this is cool is as we were simplifying the game, we made a lot of specific smaller choices to simplify things
that let us do something on a larger scale that felt simpler.
And the smaller things that we did as we were working on Hearthstone is when we were working on the game,
we were talking about, well, do we want minions in play to be able to have an ability that you can activate?
You know, a lot of collectible card games let you use either attack with your minion or use it to do something else.
From a UI point of view we looked at it
And we went we really like it that I can single click on a minion
And it's always going to mean attack. We don't have to have a pop-up menu. We don't have to have left click right click
It's it's a very simple thing so we decided for you know the the shipping of Hearthstone
We're not going to have any abilities on on minions that are triggered by you activating them. You just attack with your minions
Then a separate thing that we did was as we were looking at defenses and how creatures defend themselves.
Traditionally, if I have a guy who can stop enemy attackers, you would, you know, tap or exhaust or whatever the term is depending on the game to block an enemy attacker.
and we, at first we were thinking that was the right way to go
we didn't really like the fact that it was a response on the enemy's turn
and then I think it was actually, it was a long time ago, but I think it was actually a bug
where the taunt actually stayed up permanently
and we played it for a little bit like that and we liked it
and we thought, hey this is great, let's get rid of a defensive creature having to
you know, taunt or exhaust or...
tap or exhaust or whatever to stop an attacker and
Once we got rid of those two things we realized that
This concept of tapping or exhaustion normally applies to a bunch of different things
But for us at this point all it really applies to is whether the creature has attacked or not
So what that meant was when we were doing our tutorial, we could say,
hey, if the creature can attack, it has a green glow around it.
If it can't, it doesn't.
We're not explaining anything more to you.
In fact, we only barely explain that.
And so this whole concept sort of goes away,
and you can understand the game much more quickly early on.
Summoning Sickness is something that is also traditionally in collectible card games,
and it's a mechanic where a creature, when it first comes into play, cannot attack that turn.
And we didn't like this very much either because it had the complexity of a creature could either not be able to attack because it already attacked,
or a creature could not be able to attack because it had just come into play.
And so, and I don't again remember if this was when we were doing the flash prototype or doing it with physical cards,
but we decided, hey, let's try to remove this and see what happens, and we removed it, and it was really, really bad.
And...
Really what happened was we were trying to simplify something and we lost so
much depth that we went okay we don't really love having two different things
that are indicated sort of in the same way but it doesn't matter we have to
have summoning sickness in there it just makes for a much worse game to not have
summoning sickness so this is an example of something where we tried to simplify
the depth was just not there after we simplified so we just decided we're
gonna undo it and and do it the old-fashioned way.
And so this is one of the things that I have discovered after many years of working on WoW and Hearthstone,
which is you never end up, never stop adding stuff to your game.
And so when we're talking about the game, we're going,
okay, this is sort of the right level of simplicity that we want.
And then...
over time we start adding additional things to the game here and there for various reasons and and often it's like a little thing here
And a little thing there and very quickly you look at your beautiful simple
UI or interface or whatever it is and realize that it's not quite so simple or beautiful anymore
And that's not even to talk about what we're looking at on Hearthstone now is to be adding additional features going forward and you know having this struggle between a very simple accessible UI with all of the cool features we want to put in.
So really a big example of this is our victory screen.
When we were working on the game we were like hey we want to have this awesome victory screen we're going to make it look super cool and we did that and you know we had the big victory or defeat happen at the end of the game.
And then a while later we went, you know what, we probably have to have quests that award you for doing various things.
So, okay, okay, the end of the game is victory or defeat, and then a quest screen pops up,
because we felt like it was the best way to, or the best place to indicate that.
And then we went, well, sometimes there's two quests, so it's a victory or defeat screen,
and then a quest screen, and then another quest screen.
And then we decided that we needed to make some changes to ranked play to add a lot more clarity there.
And so then the victory defeat screen was the victory defeat screen, and a quest screen, and maybe another quest screen,
and maybe the indicator that you went up or down rank.
And then suddenly our beautiful, simple, you know, end of game screen was...
much more complicated than I would have liked.
So that's certainly an area that, you know,
if I could travel back in time,
I would have gone back and seen what we could have done
to make it more simpler or more integrated
or something like that.
But it's an example where you just never stop adding stuff,
or certainly we don't.
So the next big point is sort of a super obvious one, keep it deep, and it's sort of of course at odds with the simplify idea.
But again, really what it meant was that whenever we were simplifying the game, we were focusing on removing complexity rather than removing depth.
And if we ever remove complexity and also remove depth, we thought about that change like the summoning sickness one.
Or if we ever were in a case where we felt like we really had to simplify the game and we were going to lose some depth,
we then thought about what's an idea that we can put back into the game to make sure that we still have all of that depth there
that's not as complex as the previous idea.
So probably the biggest biggest thing that we did in Hearthstone to sort of address that directly was hero powers
and
In some other collectible card games
There's a variety of things that you can do with your mana on the board and you can play cards out of your hand and other
Things so there's a lot of combinatorics and as we change the game
We realized that we didn't have as many combinatorics as far as the possible ways you could play your sets of cards. So for instance
Without hero powers and without anything else if I have three mana and I have a card that cost three and a card that will
Cost one I'm pretty much just gonna play the card that cost three
So what we did was add hero powers, which is a thing that you can do every turn that costs 2 mana
that is not as powerful as a card, but is still a very useful thing to do, and also very class specific.
So if I have 3 mana and I have a hero power, I can either use the 3 mana card,
or use my 1 mana card and use my hero power, or maybe I just use my hero power.
And this is only in the simple case, but it's really an example of us.
wanting to make sure that there were a lot of tactical depth and a lot of tactical choices
as sort of as you were playing the game and we put hero powers in
to do that as well as a few other things but that was the primary reason.
This is a slide that will jump back a little bit to the simplicity slide.
When we are making a card, we have sort of a general rule, which is if someone new reads that card for the first time,
and they do not understand it immediately, they have to stop and parse it,
then that card is probably too complicated, and either we go back and we spend a lot of time wordsmithing that card
to make sure that that effect is something that you can instantly understand,
or in a lot of cases, we actually went through and we just...
junked that card or that idea or changed it in some way to make it easily understood and
Actually as a quick aside parse is a word that I use a lot when we're talking about the team and for me that means
does the player who's reading the whatever the text is have to actually stop and
Figure out what it meant. So if I have to I'm reading along and I go what was that word?
Oh, yeah, that word means this other thing. Okay, I had to stop and it's a bit of a jarring experience and we really want
flow state so you're reading the card and you don't even know that you've
stopped to read it you just understand what it does and going back to the keep
it deep idea for our game where we focus on the depth is focusing on combinations
of cards making for interesting interactions so for instance the first
card here is whirlwind it does one damage to all minions there's some
interest in that card in and of itself
But when you add a second card to that, that's another pretty straightforward card.
A card that whenever it takes damage, you draw a card.
It becomes a lot more interesting because you might play your Acolyte of Pain out and then whirlwind and suddenly a negative thing turns into a positive.
And throw the Berserker on top of that, that gets stronger every time anything takes damage.
And then suddenly you have a lot of interesting depth there.
But we didn't get that depth through just making a lot of text or a card you have to really parse.
Okay, so the fifth thing is immediate fun, and this was actually one of our stakes in the ground, immediate fun for new players.
One of the conundrums here is that learning is normally fun, and as a new player you'd think,
hey I'm learning a game, all these things I'm learning, it's normally a fun thing,
except that when you don't know enough to see where the fun is, to see where the depth is,
it's often not immediately fun, and so...
We talked a lot and worried a lot about the experience of players having 10 seconds into the game and 30 seconds into the game
and how quickly can a player really understand this game and how quickly are they having fun.
So, one of the things that we did was we made sure that we kept text short.
And it led to some pretty funny conversations because we'd talk about some piece of our introductory text where we're teaching you the game and we'd go,
wow that text has six words in it, that's kind of a lot, is there any way we can cut that down?
And those were serious conversations we had.
And then we used context.
in combination with that text, so lots of bouncing arrows,
sort of a green highlight around the thing
that you should be interacting with,
to very quickly get you playing the game,
rather than reading about how to play the game.
And that was super important to us.
Another thing that was pretty important, and I think it's pretty straightforward,
but that as long as the player has learned enough to actually start playing
the real game, we didn't want to teach them anything else. So sort of our goal
with our introductory experience was to teach the player enough so they felt
like, hey I know how to play this game, I'm gonna go jump into this game, rather
than teaching them everything that they needed to know to play the game sort of
in the long run. And this is partially because learning stuff is actually
really fun.
But it's also partially because we just wanted to get you to get you through this experience and through the sort of the talking
Experience and to the main experience very quickly and very painlessly
so
There was very often during development people around the company would say hey
You don't teach the player about freeze or secrets or all kinds of things that we deliberately didn't teach the player about
because we felt like
We teach the player about this.
You know what, they're gonna learn this later,
once they're actually jumped in
and having a good time with the game and playing the game.
And we just don't need to explain this to you.
You will figure it out
and you'll have a good time figuring it out.
But really I can say we actually just listened to George Fan.
He's the designer of Plants vs. Zombies.
And he has said a whole lot more than I will say today about how to make an awesome introductory experience.
And he gave a talk here a couple of years ago.
If you do a search for George Fan GDC 2012, you'll find it.
And...
Internally we really just said is this experience up to the sort of plants
versus zombies introductory experiences that's sort of the gold standard we used
and if you're working on an introductory experience I cannot recommend enough
listening to George because he's just a smart dude especially about introducing
players to games.
So this is a point that has a lot more to do probably with our games than a lot of games you're working on,
and that is embracing the medium.
And to us what that means is we're coming from this physical CCG space,
and we're going to a digital space.
And our goal was to make the best digital collectible card game we could,
so we didn't want to end up...
thinking about or getting stuck with any of the things that work great in a
physical space and do not work as well in a digital space and there were a
number of those. Probably the biggest thing that we implemented along those
lines were secrets.
And what that is in response to is in, I would say, an awful lot of physical collectible card game, there's a concept called responses, where I play a card on my turn and my enemy out of turn can play a card in response to that, and I can play a card in response to that, and so on.
This works great in physical collectible card games because of the nature of the interaction that you're having with the other player.
I mean, you're basically having a conversation with the person who's sitting across from you,
and the nature of just basic conversation has a lot of...
shifting backwards and forwards in time and interrupting and and it's sort of built for that and so
With a response in in a physical collectible card game
I can go I'm gonna play a giant and now I'm gonna play a drat and they go wait wait wait wait
No, go back to that other thing
I'm gonna counter spell it or lightning bolt it or whatever the heck you're gonna do and it works great in that space
in a digital space
because you don't have that immediate back and forth, that conversation,
it's more it's either one person's turn or the other, it causes a lot of problems.
And so because we were designing specifically for the digital space,
we put secrets in the game.
And this is because we wanted to make sure we kept the depth.
of me doing something on my turn and not knowing that I'm going to get to do all the cool stuff
that there might be a surprise waiting for me on my opponent's side.
And a secret is a card that you put into play that is triggered by a set of circumstances
and when it's triggered it does a specific thing but your opponent doesn't know what
those circumstances are.
So they can try to play around it, but in a lot of ways it's a lot like trying to play
around a response.
You know, if you are seeing your opponent in Magic has two blue mana open.
You're definitely assuming certain things and secrets are a lot the same way. So that's what we did to make it a
digital game and emphasize that.
Another thing we did was put digital cards in, cards that you can really only make in the digital space.
Some of those cards we just put in because we wanted to mess around with the space and see what the possibilities were,
like Nazdormu, which is a card that changes the turn timer to 15 seconds.
So that's a card that wouldn't work at all in a physical space, but in a digital space it's kind of fun, it's kind of interesting,
and as we try cards like that, we're going to find some that are super exciting.
For me, one of the more exciting things though was where we got to solve problems by being
in a digital space that you can't really solve in a physical space.
So the ThoughtSteel card here was originally, long ago, a card that
When you played it, you actually took two cards out of your opponent's deck rather than copying them.
And when you take two cards out of your opponent's deck, there was a lot of emotional negativity to that.
Especially from our high level players who felt like you're taking two of the cards that are my, the cards that...
you know, cement my deck together, my endgame cards, the cards that solve problems.
And it was very emotionally negative and we wanted to solve that problem.
And so what we did was we thought about it and went,
hey, we're a digital game, let's just make it copy cards out of their hand.
It still gives you the feel of beating up the opponent with their cards,
but we lose that emotional negativity of actually stealing the cards from the opponent.
So another thing that was important to us, and it's kind of funny to be saying this,
because on one hand I'm saying we wanted to look at what we wanted to be changing,
and on the other hand I'm saying don't change too much.
And what I mean really by don't change too much is make sure that all of the
things that players are sort of expecting when they come to your game,
that you are providing for them because those are things that you don't have to
explain to the player, and anything that you don't have to explain to the player
is just a godsend.
So for a first-person shooter, it would be something like,
okay, WASD are gonna be my control keys
because I don't have to explain that to the player
and they'll get angry if you don't have that.
But there's some areas where,
that are a little bit interesting
in the decisions we made in Hearthstone
and why we made them.
So for instance, early on we were talking about,
hey, this is a digital game,
one of our stakes in the ground
was embrace the digital nature of the game,
and we went.
Does it have to be a card? Could it be a rune? How about a potion vial that pours the guy out on the ground?
Of course there was lots of talk about, you know, Star Wars chess, say, little miniature monsters fighting it out there.
And so these were all, this is actual concept art for the game where we were trying to figure out...
what the heck is our collectible going to be?
Because it could be anything, it doesn't have to be a card.
And after talking about it a lot, we went,
you know what, it's crazy for us to not make it a card?
Because as a card, anyone who's ever played cards,
whether it's, you know, a collectible card game,
or hearts, or spades, or any card game,
knows that...
you can shuffle cards, that you can draw a hand of cards, that you can play cards,
that can be discarded. There's a whole bunch of things that you understand
about cards and a large group of people understand about cards that we don't
have to explain and so there's no way we're giving that up because it's so
important to have that sense of familiarity and sort of know what the
game is going to be.
Also, we spent a lot of time talking about the words that we used for everything because it's so important to use words people know.
And it sort of seems obvious that the attack value of a minion should be attack, and the health value of a minion should be health.
but one of the reasons that I point that out is because there's sometimes an idea of
hey, our game is all about this thing, so instead of health, let's call our defensive trait morale
and what that means is anytime a player sees morale, first off, they have to learn what the heck morale is
and second off, they have to end up parsing your game more, because when something says
hey, gives a minion plus three health, you don't have to parse it at all, you instantly know
I know what that thing does, assuming I know which bubble is attack and which bubble is health.
Whereas if it says give plus three morale, I not only have to know what morale is, I then have to
figure it out. And so just using terms people know is super important. We spent tons of time even
talking about what should we call the offensive trait. Okay, let's call it charge because when
we were talking to it at Blizzard...
Most people felt like that would be the trait that lets you attack right away. What's the defensive trait? It's taunt etc. Etc
tons of time spent just figuring out sort of the names for things and
even the names of
Your spells and minions and cards was pretty important. So for instance early on we are trying to explain to the player
What's the difference between a minion and what's the difference between a spell and it's not especially to someone who's new to collectible card games
It's not a super obvious thing
But if we call one of our early spells Fireball, you actually in your head already know what a Fireball does.
You know, oh, it's going to deal some damage and go away.
So while we're teaching you about spells, at the same time you have a thing that you know is a spell from your outside experience,
which you can go, okay, I know how this is going to work.
And we even actually get additional bonuses here in that...
you probably think of Fireball as a spell from the outside experience,
hey that's an attack spell that probably does a fair amount of damage and
so suddenly you know, hey six damage is probably a reasonable
reasonably fair amount of damage. So we're teaching you a bunch of stuff
just by the names of things based on outside experience
and that stuff is super valuable too in sort of keeping things the same for
players and giving them what they expect.
This is a topic that's very near and dear to my heart, supporting player stories.
And what a player story is specifically is the thing that your buddy is going to tell you that night about their experience.
in the game the day before and it's usually not about the narrative that they've read in the story.
It's usually, hey I tried to play last night and the servers were down or hey I tried to play last
night and I got crushed a couple of times or I used this crazy combo and it was awesome and those
are the sorts of things that actual player stories are and it's important for us to embrace player
stories and especially as a game that's trying to keep sort of our scope down and be very focused.
We really wanted to focus on the player story and not really worry at all about the narrative story.
So this is story time where I get to tell a story about World of Warcraft.
This is a dungeon called Sunken Temple from World of Warcraft.
This dungeon has a whole bunch of story to it and there's a green dragon and some trolls trying to do something or other to a god
and despite the fact that I worked on World of Warcraft for eight years, I still couldn't actually tell you what the real story is
but it's something like that.
And that story was not super important to me as I was playing through World of Warcraft.
The story that mattered to me was one where me and a bunch of friends went into Sunken Temple.
and back in the day it was a very, very vertical dungeon.
So we traveled all the way up to the top of the dungeon,
and once we got to the top of the dungeon,
we wanted to get to the bottom of the dungeon.
And, you know, we could have fought our way back down,
but one of my friends, she said,
hey, there's this hole in the middle of the floor,
why don't you just jump down?
There's water down there, we'll jump down,
and we'll fight, and we'll have a good time,
and we'll avoid all that horrible walking.
So all of us, of course, except for her, jumped,
and we realized the water's about, you know, that deep,
and we all died.
and we all laughed our asses off.
And for me, that's the story of Sunken Temple.
And while it's not a fantastic narrative story,
it's a story that's mine, and it's important to me.
And so I really feel like giving players those stories
is super important, and arguably more important than giving them, you know, the narrative story.
So one of the things that we do in Hearthstone to support this is we create cards that create
player stories.
and really how we end up designing those cards is we think of a card idea and go
I have no idea what that card idea is going to do. That's probably going to do something really
weird and scary and when we're making these cards we actually have a general rule which is
if the card doesn't scare us we probably should try to make it scarier and then we'll try to
figure it out in design later or balance later if it's balanced or not.
So this specific card, to give an example of a player story that comes from this specific card,
this is a card that is a very powerful card for cost two, but once it comes into play,
all of your opponent's minions are free for a turn.
And so there's a well-known streamer who, at one point on turn one, played this card,
using the coin, so they got an extra man on turn one.
So on turn one they had a 4-4, which is very powerful.
His opponent then proceeded to play a spell for free that took a bunch of cards out of his deck,
actually the Thoughtsteal, and then another copy of that that took some more cards out of his deck,
and then a card that took, that copied a card out of his hand,
and then the card that he copied out of his hand he played, which, all of these were of course free,
which summoned a random minion from the streamer's deck, which ended up being Ragnaros.
which Ragnaros immediately fired and destroyed Milhouse Manastorm.
So the game went horribly, horribly wrong, but it was an awesome, awesome story.
And it's not a story that when we were creating Milhouse Manastorm we had any clue was going to happen.
Mostly we created a card that had a lot of possibilities, a lot of open-endedness,
and then the players gave us back the stories with all the crazy things that are happening with it.
Another thing that is important to us is randomness, and that's certainly an area where there's a lot of, I would say, contention in the community.
But randomness is a pretty important element for creating player stories as well.
So this is a picture of our Arena Mode, and how Arena Mode works is you are presented with three different heroes at random.
You pick one of those heroes, and then 30 times in a row, you choose one of the three cards that is presented to you.
And we have some light controls on the rarity of some of these cards that show up, but we
don't have super strong controls, and we certainly don't control the number of any specific card
that comes up.
So it's been known to happen in the past that you play an arena run and you get...
you know, 11 copies of Frostbolt, or 6 Unleash the Hounds and 6 Starving Buzzards, or any
other combination of cards, or heck, 4, or probably not 4, probably like 3 Leroy Jenkins.
But combinations of cards that are just not possible in the real game, or I should say
the ranked game, and that create really interesting stories.
And one of the reasons we can actually do this is because our arena mode...
you play until you lose three games or win 12 games.
So no matter what the deck is, it's going to very quickly
leave the environment one way or the other,
and then there will be a new crazy deck that you're playing.
And once you get to the high end, you're playing somebody else's crazy deck.
So this randomness creates a whole lot of stories,
and those stories, again, are really important to us
for sort of the health of the game.
And this is just saying that our game specifically chose to have no story and we just focus on vibes.
So we say, hey, we're an inn, we're a warm, cozy place, come in and play games.
And what we want to do is share your stories.
And again, it's not because I think narrative stories are bad.
I think in a lot of games narrative stories are great.
I think they just require...
a ton of work. I mean it almost has to be the primary thing you're going for if you're going
for a narrative story and since that was not our focus we didn't go in that direction and I've
certainly seen a lot of games that they go well we're not really going to focus on narrative
story but we want to have one anyway and very often I see that getting in the way because
that story is told with you know just pop-up dialogues with with text in them or something
like that that is not
telling a super compelling story so mostly I'm saying if you're gonna tell a
story just focus on telling the story but in a lot of cases it's probably
better to just stick with vibe and and let the players tell the story and
certainly that's our belief with Hearthstone. This is also very near and
dear to my heart and that is that emotional design matters and what I mean
by that is it's very important to be playing paying attention to the
emotional state of the player.
as they're playing the game and as they're encountering things in the game
and in a lot of cases that's more important than sort of the mechanical design
or in some cases even high level balance.
One thing that we've discovered is very often there's emotion in unintended places that as a game developer certainly we don't necessarily, or I often don't think about and should think about more.
And so for instance, a moment of high emotion that's going to probably be higher emotion than anything else a player will encounter in your game is when they...
run into the server being down, or there being an error message, or a number of things like
that, that are not things that normally we design for, but I like, I think it's pretty
important to pay attention to, sort of the emotional state.
And this is actually an example of where we changed the game a little bit to make the
emotion of the game better.
So this is our spinner and this comes up whenever you're doing matchmaking and
It has a bunch of funny things that it says and it always ends up on well back in the day
it always ended up on a perfect opponent and
When you actually play the game after you're matched with with this opponent
Sometimes it is a blowout whether it's because they got good cards or you got bad cards or they're a better player than you
There's all kinds of reasons why it could be a blowout even if it was a pretty good match
But what that means is early on a player would see a perfect opponent
get blown out in the match and go,
I'm super pissed at Blizzard.
This makes me angry because it said a perfect opponent
and this did not feel like a perfect opponent.
And so we actually just changed the text
to read a worthy opponent because it changed qualitatively
sort of the emotional response.
I mean, it's still never fun to get blown out,
but it was qualitatively better just changing the wording
and setting the expectation slightly differently.
We also do a lot of design for Emotion. This is a discard from the physical WoW trading card game.
Discard card and this is a mechanic that we actually don't do any of in Hearthstone.
Because the effect of playing discard and certain other types of mechanics on your opponent is super disheartening.
It sort of makes your opponent feel powerless.
and it's sort of a weird state actually because it's fun to play discard decks and
Counterspell decks is another type of deck that we're not really supporting or resource destruction all of those things. It's fun to play those
But it's not fun to have those played against you and we felt like the emotional negativity that came
From having that played against you was so strong that we didn't feel like that we could really include those mechanics in our game
And it's actually in some cases a problem for us because there are certain types of decks in the metagame that it would be useful if we had discard as a tool to put in players hands to deal with sort of those types of decks.
But the emotional negativity is so strong so we're just not going to do it.
We're designing for emotion and just taking those straight out.
We also do a lot of balance for emotion.
A significant number of our changes over the last six months or so have been made.
actually for emotional responses and emotional feedback rather than like high level balance
thoughts and mind control is one of those cards that we changed. It's a card that when you play
it you take an opponent's minion and put it onto your side and now you own it and the emotional
response to that is is very strongly negative and
we heard all these people complaining everywhere,
oh my god, mind control is too powerful, I can't play against it,
it's the strongest card in the game, and we looked at the numbers,
and it was just fine, the card was not an overpowered card.
The problem with the card is it felt super bad to have it played against you,
so we actually increased the cost of the card significantly
to make it so that it would be seen less.
sort of in the game as a whole, that it's more of a niche card, even though from a pure balance point of view,
we didn't have to make any changes to it. It was just an emotionally balanced card or an emotionally unbalanced card,
I guess, that we felt like we needed to change.
Also, one thing that was pretty interesting that we talked a lot about when we were designing the game is
when do we provide the audio and visual feedback to support specific emotions.
So, when we were first building the game, our artists were working on the effects of attacking
and they're like, we're gonna make this awesome effect when my minion crashes into the enemy hero or your minion,
it's gonna be super cool.
And after we talked about it for a while, we realized that while the attack is a very important moment narratively, like in a movie, whatever, that is going to be the high moment of emotional impact in Hearthstone.
By the time something's attacking, you probably actually know what it's going to be attacking.
Or if you don't, you're like, eh, he could attack this or this. Yeah, he attacked that.
It's not emotionally high moment.
So instead, what we did is we, instead of focusing our audio and visual effects there as much,
we focused a lot more on...
summoning cards into play because actually the high emotional moment in a
game of Hearthstone is when my opponent first put something into play because it
could be anything it could change the game entirely and you just have no idea
so that's the moment of tension what are they gonna play what are they gonna play
oh my goodness it was you know Ragnaros or whatever it was so just for us
focusing our visual attention on the emotional moments that were actually
relevant to the specific game were important
And lastly, another topic that is near and dear to my heart, little victories.
And the idea of little victories is that in a player versus player game,
it's very important to give the player moments where they feel like they did something badass
and changed the course of the game.
And to sort of, and this is only referred to in a player versus player game because in a, like a player versus environment game, that's actually in a lot of cases what the entire game is, is just a series of little victories.
I mean, World of Warcraft is just you doing lots of little cool things and improving your character and it's not a big moment where you go, hooray, I beat World of Warcraft.
So, we...
So we focus on, so we talk about it relating to PvP and sort of an example I
have of a good and bad version of this is a bad version of Little Victories is
I play a first-person shooter and I get killed sort of at my spawn point five
times and then
we lose or even we win at that point but in either case I feel terrible
versus a first-person shooter where I
snipe a guy and then I sneak up on a guy and kill him and then I die a couple
times and then we still lose I feel so much better about that
and so I would argue that actually the little victories are in a lot of ways
more important than
the the big victory
So for Hearthstone, we think of the game as sort of like a puzzle, in that on your turn, how you should go about your turn is, at the start of your turn go,
the enemy has a bunch of minions in play, I'm in big trouble, I've got nothing out, I'm gonna solve this puzzle and by the end of your turn,
you've done smart stuff, they don't have minions in play, I have minions in play, I've sort of turned it around and have it go back and forth each turn.
And in a lot of cases that's how it plays out, is a lot of back and forth.
and you get all of those little victories so that whether you win or lose the final game,
it's, it's, I mean it still matters, don't get me wrong, it's still much better to win,
but it's, it makes it so that either way you still felt like it was a good and fun game.
And this is actually one of the reasons why we have been aggressively looking at decks that are called one-turn kill decks.
And this is a type of deck in Hearthstone that a player sort of just hangs out and makes the enemy not be able to do anything for a while,
or removes their minions, but it doesn't really damage you.
And then late game, it drops a bunch of cards on the table and kills you in one turn without sort of any warning.
And those decks are super fun to play and they are very challenging to play
I mean, it's it it requires a lot of skill to play a really good one turn kill deck
But how it feels for the opponent is it doesn't feel like you gave the opponent those little victories
So basically as the opponent of a one turn kill deck in a lot of cases you feel like yeah
I put out some stuff and it was destroyed and I put out some stuff
It was destroyed and I'm not doing anything cool and suddenly I lost without any ability to sort of save myself
And so, as we've been looking at the balance of the game, the effects that do one turn kills have been ones that we've been very seriously looking on and made a number of changes to.
And, I think that's actually it. So, that is all I have to say about Hearthstone for now.
Thanks a lot for coming. I'm happy to talk to people if they want to talk afterwards.