Hi, welcome all to our session,
The Evolving Audio Culture.
I'm Tomohiro Yajima.
I've designed the sound effects in Xenogear's
and Vagrant's story and the Final Fantasy series.
I was sound designer, audio director,
sound system architect in 11, 12, and 13 trilogy.
Also, I am in charge of audio engineering of Dragon Quest X and I'm supervising the audio of Dragon Quest X on smartphones.
In short, I have been involved in JRPG audio for years.
or you might have guessed by now.
But I'm not a great English speaker.
I'll try my best.
So please, no flames about my bad English in the session.
So he might start speaking in Japanese like that, so I'm going to translate in that case.
And hi, I'm Yuichi.
I'm an audio programmer in Square Enix,
and I joined the Square Enix sound team five years ago.
I worked on Final Fantasy XIII, too,
The Lightning Returns, Kingdom Hearts HD,
Dragon Quest, and some... lots of JRPGs.
And as Justin just mentioned, it's been like years,
but I was, like, in third or fourth grade back then,
so not that much into the history of development.
But I'm gonna, like, talk about what's going on
in the present time and the technology
and help him in English, I guess.
Okay?
Including the growing stories,
including Final Fantasy and Dragon Quest,
Square Enix has created numerous RPGs.
They are known all over the world as JRPGs.
And have developed their own distinct cultures.
I have been involved in RPG development as audio engineer and audio director for 19 years.
And through that experience, I have encountered many discrepancies between what is done here and abroad.
I will go...
I will be going into the details later in the session.
But some of them are.
Music that is constantly being played.
The point of focus in ambient sounds.
Characterization in voice.
sound, system sound effects in this session.
We would like to introduce the techniques peculiar to Japan.
Some of these may seem unnatural to you,
but I will be bringing new ideas and points of focus
to the developers from all over.
the world is going to make the future of game audio brighter and wider.
Today, I am looking forward to starting various discussion about the Japanese creativity.
First, let's look at how JRPG works. Since the RPGs in the ages of Nintendo, players
explored the world, strengthened the characters, and challenged strong enemies to reach the
ending. And today.
The basic process is unchanged well, actually.
I'm sure most games work like this, not just JRPGs.
And as RPG, the process is directly divided into story section, exploration section, battle section, and more.
And completing missions is the basic flow of the game.
In RPGs, the game is driven by the story.
From the opening to the ending, the player has the control.
But it is the control.
To say, of turning the page, I would
say it's like reading a book or seeing a movie.
This is the standard in Japan.
And games such as Dragon Quest and Final Fantasy
are representative cases of this.
The diagram here shows how there may
be some options for the player to proceed the story.
But those options are limited by the game designers and,
of course.
do not affect the story at all.
You can see that this is looking to a different direction
compared to the Western RPGs.
Where the game is driven by the player.
Players.
As a character existing in the virtual world.
Please enjoy the role play.
Next, let's talk about JRPG up to the present time.
When JRPG users play the latest title of the series.
Oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh.
Hmm.
See ya, Charley.
Most of them do not expect something completely brand new,
but look at how it has evolved from the previous.
These are seen in UI style.
Game process, battle system, and more.
To explain this phenomenon in one word, it is a tradition.
JRPG series such as Dragon Quest and Final Fantasy
have continued to build up on the previous projects,
adding new features while keeping
the good part of the series.
So we are the latest cutting edge creativity
into the traditional and historical game play.
It is the same in the technology aspect as well.
These JRPGs have the tendency to be always
compared to other games of the same genre.
genre.
And so every developer competes for the new ideas.
Especially for audio history, many ingenuity
have come out in JRPGs.
And I believe JRPGs have introduced
many new games of audio.
futures to the world.
Let's break down the history by hard and see how
JRPGs developed through the ages.
Let's start with Nintendo, Super Nintendo.
Nintendo and Super Nintendo,
I've already developed them.
Okay, how many of you have developed something on Nintendo or Super Nintendo?
Could you raise your hand?
Oh!
Legend!
I'm sorry, I don't have.
Ha ha ha ha!
No?
I was playing with this back then.
You were still a user back then.
When he joined Square Enix, he was developing the last of the Super Nintendo games, so he
didn't actually join the development.
I'm sure those who raise their hand right now is pretty old.
Right?
The games of this time is audio original netting by this time.
Final Fantasy and Dragon Quest already
became popular to be the representative titles
of Japanese games.
These two JRPGs adopted the command battle system and up till today.
JRPG developers have kept this as the standard.
While bringing innovation to it,
due to the hardware limitations back at this time.
Graphic rendering was nothing near realistic.
So to bring the user into the story,
music took important role in assisting
the graphics and story.
This is why music for
These games are highly emotional and melodious.
And also, it is not that the length of the music.
Considering the file size at that time.
is rather long, many creative ideas
were invented to cover the lack of simultaneous notes.
And the number of trucks, too,
were larger, considering the storage.
On the other hand,
Sound effects were mostly composed of noise
and basic waveforms.
Simple and small in quality.
Next game, PlayStation.
Recordings of their musical instruments were adopted.
But at this time.
Music was still programmed as sequence data.
JRPGs require a large quantity of music tracks.
But, media stories was yet not enough for
streaming recorded tracks.
In this time of history,
attempt for reality.
Such as stopping the music and playing
the ambient sounds only.
Were made, however,
BGM had already became a prerequisite in the Nintendo Super Nintendo games.
And many users had been excited for it.
So such attempts are at many times considered as a bug.
Bugs?
Bugs.
Music stopped for some reason.
Since then, some kind of music is always
being played in every scene.
Also, some effects have started to be important.
Not only the quality.
But the quantity and the number of simultaneous playback
enhanced.
Also, from the emergence of movie scenes,
the directors started to require audio rendering
like the movies in the theaters.
as for voices.
The storage was not quite enough yet to be used
throughout the game.
And only in movies, scenes, characters, spoke the lines.
But to use the voices to elaborate the characters.
What we call battle voices were
implemented.
You each will describe later.
No?
Koko.
Yeah.
I'll describe it later.
But this became the standard in JRPGs.
This is when game, not only audio, changed drastically.
So the time of the PlayStation was when the game changed a lot.
So the visual aspects of RPGs changed so much during this time.
Next, the era of PlayStation 2 and Xbox.
Everyone started to learn from the methods of movie production.
And I believe this is the time where everyone started to look for better quality in audio.
Because JRPGs require three times the number of sound
files compared to other genres of games.
Many in-house tools were created to cut down the cost.
But at this time, almost no tools were used.
That is.
Tools were developed for each and every project, every time.
Tools.
The increase in storage helped the audio quality tremendously.
Every character's voice.
movies became 5.1 channel.
Also, for instance,
and other methods developed in the movie scene
were incorporated.
Oh, and yes,
this is when the amount of interface
sets grew
exponentially.
As menu interfaces, such as character making,
became complex, the user's sojourn time
in the menus increased.
And more and more, some effects were
necessary to not just avoid redundancy,
but to establish the part of the game world in the menus.
Game-wise, from the factors such as the emergence of MMO RPGs,
real-time action became the mainstream.
So some aspects of JRPGs, such as command-style battles.
struggled to accommodate to the environment.
This was truly the age of technical innovation
as an example in Final Fantasy XII.
We were unsatisfied with the fact that only movies were in 5.1 channel and used Prologix
2 to have surround environment throughout the game.
PS2 had surround sound,
and the movie scenes were 5.1 channels,
and Dolby Digital was available.
Who has surround sound at home now?
So this is the time when the surround sound came in.
And he wants to know how many of you have a surround sound system at home
when you play games?
Oh, quite a lot.
Oh, a lot.
In Japan, it's pretty small, so it's not really popular to have a lot of speakers.
Well, it's not popular at all, but...
Instead, virtual headphones are popular these days.
So everyone is enjoying surround sound with virtual headphones.
And in high-end games, you have to be able to surround sound as expected,
and that's become a very popular thing in this era.
As you might know, in Japan, there's not much space for the surround speakers.
So, most people use surround headphones, they said.
And that's getting popular in Japan.
Like, for the high-end games, we have to, like, make the sound surround.
So, and this is when that was, that tradition, or, that was starting to come in.
I didn't say that Japanese houses are like rabbit cages.
Sorry.
Last of the history section comes, uh, PlayStation 3, uh, uh, Xbox 360.
Everything regarding to audio can now be rendered in high quality.
I remember feeling that all in the in-air-de-ca-tion, in-de-ca-tion?
In-air-de-ca-tion.
Ha ha ha.
Were removed.
Catching also ameliorated in quality.
including a seamless reaction to user input.
As a result, the number of pre-rendered movies decreased.
Sound effects were required to be realistic
and to be synchronized with the user input.
Due to the quantity, physical simulations and procedure
techniques were quickly incorporated and added.
We were able to use in-game material in cut scenes.
somewhat decreasing the production steps.
However, technical issues drastically became more complex
to manage the copious number of audio materials.
Cut scenes and ambient sound.
Layouts used to be done by non-audio sections of the team.
But with the enhancement of game development tools,
not tools.
Tools.
Yeah.
These processes are now concluded
within the audio section.
This extremely helps in the brush up phase,
where the audio sections can make the modification
at their hands.
Voices counting in digits of tens of thousands
managed in a database named Mormul in Square Enix.
It is distinguished from the past workflow that Zain cleaning hardware power resulted in increasing production costs.
And developers have focused on decreasing the total cost with their technology.
leading to higher quality in-ear.
Also, multi-channel environment is getting popular
in most parts of the game market.
But in Japan, the market share of surround audio system
is not as big as it is around.
So in Final Fantasy XIII Trilogy, we have realized a hybrid architecture to achieve high quality in both stealth and surround.
So PlayStation 4 is coming up, so someone please do something in the next year.
So we've seen the history right now, and we're going to go into the present and see what's
going on right now. I'll break down the JRPG audio into three categories. Music, sound
effects, and dialogues.
and how they're done and how the technology supports it.
There you go.
So first is music.
I'm sure everyone loves the music.
So Western games has the tendency to focus
on creating the realistic and persuading virtual world
to bring the user into the game, into the world.
In contrast, JRPGs focus how deep they can bring
to the story, not like the world or the game.
So many JRPG users cannot stop playing the game
once they start it.
This is because JRPGs are created so that the users
always want to know what's gonna happen
in the next phase, to say.
So music in JRPGs has a role to induce
the user's mind and thought train.
By elaborating the character's emotions,
it allows the players to pull and empathize
with the characters.
Okay, here are some characteristics of JRPG music.
Some kind of music is constantly played in JRPGs,
like Yajimasa mentioned.
This is Siena's style in Japan.
There are many fans of the computers themselves,
and as a result, the soundtracks becomes enormous.
We often hear from the users abroad
that this style is nothing near reality.
Do you agree?
But I believe this is definitely an effective method
to bring the user into the fantasy.
So various genre music like techno, rock, or vocal songs
is used to build up the anticipation of the game,
but a grandiose orchestral sound is almost always used.
At the stable scenes of JRPGs,
orchestral music is used to meet the player's expectation,
leading to deeper immersion into the scene.
Well, somehow this has been the tradition.
Also, the percentage of emotional music tracks
is high in JRPGs.
like short psychological sounds like in the Western games,
they're almost never used.
And instead, melody is the most important thing in JRPGs.
And digging deeper into the music,
so we have different genre of game musics.
One is the cutscene music.
That's going to create the empathy
between the characters and users.
And we have the level exploration music.
And we call it field music or field BGM.
In this phase, a boy and music he
uses to connect a part of the story to another.
And we have the battle music.
This is the favorite of many JRPG music fans.
So there's different music for different maps.
different music for boss monsters.
And right now, the interactive music has came into the battle
music in JRPGs.
And now we switch between, depending on how the player is
winning or losing in the battle teams.
This is going to reduce the redundancy in
battles somewhat.
So nowhere in the JRPGs the music stops, except for the
now loading screen.
And because of that, JRPGs have evolved
to make this more natural.
And I mentioned a bit when I talked about Bell music,
but the Bell music interactivity changes.
And I would like to introduce how it's done
in Final Fantasy.
And it's called...
We call it multi-layer music transition system.
Well, here's an example of how...
Here are some examples of the transitions.
Like...
Fueled music, crossfading, seamlessly turning to battle music, coming back to the fuel music
and from where it left off, and players are enthused by the melody of music, excited to
know what's going to happen next.
So in the layers, according to layer data, music commands that are done automatically
to crossfade, pause, or jump, and always in the track.
Okay, because there are some cases that the previous music
must be continued from where it left off,
number of layers times two tracks are always available.
So each of the six, in this case,
so three layers times two,
are synchronized and controlled with play,
fade, jump, or pause, depending on the command.
And this behavior is defined by the game designers
or the sound designers.
And programs like us just provides the environment and the tools.
What's important here is how the player here received the change in melody.
By changing the melody appropriately, the players understand what's going on in the
game right now, and brought deeper into the story.
So I brought a video of an example of the music.
Here it is.
I lost the cursor.
It's over. From the beginning.
Price.
So that was one minute, but we had the field BGM, the enemy
getting closer, field BGM, and back to the normal field BGM,
into the bell music, and to the fanfare.
That was one minute.
Going on.
Next are the sound effects.
So the basic idea of sound effects
are the same all over the world.
And they are made to make the world much more persuading.
As the visual aspect of the game advanced through the ages, so did the sound effects.
And you may think that there are many differences between JRPGs and games in the Western world,
but some of these are something you will never see in others.
Okay, here are the characteristics.
First of them are interface sounds.
That's very complicated in JRPGs.
And we call them the system sound effects, actually.
And they count over 200 per game.
And sound designers need to control their behavior
while various UI controls are being done.
So here, the players unconsciously
discover the part of the world in the menu UIs,
not just in the game.
And next is the design of the ambient sounds.
And music is always being played in JRPGs,
as I just explained.
And ambient sound must be effective enough
within the music.
So sound designers meticulously strive
to connect the sound to the object on the levels, waterfalls,
bonfires, waves, and whatever.
During the passive part of music,
ambient sound is going to increase their presence.
And players will hear the layout sound of the ambience.
as they see on the screen.
I think it's interesting that the wallop is in Western games
or so done like this.
But instead in JRPGs, we have wallops just being looped.
And recently, to adapt to the countless amount of sound
effects and increasing amount of sound effects,
automations were both triggering and generating
sound and runtimes being done in the game consoles.
In Square Enix, sound effects are starting to be generated and triggered automatically,
even without any designers or game scripts working on.
This makes the variety of such sound possible without increasing the manpower.
So here are some technologies.
If you went all the technology of sound effects, it's going to take a few hours, so I'm going
to pick up a two.
Out of the many?
Okay.
This is a part of a list of the interface sounds
in Final Fantasy XIII.
You can see a lot.
I'm sorry it's in Japanese, but
I'm sure you can count the numbers.
Okay.
So in JRPGs, a setting interface for equipment,
parameters, magic, and whatever that's in the game.
exist independently.
And not only the menus.
Selectable interfaces everywhere in JRPGs,
like the battles you've just seen.
So the sound effects becomes the hint
on what the user is doing right now.
You may think that having so many different sound effects,
I just counted 200, right?
On different interfaces will cause confusion.
But these are carefully designed by the sound designers so that the sound effects in the same category, like selecting sounds, cancelling sound, share the same characteristics.
But even when the design, even with that design, sound designers cannot control what the user is going to do in the menu UIs.
So sound designers can program the behavior of system sounds.
With these designs, we create the interface of JRPGs
to be fun to listen to.
This is actually where some sound designers, like Ajima-san,
spends most of their time in.
One of the latest technology in sound effects
are the procedural sound triggering and generators.
Five years ago in GDC, I was actually introduced MASDS,
Automatic Sound Triggering System for Character Motion.
Other than that, we have Automatic Triggering
for Passing Object, where MASDS is used to compute
the best fitting sound for the passing object.
Reverb parameters change in special moves and battles,
and more is being researched right now.
Also, runtime generators are under research as well.
Some of them include crashing sounds of rocks, explosions,
footsteps, weather, car engines, and more, I think.
The benefit of these technologies done in-house
that we have native application tools, visual debugger
implemented in the game system.
The audio programs like us in the company.
always strive for high usability for these tools.
So, sound effects, I think, are where the technology
prospers the most.
And the newest technologies, like Final Fantasy XV,
or Kingdom Hearts 3, that's being developed right now.
Okay, last of the three are the dialogues.
Dialogues are the youngest of the three categories,
as Yajimesen mentioned in the history section.
This was not used until the media storage was large enough.
And as the storage size grew, naturally, the number of voice
files increased as well.
Today, with all the characters having the voice of their own,
it gives more sense of existence of the characters,
that they're here with the players.
There are many distinct characteristics here,
but all of them connect to one word, characterization.
In English dialogues, dialects are used to show a character's background, like where they're from.
But Japanese voices are also used in a standard dialect.
What is special about Japanese dialogues are there are many play on words,
like the special end of the sentence word, like Kupo in Mugo in Final Fantasy.
I brought some voices here in English.
Who else? I'm always here for you, Kupo!
He sure is, Kupo.
He's working to create his very own new universe, Kupo.
I'll be right here cheering for you with all my might, Kupo.
So I'm sure you noticed that Kupo is coming out from nowhere.
Makes some kind of sense in Japanese,
but it makes no sense in English, right?
So I'm sure the localize team is having lots of trouble for this.
And, okay, second one is the battle voices.
When the player attacks, gets damaged,
or have some reaction in the battles,
some kind of voice gets played in Japanese games.
When this is missing,
most Japanese users feel disappointed.
In recent scenes, this is getting more sophisticated,
actually, to interact with the current,
what's going on in the battle right now.
Oh, I'm sorry.
Okay, the other characteristics of JRPG dialogues
is the voice actors and actresses.
Mainly due to the popularity in the animes,
the actors and actresses have many fans of their own.
And actually, one of the reasons for the users
to buy a game in Japan is because they want to hear
the voice actor and actresses in the game.
Okay, so each of the actors have
their own characteristics as well.
So this has a great effect on game characters as well,
when they're voiced.
This, okay, and whoops.
Okay, I'm gonna calm down.
Sorry, I'm losing my courses.
OK, what's next?
OK, and of course, we have to mention number.
In JRPGs, the main characters are very passive
in their speech.
And that's going to increase the number of the lines in
NPCs.
So the NPCs are those who are going to actually guide the
storyline.
This implies that the numbers of lines including NPCs is copious, very copious, compared to
any other genre of games.
To keep the work for dialogues fast and low in cost, Database tool that allows multi-user
simultaneous editing can be used.
So I just mentioned some of the technologies, but I'm going to go into the technologies
of the dialogues.
So Database, what we call MooMoo.
It's used to streamline massive amount of lines, generating ID labels for script files,
linking audio, subtitles, translation code, has dictionary management functionalities,
and has simultaneous editing and viewing support.
There was a session two years ago about this,
so you can check it out in the bold.
Just like the system SES sound effects I showed earlier,
battle voices, too, are categorized with a killsie
and use battery control system to speak
the line that matches what's going on in the battle.
For this, even the short excerpts,
such as yeah or to see in Japanese games.
have made very many versions to express the state of mind
for the characters.
In addition, there are longer lines
to yell out the special moves in Japanese games.
Obviously, this will create a long list of battle
voices to record.
OK, so we went through the three categories.
And let's see them all happen in the game.
Into?
I'm ready. Are you?
Time to repent.
Thanks for watching!
I've got something important to discuss with you.
Oops, I bumped into something there.
So as a quick overview of the categories,
the music is in charge of players' emotions.
And the sound effects are there to create the environment.
And the voice plays a huge role in the sense of existence
and characterization.
Well, with that said, that's all for what
we have in the present time.
But what's going to happen in the future?
I believe the player is going to be more active.
where I mean passive players are those who just receive the story of the RPG.
The players will not just read the story but actively make action to go find the story they are looking for.
Because...
Western games are many steps ahead in satisfying what the users think should be collected in the virtual world.
I'm sure the Japanese games will be following that current without losing the identity of JRPGs.
But it is difficult to change the story ending in JRPGs.
So the path to the ending is going
to be adjusted according to user actions.
Audio will not change drastically as a result.
But with the change in the games.
It is going to induce the users to make more action
in the way each of the players want to happen in the game.
Nagaji?
We have the end conclusion, so.
So what's the difference between the game in and out of Japan?
And we believe it's freedom against the rules.
Given the history and the role of audio categories in games,
we say that JRPGs are rendered in such a way
that the players will strongly empathize
with the characters and the story.
From the denotation of the role-playing game,
the Western games are much closer to the original meaning.
In the Western games, I always feel that the concrete stage,
the world.
for the players to freely play around
is a pivotal aspect in them.
It is common that completing the missions
will reveal a story, but the gameplay of the mission itself
is the main focus and the story is more in the background
and the reinforcement.
Compared to it, JRPGs have missions to pursue a story.
Scenario is the main experience for the players
and gameplay exists to support it.
It's the opposite.
For example, you're playing the game and you see a door,
and it has a doorknob.
And you're going to expect that that's going to open, right?
But not in JRPGs, because it doesn't matter.
It doesn't matter.
The story doesn't change if you can open it or not.
And there are always such traditional cliches,
scenarios in JRPGs, how the characters collect
information, character gets stronger,
and defeating the boss monster.
This of course decreased the degree of freedom in JRPGs,
but users are more, users want the cliche.
Another way to put this is Western games,
the player is the character himself,
but in JRPGs, the player is someone who experiences
the story with the characters.
I hope now you see why we kept mentioning
like reading a book or seeing a movie.
And finally, we are always looking at these differences
when we develop games for the world
and see how we can make the game enjoyable for everyone
on the planet.
Today, we can discuss the ideas about how we can
make the game more enjoyable.
So we're looking for more and more opportunity
to discuss with everyone here, the creators
from all over the world to refine JRPGs and other games.
to for everyone in the planet to enjoy.
Hey, thank you so much for coming here, and if you have any question
Thank you.
If you have any questions, please come up at the mic.
No?
So when you guys are working on sound effects for JRPGs, are there any kind of standards
or rules you go by, because they all seem to have a very similar sound, like weapon
attacks, monsters, menu UI?
So what's your process for that?
Process for it?
Please, can you say that again?
Just JRPG sound effects in general,
like the more kind of exaggerated ones
that you don't get in Western games.
You know, like the really meaty sword sounds
when you hit things,
and all the crazy explosions during special attacks.
So what's the process for the ideas behind it?
For like creating the sounds.
Creating a sound for JRPGs.
Say you need to go out and record something,
what would you record?
In Japanese RPCs, it's quite different from the games from overseas, right?
What's different?
Yeah, it's different.
I'd like to know what you're thinking about when you're making it.
What am I thinking about?
That's a question beyond our expectations.
I think that, despite being in the US and Japan,
our thoughts are the same,
but the culture of the country we live in has changed a lot.
That's a very characteristic of Japan.
The reason is that Final Fantasy is now up to FFXIV,
and it's been around for almost 30 years.
So, in our minds,
we feel that Final Fantasy should be like this.
It's very old.
If it's Dragon Quest, it's the same as Dragon Quest, it's been around for 30 years.
It has a history of around 30 years.
In the case of RPG, it's been around for a long time,
so there's a little bit of a problem.
So he's basing his sound effects on the previous Final Fantasy or Dragon Quest and building on it.
Does that answer your question?
Good enough.
So a lot of Western users tend to get a little...
Let me start over.
JRPG battles often feature a sort of dialogue repetition after a while, like there's a single
sound file for a special attack callout, for example, or there are a...
a grand total of three I'm-getting-ready-to-attack voice clips.
And these tend to repeat quite often over the course of an entire game.
And I know that a lot of Western users tend to get...
quite tired of that after a while.
Do you often take that into consideration
when trying to do voiceover design?
And is the perception of that the same in Japan?
Or do you think that's a bit differently received?
Or how do you handle sort of voiceover repetition fatigue?
So the question is, how do you
How do you handle voice over repetition fatigue?
How do you avoid voice over repetition fatigue, right?
Yeah.
OK.
In Japan, if you don't speak, people say you're lonely because you don't have anything.
But overseas, they say the opposite.
Let's reduce it.
So in Japan, many users want to hear the voices.
But the Western users are the opposite, right?
They don't want much dialogues happening.
So he's saying that he's going to decrease
the number of dialogues in the next title.
Oh.
OK, then.
I can guess.
I can.
Hello and thank you.
Hi.
I wonder if you could talk a little bit about pitch and musical pitch for sound effects
design.
Pitch?
Yes, because it seems like in many modern Final Fantasy games that I play, there is
a lot of pitch matching for sound effects, especially with music.
Sometimes
It showed up in the last battles scene that we saw with Lightning there.
And often that's difficult if you have a lot of different sound effects
or a lot of different types of music to match sound effects with.
And I was wondering if you could maybe talk a little bit about pitch
and that importance for sound effects design.
So the question is, how do you match sound effects pitch
with music, right?
Well, making decisions on that, because it
seems like there are many sound effects there that are pitched,
where similar sound effects in a Western game
would not be pitched by design.
I see.
For Japanese sound effects,
if there's pitch,
and there's not too much West music that's like Western music,
how do you do it?
What do you mean?
I mean, there are music effects and sound effects that can be changed with the music,
but if you think about the songwriter and the sound effects designer seeing whether that
will hit or not.
There are times when the music is quite monotonous,
so we use sound effects to make it more melodious.
The JRPG's characteristic is to make the overall music
feel melodic throughout the game,
so we make those sounds with that in mind.
Melodic sounds?
No, we make it sound melodic
in the monotonous parts of the music,
to make it sound more intense.
MAKOTO TOSHIOKAWA Okay, how should I translate this?
So, the melody is the important thing in JRPG, like we just explained, right?
So, when the music gets kind of boring, the user wants something like some kind of melody
The sound effects are in charge of that.
So and, well, of course, the composer and the sound
there is a talk, so they don't crash.
But I guess that's the reason.
Why don't you do that overseas?
It sounded like you said that the sound effects are like the
melody sometimes.
Yeah, sometimes.
And he wants to know why that doesn't
happen in the Western games.
It depends. Sometimes composers and sound effects designers are very separate.
He says that's so boring.
That's true, but sometimes they fight.
The sound effect people often get into their head while planning.
The side effects are interlinked is a characteristic.
I think they people out there seem to do it as a professional professional,
but the result might be an excessive boundary.
In Japan, sound design just doesn't work alone.
So there's like the boards are not so ambiguous.
And sound designers work with the planners, sound designers work with the composers.
And sometimes the result is ambiguous too, but the result is this, the JRPGs.
Thank you.
Oh.
Ah, OK.
If you have any more questions, please go to the wrap-up room,
and we'll be there.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.