Hello, my name is Nick Aweijian.
I'm a game designer at That Game Company.
And today, I'm going to talk to you all about cognitive maps
and how to prevent your players from getting lost in your levels.
So as I said, I'm a game designer at That Game Company.
But before I was a game designer, I was actually in architecture.
And so a lot of the references and imagery and knowledge
that I'll be using in this presentation
actually come from the domains of architecture and urban planning.
One of my big interests has always been wayfinding and navigation, which is how we get here.
So we're going to jump right in and let's first start by defining what maps are.
So firstly, a map is a tool. A map helps you achieve something. Most of the time it's
orienting yourself in relation to other things. A map is made. So I can't go out into nature and
find a map just sitting there on the ground. It's either made by me or by somebody else.
It represents spaces or concepts.
It's pretty self-explanatory.
And it's relational.
So if I show you a piece of paper,
and it's got a dot on it, and that dot is labeled Paris,
that isn't a map just yet.
However, if I show you that same piece of paper
with a dot that says Paris and another dot that says Cairo,
now we're beginning to form a map,
and those two dots can begin to anchor each other in space.
Also, a map has edges or limits.
Even if it's a globe, which is a map of the entire Earth,
you're going to be limited by how much information you can
get at particular scales, et cetera.
There are a couple of things maps aren't.
Maps aren't, quote, the truth.
They are not always orthographic.
So that kind of top-down view of something
without any perspective that we associate with maps,
maps don't always have to be that.
They're not always flat.
That Polynesian stick chart that I'm showing on the top right is an example of a kind of
three-dimensional, very tactile map that maps ocean swells and islands to help navigators
navigate wide expanses of ocean, for example.
They're also not always physical, which means they can take place in our minds, which is,
as you guessed, what a cognitive map is.
And it's prescriptive.
So if I show you a map of a part of the world that you're unfamiliar with, and I label something
incorrectly, as far as you're concerned, that incorrect label is reality to you.
So let's talk about cognitive mapping.
This term was originally coined by Edward Tolman
in his lab in 1948.
So if you've seen imagery of rats in a maze running around
trying to get a piece of cheese, this is where it comes from.
So the experiment was as follows.
They would take a rat and place a rat in the apparatus
that you see on the top left, this kind of circular room.
And they would hide a piece of cheese
where that letter G is located in that yellow diamond.
And the rat would eventually find that piece of cheese.
And then once consumed, it would,
once the cheese was consumed, they would put the rat back
in the circle and have the rat do this over and over
until it was almost like muscle memory.
The rat would go in, it knew exactly what routes to take,
and it would get the cheese.
Then they would take that same rat
and put it in the apparatus that you see in the middle.
So it's that same kind of rounded room,
but that original pathway was now blocked.
The researchers wanted to know, would the rat,
once it realizes that path is blocked,
have some sort of intuition as to where this piece of cheese was, and if it did, it would
probably bias channel six, which is geographically where you would go if you just wanted to get the
cheese. But if it didn't, we would, if the rat didn't have a kind of understanding of what its
world was in its own mind, it would just bias all of the paths equally. And
As the researchers and Tolman found out,
rats did create some sort of mental map
of their environment.
As you can see on the bar on the right-hand side,
that really tall,
That really tall bar is how many times those rats picked Avenue 6.
So that is what these cognitive maps are for rats.
But of course, we're not rats.
We are people.
We have our own people brains.
And we inhabit non-trivial spaces.
We live in cities, suburbs, all kinds of different environments
that demand us to use our own cognitive maps on a daily basis.
So we can do a little exercise to help you understand what your own cognitive map is like.
So take five minutes and draw your neighborhood from memory on a piece of paper. Don't look
anything up, just try to let your mind guide your hand and just spend five minutes to do that.
So if you want to do that exercise, go ahead and pause the video now.
If you've done that exercise, you
might have a drawing similar to the illustrations
we see here on the top.
These illustrations actually came
from The Image of the City, which
is a book that urbanist Kevin Lynch published.
And Kevin Lynch went to a bunch of cities
and asked people to do this very same thing.
Hey, can you draw me your neighborhoods?
And after parsing through all of those different illustrations,
he was able to discern five elements
that people use to make sense of the spaces around them.
Paths, landmarks, districts, edges, and notes.
The rest of this talk is going to explain
each one of these elements in detail
and how we can use those to make really strong, cohesive
cognitive maps.
But of course, this talk is also about not getting lost,
so we need to explain what getting lost is.
Now that we have a clear idea of a cognitive map,
getting lost is simply a misalignment
of your cognitive map with what the world around you
is with your surroundings.
It's that feeling of feeling like an area or a space is new,
but knowing for a fact that it isn't.
And it's generally a bad time.
This can result from changes in your environment
or changes in your place within the environment.
or it can result from insufficiently broad or insufficiently clear cognitive maps
because you're unable to respond to those changes in an adequate way.
Similar to this image, which is a map of the world.
It's upside down. We might be able to tell it's a map of the world,
but I'd be really hard-pressed to identify any particular country with the map upside down.
So let's talk about the first element.
The first are paths.
This is also the most self-explanatory element.
It's a linear space that directs movement and travel.
And it also tends to be dominant in cognitive maps.
If you did the exercise earlier, one of the first things
you might have done was started diagramming all of the paths
that you are aware in your neighborhood.
And these are things like sidewalks, streets, trails,
et cetera.
travel tends to be concentrated on them and because of that we tend to treat them differently.
You know, we pave our roads, we cut channels to make sure that water can flow through correctly,
that sort of thing. And interestingly enough, paths are the most temporal element. So a path...
isn't useful to you if you're not moving along it.
And moving along a path is inherently tied to time.
And so that process of incrementing your way
along a path is what Lynch called scaling.
There are a few limitations, though, when we're dealing with paths.
We kind of digest them and use them in two ways.
One is dead reckoning and the other is path integration.
And they're technically different, but for the sake of this presentation,
we can just think about both of these concepts as
knowledge that where I am now is where I was previously,
plus all of the steps that I took since that last reference point.
This relies on continuity, proprioception, or a good understanding of your own body and
its movement throughout spaces, calculation, intuition, etc.
However, it can be difficult or impossible to properly utilize a map using these techniques
without knowledge of those things.
And a lot of times in games in particular,
I might not be fully aware of the movement mechanics.
I might not be fully aware of how
the camera or the player or what have you that I'm controlling
can experience that space.
And so my sense of proprioception
there is really limited.
So we should keep that in mind when we're using pads.
So how can they help us prevent players from getting lost?
Paths are really good at catching lost players.
You can think of being lost in a desert.
You're lost in a desert.
You really just need to pick a direction and start walking
because you don't know where to go.
But once you come across a path or a street,
you've automatically eliminated one vector
from your field of possibilities.
So now you just have to choose, am I going to go left
or am I going to go right?
So having a path is a really good way to catch players who might be deviating away and starting
to get lost. Obviously, paths also do great level design things like establishing player flow and
connecting large areas together, etc. Inadequate pathing in your space can make it difficult to
connect areas of the cognitive map together, and we have those limitations from dead reckoning and
path integration that manifest themselves even more in games.
One of the things to look out for as well with paths
is that moving one way along a path
does not necessarily mean moving the other way.
If you've had the experience of going on a hike,
reaching the end destination, turning around and going back,
and not being fully sure if you're going down the same trail,
you've experienced this.
So just because you've placed paths inside of your level
doesn't automatically mean
that players suddenly won't get lost.
You need to make sure
that you're addressing that concern as well.
The next element are landmarks.
Also super self-explanatory and loved by level designers
all over the place.
They're single, localized, and memorable features.
Paths were these linear elements.
Now we've got point references with these landmarks.
They tend to be things you want to take pictures of.
And they're recognizable either visually
excuse me, narratively or experientially.
You know, it can be this Randy's Donuts shop
or it could be the bench that the character
had their first kiss in, for example.
Landmarks can be useful in a number of different ways.
One of those is orienting players from a distance.
A lot of the time, landmarks
are tall and so you can see them from far away, which is great.
But they're also useful for orienting players
when they're going down new paths and new journeys.
So if I'm going to an area that I haven't been to before,
but I maintain a reference point in a previous landmark
that I've already established,
that'll help anchor the new information that I'm receiving
in relation to that previous landmark.
Also, they tend to situate elements of your spaces
among themselves, which is super important.
But also to note, landmarks are essentially only useful
if they're stationary.
So if you've got a large creature,
let's say, that is walking around a big map,
that creature is no longer that useful as a landmark
because it's moving all the time.
Also, they're much better when they're directional.
So I have this Statue of Liberty here on the Eiffel Tower.
The Eiffel Tower is radially symmetric.
So if I'm north of the Eiffel Tower looking back
or I'm south of the Eiffel Tower looking back,
the Eiffel Tower is basically going to look the same to me.
But if I'm north of the Statue of Liberty and I'm south of the Statue of Liberty,
the way that the Statue of Liberty is made makes it very easy for me to discern that,
hey, I'm in a different spot now. So whenever you can, if, you know, making sure that
people can use that landmark to situate themselves around it is important to you,
try to make your landmarks directional.
Lastly, photogrammetry is the process
of taking multiple pictures of an object
and then making a 3D model from that.
You want to think of your landmarks in a similar way.
If a landmark is only referenced one time,
it's not really going to be useful for the player
to create their own cognitive map.
You want to make sure they're able to reference it
as many times as possible so that that reference point can
be continually reinforced.
Next up, we have districts.
This is also self-explanatory.
A district is a region identified
by a characteristic or quality.
And we have point references with landmarks,
linear references with paths.
And now we've got these zonal references with districts.
Here are a bunch of examples, industrial zones,
downtowns, nature preserves, et cetera.
A good way to identify districts is to do what I call the squint test.
So if you look at your map and you squint your eyes and everything gets all blurry,
if you can start to distinguish different parts of that map, you know, like this area is a little red,
this area is, you know, looking a little different, you can most of the time assume
that those are your districts.
districts have edges and you go through them so you enter into these new kinds of spaces.
They tend to be mid to large scale and another good way of thinking about districts is a color
by number image. So a color by number image is a kind of cohesive and consistent
portrait as a whole, but it's comprised of these unique and recognizable colors
that work together to make it all work out. Likewise in our cognitive maps,
having clear districts really helps to differentiate areas from each other.
An important thing with districts
is the concept of clustering.
So I have two clusters here.
I've got a set of five clusters on the left
and a set of five clusters on the right.
And the set of clusters that are on the left
are way easier to remember than the ones on the right.
And that's because they are grouped with like objects.
This type of clustering can be semantic or mechanical,
not just visual.
So it doesn't just have to be three pyramids here
and three box buildings over here.
It can be, this is an area that I can jump really high.
This is an area where I get in cars and drive around,
et cetera.
Isolating these qualities in different areas like this
is just generally good practice for world building and game
design.
But it really helps reinforce a cognitive map
because I could probably navigate away from this slide.
And because they're clustered in such a way,
the image on the left might still
be something you remember.
Whereas the image on the right, you
might forget the moment that I move away from it.
Second to last, we have edges.
So an edge is a linear reference, but it's not a path.
These tend to control continuity,
or they separate things.
Examples are gates, walls, cliffs, borderlines, et cetera.
And they tend to be elevational simply because we tend to move around the world horizontally.
So if we were, if we, you know, flew around a lot or climbed a lot of trees,
edges could be barriers that are horizontal. But most of the time, they're vertical things.
It's stuff that you tend to go around or go along or things that you go through. For example,
being on the outside of a building, opening a door and entering inside of that building.
You want to be deliberate when you're working with paths.
Crossing that threshold of a path or, sorry, of an edge,
crossing that threshold of the edge
or being blocked by the edge are really memorable experiences
if that edge is really crisp and clean.
I notice that sometimes we have this tendency
to want to blur things.
Like we don't want these hard lines cutting
through our landscapes.
And this isn't to say that you need to make hard lines,
but you should be deliberate in the limits and boundaries
of these districts in the form of these edges.
Because if the edges are blurred,
the cognitive map of players is also
going to reflect that blurred nature,
and it's not going to be as good at anchoring them when
they do start getting lost.
These occur a lot in games.
There's level transitions, level boundaries,
mechanical boundaries, portals, ledges, walls, cliffs, et
cetera.
So we have plenty of opportunity to liberally use edges,
and we want to take full advantage of those.
And lastly, we have nodes.
So a node is a convergence of paths.
It's a point reference, but it's a point reference
that is defined by paths, which is the other element.
Most of the time, these are things
like traffic intersections, transit hubs,
or home spaces, or hub spaces that allow you
to access multiple different locations
of the game from one spot.
If there is a place that has many ins or many outs,
that's usually a node.
They tend to be denser than the adjacent areas
just because these are places that players and people flock
to when they're navigating in general.
So they're good to have.
Excuse me.
There's that expression, all roads lead to Rome.
And in this example, Rome is a node.
Having a location that is repeatedly used by people on their way to get somewhere is really
important and really valuable. So when you're making a node or when you've recognized that
you have created a node in a game that you're working on, you really want to start working
on placemaking there in order to make it as recognizable as possible.
These nodes can be destinations. They don't just have to be things that you go in or go through.
And a good way to facilitate that is just make sure that people can spend some time there as
opposed to just, you know, be transient and move through something. I've been on plenty
highway intersections having grown up my whole life in LA.
But if you were to drop me in one of these big highway interchanges,
I might be hard-pressed to know where I am without all the signage.
So if you're going to make a node,
try to turn it into a place and not just some arbitrary thing you pass through.
So those are the five elements, what they are,
how you can identify them, how you can leverage them,
and why they're useful.
But now let's talk about more specifically implementing them
in our design practice.
So the first thing I like to do is do an audit,
try to look at levels and spaces that I've already made
and identify existing paths, landmarks, districts, edges,
and nodes in those areas.
Then once I've done that, I want to assess the clarity
and readability of those things.
If I'm kind of doing this audit and then I'm saying,
that could be a landmark or that looks like a good enough
district, et cetera, it probably isn't a good enough landmark
and it probably isn't a district.
So that's a key for me to go back and clarify those things.
Really, really not be shy about these design decisions
that I'm making.
Then I want to organize my space.
So I tend to work, because of the architectural background,
I like to work in plan first,
and I like to think of plan as the organization
or structure for everything.
I think the plan should be clear and legible.
And by looking at that plan, you should
be able to easily recognize almost all of these elements
there.
Once the plan really pops with all of these elements
and the really distinct, then I like to move on to section.
And section is where I think the emotion comes out,
where the storytelling happens, where the experience really
takes place.
Just because I've got one of these elements in my plan,
it doesn't mean it's actually going
to come through in my section when
I'm experiencing the game.
So if I see on my plan there's this really strong landmark,
but then when I start playing the game,
that landmark isn't really reading,
that's a key to me to go back and edit that landmark
to make sure that it's legible when I'm playing the game.
Speaking of playing the game, it's
super important to test, if you can,
without a HUD or a mini-map or UI, et cetera.
Why is this?
A couple of things.
Using tools like a radar, GPS, or a mini-map
can lead us into digesting spaces
using an egocentric frame of reference,
as opposed to an allocentric frame of reference.
So what do these mean?
Egocentric frame of reference means
I am the center of the universe, and the universe kind of
revolves around me as I go through it.
If you've used a GPS navigation system on your phone,
that's egocentric.
This can be difficult because you're navigating in this piecemeal fashion where you're primarily
focused on what your next maneuver is going to be. You know, I need to turn right and 500 feet
and turn left, etc. And breaking down the journey in that way has been shown to result in a decrease
in route memory.
It can also disengage you from the environment
because you're exploring the map or the UI or the HUD
instead of the space itself.
What you're trying to do is actually take that triangle
and move it to that circle.
And your character moving through the world
is just a byproduct of you trying
to get those shapes to align.
However, if you test without the aid of a heads-up display,
et cetera, you tend to do more allocentric mapping.
Allocentric mapping is, I am not the center of the world.
The world exists, and I am simply moving through it.
It's this kind of big picture navigation.
And when you do things this way, there
tends to be an increase in route memory.
You're engaged more with your environment,
and you're exploring the space instead of just exploring
the map itself.
I have this image here of the fish in the lake and the bird in the trees.
So the fish in the lake can see the bird in the trees,
and it can see the trees, but it can't see the lake because that's
that's where it is. Likewise, the bird can identify the fish and the lake, but not
the forest, because it's understanding things
egocentrically.
What we want to do to get a clear picture of everything
is try to get what the image in the center is,
which is essentially an allocentric frame of reference,
which is this is the environment,
and the player is simply moving through the environment.
So.
The TLDR of this talk is, one, there exist
things called cognitive maps.
It is the digestion of the environments
that you go through that exist in everybody's head.
Getting lost is when that cognitive map
is misaligned with what the environment is currently
telling you.
So how can we prevent players from getting lost?
Well, we can try to foster clearer cognitive maps.
And how can we do that?
We can use a toolkit using paths, landmarks, districts,
edges, and nodes to make sure that our spaces are robust
and can actually foster these robust cognitive maps.
And a good way to do that is just be deliberate.
I've included this lovely food tray here
because
I could take the same food tray with all of those same ingredients and just kind of like mix it all up in there and everything's, you know, all up on top of each other and blended.
But it wouldn't be as appetizing, first of all.
And secondly, it wouldn't be as memorable to me.
Excuse me.
It would have the same nutritional value,
but by virtue of the way it's organized,
it's not going to read as clearly.
And with this one, I can do my squint tests,
and I can begin to start making out districts.
I can kind of start to make out landmarks, even with this food.
So you can really apply these design strategies
to nearly everything.
Lastly, I wanted to just show you all of these different references that I have used to try
to understand these things for myself.
These are all people who are way more intelligent than I am, and if you're interested in pursuing
this topic further, I would encourage you to go here.
Here are a bunch of more names that you should continue to take a look at.
Go ahead and pause the video,
and any one of these is going to be an exciting paper for you to enjoy.
I'll go back.
Thank you very much.
I hope that this helped enlighten you
and helped you understand how to prevent your players
from getting lost and introduced a new paradigm
for understanding how you can design your levels specifically
for that use case.
My name is Nick Aweijian.
I hope you have a great day.
And that's it.
Thank you so much.
All right, bye.