All right, let's get started.
Hello, my name is Michael or Mikey,
either one if you'd like.
This is my presentation titled
Marketing Fundamentals for New Developers.
I am a marketing director for Crows Crows Crows.
It's a new studio by William Pugh.
You might know him from games like Stanley Parable.
We just put out our recent game called Dr. Langiskov,
the tiger in the terribly cursed emerald,
a world with a heist.
Before doing that, I did a whole bunch of Kickstarters.
I was doing about 10 a year.
I've been getting out of the game though,
I'm trying to kind of distance myself
from that Kickstarter life.
But before doing that even,
I released Catacomb Kids on Steam.
So I've been doing the marketing director thing
for about three or four years.
I don't have mastery yet.
That would take a ton of years,
probably like 10, probably a few decades,
because just like programming art and music,
marketing is insanely complex if you look further into it.
What I do have instead, instead of mastery,
what I do have are fundamentals.
And that has been good enough for me to get through,
to talk on stage, to get through
everything I've been through so far.
The reason why that's possible is because the industry as a
whole for indies is a little bit farther behind than the other
industries. Because people have a different kind of
understanding of what marketing is, what does it do and kind of
how it functions with their games and where does it kind of
fit into the funding aspect of everything.
So a few questions I hear all the time from people are things
like, I don't need marketing.
A great game will sell itself.
This is a great one because it kind of implies that there's
this invisible line in the sand that will tell you if the
thing will work or not.
But that's not quite how marketing works.
Marketing is actually a multiplier.
It doesn't work as a thing that just passes or fails.
It kind of determines whether or not your thing
gets really big or barely makes its goal.
But it's kind of hard to tell without looking
really far into the data.
The next part about that is that that game was going to sell,
or going to make its goal anyways.
How do you know it was actually marketing?
This is another thing that shows that,
kind of any developers have this problem
where they are assuming that the game
is going to make its goal anyways,
and they don't know how marketing affects things.
And this is something I hear hundreds of times,
actually, every year.
And this is a really good one.
Luck is a major factor in game sales.
Again, kind of implying a lack of understanding about value.
And then, this is actually the best one.
I did everything right.
I had a great game.
I had good reviews, good press,
and I went to all of the events.
If I failed it had to have been the macroeconomic state of the
indie game industry. For sure not me. This is something that
I get all the time basically on Twitter. You probably heard
about it, the indiepocalypse you might have heard. It's kind of
an odd thing to hear from people because it shows that they don't
have an experience about where funding is coming from. We have
a good gauge for when games do well because we have reviews.
we say okay this person who's an expert and a whole bunch of experts all kind of came
together and agreed that this game was very well made. But we don't really have that for
marketing. We don't really have a way to track whether or not things are working or if things
are not working. And if you don't know if things are working or not then you tend to make
mistakes all over the place, spend money incorrectly and eventually fail.
So what can we learn from getting this fundamental
understanding about the system of marketing? And you can learn
all kinds of things, actually like an insane amount of things
like should I get a booth? Will my kick start succeed? When
should I launch my game? These crazy systems you think that
wouldn't be related but actually are like tied close knit.
That brings me to what is called a conversion system. A
conversion system is just kind of a mindset that you have to be
in to understand how everything fits together. And if you think
along what a conversion system is, then you'll be able to kind
of map out if what you're doing is going to be successful or
not. If your tinder profile is doing better than you thought it
was, whatever you want to do, it will pretty much kind of solve
it if you can actually get the metrics to be correct.
So the first part of it is cost.
Cost, it could be anything.
It could be labor, it could be time, it could be money,
it could be your community, or it could even be your morale.
A lot of people get burnt out
if they do too much of something.
So a lot of time I'll see indies go from booth to booth
to booth to booth to booth all across the world,
going across to Australia and to the Netherlands,
to everywhere, and they get burned out.
And eventually you figure out that the morality
that they had
morale that they had has expired and they will not be effective
workers later. The next part is views. Views can come in all
different kinds of forms. The most common ones are curated
views. Those are things you know of like press. Then there's
other things like adverts which is views that you pay for. And
then there's finally community. Community is caused by your
community while talking about your game or sharing it with
other people. This is actually the hardest one to get and it's
also the most expensive one.
and it's actually the hardest one to control as well.
So if you have too much of a focus towards community,
it tends to be a very bad idea,
unless you have some very good metrics
telling you that you should.
The next part is called engagement rate. This is just simply the number of people who have viewed the game
that care about it in some way to get more information.
No matter what, a percentage of your views are always going to turn into an engagement rate.
It's kind of just the way of life is. If you give enough views to something,
there will always be some person who just loves it for some reason, even if your game is garbage.
The next part is called conversion rate, which is the
percent of the percent of engagement rate that turn into
some kind of value in the future. This value could be all
kinds of things. It can be things like sales, it can be
money, it can be someone buying your t-shirt, it can be someone
going to your community or going to Twitter and tweeting you,
retweeting your stuff all the time, sending you a little box
of cookies. It doesn't really matter. But some way to measure
it is really required. But this only counts if it's captured.
So that means that if you do not do anything with it,
if you get a news article, if you get a giant press release,
if you don't do anything with it
and you don't put it somewhere
in a way that keeps people together,
well, it's going to decay until it dies very quickly.
So what we're going to do is we're going to focus on mailing
lists. Mailing lists is like the best way of capturing things
because it doesn't require much at all to put it together. And
it doesn't require you to have a product made. It doesn't require
you to know what you're doing necessarily right away.
You can even like kind of have a prototype-y,
not really for sure idea about the game
and still start one of these.
It doesn't take much to maintain it.
You don't need to manage it with,
you don't need to manage physical production,
which would be things like creating figurines
or shirts or little bobble heads, whatever.
And it universally provides value when you cash out on it.
So mailing lists I love.
I use them for pretty much everything that I ever do
because it allows me to gauge value right away
even when we're not selling a game.
And that allows me to kind of map out
if what we're doing is correct or not.
So this is how you kind of get started.
And this is gonna be a lot of tools that I talk about,
but these are all kind of mandatory.
So go ahead and take your phones out if you need to
to take a picture of them on each slide.
But I will have the slides up later on.
I'll go slowly so people can get that creeped out.
The first one is how do you record cost?
This one's going to be easy.
Get a notebook.
Go ahead and write down what you're actually spending and try to keep track of where you're
putting your money and who you're putting your money with.
You can do things like have a checkbook.
You can do other things like kind of manage
where your time is going.
But yeah, the general idea is that you should probably
know your costs when you're very small.
Later on it gets more and more complex
when you need to learn about where your employees are
and how the work is coming through and all that.
But for the meantime, if you're just a few employees
or a few people just trying to make a game,
just get a notebook.
The next part is views. You're going to need twitter, facebook, youtube, analytics.
These ones are pretty easy. They're pretty standard. I'm sure a lot of people have
twitter analytics already enabled, I assume, right?
Yeah? A little hands? Good we have a few. That's wonderful.
Okay. So Twitter analytics is just a simple thing. You just
Google Twitter analytics. You just Google Facebook analytics,
YouTube analytics and it will pop up automatically. You just
sign in and then it just permanently has a little tiny
three bars next to all your tweets that tell you how many
people touched it, how many people viewed it, how many
people clicked on it, all these kinds of things.
and you kind of get obsessed with it
and it's a little path into darkness and all that,
but don't worry about it.
The next part is a little bit more complex.
This is called SEM Rush in Alexia.
You probably might not know these things.
These are just kind of metrics that gauge
how much activity is going to a website.
This comes in really handy when you're trying to figure out
whether or not that press release that you put together
or that exclusive energy view
was actually going to be something
that pays off in the future.
because if you don't know how many views you're getting
from a big media place, well, you know,
you don't really know what you got out of it.
And this system's all about determining if what you put in
is worth more or less than what you get out.
The next is engagement range.
You'll just need Google Analytics,
Google Webmaster Tools, they're different things,
and Clicky, I really like Clicky.
It's actually just a free little program.
And I'll list all the free programs I actually use.
I'm not gonna rope you into some kind of thing
that's really expensive or anything like that.
But I think clicky is a good extension to Google analytics.
And if you want to transition over,
it's kind of a, it helps you out there.
This is going to help you measure
when people land on your webpage,
which will tell you how many people who viewed the thing
actually went over and saw your stuff.
And that's really important.
And clicky is going to help you also get a little further
analytics about where those people are directly coming from,
whether it's through advertisement or it's Twitter
or whatever, it gets convoluted when you start getting like
good at stuff and you bring a lot of people in.
The next part is called conversion rate.
This is going to be where we're bringing people.
This is going to be to the website and then to the mailing list.
So how do we set up a mailing list?
Well we have four programs here.
We have Sandy, we have MailChimp, Aweber, and Infusionsoft.
Infusionsoft is like the ultra darkness of marketing.
It's like hundreds of dollars every month, but it provides fantastic analytics.
Don't worry about it that much.
Just list it so you know a path into the void, I guess.
So Sunday is probably the best for new developers because it
is very, very cheap. MailChimp is a close second. It's kind of
in the same ballpark but a little more expensive. And then
Aweber is in the same thing as MailChimp. But just select any
one of those and get started right away and set up a web
page that just has a way to sign up to your mailing list.
And finally, the value return.
So value return is such a tricky thing to measure
when you're looking at a mailing list,
because how do you know that the person that's signing up
is going to actually be someone that ends up caring
about what you're doing, and ends up seven months
down the line buying what you want them to,
or retweeting your stuff, or...
article that you just got and leaving a comment and showing
support for the things that you're getting. So how do you
measure people? Right? Well, let's talk about how humans
love each other, I guess. So there's a thing called cohort
analysis, which is a little, it sounds a little technical, but
it's really not that big of a deal. It's kind of just the
idea that people in big groups can be separated into smaller
groups. That's all it is. So if you see at the top, you'll see
that there's a big, big, big peak.
up there to the right, left, I don't know, over there.
And it'll be dropping down rapidly right now.
That's because that's just normal, it's very normal
that people sign up to your mail list,
they don't even care about your first email.
They never do, they just do it for some reason.
I'm not sure.
But yeah, they sign up and they just leave.
So that's what happens at the very beginning.
Then what will happen is that further on,
there'll be a progression of people
who continue to open your mails over and over again
until you hit this kind of weird, straight line.
That's not quite zero, but not quite a lot either.
That is your core group of people.
These are the people who will always be with you forever.
They're permanently latched to you.
And the way that we know this is back to how humans
interact with value with each other.
Well, if you go through a lot of hoops with somebody,
if you pass a lot of barriers,
if you're willing to go very far for something,
then it tends to be that you value them very much.
So you're gonna see the people at the very bottom,
if they're curving off straight.
Now if you see that when you have people signing up,
it just dives into the ground,
that means everything that you've been working towards
is kind of a failure, which is great, I guess,
because it's a learning experience,
but not so great for money.
But yeah, so if you see it diving off into a cliff,
then you know fundamentally that you're either
producing content that they don't care about,
or that you were given a chance and you failed them.
I guess that's terrible.
But yeah, so going on to the next thing.
So this little area here is the people who care zone.
You can measure out how many people that care
out of the thousands that are signing up.
So this is another ratio for you.
So you have a ratio of how many people engage
with the view count, or the thing that you're putting out.
Then you have a percentage of people
who convert from the engagement,
and you have a percentage of people from the conversion
who turn into people who actually care about you.
For me myself, the people who care about me have represented
about, they tend to convert at a rate of 40 to 70%.
So basically that means that anyone in this range
is almost a guarantee that they're going to purchase
in the future for me.
That could be different for everyone.
It's probably based on things like how you engage
with people and experience in managing a community.
But if you see a lot of people being built up here,
it's probably a good sign that you're doing something right.
So this is the full conversion system. It is a cost, it is the
views, it is the engagements, it is the conversions, and then
finally what is the output that you're receiving. And through
cohort analysis you'll be able to find out how many people
actually cared and what kind of an iffy percentage what they're
going to do. You can call this dollar sign, vec dollar sign for
short, if you'd like, I guess. There you go. Should you get a
booth?
So we can turn that information into actual questions that
provide really good answers.
So how much is this gonna cost, a booth?
We're gonna fly out to some foreign country somewhere
and buy a booth, a hotel room,
send another developer out so he mans the booth,
and we have to get the space
and a few electronic stuff set up,
so it's gonna cost us $10,000.
This is terrible for indies by the way.
So how do we know how many views there's going to be
at the event?
We kind of don't, do we?
So what we do instead is we try to figure out
a prediction of how many views we could get.
And the way we do that is...
The way we do that is we run a press release prior to the
event. You should pretty much never go to an event unless
you've already put out something somewhere. Don't let your
website kill you because, hey, you got all the press to write
about you and they went to your website and it crashed. It
sucked. Or they viewed your video and it had some really
nasty things that you forgot to take down. So, yeah, go ahead
and check if everything is clear, run a press release, and
that's going to give you something interesting.
that's going to tell you your conversion rate and that's going
to tell you your engagement rate and that's going to tell you
how many people of the people who converted actually care. So
you input in the engagement rate, the conversion rate and
how many people care at that same rate and then you try to
take the value and you do a little algebra to figure out how
many people, how many views would you have to get in order
to make it valuable enough for you to go to the event. You
just solve for V.
So how many press writers would you need is a good question to
start asking yourself to make this system complete. And how
can you be certain that those people will actually write? And
this kind of leads me to kind of the magical thing about the
conversion system is that it's teaching you things that you
wouldn't normally think about. So how could you possibly figure
out a way to make sure that the press are going to write about
you before you even go? Well, I just talk to them.
That was my secret I guess. I just go ahead and I email hundreds and hundreds of thousands of people.
I guess. Before the event I look at who's going to attend. I message them personally.
And a month in advance I try to sell them on the game.
And then before the event comes I schedule an interview.
If the interviews don't combine together to equal a reasonable amount of views,
I don't go to the event and I just cancel.
So when should you launch your game or kick starter or any of
those. This is the secret of my kick starter success. I said I
did about ten a year back in the day when I was younger I guess.
how did I end up making them all work? And that's the secret. I
just ran a conversion system until the range outputted that I
was going to succeed exactly on day one. So I just didn't launch
until it said to. That was the secret the whole time. And
that's kind of it. It doesn't seem like it would be something
that would be all encompassing, but it kind of is. And that's
kind of the problem.
is that this seems a little bit back of the napkin
kind of mathy, right?
That how can a conversion system tell everything
about what is going to happen in the future?
And the answer is that it can't.
We're playing a game with imperfect information.
But that's okay.
It's okay to not have perfect information.
We're gonna have views that we don't understand.
And we're gonna have views that could be broken down
into a thousand different categories.
Whether it be, oh, this person makes $30,000 a year
and it's a Friday and he got paid on Friday.
That's its own conversion system on a separate note.
It can be infinitely complex.
We can figure out all the people who like basket weaving.
Web comics and your kind of rogue like weird platform a video game with pixel art
And then we can put them all together
and then figure out what that more accurate look
into what the actual output would be.
But that takes a lot of time,
and that takes a lot of energy to actually understand.
You wouldn't really know by doing it just your first time
or listening to a few devlogs
about whether or not what you're doing is actually correct
or whether or not the system that you're doing
is actually providing a false positive
or is it actually giving you the results that you need.
You're not going to figure that out right away.
But what it does provide, even if from the day one,
is a mental map that can help lead you to solve problems,
or at least leads you in the right mindset to solve problems
that you wouldn't otherwise.
Kind of like saying how we know that for a fact,
if we don't get a bunch of writers to write about us
before we even go to sign up with the interviews,
it's probably not worth the risk.
And we can tell that even if the data
that we're putting into the system is inaccurate.
that if we don't have a way to solve this system,
or we don't have a way to have the system be reasonable,
then we know, at least through our experience
or what we perceive as reasonable, that it's wrong,
and we have to steer away from that.
So, when your experiences are combined with larger
view sample sizes and more accurate polling methods,
the conversion system isn't the problem.
The problem is that you're not having the right experience
and you're not having the right data to go into it.
Of course, it's a bottomless black hole,
but that's all right, we don't necessarily need that.
The closer we can get to a range
that's reasonable, the better.
So this is kind of probably an odd talk I guess.
It's because I'm not really talking about
how to do very basic marketing stuff.
But at its core, every decision that I've ever made
up to this point, and all the way through my journey
of becoming a marketing director,
and working with all these people,
and raising millions of dollars on Kickstarter,
is all at its core based on this system.
And so it's imperfect and it's messy,
but I've only had three to four years.
And that's all right.
So congratulations, you learned how to become me, I guess.
And here's my Twitter, and you can add me on Skype
if you would like to ever tell me about your data
or have me look at anything.
I will go ahead and chat with you about whatever.
Don't share that though.
Thank you.
When do you plan to release the slides?
When do I plan to release the slides? As soon as possible actually.
Whenever they will allow me.
Yes?
So you mentioned that using mailing list is one of the tools.
Yes.
Do you have any suggestions or tips on how to get people to sign on to the mailing list?
How to sign on to the mailing list?
There's a few different things.
So it depends on what you're going for.
So for the game that we put out, Dr. Langiskov,
we actually kind of obfuscated the whole email list
signing up thing because our goal was to make it
as tough as possible for people that weren't
that interested to sign on.
So the only way you would know about the mailing list
is actually if you downloaded the game already
and beat it all the way through.
And at the very end it would output,
hey, this is our mailing list.
So we were trying to put as many filters in place as possible
to try to get the most optimal people.
So if you're looking for quantity, just to sign up,
I don't think you should go after it.
Because the cohort analysis will show that when you go
for a mass market, it won't actually output something
that you want.
But in terms of just naturally growing your views,
I suggest putting together things like press releases
or trailers to try to get the word out about your game.
Thank you.
Do you have any general tips for building a good press release
and for building that list, do you just try to troll for and
collect as many different direct e-mails to press writers and all
that as you can and just e-mail them directly? Yeah, I e-mail
everyone directly. I actually just say, like, hi, I'm Mikey. I
don't really do a huge release thing. I just say hello and I
tend to DM them on Twitter. I know that sounds really kind of
hacky and weird, but people tend to like personal things. So
what do you use in the content of the actual press release
itself?
I tend to just tell them like, hey, here's this gif thing, do
you think you're interested? Or I'll just say, hey, this is the
concept of the game. And over time I form actual personal
relationships with people. I tend to message them way before
I even have stuff to show them. So I'll be talking to someone
and I'll research every single writer on every single website
that's in the top 100 or 200 of all sites.
and then I'll message each one of them personally
and then try to form a personal relationship with them
so I understand what games they want specifically.
And then if I find out,
hey, this person likes roguelikes and we're making one,
I send them a GIF, I tell them the pitch.
So it's like a much larger kind of convoluted system
than just like, hey, we have the game, here you go.
Gotcha.
Hi. Thank you for the talk. That was very informative. So when
you were talking about the cohort analysis, you had this
graph showing a decline of supporting users, I guess. I was
wondering what kind of tools you used to collect this data.
Oh, to collect information like this?
Yeah. Because in the previous two slides you showed some tools
about collecting the engagement and the what?
it's not. I was hitting the button. So yeah, on the mailing
site conversion ones, they're going to show you all that data
and graph it out for you a lot of the time. So like sendy and
they're going to output all the data for you.
because on the graph it shows how many users open the email?
They can actually detect that?
Yes they can. Oh wow, they can detect so much more.
Okay.
So this is, I didn't want to put this on the slide because it's kind of weird,
but there's a thing called mouse flow.
Okay.
And that will even let you see everything that they click on and move and input on the email.
It's called mouse flow.
Yeah, mouse flow.
So basically if you want to go crazy and find out everything people are clicking on or everything people are moving around on,
there's programs for even that.
So yes, we can figure out who opened the email, we can figure out how long it took them to click the links,
how much of the email they read, everything, pretty much, from these systems.
And Fusionsoft is going to be like the most crazy, like...
you didn't even know existed kind of thing. And sendy is
going to be providing similar details. So you can do all this
with sendy. I do it with sendy with a lot of people who don't
have very large budgets. Yes. Thank you.
could you go over the timing of when to release your kick start
again. That was a little bit of part of it. The way the kick
starter would work is it's the exact same system. You put in
how much money you would have at the start and figure out how
many views you would have to accomplish. Kind of like you
were planning to go to GDC or whatever.
you try to figure out how much views you would have to acquire
before you launch. You can also figure out how many users you
can acquire through the mailing list. Those count as like those
converted at a rate that's very high. So you add those to the
amount that you need from the press. And you can find out how
many people are reading each press thing at what time based
on things like Alexia and all the other things. So you can
say, oh, Kotaku, they're great at 2 p.m. And then you try to
get an article at that time. And if you do, then you subtract
that amount and you kind of wing it-ish.
but the point is that when I do Kickstarter,
I'm coming out kind of swinging.
On day one, I'm getting 30K, 50K,
and people say, oh, it's Hyper Life Drifter 2,
and it's like, nah, it's not.
But what I do from there is,
I'm going to actually just go through
the whole thing a little bit, if you don't mind.
I'll actually kind of explain it for you, yeah,
is that I give those views, I get the views,
I get everyone signed up,
and even if it doesn't hit the mark right away,
I still have 29 days now.
I then plan for other major press releases with things like trailers.
And anyone who supported me that actually I enjoy a lot, who provide a lot of views,
I go ahead and I bomb them with a mailing list.
I take the whole entire mailing list and I send them over.
I say, hey, this is...
we'll do an exclusive interview with pc gamer and I'll say to
all the fans on the mailing list that we've all signed up already
I'll say hey we're doing a pc gamer interview you should check
it out. And then all these users come over to pc gamer they
really like that there's like a thousand comments two thousand
comments they love that there's a lot of engagement people are
sharing it and they go yeah we'll do the next trailer too.
And then that kind of like snowballs things for us. Yeah.
Wonderful. Thank you so much.
really great talk by the way. So I was wondering when you're
first starting out with your mailing list like you have zero
users, where do you go first? Do you start sending stuff first to
press or are you trying to go for more like social media in
terms of like Reddit or Facebook or Twitter, trying to get those
kind of...
marketing type of deal. So reddit and twitter and facebook
they tend to be very bad for engagement because you are
talking within a circle and the tweets expire very quickly so it
takes a huge amount of output in order to get a good input back.
basically twitter and Facebook and all those tend not to work
very well until you already have a part of a following. So I
would suggest that you can do twitter if you want to do it for
fun a little bit here and there. But don't take it like so
seriously that you're devoting hours to it. That's one. And I
would also focus on things like mailing. If you know how to do
adverts which are kind of like a little bit sketchy for a lot of
people I suggest nobody does adverts right away until they
like get this stuff down.
But adverts would be the next solution up and then the one of course the best one is just get press interested
Which is foreign personal relationships?
I'm sure you'll find one of the 2,000 websites some are in Spanish some are in French
You're gonna have to talk to all of them and all the writers individually and figure out how they are
But that's kind of what you have to do. This is like a huge part of it. I think
The reason why it's under like understated so much is because there is this thing where people are not funding it as much like they'll
Devote maybe two or three percent to the marketing budget as a thing and the rest will just go on to production like art music
Whatever, but in reality all the other places that are doing indie stuff
They tend to value like 50% 80% of the total budget, which is massively higher, right?
So in these have this weird thing where they're not really like devoting enough resources to it
Whether that be their time to talk to all the press
things like that but it's not avoidable. It's literally a
straight multiplier. Do you want your multiplier to be zero or
20? And 5 times 5 is 25 and 5 times 1 is 5. So it's always
better to devote at least a reasonable amount to doing stuff
like that. Thank you. Any other questions? Wonderful. Thank you
all for visiting. I hope you had a good time.