Hi, I'm Dr. Scott Kirchhoff from the Volition Institute for the Advancement of Awesome.
Have you ever had that problem where you have too many layers of alpha and you have to render them in sorted order resulting in
intense pain in the CPU region?
Maybe you've heard of weighted blended order independent transparency
but were scared to try it because it wouldn't work with additive alpha. If so, you might need to try our new modification to weighted blended OIT.
which extends the algorithm to work with additive alpha,
and eliminates many other unpleasant side effects.
Or, perhaps, you've been unsatisfied with your infinite light clip planes.
Would you like to just slap down some finite rectangles and have them block light appropriately?
If so, you might need to try our light blocker and portal solution for
tile-based lighting compute and light propagation volume GI.
Or maybe, just maybe, the artists near and dear to your heart have requested so many lighting features.
that your Lighting Compute shader can barely sustain an occupancy of 2.
If so, you might need to try our feature spectra optimization for Lighting Compute shaders.
If you or your loved ones have experienced any of these symptoms, come see my talk, Rendering
Technology of Agents of Mayhem, at GDC 2018.