everybody. We're going to get started here. The usual first
few words, go ahead and move in towards the center if you
haven't already. Turn off any noise making devices, cell
phones, confetti cannons, just leave them under your seat. And
remember to fill out the surveys at the end. That's a huge help
to us, lets us know sort of how we did and it's the most honest
and innocent feedback we can get. All right. So off to the
races.
So as you can see, this talk is about the module level design of Fallout 4.
You're in the right place, hopefully.
And before we really get going, a word of caution.
This talk has a lot of ground to cover. We're going to go fast.
We are going to make slides available. You can find those online after the fact.
So don't worry too much about getting everything down on the screen.
Just try and keep up with us and we'll get through this together.
Okay.
So modular kits, modular level design.
When most people think of them, the first thing that comes to
mind is a Lego brick.
And the comparison makes sense.
Legos are small objects that work together as part of a
system to create something original, which maybe exceeds
the bounds of the original imagination or intentions of
the creator of the brick itself.
In a game like Fallout 4, we might think of a structure like
this, something made from a series of interconnecting
pieces working together as part of a system to make
something original that the game developer or the player
created outside of the original intent of the person
who made the kit.
So what you might be expecting today is a module kits 101,
sort of a primer.
And that is and isn't what we're doing here today.
This is actually the second time that Nate and I
have talked to GDC about this specific topic.
We were originally here in 2013,
as part of the level design in a day workshop.
And today we're gonna recap some of that talk,
but we're also gonna focus primarily on new ideas
and new concepts and lessons that we've learned
since we were here last.
A couple of brief words about who we are.
My friend here is Nate Perkypile,
and he's in Environment Arts with Bethesda Game Studios.
My name's Joel, I'm a level designer.
Nate and I have known each other for about 12 years,
worked together on and off throughout that time.
And between the two of us, we've worked on several games.
And of the games that we've worked on together,
all but one of them made extensive use of a modular system
for its level design environment art.
which is just to say that we've been to this rodeo, we've had
several projects in many years to try out different
approaches, find things that work, screw other things up and
just sort of learn. That's not to say that everything up here
today comes from Nate and I ourselves. We owe something to
our colleagues in the industry who have also shared their
thoughts, whether it's Lee Perry, Darius Kazemi, Derek Yu,
who are also interested in systemic level design, but also
the entire team at Bethesda Game Studios.
And not just the other level designers and the other environment artists who use this process most directly, but the studio as a whole.
Because Bethesda Games Studios is a place that has created an environment to cultivate this kind of workflow and allow it to grow over the space of time that we've been working there and before.
And I think it's important to have this kind of context in
mind in this and really any GDC talk.
Because while it's on its face about a specific process or
specific technique that you can hopefully use and apply to
your own work, it doesn't exist in a vacuum.
It comes from who we are as a studio, what our priorities
are, our culture, as well as priorities and the goals of
the games that we hope to create with it.
So today we're going to endeavor not to just give you
the how of some specific techniques, but also as much
as possible the why.
So you can understand our thinking and how we came to
these processes and best understand how to apply them
to your own situation.
So modular level design is something that's been around in
games for a long time. At Bethesda all the way back at
Daggerfall, modular kits were used to build procedurally
generated levels. Marwan had the sort of standard kit approach
where everything snaps together on a grid. Joel and I worked
together on Blood Rain 2 and that was that same kind of kit
approach. It was really obvious to the player that this is a
kit. Everything was north, south, east, west.
Oblivion had the same kind of kits, but there was a lot more
custom pieces for destruction and things like that, so it
worked a bit better. But you could still tell it was a kit.
In Fallout 3 we had standard kits for most spaces, but here
we started to try a lot of new things like directional kits
that only snap together in a certain way, asymmetrical
hallways. Skyrim had standard kits as well, but we tried even
more new things like kits that only went in a single direction
so you could have really specific architecture.
Or the cave kit where there was all these separate pillars and
walls and things that could be mixed together by the level
designer to really define the space and it wasn't just
dictated by the artist.
But today we're going to cover Fallout 4 and how we allowed
the level designers to have even more flexibility and a
lot more visual variety.
As promised, this is sort of the 101 section of the talk.
We're going to go over some fundamentals,
and again, going to go kind of quickly through them.
So when we start thinking about creating a kit,
the first thing we want to decide and understand
about the kit is its footprint.
Footprint is, in essence, the grid,
the size of the pieces and the shape
on which they're going to snap and tie with each other.
This is where the comparison to a LEGO brick probably makes the most sense.
The design of a LEGO brick is highly specific, and that specificity is what permits it to work together as part of a system.
It also has an effect on what you can build with a kit, and what the look and feel of the final construction is going to be like.
So a typical footprint might be an equilateral cube of volume.
And this is a nice footprint to have because it's going to tile
with itself cleanly in all directions. And it's going to
give you a certain type of aesthetic, a certain proportion
of space, like this hotel hallway we see here. It's worth
playing around with the different types of footprints
you can have. For example, you can double the height of that
same basic footprint and give yourself the same flexibility
in tiling on an equilateral horizontal plane, but giving
yourself a different ability to create a look and feel with
additional headroom.
You can play around with other axes as well, such as making a
wide kit, kind of like the one Nate was showing from Skyrim a
minute ago. When you're getting into these situations, you want
to be careful, though, about how a footprint can lock you in and
do things like limit your ability to tile and snap back
on itself. It's a point that we made in 2013. So with these,
like, wide footprints, we often call those a one-directional
flow kit because it flows in one direction and can't tile back
on itself.
It's okay to make these kinds of decisions,
but you should try and think about the ramifications
that it's going to have and decide how you're going to cope
with the limitations and what you can live with.
Something else really critical to understand,
something I think a lot of people misunderstand
when they start in this workflow,
is you need to treat the footprint as a maximum extents
of the piece, not sort of as a starting point.
So this is another example from our prior talk.
Now if you look, we have two pieces,
identical pieces of a hallway kit,
pushed right up next to each other.
Now if you focus on the floor,
you'll see that the artist has built
all the way out to the footprint on the tiling edge,
which you have to do, that's how the pieces
are going to meet and tile, make the kit work.
But the artist also built all the way out
to the edge of the footprint on the floor
on the other non-tiling edge, where the walls are.
What this means is that the walls of that kit are going to
be coplanar. They're not going to occlude. They're going to
have Z-flickering problems. You can't do that. Even worse,
there's a little alcove detail built into the kit, even at
this gray box level. And those alcoves are now going to
intersect and protrude into the neighboring pieces. I mean,
you can't use a kit in this very basic way. If instead we had
used the footprint as a maximum extents and left a buffer, we
could use it just like this, no problem at all.
Pivot points are also very important.
Pivot points judge how you're going to work with the kit,
how it's going to snap mathematically,
and they have to be really nailed down early on.
So we take example of a couple of kit pieces
from Fallout 4.
Here we have two.
The one in the middle of the screen is a basic sort of floor ceiling piece and its pivot
point is at the bottom center, which is the most common place to have a pivot point.
But the highlighted blue piece, that little clam shell on the side, it has a pivot point
at the bottom edge.
Both cases are going to snap mathematically fine based on the grid, the footprint that
these ones are using, but it does affect how you work with this piece.
As long as it's mathematically accurate, it is to a certain extent a matter of personal preference.
But once you've nailed down the pivot point that you have on a certain piece,
you want to make sure that you don't change it.
Because the minute that you change a pivot point,
you're going to undermine any work that level designers have already done with those pieces.
Something else that we haven't always been great about, but we try to improve in Fallout 4,
was standardizing our transitions.
The best example of this would be a simple doorway.
Early on in the game we chose a single wide and a double wide
door frame size. We made sure those dimensions were 1-0 to the
team.
And we used those consistently throughout all the different kits, so every kit didn't have to solve doorways its own way.
This gave us the ability to use door art interchangeably, but also more critically, it allows us to mix and match as level designers between different kits.
So if we want to go from a basement to a brick to a hotel, we can do this fluidly without having to get custom art to handle every single case.
It's also useful for character artists and animators because it gives them a known quantity in terms of the smallest choke point that our characters have to be able to navigate.
Looking at some sort of alternative and sort of beyond
the basics techniques, one thing that we've talked about before
are layered inserts we use with a base kit. Best example of this
remains from Skyrim. If we take a look at a very simple cave
layout that's made with a traditional grid system, it
doesn't look like a cave at all. We have this unnatural grid
corner in the edge of it. So what we do is we bring in these
layered insert pieces that go floor to ceiling, and what these
do is allow us to shear off the unnatural corner.
By themselves these pieces have bad texture seams and gaps,
but we can easily cover those up with boulders, pillars,
free-floating pieces, and even after the most rudimentary
lighting paths, we have something which begins to feel
much more naturalistic.
We relied on this extensively in Skyrim,
where we had to create so many caves and natural interiors,
but we found ways to apply it forward into Fallout 4,
because it was such a useful part of our workflow in Skyrim.
Being able to do things like create sweeping architectural
curves and lines inside an environment,
without having to make custom art to handle
every time we were interested in trying something like this.
Something else we rely on extensively, which really
boils down to an editor feature, is the ability to specify
a local snap parent.
Some other editors have this feature
and call it a custom grid.
So when we're creating a new space,
we will tend to work off the origin,
snapping along the world grid coordinates.
And that's all fine, and it snaps perfectly.
But sooner or later, we're going to want to rotate off
at some arbitrary orientation and start
tiling in a new direction.
What we can do in our editor is we can point to this new snap reference and essentially treat it as a new origin
and then snap along with kit logic and mathematical precision on whatever arbitrary direction we want.
This allows us to create sort of meandering flowing layouts that are dictated by the needs and the whims of level design
rather than always being locked into custom art to get us off the grid and back on again.
All we have to worry about is areas where we transition from one grid to the other.
One specific type of kit we use a little infrequently is called
the pivot and flange. We use pivot and flange kits in
Fallout 4. We also use them in Skyrim where this example is
from. And this is what we call the ratway kit. It's under the
city of Riften in Skyrim. And this is a one directional flow
kit, basic hallway pieces which snap together. And the pivot
point on these exists at the end and we're able to swing them
around and within a certain threshold create these gaps and
these overlaps.
We have an archway piece which seals that in and covers it visually and lights nicely.
And that's good for creating space which would feel like once upon a time long ago,
they may have been built on a straightened level, but they over time have settled into a more interesting organic shape.
Now, this stuff we did cover more or less in 2013 and we
went into a lot more detail with it. So if you're interested
in more on this stuff, by all means, that talk is available
online. It's free. It's in written form. It's been
localized in different languages. Go check it out. But
today we didn't want to just give that talk again with some
updates because we're always kind of looking forward and
thinking about where we can go next with our workflow. We never
assume that we figured out the best way to make the game we
were making. And even if we had,
the needs of the next game are going to be different
and need to affect the workflow, it goes hand in hand.
And I think it's important to have this willingness
to experiment with your process,
to always be striving to improve.
But you do want to be methodical about that,
have calculated experiments in how you approach it.
If you have a consistent set of goals in mind
that you're working incrementally towards,
you will tend to achieve them over time.
There'll be some dead ends and missteps along the way,
but you're going to improve if you choose a vector
and work along it.
Sometimes we can get into workflow ideas and tool set
changes which seem interesting but if they don't have the
long-term goals in mind we can end up with something that's
different but not necessarily better. And if you truly
misunderstand what worked well about a workflow before you
start making changes to it, you can end up with something worse
off than how you began. So yeah, once upon a time we worked on a
game called Skyrim and then we transitioned to Fallout 4.
So we think about the overall world direction,
the world building, the sweeping fantasy landscapes
and the setting of a game like Skyrim
are inherently different in several ways
than the dense compound mixed-use urban environment
of Boston and the surrounding commonwealth.
So as we start thinking about the world and what needs to be in it,
we think about where players are going to go, where are they going to meet people, adventure.
What sorts of environments do we need just to create the texture of the world
and do a good representation of the location we have chosen?
And as this vision of the world begins to coalesce and take shape,
we can take one of our first really concrete steps forward in production,
which is defining the kits that we need to create in order to support building all of these locations.
So that's what we did.
We kind of went through all the locations
and came up with the kits that we thought
we'd have to build.
And we apply our conventional logic to this,
which is to analyze which environments
are going to be built with these kits,
how robust, how important, how extensive
are they going to be, how much time
do we have in the schedule, and then we start
building out, you know, when each kit's
gonna be available to work with.
Now it's important to understand that every kit
has a certain amount of overhead.
It has baggage, and it takes a lot of time.
Kits are a commitment.
You know, if we have 10 kits that are of a certain
complexity and five kits that are twice as complex,
it takes longer to create the 10 less complex kits
because you have to figure out how is the kit going to work,
what pieces do we need to establish,
getting people up to speed on how the kit is going
to function, reacting to requests, feedback, bugs,
and the ongoing visual and cosmetic ownership
and iteration of the kit itself.
And so, knowing this and looking at the long list of kits
we need at the beginning of Fallout 4
is about when our allergies kick in.
we're really cognizant of time at Bethesda Game Studios.
Even under the best of circumstances,
our games take years to make.
small inefficiencies, redundancies in our workflow.
These time sinks can really set us back.
And critically what they do is they prevent us
from getting to a point where the game is playable.
The faster we can get to playable, the better,
because we strongly believe that the first time
a piece of content is playable is really the first time
you can meaningfully critique it and decide how to iterate.
And having all these kits we had to build
was going to delay us getting to that first playable point
with all of the different environments that required them.
So it's through this lens that we returned to that list of kits and we looked at them differently.
And what we realized was for the most part this list was defined by the usage of the space before the apocalypse.
And several of these kits had something in common,
which was that they followed similar construction techniques in terms of how they would have been built in the real world.
Foundations, supports, pillars, you know, plaster, brick, the finishes and the building materials might have changed,
but the general function and the general proportion of the spaces more or less were the same.
We try to think of kits as solutions to specific problems
and to make sure that every kit justifies its own existence.
Again, we're looking for redundancies
and ways to iron these things out.
And what we realize is that all of these kits
were solving a similar problem in terms of
the type of construction method used to build them.
And we could consolidate them down into one larger,
much more robust kit that we'd simply call the building kit.
And the building kit is gonna be the primary example
we use to analyze today.
So like Joel said, the building kit was used to build a lot of
spaces for fallout 4. But this had its roots all the way back
in fallout 3 with the office kit by Robert Wozniewski. This was
a sort of standard kit, everything snapped together on a
grid. But it was called the office kit for a reason. If you
wanted to build an attic or a basement, you either had to use
a completely different kit or you just couldn't do it because
it didn't exist.
So we wanted to take all those different construction types
and unify it. So we could just start by building one, level
designers can keep working, and then we can swap it out later as
those come online. And this had a lot of our standard stuff that
we have in all the kits. Small halls, medium halls, large
halls, so on. But the way we built the piece this time was
different.
Previously when we built a piece you would Frankenstein it
together in max. But if you needed to update a door frame
you would have to go through each one of those and update it.
So it was a ton of redundant work. So you would export out a
piece and here's your piece. It's one big package deal. There
it is.
but this time around we assemble the pieces in the editor and it
ends up looking like this. So it's composed of all these
component parts of the floor, the wall and the ceiling. So
your actual kit ends up looking like this. Instead of just
building all those possibilities, you're spending
time on visual variants and the actual capabilities of the kit.
This lets us do a lot more things with destruction. We can
just swap out parts of it for a different kit entirely. Layouts
can do whatever. And if we want to build a new piece, we can
just do that. In the old work flow, if I had a corner piece
and I have a door on the left and a window on the right,
that's a piece. What if it's a door on the left and a double
door on the right, another piece? Every time you add
functionality to the kit, you would have more and more pieces
and you would easily have hundreds if not thousands of
pieces. But now you can just swap it out.
And that's the main thing we've done, is we've taken the kit
and broken it apart.
And that's given us a lot more flexibility.
I want to take a few minutes to talk about how this shift to a
more granular style of kit affected
workflow for level design.
Now the notion of going more granular isn't something that may seem really, you know,
earth-shaking or, you know, inventive to an outside observer, but it had a lot of repercussions
on how we built.
And it's something that we had experimented with at small scales before, but this time
we kind of went all in.
You know, and the main benefit, the obvious benefit, is it gives us a lot more flexibility.
But there are reasons in terms of, you know, tech and logistics and workflow that we hadn't
gone in this deep with it before.
and the one we'll focus on right now is the workflow,
because working this way is inherently more time consuming.
So if you take a really basic blocked in space,
like this simple room with a couple of hallway stems,
using traditional sort of clamshell style of kit,
we can create this space in 20 clicks, right?
20 objects dragged into the editor.
But if you take this very primitive layout
and you explode it into the more granular sub-parts
that Nate was talking about,
now the object count balloons up to 123 objects
from the original 20.
So this is one of the moments where we have to think about
how our existing workflow has made us strong at what we do,
but what we can do to make sure we expose ourselves
to the power of the new workflow that we want to embrace.
Nate mentioned this in passing, but how we did this was with an editor tool called a
pack-in, which is essentially a prefab.
So we could use the more granular pieces and collect them together on the editor side into
a prefab.
And those prefabs were named with the naming conventions we were used to in the traditional
style of kit, organized into different parts of the editor, and we could quickly rough
out spaces in our existing workflow which we were comfortable with.
And then once we knew that the layout wasn't going to fundamentally change,
and we had iterated and agreed on that,
we could then, as needed, explode out the pieces into the subcomponent parts,
and do visible variations and one-offs as needed.
This all kind of speaks to the priority that we put on things being ready and being ready at a certain time.
Kits are absolutely fundamental to the way level designers work at Bethesda.
We literally don't have primitive geometry tools in the editor. It's the only way we're able to work.
And because of this, we front load these into the art schedule.
We work with production and environment art to make sure that they're some of the first things made in the game.
Now, level design doesn't mind that they're of grey box quality early on,
as long as we have the proportions and naming conventions that we need to work with.
They're going to visually get better and better throughout the game.
The main thing is that early on we know that those kit pieces are pretty solid, that they're
trustworthy.
This gets a little bit into how we schedule and how we think about that.
Like anyone else who's thinking about schedules, we try and be aware of our dependencies, where
and when and how we depend on other members of the studio to do work, but we also want
to make sure that our creative process is built in a way that flows in the same direction.
So our production reality and our ideal creative process aren't working against each other,
which can so often be the case.
This is actually something that I've talked about at GDC prior
in 2014. Again, we'll make this talk available to everybody at
the end. But all you really need to know about this for right now
is that levels are built in a five pass system.
And each one of those passes is tailor-made based on our expectations of dependencies on where the game is at a certain point in the project,
as well as how we think we can be most effective in iterating the level creatively.
And so in the context of this conversation, Pass 1 is where we're focused on layout,
which means this is the first point at which our core kit elements need to be usable.
But probably the more important subtlety to this is in the
subsequent passes, we also need to make sure that the layout we
did in pass one is reliable. That we're not having to go back
to the drawing board and redo the first pass every time we do
a subsequent pass because we're just going to hemorrhage time
and fall behind if we get into that trap over and over again.
And when you're in sync with the rest of your studio about your priorities in this kind of workflow,
you're able to rough spaces out very, very early on.
This is a screenshot from Concord Museum of Freedom, Fallout 4.
And this comes, you know, this is in 2012, this is at a point where Nate and I have been working on the building kit,
we're in agreement about the basic functionality, the pieces that we're going to represent,
even though it's pretty rudimentary.
And if you compare this to the shipping version of the space, you can see the similarity immediately.
And that's because Nate and I were aligned in what mattered to us most.
And probably, you know, the nicest thing about it is we were out of each other's hair.
Like, once we knew how those pieces were going to work,
I was able to do, you know, level design type of things and focus on all of those elements,
and Nate could focus on the artistic side of things,
and we didn't really have to conflict with each other in the later stages,
and the years of time that passed between first and final.
And so I find myself talking about priority a lot, like when
thinking about this workflow and preparing this talk for today.
And those priorities don't just apply to sort of the meta scale
of workflow in our scheduling, but also to the individual
elements of the kit. If we're very general about it, we can
sort of lump all the elements of a kit into one of three
categories. You have your low use count hero pieces, your set
piece objects, which only happen once in a while.
you have utilitarian core pieces, your walls, floors,
ceilings, stairwells, all the things you need to create a
basic layout to establish flow and blocking. And then you have
your variant pieces, cosmetic variants, alternates, pieces
which are maybe part of the core kit but they're used less
frequently or special requests to accommodate needs of layout.
And again, we're cognizant of time, so we want to be
cognizant about when and how we build the kits and these
different elements take priority.
Going back to the 2013 talk again briefly, one of the
points we made then was that the hero piece is numerically
the least important piece of art we're going to build. Now
there's this thing about set piece art. If you're a producer,
they're expensive to build. You kind of want to get them out of
the way early. If you're an artist, they're better looking.
They're more interesting to work on. And if you're a level
designer, they can sometimes feel like the thing which is
going to make a moment work, which is going to make the
level sing, which incidentally I think is kind of a yellow flag
in the strength of the level.
The thing about this hero piece is that these all kind of combine and make them seductive.
They feel like the most important piece of art and sometimes get front loaded in the schedule.
And we argue that you should do the opposite, that they are the least important thing.
Your humble wall, your humble doorway, these things you're going to see dozens of times
and they need to be rock solid and bulletproof and they need to be that early on.
You know, there's a stigma attached to words like generic, to words like repetitive.
And I get it.
But when we're talking about this kind of workflow, I think
it's short-sighted to get hung up on this, to get fixated,
because it blinds us to the potential. Our generic pieces
are by their nature versatile. Set pieces aren't. They're by
their nature built to solve a specific problem with very
little hope of being reused ever again. So the flexible pieces
you have in the hands of the right level designer become
problem solvers. They become the tool that you can use in many
situations. They are the unsung heroes of level design.
I've taken a scene like this.
This is from the Saugus Ironworks,
and this is sort of the penultimate moment, the scene at the end of a quest
and a dungeon space.
Now the level designer here, Drew,
would have loved to have a bunch of custom art to sell this moment.
You know, he cares very much about how this shot is framed
and how the player enters a space.
But this is actually, you know,
a space where you're not seeing a bunch of custom art.
This is a whole lot of generic art working together in concert
with good composition, lighting, and staging
to create a moment which has all the trappings of a set piece
without actually being a set piece.
And the important thing here isn't just that you can do this, but that it spares the time.
The time that we didn't have to spend building custom art for this is time we could use somewhere
else on something else that could have been more broadly applicable to the game as a whole.
So I think you saw this coming, but I'm inverting the priority.
I think the utilitarian core needs to happen early and fast.
The variants are important, too.
And the hero kit is the least important thing.
And we actually push those way to the end of the schedule.
And this mentality is all about getting out
of the way of progress, making sure
that you're not blocking anybody else's ability
to do meaningful work.
And I think if you're the artist, it behooves you to minimize the roadblocks, to not be that bottleneck.
For one, it's going to get you in a position of having real examples of how your art is being used as quickly as possible.
And you're not relying on your own guesses and assumptions in the test space about how it's going to be used.
It also allows you the most time to iterate on the visuals of the kit.
In this particular point, I think some will find counterintuitive
because I think there's a tendency with some artists to want to figure everything out
about how the art is going to look, how it's going to work,
at every nut and bolt in place, before giving it away for somebody else to work with.
But the problem here is that then you become the bottleneck.
You're holding up work.
And that pressure to figure it out and get moving
can force you into making decisions
you might rather have more time to think about.
But if you just focus on the proportions
and the functionality, which is all that level design
really needs to move forward,
you can then get out of the way, let them start working,
and have basically the duration of the project
to focus on the cosmetic aspects of the kit.
Now for level designers this can also be a shift in thinking
because you're going to have to use place holders. You're not
going to have your fancy hero piece early on. I actually
don't think this is a big problem. It's actually useful
exercise because level designers then are incumbent upon us to
prove the actual need. Take for example the Boston public
library. Like many of the spaces in downtown Boston, it's a
beautiful building filled with beautiful things. You can spend
an afternoon in this place filling a notebook with pieces
of art that you believe you would need to make the space.
But knowing the way we work, the level designer here, Darl,
he didn't have that luxury.
He needed to make progress.
He needed to get started on his iterative passes.
So he's using generic pieces.
He's recreating the key rooms, the areas that we feel
are important to the space.
And while that's happening, a couple of other things
are happening.
The game is progressing.
The kits are getting more robust, their functionality,
their visuals.
Those placeholders are becoming a little bit more
cemented into the layout.
And we're finding the places where the placeholders work
and where they don't.
We're also finding more about the gameplay of the space as Darrell iterates.
We have guesses and assumptions, but until we can actually play, they're just guesses
and assumptions.
And what we realized by the time we were ready to do any custom art was that this space,
this reading room, was the most important room in the library.
What's more is we couldn't recreate this room with placeholders.
The barrel vault ceiling that you see at the top and those big reading pane windows, there's
nothing in the kit that could handle that.
And those are the custom pieces that we made for the Boston Public Library.
The thing about this again is if Darrel had sat down and made
a list of the custom set pieces he thought he wanted and
prioritized them and we made them at the beginning, these
might not have been at the top of that list. We would have
possibly built art which wouldn't have been showcased
well, may not have even been necessary, and what's worse is
we might actually have gotten the time to build these pieces
thinking they were less important than they really were.
So visual variety is one of the big goals of the building kit.
And one of the big ways we did that
is all the architectural variants.
So with this setup, we could take any room in any dungeon
and just swap it out.
Like I can start at wallpaper, become the deco kit.
It could be a concrete basement.
I can make it into an attic.
wood paneling, brick factory. This ends up being a ton of
pieces. And just one of those architecture types is you can
see it there. But because all the logic is the same across all
these kits, I was able to bring new versions of this online in
as little as two weeks. You spend most of the time doing
just destruction and little cosmetic things. You don't
really have to worry about the logic. It's there. So that
really makes it a lot easier.
This lets us do a lot of things we could never do before like
this where in the back there's brick walls, goes down to this
concrete basement, there's these bare wood platforms suspended
there and I can swap out any one of those elements because it's
all broken apart. And we can do things like this because the
walls, floors and ceilings are all separate. They can just open
up into a larger space. That's not a custom transition. That's
just what the level designer did for this particular area.
or things like this where it's stacking vertically. There's
the deco kit on the bottom. It goes to the wood panel kit
above that. Previously when we did vertically stacking kits,
the logic just gets insane and it's all the naming conventions
don't make any sense. People get confused and just don't do it.
But now you can just put stuff on top of each other and it's
easy. But you can still do really boring stuff like this.
But even this one we couldn't do because it's actually wood panel
walls in the back, but the floor is the deco kit. That would
have been a whole new export before. Now I can just swap it
out.
or you can just blow the whole floor out. The walls are just
doing their own thing and these little damaged platforms can be
moved around so every hole can look different. In this case it
forms this ramp that you can walk up. The level designer is
deciding what to do. That hole could even be 100 yards long. I
didn't go on a max and make this 100 yard hole piece that would
get used once. But the level designer did this and it works
out really well.
and we can do things like this where the wall is angled at 45
degrees or can go on these gentle curves. When we did this
in Skyrim, there was a normal kit behind those walls and it
was all this wasted space you couldn't use. But now the walls
can just do this. Material swaps are something else that we did.
And this isn't an architecture change. It's just the textures.
And these don't take very much time and it lets you get a lot
of visual variety. So I can take that same wallpaper room
instead of changing the architecture, I can make it
crazy 50s style wallpaper and this boring blue one. Another
interesting pattern, old people wallpaper, just change the green
stripe to a red stripe, intricate green, deep red,
whatever. Most of those are made in two days. We can now go and
take every single room in a space and make it feel unique.
Because the walls, floors and ceilings are all separate, those
can all be material swapped independently. Not every kit is
the building kit, though.
And one of the first things we ask when we're building a kit
is what new functionality does it provide? Is it doing
something new? Sometimes the answer is, well, no, let's just
make another building kit. But that wasn't always the case. And
one of those is the industrial kit. And we wanted these big
blocky concrete things with these pipes rising up and a lot
of intricate detail work. It's definitely not the building kit.
And this ended up looking like this.
So the way this works is there's these big blocks that form the
core and just like mass out the shape of the building. But then
there's this intricate framework kit that has frames of every
size and every one of those sizes has variants that have X
cross frames, V cross frames, A cross frames. There's a silo
set up where there's a bunch of different widths and these are
vertically stackable so we can make it as tall as we want.
There's a bunch of different pipe kits. Some are big enough
you can walk through. Others are just tiny details.
Then there's this free room kit that we can put on top of those
concrete blocks and you can go inside of these, take cover, we
can put machines in there. Ends up looking like this. Everything
going on here is because the level designer wanted it to be
that way. I'm not dictating this as the artist. That catwalk is
there for a reason. It will look different every time. Here you
can take cover behind those pipes, that room is tucked away
in the back. This space has a totally different feel with this
spindly little pipe moving through it and all the frames
and materials swap to red.
Or we can just take parts of that kit and mix it with other
kits. Here it's being used with a steam tunnel kit. There's a
lot of versatility there. The utility kit is another kit that
we built. And this was all about this intricate pipe work. And
it snaps together in a certain way and there's a lot of baked
in detail. And the hallway kit, the left side is different from
the right side and these can move independently of one
another. And we also have these long curving pieces to get away
from that rigid nature of the kit. And that ends up feeling
like this.
So using this kit, we can have a really simple hallway like this
and we just throw a couple of trash piles on the ground and
it's pretty much done. We don't need to do this big set dressing
pass to make this look interesting. But that kit kind
of wasn't worth the time. All we actually cared about was the
pipes. Cosmetically and architecturally, everything
going on with the walls was pretty much the building kit.
And in some cases, that's even what we did. Here it's utility
kit on the right, building kit on the left and some of the
pipes you see are a separate pipe kit.
but it was a really nice kit to have. It's what we call a glue
kit because we're never going to build a space where it's all
utility kit and just this giant building full of pipes. Instead
we just use it to spice things up a little bit and it was
really useful to have. The steam tunnel kit is another kit that
we built. And this is a lot like the ratway kit from Skyrim
where all these things are jammed together organically so
we don't actually need that many pieces. But the main difference
is that the floor is broken off and it's not baked in. So you
can have a really narrow space like this or make it taller,
make it taller.
So the level designers can really play with the
verticality. You can have these raised up areas on the side and
drop down in the middle. The walls in the back can be angled
however we want. You can blow a hole through with the cinder
blocks and then bring in the catwalks. Or I could just take
those cinder blocks and put them up against the walls as a
decorative element and bring in industrial framing on the walls
and have a totally different feel. It's really flexible.
Another kit that was built by one of our artists, Claire
Struthers, for downtown is the Deco Kit.
And this was built with a lot of the principles of the other
kits, where there's all these different parts, little trim
kits, the lobby kit, the foundation so it can mix with
the street.
And one of the main things that this kit let us do is these
interior-exterior areas, where you could just move right
through it.
Previously, this kind of thing would have been a load.
You'd go up to a door, activate it, walk around for a little
bit, activate it again, and load back out.
Now you can just move right through it.
And this kit was really flexible and let us build buildings of all sorts of shapes, which
works really well with the organic nature of Boston streets.
Yeah, and I do want to talk about Boston for a little bit,
because for one, there's a tendency talking about this
kind of workflow in level design to focus on intimate spaces,
interiors, combat arenas, these sorts of things.
But exteriors can be built modular as well.
And in fact, Boston downtown was the most ambitious thing
we've ever attempted on the level design scale at Bethesda.
Huge and interlocking.
And in order to start talking about and understanding how we
approach Boston, we have to go all the way back to Washington
D.C. in Fallout 3.
Now, when it came to figuring out how to represent DC's
downtown, for a number of reasons, we had decided to
block it off.
So all the downtown neighborhoods were these
little sort of cloistered areas, these walled gardens
that you would load into, which were separate from the
open world of the game.
They all kind of had this consistent look and feel, where
you can see the buildings and the big marble
piles on the edges.
They were walls.
They were literally walls.
And that the meaningful gameplay happens in the
negative space in the interior, in the ground level
layout.
Now this made getting around downtown really complicated.
This is a map that users made to help them understand
how to get from place to place.
And I think the complexity of this map
is indicative of some underlying issues
with the implementation that we chose.
So going into Fallout 4 and figuring out how we wanted to represent Boston,
it was important to us that it was part of the open world and felt like
the beating heart of the Commonwealth.
We would have long sight lines and clear lines of view.
We'd have avenues and streets which were actually useful for navigating the city,
as you would as a pedestrian.
We wanted neighborhoods which tapered off naturally into the wilderness.
And when we start thinking about how we're going to represent a space like this,
we can get into conversations about how accurate must it be.
Are we going to try and recreate the city street for street,
building for building, brick for brick?
It's sort of the can I visit my college dorm mentality
of city design.
And we knew that was never our priority.
We were always more focused on authenticity.
Can we understand what makes Boston special
and distill it down into a core form
and represent the fallout version of the city
in a way that would feel familiar and sincere to Bostoners,
but also like a real, real location
with a real internal consistency and a sense of place
to those who have no familiarity with the city whatsoever.
So, with this mentality, we approach the actual process of building the city.
And where we begin is with the coastline.
One of the first things we create for any of our games is a rough pass of the world map.
Now, Boston is defined by water.
The Charles River, Boston Harbor, the Atlantic Ocean,
these give us hard boundaries, hard edges to most of the areas of the city we're going to recreate.
We can take this and compare it against the scope and scale of the game map that we're going to build
and now we know the square footage we're working with.
Now we know how much we have to condense downtown.
And then we can start focusing on the skyline.
The skyline of Boston is important.
It's not as iconic as the skyline of Shanghai or Paris or London,
but it's a really useful skyline because it's asymmetrical
and it provides an orienting element for players.
And in order to recreate that orienting element, we have to focus on the anchor buildings that define the skyline and get their relative positioning correct.
So this is another old screenshot of the game in the early stages.
Raf, one of our environment artists, he went through and used really temp buildings to rough out all of downtown.
And what we were focused on here is roof heights and density.
And specifically on those anchors. The cluster of skyscrapers in the financial district,
which is on the east end of the city and cuts off into the harbor.
The sort of solitary, you know, nature of the Hancock Tower and Back Bay.
And then Diamond City or Fenway Park kind of abutting at the west end of the city.
And we did end up sticking to this original past pretty
faithfully all the way into the finished game.
We were able to add a few more anchors, a few more landmarks
for players to fixate on.
And this is something that players familiar with Boston
were able to pick up on from even our earliest trailer.
People were able to take the background shot and make
accurate guesses about some of the buildings we were
representing and the position of the camera.
So with the skyline ready to go, we start thinking about the
thoroughfares, the streets, what is the skeleton, what are the
bones of the city. And when you're representing any city
space, you don't have to recreate the city street for
street in order to get the feeling of navigating the city
correct. If we're focused on creating, say, Manhattan, you're
going to be thinking about long blocks, streets, avenues. It's a
city planner's city. This is not Boston. Boston was created by
filling in marshland and paving cow paths.
a notoriously nasty city to drive in, but a really
wonderful pedestrian city. So that's how we experienced
Boston. We went to Boston. We spent time on the streets, just
moving around the city and just kind of experiencing it and
existing there and getting a sense for
what are the streets we relied on for navigation?
What is our mental map of the city?
What intersections matter to us?
What points of interest?
Where are they in relative positioning to each other?
And then with this sort of sense of priority
about what we're going to represent,
we can then go back to our condensed version of Boston
and the world map and lay these streets out.
And we actually did lay all of our major streets out.
We knew what they were going to be named
and how they correlated.
And we stuck with these layouts
with very little change all the way to ship.
Once you have streets, you can start thinking more specifically about neighborhoods.
Like any major urban center, Boston has distinct neighborhoods with their own culture, their
own history, their own architectural quirks.
And when we're starting to think about the neighborhoods
that we're gonna represent and try and focus on,
we can start thinking about ownership.
As much as we can, we try to make sure
we assign folks to areas that they're gonna own
from concept to completion.
And so each neighborhood was split off
as its own chunk of work that specific designer
and artist would work together on,
and they'd be responsible.
The onus was on them to understand that neighborhood
and how to bring it to life and how to do it,
how to do right by it.
So with all of this, we're ready to start creating,
we're ready to start iterating.
So this is all kind of pre-production,
this is all ideology and getting ready to attack the city.
Now I mentioned it before, but we have a process for this.
You know, I talked about it a previous year,
and it's this iterative process that we go through
when we build things out.
It's worked really well for level design,
and it only made sense to apply this to downtown.
You know, we have the neighborhoods,
we would treat these as super levels,
and we would just give them more time and attention,
but put them through the process that worked for us.
It didn't work.
It didn't take long to realize that building this view
was gonna be really hard.
We knew it was gonna be hard.
We knew it wasn't something we had attempted before
and there were gonna be wolves in the woods
and unexpected problems.
There were a lot of unexpected problems.
It seemed at times like everything we knew
about level design didn't apply.
Our best practices in pacing, in setting up encounters,
how our AI detection worked, how we optimized,
how well does the editor run, how do we organize,
how do we work together, nothing was going as planned.
And all these hurdles were adding up and taking a lot of time from us.
There was more revision, rethinking, and reworking creating Boston than with anything else.
And it was taxing the schedule of metrics and best practices that we had in place.
But while all of this is going on and all of this is going wrong,
there's something else true, which is that we're building the city modular in a way that we also have never done before.
Now, it's not like we've never built a city space modular before.
For example, in Skyrim, Whiterun is built with a kit.
But it's built with the Whiterun kit.
It's only used to build this city,
and the only person using the kit is the same artist building the pieces
and using them to create the city.
In Fallout 3, the level designers were using building
kits to create those downtown neighborhoods, but those kits
were pretty chunky.
And that's just kind of where we were in terms of the state
of art for us as a studio at the time.
But that was OK, because even though we didn't have a lot of
flexibility to create different shapes to accommodate
our layout goals.
Remember how I mentioned before that they were walled gardens?
That made it really easy to adapt.
If we had a downtown space in DC,
and we wanted to try something else with it,
we could just make the change to the layout
and just move the walls of the garden to accommodate.
It was really no big deal.
But in Fallout 4, everything is connected.
Everything's part of the open world.
We cannot make a change to one neighborhood
without affecting the neighborhood next to it,
and potentially the one next to that,
and creating a ripple effect
that undermined work throughout the city.
But like I mentioned, we were building the city far more modular than we ever had before.
We were taking our lessons from interior kits over the years,
and applying them to how we built downtown.
The pieces were far more granular,
which gave us a couple of freedoms.
One, when there was so much work to do,
we had more people able to do the work.
Level designers and artists both had a tremendous amount
of power to react to issues.
If we needed to change the shape of a building,
we could do that.
We could help an artist, an artist could help us,
and we could make changes without having to make
big custom pieces and get turned around
from the art schedule out of Max Lottie Dott.
And also it let us respect things like the quirky street
layouts of Boston.
We didn't have to conform streets to the buildings.
We could conform the buildings to the streets.
And this meant that when we had a problem that required us to
make a change, we had the ability to do that.
We weren't locked in to bad decisions we had inadvertently
made early on with pieces that were far too static to be
flexible to iterate with.
So while working module this way, you know, it had its own
difficulties and problems, for the most part, it did decrease
the pain and offset all the problems we were running with
Boston and let us maintain a focus on the quality of the
city without having to make a bunch of compromises in how we
approached it because of all the hurdles we ran into. Kind of
saved our bacon.
So now you're going to get the grab bag. This is the stuff
that didn't quite fit into the other categories but that we
wanted to cover.
One of those is the plug and socket system. This is how we
transition between kits. Previously when we transitioned
from industrial to utility, that was a piece we made, that was
it. If we needed to go to a different kit, we would make a
new piece. Not very flexible. So the way we solved it this time
is on the top we have these sockets and that's just a hole
of a set size and then the plugs are door frames and other
things.
So as long as the holes match, we then put the plug in there
and it works. I don't care what kit is on the other side. It's
one of those things that was really, really obvious in
retrospect, but we didn't actually do it that way before,
so it worked out really well. And the way destruction works in
kits is worth going into also. And there's a big problem with
destruction in kits in that it's really repetitive. You just have
this piece or handful of pieces that get used over and over and
it looks the same every time.
So our solution was to have all these different little pieces
that could get used together so then it can look different
every time. So for the wall holes in the building kit,
there's 11 versions of the hole. But that's only actually half
the hole. The other side can be just a different variant or a
different kit entirely. So if it looks too much like one next to
it, I can just start swapping it, swapping it, swapping it,
just swap the one on the other side. So I can have this line
of holes, swap them all.
And again, the other one is being swapped independently, so
there's a lot more potential versions there, and it's really
flexible. This lets us do things like this, where I have this
hallway, it's the concrete kit, material swapped to look like
cinder blocks, and I can just Kool-Aid man through wherever I
want. I can even go to a different kit. Here I'm going
from building kit to utility kit, back to the building kit.
The way floors work is a little bit different, though.
and it's easier to just see it. And at the bottom you can have
these square pieces and they'll sock it in with the normal kit
logic. But then there's all these free floating platforms.
And these exist in all the versions of the building kit.
And this lets us do things like this. Where we have these
really organic hole shapes. And that's not a particular hole
piece. It's just whatever the level designer decided to do.
And there's this ramp you can walk down. Or they can blow that
whole floor out. And then those platforms can be sagged
independently so there's a more organic feel to it.
And we can do things like this where the whole floor is just
caving in. And in this case we didn't build a church basement
kit. It's just the building kit on the bottom. And then we
spend time making unique architecture on the top and
there's not a lot of wasted work. Dynamic destruction is a
little bit different, though. And this is for per piece
destruction where you can shoot out individual planks and it
works with kits and they'll simulate. So you can have
things like this where you have a shack and you start shooting
out individual planks or you take a grenade.
chuck it in there. Then a whole bunch of planks go flying out.
And again, this works with kits. So we use this for railings and
other things like that. Decals and greebles are another thing
that are really obvious but extremely useful. So you can
have a really boring wall like this and just throw a bunch of
rust stains and cracks and greebles are like fans and vents
and things like that. And this isn't baked into the kit. These
are all just placed independently. So if I want to
take that fan and its rust stain, move it over a couple of
feet, you can just do that.
Now every wall can look different and there's a lot
more opportunities for environmental storytelling.
Layers are another thing that are really obvious but save a
ton of time. Because sometimes you load into a scene and it
looks like this. I don't even know what's going on. But you
set up layers and you start freezing things, hiding them,
extremely useful. That's not even the worst example. If you
go downtown, that list is just really long.
The mouse wheel swap is something else that we made.
And previously, if we wanted to swap out a piece,
you would click on a piece, bring up a menu,
and then pick which one you want, hit OK.
Maybe that's the piece you want.
Maybe it's not.
Really, really slow.
But this looks like this, because you can just
click and scroll the mouse wheel.
It's great for finding variance.
And like that wall hole example I showed earlier,
I can just do that in a matter of seconds.
You can go through a whole dungeon
in just a couple minutes.
Big time saver.
And this also works with material swaps.
helper markers are something we talked about in 2013. But we
were being kind of sneaky at the time because we had real kits
that were using it but we couldn't show it so I had to
make a fake kit to show. So this is how it looks in practice.
And there's all these editor only markers to show things like
where the doors are, how the walls line up and it snaps
together. Markers for the ceiling so I don't have to flip
my camera upside down just to click on it. They're really
useful.
but the modular workflow is useful for more than just
architecture. You can also use it for props and things like
that. And one of those things that we built is the machine
kit. And there's this large library of parts, and fins and
tanks and pipes. And an LD can just block out an area and say,
I want a machine here. And then an artist can come and do that.
One of our concept artists, John Gravato, he was really heavily
involved in doing this. And this was a great use of his time
because it was really towards the end of the project. Don't
exactly need a lot of concept art then.
And this ended up looking like this. There's all these
component parts and those are the potential material swaps on
the top. And we can build things like this. Which are composed of
all these tiny little parts. So you can make all kinds of
different things. Even vehicles and arcade cabinets. It's really
versatile. And you can also use it with other existing art like
this truck.
And in a normal workflow, each one of those things could have
been a custom asset.
Someone goes into ZBrush for two weeks, you get a custom
texture, looks great.
That's awesome.
But that takes a long time.
And using this setup, John was able to make 400 machines.
We wouldn't have been able to do that otherwise.
So think about how you can use the modular workflow for more
than just kits.
OK, so I'm going to wind us around into the home stretch.
there's a lot of ground to cover in the talk today. And we kind
of squeezed in everything that we thought we'd really have time
for. But the talk has bounced around a lot just because we
wanted to fit it all in. And honestly, Nate, myself, many of
our colleagues at Bethesda, we could sit and talk to you for
another hour or two or the rest of the day about the ups and the
downs and nuances of this work flow.
And it is a workflow that has ups and downs.
It's not a shortcut.
It's not a solution for all scenarios.
And with this and any other method or approach,
whether it's level design or production
or best coding practices, it's more important
that you understand the, more important
than understanding the workflow,
that you understand the priorities that you have as a team.
and the part is that your game has.
Because any method like this,
you should understand before adopting
because it's never one size fits all.
And I strongly believe that when it comes
to process and technique,
you know, it's the goals of the game,
the ambitions that you have as a team
that should define the process by which it is made,
and never the other way around.
Thanks very much.
We must have been nervous because we have some time. If
anybody has questions, we have microphones set up here. You can
queue up and we'll take a few. You in the middle? I was
wondering at what point in the design process do you factor in
play tester feedback regarding design of levels or aesthetics?
So we have those various iterative stages,
and all those stages can be independently verified.
So what we'll do is we have a few different processes.
We will do peer review.
So people will look at them together and offer feedback.
We will do it within the team.
We can do it with our QA department.
We'll occasionally do sort of big batches of review,
like we call it Level Designer Summer Camp.
where we all get together and we all look at every space in the game and come up with a bunch of feedback
and we structure the feedback based around each of the iterative passes
so that we kind of know what we're looking for and how we can improve.
Cool, thanks.
Over here on the right.
Hello.
My question is, what was the thought process behind choosing which pieces to give to the player
from the kit that you already had?
You mean in terms of the workshop system?
Yeah.
Workshop was kind of a different system, so it was just whatever
we thought would be a useful piece for them to have without
it being too overwhelming.
Like, we didn't want those kits to be like the building kit
where there's 500 pieces.
So we tried to pare it down a bit more.
Yeah, the functionality of the Workshop kits is slightly
different from the ones that we used.
But I think it's fair to say that over time, we started to,
like, the differences between Workshop kits and our regular
kits, it actually got more similar over time than they did
get different.
Yeah.
Thanks.
Question over here.
Yes.
Now, you mentioned that your process changed
between Skyrim and Fallout 4.
Now, given the increased granularity and difficulty
regarding recreating Boston in Fallout 4,
how has the collaboration between artists and level
designers evolved if it did?
Well, one of the big things that we have is there's an art review
process. Since the pieces are so granular, you can pretty much do
whatever you want with them. So we make sure to check everything
and give some notes, which they may or may not agree with, but
it's a bit of a back and forth and it's gotten more official, I
guess, as it's gone on.
Yeah, the main thing is that we have slightly different
sensibilities in terms of what, you know, how important is it
that something looks good and how important is it that
something works good. And so by making sure that we're kind of
both involved in creating the kit but then both involved in
kind of vetting and signing off on the spaces that we create
with them, we can kind of establish parity and sort of
keep the peace between the departments.
All right. Thank you very much.
Thank you. In the middle again.
Hey guys. First thing, great talk.
And then secondly, my question has to do with performance and metrics.
How did that going more modular affect those aspects of the game?
It screwed it up.
Our rendering programmers were not happy with us when we made this decision.
Did they hard cap you?
No, one of the main ways we solved that is we ended up
putting in an object combination system. So even though it was
broken apart into all these different pieces, it would get
chunked in and then visibility after the fact. So it didn't
really matter in the end, just when we were building it and
running it in the editor.
Yeah, but there was a lot of tech that had to be kind of
reconsidered to make this workflow possible.
Yeah, I sort of have the same question, I guess a little more depth.
Okay.
Yeah, how do you, does basically just everything get sort of baked together at the final game?
there is a baking process. So static collections are one way
that we can control essentially baking. We can select a group of
objects and say, yep, this is a static collection now. And those
get handled a little differently in terms of how they render and
how they occlude. We also have a baking process which
precalculates visibility from various directions in the kit
and then we use that visibility to compute quicker on the fly at
run time.
I guess also, do this do any instancing? How much can get
baked? If you have a level, you know, the church scene, you have
a lot of duplicated parts, but then the upper level seems to be
pretty sculpted, I guess. We're not actually instancing. It's
baked out as a large chunk. And the only things that are not
baked out are dynamic objects like a tin can or something like
that wouldn't get combined. Okay. Thank you.
So you mentioned you had a review process for how, when you have conflicts between,
I know we do environment art modularly as well, and we had a lot of fights, like unit abuse,
or like, are you using this correctly, you're not using the unit you're supposed to,
do you solve that by like a creative director stepping in,
saying what is more important, or how do you do that usually?
I mean, we kind of have ground rules. We generally, and some
of this just comes with working together for over a decade.
Generally speaking, when we fight, we already know who's
going to win. Based on the context. At the end of the day,
one side does have to win. And it's kind of case by case. It's
not too often. I guess it happens once in a while where a
third party has to step in and decide. Not often though. I
think the main thing is art has to be kind of okay that things
will happen. I think that's the slowest part of adoption in the
process.
level designers are going to be artists. With this you're going to make decisions. And the
important thing is that there's a two-way street. One of our environment artists is a
practicing architect and came back in the game development. And some of the stuff I do drives
him up the wall.
he'll tell me why and at the end of the day, I hear what you're
saying, but we can't accommodate or he'll end up inputting
something better than the process. So I guess don't be
jerks, right? Just talk. And realize you're going to win
something, you're going to lose something. The game is what
matters, not individual egos. Did those reviews help in
mitigating bigger fights down the line? If you check in once
in a while, does that help rather than?
that's something new. I think it helped a lot. One of the other
things that came from the reviews is the level designer
sort of got how things would work and it would get better and
better over time. So then the notes would just get shorter and
shorter.
Yeah, and for instance, like with the review process that Nate's mentioning,
like really that was Nate, like for the most, maybe entirely, right?
Going through and looking at all the spaces, providing notes, but like
the level designer and Nate, like both knew that
the level designer had the prerogative to ignore everything, right?
Usually they didn't because there was good feedback, but...
Nate had a good barometer for what was misused that he didn't
like versus what was a bug.
And a bug is as a bug.
This is going to cause a problem because you
have used it incorrectly.
Versus, I don't like what you're doing,
and here's a suggestion for how to do it better.
Thanks a lot.
Over here.
Yeah, great talk.
So usually when you're building a large game,
You have to use kits from certain regions and areas so you
don't mix and match tons of different texture maps and
everything. You seem to be mixing a lot of them. Was
everything baked in at the end? Or was that some of the
optimization issues that you guys ran into?
Without extending the question too much, what do you mean by
everything? Everything is baked in.
Say texture maps.
For instance, an example, in something like Lord of the Rings Online, you had an orc kit,
and you could mix that with maybe another race, but you can't mix six kits together
because you're going to pull in a whole bunch of different kind of texture pages.
So you're making more of a technical point than like a world-building and fiction point.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Technical point, yeah.
you're only pulling in the parts you're actually using since it's
all broken apart. So like in that steam tunnel, I bring in
the industrial catwalks and that's it. It's only that one
texture. So that helped. But it's still a lot. But we have
spaces that have like seven, eight kits in it. Was that a two
more questions or no more? Two minutes. All right. Right here.
When building the game, so much of the game as a placeholder initially, do you run into
difficulty with people understanding the final vision or people feeling that like working in a vacuum or
does concept art and previs play a huge role in that or do you guys work so much in this system that it's not an issue?
Well, I think one of the main things is that we don't gray box
gray box. We try to take those kits and put in the details
that matter so you can really get a feel for what it's going
to be even if it's kind of crappy and not done. And that's
made a big difference. Because when we tried to just make a
gray box kit that's just blank walls, ends up not actually
solving problems and it ends up being a problem down the line.
Hey guys, once again thank you for the talk. I found it to be really informative.
And I just have a brief question about the modularity and prefab sort of system that you guys were using.
You mentioned it briefly but it's something I haven't experienced in my previous Bethesda editors that I've experimented with.
So you mentioned that you can tie all the pieces together and then arrange them in chunks.
I just wasn't sure how you would coordinate with all the LDs and artists, how to make sure every prefab meshes with every other one.
like I said, we have a convention that we're used to
from prior games. When the fallout 4 creation kit drops
out, you'll be able to load that up and you'll see, if you're
familiar with our modding, recognizable naming conventions,
recognizable piece shapes. And so we'll have those static
collections bundled up in one part and in a separate folder
usually and then subcomponent pieces. And it's just like we
have this sort of institutional knowledge of the way we expect
kits to be arranged and we just mimicked it.
questions, feel free to come up. We have to tear down here
for the next. Thank you all.