Hi, I'm Meg...
Pfft!
I'm Meg Giant and...
Hi, I'm Meg Giant, I'm a writer, a narrative designer,
I wrote 80 Days and I'm currently working on Sable
and I am so honoured to be your host for the IGF Awards this year.
I can't wait to see you there. 🎵
Hey there, my name is Lach from Bazook Studio.
We made a little game called Just Shapes and Beats.
It's a game that goes a little bit like...
Wait for it...
THIS!
I'm very proud to say that we got nominated for the IGF Award 2019
in Excellence in Visual Art.
So, thank you very much and I hope to see you there!
And my game, Grace Brooks and it Presents, The Haunted Island, a Frog Detective game,
is nominated in the student category of the IGFs.
So you have to come and watch.
At ThruLine Games, we are deeply honoured by the nomination for Excellence in Visual Art
at this year's Independent Games Festival.
Forgotten Anne's painstakingly hand-animated aesthetic is an homage to traditional animation methods,
and we're thrilled that so many of you appreciate the effort that went into making it.
We loved every second of the process.
We hope to see you all at the Pavilion in San Francisco, March 20th to 22nd,
where you can give Forgotten Anne, among a myriad other excellent nominees, a try.
Hi, we are part of the Do Not Be The Monkeys team,
and we're really honored that our game is a finalist at the IGF Awards,
with so many cool games we admire.
This is going to be our first time at IGF, so it's going to be an amazing experience for all of us.
We're really, really excited. So thanks a lot, and see you in San Francisco.
Hello, we are Gossamer Games.
We couldn't be more thrilled that Our Game Soul has been nominated for Best Student Game at IGF 2019.
Over the past few years, we've been hard at work on a deeply personal game that captures our emotional struggle as young artists.
We're so proud to be representing Drexel University, our home city of Philadelphia,
and its amazing indie community, without whom none of this would be possible. It is an honor
to be included in such an incredible list of nominees, and we hope you'll join us at this
year's show. Thank you. Hi, I'm Geoffrof, founder of NovaVox and the writer of Sears Island. I'm
Nicolas, and I invented the art of Sears Island.
Sears Isle is an interactive graphic novel, or if you prefer you can call it a visual novel.
We are very happy that our game was nominated for the Excellence in Narrative Award at the Independent Game Festival.
We will have blessed meeting you all there, please come and visit us and try the game.
I can't wait to meet you there!
What The Golf
I'm Evan Greenwood.
And I'm Robbie Fraser.
We're part of the team that works on General Adjusting here at Free Lives in South Africa.
Our game has been nominated for excellence in narrative, which is super exciting.
We're traveling all the way from South Africa to be at the ceremony.
We've been going many years just sitting in the crowd watching other people
walk on stage and get awards and be talked about and this year it's us!
Come to GDC, watch the IGF awards on stream if you can't be there.
Do it.
I'm Jeremy Gable, the creator of Watch Me Jump, which is nominated for the Excellence
in Narrative Award.
I'm thrilled and shocked to be nominated.
Watch Me Jump is the first game that I ever made, and the fact that the IGF sees something
in this micro-budget adventure proves why I love indie games.
Even when the resources are limited, it's the passion that shines through.
Wait, no, no, don't!
Come on!
En garde!
Greetings and salutations!
I am Julien Finoglio, and I would like to thank you on behalf of my companions and brothers in arms
for nominating En Garde as Best Student Game.
Since publishing our prototype, the reception has been tremendously good.
The greatest video game ever made!
God bless you, game developer! God bless you!
If you have ever dreamt of panache...
of swashing buckles, arrowing flings and darting yawns.
Come try our game at the Independent Games Festival.
Hello.
My name is Zachariah Chandler.
And my game,
Nth Dimensional Hiking,
has been nominated in the Noh Over category.
IGF Awards.
Please come along and see it.
Or tune in.
On the internet.
And also see it.
Hmm, huh, hmm, oh, but I...
Hmm, one, whoa, one, I'm ha-ha.
Ooh, what I got? Ooh.
One, I'm ha-ha.
Ah-ha, eh, nom-a-te.