So we're going to start.
My name is Camden Stoddard of Double Fine Productions.
And I'm David Earl of David Earl Productions and we're the sound and music team of Headlander.
Brought to you by Double Fine and Adult Swim.
So we just wanted to show you a little bit of Headlander in action to start so you get
a chance to see it in full game mode.
The tranquility of the stars is yours, citizen.
You have arrived at the pleasure point, would you like to go in?
NEVER TRUST YOUR JUDGMENT ON THE ENVIRONMENT
Throw your keys, into the person who will use them
I AM DYING
it's not
All right.
So what is Headlander?
Headlander is a retro-futuristic side-scrolling action-adventure game.
It's set in a world inspired by 1970s science fiction.
It's a world of automation in which all of humanity has transferred their minds into
robotic imposter bodies, and it's a utopia gone wrong, which is run by a deranged computer.
Headlander was inspired by the science fiction movies and media of the 70s.
And when I say that, we're not talking about Star Wars.
We're talking about the more experimental and fringe movies of the 70s, movies like
The Black Hole, Silent Running, Logan's Run, and Dark Star, among others.
It takes a long time for those prompts.
These movies had some things in common.
They were experimental with heavy themes,
a bit of dark humor, and most importantly,
they were not a hero's journey.
Another common theme in all of the science fiction
of the 70s was that many of the protagonists
were full of doubt.
The character would start out with a purpose in life
and solid conviction, which is then disrupted
by a shattering doubt as the truth of the system
that they're involved in is revealed.
This gives an unparalleled sense of discovery in these stories.
What we are talking about today, the approach of music and sound for Headlander,
was our attempt to mirror the approach of the filmmakers of 70s sci-fi.
Now, we aren't knocking Star Wars, even though we just ran a line through the Death Star.
We love that movie and many of the movies and media following it.
We're just emphasizing that our influences for this film are firmly rooted in the weird
and experimental aesthetic of 70s dystopian sci-fi.
One of the most experimental aspects of Headlander is its core mechanic.
You're a human head in a life-sustaining flying helmet that can detach and attach to other
bodies, machines and vehicles. And when we asked about the inspiration for this crazy
idea, we were able to get this little clip from Lee Petty, who was the creative lead
for the, and he had this story to tell us.
So sometimes inspiration comes from really strange places.
And I remember thinking about a car accident, or a near car
accident I was almost in once.
And my girlfriend at the time was driving.
And we were going along the freeway, and the car suddenly
braked, and she pulled the wheel really strong to the side.
And I just remember the whole car skidding sideways,
like all the way across in a fast lane,
all the way across all those lanes of traffic.
And I remember that sensation that a lot of people
have in those sort of tense situations
where time seems to slow down.
I remember reaching my hand over there and grabbing the wheel
and trying to straighten the car out
because we were heading right off the road into a ditch.
And we corrected right at the last moment.
It didn't go into the ditch as the car stopped.
And I remember.
Yeah, that feeling of weightlessness, almost like I was in zero-g.
And there was that sensation that, like, maybe my head was accelerating or blasting off.
And I remember remembering that when thinking about this game for some reason.
And then the other piece of the puzzle that actually happened at that same time was she
had a crystal hanging from her reading mirror.
And I remember her reaching up and thanking the crystal for saving us, right, when of
course it was back that I grabbed the wheel.
But there was also something about the idea of a crystal, this like faith in this strange
inanimate object or this artifice that was somehow connected to that for me.
And we have crystal power in the game, so maybe that's...
So, for our creative brief, we're told that Headlander was going to be 70s sci-fi exploration
of a story that's not a hero's journey.
The player becomes less sure of themselves as the game progresses.
And the game is, like, really personal in origin.
In fact, according to Lee, Headlander is an exploration of identity.
In summation...
Really weird, unusual game.
So as lead sound designer working within these
parameters, I had many challenges.
Today I wanted to focus on just three of the biggest and
how I approached them and some of the solutions
I came up with.
These challenges were dialogue profiles for multiple
characters, evoking the memory of 70s sound design, and then
the relationship of the sound design and the music.
In Headlander, you interact with over 25 different characters, and they are all robots.
When 25 different robot characters, and sometimes all of them are on the screen chattering about,
how do you separate their voices?
How can you tell them apart, especially if gameplay relies on it?
To start, I broke the characters of Headlander into groups.
The differences between the groups were determined on a spectrum of absolute machine to almost
human.
Shepherds are weaponized and fully mechanical.
Citizens are robotic with human personalities, but they've been compromised.
It's like they're in a permanent daze.
Rebels are like citizens.
They have robotic bodies, but are fully alert and cognizant.
Global applies to only a few characters.
The deranged computer that runs the whole world, the security system that speaks to
the player through the door, and then a benefactor character that speaks to the player through
the helmet.
Yeah, the door is a character in this game.
Yes, a very rude one.
My solutions to creating unique vocal profiles for these character groups fell mainly into
three techniques, processing, editing, and spatial placement.
For the Shepherds, I fully vocoded the dialogue using an EMS 5000 vocoder plugin.
And the reason I chose this specific vocoder plugin is because out of all the others that
I tested, like the Orange, the Mouth, the Evoke 20, the EMS came the closest to the
original 70s vocoder robot sound that I was looking for.
This is because it's modeled on the original hardware very similar to the one that created
the iconic voices of the Cylons from the original Battlestar Galactica.
I don't think any voice of the 70s could be more iconic than the Cylons.
Here's some examples of some of the shepherds.
I have a dry example and then vocoded wet.
Citizens are also adviced that prolonged eye contact with shepherds will result in
immediate termination.
Citizens are also advised that prolonged eye contact with Shepard will result in immediate termination.
I love that plugin.
Cry not upon, the destruction is to be expected.
There's a little explanation here.
So there's a certain part of the game that's based on chess and all the characters were
speaking Elizabethan, like Shakespearean lines.
So it got very difficult processing Shakespeare through a vocoder.
Yeah, trying to make Shakespeare happen when they sound like a robot.
Or a silent.
Cry not upon, the destruction is to be expected.
End of line.
Yes.
I lit a car, lit a car, a castle, a floor.
I lit a castle, a floor.
All functions transferred to primary unit.
In this case, this was a really specific hunter-shepherd.
It was almost insect-like.
So we asked the actress to enunciate all of her S's and really, really hard pronounce them.
And we got this result.
Perfection.
Sleep mode activate.
Very fun.
For the Citizens and Rebels, my approach was slightly different,
because I wanted some of the humanity to poke through.
Citizens and Rebels are closely related.
In the game, the citizens are being controlled by a behavioral dampening circuit.
They're kind of out of it, like they're in a trance.
The rebels, on the other hand, are fully aware,
since they have removed that circuit.
The removal had consequences, though,
in the form of speech impediment,
robotic stutter, if you will.
The process tones of both these characters
are actually the same.
It was basically a heavy chorusing effect.
But it occurred to me the best way
to show the difference between these characters
would be in the editing.
For Citizens, I chose to show the loss of their humanity by editing out the breaths
of the voice actors that were portraying the citizens.
Now, any good dialogue editor will tell you that keeping the breaths in are good for motion,
for showing how the character is feeling.
But it was this kind of vaguely disturbing feel that I was going for, so I took them
all out.
The rebels, on the other hand, I kept their breaths in to show that they had regained
some of their humanity, but they also had a digital stutter due to the fact that they
had slightly damaged themselves when removing their circuit.
This also had the benefit of making them sound like they were struggling, which added to
their story arc in the game.
Now I gave the rebels a stutter roughly every five lines, and I had to do it manually.
So as you can imagine, this was a little bit more than trimming tops and tails, and in
all it added another two to three months of extra dialogue editing.
And here's some examples.
It reminds me that it's what's inside that counts.
Headlander!
They're also very 70s.
Artemis 11, signing out.
We're headed to the Luna Citadel soon.
I hope you'll be with us.
You know what I'm talking about, Michael.
For the next set of characters, they needed to sound like they were coming from everywhere.
These voices were actually coming out of the world around the player, including the
player's helmet on occasion.
This differs greatly from the robots that are just walking around in the environment.
These characters are the environment.
Every room, every ship, every vehicle had these omnipresent characters.
On occasion these characters would morph from 3D to 2D depending on the game state.
In order to give these characters the kind of weight and power that they possess, I used
heavy, heavy compression with a lot of drive and phasing techniques.
When I'm talking about these characters and how powerful they are, I literally mean they
are filled with electricity and energy.
It's like the whole world is talking to you when they speak.
Here's some examples.
Incorrect color, no admittance.
This is the rude door.
Yeah, that's the door.
Incorrect color, no admittance.
Take your little costume and go play somewhere else.
Lockdown is over. Let the game continue!
This is the queen in the chess world, very Eastern European.
For this character, the actor was very, very good, but he kind of still felt like a little
bit of an old man, so added a lot of weight through him through compression and sub.
Here's what he sounds like dry.
It's time for a reminder on the importance of waste management from your friendly neighborhood
refuse captain Electrosucksz4.
It's time for a reminder on the importance of waste management from your friendly neighborhood.
So, what is sound design from the 70s if not Star Wars inspired sound design?
When I was studying sound design for Headlander, the movies they studied like Dark Star and
Westworld and Logan's Run actually had pretty lackluster sound design.
I wasn't really that impressed.
But I was surprised that my memories of these movies did not match up to the reality of
how they sounded when I saw them later.
And I actually had a similar reaction recently to 8-bit music.
I have all kinds of reactions to 8-bit music.
That's another story.
I did appreciate how the sound designers of these movies worked within their constraints
and the approach they took.
I noticed that the sound design was not taking wildly different sounds and blending them
together to get a bigger sound.
If there was to be something like an engine, it would be an amalgam of engines, not an
elephant roar or dry ice on a cymbal or a ball-peen hammer hitting a cable.
Sound designers on these movies would take a single source or only a couple and then
process these few sources with very strange delays, hyper pitch shifting and massive compression.
In the black hole, the engines of the ship don't sound like new technology or particularly
futuristic, they just sound really, really big.
The transport in Westworld, which is a sort of futuristic hydrofoil, just sounds really,
really loud.
My favorite is the guns in Logan's run.
It's like the sound designer was more concerned with the energy being output by the weapon
rather than being concerned with how the weapon was creating the energy.
Now this all changed radically after Star Wars where folks like Ben Burtt would open
the door to layered sound design.
For Headlander though, I was interested in pre-Burtt sound design where constraints played
more of a role in the results.
A lot of the sounds of 70s sci-fi were more mechanical.
Later on, sounds of robotics and chips and doors and other elements would be based on
hydraulics and other more efficient futuristic things.
But I wanted to approach things in Headlander like they were all mechanical in nature, even
the computers.
And I received this creative direction from Lee who said in this world, in Headlander's
world, digital was never invented.
Here are some of the examples that I did.
Just maxed.
This is feedback being played through an 8-track player's speaker.
It had a really weird property.
That 8-track was crazy.
Tape delay for days.
This is actually the inner workings of a clock.
So the other part of 70s sound design that I noticed was the use of synthesis.
The appearance of a synthesizer in early 70s cinema especially was not blended in with
other sounds.
It was usually a cue for the listener denoting a special event, like an evil robot arriving,
a large ship taking off, or teleportation.
I realized my sound design and use of synthesizers in Headlander would need to be particularly
mindful of the soundtrack, which Dave was making, and it was wonderful.
I also noticed something about the story arc.
I realized over the course of the game, the separation of music and sound design needed
to become less and less obvious.
As the character becomes more and more confused, and the situation becomes more unhinged, the
sound and the music needed to blur.
This would enhance the effect of being uncomfortable and unsure for the player.
And Dave and I were both given instructions for the end of the game to be very, very psychedelic,
and as Lee put it, to take the gloves off.
Here are some examples of our psychedelic sound design blurring into music.
This was all made by the voices of people who work at Double Fine, by the way.
This next example is made entirely out of guitar feedback.
Ahem.
So as you can see, it had to get very unhinged.
And I would like to now turn it over to Dave and the
wonderful soundtrack and synthesis work that he did.
Aw, thanks, man.
I mean, it's amazing to work on a game where it's only you
and one other person making all of the sound.
Like, all of the sound.
It makes it a very personal thing.
So I started working on the music for Headlander in 2013
when Lee Petty was doing Amnesia Fortnight, which is
this sort of.
pitch that everybody in the company is pitching a game.
And so I was able to work on it.
And the original aesthetic for the game was to be sort of
John Barry in space.
So John Barry does like the James Bond scores.
And the original black hole was John Barry.
And when Adult Swim swooped in, the aesthetic changed.
They shoved it into the 70s.
And that made me pretty happy.
The new idea was to draw upon the electronic music of the 70s and I was beaming ear to
ear because as a kid I was absolutely crazy about electronic music.
I was really entranced with the worlds of Vangelis and Wendy Carlos and Jean-Michel
Jarre and Izao Tomita and Tangerine Dream.
He knows what I'm talking about.
And the idea that I could create music from my childhood,
like something that was just going to be this pure nostalgia fest,
had me really excited.
But there were some challenges, and I just wanted to explore
three of the sort of things that I had to deal with.
As Camden said before, the game was taking place in a world that existed without the
microchip.
And it's also noted that it had a bunch of robots instead of humans.
And even the protagonist didn't have lungs.
So it was going to make things kind of interesting.
From the very beginning, I was told that the score for Headlander needed to sound as synthetic
as the world that it was set in.
This meant that I was going to find myself some analog synths.
Yeah, there's some great software out there. But my goal was to get knobs and sliders and a
real tactile sort of writing process. There wasn't much in the 70s as far as like digital
recording was concerned, not sort of mass produced. So music was recorded to tape. So I'm
like, ah, I got to get my hand on some tape. Oh, it'll be great. Tape. So, you know, I'll talk a
little bit about that.
Science fiction of the 70s also had the kind of classic themes that were expected of film scoring.
They were still kind of throwbacks to the 50s and 60s and there were still those kind of expectations placed on the composers, just with a different palette.
And I knew I was going to need to create some themes for Headlander, but I didn't want to get all John Williams, you know, like leitmotifs and like opera.
You know, it was going to be much more simple.
And I knew that I needed to make the score sound really personal.
Sometimes cheesy and definitely sentimental.
The soundtracks that inspired Headlander sometimes conveyed an almost naive sense of
the future.
You could hear the composers tinkering around with synthesizers.
They were trying to pull emotions out of synthesizers and sort of failing.
So it was a lot of fun to listen to these composers experimenting with what they considered
new technology.
and integrate it in with their composer tendencies.
So I wanted to try and capture that as well,
that kind of sense of experimentation,
that naive, sort of childlike sense of experimentation.
So I already had an SH-101 by Roland and I had a Korg Monotron.
The Monotron is this big and it's like fifty bucks and it's awesome.
Every sound designer and composer should have one.
And then the Dave Smith Prophet 8.
And I was like, oh, you know, I could do the whole score on these three synths.
Ha ha ha ha ha.
Yeah, that wasn't going to happen.
So I ended up leaning on, I did cheat a little bit, and I leaned on Monarch by NI, and a whole bunch of reactor ensembles.
Like I have a really amazing Selina string ensemble in Reactor that I really enjoyed a lot.
And then of course I had a sampled Buchla, System 100 Buchla that helped a lot.
So I'd originally envisioned writing all the music at home.
And then going into the synth museum in Emeryville. Because the synth museum in Emeryville has
everything. They have the Yamaha CS80. I mean they have all these like really rare analog
synths. And if you ever want to go and just play with analog synths, that's the place to go.
It's an amazing, amazing joint.
They're all taken care of and ready to record and everything. But after a couple of days of
recording with my sense, I knew I was going to have to get sense in my studio because the
immediate gratification of having the sense right there, I could wake up, walk in my studio
and just go for it, well, it kind of infected me with the sickness.
So Jeff Cross is a friend of mine who works over at Apple, and he's a great electronic
musician.
And I remembered his collection of analog synths.
I went over to his house, and we were hanging out, and I was drooling all over them.
So I drove a van to his house, and I decided to ask him, after I drove the van to his house,
if I could borrow his synths.
And he agreed.
So I immediately loaded them in the van before he could change his mind.
We ended up with a Yamaha CS15, we had a Moog Prodigy and an ARP Odyssey and the
original Korg MS-20 and a lot of the soundtrack was written on these devices.
So I'm eternally grateful to Jeff but I wasn't done there. So another friend of
mine, Frank Garvey, I remembered he had this huge collection of synths and I'd call
him up and I'm like, hey Frank, you know those synths? Yeah.
Can I borrow them? Well if you get them out of Hawk. They were all sitting in a pawn shop off
of 6th Street here in San Francisco. If you know 6th Street in San Francisco, not a great
area. So that said, Candidate and I made a deal and we bailed them out, rescued them. That
included the Moog Voyager XL. We had a Dave Smith mono and poly evolver. And we had a
Another ARP Odyssey. And then of course I had all of my synths. So as you can see, got a lot of
synths going on in this score. It was kind of ridiculous. And one of the things that was
important about this was just to realize that I have this community of people that I've put a
lot of energy and time into and I try to really help everybody I possibly can. Anybody who
knows me knows that I will like...
give you whatever I can technically to help you out. And it came back. And that was just
really nice to feel that reciprocity, which was really, really cool. So on my first
date, I mean night, with the Moog Voyager XL, I ran it through Valhalla DSP's Shimmer
Reverb and it was just a total revelation. I mean, it just changed everything. And I just
hit record and started going with it and ended up with stuff like this.
It's quite a night.
Oh man, it was a hell of a night.
If you have any questions or other problems, please post them in the comments.
I will be happy to help.
Look, people walking now, they're like, what the hell is going on?
So all of that that you just heard are excerpts from a single improvisation.
An unbroken improvisation that went on for about seven and a half minutes and it's on
the Headlander soundtrack.
It's called Methuselah's Game.
And there's no editing, there's no like, no quantize, no nothing.
It's just, it's just a synth and a reverb and that's it.
So the creative direction for the game is also to have this kind of polished and slick
sound, but have some cracks in the veneer showing the decrepit and broken innards of
a world that was being held together with spit and glue.
So I really thought that using tape was going to help me get there.
And I was really excited about it.
I remember recording on tape, barely.
And I was like, OK, we're going to saturate the tape,
and we're going to get all this tapey goodness and all
this great stuff.
And there's going to be this dirt and wow and flutter and
all this cool stuff.
I even had a wire recorder set up, and I had cassette players
and all this stuff.
And in the course of using it, I remembered something.
I hate tape.
I hate it. I hate almost everything about it.
And I just, my nostalgia took me over. You know, I don't like loading tape machines.
I don't like waiting for the transport. I don't like maintaining the machines.
There's some engineer out there with like a gun.
But, you know, some of the tracks on the soundtrack ended up staying that have the
layback from tape. But honestly, it was such a pain to work with.
It was an important revelation for me.
Camden was talking earlier about how he had watched these
movies from the 70s and was like, you know, sound design
is not really great.
And I had a similar reaction when I was using tape.
So it was kind of important, because I
remembered using tape.
I remember hitting the view meters.
I remember trying to get it as loud as possible, and
saturating tape.
I remember doing that.
And it was fun.
My memories were fun.
But when I actually started doing it again, I was like,
this is a pain.
So I went back, and I started listening to old soundtracks
and watching old commercials.
I even checked out the really crappy color palette of the 70s where everything is beige and
brown and yellow and orange. Even the wood trimmed technology. You would have this really
awesome piece of tech or synth and it had wood on it. Which makes me laugh when you open
garage band it has wood paneling on the sides. So, you know, I'm not a big fan of the
Going through all this stuff, I realized that I had to put some ugly in the score.
You know, I needed some stuff that was just ugly and gross, like the 70s were,
to properly show, you know, this fabricated world that this computer was trying to think up.
You know, all the way down to like Adobe and lapels.
So tape reminded me of all that, and that was kind of important to go through that whole series of hating tape,
but I did also find out that I love tape emulation.
So...
I ended up leaning a lot on UAD for their Studer 800 and
Roland Space Echo and EP34 tape delay.
McDSP, I used their AC201 and 101, which do a really good
job of emulating that sort of hardware.
I also used Wave's Eddie Kramer tape.
And that stuff worked really well.
It gave me concise control.
My loops would come out correct.
I could play something back twice, and it
would sound the same.
It was a lot of fun to use that stuff.
And I also used console emulation from Steve Slate,
which helped me not only get these emulations of the sort
of non-linear sounds of these.
analog channels across my mix, but I could also sum as well, which worked out pretty well.
Now, one of the funniest things and most memorable things about Headlander when we were talking
about the score was no drums for you.
In the first meeting, Lee was pretty open about, you know, ideas and things about the
score and like where we were going to go with it, but then out of the blue he goes, oh,
by the way, I don't want drums.
I hate drums.
I don't want them at all.
No drums anywhere.
I couldn't believe it.
Yeah, I mean, my eye was twitching and I'm like, you know, as you can imagine, it's a
huge limitation.
It's a pretty big deal because drums do so much. They drive the soundtrack, they add drama,
they can even transport you to a decade of choice if you're using a drum kit. I was looking
forward to that, the 70s thuddy dead drum kit, like Fleetwood Mac or something. I was looking
forward to that kind of thing and maybe going towards Led Zeppelin or something. No. Nope.
No drums for you. So I'm like, well, what am I going to do? I'm going to have to drive
things along. So I ended up using sequencers and arpeggiators.
And using more of synthesis to try and drive things.
Some of my synths, like the SH-101 that I brought with me,
have an onboard sequencer and an onboard arpeggiator.
And I was able to use those and help use that to drive the
score and create motion.
One of the things that's funny about these old sequencers,
the simple sequencers, is that they go beat to beat.
It's like da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da.
So I came up with this solution of taking, you know, they take
control voltage, right? It's not MIDI. It's like you're literally
taking a guitar cable and going click and sending voltage to
make it do something.
And the clock on here basically is looking for control voltage to pulse.
So what I did is I took a cable out of my audio interface and in Logic I have this drum
machine playing a really, really, really loud stick clack.
And I would be able to use the sequencer within UltraBeat to program these kind of disjointed
patterns.
So the clock in here that was coming in was no longer this steady thing.
It would be...
And it worked really well.
It was actually really cool.
I also used the Moog Voyager XL's MIDI beat clock to CV
control as well to help facilitate that.
It worked out really well.
So what I wanted to do is just show you a
little bit about my baby.
This is the SH-101 that you see on screen.
It's the same as the one I have, except it doesn't have
that awesome.
I thought about getting the handle just for this talking
engagement, and I was going to get the little headset mic
and start zapping and rogering all over the place.
But.
So what we have is we have a modulator, VCO, you know,
that's an oscillator, we've got a mixer for all these different waves,
and we've got a filter and an envelope.
Monophonic, I can play one note at a time.
But what's beautiful is the note sounds...
For a little tiny synthesizer that can run on batteries,
you know, this thing can sound pretty amazing.
To give you an example, I can also drop that down a little bit.
And when I talk about the immediacy of
sliders, that's what I'm talking about. Like you just sit there and you grab
something and make something happen.
So I really have a lot of fun with that.
So with the envelope on the right hand side, of course, I can shape how the sound
propagates.
If I make a very short decay, now I'll load up that sequencer that I was talking about.
So I have an internal clock that's running this right now.
That's basically how that and the arpeggiator work.
Yeah, I gotta say, as a sound designer, it was really easy to be inspired with the stuff he was sending me.
This was fun.
And speaking of sound design, so I'm not allowed to use drones, right?
Right?
You know I'm gonna cheat, so...
On these old synthesizers, they always had a noise generator.
You know, it sounds like...
It's what you get when your television used to turn off at night, which it doesn't do anymore.
And so I've got noise.
But what's cool about noise is that if you add a resonant peak on your filter,
it's singling out some of those frequencies.
So you end up, it does self-oscillating, which is pretty neat and very handy.
Cause if you start adding an envelope to your filter,
you know, you have something that sounds a lot like, I mean, all that reverb,
but it's like a kick drum, right?
Yeah.
Especially in old video games and things like that, they use little
tricks like this all the time.
Then if you wanted to get a snare, you just turn that resonance down and turn
the frequency up.
And then you have this cool thing where if you hold it down, it dies.
But if you turn your release up...
Yeah, thanks, Flynn.
So it's just so much fun for sound design.
Oh, and you have the huge bass drop, you know, like if you go into a club and you're like...
I don't have much of a sub going on here.
No.
Oh, that's sad.
Anyway, so anyway, I just wanted to show you some of the things that the synth could do
and kind of how I have fun with it.
You know, I definitely have an illness.
So when I create a queue for Headlander, I would think
really vertically.
And what I mean by that is I would stack, I'd make a
composition, but then stack it very deep with stems and give
them over to Camden so that he could mix these stems together
in different ways.
It's essential to do that sort of thing so you can get as
many queues as possible, as many rooms and things covered
with a single queue as possible.
Yeah, I think the final count was 143 tracks.
It's a sickness.
The score would change.
You'd get more stems if you're in a large room, less stems if you're in a small room.
Things would be filtered a certain way.
If you're outside, Camden would throw a lot of reverb on it and things like that.
There's even one room where you walk over these lasers and Camden had pulled out this
sequenced noise and just pushed that up in the mix.
It really gave you a feeling of lasers, which was cool.
That was really unique for me.
I mean Camden had this amazing ability to remix my material
without pissing me off.
And I never let people kind of mix my stuff, but Camden just
really had an ear for it.
And after a couple levels, I knew that I could
trust him implicitly.
I think it's explicit.
Anyway.
So I knew I could trust his judgment, and we were on the phone every day talking about
this stuff.
And that was new to me as well, like having a team and feeling part of a team when you're
an external contractor doing music.
I was invited to meetings every week from the beginning, before levels were designed.
When we were talking about concepts, I was in there with them talking to people who were
building levels and rooms and people making art. It was incredible. And because of all this,
I was sitting in a meeting one time and I just kind of piped up because I saw that they had this
one level in...
Headlander that was calling back to this movie Silent Running.
And Silent Running is this movie where basically they're
flying the last forests of Earth through space to save
them.
And Bruce Dern falls in love with these forests and
essentially murders all of his crew mates to save the
forests.
And then there's this scene where he's walking through one
of the forests, thinking about killing his crew or whatever.
It's very serene.
And this Joan Baez song comes on.
You know, and it just, this like morose Joan Baez syrupy folk song comes on.
It was surreal.
And I'm like, we have to do that.
We gotta make that happen.
And I mentioned it to Camden and then we brought it up at the meeting and they were like, oh
yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, we're gonna do that.
So not only did they include the song, which I had my wife sing the Joan Baez part and
I wrote this song that was like just a total ripoff of.
It's a little bit like a movie.
I'm sorry, homage of the song in Silent Running.
They not only took the song and put it in there, they changed game mechanics, they slowed
the level down, they like ducked all the sound and all the dialogue.
And we ended up with this.
Freedom is your mindset free.
It's all gone.
Like a dreadful knowing smile,
was once made.
It's all gone.
Mass carnage.
Okay, well, you get the idea.
When it goes...
A little bit later on, a little bit later on, the full band comes in,
and there's of course a flugelhorn solo, and you know...
I went there.
But that's incredible, right?
Somebody's going to let you do an idea like that?
That was batty.
So working on Headlander got Camden and I experimenting in
a really unique way.
And by creating the sound design with these boundaries
and limitations set on us, I think it pushed us to create
something really special.
So what did we learn from all of this?
When Dave and I were first introduced to the ideas behind Headlander, we both had a very
visceral reaction to the content.
When I first saw the trailer where the Headlander's head lifts off his body, I literally got creepy
goosebumps.
So the strength of the initial idea and the core of the game's story was something we
need to keep in our sights over the course of production.
And sometimes when you're working on a game for a long time, you can forget where you
came from.
So Dave and I had come up with some ways to keep that initial powerful idea intact, and
we wanted to pass it along to you today.
First of all, distill the inspiration of the game down to its essence.
Think of it like a funnel where you put all of your influences at the top,
and then at the other end you're going to get the building blocks
made up of the sound profile of all those influences.
In Headlander, we put all of the sci-fi movies of the 70s into a funnel
and came out with a palette for sound, music, and dialogue
based on what was common amongst all those influences.
And that technique can be used for anything, any genre.
We then took that palette and we put constraints on it in terms of sound source, tools, and techniques.
And this put us in a similar position of those who were experimenting within sci-fi cinema in the 70s.
And those experimentations resulted in some very creative solutions.
We encourage you to occasionally use constraints in your projects to foster experimentation.
Remind yourself during the course of the project of where you started when you first took the
project on, you know, that initial spark and inspiration. Get it from yourself and how
you felt about it when you first heard it and also talk to the team about it and always
reinforce that initial spark that got you going. You know, if you're an external contractor,
make sure that you engage with the developers as much as you can if you're not in-house.
If you are working in-house, talk to everyone on the team and avoid isolation.
The perspectives and ideas of what the game is about and where it's going will change
your approach and enrich your perception.
Thanks for joining us today.
It was really fun to talk to you about this game.
Please rate the presentation if you can.
Yes, please rate us.
And we hope you enjoyed it.
Thank you.
And we'll take any questions if you like.
If anybody has any questions.
Anybody?
Oh boy.
Of course.
Can I eat my banana now?
Yeah, totally. That was really good, guys. That was great talk.
I had a serious question, actually.
70s aesthetic versus modern audience expectations.
So, it's so rad that you guys went there with the sound design especially,
just getting that like, you were talking about the pre-Ben Burt era kind of stuff.
I'm sorry, my voice is shot.
But there is a certain level of audience expectation for the
timbre and tonality of what they want to be pleasing.
So how did you end up balancing that?
Well, I remember while I was studying for sound design anyway, when I would go in and look at these old movie ideas and like Lee would bring in something we'd watch as a team.
I remember looking at it two different ways, which was like what was actually happening and like what I remembered when I first saw it.
Like I would kind of design to the memory as well.
So that was one thing.
Because I remember when I was growing up and I first saw
the black hole and everything, I was super inspired by it.
And when I came back, I was like, it's not
what I thought at all.
So I started doing a journal of how I actually remembered
it, and I would kind of combine that.
Yeah, you'd go on your memory, not what's real.
Yeah.
I mean, I had a tremendous, I mean, Stranger Things came out
at the same time as Headlander.
And it's just a trip to be sort of in the flow of that particular zeitgeist.
I mean, and I feel that, I mean I did definitely in the score, I cheated a lot by layering things in such a way
and using reverbs and stuff that you'd never hear back then.
And hopefully, you know, the low end and some of the ways that you adjust timbre for modern expectations, I think,
you know, we sort of inherently, we sort of did that without thinking about it, I think.
It sounds really, am I blocking anyone?
The door that was doing the laughing, I really, for me it resonated with the memory of the skeleton in The Last Unicorn.
I didn't know if that was intentional or not, but it was great, man. It was great.
Also, the layered feedback element that you played sounds exactly like a Sun song.
And this is on a serious tip. When he delivered the music to you on reels, was that a challenge
for you?
Like I would ever deliver to him on reels. That's a funny trick question.
It was easy.
I just delivered the whole machine.
First of all, where is, hi, great talk, thank you very much.
Oh, thank you.
Where is the Synth Museum, please?
Oh, the Synth Museum in Emeryville.
I will find it for you right now, because I
have it in my contacts.
Yeah, the Synth Museum is fantastic.
I will find the address.
Well, which city even?
Emeryville.
Yeah, across the bay.
Okay.
And also about the feedback thing.
Did you record the feedback and then sampled it and like, you know, played it?
Or how did you pitch it?
No.
Actually.
I didn't do any sampling in this entire project.
What I did is me and my senior sound designer, I don't know
if he's here, Paul, but we basically took my guitar in my
office and just beat the hell out of it and made it feedback
for like two hours.
And then it was all editing.
I literally just did everything by edit.
OK.
Yeah.
I guess technically it's in Oakland.
So it's 1145 65th Street.
We need that in LA.
I'm sure you do. I mean, in L.A.
Thanks for the talk.
It's called Jesper Kidd.
So, could you have, do you have any recommendations for someone who's not into analog synths to start the sickness?
To say, having one synth to start.
Uh, my, my key into that deep hole was the uh, the Korg Monotron.
Yeah.
Instant.
And the Korg, Korg has done a fantastic job of sort of reinvigorating, I felt that they were really on the forefront of reinvigorating, um, the synth movement, the analog synth movement.
And they have these little boxes.
There are a lot of things that are really inexpensive. The vulca series that you can chain
together and they have like a sequencer and they have the monotone which has a little ribbon on
it that you can play the keys on. But it has real analog filters on it and stuff and that kind of
juiciness that you get.
analog you can pull out of those. Even the MS 20 is only about 700 bucks but you can get in on
the ground floor using the Volca series. If you want to get really sick, well no I'm not going
to start you down that road. The euro rack stuff is pretty interesting, pretty cool stuff.
It all depends, you know I'm talking about analog synthesis but to be more specific I'm
talking about, uh, uh, uh, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the,
I'm doing subtractive synthesis and maybe a little bit of sync,
you know, hard sync synthesis and things like that. And I think
that subtractive synthesis is a really great place to start
because you're taking waves that are rich with content and then
you're pulling out harmonic stuff out of them using really
interesting filters. Go for the Volca series first, I think.
Awesome. Thank you. Yeah, absolutely. Anybody else?
Thank you.
Thanks.