Hello and welcome to GDC 2021.
This is our live AMA Q&A with Global Game Jams, Kate Edwards.
That was a lot of letters all at once.
I'm Joel Kinshore, Editor-in-Chief of Indie Games Plus.
I'll be the moderator for this session.
My pronouns are he, him, and I am ridiculously excited to announce Kate Edwards.
If you've got a ton of questions for her, let's rock.
Yeah, absolutely.
Thank you so much for having me here.
It's great.
As a longtime participant in GDC,
this is a little bit different from what I'm used to,
but that's great.
So absolutely, let's get moving on this.
Very cool.
So I'm gonna jump right in
before anybody else has any questions
because I'm lucky I can do that.
What first interested you
in bringing your geographer experience into video games?
Cause that's, that sounds really interesting to me.
Yeah, that was really kind of a mistake, a happy mistake, because I, you know, like many
people in my generation who are, you know, above 50 or in our, you know, up there, more
veteran status, I guess, we didn't, game design and game, you know, creating games, there's
not really a clear career path.
You know, coming out of high school or in the college days.
So for me, I basically pursued what I was interested in,
which was, you know, wanting to be an astronaut,
wanting to be an artist for Lucasfilm because I want to work on Star Wars
and then eventually settled on geography and cartography
because I've always had this incredible interest in cultures and travel
and maps and everything.
And plus the artistic artistic skill I had, I could use with cartography.
And so basically to make a really long story short, I pursued that field and I'm really happy I did.
It's been fantastic and I ended up doing my graduate school work at the University of Washington in
Seattle and I just finished my master's degree which was focused on using VR for cartography.
That was way back in 1991 and Microsoft called our department and said they needed a cartographer to
work on a cart encyclopedia, which some people out there might remember.
And so I went over to Microsoft on what I thought was going to be like a really short-term contract
to be a cartographer and you know basically help create the maps for the initial version of Encarta.
Well that turned into a longer and longer contracts and eventually a full-time position
and I in that full-time role which was still initially mainly focused on the cartography in
In Carta World Atlas, in Carta Encyclopedia, Streets and Trips, like all the mapping products that Microsoft was doing.
I did get asked by the Flight Sim team at one point, they're like, hey, you know, you're a cartographer, we need some help with some advice on this.
But where it really started for me,
when I really started working on games,
was I created an internal team at Microsoft
called Geopolitical Strategy,
because I noticed that the company was having struggles
with maintaining knowledge around what is sensitive
from a political standpoint or cultural standpoint.
um in the content that they were producing and so like you know the office tea would make a mistake
in one market and then you know another product group who does you know completely across the
company would make a similar mistake and then they'd get in all this really big trouble with
the government because you know they were making these mistakes and so I basically determined that
this is a weakness and so there needs to be a group that coordinates that kind of knowledge
across the company.
So once I created that team, that was way back in 1998,
that also gave me the mandate to work on all Microsoft products,
including all the games. So I started working on all the PC
stuff back then, like all the Age of Empires and Asheron's
Call and all those kinds of games, MechWarrior. And then of course, we got
into the early Xbox, you know, because Xbox had that
But then I got to basically work on all of those Microsoft franchises.
Halo, you know, obviously, Fable, Forza, all of that stuff.
And that's when I really found like this is my calling.
I get to do what I call culturalization work on video games.
So it's basically this incredible confluence of everything I love.
Technology, creative media, games.
Geography, cartography, all of this stuff came together in a really strange way, and I'm so thankful that it did.
And I love what I do.
Yeah, it sounds like it's really interesting work and it works well to all your interests.
And if the audience has any questions, feel free to jump in, throw those in the chat.
Otherwise, I'm just going to keep taking over the whole talk because I'm super busy.
I want to keep pushing forward. Can you tell us some of the...do you have some interesting
stories on your work with like Halo or Call of Duty or any of those?
Oh yeah, there's a lot of stories. I mean, probably one that has become...I've used this in
some of my lectures...one that caused a lot of problems is we had one game...
that probably a lot of people have never heard of or don't remember called
Cockroach Chogen, which was on the original Xbox.
It was like a hand-to-hand fighting game.
And the problem is that the game included a initially included an audio file
that had chanting from the Quran.
So it was, you know, I do remember this.
Yeah. So it was Harjinder Raab, but.
Yeah, no, exactly. So it was chanting lyrics from the Quran, which they, you know, basically that's probably that's not appropriate to have in a game in that kind of context. And so, you know, when I raised the concern, it was it was brought to me. And then I verified it with someone who was, who was in my building, who's actually originally from Kurdistan.
And so he's like, yeah, he's like, this is going to be a big problem.
I'm like, yeah, I figured that.
So basically, the decision was made to fix it right away.
But the problem was that we already had actual copies of the game
already printed and literally rolling on their way to stores.
And so the challenge then is like, what are we supposed to do with all those copies that are out there?
And of course, my decision was just destroy them.
I mean, recall them and just, you know, we'll make new ones.
Because for a company like Microsoft, it's not that expensive, you know, to redo that.
But the decision was made to go ahead and release only the U.S.
because the feeling was that it should not be a big issue, even though.
As a geographer, I'm like, did you know that there's, you know, eight or nine million Muslims in the United States?
Did you know that's like Detroit's 50% Muslim?
It's like we are not a homogeneous society here.
So there are people in this country who are going to be, you know, who are going to notice this.
And I was told, don't worry about it.
So basically, you know, and the decision was kind of a convoluted decision.
I'm not going to go into how that was made, but basically.
Because the game did release, we did get a letter from the government of Saudi Arabia that basically was telling us that this was a huge problem.
It became front page news in the Middle East really rapidly. It really started to explode in the region as a negative piece of news.
And so I eventually was asked by the head of the Middle East region of Microsoft to come over there and basically help do damage control because I, as a geographer and in the role I served in Microsoft, I knew, you know, the complex issues behind it and why this is going to be sensitive.
So they said it'd be great if somebody from headquarters like you could come over and actually explain what's going on and what happened.
And so I did, and I ended up going to Riyadh, and I landed in Riyadh two days before the
second Gulf War started. So that was exciting. So exciting is a word for it.
You know, and I didn't really, I wasn't really thinking about it. Obviously, I was aware of what
was going on in the world. But at the same time, I'm like, well, that's my job, I need to go there
and do this. And so what was fascinating is that, you know, I sat in front of representatives of the
religious council of the Saudi government to explain to them.
And it was to say it was a bit uncomfortable is an understatement.
But basically, to shorten the story, you know, I basically explained to them what happened.
And, you know, they accepted the apology and then we just moved on.
Then I went over to Dubai and had to do something similar, even though, you know, the UAE is a more liberal culture within the region.
So it wasn't quite as stringent there.
But the point being is that one audio file that somebody did not check,
that nobody asked, like, what are these lyrics? Where is this from?
All because of that, the game eventually was globally recalled because it just was so caustic.
It created such negative PR. And, yeah, it was unfortunate.
It actually showed up on eBay for a while, like, hey, banned video game.
Actually, the price was fairly high at one point, but then, of course, it immediately dropped.
So that was just one example of many, many kinds of challenges in this space that you have to deal with because, you know, choices have consequences.
And we have to be super careful about where we're, you know, putting in games, even though, you know, the developer said, well, we put it in there because it sounds cool.
And I agree, it does sound cool. It's a beautiful lyrics. It's a beautiful music to listen to. But the context is just not appropriate.
Yeah, you definitely have to keep these things in mind.
And it's good that there's folks like you who are working to kind of like be at the forefront of this stuff.
How do you stay up to date on what's going on in the world for your culturalization work?
That's one of the questions we had in the chat.
That is a great question. What I do is I read a lot of stuff.
I also have a lot of search alerts that I've set up that are like customized
that basically inform me on a daily or weekly basis.
So I'm basically constantly getting stuff in my inbox based on searches
that I created around topics that I that I need to know about,
you know, in this space.
I also have an extensive network of people I've I know,
you know, just from all the travels I've done.
people whose opinions I trust and I know basically where they're coming from. So I can ask them,
you know, if there's something going on in a specific market, I can, you know, just,
you know, chat them up and say, hey, you know, what's going on with this? What do you, what,
what's your perception of what this means? Things like that. So it's, it's really a combination of
things. I mean, I also, I read academic journals, I read The Economist, I read a lot of news.
I'm out there to basically stay informed of what's going on.
Because one thing that's really important about the job,
it's not just knowing like the specific sensitivity
around a specific piece of content.
Like for example, a symbol that some person,
an artist put on a character's outfit.
Things like that. That's kind of the baseline knowledge that I constantly try and build up.
I, for example, like symbols alone, I have a stack of books that's at least a meter high
of all these simple dictionaries that I, yeah, and I'll kind of browse those for fun because
that's kind of the nerd that I am. Because I just, I find it fascinating. But, so there's
kind of that combination of kind of the baseline knowledge of certain cultures that has been built
up and a lot of that is on the foundation of my geographer.
um training in that background but the other part of it is understanding the current market conditions
which is why I keep up on the news and the what's going on in the world because I need to know that
when this game is supposed to release let's say third quarter 2022 I need to have a sense of what
is the market condition going to be like then because you never know I mean in some places
all it takes is as we know could take one election.
And things change. I mean, you know, in certain markets, I mean, laws can change.
The whole, you know, what is acceptable, unacceptable could suddenly change.
I mean, all of that kind of stuff can change depending on or just
even the general perception of video games might change either more favorably
or less favorably.
depending on what happens in that particular market.
So that's the kind of stuff I also have to keep track of.
So, so yeah, that's basically how I do it.
It's just a huge combination of things of reading and staying up on all the
the searches and whatnot, but also talking to people.
That's really the best way to do it is just having a network of people
who you can talk to about what's happening in their locale.
And it sounds like a great deal of work on top of all the other work you already do.
It is a lot of work.
It's a lot of work.
But the thing is, I love doing it, though.
I love what I do.
I'm just this hyper curious person.
So I just I love absorbing information, you know, and it's
the best way of all is just talking to people from other cultures.
That's why I feel really thankful that over the last many years,
I've been able to travel a lot when there's no pandemic.
So typically I'm traveling like 75, 80 percent of the year,
speaking at a lot of conferences around the world.
But that gives that opportunity to talk to people face to face and learn more about their perspective on things and what they're struggling with as game developers and the issues that they're dealing with.
So all of that informs my work.
I find a lot of studios are very open to the work you're doing.
Today, yes. When I first started doing this work, which was, you know, during my Microsoft days, that was over 27 years ago.
I basically peg it that far back. So back in those days, it was challenging.
It was a challenge because the prevailing attitude at the time was like, hey, video games were edgy, were cool.
We can do stuff that's controversial.
And yeah, sure, but that's any creative media. It's not just games.
It's like, yeah, you have the creative right and you should exercise that right to basically make what you want to make.
But it's all about whether or not that is really going to be compatible with the local worldviews and the local expectations that you're going into.
So yeah, it's it's it's it's but today it's gotten a lot easier.
Obviously society has changed dramatically over the last 27 years.
The level of understanding I think has increased especially among
companies who understand that representation matters.
It really matters and you need to make the effort.
to go the distance, so to speak, in terms of making sure that your characters, your narrative,
your environment, all of these things are accurate and respectful of the cultures that you're going
to be leveraging. Even in a fantasy game, you know, it matters there, obviously, because most
fantasy and sci-fi games also get their inspiration from the real world. Pretty much every game does
by in some aspect.
And so we have to make sure that the representation is, you know, is really concentrating on that.
So I find today, and especially this punctuated within the last couple years or so, I find that
a lot of companies have suddenly woken up to the idea that this is really important.
And there's various social issues and, you know, recent events that have caused them to be
more, you know, aware of how important this really is.
And part of me.
is grateful for that, but also part of me is a bit resentful because I'm like,
it should not have taken you this long to get it. You should have, you should have, you should have
just, you know, thought this way early on. Because honestly, when I first started doing this work,
the argument I originally used was that we're doing this because we want to respect the player.
We want to respect who they are as a human being and make sure that that's, we're representing
them correctly in our games and making sure we're respectful within the narratives that
we're pushing out.
That argument didn't go very far back then.
So I had to pivot my argument and make it a money argument.
So that's why I had to say, well, you know, if you culturalize your content,
it actually maximizes the reach of your content
because then it can go in more places around the world.
And so therefore, if you, you know, that's if you culturalize
and make sure it's more compatible.
with other markets, that does happen to increase your revenue.
And that argument resonated really strongly, especially with
the higher ups in different companies. And so I'm like, okay,
great, I found the key that opens up the door. But at the
same time, I was like, I should not have had to make a money
argument to make this important to people.
Yeah, it's heartening to hear that things are getting better
now. But it's like you say, it's it's disappointing that it took
this long to kind of get to this point.
Thank you for staying kind of fluid with how you pushed to get this stuff to happen though.
Sometimes people come to you and you definitely had an I told you so that I bet you were holding
in your butt.
I try not to say I told you so but it happens sometimes.
It's too good to pass up sometimes.
We've got another question in the chat. How do you make sure that you respectfully handle
cultural assets in games and how do you grow your own economic, grow your own expertise
in these cultures that aren't your own? Part of that answer but...
Yeah, I answered a little bit of that, but that this question is a little more specific.
And I think it's a it's a great question, because I think there there's a certain understanding
and awareness I have of various cultures around the world, just by the longevity of the time
I've been doing this work, because, again, reading a lot, talking to a lot of people,
having an understanding of like kind of the baseline reaction that some cultures would
have.
But I'm obviously I'm not presumptuous to think that I'm going to represent the voice of a specific culture.
So my job when I'm doing it is basically to flag something and say,
I think this is going to be a problem in this culture based on my understanding.
But then they need to take the next step.
And sometimes they facilitate that through me and my work.
But then oftentimes I help them facilitate it through, you know, by themselves.
But basically, you need to find someone from that culture.
an expert, a sensitivity reader, you know, some person who's going to represent that culture and
be able to speak to the issues that you're addressing here, because that's ultimately
how you have to do it. You have to consult with them. And obviously we've seen games do a better
job of this over the last few years. You know, there's great examples, like for example,
some games that have Indigenous characters, like I think what, Assassin's Creed 3.
which then brought in someone from the Cherokee Nation to directly advise on how, you know,
the Connor character should be represented, the language they use, all of that kind of thing.
I did a little bit of consulting work on Never Alone, for example, which was the game
developed in direct partnership with the Inuit people.
up in northern Canada, which was, you know, and basically they were the ones dictating to the development team.
This is what how it should be done. This is the language. This is the look, you know, and I think that when you're when you make a game that is based on real cultures.
and real geography, you really have to have that kind of direct engagement. To me, that's really
the only best way to do it. Because my knowledge, I can definitely flag things and I can make people
aware that, you know, they're going down a path that could be potentially problematic. But, you
know, I, I, like everybody else, I've got my limits to my knowledge. Basically, I hit that wall. And
that's when I know either I need to reach out and talk to somebody locally, or I need to get the
company to do the same.
You know, or even take another step, which is like do specific sets of user research or focus groups
with a particular culture so that they can make sure they're not walking down
the wrong path, you know, with their creative choices.
Are you seeing any sort of common mistakes between developers that can be fixed with this expertise?
Yeah, there's a lot. I mean, even though I do see companies that are more aware today than they were
even five years ago, we're still see tons of stereotype issues, lots and lots of stereotyping
going on. To me, that's a combination of just, you know, part of its creative laziness, frankly.
It's not doing your due diligence.
If you're going to create a character that's not from the culture that you represent,
you know, then you need to do your due diligence to make sure you're making a character that is realistic to that culture
and not, you know, not leveraging any tropes that are out there.
around that particular culture. It's really easy to do because it's something of a creative trap,
you know, that we make these assumptions. And this, it speaks to the fact that every single
one of us, whether we like it or not, we are biased. I mean, because we all come from a
specific culture, specific language, specific geography. And, you know, I think most of us,
we overcome that bias with education. That's...
What the benefits of having an educational process. But that doesn't mean that all of those biases we
might have are just and I'm when I say bias, I'm not talking about like active bias, like I'm
actually thinking about doing something that's going to be, you know, problematic. I'm just
thinking I'm just saying that the bias is there because that blocks us from having that full
understanding of what other choices might be. If you're going to make us like a specific character,
say a character from East Asia.
You know, what are my choices there? Well, East Asian culture is dramatically diverse.
When you look at, you know, China, Korea, Japan, you know, other places throughout the region,
and even within those countries, it's quite diverse. You really have to dig deep and understand,
you know, what do you want to represent from that particular culture? And again,
speaking to the point about
about fantasy and sci-fi games, sometimes game developers, because a lot of our games tend to be
set in a fictional universe, we also have to be really careful because those things bleed over
all the time. Those choices are also just as complicated because we often look to the real
world to set up allegories in our sci-fi or fantasy universe, whether it's narrative allegory or visual
allegory.
But those allegories have an origin point. They have an inspiration in the real world and we need
to make sure that we have sufficient what I call allegorical distance so that the original
inspiration isn't too obvious to what actually shows up in the game. So I think that was a long
answer. Sorry. It was a really good answer because I feel like you're covering a lot of important
points and that many of us without even realizing it carry these little biases, these little things
we don't.
Maybe we didn't pick up on that we feel or in terms of phrase we use or like you say the
inspirations for some of these character styles or types or things like that
in our fantasy mediums and things like that really looked at. So to your point, it's very
important to kind of examine these things before we kind of trot out something harmful again without
thinking about it. Yeah. All right, we got another question here from the audience.
How can someone graduating high school or university today best seek out their own incredible
confluence of everything I love?
That is a great question.
I mean, part of it, like I kind of alluded to earlier, in my case, was a happy accident.
But the point is, though, I never lost track of what I love.
And, you know, I always had that...
I kind of wear my interests on my sleeve, so to speak.
So like my love of Star Wars never went away.
It's like, you know, because that's why I wanted to be an artist at Lucasfilm,
just so I could work on a Star Wars movie.
That was the whole reason.
And of course, I didn't get that chance, but I did years later.
I did work on Star Wars, the Old Republic for Bioware for four years.
So, you know, in that case, the circle was now complete.
I actually got to work on something, Star Wars.
Not in the same capacity I imagined when I was in high school, but I still got to work on it.
So that's one of those just serendipitous things about your life path and career that I always find interesting is that you have no idea
whether or not these things are going to come back along your path at some point in the future.
You know, it is important to kind of choose a path because you got to be on a path.
That's the important part.
You got to be going in a direction, but you have to be open to how that could change.
You know, I do mentor a lot of people in this industry, a lot of young people who want to come into this industry.
And one of the biggest challenges I find, but I think it's also natural with that age, is that you have, you're very focused on exactly what you want to achieve.
I want to be the chief designer on X franchise, for example.
I want to be the lead designer at this company.
That's great, and I think people should have specific goals like that,
but you've got to be really open and flexible to other stuff that comes your way.
Because I never imagined when I was in high school being a geographer, I never imagined working on video games, even though I love video games. I was seven years old when Pong showed up in the store. So that was my first video game. And I've loved games ever since. But, um, I never imagined any of this happening.
at all. It was not even close on my radar. And yet it was mainly because as the choices came along,
I was open to the idea that like, okay, yeah, I want to do that. I want to do this. Like, I,
you know, I left Microsoft in 2005, even though I built my own team there, I created my own job
there. I was getting paid very well with good benefits and all of that. But I left because
it just I felt like my job was done there. I had done basically what I needed to do with the company
And now I wanted to see if other companies want to do this too.
And I wanted to also focus almost exclusively on games,
which is another reason I left,
because then it would give me the ability
as a self-employed person to focus on what I wanted to focus on.
And a lot of people thought I was insane.
Why would I possibly leave a good job like that,
that I created at a company like Microsoft,
and go off and become, you know, an entrepreneur,
which is, you know, almost a death sentence for some.
And but it was because I just had that driving desire to to take my knowledge and do something
different with it. And so I think you have to take be willing to take risks like that and be willing
to be open to whatever comes along your way. And don't be afraid you know if you have a great
opportunity that comes your way that might be a little divergent from the path you were imagining.
I would encourage you to take it,
because you never know how that's going to come back.
And the reality is that everything you do,
no matter what job it is, no matter what path you're taking,
you are building up experience,
life experience and work experience,
that ultimately could be useful down the road.
So I just encourage you to just keep your eyes open,
because too many people get blinded
by this really solid focus.
Yeah, you get too focused on one thing.
So it's kind of like,
Allowing yourself to broaden that experience.
Yeah.
See you.
All right.
Probably time for one more question.
Of course, it slipped on down the list.
How dare you sneak off on me?
All right.
We're actually going to touch on some of your Global Game Jam stuff now.
Yeah.
I talk about this globalization stuff all day.
A lot of solo game devs struggle with matchmaking and forming teams.
A lot of people use Game Jams as a platform for this,
but many of these teams collapse after the event.
Experience Global Game Jam.
Is there a way to provide help to game devs on finding the right people to work with?
That is a fantastic question. That is something that we're trying to work on because we know
that that is a real problem and we know that became more punctuated last year because last
year was the first time we did a virtual Global Game Jam.
We did GGG Next, which is our event for younger people, last summer in July.
That was the first time we ever did a virtual jam.
And then, of course, in January this year is when we did a virtual jam as well.
And, well, GGG Next actually starts in five days this year.
And again, that's a virtual format.
And that really raised the profile on what a struggle it is for solo devs to get connected to a team.
Because obviously when you're on site, you're at a location, it's a lot easier.
Even though then it can be somewhat challenging for people because there's always that...
That little part after the theme is announced and people kind of go their separate ways to
start working on their game, there's always kind of that little forum where you have the solo people
saying, hey, I can do this. Does anyone need me on their team? And usually those people get paired
off, which is great. They get attached to a team. But if you're virtual or if you're just kind of
out there, it is tough to do that. And so we've been trying to think of ways to make it a lot
easier so that we kind of have
I don't know, I don't want to call it matchmaking, nothing like that.
But basically a way so that teens can say, hey, this is what we need.
And you also have a pool of people who say, this is what I do,
you know, to make it a lot easier, especially in a virtual jam,
because that just makes it super challenging because you're not
you don't have any like necessary communal space.
And if you're like in a discord channel or something,
it's just a lot of noise to kind of figure out what's going on.
So the short answer is that we're aware of this problem and we're trying to fix it.
Right now it's not an easy fix, but I'm glad you raised the question though.
All right, and I think that's about all we have time for today. We're down to that last minute.
So, Kate, thank you so, so much for coming out and talking with us today. It was
fascinating to listen to your work. Definitely going to keep following up on what you're doing
from here on out.
Well, thank you. Yeah, this was great. Yeah, I mean, we could talk for hours on this subject.
I will take you up on that someday.
And I'm more than happy if people want to reach out to me.
I'm pretty easy to find on Twitter and elsewhere if you want to reach out to me.
And if you have additional questions, don't hesitate.
Especially, you know, if you're looking to get into the industry, this is how you start.
You ask questions and don't be shy.
All right. With that, thanks a lot for coming out, folks.
Enjoy the rest of GDC 2021.