All right.
Hey, everybody.
My name's Brian Horton.
I am the studio art director at Infinity Ward.
And it's great to be here today to talk about our topic, which
is creating a believable hero.
I've been in the industry for about 22 years.
I've been working mostly in the art field.
But on Tomb Raider, I was able to work more
on the creative side, on game direction.
My career sort of takes me from Disney to DreamWorks to working with EA and Konami,
and most recently I worked on Infinite Warfare and Infinity War.
But today, let's talk a little bit about the topic.
And I'm going to go through a couple chapters,
each one sort of designating a different area of focus
around creating your believable character.
The first chapter is about tapping into the universal.
Storytelling has been going on for millennia,
and there are themes and there are connections
that we've made and certain people have made
that connects storytelling across all genres
and all cultures.
And I'm gonna talk a lot about the hero's journey,
the collective unconscious, archetypes,
themes and motivations,
and an actual example of a character profile.
So before we start in the fun stuff of creating visuals,
you really have to understand who your character is.
And Joseph Campbell's monomyth, The Hero's Journey,
you may or may not have heard of this,
but it's extremely important to understand it
before you think about building a hero story.
It is not something you have to use,
but it's a tried and true method.
And the way this works is the hero goes through a loop.
The hero is called to action by an inciting incident,
setting them on a new path.
The hero is inspired by mentors and supported by companions
that share this challenge.
And the hero must pass a threshold that tests the resolve,
beginning this transformation.
The next section is you're gonna see
the hero going through challenges
that pushes them past the point of normal human endurance,
facing death and despair.
And accomplishing the quest requires a heavy sacrifice and a revelation that will transform
them.
And they return with a new perspective.
Now this loop is important.
You've seen it in a lot of different movies.
We're going to go over that in a second.
But the other angle of this is archetypes and the collective unconscious, a term coined
by Carl Jung.
And it refers to the structures of the unconscious.
which are shared by all human beings.
And according to Jung,
the human collective unconscious is populated by instincts and by archetypes.
So we're going to talk a little bit about those archetypes.
So you guys are familiar with Star Wars, I'm sure.
Many of you have seen Star Wars.
The hero's journey,
Joseph Campbell's hero's journey,
and Jung's archetypes were...
what George Lucas was really excited to capture.
It wasn't a science fiction story to him.
It was a story about characters,
and the characters are the heart
of most great hero stories and myths.
So you've seen probably the Harry Potter franchise,
or Lord of the Rings, or even Lost on TV,
and each of these have specific sliced archetypes
that Young's broken down
across all time and all myth and storytelling.
So you have your hero, you have your sidekick, your maiden, your wise old man, your villain,
the shapeshifter, the trickster, the comic, the childlike adult, the adultlike child,
and the mother figure.
Now, there's other characters that will populate your stories, but these are archetypes.
And don't get them confused with stereotypes, and they can often go into a stereotype, but
archetypes are important.
They sort of have a set place within a story to help your hero grow.
So the next thing you want to think about is your theme and motivation.
So your theme should be a universal truth shared by all cultures,
and your hero should be driven by external and internal motivations.
And they will embark on this journey.
It's going to force change.
So I think about universal themes, and I often go to painting.
I studied painting in college, and I feel like the best paintings
in the world express these themes through a very strong image.
So love obviously is a fantastic theme.
Injustice, freedom, honor, liberty,
vengeance, survival, fear, or guilt.
There's many more, but if you notice all of these themes
have strong emotional properties to them.
They're something that you do not need to translate.
Every culture can understand them.
So here's a character profile, a little exercise I'm gonna do with the group.
So in this character's profile, their internal motivation is this hero's parents were killed
by a criminal, causing guilt and fear.
The external motivation, the hero is driven to defend the innocent against criminal predators.
And the theme, the hero uses fear to defeat the internal and external demons.
Anyone, raise your hands, who is this?
Of course, Batman.
Batman's one of my favorite heroes of all time.
And probably because I like the darker side of the hero.
I don't like the tried and true hero.
I like a hero with rough edges.
I like a hero with some humanity and fragility.
and it's their force of will that pushes them forward.
And Batman has no true ability, he has no true superpower,
but he is a superhero.
He does amazing things,
even though Bruce Wayne isn't a regular person.
But he uses the fear, he uses the things
that scared him as a child and incited him
to become this hero against his enemies.
So it's a fantastic loop,
that no matter which media you see Batman in,
this is his core, this is the core of his character
and what motivates him.
So, in this next chapter, we're gonna talk about
a property that I worked on, which is Tomb Raider.
A lot of our charge was to rebuild an icon.
Lara Croft has had an amazing run in video games.
She is recognizable, iconic.
She has been seen in all kinds of media, video games,
comic books, movies.
But we wanted to rebuild this icon.
We wanted this, we wanted Lara Croft to be as human
as we could possibly make her.
So we're gonna go through a little bit of a history.
We're gonna talk about charting this new course
we were setting ourselves on.
the archetype inspirations for Lara Croft,
and ultimately this concept that we came up with,
our tagline for the first Tomb Raider reboot
was a survivor is born.
And that's the big flip for our character,
is Lara as a survivor.
So, history of Lara Croft.
Toby Garr designed Lara as a smart, athletic archeologist
seeking relics with unimaginable power.
In 96, Tomb Raider was released to critical praise
and millions of sales over the world.
And for 15 years, she remained ostensibly the same.
She was badass, she was aspirational.
But as she grew in the years,
and more and more games came out,
she became less and less in favor
with the modern gaming audience.
So we wanted to chart a new course.
And my boss at the time at Crystal Dynamics,
Daryl Gallagher, wanted to reimagine Lara
as a young heroine and a believable hero.
And Noah Hughes, the creative director,
and Rihanna Pratchett, the script writer,
created an origin story that would feature
a 21-year-old Lara Croft.
And that was great, but we needed a theme,
a theme to build her on, something that was unique.
So.
The next section we talk about is this profile again, trying to come up with a profile, her
external motivation, an adventurous archaeologist driven to find the lost secrets of the world.
That's the same.
We didn't touch that.
That was the core of who Lara Croft is.
The internal motivation, she pursues archaeology to finish her father's work and to make her
own mark.
Ultimately, that is very much the same as the classic Lara, but it was the theme.
Shipwrecked on a hostile island, hunted by murderous inhabitants,
Lara must struggle for survival to help her crew escape the island.
The survival theme really is what changed her character,
and everything that we did fed into that theme.
And this is the new icon that we came up with for Lara Croft,
and I'll get to more of that in a moment.
So, archetype inspirations.
Once again, not stereotype, archetypes.
So The Descent is one of our team's favorite horror films.
It was really an amazing study about these women
who had these internal and external demons to fight
and their willingness and ability to dig deep and survive.
And there was a lot of visual things about them too
that were really compelling and that climbing ax
was a very iconic element of the film
and it's something that we really gravitated to.
But we also looked at Lost.
We were also huge fans of that show at the time.
And Evangeline Lilly played Kate.
And Kate was a complex hero.
She's officially the maiden in the archetype,
but she is sensibly a hero.
And she was relatable.
She was emotional.
She had this emotional depth.
But she also had dark secrets.
So she wasn't just a cookie cutter character.
She actually had complexity.
And the more you got to know her,
the more of those secrets sort of started to unfold.
So I'm gonna do a quick story overview.
I'm gonna get through this quickly.
If you haven't played Tomb Raider, I apologize, big spoilers.
You're gonna, we're gonna go through this whole thing.
Come on, people, it's like a long time ago.
I hope you've at least know the core story.
So Alara begins her archeologist expedition
with a thirst for adventure,
looking for the lost city of Biamatai.
And we created a mentor character for this story.
And this is Conrad Roth.
And he sort of represents what we imagined
a typical Tomb Raider might be.
He actually has the dual pistols.
He has the experience.
He has done a ton of treasure hunting.
And he serves as a mentor for Lara Croft.
And then we came up with the concept of a survivor is born.
And this is where the theme really kicks in.
So when the Endurance is scuttled by a storm,
Lara is left alone to fend for herself
on this hostile island against hostile inhabitants.
And this opening scene was sort of a metaphor
for her rebirth.
She was actually bound in a sack
and had to burn herself to get down.
And she had this terrible event,
very painful birth and rebirth of this character.
And that was an important metaphor for us as far as recrafting who she was.
So there was a vulnerability to Lara Croft, and that was new.
Because when we think of Lara Croft, at least in the classic sense,
she was almost invulnerable.
She could backflip her way out of any problem,
use her dual pistols and take names and do the business.
She almost expressed no fear.
And we needed to reset.
We needed to make her experience fear so she had an arc to get to a place
where she would be this confident hero.
And one of those things that we did is we stripped away those dual pistols.
That was an iconic part of her character,
and we completely removed them for this game.
And what we did is we replaced them with new tools.
So the fire was the first tool that she got.
And she used that tool to escape the den.
And then she eventually discovered the bow.
And the bow is also another iconic new element.
And both of these tools reinforced our theme of survival.
So in that hero's journey, she had to cross a threshold.
She had to go to a place where she could not come back from.
And that really came down to the point
where she had to kill a person for the first time.
So Lara Croft, up until this point in our fiction,
has never killed a person,
and this was an important part of her arc.
She passed this threshold,
and that really set her on her hero's journey.
Her best friend, Samantha, was captured by Matthias,
her villain.
And this is part of a trope of the story,
but this is the captured maiden part of the loop.
And she has to rescue Sam
before they can leave this island.
Now the mentor's challenge, this is where a mentor becomes really important.
Because not only are they there as an aspirational figure, but they're there to give you challenges.
And the thing that was great about this was we used that not only narratively, but we
used it in gameplay.
So each tool that Lara got, whether it be the torch, which was fire, or the bow, which
gave her long, gave her shooting ability, she eventually got this axe from her mentor,
Conrad Roth.
And this axe represented not only a...
a symbol of his trust, but it was also an important tool for her to scale the mountain
and eventually reach her first challenge.
So she had to face this challenge of the hostile island alone.
Conrad Roth had been injured, and she had to send this SOS, and the fate of her crew
was in her hands.
So this was an important thing to see her start to embrace what it means to be a hero
and to grow as a character.
Ultimately, she gets to that challenge.
She finishes the mentor's challenge.
She gets out the SOS.
There's a moment of jubilation, of relief,
because we've been so dark.
The characters had so much hardship
that we gave a little beacon of hope.
And we did everything, not only in her character arc,
to feel that confidence,
but also in the way we set the world.
We really brought in light and color,
and we wanted that moment to feel celebrated.
But this was a short-lived victory.
This plane that she had called in was taken down by a supernatural threat.
Once again, we're escalating the threats,
and we're forcing Lara to understand
that it's not going to be an easy thing for her to finish her journey.
She's going to go through a series of these trials and tribulations,
ever escalating, ever getting to the point
where she's driven to the edge of human endurance.
But she is also driven to save her companions, and she pushes through.
She's ultimately captured and gets to a point
where she is at the lowest part of the story.
But she reemerges really understanding
what it means to be a survivor.
We start to see a physical transformation in her character.
And then she's more steel.
We're starting to see classic elements
of Lara Croft come through.
She's taking the fight to the enemy.
She's no longer waiting to be attacked.
She's taking it to them, and she's being proactive.
So this is how we start to see that evolution
in her character, which makes her interesting.
So this is the most important lesson for her in her arc,
is her mentor's death.
This is classic in multiple stories,
but it puts her in a situation
where she learns an important lesson,
that she hopes to get everyone off the island alive,
and that's almost a naive thought or feeling,
because in this journey, something has to be sacrificed.
She's gonna lose friends,
and she has to come to terms with those losses.
So we've added another archetype, the turn code in here.
One of our own crew actually turns Samantha over
to the enemy, and Lara kills this enemy
using the weapons of her slain mentor.
And we give the players a glimpse of her potential future.
We give her the classic silhouette,
that Lara Croft with the dual pistols.
But she's not there yet, but this is a glimpse
of her future and her destiny.
She's gonna face one last supernatural threat.
taking her out, and she will save her friend.
But they've both been scarred by this adventure.
They escape the island with not their full crew,
and Lara feels the guilt of this loss.
And her thirst for adventure will transform more
into a passion to ever uncover the world's secrets
because they are dangerous and she needs to understand them.
She leaves the island with more questions than answers.
So that was just a little bit of a loop
of how we eventually got there with Lara Croft.
But let's click back.
We have to think about how we actually brought her to life.
So that's a story, that's the context,
that's the wrapper that we're going to put this hero into.
But we had to design her, we had to come up with the visuals,
how far we were gonna push away from what she was
to where she was going to be for this new incarnation.
So we wanted to design a human hero,
and we had to do a ton of iteration to get to that point.
And we pushed further in the realm of realism
by introducing models and wardrobe
and things that we've never seen
in the Tomb Raider franchise before
to bring her one more step to realism.
Now this title of this story, of this presentation
is creating a believable hero.
These themes, these ideas don't necessarily have to feed into a realistic game.
It just so happens that Tomb Raider was going for a realistic aesthetic.
But The Incredibles has, as a very stylized movie, has a lot of these same principles in it.
So if you have a stylized game you're working on, a lot of these principles will also work.
So when we design this hero, it comes down to people.
And I can't express enough how important
Bren Adams was to this whole process.
He was the assistant art director on Tomb Raider.
He was my right-hand man.
And ultimately, a lot of the visuals
that you see for Lara Croft come from him.
And I was just very fortunate to work with him and Cam Yu,
who was a longtime modeler of Lara Croft,
going back all the way to Legend.
So having a group of people that you can trust,
that can push each other,
that's a really important thing
when you're talking about a task like this.
You can do it on your own,
but it's great to have collaborators.
And we started with silhouettes.
And what you're gonna see in these early silhouettes
is they look very familiar to an older Lara Croft,
or to a classic rendition of Lara Croft.
Bren was just pushing the idea of how far we wanted to go with her character.
So you have your signature elements.
You have your ponytail.
You have the M-shaped lips.
You have the dual pistols.
And you have the silhouette, which looks very familiar.
Then we started to iterate.
We started to think, how could we continue pushing it?
We cut off her hair at one point.
Hey, can we lose the ponytail?
Can we give her a child companion?
Can we even give her a monkey?
I'm not kidding you.
That was actually in there at one point.
She was going to have a monkey.
It's crazy, but it was really funny.
I had to put it in the PowerPoint.
So we kept going, we kept pushing,
and the axe, the descent film came into focus for us.
We brought the axe into the silhouette,
and that was looking interesting.
We were looking at ideas of like,
maybe she would break her bones.
How do we express survival?
We kept thinking about survival, survival.
and then we realized that would really suck for gameplay
to have her having broken bones, so we didn't do that.
But we did want to keep pushing,
and ultimately we came down to the ideas of,
well, what if she was just progressing through the game?
And it wasn't affecting her control,
but you would see as she went through,
the signs of the wear and tear of the island
and the adventurist would start to progress on her.
Now, this wasn't the final incarnation,
but it was a really interesting exercise
at how you think about progression
from the beginning to end.
And ultimately we came to our final design.
And we came up with what I believe is a new silhouette.
You could take this down to just black and white,
which I probably should have done for the PowerPoint,
but I forgot to do it,
where you could see Lara with the two pistols
and Lara with the bow on her back
and the axe in one hand.
And we created a new silhouette,
a new icon for Lara Croft.
And as we kept iterating, we did head turns.
We talked about gear and how the gear would add to the character.
And even little small details like this little necklace.
It was something we designed.
We didn't have a story for it.
And then the writer saw that necklace and said, oh, that's really cool.
And they wrote a whole back story for the necklace
about it was her first archaeological discovery.
And sort of was her inciting incident to fall in love with archaeology.
So she wears that.
And that's an important part of her character.
It helped define who she is.
But the bow, and this is a Rise of the Tomb Raider concept,
so this is gonna be mixing, matching
some of the old stuff and the new stuff.
But every piece of gear that we put on her body,
we wanted to make sure told a story.
And the axe, as I talked about, was an important one.
Not only was it an important tool,
but it was something her mentor gave her.
Now, for the companions, we ended up
with a very large secondary cast,
larger than we actually probably should have had.
But we were filling the archetype roles.
And each one of them served a function.
The mentor, the maiden, the sidekick, the turncoat, the comic, the childlike adult,
the adultlike child, and the mother figure.
All of them are represented.
And I think we did a really bad job at describing these characters and they became stereotypes.
They weren't the best expression of what we hoped and aspired to do, but they were all
there.
So, you shoot for the stars, sometimes you pick a lane and you go,
we want to do all this stuff and then we realize
we weren't giving them enough screen time.
There wasn't enough opportunity for you to fall in love with them
and they fell into stereotype.
So it's an important thing to know that even though you might have
the best intentions and follow the book,
Execution is still everything when it comes to realizing your characters.
But what we think we got right were at least two of them in this crew,
which was the mentor Roth and Lara.
And we think we did a pretty good job describing those two characters.
When it came to the enemies, we struggled a lot with,
who are these enemies?
Why are they important to Lara?
What do they do to challenge her?
And what we realized is, to make them as compelling,
they had to be survivors of the island as well.
They were also shipwrecked on this island,
and they became indoctrinated into this cult.
And one of my favorite pieces of storytelling
that we did in the game was,
we got to see how the Salari soldiers were indoctrinated.
They were put into this pit of despair and forced,
to survive a brutal existence and it almost drove them mad.
And if they survived that terrible pit of despair, that they would be good enough to
fight in Matthias' army and be willing to do anything.
So if you're a fan of The Walking Dead right now, that is essentially what you're seeing
with the enemy types.
Negan will beat down these people until they're just broken and shattered.
And then who are they?
They're Negan.
They're all Negan.
And that's before we knew about that.
But man, I wish I would have had that at the time because that's exactly what we wanted
to try to do with the Solari was to make human beings that are shattered and rebuilt under
this malevolent leader.
And then when it came to the Oni, the supernatural enemy,
we wanted to make them,
we didn't want any visible signs of magic.
We really pushed away, like we did a lot of experimentation
with how much magic would be in the game.
And we said, man, every time we add it,
it feels like it's, it just broke the bubble.
We lost.
we lost that cohesiveness.
So the oni were essentially samurais, but immortal.
And what we did is we just used their behaviors.
We made them more feral.
We made them less disciplined as a way
to express their immortality.
So it was this contrast of samurai-looking characters
that acted and behaved a lot like animals.
So that was our way to express their supernatural qualities.
At the end, we just, at the very end,
we talk about Himiko.
and the queen, and that's where we get the most supernatural.
But we really protect that until the very end.
But ultimately, the most important character
next to Lara Croft is the environment.
And I cannot express this enough.
When you're designing your hero, you
have to think about the environment that they're in.
Everything that Lara does, everything your hero will do,
should be, the environment itself should be a challenge
or a compliment to something you're trying to express
in their story arc.
And I think this is probably the second most successful
character we created in the game was the environment.
Yamatai itself had a life to it.
It had this dynamic weather, it had hostility.
It was aesthetically.
just it had darkness to it.
And it would progress.
It wasn't just one look all the way through.
We went through different weather states.
We went through different architecture styles.
But ultimately what we came to was an environment
that we felt we called the second most important character
in the game.
And that was Lara's best enemy in Tomb Raider.
OK, so the next section.
We had to cast Lara Croft.
We had to bring an actor into our.
into the fold that was going to embody what is a young Lara Croft look and act like.
And we went through an exhaustive list of actors, and we had Camilla come in, and she
was sort of reading for us.
It's almost like a Han Solo thing, where Han Solo was being, Harrison Ford was not originally
considered for the role, and there was this person that, you know, Harrison was just reading
against other people, and like, well, what about Harrison Ford?
Camilla was kind of like that, where she was, came in very early, and
We were looking at other candidates,
and then ultimately came back to Camilla
because she had this truth and honesty
and simplicity about her performance that we really loved.
And we didn't want her to feel like a superhero
or a confident person in the beginning,
and we wanted her to get there.
So Camilla was a very young actress,
and she's now done many things,
you know, Grey's Anatomy and a number of other things,
but at the time, she was completely unknown.
So we were very fortunate to cast Camilla
and bring life to the character.
And then for the visualization, we cast a number of models.
This is across two games, to serve as face and body
likeness, or at least reference.
Because we wanted Lara Croft to still be unique.
There was not one actor out there
that was going to fulfill our goals for Lara.
So she was a composite.
And we had Megan that she served as the base morphology
of the face.
For Rise of the Tomb Raider, we did even more work towards wardrobe and every single garment
that Lara wore was scanned.
And I feel like that was a really important part of pushing what I call clothes, not costumes.
For believability, I think it's extremely important that your characters don't feel
like they're wearing a costume.
And that's something that you'll see in films
when they translate from a comic book into a film,
that those things become more practical.
You'll see the iconic elements,
but ultimately they feel more like a garment
that could be made.
So we actually bought clothes off the rack,
augmented them, but they serve as a foundation
to create what I believe is something
that looks much more authentic.
Here's the scan for the head for Megan.
Facial expression references.
More scan work for the torso, the jacket, the pants.
Now this is an important slide because I had this idea.
I wasn't sure if we could pull it off,
but I really wanted to see the wrinkles in her pants
articulate as she moved.
And we've seen wrinkle maps before in games,
but I really wanted to push beyond just wrinkle maps.
I wanted to see blend shape changes plus wrinkle maps.
And while I don't think we got 100% there,
these scans provided a really interesting
reference point for us.
As you can see, the difference between the folds
from one leg to the other,
that's a drastic difference as they're articulating.
So we did bring this,
we brought new technology into Rise of the Tomb Raider
to try to bring this articulation and fold logic,
dynamic fold logic into the game.
This was the scan to model.
So how the scan and the head model was fused.
And here's that example of the deformation
and the wrinkle maps and how they worked.
This is kind of a techie slide,
even though this presentation is more about theory.
It was just a small detail
that the team was passionate about.
And I think what happens when you're making these games
is it's the small stuff sometimes that people love.
So that was just one thing.
We brought that into the body
where you could see different wrinkles from her torso
as she twists.
And even her arms had muscle deformation.
And here's some of the game models from Rise of the Tomb Raider using the in-game renderer.
It was exciting for us because we had established a really interesting game in the first one
and to continue to build on it was a joy because we had figured out a lot of the hard stuff.
The rest of it was like, well how would you have different outfits for Lara Croft and
what would they look like and how do you make sure that it doesn't look like costumes and
it does feel like clothes.
So we were able to get from the first one she wore a tank top the whole time.
we really got to see her evolve and be prepared
going into an expedition.
And that was a big difference in how we approached the sequel.
And then you're starting to see distress.
This was another really important thing
for believability and grounding the character to the world.
So we had our shaders.
And this isn't a new technology, but it's something
we're really committed to, is every time that Laura
goes into a new environment, she'll
have these dynamic shaders that reflect the environment.
So if it starts to snow, you'll see snow accumulation.
It's raining, the rain will make the clothes wet,
muddy, bloody, et cetera.
So here's an example of Lara in distress state
where she has the blood and mud and dirt
and scratches on her.
And to see these things come in and out
based on her damage, it was just a really cool,
new approach to reflect the game
that you, the player, were playing
that your character felt connected to your actions.
Even small stuff like Fresnel shader on the clothes,
that little peach fuzzy feel that clothes get
that separate them from the skin,
which has subsurface scattering.
These aren't new technologies per se,
but I just bring them up because.
you have to sort of get into a bare minimum of tech
when you're talking about building a realistic game
where these features add up to creating
a more believable looking realistic character.
Once again, you don't have to,
if you're not making a realistic game,
you don't need all of these things.
But even the Incredibles had subsurface scattering
and Fresnel shaders and all the stuff
that I'm talking about to try to take
their cartoony silhouettes into something
that feels more real.
And then this is something, an innovation that we worked on for the PC version of Tomb
Raider, and we brought into Rise of the Tomb Raider, which was spline-based hair.
One of the biggest iconic elements of Lara Croft is her hair, and we really feel like
we've struck a chord.
you know, a really important thing in the games industry is to continue to push the
technology to see more secondary motion and more believable motion happen on characters.
And the spline-based hair might not be for every game, but for Tomb Raider, we were willing
to pay the expense to see a much more articulate physics simulation and physical rendering.
So every single condition that you see,
the spline hair is reacted to wind and to wetness.
You'll see all those conditions change
because we were able to build
such a robust system for the hair.
And for the game model itself, we could go into the details.
I mean, ultimately, I don't think
Lara is a realistic or photo-realistic character.
She's, we're trying to strive for believability.
So there is an abstraction, even though we're getting
more and more real, that we're taking,
she's not quite to the point where you could take
a photograph of someone and that's Lara Croft.
So that was one of the big challenges
for the character team on the game,
was riding the line of iconography and realism.
And this is one of the in-game cinematics.
We're really stoked to continue pushing
real-time cinematics in Tomb Raider
because it allowed your choices to be reflected on the model.
So if you ever play Tomb Raider or Rise of the Tomb Raider
and you change your outfit,
every single one of those cinematics
is gonna reflect your outfit choice.
And I know it's another small detail,
but it really makes you feel connected to that character.
It makes you feel like that's your version of Lara Croft.
It's who you're playing.
We were able to get a lot of really nice features in here,
like soft shadows and really bring all the work
that the character team did to bring the fidelity
of those characters forward was showcased in these cinematics.
And these are some of the production renders
that we did for Tomb Raider across the two games.
And each one has a similar theme.
They all suggest survival.
But once again, her attitudes,
the reason I put these in across two games,
you're gonna see Lara's confidence change.
So if you look at the early renderings,
there's a lot more of her, the world,
that is attacking her, and she's being attacked,
and sort of almost holding herself.
And as she goes forward, she's now hunting the enemy.
She's confidently striding forward.
She's embracing the darkness.
She's going into the tomb.
She's just not reacting to it.
So all of these pieces of key art
were helping us tell a story of her evolution as a character.
Okay, this is the most important chapter
and it's the one I have the least amount of slides on
because it's animation.
It's not something I can look at and still pictures.
But I can't say enough about how important animation is to your character.
It's everything.
In fact, it's way more important than all the other stuff I just talked about.
Breathing life into your character always comes from motion.
and that can come from the actors you choose
to do motion capture or your key frame animators.
But the reason I have this slide up here of these people
is because the animators are the ones that are the heroes.
They're the heroes, they bring these heroes to life.
Each one of these animators was Lara Croft
because they worked on her every day
and they brought the subtlety and nuance
and emotion to what is essentially I call a puppet.
Because you can have the most beautiful puppet in the world
and if it doesn't move right, you won't care about it.
So the emotion of the game comes from these people right here.
And I have a small movie.
Well, you know what?
I'm going to just skip the movie.
I just want to be able to give you guys some more time to ask
some questions if you have them.
I'm going to go through a bit of a summary.
So the first thing you should think about is who your character is.
Make a, come up with a theme that has a universal truth to it,
shared by all cultures.
Your hero should be driven by internal and external motivations.
They should embark on a journey that forces them to change.
And you should build a profile for your hero
that is based on these themes and motivations.
Something that you can always come back to and say,
hey, would they do that?
Does that make sense for this character?
And design a supporting cast of characters
that will complement or challenge your hero's goals.
This is another important thing,
and something that all of us are striving to get better at,
is how can you make each supporting cast member
as important and vital and well-rounded as your hero?
And for the design, for the visual design,
your hero should be iconic.
Start with a silhouette.
They should be recognizable without any internal detail.
and design from the general, which is the broad silhouette,
to the very specific, all the way down to that necklace.
So you have to think about your characters,
you're designing them through those different lenses.
Try to cast an actor,
even if you're not gonna work with an actor,
imagine an actor that would give your character a soul,
and then use that as inspiration
for how they perform and how they work.
And especially, in our case, how they would look.
Wardrobe should be practical.
This is my opinion.
Some people don't believe in this.
I just believe that the best heroes
have the most practical garments.
So think about clothes, not costumes.
Think about even in the most stylized games,
or like a character like Batman,
every single thing on Batman's outfit serves a function.
Even to the point of his silhouette, it invokes fear.
So that is why he can look a little outrageous
because he is trying to instill fear
in an enemy that generally isn't afraid of anything.
And every detail tells a story.
Every single thing you do to your character
is going to tell...
the viewer what they should think about that character.
So make sure you appoint your hero with props
and reinforce those themes that you've talked about
all the way at the profile into those details.
And character execution.
If you're making a realistic character,
try to cast some models that match your design.
Purchase or create clothes for your model
to achieve maximum realism.
Once again, if you're going for realism.
Photogrammetry is an amazing process to be able to capture all this detail.
And where we're living in games now are really embracing physically correct environments.
You can get all the great detail off of those, from that photogrammetry information
that will help make your character more physically correct.
You want to capture the faces and clothes
with extreme poses in mind.
So not only what they look like in the base,
but what do they look like in motion?
And then hopefully your artists can infuse
some of that detail into the character when they move.
And prepare your asset with dynamic distress.
Now once again, this is a style choice thing,
but for every game I'll ever work on in the future,
I'd love to see progression,
and I'd love to see the character fit the world
wherever they might be,
whether they're covered in snow or ash or blood.
Those things, if they're dynamic,
they're that much more impactful.
and connect the character to the world in action.
So if you think about what your world is doing,
your character should reflect those things
on the model itself.
And performance, the most important thing
is bring your character life with a motion style
that reinforces your theme.
Performance capture is a great technology
that you can capture even the most subtle performances
from your actor and bring them and infuse them
into your model with blend shapes and wrinkle maps.
So this is getting a little bit more techie,
but I absolutely love the new tech
that we're able to embrace to bring subtlety
to our characters.
Think about contextual animations,
things where your character and the world are related.
One of the behaviors that we brought to Lara Croft
is when she's cold, every time she goes near a fire,
you'll see her rub her hands and warm her hands.
You'll see when she's also cold
and not near a source like that, she'll shiver.
When she's in a tight, claustrophobic space,
she'll put her hand up on the wall
to recognize it and to crouch down.
So really think about those contextual animations
that make your character connect
to the world that they're in.
And think about secondary animation.
You know, the primary animation,
the primary locomotion is fantastic,
but it's those secondary animations
that really bring some life
into what are essentially cycles.
And if they're physics driven,
you're going to see your cycles change
based on whatever wind or conditions
that you might have in the world.
and reflect your character's growth through performance.
As your story progresses,
think about new behaviors or improvements to your character
to continue to tell the story of their growth.
All right.
Questions?
Comments?
That's all I got.
If no one has questions, I'll play that video.
All right, I'm gonna play that video.
Okay, go ahead.
So you knew you were making Lara Croft.
Do you have recommendations for teams that are coming up with an original character,
especially if they're trying to make something that's original
and not cookie cutter of all the other heroic game males?
Ultimately, when you're making a hero,
and you don't want to follow into the tropes and traps of classic archetypes,
Just know that having a structure underneath you,
even if you're doing something abstract,
like your character's a blob of goo,
as long as you're thinking about their character
and how they change and how they interact
with the world that they're in,
you can really do some amazing things.
But it's really understanding some of those core principles
that can help you at least construct a framework
to build any new character.
So all I'd recommend is,
Don't think of these constructs as rules
that you have to follow.
Just think of them as information
that you can always come back to
if you're having a hard time finding
what the center X or interest for your character might be.
In some games you need to make a character that is completely out of the game itself, the environment,
and it contrasts with the entire game and world.
And at the same time, you need it to fit into what the game is aiming for.
So, have you had any experience with that, including clothes, colors and animations?
Yeah, absolutely. I mean, sometimes you want your character to deliberately stand out.
Some of my favorite games have a character who's in...
is made of silhouette, or like made of a shadow, and they're only visible...
they're an invisible character, and they're only seen from their shadow.
Or a character that's made of light, and they stand out in front of... in a dark world.
So your character doesn't always have to blend in
or be a part of that world,
but they should have an effect on that world.
So whatever your character does,
and whatever their goal might be,
whether it's to be very unique and separate,
even stylistically separate,
just make sure that they're supporting a goal
that the game has, right?
That that is ultimately what you're trying to do
with your character at all times,
is make it reflect the gameplay intentions
that the game has itself.
Hi.
Could you talk a little bit about the death animation in Tomb Raider?
Because those are probably one of the best things that we remember about the game.
Why do you need to make them so brutal?
So, it's a great question.
We got that a lot.
Yeah, so the question was,
why did you make the death animation so brutal in Tomb Raider?
And there's a good answer for that.
One, we came back to what is the core theme of our game,
and it was survival.
And to us, you can't have actions without consequences.
So if I'm on an interactive sequence,
and my character's life depends on my actions,
and if I don't perform those actions correctly,
there has to be a consequence that makes me go,
oh, I better not do that again, I better do that better.
For some people, they're like, oh, I gotta see that again.
You know, I mean, Conan O'Brien's,
Clueless Gamer is sort of a meme, right?
It's like, it became that thing where,
because he was so bad at video games
that he kept dying over and over and over again
and it looked a little masochistic.
But the hope is, is...
you don't die like that so often,
and that they really are a source of feedback
for the treacherous situations that you're in.
So as the character progressed,
like in Rise of the Tomb Raider,
we still had our brutal deaths,
but there weren't as many, and they weren't as frequent,
and that wasn't because we were trying to be more PC.
We were really trying to say that the character's grown,
and that her competence has improved.
And that is why the tone shifted across the games.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Hey Brian, great talk.
So my question was, how much of the story in Tomb Raider
was known up front relative to the design of the character
and how much did changes to the story,
that iteration process affect either Lara
or any of the other supporting characters in Tomb Raider
or Rise of the Tomb Raider?
Yeah, so the question was how much of the story
was written before we started the character
and how much of the character came first
and the story came later?
And I can tell you that the goals were right away.
Like when we were designing the character,
all those ideas and archetypes and survival themes,
that was first.
So we really couldn't design the character
without having that.
Now, when it came to that story that I went through,
that whole loop of how Lara went through
the hero's journey, that came much later.
But, if you have that story ahead of time, it's even more powerful for your artists because
they can imbue the character with key ingredients throughout that story that are going to make
them that much more rich.
So the aspiration is, if you can, get your writers and your game designers together early
enough to talk about the arc and to talk about where your character is going to go.
that's going to inform the character artists that design them.
So that would be the hope.
But ultimately what we had was the character first,
and then as new events happened to her,
we started to add ingredients to her character.
So there was a scene when she got impaled by...
When she fell down, she got impaled by a piece of rebar.
And then we added that as a permanent part of a scar in her character.
or when she was hit in the face with Vlad by a gun,
we brought into Rise of the Tomb Raider
that little scar went into the next game.
So we tried to build and accumulate these experiences
on the character and see as her wardrobe
or her costume would reflect all the trauma,
that that was just, those were things
that we brought into the character
as the story was being written.
Yeah?
Hi, I have a question about like...
You talked about building the characters in the third person perspective,
but when you develop first person shooter,
I think most people project themselves to the characters.
So is there some different approach to develop and making characters?
Yeah, I think there's two different approaches.
Like for Infinite Warfare, we decided to make Reyes
a real character that had a voice
and that we would see him in cinematics and cut scenes.
So we were playing a character just like a third person
action adventure game.
But there are games like Half-Life.
Half-Life 2, one of my favorite games, where the character is a cypher, right?
They don't have a personality because you want to transport your personality into them.
Now that's really cool.
I think there's something really important about that, but if you want to have your character
go on an arc...
it's all then about the reflection of that art has to come from your support cast and from the world itself.
So the lift is now on the environment artists, the lift is on the supporting cast
to help reflect back what my actions did.
So this is a constant battle we have as game developers is
when we want to tell a story which has a prescribed beginning and end,
And that conflicts with a goal that a player might have.
You have what we call cognitive dissonance,
and it's something that we dealt with a lot.
Like, hey, I wouldn't have felt that way
if I shot that person.
I would have felt happy about it, not sad about it.
So one of our challenges as game developers
is how do we ensure that we have parity
with what the character's feeling
and what the audience member might be feeling?
And that's why first-person shooters that let you be a cypher,
or let that first-person character not have a personality,
that's probably the cleanest and easiest way to do that.
But I challenge all of us to think about telling stories completely,
all the way through, and retaining that connection with the character
and the way the player feels.
And I know it's something that I've got friends over here from Naughty Dog,
it's something I'm sure you guys talk about a lot.
And I worked with Taylor and Jacob,
and they worked on The Last of Us,
and it's one of my favorite games of all time.
And I remember telling him,
hey, my only beef with that game was at the end,
I wouldn't have made the same decisions Joel made.
But what they told me was really compelling.
They said, well, that wasn't your story.
That was Joel's story.
And as long as you're with him along the line,
you'll understand and appreciate that decision
that he made for himself.
So those are the kind of challenges we have
as designers and as artists,
is to try our best to tell compelling emotional stories,
yet embrace the agency that is in video games.
Thank you.
Hi. Hi.
Could you talk more about designing female protagonists?
Like, what are the challenges
and what are the things you have to keep in mind?
Yeah, when it comes to female protagonists, I don't think that's important.
I'm going to say that one more time, it's not important.
The hero is the hero.
Now, am I saying is there a difference between a man and a woman?
Absolutely.
But you just build that into part of who they are as a character.
The only reason I can say that there's a problem with it right now is because people still
obsess about it as a thing, right?
Being a female, oh my gosh, I'm a dude and I feel really uncomfortable playing as a female
and I don't know how that makes me feel.
That can exist and some people have issues with that.
But really what we're trying to get to is a place is that your character is your character.
They can be female and they can be an alien, they can be a man, they can be a piece of
slime, they can be whatever you want.
But ultimately, does their motivations ring true?
Does the characters actions reflect their motivations?
Are they compelling?
Are they interesting?
Do they have some place to go?
And as long as you have all of those things
and you could take, the reason that this presentation
was so much more about the structure of your hero
and not so much about the choices you make
is because once you have that right,
you can really design pretty much anything
and your audience is gonna be along the ride with you.
At least that's my belief.
All right, that's all I got.
Thank you guys so much for coming.
Appreciate it.