And I'll be speaking on crisis management in communities and my journey learning on how to handle crisis.
This is a deeper retrospective on the Kotaku and subsequently republished article,
What it's like to be the community manager for the worst PS4 game ever.
Using my story, I'll be looking at both the professional and personal aspects.
I'll be outlining some of the most important attributes of both areas I have found crucial,
and I'm going to tell you how I apply these to best interact with my communities.
After professional, I'll be touching on the importance of transparency,
ownership of responsibility, use of empathy, clear communication and effective messaging.
On the personal side, I'll be emphasising self-care, support networks, mental health,
knowing your limits and recovery after crisis.
So previously I was a scientist, as you can see here.
That's actually me in an airlock exiting a negative pressure room.
So my background is in science, genetics and microbiology to be exact, and I haven't had
any previous training in PR, communications or community management.
I am completely self-taught.
Currently, I'm the Community Engagement Manager
at EA Firemonkeys, based in Melbourne, Australia,
and I'm responsible for all live titles.
I'm also a relatively young upstart in the games industry,
and I've only been around for a few years.
So a question I get a lot is,
how the hell did you end up in games?
So I started in indie games on a project called Wanda.
There is where I learned my community management skills,
but also one crucial thing.
crisis management.
I originally joined to help out a friend.
I started off in QA
and moved to community management at product launch,
taking over all social media channels
without instructional mentoring.
Despite not having guidance,
my philosophy of approach at the time
was that I would try to do
what I felt was in the best interest
for both the community and the development team.
So just a little bit on Wanda.
It was an exploration, narrative-focused, non-combat
MMO for PC and console.
Yes, I know, it's quite the mouthful.
So it was in development for a number of years
with a very small team of less than 10 people
based in Melbourne, Australia.
So before Wanda's launch, there was a lot of interest
from both domestic and international media,
as you can see here by some of these headlines and quotes.
It was demoed at PAX Prime.
South, East, Australia, Gamescom, and even had an IndieGoGo Kickstarter.
There was a lot of hype surrounding the game including press interest which commented on
the first impressions of the game itself. Breathtakingly beautiful, gorgeous, sheer
joy and mystery of exploration. These were some of the headlines and quotes from sites such as
Kotaku and Polygon. Wanda was definitely different in terms of gameplay style and visually on first
impressions it was indeed very pretty.
However, Wanda was far from perfect.
This is an example of some of the problems that Wanda had.
It's what I affectionately call the slingshot effect.
And I feel it actually speaks volumes
about the game itself.
This is another example.
So what you see here is a hearer,
a humanoid form of the character you play,
clipping straight through some rocks
and blatantly ignoring the collision volume.
So Wanda had a bunch of live issues
such as constant crashing, progress loss,
as well as intrinsic game issues
such as clipping, janky animations,
as well as unfortunately clunky controls.
Unfortunately, Wanda failed to live up to expectation
and deliver at launch.
There was a significant element of media negativity,
as you can see here,
on top of really quite negative player sentiment
and criticism.
It was slammed by critics, in particular Jimquisition, who's known for his quite pointed view in games.
He was particularly harsh in Wanda.
How?
How did this game trick the world into thinking it was something,
when it was absolutely nothing?
That was only the beginning of the storm.
In amongst the live issues we had, such as the progress loss and the crashing,
it was relatively common for players to state that Wanda was literally unplayable.
This is the review page for Wanda from Steam,
and this continues right down the page as far as you can read.
It was at this time I took over the social media platforms,
Facebook, Twitter, Steam Forums, Google+,
and I even started my own Twitch TV campaign stream.
This was my idea consisting of daily Q&As with the developers.
I played through the game, answered some questions,
and fielded any feedback coming through.
Sometimes these sessions lasted for more than four hours,
which is not bad for a first-time streamer.
But the net result seemed really positive,
as we didn't receive encouraging feedback and sentiment
from the community overall from me doing this.
These are just a small selection of some of the comments
we received about Wanda.
It was an avalanche with more coming in by the hour,
on top of the negative press we were receiving.
In regards to some of the commentary we received,
we had unsavoury accusations of us trying to steal money
from the Australian government,
as Wanda had received funding for its development.
An interesting comment I'd like to point out here
is from Jennifer.
She says, a non-combative game made me rage quit.
Which says it all.
Behind the scenes, what people didn't know, though,
is that I wasn't just handling social media.
But I was also trying to support our creative director
and loan programmer as we worked through all the many days
and nights together.
I was burning myself out trying to support the game publicly
and privately.
That took a very heavy emotional toll on me.
On a few occasions, I had to simply walk away
from my laptop and just take a moment to breathe.
In the rare moments where that didn't work,
I broke down in tears.
So the shit really was on fire
with the emotional strain, stress, and ultimately tears.
I was not fine.
So I'm gonna go through and give an outline
on how I break down messages from players
and their points in any engagement across platforms.
I start by looking at key topics, friction points, tone of the message itself, points
where I can offer insight and information, as well as looking for opportunities to connect
and really engage.
I'll also give my perspective on how I respond to communities whilst also doing what I can
to turn an engagement into a positive interaction.
So this is a comment we received in our Facebook
from a player named Darryl.
I'm not going to read all of it, so.
Any game may receive comments similar to this.
A lot more comments we did receive
were not nearly as well written or as reasonable as this.
However, I'm going to use this as an example of how
I approach answering player commentary
using the professional skills I outlined
at the beginning of my presentation.
As I'm not going to have you read through Darryl's extensive comment, I'm going to break
this down into the following key points which I've drawn from his comment.
So Darryl isn't attracted to the role-playing nature of Wanda.
The play style isn't quite his personal preference.
He describes Wanda as an empty sandbox with nothing to do, as well as states that he isn't
trying to be mean in how he's conveying his experience.
He's bored yet holds out hope for something interesting eventually,
but ultimately right now there's not enough to hold his interest in the game.
He regrets buying the game and it not living up to his expectations and mentions attempting to
get a refund from Sony. But the most interesting point I found out of this was at the very end,
is that he expresses that he is apologetic for communicating his very negative experience.
This is my response to Dawa's comment,
and it's almost equally as wordy.
So I'm definitely not going to make you read it all,
but I will be breaking down my response
to show you how I approach responding to this.
In addressing the comments involving player feedback
on your product, you need to keep in mind
some very important questions.
Firstly, what were the specific issues raised?
Secondly, what are you going to do
about addressing these problems?
Like, what do you need to do?
I use these questions as a guide in writing my responses to comments, and I find them
generally useful in my everyday messaging.
A key point to remember is to communicate clearly your progress and process, such as
is there any news on terms of fixes, update ETAs, etc.
One of the things I did to help the community during my time at Wander is that I wrote FAQs
and directed the community to them, which I did actually find quite helpful.
Also when dealing with repetitive questions,
I developed a template for responses
which became the foundation for a reactive messaging system,
an effective method I still use to this day.
On a personal level,
I was terrified I'd say something wrong.
As we all know, the internet never forgets.
In the first part of my response to Daryl, I try to empathize with him and try to build
a relationship by acknowledging and understanding his point of view.
Something to keep in mind is that individuals have approached you, opened up that dialogue
and taken the time and effort to write their comment.
They've ultimately come to you seeking for advice.
In the second part of my comment, I go on to further acknowledge and address the issues
raised in his comment.
I also shed clarity on the situation as a whole and what our intentions and actions
are moving forward.
I go on to reassure him and acknowledge that his points are valid and that we will try
to do something about them.
Overall, I try to be as transparent as possible in answering.
In the last section of my reply to Daryl,
I approach problem solving by taking ownership
of the situation and giving an honest, clear answer
to the best of my ability.
I attempt to consolidate the relationship further
and build rapport.
This is evidenced by my final statement,
take care of yourself.
Connecting and showing an element of care
is humanizing your brand and product.
Part of community engagement is connecting
with individuals and your community as a whole.
By showing that you care, you are connecting with your community on a truly human level.
My entire experience wasn't completely bad. It's not all fire and brimstone, trust me.
So there were some positive things that came out of Wanda,
such as lasting friendships with developers,
both in Australia and externally.
I also made friends with players.
So for example, I have two friends of mine in Seattle,
Penny and James, who I actually met through Wanda
because they were playing the game,
and I've kept in contact with them since.
So despite the negativity that we did receive,
we did have some positive feedback from players.
I also went through brand new experiences
and discovered a whole new set of skills
that I didn't know I previously had.
But the one big thing is that I ended up
in a career in games.
When dealing with a crisis in your community,
it's important to know your limits.
I worked beyond my limits,
much to my own personal detriment.
So these are some tweets that I wrote from the Wanda account.
I wrote these times where we went home.
So as you note, 6.30 AM, 5.20 AM, 4.30 AM.
The one good thing out of all of that
is that we eventually got to go home at 4.30 AM
instead of 6.30 in the morning.
As you can see, I was working crazy hours
to the point where my car got towed.
I'd missed birthdays, dinners, brunches, coffee,
time with my friends and family.
I almost went completely broke to the point where I had $8 left in my bank account.
I got sick to the point of being bedridden, yet I still continued to stream.
The community never sleeps, but you have to.
You are at the forefront and someone who can actively do something in the midst of a crisis.
It's really important to take care of yourself.
I can't stress this enough, as you will be tempted
to push yourself, but you have to be careful,
as the last thing you want to do is burn out.
So this is one of my favorite moments working
on the project.
Pizza was ordered for us by some fans in Germany,
and it arrived midway through my Twitch stream.
So if you actually go back and read the recorded streams,
there's one point where I go, pizza!
Um, so in the middle of a negativity storm, when just about anything can go
wrong and has gone wrong, when someone tweets your address, you kind of expect
a large angry mob to show up at your doorstep.
It's not a particularly rational thought.
However, in a situation like that, it feels like just about anything is possible.
Despite the dark times, we had a support network,
which even included complete random strangers.
The community rallied around us,
both development and players alike.
It was then I began to take steps
to better look after myself,
such as wrapping up my Twitch streams a bit earlier
when I was sick or I needed rest,
eating better and looking after myself
more than just eating pizza and takeaway.
I eventually left the project in August 2015 and began my own personal journey to recovery.
I spent a lot of time with friends going out and generally reacquainting myself with the
world.
I took time to recover mentally and physically from working at Wanda and I had to teach myself,
in a way, how to relax as I'd been under pressure for such an extended period of time where
this was all I really knew.
Both mental and physical health were things I had to work on,
that I had to put myself back in a good state.
It took a while, and it was predominantly
my friends and family and a lot of sleep
that helped me get through that process
to be back to normal and the person that I am today.
Since leaving the project, I have freelanced.
But during that time, I was deciding whether or not
I should go back to science, continue on to a medical degree,
or stay in games.
because I discovered that despite the interesting experience that I had
in the games industry, I'd really enjoyed the interactions and engagement with players.
I found something very deeply fulfilling in that.
Eventually, I applied for a job at EA and they took me on,
and they've taught me a heck of a lot since my time at Wanda.
I've really developed personally and professionally since then,
and I've been exposed to new opportunities and challenges.
Ultimately, I'm really glad I made the career change and stayed in games.
I've also got a whole new perspective on how games are made and promoted.
I've seen Wanda go from an idea, from coding, asset creation, animation, testing, to its
release and aftermath.
I have immense admiration for everyone who works in the games industry, but particularly
community managers like yourselves, who are on the communication frontlines.
So in summary, never underestimate the tremendous wrath of an immeasurable horde of irate gamers.
But at the same time, never underestimate your own strength
in a dire situation.
Stay calm, communicate with your community honestly,
empathetically, and clearly.
Take responsibility where needed,
and be proactive in your endeavors with engagement.
Ensure that you're taking care of your basic needs,
physically and psychologically, and rely on your support
networks of friends, family, colleagues in the industry.
Other community managers have been a great help to me.
Know that no matter how difficult the situation is,
you will weather the storm.
But most importantly, for the sake of your health,
well-being, and your product,
take time and step away from the computer.
I'd like to share with you a particular gift
which I feel typifies the experience
of community crisis management.
No.
Thank you.
So there's a mic in the middle for anyone who would like to ask some questions.
Hey, how's it going?
I'm a community manager and I've worked for
a lot of big brands outside of gaming though.
And when they have a crisis,
maybe it's because people in games, I don't know,
maybe they feel like their money's already spent
and gone down the drain.
I know refunds are sort of a debate issue.
But I'm just wondering how you feel
about people asking for refunds.
And even though we can't always offer refunds,
is that something that you would ever use
to appease a community?
Or is that just like a dangerous can of worms
that you never ever want to crack open?
So the question is about refunds and how we sort of approach that.
That's an interesting question and to an extent it depends upon your platform.
So a refunds policy may be different on Steam versus how it is in the App Store.
So what you can really do from your side is just refer them to the correct channels for the appropriate technical support.
Usually with a lot of developers, they don't handle that transaction process.
It would still need to be gone through with the platforms.
But the best you can do to help them is redirect them through the appropriate support channels.
So in dealing with some of the different projects that you've worked on, especially having multiple
projects, from a community management perspective, how many people do you usually tie to any
one given project, especially if you have like a full spectrum support mechanism like
social media, forums, and so on and so forth?
So the question is personnel per project and how the support goes with communications and that.
It really depends upon your project.
So I've had the privilege of being able to work on a tiny indie project,
as well as something bigger such as EA,
where I've gone from a small community to, God, several million.
So it really depends.
It depends upon your staffing levels and also what your...
colleagues are willing to do what they feel like they can do in their power,
whether it's like answering the occasional tweet on Twitter and that,
that is still community management. You are speaking to a community and
individuals. So as to what might be an ideal scenario
for support for community management, it's hard to say. It really depends upon
your own personal, your, sorry, your team's
communities and situation at that point in time.
Thanks for the talk, that was great.
I really liked the way that you broke down Darrell's comment
and how you replied to him, addressing all of his points.
I was just wondering, for say, the kind of like shorter,
meaner comments that you can get that are just kind of like,
this sucks and I hate it, did you bother replying to those
and how did you go about responding
to those kind of people?
Yeah, so in regards to short comments like,
you suck, I hate your product and that,
how do you go about interacting with that?
You are within your rights to ignore
very negative or toxic comments because,
for example on Facebook, if you answer a comment
that will often float it up to the top
of the comment section.
which may not be an ideal situation.
I mean, it's great that you can,
and one strategy I would employ is to turn
a negative situation to a positive.
So someone might be really pissed off
in terms of something to do with your game,
and you can be like, right, so what exactly is your issue?
How can I help?
Have you tried X, Y, and Z?
So turn it into a positive interaction.
However, if it's just blatant abuse, then.
you're kind of better off not interacting with it to a certain extent.
How are you able to gauge or measure the effects of your efforts on the community's
attitude toward the game?
So how do you measure the effects of what you do on the community as a whole?
So there's a bunch of really great social listening suites out there.
That's really good in measuring the sentiment of your community as well as
measuring the effectiveness of your campaign.
So I definitely recommend looking into one of them.
But in terms of me starting out when I was, you know...
without any mentoring, without any sort of instruction
on that sort of thing, I basically
had to go through the responses by hand myself
to really gauge if my actions were doing something
constructive and positive for the community.
So you kind of got to do it by hand.
But if you have the means and the resources to,
I'd definitely have a look at social media listening suites,
as they can often collate stuff into a report quite easily
for you.
So that would be my suggestion.
What made you stick with Wanda for as long as you did?
Was it personal naughtiness with your friends?
Belief in the game?
What made you stick around?
That's a very good question.
What made me stick around?
I'm stubborn as hell.
But also, I believed in the philosophy of Wanda.
It was an unpolished, untested, very different game.
It wasn't an Assassin's Creed or anything like that.
But I believed in the philosophy and I still thought there was something there.
And the team members I worked with were very genuine, very passionate people who obviously
loved what they were doing. So in part I was inspired and motivated by them to stay around.
However, for the sake of my own well-being.
I had to eventually drop the project because it just wasn't viable for me to keep on living
the way that I was doing. So in essence what kept me going
is sheer force of will and also really a fantastic team and environment.
I think that's everything. Has anyone got any more questions?
All right, well thank you very much for coming to my talk.
And make sure you check out those surveys.