All right.
Yeah, my name is Mika Vehkela, and I
work for Remedy Entertainment as a lead AI programmer.
And in this session, together with Bobby and Ben,
I talk about our experiences working with behavior trees.
And in my part, I'm going to be talking a little bit
about a quick touch up on this blackboard and database, which
is used together with behavior trees
almost in all the implementations.
Then the most of the talk that I'm going to give
is about decorators.
And then little bit about splitting the trees and then
also about coordination using the ever trees.
So some of the challenge areas that I've faced using multiple
different implementations in different games have been
always the same thing it sounds like a simple stuff, but it
still comes up time after time it's the generalization and
granularity of tasks so the so in in like pre production
production.
And then of course between game projects as well so you would like to of course
build eventually this library of reusable building blocks of decorators
and notes that you could use then you know in in future games as well.
And then also there seems to be this question especially from designers
working with this this implementation is that how do you deal with
interruptions and transitions in the behavior trees.
But before I go to all these notes and decorators, a quick
glance at these databases.
So most often what people have in conjunction with the
behavior trees is some kind of a blackboard implementation
and also this kind of sensory systems that the sensors will
basically reflect the data from the game world from all
over the memory and then store it inside a database, a
compressed format.
And the behavior tree is only reading through this database.
It can read and write there.
So it's still a good idea to keep in mind
that the simpler this implementation of the database
is, and the data format, and the more compact it is,
the easier it's going to be to implement all of your nodes
and decorators, especially for conditions.
It also makes the debugging easier,
which is pretty obvious.
But if you have a very condensed and a nice implementation,
you can just basically list out of all the properties
that this NPC knows of.
And then finally, of course, it performs better,
because if you have a very compressed set of data
that you're accessing, it's going
to be much better than accessing the memory all over the place.
So one example, and I'm using this kind
of method in this presentation, how
you could implement the database would
be to have one single dictionary per tracked
entity or a known entity for each of the NPCs.
And this dictionary is just a.
list of properties, key value pairs that this NPC knows of each of these tracked entities.
So in this example, for example, we have an entry for self, the agent itself, and in this
example it would have only one property, primary target, set to enemy01, which happens to be
the other entry, another dictionary in your database that has one property which is visible
is true.
And you can reference these entries in the database in your decorators and nodes
just by using a string path.
So for example, self.primaryTarget means that you take a look at the self entity
and you read the primaryTarget property.
This happens to point out to enemy01,
so now you read from enemy01 the value of the visible property.
Okay, let's move on and go finally to the actual
behavior tree stuff, the nodes and decorators.
So a very quick recap.
You obviously, behavior trees consist of root node,
control flow nodes, which are the selectors,
sequence nodes, parallel nodes,
and then your execution nodes or tasks.
What you also have in many implementations
is some kind of decorator nodes.
So you may implement your conditions as decorator nodes,
and in this example, you would have, for example,
two conditions for this sequence.
So the above one, the abort condition,
would have to be met before it can select the child behavior
sequence.
Also, the first child node of the sequence
must be able to succeed, because if it would fail,
the sequence would, of course, also be aborted.
So both of these conditions have to be met before the sequence
can be activated.
So if this happens now, the sequence is activated.
It would proceed to the first task, the middle one there.
And if the abort condition now would turn to be false,
of course it would abort the sequence
and exit this whole branch.
But if the other one, the condition,
the first child of the sequence, would turn later to be false,
it would have no effect whatsoever.
So these would be the control activation and deactivation
decorators.
Then you have modify termination status decorators,
which would be something like always succeed.
So this always just succeeds when its child is completed.
Even if the child fails, it will report itself
as success to the parent.
So in this example, it would make the first task
as optional in the sequence.
Regardless of the task failing or succeeding,
the sequence will proceed to the final task.
And then you can have something like this add-on functionalities, for example,
if the last task would now fail, it would set a property.
So these decorators are very nice for doing cool-down or retry mechanisms
without having to implement it inside the task itself.
So all these are kind of nice and very useful.
I'm sure that you guys are using them with your behavior trees.
But there's also another way to think about them which would be instead of
decorative nodes, node decorators.
And there's a nice example, so Miesko Zielinski did this for the Unreal 4's
behavior trees.
So it basically means that the decorators are part of the nodes
themselves. They are not actually nodes at all.
So this will create, in my mind, more compact visual representation of your behavior trees
and it also allows more options to simplify your nodes in an easier way.
So the common types again would be that you have the activation and deactivation controlling
decorators inside the node, but now in this case you can easily see that this sequence,
they are within the sequence, both of the abort and the regular condition.
You can have the termination status modifiers.
Again, it's much easier to see that now this task always
succeeds.
You can have parallel execution by having
updatable decorators.
Unreal, I believe, calls them services.
And then finally, you can have the same add-on functionality
that if this task, the right one, would fail, it sets a
cool-down property to 10 seconds in this example.
So comparing these two approaches, at least myself,
I prefer the left one because it makes it much more condensed.
And especially when dealing with big behavior trees,
when they tend to actually grow up,
you would like to, of course, be able to read those trees,
especially if they're altered by multiple people
in an easier way.
So that's one of the kind of the major things
that I personally like with this kind of an approach.
So a few more examples of what you can, like how you can try to build your library of this reusable building blocks
with decorators and more general purpose nodes is an example of a retry mechanism.
So you can have this selector that will first try to, of course, activate the press button behavior.
It would be a general purpose behavior where the NPC is trying to press a button.
Maybe it even has the animation control inside this behavior.
Let's assume that it would now fail.
So for some reason, pressing this button didn't succeed.
So we have this general purpose decorator that says, well,
if I fail, set last try property to be the timestamp of now.
Also, we have a condition that checks
that if time since this property is more than 10 seconds,
then you're allowed to select the node.
So if you now fail, it would take at least 10 seconds
before you can reselect the node.
So the selector will happily select the next behavior,
which is play animation.
And we can now also add this general purpose loop decorator,
also very common in many implementations,
where instead of having the play animation to contain
a selection of I want to loop this animation,
or maybe an option inside the animation resource itself,
you can bring it forth in the behavior tree itself
and say whenever this task succeeds,
it will start over again and won't report to its parent
that it has completed.
So in this example, it would make this play animation
to simply play forever.
But of course, since the selector is monitoring the higher priority branch, the press button,
eventually it can be reselected because the time stamp will be more than 10 seconds old
and it will retry the press button.
So again, you don't have to implement this retry mechanism into any of these behaviors,
but use a general purpose set of decorators and behaviors.
An example of look at, so you can have two types of parallel execution things.
Now with these updatable decorators, so a parallel node will execute a move to,
which will move to a next waypoint. At the same time there's a look at behavior,
which would try to look at a location of primary point of interest,
if it is set. And then you can have an updatable decorator
that is separated from the look at, so the look at doesn't figure out what it should look.
It simply just looks at a point that has been set in the database.
So the scan point of interest will be scanning around the
agent and setting this primary point of interest if it finds
something interesting.
And now the look at would of course pick it up and start
looking at that point.
In this example, the updatable decorator could also be of
course put into this look at node itself.
Then we have debugging.
So we can also use these decorators very easily.
to help you debugging the behavioral trees so you can have tag decorators.
So it's a simple decorator where you can give any string, in this case, in combat or in patrol.
And you don't have to care, as a designer or a programmer, how did these nodes get selected.
The behavior tree can be complex, like above these behaviors, you don't have to care
where this is, or if somebody refactors the tree somehow, you don't have to care.
Also, you don't have to care what happens inside these nodes.
whenever to notice active this time would be active and there can be a
simple way to be basic query which tags are active at this moment and you can
display them for example on top of the characters head showing the guys now in
combat or in patrol this could of course also be used outside of debugging and
maybe control the the game playing in some way.
Same thing you could do with message decorators instead of tagging something
you can basically have a message decorator that sends a message
on activation of the node, on deactivation of the node and possibly even sends every update
some kind of message either to your debugging systems or possibly to the gameplay systems as well.
Finally of course break point decorators which act in the same way so if the
node gets activated and perhaps there's a condition if the condition is met then
the game will for example pause and zoom to this actor so it can be very helpful
if you have multiple actors running around to have this condition that you
can flag I want to monitor these particular NPCs and if any of them
happen to select this one node you would pause the game and zoom to that place
and see okay now the guy is about to perform this action.
So with all these examples, what I wanted to sort of bring forth is that building a
library of reusable tasks actually is more like balancing out how to extract options
from your tasks into decorators and kind of balancing the library of decorators and nodes
together.
And of course it wouldn't matter in which way you implement them, but I personally prefer
these decorators to be the property of nodes themselves.
A little bit about interruptions.
So we could have a case like this.
There's a selector that has a higher priority behavior,
jump to safety, if there's a grenade
within five meters of the NPC.
Let's assume that there is no grenade yet.
So the selector would pick a sequence.
And its sequence, the first thing that it tries to do
is a heroic, super slow vault to cover.
Let's say that takes 15 seconds.
It looks really awesome.
And it's going to take the character outside of the nav
mesh and do all kinds of funny things.
And it's going to be very difficult to interrupt it
in a meaningful and good looking way.
While he's now in halfway through this vault animation,
let's say that the grenade lands next to it.
So what the behavior tree will do, it doesn't really care.
It simply selects the jump to safety
and deactivates this other one.
What to do?
So, of course, I don't think it's a problem
of the behavior tree.
Personally, I think that that's exactly what should happen.
So the task that gets interrupted may, of course,
do some cleanup.
Perhaps it wants to tell the animation system
to stop playing this animation.
Maybe it doesn't.
So the second thing that it can do is also the jump to safety that gets selected.
It doesn't have to fail if it cannot perform immediately this jump to safety.
So perhaps you want to just wait out
that the body is able to perform the action that you want here.
What I'm trying to say is that it's really not oftentimes a problem of the behavior trees
to deal with these interruptions, even though there's a lot of these questions of what should be done.
But sometimes you might still have the case that...
you want to commit to an action and you do not want to interrupt this in the
behavior tree itself. So you could also of course add an uninterruptible
decorator into your node. And this would be quite simple to implement so the
only thing it means is that if there's an uninterruptible node it will freeze
all the the condition monitoring on top of the tree like throughout the
parent hierarchy of this tree.
You can chain also those uninterruptibles.
So if there's a child node to this uninterruptible,
of course that would then set the parenting hierarchy
to be uninterruptible as well.
But personally, I wouldn't really use this.
I would try to avoid them at all costs,
because eventually you could get the tree getting stuck
and weird issues that the guy is performing very long sequences
and not reacting to anything.
So splitting the trees.
That's the next thing. This is like a workflow thing and I also think it's something that people do very often.
So you can have two types of ways to split your trees.
As a property of behavior trees, of course, any sub-tree can be always considered as its own tree.
So what you can do is have reference nodes. So this would be design time nodes, where you can just extract a part of the behavior tree and save it to a separate resource.
And then you set in the parenting tree that contains this tree a reference node
and you refer this behavior. It's a pretty standard node to have in your
behavior tree implementations. So this is designed and it merges during export
or load. So it reduces the perceived complexity of the tree, not really
the actual complexity of the tree. And the main benefit is of course that it allows
you to edit these behavior trees
by multiple people at the same time without having to worry about the merge conflicts.
and you shouldn't go like crazy about these and start immediately doing them.
You should basically build this one tree and whenever it seems like logical,
you should then take a piece of the tree and save it to another resource.
Effectively refactoring your trees as you go.
There's also these other types of nodes which allows the dynamic attachment of
behavior trees. So it's just a placeholder node that's saying, well,
if there's nothing attached at this node at runtime, the node always fails.
It cannot be activated. And you can, from somewhere in code, you can attach a
behavior tree here and then it would just do the same thing as the statically
attached trees. Then it would appear as part of the tree.
So what you can do with these dynamic trees is smart objects,
for example.
So instead of having fixed pipeline smart objects where
you have, for example, a list of actions or animations
to perform when you try to use these things,
you could simply have them as containers for behavior trees
and maybe a small piece of a database that's
embedded with this smart object.
So it's essentially instructions of how
to use this smart object.
You could also have items and weapons.
So instead of having everything put into the character themselves,
you could have the combat part of the tree
actually be embedded into the weapon itself.
This would allow you, especially in the prototyping phase,
to build a single NPC,
and depending on the weapon, you can change how it actually behaves.
Maybe later on you still want to put all the behavior trees inside the character,
but this way you can dynamically say,
if I give this guy a pistol, maybe he wants to use cover,
and he wants to fight quite close by.
And if you give him a shotgun, maybe he's not using cover in the same way.
Maybe he wants to perform a different set of actions instead.
And then you can do more than just the smart objects in your level scripting.
So, for example, for spawning, again, instead of having fixed pipeline spawning animations
that the guy rushes through the door in some kind of awesome way,
you just put a behavior tree that overrides your master tree at a very high level.
When the guy is spawning, maybe it has some kind of sequence, similar sequence to
rush through this door or has some, is using like move to behaviors, but it can
also do things like if the enemy happens to be very close by, maybe I don't want
to commit into this long animation and expose myself, but instead just take a
shortcut and start shooting back immediately.
So this would be such a simple example. So this smart object could be as simple as
just a list of animations as you would have in your fixed pipeline smart objects.
And then you could attach it into this child tree node.
And the node itself can be also very simple.
So you can have the cool-down mechanism implemented again
with these generators, general purpose decorators.
And for weapons, of course, you don't
want to detach the tree if this child tree is not active.
But for smart objects, when you have finished
using the smart object, you can add this decorator
that says, when this node terminates,
it detaches the smart object.
And then finally, there's this thing that bihertories are oftentimes used and mostly
used only to control your characters, but they could also be used to do coordination
between NPCs.
So...
Thanks for watching!
Bye!
What you could have is a volume for a room, like a box, whatever shape of a volume, and
you can add a behavior tree to this volume as well, and a database to go with it.
And this behavior tree, of course, wouldn't have moved behaviors because the volume is
not moving much or controlling the body in any way, but you would basically have a custom
set of nodes and decorators that you could build up, which would be updating goals and
objectives, influence maps with updatable decorators, assigning roles.
and communicating with the NPCs either by writing that are in the visual memory
or just writing to its own memory and opportunistically these NPCs could be
reading from this database and altering their own actions.
So as a wrap up, I personally think that the way that Unreal has for example
implemented the decorators, it's a great way, it simplifies the complexity,
at least the perceived complexity, and it allows an easier way in my mind
to implement this kind of reusable building blocks.
for your behavior trees and for your games.
You shouldn't be limited to a single static tree.
Use a lot of these dynamic and static reference nodes.
And finally, behavior trees are not character specific.
Also, they are not the only mechanism
to control your characters.
And I think Bobby will touch upon this subject
a little bit more now.
Oh, and there's of course read more.
So AI game dev has a lot of articles about this
and the Unreal 4 is very well documented
as well as Angry Ants behave.
So Bobby, your turn.
All right, so for my part, it's going to be a little bit more of a best practices talk.
We're going to talk about some problems with behavior trees.
We're also going to discuss some of the solutions.
Nothing I'm going to really discuss today here is going to be revolutionary in terms
of reinventing the wheel or anything like that.
We're not going to do anything crazy.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to provide some observations and suggestions.
People have touched on this in the past, but I want to go a bit more deep.
And I want to kind of hope that I can prevent some pain
for people in the room and also kind of kick off some discussions.
As kind of an intro to this, I just want to discuss my perspective on engineering.
I don't believe in silver bullets.
I believe that every technique, every approach we have has pros and cons.
And in games especially, we tend to lose our perspective a lot
and we tend to brute force our solutions.
It's our job to sort of look at the tools we have and understand them deeply
and understand where they work, where they don't, the pros and the cons.
Also in games we have this mentality of sort of milestone driven, goal driven,
feature driven approaches where sometimes we lose sight of the bigger picture
chasing a small goal.
In my experience the better the tooling we have the better the workflows, the more
iterations we can do the better the end result is and so to have good tools
you need to understand what the flaws are.
So before I dive into the behavior tree stuff,
I'm gonna discuss a little bit of visualization.
I tend to kind of think of trees in a different way to most.
Kind of the traditional approaches you saw in Mika's display
and Angry Ant in Unreal 4 is sort of this kind of
vertical approach where we both have the priority
as well as the sequence order of nodes running horizontally.
So you'll see that both priority, high to low,
is left to right, as well as actions left to right.
I prefer to visualize trees in more of a kind of
reading approach, in my kind of preferred way of visualization, I kind of have the priority
going from top to bottom.
So when we branch, we kind of branch vertically.
And then the actions are running left to right, sort of like a sequence or a timeline.
That helps me reason about behavior just a little bit better, because I'm like, okay,
well, I made this choice, and now I'm going to make this choice, then I'll make the third
choice.
Okay, I've made the choice, now I kind of go left to right.
So, I'm going to start off discussing some of the problems.
Behavior trees are inherently bad at two things.
Those interruptions and transitions
and behavior prioritization.
Now, I know a lot of you are going to pull out
pitchforks and torches,
and yes, you've shipped games with behavior trees
and everything worked out fine,
and you know, you got everything done,
and you can, but just hear me out.
So,
Currently the most sort of common approach to behavior trees that I've seen in the industry
is event driven.
That basically means that as we kind of traverse the tree, at every single point we register
these monitor nodes until we hit a behavior that we run.
These monitor nodes get updated every frame.
And the deeper we are in the tree, the kind of more monitors we need to kind of check
the higher priority behaviors.
And when one of these monitors ends up triggering, it will end up causing the tree to sort of
abort.
reset and kind of go into that behavior they triggered.
And this is happening through the conditions
that are being set for these monitors and the entries.
This leads us to our first big problem
and that is static prioritization of the trees.
So imagine I'm currently in fighting.
How do I go to investigating?
Well, the only way to transition from high-low priorities
is to either abort or complete that behavior.
To abort, we usually need to then start sprinkling these special case conditions in these behaviors.
So if I was fighting and I lose sight of my target, I need to now write a bunch of conditions
and they're saying, well, if I lose sight of target, fail this behavior, then the behavior
tree will reset and then I can jump into a lower priority behavior.
This kind of ends up polluting the tree, especially the high-level behaviors with low priority
ones.
It's kind of implicitly because you're trying to cater for the transition lower down by
canceling a high-level thing, which greatly ends up increasing the complexity of the tree.
And then there's another even worse problem, which is that we often need to change the
priorities of our kind of high-level states based on the context of the situation.
To highlight this, I'm actually going to have some audience participation.
I'm going to show you an AI design.
I'm going to give you a few seconds to kind of look at it
and tell me if you understand this.
You guys get this? Do you see what it's doing?
Does everybody kind of...
No? Yes? People get this?
Okay, so I'm gonna ask some questions,
see if somebody can answer.
You should just shout out in the room.
When can a super attack occur?
There we go.
What happens after I do a super attack?
Cool, and from attack pattern two, what can I do?
Okay, simple, right?
What about this?
The same diagram, the same AI system.
It's a little bit harder to read.
And this is inherent to behavior trees
because behavior trees are directed acyclic graphs.
It means they have no loops.
They don't have cycles.
That AI design and AI designs in general are cyclic.
Even the most basic combat behavior cycles
between things like fight from cover, fight from position,
or wait, no, go back to cover.
We're constantly cycling these behaviors.
And what we're trying to do is we're trying
to model cyclic behavior with a cyclic data structure.
And yes, it can be done.
It doesn't mean we should.
So, how do we do this modeling of the cyclic behavior?
A lot of you in the room are probably doing this
without realizing it.
We end up doing preconditions to get the required results.
So for example, we'll have stuff in our knowledge saying,
hey, did I just do a charge attack?
Yes, okay, cool.
Then I can do this through another set of conditions
somewhere else.
Unfortunately, this requires us to sort of track this kind of stuff in an agent knowledge,
and it kind of pollutes it with execution and control flow data for the tree inside
of the agent knowledge, which is supposed to be kind of the agent's personal state about
himself.
It also greatly increases complexity, which ends up hurting robustness, understandability,
and obviously performance, since we have these monster trees we have to evaluate.
Worst of all is that we're creating these implicit transition dependencies between the
subtrees and the agent data.
Now, anybody doing computer science should be beaten into at some point that implicit
dependencies and dependencies in general are not good things.
And a personal metric of mine for code quality is more like how easy is it to delete that
code.
I'll look at a piece of code and say, if I want to delete this thing, how many areas
do I have to touch?
If it's simply just copy, paste, delete and everything works, then that is good code quality.
If I have to delete that, touch this, change this, undo this hook, remove this pointer
here, we've got problems.
So I'm going to ask you, like, how easy would it be, for example, for me to delete one of
these behaviors?
Well, I'm going to have to delete all the preconditions.
in potentially super attack inside of charge attack.
I'm gonna have to find every place
that I've hooked into this to kind of fake
the cyclic flow in an acyclic structure.
And so over time this works, but all the solutions,
especially later you get into a production,
end up looking like this, where you've beaten
this square peg into a round hole with a lot of force
to the point where now you can't even get it out
if you tried.
And now that we've discussed kind of the transitions and the interruptions and
this kind of priority, we also have another thing is that often when we do
these transitions, additionally we have to signal to the player that, hey,
I actually switched state.
So normally, kind of simplest case, we play an animation and sound.
But sometimes it gets more complex and we have to do things like, oh,
I have to turn to target, I got to pull out my gun, I got to do a bark,
maybe wait a second.
Or if we're doing like a boss fight in a brawler, we need to do something like
taunt the player, wait for a bit, that kind of thing.
That is purely kind of like a visual state.
It's not decision making, it's nothing.
It's just saying, okay, you know,
let the plane know what's happening and he can react to it.
And these reactions and behaviors unfortunately end up,
again, being shoved into the tree
and we end up with situations like this.
So this is a subset of the previous example
where you'll see now we have little trees
inside of the other trees saying,
oh, if I'm transitioning from this state, do this thing.
If I'm transitioning from this state, do this thing.
And even worse now, we have...
a lower priority behavior handling higher priority behavior.
So now we've got spaghetti everywhere.
We just don't know it.
Everything's linked to everything,
everything's handling everything,
every flag in the tree,
you change one setting here
and you don't know what triggers where.
Now I guess a lot of you in the audits
are basically saying like,
okay, well, behavior trees are awful, right?
You know, like, that,
you were supposed to tell me how to use them,
not how bad they are.
So behavior trees are actually kind of good,
but
They're good in a different sort of way.
Like if you look at the Wikipedia definition for behavior,
it says it's a mathematical model of plan execution.
I think that's super important,
something we've kind of forgotten.
It's a plan execution model.
And that sort of implies that there's a plan.
You know, not that the behavior tree is the plan,
that it's just executing somebody else's plan.
Behavior trees are really, really good
at describing a complex sequence of actions to perform.
So I'm gonna show you a simple behavior now,
and I'm gonna ask you again a question,
and hopefully you guys will shout out at me.
What does this behavior do?
As soon as somebody knows, just shout out.
Stuff.
And Dave is wrong.
Pardon?
Okay, and when do we look for a new position, for example?
Kind of if we don't have a good position.
You see that there's a little branch in there,
but yes, for the most part,
this is a very simple approach
for doing a fight from position.
Not a cover, just in the open.
I'm shooting as soon as I maybe don't have a good position
based on line of sight or whatever.
I find a new position.
And when I'm stuck in a good position,
I'm shooting the player and he aims at me,
I'm like, okay, well, let's move.
Let's give him a bit of a challenge,
a pattern gameplay or something.
So a lot of people kind of think of behavior trees as decision making.
If we look at like a standard Russell Norvig,
the behavior trees kind of fit into decision making.
That's where people have lumped them into.
Personally, I think of behavior trees as more of a control layer in between
actuation and decision making.
You know, we can still make some decisions in the trees,
but those decisions shouldn't change our overall AI goal
or AI state.
They're simply decisions to execute our decision.
If we've said, okay, you're fighting from cover,
the behavior tree can make some decisions saying,
hey, I should pop up now, or I should dodge to the left,
or I should do a reload.
But they should never say, you know what,
I actually think it's better for me
to go outside of cover right now,
even though this is the cover behavior.
For example, in the previous example,
we made the decision of, if I don't have a line of sight,
I find a position with line of sight.
So if we work under this conception of these simpler
execution trees, we need a high granularity of actions.
We need actions that are more like move, look at, reload,
fire.
I've seen implementation of behavior trees
with the actions that are a little bit more coarse.
They're like fight from position, fight from cover,
that degree of things, where you're
using a behavior tree like a decision tree for the most
part.
So simpler and smaller trees, obviously,
each one executing just a single goal.
And we also need to make some decisions in the tree,
as I mentioned.
So for example, we'll decide whether we have
a good position or not.
Now if we move to the simple execution-oriented approach,
we have several benefits.
Obviously they're easy to build because you're solving
a very small problem in isolation.
They're easy to understand and debug.
In like less than 15 seconds,
you guys could sort of understand what was going on.
And that's what you want to do if you have a new hire coming
into your code base.
You don't want him scratching his head for three days
trying to do something wrong.
It's also easy to identify the working data set.
If you want to parallelize your agent updates or something,
it's good to know exactly what data you're using so you can
kind of isolate that out so you don't have any kind of race
conditions or anything like that or overriding of data.
They're also easy to test independently.
Again, if you know your data, you can build a test harness
and just have that behavior being tested, saying,
does my fight from position behavior work?
Well, let's just test that.
Don't run the whole AI, don't run anything,
just run that behavior and test it out.
And they perform better.
Cutting out, I think.
Now, obviously you're going to say, well, how do you author these things?
What are the rules?
Well, my general rule of thumb is I basically say to myself, OK, I've made
this decision, I want to go to cover and I want to fight from cover.
What are the steps I need to do to execute that?
That's generally how I kind of think.
I like simplistic approaches.
Maybe I'm a bit slow in my old age.
But I kind of like things that are simpler to understand,
simpler to build, simpler to reason about.
Especially like three months later
when I come back to something,
I don't want to be like, what did I do here?
What idiot wrote this?
Oh, it was me.
You know, so again, I guess a lot of people are saying,
well, first you said they're bad, then they're not.
Now you're saying, don't use it for decision making,
but I can make some decisions.
It's like, what should I actually do?
Well, we're spoiled for choice.
We have a lot of techniques available to us.
We have state machines, we have planners,
we have utility systems.
These days there's a revival of neural networks,
machine learning, that kind of stuff.
We have a lot of these options out.
You don't have to pick one.
You can pick multiple, you know?
choose. What I've kind of found to be an elegant approach to solving this problem, for me at least, is
something I like to call a hierarchical finite state machine behavior tree hybrid, or
hoversome but-a-her, for short. Rolls off the tongue.
Hoversome but-a-her.
So, I guess a lot of you are asking me, like, state machines, you know, didn't we go through this already?
You know, there's problems, you know, that kind of thing. And there's a whole bunch of you probably going like,
I've seen this movie, I know how this ends. But, hear me out.
So state machines are excellent for describing states and transitions.
They're easy to visualize, they're easy to author, they're easy to understand.
They're horrible for defining sequence of actions.
Absolutely horrible.
Behavior trees are excellent for describing sequence of actions,
and they can do parallel execution of actions.
But they're awful for describing transitions and these cyclic behaviors.
Both of these techniques are relatively well proven,
they're well understood, they're super low risk.
You know, there's a very high reward.
But alone, both of them have their problems.
And what we're trying to do is kind of combine them together
to kind of build something that's greater
than the sum of the parts.
We want to kind of accentuate the pros of one
and the pros of the other and try to minimize the cons
by just avoiding them at all.
So I'll give you an example of this
based on the simple combat investigation AI system.
If we look at this diagram, it's kind of the same as before,
except it's a little bit more clear.
We can say, okay, our combat behaviors
can alternate between these three.
We know that from each one, we can go to the next
and alternate back depending on what's necessary.
We can say, okay, we can go from idle to combat,
but if we want to go back to idle,
we have to go through an investigation
because maybe our game loop is set up to say,
fight, when I lose a target, I investigate,
if I can't find him, oh well, go back to idle.
If I was alerted in my idle, like I heard a noise,
then it's okay to go back to a relaxed idle.
It's sort of very clear that you can look at this
and say, yeah, I get what this is doing, you know?
Cool.
Also, if you click one of these transitions,
you can then set up a set of conditions there saying,
hey, if these conditions are met, I do this transition,
but I just play a simple reaction behavior.
Or, hey, if there's a different set of conditions,
then I need to do something more complex.
It gives you the flexibility there
to kind of do specific transitions.
And again, it's very simple to understand.
And now again, if we go back to my code quality metric,
if I want to delete investigate, what do I do?
I select investigate and I hit delete.
All the transitions go with it.
All the logic for the special cases go with it.
Everything's clear.
It's like it never existed.
And I think that to be a very kind of elegant solution
for that.
Now,
I don't want you to miss the point here.
Don't get me wrong.
This approach obviously isn't perfect.
Pros and cons everywhere.
There are some tricks with this approach
that you need to know, like regarding how you do hierarchies
and entry states and that kind of thing.
If you want more details about this, ping me.
I'm available this week, whatever.
But my point isn't about the state machines.
I could have just as easily used a planner
or some other technique.
For example, these sort of execution behavior trees
are great for use with like a HTM planner
where the tasks themselves are the trees.
My point, and that I'm trying to get to this talk,
is that behavior trees are not an ideal technique
for decision making.
We are abusing them, and through that abuse,
we're scaring new people from these things.
I've had situations where I've come to a company
and looked at a behavior tree with 40,000 nodes
and been like,
oh.
And then it's like a week later, I know maybe one tiny portion of it.
We are making things unnecessarily complicated for ourselves,
and we're sort of drowning in some complexity.
When you get to a point where you want to do a simple combat behavior,
and it takes you three weeks of breaking stuff
and kind of trying to figure out a way to crowbar it in,
we have problems.
So, what I'm trying to get at is fundamentally is...
understand what you're building with, whether it's behavior trees or any other approach.
Behavior trees especially is that these sort of cyclic problems are not very well discussed
or known.
That's something to keep in mind.
So in conclusion, I'm just going to give you some do's and don'ts, just basically wrapping
up what I just talked about.
It's simply behavior trees are excellent at describing individual behaviors, hence the
name, I guess, behavior trees.
So use them for that.
Keep them as small and as simple as possible and combine them with other techniques to
get the most out of them.
Also, things that are bad is, as I said,
interruption transitions, the cyclic problem,
and please stop building large monolithic trees
that have multiple responsibilities.
You know, don't have this massive tree
with the static prioritization of combat over,
investigation over this, over that.
Imagine trying to build a boss battle in a behavior tree.
It's gonna be a nightmare.
So, you wouldn't do that, you'd probably use the state machine for that.
And that's what I'm trying to get at, is kind of understand the tools that you're using.
And more than anything else, is stop using behavior trees for your decision-making logic.
Use them where they work.
So Ben is now going to kick in with something a little bit more interesting and complex.
Hello everyone.
My name is Ben Weber and I'm on the science team at Twitch.
Today I'm gonna be talking about a lot of my experience
with behavior trees during my graduate study
at UC Santa Cruz.
So, here's the topics I'll be covering
for my section of this talk.
A lot of my experience was with the reactive
planning language and there's a lot of different features
of that language that are useful when you're
authoring behavior trees.
So I wanna give some ideas and inspiration
for some patterns you can use from that.
Also, as you start to author more complex trees,
you start to see patterns being used over and over again.
I actually didn't follow Bobby's advice
and made one big monolithic tree.
Had I seen this talk before,
I might have done things differently.
But I'll give some ideas for how I handle that complexity.
And then third, I'll talk about some extensions
to behavior trees.
So Bobby talked about finite state machines
being used in collaboration with behavior trees.
I'll talk about some learning mechanisms
I used with behavior trees.
So a lot of my experience with behavior trees is actually
with the Able Reactive Planning Language.
And this was a language that was used to author
the autonomous characters in Facade.
So a reactive planning language is like an HTM
where you basically execute as you're planning.
And it has a number of primitives
that are similar to behavior trees.
So you can kind of talk about it in a similar way.
There's selectors, there's parallel and sequential nodes.
They just have different terms.
So I'll try to map those to the common terms
here in this talk.
One of the node types that's really useful when authoring agents that need to handle a lot of goals
and do kind of concurrent action pursuit is spawn goal.
And this is a node type where you basically create a new goal to pursue,
but it's a separate thread of execution from the current node.
Scoped at the node that it's created from, it's basically a selector node,
but it's pursued concurrently from the current execution flow.
And if that node goes away, the parent node...
is removed, then that goal goes away as well.
So it's a way of doing concurrent goal pursuit
that's scoped within a particular task.
So I'll provide an example of how that's used
within a bot that I produced.
Another example is working memory modifiers.
So Mika already talked about these decorator patterns
where you can read and write from the blackboard.
I'll talk about how that's used
in the system that I produced.
And then a third node type is success test.
And this is a type of node where you basically
can combine it with a wait step
to suspend the execution of your tree.
So if there's a set of conditions
that you want to become true before you proceed,
you can use this node type to do so.
So you basically continue to perform an action
until a set of conditions is met.
So I use this tool that actually runs asynchronous
from the decision cycle thread, and it creates issues
whenever you need to actually execute actions in the game.
This probably isn't a problem if you're using
a behavior tree library, but I did have some issues
with things like task scheduling and resource contention
where you need to make sure that if you have
concurrent goal pursuit that you're setting state
or locking behaviors so that you don't have multiple goals
that are trying to use the same unit
or cause multiple threads of execution to happen
for one character at the same time.
Also, I had a performance issue with dynamic behavior
expansion, where you can actually pass parameters to
your selector nodes.
So a lot of what you can do to expand the tree is done at
runtime, which isn't really too big of a performance issue.
But in the initial days of Behavior Trees, I think that
was more of a concern.
So a lot of my experience with Behavior Trees was authoring a
bot for StarCraft.
So this was called IceBot, and this was done back in 2010.
And
It was based on this reactive planning language.
And what I wanted to do was have something that could play
at the level of like Flash here, where you could do
hundreds of actions per minute.
You could do really cool text switches.
You can learn from demonstrations and have this evolving metagame.
So I tried to author this huge monolithic behavior tree
that could handle all those situations.
So some of the design patterns I came up with as I expanded this tree
were things like daemon behaviors where this is a fixation of the agent that's done
concurrently with other tasks being performed.
And it's a way of handling kind of low priority actions that need to continuously be pursued.
There's this concept of managers where the AI is built into different subsystems.
So when you have something complex, you have a lot of different actions to take,
different competencies to manage, it's good to split up the behavior.
To coordinate between these different managers,
I use some message passing patterns,
and that's similar to some of the decorator patterns,
but I'll show examples of this.
And then behavior locking is another version
of message passing where one manager will prevent
another one from doing an action.
And finally, unit subtasks, which is basically
using the unit for a short amount of time
and then giving it back to the manager that owns it.
So I'll talk through different examples of this
and actually provide some ABLE code
and talk about how that works.
So daemon behaviors are basically a way of
handling a set of actions that need to be
pursued concurrently.
So I use this in my system to basically make sure that
units that need ammunition produced are basically
always topping those up if they have them.
And this is implemented with the spawn goal behavior.
which then calls a selector node that pursues a goal kind of persistently.
So it basically spawns a selector node,
it has a node decorator that says,
while true, continue pursuing the sub-goal.
So in the case of this ammunition example,
it basically spawns a goal to always be topping up the ammunition for the agent.
So how this is realized in iSpot is through this
daemon behavior for restocking units.
So here's some Able code.
Able is translated to Java code and then compiled into
byte code for runtime.
So it's not a data structure or a tree.
It's actually a language that gets compiled, which has some
side effects, but it was what I used at the time.
So first there's two behaviors in this example.
There's initial tree, which is the root behavior,
which is parallel.
And then there's a second behavior called restock units,
which is another parallel behavior.
Each of these has two steps.
The root behavior basically says,
create a Spawn Gulf to restock units,
and then go set up the managers,
which I'll talk about in a second.
And then the second behavior is basically continuing to pursue these different behaviors.
So with persistent means continue to pursue this, and subgoal is equivalent to selector.
So you're basically continuing to look at training new interceptors or new scarabs for your carriers
or reavers in your Starcraft bot. So these are units that are empty in terms of ammunition when
you start them, so you need to actually produce units for them to be useful.
So to decompose StarCraft gameplay into something more manageable,
I used this concept of managers, which is basically different subsystems.
And this is something that was pretty common with StarCraft bots that were authored for the AI competition,
where people would make like a tactics manager that handles combat,
a strategy manager for handling the build order.
things like resource manager, tactics,
reconnaissance, and so on.
So here's some examples of some of the managers
that I used in my system.
You have things like the income manager,
which is responsible for managing the worker units
for gathering resources.
You have a construction manager,
which is responsible for actually producing units
when there's a request.
The tactics manager handles actually forming squads
and then detailed behavior like micromanagement,
dancing units around, things like that.
And then there's a scouting manager
which is responsible for reconnaissance.
So it actually takes a worker unit and goes around the map
and later on in the game it handles other units.
There's also this high-level strategy manager,
which actually doesn't perform any actions itself.
It coordinates with the other managers
to actually execute those actions.
So it selects the build order,
but it doesn't go about actually telling
the units what to produce.
That's done through some message passing examples.
So here's an example of one of the managers in iSpot.
This is a subset of the behaviors that get called
for the income manager.
So at the top, you have behaviors like pump probes,
where this is, again, using that persistent keyword,
where it's continuing to run this selector node
for pumping probes, which means keep producing worker units
while a set of preconditions is met.
So you would have different instances
of pump probe behaviors
with different sets of preconditions.
But basically, this is saying try to produce probes
if those behaviors are ready to be activated.
There's also things like putting workers on gas,
taking workers off gas, which helps manage the income ratio
between minerals and gas for the unit.
There's other behaviors where it actually has to coordinate
with some of the other managers.
So for processing an expansion request,
the manager doesn't actually decide when to expand.
That's done from the strategy manager.
But the income manager is responsible
for transferring workers to that new unit,
to dispatching the construction requests
and things like that.
And what's great about this is you can actually
kind of decouple these managers a bit.
make sure that the strategy matter uh... handles things like it's now time to
attack
time to expand
and in commanders responsible for more the tactical actions within that
So to achieve coordination between these different managers,
we need to have some message passing or coordination between them.
Here's how this is done in Able.
You basically have these sequential behaviors that I show,
basically what a message producer is and a message consumer.
The message producer has one step, which is a mental act.
And in Able, this is inline Java code,
where you basically say, grab your working memory or your blackboard.
and create a new object called a message working memory element
and put that on the blackboard system.
So it's basically just saying, grab a reference to this,
add an element to the blackboard.
And then the second behavior here is actually consuming that,
dispatching a subgoal to complete that task,
and then removing it from memory.
So there's two steps here.
First, there's a precondition not really considered a step,
which looks for something on working memory.
So if there is a message working memory element
on the blackboard, it binds that to the message parameter.
It then calls a subgoal with that message.
So enable, you can actually call selectors with parameters.
And then once that's completed, at the end,
we'll clean that up and remove it from the blackboard.
So it's a way of actually having different managers
communicate with each other.
And you can create all sorts of different objects
with different parameters.
So I talked about an example where you actually need agents to coordinate.
So you might have the strategy manager say,
it's now time to produce a gateway.
It creates a working memory element that says, produce a gateway.
And the construction manager will go process that request.
But you also have situations where you want...
another manager to not perform an action.
So I call this kind of behavior locking,
where in StarCraft you might want to remove worker units
from gas and focus on minerals.
So here's an example of where we're actually using
the success test node type.
And the way this reads is basically,
first you're gonna bind an assimilator parameter
if there is a simulator working memory element in memory.
And the not condition here says,
do not succeed if there's one of these on the blackboard.
So it's a negation term that you can use.
So basically the way this is gonna work is,
if there's a simulator ready, it's gonna proceed.
But if there's not one yet,
or if there's this element working memory
that says don't proceed,
it's gonna suspend the execution of that behavior.
So it's a way of actually blocking
other managers from executing.
So it's essentially a fancy decorator,
but this suspending of execution's a great way
to...
execute authors, or I mean, to author behaviors,
because you can do a sequence of steps,
which is useful when you have things
that have a lot of preconditions.
So this is used in an example when you're doing things
like expanding and you want to focus all your workers
on minerals versus gas, and you can basically have
the strategy manager decide to perform that
high-level strategy, and then have the income manager
handle the actual tactics of that.
And then one more pattern I use is this idea of unit subtasks.
So this is where you're actually using a unit for a
few seconds or a duration, and then returning it to its
original task.
So an example of where this is useful in StarCraft is if
you have a unit that's being kind of harassed
by an enemy worker unit, you want to basically
counter-attack and then return to mining.
So this is where you want to spawn a goal
to handle the harassment and then return it
to the mining task.
So this is used in a few different ways in iSpot.
One is for micromanagement tasks.
So you group units into squads,
but then you want to be able to do tactical behavior
where you have units dance around and then return to action.
I already mentioned this worker defense case.
And then also another example is construction.
So you actually claim a unit, you go produce a building,
and then you return it to the income manager.
So this is an authoring pattern I
use whenever you have overlapping between managers
that have to share units.
So here's an example of what this looks like with able code.
This is for a Dragoon dance behavior, where basically
if a Dragoon is taking damage, you want to back off and then
re-engage the enemy, because it makes your units more
effective in combat.
So here's another example of where the success
test is being used.
This will bind the unit parameter to a Dragoon if
there is one.
on the blackboard where it says that damage is true,
so it's recently taken damage,
and it's not currently in a flea condition.
So basically this behavior is kind of executing
until this set of conditions is met.
When that
set of conditions is met, then a mental act is used
to basically say, set the status of this unit to flee,
and then spawn rule is used to actually handle
this subset of behavior.
So, this is actually introducing more state into the tree,
but we're actually spawning a separate thread of execution
to handle this micromanagement task.
So there'd be a number of different behaviors to handle,
like the actual placement of the unit,
how to engage and reengage with the unit,
and then once that behavior is completed,
it would change that flag again back to,
basically it's not fleeing, it's now in attack mode,
and that would clean up this behavior.
So it's a way of saying, like, handle this set of behavior
and then return the unit whenever it's available
to be claimed.
So here's an overview of the agent in action.
It is one big monolithic tree.
Basically at the start you have these different managers.
This is basically expanding as new behaviors
are being executed in the game.
So at the start you have things like the construction manager
and income manager that are just pumping probes,
warping in pylons, creating some gateways.
And then once the agent progresses further into the game,
the tactics manager will start forming squads.
You'll have the reconnaissance manager
grab units and go scout the opponent.
And later in the game, once you have a big enough force,
like the strategy manager will create
timing attack working memory element,
which basically tells the agent to
create a squad to go engage the enemy units.
So, this will proceed a bit.
Some units will be produced.
And then it will start to engage the enemy.
And then as behaviors are executing,
you basically see it turn blue,
which means that the tree's been expanded.
Now the unit's kind of scouting in the middle there.
And here we go.
So now the agent's actually engaging the enemy,
and you'll see that once these units
start to take a lot of damage,
they'll basically back off and then re-engage the enemy.
So that's an example of using that unit subtask behavior.
So the agent uses just these different managers
to do different subsets of the behavior
and execution of the agent.
It's doing all the decision-making within the strategy manager,
which is itself implemented as a behavior tree.
But it's a nice way of decoupling those dependencies between the managers.
So what I've shown so far is basically a scripted agent
where the build order and decision making was done
through the strategy manager.
And what I wanted to look at was how can we actually learn
from demonstration from professional players?
So that was part of the big inspiration for this agent.
And the way I achieved this was through
a few different patterns.
So here's kind of an overview of the agent architecture
where you have a set of learning components
which feed off the data from replays.
They then interface with either the agent's blackboard,
which is called the working memory.
or with the behavior library and active behavior tree.
So the most direct way of basically interfacing
with external systems is basically reading
and writing to the blackboard.
So if you just open that up to other components
to read and write to, you can do things like
the particle system I used where it basically tracks
where it thinks enemy units are,
and then the agent can use those estimated locations
to determine where to attack.
Basically, writing to the blackboard
was the most direct way of extending the system.
Another way of extending behavior trees is actually having an external component
generate the behaviors to execute. So instead of authoring everything, you can
basically have a set of replays that populate some of the behaviors to perform. So
here's an example of what this might look like. You basically have a replay file
and then on the right you have a behavior
that would get generated.
So this was actually done by a project at Georgia Tech
called Darmok, where they actually called it
case-based planning, and you basically feed it replays,
it creates a behavior library,
and then executes those at runtime.
I did something similar, but I actually did it
by basically placing new elements in working memory
one at a time, kind of as a build order sequence.
But I think it's great to show this example here
because it shows.
some of the types of work that can be done.
And it's interesting to see that you can create behaviors
at runtime from examples.
And then a third way to basically extend behavior trees
is by having other components.
augment the state of the tree,
so adding new nodes or removing nodes.
So this is a basically way of having external components
say, here's a goal I want to pursue.
So I use this in two ways in my system.
The first way was for, basically,
I had a system that detected whenever
the opponent was doing something
outside of your expectations.
When this happened, a discrepancy was fired
and then a new spawn goal was used to basically say,
pursue this new tech switch.
I also used it for this mixed initial model I built where you basically say like...
It was a GUI where you basically say select which build order to do and that created a spawn goal for the system to pursue a new
behavior to execute. So
basically, it's a way of having external components tell the agent what to do and it's useful for
removing some of the decision-making logic from the agent.
So instead of having the behavior tree decide when to attack,
having the tree decide what the build order can be, you can have external components do that.
And if you've set your agent up with this manager subsystem
and message passing between them,
you can basically swap out one of those managers
with an external component.
So it's a great way of adding
some extensibility to the tree.
And there's also some features of ABLE
that I didn't really interact with that are useful to note.
So joint goals and behaviors are basically
an approach you can use to have multiple ABLE agents
actually agree to perform an action and coordinate on that.
So.
As Roxanne just mentioned in her talk,
dialogue was something that was challenging
to actually execute,
because you have a lot of autonomous agents
and they actually need to agree on a task to perform.
With Able, this was actually a primitive
built into the language,
so it made it easy to author interactions
like where Grace and Trip argue about their trip to Italy
or things like that.
Another feature is meta behaviors where you can actually introspect and change the layout
of the tree or change, say, the priority of steps in the tree at runtime.
And it's a really powerful authoring tool, but it's also kind of dangerous because it's
opening up the tree to a lot of potential issues with orphan goals and things like that.
So you need to be careful when you kind of change things at runtime, but it's a powerful
tool.
And then more of a kind of academic project that was done
was this idea of partial programming where you
under-specify your preconditions for a behavior
and then the proper preconditions to use
are learned at run time.
So you basically specify a reward function
and then a policy is developed as an agent runs
in order to figure out when to perform
those different actions.
So this would be complicated to do with something,
the scale of StarCraft, but if you have
a much more refined environment,
it's a really cool approach to use.
I hope you've learned a lot about behavior trees today.
We talked about node decorators,
we've talked about some best practices
and some extension to behavior trees.
They're a powerful tool for authoring
and can be applied to a variety of different situations.
Thanks.
Thank you.