Hi everyone, welcome to the GDC Twitch channel.
My name is Brian Francis.
I am the invisible voice inside your head.
I am here as always.
We are here on the GDC Twitch channel playing interesting games, talking to interesting
people who make them.
Today we are checking out After Party, which comes from Night School Studio based in Los
Angeles.
And one of the people from Night School is here in the lower left hand corner of the
screen.
Adam, how are you doing?
Could you introduce yourself?
Because you can do it better than I can.
Well, thank you. Hi, I'm Adam Hines. I co-founded Night School Studio about five or six years ago with my cousin, Sean.
And I'm kind of the de facto game director, and I wrote...
Kind of 80 to 90% of the script of this game.
And then I had a ton of help with the design and the art and the whole rest of the team
built out it all.
I can describe After Party, I would describe it as a kind of comedy game, comedy adventure
where you're fighting your way out of hell.
Instead of fighting your way out of hell, you're drinking your way out of hell.
And there's Twitter in hell, which we're just seeing right now behind us.
Adam, how would you describe After Party?
Afterparty. I would describe Afterparty as a game about two college kids, Milo and Lola,
who, uh, they've just graduated college, they've been best friends their entire lives,
and they think that they're about to kind of leave school and start their adventure off into adulthood
and kind of figure out who they want to be, but it turns out that they have died.
They have died tragically and have gone to hell, and they do not remember how and they do not remember why.
But throughout the first hour where they get processed,
and it's kind of like a hell version of DMV where you have to stand in line and
kind of get accused of the things that you've done and assigned what your torture will be,
right before they're about to get assigned, the kind of work bell chimes to six,
and the demon's like,
Okay, I'm going home, report back here in the afternoon.
And they're like, Okay, but what are we supposed to do until then?
And he's like, you know, just hang out and get your
You know, get your stuff straight because you're going to be in hell now for the rest of eternity.
And they decide to go to a bar, and at the bar they figure out that there's a loophole.
And if you are able to find Satan and out-drink him and out-party him, he will actually let you back.
And let you back to Earth.
So Milo and Lola specifically are two people who are not big partiers.
Milo is a guy who...
His kind of his whole schooling years and college life, he's kind of wanted to be more of a social guy and wanted to kind of make more friends.
And so it's been a little hard for him.
And Lola is the type of person who just does not care.
She just wants to make an impact in the world and make a positive change.
So she's been very kind of focused on her career and what she wants to do.
So they're both kind of untrained and really being party animals.
So, of course, this is like the worst situation for them to fall in because now they're stuck in hell.
So the game is trying to basically be on the supernatural adventure bar crawl where you're trying to find Satan and out party him.
Right on. Alex, I forgot to let you introduce yourself.
Hi, who are you?
I was following podcast rules.
I was seeing how long we could go with me just not talking.
Alex, how are you doing?
Hey, what's up? I'm all right.
I work on GDC with Brian here.
I'm having a fantastic time.
Adam, thank you for joining us.
This game is super cool.
I kind of want to start by just digging right into the writing.
I've played a little bit, and I'm just really charmed by these characters and the situations
they fall into.
Like, how do you write funny characters that are a decade or more younger than you?
It's a good question.
Like, people typically in writing...
themselves up is that they tried to think of it in that way of thinking of it like,
okay, now I'm a 22 year old person with this specific upbringing and this is where I live.
We lost you, we lost you to internet lag.
Oh, okay. Sorry.
I liked it.
Yes. No, I was just saying that I feel like.
People kind of trip themselves up in writing characters where they try to really put themselves in a very hyper-specific mindset,
where if they're writing like a 16-year-old or a 22-year-old or an 80-year-old,
they're trying to get in a good location with talk and act.
And I kind of, and we as a studio, definitely just approach it that way.
as
characters are not really caring if they don't exactly sound like your typical 21 year old or 25 year old or 16 year old.
It's one of those things where this is going to be a very random reference.
But I remember when Dawson's Creek came out and the reviews for that show were like,
no teenager talks like this.
Like, they talk too smart.
And I remember thinking, why is that a bad thing?
That's not so gay.
If the characters sound different than how you would naturalistically expect them to
be able to express themselves.
As long as the stories are impactful and interesting and the characters are unique and engaging,
then you're doing your job and that's all you really need to worry about.
So yeah, I just took a lot from my own life too and from just people that I knew and their
own concerns.
This is one of those things where particularly with these characters, you just hear over and over again,
just, you're afraid that you're kind of missing out and it's that FOMO thing of just,
I don't think I'm ever at the right place that I want to be, I'm not having as much fun as I can.
With Instagram and the internet, this is kind of ramping up that feeling of you're only seeing everyone else's best
times and you think if you're not having those times too, then you're doing something wrong.
And that's definitely kind of Milo's point of view. And then just how
how awful everything seems right now with just everything that's pouring out every day from the news. I feel like
particularly the younger generation,
I'm sure just feels a helplessness and just how to make a positive change and just where to even start.
So that's kind of where Lola is, where she's at too.
Nice. Yeah, I mean, fortunately, like, the internet does not want these secrets to get out,
so you got kind of choppy in the middle of that there.
Oh, I'm sorry.
No, it was great. It's not your fault at all. Again, it's higher powers.
But like, if anyone missed it, like, what I got from that is that you really didn't
stress too much about trying to write young people.
You thought, you tried to write characters who had meaningful concerns
and meaningful personalities and just went from there.
And it seems to really pay off. I'm curious.
Because I find, you know, the art of writing, of good writing in a game seems so mysterious.
Like, how did you check yourself on this?
Did you playtest it with people of a certain age group or certain places?
Did you show it to friends?
Did you, like, have consultants?
Like, how did you verify that the work you were putting out was actually something that's
like funny and entertaining to people who don't know you?
Yeah, so we are...
Because it is.
Yeah, it's kind of a combo.
Well, thank you. Yeah, it's kind of a combo of things. One is that, yeah, I and Sean and
Sean and I and the leads of the studio kind of always have a very concrete and kind of
very specific feeling that we want to go after. And we're always just very honest with ourselves
if we're hitting the mark or not. So it's just a lot of rewriting and a lot of really
just going over and over and over and editing and being just.
trying to be very honest with ourselves if it's working or not.
Obviously, within kind of the time strains that we have to make a game and still
stay and still stay an actual
company. But so we just kind of really just have a lot of faith in our
abilities to make this stuff.
But then also the the team who's playing this this stuff and
reading the scripts and.
and doing the game and kind of really thinking a lot.
They're always very honest with us.
If they feel like a joke has gone too far,
or if a character's not getting enough room,
or just any kind of issues that they feel like cropping up,
where if I'm writing page 600 of an 1800-page script,
and I'm just very, very focused on,
okay, this quest needs something X, Y, and Z.
If I'm kind of missing that,
oh, I actually know Milo needs...
moment here or Lola needs more of a scene here.
The people who are just kind of making the game and implementing it will always
tap me on the shoulder and tap us on the shoulder and say, I'm really feeling
this and that, I'm really feeling like this
misses the mark or this joke is punching down or
so we're just kind of always really trying to check ourselves
and with these games in particular it's frustratingly hard
to kind of put it in front of
um, people who aren't actually making it yet to play it and play test it and really see how it's working just because these games are
Horrible until they're like almost done
So it's like until it's like the animations are doing the right thing and all the vo is in and the timing is there
Because they're so story
focused that if
But even if everything is in, but just the voiceover timing is off,
then it's like that kills every joke.
And the feeling is very different than the one that we want.
So it's tough to kind of put it in players' hands until
it's almost too late to change too many things,
which makes it pretty scary when we're working on it.
But that's just why we always have to really
kind of be really honest with ourselves
and keep us in check about what's really working and what's not,
and going back, and if it's not working, try and...
Over in chat, Statistat has a good question.
How far did you go through an iteration, I guess on each section, before you checked whether it was working?
Statistat guesses you didn't rewrite the entire story every time you were iterating on a section.
We did not.
So yeah, basically our process is that we'll come up with a story, just conceit.
And the obvious one for this one was,
if you're stuck in hell, you have to outdrink a bunch of...
Demons and characters that you'll be running into.
So it's a bar crawl focused game with kind of a supernatural bent.
And we'll try and think of different, just pure gameplay mechanics that can support that and be built around it.
And once we've kind of like kicked the tires on that a ton and felt like good about kind of moving on to what...
Story then can kind of support the gameplay mechanics. Then we try and make a really strong outline of just okay
These are the big beats. This is like chapter 0 chapter 1 chapter 2 chapter 3
And really go over that and debate it and argue and see how much that we need and how much that we we want
And then we just start to just jump in and we just write each
scene and we'll have read-throughs of each scene where the entire team kind of comes in and
and plays a part.
And then one person will actually play the scene,
meaning they'll make the choices and will jump in the script to where that goes.
And at the end we just kind of talk about it,
and we talk about what has worked and what didn't,
what jokes we thought were good, where you were confused.
That's kind of a way to know your goals and what you're doing,
and you can be kind of surprised.
The audience was like, oh, I didn't know that guy was like the thief the whole time, but in a game you kind of have to know there's always going to be elements of narrative surprise.
So it's kind of a careful act of smoothing things from the scripting phase.
And then once we feel like everything is pretty locked in to a degree that we're confident that even if there are rewrites, which there always are, we can start building the big...
pieces, then yeah, then we just start to implement things and play it as we as we can. But there's
typically two or three more passes of rewrites once we start to play it and we see like this
is taking too long or I don't know why I'm doing this, this is confusing and we'll change and tweak.
Nice. Yeah, I um...
We should talk a bit about the way you overlaid a system of drinking on top of all that.
I think Brian's seen more of it than I have, so I can't speak to it with any kind of expertise.
Hopefully we'll see it in a second, but it's the system where drinking changes the dialogue
choices, which creates a third...
It sort of creates...
If there's a dialogue choice, there's usually two options.
There's a third option, but I guess we can...
So far from what I've seen, there's five different options for a conversation.
Depending on what drink you get but you can only access one of the one of the thirty
You only have three available to you
But the it seems like you guys planned a total of five for these conversations like drinking game logic is fun
How'd you come up with that and and what's the logic behind it from a structuring and scripting standpoint?
yeah, we we definitely wanted to make drinking be fun in this game and be a hundred percent fun and not be a
any sort of a
A hindrance or penalize you because in every other game it had felt like you know you take a drink and like in Red Dead you'll be drinking the screen will get wobbly and like you can't walk and we were like well we obviously can't do that with this game because the entire game is about about going to bars and having a drink and have that affect you.
So we came up with this concept where basically in hell these drinks kind of act more like a magical potion where.
The ingredients that go into these drinks are impossible to make here.
They're like, it's a child's tears with a dollop of insanity, and that makes this drink.
and when you drink the end every drink in the game, like you said, every bar has four drinks
and that basically comes out to about three specific types of personality traits that you can get per bar.
So for instance, you'll go into a bar and you'll see the menu and based on the reviews, you'll get an idea of what that drink will do.
So it might make you more angry or it might make you more want to flirt with people in the bar
or it might make you talk like a pirate or.
Talk like a mobster or throw up your conscience, and then your conscience is a little character, and then all your choices are bad.
So the variety of what the drinks can do to you is pretty... are.
So we wanted to expand on Oxenfree, our first game.
That game, for those of you who haven't seen it, you always have permanently three...
choices whenever your opportunity to speak comes up and those
come directly from what Alex, the character you play as, what her personality, would just naturally let her or
allow her to say. Just, just the
the things that that person would possibly want to say are kind of your choices in that game. And in this game
we wanted to make it more like, no, you can kind of...
set what you want your personality type to be based on when you walk in the bar and you
kind of survey who's there and what the bar is kind of like.
Because it was important for us to kind of get at the feeling of an actual bar crawl,
meaning when you go out and you're like, no, actually I know I can't drink too much vodka
because when I drink vodka I get pissed off, or when I drink Jack I'll just end up passed
out.
But maybe you want to feel those ways so you kind of drink in that specific way.
So we really wanted you to kind of have that in this game.
And it kind of dovetails into the puzzles and kind of how you want to approach certain obstacles and goals.
There's a part early in the game where some friends of yours go upstairs to a private VIP part of the bar and the bouncer won't let you up.
So you can drink a bunch of drinks and play beer pong against another person and to impress them you can insult them based on the personality type that you have in the drink.
or you can drink a particular kind of concoction that will make you more angry
and then kind of rile up two people that are already in an argument into a fight
and then that'll distract the guy and then that can get you upstairs then.
So we just wanted you to kind of be able to overcome certain chat challenges and play
these bars and kind of the personality type that you wanted to.
And then also just to kind of feed multiple pull-throughs just because
every time you say anything there's some...
joke. And if you didn't like the last joke, if you wait 10 seconds, it's going to be a new joke.
So it's just that type of game.
Right on. Yeah. I imagine that must have complicated the production process.
Like, how did that change the way you guys approach designing, laying out and sort of writing
through all these different options?
It didn't change it too much.
It changed it in the way that you just had to know ahead of time that, OK, all of these
Dance for those types of events.
So for instance, there, there's a bar where you go into and there's a kind of a light puzzle in the conversation of both trying to convince someone to at least make an effort with someone that thee just broke up with.
And there's no cases where that concludes the art course.
So it's really about trying to convince someone to at least make an effort with someone that they just broke up with.
And then there's other stuff that also happens in that bar.
But we knew that at least one drink then had to be kind of focused on romance,
just because that was going to be a thing that was going to happen in that spot.
So it was just really a matter of kind of charting that out ahead of time
and making sure that all made sense.
Whereas in Oxenfree or in other narrative games, it's very just context based.
Just the things that you say above your head or in the menu are just exactly what needed to be in that at that time.
But in this game, of course, if you're drinking a drink and the drink makes you really angry,
there has to be an angry choice for every single possible time you can speak in that bar.
And that made it hard sometimes because it's like if.
you want to challenge somebody to a fight, we have to kind of let you do that and have
it somehow get back to the main plot and not spiral out of control through this whole other
game.
So that was the hardest part, was just making it feel still like you're able to customize
the experience as much as you would want to, but not make a game that has 800 hours worth
of content.
Yeah, it's crazy.
I think this game is pretty funny and comedic timing.
You would think, you know, making a game is hella hard, but you have full control over
like everything.
You can set the timing, you can set the speed of the dialogue, you can pick the actors.
You would think it'd be pretty easy, but actually it's incredibly hard.
You would think, yes.
You would think it would be very easy.
Honestly, yeah, the tough part, yeah, particularly with comedy is just the timing.
If the timing's off even a bit, then yeah, the joke is killed.
With a game that we really, in all of our games, we really want you to always have just control of the character as much as possible.
So there's very little times where we'll force you to like stand here or force you to lock in or the camera will move in and we'll force the characters to walk around.
We definitely had to do that more in this game than Oxenfree just because there's way more going on on the screen.
and it kind of gave Oxenfree a cool feeling, uh, because, um, you're just with one other
character kind of in these very, uh, spooky, empty, um, outside env- environments for the
Most part and it felt good to let you just kind of be running around and climbing trees and jumping on logs and stuff as
You're having a conversation and not really care that it doesn't really look like you're looking at the person you're talking to just because you're walking
And you're going on hikes and things but in this game
You're like sitting at bars, and you're leaning on stools, and you're looking at a billion characters on screen
And we really kind of had to treat that a bit just to make sure that the timing there and the voice acting kind of all
worked
But yeah, but it was still hard at times because we'll watch people play it.
And I'm like, oh, here comes this brilliant joke.
And then they'll like walk off screen, like right when it hits.
And like, oh, OK.
But you just have to like let that go just because, of course,
the freedom of being able to control it is worth so much more than like,
now you got my dumb poop joke that I put in there.
So nice.
Yeah, I don't know if Brian, if you want to walk back to the bar for a second,
but like how many how many drinks did you have to come up with for this game?
I don't think I can order another drink, but there were four right there.
They were very good ones.
I guess the question is how did you get to Captacom?
Yeah, I think after you stopped talking you might be able to.
But yeah, naming the drinks were a ton of fun.
Nice.
Just because I was sure I couldn't give them these horrible things.
I want to jump back to chat real quick, and a quick reminder, we didn't stay at the top
I don't think, but if you have any questions specifically about game design or game development
in general, please throw them in chat and we will do our best to relay them.
StatueSats are already on it, and they want to know again, this game reminds them of Valhalla
a little bit, so they want to know were there any particular games that inspired you or
the team?
It was definitely, I mean, for me, at least the two games I kept referring to in my head,
it was the Space Quest series from Sierra from the 90s.
And the old Sam and Max hit the road.
So these are two adventure games and they place a lot of emphasis on comedy and Sam
and Max in particular.
just the timing and the cartoon nature of it and those conversations between Sam and Max.
It's just, it's like movie level quality, just everything about that game.
And that was definitely like our bar that we wanted to hit.
And the Space Quest series and the Monkey Island games, too,
they do a lot of fun things where they always kind of break the fourth wall and kind of poke at the player.
And we wanted to do that a lot with the Sister Mary Wormhorn character,
which I think you'll eventually see in this playthrough.
But this is the... she's the personal demon that you get assigned early on.
And she's there to kind of be...
Poki in the games world, she's there to kind of be
Tormenting you in the hours. We are not being physically tortured
So that means that she brings up like your past and mistakes that you've made and will point out
Choices that that the player has done it kind of made and kind of makes fun of you just for even playing a game
So we really wanted her to kind of be that fourth wall breaking type.
So kind of like her and Satan are the only two characters in the game where they like know they're in a game
and kind of talk around it and kind of allude to that.
So those are two big kind of inspirations.
And we've talked about, you know, coming off of Oxenfree and like jumping into this.
But like, I feel like I don't want to gloss over the fact, you know, you guys did
at least one other big game project, which is the Mr.
Robot mobile game, which is like a significant thing.
So I'm curious, like, were there any things you learned in that process
or that production that influenced the way you approach designing this game?
Mr. Robot, it was a unique game in that it's that one.
We really wanted you to feel like you're just texting and to make it feel like
You are texting another human and that everything on your phone kind of should reflect that and it should be this very kind of seamless thing that you almost forget like you're playing a game. And with that one we
Yeah, we really kind of leaned into the actual physical act of that.
So it's like, you'll see the text come in and you'll see like you, like you, the person that is choosing it, like you'll see him, like, make a mistake, you know, erase and then rewrite it again and, and really kind of play with just kind of how people talk on text versus how they talk in real life.
So if, if, if anything, it kind of.
Just like was a good exercise and just thinking totally outside of the box before jumping into another very real time thing
um, but yeah, and and two that was done for a um for an
External partner because of course we had partnered up with the mr. Robot team to kind of make that that game
Sure. Um, so just like hearing kind of what they
Were interested in
It was funny, like when we first started working on it, you know, like with Oxenfree, we, you know, we're kind of pitching our idea for this game.
I was like, okay, so it's all going to be on your phone, you know, text and, and, and like in Oxenfree, you'll be able to control the story and you'll have a million different endings.
And I'm like, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, we don't, we, no, Mr. Robot is a set thing.
You will not have multiple endings.
That's not a very specific end and a very specific thing.
Like, oh, okay.
And in making that game, we're like, oh man, are people going to think it's boring if it's too straightforward?
And nobody really cared, they just thought it was a cool, fun thing still,
and you're able to make enough choices within it to still feel like you're picking apart the game.
So we took that lesson too in here and not focus so much on being able to,
every single thing you say, be able to branch and dovetail back and da-da-da-da, and just kind of...
focus on making just a really good story that you can...
Like, there are a lot of different kind of endings and halfway through
the game and after a party, it kind of leaves it up to what goal you
want to be. Not to spoil things, but kind of
changes from the beginning of what you just have to
get out of
hell. It kind of becomes more of a complicated, like,
and what do we really
Right.
Hmm.
So I wonder...
I was gonna say, hell seems to be getting in the way of our chat.
Making a really good plot.
Sorry.
It's okay.
Adam, real quick, are you on Wi-Fi?
I am on Wi-Fi.
Does your computer have an ethernet port?
It does not.
F*** that.
We are summoning demons.
Oh, really?
Yeah.
That's a good point.
Because actually, unfortunately, if I unplug it or move it, it'll just shut off because
my battery is completely dead.
Yeah, let's not do that.
We'll muscle through it.
Okay.
Sorry.
I think we got the most of that.
Adam, I think we can...
I know you're game...
I'm going to ask for your brain as a game director for a moment.
How do you and your team prioritize creating...
You know, I think like a lot of narrative games sort of struggle from in order to be truly compelling,
they need to be end-to-end with content and end-to-end with interesting places to look in the
game. How do you and your team like sort of process like we're looking at standing in a
room now that like has a lot of unique stuff like the guitar, the art on the wall, the demons like
kind of mingling in the foreground and background, like the people I guess some of the people get
reused. But what's your studio's process for working as a small...
Small team and still making something that feels like it's loaded with personality and you're sort of able to trade on more than just words alone.
Yeah, we had to come up with a very smart system early on for just how to make a lot of characters.
So we kind of came up with this demon and human making toolkit where we were able to kind of make a lot of different heads and arms and legs and body types.
Kind of.
All right.
Almost.
And then for the bars themselves, yeah.
We just really tried to plan out things very well
ahead of time in terms of what each bar would need
and what each bar the feel would be in the art style.
And just make sure that we kind of stick to that.
And once we're sticking to that and not make a lot
of changes after the fact.
But yeah, because we're so small, I mean, we have a team of about four artists,
and yeah, they just had to make every single thing that you see in this game.
So we weren't able to, yeah, say like, oh, if it's not working in eight months,
we'll kind of like pivot and change things.
Like once we're kind of building things, we have to be confident that that's what we want.
So it was really just a matter of kind of making a really solid outline for the story
and an outline for the game mechanics and the overall design
are really sticking.
Nice. What do you think makes a good story?
Because every story that he did came from something else.
Which is what makes those stories great, or just how the characters put how they're feeling.
And I feel like that ultimately is what makes a good story.
It's just the... it's hyper-specific to what the writer or the team or the artist...
kind of wants to talk about or wants to say.
And having the characters kind of express that in a very way...
in a way that is unique to them.
And I'll kind of, I'll happily watch any story about anything as long as I feel like I'm
seeing new perspectives about the same old stuff.
Right.
That's so interesting.
I mean, that would seem to flow directly out of your work on Mr. Robot where that fear
about not having like a panoply of endings sort of like winnowed down and you focus more
on characters and character interaction and that kind of thing.
There's another question here in chat from Statuesat.
They want to know, like, so just what do you think about companies, game companies
specifically, pushing back on people
spoiling games, you know, like it's been a while,
but I think they're referring to stuff like when Persona 5 came out
and people were like, don't stream it, don't talk about it.
Ironically, they were limiting streams a lot, like which ironically said
is we're streaming after party and spoiling the second hour. Yeah.
You make narrative games, how do you feel about that?
Oh no, he froze.
Oh no.
The internet just shot him down.
He's like, nope.
Can't let these opinions get out.
Man, did the PR team jump in here and sabotage the stream or what, guys?
It's Halloween comes early today.
Spooky internet.
I am cursed.
Adam, if you can still hear me, shoot me a message in Skype and we can try and reconnect
to you.
Man, it's also kind of funny because his face just sort of froze.
This is really awkward.
In the meantime, what's up, chat?
How's it going out there?
How you doing? There's 15 of you.
Come on, Statue State can't be the only one with a keyboard.
Do you guys play this game? You like it?
Yeah.
Seems good.
Yeah, it's a lot of fun.
Like I've been having to conceal my laughter over here
because I've been laughing out loud at some of the jokes.
I'm serious, man.
Humor's really hard to do in games.
That's why this game, Outer Worlds 2,
like the writing and the timing, it's just...
Hmm.
It's hard work.
I don't know. We're this we're this you just keep playing. Yeah, I see where this goes. Yeah
Maybe his laptop died. He could probably move it
This is so wild never seen I'm just having a bad tick week probably got so excited about
Spoilers that he knocked his laptop over and it shut off
Let's give it a couple minutes. See if he comes back and then we can call it
I'm just going to post a message.
You're going to see something weird on screen for a second, guys.
Do you think they ever get out of hell?
Oh! Oh, we're back!
Oh!
What's up?
Did something happen at your end, Adam, or did you just hear us, like,
talking for a couple seconds about how we couldn't hear you?
We, yes.
It was just the lead ad me shouting, like,
can you hear me?
Oh, no.
I'm sorry.
It's fine.
No, I'm sure it's just because...
Because I'm in a very weird corner, so the internet is awful here.
But, um, so yeah, so the question was about the spoilers, right?
Companies restricting spoilers.
Yeah, so, um, so yeah, I definitely feel like, um, or I did feel at the beginning that spoilers
would naturally hinder, um, at least someone's desire to play a narrative-focused game if
they're already seeing how the story is going along.
But my time at Telltale, when I worked there in 2012-2013, all of their market research
had actually showed the exact opposite.
That the more you show people what the story is, the more they'll want to apply, because
they'll want to make their own choices.
I've actually heard that a lot from trailers too.
Us, the audience, complains a lot about trailers that give away too much.
But apparently, studies have shown that if a trailer actually gives away a lot, it makes
people want to see the movie more.
Which I don't really understand, but it's hard to argue with, I guess.
I personally am someone who's not really bothered by spoilers, in that I feel like if I'm hearing
the big building blocks of a story. It's still not spoiling what I like about movies and books anyway,
which is again just the details and how the characters are talking and just the way that they get to those points.
But yeah, I feel like
streaming and showing the game is really only a good thing and only a positive thing and
and the people who want to avoid spoilers can kind of do that at their leisure.
And that it's only kind of a bad thing if an article like springs a spoiler on you that you didn't want.
But just the act of showing the game early and showing the entire game,
honestly I think is only a way to kind of spread the word that the game is out there
and this is a thing that you should try.
Nice.
This is like a really outdated question, but I haven't talked to anyone about it in years.
And I just wonder what it's like.
Do you remember like two years ago when Steam started doing refunds
and there was like a brief moment where everyone who made a game less than 50 hours
was like, oh, no. Yes.
Do you do is that ever still a concern for you and the team,
or did that never prove to be a real problem?
I think it was a concern mostly for
yeah, games that were trying to get one over on you,
where it's like.
If you play it for a half an hour or 45 minutes and then you've seen every single possible
thing that that game has to offer, I might be concerned there.
But with a narrative game where you know what you're getting into and the people kind of
know what they're buying, yeah, honestly, it was never really a discussion with us or
a concern just because it just seemed something that...
It seemed mostly fair to us, just in a way of like,
oh, if I was purely a consumer, that would be a thing that I'd be happy that I could do now.
And also just nothing that we could really control.
Like, it felt weird for us to almost have such a strong opinion about it.
Like, no, once you buy the game, there's no refunds.
No takebacks, yeah.
So, yeah, we honestly never really were really concerned.
I think one challenge for selling narrative games in 2019 is people are interested in
them.
People talk, they get a lot of press, journalists are interested in them.
There is obviously demand, you see it on Steam, sometimes these things sell like hotcakes,
like you had Plague Tale Innocence earlier this year.
But I think the challenge for any narrative studio is that scaling and keeping costs and cost management works totally different than for other companies where,
if say your multiplayer game is getting bigger and bigger, you want to scale up to have people to fill roles to keep the multiplayer going, but narrative is definitely on a project basis, I guess.
There's less of a liveness to it, there's less of a...
What are your thoughts for running Night School, especially in a city like LA, and keeping it so that you guys can keep making games, you know, and keep making the next one even if after...
You know, Oxenfree seemed to sell well, you made your way to the App Store, I'm always seeing it featured in the App Store, which is probably a good sign, but I guess what are your thoughts about...
Making sure that when after party ship you guys wouldn't just be a two...
Well, I've been asking the question for a couple weeks because I was at a conference,
and before I was saying one game studio, but I guess now how do you guys make sure you're not a two game studio
and able to still work at the size you're at?
Yes.
Yeah, with a question this big of course there's a couple different factors that kind of go into it.
For us I think primarily it's about making sure that we keep the studio as small and as lean as we can.
and we hire the people that are absolutely filling kind of multiple holes.
Like everyone in the company wears a couple hats
and we all kind of take a lot of ownership and responsibility over the parts that we put in.
So that just helps us, yeah, just with the overhead and just the amount of just heads in the office, of course.
But then too, it's kind of, it's also a combination of...
doing projects that we either have deals ahead of time with,
where we know if everything explodes, like the Mr. Robot game,
if nobody buys this at all, we still got paid,
we still got the money that we needed to keep the studio afloat
for those months and weeks and days.
And then also doing the projects like Oxenfree and Afterparty,
where we're funding it entirely ourselves,
based on profits of other things.
And just making sure that we always have a balance of...
future checks coming in and making sure that
we just have kind of always multiple kind of irons in the fire,
because with anything, and particularly in L.A.,
it's like you can go on 100...
Whoops, Adam. We lost you after the word 100.
That's why we started drinking. Everything slowed down.
Um, sorry, we lost you after 100.
Uh...
Meaningless...
Yee...
Aw...
You guys are so stupid.
So haunted. We're so haunted.
If you heard...
Did you catch any of that?
We lost you, as I said two times and I'm sure you heard, sorry, we lost you after 100.
Oh man, sorry.
Did you get the response from that or no?
No, I'm sorry.
No worries, it's just the internet.
Normally this is fine.
So yeah, maybe the LA fires are creating a thing right now.
Yeah, no joke. Maybe like just this answer is cursed.
You want to just move on or you want to try after hundreds again?
Yeah, right? Yeah.
Well, the very short version of it is to just try and make sure that it falls apart.
We always have something else to kind of like keep the studio on.
That makes total sense. Yeah, for sure.
Maybe we can talk a little bit more about business if you're up for it.
I'm curious to know how the launch has gone and sort of like what you're thinking was
between putting it like I know it's on the Epic Game Store now and Steam.
Like how do you feel in general about where game store fronts are at these days
and what shaped your decision to put the game out where you did?
Oh no. Oh no.
Well.
It's worth a shot.
Well, we're about to put on a dance show.
I'm sorry buddy, you cut up again.
It's a we lost you.
It's just a frozen face.
Oh boy, and I gotta hit some face pads.
It was the day before Halloween.
And all through the Internet.
I call up.
Are we good?
We got a little bit of it. Yeah, we can hear you.
No, man, I'm playing DDR over here.
Yeah, that's looks fun.
So I yeah, I did not hear that question whatsoever.
Sorry. It was just like, you know, I'm curious to know how you feel about
the state of game storefronts these days and what shaped your decision
to put the game out where you did.
I noticed it's on EGS and Steam and console.
So how you feel in these days about.
the visibility of indies and how is the game done?
Yeah, so the game is doing well.
I honestly have been kind of avoiding hearing too many details about what these sales are like.
I'm going to wait until this weekend, but I've just kind of tapped Sean, the other co-founder and studio head.
Just like, is it going okay?
He's like, yeah, it's going great.
So it seems to be doing well.
And I've been more focused to on the reviews as if they've been coming in.
But but yeah, but then in general, just about the storefronts,
I definitely like can understand the complaints about having
that, like too many things that you just don't want to install on your PC
and have to deal with and like ways to get games and.
And I feel like a lot of that is folding into the conversations now about, like, is it a good thing that there's like a Disney streaming thing and a Netflix and an HBO and an NBC and is, are we kind of getting to the point now where it's like people will start going back to cable just because it's an easier I just want it all just give it to me I'll just pay the one fee.
But at the same time, it feels like a minor hurdle to be able to really customize how you want to get your games and which games you specifically want and not have to kind of pay for something that you're not necessarily going to use or see.
So, yeah, my feeling is that the industry as a whole is generally moving into a better space than it was, and that you're just having more options now of just how you want to...
get things and there's definitely more options for the independent studios to just stay afloat,
where it feels like there are these massive, massive games like Fortnite that come out and
generate just untold sums of revenue. And then those companies are kind of able to use that
as a comfort and able to kind of take more risks and take more gambles on indie studios that they
want to support and put up more kind of
These are more just cooler, kind of experimental things.
And I've heard that's kind of the same way in the book publishing world, where it's like
something like Harry Potter and these giant massive books that we hear about
kind of make like 99% of book sales.
And that's what funds everything else, like the things that win all the prizes.
So that kind of feels like what games are right now.
And at least for right now, I can't really think of a better way to do it.
I mean, this is kind of what the public kind of jumps into and what these
these organizations and the companies and what the indies are able to kind of do
and how they're able to serve five.
But yeah, I personally feel like it's kind of arcing towards a good thing.
Yeah, it's interesting. You mentioned the.
You alluded to cable there.
It's like people just want this big package.
And I hadn't really thought about it before, but there's a lot of that in games
now between Apple Arcade, Google Play subscription, the humble thing
where you just get games every month and this whole like curated collection.
There really is more and more space for people who don't want to deal
with having to sift through the marketplaces and just get a curated collection.
Is that something that you'd be ever interested in doing with your games?
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, we yeah, we're kind of always interested in
Even apart from the business aspect of just where the games are showing up, but just being in
a bunch of different ways that you'll experience it and just a bunch of different like place
dials like Oxenfree and Afterparty of course are meant to just kind of you sit down and you play
the game and you're there for an hour or two but it's interesting being yeah seeing kind of the
playstyle is much more, you kind of jump into this ecosystem of many games and you're maybe
expected to try one out for five minutes or play one for ten minutes and then hop out and come
back in and to really kind of think about what an interesting storytelling mode would be for that.
It's just an interesting like creative challenge.
So yeah, we're just kind of always interested in just how to tell and how to kind of make these games just fit those
the
Delivery system and kind of the best way
Yeah, right on. I am we got about 10 minutes left in this haunted stream
So if you have any questions anybody get them in now
I'm gonna get a question and then I'm gonna need to for timing sake because I'm unfortunately on a tight tight schedule today
Brian, you have a question? Go ahead.
In the back there.
Man, um, uh,
Adam, my fascination
with your games is that you guys may do interrupting
really well. Like characters interrupt and talk
over each other in a way that when most of their
games do it, someone literally has to, they'll be
talking and then, and then the
next line of dialogue pops up.
Um, uh,
so, you guys do it a lot better.
How do you do that?
Um, so the
The sad answer is that there's just a lot of writing.
There really isn't like a trick to it.
Like, because how you make the interrupts work
is that you just put a ton of bookmarks in the conversation
so that what that means is that
when we know at any point you can cut off a line or cut off a thought
that there just has to be three or four or five different lines then
that can feed right back into what they were saying.
So it's like if Milo is like, man, when I was six years old, and then you click on a
demon that you want to talk to and you have a minor conversation with him, that the game
kind of keeps track based on that bookmark.
And we'll know Milo wants to get back to talking about when he was six years old.
So let's go back down to the next kind of version of him talking about that.
That's in the that's that's in the in the sequence.
So so then he'll say.
Anyways, I was talking about when I was six years old and if you interrupt him again, there's even more versions of him kind of getting back to that.
So it's just a matter of just writing a lot of different versions of the same conversations and allowing the game to kind of dip in and out of any of them in any order.
And just kind of keeping a kind of mathematical track of exactly what point in the overall story you're at.
Um, just cause for me it's a big thing that I never really want to hear repeating dialogue in the game
just cause it kind of breaks your immersion.
You get that a bit in After Party just cause you're able to kind of challenge demons to
beer pong and lose and you have to be able to reach challenge them in situations like that
where we just can't write infinite versions of okay again beer pong.
So you'll just have to hear repeating stuff there but.
As much as possible, I like it to just feel like it's just a natural flowing talk.
But yeah, so you just have to write a lot, unfortunately.
We're sort of out of questions so I'm going to start wrapping things up.
Thank you everyone for joining us today on the GDC Twitch channel.
Oh, uh, oh, nope, Mince Words jumped in with a last second other questioner.
Gotta answer it.
Hi, Mince Words.
They're curious if Adam has a philosophy about what kinds of stories Night School wants to
tell.
Axentree and Afterparty have similar protagonists with supernatural contexts and they wonder
if you see these as signature elements or if you have ideas about what else you might
explore in the future.
Yeah, we always like genre blending stuff, so I don't think you'll ever see us make 100% comedy, 100% horror, 100% action.
Oxenfree was very kind of like a teen coming-of-age story that could very much be Stand By Me, except we added in weird, spooky, creepy horror things.
And it's a ghost story at the same time.
Afterparty could have just been, yeah, a bar crawl and you're just out with a bunch of random...
people and you're getting out of college and you're thinking about what next to do, but we wanted
again, something kind of crazy to add it. So we just put you in hell. So we're always going to
kind of have kind of a mix of things and we just like the kind of counter balances that those make
and I personally like always like a and enjoy a mixture of tones and movies and books and things
where you're laughing and you're scared and you're crying and you don't know if you should be laughing
but it's kind of...
Funny and um, where it's just always kind of keeping you on your toes. Um, but yeah, we
It's kind of like things that um, yeah, just have a lot of
kind of 80s spielbergian amblin entertainment like heart feeling at
The at the core, um, but that's that's that's probably always what we'll like aim at
Did I miss the taxi pickup or am I still walking towards it? That's my question
Oh, I think you're still, this is, this, this island you're on is huge.
I think this is it.
Okay, cool.
Uh, Mintz, uh, Mintzwords, thanks for your question.
Um, uh, that was a really fun level of after party.
Adam, thank you so much for joining us.
Sorry about the demons haunting our internet.
No, I'm sorry.
I am sorry.
Yeah.
I kept blinking in and out. I hope you understood ten words of that.
We got some good answers. We harvested content. We pardeemed our way out of hell.
Well, I'm still in hell.
And with that, I'm going to leave everyone to have a wonderful day.
If you are out there in the audience and you are yourself a game developer,
we would just like to remind you that...
Registration for GDC 2020 has opened.
If you go to our website, you can get your pass.
We have a lot of different options for developers of all different backgrounds.
So, whether you're a AAA developer looking to pick up as much as you can
across the game development spectrum, we have something for you.
If you're an indie developer, we have lots of great choices for you as well.
If you want to join us in the X-Bowl 4, if you want to see the talks on Monday, Tuesday,
if you want to see the end of the week, there's all kinds of options,
and we'd love to have you at the show.
If you are not a game developer,
If you can't make it to the show, or otherwise just like making games, or like the topic of game development,
we would love it if you clicked the follow button on this stream, so you can get a notification when we go live.
We're doing a rare two streams in one week this week, because tomorrow we're talking to the folks over at Obsidian about The Outer Worlds.
and we're actually going to have...
Oh, God, I hope we get their names right.
Tim Cain and Leonard Boyarsky.
We've confirmed them.
If you're here today, come back tomorrow because that's going to be really awesome and I'm
so excited for that.
With that, have a good day.