Welcome everyone to a talk on Civilization 6. I'm Ed Beach from Firaxis Games. I've been the
lead designer on Civilization 6 that was released last October. My talk here is going to run
about 45 minutes, giving us some time for questions at the end. I want to thank the GDC
folks for the way they scheduled things this morning. They put Sid Meier's Civ 1 post-mortem
talk right before mine, so it got all the Civ fans here before.
How many people actually came to that talk as well?
OK, so actually a good percentage of the audience.
Just wanted to invite you to take one more talk with me
right now.
So in that Civ tradition, we'll take another turn here
and move forward.
Now, jumping forward into the future 25 years and talking
about Civilization VI.
So, one of the things I'm going to focus on during my talk is
about how many people have opinions about Civilization games
and about Civilization VI.
So, I'm sure there are quite a few opinions out there
in the audience.
And so, I've been told that we can even spill over a little bit
on time at the end if we want to fielding questions.
So, if anyone does have questions, I'm happy to take
them at the end and we can dive into things
in as much detail as you want.
So anyways, let's go ahead and get started.
The first thing I want to do is just give everyone a quick refresher
on the Civilization series.
In the beginning,
the Earth was without form
and void.
The sun shone upon the sleeping Earth.
Into this swirling maelstrom of fire, air and water, the first stirrings of life appeared.
The seeds of life grew and strengthened, spread and diversified.
Now it required but one more ingredient.
To unite the quarreling tribes.
To harness the power of the land.
To build a legacy that will stand the test of time.
A civilization. ♪
So, Civilization has now been six games,
25 years,
five lead designers,
dozens of intro movies, and quite a few animated leaders,
some of them a little slicker than others.
I've seen the last eight of those years
and served as the lead designer since the
Gods and Kings and Brave New World expansions to Civ V.
But that still means that when we started
the process for Civ VI design, the Civ series itself
had been around seven times longer
than I'd been a lead designer.
So taking the reins of this series
was definitely a daunting proposition.
To add to the pressure, Civ 6 launched, excuse me, Civ 5 launched in 2015. And one thing that you'll
note about Civ 5 is it spent all six years right there in the top ten most played games on Steam.
This screenshot is actually from the Steam stats page one week before Civ 6 released. And you
could see Civ 5 was doing.
doing quite well, still very healthy and in third place there. An additional factor going
into releasing Civ 6 last year was that 2016 was going to be the 25th anniversary of Civ 1. So
we're going to have 25 years.
of the same franchise and there was a lot of attention both in
the media and in our marketing devoted to that 25th year
anniversary. You can see here we have a picture of Bruce Shelley
and Sid who just did the previous talk. Meeting with some
of the other early CIV lead designers at the Dice Summit in
Las Vegas. It was about a year ago last February and that was
sort of a focal point for that conference was that
panel where they were doing a retrospective on Civ. We also
had a big marketing campaign that rolled out as the year was
going on. You can see here at E3 last year in LA, we had
Civilization VI themed stairways leading into the convention
center. We had a theater presentation narrated by Sean
Bean, who you just heard in the trailer I just played for you.
And there were a bunch of media events that were happening associated with Civ 6,
including our first event held on Facebook Live where we did a Q&A session
with our community manager and sort of answered a lot of the early questions
about what Civ 6 was going to be.
That session alone attracted a lot of attention.
We definitely.
realized it was picking up some hits on Facebook when we had a certain man with 86 million
followers on Facebook tune right into the stream and tell us Civ 6, I'm looking forward to it.
So it's an intense year. I definitely, I'm not going to lie, I'm not going to lie, I'm
You know, as being the lead designer for the first time,
I had a whole bunch of interesting experiences.
But I did look forward to getting at least a slight break
from the action in the middle of the summer,
because one of the things I like to do every year
is go to a World Board Gaming Championships
and both play and run some of the board gaming tournaments
there.
So, got this three, four day break, went to that tournament,
and one of the things that I noticed was the sort of the Civ
VI hoopla followed me right into this event. So, one of the
lighter, more casual events I attend each year at this
convention is, it's really a comedy show disguised as a
trivia game, hosted by John Corrado, who's kind of a friend
of mine, who I'm showing you on the screen here. John knew ahead
of time that I was going to be there.
And he kind of asked me early in the week, he's like, you going to be there?
You don't mind if I bring up Civ 6 a little bit?
And I was like, sure, go ahead, whatever you want to say, that's fine.
Well, I was in the audience.
In fact, I was right there in the audience.
And John made no, had no hesitation about pointing that out to people and sort of diving in.
Like, we've got a Civ 6 lead designer here right now.
And he actually used it as a platform to kind of get across his message that.
There's absolutely no pressure on you, Ed, but I love Civ 5 and
if you mess up Civ 6, you're in big, big trouble. Um, so...
Even on my breaks, I was having trouble getting away
from the Civ VI hoopla.
The only consolation I got out of that
was in this particular event, since he had themed it
around Civilization VI because he wanted to highlight
my presence there, I did get a few categories
that he chose for trivia that were sort of right up my alley.
So we had 100 most played games on Steam.
And then the one that I definitely aced, just sort of ran that category right away.
So, yeah, I know a little bit about the wonders of the ancient world by now.
So maybe there was a little bit of pressure here.
With that in mind, I kind of want to dive into...
you know, with a backdrop like this, with a successful series
that's been around for 25 years, how was our team going to go
ahead and attack this project? How would anyone designing the
next game in a hit series proceed? So, one other thing I
noticed was that, um, the, the, the, the, the, the, the, the,
this question of how do you proceed in a hit series
was something that a lot of people were wondering about.
In all those press interactions at E3
and in some of the other interviews
we were doing last year, it was a repeated question.
They kept saying, how are you going
to find anything to add six games into the series?
And so I started thinking about that
is something that's perplexing to a lot of people.
It's something that.
you know, is going to be applicable to lots of people in the game industry
because so much of our work and our titles are based around the fact that we
have an established franchise and we have to add on to it and augment it.
And so that's why I got the idea that, yeah, maybe this is a worthy topic to
address here at GDC.
So I actually found it sort of an interesting question
because we had adopted a process that we'd used
kind of first with the Gods and Kings expansion.
And it sort of made that question not as difficult
as it seemed like the press was feeling like it should be.
Because what we wanted to do when we were creating.
sort of any successor in the Civilization series,
whether it's an expansion pack like Gods and Kings,
or whether it's Civilization VI,
is we want to really take a hard look
at what we had done previously
and think about, as game players, as game designers,
what is working and what's not working.
And we did that as part of our development process for Gods and Kings.
We may not have had a whiteboard in the office that had exactly these lists of four items,
but we certainly came up with lists of items, these four items were all on them, and we
do a lot of internal discussion.
We have an external beta test team.
that is sort of like community leaders and giant fans of the series.
Some of them have been working with us for two or three titles in the series, maybe even longer.
And we're sort of always looking at our game and what's working and what's not.
So.
Just a couple examples from the Civ V expansion packs,
in Gods and Kings, we were seeing that
the combat wasn't balanced the way it should be.
There were cases where, because the rule of combat was
every time you made an attack,
you were always gonna do one hit point of damage,
no matter how weak you were.
We were having situations where 10 archers
in the ancient realm could still be around,
facing something like a giant death robot
in the modern times.
And as long as you had 10 of them, you could take that giant death robot down.
So, one of the things we introduced for Gods and Kings was a 100 hit point scale to better
balance combat.
We had a problem that we were thinking we wanted to attack
with the Civ V base game where players would get into a game world,
they'd get into a situation and they might have picked a civilization to play
that just wasn't a very good fit or there wasn't any way for them to kind of customize the bonuses that they got
so that they would really be adapted well for the terrain around their initial cities and for...
the type of victory they might want to pursue. And in Gods and
Kings we were able to address that by adding a religion system.
We also saw that there wasn't that much awareness of what the
AI was doing, that there was a lot going on in the depths of a
Civ 5 game that the AI was taking place in, but people
weren't seeing that, and so we added an espionage system to
address that.
And then finally, the problem that we had was that the naval units, they were all attacking as range units, they were very one-dimensional, they weren't much threat to anyone's city because they weren't allowed to take it, and so for that expansion we added melee naval units.
And this process of sort of self-examination and...
you know, becoming critics of our own games and using those as springboards to figure
out what capabilities we were going to put in the expansion was something that we just
kept going with.
So we went into Brave New World.
And Brave New World, again, we made a list of items that we thought were still not working
right in Civ V, even with the Gods and Kings expansion.
We felt like the culture victory was kind of bland.
It was just finish a certain number of social policy trees and then do one building project.
So we added a tourism and great works system to address that.
We didn't like that with the new base movement rate of two spaces
in Civ V that the exploration game ended so quickly.
So we wanted to add more exploration later in the game
and we added an archeology system to address that.
We felt like the diplomatic victory was pretty bland.
It was just a matter of kind of spending a lot of money
on city-states and that sort of was sort of a.
people called it an economic victory instead of a diplomatic victory because it's really
how much money you had. And when we added the word Congress for Brave New World, it
really made that part of the game more interesting. And then there are a couple more items. You
can see the economic interdependencies didn't become as rich and as important until we
added trade routes. And then that
sort of final push to victory, the climax at the end of the
game, the tension in the 20th century was addressed with our
ideology system. So you can see again here, it was a matter of
kind of really taking stock of where we were at, looking at
what was working, what wasn't working, that was the way we got
those expansions to kind of flesh out the Civ V experience
and give you exactly what you get now when you play Civ V
complete. So that's sort of...
where we started the Civ 6 work.
We looked at how we had proceeded with those expansions.
We looked at how they were a matter of itemizing issues
and then using that as a springboard to move forward.
And we felt like even though Civ 5 was very successful,
was still being played a lot on Steam.
you know, it was not a perfect game. There was plenty of opportunities to find places
where we could improve it. And so we started going about making our list of what we wanted
to address for Civ 6. Now one way that we really, you know, pushed this further is I have to
continue to give shout outs to our community.
We have a very engaged community, a very passionate community, but one thing that they always
are good about is they're never short about giving us opinions.
And so it's always easy for us to go up there and, you know, if we're wondering about which
SIVs are overpowered or underpowered with the current release, they've already produced
a list for us and itemized all that for us.
If they're telling us, if they want to tell us, you know, which system they like better
in SIV 4 and which one...
went way downhill in the Civ 5 and is only finally making a
company, you know, all that data is up there. So, um, I see posts
now and again where the community people are like, did
Fraxis ever read this forums? I don't think they're paying any
attention to us. That's totally ridiculous because, you know, I
have a whole office of designers that spend way too much of their
day reading the forums. Sometimes I have to pull and
don't read the forums right now. We need to, you know, buckle
down and...
get going. So, one thing that I did when I was looking at what
they thought about Civ V, and this is the strategy form for
Civ V just yesterday afternoon. I just pulled it down and pasted
it in here just so you can kind of see it's still hotly debating
things about how to get to the science victory as fast as
possible and posting guides for players who are trying to win on
immortal and deity. One thing we noticed is that
they had looked at the tech tree and they had all sorts of plans for exactly how you attack the
tech tree. What is the optimal strategy? I'm not going to swear that this is the right optimal
strategy, this is just the one I pulled off Civ Fanatics yesterday, but I found it
interesting because with the arrows there and everything it's sort of a perfect example for me
of how people found Civ V to sort of be a solved problem. They kind of, you know,
identified this one overarching problem that we kept coming up
against, and that was that there was just a single path to
victory that would always get you through the game
successfully. Didn't necessarily matter which map type, which
victory type you were going. If you follow, I think it's five
little mantras that I've got here that I got from the
community, you were able to be successful and win a Civ 5 game.
So let's look at those.
Build only four cities.
Rush to the National College.
Science is king.
Tradition for your social policies, not never liberty.
And get to rationalism as soon as you can.
So those, I mean, they're probably more that the community focused on, but these were the
kind of things I kept seeing over and over again. I kept going there and these were sort
of the magic recipe to get you to a successful conclusion in a Civilization 5 game. And this
was the number one thing I wanted to address for Civilization 6. I wanted to be sure that
players were going to have to think on their feet. They were not going to be able to use
a couple key points every time. There was going to be situations that the game was going to
throw at them that they were going to have to react to. They were going to have to think on
their feet. So you'll see as we go through the talk that that's sort of my number one
principle in terms of guiding us to what we're going to change for Civilization 6, how
we're going to change it, and then we'll wrap up at the end today and you'll kind of see how
there was one key component to solving this problem.
So I started thinking about solutions.
And I'll sort of give away what the key component is right now.
But how it works into all the different things
that we came up with is what we'll
end up diving into more deeply.
So in order to come up with a solution to this problem
about players being able to always use the same strategy
to win, we had to look at what changes every time you
play a civilization game.
because it's those things that are changing that are going to force players to think on
their feet. If they're presented with a situation that doesn't look like what they were faced
with in the previous game, they're going to have to adjust. So, I love the Civilization
series. It's the perfect game for me working on because I love history, but also because
I love maps.
And what changes every time you play is the map.
And that's sort of the most exciting time for, I think,
a lot of civilization players.
There are a lot of people who say, I play the beginning, see
what the map looks like, explore it.
I may not finish that game because it's just so exciting
to get back to that point where I get to start a new game
again, and explore the map again, and dive back in.
So I knew that the map.
was sort of the key to what makes the civilization magic
work.
Sid and Bruce Shelley talked about that a little bit
in their talk about how important
it was to stick with randomizing the map every single time.
And so that was going to be sort of the centerpiece
of the solution for Civilization VI.
So what I'm going to do right now
is we're going to start taking a deeper dive.
We're going to go into those areas on Civilization V
that I felt like we needed to make improvements.
So we're going to dive into five different areas. And what I'm going to do is I'm going to
identify sort of what I see as the problem in Civ 5 and then talk about how we solve that for
6. So the first area I want to look at is how tiles are used outside the city. And I looked
at how they were being used in Civ 5 and I felt like those decisions were kind of lacking. I
called them rote decisions because there wasn't a lot of thought being put into it.
So if you look at this particular screenshot, it's just a nothing special. I just grabbed
like the first Civ 5 screenshot I could find off the internet. But I started looking at the
improvements outside this city and you see farms are placed on the flat land, especially if
they're near the river. You've got mines anywhere there are hills or resources that require
mines. The resources that require a special...
improvement like a plantation or a camp, they get that improvement. And pretty much all
those choices are automatic. You don't have to think about what you're doing with those
tiles. It's just automatic. There is one thing that we added for Civ 5 that was sort of a nice
hint at where we might be going for Civ 6. That last arrow that is put down in the corner,
that's showing you an academy, which is a great person building. And those sort of went
into any tile.
you know, that you wanted.
And the kind of interesting thing about that
was it was sort of always was one of your leftover spaces,
whatever you considered like the least useful area you're
going to use for that.
But at least it was you had to scan all the tiles
around your city to try to figure out
which was the best place for it.
And that was sort of what we decided
we wanted people to be doing much more frequently in Civ 6.
It was like having to look around all their city tiles,
look at all the possible places, and then
choose where their next move is going to be made.
So that's exactly where we went with Civ 6.
And this is actually our unstacked city system.
That was a change that we were sort of dying to try, even
when we were in Civ 5 development.
We had really pressed, our development team really had
pressed John Schaefer, the Civ 5 lead, to try to
put the wonders out on the map. We knew the art would look a lot better. We knew it would
be interesting in terms of placement decisions. But I think John made the right call. There
was a lot going on already with Civ V. We had taken the combat system and moved it out
onto the map and unstacked all that with one unit per tile. And it would have been just
too much change at once. But these unstacked cities, you know, probably two years before
we started Civ VI, I knew that this was going to be...
one of our number one features for that game. So you can see in this particular example, if
you haven't played Civ 6, sort of how this works. We have a science campus up here, nestled
up against the mountains. We have a commercial hub along the river, a holy site. It's also
inspiring for religious worship to have a mountain backdrop, so that's a good place to put
it up against the mountains.
And then also the fourth item here, the Hagia Sophia, that's one of the wonders outside the city.
And so what I think is so interesting about the way this works is now, rather than there's one use for every tile, with those tile improvements that I was showing you for Civ V,
we actually have at least three different layers of items that go outside your city.
Both the tile improvements from Civ V, these new districts that I'm showing you, because we pulled the buildings out of the city and put them out into the districts.
And then wonders as well have to go outside the city.
So now you have those three competing layers
and they're all looking for a spot outside the city.
And now every time you're building in the city
you're having to make choices and trade-offs
about how you're gonna use each of your tiles.
you can actually say that for a lot of our civilizations, we make it even worse for you
because we add in unique improvements for that civilization. So like the Egyptians get the
Sphinx, the Sumerians get the Ziggurat, and now you sort of have a fourth layer, where are we
going to fit in unique improvements into this jumble? And then we said, well, there might be
some civilizations that don't get unique improvements, so...
What are we going to do for them?
They need to have that same just torturous situation
as a player trying to figure out how to use every tile.
So what we did is we went ahead and created some city states
that also, if you are allied with that city state,
you get to temporarily use their ability
to create unique improvements.
So we have the colossal head unique improvement
that's allowed outside the city.
So maybe if your civilization doesn't even
have unique improvements, you can go ahead
and have to worry about them.
So this is actually, it doesn't always happen in game development, but this is a system where we sort of had this pent-up desire to put it in.
We tried it in Civilization VI, in some of our earliest prototypes, years before we actually got to 2016 and shipped it, and it worked right away.
So, definitely a success, but I'll get to some areas where we struggled quite a bit more.
Okay, so problem number two that I identified from Civ V was the way the tech tree worked.
And if you came to Sid's talk earlier,
you saw that the tech tree's been
a huge part of civilization.
It's pretty much worked the same way from Civ I
all the way through to Civ V. And we kind of
looked at it as a place where not much innovation had
happened.
Maybe we should look at it.
And there was one thing about the technology tree that
had always bothered me in civilization games.
So let's focus on that for a second.
So let's look at sort of the same screenshot I had up before, but now we're going to drill
into the top of the tree and look at the sailing line. And you can see sailing and optics are
both technologies there. Now, sailing takes 13 turns. Calendar takes 17 turns. It really
doesn't matter what's going on in my game world. Those are always going to be proportionally
take the same amount of time, my people have just as good an opportunity to get into sailing
as Calendar, even if I'm in the middle of the biggest continent you've ever seen and
my people have never seen the ocean.
And that just didn't make any sense to me.
How are you guys learning about sailing when you have no water anywhere near your civilization?
It just felt like the tech tree was off in this own disjoint universe that had nothing
to do with what was going on in your actual game world.
Why shouldn't those two be married together?
Why shouldn't they have some interdependencies?
You know, the technology and the research of your people
just needs to be something that is inherently tied
to what they have done so far
and what they're about to do.
So we looked at that.
And one thing that we came up with was
it would be very interesting to go ahead.
and come up with a system where you could trigger things by
doing actions with other units or your cities out there in the
game world that was gonna be sort of gameplay directed
actions that help you with this path through the game, with your
progression through the technology tree. So...
That's how sailing came to have a boost.
Go ahead and found a city on the coast,
and all of a sudden, what we're gonna do
is fill up that half of that circle you see there.
So 50% of the credit towards the sailing technology research
is gonna be given to you for free
if you can get a city on the coast.
And we started out, it was tricky at first
because the first time I sat down
and was looking at the ancient and classical tech trees,
and I had to come up with boosts for all of them,
I was like.
I got the sailing one nailed, but there are another 20
technologies here, and what's going to make sense?
And that probably took me a full day and a half, two days
to come up with just the first cut of what that would be.
And we put that in the game, and we played it that way for
probably three or four months, just to make sure that the
system was working.
And everyone liked it right away, which was great.
It led to sort of more directed play early in the game.
It gave you sub-goals.
It sort of even gave us a way to tutorialize things.
Like if players aren't going to find a trade route because
they just never really found that particular unit, well,
maybe we put it on the boost.
you get a boost for making a trade route.
And now all of a sudden people are like, oh, OK, I've got to
figure out how to make a trade route.
That's going to be important to me.
So it had a whole bunch of positive outcomes that we were
seeing right away.
We were really excited about it.
But I knew that I'd only spend that day and a half, two days
to do the ancient classical boost.
And I knew I had a whole five, six more epics worth of boosts
I was going to have to come up with.
I kept putting that off.
Probably it was like.
Six or nine months later, I actually
got around to doing boosts for the whole tree.
And it was a little tough, but we ended up
finding a pattern that you look for things
that you had unlocked recently.
And if you haven't used those things,
even though you've unlocked them,
then perhaps you shouldn't be moving on
to the more advanced technologies.
So it took a little while for us to figure out
how to apply this kind of kernel of an idea that
worked really well in the ancient era
throughout all of history.
But overall, this was definitely a success and something that we
didn't struggle with too, too much. But now I'm going to get
into something where we did struggle. And the problem here,
I already alluded to it before when I put up those mantras of
the Civ 5 players, go to tradition, never go into liberty.
rush to rationalism as fast as you can. This social policy tree, we loved a lot of things
it did. It was very thematic in terms of giving you things that culture could unlock for your
civilization and give you boosts. It was really...
sort of an integral part of what had happened with Brave New
World, with our ideology system.
So we didn't want to throw this out.
We wanted to keep the idea of social policies being items
that could give you specialized boosts in a
certain direction.
But there were a couple problems that we felt like we had to address.
And I think the number one thing that we wanted to attack here in terms of social policies
was we had sort of lost something that had been in the series previously with Civilization IV.
In Civilization IV, you had been able to, what a lot of players called, pivot their government.
So something dramatic had happened. You went to war. You weren't expecting it.
or you're coming back from a war and you have to kind of rebuild your economy,
you could switch out civics, go back to things that you had
focused on before.
maybe jump ahead to things you haven't had before,
but there was this sort of ability to kind of retune
the way your society was working,
the way your government was set up,
and that sort of gave players a lot of sense of control
and sort of like they were making policy decisions
sort of like a government leader would
in charting the future for their empire.
So that was sort of a good thing that Civ IV had that we lost in
Civ V because once you made a choice on a social policy on one
of these trees, it was locked in. And what was worse is once you
jumped into one of these trees and started developing it, we
gave you a big incentive to finish it. So we sort of locked
in not only the choice of that one social policy that gets you
into the tree, but we sort of encouraged you to make a
commitment to keep going on that tree until you're finished.
and that ended up just not being as configurable and as flexible
as what we wanted. So for Civilization VI, what we
started out with actually looked a little bit like this. Now,
this is just in Visio. The next few slides were unearthed from
the archaeology system that is our design docs and going back
and pulling out screenshots from them.
But you can see here what the Civ VI civic system, and yes, that is a tongue twister.
We realized that right away.
We were going to have problems pronouncing that.
But the Civ VI civic system started with this design for social policies.
Now, some of it survived.
You can see right away it had military policies in sort of the orangish red
and economic policies in the gold.
the wild card and diplomatic policies we ended up with. Those were around from the beginning
and we stuck with it.
It had all these little sort of aqua blue unlocks associated
with every single social policy.
And it was similar to our boost system.
I think we were too enamored with our tech boost system
at this point.
And we were going to make everything in the game
unlock with that.
And so why not every single social policy
have a different unlock?
Because we could come up with something that
made sense for everything, right?
So, so many unlocks, just way too many unlocks. It was, I don't even think we got this
implemented before we started realizing there's just too much cognitive overload on the
player. There's no way they're going to be able to remember what they're pursuing.
We did pair this with a list of governments
that we wanted to have.
And this, we changed a few of the names around,
but this set of governments and the fact
that governments have different numbers of policy slots,
that stuck through.
But what we found with our players with this first system
was they didn't know.
what they were doing in terms of how they were supposed to be
progressing through that tree. There were things like we had
this imperium government, it sounded really cool, maybe they
should stick in that for a long time. Are they supposed to go
through all, you know, some players thought they should go
through all nine in order. And, you know, that's switching
governments way more than we thought people should be doing.
So it was just a little too chaotic and the progression
path through these governments was unclear.
So we didn't throw out all of this.
We kept some of the code, but we had to redesign,
refactor some things.
And so our second try at the Civic System,
we did add government tiers.
So that you could kind of at least get a sense
that these three governments were all more powerful
than where you started.
But they were more on a par with each other,
so that you could kind of pick one,
and you don't have to feel bad that you skipped the other two.
And that just sort of made sense to players,
that with a tier like this, we were anticipating
you were going to switch governments at least three
times during the game.
And with this tier structure, all of a sudden,
that just sort of fell into place.
So that was a nice change.
But we did have kind of this weird construct
that we borrowed from Brave New World for how you
get into the different tiers.
we sort of were forcing an upgrade when a certain dramatic
event happened in the game.
And we actually kept the exact trigger for the last three
governments that once you get a certain number of factories
in your empire, you're going to have a big working class.
And they were going to just dictate that you have to
govern them with one of the 20th century
ideological governments.
And we sort of felt like this interesting decision about
what government you're in.
that we were trying to make kind of cool and fun and a new thing that was going to be
introduced for Civ 6 was kind of fighting against these forced upgrades that we were putting
in play every time you hit one of these tiers. So we tried to relax that in our next
version, Civics System version 3.
And this one was notable because now we finally put in bonuses for the governments. We
thought that if you get to pick, maybe you've unlocked the tier 2 governments but you
really like that tier 1 government, it's really working for you right now. We wanted to
let you stay in that but the incentive to staying in it would be if there would be bonuses
associated with those governments that you wanted to hang on to a little bit longer.
we were getting somewhere, but we still had one big problem with the civic system. Um, and
that was the fact that the way, I sort of hadn't really described how you...
um, move into a government, how you slot in a policy. But we had this really
cumbersome system that all of this was done by spending culture. And you would
sort of accumulate a treasury of culture, just like you do of gold. And every time
you want to make some type of governmental change, you would just grab some
culture from that culture treasury and apply it to the problem. And all of a
sudden, boom, you'd be able to switch governments or slot in a policy. One that
sort of felt weird.
because accumulations of culture sitting around for thousands of years waiting to be spent,
that doesn't make much sense in the real world. And then the other thing that was happening
was we were having problems where you'd spend all your culture, get your government set up
right, and then something would happen in the game world. We were tying everything to the
game world and something would happen and it would be the situation where, oh, wow, I just
unlocked this new government. Oh, I don't have any culture left to switch into it.
And so even though it would seem like the right time to make one of these cultural shifts, you
couldn't do it with this spending down from your culture of treasury that we had going. So we
finally kind of took the big step in the right direction with Civic System version 4. And this
was something where...
We finally went ahead and created the parallel civics tree that anyone who's played Civ 6 has
seen. This is an idea that had been kicking around. We had talked about doing this probably
for a full year before we actually switched over to it. And we were wrapped around the idea
that, oh, civics has to be done different than technology. It has to be something that feels
more cultural. It can't feel like technology.
But if you look at the technology tree, that sort of is a gaming construct put on top of
science and that gaming construct works actually very, very well for us here because now...
You don't have to have individual unlocks for each policy. You can have the policies unlocked in a
bundle when you finish one of these civic nodes that are the equivalent of technology nodes. We
can associate boosts with the whole civic. And so those little unlocks that we had that were
from doing things out in the game world, now those could, we wouldn't have to have as many of
them, maybe, you know.
a third to a quarter as many of them, but we could still have
that type of system. So in general, as soon as we finally
made the switch over to the civics system, things started to
fall into place. Now this particular civics tree, which is
the very first civics tree we tried, did have some problems.
If you look at it, the pink nodes, again this is apologies
for my Vizio art skills, because they're just Vizio art.
But the pink ones are required, the white ones are optional.
And you can see, you can just blow through the ancient age
pretty quickly.
There are only three nodes in the whole ancient area civics
tree that you have to go for.
We also had governments all out on their individual nodes.
So you can sort of pick and choose from those.
And so you ended up skipping a lot of the classical tree too.
And in general, there wasn't much decision making to your
path on this tree.
There was pretty much one path.
to follow, you know, with maybe a few choices.
But we need to make this tree richer and deeper and more varied.
So that's sort of how we ended up with our final civics tree.
is we went ahead and created something that looks like the
tech tree. And it was really fun. This was one of the fun
exercises of Civ 6, was trying to reimagine all the improvements
that societies and governments and cultures have made through
the year and what those look like in terms of how they
interrelate to each other, which ones lead into other ones. And
so we ended up with a tree like this. This is showing it later
in the game.
and the government screen here where we finally came up with that time where you finish research
on a new civic.
And actually, we never called it researching a civic.
We felt like that was the wrong term.
You only research technologies.
So internal to the team, we came up with this term that you research technologies, but you
cultivate civics.
And so you'll actually, if you dive deeply enough into the XML
and the files, you'll see all these references to
cultivating.
That was our favorite term.
We ended up almost shipping the game and telling people that
they were cultivating, even though that's not a real word.
And it only makes sense in this very, very specific context.
But if you guys want to start using cultivating, I totally
approve of it.
It's one of my favorite words of the last three or four
years, so go for it.
Okay, so two more problems to go through and then we can get on to questions.
And this is, these last two are areas where probably Civ 5 took a lot of heat.
And some of it was deserved.
And some of it we agreed with, so that's why it made it onto our list of top five problems with
Su-5. And that's the one unit per tile system. I absolutely loved it. It brought tactical
nuance to the game, but it also brought some problems. So let's look at the biggest one of
those, which was unit congestion. And so if you look at this particular screenshot,
Right here I'm pointing to a mobile surface-to-air missile unit and really its main purpose in the game
It can defend so you can sort of use it as a defensive troop if you need to
But it's pretty much its main purpose in the game is to shoot down aircraft
but in this particular configuration, it's sitting there occupying one of the key tiles that
the Aztec army needs to approach Katmandu and to capture that city. So it's in the way, it's
blocking things, and that's just part of, you know, kind of the repeat problem that we kept
seeing in Civ 5 games was that people were having their units fall on top of each other,
you know, stumbling upon themselves, and they couldn't get a clear path to what they were
trying to get to with their military.
You also notice on this map that it's a cool looking map. It's got a lot of interest.
Kathmandu is in this really strategic position right where all these peninsulas come together.
But those strategic positions right where the peninsulas come together are also the worst
places for unit congestion. So in this kind of situation where you're trying to attack it, it
actually becomes pretty frustrating.
So we wanted to look at that and, um, that was, um, something
that wasn't too tricky to solve as long as we just, you know,
sort of attacked that problem directly from a design point of
view. So we added three different things, um, skip
ahead to the next slide, and, uh, go back to, yeah. Um, so,
we had three things. We had support units, so now all those mobile surface-to-air missiles,
anything that is not a front-line fighting unit but you want to have in your army was going to
be something that could be stacked with other units and that was going to help with the
unit congestion and it was also going to be able to move as a grouped unit with your other
military units.
And then the other thing that we did was we allowed you to group
units of the same type together into corps and armies. That was
immediately going to reduce in that one localized area the
amount of map congestion we had by a factor of two or three.
But we were very deliberate about that decision. We didn't want to go back to the mixed stacks
that Civ 4 had because then you started losing the clarity as to, you know, is he sending his
mounted troops around my flank? Does he have his melee units up in the front that are
guarding range units behind them? So we wanted to be very careful to maintain that sort of
tactical rock, paper, scissors nuance to what was happening on the battlefield. But we
wanted to...
collapse units together and let them occupy the same tiles. So, uh, you can see, um, that not
only do we have, um, the helicopter army here, but we also have, um, the, uh, the, uh, the
naval units that are grouped into corps and armies. We just happen to call them fleets and armadas.
So in general this definitely helped with the
over-stacking problem and
we felt like we were able to kind of bring things out in the map
and we're allowed to have those kind of cool choke points like I was showing on that progression up to Kathmandu
and it was going to be okay in our game.
OK, and now I'm getting to the fifth item.
And this problem is something that probably is,
the solution we came up with here
is probably the most controversial of the solutions.
We've had members, even internal to our development team,
that were telling us just a couple of months
before we were shipping that we were making a huge mistake
with the decision that we made for Civ 6 here,
because it was going to confuse too many players
and we shouldn't do it.
But if you think about what
I've been emphasizing here is I wanted to make sure that the map was important in your
games of Civilization VI.
I wanted to make sure that the use of all the tiles around your city was important.
I wanted to make sure that you had to think about where you were in the world in terms
of which technology boosts and civic boosts you could unlock.
Maybe you don't have stone nearby you.
You cannot go into masonry as early and get the pyramids.
If that's your...
big plan to how to get ahead in the ancient era and there's no stone or there's no desert
nearby, you can't actually get the pyramids in this game. So we had done these things
through the unstacking the cities, through the tech boost system that were really helping
us bring the map out to sort of, you know, a preeminent role in Civilization VI.
And what we didn't want to do was let people kind of get away
from understanding the map and appreciating the map and
realizing the importance of the map.
And so there was this thing that had happened in all
civilization games with movement rules that I called
cheating the terrain.
And the problem there, if you look at this screenshot right
here, you'll see that we have a Indonesian
Chris Swordsman in Civ 5.
He's only got one movement point left because
He's already moved into this clear terrain space that he occupies right now.
But despite the fact that he only has one movement point left and should not be able
to get anywhere except for another clear terrain space, according to the rules of Civ V,
Doesn't really matter.
He can just dive in there.
He can go into either the desert hills that
are highlighted with the blue circle,
or into the woods to the west.
And that actually led to this really sort of awkward movement.
in CIV 5 where what you want to do with your guys is always end
their turn in difficult terrain. Because then they have better
defensive bonuses. And you can do things like you can scoot
down a valley where the terrain is nice and clear.
and then on your final movement jump up onto the wooded hill and see way off into the
distance as you're scouting the terrain. So especially when you're scouting the map and
especially when you're worrying about defending, you always want your last move to be in this
impossibly difficult terrain that should cost a lot of movement points. And it was fighting
against people's appreciation of the map. So what I wanted to do for Civ 6 was change that.
And one thing that I noticed about Civ 5, before we leave Civ
5, is in order to get this blue movement skirt around the unit
that highlights the places you can go, you had to know to click
on the special move mode button. And only if you turned on the
move mode would you get the ability to see the valid hexes
your unit can move to. Otherwise, you would just right
click and just move there.
So we got to Civ 6 and I proposed we're going to have new movement rules. They're going to
actually enforce the proper movement point cost for terrain and you're going to have to pay
that much to go in there. And I put it in and everybody hated it. They just felt like I don't
know why my guy only, you know, he's got one movement point left, I want to be able to do
something with it. It just was confusing players, the turns weren't ending right.
I got a whole bunch of flack from the team internally and if I struggled with the civic
system getting that right, this was one where I was just actually getting people coming
in telling me that I was absolutely taking the franchise in the wrong direction and I
needed to change this now.
So I thought about this some more, and I did not want to give
up to it. And luckily, I had two or three other allies in my
design office who appreciated why we were making this change,
loved this change, and were really willing to stick it out
with me and work through until we had this working properly.
And so eventually, sort of long story short, what ended up being
the key thing that made me comfortable with the way we were
going to proceed here was I started thinking about Firaxis's
sister game, XCOM.
I started thinking about movement in XCOM.
And there's a lot of complicated moves you make in XCOM.
I don't know how many of you guys play XCOM,
but you go up and down ladders, you jump off buildings,
you, you know, there are like multiple levels,
there's different types of terrain you have to go around.
And I don't understand, I play XCOM all the time.
I love XCOM.
It's what I do sort of when I get a break from Civ.
I go off and play XCOM for a while,
because it's a different strategy game
that's got very, very different rules.
But I have no idea how the XCOM movement system works.
I have no idea how you spend points for that,
what your range is.
And I don't need to know as a player
because when I have a unit selected,
it just shows me a blue movement boundary
for everywhere I can go,
and I just click on one of the hexes in that area.
And all of a sudden, that just works.
That's my move for that guy for that turn.
I don't need to know the specifics of how much everything costs. And so what we did is we took
that blue boundary that you saw in Civ 5 was only available when you went in that special
movement mode, and we made it always a part of how you made a move in Civ 6. As soon as the
unit's selected, that boundary's going to show, and you know where all the valid tiles are.
And when you're in this situation, like shown on the screenshot here, where you only have one
movement point left, the boundary will shrink down to just where he can go sort of for the
second part of his move.
So we put that in and all of a sudden our user tests were
coming back, people understood it, they got it, things were
looking like we could actually ship the game and have this
system in place, people were going to be able to have the
proper appreciation of the map that I wanted.
So let's see where that leaves us.
So.
I'm listing four different things here on the left side of
the screen. Pretty much the four major problem areas that
we've identified from Civ 5, where we've sort of taken a
hard look at ourselves and kind of been real critical to figure
out what we need to change for Civ 6. The only one that's not
listed there is the civic system, which is not really
necessarily directly part of map driven play, but it does
respond to that.
overarching goal I had about having to think on your feet and not having a single path
through the game, because the civic system lets you reconfigure what you're doing with
your empire and sort of launch yourself into a new phase of the game that's going to be
aligned with your new short-term goal. But if you look at these four things here, I think
in all four of these areas, we really...
decided that the best way for us to hit this primary goal of making it so that you're going
to have to think on your feet more and have a more
you know, customized experience each time you play, because you're going to have to
redo your strategy. All four of these items contributed to it, and they all brought it
out through driving the play through the map. So one of the things I love about what we
did with Civ VI is not only was the map important to the gameplay, but we sort of followed that
mapping motif with our artwork. So you can see here, not only does the fog of war look
like an ancient map.
It was sort of that old parchmenty look, but we
actually, it's not shown on this screenshot, but we
actually themed the user interface, the heads up
display has sort of a age of exploration
theme to it as well.
So that's kind of what I wanted to go over today.
I think because we have a little bit of extra time, I
can still take at least 10 minutes of questions.
And I thank you for coming out to the talk.
Hi, thank you. I really want to sneak two questions in, but I was here with Sid and I asked him, like my favorite part of the franchise is the Civ I, the end of game, replay, really tied together like this accomplishment over 30 hours and I was wondering why that disappeared.
Yep, and I was here for that session. Sid apologized that he had thrown me under the bus because he had not answered your question, but I'm happy to answer that question.
I'm not sure whether I'm going to do a talk like this
in the couple years at GDC.
But one thing that has been clear to me
as we've been working on Civilization VI
is that the process of rolling out
a new title in the Civilization franchise,
it's a five, six year proposition.
And we have to make a lot of decisions
about where everything is going to hit during that rollout
and what's...
the right things for the base game and which things, you know, maybe we have plans down
the road in the future to really do a great job with and so some of the support that might
be expected will come down the road. So I just ask you to be patient because we actually,
it may look like we don't care about replay systems at all, but it's actually something
that is still very forefront in our thinking.
So what is the process for iterating on design on a game
that takes 30 hours to play?
It's tricky.
And there are a lot of ways we sort of cheat that.
If you look at the fact that some of the setup options
in the Civilization game, I don't
think our players ever use or use very, very rarely.
But they're instrumental to what the team does in terms of us
being able to iterate on things.
So for instance, we have what we call our advanced starts,
where you can start a game in the Renaissance
or start a game in the industrial era.
We use those all the time.
That's how you can just dive into a part of the tech tree
and see how it's playing.
You can try out air combat without having
to play for five hours to get to it.
So there are tricks and techniques
like that that we've sort of adopted over the time.
And some of those are built in as options
that players don't use very often,
but the development team uses quite a bit.
Thank you.
Hi, I'm Arthur, I'm working at Amplitude Studio.
We are creating games like Endless Legend for this game.
First of all, congratulations for this amazing sequel.
Thanks.
Really.
So I really like the tech boost system.
But after some games, I just realized
that even me, who are not really an optimizer player,
I was starting to.
trying to achieve all the conditions to have all the boosts and at the end I just you know
have all these units that I don't really want and this improvement in my city that I don't
really chose. And I don't know if you thought about that and maybe thought about a more
random system for this boost.
Civ 6 can be a bit of a frustrating experience for somebody who wants to try to achieve sort
of that perfect game and optimize everything.
There's a lot of things that we deliberately put in your way to make it so you can't have
the perfect setup.
So you can't get all the wonders.
You have to make trade-offs about how you're going to use the tiles outside your city.
Sometimes it's the science campus tile.
up against the mountains that you want to use for that gets
pilfered to put in your holy site or a wonder that
has a specific requirement.
So yeah, I realize that we sort of made the choice
to force people away from having a perfect layout
and a perfect plan.
But if you look at what I was going for here in terms of
trying to make people have to adjust and not be able to rely
on the same strategy every time, I think that you end up
there no matter what.
Um, so, I actually was going to come up and say that I really hated the movement system, but you
apparently went over that right at the end of the talk. Uh, yeah, even yesterday in my
playthrough I was trying to go into a forest and my dude stopped and then I lost the city and I
was like, you movement system! Um...
But actually, my question to you is slightly less game mechanic based and more about the
Civilopedia. So in Civ V, Civ VI, you guys introduced religion and did a lot more things.
And one of my favorite parts of Civ has always been the Civilopedia because it's text that
we've actually learned from over the years. And I feel that
in Civ 6, a lot of the Civilpedia entries and a lot of the tech research entries that you get,
the quotes that come up, they seem a lot more snarky, snide, almost kind of mocking the
thing that you either discovered or are trying to research. It seems a little bit more hurtful,
I guess, than you would expect from a Civ game. And I was just concerned with, I guess,
wondering what the designs behind that were.
Yeah, we've gotten that feedback before. It's certainly not the first time I've heard that.
And if you came to Sid's talk, you can see that even in Sid 1, they were wrestling with
what's the right balance between sort of respectful, you know, true historical treatment
and humor. And there probably are some areas where we missed the bar a little bit on Civ 6.
So we'll definitely learn from that. I don't think we've made a permanent shift in one
direction. I think that's something where...
You try some things out, some things work, some things the
community pushes back a little bit.
And that's probably an area where we learned a little bit
more about what the community really likes.
Yeah, and also, you guys misspelled Guru Nanak's name in
the civilization entry for Sikhism.
And I feel that that's a 10 second Google search, maybe.
You could fix the major important leader.
Well, we'd absolutely love to fix it.
And we do that all the time.
We go back, and if people email us or whatever, tweet me,
whatever, we go back in and we patch up everything.
Because we know that people are going
to be playing Civ VI five years, 10 years, hopefully, from now.
And so we might as well get it right for people
all the way down the road.
So send those on to us.
There's a lot of text in this game.
It gets localized into over 13 languages.
Things like that do happen.
Hi, how are you?
So I've played all the Civ series from one through six,
and I want to congratulate you that Civ VI really feels very
much part of the series.
And it's actually a very good game in the series.
So I've been very impressed by it.
Thank you so much.
Thanks.
Before I get to my question, like in the earlier presentation I did bring up a question about
what you just said, but I wanted to bring it back again to social responsibility as
a game developer.
As an industry as a whole, I think we want to be moving towards more of that and I think
you know, for access.
play like this game really can play a big role in that and I would like to see a bit more on the
educational aspects to be highlighted and kind of in the tune of the sociopedia question as well
I think we're losing a bit of that and especially at this day and age it's important to bring
more of that back so I'd encourage more of that.
My question is how you guys understand what users are doing with the game.
So I heard a lot from you about listening to the community via the forums,
but how much are you also looking at actual usage of the game and analytics in terms of how people are actually playing the game
and how do you balance that with what people are demanding on the forums?
Okay, and I just remembered I'm supposed to be repeating the questions for the forum vault video for this, so I'll start that right now.
The question was, how do we use analytics and look not only at what the community is saying, but actually some raw data from how the game is being played?
to inform our decisions going forward. So we are definitely looking at that. We did not have a
full telemetry system coming back from the game in Civilization 5, but we have put that in for
Civilization 6. So all of a sudden we do start to get aggregate data. We don't ever focus on any
particular user, but we get aggregate data for how often certain tech boosts get triggered.
which civilizations people are playing, which types of
victory are they going for.
And it's actually, I know that's a new trend in games,
is to get that kind of telemetry in there.
But it's already very, very clear to us that this is a
huge new tool that's going to help us going forward.
And it should make us able to tune and really get Civ VI to
the best possible place without having to make as many
guesses as we had to make in the past.
So.
It's a great question and it's definitely something that we're focused on.
We also run a whole series of focus tests before the game ships.
That's another great source of data about how people are playing the game and what they're
struggling with.
So yeah, I'm noticing that it's sort of a whole new world in terms of having that kind
of supporting data to really influence your decisions.
Some of what I showed you here was, you know, designer instinct and maybe not necessarily
based on data.
But I think you need a combination of the two
to really move forward in the best possible way.
Thank you.
OK.
All right, so let me take one more, or should we end it now?
All right, that's it for questions,
but I will still be up front, and I'll
take your questions personally.
OK.
Thank you.