Survive Thursday night, only one more day to go.
Okay, so I'm Hugh Monaghan.
I am the co-founder and designer at Stellar Jockeys.
My brother Jack is the other co-founder.
He ran a design blog called Design Reboot for a while
and worked on some other projects.
Brigador and star jockeys have the prestigious.
A quality of being the first thing that I've really worked on in the games
industry. So take all that in mind when we go through this. Before we really get
started. Couple things you know cell phones you guys know the drill.
Also I think Chris Charla he was my advisor on this and you know I've only
shipped one game he is around for a little bit longer than that to give
some good context.
So yeah, so this is all systems know learning from the doomed launch of Brigador, or as
I've been calling it, just how I cocked up our launch.
Not a big deal.
Okay, so what did I mean by doomed?
What's this overall thesis for this talk?
The 1.0 launch was a failure before it happened.
I didn't know it, but a myriad of factors
went into basically preventing us
from ever getting any kind of real momentum with the game.
So the real question though is,
was it doomed as in nothing I could do about it
or doomed as in all my fault?
Yeah.
And it turns out that's something that you need a lot of time away from it to really get the context you need.
So yes, I'm sure anyone who can, you know,
anyone who's shipped a game can vouch that like,
that month before and after is, you know,
everything's kind of a blur, you don't really,
nothing really makes sense.
And the other thing is that when things don't go well,
your immediate instinct is to look to the other, right?
So, okay, this project didn't go so hot, who screwed me?
And...
Thankfully I kind of just let that sit for a bit and now we're 9 months out
from that original launch so I've got a little bit more context and I think a
little bit of a cooler head to be able to talk about this stuff.
So before we really get into it though we need the context for the launch for
the game the studio just everything so we're for full-time devs between 2011
and 2016. Mostly full-time.
early years were kind of off and on.
This was the first commercial game for 3 4ths of us.
Like I said, my brother had done some contract work
and had worked on Darkest of Days at 8 Monkey.
But for the rest of us,
we were freshly minted game developers.
This project was 100% self-funded.
And so, I mean, specifically, I mean, we took no outside money.
We did not work with a publisher.
And because we were, you know, fresh in the industry,
we also had almost no connections at all.
So we also scratched both the engine.
This is something we took a lot of flak for,
a lot of armchair generals in gaming forums.
And the thing that I wanted to point out there is.
It's important to remember the context for this.
In 2010, 2011, the landscape for licensed game engines
was very different than it is now.
Unity was not quite what it is,
and Unreal was also extraordinarily more expensive.
And the other thing, too, is that
Because we didn't have full funding for this project,
by necessity it was a passion project.
For me personally, that was getting to be a designer
and putting all my bad ideas into a game.
And for the programmers,
that was being able to make their own engine.
Unlike me, Harry and Dale, both of the wonderful programmers
on the project, had much better offers ready to go for them.
And they chose instead to work with my brother and I
on this project.
And so you need to be able to bring something
to the table when you're asking someone
to sacrifice a very, very healthy wage on the West Coast
and permanent sunshine with near poverty wage
and living with me for three years.
So the goals on the project, one was to make a unique game
with a high skill ceiling.
I should qualify that.
So Brigador was a ridiculously ambitious project,
especially given our means and experience at the time.
Much of that was driven by a communal desire of the team
members to make something distinct.
If we're going to go through these tremendous pains
of developing a game, then it should
be one that sort of bore our distinct imprint.
Something that hadn't been done before, at least in some respects,
and which respected player time.
One of the things we talked about a lot was the Doom Rule,
which is that you get into a game, you spam Enter,
and within one or two seconds, you should be in combat playing the game.
If you boot up Brigador, that is absolutely true.
And it also kind of pervades the overall mindset with the game
is that there's only downtime if you want it.
There's nothing worse for me than having
these sort of designer-mandated wait periods.
I mean, it's understandable in the case
where it's a disguised loading screen.
But if it's not necessary to actually,
you know, a mechanical component to the game,
I prefer to avoid that.
And regarding the high skill ceiling,
part of that is just having a game that's reactive
to the player in some component.
Like if we wanted to be able to reward players
who were willing to put in the time and the effort
on a game to truly learn all the mechanics.
And I think we accomplished that.
And it was also relative to one of the programmers,
Dale's an avid Counter-Strike player.
And so that kind of mentality for precision play
is something that I think continually crept into our design.
The second goal was to make enough money to do it again.
That's fairly self-explanatory.
I mean, it's nice if you break even.
Great if you can fund another project.
The third goal was to keep the team together after ship.
One of the unfortunate realities of game development is that
oftentimes a team doesn't really just until the,
you know, getting towards the end of a project.
And then, you know, you ship a game and then things happen,
studios close, people move on.
And so our hope was that this was the first step
in a much longer journey together as a studio.
And the fourth goal was to build a reputation
as a high quality developer.
The best way to sum that up is just,
I mean, you wanna be known for being the guy
who makes really good stuff.
Pretty straightforward there.
Anyway, sorry.
So as far as actually whether we hit that or not,
excuse me, didn't need to drop that note.
Okay, so did we make any unique game?
I think we did.
I'm not gonna give any wiggle room
on some of the distinctive components.
I'm very proud of that we managed to capture
that granularity of aiming that I mentioned
with Counter-Strike.
The goal was to make a first-person shooter,
to bring the precision that you get in those kinds of games,
but into an isometric environment.
It took a year of prototyping to get an AIM scheme
that really worked there, and there were all other sorts
of wonderful problems that we had to deal with,
but we got there.
We did not make enough money to do it again,
at least not yet.
So the little asterisk there is that
Even though Brigadier's launch wasn't so hot,
we've actually been trending up in day-to-day sales.
Now, as much as I'd like to attribute
that to my own personal charisma and running my mouth
continually on the internet, I think
there's also a component of the launch itself just
being that bad.
That maybe it was just you needed
to get the ball rolling a little bit more.
We did not keep the team together after the ship.
It was a very amicable parting.
There's nothing, there's no like terror story here.
It was just, we finished the game,
we didn't have money to do it again.
And we had all gotten largely
what we needed to out of the project.
So I'm very happy with just,
even though we didn't stay together
and that goal wasn't itself met, that.
this was a stepping stone for all four of us to actually move forward in the industry.
And as for building a reputation as a high quality developer, I'm not,
I'm not the person who can really make that judgment.
And the other thing too, is that I don't think you can make those kinds of qualitative assessments
until at least your second or third project. I mean,
You know, everyone's heard of like One Hit Wonders.
That's mostly referred to, I mean, you mostly hear that
in the context of music or film,
but I think it can certainly apply to games as well.
And then just a quick run through on end results.
So.
Like I said, Brigador shipped June of 2016
after a nice stint in early access
starting in October of 2015.
We had review scores ranging between four out of 10
and 9.5 out of 10.
Obviously I prefer one of those.
Our final Metacritic score was exactly 70%.
It was 78.
And then our very last review was that 40%.
So that one stung.
We actually are overwhelmingly positive
on our Steam user reviews.
That's been a nice vindication.
And actually, we just, even though we've been
at that percentage level for a while,
we just hit the minimum review threshold
a week before I flew out for GDC.
So that's a freshly minted title.
Now, nine months out from release
for a game that took five years to make,
we are standing at 15,000 units sold.
I'll let you come to your own conclusions there.
But we did ship a game, a two and a half hour soundtrack,
a book, and an audio book,
all as part of our first project.
And then the double asterisk there is that
a lot of those negative reviews we received
were relating to controls,
something I will more fully address later in the talk.
When we went into ship, that whole thing I mentioned
about high-quality developer and wanting
to kind of make a splash, I definitely
think I bit off more than I could reasonably have chewed.
And you end up paying the price for that in different ways.
But at the end of the day, we still
managed to produce all of these things.
So the game itself. I've been doing a lot of prefacing without actually talking
about the project.
So what is Brigador?
It turns out that's actually a very difficult question to answer.
We were plagued for the entire two-year stretch running into release,
trying to articulate it in a pithy fashion.
So the best I could do at the time was just figuring out what it wasn't.
So it's not a twin-stick shooter.
And this is actually something that if I had taken that to heart much earlier in the development cycle,
I might have better been able to market it and anticipate.
some of the issues we had going into launch.
But it looks like a twin-stick shooter,
but it very much is not.
It's a very mechanically dense game.
It's slower than a twin-stick.
And they're just distinct elements.
It's not Tiberian Center and RTS.
I mainly bring that one up because we
use sprite-based graphics.
both out of a stylistic decision and out of necessity.
The entire game art was produced by a single artist,
and that includes over about two and a half years of art,
130 units, and over 1,000 environment assets.
If we were to do that in a 3D pipeline,
we would have been able to build a fraction of that.
We utilized a kit bashing style to produce all of the in-game assets since
we didn't have to worry about apology or the you know any of the qualities of the
3 render itself for the 3 model itself all that mattered was the render.
We were, and by we I mean Jack, was able to produce these assets at a diabolical speed.
By the end of the art pipeline, by the end of the process of art assets being produced,
he was able to create a finished vehicle for the game within about six hours.
So it's not a roguelike or a roguelite.
There were certain aspects of roguelite
that we wanted to hit.
I feel like everyone who's been up on stage on GDC
for the last couple years mentioned
Spelunky in some capacity.
It's a very important game that kind of tickles
the back of everyone's brain since it came out.
Our only real touch, touching on to that genre,
was that we had an entire segment of the game
that was built around these sort of semi-procedural runs
where you set up your equipment, you go,
and then either see how far you can get
or go until you die.
So the only thing we could figure out
was that it's kind of like Desert Strike,
kind of like Crusader, no remorse.
But it turns out it's a bit of a problem when your major touchstones came out 22 and 25
years ago, respectively.
A significant portion of our player base weren't even alive when the games that we would refer
them to were made.
And that's just...
It's a similar problem as anyone who's making a truly new game.
I don't know if any of you caught the For Honor
talk about its development.
But that is a game that is truly unique.
And so when you don't have any of those kinds of natural
touchstones to draw from, Brigador is like Dark Souls
plus tanks.
We didn't have the easy shorthands to pull from.
And so the best we found was,
and I'm just giving a sampling of what we did get.
PC Gamer Review said,
it's a colorful and chaotic isometric 2D mech shooter
set in a world steeped in 80s futurism.
It's a lovely description, but it's also mouthful.
And if you just walk up to someone and say that,
they're gonna kinda give you a little squint.
We have a pretty active Something Awful thread,
the forum, and someone described it as a tank western.
That has a nice romantic quality to it,
but again, it's not super useful.
And the one I ended up using the most in talking with press was it's a Kool-Aid
man simulator. That was because I lacking the ability to have distinct
game touchstones. I started to move in just the evoking the feeling of the
game and something we had start saying internally was that you need to feel
like a Kool-Aid man at least when you're in the you know the big giant
building sized tanks and Max.
So
For a little context, I don't know how familiar everyone is with the game, but I'm gonna play
our early access trailer.
So this was when we launched in October of 2015.
So.
So that's not supposed to happen.
So the interesting thing about that trailer is that.
It's a very good trailer for a different game.
When we went into it.
original trailer, which I'll actually play later,
was very slow, it was very,
it was more concerned with atmosphere.
And our assumption was that going into our actual launch,
we wanted to show gameplay,
show that it's like the bombastic quality of,
hey, in Brickdoor you can blow everything up.
The whole shtick of our game, the whole premise,
is that the entire game world is destructible.
And we figured we would highlight that.
through these high-intensity quick cuts,
things blowing up, people like explosions.
But the problem is that it showed the game
as a twin-stick shooter.
And the urban destruction elements,
I mean, it kind of got highlighted
at the end of that trailer,
but it was still more of a peripheral element
to just, oh, this is like a high-intensity loud thing
where the music never changes, apparently.
This trailer got about a third of the views of our original launch trailer.
Now part of that I think is just natural diminishing returns.
Once people know a thing exists, it's harder to build up excitement
on subsequent trailers and press releases.
But it also, it just wasn't as effective.
We weren't able to draw people in.
OK, so the one way that we did manage to draw people in
was through me running my mouth on the internet.
So.
Back in February,
so this is prior to release,
February of last year, excuse me,
we had a poster on our Steam thread
who was very insistent that
Brigadier should cost $15 and not $20,
which is fine.
I mean, I don't agree with you,
but you're welcome to post your opinions.
The last straw came when...
He posted back again on it, genuinely confused and insulted
that I hadn't taken his advice.
And he was actually like genuinely sad and perplexed,
like why didn't you take my advice?
I could have helped you.
So my initial response to that was 2 in the morning,
two or three beers in, and just a long list of, uh, you know.
And because I had a good English teacher in high school,
I decided to do a second draft, sat on it for a bit,
and then realized that oftentimes the best way
to reach people is through humor.
So I rewrote it just as like, OK.
here's all the things that you are willing to pay $20 for
and that people don't really balk at,
things like a Nickelback poster,
or a case of beer, toilet plunger,
all these sorts of things that,
because of the context and the usage,
people have completely different valuations of those things.
So I wrote that reply, and this actually...
relates to a very important lesson that I learned,
which is that most virality has to be stimulated.
I mean, manufactured makes it sound
kind of evil and dubious.
So I wrote that post,
and if I had just left it on the Steam forum,
I don't think anyone, it wouldn't have blown up.
And maybe some people would have shared it.
But instead, I wrote that post at very late in the morning,
but then I emailed it to everyone I had made contacts
with, both as developers and as journalists,
the few that would listen to me.
Emailed, I just did a big, big blast with this.
Just say, hey, here's this thing that happened to us.
You might find it interesting.
Cool beans.
And then I woke up 8 hours later with my face plastered on some of these
different sites and with coverage on Kotaku all these kinds of
the response to that was the coverage that we've been trying to get for the
game itself and had failed at miserably.
So then later about 2 weeks after our launch.
In a.
less considered fit of frustration.
We were two months out of launch
and we had yet to receive a Metacritic aggregated rating.
I can't remember if the minimum was four or five,
but whatever it is, we were one below that.
And I was furious at this,
because it was like we had done our due diligence.
And it seemed like it was emblematic of
what I perceived as like, well, everything that was wrong
with the games industry.
And so I wrote this big blog post on Imgur about how,
don't become a game dev.
It's terrible.
I have terrible health problems leading into launch,
all these kinds of things.
And yeah, that got shared around.
And it ended up with me doing a follow-up interview
with Nathan Grayson on Kotaku.
I would prefer a slightly different headline, but again, that interview with him alone ended
up being about 85,000 views.
The Imgur post was about 70,000 views, and that doesn't even include just sort of word
of mouth elements as well.
This one's my favorite, though, because this actually was following the Price post.
I made a few waves with that soon after Jane from Firewatch, and that whole debacle about
people returning the game after beating it in under two hours.
The close proximity there meant that people were kind of putting these two together.
But in the process of talking about it,
everyone who approached it was like, yeah,
there's Firewatch.
Everyone loves Firewatch.
And then there's, I don't know what this game is.
But apparently, there's this price component here.
So that wasn't so good.
But those three things tallied up
for about a third of our sales.
And that's a very, very important thing.
So let's look at total Brigador purchases from 2015 to 2016.
I don't have Christmas in here.
This chart was made a few months back.
Those three posts, or rather the posts and the reactions to them.
So the $20 price post, my Imgur, DevLife post,
and then the Kotaku interview that was actually significantly after it.
Those three elements are directly responsible for about a third of our sales.
And we've done a few more things after that and we've had more sales and everything, but
that response of press reaction to, I guess you could call it non-traditional marketing.
I wasn't even intended as marketing, it was just me being angry on the internet.
But that was a significant role in broadening the exposure of Brigadore.
So this brings me to kind of summing up all the things that I learned over the course of this launch. My litany of doom.
So the first thing is priming. You have to teach the consumer how to react to and interact with your game.
I kind of touched on this a little bit earlier with our trailer and how it was a great trailer for a twin-stick shooter, not for Brigador.
of actually I've got some more slides for that. But yet another thing is that
you have to be you have to start doing that before they play it. If a player is
in your menu or you know just booting up the first level of your game. And they
don't have to know exactly what the game is but they need to know to a degree
what to expect or how to approach it.
This, I mean, for anyone who's not actually familiar
with the game itself, this is a test that we did
for what proper full destruction in the game
could look like.
And this is the kind of thing that we should have focused
on a lot more.
We had a pretty good success sharing GIFs of the game,
I mean, exactly this kind of thing.
But the problem was that we didn't convey to the player
anything more significant than shoot stuff, blow stuff up.
And what happens is that there's kind of an embedded message
in that kind of ethos, which is that you are
super powerful going in and that it's more,
it's more of that empowerment fantasy.
And as a result, when you subvert that,
you know a player can get killed by walking into a gas station which we
thought was hilarious early Cypher was hilarious. I think it gave one least one
of the programmers an aneurysm.
That's that getting killed by a gas station when you're cool mercenary in a
giant Mac is like the least empowering thing that can happen in the game.
And.
That was part of the whole messaging.
And we didn't...
Players came into the game like they were a bull in a china shop
as opposed to something more like a matador
where you're actually trying to avoid and corral this much more powerful force.
So this was our very first trailer.
This is February 2014, right before I attended my second GDC.
Oh, no, no, no, no.
Let's actually play that.
OK, here we go.
Like and Subscribe
Yeah, so that was before we learned how to encode trailers.
And also, there were some things a little embarrassing there.
Also, it turns out, don't name your game
before you do copyright checks.
and IP searches and also search engine optimization.
Because matador turns out kind of a common word
both in general use and in business.
Doing a cursory Google search for matador,
you come up with matador beef jerky, matador condoms.
And if you look, okay, well let's refine a little bit.
Matador trailer, ha ha.
Pierce Brosnan movie.
So having to pivot on that didn't exactly help us,
but that's not really, it's not nearly as important,
I think, as a lot of these other elements.
So regarding this whole priming thing,
let's give me the next slide.
Okay, so I'm only gonna briefly talk about Bioshock Infinite
specifically because the messaging for that game
was almost entirely based around Elizabeth,
around storytelling and how like when you play this game,
you're gonna have this great,
like it's gonna be a great story and like a great,
you're gonna be emotionally involved.
And.
very little of it was actually focused directly on it's a shooter.
Even though it's a shooter.
And I think because of that focus, well first of all it primes people for being focused
on the things that they did well in like the, I mean not that they did things poorly, but
like the storytelling elements.
They put all these energies into those elements of the game,
and they set up their audience and their critics as well
to look at those things.
They put the spotlight on them, which I think is also
why when the cover featured Booker.
I think that's part of the reason for that backlash is because their entire marketing
campaign leading up to that was putting all the focus away from the traditional shooter
setup and as a result those players who were already part of that message, there was a
bit of a dissonance there in that messaging.
Alien Isolation, I think, is just a great example of a game where you had this coherence
across what the game was, how it was marketed, how it was presented at trade shows, and on
top of that, they were having to overcome the challenge of the reputation of previous
games, both from a qualitative standpoint and from a genre standpoint.
This was a proper horror game.
Tim Keenan's Duskers, I think, is actually,
given similar challenges that we faced for the players,
this is how you do it correctly,
which I wish I could have figured that out about a year ago.
But with Duskers, and he actually mentioned this
in his talk, originally they had a mouse interface
on the menu, and he said that it wasn't until they,
when you enter the game,
from the get-go, there's no mouse input,
and everything is keyboard only,
that they stopped getting complaints
or having issues with players,
not only just trying to use the mouse,
but even having a problem
with that direct keyboard interface.
Also,
it looks like a game you use a keyboard for.
And there's kind of like an intangible quality to that,
but there's the console commands.
And his overall just presentation of the game
was much more in line with the way
that players ended up playing it.
I think the best way it can be summed up is that he.
The trailers and the marketing for that game
much more accurately described the experience
of playing it rather than the physical realities of the game.
It's the subjective experience of that game.
And that was a lesson that I didn't understand,
which is that we tried to be very
literal in everything that we showed with Purgator.
It's like, we didn't have the budget for.
trailers that didn't exclusively use gameplay footage.
And we focused on,
it was also kind of like our counter-marketing thing
where it's like, everything that we're gonna show
in this game, for the trailers and everything else,
is going to be unadulterated gameplay footage.
Nothing's gonna be fabricated in that regard.
And while, you know, we did that,
the downside of that was that
that was ineffective marketing.
So, you know, why do it in the first place?
The last one I want to say is that Zac Tronics,
he's sort of...
a great example of taking that priming and applying it across multiple projects.
I mean you, you know to an extent that you're getting into some serious puzzle
shit when you get a Zachtronics game. You know it's going to be different and
you know you're going to need to sit down and like have not don't let anyone
bug you for a while and just dig in.
So priming.
uh... death of the designer
what do i mean by that
so uh...
all that really matters at the end of the day is
whether players buy and enjoy your game
uh...
this determines sales and sales determine longevity
controls are a very interesting thing
So, Brigger was designed around tank controls,
where pressing W, A, S, D, or a left control stick
on a vehicle, W is forward, not up on the screen.
So it's relative to the orientation of your vehicle.
This hasn't really been a common control scheme for a couple decades.
Again, Desert Strike, Crusader, No Remorse, these are touchstones, are older than most
people's children and cars and even their, you know, anything of substance in their lives.
And I fail to account for the fact that.
With video games, most players going into a game,
it's not the first game that they've ever played.
That's a problem that mobile developers have to deal with
a lot more, I think.
But generally speaking, you can usually assume that someone
has played a video game before yours.
And that means that there's a sort of legacy knowledge set
going into it.
If you made a shooter, usually someone's played a
shooter before yours.
So for us, we had this legacy skill set of people who had
played twin stick shooters.
And I don't really know of any twin stick shooters that use tank controls.
So we had this entire player base where they were expecting a twin stick shooter and then
not only is the game mechanically very different from a twin stick shooter, but also the control
schemes are like, why, why, why would you do this?
And this is a genuine case of my sort of arrogance and enforcement as a designer, because in
my mind.
The game was designed around a tank controls control scheme.
And I both wanted players to experience this like ideal way of playing the game.
And also, because of the limitations of adapting it to a twin-stick style control scheme,
players who tried to progress with that would eventually hit an artificial
ceiling in what they could do in the game.
And so I didn't want to ambush players with this like okay, you know, gotcha
where you put five hours in the game and now all of a sudden you have to relearn a new
control scheme in order to be able to meaningfully progress.
That's just flavor picture.
So the problem there, oh, no, I thought I had another slide there.
Well, so to actually articulate that, the issue that comes up there is that A, most
players don't make it far enough to actually run into any kind of a skill ceiling.
And B, if a player isn't engaging with your game right off the bat.
Very few people are going to bang their head against a wall
for 45 minutes or an hour until they start liking a game.
Very few people can trust in a game or a developer.
You have to have some very strong external motivators
to get people to stick with something that long.
And we had all this data right in front of our noses.
We found that for most players, it took them,
most players who weren't acquainted with tank controls,
took them 45 minutes to an hour
to start to settle into the game.
Now, in a testing environment, you have someone who's either paid to be there or they're your
friends, so it's like a social payment.
They're going to get beers later.
They are there, they're incentivized to stick around with the game.
And so we weren't.
responding to the fact that for most players they would come in
not like the controls and just immediately be done with the game.
It's an instant return. We had a whole set of 0.1 hours,
returns, negative review. These controls are so dumb.
So we did eventually pivot on that.
Added a twin stick style control scheme. We added in controller support.
They weren't ideal control interfaces but
again at the end of the day if a player is having fun...
and they purchased your game that's that's the thing that's important.
So tying into this the first like the first 60 minutes Foundation.
So the majority of your players also as the ones who fund your company will
never make it past the early stages of gameplay.
This varies depending on genre.
But if you look at Steam achievements,
and any kind of usage statistics for most games,
you get kind of like the hockey stick, right?
Most people aren't actually making it that far into games.
So I talked with the guys at 17-bit.
They had much better data tracking than we did.
And they told us that 17% of their players
dropped out before completing the first level.
And then 92% of their players dropped out before completing the first dungeon, which is roughly 2 hours in.
So you've got 92% of your players
never see anything more than your intro content.
Like, yeah, and that blew my mind.
I knew to an extent that you had a fall off.
I had no idea that it was of that magnitude.
So this screenshot's pertinent because on the left is our tutorials, or rather, the
first hour of playing a game, or of playing Brigador.
On the right is what the game actually looks like.
We did this sort of virtualized, abstracted environment for the game, but because there
was so much the player needed to learn, so much of a skill set, and also because this
was
not the first draft on our tutorial.
And so this was something that we had
banked out right before launch.
Everyone's under time pressure.
It was easier to do this abstracted environment
and not have to set dress it.
And also because we wanted to get the players
directly into the game,
we actually ended up with a much shorter tutorial
as opposed to.
bridging that gap in player knowledge and skill over a much longer period of
time. And as a result,
we had a bunch of players dying in the tutorials because we were putting too
much in there. The tutorial levels were taking too long.
So you would die at the end of a tutorial level that took 10 minutes to play.
And then you'd have to start over again.
And that is not a way that you endear yourself to your players.
So impedance.
The more unusual, complicated, or difficult the game is,
the stronger the incentive is required
to get both players and reviewers to buy in.
This ties in a little bit to what I was saying earlier,
but if your game is different or not,
in some way not immediately approachable,
you have to have something to hook them in,
either within the game itself or external to the game.
For us, we thought that we were doing that with our aesthetics, with the music, with
the lore and everything, but A, very few people care anything about lore before they're already
like 5 or 10 hours into a game.
So you can't use that as a pull, unless it's a sequel or something.
We didn't have the kind of momentum
that you get from a game like Dark Souls.
Which also, I mean, they did some brilliant sort of,
I don't know how much they were directly involved in that,
but the whole Dark Souls hard mentality,
where there was almost like a social pressure
to play that game and to excel at it,
because like, oh man, like did you beat Dark Souls?
You know, I did it on the naked run with no equipment or anything like that.
There was this whole momentum behind that game that helped players to stick around when
they might normally have given up.
Tangentially related to this, this was a post that was going around on Reddit a while back,
this would have been about a year ago, which is that game developers should never ever
be afraid to innovate.
And it's a wonderful sentiment.
So this screenshot is from the GameSpot October 2000 review of Alien Resurrection.
The game's control setup is its most terrifying element.
The left analog stick moves you forward, back, and strafes right and left, while the right
analog stick turns you and can be used to look up and down.
You know, early advent of what is now the staple control scheme.
So my, like, asterisk for this is that when you do something different.
Unless it is something that is immediately obvious or very easy to learn,
that you have to, there's a price you have to pay.
You have to have those motivators to get people to adapt to that new thing.
Otherwise, your innovation actually comes at the cost of a non-insignificant portion of your player base.
So, press is transactional.
Let me decode that a little bit.
So, I worked on Brigador with this mentality
of, you know, field of dreams.
If you build it, they'll come.
It was a very naive understanding of games development,
of just the nature of how you build hype,
of how you build interest in a game.
So,
I think the most helpful thing for developers to keep in mind
when they're interacting with press is,
what do you bring to the table?
Because at the end of the day, games press are doing a job,
and they have to earn money.
There's a very interesting podcast.
Austin Walker over at Waypoint was talking with Pat Klepek.
I think it was just right after the new year.
But they were talking about how.
Austin has all kinds of things that he would love to cover.
He has these kind of passion projects or these sort of things either directly related to
games or tangential to it that are very interesting.
But it's his responsibility to put things up on Waypoint
that are gonna generate views.
It's a business, he employs people,
he has those responsibilities.
And so for you as a person who's trying to get people
like Waypoint to cover your content,
the only way you can consistently do that
is if you can offer them something in return.
And this isn't to kind of cast this negative light on it.
It's just understanding that that's the way things are.
There's no free lunch.
And so if you can...
figure out how to contextualize either what you're trying to promote or your
game in general as an interesting thing. A really common phrase among game
developers is that you know what's what's your story what's your story as a
studio or as a developer or as a person or like give them something to latch on
to because
What that boils down to is having a headline, having something that grabs their audience,
because games press are having to deal with their whole own host of problems.
You know, I'm not a games journalist, so I don't know, I'm sure there could be like a
parallel version where I'm giving this talk about how I'm a terrible games journalist.
But there's all kinds of things that they have to deal with, so you have to meet them
in the middle.
So, kind of articulation of this, I don't know if you guys have heard of Slaughtering
Grounds.
There was this whole debacle a while back.
It was a game, it cost like one or two dollars, and Jim Sterling had a thing where he would
look at games that he does not think are qualitatively good.
and then he would say things about them,
and then sometimes they would say something back.
There was this whole series of,
oh man, there was this video that Jim Sterling,
where he like totally trash talks this dev,
and then the dev wrote a response, trash talking back,
and then there was a lawsuit involved,
and then something happened.
None of that itself is actually important.
What's important is that it was a good story,
so people talked about it.
It was interesting.
It was an easy headline.
I'm not saying go out and pick a fight with Jim Sterling.
I mean, maybe.
I'm sure it would be interesting.
Don't, don't, don't do that.
Or at least don't say that I sent you.
that I mean it brought something to the table and so
here's a game that prior to that hadn't got really any attention at all and all
of a sudden you've got most of the major games press sites
articulating that like, I mean like giving coverage to this thing
uh... and then last of all the reserve tank
The week after shipping is just as demanding,
if not more, than the week before.
And this starts just going into personal health stuff.
And obviously, no one wants to take poor care of their health.
But so this was that imager post that I wrote a while back,
intentionally trying to be a little goofy
with that first picture.
Like, oh, look at naive young cherubic developer,
then hard and grizzled veteran at the end.
The part that I talk about in that post, though,
is that I gained 40 pounds over about the last eight
months of development and got into a whole slew
of very unhealthy habits, partly just out
of the continuing push.
We had gone five years in development
and still hadn't shipped a game.
So that's a very strong pressure.
But also,
You know, we talk a lot about crunch,
and it should be talked about.
It's an important thing to be aware of.
But oftentimes, it's something that
is used as a proxy for a lack of time or a lack of money.
And at the time, for me, not knowing really
anywhere else to go and not having the experience
to contextualize it, that was the only thing
I could reach for.
So yeah, some final notes that I'll just zip through real quick.
This is just what the actual game looks like in the menu.
We tried to do some interesting stuff with pilot-related difficulty
and making the game as modular as possible from a player choice standpoint.
So you can change your difficulty through your pilot,
through your vehicle, through the levels you play.
None of that matters if your baseline difficulty is so high already that no one's even hitting
that low difficulty, that, you know, the minimum level of difficulty.
And I mentioned this earlier, but yes, we ship the game as
well as a book and an audio book.
I mean, that's insane.
It was cool, and I'm glad we did it.
But also, I was in the middle of trying to design levels
for the game, and then I was editing a 300-page book.
And then also because he's a thing we like that book so much a guy in Brad
but Brad Buckmaster was sort of a technical consultant for us during the
game for military hardware so like we would design a tank and we would ask
about it like yeah, you know that that seems kosher and like you help us write
a lot of descriptions. It was a very natural fit so we decided hey we don't
want to write a book.
So we did, and it was great.
And we liked it so much that we're like, okay,
but no one reads video game books,
unless you're like a big, big studio.
So it's like how do we get someone
to read this video game book that no one reads?
So it's like, oh, audio books are cool.
So we did an audio book adaptation.
And again, that was also a lot of time and effort.
And another thing that had to be finished by the time we shipped.
So the bright side of this is that we had some great reviews.
I mean even now it's still standing at a five star review on Amazon books.
Great feedback.
But the other thing is that this kind of tangential content it was just.
Rather than bringing people from the outside to the game,
I can count on two hands the number of times that happened.
Mainly it was just people who were already
hardcore Brigadier fans.
This was the icing on the cake for them.
So it was something that endeared us to our fans,
but from a business standpoint,
it didn't do a whole lot more for us.
So that's the audio book.
And then also, we worked with Makeup and Vanity Set.
They did a killer soundtrack.
And then on his own, he actually did,
we helped him with the cover art for it,
but he also did vinyl pressings of the soundtrack as well.
So we had a lot of cool stuff.
And I'm gonna end on just,
this was a single Steam review that we got.
That was really cool.
And I think anyone who's a content creator,
when you get this kind of a strong reaction from a user
base, it's one of those things that
helps you weather the storm.
And also because I didn't want to make
this sound like a really terrible, lugubrious talk.
The final context for all this is
that we're relaunching Brigador this coming June.
We added localization, new content.
I'm sanding down all those really, really rough edges.
And like the
the difficulty curve that used to be like a just giant plateau
is now going to actually be a curve.
Doing all these things that we can manage to course correct
and see where things go from there.
So thanks very much.
We've got time for a couple questions, so anyone?
Hi, thanks for the talk.
I bought the game, so hooray.
I had a question actually about that purchasing experience, though.
One thing that I noticed in following Brigador and then not following it and then eventually
buying it is that I heard about it way early before it launched, was interested because
I played those games back in the old SNES days and was just curious, then forgot about
it.
for quite a while and I did not even think about it again until the imager post. I actually
saw the imager post and I was like, oh, I completely forgot about that thing and went
and bought it because I wanted to support you guys and I enjoyed that the difficulty
curve is insane. My question is, did you talk at all about the timing of when you started
talking about the product to when you could actually launch it?
And how that impacted things because that distance of excitement when people first got into it to the point of purchase in my
Opinion and I'm not an indie dev
I've worked for others, you know larger studios
But I found that to be a big problem when you talk about something for three years and never comes out everyone just fatigues and forgets
Yeah, how is that?
changing as you thought about at all and how it absolutely so
uh... the the shortage of that is that the to your gap to our first trailer
and
uh...
i think it's two-and-a-half yet to have your gap between our first trailer and
our launch
was entirely unintentional
uh... when when we ship that first trailer like
Oh yeah, we got like another 8-12 months of work left.
Like at the worst.
And because I did spend a lot of time looking at the distance
between first press and shipping for a lot
of different indie titles.
I don't remember them off the top of my head,
but we looked at Hotline Miami, we looked at Bastion.
anything John Blow did.
And what I found was that the minimum time
was about three months prior to launch.
And that's actually, most PR agencies that I've talked to,
they prefer to have at least a three month window
with which to build the hype train.
And then the longest I found was like three years.
But in almost every case, anything like that.
hyperannuated, like longer than a year and a half, two years.
Those were either AAA titles, or those
were games that were indefinitely delayed.
They're pulling a Duke Nukem Forever or whatever.
So yeah, if I had my druthers and a proper set of experience,
I think I probably would have shot for a year or less
between Announce and Ship.
How do you, since no one else is asking questions,
how do you handle that with the uncertainty
of being an indie dev then?
You know, because you don't necessarily have a good context
for your window, it seems like.
So what kind of advice do you have for people
that are trying to figure out how to do that
and are trying to figure out what that year window
could possibly be when they're not sure what that is?
Yeah, so what I found is that,
And this is advice that seemed to be pretty common from everyone that I've talked to with
experience in the press is that when you're at indie scale, it is better to have as big
of a single blast as possible than a bunch of small little announcements and things because
there's a certain threshold you have to hit.
to get the general public or general press interested in what you have to offer.
And so if you distribute that across a broad set, there's a chance that maybe you'll get
one, maybe two times covered, but for the most part, most of that stuff is just going
to fall under the radar.
Early Access is obviously, I mean, it's not the right choice for everyone.
For us, it was, originally, Brick-It-Or-Head had no story campaign.
It was entirely in this spelunky set of, here's the freelance mode,
you pick your thing, you pick the mission, and then there's some procedural stuff,
and you either win or you die, you start again.
And when we were launched on Early Access,
the universal response was, this is a great tech demo.
Where's the campaign?
So we entirely retooled the game to actually hit that expectation.
Anyway, so yeah, what I would say is like,
maybe an ounce before early access, but at a small level,
I think bundling all that together is actually maybe the right way to go.
Thank you.
Hi.
even with a relaunch, knowing that there's only so much
you can do to change the fundamental design of the game,
if you were to make a sequel, is there anything
very fundamental about the game that you would do
differently if you don't necessarily have to take on
the baggage of the actual from the initial development?
Yeah.
Yeah, so this is a combination of stuff that got cut
from the game as well as just
things I learned about the design of the game
as it went forward.
So...
One thing I would do is that in the game you've got two guns,
a broad variety of vehicles you can choose from,
and a defensive ability.
So every vehicle has two guns and a special ability.
And that part was OK.
The problem is that
We had no way for the player to actively defend themselves.
So there's sort of an assumption built into Brigador
that you're going to get shot.
And what happened is that ultra light vehicles
either means that you had to play super cat and mouse
and use stealth tech all the time,
or for the ultra vehicles,
that we added in damage resistances,
but also we made them slow
because you can't have something that's both super tough,
a lot of firepower.
It just ends up being boring.
So like something more active components,
something we considered was actually having
the shielding be a toggle.
That like shielding just slowly burns out as it's on.
So you actually have to decide
when you're gonna have your shielding up.
I think our whole armor mechanic didn't work all that well.
Maybe have something akin to like a guard break
where it's like being able to time like flashing the shield.
These sort of more active components.
We had a lot of concerns about player attention,
but.
You know, that's a different case.
The other thing I would say is that we, um...
We originally had a prototype for hand braking in A-GRAVs
and in tread-based vehicles.
So there's these tiny little motorcycle tank things.
And we had a prototype where you could skid around a corner.
It felt awesome, but there was a whole lot of stuff.
There was all these horrible edge cases
that it was just going to be too much of a time commitment,
and we were too late in development to get that in.
I mean, the answer is that there's a lot of,
I mean, the game itself, the core would be there,
but there's all these kinds of refinements to the formula
that I'm, you know, I have a notebook full of them, so.
Cool, thank you.
Yeah, cheers.
I think we're supposed to be out of here,
so thank you very much, guys,
and I'm happy to chat more.