Hello everybody.
Thank you for attending our panel today.
Our talk will be presented by the three of us, the holders of the three pieces of the Triforce.
First off is myself, the game director, Hidemaro Fujibayashi, the holder of the Triforce of Courage.
Together with the game designers, I wield the courage to tell the staff any idea, regardless
of how ludicrous it is and how agitated they may look.
Next, we have the technical director, Takuhiro Dota, the holder of the Triforce of Wisdom.
Along with the rest of the programmers, he wields the wisdom to realize all of the aforementioned
ludicrous ideas.
and art director who has transformed the world of Zelda with his team of designers.
I'm Satoru Takizawa, the Triforce of Power.
Thank you for having me.
And finally, we have the art director Satoru Takizawa,
the holder of the Triforce of Power.
Along with the rest of the art team,
he wields the power to take all of the different elements in the game
to create a cohesive world of Zelda.
We hope you enjoy the panel.
Hello everybody.
I am Hidemaro Fujibayashi,
the director of Breath of the Wild.
Thank you for attending.
I am the director and game designer of the Zelda title.
I have been working on Zelda for about 20 years.
I am surprised at myself.
These are some of the past titles that I've worked on as a director and as a game designer.
Looking back, I've been working on Zelda titles for 20 years.
I'm actually surprised myself.
Well then, let's get started.
First, please take a look at this.
What does this look like?
At first glance, it might look like the original Zelda on the NES, but take a closer look.
You'll notice that Link is blue, there's a leaf, and also what looks to be a brown pipe.
As it turns out, this image here plays a crucial role in our topic today of constant and change.
But let me come back to this a little later.
As you probably already know, this is footage from the Legend of Zelda Breath of the Wild,
which is scheduled to release in just two days, on March 3rd, along with the Nintendo Switch.
What do you think?
Thanks. Great.
Okay, let's move on.
I'm relieved to know that you are aware of this title.
So, how did this new Legend of Zelda Breath of the Wild look to you?
Does it look like it's made a breakthrough and completely changed?
Or does it look like not much has changed at all?
When planning for this title, I first thought to myself,
what do I want to do with the new Zelda?
And then I thought, what is it that I need to make that happen?
You may have heard this keyword before, but it was a natural re-examination.
And the key to answering these questions were in these two concepts that you may have heard before,
rediscovering the essence and breaking conventions.
The number one thing we wanted to do at New Zelda was to make the user free to play in a wide field.
and by exploring the world, I wanted to experience exciting things one after another
and to be able to capture these experiences with my own free thinking.
What I wanted to accomplish with this new Zelda was to create a game
where the user can truly experience freedom in an expansive playfield.
And through exploring this field, I wanted the user to be able to experience
a new sense of adventure again and again
and be able to freely navigate through it as they see fit.
In other words, this means a game where the user can think and decide on their own where they want to go and what they want to do.
And when I started to think this way, what came to mind was the original NES Zelda.
Doesn't this just sound like the original Zelda?
Battling daunting enemies and scrolling across the field, and every time the screen scrolled,
there was a new discovery to be made and a new solution to uncover.
A game where the user can think and decide on their own where they want to go and what
they want to do and experience excitement and adventure.
I thought to myself, maybe what I need to do to create such a game is to go back to
the essence.
This is a thrilling and pulse-pounding experience.
In this respect, the land of Hyrule, the setting of Zelda, is full of romance.
What do you think of this map?
Thrilling and pulse-pounding experiences.
The land of Hyrule, where Zelda takes place, is filled with a great spirit of adventure.
Take a look at this map.
This is an illustration created by an artist a few years ago,
who wanted to make the land of Hyrule more specific.
This may look familiar to some of you, but this is an illustration that an artist created a few years ago, in an attempt to actually put down on paper this great spirit of adventure.
But, please take a look. It's really interesting.
It's a map of Hyrule, and it's something that I stumbled upon while I was sorting out assets for this presentation.
This actually has nothing to do with Breath of the Wild, or with the previous title, Skyward Sword.
But take a close look, it's pretty interesting.
An island floating in the sky.
There's a floating island, and although the placement is off, there's what looks like
the Great Plateau where Link awakens this time around.
And there's even a little cave entrance.
An immense, beautiful castle that reminds you of medieval Europe and scorching volcanoes.
A dense forest that once you enter, you may have no hope to escape.
And of course, dungeons that hold countless mysteries.
The land of Hyrule has all the necessary ingredients for a great adventure.
But I realized that to create a game in which, as I mentioned earlier,
the user can think and decide on their own where they want to go and what they want to do,
there were quite a few hurdles to overcome.
Not being able to move forward with an event without having followed a set path.
Having walls that you can't get around due to level design.
Or it could be that unless you've gone through a predetermined set of experiences, clues or difficulty may not be appropriate. This won't do.
And let's not forget the fact that all the solutions to all the puzzles that you've painstakingly prepared for a dungeon are all made available on the internet.
These were all conventions of Zelda.
We decided to start with game design and create a game that is more dynamic and dynamic.
So our first step in designing the game was to re-examine these conventions and put our sights on changing the structure of the game from a passive one, where you play within the confines of a pre-prepared mechanism, to one where the user can actively engage with the game.
So, what is an active game?
Our first approach was to remove those impassable walls, which were a convention of Zelda,
by transforming the walls and allowing the user to climb them in our experimental game field.
By transforming walls, which were used to represent boundaries, into another optional path,
it's as if the entire landscape delays before the user opens up, asking them,
so, which path are you going to take?
At that time, I felt that this was the game design that we were aiming for,
and the possibility of a dynamic game.
And it was at this point that I realized this was the kind of game design I was striving for
and holds the potential to create this active game I had envisioned.
And so, naturally, after you make the climb to the top of a tall mountain and look down,
there's only really one thing you can do.
So, you jump.
By introducing an action whereby you can glide through the air with an item, once you climb,
you can fly to wherever you want.
I felt that this was the crucial ingredient that will expand the sense of freedom in the
new Zelda.
I concluded that the multiplication of the player's action times the field
gives me an infinite number of ways to play,
and that this is the answer I was looking for.
After witnessing a simple multiplication of player's action and field
create an infinite possibility of gameplay through one movement,
I came to the conclusion that this concept of multiplicative gameplay
is the answer I was looking for.
Many puzzles found in Zelda games are based on things like natural phenomena or simple science facts that don't require a lot of prior knowledge.
But with the way we had been building games thus far,
we were using each of these individually as clues or hints to solve puzzles.
The objects that make up each puzzle are not only made for the purpose of the puzzle,
but they are also very sophisticated.
On the other hand, they require a lot of resources,
so this addition method is not suitable for the new Zelda.
It's not a stretch to say that the objects that made up each of these puzzles were made specifically for those puzzles.
This, of course, allows us to fine-tune and polish the gameplay experience,
but unfortunately it requires a lot of resource,
and this method of development by addition was not going to work for the new Zelda.
So my next thought was,
I wonder if I can use this idea of multiplication
and apply it to the mass production of these puzzles.
We created a game that would be able to play with the player's actions, objects that react to them, and objects that affect each other.
We thought that if we could do this, we could take the game to a level where players could play it in a more dynamic way.
make the game so that objects react to the player's action,
and the objects themselves also influence each other.
If we could do this, I felt that we might be one step closer
to creating an active game.
And first, I thought I'd use this hypothesis
to apply it to Zelda's gameplay,
and see if this multiplication
really makes the gameplay more dynamic.
I thought I'd try to experiment with this
in the simplest possible way.
So I had to find out if applying this hypothesis to Zelda and implementing this multiplicative gameplay will actually result in an active game.
I decided to experiment with this in the simplest way possible.
And this is what I tested at the beginning.
And what resulted was what I showed you at the beginning of the panel.
First, we wanted to quickly create a game of rock-paper-scissors,
and present it to the team staff.
We wanted to make it in 2D,
so we brought in the character data from the technical director, Dota,
who was going to be on the stage after this.
I thought that the quickest way to bring this idea to life
and to present this to the rest of the team
would be to create this in 2D.
So I brought the character data to the technical director, Mr. Dota,
who will be coming up after this, and ask him to make it.
As you can see, this is a 2D Zelda prototype.
It's a prototype of Breath of the Wild.
That's why Link is wearing blue.
It's nostalgic.
As you can see, this is a 2D Zelda.
But we used this as a way to experiment with the mechanism I was talking about earlier.
So you could say this is a legitimate prototype of Breath of the Wild.
And hence, Link's blue clothes.
This is very nostalgic.
Let's take a look at this footage where we compare the experiment and the result, which
is Breath of the Wild.
you
What did you think?
Great!
This prototype does not have a puzzle.
It only has a situation of a river and a tree.
But the user can still think for himself and find the way.
This prototype does not include any puzzles.
All we did was provide a situation involving a river
and some trees.
But the user is then able to think for themselves
and create a path forward.
In this simple setup, there was only one rule.
There's a situation and a goal.
Can you reach it?
When various actions, items, terrain, and reactions of the player are multiplied,
various events occur, and the user can freely create a release and reach the goal.
And when the player's diverse actions, items, landscape, and objects that react in various ways
are multiplied together using this simple rule, an active game was created,
where countless different events occur, for which the user can freely create solutions.
Through this kind of simple, primitive experimentation, we made the call of what to change and what
not to change to complete the basic game design.
Now, let's see how the Technical Director, Mr. Dota, realized this multiplicative gameplay.
Hi there, everyone.
My name is Takuhiro Dota,
and I am the Technical Director of Breath of the Wild.
I joined Nintendo in 2003,
and have contributed to a variety of titles
as a game programmer,
or through game tech and engine development.
In this game, our programmers re-examined many of the commonalities.
Over the course of development, the programmers on our team had to break all sorts of conventions when it came to in-game tech.
From the terrain system used to construct a massive world to things like graphics and
sound, level design methodology, AI, animation, even our pipeline for asset creation and managing
tasks, we were forced to rethink our approach to all sorts of tech-related challenges.
The ways we solve these challenges make for interesting stories in and of themselves,
but we're a bit pressed for time here.
Someday if we have the chance, I'd love to tell you all about it.
So I'd like to talk today about how we went about realizing this idea of multiplicative
gameplay that Mr. Fujiyabayashi mentioned previously.
It's actually a matter of physics and chemistry.
But don't worry, this won't be an academic lecture or anything.
The Legend of Zelda is an action game.
To go back to the basics, we decided to go back to the primitive elements of an action game.
The basic structure of an action game is collision, movement, and state.
In its most basic components, an action game is made up of collision, movement, and object states.
Taken together, collision and movement make up what we call physics in games.
But of course, when it comes to game development, you don't want the sort of physics you find in a textbook,
but a kind that fits the needs of the game you're making.
We call this game physics.
This game physics has been born from various games since the NES era.
And this is what we call game physics.
Since the NES era, a plethora of games have added to our understanding of this concept of game physics.
Game physics is, in other words, a lie.
Why do we lie?
Game physics could also be called false physics or liar's physics.
But why would you need to tell lies?
This is something we do to increase controllability and responsiveness.
In other words, to fulfill the demands of game design.
Sometimes to make it easier to process and to optimize.
We also end up telling these lies to optimize processing power and sometimes even to increase the sense of realism.
On the other hand, if we're telling lies, what use do we have for the laws of physics?
I think it's so that we can build a sense of trust
between the player and the game.
Players encounter in-game events
they've observed in the real world
and come to believe in the game's particular set of rules.
And that's the basis for the clever lies we tell in games.
And of course, the Zelda series is no exception to this.
Past titles have made ample use of game physics
to make performing actions and solving puzzles
more intuitive.
How to tell a clever lie,
or how to express a phenomenon unique to the virtual world,
is one of the fun things about programming.
One of the joys of being a programmer is deciding just how to go about telling our clever lies
and how to best express the things that happen in an imaginary world. 今作でもせっかく広大なフィールドが舞台なので、それが生かせるスケールの大きなゲーム物理を作りたいと考えていました。
Given that this game was supposed to take place in a vast world,
I felt it deserved a correspondingly robust game physics that would help bring it to life.
YOSHIMASA ENJI, JPNICI EDITOR-IN-CHIEF
On the other hand, creating a high degree of freedom
had been an important theme for us
since the earliest stages of development.
YOSHIMASA ENJI, JPNICI EDITOR-IN-CHIEF
For example, the freedom to carry any object you like
to any location in the game.
If you try hard enough, you can roll this rock
from the beginning of the game
to the place you fight the final boss.
But of course, in a physics simulation,
you have to make this sort of thing possible
in a set of complex and near infinite situations.
The development resources associated with creating this type of physics simulation would be immense, but we were dead set on making the physics in this game fun.
We realized that if we continued using the same approach we had in previous games, we'd run out of steam long before reaching our goal.
And so, after running some tests, we decided to use Havok to help create our physics simulation.
The stability and robustness of the engine,
not to mention its proven track record in the game industry,
made Havoc an appealing choice.
This would enable us to tell all the clever lies we wanted.
The new action and items introduced in Breath of the Wild
have made the most use of game physics.
This is the result of putting a lot of effort into the parts we really want to make.
Most of the actions and items we've introduced in Breath of the Wild rely heavily on game physics.
This came from being able to focus our efforts on the elements we most wanted to make.
Let me show you a few examples.
First is Stasis, a rune that allows you to stop the effects of time on specific objects.
It may look as though it's simply stopped, but internally the object is working hard
to maintain its stasis.
It's the law of conservation of energy, except really that's a lie.
It feels right in the moment it happens, but makes less sense the more you stop and think
about it.
Game physics are at their best when they let you create things like this that can't exist
in reality.
Next up is Magnesis, a rune which allows you to move metal objects at will.
It looks like magnetism, but it isn't actually.
Instead, it's something like magnetism.
The point here is to prevent instability
from a programming perspective
without sacrificing control for the player.
And here's the rock climbing
that Mr. Fujibayashi also mentioned.
We have connected the link to the wall by creating a constant between the link and the wall.
This implementation is done by a programmer, and thanks to this, it is now possible to climb objects that move.
The part that solves the constant is made into a haboku.
By creating a dynamic constraint between Link and the surface he's climbing, we connect him to it.
The programmer in charge of this climbing movement really focused on getting it right,
and thanks to that effort, we were able to make Link climb moving objects in a satisfying way.
And it's Havoc that did the work of solving the issue of constraint for us.
The act of cutting down a tree is made possible by a false sort of destruction.
The moment the tree begins to fall, it transforms into a log object.
When the log falls into the water, it floats. This ability to float in water holds an important
meaning for game design.
When an object floats in the game,
it means you've invented a unique,
but illusory kind of floating.
Now, I'd like to get back to the theme
of multiplicative gameplay that Mr. Fujibayashi mentioned.
As we tried to think of a game physics,
we realized one thing.
If we connect the world with consistent physics,
we'll want to try more and more things.
In our various experiments of trial and error with game physics, there was one thing that we noticed.
If you unify your game world with a set of consistent physics rules,
the player will come up with ideas for all sorts of things they want to try.
So for example, this metal slab is placed here to allow you to cross this river.
But once you pick it up, you might find yourself suddenly wanting to try dropping it on top of an enemy.
Once you see that log floating on the river, it's natural to want to try jumping on it.
Just riding a log down a river seems like it would be fun. You might remember this from the prototype earlier.
動くものにも登れるということは、巨大な敵の体に登れたらどういう戦いが作れるか。 And if you can climb moving objects, what sort of battle would unfold if you were fighting a giant enemy that you could climb? ステーシスで勢いをつけたオブジェクトに登ると、さて何が起きるか。
What would happen if you climbed an object that you'd charged up with energy using stasis?
YOSHIMASA ENJI, JR.: My point is that I ended up getting
flooded with ideas like this.
My excitement was coming not from my perspective
as a developer, but as a player.
YOSHIMASA ENJI, JR.: What if I tried that?
Or wait, maybe this.
This would be a world where combining simple elements could produce complex results, where
you'd feel the thrill of imagining the things you wanted to try as you played.
I realized that was the game we should try to make.
Now, I'd like to switch topics a bit.
These two are members of our development team.
They're discussing just how we should go about breaking these conventions of ours.
Looks like they're having a good time.
This must be a heartfelt conversation.
Okay now it looks like things are really heating up.
It was during this discussion that a certain key word was born.
If physics engines are such a thing, why don't you ever hear about chemistry engines?
As you likely know, the Zelda series has long made use of the sort of events that occur
in chemistry as in-game elements.
Just like with physics, creating puzzles with solutions that reference the way the real
world works can help players solve them instinctively.
We decided to develop a chemistry engine.
So what exactly is this chemistry engine?
In other words, it is a computer that calculates motion based on rules.
One way of describing a physics engine is as a rule-based movement calculator.
In comparison, we decided the chemistry engine would be a rule-based state calculator.
I mentioned this before, but action games are made up of collision plus movement plus changing states.
And it's our chemistry engine that calculates these changes in the state of things.
So I'd like to give a simple explanation of our design to show just what sort of calculations
are being run by this chemistry engine.
First, we refer to things like fire, water, and ice that don't hold a constant solid form as elements.
Next, we refer to objects such as players, weapons, and other objects as materials.
Next, we call solid objects like trees and rocks,
even the player character and weapons, materials.
The chemistry engine uses these things to make its calculations based on three simple rules.
First up is rule one.
Elements can change the state of materials.
So the leaves on the tree burn up and disappear.
Next is rule two.
Elements are able to change each other's states.
So the fire disappeared when it came in contact
with the water.
And finally, rule three, materials cannot influence each other's states.
So you can see neither of them changed.
And that's the chemistry engine in a nutshell.
The model is an extremely simple one, but allows for the expression of all sorts of
events.
Whoa!
What's that?
All these types of interactions in the game are realized by the chemistry engine.
Wait, are electricity and wind a part of chemistry?
In a textbook, the answer is of course no, but in the chemistry engine, you bet they
are.
Aside from rigid body dynamics, we consider all phenomena that occur in nature to be chemistry.
And so for our purposes, things like wind and electricity
are all considered to be elements.
Again, treating them this way gives us a simplified method
with which to model the world.
WAREWARE WA BAKEGAKU WO SAIGEN SURU ENJIN GA TSUKURITAKATTA
ON DEWA ARIMASEN.
It's not that we wanted to create an engine that
replicates chemistry.
IKKANSEI NO ARU OBUJEKUTO NO SUTEITO KEISANKI GA
TSUKURITAKATTA ON DESU.
Instead, we wanted to create a state calculator for all these
objects that are connected to one another.
There's one other reason we referred to this sort of thing as chemistry.
During development, we called this multiplicative gameplay we were trying to create chemical
reaction play.
This engine is the device that makes this sort of play possible, so in that way too, it can be considered chemistry.
Elements can generate energy and impact the physical world.
This is how the world is connected to the rules of physics and chemistry.
Given the right situation, elements can also generate energy and impact the physical world.
In this way, all the constituent parts of the world we created are governed by our rules of physics and chemistry.
And with that, we had the game that we had hoped to make, one that used multiplication
to increase the things you were able to do.
Earlier, Mr. Fujibayashi posed the question,
how can we create a game that uses multiplication
to expand gameplay?
It turns out our answer to this was
to build connections between everything in the world.
SPEAKER 2 IN JAPANESE
This means that everything you see in the game
is linked together, so to speak.
SPEAKER 1 IN JAPANESE
And these connections don't simply occur by accident.
Instead, they're intentionally designed
to have an overall consistency and to feel instinctive.
And of course, they contain all sorts of those clever lies
we like to tell.
We didn't have a firm belief in this approach from the start.
So we took the 2D approach to make the prototyping process as fast as possible.
And that's what we call 2D Zelda.
But when we started out, we had no guarantee
that this sort of approach would work.
So I used 2D graphics to quickly create a prototype
as a proof of concept.
That was the image of 2D Zelda that you saw earlier.
The merit of 2D prototyping is that you can clearly
symbolize the game and build the logic.
2D prototyping is handy in that it allows you
to reduce the game to a set of symbols
and clearly display the logic behind an idea.
As you can see, this prototype is actually in 3D, and under the hood there were early
versions of our physics and chemistry engines at work.
In the world of Breath of the Wild, this multiplicative gameplay is found in the space between situations and goals.
If you can see these connections between elements in the world, the scenery around you takes on new meaning and poses questions to you.
It should also inspire you to experiment and try out all sorts of ideas.
We've filled every corner of the game world with these sets of situations and goals.
And of course, we've envisioned correct ways to solve each of them.
But that's not to say we want the player to search for and find those correct answers.
Instead, we want them to have fun thinking up and trying solutions on their own.
Having listened to our presentation up to this point,
have you found yourselves puzzling out your own answers
to the situations we've shown on screen?
Even if it's a little inefficient or an unexpected shortcut,
as long as you enjoy the experience of thinking, trying, and completing it,
I think that's the right answer to this game.
If thinking up, trying out, and eventually finding roundabout solutions or unexpected
shortcuts is fun, then I think that in itself is the correct way to play this game.
One convention we broke with in making Breath of the Wild
was to create a world where fun occurs through multiplication,
as opposed to one in which fun elements are simply
added together in a sum total.
Action, the field design, and the object.
By multiplying actions with the design of the play field
and the objects placed on it, you
create a situation in which almost anything can occur.
and provide a more dynamic and free gaming experience.
I hope you enjoy the puzzle solving process.
It was our aim to deliver a more active and open-ended play experience.
And I hope players will enjoy coming up with their own unique solutions to the game's puzzles and challenges.
I really want players to relish those moments where you do something and think, oh my gosh,
I'm a genius.
Now, changing subjects, I want to show you an email we received during development of
the Wii U version of the game.
We were given the additional mission of releasing the game for Nintendo Switch.
And that's a producer for you.
He has even more of that courage to say than Mr. Fujibayashi.
But to cut to the chase, adapting the game for the Nintendo Switch was easier than we thought it would be.
That's my honest opinion as a game developer, and I'll sum up what I mean.
And that's my honest opinion as a game developer, and I'll sum up what I mean.
First, the SDK really helped us with this point.
The Nintendo SDK is the standard development environment for the Nintendo Switch.
First, the SDK helped us out quite a bit.
The Nintendo SDK is the standard development environment for Nintendo Switch.
On the hardware side as well, the attributes you can see
on screen gave it a versatile architecture
that was easy to work with.
I have been involved in the development of all platforms
such as Nintendo DS, Wii, 3DS, and Wii U since GameCube,
but this was the first time I had to implement a tricky
implementation that was conscious of architecture.
I've developed games for the GameCube, Nintendo DS, the Wii, 3DS, and Wii U, but this was
the first time there was no need to implement any tricky workarounds because of hardware
architecture.
When the game first started running, it didn't have any optimization, but the framerate
was more than the same as the Wii U.
When we first got the Nintendo Switch version running,
but had yet to do any optimization,
we were already seeing frame rates equal to or better
than the Wii U version.
And we started thinking about how to make Breath of the Wild
more appealing to this platform.
We also began thinking of ways to use Breath of the Wild
to show off the appeal of the platform itself.
Nintendo Switch has a variety of gimmicks, including Joy-Con,
and we are very proud of the game design using these gimmicks.
But Breath of the Wild does not use them.
The Nintendo Switch features a number of unique play elements,
with the Joy-Con controllers being the most obvious example,
and I think we excel at designing games that take advantage of these tools for play.
However, Breath of the Wild doesn't include anything like this.
For Breath of the Wild, we wanted to deliver the same game design to players on both the Wii U and Nintendo Switch.
But looking back on our previous hardware, we've always had launch titles that carry the additional duty of making the appeal of the hardware easy to see.
What did we want to convey with Breath of the Wild?
But then, what did we want to try and convey with this version of the game?
It's the novelty of being able to take it with you anywhere you go.
And without any special game design, you can get this added value automatically.
We were the first ones to be surprised by this.
We wanted to share this surprise with our customers and developers.
I don't think there is a title as easy to enjoy as Breath of the Wild.
In the final stretch, we made some improvements to graphic and audio quality,
and Breath of the Wild for Nintendo Switch was complete.
There's one last thing that the Nintendo Switch made possible for the game.
This is our team staff looking at the screen.
They're looking at the screen and saying,
The gentleman you see staring at the screen
is one of the members of our development team.
The game's moving and all he's doing is staring at it.
According to him, this was just the most comfortable way to play.
Breath of the Wild is a game about freedom.
By bringing it to Nintendo Switch, we extended that freedom to being able to choose your preferred play style.
This play style isn't necessarily the correct one that we envisioned,
but if this makes the game fun to play for you, then that becomes your correct way to play on Nintendo Switch.
That brings my part of the presentation to an end. Thank you very much.
Finally, we'll move into discussing how we gave this complex world its art style.
I'll leave that to our art director, Mr. Takizawa, the man with the Triforce of the
Power to Show.
Hello everyone.
I am the art director of The Legend of Zelda Breath of the Wild.
Satoru Takizawa.
I've spent most of my time at Nintendo as an artist
on development of The Legend of Zelda series.
Let's start by taking a look at some of the artwork trial and error
for Breath of the Wild.
Here are some concept sketches of the main character, Link.
And here are design sketches of the ancient ruins that appear in the game.
Thanks for watching!
Next up, Hyrule Wars.
Link in Kyoto.
And here's an invasion from outer space.
Yeah, this is where things got a bit dodgy.
Jar-Jr. Link.
Track suit link.
Rider link.
Biker link.
Musician link.
Link in Metroid.
We had a lot of ideas.
Finally, this is the design we settled on for the ancient ruins.
And here's the final design for Link.
Now let's take a look at some screenshots from the completed game.
So today I'd like to talk about why we chose this art style
and some universal topics that arise in art creation.
That is to say, what remained constant.
So first, let's take a look at the Zelda titles
I've been involved with.
Ocarina of Time.
The Majora's Mask.
The tech demo we revealed for GameCube at Nintendo Spaceworld.
The Wind Waker.
Twilight Princess.
Skyward Sword.
It's been 30 years since the launch of the NES Zelda.
I've only been involved in a small portion of the Zelda titles, but even so, something
that struck me about this long-running series is how aggressively the game system has been
changed each time.
I think that's a fairly rare thing.
In order to meet this challenge, the artists have had to continually search for art style that makes it easy to lie.
So what is art style that makes it easy to lie?
It's an art style that suits the game while fulfilling the playability demands without losing a feeling of reality.
What is playability?
So what's playability?
Playability is the comfort of the game, in other words, the behavior and appearance that are in line with the function.
What makes a game comfortable in terms of game cycle and response?
the pleasantness of behaviors or visuals based on gameplay,
or in other words, function.
For a game, the optimization of the pleasantness
of the game cycle and response is
the most important thing.
A reality players can sink into.
This is also very important.
As you move further away from realness, both tempo and visibility improve and the level of pleasantness increases, but the reality of the world is apt to be lost.
However, if you focus too much on the realism of the movement, you will lose a pleasant game cycle and response.
That being said, if you place too much importance on the realness of behavior and presentation,
you can damage a pleasant game cycle and responsiveness.
So what is a suitable art style that makes these two elements compatible in a good way?
That is art that makes it easy to lie.
So after Skyward Sword, how did art that makes it easy to lie have to change to bring Zelda into the HD era?
This question was the beginning of the trial and error process which led us to the art style of Breath of the Wild.
This is the tech demo HD Experience that was released in 2011.
We tried to make it look more realistic by adjusting the resolution of the screen.
Here is the tech demo HD Experience we showed at E3 in 2011.
In response to the adoption of high resolution screens, we took a straightforward approach and filled the screen with a lot of detail.
While doing PBR, physically based rendering tests, we tried our hand at creating common cityscapes as well.
We threw models from previous titles into our new development environment and tried some HD mockups.
Skyward Sword.
Here's Skyward Sword.
Not sure why, but the gang's all here.
Twilight Princess.
Here's Twilight Princess.
And the Wind Waker.
This new Wind Waker art stood out from the other HD mock-ups and really captured the imagination of the lead artists on Breath of the Wild, myself included.
This art guarantees playability from all aspects, including visibility and action, and still
allows for the construction of a unique reality.
It's an art style with which it's super easy to lie.
It has great originality and has remained fresh even after 10 years.
And it feels good to play.
This led to the official creation of the Wind Waker HD remake.
It's also connected to something that happened one day and led directly to the
finalization of the art direction for Breath of the Wild.
One day during the final stages of the Wind Waker HD development process, I was summoned by Breath of the Wild director, Mr. Fujibayashi, and producer, Mr. Aonuma.
Mr. Fujibayashi pointed to a Wind Waker HD screen and said,
This, right here.
Right? I replied.
The other artists and I were in complete agreement, so I did not hesitate to speak up.
Mr. Aonuma said, I agree.
And with that, it was decided.
The whole thing took less than a minute.
At the time, we were very surprised.
But during the development of Wind Tactics HD,
we saw how the world's realistic world was being expanded day by day,
without losing the original playability.
Looking back now, it may have been a natural match.
It was really surprising at the time, but looking back now and seeing how the game lost none of its originality or playability over the course of development of the Wind Waker HD,
plus the fact that the entire staff witnessed the solidification and expansion of the game's reality day after day, our agreement on the issue seems quite natural.
This is a bit off topic, but here's something that supported our common belief that we're good at this type of art creation.
The difference in the development of painting in Japan and the West,
and the way of liking that transcends the generations of manga and animation in Japan.
I think it will be a very interesting subject to consider, but I will omit it because the story will be left out.
The difference in the evolution of painting between the West and Japan.
We could have quite an interesting discussion if we began delving into how manga and animation art has crossed into a wider, more mainstream appeal in modern Japan,
but that's not why we're here, so we're going to have to save that for another time.
Now, back to the story.
Based on the wind's tact, we decided to consider further painting.
So let's get back to our discussion.
We continued with exploring art creation based on the Wind Waker and came up with our final art creation slogan.
Refreshing and full-flavored.
This is the very important art creation slogan we adopted for Breath of the Wild.
In Japan, I think a lot of people would hear this and want to have a beer.
How about you?
So, why did we choose this slogan?
There was actually one weak spot in the Wind Waker HD art style.
An important point in Mr. Fujibayashi's game concept
was to fill the vast game world with fun multiplicative experiences using physics and chemistry gameplay.
And this was difficult to achieve with the Wind Waker HD art style.
Why is that?
The Wind Waker art style, in its depiction of form, feel of materials, etc., is very stylized.
The game's physical and chemical gameplay is intuitively reminiscent of a real-life experience.
One of our goals was to have the art intuitively suggest possible physics and chemistry gameplay
based on the player's own experiences in the real world.
The problem with the Wind Waker art style is the lies it told were too big.
Another point is that if you can understand everything that is shown on the screen in an instant,
you will be seen as a child.
So, you will be seen as someone who is older than you,
and you will be seen as someone who has nothing to do with you.
There was also another concern with the Wind Waker art style.
The concern was if older players could look at the screen for just an instant and understand
everything they were seeing, they might feel the art was intended for children and was
not for them.
So...
Based on the art on something easy to tell lies with, like the Wind Waker art, we could more easily guarantee function conforming to playability, and more easily construct the reality within the game.
Above and beyond that,
A high-definition, mature-like illustration that has a certain realism that allows you to imagine what anyone can do based on the real world.
We needed to suggest things anyone could do in the real world,
so we needed a certain level of realism,
and we needed an information-dense, mature art style.
Our goal of supporting these elements equally led to refreshing and full-flavored.
So we made this our slogan, and it led to the establishment of the final art style.
Shader, lighting, model, terrain, effects, UI, weather, and environment were all part of this slogan.
Shaders, lighting, models, terrain, effects, UI, weather environments.
Our slogan is the foundation upon which all these sections constructed their designs and behaviors.
Considering the tempo and efficiency of Breath of the Wild's game cycle,
we needed a very quick response and event production,
but we were able to achieve this in the end.
So a fairly streamlined tempo and event presentation was necessary
to efficiently present the Breath of the Wild's game tempo and game cycle.
I'd like to show you the results of our being able to realize this
as more than just a requirement.
You're carrying an axe and see a tree you want to chop down.
You hit the log with your axe and poof! In an instant you have bundles of firewood.
They're even conveniently tied up with rope.
Shoot a boar and poof! It's a haunch of raw meat.
Birds, poof! Same story.
You can even get acorns. Gathering foodstuffs is speedy business.
Here's Link eating.
This is perfect fast food, right?
And here's Link running around with some ingredients.
If I had to make that look realistic,
I'm not sure what I would've done.
That's one needle I would not have been able to thread.
And here's Link cooking.
Figured ingredients are tossed into the pot
where they do a little dance
and become something delicious.
It's all automatic.
Yaku, niru, itameru, sweets, subete okey.
Roasting, boiling, sauteing, baking, it's all good.
Bin made support.
Even bottles are supplied.
Kono chiisana kaito de gake kara tobioriru yuuki.
Jumping from a cliff with just a little kite takes a lot of courage.
In reality, you wouldn't be able to stop so quickly.
When you come across updrafts, you're going to want to give them a try.
You can even transition into shield surfing.
Nice print.
Here's Link doing some wall climbing.
He resembles a famous American comic book hero, but Link is barehanded.
I'll never forget how the blood drained from the faces of our terrain and players' artists' faces when they learned of this climbing feature.
It's so cold!
So what do you think?
So if you imagine these actions and whatnot in the real world, what we've presented might be considered impermissibly comedic.
When all the poofs and dancing foodstuffs were implemented, I didn't feel the absurdity of it, but rather the fun of it.
It was the moment I felt we had come up with the answer to what this game needed in its art style.
So this title's art style is...
The reconciliation of the conflict between playability and reality.
It's the result of our quest for art that makes it easy to lie to match this game known as Breath of the Wild.
This is without a doubt the same trial and error process we've done throughout the history of the Zelda series.
The final art style appears different from any other title, but you can say it's the constant we reached as a result of our universal thought process.
Now, that alone is not enough to create a stunning work of art.
However, this alone does not get us to the creation of gutto-kuru art.
Do you understand gutto-kuru?
In Japan, when we remember something that stirs the soul, we use the phrase gutto-kuru to capture that feeling.
You can't create good-looking art, or a world just with art that makes it easy to lie.
To create an appealing, never-before-seen world filled with new surprises, you need to break conventions.
You need to be creatively reckless.
You can't create good-looking art, or a world just with art that makes it easy to lie.
To create an appealing, never-before-seen world filled with new surprises, you need to break conventions.
You need to be creatively reckless.
And perhaps it's safe to say, in some ways, we game creators really enjoy violent work.
In what way did our artists
Add that guttokuru feeling to their art, they rack their brains each and every day throughout development to fully manifest their individuality. アーティストの皆さんには共感していただけると思いますが、ここが一番楽しいところだと言っても過言ではありませんよね。
I think all the artists here today will empathize with me when I say it's not going too far to call this the most enjoyable part of the process.
While art directors don't get to decide on functions or guidelines, when the chance arrives to choose between multiple art styles or designs,
I have the authority to let loose the somewhat reckless triforce of the power to show to
choose what we believe will gutto kuru, stir some souls.
I think it's possible that at this pre-launch point in time, I'm the man who's had his soul stirred most by the art of Breath of the Wild.
I hope from the bottom of my heart that the entire world will explore the vastness of Hyrule and have their souls stirred again and again just as I did.
And finally, I would like to invite Mr. Fujibayashi, the Triforce of the Dragon-Spirit of Itemi.
All right, let me turn it back over to the holder of the Triforce of the Courage to Say,
Mr. Fujibayashi, to wrap things up.
We had the Triforce of Courage, the courage to be able to say whatever needs to be said, to bring about a new way to play a game.
The Triforce of Wisdom, the wisdom to bring all of the game logic into reality.
And the Triforce of Power, the power to construct a world of Zelda from all of the above.
As you've seen in our talk today, along our path to bring this game to completion,
the three of us, as well as the development team,
made some significant changes to some elements, while leaving others as they are.
I hope you were able to see that breaking conventions means to change,
but it can also mean to not change, to keep things as they are.
Zelda was born in 2016 and has been supported by fans for 30 years.
In 2016, Zelda celebrated its 30th anniversary with the support of all its fans.
Breath of the Wild is a culmination of this long history of development.
It is a new game, but at the same time re-examines the fun that lies at the essence of the franchise.
and if this discovery is a key to future game development,
I have no greater joy.
Thank you for your attention today.
If you found our discussion today interesting,
please give Breath of the Wild a try.
I think you'll be able to make new and interesting discoveries,
and nothing would make us happier
if some of these new discoveries provide you with a clue
or inspiration for your future game development.
Thank you very much for attending our panel today.
Thank you.