Thanks for being awake at 10 a.m. on a Tuesday, everybody.
Don't forget to turn off your cell phones, fill out the
questionnaire at the end, all that good stuff. And also, we
are hoping to have enough time for a little bit of Q&A at the
end, but rather than use the microphones, we are going to ask
you to tweet questions to at Steve Swink as you go along.
So keep those questions in mind.
And also we'll go to the wrap up room after this.
By the way panelists,
we're gonna go to the wrap up room after this.
Okay.
So right, this panel features five panelists,
all of whom have released games into the marketplace.
And those games feature a range of success
to not so success.
Embodies different platforms,
different approaches to the market,
different backgrounds in indie games.
And as Steve mentioned,
our goal is to elevate this discussion with hard data,
both from our own businesses,
researched from the internet and other places.
And also some speculation and subjective ideas as well.
One thing we all agree on is that this word is super crappy.
It's very button pushing and reductionist.
It implies things that no one here believes in.
So we think of this as like a market phenomenon,
maybe a slump or a downturn.
And we're hoping to address all of these types of topics.
First panelist is Jeff Vogel.
He is the president of SpiderWeb Software.
They've been making indie games for 20 years
and because of the consistency in these games,
Jeff has been in a great position to notice market trends
and this has made him a high profile indiepocalypse blogger
in the past few years.
We have Rebecca Saltzman, CEO of Finji. This is a small
publisher and developer of recognized indie games who
stretches all the way back to cannibals. They recently
released panoramical and feist. And they have upcoming releases
overland and night in the woods. We have Ayman Ibrajagic who is
a game designer and PR manager of coffee stain studios. Best
known for the wildly successful goat simulator. But he's also
going to be talking about the sanctum series of games.
This is Jordan Thomas, the co-owner of Question who
recently released Magic Circle. He's a recent addition from the
mainstream industry where he worked on the BioShock series
among other things. And myself, I'm Randy Smith, co-owner of
TigerStyle, we're best known for iOS releases. There's two spider
games in Waking Mars and we have a little bit of a foothold in
the Steam market as well.
So is the indie apocalypse a real thing? We've all read those
blog posts about indies not making as much money these days.
Sometimes lots, lots less money. We've heard scary stories about
games that should have been successful but weren't. I've
unfortunately heard a couple since I've arrived at GDC this
year. This is usually contextualized as a relationship
of supply versus demand. Supply is going up, demand isn't
keeping pace.
One of our biggest market places is obviously steam.
And the data we're looking at here and all of our steam data is credited to the steam
spy guy who generously provided this stuff.
And what we're looking at is how many games were released each year into steam.
And you can see obviously it curves up.
The green light is considered one of the horsemen of the indie apocalypse.
This is where it was launched in August of 2012.
about a year later is the first time a batch of 100 games was
green lit at once. And by the end of 2014 we have many
hundreds of games being green lit in just a few days. So no
big surprise here. You open the flood gates there's more supply
in the market. Looking at demand we can take a look at owners. So
what this is the total number of owners for all those games
released in that year. So for all 86 games released in 2010 if
you add up all their owners it's something like $17.1 million.
Now there's an obvious upward trend here.
and the reason it goes down in 2015 is because those games came
out more recently and they had less time to accrue owners. So
it's hard to know exactly where this should be but probably we
can assume it's at least as big as 2014. Now there's a really
important disclaimer here that because of the way the steam spy
algorithms work if a game accrues less than 1,000 new
owners per month the margin of error for that data is enormous.
So there's a lot of noise in this data. I included the high
margin of error noise data.
So we can put both of those sets of data on the same graph and
we can even divide total owners by total games. And so the peak
here is in 2011 with just shy of like half a million owners per
game. But importantly that's just really crude math. There's
no mythical average game. But what we do see is this general
downward trend.
The reason we use owners as a metric is because valve doesn't
make public steam's total sales numbers each year. But steam
spy was able to estimate the size of the market and hot off
the presses here for the first time ever thanks to Sergey again
the steam spy guy. We have some numbers which estimate the size
of indie games market in particular. So there's some
important disclaimers I mentioned below. Most
importantly because Sergey is a lot more rigorous about data
than I am. He refused to include any games that accrue less than
1,000 owners per month.
that includes a lot of indie games. But basically what we can
see here is that valve processes significantly more than $1
billion of indie game sales every year and it's right around
one third of their overall games market. So that's pretty cool
stuff. Turning our attention to the mobile market, this is data
published by statista. Some important disclaimers, this is
just Apple, the app store.
games. It's not indie games. It's all games. And moreover,
only the dark blue part of this bar is games. The rest of it is
like all apps. So what we're looking at is between July 2008
and July 2015. This is the number of apps in the app store
total in the thousands. So we're approaching 2 million apps by
the middle of 2015.
And then demand, this is sort of covering the same time frame
and what we're looking at is the number of downloads in the
billions. And so we're approaching 100 billion
downloads by 2015. So you can really crudely superimpose these
two graphs in photoshop and see if there's anything worth
noting. It kind of looks like in 2011 and 2012 supply is growing
faster than demand.
catch back up by 2014. There is a disclaimer here of course
which is that free to play. The freemium apps are only about 11
percent of the apps on the app store but they acquire 92 percent
of the revenue. This is the beginning of 2015. So free to
play is another one of the horsemen of the indie apocalypse.
It was introduced in the middle of 2009. March 2011 is the
first time freemium revenue overtook premium revenue and it
never went back.
want to be clear it's very easy to be misleading with data even
if you're not intending to be. As a primary example those prior
slides don't prove it's harder to succeed today than it was in
2012. For example I heard a theory that a lot of newcomers
to the market are hobbyists and they're not taking out more
demand than they're putting in.
That's a possibility. We did our best to do this 100% properly
as a month long research project for each of us. That's not what
we did. But we are going to try to present you with some good
information anyway. So here we go. Without further ado. Let's
bring up Jeff Vogel. That was terrifying. I just want to go
back to my hotel room and cry. Hi, I'm Jeff.
check, check. Okay, who am I? Why am I standing here? I run a
little mom and pop shop called spider web software. We're based
in Seattle. We are older than the stones and the dirt. There's
my URL, Twitter and a blog upon which I've written a fair amount
on this topic, which is why I'm standing here.
And what do we do? We write fantasy role playing games.
Really old school, cheap, retro, Mac, Windows, iPad, Linux and
Android. I can get someone to do the port for me. Very text
heavy, very story heavy. Most importantly, all of our games
while not identical are very similar. That will become
relevant when comparing sales later on. Here is a list of our
games. Don't be ashamed if you haven't heard any of any of
them.
I don't write hits. Don't get me wrong, I love hits, I'd love to
have one, but I'm more, I'm in the business of writing
respectable niche titles in order to make a respectable
middle class income. Here is a picture of my latest game for
the iPad. You can see that, you know, it's fine. It's basic,
it's simple, it's functional. I mean, it's not going to set the
world on fire, but I'm also not publicly soiling myself either.
So I want to talk about the Indie glut, the Indie boom and
bust, or as it is commonly known, an economic phenomenon I
believe called the business cycle, which is much discussed
and I will get back to in more detail in just a minute.
When I wrote about this, I used the term the Indie Bubble,
which is a really nice click-baity title.
It got me a lot of attention.
It is not technically true.
It is not a classic speculative bubble in any way.
I also will not be using the word Indiepocalypse,
not because the word is silly, childish, and reductive.
I like things that are silly, childish, and reductive.
I'm just not really going to use the word because it's basically inaccurate.
There is no apocalypse.
Indie games aren't going to go away because we're awesome and people love what we do.
But business circumstances change and we need to pay attention.
So I'm going to tell you a little very brief story about
what I think happened that will require proof. And I'm going to
be chipping in some of my sales figures just to point in the
direction of what might be going on. This is just going to be a
few points of data. It's not going to prove anything, but it
is a start towards accumulating data and telling stories. So
what's the story?
Around 2008, there was an influence of three big events.
First of all, AAA development could arguably be called
very stagnant with not a lot of innovation.
A lot of people were getting kind of tired
of what they were doing.
At the same time, a bunch of indie developers
showed that they could really bring it,
could really bring really compelling,
awesome, high-quality products to market.
While at the same time, indie-friendly stores like
Xbox Live, like iTunes, like Steam became available.
And as someone who's scrambled for individual sales
on CompuServe in the 1990s can tell you,
Steam is an infinite bag of miracles.
Indie games became really hot all of a sudden. There was a big
demand for them. People like me who had a back catalog that went
on for days were able to make far more money than we deserved.
Demand became really high. Oh, my God, indie games are cool. A
lot of people flooded into the market. A lot of indie games
started being written because people wanted to follow their
dreams. Demand is really high. Supply goes up to meet demand.
So what happened was...
First, and this happens all the time in all sorts of businesses, there's a growth period,
a new market with a lot of demand appears. People see that there's money to be made,
they flood in, supply goes up to meet demand, but the supply keeps coming in. That's when
you pass the peak and you enter what I believe we have been in for a while now, which is
the recession period, which is the long, gruesome, agonizing, bloody process where the supply,
also known as human beings following their dreams, goes down until it meets demand.
There are some hard realities. Human beings only own finite
money. There's only a finite number of gaming websites. They
only have a finite number of space to put new articles. If
titles keep flooding in, there's just not enough. And that's what
leads to the painful recession process that I believe is
happening. But there is no apocalypse. Indie games aren't
going anywhere. We're a thing. We're a billion-dollar-a-year
business. That's amazing. There's just going to be the
occasional adjustment and the occasional necessary shrinkage.
Was anything I just said true, really?
I'm going to tell you sales from my last four games and you can
see my story and make your judgments from there. I'm going
to be talking about my last four retro role-playing games.
There's Avedon and Avedon 2, which are new IP, and Avernum and
Avernum 2, which are remasters of older games. For comparing,
it's better to compare games from like series. You can see
the years they came out. Earlier was very much when indie games
were go, go, hooray, and the last one came out last year when
maybe not so much. I had to raise the price for the fourth
game because I had to.
so my business wouldn't explode.
It's hard to do research on this topic,
because it's hard to compare two games,
because comparing sales of two games is really
apples and oranges, which is why I think I can be useful,
because my games are really similar.
They all have the same style.
They're all the same sort of game.
They're all for the same platform.
They all get most of their sales from the same place.
They all do their PR in the usual
word-of-mouth bargain basement kind of way.
There's just a couple differences I'll point out for the sake of intellectual rigor.
The earlier games got a lot more press and a lot more bundle coverage, although I think
that's more of a factor of it being early in the indie boom before the glut happened.
And also obviously the earlier games have been out longer so they've had more time to
get sales.
But all of these games are well past their initial sales surge.
All of these games are in long tail territory.
I'm going to tell you two things. I'm going to tell you the number of copies sold on Steam and the amount of earnings on Steam.
The key difference here is that number of sales on Steam will include Humble Bundle and other bundles.
But it will not include the money from Humble Bundle.
So the sales numbers are going to be really high but a lot of
those sales were for a dime each because yay 2015. There is a
lot of inexactness. It's hard to do economics research sometimes
so I'm going to need to ask for a certain amount of forgiveness.
So here are the actual numbers. I'm going to draw your attention
to Avidon and Avidon 2 first. So you can see that in between
2010 and 2013 there was a fair amount of drop in numbers of
sales.
there was less interest. There was still some, still getting
bundle interest in Avedon 2 which is why the number is
fairly high. But you can see that the actual amount of cash
made was a lot lower because everyone was waiting, at that
point everyone had learned just wait for the bundle. Avernum 2
very much the same thing. Avernum got a fair amount of
bundle interest. Avernum 2 has gotten basically no bundle
interest.
But, you know, maybe I'll offer one of the humble bundle guys a car or something.
The number of sales, therefore, went way down.
And, of course, the earnings went down quite a lot as well.
I'm going to have to ask you to take my word for it that the quality of these games is roughly similar.
The user reception among the people who actually bought it was roughly similar.
You can verify that somewhat by looking at Steam reviews if you want.
All of my other games on other platforms have followed the same
pattern. I don't really have time to go into that and also a
lot of those figures I just don't have access to it anymore.
So this is again another take my word for it and maybe sometime
I'll do a longer talk.
The big story, the big lesson from this story is that the game
business is hard. And it's a tough, competitive, miserable
blood sport kind of business. And there was a time when a lot
of people were making a lot of money and it became possible to
forget that. But now people have to remember in the games
business, success should always surprise you. Failure should
never surprise you. That's the cost you pay for living your
dreams. That's my story.
Unfortunately there are a certain number of people who
are going out of business and that will continue until life
becomes tolerable for those few who survive. Have a great day,
kids!
That was awesome. Thank you, Jeff.
So please welcome to the podium Rebecca Saltzman, CEO and
cofounder of Fingy. I have to push a start button for you. I'm
looking at a spinning pin wheel. Okay. Cool. We got it. Okay.
You're on.
Hey, my name is Becca Saltzman.
I'm the CEO and co-founder of Finji.
I run the studio in Austin, Texas with Adam Atomic Saltzman.
We've been doing this since 2006.
That's about how long the studio's been around,
under various names.
I handle the business, legal, financial aspects
of the entire studio.
I also basically take care of our publishing branch.
I also do writing and design on our games,
which people don't know.
So yeah, I do a lot of things.
I'm also a mom of two kids, and they're crazy.
So that's me, that's my youngest, and that's where you can find me.
So I'm going to talk a little bit about first year revenue for our games, and these are
like actual legit numbers.
And you're looking and I'm thinking, holy crap.
That's really high. But it's not. Most people think
Canabalt made us like millions of dollars and like that is
legit not the case. Right now that number you're looking at is
715,000. That's like our lifetime revenue on Canabalt.
Which came out like what, six years ago? The first year, that
273, that's what we made in the first year.
These are some of our other titles that we've had.
Gravity Hook, First Year, 46,000, Lifetime, 54.
Hundreds, 437 in the first year.
It seemed really awesome.
Look at our lifetime.
Likewise, Capsule.
about 6 grand so far, or 14 grand total.
And then our two most recent titles
that were released last year, both of which
are IGF-nominated games.
Feist is currently at about 105.
Panoramical is at 33.
All of these numbers are pre-platform holder cuts.
So yeah, this next one's kind of interesting,
because you're like, that's a lot of money.
Nice job.
How do we actually work in this industry? We're all on rev share. This says how many rev share
owners are on each of these projects and about the average or the yearly average. But you have to
understand most of our income has been made in the first year. I want to point out specifically
hundreds, which looks like it's done great, but it made all of its money in the first year. It
didn't actually pay itself back.
So yeah, our highest revenue shareholder
would have averaged like $44,000 a year on Canabalt.
We've had three rev shareholders.
Panoramical has nine.
And that's how it works.
It doesn't actually come out to be much money when you start
cutting everything away.
So just for numbers sake or whatever, this is where the
majority of our income actually comes from. Obviously for
Feist and Panoramical the majority is from steam. We have
another category which would be weird deals that we've made with
various companies. GOG, itch.io.
So that's like our most recent PC release money.
And then our mobile games.
We've always done premium games on iOS.
We sell mostly on iOS.
That's where we've been.
We've had a really great partner with iOS.
But yeah, we've always been premium games.
We've never done freemium.
So our Android market's very little.
Now I'm going to talk a little bit about what
our expectations were before we released a lot of our games.
Cannibalt, we didn't have any. No expectations. Cannibalt went viral as a non-monetized
flash game. We didn't even have an ad on that. Hit like 10 million people in the first month.
We didn't even put an ad on it. We ported the game to IOS in under three weeks. What did it
have though? It was novelty. It was the first. It was an auto runner. It's like a whole genre
now. Added Wikipedia page. It's hilarious.
We had this weird media integration on twitter. Twitter was sort of a new thing at that
point. We also used the hardware properly. In 2009 people were still sticking virtual
d-pads. Which just kills me that that was like a thing.
Our next game gravity hook, why were the expectations so bad?
We've only made like 55,000 on this particular game.
And it took six months too long.
And we totally had a clone.
We were beat to market.
And we were late to market.
And the game was actually broken.
We didn't figure that out for a year.
There weren't enough things to grapple.
So good job us.
Hundreds took 18 months, it was 12 months late.
We thought it was gonna take six, it took 18.
We expected, because we were grownups at this point,
300,000 in the first year,
which we totally hit with Apple backing.
But that was our worst case number.
This paid back development for four people.
So it did not pay for our next project at all.
We only had about $100,000 maybe to go forward
to space out over four people.
We expected a long tail after a high launch,
and it dropped off significantly after the first 14 months.
And the Apple store, like the store started to change.
There's a race to the bottom.
People didn't want to pay that much for a premium game,
and they didn't want to pay money at all on games.
Capsule.
the game is about a fix this affix fixation for heaven's sakes like it's
slightly niche like if you don't get PTSD from playing this game like I don't
know who you are like are you a human are you a robot I we had no expectations
for this like it was a passion project Adam like sort of dives in on these
things he's like I got to do this
Feist, we just missed the F in boat entirely.
And I'm going to talk a little bit more about this.
But our worst case, like mine and Adam's absolute worst case
number on Feist was 100,000.
And we hit that.
So people are like, only 100,000 on Feist.
I'm like, dude, we hit our worst case number.
It's not a failure when you hit the number you expect.
And we hit that in four months.
panoramical. What the F. How do you market a game. Worst case
in revenue was 20,000 on that and we hit that in about four
months. So why? Why did we not make our Scrooge McDuck money?
What went wrong? We have had cloning problems. That's a
legit thing. We made a game about asphyxiation. Not exactly
like high popular title. Remember limbo?
like that awesome beautiful game that was in development at the
same time as Vice. Vice just took seven years too late. And
we underestimated the impact that that would have on the
market. We don't watch streamers. We're like old
people. We didn't realize that that was like a legit thing and
we undervalued that. And we didn't have the vocabulary
really to explain what panoramical was. How do you talk
to people about this?
We also have perceived clone ripoff problems with feist. Short
awareness build up. It was priced too high at $15. There's
things we just missed that we could have changed if we had had
a little bit more foresight, which now we have. Because we're
doing two new things. We have overland and night in the woods
coming out this year. Really, really awesome things. So what
are we doing now?
We're streamer friendly.
It's been from the ground up on Overland.
This is a game for streamers.
We're building in features that are for streamers specifically.
We're talking to streamers and asking what they want.
We have replay value. Feist is an incredibly beautiful
experience but it's like a two to three hour experience. How
much replay value is actually there? We didn't even put in
speed runs. That wasn't even a thing. We didn't have an
achievement for that or anything. You played feist and
you're like, that was nice but why would I ever play it again?
It's so ludicrously stupid looking back at it that we miss
that. So replay value. It's procedurally generated with
overland.
basically infinite. Art tokenism is just like people say your
games are so beautiful. We look for things and design for
iconic. We don't want someone to go like, oh, your game looks
like X, Y and Z. So we give a lot of like leeway for our art
designers to like do it, man. Own it. It's yours.
We have multiple releases scheduled, as many press bumps as possible. We're providing the
words for players to describe. We really hone down on exactly how we want people to talk
about our game. We have 100% team online presence and we push people. Our art designer for
Overland has like, you know, 100,000 plus Tumblr followers. And we sometimes end up on the
front page of Tumblr. And that's not because of us. It's because Heather's awesome. And
we're utilizing Heather to push the game forward. We're not shy about that.
We think project vulnerability is an asset.
We talk about our funding problems.
We talk about our crazy kids and our insane schedule
and how we budget and like we're real people
with real problems and we're in this industry
so we're humans and like that's a legit thing.
We want to be that.
so people can talk about us in a lot of different ways.
We also have cross-media appeal.
And we have mailing lists.
We talk to people outside of the traditional gaming press.
Like board game press, especially for Overland,
kind of a big deal.
There's a lot of cross-pollination there.
I can't believe I just used that word.
I'm sorry.
with night in the woods. What are we doing for this? It's
super style driven. Nothing looks like night in the woods.
This is Scott Benson. This is what he looks like. Kickstarter
the supplemental free stories. Direct email marketing. I mean,
I could go on forever. Creative marketing. The game size and
team story. These are things that are
directly correlated with this particular game when we talk
about this. And conventions, be not here, be at a convention.
It shows really, really well. So the pool is getting really,
really crowded. This isn't an apocalypse. It's an overcrowded
market. I told you I got kids and dogs. Because the barrier
to entry has been democratized. This is basic economics. You
have to step up your game. So don't go swimming without your
flotation device. Hedge your bets and hedge those bets and
hedge those bets because that's what we're doing and we have to.
Have a backup way to make money. You have to eat.
I'm going to be in the wrap up room afterwards.
Thank you Rebecca.
Okay.
And please welcome to the stage Armin whose last name I'll allow him to pronounce.
Thanks. Hi everyone. I'm Armin Ibrisagic. I work as a game designer and PR manager at Coffee Scene Studios.
And I'm going to talk a bit about our experience with the so-called indiepocalypse.
We've released actually not only Goat Simulator, we released a couple of other games on Steam as well.
I'm going to talk about Goat Simulator, but I'm also going to talk a lot about Sanctum 1 and Sanctum 2.
Because Sanctum 1 came out, you know, in the golden days of indies.
Sanctum 2 came out a little bit after that and six months after Sanctum 2 came out people
started whispering in the apocalypse. So I think they are really interesting games to look
at. When we released Sanctum 2 I noticed that it was a little bit different than when we
released Sanctum 1.
we, there was some loss in discoverability. My gut feeling was that people were a little bit
more reserved in 2013 and of course green light hit steam sometime after Sanctum 2 came out and
that was quite a big deal.
we've all been to steam spy. We've all looked at the numbers.
But what I think is really interesting is I did a quick
search at the words steam sale, steam holiday sale. And as you
can see it's not really big in 2011 but sometime around 2012,
2013 it just goes crazy. And if you've seen that meme with the
Gaben with the crown and dollar signs behind him. It has like a couple million views on
YouTube now. That's when people started talking a lot about the steam sales.
And so when we released Sanktum 2, those early award-winning games like, you know,
Braid, Limbo, Fez, if you've seen Indie Game, the movie, all those games from that movie
started going on 75% off. So what we noticed was that we're not just competing with the games that
are releasing right now, we're competing with the games that had like 95 in Metacritic score
and they're on 75% off.
There was a quote that a player said,
he was like, oh, I was such a huge fan of Sanctum 1,
can't wait till Sanctum 2 is on 75% off.
And as a developer you get pissed off. Is there a competition that I don't know about
that's all about giving as little money as possible to the developers that make games
that you love? But of course that's how consumers work. That's how I work. I'm not going to
go and buy a shirt that's really expensive just because I want to give as much money
as possible to the guys that made the shirt.
So that's something that we need to get used to.
When we made Sanctum 2, it had so much more content
than Sanctum 1.
Sanctum 1 released with like three levels.
Sanctum 2 came out with like 16 levels
with so many more enemies, more weapon variation.
it was just like bigger and better in every single way.
But it still sold roughly as well as Sanctum 2.
Which kind of, it messed us up.
Because you realize that, you know,
just because you make twice as much content,
that doesn't mean that you're gonna get twice as many sales.
And you know, maybe you don't think that's a big deal,
but when making twice as much content,
it costs you hundreds of thousands of dollars.
And that's, you know, it's quite a big deal to think about.
40 percent of the players never finished the first level in
Sanctum 2. We had an achievement when you finished the first
level and a lot of our players didn't even have that. Probably
because a lot of people bought our game on a sale, never
installed it. A lot of people bought our game, started it and
they were like, I'm going to make some food instead, do
something else. Can't be bothered. It was just $2.74
either way.
So that kind of opened up my eyes for that.
We made Sanctum 2, the purpose was that we're going to make the coolest,
we're like 20 employees at Coffee Stain, so we're like, we want to make the coolest
indie game that you can make, we want to set the bar for indie games.
We joked around that we were like small AAA,
lowercase AAA, and...
The purpose of Goat Simulator was just to make it the craziest thing we could possibly
conceive.
And of course, Goat Simulator was widely more successful than Segment 2.
This is the revenue on Steam for us, our games.
As you can see, Goat Simulator has...
One third of Goat Simulator has more than all our other games combined.
As you can see Sanctum 2 sold a little bit better than Sanctum 1 but I think that's mainly
because we discounted Sanctum 2 harder than we did with Sanctum 1. Why is the market like
this? I think it's because money isn't a bottleneck for consumers anymore. It's time.
Especially with humble bundles. You know, you pay one dollar you get like five award
winning indie games and one triple A game. So it's not like I don't have the money.
$14 to buy this game. It's more like I have a backlog of 100 games that I haven't played yet
So I don't want to buy any more games till I finish those
Steam doesn't have physical shelves. It's not like when you're at GameStop
You have you know like 50 games on shelves and they have them for six months
And then they remove them and replace them with new ones. They have all the games that ever released on Steam
So you're not competing with other people on your shelf. You're competing with every single game. That's ever released on Steam
And they're also on semi-pipes.
So I'm gonna get to, I've been very negative,
I'm gonna get to my more positive slide.
How do you release a game in today's market?
I think making a radically different game
just gives you a better chance of success
because it bypasses a lot of the barriers
that are on Steam right now,
such as people's huge backlogs.
Why buy something that's similar?
Like if you're gonna make, you love Braid,
and you're gonna make something similar to Braid,
why would people buy that when they?
Maybe they already own Braid and haven't played it.
Maybe Braid is gonna go on a sale soon anyway.
So I think basically what it comes down to
is that we're just gonna get more variation on the scene.
People are just gonna try and make even more
different things than they did previously.
It helps with discovery. There is a game called cluster truck made by genius Swedish people.
It's about fucking trucks. And a game like that is when you see cluster truck you just got to
click on it. I hope go home and look up cluster truck. You are going to remember the name
anyway, right?
and shareability. I think games that are fundamentally different from what you've
played so far are better water cooler conversation. It's more interesting to
talk about that insane game that you played yesterday than, oh, I played this
very well balanced game with good content and it had a good variation in
enemies and there were a lot of different weapons. It's just more fun to
talk about something that's totally crazy.
You did it.
I did it. Thank you so much Armin and welcome to the stage
Jordan Thomas of question.
Thanks, Randy. Yeah, so, hey, I'm Jordan. You're looking at a
picture of the magic circle. It's the indie game we released
in July of 2015. I'm going to talk to you a little bit about
how it did on steam, because as you pointed out, it's all on
steam spy anyway, so why not share? But to do that, I kind of
need to find a metaphor that makes this a little bit more fun
because, Randy, we only have the one game and this is all still
pretty raw. So in that spirit, I'm going to go with enhance,
enhance, enhance.
A six minute murder mystery. The end apocalypse if it exists is
such a widespread phenomenon or cycle that I can't wrap my head
around it without zooming in. Personalizing it. Thinking of it
as a predator that has it out for games like ours. So
Before I can do that, I need to talk about the game from an
objective point of view and then we'll get into the subjective
fun stuff that might have doomed us. So the magic circle is the
story of a legendarily unfinished game. You play the
hero of that world and you're sick of waiting for your story
to start. So you steal the tools of game design and sort of fix
the game from the inside. Retailed at 20 bucks. Our team
comes from the Bioshock series, dishonored and so forth. In
theory we know how to close from many years in AAA shipping lots
of titles. We spent roughly 100K of real money not counting
crucially two years of opportunity cost.
But that did lead to some strong mainstream media coverage
for our game.
We had a lot of positive attention leading up
and a reasonable social reach when our trailer came out.
So we sort of leveled off at about 80% on Metacritic,
90% on user review scores,
and we were recently nominated by the IGF
for excellence in narrative.
Thank you, by the way, if you're in here.
But the upshot is that we sold about 16,500 copies and we're on
44,000 wish lists. So this is not sustainable for us to go on
making games like the magic circle. We need to move on and
fast.
So this chalk outline kind of represents how the Magic Circle
did on Steam, now that you know.
We are a little bit like a teddy bear who
wandered in the woods in search of gold and got promptly shivved.
So the question is, though, did we shivve ourselves?
Did some of the decisions we make
come more subject and more internal,
or are they things that might affect games like yours?
Well, let's start with the external stuff.
The stuff that, at the very least,
there are many parallels for in other short narrative games.
So first, that's our big thing.
Three to six hours, give or take,
and Steam players responded with violent negativity to that.
They, of our negative reviews,
over 50% mentioned length as the deal breaker.
Even reviews that otherwise read like ads for us.
That surprised us.
But it dovetails in a pretty ugly way with the culture of sales on Steam.
As some of my colleagues have pointed out, Steam players know that on a long enough timeline,
they can have your game for next to nothing.
And so it's not about whether they can afford you, it's about whether they, it is love at
first sight, whether there's a reason to buy your game right now.
Because otherwise, they put you on a wish list and promptly forget you.
And then finally, Steam is very much like the app store,
as my friends have mentioned here.
The truth is that a short narrative game
that does not update as often is less commonly
on the front page of Steam.
So keep that in mind.
Now, what about the more flattering stuff
that suggests that we screwed ourselves
and we can do better in the future?
Well, first we had no marketing budget.
We kind of ignored the potential for marketing
through Kickstarter because we felt it was at odds
with the tone of the game.
We focused at first on making a great game
and hoped the rest would sort of self-align.
That was the wisdom of 2013 when we started the thing.
But the big one was that our game is pretty polarizing.
It has a very stark art style, which
people tend to love or hate.
It was billed as a comedy, but it has some very serious parts.
It sort of focuses on how games and game developers
can go wrong.
And I remember the IGN review was just like,
this game is angry.
And that kind of stuff leads to fairly polarized opinions
in the user base as well.
But we had compromised for so long that we really needed to make something that was radically unlike everything we had done before.
And we're still quite proud of that, but it has had some cost.
And we, on that note, could have focused on something that had a
more clear genre for our debut title, which a lot of
developers have done. Steam players really do respond well
to your game being like anything, some kind of touch
zone. So, you know, where does that really leave us? Question.
And you guys, if you are thinking of making something
like this. Well, first, I would say that if you are considering
a short narrative game,
Maybe don't rely on steam to make you piles and piles of gold and fund the next projects exclusively and if you do certainly consider
Some expansion plans so that it isn't just a fire and forget project
There is a happy ending here, though, which is that teddy
bear chalk outline was pregnant and the paramedics made it to
her baby. We are here. I'm able to talk to you. But just look
at him. He's kind of mean and he might turn out to be some sort
of vengeance-driven vigilante. The time that we have spent on
the magic circle has sort of claimed our innocence. We are
not the same as we were when we started out. And that might be
healthy, but it still feels like a little bit of a loss right
now.
But curation is your friend. Curated bundles coupled with
consoles which are harder to get on to have a very strong
possibility of bringing your game to a somewhat sustainable
overall loop. Relying on steam solely was sort of our mistake.
Mike Rose's talk which you can find at that link or just in the
GDC vault under Mike Rose talks about how if you have reasonable
support from the platform holder and decent scores you can see up
to 30,000 sales on the PS4, 20,000 on the Xbox one.
that even somewhere in between would put us in a position
where we might recoup some of that opportunity cost I
mentioned earlier. Our next project is much safer. It is
multiplayer focused. Has a very long tail and does actually have
a solution in place as a primary design goal to help players
understand why they would want it now. But I can't go deep on
that.
However, if you survive through AAA, especially PC AAA,
this might be something a little bit familiar to you,
the flight from PCs to consoles,
the focus on multiplayer,
and the receptivity to publishers,
all of which, we kind of went through this once already.
I'm just hoping that if we go through
another one of these boom-bust cycles,
we can pick a better name than Indiepocalypse.
Thanks.
Thank you Jordan. All right.
super cool animation. Again I'm Randy Smith of Tiger style. Tiger
style's first indication that there might be such a thing as
an indie apocalypse was when we released a game in 2015 and it
was doing much less business than games we released
previously in 2009 and 2012. So what we're looking at here is
our first six months of revenue for a flat comparison. But it
gets a lot worse if you add in lifetime revenue and development
time.
So spider 2 took us nine person years of effort but made
significantly less money. If you look at that in terms of ROI
specifically net revenue per person year. In 2009 spider 1
was making us close to half a million dollars per person year
but spider 2 is making us 13,000. So this is a very not
sustainable.
indication. We had every reason to believe that spider 2 is a
better commercial product than spider 1. It's on more
platforms. There's a hilarious story about how we promote
spider 1. We just released it into the app store one day with
absolutely no messaging or promotion whatsoever.
games. We did a bunch of things when they are promoting a game.
We had the social media stuff and a website and a trailer and
we went to expos and all that kind of stuff. Both games were
covered pretty well by the mobile press but spider one was
absolutely ignored by the core gamer press where spider two was
picked up favorably by the good smattering of the who's who.
of the core gamer press. They are reviewed about the same way.
They are both good games by most metrics if not all metrics.
Spider one is very minimal game. It's extremely focused on this
one core high concept. In spider two you better believe we spent
those nine years adding stuff. There's tons more content. It
features lots of polish, depth, replayability. We kept the
previous high concept and expanded it with some things
including this feature where it knows where you are in the real
world and it matches the time of day and weather in the game
where it is at your location.
So all kinds of things for the press to talk about.
But despite that, Spider 2 did all the work,
Spider 1 got all the glory,
it was the one that got editor's choice from Apple,
Spider 2 got a less important banner from Apple,
no coverage from Steam whatsoever.
Spider 1 was game of the year
on a bunch of different websites
and the IGF and some other stuff.
and spider 2 is on the end of your list for quite a few mobile
websites which is very pleasant. So obviously spider 2 is a
better product but is it 3.5 times better if you look at the
first six months of revenue or if you want to go ROI is it a 40
times better product? Because if it's not then maybe the market
is to blame. So do we blame the indie apocalypse? Well, the week
we came out you could buy Batman Arkham City game of the year
edition with all downloadable content for less than $5 on
steam and of course clash of clans is still pulling in $1.5
million every single day.
and we cannot compete with these games obviously. But at the same
time there was a game with absolutely no graphics about
programming in assembly language that was kicking our ass and
making the kind of money we were used to making and there was a
choose your own adventure game that was told with push
notifications that was raking in lots more than that and this
kind of illustrates a big games versus small games concept that
I'm going to come back to later.
was there something wrong with spider 2? It was a multi
platform game and that probably meant that's why we got less
support from apple. It's not a great match for steam. It was
really hard for us to shake our mobile legacy. We didn't play
the steam PR game very well.
Is it because it's a sequel? I think it might be. We felt like
this was a good decision because it was less risky. We had a fan
base that was clamoring for us to produce a sequel. We knew
that we hadn't reached our full audience so we could expand into
them. And we did our jobs correctly for sequels. All of
the press quotes are like this is exactly how you're supposed
to do sequels. We retained everything that was good about
the old and we made a bunch of new stuff too.
But Armin and Jordan have already alluded to this.
This is an audience that's interested in cool new things.
And so even if your design and art and everything
about your game is all but objectively better
than the prior game, which they gave a game of the year award
to, that type of attention is going to fresh new concepts
in this market.
the market likes high concept stuff. We were diluting our high
concept. The audience had to spend more effort to get to the
part that was cool and unique and fresh about the game this
time around. We might have been better off focusing on one
thing. This is just a game that focuses on that real world
location, time and weather type stuff.
Maybe a different way to think about it is to think about what
Spider 1 did correctly or benefited from, why it was
successful. It was released at the dawn of the app store. It
was a much less crowded market. Free to play didn't exist yet.
The market was growing very rapidly. Our intention was to
stand out by making a very solid heartfelt game on a platform
where that wasn't the standard at the time. Among other things
it made Apple's hardware look good. They supported and
featured us a lot.
So coming back to this chart, another way to consider this
comparison is like, you know, spider 2 hit a market upswing
and hit the right notes to ride that upswing versus spider 2
which was released into a perilous marketplace and it was
not indie apocalypse retardant.
So what do I mean by an indie apocalypse game. I like to think
about games that are big, medium and small. Big and small are
good and medium is a bad idea financially speaking. This is
kind of mostly in terms of production effort. You can see
the big games are like the triple I games if not triple A.
The problem is that medium games can't compete in the arms
race against those big games which are so expansive and have
all this depth and spectacle and gloriously long play times.
And compared to small games, medium games are really
expensive and they're also diluted. Those small games get
right to the crucial high concept more immediately.
They're more self-evident. But that said, there's a bunch of
other medium-sized games I could list here. Potentially you
could qualify them that way. And they've done very well. So
you can think about, hey, why did these games succeed whereas
Spider-2 did not?
I think it's super important to target your platform. So if
you're targeting the app store, it's a really good idea to be
Apple exclusive and show off their hardware features. That
audience really likes games that are very immediate, very
beautiful. And your goal is to get some featuring from Apple.
Because if you don't, you can just throw your game out the
window. On steam there's a bunch of design qualities that the
steam audience seems to like. They're looking for deeper, more
beefier, more involved games. They think like things like
systemic game play, replay, multiplayer and so forth.
I see games successful when they have this very long PR campaign
with multiple stages to build a big audience and awareness
before the game comes out. And the goal is to launch strong and
have those steam metrics put you on the front page with
featuring. And of course there's consoles as Jordan mentioned
last year Mike rose spoke at the IGS about the console market. In
particular it's still curated so it does limit supply. And we're
porting spider to the PS4 and Vita so we're hoping that will
work out for us.
I don't think it's a great idea to go multi-platform on launch
day. Especially if you're a smaller game on that side of the
spectrum. I know there's a lever in unity and you can pull it and
it pops out all these versions and it's so free. But these
things are a big distraction and take a lot of time and
attention. You should be tailoring your PR campaigns and
your game design around them. My approach is don't do it
simultaneously. If a game is taking off and successful think
about where to port it. If you're going to port between
App Store and Steam, definitely start on Steam.
not the other way around. I think Indy teams of the future
are probably going to need dedicated PR people and
dedicated business people. Which is a little sad because if you
are like me you sort of got into Indy to get away from this kind
of stuff. But there is a lot of really important work here and
you have to treat your business like a business and have people
who are helping out with these important things. And I think
we might need to reconsider publishers because they provide
all of those things that I just mentioned and they also really
help with discoverability. They can provide you with funding.
when I think about the future of indie games, I wonder a little
bit, I like to compare to like indie music or indie film. Indie
music is just an enormously, ridiculously crowded space.
Basically everyone is a hobbyist who doesn't think they're ever
going to make any money no matter how great their album is
or whatever. Indie film is not that far apart. The barrier to
entry is a little higher but it's still risky. I wonder a
little bit about are we going to come up with better
discoverability tools. Indie music has a really strong
emphasis on blogs and labels and so forth.
I'm old enough to remember what it was like to make games in the
90s and it was fucking awful. The publishers had a strangle hold
on creativity unless you were making a game where it was like
your Edward's pistol hands killing mother fuckers it wasn't
going to get published. You had to try to squeeze in your
expression and art on the side of that. It was pretty awful. We
got everything we wanted. We have this list of stuff we talked
about in the 90s. This is what it's going to take to bring
games out of this ghetto.
we got what we wanted and now we have a much bigger market place
full of more creative people and I think that's a really good
thing. I'm happy to have them here. So that is it for our
presentations.
Thank you.
Let me start with one and then we'll review this together.
So Armin and Jordan, I'm going to give you the hard question
that Jordan asked to dodge.
So do your best, Jordan.
But you guys both mentioned this idea of games that need to
be bought now.
And as a customer, you can't just wait for the sale.
So can you give us a little bit more thoughts about what
that means and what to look at?
And I'll let Armin go first so Jordan can dodge better.
Yeah, definitely. I think it's really important to make something that...
You know, you can wishlist things on Steam and then you get an email when the game is on sale.
How fun isn't that? If you're Valve, that's a lot of fun.
Absolutely. I think it's absolutely correct because we all have our Steam backlogs
and I think making something that people gotta play right now,
you just gotta click it, you gotta buy it. It makes life so much easier.
I guess I would add to that, in addition to the sort of like, that's a toy, it's not like any of my other toys, and I must touch it, because there's not going to be another goat that I can sort of molest and ragdoll.
I think there is also some value in the idea of a community driven game, that there is
a wave that streamers and other folks wish to ride. In other words, something about your
game where there is some benefit to mining out the unknown for kind of collective games
culture around your title. There is horror games are very good at this. Where there is
a lot of new scares and eventually they do kind of get used up by the sheer aggregate
of streamers. But early on, they kind of want to be there before anybody else can. So their
reactions are novel. So the people who can
who come to their stream to watch your game exclusively,
get something that everybody else
hasn't already kind of mined out.
I just want to add one final thing.
It doesn't just have to be farm animal simulators.
What Jeff does is basically, I think,
when your fans see your games, they're like, holy shit,
there's a new Avernum out.
I got to buy it right now.
nothing beats having a fan base.
Yeah, exactly.
So I think it can be doing something totally crazy,
but it can be having a niche and providing something
that no one other provides.
Cool.
We're getting a lot of questions on the tweets
to the tone of like,
why do we think supply is going to go back down?
If the tools to build games are so accessible and so easy,
doesn't that just suggest more people
are gonna come in here and want to build games?
Again, kind of to my indie music point,
whether or not they're intending to ever make money.
Do either of you two want to answer that? Have thoughts? Go
ahead. The beatings will continue until morale improves.
Of course people are going to keep writing games. People are
going to keep writing games like crazy. But if people want to
keep writing games to make money, there is only the money
pool is still finite. And what I'm saying might not be true. I
hope it's not true. But I believe that, you know, if
people, while people are going to keep writing games, people
keep writing lots and lots and lots of really big budget really intense games
they're gonna they're they're they may run into to problems.
Yeah just to add on that this is actually something Randy talked a little bit about
but the market's not going to get less crowded like that's just not going to
happen people are going to become hobbyists they're going to get like real
jobs they're going to you know hedge their bets like a thousand times but
what's going to happen is people who work for just like do
discoverability like
you know, they'll start cross-pollinating their own audiences.
It's something like that's half the reason why we entered the publishing market.
It's like, how can we grow a bigger audience?
And it's, we get a whole bunch of games under one umbrella,
and then we have access to a whole bunch of other people.
I think that's where it's going to go, is like it's going to constrict down,
and then you're going to...
like PR is just, sorry, sorry Indies, we've been talking about
this for years, but PR is just going to be a fucking thing you
have to do. And like it sucks, like you have to find somebody
that's good at it and can talk to people and get the message
out. But like our audience is like a fraction of a fraction,
like that's who plays Indie games and you got to hold on to
your customers and like get the message out.
cool. This next question kind of dovetails with that. What are
your thoughts on if you have done everything right in terms
of your marketability, your game, it's good to stream, you
have good talking points, a distinct art style and it's not
catching on. Is there anything you can do to salvage your
marketing campaign? What are your thoughts on that?
I can actually pop in, because we're doing this right now.
We talk about this a lot.
We take legit contracts.
When we release a game, we know exactly how much.
This is how much we spent, and this is
how much we need to make back.
And if it doesn't make that back in sales,
we have 300 other backup plans in place.
And that's just what we do.
Like, we have a family, we have a house, we have a life,
and I can't destroy that because I work in a volatile market.
So that's just the reality of being a grown up.
It kind of sucks.
But we have backup plans on backup plans on backup plans.
And I could talk about that all day.
I would add to that. Sorry. Just that the curation thing is
also potentially your friend, like I mentioned during the
talk, that there are bundles out there which can sort of buy your
game in lump sum and create word of mouth that would otherwise
not have existed at the moment of launch. That stuff has at
least created a nice little blip in the curve of sales friends
that I know who have released games and been approached a
while after release.
So one of the most amazing advantages of being an indie
that people discuss not often enough
is that you get to own your work.
And that's incredible.
Because if you release it and it kind of flops,
you still own it.
You can release it for new platforms.
You can wait three years for a better market and remaster it.
You can wait 10 years and remaster it and re-release it.
You don't just have the cash.
You have a thing that can be generated for you
to generate more cash later on.
It's true. We have cannibal. Maybe someday we'll do
something with that. It's there. It's just sitting there waiting
to be mined someday. Exploited. Exploit that shit.
We're also getting questions about sales and the sale, the
prominence of sales and how they drive the customer's behavior.
Is there any thoughts anyone has about promising never to put
your game on sale for the first six months or anything like
that?
Dude, don't make that public.
No, don't do that.
Don't say that.
Why isn't that a good marketing strategy?
Because, no, what are you going to do?
Are you going to write it on Facebook?
Like Senator Pressley's people aren't,
like everyone doesn't know everything instantly
about your game.
Dialogue window at the beginning of your game.
No, but why not do that?
No, try it.
I don't know, try it.
The forums, you're putting these games out on places where the forums are like cesspools of horror.
They're looking for any reason to destroy you, and they don't care if you've made something amazing.
Why give them, you may internally say, I'm never putting this game on sale, that's fine.
You don't got to tell anybody that.
you may launch this game and be like, dude, this was bad, but I
made this public statement. Now there's another thing. Now you
put it on sale. There's some stuff where it's like you don't
need to talk about this stuff publicly. Like tell your fan
base, like, gaming, the forums are cesspools, you guys. Don't
give them ammo to be mean. Make your games and be a business
person on the outside of that.
security cameras because someone is going to pipe bomb your
house. Don't let your mom read the forums. Last question, are
we all screwed by VR? Do we all need to get VR jobs? I already
have one. My answer is no. I hope every single one of you
moves to VR because then more candy for Jeff.
everybody for coming. We're all going to move to the wrap-up
room. I'll be taking on all comers until free lunch is
available.