Hi, everybody.
Sorry about that.
So I'm Seth Marinello, as Corey said.
This is my third year getting to speak at Level Design Day.
And I didn't necessarily intend on being the first presentation
when I came up with my title, but it seems
to have worked out really well.
So today, we're going to be talking about a series of first steps.
Specifically, we're going to be looking at strategies for sort of capturing your initial
design and coming up with something that you can take back to your team and turn into a
great piece of content.
So we're going to be looking at sort of like everything from conception through sort of
the block worlding phase where I would say, all right, we've got a design, we've got something
that we can move forward with.
And now the idea for this presentation came from when we started doing the book project.
I went back and started looking through our previous slides and looking at some of the
stuff that I did in 2012.
And I saw this slide in there.
And you can see that, you know, my main thing I was talking about was this dominant feature.
Having a central theme or idea that...
ties all the details of your content together.
And I sort of said, well, you know, after you're done with that,
well, just block out the level around these objectives, right?
Just, because that's easy, right?
And I started realizing, you know,
I haven't talked about some of this stuff before.
Like, we just sort of skip over the beginning part,
and we talk about these high-level concepts of how we make good content,
but how do you even get started building anything, right?
anyone that's been involved in a creative process of whatever, you've dealt with this sort of blank
page syndrome where you have some days where you sit down and you're like, I know what I want to
build. This is going to be great, right? And you just, you just go. And those are the times when,
you know, you don't need to follow some sort of crazy process. But there's the other days where
you're like...
You know, it'd be great if I could get anything on the screen, even if it's just some kind of like random boxes, right?
I just want to get something up and feel like I've got some momentum.
So we're going to be specifically sort of looking at, you know, those days where you don't have forward motion of what you're trying to do.
How do you get started, right?
I think that if we're trying to create something and you're not sure how to begin, you need to define clearly what it is you're trying to build,
what's success going to look like and where are we trying to go.
specifically the first thing we want to look at is what's your primary constraint, right?
If you're trying to build a single player game where we're making a dead space title or
something like that.
Ultimately, you're responsible for producing a certain amount of, you know, duration of the main
campaign, right? You need an hour worth of good content that's coming here. And this is sort of
the primary thing that's going to drive you forward. If you have a more narrative driven
game, it could be that it's like, we have two characters and we have to get them together and
this is the main point of this. If it's 20 minutes, if it's a half an hour, it doesn't matter as
long as we deliver on this narrative moment. You're making a multiplayer map, it's like, you
have to have 64 players in this multiplayer map. And that's going to determine a lot of things
about the size of the space.
the number of capture points, and how much you can do with art, right?
So there's always going to be kind of this short straw.
And that's the thing that's going to determine a lot of decisions you're going to make down the line.
So if you can identify that up front, it helps build sort of this constraint box
that you can work within and then create from there.
Another thing that you can do is look at what are the things that every level is going to have in
this game, right? If you're making a Mario level, a Doom level, a Dead Space level, whatever,
you're going to probably have something like a start point, an end point, some enemies, some
pickups. Like what are the basic building blocks of your game that appear in 80% of all of your
levels? And you've got this, you're like, well, these are the things that have to be there,
right? So if I don't know other things, I can at least start figuring out, well, you know...
where I'm going to put my suit store or my upgrade bench or my kiosk, right? We have general
plans in our phase definitions that explicitly say like, hey has the LD sat down and thought
about like walker locations, pickup locations and things that are paced out through, you know,
interspersed with the combat and the other events. So these are some of the things that I
just pulled out of some of our random documents for Dead Space 3. But this is stuff we've
explicitly listed out.
And you don't have to do this every single time you're
building a level.
But the first time you're working on something
on a project, it's good to have this written down.
These are the elements that I have to mix in along
with everything else.
So once we've got this, we've kind of got a general idea
of what is it that I need to build.
But then how do I start building it?
Well, step one for building something
is to capture the intent or capture your design.
And what do I mean by this?
I think that there are three main components
to delivering a design if we're talking about making
like a single player level.
You've got a concept, which is just
this high level sort of x statement thing,
or your dominant feature, or whatever it's going to be.
You've got a walkthrough, which is a description of what
you want to build.
And it doesn't have to literally be a walkthrough
if you're making a multiplayer map or something.
But it's a plan of, well, what's the setting of the map?
What are the different sort of points going to be?
How is everything going to work together?
And.
what's the content going to really entail. And we'll go through each one of these sort of
images and finally there's a block world. All of this is the design and that's the
deliverable that we're trying to get to at the end of this. You want to have a thing that
you're like, I'm a level designer and I've produced this thing and this is what we're
going to go forward and build. It may not be the final design but it is a design and it's
the point from which you can launch forward. So going through each one of these
individually. Concept.
This is, in some ways, the simplest because it's just like, well, this is the main idea or the main thread that I'm trying to take through it.
But it's also one of the hardest things to kind of walk down.
In my 2012 talk, I was talking almost exclusively about coming up with a central concept.
And I said, you know, sometimes you look at a level and you want to be able to say,
well this is the, you know, this is the underwater level, or this is the nighttime stealth level,
or this is like the at sea level.
Something that's the central element to the art and to the gameplay and to the story
that's going to pull it all together.
An example that I wasn't able to use because we hadn't announced that we were doing Dead Space 3 at the time,
but was like sitting in the front of my mind, was a level I was working on called the Command Ship.
So I had this idea that it was, the whole idea was that you're awakening this sleeping ship.
This, the first time that anyone's been on this, this, this abandoned ship in 200 years, and everything in it...
It was like all the handles you had to manually operate.
There was dust.
There's necromorphs that are sort of hanging in cocoons
that we hadn't done previously in the game.
Just to sell this idea that there's kind of like this latent evil,
and you're showing up and kind of like kicking it back to life, right?
And that culminates in your sort of final generator encounter
and all this stuff tied into this central idea.
And now, you know, this isn't something that just pops into your mind, though, out of nowhere.
Like, we had this whole sort of underlying thread of kind of Mountain of Madness Cthulhu stuff going on
really early in Dead Space 3, so that's sort of where this idea evolved out of.
But you can't just assume that you're going to come up with your concept out of the blue, right?
You have to brainstorm, find references, talk to other people.
The amount of time that I spend just grabbing other designers and being like,
hey, so I need to talk to you about this thing.
And it's just like, what if we did blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, right?
And we'll throw a bunch of ideas up on a board.
And I have.
just folders and folders of random machines and things like that that I've found on Google
image search and Tumblr. I have no idea how people, I guess you just looked through books
or whatever and added little sticky notes to them in the olden days. But you have all
these things that are going to inspire you and you put together and you've been trying
to find threads that connect these different things that are exciting and from there your
concept can grow. I want to take it in this direction.
And then you sift through that stuff, and the stuff that really resonates with the concept that you're trying to make, you distill down into a walkthrough.
And, now, what form it takes, it is going to depend on what kind of content you're trying to make, what kind of game you're trying to build.
But I think that there's some core things that your walkthrough needs to answer, right?
You need to have, what are your major objectives? What are the major things that the player's doing?
What are the major beats?
So what kind of things are we highlighting in the level?
And these things are going to determine
the scope of the level.
You're going to get an idea of how many custom gameplay
scenarios do I need?
Do I need custom texture sets?
Things like that.
This is the first time where we can start evaluating,
well, what is it that you're really asking to build?
But it can be kind of hard to parse all this information out
of 20 pages of me rambling about all these scary corridors
and stuff like that.
So it's really important to include.
a top-down map in your walkthrough of whatever you're trying to build.
Because this condenses this whole scope concept down into one thing that you can look at,
and it really captures the flow of the level.
You can look at it with your eye and trace how the player is going to be moving through the space,
and even start to evaluate things like,
well, maybe I need some more space in between this beat and that beat, right?
Like, am I actually asking for the right amount of rooms?
And this is all great, and you're really excited.
And you're like, I've got this concept.
I've got this pile of fantastic reference.
And they're checking it all into Perforce.
And who's going to read it?
You're going to read it.
Your producer's going to read it.
And you're going to high five all day about how awesome it is.
But half of the artists that are working on your level
aren't necessarily going to see this.
So I think that one thing that is important
is once you feel like you've got some momentum behind what
you're building.
is to take it, and we do these boards where we'll get some key art, some key images,
we'll have a story summary, you know, the top-down map, and then because in Dead Space
we're really worried about the lighting and the tone as you're progressing through the level,
a color script of kind of like how we're going to make things so if we have a major state change,
like in Command Ship where you turn on the power.
the second half is going to have a different feel.
And that's mentioned in your walkthrough,
and it's captured here so that you've got a 100 person team.
They can all look at it.
Now, if you're on a five person team,
it's easy for you to just sit down and talk
about these things, right?
But if you've got someone that's building
a desk for your admiral's quarters or something
like that, you want them to be able to kind of get
a general feel for what you're trying
to put forth as a designer, right?
And at this point, we've got this pretty board.
We've got all this stuff.
It's like, well, our design's done, right?
And it's interesting because I was talking to our lead level designer from Dead Space 3
about this presentation. I'm like, yeah, yeah.
And we had done this thing early on where we were like, we're going to plan out the whole game,
what the general high-level beats are, and we're going to write really short, you know,
like a couple paragraph walkthroughs of what each level is going to contain,
and then gave them out to the designers.
And they would finish through the walkthrough and it would get approved.
And then they would start building the block world.
And the approved walkthrough that everyone had agreed,
yeah, this is what we're building,
would differ insanely from the block world that
would come back.
And once we had the block world approved,
the level didn't change that much.
We were like, OK, we know what was going on.
But it was obvious that there was
major questions that weren't being answered
by the earlier part of our process that
needed to be sort of worked out in the block world.
And the things that I think that we're missing so far in our process are we hadn't captured the working field space.
You've got concept art and reference and things like that, but you don't know what it feels like to actually be there on the controller, standing in the space, and thinking about, well, you know, how big is this room? How high is the ceiling? What are the sight lines, right, between this moment and that moment?
Am I going to have a thing in my top-down map? You're just not necessarily thinking of, well, I'm coming into the room, and I've got the door that I need to go to, and it's on the left-hand side of the room in my top-down map, and you get there in the controller and you realize that...
we're a third person game with a character on the left hand side of the screen and the character covers the place you're trying to go.
You have to think about these things. The other thing is, you've already got all the beats and you know what the player flow is going to be, but how do they connect?
In the first chapter of Dead Space 3, we had a moment where Isaac meets Danek, the bad guy, up on this balcony.
And you've moved through the whole level in a continuous space. We haven't really had an opportunity to teleport the player or move them anywhere.
And then Isaac falls off of this ledge and lands in this alley and has this whole encounter.
And on a top-down map, it makes a certain degree of sense.
But when you're sitting down and actually trying to build it in 3D, it's like,
do I actually have enough rooms to get me from, like, the public sector to here?
Is a balcony going to make sense? Do I have a doorway that kind of opens into nothingness?
Like, does this space actually work?
And that's what building your block world is going to do.
So now I guess the big thing is, we've got to build a block world.
Step one is you sit down and you just make some boxes.
At least this is sort of the strategy that I employ.
Start off, get sort of some kind of central point
that you're going to go from, and then I kind of
grow the level from there.
An example, another one from Dead Space 3,
is the research ship.
So this was my initial walkthrough, top-down map
for the level.
And you'll see that.
there's this room in the middle of it called the connecting hallway upper.
And there's actually there's a lower part but this is because later I had to
cut it into two things because they initially was like
hallways are easy right I'm just going to put in a hallway and that'll be a
point and I'll just start growing it from there
and I start looking at it I'm like well but I want to have a window over here so
that it connects the outside to the inside.
of the ship because we could go in the exterior. I never built something like that before.
And then I'm like, I need, I want a pillar because I want pillars and ducks in this level.
And I'm defining what the look and the feel is and the room started to grow.
And from there I was like, well, okay, well now I know what this hallway that's connected to this thing is going to look like.
And the whole level kind of grew out of this, this one central point.
And if you open up most maps that I've worked on and you find the room that's at 0, 0 in
Maya, that's probably the first thing I started with. And sometimes it ends up being a really
big room. Other times it's like a dead end hallway and it just grew from there. And, you
know, I was wondering, like, am I crazy? Is this kind of...
Am I the only one that does this? And there's this interesting article online by David
Johnston who worked on D-Dust and it's a fascinating read actually because he's basically
had this screenshot and one other screenshot from the early Team Fortress 2 version that
Valve ended up canning. And he saw this and was like, I see these elements, I like these
arches, I like these textures. And he was like, I wonder if I can do this in Counter-Strike.
And he basically built this room.
And from that room, that ended up being the very bottom of this map, which is the CT bond point.
And the rest of the map, he was just sort of filling in.
And it's interesting, as he's going, he's talking about how he tried adding in an underground section,
but it didn't feel right because it didn't have a lot of the architectural elements and the general vibe that the initial room did,
and he ended up pulling it out.
And when you've got something like that, you've got a piece where you're like,
okay, this is capturing kind of the vision and the feel of the space that I want,
that you can then judge other bits of content,
then you know you've got it, like you're going forward.
But as I'm looking at this, a thing sort of occurred to me of like,
well, there's definitely other people that do this, but...
Aren't I basically just advocating for following the WorldCraft tutorial?
Like, aren't I basically saying, like, stick a brush in the world, hollow it out,
dump it in InfoPlayerStart, and hope that you've configured all your pack files correctly,
and it's actually going to build? Right? Have I really not changed the process in which I build
levels, you know, in the last, like, 15 years? And I went through a serious crisis about this,
because I was like, you know, have I been sort of just, like, limited to thinking about things
in terms of, like, brushes and boxes?
How am I going to break out of this, right?
Because what we were doing in the hands earlier is,
a lot of people now are, you're either not making something
that's on a real tournament deathmatch level,
or a Half-Life level, or something like that,
or you're working in an indie space where you're using
a completely different kind of tool set
than we're using in AAA.
So, it's like, how do I kind of break out of this box, right?
Because I was looking at games that I found interesting online,
and it's like, well, how am I going to turn a box into DayZ?
Or how am I going to turn a box into a city in GTA V?
Or how am I going to turn a box into a level for Cut the Rope,
right?
Like, what does all of this mean?
And so I called up our creative director from Dead Space 2, who had moved on and was working at Zynga for a while, and I was like,
hey man, so I'm working on this presentation about block worlding, and I'm worried that it might be like, you know, a little too...
locked in kind of like the work that you know that I've done like kind of traditional level design
of this sort of thinking about interiors and not necessarily thinking about like
an exterior space where you're worried about the relationship of different points together but
more like defining the whole of the level like how am I going to generalize this it is like
oh this basically I feel like I've been building kind of D&D dungeon maps the whole time right
and like as soon as you get past the point where you're defining the edges of the dungeon what
what are you going to do
Um, and so his, his response was, well, I mean, if your presentation is really just
about white boxing purely, then I think you're, you're, you're talking about a very specific
kind of game and a very specific kind of tool set. So that's when I started to incorporate
some more stuff about the general process and how we would integrate your design. But
I also realized that maybe I needed to sort of like look at things beyond just what I
do sort of in my day to day process. And I started asking people that work in other disciplines,
well, you know, how do you get started on doing design stuff?
Because I realized, maybe if I want to expand beyond this,
I need to get a new strategy.
So I talked to some people that do UX design.
I was really interested in user stories
and things like that for a little while.
And I started reading a bunch of IDEO papers
and going crazy on design thinking for about two weeks.
And then I was like, I don't know.
This might be getting a little far off base.
It's maybe getting a little generalized, right?
Because this is a level design talk.
And as a level designer, you're often not
creating the interface.
that you're using, you don't create the controls, you don't create how a lot of things feel.
So there's a lot of really interesting stuff there, and I think that's a whole other talk, basically.
I was just getting too far away from block building.
But one thing I did find interesting was,
I was talking to my friend who's an architect in New York,
and she does like condos and retail spaces and things like that,
and I was like, well, how do you get started?
And she said, well, she makes a few bubble diagrams.
And I was interested in how focused
she was on what the human or the user or the player
was going to be doing at the time,
but also just how they're thinking of, well,
how would these spaces relate to each other,
and what does it imply?
And so I was looking at some bubble diagrams.
Some of them are very blueprint-like, but.
Other ones are kind of abstract.
And the thing I think that's interesting about this is
you can have a room that's got a kitchen, a dining room, and a living room
all in the same space, and there's no walls separating them, right?
But they'll have separate bubbles, because the bubbles are representing
the function or the intent or the purpose of a space.
And you're thinking about how these relate to each other and how they connect.
And this is sort of abstracting out.
you know, things to a certain degree. And I was like, oh, this is really interesting,
it's spatial, and maybe this could go somewhere. At the same time, I did the global game jam.
And I'm building this game in Unity,
and of course I'm doing sort of the level content.
And we're building this joust-like game, right?
So it's a single screen thing, and I
have this terrible little drawing that
was in my notebook of my first version of, well,
what's our level going to be?
And I remember that my thinking was, well,
I don't want it to feel like Mario Brothers arcade, where
it's just a bunch of boxes.
I want it to feel like there's unique areas and unique spaces.
And if I go to this corner, I'm like, oh, yeah,
I like this place.
And as I'm doing it, I've been thinking about bubble diagrams.
I start realizing that I'm like, oh, well, in this corner,
I'm going to have a little diamond cave.
And I want to have a nice little narrow thing in here
and a little something you can fall down.
And I'm just thinking about these unique areas that
are sort of like bubbles of purpose or bubbles of function.
And the main thing that I'm doing as a level designer
in this action is, how do these things flow?
How do they connect together?
you know, I had this initial version of it, and you can see that I sort of expanded a few things,
moved some things around, I moved my little diamond cave down to the bottom.
But then in the final version, a lot of those core elements were there, right?
And even if I look at this, I just see like there's a central conflict point,
there's some side areas where you can have pickups and things like that.
And by creating these pockets of interest, we've kind of generalized the way that you're thinking about space and function.
And you can use this for a single screen game, or if you were building a city and you want to have different regions and then how you flow between them and when these things become accessible,
I think that if you look at designing a world in Metroid, designing a multiplayer first person shooter battle level, or whatever, everything will work.
But at the same time, you don't want to...
make everything too complex. You don't want to make everything unique, right? You want to make sure that each area has a purpose, and
the players should have options, and that's why thinking about the flow between them is so important.
Because you need to have options, but it can't be like you come into a room and it's 360 degrees and
every single thing is a door, right? Because then the player's decision is just like, well, I don't know.
It's a crap shoot. Really complex maps are hard to learn. This is something I learned really early on. I was really obsessed with like the crazy Counter-Strike maps where there's like a million ways to flank and vents and all that kind of stuff. And no one plays those. Everyone plays Dust and Office, right? And it's because it's an easy thing to learn and you kind of have a metagame of, well we go down this route or we go down this route, right? And you go one way five times and then you go the other way once, right? And it becomes interesting. And single player maps
you know if you get too confusing the player kind of loses sight of what it is that they're trying to do.
I found this as I was digging through some architecture stuff as well and I think this quote is kind of interesting
because it ties in the idea that you're always thinking of things in the next larger context
and I think that thinking of these bubbles of function when you're planning out things really sort of
enables this and it also ties in a lot with what I've been talking about in my
building universe through details talk of having this kind of mosaic of
narrative of how there's a story to each fight, each room, each level, each game
and everything sort of fits within each other. And from there I think that you
know you can you can come up with the design and you can vet it at each phase
and make sure that you've got something.
But once you've got that thing, it's like, well,
is this design good?
At a certain point, you have to sit down and evaluate.
We've got all these things.
Is this what we want to do?
Is this where we want to grow from?
I think that an important thing to keep in mind
as you're going through all of this
is that at any point, you need to be.
willing to go to step one if things aren't working. Which is throw everything or anything away,
right? You don't necessarily have to get rid of everything, but I used to be a computer
engineer and one of the things that one of my professors in undergrad taught us was that, you
know, you write a function and you write this function and you're having problems all the time.
It's like your center, it's...
It's really complicated and hard to do and it's where all your bugs are coming from, right?
And people are often scared to tackle that kind of stuff. But if you have a part of your
design or your level is just not working, you've got to be willing to kind of throw it
away because you've learned something, right? You've learned why it's not working. And once
you've identified that problem, redoing it again is probably only going to take like 10%
of the time it did the first time. And what you've got is going to be sort of leaner and
cleaner and better.
you know, is create a finished product. And if you're pouring, uh, like metal or plaster
into a mold or something like that, you're going to have this little thing called sprue,
which is like the avenue which you're pouring the plaster into the mold, you have to cut
off a little like nub at the end, right? And sometimes that's your initial design. It's
something that you needed in order to get it done, but you just had to kind of cut it.
I've had so many times where I've built a room, like this room was one of the ones I
did in Dead Space 2, and like you can't see the exit.
the enemies make no sense and I have this like nonsensical ramp that goes down
only just to go back up again. And whenever I start doing that I'm like
oh I'm just trying to arbitrarily change the heights of the floors to make it
more interesting. But then you sit down and you kind of come up with
you know some central idea like you know having a window separating
you from what's going on. And this room right here you can see
ended up becoming this in the final game.
And that was because the block world captured enough
of what I was sort of trying to do
that we were able to go forward.
Because ultimately, that's what we're trying to do here.
We're trying to get a foothold.
We're trying to take that first step
to climb up this mountain of production.
And it's only then that we're ready to move on
to step two at last,
which is to take that design and iterate upon it.
And that's what Joel's gonna talk about in a little bit.
So I'm Seth, you can find me on Twitter at Seth Marinello or email me at Seth at AlterDreams.net
and I'm interested in whatever questions you guys have.
**applause**
So if you guys have questions for Seth, you can go up to these microphones here, here, here and over there.
And we have a few minutes.
What was the name of your game jam game?
Uh, the name of my game jam game was, uh, Wizard Wizards.
Go on.
that there's, there originally were supposed to be wizards but they ended up being dragons but
you know, you can't, you can't change things when you've got 48 hours. Uh, and uh, it was just, it
was like, it was a multiplayer kind of Joust-like game. Uh, and you had magical powers that you
could pick up different little hats. I don't know. I was really excited about having a wizard
tower.
Speaking of not being able to change things,
when's the line drawn to compromise,
where you can no longer change the level it needs to be
pushed off to the next step?
I mean, in an ideal world, never.
But obviously not.
I mean, that's one of the reasons why I'm emphasizing.
And so in the talk.
I'm advocating for including the block world as part of the initial design phase. And I
think a lot of the time you would, you know, if someone was scheduling things out,
they'd be like, well, they wrote a walkthrough and we have key art and we've got a
concept, right? This level's done. Check mark. Right? Let's just ship it off and build it.
And I really think that you need a playable block world that you can at least run around
in before you can say with any degree of confidence, like, I have a design that we could
ship and build. So.
I mean, that's the point where I'd say major changes to the level, like I'm going to, you know,
completely alter the flow, is probably, becomes out of the question once everyone's agreed that
they've got a functional block world, but I think that that gives you a good point to say,
you know, all right, everyone agrees that this is where we're going to go.
Can you go into a little bit of detail about starting your eighth or ninth map,
once you've actually gone through a bunch of them and you feel like you've run your course,
you're not sure where to go next, like now this is a brand new blank page?
Um...
I mean, I find that everyone is sort of...
Everyone is sort of unique, particularly if you are moving around games, right?
If you're building, like...
If I'm building another Dead Space map...
there's a certain element of okay, alright. As I was talking about earlier, I know there's
sort of a pattern or a rhythm to where you're going to have the combat and things like that.
But that's just information that you're bringing in. I think that every single level is sort of a
unique thing and the only thing you do is get better with the tools over time and you become
slightly more experienced. But normally...
I feel like the skills you gain are things like when things start going wrong,
like you're working on an encounter and people are confused about
where things are, where the enemies are coming from and stuff like that.
Those are the kind of problems that I feel like I spend the most time solving
and feel like I'm getting better at.
The beginning phase is...
it's sort of just unique to every project.
uh when you're starting with a block world what kind of uh level of detail do you start with?
Like do you place every uh like a block for every crate or do you just kind of put a big block
like this is just going to be a pile of crates? Like what kind of level do you start with?
Uh that's why I included some of those those pictures of like what the sort of general
finished block world would be like so I'm not doing any texture or any detail or anything
like that. Um I mean I would say that until you have
like a hallway or like a general room with nothing in it that feels good, like don't
start adding anything to it. Like the smallest amount of detail possible to capture what
you're trying to do is good. Unless you're, you know, a good 3D artist, right? Like I'll
sit there and I'll just thrash in Maya forever trying to make something look good. So I don't
even try.
Did you find out at the end that even with the bubble diagram, you started with the central bubble,
one bubble, and then creates the bubble around?
Because that's, for example, my approach, that I'm kind of...
I don't have the central room, and then creating from the one central room,
I have the one bubble, and creating all the bubbles around.
Did you end with the same?
Um, well I think what you're describing is sort of, uh, in line with how I build a lot of levels
and what I was talking about earlier, sort of starting from a central point and flowering out
from that location. Um, I'm not necessarily sure that...
the way that I would build something would tie into the way that I'm thinking about sort of this bubble concept.
But I look at that as more of a way of encapsulating a bunch of function like this is a town
in my open world map or this is an island in like Assassin's Creed 4 or something like that.
And what you're thinking about is the relationship of that bubble to another bubble, right?
How they connect, how they flow, or even if you're making a cut the rope level or something like that,
where you place the stars and where you place your obstacles or whatever,
they kind of create these little relationships or spaces that are going to define how the player thinks about that space
and how they think about your piece of content.
And that's sort of what I'm thinking at that.
Particularly in the first few steps of building a level like this,
do you ever get the level designers equivalent of writer's block?
And how do you deal with it if you do?
Yeah, I mean, that's sort of what I was, I was, I was getting at at the beginning of, of the
talk about, you know, if you, you really don't know what you do, you sit down and define,
well, what is it that, this, what does this content have to accomplish in order to be a
success? And what are the basic elements that there's no way we're shipping this without
getting, you know? Um, as, as I was sort of talking about, if you...
if I know that I have to have a room that has a suit kiosk in it, like maybe I just start
building that room. Uh and and fitting it into the thing just so I feel like I've got some sort
of momentum. Um but it again it differs from like level to level. I've had times before where
I've like gone back and just started like doing top down maps in some like ancient game just
to kind of get a feel for what I want to do and not even think about what it looks like.
Um, I have seen this, uh, for game this day about the level design, some designer plan to, like,
trick, trick player to go to like a detour or to the dead end. When, when you design, is it, is, is
that have, uh, like a criteria of the design that how long this world should take? About time?
how long going down a dead end should take?
No, I mean, if you want the player to go to the right way,
to go to the next level, but sometimes you
have to go to that way, or maybe to the dead end,
maybe to a detour, how long for one level
should take, like the spaceship that you have?
I mean, this is going to vary drastically
depending upon what kind of game you're trying to make,
right?
And even in something like, like in Dead Space it's not even necessarily that one level needs to be a certain amount of length, but it's like, what do we want the player to accomplish, right?
If it's a simple side mission and all we're trying to do is, you know, I did one in Dead Space 3 where you're just trying to capture some extra munition supplies before the bad guys get them and it's an optional thing.
you know, that's like a 15 minute level. Uh, because what you're doing isn't that big. You
can tell that story pretty fast. Right? And I think that, again, it's whatever your primary
constraint is that's going to determine the size and scope of your content ultimately. So in
Dead Space it's often narrative. Right? Um, in, in a multiplayer map it would be the
number of players or the game modes you want to support. Earlier you talked about beats.
Yeah. And linking of beats. Can you elaborate? So
beats is one of those sort of weird words that I feel like is generically refers to some sort of
event that's not just walking around. But in a level specifically, those are often the
objective points when I complete an objective and then I move forward or I have some sort of
major notable encounter. Right? So in
in command ship you you you enter the ship so that's that's a beat basically coming into the
ship entering into the space and there's a scene and then you receive an objective which is you
know go find someone right and the time in between there and that next beat which is finding
this person you're looking for that's filled in with a bunch of gameplay but kind of how those
things connect and beats that are really next but close to each other um or where you get in
these sort of like tricky situations of like so beats of verbs
Yes, pretty much.
OK.
Yeah.
So I was wondering, the parallels
between level design and architectural design
are really interesting.
And I was wondering if your architecture friend
was able to shed some light on the psychology of space
and volume, and how much that comes
into play in your early bubble diagrams and stuff.
I think there's a huge overlap in terms of like,
the science of it, or like the psychology of it. But in terms of like the practical application of
like architectural... Games are this weird pseudo reality, right? Where everything is like extra
big and the way that everything flows together is just very different. Like you, when you, like
this room right here wouldn't be unusual in a game, but in real life it's like this room is giant.
right? And so sorting that out I think is the hardest thing for someone that's coming from
architecture to put in. But the idea of basic forms and how you break up space and how you
separate things, things like pillars and architectural supports are super important
and like looking through architecture books is like the best.
How do you balance this process with the level artist who's probably equally excited about making
vistas and big rooms and things like that and ensuring that both of you come together to create a really coherent design?
Could you repeat that?
Sorry, was that not coming out very clearly?
Sorry, how do you and your level artist
work together through this process?
Because they've probably got their own aspirations
about what they want to achieve,
and ensuring that you both come together
to create something that's really coherent
and therefore successful.
Yeah, I mean, for me, the ideal situation would be that after I've got maybe a really, really rough block world done in, that I then proceed and work like walking like hand in hand with my environment artist for all that. And that's actually one of the things that I was talking about the brainstorming phase. At that phase, I'll pull in whoever's going to be my environment artist.
my concept artist or whoever's the writer for that area,
and just throw ideas around with them and get that stuff down.
Like a lot of it is going to be dictated
by the story and the gameplay.
But how the level really flows and how
you add visual interest at that look and feel stage,
I think it's really important to work with.
Anyone that you can collaborate with, do it, basically.
When your level design contains puzzles or puzzle elements,
how do you represent those in your block world?
Um, it depends on how important I think it's going to be to the architecture and the flow of the
level. If it's a self contained thing, like, um, something that I walk up and engage with and
then I enter essentially another form of control and then I'm going to pop out of, it'll
just be some debug text and a switch and like I need 3 by 3 meters over here probably for
something.
if it's a large environmental puzzle, um, you need to at least block it out in Maya or
something so you can slide the different elements that are going to move around and be
like, see, I'm going to be able to build this and it's going to make some sort of sense.
Uh, cause if you're, you're betting your hero room on this, you know, fantastic
contraption thing and you don't have it visually represented.
it's yeah. But those I'll often treat as like it's own project. We'll be like we're gonna have
an epic puzzle like at the end of the Despy's 3 DLC we have this gigantic room that uh we
basically did the whole thing and then separately we're blocking that final like boss puzzle
room. And that's generally how we'll do it and it'll have it's own kind of design docs and
all that.
OK.
When you try to decide the intent of the level
you are designing, you decide it depending on the game
features, or you decided that the feeling you want the player
to feel, or some others.
Can you talk about that?
In some ways this ties into the primary constraint,
but it also ties into what kind of game you're trying to make.
If I'm building a level for a braid or a portal
or something like that that's mechanics driven,
then the mechanic is going to be what
drives a lot of the content.
And my x statement or my concept should
be something about exploring the different permutations
of that mechanic.
In Dead Space, we tend to, we have got a few basic mechanics,
but they generally are featured in every level.
We may have a moment where we're like,
well, we really want to focus on stasis,
or we really want to focus on TK,
but ultimately, it's a narrative
and an experience-driven game,
because the mechanics aren't what we're using
to create kind of the mood and the atmosphere,
which is what a lot of the franchise is about.
How often do you have the situation where you're told your level is too massive or too much of a
strain on system resources on a constrained system? And have you avoided that in planning or
deal with that? Pretty much all the time. In the last week our lead technical artist came up and
was like, really? You want to do this rodeo show again? Because I have a tendency, I'm
relatively technical and I tend to be like, no, we can do this.
this will be fine. And then at the end of the day it's like, for that boss room at the end of the
dead space awaking thing I was like I'm going to make the biggest room that's ever been in a dead
space game and I'm going to include all these mechanics that I've personally never got to put in
a level somewhere. And it was kind of a nightmare to ship. But that's the part that's fun though.
You, you, you gotta pick your battles though. Like when I'm doing something like that I'm
intentionally being like, alright, this is going to be a moment that I want people to
remember and that I want to be like something that I'm like sort of proud that I put
together. You don't want to like make hallways that randomly have like transparent glass
in them all over the place just to, you know, make your rendering engineer cry.
I had a question on, you said on purpose of areas in your level.
Yeah.
Is it a good design principle to say to have just an area in your level where just the
only reason it's there is for the player to explore and has no other purpose?
Yeah.
But to look good?
I mean, it's part of building out your world.
Like it should have a purpose.
but it doesn't have to be a required alpha path gameplay purpose, right? Like, I, uh, it, it
might have been last year or the year before, at some point, I talked about how somewhere in
your game you need to have like one bathroom, right? Like, just to fill out the fact that, you
know, these are people and there's a bathroom somewhere, right? Like, those are the kind of
things that flesh out whatever it is that you're trying to do. And I think having, um,
you know, having little nooks or dead ends that the player's going to discover, and if they feel
like they found something cool, then it enhances their experience. So it's, I mean, I'd put as
many, like, interesting little side paths as I can get on the environment art budget.
I think we've got time for one more. Yeah?
My name's Ben. I'd like to point out always looking at the larger context of things. So I was
wondering what
How big a role do other levels play in the design of your level?
When I'm working on something on a sort of a day-to-day basis,
not that much.
I mean, unless I'm looking at, well, they've got a mechanic that I find really interesting.
Like, we had a decompression mechanic in Dead Space 2, which got repurposed for like a million
different things in other levels, not always just decompression.
So there's that element of it.
But that's actually one of the reasons why when we were doing DS3, we started out at
the beginning trying to look at things from a very high level, because we wanted to have
this experience where there was...
sort of more open or hub like moments followed by a more linear section bridging you to kind of
another hub. And at that point that dictated a lot because we had a vision for what the overall
game flow was going to be and that dictated what the flow of the individual levels were in
relation to the other bits of content, right? It also just depends on how much your stuff flows
together. You know if you're making like a Bioshock 1 or something where you can actually
move and backtrack a lot then it does matter a lot.
Thanks.
Nice job.
Awesome.
All right.
Thank you, Seth.
That was great.
So we've got a 15 minute break,
and then Joel's talk, how we shipped Skyrim
and Fallout 3 using iterative level design,
except backwards.
That will be in 15 minutes, so go hit the head,
grab a drink, and come back 15 minutes.
We'll pick it up promptly.
Thank you.