get started. It is a long title for this talk. Whose game is it anyway is the question. How
community relationships shape games, five years of Warframe. So that's what we're going
to talk about today. My name is Rebecca Ford. I do live...
Stop!
I paid them all to do that.
I'm, yes, I do live ops and community at Digital Extremes.
I've been there for about seven years
and I've worked exclusively on Warframe in that time.
So there's two things on this
that you might need to know a bit more about
to understand the context of this talk
and that is who are Digital Extremes and what is Warframe.
So geographically, Digital Extremes,
London, Ontario, Canada, my beautiful,
I know we have a multimedia guy here on our team
who probably hates this slide.
But that's an arrow pointing to us.
Our closest US city is Detroit, so that could give you
an idea of climate and or other things.
But the company has been around for 25 years, actually,
this year.
This is 1993 founding.
And in 2012, things really changed for the company,
and that is because of Warframe.
So this is a marketing version of what the game is.
In my words, it's free to play.
It's co-op.
It's a third person action looter shooter.
And that's what's, you know, we've been doing it for five years,
and I'm standing here today to tell you about that journey.
And I'll do it kind of structured in the classic Agenda style.
This is sort of what we're going to get through today.
We're going to talk about how we operate with Warframe
as a free-to-play game that's been operating for five years.
Then we're gonna get to the hits and the misses.
This is sort of, if you take as many swings at bat
as we have with all our updates,
some of them are hits and some are misses,
and when I say misses, this isn't disparaging work
that we've done a bad job,
it's just the way the community responded to it.
And we have an amazing group of developers
and just sometimes things don't go the way we had hoped.
And then if there are questions at the end,
we can absolutely talk about those.
So again, multimedia cringe,
but I tried to make my character look like
the operation board game guy, but it didn't work.
So anyway, we went from a 750 meg file to 30 gigs.
That's a lot of growth.
That's a lot of game changes.
And how did we do it?
I bolded the only word that matters, which is consistency,
but the rest is, you know, good note taking.
It's because we really do update consistently with Warframe.
When you're a Warframe player on PC,
every week you're getting something.
If you're a Warframe player on console,
likely every month you're getting something,
and that consistency sort of makes its way in three areas.
It's either a fix, a change, an addition,
one of those, all of those, some combination of the two,
or the three, rather.
And that's a routine that our players really expect.
If it's a Wednesday on PC,
and we don't have a hotfix node out,
the players start asking,
where is it, what's happening this week?
And we tell them.
We say, okay, well guess what?
We are a bit late with this week's update,
so expect it tomorrow.
Or we tell them, oops, it's actually gonna be Friday.
Or sometimes we say, actually,
we can't do anything this week.
But the communication is always consistent as well.
And that's with every relationship, I think it's the first part that is a take away is
that the community understands our routine of what we're doing with Warframe and when
they come to the forums to see what update we have, they know that we're going to have
something for them to read, whether it is the update or status of where that is.
But that routine has visuals.
It looks like this.
A weekly update for five years tends to change
the way the game looks.
So in 2012, a player would have come to Warframe
and seen what's on the left there.
They saw some blue menus,
they saw their character in the middle.
And in 2018, if a player comes to Warframe,
they see, you know, this is the same screen.
It serves the same function,
but they're seeing five years of growth and consistency.
They're seeing a UI overhaul.
They're seeing better lighting.
They're seeing a physical space for their character
rather than sort of floating in space.
And they see cloth physics, which is great.
That's a great from a dev lens, you know, you can see really clearly the improvement that the game has gone through from the hard work of a team.
But from the community lens, because that's what we're talking about today, it looks a little more like this.
It's Space Barbies now. We have hot pink and we have...
purples and we have a very, very nice stance going on here.
And I know it's a bit of a joke to say space Barbies,
but the relationship that this picture shows
actually is quite in depth.
And it starts with something silly like a bobblehead.
Cause you know, when Warframe added spaceships to the game,
players thought a good thing for a spaceship
would be a bobblehead.
So Dev made it so.
And players are quite talented, and the community can really
foster some interesting artistic talent.
So we started doing user-generated content,
and players had that idea.
We were able to do it, so dev made it so.
We have my, I think it's my right foot on my left thigh,
looking quite graceful, because players wanted
more in-depth customization.
So they said, we should be able to mix and match
animation stances, so dev made it so.
I'm holding a gun here that is only accessible
if you've played the game for a long time.
It's a loyalty reward of sorts, a login reward system.
Our original login system wasn't particularly rewarding,
so the players wanted a new one, so dev made it so,
and now you can get weapons through it.
And the last sort of thing that's hidden behind all my other arrows, I guess,
is a beautiful cape.
You know, what's a game without capes?
But that was something that Dev actually wanted.
They thought having cloth physics in Warframe,
being a little more robust, would make it look better.
And players agreed.
So Dev wanted it. Players thought, hey, that's pretty cool.
So again, Dev made it so.
And that's really the simplified version
of how our relationship works.
can want something and dev makes it so.
But of course it's not that simple
because there's sometimes thousands of players
when we were starting and now we have millions of players.
So when millions of players want something
and you only have about 200 devs to make it so,
how can you solve that problem?
So what we try to do is empower our community team
to try and make sense of all that,
to prioritize, to learn how to say no or yes
to either sides of this equation, the beginning or the end.
And basically with this structure,
we've been able to have a lot of hits and misses
with our community.
We have tried a lot of different things
in Warframe's lifetime.
And it's been a long and wonderful five years,
and we will start talking about what the hits and misses
have been with the community relationships
on these deployments.
And when I say deployments, I truly mean
a lot of deployments and a lot of swings over time.
This is some publicly available data from Steam.
It's our concurrency on Steamspy,
so you can see that we started,
and luckily we've grown and grown,
and it's going up and it's great.
And of course, there's timestamps of years on this,
so we should talk about those years,
and we should talk about what happened,
what good and bad things happened
with the community relationship based on Warframe.
So a bit more structure for you, as time is linear,
I will start in 2012 and make my way over the years
leading up to today to really give you a hit,
give you a miss, talk about what we did, and then recap it.
But all Warframe stories should probably start
at the beginning, so to 2012 we go.
So once upon a time, Digital Extremes, the company,
is mid-layoffs, and Warframe really is a last ditch effort
for the company to not go under.
So this year we were, the hit of this year was infrastructure.
And this is something that isn't reflected in the game,
but it's reflected in the tools we built around the game
to do it ourselves.
Because we had no publisher.
We only had the sort of, I'll say,
desperation to make it work.
So what did that mean?
We did a lot of research into things like Zendesk
having forums, having a scalable back end,
which is some fun stuff to work with for a free-to-play game.
How are people going to download the game client?
How are they going to log in?
How are they going to authenticate emails?
So doing all that type of research,
it was a very accessible game in 2012,
which was great if the game didn't have a miss,
such as bad free-to-play design.
So not that it was bad, it was just
we were making a lot of mistakes.
And those mistakes are scary when you're doing it yourself
because to release a free-to-play game
and have some of the first reactions to it be pay-to-win,
That's very dangerous and for us, very early on, we really spent a lot of time making mistakes
that we didn't know we were making because we had never done free-to-play before, which
could be the case for some of you, could not be the case, but it's scary and it feels really
bad to see that your community that was born two months ago is starting to say things about
it.
the game that you might not have realized was negative.
And it's really easy to pinpoint,
if you listen to the community,
what the mistakes looked like.
So another red arrow, a different styled one this time,
is pointing at this gold icon,
which our community calls potatoes,
which in early 2012, Miss Warframe signified pay to win.
It signified having access to power levels
through real money.
And that was bad, and that's not a good way to start your free-to-play journey.
So what did we do?
It's quite misleadingly simple, in fact.
This year we just listened and changed very quickly.
So we're sitting at forums that, of course, we did not invent forums,
using software for support that, of course, we did not invent.
But we used it with the desperation of a company that was on its last legs
to really do what we said we wanted to do,
and that was to make fair free-to-play.
And what we found was that relying on the community
to decide what is and isn't fair
was a really important part of early Warframe.
And we knew from, you know,
as we learned from the error of our ways,
which had no malice behind them,
we were just simply, we didn't know.
We knew that we wanted fair, free to play
to be a part of Warframe's DNA.
Which leads us to the next year after 2012, which is 2013,
which is a year that was really interesting for Warframe.
We started doing some real-time communication
with our communities that did change the relationship.
And the first hit of this year
isn't an in-game thing yet again.
It's the way we talked about our game,
which was with dev streams.
So dev streams are something we started in 2013.
We've been doing them for five years now bi-weekly.
This is a thumbnail from almost every stream we've done.
Get all the devs on there,
sometimes the regular crew, sometimes not.
What we did was we just talked about the game.
We talked about what's changing,
and we used it as
a scalable way to answer questions from our community.
If you have 200 forum posts asking the same question,
you can answer one and hope your answer spreads,
or you can see that there's clearly a need for a broader,
more scalable communication, in which case,
ta-da, we did Devstreams.
We do them on Twitch.
It's one of the many tools we use for community.
including, you know, you have your forums, you have Reddit,
you have, of course, DevStreams, the Wikia is good for us,
as well as, you know, your web tools
that you can sort of customize for blogs and what it may be.
But these have been great and, you know,
five years going with them.
However, in the actual game sense,
a hit this year for the community was Clans.
This is an explicit social structure in Warframe.
This is someone coming into Warframe, doing their missions,
but then staying in Warframe because their clanmates are there.
And they're staying in Warframe because they get to build this
space treehouse dojo that is theirs and theirs alone.
And that's really great for the social and relationship experience between clans, but...
Statistically, we've found that the sooner someone's in a clan, the longer they play
Warframe, the more they engage with, so it's good for retention as well.
And it's actually also really interesting from a relationship point of view, because
clans have identities.
You know, if you've been in a clan that's PvP focused, or perhaps customization focused,
competitive, it gives people on the inside a way to access...
a member of that clan, perhaps the leader of it,
and get really concise information about players
with that goal set for the game.
So they're really useful if you can get close
with the clan members sometimes.
They don't wanna get close to you, but it's totally fine.
You just gotta make it work.
Yes, now The Mist.
This is always the fun part because things go wrong.
This is a fun comic from Penny Arcade.
You know, you got your player.
your Warframe landing in and he looks over at his co-op buddy and he's all decked out in cosmetics because of course
In free-to-play you'll often find cosmetics are a way to monetize and we have done that with great success
But it's not always been a consistent success because early Warframe
Stats had cosmetics and if you're buying something and it changes the way you play that's also dangerous for free-to-play. So
We stopped doing that in 2013. We said no more stats on cosmetics
But the eternal war had only begun in that line of work
because here I am in 2018 with a screenshot of my character
with a helmet that has stats on it.
So in 2013, we got rid of stats on cosmetics,
but in 2018, I still have the item.
So how can that be?
How can these things coexist?
And the answer is community relationships are complicated.
So this is when your eyes may begin to lose focus
because it's a lot of words on a slide,
but it is a complicated history
and that's sort of the essence of change
and community growth is that there usually is a history.
So in 2012 and 2013, our nice looking helmets
had stats on them that Dev decided.
But in 2013, we saw that the community didn't want that
because they didn't want to have to spend money
on things that changed the way they looked.
So we said, okay, no more stats, but guess what?
Anyone that had that item, you're grandfathered in
because you can't take away a loyal player's investment.
So then 2014 rolls around and those loyal players
wanted to take off those stats,
so we added a tool for them to do that.
And then 2015 rolls around and you know what?
What if we put stats back on cosmetics
but players could choose their own stats?
So we did that.
And now it's 2018 and literally two weeks ago,
cosmetics don't have stats anymore.
So if that's making your head explode,
that's sort of the point.
Community relationships are complicated,
and just a little slice of the work we do,
even if something as simple as stats on cosmetics,
it has history, and the history always,
in our case, at least we try to respect
the player investment up until that point.
So a loyal player that liked the stats on cosmetics,
they should get to keep them,
even though we're changing the way the system works.
So yeah, it's sort of 2013's myth that carries on
to the eternal war to this day.
But what did we do?
In the same way that Goku can take the energy of people
and turn it into something useful on the community team,
we sort of tried to do the same thing.
You really just need to focus on the consistency
across the players' messages to you
to make sure that what you're taking in
and putting back out is useful.
And you know, nothing's better than a spirit bomb sometimes.
But, great.
Recapping that real quick, in 2013 what we found was,
for this relationship with our Warframe players,
we had to grow our channels to communicate
and we had to use them to talk about change.
We don't just sit on a dev stream and say,
here's a new thing you can buy in two months.
It's, hey, guess what?
This change is coming again.
And you know, you see Twitch chat explode
with sometimes negativity, but that's okay
because you're there and you're gonna deal
with it on the spot.
And 2014 rolls around as you would expect.
And for the game this year, things went a little rapidly crazy with change.
We're on a
of a year where we're changing combat, we're changing visuals, and we're actually adding
story to our little looter shooter.
So in, you know, 2014 we have our hit.
I'm not going to play the sound on this, or will I, because I don't have a choice.
Okay, I'll talk over it.
But this is Melee 2.0.
So Melee 2.0 comes around, it allows a player to equip their melee weapon and do combos,
they can block incoming fire, and they get to equip that sword and that sword alone.
Up until this point, players had only been able to quick melee,
so their swords were sheathed, and they could only pull them out quickly
and maybe do a charge attack, but that was it.
And we redid our melee system because the players wanted us to.
They were growing a collection of melee weapons that they felt were too similar,
and they thought it was about time that we redid that system.
So if you've been making a game for two years at this point,
and you hear it's time to redo systems...
Well, you better get started if you're us.
So we didn't just redo it, we redid it sort of biweekly reports to our community.
We showed our team, our community rather, through the dev streams like here's a gray
box of what I was working on two minutes ago and this is what it's probably going to look
like because it allowed us to, and then the one on the other.
that's actually a really cool gift,
but that one is a newer melee thing that's coming
because we're still working on this.
Even in 2014, introducing the system was one thing,
but players still wanted more,
so we continued to revisit it to this day.
And that was a massive change for the game
because we added so much more to the system
that players were asking for in the effect of,
I want to go out there with my own sword like a ninja
instead of always having to have a gun with me.
And we did it.
and we showed them the progress.
So, a miss.
The words grind frame sometimes come to mind
for people with Warframe, and it's not, you know,
I play all the time and this is the world we live in,
but it's easy for us to sometimes contribute
to that narrative if we're not careful.
And we're never malicious about anything,
but it's just really hard to balance resources
in a free-to-play game, because the way players engage freely
with your game, they have to earn their gear,
and they get to go collect resources.
And this particular resource, you know,
it looks quite innocuous at a glance,
it's nice and crystally, but it's actually called Oxium,
and it's something we added to the game
just to give players something else to go after
to build the new content we were making.
Because we're adding, and in order to have people
start all from the same place to get that gear,
everyone gets a new resource to go after to do it.
And sometimes we miss the mark on balancing that and understanding that a player maybe
doesn't want to spend six hours doing the same thing over and over again, or maybe they're
okay with it if the gameplay is a little different.
But ultimately, Oxiom represents sort of the beginning of the difficulties we've had with
resource balancing.
And what's really interesting statistically is when the community notices, which, you
know, they notice the moments that something like this happens, they keep track of it.
And there's often a point from the community where they'll say something like, you guys
must be raking in the platinum because you made this so hard to get.
And that's actually not true.
A lot of the data that we've looked into for this.
is if you look at something that has a high grind cost,
it doesn't actually sell any better
than the things that are easier to make.
So we're not really benefiting from it at all.
All it's doing is giving the community points of,
basically pain points to say,
this doesn't feel good and you shouldn't do this.
So you always need to think about that
before you release something.
But if you're releasing an economy from scratch,
you do your best, but it doesn't always go right.
So what did we do this year?
In many ways, we just took it all in.
The great things that were coming from Melee 2.0
were extremely positive feedback,
engagement with the Melee system.
Players were very satisfied with that,
but at the same time, we were taking in all the feedback
about what players were saying Warframe was becoming,
which was grind frame, which has a negative connotation,
but ultimately, the way of the game is to get your resources.
So it's tricky.
So you just take it in.
And in 2014, we learned that change is one thing,
overhauling is another.
So don't just change, of course.
You should overhaul.
And when the community does start to weigh in
on grind tolerance, take note.
So on our team, we were taking note of how,
what was the difference between someone saying,
oh, I can't get this now,
or the more voices added to that
particular line of feedback.
All right, another year, here we go, 2015.
This was a really interesting year for Warframe.
We added our first cinematic quest this year,
as well as our first region locked content,
which simply put, we added a really good surprise this year
and a really bad surprise.
So the good surprise was the second dream.
And I do have a little video on this
because of course the word community relationships
were heavily in my title.
Having a good surprise for a player at this point who had been playing for three years,
the way they reacted to us surprising them with content that told an emotional story,
because up until this point, you know, you're going into different maps,
you're shooting, you're getting your loot, your character's starting to feel really awesome,
but there's no emotional weight to what you're doing
to the degree of what we unleashed this year with The Second Dream.
So I'll quickly play this video.
And it's just a collection...
Well, you'll see, I'll show it.
Wow. Oh my god, that looks sick. What is going on?
Oh my god. That is mind-fuckingly amazing. Just incredible. Oh my god. What?
Oh my god, that's so cool. Oh, you gotta be kidding me. Wow, this is so cool.
This was unbelievably amazing.
Oh my god, I enjoyed that more than anything I've ever enjoyed in Warframe.
Right, so if you are in a three-year relationship
with your community and for the first time ever
you get a reaction like that, it feels great.
And the reason we were able to do it
is because we surprised them.
So on the one hand you have these dev streams
and you're showing the gray boxes of your melee animations,
you're showing just crazy things happening
in the game that they expect.
And then to deliver the unexpected
to that loyal player base, yielded a reaction like that,
which for the relationship with the community
really expressed a turning point in,
not only did they want us.
They didn't just want the entertainment of Warframe space ninjas, they now wanted more story and they wanted to relive this moment again.
So we've been trying to do that year after year. It's not easy, but we'll get there.
So that's a good surprise, but a bad surprise. This picture again quite innocuous without context, but this is Umbra.
This is when 2015 hit Warframe
got a deal to launch in China and to hype it up we
had added region-exclusive content to that build.
And the global player base saw it and said,
when do we get that?
And we didn't have an answer, because we didn't know.
So everyone's Google translating the Chinese press release.
I'm reading them saying, is this true?
What's going on here?
Because we had a bad surprise in many ways.
And we weren't prepared.
to communicate this information to our loyal players
who wanted nothing more than to know
when they were getting this.
Which, by the way, they still haven't gotten.
And even last year when we announced Warframe's open world
on live television, the most used words in chat were Umbra
because they had waited so long.
And even though we just minorly teased Umbra last year,
that's what the Twitch chat really grabbed onto.
So you can see on the left-hand side.
So that's a bad surprise.
There's always hindsight with community relationships.
I wish we had communicated it differently.
I wish we had known about it in advance.
But that doesn't, you can't, that'll never work.
You can never go back and redo something
in a community relationship.
So what did we do?
Well, we did two things.
On the one hand, it was, you know,
with the dawn of streaming and YouTubing,
I'm sure everyone sees how big that's getting,
having the players broadcast themselves,
playing our content, allowed us to capture the moments
that really,
you know, the surprise and delight of doing a Warframe quest for the first time.
And on the other hand, uh...
We had to try and put out a lot of fires with Umbra
that we actually continue to do to this day.
And what can you do?
Bad surprises linger, but there's a thirst for it now,
which is kind of interesting to observe.
But either way, 2015 was all about taking risks
and really planning to surprise our loyal players
with the good surprises, but not bad ones.
Well, what can you do if a bad surprise comes out?
Because usually you're caught in the crossfire as well.
So, on the heels of that inspiring reaction video
about The Second Dream, 2016 rolls around
and the way that the players reacted to The Second Dream
was starting to sort of deteriorate the desperation DNA
we were having as a company,
because we really felt like we were onto something.
Because when your game you've been working on
for three years starts to elicit a response like that,
it really feels like, okay, we're doing this now.
Let's see what we can do with this.
So, of course, what best way to take a...
a successful moment than to not just turn around and look back and say,
what did we leave behind along the way?
So 2016's hit was a little bit of nostalgia.
Up until this point, the game had continued to change, grow.
I don't know exactly what our file size was in 2016,
but you know point A was 750 and point B today is 30.
So we're talking somewhere around 20 gigs probably.
and that's a lot of change and additions.
So we decided to redo our navigation system
for about the fourth time this year
because the players wanted us to.
We had given them this in 2016 and a bit earlier,
which was a console-friendly, we thought,
a user-friendly way to navigate our game.
You know what planet you're going to,
you pick your mission tile.
But it turns out the players didn't like it
and had been telling us for a long time.
And not only that, it actually was worse
for retention, statistically.
So.
with all great things, go back to some nostalgic roots,
and return the star chart to its node and line form,
which was something the players had really wanted
since we abandoned it for the tile system.
And this brought, even though this was a bit
of a bumpy launch, as it can happen,
the players saw our commitment to the past Warframe vision
and felt that even though we had changed the story
in the year prior, the roots were still there, especially.
in the visuals access points to all things Warframe.
Every planet and every mission was starting to look
a little more like it used to.
And Amiss this year, so with every hit comes Amiss,
this is something that, again, it's a brief video,
that it was the most fun I think a lot of people
at DE had developing it, which has,
that doesn't mean the player as well.
So let's take a look.
You have refused the blood of the conclaves.
I call to you to join us in honor-bound tradition.
Team Aurora, at the ready!
Okay, so we were at PAX and we were coming off the heels of the second dream and we showed
that video and we were all grinning because we were like, yes, players are going to love
this.
And because we love, you know, you heard the chanting in the video, that's the devs in
the theater, like having a great time.
We were adding a sport to Warframe because Warframe is not a competitive game, it's cooperative.
So surely the way to do competition is with a sport.
and it was just silent, the reaction at PAX East.
And we had to release it, of course,
and we still, I still love it,
and I just know that even though we loved making it,
it did not resonate with our player base at all.
And you kind of had to.
acknowledge that.
And you had to look at it and look at the way it released
and say, okay, I guess we're not updating
that content type anymore,
even though we had a lot of fun making it.
Which was sort of, what did we do, right?
Well, in the same way that,
we tried, and honestly, the team worked so hard
on surprising our players with different things,
and I wouldn't have not done it ever
because it was just so fun.
But the players understood that we were taking risks
and trying, and they're not gonna be mad
about your mom embarrassing you.
you know, it's fine.
And we also found that this year, 2016,
we were really hitting our stride on our platform launches.
So we're not just a PC game anymore,
we're also on PlayStation 4 and Xbox.
So things were starting to get a little muddy
about who's getting what information.
So because we eat a lot of Domino's pizza,
we thought we should do a pizza tracker for our builds.
So we built, because you know you get your pizza,
George is making it and Tracy's bringing it to you.
So on our website, we built a sort of,
that version for our platforms.
So on PC, there's really only two states
in development and live,
but on consoles you have development, cert, and live.
And these always point to a human source of information.
So one of our community members on that team
makes a thread, says, hey everyone, guess what?
the build's in the oven, and it's going to have this, this, and this,
and we'll let you know when it's insert.
And we used this, we just made this little widget.
It points to, you know, different statuses and different links
for you to always base in our forms,
just to have these conversations with your players
about where their builds are.
And of course, if you have a complex multi-platform game
with no build parity, you might want something like this,
which is our case.
So, yeah, 2016, what we learned that year
was never stop changing and overhauling.
And as a group of devs who have, at this point,
four years of lessons, the fun you have developing
something might not resonate with your players,
and maybe you should move on quickly from that,
if that's the case.
And so we did, even though, I don't think I played it in our own like a year, but I'm
going to now because I got nostalgic, which apparently was a lesson from 2015.
Oh no, actually 2016, sorry.
Anywho, so 2017, this is last year, and this was a year for Warframe when we talk a literal
community relationship.
We had one of the worst.
and best moments in the same year.
So I'm gonna start with the miss this year,
and then I'll talk about the hit.
So whatever structure I gave the past years,
just not anymore, the miss.
So DE versus data mining.
So for all these years now,
we had really turned a blind eye
to the data mining side of Warframe
while we had done things under the hood,
you know, to make sure that we weren't leaking content,
that we weren't ready to announce or anything.
We just really hadn't.
acknowledged it, I suppose.
But when we literally ask the question,
whose game is it anyway?
If someone has a free game on their PC,
is it within their rights to go through the files
and start looking at things?
And that's the community's vision of it.
So we're not one to say, okay, stop doing that,
unless it gets ugly.
And this year it got ugly.
We were seeing some things happening that,
remember that Umbra I was talking about
that isn't in the global build.
it was in the global build somehow because somehow some people had hacked it and added it in and we were able to conclude
where it was coming from and what the source of it was so we had to take action and it was in that time that the
players had
seen an action from us that they felt was the worst thing we had ever done by going after data mining
we had become the bad guy because we were now trying to hide things and any transparency
that they felt Datamine offered them as a community to see like, oh, DE screwed up a
drop rate or whatever it may be had vanished by us taking action.
So it was really tricky because we, like, of course we would have handled it differently
now.
And we just at the time were really scared because we didn't want
things leaking because again we were wanting to surprise and delight our community again
with something like the second dream and that was the hit of this year which was open world.
So you have your sort of data mining scandal and then all of a sudden all eyes are on us because
we have a big announcement for our community. We want to tell them we have something really
exciting for you guys and that was open world. This was a day in Warframe's history where we
walked through a set of doors and showed the community what we were sort of being so secretive
about.
And that was this, this was the Plains of Eidolon announcement,
which we did live in front of our audience, and it was wonderful.
And this was a really great moment for Warframe and the community,
because they saw us do something that they and we had said was impossible.
And our procedural game had gone from that.
thanks to the developers to now open world.
And that was a really special moment in the relationship
because it was that surprise and delight
without it even being released yet,
which was quite exciting.
And what did we do?
Well, we looked and we said,
wow, people really liked that.
You released this most hype update in Warframe's history
and we took a look at it
and we saw that it had put Warframe in a position
it had never reached before.
And it of course reinforces the ambition
to do things like that.
of course, leading into this year as well.
And that was a really, really, really exciting time for us
because we had a community that was overwhelmed
with support for the idea that we were going to do that.
But so, of course, you're excited and want
to keep that alive.
But when I go back to data mining just now,
because I'm going to tell you what we did about that,
because data mining is really tricky,
and we're a free-to-play game.
We have drop rates.
So what did we do in that situation when that happened?
We built a drop site repository because we saw the most
The most feedback on the the players point of view about us going after dynamiters was that we're not being honest anymore
And we felt that the best way to be honest was to give them the info directly for what they were looking for
So now the community team has a new routine every update
thanks to some tools that Dev built us
that we basically run a script of every drop table in the game
and output it to a web page and upload it to our web server
and we update it any time our drop tables get touched.
we did it because we recognized that the community wanted that information and
they were getting it but if we could provide it ourselves, you know, we would
show them that we didn't go after data mining for that reason, it was a broader
issue with hacking.
And this website, even I use it all the time
because it allows people just to get information
about Warframe more quickly.
And that's someone that's engaged in your game
and they want to know more.
And it's very rare for someone to go,
which is actually quite surprising.
People don't go on this website and look at it
and send screenshots to our inbox
about how rare something is
because that's not what we want to do.
We have rarities, of course,
but we're not in it to look to trick anyone
into a rarity that they may or may not have expected.
So yeah, this website is an interesting thing.
We only added it last year.
It starts with a disclaimer about, you know,
we don't even know if we should be doing this,
but you guys want it, so here we go.
And yeah, but there's some people in the room
that have helped build this, so I can see them now.
Thank you.
It's been great for the community relationship,
which I can, of course, succinctly recap
in sort of the advice that if you become the enemy
in a relationship, work on repairing it
with more than words.
which is what that website represents as an action
because you can always say,
don't worry, we're not gonna do X, Y, or Z,
but if you show a plan to address the community concerns,
it is great for the community relationship.
And of course, if you're years into your game
like we are at this point,
you should definitely do things that were once impossible.
So open world Warframe, for example.
which has been fun.
So, you know, whose game is it anyway?
That is the question that we are trying to answer.
And the best way I can talk about that
in the context of Warframe is that it's shared.
We've added so much to the game
based on what the community has wanted.
And the community has seen that our ability
to add these things.
is shaping, working into what it is today.
And we, you know, you try and do it in that
the community wants something,
the devs are the only ones that can do it,
so how do you make, how do you reconcile that?
And that's where we stand in the middle
with the community team.
And after five years, what we've really tried to...
view in this relationship we have is that the players really are citizens.
When I was talking about dev streams,
you probably have been watching perhaps or put on dev streams of
your own that are a bit political and title something like state of
the game or other things that sound just a bit more,
this is more than just a game because really you're dealing with a group of people,
your player base that have a voice and bring
their loyalty to your game and their interest and their passion,
and they should be represented in the same way.
that other governments work.
Not that we're a government, but, you know,
citizens, not government.
Totally different words.
Also, so we also have tried to have the community team
have a seat at the dev table after these five years,
just making sure that, you know, in 2014,
if we had a resource problem,
maybe the next time we're introducing a new resource,
the community team knows about it,
and we're looking, and we're,
trying not to repeat the issues we had done in the past.
Because really, all it has been about
is learning from our mistakes as early as 2012
when we weren't doing free to play right.
And that's continued year over year.
And with DevStreams and whatever else we do in that capacity
we've found that transparency is painful but crucial
and it's good to humanize and admit mistakes.
We find sitting down on the DevStream couch or whatever,
setting is appropriate at the time.
To admit a mistake on camera is really humbling,
and it really shows the players that you are
capable of making mistakes, because one thing that happens,
and you often hear fan language is,
you know, I have faith in this developer.
And when you get that sort of faith-based belief
in a developer system, it's dangerous,
because mistakes are frequent.
They are.
We try to make it clear it's not out of malice,
because that's the most dangerous part of a relationship
is if they feel the decisions you've made
are out of malice, which we try very regularly
to reinforce they're not.
But I did that quickly, because it's the last presentation
and GDC perhaps for some of you.
So that is it.
So I have 40 minutes of talk for you guys.
So.
I shouldn't have talked over the videos.
They could have just run.
But if you do have any questions,
now would be a good time to line up at either microphone side.
And if not, that's totally cool, too.
Thank you very much.
You know, you were talking a lot at the beginning
about how the.
The players ask for something and so the devs make it so.
And I was wondering, how do you...
Sometimes it seems like that might not be good for the game.
Like, maybe the players don't know what's best,
or maybe there's a vocal minority that isn't really speaking for the larger player base.
So I was wondering how you tackle those kind of concerns.
Right, so what we try to do is take what the players want and make sure it's actually a scaled want.
So a dev stream for us is a really good example because when we generate questions for it,
we look to see what the actual most used words are.
And then if we see a high frequency of the same request, we address it on air.
And then we literally on air say yes or no sometimes
and try, if we think it's bad for the game,
we'll say no, sometimes we'll say why.
And if we think it's good for the game,
we sort of build a wish list of things
that are good victories to add to the game
for the community.
And what's surprising about that
in regards to players wanting things is.
They typically do want realistic things.
Like there are things that you can of course say no to,
you know, like turn Warframe into first person
or do something like that, which we do say no to,
but generally if a player is at the point in this community
to ask for something, they ask it and they typically,
they explain why they want it, which allows us to,
you know, address it more on the nose
in the scheme of Warframe's design and future.
Cool, thank you.
Hi, have you ever had to tackle pockets of toxicity in your community,
either community to each other or community to dev?
Yes, so toxicity in the community is, I think, many games face it,
and we have had to deal with it time over time,
and we really look at why it's happening,
and a lot of what we've found in dealing with it,
you know, basic moderation is really helpful, of course, you can read out.
with all your tools, get someone out of there
that's swearing, doing this, doing that.
But if there's, for example, a clan
that's particularly toxic, that's harder to deal with
because there's a lot more of the toxic individuals.
And we try to make sure that we're as strict
with our code as conduct as possible.
So if we can clearly see, like you violated this,
you're out, there's no disputing it.
But sometimes, pitchforks come out, right?
And toxicity can spread, especially if it becomes
an us versus them scenario.
And I always just try and work with that on our team
as well.
succinctly as possible and using our guidelines to work with it.
Thank you very much.
Hello.
Hi.
Are there any, you talk a lot about engaging with the community in general.
Are there particular platforms or communities that you find easier to use or better for
reaching a large audience or particular audience?
I am a really big, so in terms of tools to engage with our community, I do think DevStreams
have worked out really well for that because we've just built this sort of five-year familial
bond about what we're working on.
You know, Warframe is going to always change and grow, so why not use a tool that's...
not super polished in our case,
but really honest about what we're doing.
That one, again, has been huge.
I would say right now,
it's really nice to rely on Discord a bit more.
Our official forums are like the library of Alexandria.
They house everything we've ever done,
and they're not the best for conversing.
So you have to pick what your goal is for
a particular engagement and use
something more accommodating to that,
which Discord is great for conversations, of course.
Awesome, thank you.
Sweet.
Hi, I'm, oh sorry.
Hi, it's, most of the talk was about the early years
until, up until 2017.
I'm just curious, what are the challenges so far this year
and what's Warframe like in 2018 with the community?
So 2018 has been actually really interesting
because we haven't released, actually Tuesday of this week
marked the release of new content.
We hadn't added a single weapon or warframe this whole year
so far up until Tuesday.
So the year has been one of, you know,
I was talking about change and nostalgia in 2016.
It's heavily been on that for the first part of the year.
We've gone and looked at every weapon
we've released in the primary and the secondary capacity
and rebalanced them.
So the devs have been working hard on.
basically doing spring cleaning, but more winter cleaning,
for all the game's content, rather than adding a new gun,
or something like that.
So it's really been an exercise in revision.
And it's interesting to see how the communities responded,
because again, they're used to consistency.
But the consistency this year, the weekly updates,
have been cleanups, rather than, here's your brand new XYZ.
Thanks.
And we told them that.
We said, hey, you're not getting new stuff this year.
You might have noticed, and they were okay with it.
Hi, so a company I worked at previously,
like the community definitely did not have
a favorable view of us.
So frequently when we released even a positive announcement,
it would get twisted around.
And so I was just curious,
what sort of like language was most twisted against you
and how did you reframe your wording of it?
The language is, we are, I feel like one,
it's not a tactic, it's just a thing that's happened
in terms of language we've used.
We talk so much on DevStreams,
it's really hard to pinpoint the bad things we've said
because we talk so much and they can't get mad
about that one, like, oh, we're listening
because we say it in so many different ways all the time.
But when it comes to the community.
picking a moment to think that DE is doing a bad job of something
and therefore what is coming should not be celebrated.
It's typically in the growth of the game and the idea of neglect, right?
So if a player sees we're adding something new,
they'll say, that's great, but what about all the other stuff you've left behind?
And they often criticize any...
any new things as bad because other things are being abandoned.
So for example, when we added Lunaro,
you could imagine that the PVE players that wanted endgame were like,
what? Why are you working on this and not that?
You know there's all the false dichotomy ways to talk about it,
but we try and address that.
We see the bubbling.
discontent and just say, well, that's actually not true
because here's work that's also happening at the same time.
But sometimes you might not have that luxury
because you've become the enemy so greatly,
like we had with the data mining situation.
And you just don't give up.
We just don't stop trying, is the best way I could say that.
Thank you.
So I was curious, how early do you guys talk about the things
you're working on?
So like for our game, we have a really hard balance
between like we want to talk about stuff early
and let people know we're thinking about the things
they're concerned about, but if it's too early,
we don't know exactly what we're gonna do yet,
and then we are taking things away from them,
we're breaking our promises when we change our mind,
and if it's too late, then we're just being told
that we're ignoring them, but we're not.
So how do you find that balance?
So the issue of showing something and never shipping it
is a very frequent one for us.
I believe in, I don't want to simplify this,
but if you made a list of stuff we've shown on DevStreams
versus stuff we shipped, they'd probably be even
because we just show whips all the time
and we make it clear that that's what's happening.
So if something's really close to being a shipped item,
we demo it a bit.
more confidently, I would say.
Whereas if something's like, here's some concept art
that could be a new faction in a year,
we kind of say that because we know our own work pace
and we know that no matter what it's gonna happen for us
if we release something people expect it to come out.
So we try very hard to emphasize the actual progress of what it is we're showing.
And we just want to show it.
Like even if it is a year away, we typically do show it just because we want to.
So it's at your call of course, and it is a struggle.
And it's whether or not you're...
prepared to lower expectations about things that you yourself have doubt about.
Like it'll be a time on a stream where someone's really talking optimistically
about something and I'm like I don't even think I've seen work started on
that and I'll say that out loud just to make sure players see that this is messy
because things aren't easy all the time.
So does the community now have an expectation
that a lot of that stuff could not be that way
and sort of accept it now?
Yep, it's amazing the power of their own wisdom
about how we operate at this point
because they are able to set their own expectations
sort of as a group, which is nice.
Cool, thank you.
Yes.
Hello.
Yeah, sorry.
I just wondering, as you have said,
you release a version later in China, right?
Yes.
When you're referring to the community,
you're referring to the global community or different country
community.
As I know, some players in some different countries,
they have different or conflict opinions on these
to the same released version.
So do you have any?
share experience about the conflict opinions?
It is tricky with conflicting regions.
The only true region restrictions are mainland China
for that build, and the rest of the world
is considered global.
And it's been, in that respect,
there have been conflicting opinions
about stuff we've released,
the way the community responds to it.
overall, and it's always just a matter of,
luckily we have an in-house team that's able to
help with region-specific issues.
They do mainly do support, but they also can help
with community stuff, and they bring that to our attention,
and if it's a developer issue, we try and resolve it.
Like, if we accidentally release something that looked
not appropriate for a specific culture,
we'll remedy that based on the advice
of those region-specific communities.
Well, okay, thanks.
Hi. Um, yeah, what the, uh, data mining stuff that you were talking about when you
release the tool and when you release the planes of Eidolon, um,
did you see a large reduction in people complaining about not being able to data
mine or are there still people complaining about that?
It still happens. So we didn't stop it. We just tried to stop it,
which I think is, I think they call that the Streisand effect or something.
Like if you try to stop something, it actually makes it worse.
So it's just what we,
what had happened was Umbra had gotten into the global build and we had to
address that situation. So with the planes of Eidolon launching, we were.
We made sure that the tool could accommodate the new reward
structure style, so we needed dev bandwidth
to update the tool to make it read this new world.
And at the time, players looked to that site,
and they actually now build.
I think one former data miner builds their own tool
based off of our data now just to make it more readable,
because it's just an HTML table.
But now it actually is the source of a lot of other player
tools that are just built on it, which has been really
wonderful to see it being used in still a player-owned way,
because they, of course, make their own websites and
everything off of it, which is nice.
Thank you.
Hello, sir.
Do you find that console and PC communities have different
wants, and if so, how do you address priorities of that?
So we have specific teams for each of the platforms, which is great, but the pipeline is always PC first, then console.
And what's happened on console is, when I said region locked content, that's one thing, because no one can have it,
but there's also console specific content, which is more, it's received fine.
Like if a console player has their version of skins, players don't mind.
Xbox has their version of skins, it's okay.
And same with PC.
And the way that they speak of the game and their needs is...
Typically the most common, it comes down to UI usability
and working on having an experience that
is more controller-friendly.
And that's essentially been something
we've had to work on since the day we launched on consoles.
And players continue to say it's not quite good enough.
So we still try.
So I was just, in regards to players being vocal or less vocal, how do you deal with, I guess, the comfort level of certain players just commenting on their opinions of various builds,
because some players might be a little more vocal and more confident in talking about the content they want or their opinions on updates,
whereas other players might be a little bit more, less vocal about it for a variety of reasons, maybe just accessibility.
Well, there's different ways you can get broad player
communication or specific.
Not everyone wants to write a long form forum post.
Some people just want to click a vote on a poll.
Some people just want to, but just by showing up, they're
showing they're interested.
If we do a dev stream on a certain topic, if the
viewership is quite large, we know that there's maybe some
players that aren't talking to us about that that are still
interested in it.
So we just gauge based on traffic.
And you try and use social media with the poll features
and everything.
That's a good way to get.
You never want to commit a poll to design gospel,
but it can happen.
And you just have to make sure that whatever tools you've
built and you own are being used frequently,
and be aware that players that may not
want to use those tools.
Like, we don't have an official Discord, but we're on Discord.
And we found that there's a lot of value there,
and people behave differently and more themselves there,
perhaps, than on an official forum.
So just acknowledging that the tool changes,
attracts different types of players.
And I totally forgot to say turn off your phones.
And I just realized that.
And also that you can create the talk after.
So I just realized now.
Sorry.
Hi.
I was wondering how you guys handled
international communities.
Our game, for example, I think 60% of our player base
is Chinese and Russian.
We're all English speakers on the dev team, primarily.
So we don't have a great way of communicating with them.
I was wondering if you guys had a second team in those regions,
or how you handled smaller regions that you can't really
communicate with, but have very different and special feedback.
We're all in-house.
The community team is a seven-person English-speaking
team at this point in time.
But we also have an in-house support team,
which is run by a gentleman sitting here,
that has all the languages that we support.
And we're able to use them as a lightning
rod for really specific issues in that community.
With Warframe's growth as it is today,
I expect that we will start trying to have dedicated
community people in our bigger regions, like Russia.
But we don't have that right now,
and we just try our best with the resources we have
to make sure the main developer updates get translated.
And ultimately, we could be doing a better job
of including those communities,
but we still haven't figured it out very well.
So it sounds like we're in the same boat.
Okay, thank you.
You're welcome.
All right, I think that's it.
Hello.
Could you reflect a little bit on the Twitch event that you had in the fall alongside Planes
of Eidolon?
Yes.
And, because it obviously exploded, it also exploded your servers.
So the success of that, how you would do it differently, would you do it differently again?
Right, so the Twitch event we had.
So Twitch is exploding, as we all know,
and there's something called Twitch Drops,
which allows you to have the viewers of your game
get rewarded with items in game simply for watching.
So we launched a Twitch Drop campaign
with the launch of our open world update.
to reward people watching Warframe streamers.
And if you get free loot in Warframe, you're gonna show up.
So we launched it at such a scale
that it did bring our servers down the first day,
and it did expose a vector of exploit
for people to have six windows open and watch our stream.
And there was a drop table that had 30 items in it,
and they were getting multiples.
And I wouldn't have done it differently
because it was so, well, I'm sure everyone on the team
is like, never again, but.
And it actually created two levels of issues for us,
obviously technical, but there was also
the court of public opinion that we had paid for view bots,
which simply wasn't true.
People just didn't understand the draw
of free Warframe loot, of course.
And the streamers were having fun with it.
They were gamifying it a bit.
And we have refined the tool since then.
It is no longer exploitable.
It's a lot less...
crazy in the campaigns we do, we still use it to this day,
just at a much more sane level.
And I think it's worth looking into if you have a game
on Twitch Drops that could utilize this system,
because it is pretty cool.
Hi, great talk.
You talked about a seat at the development table
with the community team.
Can you talk in a little bit more detail,
are you just collaborating with leaders
or individual contributors, small teams, big teams,
and just how that all coordinates?
So Slack has made it really easy to sort of have a virtual
seat at every table.
So we always try and include a community team member in the
features channels.
And the community team at Warframe also works on live
ops, so when deployments go out and when people are
debating whether or not to include something in a
deployment, we are involved in that.
So in many ways, Slack is sort of the simple answer to that.
I think the dev team is okay with it,
because it's kind of annoying to be the person in the room
that's like, well, the players aren't going to like that,
so don't do it.
But it's just the nature of our relationship
with our community that we need that,
you need that temperature check of grind tolerance,
for example, or...
you know, well there's not really a lot of PvP players right now and it goes both ways if we
know that dev is really focused on doing something change wise, we need to prepare the community
materials. So having a seat at the table isn't just about being the fun police, it's about being the
okay this is really good information to start working on. Like we removed a content system from
the game known as trials because there was a rapid exchange that you know we just couldn't support it
anymore and the devs really knew that it just was not being given the love they wanted. So we
from that moment had like
to get ready to break that news to the community.
So.
And just a quick follow up.
Did you find that it was a sort of development
cultural evolution at your studio
when you were getting involved this way?
I think the, so the early, early, early Warframe,
it was.
I was there on the community team
and there was like eight developers.
So we were all in it together from the start.
So it was, yeah.
So before all that, we had been doing publisher stuff,
work for hire, we never had a community team.
So it was there at the foundation of all this.
So it wasn't added later.
It's been there the whole time,
which may not be the case for everyone.
Great, thank you.
You're welcome.
All right, I think that's it.
Thanks everyone.
Thank you so much.