Ladies and gentlemen, please welcome to the stage, Chris Hecker.
Welcome. So, one of my favorite things about Will Wright, besides the fact that he's fucking brilliant,
is that he's so approachable and how humble and mellow he is, even in the face of his obvious popularity.
And so he doesn't want to be in this room, for example. Like, he has no interest in being a keynote.
He just wants to come to the GDC and share information. And every year, we put him in a bigger room.
And then it fills up and people complain.
And then we put him in a bigger room,
and then it fills up and people complain.
And so next year, I think we're going to have to get, like,
the Oakland Coliseum or something.
It's not exactly clear what to do here.
But even in the face of all that,
he still is all about just sharing information
and being really approachable and being really cool
about just, like, the free flow of information.
So help me welcome Will Wright.
Hi, everybody.
Let me go to my PowerPoint here.
Okay.
So, every year, they kind of ask me to come give a talk.
And every year, they kind of then ask me what my talk is about,
and I procrastinate.
And so they just assign a title to my talk.
Oh, by the way, the images that you might have seen coming in
were all from the Hubble, you know, which, and the Hubble I love.
It's like one of these things that appeals equally
to the scientist and the artist, you know,
and there are very few tools of humanity
that I think kind of have that amazing balance both ways.
But at any rate, so this is not the title of my talk at all.
Um...
In fact, I mean, people are always saying,
oh, come give a talk at our school or at this or that
about game design.
And so I talk about game design and game design and game design.
I'm kind of sick of talking about game design, actually.
So I thought I would talk about something quite different here today instead.
But then about a month ago, I saw Jamil that runs the conference, and he said,
oh, by the way, we made you the game design keynote.
And I thought, uh-oh.
This isn't about game design at all, and I'm the keynote.
So I kind of scratched that plan.
So I kind of reworked it a bit and thought, you know,
well, you know what I really enjoy is, you know,
the obsessive research stuff that I get into
when I just really get fascinated with a subject
and then kind of want to turn it into a game.
So I kind of reworked the thing into this.
Uh, you know, for me, you know, I start a game idea,
and usually there's this concept at the beginning,
something that sparks an idea.
Then I go out and do a lot of research,
get really involved in it.
Then, of course, you know, kind of the standard modes of, you know, pre-production, production,
testing, marketing. It seems to me at GDC that we cover these last four sections pretty
well, you know, with the topics that are covered at GDC. But I've seen very little stuff kind
of done in the very early phases, you know, the research phase of how you start with the
very core of an idea, usually one person kind of doing background research and doing the
very early formulation of that idea. And that's really my favorite part. That's the part I
enjoy the most by far. So, you know, it's kind of tinkering around in your lab.
doing stuff. So, I started thinking about, okay, what can I say about game research?
But then, you know, I had this nagging thing where I really still wanted to talk about
this other thing, you know? And I thought, well, okay, maybe I'll just do both of them,
you know? What should I do first, though? Do I do the game research, Astro, you know?
It felt kind of weird to have, like, half a talk and then another half a talk. So I
decided I would actually interleave the two for maximum confusion. So...
We're going to be going back and forth a bit here.
In some sense, you know, one is an example of the other.
So, starting on the research side.
Typically, you know, when I start researching an idea,
it involves talking to people,
going out and interviewing experts in the field,
reading a lot of books,
searching the web for whatever I can find.
Books really seem to be my primary inspiration.
Most of the games I've done, you know,
were kind of directly inspired by one particular book I read
that got me interested in that subject.
And it's not like the entire game was really, it's not like the blueprint for the game or anything.
It's actually more like that book will kind of spark additional interests.
And I'll start reading other things.
And it'll start pulling me off in these different directions that I find interesting.
As I'm, at the same time, kind of formulating what this thing might become in my mind as a game.
And then later we kind of bring the prototyping.
Um, the Japanese have this great term called otaku.
Uh, how many of you have heard this before?
Um, yeah.
It kind of usually refers to a 14-year-old, you know, kind of socially dysfunctional guy who collects little anime dolls.
It's rather derogatory.
But, you know, I kind of embraced that philosophy, you know, in the early stages.
When I get interested in a subject, you know, I just get, you know, obsessed with it.
And I'll speak to everybody I can about it and tell them how cool it is.
And in some sense, that's my very early stage of prototyping.
How can I take that idea of that subject?
Why do I find this cool and how can I communicate that to others?
And I'm doing that all the time from the very early stages.
Last year, I came here and talked about Spore a little bit.
Kind of, you know, where that was going, you know.
how the content battle that we were fighting in game development
seemed like a losing battle to me.
And because of that, it kind of drove me to generative systems.
The project I was working on just before that was The Sims Online.
And, you know, we basically had to fight a lot of those battles.
It kind of brought me to the idea of Spore.
This is roughly the development team for The Sims Online.
It was about 140 people, the largest project I had ever worked on.
And there was just a huge amount of inertia.
You know, not just with, like, the server client issues,
but the design issues.
A lot of content we had to bring in.
A lot of content that had to be reworked from the Sims.
And once we got it working, you know,
in a multiplayer environment,
there were a lot of things that were fundamentally different
than the Sims that kind of broke the Sims idea.
First of all, we couldn't control time.
And if you, you know, when I played the Sims,
I always had one hand on the speed control,
and you always speed through the boring parts.
And when all of a sudden you're stuck in real time in the Sims,
it is a pretty boring game.
Custom content, which was one of the big, you know,
kind of leverages of success we had for the Sims offline.
You know, we had aspirations for the Sims Online to have that,
but it was just unmanageable.
The amount of bandwidth, the size of the data, in fact,
you know, made it hard for us to kind of bring that in
effectively into the Sims Online.
And we find that it's like 60% of the players
playing the Sims use cheats.
You know, they'll play it as a game part of the time,
and they'll use cheats and play it kind of as a dollhouse,
freeform, design your mansion the other time.
And of course, you can't have that in a multiplayer game.
Instead, you have to have these incredibly tall advancement ladders,
um, you know, spanning these different ranges of skills.
Now, meanwhile, while we were building The Sims Online,
actually, around the same time, over in Germany,
they were building this thing.
So...
This thing is cool.
This is the Bagger 288, and it is immense.
It's actually a land vehicle.
It actually drives across doing mining in Germany.
It's just got a billion treads.
It's about the size of kind of an oil platform.
There are actually these large veins of coal that run through Germany,
and there are actually two of these machines,
and they actually disassemble highways to let this thing by.
But just to give you a sense of the size of this thing,
this is a Jawa sand crawler in comparison.
And the sand collar doesn't even exist.
But the reason I bring this up is this is basically
kind of how The Sims Online felt to me.
Um, basically I was driving this thing, right?
You know, and we'd make a design decision,
and two weeks later, what happened with that?
Oh, it's in process.
Oh, we got the server code working.
Now the client's, you know, getting in sync with it.
And maybe two months later, we might see this minor
little design decision actually trickle into the product.
Um, so when I left The Sims Online
and started Spore, it was basically kind of like
getting out of the driver's seat of that thing
into a Ferrari.
and zipping away.
I mean, we were doing prototyping, making design decisions,
and, you know, I was seeing progress hourly
rather than once every other month.
I was really reluctant to kind of grow S'more back in that same direction,
which drove me to this idea of, like, the procedural content and stuff.
So, but there are a lot of still cool things from The Sims
that, you know, I really kind of didn't want to lose
in the next project I worked on, you know,
primarily the idea that the players are surprising us,
that they are actually even going beyond what we think the box is
that we're giving them to play in
and exceeding that box in weird and interesting ways.
Um...
And this gets to kind of the question of the abdication of authorship, you know.
you know, you know, kind of pour your heart into this thing
and you're gonna create this, you know, lovingly crafted world
and, you know, you have aspirations for that,
it has meaning, you know, that you want to convey.
And once you give it to the fans,
you just don't know what they're gonna do with it.
So...
Came to the idea through my fascination with the SETI program.
And I talked about this a little bit last year,
kind of Drake's equation,
which led me to the science of astrobiology,
which is the study of possible life in the universe.
And it's, you know, an interesting subject
because it only has one data point,
and that's life on Earth.
Everything else has to be inferred, you know.
So everything we know about aliens,
we've basically imagined, you know, we've never seen.
One of the early concepts for Spore was that each one of these terms in Drake's equation,
you know, these are things like how many stars, how many planets, how many of those have life.
One of the early concepts of the game is that the player would play a level to set those
sliders and then you would have the resulting galaxy to play in.
But it turns out that most of the combinations of those sliders are incredibly boring.
So that didn't really feel like it was kind of going in the right direction.
Another kind of very early concept for Spore
was that it was kind of a greening the galaxy thing.
You were going around, you know, seeding and promoting life
throughout the galaxy, and then kind of seeing what arose
and then trying to nurture it.
This is actually, for the few people that read the book,
2001, that was the backstory for why the aliens
were dropping monoliths on Earth,
is that they were actually trying to kind of farm mine
in the galaxy.
At the same time, there was, of course,
this powers of 10 idea kind of lurking in the background.
After doing a little bit more research, I found out that the powers of tenthing,
actually, the Eameses didn't do the first version of it.
The first version was actually done by a Dutch school teacher in the 50s named Kees Boelke.
And he got his students to draw the pictures.
And it was actually a remarkably cool book, although very weird in comparison to the Eameses.
He actually starts, like, with a little lady holding a baby in a chair.
And then as he zooms out, there's a whale,
and she's in the middle of the street and cars are going by.
And I've been to Holland, and I didn't see that.
But anyway, going back to Drake's for a second.
The really interesting term in here,
the one that we know probably the least about,
is the probability of life occurring.
What is the chance life can spontaneously arise somewhere?
So then that drove me down a totally different direction,
the origin of life.
And there are all these convoluted theories
about how life might have started.
They basically usually resolve down to this.
But...
Then we looked into it.
And this really was part of the powers of 10 thing.
It was drawing us down into the microscopic world here.
And so I thought, okay, initially this is kind of a space thing.
Maybe it's a microscopic thing too.
Now, a little bit of overview here.
14 million years ago, billion years ago, big bang, and here we are now.
The Earth remarkably formed about 4 billion years ago,
which is a significant fraction of the age of the known universe.
And the fact that the Earth has remained fairly stable over that period of time is pretty remarkable.
Another remarkable thing is that evidence of life on Earth was very soon after the Earth formed.
And they're still trying to refine that.
Every time they find an older one, it gets a little bit closer and a little bit closer
to the time when the Earth finally cooled off.
Now, we see that it took about 2 billion years for life to go from very primitive prokaryotic
microbes to more advanced eukaryotic microbes, and another 1.5 billion years to get to what
we consider kind of macroscopic interesting life. So, it was about 3 billion years before
life, you know, got kind of large, multicellular. And it's only been that for about 500 million
years so far.
One of the early trips I took researching spore was to the Scripps Institute down in La Jolla
and met this guy, Stan Miller, who back in the 50s did the very first origin of life experiments
where he would take these flasks, fill them with, like, you know, methane and spark them
and see what would come out of it.
You know, he was trying to recreate the early prebiotic atmosphere of the Earth
and he actually was creating amino acids
and it was the first kind of idea that maybe this stuff could have arisen naturally, these chemicals.
One of my prized possessions is this that he gave me
that he actually signs, it says Stan Miller.
It's like sitting on a shelf in my house.
Every now and then, somebody will come and say,
Oh, you should throw this out. It's ruined.
And I was like, No!
I also met David Brin down there,
who's one of my favorite science fiction authors.
One of his best-known series is the Uplift series,
which is a concept that we kind of, you know,
are bringing into Spore, where you can kind of
uplift unintelligent animals to intelligence.
In describing Spore to him, he basically said,
Oh, it sounds cool, but I want this game.
I want the game where I can change the fundamental
consonants of the universe and see what emerges.
And...
Aside from being kind of a difficult thing to do, even in comparison to Spore,
it turns out that most of those things, if you move them like 1% one way or the other,
the universe lasts about 5 nanoseconds or something.
So, that had the same problem where the combinations of sliders, you know,
it was a very narrow range where you had an interesting kind of play experience.
Diving a little bit deeper into the theories of the original life,
one of the leading candidates is this thing called autocatalytic sets,
which is roughly the chemistry over time will evolve.
more and more elaborate, you know, chemicals in a given environment.
We actually did prototypes of this,
and to be honest, it wasn't very compelling.
So we moved up a level to the cellular level
and started looking into cellular processes and metabolism and stuff,
and we did a pretty nice simulation of this,
and again, you know, it just wasn't going to kind of reach the same numbers as the Sims,
I thought.
So...
Another kind of intriguing theory is the pan-spermy theory,
which is the fact that maybe life didn't start on Earth at all,
but in fact came here from somewhere else,
maybe an asteroid or a comet,
landed on Earth.
This is a rock we found, LH 84001.
came from Mars, and we know that, you know, pretty well just by analyzing the chemical composition of it.
And we found these little weird things on there that, you know, we've never seen before
that looked like they could be, you know, maybe fossils of living organisms.
The jury's still out on that. They probably aren't because they're so small.
But still, the idea that material could have traveled from Mars to the Earth is pretty well known at this point.
And there's a surprising amount of material, like when an asteroid hits the Earth,
all little pieces of the Earth go out into orbit around the sun.
Some of them will fall back in other planets, like Mars, for instance.
And so there's this idea of planetary crosstalk,
that if there is life in a planetary system,
chances are it will spread to other nearby planets,
because it's a matter of tons per year
that will fall, like in the early stages of this.
So there's a huge amount of crosstalk happening between the planets.
And not only that, but it's looking more and more probable
that there's the possibility of interstellar crosstalk,
which is some of this material could actually travel to another star,
because some of these bacteria can last for millions of years in a desiccated form,
and they're very radiation resistant.
So, we'll get back to this a little bit later.
There's actually, now what I'm talking about so far is undirected panspermia.
There's this other idea of directed panspermia,
and in fact a society I found that is promoting this,
that let's start sending spores out into space
and, you know, five million years from now they might land somewhere
and start, you know, growing on another planet.
And it's cool that people think that far ahead, you know.
Okay, back to the research side.
Um, one thing that I have to confront a lot,
especially in the early stages, is, you know,
where I fall kind of on the fact versus fiction side of things.
Um, frequently, we simulate things
not the way they would occur, but the way people would expect them to occur,
or, you know, for entertainment value.
In SimCity, when a nuclear power plant, um, catches on fire,
you know, it just goes nuclear.
You know, it just blows up in this big crater where it used to be.
And, of course, nuclear reactors don't really do that.
But, you know, a lot of times in games,
we will purposely basically break reality
for the player expectation.
I'm not against that at all.
In fact, I think, you know, fiction is a very interesting way to kind of approach reality.
One thing that Rod Sterling said when he was doing the Twilight Zone,
he said that was the only place in television where he could do real issues.
And this is back in the late 50s when he started the Twilight Zone.
And he could actually do things about gender equality or racial issues.
by making, you know, one guy an alien and one guy an earthling.
Where at that time on TV, if they tried to deal with these racial issues
with blacks and whites, they would never get it on the air.
So it was a way for him to get a message out there
that at the time was very hard to get out.
As far back as Mary Shelley writing Frankenstein,
you know, she had a very deep message embedded in this work of fiction,
you know, that she was hoping to have some impact on society.
So really, you know, in some sense, I wanted to interact
with lots of interesting aliens in this game.
And the idea of having to deal with protein folding and cellular metabolism
was kind of a little bit at odds with that.
And, you know, you'll see a little bit later
kind of how we fell on the side of the fence,
you know, which side of the fence we fell on different issues.
A lot of times in research, you know, we'll start doing prototypes.
I don't know if any of you all saw the excellent prototyping talk this morning
by Hayim and Chris.
Yeah, it was a great talk.
And as I was mentioning, you know, we do a lot of simulation prototypes.
You know, the very best ones, we will actually kind of bring
to more extensive gameplay prototypes.
Originally, we were just simulating dynamics of a simple system,
but then we'll start adding user interaction.
And is this fun, you know, to manipulate and kind of interact with?
A lot of times, we will kind of iterate those prototypes.
Oh, I think it would be better if we tuned it this way or that way.
But frequently, some things will come out in the prototypes
that will go all the way back to the fundamental research
and say, ooh, we should, you know, go off in this direction.
And the gameplay will actually suggest it over this longer loop.
So when we do research for games,
or when I do research,
I end up reading a lot, covering a lot of topics,
but really I know that at the end of the day,
only maybe 10% of what I research
is gonna end up in the game.
You know, the art of this
is figuring out what 90% to leave out.
This is kind of another view of, you know, the design tree.
You know, each one of these branches
is a decision point you're gonna make
at some point in the design.
The leaves of this tree,
every little leaf on the outside
represents one potential product.
that you could end up at.
And how you navigate this tree is gonna kind of determine
what product you end up building.
You know, a kind of more close-up view of this
is you might start reading a book, get you inspired.
Maybe you go out and do a prototype of it.
Maybe you have a conversation about it.
Then you change course and say,
let's go do a user test this way.
That doesn't work out.
Maybe you go all the way back to the original source,
and then you see a game that kind of reminds you of it.
You play that game and then maybe talk about that.
And this is kind of what the internal structure
of that tree looks like.
it's, you know, a lot of different kind of forms of media,
interaction, conversation, tests that you're doing
to make decisions at each branch in that tree.
But usually, at the very base, you know,
before I even kind of start climbing down this tree,
I start by asking some very early questions
about what I want to, you know, do as a designer.
And I've kind of reduced those to, like, four major areas here,
innovation, risks, fun, and messages.
On the innovation side, you know, I think it's important, you know, with every title
that we do to try to innovate somewhere, you know, to some degree.
You know, innovation is something that you kind of know when you see it.
It's hard to define exactly.
And it doesn't always lead to success, you know.
So you can have something that's very innovative, but not necessarily very successful.
But what it does do is it does get you above the signal to noise, you know, in the marketplace.
You know, you want it to be that signal getting above the noise
because we are living in a very noisy marketplace.
You know, every year thousands of titles are released.
And, you know, if you have an innovative title, people will talk about it
because it stands out. It's a signal.
And that's just kind of like one of the very first things I try to think about,
you know, as almost a prerequisite for a game that I do.
In Sporrer, you know, the innovations I decided would be the procedural content, you know.
Well, actually, I've been being teased a lot about this procedural content thing.
I heard about this, like, drinking game.
Every time I say procedural, somebody takes a drink.
So, I decided actually here, I'm going to let you all vote on what I'm going to start calling this instead.
Okay, so, so these are the candidates.
Look them over for a second.
And I'm going to put this to an audience vote.
From now on, I'm just going to start calling it something else.
So, how many people think I should call it algorithmic content?
Okay. Okay, parametric content.
That's what I'm talking about.
Okay, generative content.
Whoa, okay.
Okay, we have a winner.
Okay, so the generative content was going to buy us player creativity,
you know, an unbounded world potentially, since we can generate so much.
The pollinated content, uh, by the social currency of players kind of having some value,
people getting to know the best creators in this world.
Uh, thematic diversity, because people are gonna just do all sorts of weird things in different directions.
And then this kind of multi-genre gameplay, um,
which gives us epic scope and some familiarity, approachability.
Okay, now, back to the aliens. Uh, okay.
Now, the panspermia thing was interesting.
But really at some point I realized it's all about the aliens, right?
You know, that's what I really wanted to do in this game,
was fly around and meet lots of interesting, cool alien creatures,
especially if the player's creating them.
So, and it could have been almost, you know,
this talk almost was about robots instead of aliens,
because aliens and robots to me represent, you know, very similar things.
You know, they kind of represent views of humanity.
You don't really realize how amazing the human hand is until you try to build one.
Once you try to build one, you go back and look at this and the dexterity and the strength and the flexibility.
It's just an amazing, amazing thing.
So in some sense, robots give us a better understanding of who we are and, you know, what makes us tick.
Now, you're going to hear me talk about this movie a lot.
My favorite movie of all time, 2001.
I'm completely operational and all my circuits are functioning perfectly.
So when I was 7 years old, I saw this movie and I met Hal
and it had a deep impact on me.
You know, the idea that there could be this machine
that thought like a person and you could interact with.
And it just fundamentally, you know, just blew me away as a kid.
What's interesting is, you know, people saw that movie
and they came out and, you know,
this is right at the dawn of AI, really, right?
And they were amazed that a computer could beat this guy at chess.
And they weren't amazed at all that he could have these conversations,
do all this common sense reasoning, you know.
And that was a very interesting insight into human intelligence.
You know, because we had thought of, you know, playing chess as being, you know,
something that required a lot of intelligence,
and tying your shoes as being simple.
And we're finding out that's not the case.
You know, and we found that out through trying to recreate those abilities in machines.
Um, you know, the lip-reading stuff he did.
Uh, so in some sense, um,
aliens and robots both represent kind of boundaries or aspects of humanity.
Uh, you know, we have, you know, nice aliens, friendly aliens.
We have really mean, scary, you know, vicious aliens.
We have really smart and really stupid aliens.
You know, so they're kind of building this boundary,
but they're all still in the same dimensions, you know,
humans are built out of.
So really, both of these things are kind of, I think,
a window into humanity.
And as we, you know, look at imagined aliens,
and as we build robots,
we're actually coming to understand ourselves more thoroughly.
Now, the idea of aliens isn't really new.
You know, there are examples from way back in art
of things that they might have called demons or angels.
More recently, there were a few sightings in the 1800s.
There were these things that they saw during World War II called Foo Fighters.
But it was really after the advent of nuclear weapons
that the kind of whole modern alien craze started.
The Roswell Incident seems to be like ground zero
for where a lot of the kind of modern mythology around aliens spread.
And initially, you know, these aliens were things that were probably very hostile, probably going to come and hurt us.
They were scary.
In some sense, I think they were a personification of this power that we suddenly had to destroy ourselves.
In other contexts, they were also this yearning for adult supervision.
You know, we were hoping that somebody out there was smarter than us and might actually come and help save ourselves.
or even provide an example that maybe we can survive this period in our time.
And this is just one kind of cultural response to kind of this sudden ability to destroy humanity.
Different cultures had different responses.
In Japan, it was Godzilla, which is a little bit different.
It was more of a personification of what would nature say if she could see us doing this.
And so Godzilla was kind of like the revenge of nature, you know, after we had been...
playing with these weapons. But the aliens, in fact, weren't like Godzilla.
They were very vulnerable. We could almost empathize with them. What made them powerful
was their technology. And that was something we could aspire to. We could aspire to become
these gods, which also made them very different than, like, the old Greek and Roman gods that
we could not aspire to become. Okay, so back to the research.
We covered innovation, project risks,
is something that you really have to take seriously.
You know, at every stage of the project,
all the way from beginning to end,
I divide most of the risks that I think of
into these categories,
technology, design, production, marketing, political.
I'm lucky that most of the ideas that I want to do,
you know, I have a freer path.
I think most people here
that have a really cool, innovative idea,
you know, one of the very first battles
they're going to be fighting is the political battle.
How do you get a green light inside your company?
Electronic arts, it actually,
I found it's a very simple trick.
It turns out that all the execs play Worlds of Warcraft.
And so all you have to do is say, oh, it's going to be like World of Warcraft,
except it starts in a tide pool and you end up in space,
and it's not quite multiplayer, but it works.
Yeah.
So, the top risks I saw for Spore, you know, in sorted order,
were the generative animation system,
editor usability, design scope of the project,
quality content, and content pipeline.
Two of these are technology risks, you know,
which kind of involve one approach.
Two of these were design risks.
And the last one was really kind of a production risk.
So what you really want to do in this case
is front-load the team, get the very first core members
in positions to solve those early risks.
I knew that if we couldn't do the generative animation system,
that the whole idea was sunk.
And so one of the very first people I brought on the project
was a guy named Case 1 Pushkin,
who, people know him.
He's a great guy.
And he was like my deep researcher.
And he actually, I had him look at all the procedural
or generative systems out there.
You know, we found some really cool examples.
They were very hard to use,
but they kind of gave us some indication
of the direction to go.
Later, we had Ken Perlin come in
and do some consulting on it,
you know, showing his stuff, his generative stuff.
And then later, Chris Hecker
is now kind of building the tool out for animators.
And so, basically, it was getting
a very qualified team of specialists
to come in and attack that risk.
And I find that these risks are best attacked
with a very small number of very sharp people.
rather than a giant team of kind of more average people,
in which case they'll never solve it.
But the very tightly focused team usually can,
especially if you say,
I don't think you can solve this, there's no way,
and make it a challenge for them.
Now, the Polynesian content,
that was something where
we actually had a lot of experience to draw from.
We have these Sims websites,
and a lot of fans are uploading stuff to our Sims website
and sharing it and tracking the creators
and the popularity and stuff.
So I brought over two of the people that actually had architected that system,
Kelshawn and Colin Andrews, to run the pollinated content side.
Yeah, they're great.
And they, in fact, started building prototypes very early on of this system
and capturing all the stuff that we were in development, making in the editors,
and starting to sort it and aesthetically figure out what the categories were.
And...
The fact that they got that prototype going so early
lowered that as a risk factor tremendously right off the bat.
You know, whereas the generative animation system
was kind of a long, ongoing battle that we kept fighting,
and it kind of stayed at the top of the list for a long time.
Design scope, you know, games used to be, like,
about that complex, you know, back in the 80s or so.
Uh, now they're more like this.
And so I knew that I wanted to do a game across all these different scales,
and I kind of reasoned that, well, if I didn't make any one of those scales too complicated,
the whole set of them still would maybe be about the same complexity as a modern game.
And so that was, like, kind of step one for mitigating the design risk.
Another one was bringing in, again, people that
Jason Schenkel
was the lead programmer for Sim Wars,
which is a project that we worked on,
but we never released.
But Jason did a huge number of prototypes
of planetary ecosystems and whatnot
that we drew from.
And so his experience,
he was actually, like,
the first prototyper on Sporb.
Uh, then playing a lot of old games
that were just great,
like Sundog on the Apple II.
Has anybody ever played this game?
This is way back.
This is a great game.
You know, it had multi-scale gameplay,
flying around the galaxy.
Uh, Elite, of course.
Um...
Cosmic Osmo,
which might seem like an odd choice,
But that was a great game, too, in a differentin a kind of a toy sense.
And then kind of more offbeat things, Microsoft Space Simulator,
which was not a great game, but it was a really fun toy if you were into space.
The kind of more recent version of that is this thing, Celestia,
which if you're into astronomy, you really should download this.
It's a free download, and it's got great plug-ins, and it's really cool.
Homeworld, of course, the visuals, the gameplay.
These are basically free prototypes, by the way.
You know, I didn't, you know, I made 50-buck prototypes.
But, uh, we learned a tremendous amount
just kind of going back into these libraries
of things that had been done.
And, you know, a lot of games have been out there,
and you can learn tremendous amounts
just by going and doing, basically, game archaeology.
Um, on the evolution side,
we dug up every evolution game we could find.
You know, board games, you know,
all the way up to, like, Carnivore,
or Cubivore on the Nintendo.
And, of course, we did a billion and a half prototypes.
Now the prototypes are kind of like the books, where you end up doing lots of prototypes all over the place,
and only a very few end up actually kind of dealing with the actual dynamics in the game.
And really, that's okay, because that's what they're for.
One thing that I found that works great for prototypes are interns.
And I've had really good luck with interns.
Generally, the balance I'm trying to strive for on a team now is about one-third veteran,
one-third kind of intern is young blood, and one-third mid-level.
And that seems like a really good kind of chemistry on the team.
A typical thing is that we have a lot of people coming in, we're trying to filter for hiring,
is we have thousands of resumes. The HR people don't quite know exactly what we're looking
for because they're not experts in the field. They try their best and sort and give us a
pile of resumes and we kind of choose from those. And it's a very ineffective filter
in a lot of cases. You know, what I'm finding is a much more effective filter is a few programs
in these universities that are teaching, you know, interactive design now.
We have a few students come in and do very well in those programs.
And then I let the professor recommend to me, you know,
knowing exactly what I'm looking for, and they've known the student for years.
And so in some sense, these students are kind of like the salmon swimming upstream.
And I'm like at the top of the stream, you know, waiting for the best salmon to get there.
And that's turned out to be a great filter for me.
And like I said, like three schools in particular that in fact we're getting our best interns from.
And I'm not going to tell you what they are, because I don't want to kind of have to compete for them.
But on the...
Editor usability, in fact I had interns working on this, you know, from very early stage.
We looked at all these other games that involved constructing things, Bridge Builder, Magic Pinjail.
This was a very interesting one. In fact, it was based upon the work of this Japanese computer scientist, Takio Igarashi.
And he did a lot of other basically constructive systems like this that had a lot of embedded intelligence in them.
Um, so we're dealing with this, with user content.
And this is kind of what we're trying to,
the curve we're trying to fight with the editors.
Is, you know, we get a lot of content
that's at low quality.
You know, it's basically crap.
Um...
We get a fair amount that's kind of a good effort.
A little bit that's pretty good.
And a very small amount that's great.
And what we really want to do is we want to pull up this curve.
And this is kind of why we're focusing on editors.
How can we make players be creative in the game,
but also have that stuff be good enough
to where other players get value from it?
I mean, if they want to just sit there and make crappy stuff
and it's in their game, I could care less.
But if we want to redistribute it to other players
and add value to their world,
we want to kind of bring everybody up on the quality bar here.
And so we did a lot of early prototyping of the editors
and usability tests,
because this is really kind of a usability issue.
Now, the content pipeline was our last risk.
Electronic Arts is moving over to RenderWare as a framework.
A lot of RenderWare is really about, you know,
the pipeline for animation and modeling,
stuff that we're all doing generatively.
So we pretty much had to kind of roll our own pipeline.
In some sense, you know, looking at the art staff,
you know, I was finding that the artists
are already getting extremely technical.
They're writing, you know, pixel shaders,
working in Maya.
And it wasn't that far of a jump to kind of go toward this idea of a generative artist.
Yes, generative artist.
What I found in looking at kind of the skill set that works well is you want somebody that can kind of observe nature
or observe whatever and from that, you know, with almost a scientific eye
and deconstruct what they're seeing.
And when they can deconstruct it, they can kind of bring it into a larger conceptual space.
and abstract it out into eventually data structures.
And then we use those data structures to regenerate,
you know, through algorithms, you know, new content.
And so this is kind of the process
that I'm trying to train our artists
into thinking this way.
And there's really, we have one prototype of this.
And we're also trying to build tools
that will allow artists to do this more easily,
and eventually our players,
because eventually this is kind of what we want the player to do
on a little bit simpler, higher level.
So this is my lead artist, Ocean Quigley.
And he's like the first generative artist that I've ever met.
You know, he's kind of trained himself in that process I just showed you.
He's proven remarkably difficult to breed in captivity, but...
On the other hand, we found that we've gotten extreme leverage.
I've paired him up with one of our best programmers, Andrew Willmott.
Andrew developed this custom language for Ocean.
And, you know, they worked very closely together.
And, you know, whenever Ocean had a limitation on language,
Andrew would go back and add a few more things.
And he made a very comfortable editing environment
to where Ocean was basically scripting and writing programming.
Um, and because of that, you know,
we got probably ten times the efficiency out of Ocean.
So, um, this is an interesting experiment
where we can get extreme leverage
out of certain people in these, you know, roles.
But then this might become the template later
for bringing people into these roles and training them.
Okay, back to the aliens.
Okay, so, Copernicus came up with this idea that maybe the whole universe doesn't revolve around the Earth.
You know, maybe the Earth is just one kind of place out there like a lot of other places.
And because of that, people kind of abstracted the idea,
okay, well, if we're just like everywhere else, maybe there are people like us everywhere else.
And it was almost a given that there were aliens out there somewhere, maybe even nearby, on Mars.
You know, back in the 1800s, they thought they were actually observing canals on Mars.
They were waiting for them to come attack us, basically, you know.
And it wasn't really considered that out there of an idea.
It was, you know, highly plausible.
More recently, this new theory has come around, called the Rare Earth Theory.
And it basically says that maybe we're a lot more unique than we thought at first.
And it's a little bit different than the Copernican Principle.
For one thing, we have this amazing moon,
which has a lot of impacts on keeping the Earth more stable for a lot of reasons.
The leading theory of how we got the Moon was that this big thing hit the Earth, kind
of sloughed off, and then went into orbit around us.
It used to be much, much closer.
The Moon used to be about 14,000 miles away from us, if that was true.
Now that would have been really cool, you know, to be back then and see that, because
it would be this huge thing up in the sky.
It also would have caused one kilometer land tides, which is that the land would actually
go up and down a kilometer twice a day, you know.
And that would have been really cool to see.
Another kind of unusual thing about our situation.
is this thing, Jupiter.
Jupiter's a big planet, it turns out.
In fact, it's not only the heaviest planet in our solar system,
but it's twice as heavy as all the other planets put together.
What that means is that most of the crap
that comes flying into our solar system gets eaten by Jupiter.
It's a big shield.
If Jupiter weren't there,
Earth and all the other planets would have been bombarded
many, many times more than they were.
So it's actually protected us quite a bit.
We actually saw one of these impacts.
about eight years ago, the Shoemaker-Levy comet hit Jupiter,
and we actually got photographs of where it hit.
So it was pretty cool to see something like that in our lifetime.
Now, if we pull back a little bit, away from our solar system,
at the galaxy level, the galaxy is a very thin, flat disk,
the spiral galaxies.
We're about halfway out from the center of the disk.
And these spiral arms aren't exactly what you might think.
You know, you look at these and you think,
oh, that's where all the stars are.
That's not really the case.
That's where the bright stars are, the really young stars.
They're lighting up the dust around there.
The actual stellar distribution is pretty even through this disk.
Stars form in these dust clouds and once they form, they ignite.
And depending on the mass of the star, you get, you know,
like a blue giant or a mainline star or maybe a red dwarf.
The bigger the star, the shorter the lifespan.
So these large blue giants actually go supernova very rapidly.
So they only last a few million years.
And so the spiral arms are actually those supernova lighting up
and the blue stars lighting up these regions of high dust.
Now.
What that means is these arms really are governed by hydrodynamic principles.
It's like pressure waves moving around.
So they actually maintain their structure as they revolve around the center.
Otherwise, they would kind of dissolve.
They orbit with a period.
of about 200 million years, you know, for one revolution.
Now the stars and planets are actually governed by gravitational, you know, forces.
So ones closer to the center go faster and ones further out go slower.
That means that the ones closer to the middle are actually going through these arms very often,
you know, every 10 or 20 million years.
Ones that are further out are actually being overtaken by the arms
because the arms are going faster than them.
Now, these arms are actually very high radiation zones,
both because of the supernovas going off and because of the blue giants
and the dust and a lot of other things.
They're actually pretty disruptive areas for like a sun to go through.
And there's actually a very thin zone here.
where the stars are pretty much in sync with the arms,
and they are not passing through the arms very often at all.
And it turns out that we actually live in the exact center of that zone.
So, this is, you know, one other possibility
that maybe we're in a kind of more unique situation than we think,
that there's this habitability zone in the galaxy.
There's another one.
The early stars were almost entirely hydrogen and helium.
Over time, they blew up, made dust.
dust came back, collapsed, back into kind of protoplanetary disks, and then new stars
were formed. But these new stars had higher metal content. And in this case, anything,
you know, above helium is considered a metal. So that would be a second generation star
on the bottom, a first generation star on top. Our sun actually is a pretty high metal
star. We think it's a second or third generation star, which means that the, you know, original
star blew up, made dust, another star was created, back and forth to make our sun.
Which means that there was enough metal in our protoplanetary disk to make things like terrestrial planets like the Earth.
Otherwise, it would have just been probably gas giants.
We've also found correlations where the higher metal content stars definitely have more planetary systems.
So there seems to be this idea that the metallocity of your star is also maybe a requisite for life as we know it.
And this is actually kind of a map.
The high metal stars slowly evolve, spreading out further and further from the galactic center.
And we're just about the point in time when that green band is overlapping the other band I showed you.
So this is just stuff that we've, you know, fairly recently kind of discovered.
Okay, back to the game stuff.
Now, on to the obvious fun.
Um, for every game, you know, you kind of want to start with,
why am I doing this?
I mean, and when you start getting into the game concepts,
it's always about, you know, what is obviously fun about this?
You know, when I put this on the back of a little box,
why does somebody think, you know, they're gonna want to play it?
What's the hook for the player?
Um, just to give you an example, you know,
when we were doing the space stuff, we thought,
OK, suppose we had a UFO, and we could go anywhere.
You know, what would we want to do?
You know, all these worlds the players have created.
And then, you know, we kind of dove in, and it depended on every level of the game.
You know, we thought on a wild planet, we'd probably want to do the uplift thing, you know,
making them smart, or maybe just kind of collect them, you know, like Pokemon.
On the tribal, you know, really, you know, it seemed like we wanted them to worship us,
maybe make monuments, you know, and be their god.
You know, civilized, you know, maybe play first contact, adult supervision,
or maybe just kind of mess with them and do crop circles, you know.
And then spacefaring, you know, obviously combat, trading,
maybe building interstellar federations,
but definitely exploration,
because at that point the world gets so expansive.
But for every level of the game, we would go through
and just kind of figure out, what are the obvious things that,
you know, if I asked somebody in two minutes,
I'm scrubbing the game,
what would you want to do in this game?
You know, and we'd put those all down on a list,
and those became kind of landmarks
that I talked about a couple years ago.
Okay, back to the aliens.
Now, there's SETI with an S, searching for aliens,
and there's SETI with a C, which is communicating with aliens.
You know, we've in some sense already been communicating.
We've been putting plaques, this is a plaque from Voyager,
that's off on its way, and it's going to hit some other star
in about 20,000 years or so. It's kind of slow.
We're also radioing messages.
This is a message that was radioed from the Arecibo telescope in 74,
and I'm not going to go into what that means,
but it was badly, badly designed.
Even unintentionally, we've been communicating, you know, with all the radio waves that have been leaving Earth.
You know, so, for 55 years, you know, aliens out there can receive I Love Lucy,
and that includes 1,400 star systems.
Um, 600 stars can receive Gilligan's Island,
and a lucky 150 stars can receive Deuce of Hazard.
Now, of course, we've been listening.
You know, a lot of you might have had,
this is your screensaver, SETI at home.
It turns out that the SETI program's actually
listening to quite a bit of the bandwidth
and frequencies out there and quite a bit of space.
This is a map of, you know, by size of civilization
on one axis, how far out we should have heard of them.
In fact, we've thoroughly searched, you know,
fairly large civilizations in our galaxy
we should have seen by now.
That's brought up kind of an interesting thing.
You know, back in the 50s, Enrico Fermi,
a physicist, was having lunch and they were discussing
Drake's equation, and he had this simple
question at lunch, which is, where are they?
You know, by most of the estimates they were
plugging into those numbers, we should have aliens
all around us. They shouldn't be hard to find at all.
We should be overrun with them.
And this became known as the Fermi Paradox, or the colonization argument.
He reasoned that even if we went slow, sublight velocities, from our home planet,
took hundreds of years to get to the next star, stayed there for hundreds of years,
built, you know, maybe another ship, and went to the next set of stars,
that really, you know, with this branching factor of us spreading through the galaxy,
we should be able to fill the galaxy in less than five million years easy.
You know, which five million years sounds like a long time,
but to put it in evolutionary perspective, you know, back to this map.
Here's the complex life, you know, that we've been for the last 500 million years.
We zoom into that.
You know, the dinosaurs have been around for about half that time.
They were around for a remarkable period of time, several hundred million years,
until this asteroid came and, you know, killed them.
If we zoom into that, like the last 65 million years,
and if we had just given the dinosaurs another 20 million years to evolve,
and they were every bit as biologically complex as we are,
they would have filled the galaxy by then, you know.
So, that's a very short period of time, you know,
that it would take any alien civilization to be just all around us.
And if that actually occurred, it would actually turn out that Star Trek was right,
that all the aliens did kind of look like one species,
because it would generally be one alien species
that would be out there basically filling this galaxy.
There's this other guy, a mathematician, John von Neumann,
that came up with this idea of von Neumann probes.
This is the idea of a self-replicating machine.
And his idea was that you build these machines,
send them off, they can take as long as they want to,
100,000 years or whatever, to get to a star.
They assemble raw materials to make duplicates of themselves,
and then they'll send those duplicates off,
and then they can sit there and terraform those, you know,
or drop life, bring genetic databases, whatever.
So it's probably likely that in fact if we do meet aliens out there, the first ones we meet will probably be mechanical.
Because this is a far more efficient way.
You know, I think somebody with the wealth of like Bill Gates,
about a hundred years from now, we'll have the technology where somebody like him could probably do this on his own.
It wouldn't even have to be a giant government program.
He could just go off and build a von Neumann machine and send it out there.
Nobody's going to stop him.
Now...
This is my little side rant just about how valuable the, uh, basically robots in space are.
You know, robots are getting cheaper, more efficient, faster every year.
Humans are not. You know, I love the Manned Space Program.
I think it's really cool, amazing history.
But really, for the dollars we spend, we get so much more science out of the robots.
In fact, when I was thinking about it, I was trying to think, you know,
what was the biggest scientific benefit of the Manned Space Program?
And, uh, I think it was probably when they went up to repair the Hubble.
Um...
Which is not to take anything away from the astronauts.
I think, you know, living and working in space is, you know,
eventually going to be human destiny.
But for right now, on a limited budget, we're getting this
tremendous kind of bang for our buck out of these machines.
As a matter of fact, if you just take the price of the Hubble
telescope, that equals about one week of the war in Iraq right now.
And if you took the total cost...
If you took just what we spent in Iraq so far,
that would buy a Hubble for every member of the UN.
And you'd still have 150 left over for Antarctica.
Because nobody ever gives Antarctica anything, right?
But I want to show you a little prototype here.
This is just a very simple prototype of...
What would happen if, you know, there was panspermia, where lifeforms can spread, kind of undirected from star to star?
And how that might look. This is a very simple little galactic model.
Here we're seeing stars form. This layer is actually the radiation that those arms are causing.
These are like the spiral arms of a galaxy.
Now I can go into this and see life. I can drop in a very simple lifeform.
Oh, actually that was a star.
that green thing. Now, it'll start spreading, you know, this is taking thousands, millions
of years, but still, over time, oh, that one didn't. So much for my point there. I must
have dropped them into a high radiation zone. Yeah, I'm dropping them into a spiral arm.
Now, at this point, we'll see. It'll take some time, but over time, this microbial, this represents microbial life being spread through comets, asteroids, whatever, will spread out and eventually kind of diversify.
There's a very low probability that this life can become multicellular in this model and it will turn yellow.
And the multicellular life cannot spread that way, okay?
And so they're stuck and if they get, you know, killed for whatever reason, supernova nearby, then they're gone.
And there's a very slight chance that if those yellow multicellular things last long enough, they'll become intelligent.
Now I'm going to just kind of cheat, skip ahead here and force one of these guys to become intelligent.
Once we drop intelligent life into this model, the blue is intelligent life, you know.
This is it spreading through the galaxy.
And this is in spaceships colonizing whatever.
So from this, you know, I kind of played with a lot of parameters around this model.
And I kind of came to the conclusion that the most probable galactic states we would
encounter would be either a lifeless galaxy, like at the beginning, one that had a lot
of microbial life spread through pan-spermia, or a lot of intelligent life.
And the transitions between these phases would be relatively rapid, especially between the
last two.
So, the rear-Earth thing kind of says that there might be all these preconditions that make it special.
A high-middle star, being in the solar habitable zone,
having the Moon to help stabilize our planet, Jupiter, the galactic habitable zone.
These last three things really bought us four billion years of stability,
which is a remarkably long period of time for one planet to be stable.
This also kind of bears on what's known as the anthropic principle.
This is kind of the idea that...
It's hard for us to infer from where we are how improbable the string of events was required to create us.
You know, if we're required as observers to ask the question.
So we wouldn't be here to ask the question unless those million improbable things happened.
It might be common, it might be improbable.
We just cannot make a determination about it.
So we cannot assume that we are common elements in the universe.
Which is kind of against the prevailing Copernican principle that had been around for several hundred years before that.
Possible answers to the Fermi Paradox involve things like quarantine,
the prime director from Star Trek, you know, let's not upset the natives.
Maybe they're hiding from us. Maybe the galaxy is a very dangerous place
and they don't want anybody to know where they are.
Maybe we're looking in the wrong place.
Maybe they don't use radio waves, they use tachyons,
or something we can't detect right now.
Or maybe they don't spread, don't colonize.
But each one of these arguments kind of assumes that the aliens are applying one strategy.
And if anything we've learned from studying human history,
is that humans tend to spread and diversify in their behavior.
And with the distances involved in interstellar travel,
there's no way to maintain like a federation or enforce the prime directive.
So, it seems unlikely to me that any of these things really are good answers to the Fermi Paradox.
Okay, back to research.
Deep messages.
early on in a project, I'm always trying to figure out,
okay, what do I really want to convey to the player?
You know, we have this amazing tool,
and, um, it's interesting because I always think
of the player model as the model I'm building.
The computer model is really just kind of a path to get there.
It's an intermediate path.
And the, uh, the game really, in some sense,
is a compiler for the middle model and the player.
This is one of my favorite quotes.
Education is not the filling of a pail,
but the lighting of a fire.
I think games are actually...
even more effective to motivate people than they are to educate people.
I've gotten so many letters from people that played SimCity
and it motivated them to go off and, you know,
do a career in civil engineering or whatever.
I don't think they learned that much about civil engineering from SimCity,
but the motivation on the subject, just the introduction of the subject,
and giving them that front door to,
hey, this really is cool, is tremendous, I think.
Montessori toys are kind of an interesting example of that,
like self-directed learning, where you give them a toy
and they discover their own principles.
There was an earlier example, Froebel,
this German kindergarten teacher that came up with this block set.
people do architectural things with.
So we have this ability,
you know, to basically change our players
and at a fairly deep level, I think.
Now, the deep messages I wanted to do in Spore
involved some of the things I just talked to you about.
Pring and Principle, Fermi Paradox.
I didn't want to, you know,
beat them over the head with this.
I wanted these things that they roughly kind of
discovered on their own
after playing with the game for a while.
But after the game design evolved
and we started doing more prototyping,
these messages started to evolve as well.
So the kind of more recent messages
that I'm trying to embed in the game, you know,
include things like life is diverse.
You know, it comes in all different shapes and sizes.
Also, you know, looking at the editors and what people have been building in them and how they feel about what they've built,
to me that feels like a great message, that anybody can be creative.
You know, I want somebody to feel like they have a future at Pixar.
That, you know, after playing with this thing for half an hour, they've created a creature on the screen
that's as cool to them as something in a Pixar film.
And then it comes to life and surprises them.
So in some sense, they end up being surprised by their own creativity.
As a kid, I spent a lot of time, like, in the planetarium,
looking at these star shows on the dome overhead,
and watching star maps.
And it always frustrated me in some sense
because space is not flat.
You know, it's this wonderfully 3-D thing
with these colorful things and those Hubble images
that you might have seen walking into the auditorium today.
And so I really wanted to convey that,
that space was this wonderfully 3-dimensional dynamic thing, too.
It wasn't just static.
Looking at other games and the way they kind of present space
and stars and galaxies, you know, for most games,
a really big kind of play field is a few hundred stars, you know,
and a few hundred stars is a big play field, but it turns
out galaxies are bigger than that, like a hundred billion stars
in a typical spiral galaxy, and which is oddly enough,
it's also about the same number of neurons in your brain
and the same number of galaxies in the observed universe.
Now, why is that?
I don't know.
But...
Anyway, galaxies are large. I mean, they're really large.
And so I wanted to convey that to the players.
You know, they have this immense play field,
you know, full of interesting, cool stuff.
Uh, talk a little bit of research material.
As I said before, you know, I use books a lot.
Um, and probably read over 100 books
just researching support alone
because I get totally obsessed again with the topic.
Um, also movies and stuff.
You know, these, you know, became a lot of kind of the, uh,
templates for the, uh, metagames that we want to do
in our space game.
One of my creative heroes is Stanley Kubrick.
Some of my favorite movies were made by him.
One thing about him is that he was totally obsessive about his research.
And it also took him, you know, a long, like, five years to make a movie,
which is about how long it takes me to make a game as well.
But his research was just kind of an amazing process.
When he did Doctor Strangelove in 64,
you know, he had these recreations of the war room and the inside of the B-52.
And when the movie came out, the Air Force actually came to him.
I thought there was some leak, that somebody was leaking blueprints of a B-52.
But he actually kind of cobbled this together from public information sources
and interviewing experts about what it probably looked like,
and he got it almost dead on.
Um, he was also able to embed...
really deep messages in innovative forms.
You know, when he came out with Doctor Strangelove,
a lot of people at the time in the studio were saying,
this is crazy, we shouldn't do a comedy about nuclear war,
that's not a joking matter.
But yet, by making it a black comedy,
he was able to basically reach an audience
of younger kids that were trying to ignore this,
and all of a sudden, this is a message they could hear,
and they went and saw the movie.
And, you know, the movie was just about that,
you know, everybody that's involved in this must be mad,
you know, which is, in fact, what they were calling mad.
And so it was a great way to get this very deep message out in a new form that nobody thought was feasible.
2001 was really interesting from a research point of view in that how he got space right.
Unlike almost every other science fiction even since then, you know, every single scene you were dealing with gravity.
There was no cheat for gravity where everybody is magically walking on the floor because the gravity generator.
All the space scenes were totally soundless because in fact there is no sound in space,
even though you hear TIE fighters and things making noises as they fly by.
He did background research on human anthropology,
interviewed people at NASA,
the kind of plans that they were building for moon bases and space stations,
and artificial intelligence experts as to what, you know,
a smart computer of the future might look like and how it might be used.
Even this scene where, like, Dave gets blasted in with no air
through the vacuum to turn on the pod,
he had read a research paper that the Air Force was doing.
I don't know why they were doing this,
but they were seeing how long monkeys could survive in a vacuum.
and they found that they can survive for about a minute, actually with no permanent damage.
And so he actually based this scene on how long a human could probably survive in a vacuum,
you know, to turn the airlock knob back on.
They were also pretty innovative in terms of marketing.
This is the original poster for 2001.
And they found at some point, this came out in 1967,
that a lot of college students were dropping acid and going to see the movie,
you know, for all the cool visuals and stuff.
So they redesigned the poster.
You might notice they changed the tagline as well.
He did this in conjunction with Arthur C. Clarke, which is one of my favorite science fiction authors.
And Arthur C. Clarke was similar in that he did a lot of research for his books.
And his books were almost like a combination of fact and fiction,
which is kind of a really interesting gray area, especially for researching the kinds of things we do.
There's a very interesting group of books called world-building books
that people use to create fantasy environments for role-playing games or science fiction writing.
There are some very good websites out there, very good resources that have this as well.
And Wikipedia just continually gets more valuable to me every day,
primarily because it's filling in the gaps in these research areas.
It's not really clear whether you're going to find a book about this or a film or what.
Wikipedia is a great kind of filling in the gaps research resource.
Oh! Okay.
I didn't get a chance to do this last year.
It was too busy.
But, yeah, this is totally off topic, by the way.
I mean, this is as off topic as you can get.
And I love this picture.
It's like they're going out for a church picnic,
except they're going to launch a rocket.
Let's go launch a rocket today.
Okay.
I'm going to tell you the story of the Soyuz 23
that was launched in 1976.
Cosmonauts Zudov and Rozhdestvsky.
These were actually military cosmonauts.
Special...
core that was trained going up. The Soviets had the very first space station, the Salyut
series, and they launched six of these. These were scientific space stations, or so we thought.
It turned out that they had a military space station program as well, and they couldn't
hide the launches from us, so they just said, oh, we have six Salyuts. But it turned out
that every other one was, in fact, not a Salyut at all, but an Almaz station, the military
station. And they were interleaved, the launches. And it was a great deception, and we didn't
find out until, like, 20 years later about these things.
The Almaz were interesting. They were basically manned spy satellites.
They had these huge, you know, telescopes
that the cosmonauts could point as they were flying over
and photograph whatever ground control wanted photographed.
At the same time, the US was developing the US Dynastar X-20
as this kind of re-entry vehicle that maybe could be used as an interceptor in the Russian slot.
And so they were convinced that if we found out that they had manned spy satellites,
that we would go up and shoot them down.
So they decided they had to defend this thing.
Now witness the firepower of this fully armed and operational battle station.
So in fact, these were the first armed battle stations in orbit.
They were armed with 20mm anti-aircraft cannons
that were bore-sided along the length of the space station.
They actually, you know, destroyed several targets in target practice,
you know, satellites at about a mile distance,
but it was terrifying to fire because
it had to be tied into the reaction control system of the space station,
otherwise they would de-orbit the station with the recoil of the gun.
So, they were pretty risky.
So these guys pull up in their Soyuz, but the approach computer has them like almost crashing into it, going way too fast.
They didn't trust it, so they shut it off and they did a back burn and all this.
And before they knew it, they'd wasted all their fuel.
They didn't have any more fuel to do a manual docking, so they had to abort the mission at that point.
They never got to dock with the Almaz.
So they're coming back, and Mission Control sends them the wrong coordinates for reentry,
and they end up coming in like a hundred kilometers off target.
That puts them right in the path, right in the middle of this giant blizzard
that's blowing through Kazakhstan at the time.
And the blizzard pushes them another 50 kilometers off target.
and they end up coming down into scenic Lake Tengiz, right in the middle of it,
except it's not so scenic because it's like a blizzard and it's 20 degrees below zero at this point,
and they hit the ice and break through the ice of this frozen lake and start to sink,
and the parachute drags the whole Soyuz capsule upside down,
and now these guys are stuck in their spacesuits upside down, bopping up and down in a storm,
and this is when it starts getting bad.
The inside of one of these Soyuz is like the inside of an old VW.
And they're wearing spacesuits. They can't really...
They've never been able to take off the spacesuits while in that capsule.
So they had to cut them off with knives.
And there was an air vent that opened
because they assumed that they'd be sitting on the ground and they didn't need air.
And then water was rushing in the capsule at this point.
And so they were scrambling, grabbed the rags, managed to plug the hole to stop the leak.
And at this point, they were also out of air
because they, you know, the air vent was open and let air in.
One of the guys happened to be a diver, and so he knew that the real danger was the carbon dioxide poisoning.
And so they had almost no battery life left. They turned off every system, including the radio beacon.
to find them and he stayed up all night
bobbing upside down in the water and he,
right before he passed out from the CO2 poisoning,
he would turn on the CO2 scrubber
just long enough to get clear-headed again
and then turn it back off to save the battery power
and basically stayed all night doing that.
And the next day, he cleared a little bit
and an intrepid helicopter pilot saw the part
of the parachute cable sticking out of the ice,
managed to hook it with the helicopter
and drag them like five kilometers to the shoreline.
And to their amazement, when they opened the capsule,
both cosmonauts were still alive.
So this one has a happy ending.
That's the Russian Space Minute.
So back to the research.
When we do research, one of the other things we want to do
is establish kind of what is the style, texture of the world?
And this is almost more in a visual kinesthetic sense.
Is it real?
Is it toy-like?
How familiar does it feel?
Is it a caricature?
In sport, we actually very early identified this kind of split
in our team, kind of between what we call the science
team and the cute team, in terms of how should this thing look?
And these are kind of representative samples
from both teams.
Uh, we eventually decided that we really, whenever possible,
wanted the players to be able to make that choice themselves in the editors.
And we tried to make the editors fairly malleable,
and that would be the primary dimension that they were kind of exploring.
Um, some of the research material spanned both of these things.
We kind of went from fairly realistic stuff.
This is the work of Dougal Dixon,
who does a lot of kind of imaginary zoology stuff.
He actually also later worked on the series The Future is Wild
for the Discovery Channel, which was an excellent series
about maybe the future of evolution on Earth.
More imaginative stuff, we found great sources.
Disney did these series of movies with NASA back in the 50s about space.
And their animators were imagining what life on Mars might look like.
This is a great movie. I don't know if any of y'all saw this movie.
It had these really imaginative plans and things.
And it was like this French, Czechoslovakian, weird animated thing.
But still, the creatures and things in there were great.
As far as vehicles, you know, this is, like, great, Thunderbirds.
You know, these toy-like feel.
It turns out that Thunderbird 1 was actually based upon the Soyuz launcher, by the way.
And then these things, which I showed a little bit of last year,
these comic book covers, and these are definitely going more in the cute kind of caricature direction.
And it was just amazing how many of these things I managed to dig up.
And each one of these is several years' worth of issues.
Future, future, Captain Future, Man of Tomorrow, Tales of Wonder, Uncanny.
They just go on and on.
And each one of these things has this interesting combination of an interesting world,
maybe some cool vehicles, some aliens.
Exactly the stuff that we wanted to have in our game.
My animation director, Bob King, actually did a couple for us,
kind of in that style,
just to get a sense of what that would feel like.
It always helps to actually get like a real sample that's relevant to what you're doing, you know, in that style, and it really helps you kind of visualize it.
Um, this is actually the very first box I designed for Spore way, way back.
You know, one of the first things I always do when I do a game is I design a box.
And I was trying to give people a sense for what I was thinking, and it's, what I'm thinking has changed a lot since then, but this is kind of my original title and name for it.
This is the back of the box.
And so I do the back of the box with bullet points,
little screenshots, you know.
And in fact, I put this on a real box
with something inside of it so it feels heavy
so I can hand it to somebody and they can imagine,
oh, yeah, I'm in a software store holding this.
Would I buy it?
If you zoom in here, you'll see that this is early on
when I was thinking that we would be colonizing
at sublight velocities and how exciting that would be.
I kind of changed my mind.
These are the system requirements
that I was estimating at the time.
Now, you know, early in this phase, we wanted to go through this process of deconstruction
and reconstruction of creatures, vehicles, buildings, planets, all the stuff in the game.
We actually had a lot of people come in and say, draw an alien creature. If you could
design a creature in the game, what would it be? And we had them do drawings. And we
studied the drawings. More recently, our fan sites have started doing that. This is what
I want to build in Spore. These are from one of our fans, Hydro Mancer.
These are drawings that he's done of things that he wants to do in the game.
And it's really instructive for us to go look at those expectations and say,
can we measure our editors against this?
This is actually a really cool little prototype that appeared,
I think, after we showed Spore last year at GDC.
These students at USC took their first level, the cell level,
and built it, basically, you know, in Flash.
A very cool game.
And it's great when other people do your prototypes for free,
you know, without even asking like that.
I got to meet Jenova Chin just like two days ago, and he's a brilliant guy with a great aesthetic.
We also hired this conceptual artist, Christian Schur, who came in,
and we had him draw all sorts of things that we then went through this deconstructive process with.
We had him draw things in different styles, like scary aliens, maybe goofy things.
you know, other things that were just kind of odd and alien-like ways.
Um, after taking all these creatures, some of which were related, some of which weren't,
we then started deconstructing them into parts.
You know, if we had to pull sets of parts off of these things, what would they be?
And, um, we found that the eyes and the mouths were like the most expressive parts that we could pull off.
But then we had all the other ones, hands, wings.
And then at some point we started putting these deconstructed parts into a taxonomy.
How do we now sort these parts with some sort of evolutionary relationship?
You know, what is the path in which a player might explore these on a tech tree, for instance?
And what is the functional categorization?
So these might be carnivorous mouths up here.
These might be herbivorous mouths over there.
And so we're just getting some sense of how we can kind of take these whole constructs
and pull them into lower and lower level pieces
and then establish the relationships between those pieces.
And then we move them into modeling, you know,
because it's a big difference going from kind of illustration to modeling.
And then we start building larger sets of these things
that we're actually going to use in game.
Each one of these parts also, by the way, has morph channels.
So each one represents the center of, in fact,
a fairly wide morph space where you can stretch the toes out
or make them curly or add this or that feature to it.
And then eventually reconstruct features
after going through that deconstruction-reconstruction process
that I mentioned with the generative artists,
doing it with the content here as well.
Same thing with textures.
brainstorm ideas, then go out and actually develop the
particular scripts, apply them, see how close we got to the
targets.
Vehicles, pretty much the same thing.
Conceptual, air, land, sea, build the models, texture,
buildings.
Same thing, blocks, models.
And then finally put them in a scene.
Planets were a little more elaborate.
On the planets, we actually started with a lot of very simple descriptions
of the variety of worlds we wanted players to be able to create in the game.
We took a few of those and we went really deep on them,
looking at the materials that we might find on that world,
how that might influence the coloring,
what sort of items, vehicles, trees, landforms we might find on those worlds.
And then developing these kind of pictures showing the world.
Another process was actually taking worlds and going through and building a backstory.
What sort of cities would they build?
What would their industry be?
What would their sociology be like?
What are the elements of their technology?
And so these are all from the same world,
kind of looking at different snapshots of how these people live and how their world looks.
And then eventually developing the characters, reassembling it all into one scene.
for the final rendering. And, you know, it isn't that we want the players to build exactly
this world. Each one of these worlds represents some outpost of this space, this creative
space that we want them to be able to build themselves. And so they're like almost eigenvalues
around the planet space. Now, eventually we get to the geology level and we're actually
developing scripts that will carve out and make these planets. Some are more fantastic,
some are more realistic.
We have one guy, Christian Stratton, who's kind of like my Magrathea.
This is the guy that builds my planets for me, one of my artists.
He's actually been building a taxonomy of what types of planets we would find in different zones,
how they should look, plus their relative distribution in the universe.
We have some that are very out there, imaginative, more Dr. Seuss,
that we want to be very rare. If you find one of those, you get excited about it.
Most of them are more terrestrial, so there is this concept of kind of...
whimsical equals rarity, that as you're exploring the galaxy, you feel like you've discovered treasures.
As we pull away from the planets, we get out to all these cool Hubble pictures.
And we're trying to recreate all these in 3D. These are actually from the game,
game versions of all the Hubble objects, so they're three-dimensional things that you can kind of move around,
interact with in space level.
Now to wind down really quick here...
Okay, back to Drake's equation.
Now...
Clearly all these values are not zero.
And in fact, none of those values can be zero.
If any of those values were zero, we wouldn't be here.
So each one of these values has to be something.
If we take fairly pessimistic assumptions
and we bump them all up to .01,
and most of these are fractional, so it's like 1%,
and then we just take those numbers
and we multiply them times the, you know,
100 billion stars in a typical galaxy
times the 100 billion galaxies that we know of,
we still end up with a pretty large number of aliens out there,
about 100 million in this case.
That's a large number, but on the other hand, that's only about one alien species per thousand galaxies.
So even if we bump those numbers up a bit, we're still talking about
probably less than one alien species per galaxy, especially if they spread into a galaxy very rapidly.
So my conclusions from SETI, not that you really care,
is that they're out there, but they're probably really far away, not in our galaxy.
And that has a lot of implications for the search for SETI,
that we should be looking further out to distant galaxies.
My research conclusions are that, and this is something I do always at the beginning of every project,
is I take a lot of time to consider it, and don't get too committed to any one idea too early.
And that's what I'm doing a lot of the reading and the research phase.
I cast usually a very wide net over subjects, and a lot of times, like in the Sims,
which started as an architectural simulator and led more to behavioral stuff,
I'll find myself taking very interesting kind of twists and turns through that research path.
And what you really want to know is what 90% of the material is irrelevant to that core idea,
because that core idea is going to be shifting around underneath your feet all the time,
and you need to kind of understand the region of space it can shift in.
I have no problem with this one.
But getting totally obsessive about your subject, I find, helps a lot.
You know, it drives the interest.
You know, whenever you see anything that's relevant to what you're working on,
you'll see it more readily on the shelf,
or somebody mentions something, or an article.
You'll just find yourself absorbing this stuff so readily
that it's almost effortless.
And then you want to cultivate that onto your team, you know,
as you talk to your team about this stuff, you know,
and get them interested in it.
Pretty soon you'll be talking about this stuff over lunch,
and you're all really enjoying it and learning from each other.
And this kind of, you know, comes to the fact that eventually you're going to become a teacher.
Not just to the people on your team, but to the people in your game.
You know, these deep lessons that you're learning through research
are eventually, through several filters, going to end up, you know, kind of as a player.
And this is one thing that is probably the most important to me,
is the fact that we always have the opportunity to change our players at a very deep level.
I mean, to the point where we can influence their future career, for instance.
And that's something that we shouldn't take lightly.
And it's something that we shouldn't squander.
So we should probably make the best use of that whenever we can.
So thank you.