All right, so welcome to my talk.
This is the development diary of Marvel's Spider-Man.
Specifically, I'm going to be speaking more
about the cinematic creation in Marvel's Spider-Man,
but I worked a little bit on combat
in the beginning of the project.
And we'll just get rolling here.
So my name is Brian Weiser.
I'm a lead animator at Insomniac Games.
I've been in this animation racket since the last century.
I've been doing this for quite a while.
I've worked in VFX.
I've worked in games mostly.
Spent some time in tech
and even had a period where I had my own company.
About five or six years ago,
I came to Insomniac to work on Sunset Overdrive.
And then shortly after we completed Sunset Overdrive,
Sony came to us and said,
we'd like to work with you guys on a Marvel property.
What do you think?
So we were obviously excited.
And we, let me hit one thing here, sorry about this.
There we go.
Gonna time myself better here.
And we got the opportunity to choose
which character we were gonna use.
So me, being the animator or the artist,
I really wanted to do some obscure character,
but boy was I wrong.
We chose this guy, Spider-Man.
So I hope to provide a little bit of insight
into our cinematic process and Insomniac Games.
I mean, maybe for some of you this will be a review,
for some of you this is maybe what you do every day,
but hopefully I'll either give you some tips
on how you can improve what your storytelling
or your projects turn out to be,
or I can validate some of the things
that you're faced with every day
and you can realize that many of us
face these same problems.
The other thing I want to say is there are definitely spoilers in this talk.
I apologize.
There's a few moments that I wanted to highlight.
And really though, our game has been out since September, and if you haven't played it, maybe
you can't afford it, go borrow it from a friend.
What I will say is, swinging through the city is pretty damn fun, and I had nothing to do
with that.
That was an entirely different team, but get it.
Try it.
It's awesome.
All right.
Here we go.
Spoilers.
Walk out if you need to.
All right, so early on in Spider-Man, like I said,
I was working on combat.
Our animation director, Bobby Coddington,
he was serving as the main animator.
And then a few of us rolled onto the project
in pre-production.
We spent a lot of time focusing on comic book imagery
as the source material for our posing.
And I'll step through a few of them here.
And at one point in time, my talk
had the exact comic slides that would match up
with these images.
but I couldn't clear those through legal,
so we can't get those.
You can't see them.
You can just guess.
Some of these are pretty clear.
Some of these are similar to covers.
We also jumped into tests.
This is the thing I did on the first day of the project.
I was just playing around
with our Sunset Overdrive-based Spider-Man.
We really didn't have a character yet.
And I was trying to figure out ways for.
us to present an alternate form of combat,
something that isn't just punching and kicking.
And along the way in combat, there was another test
we threw in, which I think made it into the game,
the slide under dodge.
This was actually something that was introduced
by myself and an engineer during a little bit of downtime
right after a milestone.
The counter and kick after that, I think, got cut,
but at any rate, we got some of it to stay.
In addition, as you guys can see, there's a theme here.
I was really into getting Spider-Man to climb all over his villains.
I didn't want him to just punch and kick.
I wanted him to just disable them in other ways that only this villain can to differentiate
our project and lean into those differentiators.
Again, none of these tests are actually final.
This is just something I was throwing together.
So to give you a little bit of background,
at Insomniac we have a system that is based on Maya.
We export our scenes from Maya,
and they get funneled into our cinematic editor.
So this is a view of our timeline in the cinematic editor,
and to anyone in here that has edited before,
it's really incredible for us that we have a tool set
that looks like a nonlinear editor.
We're able to slide around shots, add tracks,
add effects, add lighting,
and all the other aspects of our scenes
can be easily entered into this editor.
This is also accompanied by a viewer,
but I didn't want to show you that.
It just doesn't.
run as well, and at any rate, it's not there.
The other, I think, advantage that we've added
to our pipeline is our camera.
We've spent a lot of time working on ways
to improve the way we shoot.
Most of this work has come from trial and error
and Insomniac, but a lot of us have come
from other studios where we've experienced
creating films or shooting for other cinematics,
and there's benefits to what we do.
One of the things we're always trying to think about
is where is the camera?
Who's operating the camera?
Who's holding it?
based on the answer to that question,
it'll define how the camera functions
with a little bit of frequency and a little bit of noise.
To aid in the animation work and make our job faster,
we don't hand animate all that all the time.
We have a number of different sliders
here that you can kind of see in this initial column.
And really, all that these are are a way
to dial in the weights of a number of different frequency
or a number of different wavelengths that apply
to the translation channels on the camera.
So for instance, shake.
is something that you'd often use if you were in a helicopter shot where the operator might be
sitting there and something that's vibrating and wave is something we use often when we're trying
to do a little bit of handheld. The other advantage that we or the other addition that we've added to
our camera
to help us be more cinematic in our thinking
and the way we're trying to tell stories
is we've actually mirrored real-world lenses
from an Alexa Prime camera package
that you would find on a film set.
This came from one of our incredibly talented animators,
Josh Gridley, who had joined our team
after leading a number of productions at third floor
and working on film previs.
So, now back to the story.
After about a year or so working on combat,
our narrative team started to shape the scenes
and the overall trajectory of our story
in a way that we could start working on it.
So I moved from combat over to cinematics,
and we started to realize we were looking at
about 90 minutes of story cinematics,
and that's just our story cinematic team
that I was the lead of.
There was a number of other animators involved
in two other animation pods that worked on
in-game set pieces and massive moments
and other mission-related cinematics.
So on my pod we had 12 animators.
That does include myself and the animation director
who were very involved in the scene creation.
We had roughly two years at that time to finish our story.
And yes, it was freaking daunting.
I mean, so many of us were really concerned
with the fact that we were jumping into a character
that was arguably overly saturated in the market.
Maybe people are bored with him.
What were they going to like what we made?
So I was pretty freaked out.
So, just to give you a high-level view of our process when it comes to creating cinematics,
we start with Previs.
Most of our animators will jump into doing thumbnails or animatics on their own, but
that's not something that we've actually incorporated into our workflow because in my experience
and in the experience of our team, it's much more efficient for us to jump into 3D as fast
as possible.
Once we identify our previews, we get to a level of time lock,
then we'll identify what we can animate with hand-keying,
which is a lot of the Spider-Man work
or a lot of the villains that are in the scene.
Or we'll identify the scenes that we need to take to PCAP.
After we get data back from performance capture,
we'll lay the scene out again.
Part of that is because we don't want to infect
our animators with, or excuse me,
our actors with our previews.
In most cases, we don't even show them our previews.
We give them good blocking instruction.
We tell them where the cameras will be,
but we want them to help bring about the performance.
We want them to help us make a better character
or a better scene.
which requires us to layout again.
After we get through a number of weeks of animating
and working on layout and coming to a final edit,
animation is finally ready to release that scene
to the other departments
that will help bring these things to final
and actually make them so much better
than we can create on our own.
So we lock the edit, we release it to visual effects,
lighting and audio and score
and anyone else who has to contribute to the scene.
And finally, concurrently now at that point,
we're polishing the scenes, we're fixing bugs,
and we're banging away on many other scenes.
So, Previs.
Generally speaking, at Insomniac,
we assign one scene per animator,
and we try and cast these scenes out
to animators that have strengths and weaknesses.
But we're not limited to that.
We don't want to pigeonhole people,
so we allow them to try different scenes.
We iterate exhaustively on Previs, especially on i20.
We would meet twice a week,
where we would gather together the entire cinematic team
and sit for an hour, hour and a half in a room,
and all go over the scenes, provide feedback,
a safe place to weigh in on what we're working on.
This also helped us because we didn't have a singular person shooting them or editing them,
so it helped us to remain connected.
And the other benefit of jumping right into Preview is...
is we're readily able to add these into the game,
like this little joke that our animator threw in there
at the end of the scene where we didn't have all the pages.
Once the previews is built, we can put this in the game,
we can identify hookups, or as many of the people
in this room might know who work on cinematics,
that's the point where the character leaves gameplay
and goes into cinematic, and then leaves cinematic
and goes back to gameplay.
We spend an incredible amount of time
just focusing on those little bits.
It's actually a disproportionate amount of time.
All right, so as I said, the animators on our team
are cinematographers as well.
So we spent a lot of time working through previz
and when we get back into layout,
thinking about how we can use the environment
to help tell the story.
We're thinking about depth planes.
We're thinking about ways to really work
in old 2D animation styles.
And as you can see here in the bottom two images,
so we had a shot with Peter or Spider-Man
suiting up in the very beginning of the game.
And in the one on the left,
Late on in the project we realized it was a pretty flat shot.
There was a lot of information but it was equidistant from the camera.
So we just threw in this bed to give us a little depth of field element in the foreground
and that I think plus the shot.
One of the other things we do in my opinion is we shoot scenes overall twice.
The first pass is to get comprehension.
It's to allow us to build something that makes sense.
We're not crossing the line of action unintentionally.
Scene geography makes sense.
You know where actors are.
And then we take another pass.
We jump back in and try and infuse subtext as best we can.
And that could be altering compositions,
moving the character to the center of the screen,
or offsetting and having them look
into the short side of the screen
to let the audience feel awkward,
or looking for frames within frames or other opportunities.
And again, this is a massive art form in and of itself.
I won't go too deep into it, but it's something
that so many people on our team are really
working hard to do in addition to being animators.
So another thing, we have to shoot a lot of dialogue scenes
when it comes to the story cinematic pod.
And you're.
It's some people's tendency to want to shoot the words that are coming out of a person's mouth.
And I want to raise the importance here of reaction shots.
Reactions of characters within a scene help the audience understand how they should feel about the scene.
They help us understand the emotional journey that a character is going through.
I say no dragnet because that's an example
that I found in a Walter Murch book
where he describes that old show,
I don't know if anyone in this room knows that old show,
but the way that they would shoot it
is they would point the camera at the speaker
and it ultimately felt like a tennis match.
You'd see one person speak and they'd cut
and put another person and they'd cut
and they'd put another person and they'd cut.
And you didn't really understand the emotion of the scene
and I suppose it will work for a factual based story
but not necessarily something we were working on.
So this scene, again big spoiler, you know what I'll pause this if anyone does not want to watch
it and go back. But anyway go back to that again, sorry about that. This scene was actually the
topic of conversation. We got feedback. You knew? That I was told to put the camera on Aunt May when
she's talking to Peter. I never wanted you to worry. I did and I am so proud of you.
And Ben would be too. All the people you've saved.
And that's just one small example where,
I mean, it's small, but I think it's important
in that scene where we understand Peter's journey,
we feel with him.
And if the camera was on Aunt May,
it wouldn't have had the same impact on the audience.
So reaction shots are important.
So the other thing that our animators work on is editing.
We're animators, cinematographers,
and we're also editing scenes.
And just to quickly gloss over some of the things
that we think about, we certainly want the edit
to mirror the emotion of a shot, of a sequence.
So in these initial shots, this is a conversation
between Peter and MJ, and it's a very low-tempo,
calm scenario, and...
we give you long shots.
We're not cutting around this very frequently.
We're not affecting the audience
with how fast we're going from shot to shot.
We're trying to allow the rhythm of the shots themselves
to support the action.
In contrast, what I'm about to show is a fight scene
where as you can see,
these shot lengths are distinctly shorter.
We're bouncing around very quickly.
We're trying to get you to feel the chaos of the action.
And in addition, we keep the camera moving
and really just kind of keep the pace rolling.
And lastly, to talk about editing, there's the power of discontinuity.
So, sometimes within an action moment, you want to show an action twice, so it heightens the importance.
This is seen often in John Woo films and Jackie Chan films, where in one shot they will show...
an impact of a fist hitting the face.
And then on a cut, the next shot will show
three or four frames prior to that impact,
so you're seeing it twice.
Now the audience doesn't catch that,
but it adds importance to that shot.
It adds importance to that action,
and it helps to sell what's happening in the scene.
So in addition to editing, when it comes to timing.
We were close.
Go ahead.
I'll let this play.
I'll keep trying.
I will find a cure.
I will.
I love you, son.
So one of the first things we do when we assign previs
is we record temp dialogue.
We get our animators in a room, and we record the script
as best we can.
Some of our animators are better actors than others.
I am not one of the good actors.
This animator, Alex Zimke, is actually fantastic.
He's a great animator, and he's a great read.
He's in so many of our previs moments.
But the point that we want to get at is previs for us
is so much about selling the writer's ideas
and selling our ideas to the broader team,
and we can get buy-in to build these moments.
To quote Walter Murch, an editor who worked on so many incredible films from Apocalypse Now to a number of other things,
sound is a huge influence on people's attention.
And with that in mind, we really try to make sure that our previews contains scores,
sound effects, VFX, and really anything we can do to help sell our ideas better.
So...
In a mocap-based game, as anyone in this room can attest to,
mocap is definitely not everything.
I never stop.
Even when you have a scene where it's just two people
sitting at a table talking,
well, there might be a moment where they gotta kiss.
And it's kind of impossible with the HMCs.
So Laura Bailey and Yuri Lowenthal, fantastic actors in their own right.
But this is a perfect example of where, you know, mocap is not just going to slide in the game.
It just doesn't work. Animators are needed. Don't worry, anyone who animates here, your job is safe.
So something else that we do a lot on Spider-Man that I think is a huge advantage to the way we're telling our stories,
let's see, here we go, is we tend to shoot some of our action sequences...
with two actors on the stage at the same time,
but delivering a singular performance.
While this takes a little bit more time
in our prep and our walkthroughs.
All right, we'll pause that.
What it gives us is a unified performance with voice actor and stunt actor,
and we allow the experts to bring to the table what they're good at.
You know, Yuri's fantastic, but I'm not going to ask him to do a backflip on the stage.
We need him. He's too important. He's going to get hurt.
But what this allowed us to do, and many of the people in this room probably understand
when it comes to animation and cinematics,
you'll often have 80-yard lines or lines that are added after the fact or the script was changed.
And as animators, we need to go in there and add head accents and connect those to the body.
This is a very quick way for us to capture and get the complete performance all in one.
It also helps us to avoid stitching, which is something that you have to do a lot with mocap,
where we would have, if I was to take this sequence from our Black Cat DLC,
you might have a moment where we're working with the performance actor, and the stunt actor comes
in, and the performance actor comes in, and then we as animators would have to blend those together.
That's just a big pain in the ass. It's so much easier to have all this together.
So another thing that our Previs allows us to do is innovate and solve problems early.
So this was a shot that early in our very first cinematic we were putting into our vertical
slices, this is actually the first Previs I put together, on the page it said
A lot of crazy action happens, truck gets, takes off,
and Peter's gonna chase the truck.
And we leave Peter on the rooftop,
sitting in a perch position.
So as an animator, I just kind of didn't think
that was right.
Come on, Spider-Man's never gonna wait.
He's gonna chase after this action.
So with this, I pushed for our ability
to blend from cinematics to gameplay on the move.
Early on, a lot of people balked at this
and thought this was a big concern
and maybe we shouldn't try that for our...
initial vertical slice.
Long story short, we now have a system that allows us
to blend into many states throughout the game,
most specifically,
falling and in the air, which is actually
quite easy for us, there's no contacts, and we do this
all the time now.
Alright, so,
the project's going well, everything's fine,
and then you open up your shocker scene,
and this is what you see.
Or,
you go back to your MJ scene,
where she's in Grand Central Station,
and this is what you see.
And we all know gameplay's messy, so when Otto and Norman talk, this might also be something
you see.
Now, I'm just pointing this out because, as we all know, there's a lot of problems when
it comes to creating games.
There's so many of us involved.
Things change every day.
No scene stays the same.
Trust me, the scene looked better when we shipped it.
But to solve this...
One of the things, and I'm going to talk about a meeting.
I'm sorry, everybody.
We actually introduced a meeting midway through production
where we realized that most of these problems
come from communication gaps.
So we have an assets meeting now.
That's every week.
And what happens in that meeting is
I sit in the front of the room and I go through our previs.
I go through anything that's in production.
And we talk about it with all the leads
of other departments to identify holes
or identify areas where either they don't have the bandwidth
for this coming down the pipe, so we need to change course,
or.
they can introduce their ideas early on and we can get buy-in and finish our scenes together.
So yes, meetings are important.
One of the other things we have in Spider-Man is many costumes for Peter
when he's as Spider-Man.
In general, the narrative team and writing helped us to avoid many of the problems with him where
we had to remove his mask and it wouldn't have been very easy for us to do that with all of
the possibilities that he has for his costume. But it wasn't limited to our hero. So we had
this moment.
in the game where a spider was to stow away on MJ.
And this spanned a couple of different missions
and it was through a number of different cinematics.
High alert.
And once that spider got to the feast center,
it was supposed to leave MJ,
as you can see in this incredibly animated scene
by one of our animators, Liam Murphy.
And then it's gonna go on and bite somebody else.
I won't spoil that.
even though I spoiled other things here.
However, this is what we saw, again,
when we went back to the scene later on,
because the designer, rightfully so,
had put in the proper suit, and the spider's gone.
So the solution to this was simply brute force.
Unfortunately, we had to assess the problems.
We had to go to each of those scenes
and any other mission or anything
that's related to those moments
and identify where the least work would be needed,
and then we'd fix that.
Moving forward, our lead animator, Gavin Goulden,
essentially mapped out all of the clothing
that any of the actors can wear in our game,
and we had a kind of a timeline of their life.
So this is something that,
while it becomes forgotten pretty quickly,
you need to remember that continuity is important.
All right, so another problem
when it comes to creating cinematics
is it's rare that you're aligned with the rest of the game.
So in this particular moment,
we built a scene that was solely based on the concept below.
We shot it, we had this great idea
that Spider-Man was gonna be tethered to the ground,
and it was going to be really exciting.
And then midway through production,
we realized that gameplay might not even be building that.
We may not even have a tether.
It's not a thing that'll work.
Unfortunately, we had to pivot,
and we took what was a part of our Sable agent's bola
that worked, but I guess the point I'm trying to make here
is cinematics themselves are often challenging
to keep in alignment with mission development,
and you just need to remain aware
and communicate with your teams.
Scene rot is a term that we've coined for when you leave a scene alone and something's
going to happen.
And this is no one's fault.
It's just, there are so many of us making these games.
So many things that are going into them that something is bound to change inadvertently
and it will affect the scenes as we go back and edit them.
So you might have a moment where Spider-Man was supposed to be on a building.
You can see the little speck there in the middle.
Well, there's no building anymore.
Or you might have a moment where one of the Sable agents is also supposed to be on a building.
There's no building there.
Or our villain, after a huge climactic moment,
was supposed to look unconscious in a helicopter,
but there's a chair going through his chest.
And finally, I think one of the most egregious
of these ones that I'm highlighting,
you saw this a little earlier,
where Spider-Man swung through an open space in a billboard.
Well, one day we opened the scene
and this is what it looked like.
To our team's credit, though,
the moment these are identified,
everyone jumps to and we fix these very quickly
in all departments, it's great support in Insomniac.
So we've had a bunch of problems.
We've developed a workflow.
We're working pretty well.
We're starting to rise above and fix those problems.
And we get to the point where we need to start
releasing these scenes to other departments
and finish them and finish the game.
And it's at this time in our production
that our animators almost become,
well, they're also polishing animation
and finishing their work.
They become shepherds for their own scenes
and they're communicating with others
to make sure that the remaining details are completed.
This scene in particular epitomizes the collaboration
with other departments and other people to create a performance.
So we have an entire fight scene that's
on a rooftop at the end of our raft mission.
And I would say there's a.
Not a single animation in this moment that doesn't include the work of a stunt performer,
or an actor, or an animator completely changing the performance.
In fact, there's a moment in the beginning of this where Spiderman leaps off of Scorpion's tail,
lands on Scorpion, then lands on the ground.
And I happened to be working with one of our stunt actors just the other day,
who was involved in this, and he joked to me, he said he was playing through,
and he was watching the scene and said, well, there I am.
Oh, no, that's not me.
No, no, that's not.
Oh, there I am again.
I'm just kind of identifying how much we kind of work together
to create one performance.
Arguably, I think it would be great
if we could go back to crediting the way Disney used to,
where they'd have actors and animators and anyone else
involved in a character credited on the same slide.
All right.
So one of the other problems that we have in a massively,
well, in an open-world game is we will often
have scenes where we want.
a continuous narrative to move through a number of different locations that are nowhere near
one another on the map.
This would have been completely unacceptable to have loading screens between each of these
vignettes.
So, we kind of started building these frankincense.
We worked closely with the art department
to identify all of the parts we need,
kind of pull them together and make a unique set
that we just throw underground for these cinematics.
So while ideally it would be in the open world,
it was just simply not possible.
And through their support, we were able to complete these
in a way that didn't really ruin the game.
Can you, can you-
Here's another example of a Franken set
where we go from the Feast Center
to MJ speaking at a desk,
all the way to Norman's apartment.
But in the interest of keeping my talk moving along here,
maybe I'll get to some questions.
I'm going to kind of skip through some of this.
transit points. Throughout the city...
Alright. So not only is this
frankenset notion one way we hide
loading, but sometimes we can't do that.
The thing we want to hide that's getting
loaded is far too massive.
And specifically in the beginning of our game,
Spider-Man shows up at Fisk Tower
and is going to help the police go in and
take down Fisk. So we wanted to go from
open world directly into this entire
instance of our lobby and the entire
building of Fisk Tower.
Did you see the cut?
See where it happened?
Someone there?
Anyway, so our goal is to, again, work directly
with all of the other departments involved
in creating anything for our game,
and we have to collaborate to make this work.
This was really a long process.
In fact, to the extent that people told me
we shouldn't be doing any of this, this is not a good idea.
But we work closely with design and lighting and effects
to identify the singular frame on which we are going
to teleport Peter from being within.
the open world to going to the instanced interior
that he's now going to continue on.
The bigger challenge we have here
is constraining our cameras and working with environment
to provide visual blockers.
But again, this is something we hope to do more of
in the future.
It is our goal that games at Insomniac
ultimately eliminate the loading screen,
and we'll see if that works, I don't know.
It's a big challenge.
Facial animation is another challenge that we have.
Sorry, I just burst the mic.
So when it comes to facial animation,
it is critical that lighting is involved
as early as possible.
I can change in six months.
So when we look at these scenes.
Why did you ask me here, Pete?
You can see a dramatic difference between final lighting
and even a passive lighting that was pretty close to final.
To the extent that as we're reviewing facial animation
that comes from Cubic Motion, incredible team,
did some incredible work for our project.
Can't thank those guys enough.
You can see the distinct difference.
I might not have approved something
with that near final lighting versus the final lighting.
So really what this boiled down to at the end,
again working with another department,
we got into the cycle where we would get
first pass animation here.
Next time you get in my way, I will not be.
We'll get first pass animation in,
then we'll get first pass lighting in.
And then we'll go back and get more fixed animation.
We'll adjust head and neck,
because in our facts-based facial animation system,
there are blend shapes that'll emerge
if the head is pushed back too far,
things we can't see before the facial animation
goes in there.
And then lighting, we'll light again,
and so on and so forth,
until we kind of arrive at this final
that we can approve and feel is successful
and ready to ship.
And I can change the six points.
Head and neck.
One of the other challenges that we have in our game
is the living world.
We often had scenes that were in the exterior,
through which we had to contend with the fact
that we have this incredible system of vehicles and bots
that is a technical and creative achievement.
If anyone notices, that's my head
actually getting beaten down there.
But at any rate, so within these scenes,
it would be impossible for us to shoot this
as an entire cinematic, to contain every character
that we have here within our scenes
and actually work with it.
There's no way Maya would actually even function.
So we would break these down and try and leverage
the in-game.
systems as much as we can to tell the whole story.
And there's a shot that comes up here
that can better articulate what I'm trying to say.
Let me pause this one.
So this is a perfect example.
So within this shot, our cinematic is constructed
primarily of these three actors.
We have Miles Morales, Rio Morales, and JD Morales.
And then...
We have some mid-ground characters
that are coming from a secondary cinematic that
is funneled into that same one.
And then we also have other actors
that are coming from the living world.
So it's in combination with all these other departments
that we can create this one scene.
Otherwise, there's no way that we could handle it,
and the scenes would no longer be performing.
So one of the other things we had to contest with
is screens within our scenes.
So often on the page, it'll just simply say,
and Peter walks by a screen and sees x.
Those were often their own cinematics.
We had to actually build those out as their own thing.
And it was a challenge and often forgotten
because it was one of the things
that would either fall on effects or lighting
or no one really claimed them.
We have another one here where Norman
is supposed to be speaking on a TV the entire time.
If ever you see that in a script,
go back to your writer and make sure they realize
they need to write that whole speech.
Whether or not you're looking at Norman,
he should be talking the entire time.
And in addition, we have other reveals that are on screens.
Again, these are their own cinematics
that were unaccounted for,
kind of came up in production,
and we had to throw it together.
So in conclusion, I hope that you enjoyed this,
first of all.
Secondly, I think at Insomniac,
we've leveled up our storytelling techniques
and our abilities to give the audience emotional journeys.
I think cinematics have their challenges.
I think I've highlighted a few of them.
I'm sure there are, I mean, I don't have enough time
to go through all of the problems and issues that we face.
And many of you, I'm sure, can deal with that here too,
or can speak to that as well.
And lastly, I hope there's at least a little bit
that you can take from what I've said here
and maybe it validates what you've already done
in your studio or you can use a little nugget
of information to help improve the way you guys
tell stories with more confidence in the future.
And that's pretty much all I got.
I'm open to questions at this point,
but thank you all so much for coming to my talk.
Thank you.
It's great.
My kids are going to think I did a great job.
So I'll take questions as long as I can.
And I know there's another room that we
can walk to if there's more questions after this.
So feel free.
I can take one question.
All right.
You, sir.
Hi.
So where, I have two questions and they're
somewhat related to each other.
Where in the process do you loop in the downstream teams,
like lighting and effects and sound,
into what you're making for a cinematic?
And then you mentioned that you like to include VFX and SFX
in the previous process.
Your animator is doing temp versions of those assets,
or is that after you've looped in the other teams
and they're providing temp versions?
So the question was, where do we include the other departments?
And are the animators doing the temp versions?
So I'll answer those in the inverse order.
So in Previs, the animators are putting those in.
But we're not trying to drive the other department's work.
We are not the experts.
We're just trying to, again, like I said, sell ideas
and get people to buy into these scenes.
When it comes to when we engage other departments,
we try to do so as early as possible.
They see scripts.
They see what we're working on.
But with the introduction of that asset meeting
that I mentioned.
we actually engage them in early previews now.
We show them the things that we're working on.
They're not actually actively working
on the scenes themselves,
but they at least understand the work that's coming to them
and have the opportunity to tell us
whether or not they can support that
or introduce new ideas that'll help us
and improve the scenes in general.
We are not the experts in those departments at all.
I mean, myself, I have a history in animation
and so does my team,
and we're branching out into other things
as we develop these scenes.
Thank you.
Thank you, everybody.