Hello there. Do you like puzzle games? Yes? So do I. I'm Brett Taylor. I recently made
a game called Line Light, which did pretty well. I am here at this GDC to share my secrets
on puzzle design. So what makes a great puzzle game great?
In this talk, I'm going to unpack the different components of interactive puzzles.
So games like Sudoku, Braid, Threes, sort of anything that falls under the puzzle genre.
Give vocabulary to it so you can see and evaluate puzzles more clearly to equip you as a better designer.
Also go through the different lessons that I learned making LineLight.
There were a lot of lessons.
And give actionable takeaways, like a toolbox of strategies,
that you can use right away to begin designing better puzzles.
So join me this Wednesday, March 20th at 5pm for a train ride into Fun Town.
Next stop...
Fun Town.