Hi everyone, welcome to the GDC Twitch channel. My name is Brian Francis. I am the invisible voice inside your head
I'm here as always representing GDC as the community manager representing the fine folks at Gamma Sutra
Oh boy
This is a new puzzle
Oh man, also, why is my
Uh, hang on.
Okay, sorry, I'm going to do the intro and then I'm going to worry about this game.
Okay, cool, that's intentional.
Hi, I'm Bryant, I'm a contributing editor at Gamasutra, I'm a community manager at GDC.
In the lower left hand corner of the screen, my friend Alex Walro has joined us today.
Alex, how are you doing?
I'm doing alright.
I just realized how odd it is that because of a camera mix-up, I'm the only face on here.
And yet I'm the least interesting person on this stream.
We have a very special guest with us today.
A very special guest.
Would you please tell everyone who you are and what you do?
OK.
Hello there.
I'm Arvi Teikari.
I'm the developer of Baabai Zuu, and I was kindly asked to
be the disembodied voice on the stream
to describe possibly what is happening on screen.
I mean, some other things.
Why don't we open a puzzle that just broke my brain is all I can say
Baba is you is a game developer choice award nominee this year. That's why we are here streaming it with our feet
Are we also this game one? So it was nominated it didn't win. It was nominated back at the IGF's in 2017 or did it?
18 yeah
It was nominated in four categories and it won two categories
Yeah, like oh, yeah
It was nominated in Grand Prize Innovation or Nouveau Award,
the Excellence in Design and Best Student Game,
and it won Excellence in Design and Student.
Right on, with that in mind, we are here,
oh, nope, don't want to do that.
We are here playing Baba this year with Arvi,
just taking your questions, chatting about the game design and development,
after seeing it do so well at the awards this year.
We just wanted to come back and chat with Arvi
and see how things are going.
You're working on a level editor, right, Arvi?
Yeah, we are going to release a level editor sometime this year.
I was really hoping for a spring release date, but as it happens, things always take longer than expected,
so at this point I'm trying to avoid promising any dates, but yeah, it will be sometime this year.
It's surprisingly difficult, like when you're a game developer,
you sometimes want to make a level editor for your own use,
and there you can just hide everything behind obscure button combinations,
but when you make a level editor for, like, actual users...
you kind of have to make it nice to use and that's surprisingly difficult.
Right on.
While I try to figure out this puzzle right here and mostly just embarrass myself, would
you mind getting into, I should also give a shout out to the folks in chat, we've got
folks like Ryder of Blox hanging out.
Ryder, thanks for joining us, we'll be taking questions from folks like you as we go on,
so if you have questions for Arvi, please feel free to put them in chat.
I'm going to set about trying to solve this puzzle, so Arvi, I'm going to ask you a question and then go do that,
because this is really hard on my brain.
Would you mind, I know,
would you mind retelling the story of where Baba is you came from and how you took it from
prototype to full-fledged indie game?
That's a very nice big question. Gives plenty of time for the puzzles.
So...
I was at the Nordic Game Jam, which is one of these events where people make games in
a time limit following a loose theme.
Game jams are kind of popular nowadays.
I guess most people are, maybe at least to some extent, aware of the concept.
But anyway, the Nordic Game Jam is one of my favorites.
It's a very cozy, nice jam held in Copenhagen every year.
And I was there in 2017.
I was actually going there to...
meet my friends, because I have a lot of friends in Copenhagen and I had existing projects
that I wanted to work on, so I was actually kind of sneakily going to the event with this
mindset that, okay, I don't mind if I don't make a game for the jam, I'm here for the
like social element of it.
But then the theme of the game jam was released, or revealed, it's a very loose jam, like
you are not this.
supposed to be super strict about following the theme, you are free to interpret it however you
want, and the theme was not there, which kind of... I just pondered about it. Congratulations,
nice work on the level. Thank you. So I thought about the theme and for some reason I don't...
no idea why, I latched onto the first part, the not word, and started thinking how in logic and
I guess programming, you can say, have a like concept, something like push, and you can inverse
or reverse its meaning by saying not push. So not has this kind of reversal meaning in some contexts.
And the...
I had played some really good puzzle games over the past couple of years.
For example, Steve and Sausage Roll and Snake Bird,
two extremely difficult but very satisfying, very enjoyable puzzle games I had liked a lot.
And Raid, several years earlier.
All those games had kind of filled me with a desire to make a puzzle game.
But I had always run into some design problems.
There were some things I couldn't kind of get working when I tried to make my own puzzle games.
And the kind of inspiration I had gathered over years from these puzzle games
wobbled in my head as I thought about this not-there theme.
And eventually they just kind of combined together into this mental image
of like a block pushing game, where there would be a pool of lava,
some blocks of ice, and the ice...
Congratulations!
The ice would be meltable.
in the lava, obviously, because lava is hot, ice is meltable.
But then you would be, as a player, able to say
ice is not melt.
And that's kind of the, as far as I can remember,
that's kind of the beginning of the idea.
And, uh, yeah, I wasn't super certain about the idea at first.
It sounded like, uh, it would be maybe a bit dull
or it would be difficult to figure out puzzles for that kind of a concept.
And also I wasn't really sure at first what kind of a game it would be.
But I started working on it, because one of the nice things about Game Jams is that I can just...
I just decided, okay, I'll do something. If it doesn't work, I can scrap it. I don't have to think about it anymore.
I can go cry in a corner. If it works, I can be happy and get friends.
And so I just started prototyping it, and it turned out to be working pretty well.
And other people also, they kind of came to look over my shoulder and said that, hey, that looks super cool.
are pretty cool at least.
And that encouraged me.
And I ended up winning the Game Jam,
like being voted the best game of the Game Jam.
And that's combined with that encouragement
from my colleagues convinced me
that I should make a full game out of it.
And then two years later,
things happened and the game was released.
Yeah, I'd say some things happened for sure.
I mean, you won those awards, the game came out,
it seemed to do quite well.
Something we didn't mention at the top of the show, you are nominated this year for two
Game Developers Choice Awards at GDC. I think it's Best Design and maybe Best Debut,
or Most Innovation, I think. I think it's Innovation and Design, yeah. Yeah, Innovation
and Design, quite right. And those are really incredible awards to be up for, and I think Baba,
as you, is eminently deserving of that. When you talk about... No worries. When you talk about
the process of implementing that basic idea during the jam and seeing that it worked pretty well,
I feel like you might be glossing over a lot there. I really want to know,
like, how did it work at first? Because this, the entire idea, this negation of,
well, the approach to the design, like, I've never seen anything like this in a commercial game
that I can recall, and I would guess that it must have been real tricky to implement.
Uh, hmm. Well, first of all, the whole
not there, like the not word kind of disappeared in development because pretty quickly when I
started working on the prototype I realized that it's actually thematically way cooler
if the lava is not hot by default and the ice is not meltable by default like if nothing has
inherent abilities but instead everything is stated by the rules. It felt just like a way
cooler thing in my head.
But also it kind of invalidated the whole not thing.
Why say ice is not melt if the ice isn't melt by default anyway?
So that's kind of one of the first things that happened when I started working on the game.
But to be honest, because especially at Game Jams,
you don't really worry about implementing things well.
You can just hack things in.
The only thing you need to care about is that you have something that at least seems to work
after the 48 or 72 hours or however long the game jam takes or lasts.
So with BaBaIsYou I kind of...
I had fairly recently, only about a year ago, I had learned the Lua scripting language
and I fairly quickly figured out a pretty simple syntax that would let me just kind of...
read the rules on the screen, put all those rules on a list, or actually on a couple of different lists,
and then let me, on runtime, ask the game, like, hey, does this rule exist, or is something you?
If something is you, please return all the things that are you, and then I can do something for all those things that are you.
So the kind of basic system of the game is built very largely around this,
kind of asking these questions of, hey, game.
Please tell me everyone who fulfills this requirement.
Especially later on when I added this kind of conditional words,
spoiler alert,
eventually there will be conditionals that can be added to the rules.
So especially when those were added,
it became even more important to have these kind of...
Please return me all the things that are you,
while also taking into account all these kind of conditionals or special...
cases that might appear and those special cases are where the development became like really tricky.
I would say that the basic rule system is actually fairly simple but there are some
certain areas where the game even now is not working at all perfectly and when I release
the level editor I will probably spend endless hours pulling my hair out trying to make some
kind of a passable compromise between
things working and me dying of old age.
That actually brings us to a good question from chat,
which is, oh, I have a question.
What's the most challenging thing you've encountered
when developing the level editor?
That comes from writer of blocks.
Yeah, thanks for the question.
I'd say that so far,
one thing that we haven't implemented fully yet,
and I won't be responsible for large parts of the core,
most of the code, because I can't do networking stuff,
but the...
the level editor is going to have a level sharing functionality,
you will be able to share levels with others.
And I'm pretty sure that there will be some things related to that
that will turn out to be surprisingly tricky,
like how to handle which levels to show first and so on.
But that's not my concern, kind of,
so I guess I should say about the things I myself implemented.
And from those, I'd say that the...
When I made the level editor for the game originally, the one that I used personally to kind of make the game,
I had only a fairly limited amount of things I could put in a level.
Like, in this level you can see there's Algae, Algae, Algae, how do you pronounce it? I don't know.
There's Baba, sorry?
Algae.
Algae, thank you.
So there's some tiles, there's some brickwork, there's some walls, a flag, blah blah.
There were a limited amount of those, a limited amount of words, so I could just do a huge
list of everything and when you press tab in the editor it just shows you almost everything
and you can pick from there and do some adjustments if needed.
But for the final editor there will be too many things to really show just as a single
list it would be really.
confusing to use if the player had to kind of browse a huge list every time they want to add something.
Do you want a hint?
Yeah, take it, Brian.
Hmm, so you beat a level when something that is you touches something that is win.
Yes.
So... Yes.
I will go with that.
Hehehehe, okay.
Congratulations!
So, for the final version of the editor, I had to implement a system where you kind of have a palette or a selection of objects you can pick from to add to the level.
And then you can add and remove objects from that list.
So you have kind of like a level-specific palette of objects, and then you have the full list.
have to be able to interact with those and there has to be like a search functionality and tag functionality
so you can easily find the things you want to find.
And implementing that system has been
not as terrible as I assumed it could be,
but I've been streaming Developing Baba Is You pretty frequently this year
and during the last stream I definitely felt pretty exhausted
at the end of the stream when I kind of...
managed to optimize a system for finding certain objects and displaying their icons in the editor,
so it's a fairly complicated thing. It's also kind of probably pretty uninteresting sounding
because it's such a kind of like a technical thing, but to answer honestly that would be my answer.
I think you should be very technical and detailed. Like, most people watching this are going to be game developers themselves.
Or just type-writing fans of the game. We got some folks like Kyron Gliff who dropped in the chat saying,
Hey, I'm poorly, and Nick's Mad Science thinks it's cool to see Bala getting a GDC shoutout.
Man, Nick, you got that backwards. It's cool that he came on to our stream.
That's right.
It's very kind of you to invite me, as mentioned.
Super nice to...
be able to see people play the game and say words about it as well.
Alex, I'm going to toss the question ball to you.
Oh, yeah, we've covered a couple of things I wanted to dig into deeper.
Let's just pick one at random.
Tell me a bit about
puzzle game design, because, you know, I've been keeping track of your work.
Folks who don't know, you've made, I think, dozens of games, right?
They're on your website. This is sort of.
the one that has gotten a lot of attention recently, but you're working on some other
stuff as well.
And I think your last project and your next project are sort of a more Metroidvania type
game.
So I'm so curious, what do you appreciate about puzzle game design and what is challenging
about it that you are dealing with right now?
Because I imagine laying out these levels must be brain breaking.
Well, for the things you said earlier...
I think I counted all the games I've made, if we also count like very small jam games,
and I think there was like 45 or so that I've made over the past 12 years, I think.
Yeah.
But yeah, most of them are just like, I made this in one hour because I was young and decided
that making a game in one hour is fun.
And yeah, the game that I'm working on currently is a sequel to my first commercial title, and yeah, it's a Metroidvania.
I kind of promised people that I would make a sequel, and it's fun to make a Metroidvania,
even though I've been more in the puzzle world lately.
But yeah, for puzzle games, I think the thing that I like most in puzzle games and puzzle game design
is that when I make games, I usually strive for...
making something surprising or amazing.
I haven't really found the good words in English,
but the idea is that, to best express what I mean,
is that for me, it's a lot of fun if I see someone play my game
and the game does something that catches them by surprise
in a good way so that they maybe burst out laughing in surprise.
Like, whoa, the game did this kind of a thing? What?
That kind of...
experience is what I live for when making games.
Metroidvanias are nice for that because they can have secrets and boss fights and that
kind of thing, but I think puzzle games are even more suited for that because they can
have like meta puzzles, they can have things where some simple idea is iterated in some
way that the player doesn't expect at all.
And in Ba Ba Is You I kind of try to make every level, or as many levels as possible,
do something new so that I would kind of maximize the amount of these kinds of surprising moments, surprising twists.
That is something that I learned from the Stephen Sausage Roll and the Snake Bird games.
Those games both kind of do a really good job at requiring you to do something at least slightly unique.
in every level and that is something I kind of strove for and that I find
enjoying enjoyable when I play puzzle games myself and I'm actually kind of
trying to always trying to find more puzzle games that follow a similar
system. This actually just to pause for a moment and talk about the game being
played here. So it's actually a very good kind of non-tutorial moment that I
should have maybe tutorialized better which is that there are these
two new words, open and shut.
And what those words do literally, spoiler alert,
is that if something is shut,
if it touches something that is open,
they destroy each other.
And saying like, if something is open,
if a door is open and it touches a key that is shut,
they destroy each other.
But obviously, for a very obvious reason,
if the game says door is shut,
people assume that the door is like a solid object,
that you cannot move through it.
But that is not actually true.
And the reason why breaking the rule, door is shut, didn't let you pass through the door is because there is also a door is stop at the top.
And that level causes a lot of trouble.
And I feel that it's kind of a, at least to some extent, it's a failure from my kind of tutorializing.
I just kind of wanted to point it out.
That's interesting because from a subconscious perspective, my brain was already tracking
towards if I change what the door is, I can get through the door.
Sorry, Alex, I jumped on you there.
No, not at all.
And that's it's interesting to hear you describe that problem, because I did sense it as I
ran through it, because I got confused why killing doors stopped didn't do anything.
But then it just sort of thankfully my brain just subverted or moved to the next problem
solving technique, which, you know, like I was testing a hypothesis, right?
Like this game is very hypothesis. If I try this, then this will happen.
and thankfully that just let me try something different. Nope, wall is defeat. God damn it.
Yeah, someone pointed, like a player pointed out at some point that I should have made the word
open should be unlock and shut should be locked and I agree. It would be maybe a bit more
informative or like more intuitive.
There's actually a pretty interesting story, I'm getting sidetracked, but there's the word
DEFEAT, and in the original game jam version of the game, the word was actually KILLED.
But because the game is so cutesy, and I also kinda, despite developing a Metroidvania,
I generally prefer having, like, non-violence in my games.
I try to find and figure out solutions that are less violent if possible.
So I felt kill was a very violent word, especially, like, if you see, here's Baba.
Baba is killed. That's brutal.
And I spent, in the end, I think like a half a year
trying to figure out what to change the word kill to.
And because the idea is that kill only destroys something that is you.
It doesn't harm anything else but you.
So the idea is that it's harmful to living things, so to say.
And kill conveys that idea really well.
And I think, like, after trying many ideas and getting suggestions from people,
defeat was the, like, next best answer.
There was, like, gone and poof and...
I don't remember the others, but there were several suggestions we went through.
It was an interesting problem.
I'm gonna ask a question based on what's going on right here.
Folks in chat, we are going to get to your questions.
Thank you for hanging out and chatting already.
I do want to give you guys...
I'm faced with a decision right now to either keep clearing out the levels in here,
and I...
Or I have the decision to move on to the next area
Which is loading going back up to the map. I don't know why it loaded this for some reason
I don't know why that oh because I'm using the wrong controller
Or I missed so
What I would like to know is what was your mindset behind creating these scenarios where players
could either finish an area and then move on versus like giving them the opportunity to
move here. I'm going to go ahead and move on to the next area just so we have some variety on
the stream and I'm curious what your thought process was behind that as a game designer.
Before you go I would suggest playing one more level in the previous area.
That's what I was worried about because I was worried that if I skip something I wouldn't learn.
If you play level 9, this explains a thing that could be helpful.
But if that's the case, why did you let me do that?
Why would you let me advance here without learning something useful here?
I guess in this specific case it's an oversight from my part.
But the reason...
The kind of...
If we discount this specific situation where something that would be useful
is maybe not taught by the game if you skip these levels...
I wanted to make it so that you always have as many options as possible for kind of progressing
because in a puzzle game it's very easy to get mentally stuck.
And kind of if you only have one option for a puzzle if you get stuck in that puzzle it might
be that you kind of you won't get anywhere because you are stuck trying a single idea.
over and over and not kind of refreshing your mind. You need to take a break to kind of refresh
your concept on what you are doing and the offering the players multiple options to pick from
I feel is nicer because if they get stuck in one puzzle they still can do something in the game.
They don't have to close the game and wait until they get the insight. They can go to other level
which might be easier for them.
Another reason is that in Baba Is You I felt that it would be best if the levels were grouped
by the words used in them instead of by, like, purely by difficulty.
Obviously there needs to be, like, a difficulty curve, but especially because some of the
specific words are very... odd, so to say.
Like, very complex, very specific.
I felt that it would be nicer if the player doesn't have to learn so many words at once,
but instead different areas would have different words.
And if I group the levels using that criteria, there will inevitably be levels that are easier
in one area than there were some levels in the earlier areas.
Like if I introduce a new word entirely, a new concept.
I need to make an easy level that tutorializes that concept.
And so I thought it would be odd if the player kind of expects...
an even difficulty curve and then gets into a new area and they're like, hey, this is a super easy level.
So I decided to go with the concept that every area kind of resets the difficulty curve at least a little bit, like pushes it back.
So in every area you can start from the easy levels, you can beat the easy levels and move on,
but if you want you can keep going for the harder levels that like really explore the limits of the words introduced in those worlds.
And this is partially also related to how, because I knew that the game would be possibly pretty difficult.
It's very hard to estimate as a game developer how difficult a game is by yourself,
but I assumed that the game would be pretty difficult.
But I knew that there would be people who like to play these kinds of games.
or them there that would like to see like BABA in action, even if they don't enjoy playing super hard puzzle games.
I wanted to have a system where they, or actually a tester suggested having a system for kind of opting out
once you have seen enough, so that people who want to see the system but don't want to get super hardcore on it,
they can play the game.
they get offered some, like, hey, if you beat this level, you can say that you beat the game
and you can move on, you don't have to get stressed and annoyed about the difficulty.
So, the game is now structured so that you only need to beat, I think, about 30 levels
to get access to the final level.
There's still more to do, there are plenty more levels after that,
but you can still, like, you can complete the game technically at a very early stage,
and that's also related to this kind of map structuring.
Nice. I'm gonna go ahead and grab a good question here from chat because there have been so many.
Ryder Blox wants to know what inspired the cutesy design of the game? They love Baba's design.
So how did you come up with this unique aesthetic? Yeah, so at the Game Jam you have, or I had,
only 48 hours to make everything. So my go-to method has been to use the default Windows Palette,
like the old.
Windows 98 Palette with fully saturated everything.
I actually kind of like that palette nowadays because I've used it so many times and I've been corrupted by it.
And in Baba is You everything was static.
They were just like moving pictures on the screen.
And when I started working on the full game, I spent some time worrying that
maybe I should make the graphical style very kind of
appealing to the masses, so to say, to kind of put it in a kind of a condescending way.
I wondered if I should go for 3D art. If I went for 3D art, I would have to learn a new tool,
because the tool I used to make Baba Is You cannot do 3D art. So I was kind of conflicted
about this kind of, maybe I should spend the extra effort to make the game really appealing,
and then spend more time having to learn the tools to make it.
get it finished or maybe I should go with a style that I can already do and accept that the game will
probably be a bit less interesting looking or a lot less interesting looking. And the final decision
for this specific style came from two sources. First was that I had played the game Crayon Physics
Deluxe by Petri Purho in 2008. It won the Sumas McNally Grand Prize in 2008.
And it had a really nice, this like, crayony style where things had this kind of slight animation, slight wobble all the time.
And as a young game developer, I actually made clones of that game.
Petri likes to mention it from time to time when we meet.
But I got really attached to this kind of wobbly style, and I also used it in some non-clone ideas later on that kind of a similar...
Idea where I draw every animation frame several times to get this kind of slight wobble to everything
So I already knew that that that style works and the other inspiration came from a fellow developer
Jason Boyer who has actually just recently released the Kickstarter for their new game like a mecha dating game, right?
I'm so sorry. I don't remember the exact right now. Don't feel bad about it. Yeah
They made a stream playing Baba Is You with their friends pretty quickly after I released the original Game Jam version on itch.io.
The game is actually still available for freeware on itch.io if you want to see the very original version of it.
And for the stream they made, or video, they made a piece of fanart where they interpreted Baba as a cute, bipedal goat person.
In the original sprites...
I had intended Baba to be a robot.
They had like a tiny antennae,
and they were like bipedal robots,
but Jason interpreted those antennae as horns.
And to be honest, I really liked that design.
A robot is kind of clinical, often, not always,
but often kind of boring.
It's a very easy, this kind of non-personal,
abstract main character option for hacks like me
who don't know how to do interesting looking robots.
So after seeing Jason's fan art and kind of pondering where I should go with the visual style,
I realized that, okay, maybe actually if I use this wobbly style that I'm comfortable with using
and I know how it works, and if I do like a cutesy style, I think it would really work really well
with the game. Also because Baba Is You, like many people told me after the game jam that Baba Is You
contains in their eyes some kind of...
interesting philosophical concepts. You can consider the word you to be like the consciousness
and the consciousness moves through objects. Many different things can be conscious and they have
their own agency when they are conscious but they can be only conscious one at a time. This kind of
thing. And I thought it would be a kind of a funny juxtaposition if some people could see these kind
of deep themes or kind of morbid themes in Baba-Yazoo.
But at the same time, the game would have this very harmless visual style going on.
I love that.
Yeah, I had not thought about it at all, about how this game reflects the notion of consciousness
as transitory.
That's, ah, wow, that's good.
Yeah, there's a Buddhism going on, if you look into it.
You made a good video game.
There's a question here.
I have more questions, but there's another one here in chat that I want to get to.
It's a good follow up.
It's forgive me if I butcher this.
It's it's me.
Avinash asked.
They have a technical question.
They want to know, how did you learn to code games?
They know a little bit of Python and C++, but engines like Unity
seem very difficult to learn.
Yeah, this is a kind of a
embarrassing question in a way.
Not really, but.
Oh, do go on.
I was just wondering if I should ask if a hint is needed, but I guess not.
No, no, no, no.
We're not here to win. We're here to play.
Yeah, so Baba Is You was made mostly, or like the base engine, is a game creation tool,
kind of like Game Maker, but not exactly Game Maker, called Multimedia Fusion 2 by Clickteam.
It's a fairly old program. There are newer versions, but I use an older version because I'm old school.
And...
Multimedia Fusion and its predecessors were actually the kind of one of the first graphical
no coding experience needed game creation tools in the market.
The first version was released in 1994.
So it's a pretty old, old family of tools.
And they used to be very popular, but then programs such as Game Maker and Construct
kind of advanced so far that Multimedia Fusion and Clickteam Fusion, it's a follower.
have been a bit less... they're not as common nowadays that they used to be like 10 years ago or so.
And I was in primary school, a schoolmate asked me if I wanted to make games. I super wanted to
make games. I had played Super Mario World on my cousin's Super Nintendo and I really wanted to
make games. I had also drawn video games in kindergarten on paper. I wanted to make games.
So, Schoolmate introduced GameMaker to me. I think GameMaker was in version 4 or something at that point in those early times, like 2002 or something like that.
And we started making games, we made like a Space Innovator with Pac-Man in GameMaker, stuff like that.
But GameMaker has its own scripting language, the GML.
And because I was in primary school, I didn't understand English very well and I didn't have very much patience.
So learning a scripting language was way beyond me, apart from like simple copying code from examples that wasn't really satisfactory.
So eventually another schoolmate introduced the program called The Games Factory to me, which is basically the predecessor of Multimedia Fusion.
And that one didn't require any coding. There was no scripting at all. It was purely graphical.
And that was perfect for me, because even if I didn't understand what something meant,
I could trial and error my way through it. So that's how I started.
And there was actually a boom of pre-teen kids making their own games in the Games Factory,
in Finland specifically, in early... how do you say, in the early 2000s.
Right.
And I kind of...
Yeah, I followed that boom even though I didn't have my own website and I was too young to put my games online or even to finish anything.
And then in 2016, after using Multimedia Fusion for like 8 years happily, without knowing any programming, I tried to get into Unity, I tried to get into ActionScript, I tried to get into some other languages, but they always felt too intimidating.
A good friend of mine, Lukas Meller, who has taught me a lot of things about game development and programming,
told me that there's a plugin for Multimedia Fusion 2 that lets me use the Lua scripting language.
And they basically taught me, they made me tutorials for how to use Lua in general,
and also how to use Lua in Multimedia Fusion specifically.
And then, I guess the time was right, I was old enough.
At that point I kind of understood English a little bit, at the ripe age of like 23 or something, 24.
And, uh, congratulations, nice.
Thank you.
And, um, so I got really quickly into Lua, and one year passed, and I got the idea for Baba is You,
and, like, Lua has been very integral for the process.
So right now I just make games by using this.
engine from 2006 combined with Lua.
Nice, it's classics. Real quick, I'm just curious
what is not having English as your first language like when you're trying to
be a successful international game developer? I mean that's a specific
example of how you sort of found it difficult to use the tools until
you were at a higher proficiency with the language, but in any other way, like
has it been...
Has it been challenging or in any way interesting to try and overcome those barriers?
Not really, because in Finland most kids of my generation learned English really quickly
because it was the time of MSN Messenger and internet forums and so on. So a lot of kids,
even those who were not interested in making games or even playing games,
learned English at a very young age. Also Finland doesn't have the kind of
dubbing as much. We use more subtitles on TV so many kids learn English by watching movies,
a subtitle and so on. So it was never really a problem. I've looked at some of my earliest
posts on some internet forums from like from like 2006 and yeah there they are.
they are filled with XD and typos and some interesting...
There's actually a very nice anecdote where
using English was really cool, obviously, even before I could understand English, but like, just like
when you don't speak English, it's always slightly cooler to use a different language than your own.
And I tried to make like a...
game where you're a soldier fighting against aliens, and you go into missions to kind of...
just to kill aliens, basically.
And the first mission was such that you are in a like a anti-air artillery bunker and you need to eradicate all the aliens there.
And I had tried to write that like mission explanation without knowing much English.
And the final sentence that came into the game was,
wash the fly bunker for aliens. And it wasn't really...
I mean, I didn't know.
I got I got some words like some of the grammar makes sense. So it wasn't total failure, but it didn't really convey the
correct idea
Right on. Yeah. I mean I I only ask because I specifically
I have never even though I probably should have heard this more often
I have never heard a game designer mention English language proficiency as part of one
of the hurdles to adopting a new programming language or learning the more complex nature
of a language.
So that's just something I never really thought about at all, is sort of another aspect of
privilege that comes with that language, is so many of them are written by default in
English.
Yeah, it's definitely like, definitely when I was in primary school, it kind of slowed
the process.
and it might be that if I had understood English natively I would have been able to get into
actual programming languages instead of game creation tools but who can say what would have
happened so it's it well I didn't really consider it a huge problem and it's actually a huge perk
that English words look cooler because it's very way easier to give like fantasy names to things
like there's the Super Nintendo game F-Zero where one of the
ships or the racing things is called wild goose or wild geese or something like that.
And as a kid I didn't understand what a goose is and I was like oh this is some cool sci-fi name.
It's like a super monster and then when I realized oh it's a bird it was like if I would have called
it uh villihanhi in Finnish it would have been...
That must have made Top Gun really weird.
Yeah, it's a scary bird. I mean, I live across the street from a bird habitat and geese will
mess you up. I mean, wild goose is not... isn't intimidating. Anyway.
I didn't know that then. I think everyone has learned about geese over the past year.
Right, yeah. Nix Mad Science in chat calls out Untitled Goose Game as the new harbinger of the
goose future.
Yeah, there's more, actually there's maybe not, there's one small question in chat maybe we can
just clear up from Nixman Science, they just wanted to check in and verify, when we were
talking about Lua and Fusion interacting, do the Lua fuels, pardon me, do the Lua files,
does Lua kind of dictate what happens in-engine or is there any greater
tie there between the two tools? That's a very interesting and possibly
difficult question to answer. Yeah. Well...
But in Babaisju specifically, multimedia fusion mostly handles anything that is kind of graphical
in some way and also some things that are just more intuitive for me to make using multimedia
fusion syntax. For example, if I need to attach an object to another object for whatever reason,
there are some situations. For example, if there's a button and the button needs to have
text that is kind of stuck in the button, that is easier for me to do using MultimediaFusion
than Lua because MultimediaFusion handles things like destroying objects and creating
new objects. But for the most part, the actual rule changing logic is in Lua. And the plugin
that allows me to use Lua functionality in MultimediaFusion.
has some really nice tools. For example, because Multimedia Fusion is an object-based language
and all the things you see on the screen are just objects, that kind of animations and things
happening to them, so the plugin allows me to kind of add objects from Multimedia Fusion to Lua, so
they kind of become entities in the Lua, so I can just refer to them and change their values
directly in Lua instead of having to do some kind of like a here so
Lua function that calls Multimedia Fusion to do something to the object and return something back.
And instead I can just do all of that directly in Lua and it's been extremely helpful,
except for the part where the plugin, sorry, where the plugin's developer stopped working on it at
one point and there's a memory leak related to that specific functionality. So if you play
the multimedia fusion version of the game for long enough, it will crash.
But apart from that, it was very powerful and useful.
Yeah. Thanks for thanks for getting into that.
I know it can be tricky sometimes to explain in a cogent way
the weird ways that tech tools and, you know, programming languages
have all kind of hinged together.
But that's that's kind of what we're about here. So I appreciate it.
Uh, yeah, no, this is, uh, let's, I kind of want to, as we get to the end of our hour here, and
please, we got about 15 more minutes left, so if you do have any burning questions, get them out now.
Um, I kind of want to know how you're feeling now that the game's out and released. I mean,
you're working on meaningful updates and a new project, uh, and you're up for a new slate of
awards, uh, next month. Um, how are you feeling? Like, how has this game changed your career as a
game developer, and what's different now, uh, the Baba is you is out and in the world?
I get more emails. After the release of Baba is You, I recently counted and I've like
personally answered to well over 1300 emails on my own. Don't do that.
No. It's not a good idea to answer that many emails. You should preserve yourself from that.
But um...
Yeah, Baba's success has definitely enabled me to be more relaxed about my future things.
I can be in a situation where I can plan my life so that I can actually kind of have working
hours.
I can try to make it so that I get enough exercise and I can like, I just have more
ability to plan.
what to do with my life so that I live a healthy life instead of having to worry as much about like
everything burning down on me, like ending up bankrupt or something. It kind of
it kind of simultaneously gives me that kind of peace of mind but partially related to those emails.
It does also make everything more stressful because it also means that there are more eyes on what I do.
It hasn't... that part of it hasn't really manifested in the way it could have.
Like I could imagine there being some really awkward situations and there might be in the future,
like if someone gets really invested in Baba and expects me to do something and gets angry
when I don't do that and that kind of stuff. I'm very neurotic so I'm very good at imagining.
those kinds of things happening, but that kind of stuff hasn't really happened, but it's still like the idea that okay
Those are now more of a possibility than they would have been
earlier is
sometimes
sometimes stressful
and
Yeah, I guess I guess I could list things like that I guess the like baseline is that things are
more stressful in some ways, but they're also more peaceful in like economical,
what do I spend my time on ways. Yeah, I mean I'm generally glad to hear that. It sounds
like the price of success. Are you still contributing to Noita at all? I know you
were working on that for a little while. Yeah, actually like a spoiler alert,
Baba is You was made entirely on my free time. My day job was Noita for the past seven years.
I'm now, I'm currently not working on Noita anymore.
After seven years, it was kind of, the game came out on early access.
Early access and the scene has been doing really, like,
people have been seeming to like the game a lot and so on, so it was kind of,
it was time to look for, look for other, like,
set my sights in the future as they say. I'm sorry you can't see my hand waving over here but
like imagine artistic hand waves but yeah Noita was kind of has been a big part of my past
several years. Nice. Yeah and Noita is also in GDCA awards this year so that's that's also a thing
it's nice that people have kind of received it so so very kindly.
Yeah, no, absolutely. I think that sort of points to a through line of these two games, right?
I mean, I think both were also in the IGF as well. I mean, both have sort of gotten attention
for being sort of innovative and rule-breaking and sort of getting into like the real...
Well, they've both gotten attention for a lot of good reasons. And I'm so curious to know,
like, they both sort of point to a theory of game design that you spoke to earlier,
how you love games that...
foster opportunities for players to go,
oh, like aha moments, right?
Where you just realize what you're supposed to do,
where you discover something you didn't know worked.
So much of Noida is about, like,
figuring out how systems work together
and discovering new and interesting ways to use them.
I'm just curious, what, do you agree with that?
And if so, like, what is it about
the school of game design and game, you know,
that really, you know, motivates you and inspires you?
Why do you think?
I think it's.
From my personal perspective, I maybe wouldn't do an entirely similar comparison,
because from my point of view, in Noita, the kind of surprise of how things work is very closely related to synergy in games,
which is a very big old-school roguelike thing.
The thing where surprising things have been taken into account by the developers,
and you can do things that you...
that might not work in all games because they haven't been coded to take those into account,
but they still work in Noita.
Whereas in Baba Is You, it's less the kind of emergent, dynamic world part of it,
and more the kind of developer intentionally building hard-
not hard-coded, but like building handcrafted tricks to trick you and surprise you.
words and also with Noita.
All the, basically all the cool things you have seen of Noita, all the synergy and dynamic things are more to the credit of the amazing programmers Olli and Petri in the team who kind of made those things a reality.
I'd be more in the kind of design and graphics department of things.
Because I know that that kind of synergy, the fact that...
things that usually in games you don't expect to work do work and have interactions together
is something that I would say has been a very big driving force behind Noita specifically.
Yeah no fair enough that's a great point it is so much about Bob as you is about that feeling of
you know like dealing directly with the mind of the puzzle designer and trying to figure out
what they want you to do.
Again, we have about five minutes left, so if you have any questions, then get them in.
I think she's an associate publisher as well.
She's a big deal.
She's an associate publisher.
I should use her right title.
Yeah.
She had a question.
Her question was literally, how level design is possible?
And my joke to her was that clearly you just wrote down
level design and possible and stuck an is between them.
And that's how level design happened.
What was your mindset for making Boba's U-Levels?
I mean, I guess, like, this is...
We're at an interesting level right now, so...
I guess you can explain some of your thoughts to us using this level?
I don't know, maybe?
I don't know if that's a good one.
It was basically like...
Pikachu came to me in my dreams and told me
that you need to make these levels.
And I just followed the holy word of Pikachu.
That's fair, that's fair.
That'd be good.
So, the way I kind of used to explain...
Sorry for cutting you off.
No, no, no, no, go for it.
Okay, okay.
So for me, the way I've explained
Babai's use of level design has been using the term
reverse engineering and completely misusing the term,
but here we go anyway.
So the way I approach level design,
or I would like to say I approach level design this way,
obviously, anytime a game developer says that
I did this to make the game, they are lying
because they are combining many things,
both consciously and unconsciously, but.
At least when it comes to what I consciously know that I tried to do in Baba Is You
I have these different words and different mechanics
There's the block pushing part, the different movement systems and actually implementing the movement system was one of those like extremely difficult things that are still
Broken in many ways that you hopefully don't notice
And I have these different rules that could interact with each other
so when I start at a new level or when I kind of
made mental notes about level ideas, I usually try to think of those systems and concepts and words
and combine them in my mind, just kind of trying to figure out combinations of words or combinations
of words and mechanics that I hadn't considered before. Like, what would happen if I have this
and this thing co-existing at the same time? Is there something cool that could happen,
like something that looks cool or feels cool or is surprising in some way?
And for a very long time it was very easy to come up with those surprises.
Like I could get a lot of ideas of kind of, oh that would be pretty surprising, all right.
And so I kind of took one of those ideas, those that felt especially cool,
or sometimes those that didn't feel especially cool,
and those didn't make us good levels and I canned them eventually.
That's something that felt like it could have potential to make an interesting...
interaction and then I made a level where I tried to build a structure that forces the player to use
that specific interaction to solve it so that if I think the interaction looks or feels cool
the player has to see the cool thing to solve the level. So in this particular level this was
actually added later after the release because I felt the
weight functionality that you can press a button where things that are move move but Baba doesn't move
needed some tutorialization. I completely botched the word because this doesn't work really well as
a tutorial but that's the kind of intention behind this. So here my mindset was that okay
you can press A to wait and let things that move move but make like you not move for one turn.
I would like to make a level where you're forced to
to use the wait button to solve the level. And then I just like organically put walls down.
It was very hard to make paper notes for Baba Is You because it was so much easier to kind of doodle
things in the actual editor and see how things work. So in this case I just doodled the level.
I think I took a couple of tries, but eventually I ended up with this structure. Sometimes
afterwards I felt that the...
solution was too obvious and added some like extra elements to kind of obfuscate the solution,
but that was sometimes also a bad idea because it could like drive the player's attention away from the cool twist.
But then,
yeah, that's kind of the basic process.
I guess this level is not the best example because here the cool interaction is a very simple one. It's like press one button.
I won't tell you when you need to press that button to solve the level, but...
That's what you need to do at one point of the level to solve it.
I guess a better example would be that there's later on the word shift that makes things work as conveyor belts.
Like belt is shift and if you move on a belt, the belt pushes you along.
And I realized that if you put two belts on top of each other, obviously they push each other at the same time.
So they just become like this perpetual mobile that just moves on.
forever, like two conveyor belts pushing each other.
And I made a level around that, because it was a cool sounding interaction
between the same work, but still kind of two things doing some something.
This level is instantly one of my favorites, because I failed and found the salute.
I failed and it showed me a way forward.
Yeah, that's nice.
That's what I'm working on right now.
Man, I could play this game all day.
We could yak it up all day.
Um, uh, but, uh, I do not quite, we do not quite have the time to do that.
Um, oh man, I'm so close, I'm so close, I need to make Skull Bolt, I think.
Um, maybe I'm wrong.
But, anyway, I just have the need to wrap things up.
Uh, if you enjoy BaBa's U and you want to see it, uh, at the Game Developers' Choice Awards ceremony,
you can either attend the ceremony live at GDC, which is coming up next month.
Jeez, we're only a month away.
Oh, geez. Oh, geez.
Um...
Uh... and, um...
If you are not coming to GDC, we'll miss you,
but you can watch the ceremony on March 18th
here on the GDC Twitch channel.
Just click that follow button.
And if you do that, you'll get a notification
when we go live. We'll also have other great interviews
coming up with some of the other nominees.
We've got all year round we are doing interviews of interesting game developers, because GDC
is about learning about how games get made, how games get sold, how developers make games,
what their lives are like making games, it's all those things, it's more, and we try to
embody that here on the channel by talking to the people who make games, and playing
them, and showing you sometimes how frustrating it can be.
But sometimes it's great!
Arvi, thank you so much for joining us and I hope you have a wonderful day.
If people have questions for you at BabaSU, where should they ask them?
I actually just opened the stream, so I will be in the chat if some people want to ask questions directly.
But otherwise, you can send me questions on Twitter.
You can say at BabaSU under Dash on Twitter.
I think that's maybe the easiest way to...
get questions to me. I usually answer, at least I answer easy, nice questions very quickly.
If there are difficult questions, then I might hesitate, but thank you very much for having me.
It was very nice to talk about Baba Is You and, yeah, be a disembodied voice, as mentioned earlier.
I really like sometimes being a disembodied voice. It feels like I'm a ghost.
You're good at it. You sell it.
Thank you. You too.
Thank you all so much for watching.
Have a good day everyone. Bye.