Hello and welcome.
My name is Mikkel.
I'm a graphics programmer.
This is Mikkel who will do the second half of the presentation.
Mikkel is a very technical artist, as you'll see.
We both work at a company called Playdead that once upon a time did a game called Limbo.
And neither of us worked on Limbo, but we have worked on the follow-up title, Inside,
that just shipped in June on Xbox, in July on PC, and will ship next week on PlayStation 4.
And that's what we're going to be talking about.
More specifically, we'll be talking about the rendering of Inside.
And we sort of picked some topics that we thought would be relevant to other games,
and then we thought that...
that you guys could steal and implement in your own games the same as we've stolen tons of stuff from other presentations.
So, I'll show briefly a trailer so we sort of know what the game that we'll be talking about looks like.
Right, so now that the game's actually out,
just out of my personal curiosity,
how many did actually play the game?
Excellent, it's like half of my fan base.
All right.
So as you can see, and as many of you have already experienced,
it's a 2 and 1 half D game.
It's a puzzle platformer, and it's
made with a fixed perspective.
So the camera is always fixed.
This means that our artists, when they create the art,
they can make sure that they know
that when the game is shown on a gamer's screen,
it will look exactly like it looks on their screen.
that sort of means that they can go and tweak every pixel for perfection
and they can sort of rely on really subtle details being the same
on the monitor when the game is played.
This sort of in turn means that we can't have too many distracting artifacts
because we have these very subtle details that need to remain on screen.
So that means we can't have sort of banding and flickering and aliasing
and that sort of thing.
So that's something this talk will return to a couple times.
From a technical point of view, just to get that out of the
way, we shipped at 60 FPS at 1080p on all targets.
And we are using the Unity engine.
We have a source license for that, so we made some
modifications for that.
uh... from a rendering point of view I'll be using a light pre-pass
rendering which looks something like this so we have
our first pass over the entire scene which is a base pass
that outputs depth and normals
we then have a light pass that goes through all lights and
samples those depth and normals and then outputs
the lighting. We then have a final pass
that
that applies the materials, samples the lighting,
then a translucency pass, and sort of a post-effects pass
to wrap the whole thing up.
So one thing that turned out to be important rather early on
was fog to sort of create the atmosphere
and the mood of the game.
So initially, actually, quite a lot of scenes
were literally just geometry and this depth fog.
which, sort of in line with Limbo, relied a lot on silhouettes to create the mood.
So to kind of show you how much mileage we get out of that, this is a scene without any
fog and then literally just adding a linear depth fog we get something like this, which
is already rather moody.
The only interesting bit we're doing here rendering wise is that we're capping the intensity of the fog to a maximum level so that really bright light sources will shine through.
Whereas if you're using exponential fog, of course you converge towards one and bright light sources will always shine through.
So, on top of that we have this sort of fake fog scattering, atmospheric scattering pass.
The reason why I'm being very unspecific about that is because it's really just a really
white glow, so we're blurring the entire screen and adding that back on top.
So this was something our artists did rather early on, and I think they used it for great
effect, but really rather easy to do.
So now that we're using glow to do this fake atmospheric scattering, what do we do about glow then?
Well, we have a second path that does these really narrow high-intensity glows.
So the way we do that is like many other games, that we write out a mask from emissive materials.
and then we sort of remap that mask to a HDR value
between one and seven, and we calculate glow from that.
So one thing that's obvious in hindsight,
but wasn't really while we did it,
was that of course when,
because the bloom sort of is an indication
that you have a high intensity pixel,
if you then don't render that pixel
with the high intensity, that looks odd and looks like.
you have nothing glowing that's giving off this massive glow.
So it was really important to actually write back the HDR values for it to look more natural.
So that means that we have a post effect pass that looks
something like this.
So we have a temple anti-aliasing pass first,
and then we have the two glow passes.
They're really separate, but interleaved
for performance reasons.
It's important that we have the temple anti-aliasing
before the HDR bloom, because if we have too much aliasing
with the high intensities that we use in the HDR glow,
leaving a little bit of aliasing
will make it flicker quite a lot.
We then have a combined post-effects pass that applies the glow and does this HDR result
we talked about before, some lens distortion, some color offset and color grading.
I'll talk a little bit more about that.
So the chromatic aberration like this lens, red, green, blue offsets.
Most of the time we do it like most other games where we just sample red, green and
blue separately with a little bit of radial offset.
But in situations like this underwater we use rather large offsets, which means that
we then get this sort of triple image effect that looks weird, whereas really what we wanted
was a rainbow-like effect.
So a trick to fix that is something we found in the demo scene, which is to use a red-green-blue
texture and then we do a radial blur and then in our samples of the radial blur we then
also sample through the red-green-blue texture to get the weights of each sample.
So that's the way we get coloring.
Of course the reason why that works is because we're using, or when sampling a texture we
get bilinear filtering.
uh... for free using that so that was uh...
a nice trick that we didn't come up with ourselves but uh...
completely so
so uh...
one another thing we do in the final post effects path is that we
uh... we want to make sure that we want to be able to adjust the brightness
and the way we do that is just as simple as possible we have
uh... sort of a photoshopped levels filter where we are able to adjust the
black level and white level
uh...
And the issue with that is that it's very easy to cut off the whites and get these burned out white areas.
So what we did was that we used what's called smooth minimum functions, smooth minimum, smooth maximum functions.
we use, we take the smooth minimum between the brightness adjustment curve and then one.
And that means that we get this sort of smooth falloff.
And that's code in the slides.
That's a ShaderTor implementation of that.
So this worked out really well for us and it was also really easy for the artists to tweak
because they just had one parameter which was how smooth should the kink between the two be.
All right, so I'll leave the post effects and get back
to the atmosphere that we were talking about before.
So the fog, we figured out rather early
that we needed more than just this global fog
to get the effects that we wanted.
So we did this local implementation
of this local fog, whereas this scene is an example.
The flashlight is rendered using this effect.
And how we did that is that for every pixel,
We sample all the way to the depth buffer,
and for each step, we sample the lighting function,
so the projected texture and the shadow map
and falloff of the texture.
And if you do this in sort of a naive way,
then you end up with something that's very slow.
In this example, 128 samples to make it look just okay,
and that takes more than roughly a frame and a half.
So if you try to make that faster just by reducing the number of samples, you get something
like this with quite a lot of artifacts and quite jarring artifacts as well, like these
really sharp lines.
So what you can do of course is that you can go and add a little bit of random into your
ray offsets.
So if you do that, then you get something that looks a lot better.
It's a lot slower though now because when you're actually sampling your...
uh... your textures than the texture cache is working a lot worse because now
you have random jittering
uh... in your samples but
but looks a lot better and and uh... the reason for this is the eye is actually quite
forgiving towards noise
so that's something we uh... we chose to look uh... into a bit further
So this is the same example but with three samples rather than 24.
And that's a lot of noise.
You can only almost make out the actual light and shadows in this.
So what we can do then is we can use a different pattern to do the jittering.
So rather than using white noise as we are here, we can use a biomatrix.
And already that looks a lot better.
The reason why that looks better is because
within a sort of small region, a biometrics
is guaranteed to have all values.
within that small region. And that's really good and the reason why it looks better. But
whereas the eye is very forgiving towards noise, it really isn't very forgiving towards
patterns. So we're looking for something that has this locality property at the same time as
not being a pattern. So what we ended up finding was what's called blue noise. So that's
essentially white noise that's high pass filtered. So...
Blue noise can be still uniformly distributed.
So that means that within a small region,
because it changes rather rapidly.
which changes rapidly and is still uniformly distributed.
That means we have this same property as the biometrics,
except, of course, we're not guaranteed
that every value is represented.
But it's very likely that most values are represented.
So we still get really good sampling
without it being a pattern.
So that worked really well.
And it meant that I think we reduced the number of samples
to half around somewhere around that.
Alright, so I'll leave the sampling for a bit and talk about how we actually go and distribute the samples.
So the way we set up these local fog volumes in the game is that we insert boxes and within those boxes we have fog.
So of course we don't need to sample outside.
those boxes because there's no fog.
We also don't need to sample outside the lights.
So what we do is that we do a geometric intersection between those boxes and the light frustum.
And that sort of boils down to just clipping the light frustum with each plane and then
patching up the holes.
So that means that we have this two-pass algorithm
where first we write out the front faces
of the clipped geometry,
and then afterwards we render the back faces
and then we sample the front face depth,
and then we have the front and back points
that we sample in between those two.
And that gives us sort of an optimal
range that we need to sample.
So this thing about using boxes is something we actually use for effects.
So in this scene above water, we're using two boxes, one above, one below.
And the one above is just sampling the light as is, whereas below we're using this animated
texture to fake caustics, which is working really well.
So something that you may have noticed,
that many others have noticed before us,
is that this is actually quite a smooth effect.
So sampling this per pixel is rather overkill.
So of course, we don't do that.
We sample it at half resolution instead.
We could probably get away with sampling it
at even lower resolutions, but this was sufficient.
So that means we then have this three-pass algorithm, so the two first passes are the
same as before, only at half resolution, so we write out the front face depth, we then
do the ray marching, and then we have this third pass that does upsampling from half
resolution to full resolution.
And while we do the upsampling pass, we also add a little bit of sort of a noisy blur into
the...
into the upsampling.
And the reason why we do this is to get rid of this half-resolution structure that we still have.
An additional reason why that's a good idea is because we, as you may remember, have a temporal anti-aliasing path.
And at least in our implementation of the temporal anti-gazing,
we're using what's called neighborhood clipping.
And the way that works is that for each pixel, it looks at the immediate neighborhood,
and any value that's within the immediate neighborhood is accepted.
So that means that it's very good at picking up per-pixel noise,
but it's not very good at picking up half-resolution noise.
So converting this half-resolution pattern into a full-resolution noise
was something that meant that it sort of played into the hand of timbral anti-aliasing a bit more,
which is a trick from DICE, I think.
All right, so this is the final result.
This is shown with six samples at half resolution.
This takes just less than a millisecond
if we were to sample every pixel on screen,
which of course we don't.
We only sample within the actual light cone.
Also, most of the time, we're actually using
three samples per pixel at half resolution.
We're not using six.
So that means that we are doing just less than one sample
per full resolution pixel to get this effect.
So the reason why we've been obsessing so much about
the number of samples, of course,
is that the effect is bandwidth bound.
Like it's bound by the number of samples we do.
So we also do all the other things that we can
to reduce the number of samples.
Oh, sorry, reduce the bandwidth.
So we lower the resolution of the projected texture,
we lower the resolution of the shadow maps.
Of course, we can get away with this
because it's, again, it's a rather low,
it's a rather smooth effect,
and we also, there's quite a bit of blurring involved.
So we can get away with that.
So the way that fits into the pipeline is like this.
So during the lighting pass we save off the shadow maps that we know we're going to need.
Then we do the two first passes of our algorithm rhythm.
Then we save off this ray-matched texture and then in the translucency pass we re-render
the clip geometry and sort that with other translucencies.
Okay, so I'll leave off for now and talk about a different thing that was very important
to get the look that we have in InSight, namely banding.
So this is a, well the effect is still, the artifact is banding, the effect is still there.
So this is a...
a scene from the game and I've sort of upped the brightness a bit so we can see what's going on
and if we look at this then you can see some of the things I've talked about in the beginning
we have these very smooth transitions and there are a lot of sort of details that you can almost notice
So this image actually has quite a lot of noise in it,
which hopefully you can't tell too much,
but if I remove that noise, then it looks like this.
Has quite a lot of artifacts,
it has these sort of sharp lines
all the way through the image.
It has these sort of rainbow-like effects, and also it animates, so it's really rather
distracting compared to, in relation to this art style where we want subtlety as well.
So of course what's going on is that we're rendering out into 8-bit color buffers.
And 8 bits per channel really isn't sufficient.
The human eye is able to perceive something
along the lines of 14 bits.
So what we could do, of course, was
to render to higher precision buffers.
But on some platforms, that would be slower, even too slow
to work.
And so something else we could do
is use the sRGB targets, render targets.
But again, on some platforms that has interesting
implementations to say the least.
So we chose to sort of explore dithering instead
to solve this issue.
So the way that works, this is an example
where the orange line is the signal
we are trying to represent.
And if we look at the value of 0.75 bits,
we then add one bit worth of entirely uniform noise.
That means that when quantizing, 75% of the time we end up quantizing to the value above the signal
and 25% of the time we end up quantizing to the value below.
And that's because the noise is entirely uniform.
So that means that on average we're actually getting exactly the signal that we started out with.
So just so you can tell this is not completely black magic,
this is how you would actually go about implementing it.
So this is a pixel shader and on output,
you just add a random number.
You can get this, like you can calculate this
or you can get this from a texture,
it doesn't really matter.
So I just wanted you to keep in mind that this is actually spectacularly easy to add and rather cheap as well.
So there's really no reason why any game should ship with Bandit, including indie games.
So, just to explore this a bit further,
so above, on top, we have, again,
the signal we're trying to represent,
then we have the rounded, quantized output
in the second row, and then we have the error
in the third row.
And if we then go and add noise to this,
it looks like this.
Now, already, that's really good.
It's a lot better than before.
But if we then go and animate this,
move it about, you can see that we have
sort of these bands of no noise in the second row.
So, what's going on there is what's called noise modulation, and it turns out to be a
property of the type of noise we're using, because we're using entirely uniform noise.
Noise modulation means that the error in the output image compared to the signal is dependent
on the signal.
And that's a property, of course, we don't want because, yeah, it looks weird.
So...
So fortunately we can just change the distribution of the noise.
So if we use a triangularly distributed noise instead, we get this.
And now we don't have noise modulation, so we don't have, like, the final error is completely
independent of the signal.
So if we go back and try to apply that, we see that we get the same smooth gradient that
we did before.
And if we animate it, we can see that we no longer have these bands that we noticed before.
But now we have quite a lot of noise.
That's because we've now added two bits worth of noise rather than one to compensate for
the triangular shape of the distribution.
So what can we do about that?
Well, we can go back and use the blue noise that we also looked at for sampling.
And if we do that, then of course we need a triangular distribution for that, but if
we go and use that instead.
we get something that's visibly less noisy,
but also doesn't have these bands of noise again.
So the way we implemented that was to just pre-calculate
blue noise into texture, and then we sampled that
everywhere on screen.
That gives complete texture cache coherency
between edges and pixels.
So that's actually really fast.
So in the few cases where we are actually bandwidth bound,
we then use an ALU version where we calculate two white noises
and add them together and add that to the output.
All right, so now that we know how to dither an output,
we should think about what to dither.
So this is an example of a single spotlight that
shines a very bandy light onto the scene.
So of course, the first thing we do is that we dither the lighting
pulse.
So if we do that, then it looks like this.
And that's already a lot better.
But we sort of have these waves through the light.
That is not due to the type of noise, as you might think.
But of course, because the final pass
is reading the lighting buffer, and then applying materials,
and writing that into an 8-bit buffer.
So of course, we need two to do the final pass as well.
So in doing that we then have an entirely banding free output in this scene.
So afterwards we have the translucency pass and the translucency pass might be the most
important pass to dither because during blending you tend to read and write the same values
over and over again into the render target.
and so you end up re-quantizing to 8-bits multiple times.
So of course we need to dither that pass as well.
The post-effects pass is also surprisingly really important to dither.
You tend to read and write from 8-bit render targets quite a lot in the post-effects pass
because...
bandwidth tends to be a limiting factor during that as well.
So here, as an example, our wide glow path,
we actually ended up using a 10-bit render target
and sort of power of two compressing it
and dithering to get something
that was entirely banding free
and at the same time didn't have too much noise.
So, so far we've been talking about
uh... bending as an artifact of colors and really doesn't have anything to do
with colors it's all about the quantization to 8 bits
so in our base pass when writing out
normals we are writing those out to uh... to 8-bit render targets as well
24-bit render targets
So of course we can deal with the normals as well and exchange the banding for noise.
We do this only in the few cases where it's actually needed, which is the very few cases in the game where we have these really intense
spectacular highlights with normals sort of varying across really large surfaces.
Okay, so now we know to do the everything and how to do so.
Is there anything else we should keep in mind?
Well, it's a really good idea to animate the noise.
If you don't, then when the camera moves,
you sort of have this dusty lens effect
where the noise moves with the camera.
Also, because we're using the temporal anti-aliasing, that means that if you animate it, the temporal anti-aliasing will sort of integrate the noise over time and will kind of soak up the noise, so it sort of disappears, which is nice.
Also, of course...
Yeah, you should do the UI, because that tends to be a lot of transparencies and a lot of
different, like, fades and animation and that sort of thing, which is really important.
And finally, when you are outputting to a monitor or television, then...
if that television for example has, is set to use limited range RGB, there may be a small chip that will do a conversion for you, to make sure that you match that TV.
So if you can, then make sure to output the correct format so you can properly dither your signal and output, rather than having the hardware do it for you, because that's quite unlikely to do proper dithering of that.
And with that I'll leave you to the very capable hands of the other maker.
Hello.
So from a lot of post effects, a lot of debugging we're going to drive into some lighting now.
As Guido said, we're using pre-pass lighting for our rendering pipeline.
So that means that during the second pass with our normals and our depth buffer, we're
writing several objects into our lighting buffer, like spots or point lights or directional
lights.
But if we want, we can actually just render whatever we'd like in there.
So we've got a few types of custom lights and whatnot.
So let's take a look at the first one I'm going to talk about,
which is the bounce light.
The bounce light is probably the simplest of all of these.
It's very basically a thing that we
use to simulate pseudo-global illumination
in a very handheld way.
and uh...
if uh... we take a look at this screenshot here it's got a little point light down there
by the box
but uh... that's it's not a sharp point light that we want so uh...
this is the uh... the lighting product that we get around the sphere and
what makes a bounce light different is that we just you know
wrap the lighting on the other side
and this is something that
that Valve has been doing for character lighting for a while.
It's called Lambert Wrap or Double Lambert, stuff like that.
And we've just got a parameter for that called Hardness
that we can use to just fade off that, you know,
front to back side product around our objects.
And it just makes it less obvious
where the light is coming from.
It kind of makes it look like it's coming from an area
rather than a singular point.
So in this case we're wrapping it from front to back but we can actually fade it off completely if we want so that we just get a straight up ambient, nothing but fall off light.
So we use this mostly for doors opening or just spreading light around the room when we have a very sharp fixed light hitting something.
But we can also just attach it to spotlights and hit the ground as the spotlight moves around.
But yeah, mostly for windows opening and the likes of that.
Now, a small property that's kind of a no-brainer,
but also just gives a lot of freedom
is we don't restrain it to just being
like a point on the radius, because that
would mean that to fill up this room with lights,
we would need to just place and place
four lights with all sorts of overlap and overdraw.
So we let artists scale the lights in any which way
they want, just non-uniformly.
Replace these points with a pill instead.
And it's just a little more effective and actually makes it look a little more smooth
because you don't have overlapping things.
So yeah, that's our GI figury.
And next up, because we have a pass just for lighting,
we can not just add lights to, but also subtract or multiply things onto this buffer.
So we don't just need to...
to do an additive blending.
We can do whatever blend mode we want here.
So we've got a few ways of doing ambient occlusion, or shadows,
in a very custom-handheld way, as opposed
to using screen space, ambient occlusion,
or any effect like that that's baked, or screen space.
So we've got three types of ambient occlusion casters.
And let's look at the first one, and actually the most used one,
which is the point.
So the point is mostly used for characters.
The point is just to try to ground them to the ground and to themselves and to each other
and make this large boy band kind of look like they're huddling together a little closer.
So in there we've got about one per limb and we've got about sixteen dudes.
got over a hundred of those little
bastards there
uh... so
how that thing works is very simple if you have a bounce light, you know a light that wraps
from front to back of the geometry
and that's got an additive blend mode, well the AO decal is very simply just flipping
that around to a multiplication
blend mode
and that's basically it, it's non-uniformly scalable
and all that says
One thing though, because we place a lot of them,
we don't want that many settings on it.
So we just have an intensity setting,
and we can place and scale it however.
So we don't have a wrap parameter for this one.
It just wraps from front to back.
Very simple.
and that's the AO-Decal number one.
So, second one we have is,
this one we use a little more sparsely,
just because, well, it's more for bigger occluders,
like this Submarino.
So the difference between the point and the sphere occlusion
is that for the point, you can just see it,
like, intensifying as it gets closer,
but this, the sphere, the point is
that you want it to get sharper
as it gets closer to the occludi.
or the ground.
And so comparing the two, the point of the sphere,
a sphere is just the angle to the ground.
No, the point is just the angle to the ground.
But we really want to know what the sum of occluded angles
are for this ground.
So the way to implement the difference
between these implementations is if you have this normalizer,
which is just normalizing the direction of the.
of the occluder.
We just need to change that product
from this inverse square root to this thing here.
And then actually that gives us the perfect product we needed.
And we get a nice, sharp occlusion for basically cheaps.
Third up on the AO scale is the box occlusion, because we've got a rather small times a crate.
In our game, I think a third screen or so, there's a crate.
So for all these draggable crates and boxes, we need something specific to them.
And what we really want is like, have sharp corners around the sides and, you know, just make it look crate-sy, if you will.
and the way we do that is we start with what you could call an unsigned distance function to the
box so we have the position minus the size and we got like the distance to the first edge of the box
and then what we do is we take the angle around that
so we know on which point around that
around the faces we are
and that will give us that very sharp result up there on the top
which is not nice, you know, we got these sharp V shapes
so instead of taking just the unsigned distance
we take the, let's call it square distance
which also happens to be unsigned because...
Yeah, it's squared.
And that just smooths out the first gradient,
as squaring things does.
And that's a totally empirical, non-physically-based way
to do this.
It just happened to look kind of neat.
you know, one side of this angle around is going to look like that side up there
and if you compose all four together, you get those sharp edges around the sides of the box
and yeah, it's just going to kind of look like the occlusion of a box
and that's nice
so
Those are for ambient occlusion, cast in every direction.
We've also got one for specifically directional shadows.
And we use these for places where we have a lot of ambient lighting,
very non-directional kind of wide lighting.
and we just need to cast some very soft, very placed down shadows that might not even be
from the right direction.
So this is the scene without these, and if we add them, it kind of looks like this instead,
these scenes.
And so there are a lot of these placed around.
In fact, this is like the places they've been put, and all they are are a, what's it called,
a...
a projected decal with a texture and just multiply onto the lighting buffer.
That's all there is to it.
And we use these both for these static scenes where we need soft shadows, but also for like,
of course, dragging objects around and that shield there.
And we do these.
kind of Ocarina of Time period
shadows around the boy's feet when he's got a torch
and it's a nice way of
faking some really really smooth shadows
So, like I said, we do a lot of these, so we also need the projection maths to go fast
because projections could be expensive if they are not fast
and the way that you would neatly implement
a projected piece of geometry is in your vertex shader you would get a view rate
and in your fragment shader you would multiply that by the depth to get a view position and then
just transform it with a full matrix into your object space or your decal space.
Now that's not that nice because we got a full matrix multiplication in there.
It's got a large row of mad instructions in there.
So we would like to minimize that.
Luckily there's a way to do that if you know how to do well spaced reconstruction from depth buffer.
In which case you would get a view ray in your vertex shader and you would rotate the ray to world space rotation
And then in your fragment shader you just need to multiply this world ray instead of view ray
by the depth and add a world space offset
and you're done
so you can probably guess where that's going
we still need to use a transformation matrix
in order to get this world position to decal space
so that's obviously not what we want
but, you know, same technique works on object space arrays
so you take a view array
multiply it by the object space matrix
and you get an object array
and uh...
that also both includes rotation and scale
in your fragment shader, multiply by depth,
and add an offset.
So now you've gone from a matrix multiplication 4 by 4
down to a math operation on a vector 3, which is neat.
So.
Another place that we use these decals are for reflections.
So we've got screen space reflections in the game,
and rather than it being a full post effect on screen,
the whole thing we just needed in certain places
where we kind of needed the puddle shader,
the puddle entity that we needed to puddle down in places.
And we like these screen space reflections
because they have a very simple, very flexible setup
rather than going through.
uh... doing a planar reflection where you need to tag objects that need to be rendered or
make a cube map or anything heavy like that. This just reflects
what's on screen without any sort of
heavy duty work.
And setup wise, it's very simple.
You just get the color that you want the reflection to be,
at least for us, and the background color, which is,
well, if the ray doesn't hit anything,
we need to displace something.
Texture for projection, Fresnel power,
and how long do you need the trace distance to be.
So very minimal setup on the material.
But as the advantages is pretty good,
what you see is what we reflect.
That's a very nice thing, but that also means
what you don't see is not reflected.
So in this case, you know, at the edges of the screen, what you usually do with screen-space-perfection
is you would either fade out to the edge or kind of stretch it, but, you know, in this
case, fade out.
And you get these very light, bright edges where we, you know, reflect the sky color
or whatever, very close to the edges of the screen, and it just doesn't look nice.
And this is of course happening because we can't anticipate which way we're reflecting
so we're assuming the normal scope point in which way and we could be reflecting out of
the screen and we need to fade out before that happens to not have like clamp-in textures
or whatever.
And luckily we have, this is not a universal solution, but for us most of the time we place
down a puddle on the ground pointing upward and we're a 2D game mostly looking in toward
the world.
So we can be left with just forcing all normals to point straight up and in
and never have any deviation on the x-axis
which takes care of this problem and now we don't need to fade at all
because there's no way we're going to go off screen anymore
it's just not going to happen.
Now, that's the first way that we can not see what we want to reflect
and have a fix for that.
But the other thing is a little bit more bitchy to handle which is...
if you have something behind something.
So, like, say our boy is jumping in front of a haystack
and we've got a camera and we need to reflect that somehow.
So we have a camera and we have a reflection ray.
Anything that's behind the boy is technically invisible.
It looks like this. We don't know what it is.
But of course we're not going to reflect him as if he's infinitely deep.
In fact, we're going to pretend he's quite shallow.
uh... we need to have a little bit of a
cut it off right here, we're going to say that there's an edge
and in this case we're just missing everything, we're just going to reflect off the sky
and it's going to look awful
uh...
with checking that depth parameter
But of course we're not just reflecting a full resolution thing.
We're taking very quantized steps.
We're only stepping about 16, 24 times through this reflection algorithm.
So actually what we're reflecting through looks something like this.
Instead for each step...
And what we want to find in order to fix this problem is we want to find these two edges
because they're going to be useful. What we want to do is take a mix of what's just above
and below these things and assume that we can kind of like stitch it together behind them like that.
So we need to find these. How do we do that? Well let's try to step through.
For it, we're gonna need a few parameters
to keep in our pocket.
When we are tracing, we need the depth
from the last time, from the last step,
we need the difference between the depth
and the ray from the last step,
and we just need the old position from the last step.
So, if we are not behind something,
we save these things, like last time
we were successfully aware of our surroundings,
we save these guys, and then we always save the last depth.
So we step through and...
Oh! That was a hard wall there.
So we're no longer going to be saving the old...
Old diff and old position.
So we save those for later because we want to sample the old position.
And we keep stepping and...
Oh! Shit! That was the other one.
So we checked...
the last depth and the current depth you see,
well if they're very far apart,
there was probably like a split there somewhere.
And then using that information,
we just take the old position from last time
that we were down at the red line,
and the position now,
and just kind of like sample somewhere on that line
with like two samples and just there between them.
And that actually covers 90% of our scenes
that we would have otherwise with the boy
or any occluder in the game.
And finally, for projection maps on this guy,
we have a view ray, and we wanna put it into frustum.
We wanna make a frustum ray.
So unlike, what's it called, the projected decals,
we don't need to take some view space to object space.
We need to take it to a projected space,
a skewed space here.
and uh... the naive way to do that would be to uh... you know
take your uh... your reflective position
and uh... put it through a full matrix and then subtract your
your screen space position
but uh...
I don't like that so much. Also it doesn't handle the near clip plane. If anything goes
behind that you
just start going back into
infinite negativity
so
Our solution to this is to cheat a little bit
and create a little variable on the CPU
where we need the size of the viewport in projected space.
Like on X and Y, we get the resolution of the screen
and the aspect ratio and field of view.
And for the set value, we just need the depth range,
which looks like that.
And then in order to transform a view ray
into a projected ray, it just looks like this instead.
and it handles anything behind camera just fine now.
So, that's raised now.
Like I said, we only do a few steps,
and just like the volume lighting,
we need to do something about these step artifacts.
So obviously, you add some noise to your first step,
and you've got some jittering going on.
And this is just to...
reiterate that white noise is nice and easy but very noisy.
Bayonet UCs are still nice and structural but structural in the bad way too.
And blue noise is our general saviour and you too should use it.
And with simple anti-aliasing it's really, really nice.
So finally, about that thickness, the wall thickness.
With screen-spreader perfection, like I said, we can't assume that the depth buffer is the
perfect information of what's on screen.
You know, it's just the outer shell, the first thing we can see.
So we need to step through it assuming some sort of wall thickness.
And we want to get away with the minimum thickness we can basically come up with, to not have
any stretched objects, or as artists called it, the boy with MC hammer pants.
and the simple way that we started simulating this thickness is to say well
let's use the uh... you know how much is our screen rate moving in set
and just say that's our thickness because that means
if between now and the last step we have passed through some depth
we're good
but that has one problem at that wall there and the wall is pointing
45 degrees to the viewer, which means the view ray is going straight across the screen,
which means it's not moving instead at all, and it won't reflect a thing.
That... that sucks.
And, um, well, if I take what that view ray set was made of, this is what it was made of,
and all you really have to do is take out the reflection direction itself,
and just use that, so that's like the total potential movement that it will have.
And you've got a...
You've got my favorite wall thickness there at least.
It will basically catch anything on its way.
Another way that we use reflections, but different reflections, are of course for water.
So we've got some water rendering system.
For those of you who played the game, we have quite a long water section.
So, yeah, we need a bunch of water.
And we need a few layers for this water.
We need some fogginess or murkiness, like see the depth of it.
We need to render a bunch of transparencies into it, like you mentioned, the volume lighting
underneath the water to sort of sell the thickness of it, stuff like that.
And we need to refract it.
and make it watery.
And finally, reflections.
And these are not screen-space reflections.
These are planar reflections, because on a big water surface
that just spans most of the screen, a lot of the time,
we just can't handle the artifacts.
So for this one, we do use planar camera reflections.
And so we render out these layers as individual objects
because it's actually the abstraction layer
that we think about water is actually useful
for rendering as well.
So this is what happened when we were above.
When we were below, we actually flipped the rendering order.
So we render reflection first
because that's the furthest away thing.
You know, we render back to front
like any transparency you do.
Then we render the murkiness on top of that
because we wanna murkify the reflection too.
then the refraction, and finally the transparency is down here so they don't get affected by that fog or anything when we're down under.
And now for each of these layers, in order to get a consistent surface, we actually render each layer three times.
We render first up a displacement edge close to the camera, which...
looks something like this with wireframe turned on and that's like from the camera perspective
just a bunch of things that only exist in the frustum making waves and just making sure that
when you pass through there isn't like this oh the water was a pancake i guess flat polygon effect
and just makes it look deeper it only goes about six to eight meters into the screen but that's
all you need for parallax in order to sell the the deepness of the water
then we render the outside of a box which takes care of the rest of the
outside surface
so kinda like the outer faces of a box in case
this like this water volume here is a box
and uh... when we're done with that
then we render the inside face of the box
but you'll notice it doesn't render on top of what we've already rendered and that's
because
for each
yeah this is how it looks like by the way for each
of these uh...
for each of these layers that we render out,
we actually write into a stencil bit.
Let's call it the I have rendered water stencil bit.
And if any geometry reads from that bit
that it's already been rendered,
it'll just discard the fragments.
So we render the transparencies front to back
rather than back to front with rejection instead.
So we only have one layer.
So it's kind of like a pseudo set buffer in a way.
And, yeah, that's it for now. Let's change gears and go into a little bit more of the VFX area with some smoky smoke.
So, that very simple smoke stack there had a bunch of effects on it. Let's try it again and just stop it.
and uh... the strategy of all the events
so that's it now it looks very plain and in fact it looks like it's
blending into the background you can barely see it
that's because it's base color is just the ambient color of the room
and nothing else so that it will blend in most cases
now the first effect we put on is the presence of
a uh... we have a fake point light that we attached to the uh...
to the smoke to make it look like it's been hit by the light from the window
kind of grounded in
and uh... up next
The texture itself, we need to wobble it a little bit around in order to sell some extra...
Sorry, we need to light this thing a little bit more just to sell some gradient.
We need to have it lit from top and darken from below to kind of ground it.
And it's very hard to see, but if you pay close attention, there it is, and there it's not, and there it is.
And finally...
we rub all the texture around a little bit, which just gives a little bit of sub-particle motion where
it'll be hard to tell where one particle starts and the other...
one particle ends and the other starts, just because they sort of...
yeah, the texture itself is not fully...
comprehensible. And we wobble it around using this, I like to call it swirl noise, which is basically
a UV
Map in Photoshop with the swirl effect a bunch of times on it
and just apply it over and over a few times
and we scroll it downwards in this case to kind of like give the effect that the
Steam in this case is going downwards, but it could also go upwards in whichever which way it's just it's scrolled one way in world space, basically
So next up, some more vapor of the hotter kind.
So I'm throwing around this box just to sort of illustrate how
it handles movement somewhat well and remains fiery throughout said movement.
So, we've got the smoke effect going up in the background as well here.
That's just the same smoke as before with the light.
But the fire, what makes it special, it's using all the same effects,
the distortion and all that, and even a bit of gradient lighting,
but the most important part about the fire is consistent coloring.
When we first tried fire, we just had like, you know, fire going from red to orange to yellow and white in the middle, and then blue at the edges.
But then, if a lot of layers of blue are layered on top of each other, you could end up with a very bright blue that would look really crappy.
So what we do, we have...
essentially a fire buffer. That's a lie, but we have a fire buffer, which is just the alpha
buffer of what we're rendering into. The alpha buffer is the HDR bloom value that we already
use, so that makes perfect sense because, well, the fire is going to bloom, so why not use this?
So we render out a bunch of black and white sprites of essentially fireiness or hotness
buffer into one consistent thing with additive blend mode.
And then we apply one gradient to this
before we read it back into RGB.
And that makes every individual sprite look like this
or composite it like so.
And it just makes it more consistent
to look at color-wise.
Now, with fire, motion was not enough
to just have with distortions.
We've also got this here map of, what's it called?
It's called Thipbook.
So we've got a flipbook to go through and we had a couple of issues with this
We're trying to like animate these just very few cartoony frames of fire and we tried first, you know going sequentially
but then that would mean that these nine frames would loop every one second and would look very
loopy and then we tried doing random but
there's an 11 point something chance, percent chance,
that you will hit the same frame twice,
which will, so the eyes just look like lag,
so that was horrible.
So we used an in-between thing,
which is, you know, we choose columns sequentially,
and we choose rows randomly,
which means that we don't get looping that often,
and we definitely don't get two frames at the same time,
and that worked out really well for us.
Now, to animate between these different layers, this is if I just make each flip of piece
a solid color, a random solid color, it would look like this, but of course we don't flip
between them hard, we fade between them, but we also don't do that, we fade between them
using a vertical gradient upward, with noise, because why not?
And that's fire.
Next up, the Bay Flares.
So we've got these events fairs and unlike the bloom they are very
like specifically put in like you put in
a events fair entity onto a flashlight or onto something bright and
it'll flare up
and uh...
we do this just because we like to have our you know our
hdr bloom settings different from the flashlight settings
and the flashlight might be smaller than one pixel so it wouldn't get picked up
uh...
so
The way we do it is with a quadrant, like a 2x2 sprite there.
And in order to have occlusion from things, we could do what the standard thing is,
is to just ray trace toward the screen and get collision a bunch of times,
but A, that would be expensive.
B, we don't want to set up collision on trees that the boy or anyone is never going to collide with.
That would suck.
So what we do is...
For each point in the vertices here, we sample the depth buffer per vertex a bunch of times, stochastically,
because that's only four times rather than per pixel.
But of course we don't sample at the corners, we sample at the middle.
and you know we pass this on to uh... to the fragment shader and multiply it by the texture of the fair
but of course
we could sample it not at the middle
but slightly between the corners and the middle just to get like this
gradient going across making it look like it's got some volume
because it's free we're sampling all four vertices anyway we might as well give them a little variation
and that's basically that
so next up
some water
more water
and we're not just talking about water
rendering here we're talking specifically about effects on top of the water
and uh... here we've got this uh... stack of uh...
of foam, that Olympic dye foam going on.
And it's got a bunch of effects, almost the same effects,
no, sorry, exactly the same effects as the smokestack.
So if I take them all off, they look like...
If I take the motion off, it looks like this, all still.
If I take the lighting off, it looks like this, all flat.
And putting back in the gradient lighting and the motion,
it looks like this.
So it just kind of like, blends a bunch of sprites together really well,
makes it look really thick.
Over here we've got this flashlight.
And for those who haven't played it,
if you go into that flashlight, you suffer.
So we need to emphasize this flashlight
with a bunch of effects.
And the effects that we use are, first of all, the rain.
So we have a bunch of rain.
and uh... we tried both doing like post effect scrolling things but that didn't
really have any good parallax in it
then we tried some sprites
scrolling down with textures of rain but that was a lot of overdraw so what we ended up
with was
a mesh
with individual
raindrops in it
and uh... that has much less overdraw but uh...
but animation could be more costly.
So what we do is we just have a vertex shader
that for the raindrops going down,
as soon as the vertex hits the bottom of a volume,
it just goes back on top and goes down again.
That's it.
And the splashes on the ground,
all they do is expand with a random rotation,
and as soon as they're done with that and fade out,
they go to a new position and do that again.
And we just do that using, like,
the animation unfolding is, you know,
the fractional part of time.
So for every half second,
it goes up and for every
integer part of time it moves to a new position with a new seed
and that's basically it for them. Next up we've got
the volume lighting above the water to just
show where it is and finally we've got this
plane on the water just showing
where it's hitting the water itself with basic
It's called Fong, specular lighting and a bit of diffuse lighting.
Going underneath, we have a bunch of the same effects and a little new one.
So the different effect down here is we have these dust moats underneath the water that are lit up by the...
by the spotlight and they're lit up the same way that the
they're moving the same way that the spotlight, that the raindrops are
they just move across and when they come to the other edge they
loop back in and just keep going. They just scroll
across in a volume and
come back to the start using
what is called modulus, that operator, fmod
and uh... we've got the volume light underneath but unlike the one above
of course these are different volumes just like you said
uh... this one underneath has
uh... a texture on it
that's animating
of like caustics to make it look more underwater
and finally the phone reflection which is now a phone refraction
just to show exactly where the light is
and that's it for under
So for above water we've got these waves coming out from the buoy there.
I could have chosen a better place to show these because they're very subtle here.
So the way these waves are done is they just resample the reflection and refraction
with some wavy distortion around him.
They're done with particle-based rings, like just these little ring meshes that go outward.
And the way we get those distortion normals is very simple.
the direction around the ring, and we have the phase from center to outward,
and we just take that direction on the ring as the normal,
and multiply it by a sine that's sampled over the phase of it.
So it's, you know, zero at the start, zero in the middle, and zero on the other edge,
and then negative a lot in the first third,
and positive a lot on the second third, and that gives a wave normal, essentially.
And now for a different type of water.
so this is the uh...
this is the whirlpool
and uh... this one has much different motion on it
uh... so it's got some motion going outward rather than just scrolling across
and uh... the way we do that is with this uh... this mesh here, this high poly mesh
and the reason is it's high poly is rather than
calculating these texture coordinates in uh...
In Fragment, we just made it higher polycount
so we could calculate it in vertex instead.
Now, we could have picked scrolling, expanding textures
outward, but that would be somewhat difficult.
What we chose instead was this scrolling outward,
but that makes texturing somewhat more difficult.
So the texture that we have scrolling outward
looks like this.
And the criteria before was it had to look wavy and it had to tile really well, but in
a non-obvious way.
So luckily there is a good way to tile these things that you might have seen outside.
Like these cobblestone bricks, they tile perfectly, with a wave shape, like water.
So if I took a picture of this, started tracing lines of the wave shapes.
then took some stock images of waves and layered them underneath and then removed the lines.
Suddenly you've got a texture that looks like, well that doesn't tile, but it totally tiles.
And yeah, that makes up for a pretty good tiling foam texture.
You guys.
Finally, we've got this flood.
Which is a lot more dramatic with sound.
it's got a bunch of elements stuff we've already
talked about
couple of new ones
just stuff we've talked about
first up we've got this water volume
coming outward
and it's using our full water rendering
uh... thing
and uh... that thing however is of course animated
so how it looks like it's using three morph targets one for before breaking
one for after and one
uh... for in between
it looks like this if you just look at the
mesh itself
so we're using morph targets exported from 3ds max with these three
water shapes and animate them
and that's how we do the animation of that
and uh... we scroll textures on it the same way that we did on the whirlpool
and uh... then
uh... we've got this uh... thing on the ground this uh...
this big decal of uh... screen space perfections and the same wave texture
that we had before scrolling in the same way that we did before
uh... and the texture coordinates what was important to the texture coordinates
was that they
uh... are faster in the beginning
and then kind of like ease out as it goes out toward the end of the decal
and we do that by just having like applying power to the y component of the
of the texture coordinate
so that it goes very fast in the beginning
and then over time it will slow down
and finally we've got this carpet of particles
which are lit from behind
to just so that these club cars are...
alighting it and we've got the same thing for an impact down below and
finally we've just got like some some swooshes that make it more swooshy in the beginning and
feel more powerful in the start of it and
That's basically all the components of that
So in conclusion, if it isn't apparent already for sampling,
we really like blue noise, and you should like it too.
We really like temporal anti-aliasing
because it really lets us do all these stochastic effects
that we otherwise would not be allowed to do before bedtime.
You should dither all your things
with a triangular distribution function.
And you should expose customizable shaders
to artists if you're using any sort of deferred pipeline
or any pipeline whatsoever, because you get cool decals.
Screen space reflections are cool and useful.
And non-screen space ambient occlusion
is cool and useful as well.
Thanks to all these people, our colleagues at Playdead,
people at Microsoft, graphics team at Unity,
Double11 for making our code fast,
and the Twitterverse for helping with this talk.
And that's it.
Thank you.