I'll probably start on page one.
Every year I come to GDC, I play a little game called
Who's Corporate and Who's Indie?
Wait a minute.
What happened there?
There we go.
Who's holding down a full-time job with benefits, wearing a
logo shirt and staying at the W on the company dime, versus
who's an independent contractor schmoozing for that
next gig, staying at the Mosser if they're lucky?
But more importantly, what were they last year?
More than with other game development and technology disciplines,
it seems like audio folks tend to spend their careers going back and forth
between holding down corporate gigs and freelancing from backroom project studios.
There are certainly some who have always had jobs and others
who have never produced audio except under contract.
But if you work long enough in this industry,
odds are you will eventually transition from one state to the other.
Now that's certainly been true in my case.
More, in 1997, I went to my first GDC in San Jose as an indie, green and desperate.
Five years later, I showed up at GDC 2002, proudly wearing a Danger logo shirt,
where I began my career as a mobile audio guy.
Later, I got assimilated by Microsoft right before GDC 2008,
but was back to be an indie for GDC 2010.
I moved back to the Bay Area from Redmond in time for GDC 2013 and interviewed for an
audio engineering job at Kik's Eye during the conference.
In 2015, I attended the show as an indie again, wearing a flash leather jacket and with a
pocket full of twittering machine business cards in full schmoozing for work mode.
And the first guy I ran into when I got off the BART was George the Fat Man Sanger.
I said, hey George, how you doing?
He looks at me and goes, Drescher, I got a job for you.
And that was that.
A few months later, I'm living in lovely Fort Lauderdale, Florida.
and attended GDC 2016 and 17 as senior audio engineer at Magic Leap, the world's most enigmatic
unicorn.
And now, here I am again, right back where I started from, living in California, working
as an independent contractor for my backroom studio, and kind of loving it.
So to discuss the pros and cons of working freelance versus holding down a job, I am
lucky to be joined on stage by four distinguished colleagues.
who have also worked both sides of the equation.
In alphabetical order, Damian Kasbauer,
currently at ArenaNet, formerly at PopCap,
plus many independent projects,
including the Oscar-winning Carni y Reyes.
Wilbert Roget, award-winning composer
for Call of Duty World War II, Lara Croft,
and numerous LucasArts titles.
Karen Widener, president and founder
of 8Ball Sound in Los Angeles,
formerly at Game Tracks and Sound Deluxe.
Guy Whitmore, currently independent, formerly at PopCap and Microsoft Game Studios.
And of course, you can call your humble moderator PDX.
So we'll now discuss five topics for eight minutes each and then do Q&A.
So the first topic, there's the topics.
Art.
How does being corporate or indie help or hinder the creative process when producing
a game soundtrack?
So, let's start with the first topic.
How does being corporate or indie help or hinder the creative process when producing
a game soundtrack?
Now for me, this kind of, one of the things I always do is I always maintain my own home
studio because I find being creative in, outside of the corporate environment where there's
meetings and people running around, blah, blah, blah, and you can't really be as free
as you might like.
So, if I'm doing a piece of music, I would try and write in my home studio and then bring
it in to the corporate studio to implement and test.
And this becomes important in some cases.
One of the stories I like to tell is the time I was doing a music title for a kids game
where my monkey was the main character.
And so I was in my house, half naked, jump around the furniture making, ooh, ah, noises,
trying to come up with a melody, and my girlfriend walks in.
No, really, honey, I'm working.
So how do you guys feel about being corporate or creative in the corporate or indie environment?
This one's interesting.
I'm not very...
shy about most things. So my first job at Sierra, it was an
office door that might have been paper. And I wrote a lot of
music in that room and people just got used to it. So
inhibitions, the only inhibition I really have is if I'm doing,
you know, singing something. And that I like my privacy for. But
I can be creative in a public place pretty much. So... But if
I'm not bugging people, that's a bonus.
I mean, I guess the obvious answer is that when you're in-house, you're being asked to
be creative from the hours of nine to five.
Exactly.
Yes.
Can you really guarantee that that's when you'll have your melody?
Can you really guarantee that that...
Most of my ideas come really, really late at night and basically nocturnal.
And my creative process involves coming up with some blue sky idea at night, jotting
it down in whatever way possible, sleeping on it, and then in the morning worrying about
things like, is it good?
How do I finesse it?
You know, all the details and all that kind of thing.
That was very difficult to do.
Not only are you in here from set core hours or whatever,
but also you're constantly going to be interrupted
by meetings and by, maybe your friends come by
for whatever reason, I guess,
because we have offices and they like to just
shut themselves out from the rest of the team or whatever.
And you're constantly being basically assaulted
by just all these other details that have nothing to do
with your creative work.
Whereas if you are a freelancer, you can kind of set a creative space.
It's a little easier to pull that off.
So for me, that's sort of how it's gone and why I'll just get this out of the way.
I do prefer the freelance world, and I guess we'll kind of keep coming back to that.
Yeah, I was going to speak to that, too.
One of the things for me is a lot of times I get hired for
sort of specialized things that mainly work as a sound
designer.
And I find being out of house, being indie, well, I guess
half my career has about been indie and half in corporate
at this point or in house.
I find I can focus more on specific things because of
kind of what Wilbert was saying, where you're less
interrupted with meetings.
And oftentimes, I'm not implementing either, which is
good and bad.
But.
it kind of takes that focus just to the creation side.
Like for instance, I worked on LawBreakers
doing Foley and sound design for that game
for about eight months,
and to just focus on the Foley and sound design
for the cut scenes and not have to worry about other stuff.
I think that helped the creative process a lot.
I'm just going to underline focus again. It's like the biggest deal, right? As a freelancer,
yeah, sure, maybe I can dive into a technical system and really, you know, craft this elaborate
Faberge egg inside of some middleware integration with the game.
But that comes at the detriment of when you're in-house
creating that same system.
You may not have the same focus, but you have greater
resources to maybe push the creativity of it in a
different direction.
Instead of the insular system that you create abstracted
from the team outside the fence, you have the resources
of the team in real time that you can push forward the
creativity deeper in that direction.
Well, and that's actually a good point from the advantage of working in a corporate environment
is you have the ability to, from a creative point of view, bounce ideas off of people,
particularly people you know and trust and who are involved in the game.
or the product in a similar manner that you are.
That can be a match.
Whereas if you're just by yourself in your studio all day,
which tends to happen on a regular basis,
sometimes you don't know if what you're doing is good or not.
You don't really have anything to bounce it off of
until you then send it out,
and then maybe you hear something back, maybe you don't.
Yeah, and that's true.
For instance, making stuff, in both cases for me,
I have to consciously make.
these barriers that you were talking about.
I was like, okay, even with freelance,
I still need to put like, okay,
from these hours to this hours,
I'm not gonna look at Facebook, I'm not gonna do this.
There's more discipline involved,
and it can be at midnight or whatever,
but there's still a discipline of,
yes, I'm gonna start at 10 and go.
But I also have to do that at work, it's harder,
but I used to have this little door sign
I'd put on my thing that says, do not disturb.
So I would have these hours at work and you have to have that.
That's the only way I could do anything at work.
Did they respect the do not disturb?
No, they didn't, but Becky made sure they did.
Becky would be like, he's a kid.
Awesome colleague. So it ended up being respected. Okay. Yeah.
So it worked. Well, they respected Becky. Yes. You know,
and I remember your office in at Microsoft, though, had was like
a glass booth. Oh, that was horrible. I didn't get any. But
that was a different job. I wasn't doing creation in that
office ever. Right. Right. Yeah.
I had a glass booth where I did do creation at Danger, and the first thing I did was I
put up Oralex foam across the window so people couldn't see what was happening.
And this actually became a little bit of an issue in the office because people want, you
know, what's he doing in there?
What's going on there?
It became both more of a mystique, but also a little bit standoffish.
Oh, he's got his thing, and, you know, he's that guy.
Or as I usually call it, the pad itself, the lock on the inside.
Right. You know, also one other thing too is that I almost always get my best ideas when I'm walking my dog.
It's like I'm out there, I'm in the thin, I'm not thinking about the work, and then I'll look at the trees, and I'll work up a sweat,
and then some idea will come to me, and I'm like, oh, that's a good idea, and then I'll go home and I'll work.
On the subject of inspiration, one angle that I'm not sure has been touched on,
but sometimes you can get inspiration from sources outside of audio.
And if you can make friends with people in the art scene,
some of the best, quote unquote, best ideas that I've had
haven't come from audio people at all, but from designers and artists
and concept folks and making friends with them,
which I know is not the easiest thing in the world to do,
because usually it's like Audio Island out there
where we're sequestered into our little corners.
But if you can make those connections...
they have brilliant insights and and you know they can they can
offer a perspective that's sort of zoomed out you know we're so focused on
our details and
and if you're if you're in certain kinds of games like a cinematic title then
it's very easy to fall into the trap of thinking oh
it has to be so serious it has to be so dramatic you know whatever
and you forget that we're just making a game to sell to people for money
and so it's it's good to it's good to
Just kind of interact with folks who are outside of that particular rat race and understand that you can take information from other sources.
The power of a liberal education.
Well, and that's the, but beyond that too, it's also a corporate setting does allow for that direct collaboration, creative collaboration.
Like I, I was freelance for a while in the early 2000s.
And it was really hard to get adaptive scores done at that point in time
because he didn't support was challenging and there wasn't the weren't
the technical resources in order to do it not communication resources.
So I purposely went back in-house so I could affect change from within.
Because there's certain creative changes I couldn't
do as a freelancer that I wanted to do, both at
Microsoft and PopCap, for example.
Now, between middleware and communication tools and
culture changes, it's actually doable now.
I'm on a project where I'm checking in banks to Perforce
and we're communicating on Slack.
And it's great.
It's like the best of both worlds in a way.
I still have to reach out for personal communication.
It's really nice now.
Which is a great segue to our next topic, work.
How does being a member of a team, rather than a hired gun,
help or hinder your workflow when producing game audio?
So like what Guy was saying, if you're in-house
and you're a member of a team, and
it seems to be a lot easier at times to be able to check things in and try it out and
play things for people and see how they react and also all the other stuff, the meetings
and the reports and all the things you have to, emails, et cetera, and political battles
you have to fight. That can be a lot easier when you're in-house as a member of a team.
At the same time, when you're just a hired gun.
You know, it used to be, like you say, nowadays it's getting a lot better, because you can do a lot of the stuff you used to have to only be able to do in-house.
You know, like if you used to work at Sony, you had to use Scream and that was it.
And if you were outside, you couldn't use it. It was just not available.
But things have certainly gotten better now.
But, you know, in the bad old days where, as a contractor, you make sound, you toss it over the wall.
that's it. A couple days later maybe you get a build and see if
it got implemented correctly or not or if it still sounds the
way you think it should. So there are advantages and
disadvantages to that, too, just for the workflow of how you
produce the game.
Yeah, I have a comment on that.
Actually, not too long ago, working with Blizzard as a
contractor, and since they wouldn't let us run any part of
the game remotely, it was difficult.
And also, the audio lead had to go on a recording trip for
a couple weeks, but we couldn't stop working.
And I asked the audio producer, you know,
maybe we should take a hiatus because we're going to be like
there were like five of us making sounds we're going to be
like sending a lot of sounds in that time. He's like, Oh, no,
it's fine. We're gonna have somebody else, you know, listen
to them instead. And he's like, got it, you know, approved to do
that, make that those decisions. And of course, sure enough, he
listened to everything green lighted a bunch of it. So that
was good. Got some fixes on some things, but mostly it was good.
Then the lead comes back. And of course, like he had a totally
different opinion on all these sounds. And I'm just like
Oh, my God. We're so behind. So that was definitely a challenge
being a contractor in that way where we couldn't put anything
in and test it and kind of make our own decisions. I think we
would have been better if we could have put our sounds in
while the lead was away. But since we couldn't, it was tricky.
Now, Damian, you're like the pipeline guy.
Yeah, I guess I was going to propose, you know, is there any
hindrance?
to being in-house when it comes to workflow and tools?
Oh, I see.
Is there a negative to it?
Because I think the greatest negative to,
or the greatest impact to workflow and tools pipeline
is actually being out of house.
Whereas if you're in-house, you have all the toys.
So it doesn't really, being in-house doesn't affect your workflow and tools in that you have them.
Well, yeah, I mean, this is probably what you're about to say, but in terms of things that are connecting to the game, absolutely.
The tools are right there if you have a problem.
IT is right there, and all the other people who maybe made the tool are right there in the building.
But, um...
I suppose one aspect that you might not have as much control over is your own software.
I mean, you might join a studio where they're just, we are a Pro Tools studio and that's
it.
Or we are a Logic studio and that's what you get.
Whereas if you're at home, you have the flexibility of picking whatever DAW you want, whatever
sample libraries and from that production end, you have a little more freedom.
And also when you want to do, I don't know, it's interesting.
if there's some kind of tool or pipeline process that you want to do, it's somehow, if I'm just
independent, I'm just doing it this way, done. Whereas when I'm in-house, I have to...
you know, not only do the job, but sell the job to the people I'm doing it for,
and then once the job is done, explain to them how it was done that way.
And there's a whole process for getting your work approved.
Yeah, there's the overhead you're dealing with.
There's a lot of overhead.
Well, the other thing that I was...
When Karen was talking about working with Blizzard...
That was, in a lot of cases, they're not alone,
still majority, particularly larger companies,
there's a cultural resistance to working
and allowing access to builds.
You know, and that's understandable.
A lot of them get released inappropriately,
even with VPN and stuff like that.
So you find middle and smaller companies
more willing to open up their pipelines,
which makes you closer to the team as an independent
and able to do a lot of this stuff.
There's the other side of that as well, because right now I am doing a Wwise implementation.
I do not have access, there's no VPN, there's no, I don't do Perforce, we use Git so it's
open.
There's a lot of, there are a number, you know, I can't file bugs, I've got to tell
the guy, hey, this is not working, blah, blah, blah.
No JIRA, etc.
This is where we are right now, but there could be.
It could be and it has been in the past, but in this particular case, I'm not allowed to do that and that's a little bit of a hindrance of being an indie as opposed to being in a team.
It seems like it's up to the game developers really. It varies so wildly across studios. Some of them are very open to...
I mean, when I was working on Lara Croft, they literally just gave me a PC and I could
just implement however, you know, all willy nilly.
I could play a level, decide that I'm not smart enough to fix this puzzle and then just
implement a new music cue for people like me who take forever to solve it.
And I could just do that.
And then it's in the game and there we go.
But then there's other cases where...
Sometimes for secrecy reasons sometimes for technical reasons. I just don't have any access to the game at all
I never played Star Wars the Old Republic ever. I've never played the game despite writing
Played a score. Yeah. Yeah, because there was just no way to
Send it out to us. And so we just had to go off of concept art and
Some lore documents and that's it. So it just what it's just wildly varies, but I mean to Damien's point
being in-house means that you probably have the best situation in terms of workflow overhaul.
Now, don't you guys all think that it's improved over the last, even five years?
Oh yeah. The first seven years of my career I was a freelancer working specifically
between content and the game as a technical sound designer. Right?
So I lived in middleware tools, whether they were off the shelf or proprietary.
This was my jam, right?
and I did it remotely as a preference and I was able to be
very effective when given the resources that I needed like
access to the build, access to the tools, access to a
development platform. These were things that I could
absolutely do. Now, that
became very interesting for me after a time because while I did feel very effective and
very able to from the remote perspective do my job, it became increasingly more important
to a developer towards the end of their production to actually have me physically on site. And
so I then ended up spending, you know, months at a time servicing a developer on site.
to be closer to the tools, to be closer to the team, and to be closer to the changes
that were rapidly emerging towards finaling a game. And so you had this like almost race
to the finish line where, sure, working remotely was, I was highly effective and highly capable
and highly enabled for a period of time, but in the rapid acceleration towards, you know,
finishing the game, that just wasn't enough.
Yeah. Cool. Okay, let's move on to the next topic. Another easy
one. Money.
strategies for maintaining studio gear on an indie rather than a corporate budget. Now,
one of the things I mean by this one is, and I was talking about this earlier, not here
but with some folks, is this idea that whenever I start a new project, I always make, or even
when I'm building a studio for whatever purpose, I always build a studio for the purpose of
the project I'm working on.
So, and even when I start a new project, if I don't have to build a whole new studio around it,
then I always, always buy a new toy or a new plug-in or a new synthesizer or something,
just so I can have some fun playing with these things,
and I feel, I hope that that kind of fun translates into the work.
But it's always geared toward, the gear is geared towards...
a specific purpose, a specific project that I'm doing.
So right now I'm doing a mobile game.
My Pro Tools rig, Florida killed it.
And so I had to build a new system
when I got back to California.
And so for that, I'm doing a mobile game.
I have no need for a surround system.
I got no need for subwoofers.
I got nothing.
So I don't have them.
I got two really big, nice Genelecs.
But that's all I really need for a mobile game.
Whereas if someone wanted to hire me to do work on a
surround sound system, then I'd go and buy a surround
mixer and a bunch more speakers.
Whereas when I'm building a studio in a corporate
environment, you kind of want to think about all the
possible things you might want to do in a corporate setting
and then build for that.
So like at Magically, if I built a system, and again,
magic leap device, where you wear it on your head, there's no surround system, there's no
subwoofer, so I just had a couple of big gentle legs and that was great for what I was using
for. Whereas in other situations like a danger I had, there was a bunch of different things
that I had to do with it, and so we had a bunch of different systems and I had like four or five
computers in a row in my office in those days for doing specific things for different parts of
the product as it was being made. So how do you guys feel about, you know, building your own
studio versus building your studio on a corporate budget?
You don't actually have a studio.
Where's the guitar pedals?
Not to sort of self advertise or whatever, but in 2016 I did a GDC talk about, I think it was just called like triple A virtual orchestration on an indie budget.
And I went over a bunch of different strategies for basically how to stretch a small amount of dollars as far as humanly possible.
Things like how to work with live soloists in the most effective ways and so on and so forth.
But...
Along with that, one recommendation I can give, especially towards people who are doing more kind of dramatic music or orchestral music or whatever, is only by...
sample libraries that are basically the best.
If there's a decision between like,
oh, there's this library and I really love it
and its sound is gonna work so well
for whatever I'm working on,
but then there's this one that's cheaper,
don't get the cheap one.
Just wait until you can afford that.
First off, sample library prices often come down,
unless it's Spectrosonics, but that's another conversation.
They often come down, and so if you can just hold off a little bit and only buy the ones
that really fit for your, you know, what you have in mind for what you're doing, you'll
save money in the long run.
Fewer but awesome.
Yeah, exactly.
Absolutely.
That's true of all gear, actually.
It's true.
I'm kind of, we all go these phases of gear, right?
No matter what we're doing, because gear evolves, right, along with us, the technology, so I'm
in that phase.
And my motto is...
fewer more awesome pieces of gear.
You know, my studio's actually kind of doing this
in some ways and doing this in others.
My home studio's always been more capable
than the corporate studio I've ever worked in,
you know, except for like the studio,
not my office, like at Microsoft or something.
And that's the exception.
But my home rig has always had more samples
and I've often done work at home for work
at the corporate side.
But as an Indy, it's an actual direct investment in what you're doing.
It's tax write-off.
It's all of that.
So, yeah, it's harder, but I think I invest more while I'm an Indy for sure.
You invest more as an Indy.
Oh, yeah, absolutely.
Yeah.
I want to underline tax write-off.
Well, there's that as well.
While I'm not a tax attorney by any stretch, I think we all know that there are opportunities
to maximize equipment for self-employed purchases.
Well, and I'll even go farther than that, in that the only way I've been able to afford
the studios that I have had when I've had a corporate gig...
is by running the studio.
So it's like I have a corporate gig,
I'm making a bunch of money,
and the government takes like that much.
But then as a side project, I'll do like a little project,
and then I'll spend a bunch of money on gear.
And then that amount of money
comes off of my corporate taxes,
and so I get more of it back than I would have otherwise.
That way the government is actually paying for my gear
on a regular basis over time.
And that's worked for me rather well.
Now, it's different when your income is only in the...
you have to do other tricks, that one doesn't quite work.
And I'm not sure, I've been doing that for a long time,
but there's years when I'm indie,
and there's years when I'm doing the corporate,
running the thing off.
I don't know if I were to do that every year,
for like 20 years in a row,
the IRS might come after my ass.
But-
Yeah, business has to make money, actually,
after a certain amount.
After a certain amount, you have to make money.
And usually by that time I'm indie again anyway,
so the only income I've got is video.
But, yeah, the studio investment is one part of this whole money thing.
Obviously, it's the investment piece.
But Karen and I were talking yesterday about the extra costs of being independent.
And I don't know. We're all independent now.
And I just had to buy insurance for my whole family, health insurance.
uh... and that was an eye opener
uh... hesitate to say the price tag but it's it's wild
what for a family of three
uh... what health insurance is and it's not as good as health insurance as they had at
microsoft by a long shot
so in the u.s.
in the u.s. exactly in the u.s. and and that's a... well everybody else that's part of your...
so it's a hindrance it's a weight
on the on the independent community that is actually very real and I think it's going to be
it's going to be real for all americans at some point but
It's in it. I know for a fact that that weighs on people's decisions whether to go indie or not in a negative sense
Right. No, absolutely. It's certainly more
expensive to be in the but also can be more rewarding in its
and last times effort you know I was I was thinking about starting off this
a session with the line is
in the just another word employed because
certainly in my case yeah you know there have been times that I've been working
anything and then
I got reordered out or it was just time to go
and like it was like I had anything to go to so
well guess I'm in back to be in India yet so it's interesting that way
I was just going to add one thing.
One of the strategies I employ, since so much of my income
does go to medical insurance, is I
will see what I need for that particular project
and then buy accordingly a lot of times.
And then, of course, use that for tax write-offs as well.
And then look at where I'm at in the middle of the year,
like August, do I have to spend more money?
And if I do, I buy more equipment.
And then again in November, December,
especially Black Friday, all the plug-in sales.
That's right.
what can I buy at half off or whatever?
And so I do that and that helps.
Or you can also share with other indies sometimes,
like sound library, well we're not supposed to do it,
but everybody does it.
Trade sounds and maybe borrow a microphone
instead of buying it if you're not gonna use it a lot
and that kind of stuff helps too.
Cool.
Next big topic, power.
Advantages and disadvantages of being an employee or a contractor when managing office politics.
Now, we all know that politics and selling your job and telling people what you're doing
and convincing them to buy in on it is at least 50% of the job, if not more.
A lot of times I say, you know, doing the job is only half of it.
It's like everything else is part of it, even when you're an employee or a contractor.
But if you're a contractor, you tend to be able to sidestep a
lot of stuff.
You also don't have to go to so many meetings.
And even when you do go to meetings, a lot of times you're
on Google video chat.
And so you can kind of put that there.
And you can just mute your device.
And you can go do all your other stuff.
And you can continue doing stuff.
But if you're in the room, you have to be part of the thing,
even when you don't agree with what's
happening or whatever.
It can be.
a little more, the problem has become more important, I think, when you're in-house and
when you're an employee or when you're a contractor.
Agree?
Disagree?
Yeah, I mean, like, I think it's important to make sure that you're as close as possible
to whoever your representative is.
Maybe it's the audio director, maybe it's a music supervisor, but try to be not only
close professionally, but in, you know, almost like a personal level so that they're really
fighting for you.
Because it is a struggle, you know, everyone has their opinions, especially with something
like music.
One example actually, I was the composer and music supervisor for a game called Star Wars First Assault.
And for that one, we budgeted, it was a 75 minute score.
And I looked at the game and I realized this is multiplayer only.
And we wanted to have a feel and a vibe and a story to it, but there's no single player.
So I basically said, all right, well, 15 minutes of the music
will be just main themes, just things for the opening menu
and just a whole playlist of that.
I don't think I ever would have gotten away with that
if I were out of house.
Right.
Number one, it was me making the decisions.
I could do almost whatever the hell I want.
Also, it was easy to just put it in the game before it's live recorded,
before it cost anyone anything.
Put it in, show people where my mind was at, and get their buy-in on it.
You've done that a bunch.
One of the, again, another huge advantage and why I have gone in-house so that I could
get, I mentioned earlier, leverage.
You say the word power, but it's more about that leverage and being that advocate inside
the corporation.
That has to exist no matter whether you're out or in.
If you're a freelancer, you know the person who has that leverage.
You're working with an audio director, hopefully, who has, as an independent, who has that upstream
know-how of the corporate environment and can get the buy-in for audio.
you know, I got good at that and that was to my advantage and I was able to, you know,
allow creative people, including myself, to do creative things.
So that's its own thing and you can only do that really from within, so to the nth degree
at least.
Well, and what you get when you sign up for that in-house is a myriad of things that
mean nothing to someone outside the fence.
So you don't have an investment in the company
and their success or failure so much.
You definitely have a commitment to the product
and your contribution and its success,
but you're not rounding up at the company meeting
to hear financial reports about how the company's doing.
And that's not woven into the fabric of every conversation
with every coworker that you have about the,
morale or temperature necessary
Necessarily on a daily basis right and so when you're outside the fence you're like
Rock I can do this all and you don't have to deflect the political business that goes on in-house
with with good cover good leadership in the in-house the
The freelance folks can really be streamlined and efficient.
And that's key to a good pipeline.
I don't want to embarrass you, but I lived in awe of Guy when
I was working at Microsoft, because he got shit done.
And I couldn't, personally in my own group, I couldn't get
anything done.
I couldn't get anybody to listen to a damn word I was
saying, it was very frustrating.
But you started an initiative about plug-in initiatives.
Yeah, DSPs, yeah.
I was in the buy and boom, boom, boom.
I'm like, how did you do that?
Oh my God.
Let me add one more thing.
Guy is a manager.
deflected political bullshit for the team that wasn't important.
And so he was the shit shield that basically deflected things that were really not a concern
on a daily basis, right?
He was a good filter, but also, you know, a transparent communicator of things that
would have an effect.
Right. That person, whoever it is, has to have the best creative goals of the game and the company in mind.
And that's the key role of any audio director, particularly at a sizable developer or publisher.
You know, one thing you were talking about, though, about dealing with different audio people,
you know, for me, a lot of times I've been the only audio guy there.
The people I'm dealing with are managers and engineers and other people who don't really understand audio at all.
And the political battle tends to be, believe me, I know what I'm talking about and trying
to sell the idea of yes, this is the way we want to do it.
Even if it's at odds with, well, that means the engineer has to do a bunch of stuff and
I'll have to set my schedule and I'll have time for blah, blah, blah.
And dealing with those kinds of political issues.
Again, it's much, it's doable in-house.
As a contractor, you can't reassign the engineers.
Here, you need to do this for me,
and it's gonna take you a week,
and, you know, as a contractor, you can't do that.
But as in-house, you can go to that guy's manager,
you can go to your manager, you can go to his manager,
et cetera, et cetera, to get things done.
You know, Karen, you and I were also talking
about the different shades of corporate.
This is kind of where this comes in,
where I'm hoping.
that more and more as an independence, we can do more of that.
You know, have more of this creative state.
As teams become more pick up ball games to get a game done, it looks a little more like
a, I hate to say it, but more of like how a movie gets done.
And there might be more of that.
And in that case, there might be less bifurcation between corporate and, but the indie might
be able to have more input in.
technical say for example.
Right, like a virtual audio department?
Yeah.
As it builds with smaller teams,
multiple contractors working together
with like a developer possibly.
The more they let us into their code base
to do stuff in Unreal and Unity at that level
and script in there.
We're working by the week or by the day or by the hour
and that's a different ball game.
Yeah, I think the model of, you know, the contractors out of
house and all they're, you know, not here, and we don't need to
tell them that it's starting to go away, thank goodness. Because
so many times I've had to fight to find things out that I'm
like, well, what, we don't have the latest animations like you
did, you know what, this changed a week ago, we didn't get them.
Like, yeah, I'm often the one that's doing the tracking for
the client, I find, and I was like, well, I shouldn't be
doing this. But I do it because I'm protecting myself and the
deadlines and my deliveries, and I want them to be happy.
But those are services now we can offer.
That is true.
So we should start turn that around.
Right.
And as independents and say, well, we have a little fee for that.
Yes.
I'm your producer.
Yeah, I caught your producer.
Uh-huh.
Cool.
OK.
Final topic, hashtag game audio.
Ways you can contribute to the game audio community as an employee
and as a contractor.
Damian here is the game audio community in some ways.
And the hashtag Game Audio or hashtag Game Audio GDC is a way that we can communicate
about issues in the industry and what's going on.
How does being in-house or a contractor help or hinder that process?
Because you've been both.
Yeah, I mean, I guess it ultimately comes down to that little disclaimer that people put into their profiles that says something to the effect that these are my personal views and do not represent those of my employer.
When you are your own employer, you don't need that disclaimer, right?
Otherwise, you are...
you have a heightened awareness of what is appropriate for you to share and there's just
a little more focus on that. So that's the first thing I can think of.
I think there is a difference on some levels. Not in terms of participation, in fact there's
strengths and weaknesses, but that for certain.
When you're with a corporation, whether they're, and every place I've been has been very open
about letting me speak, letting me blog, even in creative projects.
But you're still wearing that hat when you come out.
So when I was at Microsoft, I was a little bit cautious about behavior and things I say
just because I'm representing a large corporation.
And now I can go, yay.
and do anything.
But the advantage, though, is you represent a big
corporation, and you can actually push initiatives and
carry a little bit of sway with certain things.
So there's good on both sides.
I'm going to tell one, I hope I don't embarrass you, Guy
Whitmore story, where when I was an independent, and I used
to write this thing called the Annoying Audio Blog, which was
a series of articles designed to be kind of about as
outrageous as possible about audio topics.
and I had gone to a conference and listened to a bunch of the new games that were out
and I wrote this rant about why is it that we have these humongous machines with hundreds
of tracks and all the games still sound like 1950s gladiator music and the same Sturm und
Drang and full choir I've always heard.
And I published this, and it caused a little bit of a stir.
At one point, I think actually at the barbecue, a guy took me
aside and goes, you know that thing you wrote?
I'm glad you said that, because I can't say that.
When he was at Microsoft.
But I don't think being in-house or freelance, as far
as community participation goes, maybe in a soft
environment, not necessarily the hard black and white of
the online experience.
I don't feel like having bounced across those barriers in the past years has really changed
the way that I approach community from a grassroots level.
And if anything, like you mentioned there,
there's a even greater responsibility and or power
that comes from having a position in-house
that you can maybe leverage towards, you know,
space or food budget or, you know,
connections with other studios, you know,
towards trying to bring community together.
And so at the same time, when you're freelance, wow, you
might have more time to really pull together things and bring
a more diverse experience to whatever community you're
participating in.
And so you have a little bit of a balance there between those.
Yeah, one thing that Damian and I were talking about kind of offline was that when you're
freelance there's certainly a lot of benefits to being very active in the greater game audio
community.
Right.
Whereas when you're in-house, you're collecting a check no matter what, there's a danger of
becoming comfortable.
Yes.
I'm glad you brought that up.
Yeah, you, well, I mean, you guys can expand on this, but basically the idea is that, you
know, you have your job, you do your job well, you'll keep your job, hopefully.
Thanks.
you know, why not go home?
And why go to the extra effort of, you know,
throwing events and participating in the community?
And it's valid.
But my take on it is that you have more potential,
in my opinion, you know, you have a little bit more power.
I wouldn't necessarily say responsibility
because it's not for everyone, and I understand,
but when you are connected to a company,
There's more opportunities for you to give back I think and once again I really have to highlight both
PopCap and ArenaNet for opening their doors and actually a bunch of different Seattle companies.
We have a series of lectures and meetups at the various studios, Bungie as well, 343 I think,
where they've just invited anyone in the Seattle Game Audio Group to just come.
and give a lecture and hang out and there's often like food and it's just been a wonderful
community that has grown out of this because they didn't become too comfortable and just
kind of nine to five it.
Well, and if you're a freelancer on the other side of it, you've got a super vested interest,
right?
Hey, if you put a flag on the moon for community in your town, like all of a sudden people
know you.
You're the person who is like putting it on the map for people to like get down and you
know share their experience or share their knowledge or you're the person who is bringing
them to a studio and allowing for educational opportunity and as a freelancer, wow.
that kind of thing is great, right? And so you have a great
opportunity there maybe with the addition of the extra time you
might have in between things to really do something positive
that has a mutually beneficial kind of plus to it.
I was just going to say, I find that as a freelancer it's essential to be more involved
in different organizations, go to conferences, go to meetups.
I'm from L.A. and there's just always something going on.
I could spend my entire week going to different VR events.
conferences and stuff I have to actually pick and choose because it can get a little overwhelming.
But that's very been very essential for me because I get most of my work from either people that know
me or referrals or people I meet in person at different conferences and stuff so it's been
very important. You know I'd like to yeah pick up on that and what you were saying about the
complacency thing because what I found as someone if there's advice I would give to people kind of
traversing this in and out thing is treat
your corporate job, as if you were an indie, needing to both
grow both your skills and the people you're meeting.
You don't have the for sale sign-up, but you're active,
and you're not stagnating professionally either.
You're actively seeking out the latest and greatest things.
What happens in a corporate setting, you're often asked to focus on a specific thing.
And it's easy just to tunnel vision in, whether it's management,
whether it's a particular type of area in your sound design work.
And you've got to remember, bring the head up and go look broader and keep it active.
Because if something comes along like a layoff, hmm,
and you find yourself adrift in the world...
If you've been engaging with community,
you might have your finger on the pulse of what's next.
Yeah, it's all about the people.
That's my motto.
And on that note, that's a great ending for that one.
That was the topics I have.
We'd like to take some questions from the audience.
If anybody wants to ask about corporate and or indie
or anything else at all, come up to the mic
and state your purpose.
Hello, hello. Thank you for that talk. I was a little late in the beginning. I got here late. I apologize for that.
But if you haven't already discussed it, what are some, I guess, techniques in giving direction to sound designers
who are providing you with sounds in the way that you want to implement them?
Sometimes I have trouble with giving that direction, and then I get the sounds, and I'm like, oh, it's not the, like, I want to create different random containers, and, you know, stuff like that.
So the question is, if you're in-house, how do you deal with contractors giving you the sounds you want?
Sure, yeah, yeah.
I have to repeat that.
Yes.
I'd love to just jump in on that real quick, because my...
thought was to, I'm the one trying to change a culture from within to make the people I
work with out of house to be more part of the team. So for instance, allowing source
control if possible or at least being able to create a wise work unit so that the work
is more fully integrated as it comes in. That's just one of my personal preferences. And then
you know what you're getting. They're hearing, the intention is already more interlocked.
that note, I would say sure, templatize that stuff for folks
outside the house even. Let me hand you a work unit or a FEV.
And this is the
this is the format, shovel your content into these buckets and
then re-deliver the whole kit and caboodle, right? But I think
I might have heard something else in that question about
like communication of, you know, creative.
Yeah, like how to deliver what formats delivered, do I want
one shots, do I want loops, is this animation going to be, do
I want to
bespoke animation, you know, three second or do I want like
three one seconds to put in it, you know, stuff like that.
Sure. Communicating elemental systems components, right? And
that's a tough one. I would say that you, the place I would
start is establishing the vocabulary. You're going to come
to a contractor with
with the idea, right?
And you're going to have a language that would be easy
for you to describe that.
But I think there's a danger in just jumping to it without
making sure that the words that you use mean the same.
as what they hear when you use those words.
And so I guess it's establishing that vocabulary so that,
and establishing it early, right?
Whether that's a style guide kind of thing
where you talk about, you know, things that it...
that explain the aesthetic or whether it's the technical side
of it when you say one shot or when you say surface only
material sound, you know, or what is an appropriate amount of
silence at the end of a wave file or attack, you know, just
again, simplify a vocabulary that you can agree on.
And just one thing to add to that, naming conventions and having them be really well thought out are like a gift from God.
I mean you can be as anal as you want and as a freelancer, I love that.
Because it just makes sure that there's no confusion later on and you can easily implement stuff in your game
and it just works and there's no, there's no, I think that almost would solve a lot of these issues with vocabulary.
Is it just me or does every studio call cutscene the different thing?
Yes, there's vignettes, there's cutscenes, there's cinematics,
and then there's in-game versus pre-rendered.
I mean, it's mind-boggling.
My favorite?
Polygonal cutscenes.
Or polycuts.
I was going to say a lot of times projects I work on, sometimes it's as primitive as
Google Docs, but that helps just to have everything mapped out on a spreadsheet with what like . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
you know, the naming convention is, and if it's looping or not
looping, and like the categories of all the sounds and the
material types and everything like, because then if there's
any question and it's in your contractors are working and it's
two in the morning, they can keep going. And they don't, you
know, it's good to have stuff written down. That's so much
work. Yeah. And then they can track, you know, also, if they
sent the sound or what, you know, the feedback and all of
that, if they're waiting for feedback, and it just it gets
maybe not in the same document, but
And I feel like the level of aptitude should be really high
right now out there with people that are working outside the
fence, right?
So that if you do create a prototype system in a
middleware tool that's extensible, you should be able
to hand that to them.
They should be able to read the tea leaves of it and
understand kind of at a glance what you're doing.
So I feel like that is an ecstasy of communication if
you can just.
give them that implementation.
Absolutely.
Thank you.
Hello.
Thank you for being here and sharing your collective
wisdom.
So in a corporate job, it seems like you have a lot of
extrinsic motivation to keep doing your job, because or
else people will be mad at you and whatnot.
And same thing if you're actively working on a project when you're indie.
But I'm curious to hear about how you go about keeping yourself motivated to keep hustling
when maybe it's sort of a dry spell and there aren't as many projects going on,
but you need to keep working and doing your thing anyways.
Just curious to hear your thoughts on that.
Motivation from a corporate and an indie point of view.
Sure.
I think it's...
Every...
good managers obligation to make sure that their work, the workforce, the people working
for them have something that they're doing at all times, all times, not just down times,
that is inspiring to them.
I have the one thing rule.
Sometimes it's a project I call the one thing rule,
that everybody who was working for me had something
that they were like into.
And whether it was something directly related to a project
we were working on, and usually that was the case,
it's like, I want to do this for this project.
Great, that helps us.
And you get to do the one thing or two things, right?
So you're always doing something that's keeping you
in a growth mindset.
That's the other side.
Make sure they're always doing something
where they're learning something.
And learning something that they want to learn,
even if it's not directly related to their project.
Right. And as an indie, same deal. More so. So, like, there have been times when I've been working
on a project and it's a bunch of work from Google, and then there was like this lull before, you know,
I wasn't sure what the next thing was going to be, but there was this lull. And so instead of
trying to generate work, I just started doing things that I wanted to do. I started getting
more into programming. I built a little game that demonstrated this, uh...
interactive audio idea that I hadn't seen any place else and I just wanted to
demonstrate it so I could show it to people and that just that wasn't
generating any money for me but it was certainly
flexing my programming skills, showing that I knew what was happening in the interactive
audio world, showing that I was innovative and had some creativity involved, and those
apps that I then published helped me get the next gig.
And so, you know, it's not, particularly when you're freelance, there is no downtime.
If you're not always working all the time, you should be.
Right, it's a good time to do some marketing too, like go do lunch meetings and more conferences
and more meetups and things like that if you have downtime.
Because that also will help, I know for me, I get kind of isolated working mostly now
from my home studio, so it's really like a big boost to my creativity and motivation
to go and meet people and talk about what's happening with what they're working on and
just kind of get plugged in again.
kind of like what's happening right now i told my clients i am unavailable this
week and doing this
and uh...
and i think marketing extends to not only
let's say phone calls emails and meetups but also
blog posts tutorial videos
rocking your resume
there's there's a whole slew of marketing
that I would maybe consider soft marketing, where it's more like, you know, trying to
establish you and your discipline or your company as someone who knows something, I guess.
And that kind of marketing can go a long way towards, oh, eventuality of a gig at some point.
Yes, so just two quick things. One, I would say keep a diary of side projects that you want to do, but you have absolutely no time to do so.
I love Trello. I have it on my phone and my computer and everything. And whenever I have any idea of I would love to do this, but I don't have time, just do that.
You will never go drive because you'll always have something to do. And secondly, and this is very specific.
I don't know if you had a chance to see this, but Anton Voltec from Guerrilla had a wonderful
talk where he basically outlined three different stages of development.
I know the generic industry definition is, you know, you're in crunch mode and you're
in whatever, but he called them waves.
Basically, he would say, OK, well, you'll be before the wave,
which is when things are not so busy.
And he had a great list of things that you can do.
I think they're applied both to freelance and corporate, things
you can do when you're not so busy,
but that'll help you when you're in the wave,
and you're so busy that you're just, OK, it's
time to just work on this and not worry too much
about process, because there's no time to deal with that.
And then after the wave, where it's basically boiled down
to analyzing.
how you were working during crunch mode or whatever you
want to call it and trying to fix things that maybe went
wrong or work flow issues or whatever it ends up being. I
would definitely check that out in the vault whenever it comes
up.
Yeah, exactly. It's very prescient here. And the last
thing I'll just add to that is that if you're in house, like
maybe you're in production, you don't have time to experiment
with things, but you're going to be in that wave situation. And
I would say that probably the thing that
one should always return to in those times of question over what is next or what should
be done is advocacy. Like reaching out to other disciplines and departments in-house
and firming up relationships or creating new relationships that can then continue to carry
you through that production process.
Thanks. I thoroughly enjoyed this and I agree about Anton's talk. That was really great.
I want to revisit it even though I've got it memorized and repeating in my head. My
question is I came from corporate, I've gone freelance, and I'm now sort of considering
going back in-house. And I've come to really love my work-life balance and the freedom
that I'm able to create.
because as creatives it's sort of you have your specific zones during the day
where you find I am in it and it's like those are your you make those your
untouchables and you get so much done. I guess my question is related to some of
the topics you brought up in terms of
politics and then maintaining that work-life balance because that's, I guess, a fear of
mine is going in-house and losing a bit of that.
So what would be your
advice to question and inquire about both the current manager's ability to deflect politics
as well as the ability to manage your work-life balance and not be sort of slaved to that
crunch or burnout.
So the question being work-life balance from a corporate point of view.
I'm a little bit off the beaten path in that I don't believe there is such a thing.
I think work is life, is life is work, and it's all the same stuff to me.
I don't have a wife and kids or, you know, other stuff I do besides.
Basically, if I'm not working, I'm not living.
And in a corporate situation, even then, I always try to do...
I work from this time to this time, and when I'm in this mode I'm in that, and then afterwards
I'm doing something else, just even kind of let my brain decompress from what was happening
during that time.
I tend to try and do that even when I'm freelance, so that the definition of work
And also, I'm working now.
This is my work time.
And then everything else I do is life, but some of it is
even kind of I'm not working so that I can go back to work
better kind of thing.
But that's just me.
I'm not.
It's interesting that you kind of are more wary of the
corporate workplace for work-life balance.
And I think a lot of indie people would argue that that's
a more dangerous place for work-life balance.
In corporate, you don't really.
have a choice necessarily i mean it's it's just it kind of is what it is
well that you can you can do your best but at a certain point it it might be a
situation where if you just find that a studio is being kind of toxic
where yeah you know making people stay till midnight or whatever then
maybe it's time to leave
I would say you do have a choice in some ways.
Remember, you're interviewing the corporation as well as
they're interviewing you.
And you have to kind of become aware of what that culture is
known for and what it's like.
And there's ways to find out.
That's exactly what I'm asking for, is what's the best ways
to kind of find that out.
To talk to other people who work there.
And then actually, and you don't have to do this during
an interview, it's kind of awkward.
But you do your own intel from colleagues.
But then after you get a job, then say, well, what is this
like before I decide?
Now it's my turn to say, what can I make this?
I'll share in-house experience just very briefly because ArenaNet is very public about their
work-life balance.
And so this was something that they were very forthcoming about and definitely something
I'm concerned about as someone who's in-house.
And again, I think when you find a company who's willing to say, yeah, work-life balance,
we get it, right?
I think you've found a mature company that's willing to accept responsibility for that.
and what that means for a schedule and for a culture.
So I would say demand it.
We are out of time.
Thank you all so much.
I want to thank our panelists.