I am Derek. And I made a little freeware PC game called
Spelunky and it turned into a much bigger XBLA game by the
same name.
And when I think about how that happened, how I started with
this tiny little game and how it became something so much bigger,
I'm still pretty amazed. It still feels pretty incredible.
But in this talk we're going to try to make some sense of it.
So I started working on Spelunky pretty soon after I finished
Aquaria with Alakaloka. And that was a game that we released on
December 2007.
And it was, the project took us over two years,
and it was a really intense and difficult development
as I think Alec would attest to also.
It was about as stressful as it was wonderful.
So after that, I really wanted to work
on something a lot lighter,
something small and kind of fluffy.
And it's kind of ironic because Spelunky's now
turned into a bit of a monster itself.
But when I think about it,
with all of my big projects, and those are Eternal Daughter,
Aquaria, and Spelunky XBLA, those games all took at least
two years to make. Between all those projects, I always made a
lot of small games and released them. And when I think about it,
those small games always led to the bigger ones, whether
indirectly or directly. So, for example, with I'm OK, working on
that is how I met Alec, and that eventually led to Aquaria. And
all the small games that I made before Eternal Daughter,
you know, they got progressively bigger and they gave me the
confidence to do a project of that magnitude. Spelunky, the
freeware version, of course, led to Spelunky XBLA. So small games
led to bigger games. And Spelunky itself I considered,
the freeware version, I consider it to be really like a refined
prototype. And that refined prototype came from a number of
even smaller prototypes that I never finished.
So when I approach prototyping, I like to treat it like
drawing. You know, with drawing, if I want to come up with an
idea for something to draw, I'll just pick up my sketchbook and a
pen and I'll just start doodling all over the page. And I'm not
concerned about trying to create something that's going to win
IGF or create something that's going to make a million dollars
or even create something that is going to make people like me or
that people are going to approve of. The key, I think, is really
just to zone in on
what I'm enjoying at the time, things that I'm interested in.
And when it comes to making games, tools, game making
programs like Game Maker for some people it's Unity, for
some people it's Flash and libraries and frameworks like
Flash Punk and Flixel, those are like the equivalent of a
sketchbook for me because it lets me get my ideas out very
easily. So this is, these are screen shots from the
a roguelike prototype that I started working on before
Spelunky. And the goal for this prototype was really just to
have fun. I had a lot of fun making the graphics and I was
trying to boil down the essence of roguelikes into something
that was just simple and fun to play. And if you're not
familiar with roguelikes, they're dungeon crawlers that
have random level generation, permanent death and a lot of
variation. And it's a really compelling genre.
Because those three things really make the game very
exciting and infinitely replayable. And even though it's
a pretty niche genre, it's had a lot of influence on a lot of
really popular games like Diablo, Minecraft, and ToeJam
and Earl. I really love that game. Those games are all based
on rogue legs. I think the reason why they're still niche
is because they haven't really advanced in terms of their
interface beyond the original rogue game.
which is just, which was just ASCII graphics basically.
On the other hand, platform games is, you know,
they're a really well understood and well loved genre.
They're action based, they require reflexes
and precision timing and memorization of the levels.
And I think, you know, everyone is pretty intimately
familiar with platform games.
So here are a couple of screenshots from just,
really simple platform games that I was working on at the
same time that I was making those roguelike prototypes. If
you look carefully, you can kind of see some little elements
actually made their way into Spelunky freeware. So, you know,
working on platformers and working on roguelikes at the
same time, working on these small prototypes, it really
didn't get very far. I came up with the idea of
combining the aspects of roguelikes that I really liked
that I thought were really compelling, the random level
generation, the permanent death, the variation, the fact that
you get into these unscripted situations that are really fun
to get yourself out of. I wanted to combine that with a platform
game, you know, and I'm a big fan of that genre and as I said
before, it's a very accessible and well-known genre. I wanted
to make something that was...
new and exciting but also accessible. And the big
challenge I think between reconciling those two genres
was the level design because platform games really depend on
their levels, on their platforms and roguelikes are exciting
because they're randomly generated. So I thought I'd
quickly just go through the algorithm that I used to
generate levels in Spelunky. So each level in Spelunky really
starts with a grid of
16 rooms, four by four, just like this. And then we draw a
path from the entrance at the top of the level to an exit at
the bottom of the level. You're always going down in Spelunky
for the most part. So we generate this path and mark each
room as being part of the path. And for each room, we have a set
of template rooms that we can pick from. And what set of
templates we choose depends on the area of the game that
that the level is in and whether the room falls on a path.
So for example, you know, if we want to have,
if we need a corridor that connects to other rooms,
then we draw from a set of corridor templates
and put it in there.
And within each template,
there are these little randomized chunks that are specified.
And that kind of, it just adds variability
and more interesting...
things to these set templates and at the very end we add
monsters, treasure, traps and whatever else to kind of
complete it. And that's about it. So working on a game like
this is really fun. It's very satisfying because you can
create a lot of content with a small team. You know, if you
look at a game like Dwarf Fortress, it's essentially
programmed by one guy. It's a two-person team. And they're
making entire worlds, you know, like it's just
it's really awesome. And as a developer, it's really fun to
work this way because you're always surprised by your own
game. You know, even playing Spelunky now, like having worked
on now two different versions of the game, I'm still having fun
with it because I'm always running into things that excite
me. So it's really fun to develop. Spelunky is not the
first sort of refined prototype by any means either that turned
into
a bigger project. We see examples of this in all kinds of media. Super Meat Boy, for example,
started as the Flash, the free Flash version called Meat Boy. And Google, they've got this
thing called Google Labs, which they describe as a playground of experimental prototypes that
people can just give feedback on and, you know, if anything good comes out of it, they turn it into
a full-blown product. It's a great way to test out ideas.
And it extends even into other creative mediums like writing.
The author Haruki Murakami, in the intro to a collection of
short stories that I think is called Blind Willow Sleeping
Woman, but I might have gotten those mixed up. But anyways, in
the intro to that collection, he describes his process and he
says that right after he writes a big novel, the first thing he
does is he writes a bunch of short stories and he keeps
writing those short stories until he comes up with
inspiration for his next big novel. So making these small
prototypes and then refining them into something and
releasing them is a great way to test out ideas. It's a great way
to refresh yourself after a long draining project. It's a great
way to, you know, get that relief creative tension, you
know, and it's also just a great way to get into.
your next big project. So Chris Hecker, who I know loves to be
quoted out of context, in an interview with Edge that he did
with John Blow, he described small independent games that
don't fully reach their potential as mulch. And he said
that big, you know, big games, bigger games that reach their
full potential, he described those as trees. I really like
that analogy. But...
The way I feel about it is that you can be a mulch and a tree
person and it actually goes really well together. So if
you're someone who wants to release big games, and I really
define myself and my work by the big projects I've released, but
at the same time, working on the small games on the mulch has
allowed me and given me the opportunity to work on the big
games. So on that note, I'm going to hand it over to my
friend and partner Andy Hall. He's going to talk to you about
the XBLA version of Spelunky.
So as Derek said, my name is Andy, that's true. This is a
picture I drew of myself. I was a little bit generous with my
hair. But other than that, basically despite that, what I
mostly work on on Spelunky XBLA is the programming, although I
am helping with the other aspects as well. So I thought
I'd start with how Spelunky XBLA came to be. And basically it
all started with a man we all know and love, Jonathan Blow.
Jon was a big fan.
It took a while. You guys had a pause while you read down the list. So John actually was a big
fan of the original game and he contacted Derek and said, hey Derek, would you be interested in
doing an Xbox Live version of Spelunky? And of course Derek said yes, of course. And that kind
of got the ball rolling with the green light process with Microsoft.
The green light process was fairly easy because Derek
already had the original game to send into Microsoft. They could
play it, see what made the game fun, see what made it work, and
also they saw that the game already had a built-in
audience. There were players that were already enjoying it
and loving the game a lot. I think a lot of people, myself
included, feel tentative about releasing smaller projects that
maybe don't express the extent of what we think our abilities
are.
But I think Spelunky really shows that people will see the
game for what it is and be able to appreciate the things in the
game no matter what level it's at. And I think that the
feedback from those games helps improve the games so they'll get
even better. And, you know, the game and the ideas involved will
evolve as you work more and more on the project.
John also actually offered to let Derek use the braid engine
for Spelunky XBLA. Derek took him up on this and actually had
a very early version of the game running in the braid engine.
And that's when I came on board. We spent about a month and a
half working with the braid engine and we were having some
problems understanding some of the code. There was unneeded
features such as the timer winding which we weren't using
that were complicating matters.
And when we contacted John to ask about some parts of the code, he had moved on to other
projects and really wasn't familiar with the code anymore.
So it made it difficult to get information on what was going on.
At that point we decided that it would be best to start again with an engine from scratch.
Because we had the original game to look at, we knew the features
and scope of the engine that would be required to make it.
And we felt pretty comfortable that the two of us could handle
it. And we also liked the idea that we would be able to reuse
the code for later projects that we work on after Spelunky. So as
we're working on Spelunky, we're really treating it more as a
sequel to the original Spelunky than trying to just do an HD
remake of the game.
And this might be scary to hear, but we can't be afraid to change things from the original
game.
And this took me a little bit of time to get used to, because I love the game, and I think
it felt awkward at first, feeling free to change things in the game.
But that's the only way we can really evolve it and make it feel different and special.
This was made easier by the fact that the original game will still exist.
We're not deleting it by making the Xbox Live version.
people can still go back and play that and appreciate it for
what it is. That said, though, we don't want to break what
worked about the game. We want to improve it. So we want to
keep the complexity and interactions and things that
made it really fun to begin with. So obviously we're trying
to improve the game in all sorts of different ways. And I think
the most obvious, and I think most of you have seen a lot of
the screenshots that we've put out so far, is the art upgrade
to HD.
less obvious is that we're really working on streamlining
the controls and the interface to make it easier for players to
get into it. When I first played Spelunky, I didn't stick with it
very long on the PC. I had a little bit of trouble with the
controls and it wasn't until I kept reading on the TIG force
forums that people were raving about the game that I said, oh,
okay, I need to sink some more time into this and really
uncover what is so great about the game.
We wanted to eliminate that hurdle of the controls. So as
an example, in the original game, if you want to go into a
shop and buy something, you have to use two different buttons
just to pick up the item, just to check the price to see if you
want to, can purchase it and want to purchase it. If you do
want to purchase it, you have to hit a third button. If you don't
want to purchase it, you have to hit another two-button
combination to drop the item, and you risk hitting the
shopkeeper, who will become enraged and shoot you in the
face.
So to make the shopping experience a little more pleasant, now when you're in the shops,
if you're overlapping an item that's on sale, it will immediately pop up with the price.
And if you can buy it, there will not be that little red mark over the RB button and you
tap it and you'll immediately purchase and equip the item.
So roguelikes are founded on this idea of having tons of
different monsters and items in the game and all the different
interactions that come up between them is what makes the
game interesting and fun to play. So we're going to be
adding more of that stuff to make the complexity go up, keep
the variation of the games up so that not only is the game fun
for new players, but existing players will find new and
exciting things in the game as well.
There was one feature that was probably more requested than any
other feature from the freeware game. And we decided we had to
do it for the Xbox live version. And that is multiplayer. So...
So the game will support four player local play.
And it really fits in the kind of chaotic nature of the game.
If you're playing with someone, you're able to toss them up to
a ledge they wouldn't normally be able to reach. But if you
mess up, right, they might ricochet off the wall and fall
into the spikes. But maybe that's what you intended all
along because you want their jet pack. So basically we'll
have more information coming out about the different multiplayer
modes as we get closer to release.
So in conclusion, the freeware game really acted as our design
document in making the Xbox Live version. And it made it easy
for me as the programmer because I didn't always have to contact
Derek about small details with the game. I would just refer to
the original design and make it function in the same way. I also
used the Spelunky wiki a bunch for everything from finding out
how much the different gems cost to the different interactions
with monsters. And I think Spelunky really shows that.
There's more benefits to releasing these games than I think people realize.
And that even though you have these small, polished games that you think kind of are
these small projects, they really can go hand in hand with the larger commercial projects
and grow into something really cool.
So I think if we can take some questions now, that would be great.
Thank you.
I have a very simple question, actually. I was just wondering
how long did the original Spelunky take to make from like
once you got like, oh, I know what I'm doing to and compare
that to how long is the current Spelunky taking?
I started working on the first version of Spelunky like the
summer of 2008. And I think I released version 1.0, like
I don't even remember, actually. When I first released the game,
it was like version 0.6 or something, and I kept working on
it for a while, and I think I ended up releasing a version 1.0.
It probably took me like a year and a half for the original
freeware game to get it to 1.0, and this version is probably
going to take around two years. So it's actually pretty similar
for the first version of the game and the XBLA version.
I think that's because the first version involved a lot of
design work, which can be really difficult and you have to kind
of like go back and forth a lot. But the XBLA version is just a
lot of like, you know, there's a lot more technical work and
stuff like that. So it ends up evening out a bit, actually.
All right. Thanks.
make more sense to bug you about it in front of 500 people.
So when you talk about Spelunky and your development process,
it all sounds very loose, right?
I mean, you're sort of creating these systems that
are going to procedurally generate all sorts of stuff
that you can't even imagine what the final layout is going
to be like and so on, right?
And you're surprising yourself every time you play.
But if you go and study Spelunky like I have,
there's a lot of very tight.
things that happen in terms of the design. The reason you want
to play just one more time and you end up playing 100 times in
a given evening is because it seems like there were decisions
made about how rare certain things are, how likely you are
to see a damsel, how likely you are to find a shop with a
shotgun just waiting there to blast the owner with. And it
doesn't just seem like just anything goes, like just throw
all these random things together. It seems like there's
so many tight game design things that come in there. How did you
come up with that stuff? Were you conscious of it or did it
just kind of roll out of the procedurality and that kind of
thing?
You know, I got to say it wasn't too strictly planned a lot of
that stuff. Like, for example, how often does a certain thing
appear every time? I kind of just went with what felt right,
you know? One out of ten or something like that. And it
tended to work. You know, I just tried it and it would seem to
work.
you make decisions at a certain point where you tested it and
found like, oh, God, you know, having a damsel come 50% of the
time is too much and I'm going to tweak it down because it
feels like it's ‑‑ I want it to be more rare than that. Did
you make decisions like that at certain points when you were
testing?
I did, but I can't say that I remember anything that was so
significant that I added it and then it was just completely
broken the first time around. I think part ‑‑ one of the
things that helps is just having ‑‑
So many things going on and not having any one thing kind of
dominate everything else so that, you know, even if the
formulas aren't completely focused test, tested to a T or
anything like that, it still feels really compelling.
Right.
So I guess we just have to chalk it up to genius.
I wouldn't say that.
I didn't say that.
So.
In fact, in a lot of ways I feel like it's maybe a lack of genius
that helps you come up with solutions for some of these
things. Like for the level generation, I really just tried
to do what was simplest and what seemed like the most just brute
force way to make a level that worked. So I'm no genius, quote
Derek Yu.
Could you talk a little bit about the production
requirements for the XBLA version? Is it just the two of
you?
Yeah, it's just the two of us. And we have dev kits. And Andy
actually lives in Connecticut, so we usually, you know, he'll
come out here and we'll jam together for like a couple weeks
at a time. But usually we just work over Google video chat and
pass code back and forth. I think
I'd be pretty embarrassed to actually go through our entire
production process because it's pretty ghetto fabulous.
So definitely got our indie cred going on.
Do you guys have to worry about, you know, like marketing
and PR of this or are you kind of relying on the community?
That is something I worry about and it's something I worry
about because it's honestly something that I'm not that
interested in when it comes to.
You know, I can't say that I'm really passionate about marketing at all.
I like talking about my game and I'm really enthusiastic about working on it, but I'm
just – my personality, you know, I don't know, my personality, I'm just not – I
kind of – when I'm working on games, I kind of really like to put my nose to the
grindstone and actually kind of – my inclination, I think, is to really just
hideout. So I am worried about marketing and we're trying to
think of things to do that fit our personality and our fun. But
it's something that we really have to work on, I think.
Yeah, I mean, I come from a more traditional product company. I
was a toy designer for a while. Five years. For five years. Five
long years.
But I, when we're talking about how we're going to promote the
game, I'm very much in line with traditional ways of marketing
it. And, you know, suggesting things, I mean, I see Derek's
side of it, that, you know, we do want it to fit the aspect of
the game, you know, kind of the feel of our team and you don't
want to kind of do something that's not in line with the
game. But at the same time, we don't want to be too
understated as well. So I think we're still trying to find that
balance.
I do want to mention that there's a third person on our
team and that's our musician Eric who is in Norway right now.
He runs the pause indie music, indie game music label. So
anyways, want to put that out there. I think we got one more
question. In the last few years there seems like there's been a
resurgence in the more difficult games like Spelunky and Demon
Souls, that sort of thing.
What do you think has caused this resurgence and how do you
balance like difficulty versus frustration in your game?
Right. I mean, I think it goes back and forth. So, you know,
it feels like games are getting too casual. You hear people
really complaining about not having games that they can
really enjoy. And I think the key to making a challenging game
that's not frustrating is just to
give the player all the tools that they need to overcome the
challenge and never make it the game's fault that they lost,
essentially. So, you know, with games like roguelikes, one of
the things that's so fun about them is that you have all of
these tools at your disposal. You never know when you could
get into a situation where, you know, I don't know, you're
surrounded by monsters and all of a sudden you have to use
a tin of goblin meat to get yourself out of it and you feel
really smart about it. Roguelikes give you lots of
those tools so even though they're really tough, it's
always fun. And I think that's it. So thank you very much.
Thank you.
<p
begin="00.0333.333.333"><p