Center. Center.
Sound hardware initialized.
This program will install command and conquer to the following directory.
If you wish to install to another directory and or drive, please type it in below.
Thank you.
Installing. Please stand by. While you are waiting, please fill out your registration card and send it in.
For last minute changes and notes, please examine the README file.
Installation complete.
We're going to have to act, if we want to live in a different world.
All right.
I need my mic, I think.
So as Frank said, everybody, Frank Lepacki, one more time.
Woo!
Welcome to the C&C Classic Game Postmortem.
I got to tell you, I knew that was going
to be really hard to follow.
But at 10 o'clock in the morning on Thursday,
we've got to wake everybody up a little bit.
Excited.
Plus, we want everybody in the other rooms to go,
what the hell is going on in there?
So.
Oh.
You know, I'm Lewis Castle.
I'm the co-founder of Westwood Studios, the company that
created Command & Conquer.
And every year I'm on the game developers, the board, the
conference board.
And every year we talk about doing classic postmortems.
We talk about C&C.
And the problem that I always have with C&C is that we've
got some folks that aren't in the games industry anymore.
And we've got other folks that just don't want to be on stage
and talk about it.
They're really important and pivotal.
to command and conquer.
And so I just always said, no, I just really don't think it's right.
But this year, and kind of serendipitously, I finally just said, you know what?
I have a way of doing this.
I figured it out.
What we're just going to do is we're going to go record all of these folks, the ones
that we can, video and audio, and we'll put it all together into something, and that'll
work.
So it's a different format.
You guys probably never see a GDC talk like this.
If I had proposed it to myself, I'd probably refuse it,
because it's too many people, too complicated,
and really a live guitar.
That's crazy.
So on the stage, myself, Louis Castle,
Frank Lepake, we've already talked about.
We have Steve Weatherill, who's the technical director
for Command & Conquer, and Eric Yeo, who is a lead designer.
So as I already said, this is going
to be a little bit of a different format for a talk.
Like most great games, Command & Conquer,
it really wasn't made by any one person.
And we have this cult of personality
that we build in our games industry around our heroes.
And there are certainly some creative directors
that without them, the games could never be made.
But we can't forget the fact that so many people,
so many people like everybody in this audience,
put their hearts and souls into the products that we build.
And it's when all that stuff comes together,
and so many people put it together, that it makes it work.
So these are the people that I was able to both con into putting themselves on video for me
and get them to do a recording.
And I will point out right on the front, I recorded this all in Frank's little casita,
which is like an audio recording booth.
So this is not professional video.
This is very much like Command and Conquer.
It's just a bunch of people who are passionate, just throwing something together
to try to entertain people.
So I hope that you appreciate the authenticity of it and, you know, don't review it badly
because the AV production is not terribly great.
But it's more important about what people are saying.
So on the video, you're going to have Brett Sperry, who's the co-founder of Westwood Studios,
and he's definitely the creative director behind Command & Conquer.
Joe Koukun, who played Kane, who many people may not realize was actually a video director
also.
So he actually cast.
and directed all the talent.
Adele Castillo, who is our producer,
Eric Gutch, one of the many artists
that contributed to the videos,
Maria Delmar-McCready-Legg,
who is the engineer
who did all the introduction sequences
to all of the Command & Conquer games, all the way up to Renegade.
I thought it was really cool to get her on there.
And Ted Morris, who was our first community manager,
Bill Randolph, who was one of our lead designer or lead
coders, and then Kaya Montgomery,
who was Kaya Hunsinger at the time, who was the voice of Eva.
So that's who you're going to hear from today.
Again, this many people in a talk,
I'm going to be moving pretty quickly
because there's a lot to get through.
So I guess without further, oh, sorry,
I don't forget this too.
That actually is just a very, very small sample
of all the people that contributed to Command & Conquer.
In fact, these are the credits, the official credits
from the original, just the development team
for Command & Conquer.
And this is 1995 when many games
were only made by four or five people.
So it was quite a large group of people.
names are the ones that you're actually going to be hearing from today.
So you can see it's just a small sample.
And I would really be remiss.
I hope they're watching or they'll watch it on the vault.
If I didn't thank all the folks at Virgin
for from a series of things, maybe we can get to in the Q&A.
Virgin put so much effort behind.
the Westwood games, especially Command & Conquer, and without all the effort they put into it,
I don't know that any of you would be here today and I don't know that it would have
been a success.
It's impossible to tell because when so many people contribute so much, how do you sort
it all out?
It's just like a big bowl of spaghetti.
That's how I've always felt about it.
You'll see that I'm not in the credits actually,
although I did a lot of stuff on the compression
and a bunch of other things.
At that time I was working on, oh gosh,
Lion King and Blade Runner and Monopoly
and a bunch of other stuff too.
There's a bunch of folks in the front row here
that contributed to Command & Conquer
but also not in the credits.
So it's actually only a small sampling
of the people that were kind of on it
from the beginning all the way to the end
and really drove the vision of the game.
So I guess without further ado, let's hear it from Eva.
Tell us what inspired Command & Conquer.
Command & Conquer came about as a result of years and years
of me thinking about what kind of game I wanted to do next,
and a little bit of the zeitgeist,
the spirit of the time, and also a kind of a bet
that I made with another industry executive about.
real-time strategy games.
And the basic bet went something like this.
He said, nobody wants to play strategy games.
And I said, well, no offense, but the reason
why nobody wants to play your strategy games
is because they're really, really boring
and you're not doing anything new.
You're not pulling anybody into the real meat
and the guts and the fun of what it's all about.
That's Brett Sperry, of course, the creator of Command & Conquer.
I think the next thing I would like to hear from is Frank because I don't know if you
guys have picked up on this or if you remember, but the music of Command & Conquer was like
nothing else anybody's ever heard.
So Frank, if you could tell us a little bit about what inspired the style of C&C Music
and where you got your inspiration from and what kind of guided your choices.
Yeah, so basically at the time I was 20 years old, and it was a new kind of thing.
We were technologically moving from what at the time was MIDI playback only through sound
chips and whatnot from sound cards, and we were going to streaming audio.
Command & Conquer was one of the first games to do that, so I was using synthesizers and
live guitar for the first time in a soundtrack that was going to be...
used that way. So the kickoff meeting went something like this. I got in, Paul Mudra,
who is the audio director, went into his office with Brett Sperry, and the three of us sat
around and just had a listening party, basically, with stacks of CDs, compact discs.
And we shared different music influences that we thought would be fun to include into the game.
The only problem with that was it was all over the board.
It was everything from movie soundtracks, orchestral stuff, to heavy metal, techno music, hip hop,
you know, and anything in between. Ambient, moody stuff.
So the takeaway from the meeting was, okay, well, we figured out we like a lot of these
different elements from all of these things.
Why not try to put them all together and see what sticks?
So it was a big experiment, really.
And the cool thing about this process was that I was allowed to be experimental and
have creative freedom to kind of do what I wanted with that.
So that ended up being what C&C became,
which was a variety of styles put into that game
that were all allowed to coexist together
and somehow made that environment work in that capacity.
And then the other cool thing we added to that,
of course, was the jukebox mode,
which allowed players to select which tracks
were their favorites that they wanted to go
and annihilate their enemy to.
So that was another fun tidbit.
Thanks, Frank.
And we're going to hear from Brett now a little bit more
about the Command & Conquer universe.
Just one little riff, because it's not in the presentation,
but I still remember when Brett said, hey, we've got to
have the full screen audio video for Command & Conquer.
And I was working with Steve and some other folks on the
video compression, because new technology that was built on
some stuff I had written way back in the past.
And I go, I don't know, Brett.
If you look at data entropy and the conversion rate,
there's no video codec that can play on a single-speed CD-ROM
at 44 kilohertz, full-screen audio and video.
It just doesn't exist.
And he goes, oh, Lou, you're just being lazy.
So on to Brett.
And the CNC universe was developed very, very slowly
over a long period of time.
Partly, it was created by.
fiction that I had in my brain about some kind of future world and the central
character who we call Cain and the rise of a global defense initiative as the
various armies of Earth
Countries as the order were kind of starting to fade away and there's the rise of sort of a new world order.
You have to remember this was in the late 80s and early 90s when I was thinking about all this kind of stuff.
And then working with team members and saying, well, hey, I want to do this and I want this central theme and I want this central character.
And here's this massive backstory, you know, that I've been thinking about for a long time.
And so, you know, they would contribute parts and pieces to that whole thing.
But, yeah, it took...
Like a lot of good stories and a lot of good backstories, you know, the foundation upon
which the game fiction was built on took many, many years of just quiet contemplation and
notes and thinking about how this can make sense also.
Where is the intersection between the fiction and the gameplay?
And so Eric, we'll get you up next,
then why don't you tell us a little bit
about developing Command & Conquer
and what did the world mean to you
and what are your favorite memories
of the development process?
Well, the world was really interesting at the time
and it was rife with inspiration,
which was really helpful.
There was a lot of stuff going on in the world at that time.
But I think, as Brett noted,
there was a lot to draw from from the backstory
that he and Joe Bostic had been creating.
So that was a big inspiration
and trying to work with the writers and...
milled the story that was being built into the missions and then back out again was interesting
and difficult, but also really, really fun.
But I think that was one of the more interesting parts for us was trying to find that intersection
and trying to merge the two pieces together.
And a lot of folks have asked in the past, too, where do we get the visual inspiration
stuff?
And at the time, there was like Soldier of Fortune magazines and all this stuff.
There was no real internet.
We're talking pre-1995, before...
Windows put browsers into the operating system.
So you couldn't just go Google it.
You had to go find stuff.
So they probably thought we were ready to go do some great
takeover of the government or something, because we had all
these subscriptions to magazines that would bring in
all these new technologies.
And we're trying to really be fans of what's happening in
the world and what might be being done by the government.
So Command & Conquer was always meant to be a near
future version of the world.
And we're going to hear from Ed DelCastillo next, who is the
producer.
I think my favorite memory revolves around those things that we did that were unexpected
and unasked for that pushed that product above and beyond to be the success it was.
So I'll give you one example of that and for me that's the mission briefings.
So you know we were on a path of doing mission briefings that were going to be straight teletype
you know just.
you know, just spitting text out slowly across the screen to tell people what they needed to do.
And, you know, the team was so enthused about the game and was so in love with the game that
that just didn't seem like enough for us. And so we came up with this idea to kind of take,
at the time it was really early, but take television style graphics and put them on top of
a video briefing to produce a
a briefing that was something people hadn't seen before, something that, you know, the story we had come up with was that there was this interactive panel between the player, who was this remote general commanding armed forces from afar,
and the guy giving the briefing, be it Kane or be it General Shepard.
And that interactive screen could be touched by the briefing giver,
could have graphics thrown up onto it,
could have all sorts of wonderful things done to it.
And so one day we went into the studio,
we just did this really, really, really bootleggy kind of demo.
We did it on a weekend, so we weren't pulling away from company time.
We edited the whole thing using Lightwave.
And the guy I was doing with, Felix, was really good.
We had come from New Tech.
He knew Lightwave.
And we just kind of spent that whole weekend.
I mean, we barely slept.
putting graphics onto a briefing and making it so that, you know, it was me doing the briefing,
it was, I was throwing maps out onto a screen between the player and the briefing giver.
We were showing, you know, I would open my hand and a world appeared in my hand.
I pointed at the world and Angola got highlighted and zoomed out.
I mean, we did all of these really, really cool things and no one had asked that of us.
One of my favorite memories from the first Command & Conquer was when the user interface worked as well as I had hoped.
The refinements and some of the additional changes that came as we kept perfecting it more and more and more.
You know, I would play the game and see the interface that Joe and some of the other guys had put together for me along the lines of what I was really, really hoping for.
And then when it worked so well, finally, because it took a lot, a lot of iterations.
in the precursor to C&C and C&C itself,
that when it finally came together, you just had this...
I had this great heartfelt...
Ah! This is it! Finally!
What it really, really wants to be.
It was a lot of fun, and it was so elegant and smooth,
and it allowed you to just play the game in a whole new way.
In fact, you got to focus more on playing the game
than in controlling the game,
which was one of the DNA components of the C&C universe.
One of my favorite stories about Command and Conquer was actually about Joe Bostic.
A group of us had decided to go skiing and we were sitting, I think, at dinner and I looked over at him
and he had this notebook out and he was working on something and I asked him,
what are you doing? And he said, oh, I'm working on Command and Conquer.
And I was just so struck by how dedicated and passionate.
He was. Here we were trying to have a vacation and he was just living and breathing Command & Conquer.
It was really like that for everybody on the team. It was truly an amazing experience.
My favorite moment from Command & Conquer development was
something I always just kind of remember was the way that we could all
provide input into the game experience and the development.
I was a community guy, I was a customer service guy at the time.
My input into the game wasn't as great as other people obviously,
but the nice thing is that we all got to play in the evenings
and we would play multiplayer and then we would all submit ideas into it and
because the game team was so small we all had a
really valuable voice into the game.
things that I would suggest got in there,
things that other people would suggest got in there,
and it was very quick,
because we were such a small team at the time.
So, you know, I would mention something to Joe Bostic,
and then like an hour later, he said,
okay, there's a new build, and your idea's in there.
And it's like, oh, that's awesome, you know?
And so, it was really fun to play even a small part
in the development of the original Command & Conquer.
It was just, it felt like a very small and dedicated team,
and we were just so...
involved in every way in making it better because we just loved it so much.
But it was people going above and beyond because they loved the product
and they really, really, really wanted it to be better than even expectation.
My favorite memory was, I think it was Mike running into my office with one of the PC
games magazines and it was awards.
And Command & Conquer, of course, was nominated.
But in the corner was this little block
that said we should have a special category
for installations because this one was so awesome.
And that just made me feel so good
because somebody, the audience out there,
the players appreciated all the effort that went into it.
So that was a really good moment for me.
One of the interesting things that CNC did was this idea of kind of telecaster broadcast interruption.
We even did it during the installation of Command & Conquer, and that was really, really fun.
where the gameplay actually began at a space that it normally didn't begin.
And the idea, of course, given the limits of technology and graphics,
was, oh, there's this kind of interruption, like it's a signal, a video signal coming from somewhere.
It's encrypted and it's actually breaking onto your game screen.
So that was really, really fun.
And the idea of continuing to use cinematics and outtakes and things like that...
just felt right. It made sense for the time and the place and the game and to create this
this immersion, this larger-than-life sort of strange mythos that only you, the game player,
you're being talked to directly. It's kind of like a secret agent commander sort of thing.
It's a lot of fun. It started really with the art, because I would get all the art of what
they wanted the whole thing to look like.
and then I had to have them break those animations down into pieces.
Then I used the last image of each animation as my background,
because some of them already had built-in where they wanted all the gadgets to be.
So I had to basically do my gadgets on top of that background and fill it in.
Sometimes they had invisible backgrounds, sometimes not,
just depending on what they wanted to do.
That way we got through in pieces and sections.
And as soon as that information was gathered,
we played the next animation
and seamlessly go into the next sequence.
So there's a lot of things that I won't remember,
but I'll do my best.
So in putting together the video sequences,
what I recall was that it was relatively piecemeal.
Now, like, we made a lot of stuff up as we went along.
There were things that were being written and then rewritten.
I remember doing some writing myself on some of the monologues and some of the scenes
because, you know, we had hired a screenwriter to come in who was completely unfamiliar with the genre.
I guess as unfamiliar with the genre as any of us were because it was such a brand new genre.
But I remember doing a lot of rewrites.
I remember sort of doing a lot of things piecemeal.
We were in a smaller space at this point.
Westwood was, we were growing,
and we were soon to move to our larger space
and the big 40 by 40 green screen
and then the back lot and the soundstages that we had.
But that hadn't happened yet.
So what we had done is we had rented another space
in the same complex, but it was a quarter of a mile away
across three parking lots and upstairs.
So when it was time to record, we'd go over to the studio,
and we'd hike ourselves over there,
and everything was upstairs.
Now, all of these were shot with a,
well, like this, on sticks with a dead-hung camera.
But any sort of movement across the stage,
we were sort of bouncing on a suspended floor.
Like, it feels very primitive in recollection.
And I don't think it felt that way at the time.
I think it felt very new and, you know,
avant-garde and exciting and envelope crushing
and brave new world, envelope pushing
and brave new world and all that.
When we first started out with our videos,
it was so seat of the pants, it was kind of hilarious.
I don't know if you remember, but we-
warehouse and I had gone to a carpet store and bought a roll of linoleum
flooring, brought that back and we stapled that to the wall and we didn't
even have chroma key paint. I just went to our hardware store and said,
I need some green paint. And then painted that and that was our first green screen.
So Eric, why don't you tell us a little bit about the design process of CNC.
How did we work, how did you guys work with the technical team and how did you come up with the missions and,
and the, you know, deal with the AI and all those things?
I think, um.
For me, it was probably one of the most collaborative games I've ever worked on.
As other people noted, the tech team was really approachable.
So you could walk into Joe's office or talk to Steve and go, I've got this idea.
They'd look at you cross-eyed and say, we'll figure it out.
And inevitably, they would.
And one of the really great things was you could ask Joe for something, and
you'd get it really quick, and it would be like 90%
right. You know, there wasn't this high iteration back and forth where you had to go,
well, it's not really what I wanted and this and that. And he'd add his stuff on top of that.
So you'd get this really great collaboration of pieces parts. So that process was really
seamless and it wasn't necessarily by design. It was just, we had such a good group of people
that worked really well together. And it.
The whole process felt like lightning had kind of struck.
You know, we had the right people working on the right product at the right time.
And it just felt good.
I don't remember any of the process being by design.
It was just a group of people that had an idea and wanted to make it work.
And as others have noted, we did a lot of stuff just unasked for
and just because it sounded cool at the time.
Thanks. And so Steve, why don't you tell us a little bit about your favorite memories and maybe some of the technical challenges and things that you guys might have run into?
Yeah, so favorite memory for me is around the multiplayer.
And, you know, many people over the years have told me
that they played Command & Conquer in their dorm room.
And it's always great to hear that.
And I think there was a sort of a viral aspect to that too,
because there were two discs for the game.
You had the Nod disc and GDI disc.
So you could play with a friend with one copy of the game.
And I think that actually benefited us.
But the thing about it is, as a player,
you don't see how the game is created.
The multiplayer obviously was evolved over time.
And so for me, I remember the very first time
you could play multiplayer.
And the only thing you could build were rocket soldiers.
That was the only thing you could build.
And so you've got four guys who jump in.
You'd all build your horde of rocket guys,
send them over to the other guy's horde of rocket guys,
and try and win.
It was very.
very primitive, but it was the
The baseline for the tech and send that over the coming
Days and weeks after that we'd add more and more units the buildings the tech tree all got into the game
and so the memory for me is sort of a
realization moment that
You know every night after work basically the whole company was staying behind to play multiplayer
And there's tons of excitement in the office,
you know, what new unit got added to the game,
that's in the commandos in the game today,
you can blow buildings up, you know, that kind of stuff.
And lots of excitement using the company phone system
intercom for the real time communications.
So, you know, you're gonna form an alliance
with your friend and get the other guys,
all this kind of stuff.
And the realization was, wow, we're actually building
something that's pretty freaking special.
And it kind of hit me at that point,
that, wow, we've got something very unique on our hands.
So that's my favorite memory.
In terms of technical challenges, there were a lot.
You know, there was multiplayer, I talked about that.
But I think the thing that stands out
is the sort of computation limits that we ran into.
And I'll explain what I mean.
So I think there were three components of that.
The first one is all of the 3D animations
that became like a signature part of the game.
All of the mission briefings, all the tanks and planes,
all this action going on.
And of course, the artists wanted to render out
these animations, and it was prohibitive.
It took hours to render seconds of animation.
And so at the time, Autodesk came out
with their network render.
functionality so you could have a farm of machines which we did so we set up
10 20 30 40 machines in racks and it got bigger over time I think we got up to
over 100 machines eventually and we started out with these machines and so
the artists could then submit their animation jobs and get reasonable
turnaround times so so the compute cost in that respect was solved
But the next problem was, of course,
we have all this live action, and we're
going to do this compositing with the 3D videos.
And we have all this video we have to play in the game.
So we came up with our own, as Lewis mentioned,
we built our own video tech.
So the real-time part of that was fine.
We could play back at a reasonable frame rate,
glorious 15 frames per second, 320, 200,
which was fine for the time.
And it fit on a CD.
But again, the compression times were crazy.
It would take hours and hours to render
a couple of minutes of video.
So one of the lead engineers at the time, Bill Randolph,
said, hey, I think I can fix this.
And so he spent some time, and he came up with a way
of using the render farm to batch out the video
compression.
So we had these machines, and we could use them for the 3D rendering,
we could use them for the video compression.
But of course, the artists wanted to render their movies,
and we wanted to also, the video guys wanted to compress their movies.
And there weren't enough machines.
So to solve that, we came up with a policy.
We basically realized that when people went home in the evenings,
there was a machine sitting there doing nothing.
So we came up with this policy where when you left for the day,
you ran your machine in VQ slave mode.
So we went from 50 machines to 100 machines.
And we were able to get decent turnaround time on the movies that way.
So the third thing, though, we sort of ran into code complexity issues.
So we were using C++.
We were learning C++ and using every feature the language has.
And so the build time started to increase.
And we were talking about an hour plus build time,
which was crazy for us.
So again, Bill Randolph, I think it was, said,
hey, I think I can fix this.
And he came out with a way of using the render farm
and the slave machines to do distributed builds.
So we got the build times, we could build in parallel,
and it brought the build times down dramatically.
And a sort of interesting footnote to that,
I was talking to the Petroglyph Games guys the other night,
and you guys may have heard they're doing the
CNC HD remasters.
And so it's come full circle.
Petroglyph is basically the sort of
continuation of Westwood, I guess the co-founders
of Petroglyph are from Westwood, Mike, Joe, and Steve.
And I was talking to Steve and I said, you know,
I'm going to be talking about the build time problems we had.
And he said, oh yeah, we're working with the original
CNC source code.
And it takes five seconds to build.
So I guess that's 25 years we'll do that, right?
That's awesome.
Just a bit off script here, too.
The thing was really funny.
Eventually we had hundreds of these Pentium 90s in racks,
gorilla racks all lined up.
And they were sitting in an area that was kind of a
common area.
And what was happening was we got toward the, it was fine in
the winter in Vegas, but it was starting to get toward the
summer, these are basically little BTU farms.
And they were driving the heat up in the building.
We were like, we were basically cooking ourselves
with our computers.
And so we created our own zero pressure room by taking a small room, closing it all off,
having a big air conditioning unit added to the roof, it was like a 15 ton air conditioning
unit and having only little slits at the door, at the bottom of the door with a brush was
the only way for the air to get out so you would actually open the door and you'd feel
a pop.
And that cold air would come in and cool off the whole room.
And it had no return air, Mike Ligg, no return air.
So anyways, we have a little bit more from Brett.
We all played every single night.
And as you can imagine, probably you've already got a
sense of Brett's personality.
So I wanted to conclude this little clip here because he
talked a little bit about his play sessions at night.
I know it sounds like bragging, but I could beat almost anybody, head to head, playing any side, any time.
Every time there would be this argument, because I had this big...
I had these strong feelings about what makes a game balanced and what made our game really, really balanced and fair.
And so every now and then somebody would challenge me and say,
Hey, you know, Nod is stronger than GDI, or this unit's better than that.
And I said, No, you're just...
You're not taking the unit until merits, and watch.
And we'd just play head to head, and so we would.
I used to be Overlord.
I think it's Brett's very Overlord, yeah.
Yeah, his memory's a little fuzzy, I think.
It might be a little fuzzy.
Brett does have his own version of reality that is very, very cool.
So Steve, why don't you tell us a little bit about the technical challenges that you, Joe,
and the team faced.
I think there was actually two of them.
There's the networking stuff, because there were multiple networking layers, and then
there was pathfinding stuff.
Yeah, the networking was interesting.
It was pre-internet, so we had local area network play with IPX.
Then we supported modem and non-modem connections.
So the latency and bandwidth characteristics of those are very different.
And we would add a bunch of stuff.
that worked great in the local area network
and then poor Dave Detmer was doing
the modem connection stuff.
He's like, there's too much data, it will never work.
Yeah, so we spent a lot of time with
trying to figure out ways of minimizing
the amount of stuff that was sent over the wire.
And unfortunately, one of the things
that we didn't get into the game
that we wanted to get into the game was internet play.
But that would follow in Red Alert, we figured that out.
So, yeah, some interesting challenges there with the networking.
And the pathfinding stuff, it was actually, it was a challenge.
I was generally pretty pleased.
I mean, you could select, you know, 50, 100 units,
and they behaved in a pretty solid manner,
and would path around each other,
and there were no practical limits on how many units you could select,
and they would behave predictably.
Except maybe for the harvesters, which sometimes had a mind of their own.
Me and Steve Weatherill and Jonathan Lanier were pulling an all-nighter trying to find a bug.
And we left the office around 2am to go get donuts to try and keep us awake,
because we thought donuts would keep us awake, I guess.
And I had this car that I inherited from my dad.
It was a really hideous car, but it was the car I drove.
So we hopped into the station wagon and drove to the donut place and it was 2 a.m.
And we were leaving and I got lost in the parking lot and I couldn't find the way out.
And so one of the guys says, where are you, a harvester driver?
And from that moment on, that car became known as the harvester.
How did the cast of C&C get assembled?
So casting was.
Kind of a challenge, you know, I come from a.
theatrical background. My, my, the entirety of my career was spent either in
teaching or directing in theater in Las Vegas. And so I had some access to
actors, but a great many of them were community theater actors. They were
hobbyists, people that were bankers during the day and actors at night. So
sort of reaching out into the professional acting community of Las
Vegas.
another brave new world for me. So I talked to the talent agencies in town
that I was familiar with and we set up auditions and we started bringing people
in and we found pretty quickly that you know we we started getting access to
some of the performers on the strip that were looking to expand and do some
things. Eric, I can't remember Eric's last name, played
Shepard. He was actually a one of the Blues Brothers impersonators back in the
day when
Imperial Palace was doing impersonator shows.
So he came from that call.
A lot of the performers were people that I knew.
And truth be told, a lot of the performers
were people that were in or around Westwood at the time,
because it was just easier to snag somebody
once a script had been finished,
and bring them over to the studio
for a quick recording session.
Joe Coogan was in my office one day.
And we were talking about some shots that were coming up,
because we rendered our own background plates.
And then after we shot green screen,
we dropped that footage into those plates.
So we're talking about some plates.
And Joe said something like, and that's when we see Seth.
And then he stops all of a sudden.
He's like, oh, crap.
I'm like, what?
He said, we forgot to cast Seth.
And I'm like, who's Seth?
And he looks at me and goes, you could be Seth.
Do you want to be Seth?
So I said, yeah, sure.
So that's how Seth started.
Well, I was working at Westwood at the time.
I believe I had been the receptionist for a while.
And so my voice was on all the away messages
and voicemail messages for Westwood.
And one day, Paul Mudra came to me
and asked me to record some.
holder lines, place lines for command and conquer. And we went into this little tiny room basically,
it was I think a closet that he had put up a whole bunch of soundproofing. And he had me read the
lines from there. And so I did. And I think the team, you know, liked what I had done. And so
they decided that they wanted to use me going forward.
So a lot of other people at Westwood had done various voices for the game.
I was super excited. It was my first time doing something like that.
And I was just tickled pink that he liked what I had done and that they wanted me to do even more.
So I was super, super happy.
Yeah, and it was the closet. It was the janitor's closet that used to be attached to the
bathrooms, which we turned into our server farm, which we later got sued for.
And we'd shave the orangutan down.
And we'd put the orangutan in front of the camera.
And we'd hang, we'd put a whiteboard with the cane lines over the orangutan.
And so that, you know, we would change, wipe them off and change every line.
But when we put, when we compressed all that down into the game...
You couldn't read the lines at all.
The orangutan was great, don't get me wrong.
Everyone loved the orangutan.
I think his name was Sparky or, yeah, Sparky.
Anyway, everyone loved the orangutan,
but we couldn't read his lines,
so I went in and I dubbed all of the orangutan's lines,
and we had a guy in a green screen glove
come in and move the orangutan's mouth like this,
just move his lips, while I would say the lines.
And then we took out, of course, the green screen glove.
But that wasn't very convincing either.
So finally we looked around and we said,
who looks the most like a shaved orangutan?
And it was me.
So I mean, because of my,
if you look at the original game,
a lot of people don't know this.
If you look at the original game,
a lot of those sequences,
we have used some of the frames of the orangutan
and just switched me out really quickly.
And it's nearly impossible to tell the difference.
It was really, really weird.
Remind us what it was like to work on C&C.
Actually, I'm really, really, really demanding.
And I'm in everybody's little details.
And I'm very, very specific about what I want.
So it can be, at times, a little bit challenging.
But you know what?
In the end, that's how we got to create
this amazing, amazing game.
The meetings where we would all get together
with bread at the end of the table.
Yeah, you know, we used to, some of us used to call those the Savannah Meeting,
because the way we would say it is there was this hungry lion who would come into the room,
and he was always looking for the slowest moving gazelle.
And it was everybody's job not to be the slowest moving gazelle, because the lion was going to eat.
no matter what which day it was, what meeting it was, the lion was going to eat.
It was just a matter of who he was going to eat.
The dinosaur levels came about through this odd way where Joe Bostic introduced a little bit of
code and there was a little bit of art for a couple of dinosaurs. And I learned about it when
I stumbled across this in the code and I asked him about it.
And he told me, yeah, this is a little Easter egg we're putting in, but Brett Sparrow, he doesn't know, so you can't tell him.
So I said, okay.
But then the art guys made a big art plate for the sidebar that was an homage to the Jurassic Park logo.
And they made more dinosaurs.
And then the sound guys got involved and made sounds.
And then the video guys got involved and made a whole video.
And at this point, Joe and I realized...
Brett still didn't know about this.
And when he found out, we didn't know what was gonna happen.
And we were both really scared about what was gonna happen
because we were ending up using company resources
on this dumb little toy.
So one day in QA, a bug caused that sidebar art to reveal.
And suddenly the sidebar became a big dinosaur head
and Brett was there when it happened.
So he and some QA guys showed up in our office.
And he was pretty mad.
He pulled Joe into his office and they closed the door.
And I don't know what all was said,
but when Joe came out, he looked pretty shaken.
And I said, Joe, what happened?
And Joe said, we're pulling it all out.
We're taking it all out.
It's just gone.
It's over.
I'm like, what?
And so we gave Brett some time to cool off.
And I went into his office, I think in the next day or two,
and I begged him to keep this stuff.
I just pleaded with him.
And he basically said, okay,
but you have to do it all yourself.
and you have to do it all in your spare time, you cannot impact the game with this."
I said, okay.
And, you know, Command & Conquer, I didn't know it at the time,
we were creating such a big and amazing game,
I had no idea how much it would move the needle in game development itself,
and how many people would, quite liberally, directly,
take and copy elements of our interface, our gameplay, etc.
But it created this huge wave of other games and admirers and things like that.
And so that was a form of...
It was a little frustrating sometimes when the copying was so direct.
And then other times it was very, very flattering to see that people were building on our work.
And sometimes even taking it to the next level a little bit.
One of the things I'd really love to leave people with is the idea
that just because something's hard or just because you don't like the way something's going
doesn't mean you can't learn anything from it and that you won't become better for it.
You know, there were a lot of unforgiving days in CNC. There were a lot of days when I walked home
feeling incredibly defeated, like I did not accomplish what I was supposed to.
for any number of reasons, right?
Whether my boss was saying that or I was feeling that,
it doesn't even matter.
But I would go home feeling defeated.
And what pulled me through that was not quitting,
was just the idea that I'm gonna stick this through
and rather than having the situation dictate me,
I'm gonna dictate that situation.
I'm gonna learn and I'm gonna be better.
And I can say today that I have never had
a more challenging time than when I was at Westwood.
And I can also say today that I never learned more from any institution than when I was
at Westwood.
It had everything that I wanted.
It met every goal that I wanted to set out.
It was fun to play.
It had a lot to replay.
It was balanced really, really well.
I like the graphics.
I like the effects.
I like the story.
It came together beyond my wildest imagination.
So it was incredible.
So that's the end of the material we have.
We're going to move to Q&A. But before we do, give me a
round of applause for all the people that worked on
Command & Conquer.
So they hear this.
Thank you.
As a good advisory board member, I always like to leave a little bit of time for questions.
So we have about five minutes because there's a special thing we want to close with just
before the end.
So if there are any questions, there are microphones.
Some people have already figured out they can stand up to them.
And we'll be happy to answer those to the best of our ability.
Thankfully, we don't have to worry about lawsuits anymore, so we can be pretty candid.
Hi, I just wanted to say to Frank your song Mechanical Man is incredible.
As you may know, World of Warcraft released a take or riff on that song, I'm a Medieval
Man, which was a lot of fun.
I wanted to know what you thought of that and are you planning on releasing a riff to
their riff?
Thank you for that, first of all.
Yeah, that was a popular theme for sure,
and I did hear the Medieval Man version,
and I actually met the composer of that
at a Video Games Live show a few years back,
and so we had a fun chat about that.
Yeah, it's just one of those things where you just come up with a fun idea and you make
a song out of it and it ends up in the game and it catches on.
Same thing with the main theme to Red Alert, like Hellmarch, everybody just caught on to
that.
It's still a video meme for so many people to this day, so it's a fun homage.
So thank you for that, appreciate it.
Because we're to both sides so we get everybody go ahead. Yeah
During development were there any expectations of what would be more popular single-player versus multiplayer and
Were you guys surprised by reactions to it?
Take that one for design.
Yeah, sure.
I think at the time, multiplayer was still pretty new,
so we didn't have a lot of expectations on it,
but as people noted, people were staying late
every night to play, which made my job
balancing the game really easy,
because I was used to wander around the office
and lurk over shoulders and get ideas.
So I think going into it, we didn't know
it would be as popular as it was,
but we did get a sense of that before it came out,
because people were literally staying 10, 11, 12 a night
to play on their own time, on their own dime, essentially.
Cool, thanks.
So for me the first RTS was mostly Dune II,
which I was surprised wasn't mentioned at all
during the talk.
I don't know if there's a specific reason for it.
No, none whatsoever.
Dune II was absolutely the first of the style of games
that are recognized as RTSs and it had animated sequences.
They just were on a single floppy
so they weren't full screen and video and all that.
Postmortem is about Command and Conquer,
but you're absolutely right.
That's the very first game, also made by Joe Bostic,
and he was a principal designer as well as coder on that.
Which was amazing, thank you for that.
But I was wondering if, because one of the biggest additions was being able to move multiple units at the same time,
which was a huge pain in the ass in Dune.
But did you take other inspirations?
Did you try to improve on what was done with Dune?
Because, yeah, multiple people worked on both games.
Yeah, I mean, I don't want to... I mentioned earlier there's some folks that just don't like doing public speaking, so I'm not gonna...
Okay.
I'm not gonna... I'm gonna hit poor Joe. He is here, but...
Okay, fair enough.
I'm not gonna make him do that.
So I'll answer for him, and he can correct me if I was wrong later, but we absolutely got inspiration from all sorts of games,
everything from Horse Ox-Fi to Cytron Masters. There was three games. There was Rescue Raiders...
Populous 2, Rescue Raiders, Military Madness,
Military Madness, and I can't remember the third one,
but there were these three games that,
Middleman, Military Madness on the NEC,
and they had this sort of feeling about them
of being able to do, strategy games at that time
were thought to have to be turn-based
so you had time to think.
And all these games had a way of putting you under pressure
and making you have to think and move at the same time.
And so there was lots of inputs from all that.
And I have to say, somebody mentioned it earlier
for the songs.
In the beginning, there was some tension
between Westwood and Blizzard.
I could tell you all about this some other time why that was.
But once the team started really deviating the products
and they were clearly distinctive,
I always found that it was really inspiring.
And having another company out there
that was trying to one-up the game.
really made you work a little bit harder.
And I think healthy competition is really important
in any medium, and it's great to have somebody
like Blizzard that kept us on our toes,
and each time we would wanna outdo each other.
And obviously you see where they've gone
as far as quality is one of the most revered
and rightfully so game companies in the world.
So yeah, we took inspiration from all sorts of places.
And I don't know if you guys wanna add anything.
Yeah, if I remember correctly, I could be misremembering,
but I think early on with C&C,
we wanted to make it so you didn't have to
sort of repeatedly click on the sidebar to the actions.
So I think the early versions of the games,
you could click a unit and move it,
but you could not drag select.
And the drag select was added, it was like,
hey, what if, it wasn't sort of a design,
it wasn't sort of, hey, we will do massive drag select.
Well we experienced the same pain
that everybody else was experiencing.
Yeah, it was like, you know,
we want to move a lot of stuff at once.
So I kind of have this memory of staying late one night
and sitting with the engineers,
and it's like, what if we just try drag select?
and we just put it in and it seemed very natural
and we went with that obviously.
So yeah, but I think initially we had,
it was more context driven way,
you could click on a unit and then click move,
but it still didn't feel quite right
and so the drag select I think made it a lot more fluid.
Absolutely, thank you very much.
Yes, over here.
Thank you all, and I gotta say that Command & Conquer
had a big influence on not only me,
but also my entire family,
and our go-to was always Red Alert.
So if Red Alert came out, as I'm just sort of
double-checking, Red Alert came out in 1996,
but as you mentioned, making Command & Conquer,
which came out in 1995, took a long time.
Can you talk a little bit about the transition
into the second game, and what was easy to redo,
and what wasn't easy to redo?
You wanna take?
Yeah, I think, and again, it's been 25 years, so my memory is hazy as well.
As I recall, Red Alert was originally going to be an add-on to Command & Conquer.
That's right.
And it just kept growing and taking on a life of its own and eventually became its own product.
But, yeah, originally we were just going to do a release for the 50th anniversary of World War II or something.
Yeah, I think it was supposed to be like a four-month project.
Actually, I can add a little bit to that, because the original one was supposed to be...
I told you earlier, the inspiration, a lot of discussions with Brett about the near-future technology
that was just around the corner, that was Command & Conquer,
was supposed to be just beyond reach, we could imagine it existing today.
And so Red Alert, as we were doing historical research,
came up quite a bit, that there was a lot of stuff
like the Philadelphia experiment,
and most of the stuff in the original,
in fact everything in the original Red Alert,
was actually, somebody thought that would work, right?
So that was the fun of it,
was like the attack of the 50 foot woman,
the 50s where science was kind of like magic,
anything could happen.
That was actually inspiration,
and it was like, hey, after covert operations,
which were really just hard versions in the dino missions,
Let's do something that's more thematic around this sort of historical,
almost magical kind of technology, this magical revering of technology.
And as it started getting bigger and bigger,
it was pretty clear that it just had a different sense to it.
And it was, certainly in the early days, people always ask this,
was it part of the Command and Conquer universe?
In the early days, it was undecided.
It was intentionally not.
forced to be one thing or another,
that's actually why Cain shows up in there and everything.
That's more about Cain's backstory
than it is about Red Alert.
And it was fun too, just we ended up asking
some what if questions about a lot of it
to determine what would happen.
And one of the questions was,
what if Einstein had invented a time machine?
No, he's too smart.
He would never have actually used it.
He knows the repercussions.
Well, maybe he would remove Hitler from history.
So then that led to a lot of other ideas
and it just kept going and going and going
until it was out of control and had to be its own product.
So we've got one time for one more question.
Got two minutes because then we have a special thing to end
this with.
OK?
Hi.
My question for each of you four is GDI or not?
When those Tiberium crystals crash land on our planet and
kick off the eternal war, who will you swear
your allegiance to?
Brotherhood, unity, peace.
You know, I can't take sides because then it would...
Aww.
Wah, wah, wah.
If I had taken sides, one side would have been way out of balance.
It wouldn't have been fair and everyone would have complained about how I favor GDI over
Nod.
Yeah, in my mind I want to say GDI, but I suspect in real life I might be tempted by
the Nod side.
Well, I wore the Nod jacket at MAGFest, so I think that's been an appearance.
So...