Hello, I'm Alexis Kennedy.
I've made three games that you might have heard of.
The first is Fallen London, this beige, grindy, free-to-play thing
made on a budget of zero with a core team of two
that's still running 10 years later, has been quite successful.
The second was Sunless Sea,
which is notoriously the world's slowest RPG,
with permadeath, on a boat, core team of three,
tiny budget, a million copies sold.
The third is Cultist Simulator, which we launched last May,
hit number one on Steam.
Ridiculous idea, opaque, deliberately hostile, occult solitaire with no tutorial and permadeath.
And all of these games in fact were quite daft ideas that did well, I think, because they were
quite daft ideas. So I want to talk about melding experimental gameplay with commercial success.
Thank you.