Hi, everyone. We're really nice and on the sides here. Thanks for joining me this morning.
And super, super excited to be at GDC. So this talk is lessons from D'Alingo from startup
to IPO.
And there's actually a lot to get through today.
So let me first tell you about what Duolingo is,
and then I'll tell you why I'm here to talk with you about it.
So Duolingo, if you're here, hopefully you know what it is.
It's the most downloaded education app
with over 42 million monthly active learners.
And it was designed to make language learning feel like a game.
We got inspiration from games, from game creators like you,
on how to make learning as fun as possible.
We launched in June of 2012, almost a decade ago,
and we IPO-ed last summer,
which is a really, really exciting experience.
So who am I? Why am I here talking with you about this?
My name is Karen.
I have a background in computer science and neuroscience,
and I had the pleasure of being with Duolingo
since three months after its launch in June of 2012.
So I started as a brand new, bright-eyed, bushy-tailed software engineer,
now a senior director of engineering.
And I love coming to GDC because, one, I love games.
Duolingo has been inspired through games throughout time,
but I think game-adjacent industries have a lot to also sort of offer and learn and share
with the game industry.
So I've been to GDC before twice.
In 2019, we gave a talk on how to make learning hard things
easy using data from Duolingo.
In summer of 2020, we talked about sort of
our A-B testing framework and how to turn good intentions
into good numbers.
Was really sad to miss 2021 due to COVID and such,
but so thrilled to be back here in person with you all.
in 2022.
And what I like to share every time I come to GDC
is my current obsession with games.
It is currently Final Fantasy XIV.
So if you play this game or want to talk about it for hours,
please talk to me after.
OK, so for today's talk, really wanted
to reflect on what I thought were important decisions I've
observed through witnessing Duolingo's journey
from tiny, tiny startup of about 15 people 10 years ago
to now a sustainable company of over 500 employees.
So that's 10 years of.
worth of learning to try to cram into less than an hour's worth of time.
We have a smaller group here, so I definitely want to leave time for discussion afterwards.
So we're going to go pretty fast.
I like to slow down during presentations, but today we're just going to go.
Lots of bullets, lots of topics.
We're going to talk about people and hiring and early hiring decisions,
business strategy early on, prioritization, organizational structure
and some key processes that helped us.
And finally, some anticipated growing pains.
Honestly, I ended up hiding like 10 slides this morning
because I was like, this is way too much.
But if you're interested in sort of more processes we have as well,
the slides will be available after this talk.
So don't stress too much about writing everything down or taking notes.
I'm happy to share the slides with you.
All right, first, some disclaimers that hopefully should be fairly obvious is there is absolutely no playbook for how to be a successful startup.
If there was one, it would be a much easier journey.
We came in at Dolingo with a lot of advantages and had a ton of luck along the way.
For example, our CEO already had a good track record, so funding was probably a little easier for us.
We managed to hire and retain really excellent people.
And the market is very different today than it was 10 years ago.
And some really lucky things happened.
So our owl mascot became an internet meme sensation.
Usage soared throughout COVID as people looked
for productive things to do with their time.
So we got really lucky in many ways.
So all this to say the goal of today's talk
is to describe what happened along the way
of a single company's journey.
And it's not meant to be prescriptive
because different things will work for different companies,
but it will aim to be generalizable.
So the main takeaway I want you all to take from this talk today is not necessarily what to do or
what to copy in terms of what we ended up doing, but more what were the problems that we encountered
along the way and how might you be able to proactively address them within your own environments.
All right, we're gonna jump right into people.
So when you start at a company,
and I guess maybe just for my own reference
and show of hands, who here is in leadership
or management at their companies?
Perfect, perfect.
How many of you are in companies
that are 50 people or less?
Okay, cool, cool, awesome.
And how many of you are here
just because you're either a Duolingo fan
or you feared our all mascot would come after you
if you didn't come to this talk?
Okay, just me, cool.
Great. So people when you start a company and many of you are at small companies, you have very, very limited resources, as you know, and even as you grow, like even with us at 500 people now, there will never be enough employees to cover everything that you want to do. So we focused really heavily early on on growing our talent pool very carefully and honestly quite slowly and making sure we were making the most
of the people we had and putting them in places where they can have the highest impact and
succeed.
So, early hiring, just have a few bullet points of things we sort of observed and learned
over time.
For early employees, we found that generalists
are super, super important.
In the beginning, people need to wear so many hats.
Product, QA, engineering, even design.
And also to have a high level of independence
because you just aren't going to have a ton of senior leaders
to go around managing people.
So we only really started specializing more
and hiring more specialized talent much, much later.
And later in this presentation,
I'll sort of show a timeline of when we hired
certain key roles to give you a sense of
how scrappy we were able to be at the beginning.
Relatedly, it's really hard to find perfect hires at the start.
You need to find people who are passionate about what you do and willing to take the
risk to go along for the ride with you.
So you have to get really good at identifying potential.
You know, it will be really hard to find a resume of this person has taken a startup
from.
zero to 100 and you can hire this person.
But the thing is, if you find someone
who has an incredible growth trajectory,
invest in them a ton, I mean a ton.
Give them opportunities because they will grow
into someone you probably could not have hired.
And I think if you are someone
who maybe is not a leadership manager,
be this person, really try to be this person.
It will pay dividends for sure.
The other thing I want to highlight here is that early diversity makes it so much easier to maintain diversity and grow it.
We found that having a diverse team early on made it so much easier to continue hiring diverse talent and being appealing to diverse candidates.
And injecting diversity after the fact is always going to be so much harder.
So keeping this in mind when building your team is what do you want your team to look like and how do you want it to represent your user base going forward as well.
And finally, this is potentially a controversial point,
but this is something that we did early on
that I actually think was somewhat of a mistake for us
that we got better at.
Is we basically, we are a tech company,
we should have internships.
Great, internships are fun,
but we originally looked at it as like a,
hey, maybe, and we did paid internships, of course,
but we thought, you know,
maybe we could just get some extra resources
for a summer, et cetera.
Great.
We found as we, it turned out to be a little better
for us to prioritize internships as a hiring funnel.
and really invest in full-time hires of our interns,
at least early on until you produce the sort of slack
to be able to not have to ruthlessly prioritize as much.
So originally, right, we made internship programs
because we wanted to offer the opportunity, et cetera,
but then we had to really prioritize
our senior engineers' time in mentoring and training interns
and interns were fantastic if you invest in them
for converting to full-time hires.
So that's what we had focused on.
Similarly to I think there is a fantastic place for contractors freelancers. They are wonderful. But we also early on really
focused on trying to hire full time as much as possible so that we could invest very heavily in our early employees.
Contractors are fantastic for well scoped isolated straightforward projects that have easy handoff but very early in a
company we found there were a ton of projects like that.
And we needed someone who could sort of own knowledge and become knowledge experts over
time for years to come.
Similarly, when it comes to shaping your team,
there are a few things we encountered along the way,
you might already be experiencing it,
is the hiring bar needs to remain super high
and there will absolutely always be pressure to move it down.
So make sure you have bar setters
and reward them for being bar setters.
Making sure that you're not compromising
because it is so, so costly to have hired the wrong person,
super, super important.
And similarly, if it'll take six months to hire for a role,
make sure you look around and see if you can grow someone
into it within six months.
Seems obvious in retrospect, but you know,
looking around you and having someone grow into that role
is oftentimes one of your best bets.
We did this very frequently.
We had people even swap roles.
Like I think we had someone convert to a PM
who was originally a marketing intern
because he was fantastic.
And these things worked out super well for us.
Other thing to sort of suggest is,
I think we tend to focus a lot on sort of the hiring funnel.
How can we get as many applications as possible?
How can we be appealing to new hires?
One thing to note is just a good employee retained
can be a lot better than actually being able
to hire someone.
So a lot of companies focus on competing for talent,
but they sort of neglect addressing turnover
or reducing turnover.
But if you don't lose someone,
that means you don't have to hire someone else.
So in some ways, it's a very, very high ROI investment.
And also long term employees, like I said, have deep institutional knowledge and help persist culture.
So invest in both internally and externally when it comes to building your teams.
At the same time, this is something that I think Duolingo has gotten better at, but was really hard is if you do manage to hire really amazing industry hires, giving them space to sort of innovate and to challenge the status quo and be accepting of change, I think is super, super important when it came to building our team early on.
And then finally, incentives should align
with what you want people to do.
Again, these things said out loud, I think seem obvious,
but one of the things we realized is career growth,
compensation, recognition, et cetera,
really needs to align well
with what you actually want people to prioritize doing.
And that includes hiring and interviewing
and building teams and persisting culture.
So make sure that the sort of invisible work
that is important to your company
becomes visible over time.
Great. And so this is my favorite quote when it comes to people from our awesome CEO Louis Fanon.
This is a principle we abided by for a very long time and still abide by at Dolingo.
It is better to have a hole than an a-hole is what Louis said.
We at times waited on key hires until we found the right person even if we suffered in the absence of that role.
And at times we waited over a year to hire those key hires.
But we have never ever regretted waiting.
So this is simply advice to have at the beginning is it's going to be very
tempting to say, well, this person's probably good enough or this person kind
of doesn't fit with the vibe or the culture we want, but they're really
accomplished. We've been able to resist that and we've never regretted it.
So keep this quote in mind.
Great. All right. So let's talk a business of strategy and this will be like the meatier part of this talk is the sort of way that we approached strategy going forward with with limited resources.
Early key decisions is and this is hopefully familiar with this audience is we bet on making a mobile app about 10 years ago and rode that wave with the rise of mobile apps and this is very sort of analogous with the rise of free to play over boxed products.
over time in the games.
At the time, language learning was very much
a sort of you attend classes, or you learn it on a CD, et cetera.
And we kind of had to make the risky bet of saying,
what if we made an app?
People were saying at the time, you cannot learn
through technology.
But that's what we wanted to do.
So at the start and rise of mobile apps,
we decided we're going to invest in iOS,
we're going to invest in Android,
and we're going to have it so that you can learn
a language on your phone.
And so the thing to sort of always ask yourself because I think this was actually the most critical part to our success is what will that next wave look like and will you catch it or be left behind.
I've attended a lot of NFT talks here so we will see if that is the next wave.
So the other thing that we decided to do really early on is to not try to do everything at once.
And this is very, very hard to do because you're going to have naysayers.
You're going to have people who are pushing you to work on everything.
And we very intentionally decided to focus first on user growth.
And then we added monetization.
And then we decided to invest in longer term bets like our learning efficacy over time.
And then philanthropy in that order.
And we're going to focus a little bit more on these first two, user growth and monetization,
because I think they'll be most relevant for this group here.
The other thing that we did very early on is we invested in data a lot.
A-B testing drove all of our decision making and allowed us to move very quickly.
Adil and I will talk a little bit more about experimentation going forward as well.
So let's talk about growth stage first.
So we decided that we wanted to focus on building the most
engaging learning product we could and ramp up our user base
as soon as possible.
And I will say we did this at the cost of not monetizing
early.
and also honestly not focusing on learning efficacy very early.
And there was a lot of criticism about this.
But here is our logic is the more users we had,
the faster our sort of experiments can resolve
in terms of statistical significance and the data we get
from what makes an engaging product,
the faster we can iterate, the better product we can build,
and then the more users would come
because we had a great product.
I think this flywheel was by far the most powerful thing that drove Duolingo to its success in the early days is we simply had more people than anyone else did and we could learn so quickly and iterate so quickly on our product.
We could provide our services for free attract a large audience and then we could bet that before we run out of runway we could monetize quickly enough.
So the question is to sort of ask to is our moat was the number of learners we had and as well as a very sophisticated A.B. testing framework.
And the question to ask is then,
what are the moats that you want to invest in?
Like what gives you that competitive edge
in the market at your stage of startup as well?
The other thing that we wanted to make sure of
is to stay ahead of the curve when it came to product.
We decided that we were going to be our own competitors
and try to innovate in this space.
So for example, over time we've done several redesigns
of Duolingo and sometimes had to pause our feature freeze
to say we're doing all hands on deck to update our product,
update all of our assets so the app never felt too old.
And this was a perfect time also to clean up technical debt,
to clean up product debt, to clean up product complexity.
and was something that we definitely invested in a lot over time.
So I wasn't kidding when we said we do a lot of experiments.
This is the number of experiments
we create a month at Duolingo.
You can see it's hovering around or near 300 experiments a month.
That's like 10 a day that we run.
And when I say experiment, it's things like as simple
as let me change the copy on this button
and see what results in my click-through rate,
all the way to this is a whole new feature
that we're going to A, B test and slowly roll out.
And we are able to do this because our user growth,
this is our monthly active users over time.
You can see we get spikes on New Year's because of New Year's resolutions.
These two graphs are very similar, right?
We can run a lot more experiments with more learners that we have.
And also, running more experiments allowed us to make a better product that retained
and attracted learners over time.
So this is the sort of power of our flywheel.
And after we accomplished a massive number of learners, we paused and said, OK, well,
how do we survive as a company now in terms of monetization?
So stage two, monetization.
Now that we had a ton of users, we
could have the privilege of turning a switch,
kind of to start monetizing and extend our runway.
So the way that we approached this
is it was honestly really hard.
We started with ads.
Honestly, we didn't like ads.
We really liked having a very clean product.
But we started with ads because we decided, hey,
this will buy us runway to figure out a longer term bet.
And that longer term bet was a subscription model.
So Duolingo monetizes through a subscription
that gives you some perks.
And ever since our subscription model, we started also explaining the potential of in-game currencies and in-app purchases also inspired by games.
So the other thing that we also added in was starting to bet on new verticals.
So this is the order we did things as we did ads, we did subscriptions,
we're investing in in-game economies now,
and we also are investing in new verticals to monetize at Dolingo as well.
So this is the breakdown right now, as of I think a few months ago,
in terms of where our revenue comes from.
You can see it's dominated by subscriptions.
But the other sort of assets you see ads started out being everything
and then just shrunk to 15 percent, which we're quite happy about.
So a few things learned along the way from monetization.
Because we were such a driven mission driven company at first
and people who joined Duolingo early on really just believed
in that mission of free education.
We had to do a lot of work to align our business objectives
with that mission.
Without that alignment, there was no passion for the product.
And one of the hardest things we had to do was honestly convince ourselves making money wasn't evil.
And I'm not kidding when this took several months.
There was a lot of people who thought we would simply dilute our mission
or stop caring about our product once we started monetizing.
And I think the only way we were able to really combat that both externally and internally is to really, really stay true to being an authentic and mission driven brand and saying, we're going to need money if we want to win in this space.
And if we win in this space, it's going to be good for the world.
So we had to convince our employees.
We had a lot of like sort of open discussions and forums about it.
We listened to concerns.
I was I was still suffering during your time.
I wasn't even leadership and management.
So I still remember this kind of from both sides.
And we did it.
And I think one of the things we also did was we wrote down our monetization
principles to sort of say everyone should always be able to learn for free
on Duolingo.
We're never going to get anyone with money.
And I think that guiding principle is still about one that we hold today.
Our user base loyalty was very high at the time.
I think it's important to sort of demonstrate your mission and not just say it.
And it played a really critical role in how accepting people were when we started monetizing.
And I think one of the affirmations for that is once we released our subscription, you know, it came with perks like you can download your lessons offline, you get, I don't know, some cute like skins for the duo, etc.
The number one reason people subscribe was to support the mission of free education.
And I think that was saying a lot in how we branded our monetization and how our intentions were made clear to our learners.
All right. So then we monetized. We decided we were going to keep living as a startup. And this stage I won't spend too
much time on learning efficacy is maybe not that applicable to games. But the reason I'm bringing it up here is this was
the stage after monetization that we decided to to really invest in longer term bets.
And we decided to start investing heavily in measuring learning,
measuring efficacy, doing curriculum overhauls,
because we needed to fulfill the promise of actually teaching
you a language, right?
We didn't want to be a scam.
We didn't want to be a place where people only
went to casually learn a language
and then stop forever.
What this taught us was actually that some things are not measurable and this was something that was hard for us to learn is as such a data driven 300 experiment per month company we had to learn that there was a huge important aspect of D'Alingo that we would just never be able to really A.V. test well.
So we had this conversion in this sort of renaissance within the company that we.
needed to stop saying every experiment needed to win and increase metrics and instead started shifting to
let us increase pedagogical value based on the experts who know how to teach a language
and let us simply try not to hurt our gargoyle metrics. We went from neutral experiments are good
if we are increasing the efficacy of our product.
So the reason we invested in all of this was and the take I want you to take from the section is we knew that learning based initiatives would increase the cap of where we could be three years from now.
You know we would hit a hard wall on growth or a hard wall on monetization if we were never able to extend how far we can get you in learning a language.
So the question to ask yourself is what will you be limited by three years from now.
What do you think the cap will be in terms of potential of your product and what can you work on today to uncap.
And we decided after we had enough learners after we decided we could be sustainable as a company.
This was our cap was learning efficacy.
And then finally, fourth stage that we're still expanding on
is innovation and philanthropy.
Not saying innovation can't be there at the beginning,
but sort of risky boulder bets in innovation,
I think you get more slack to do
once you're sort of out of the, in the clear.
So we started investing in in-house technologies
and tools at this stage.
And note that we didn't do it earlier than this stage.
So we have our in-house analytics framework,
internal tools for curriculum creation,
custom speech recognition.
etc. But the main advice here is to not reinvent the wheel too early. So use existing stuff if
it's available because the time of your team is the most valuable thing you have right now.
And build internally only when it breaks or if you've outgrown it.
Also new verticals, bold bets.
We had several new verticals.
We failed at most of them.
We succeeded in a few of them.
So we did language certification, literacy,
kids, math, flashcards.
Some of these succeeded, some of these did not.
And I guess one slight point of guidance,
and this might be different for your companies,
is we decided to invest about 70% in optimization
and the things that we know would get us gains
in building the machine, in running the machine,
and about 30% in R&D and innovation and exploration,
and we try to design our teams such that that is true.
So a few learnings.
It's really, really easy to go overboard and say,
it's really, really hard to say no to philanthropic things.
When someone says like, hey, we should do this,
you don't want to say no if it's a good thing to do,
especially with a very passionate employee base.
But the advice I'd give, especially when you're small,
is to focus on the impact you're best at making.
So for Duolingo, it was that we were uniquely positioned
to do things like support the addition of underrepresented
or endangered languages on our platform.
But one of my favorite quotes from our CFO is like,
we like the whales, but we shouldn't focus on saving the whales.
And I think that is a sign of Duolingo is not in a position to really go and
try to save the whales or
do a lot of other things that weren't directly related to our company.
So really focusing on the things that you can have unique leverage on will help you
kind of scope.
Relatedly, right?
Prioritization.
So making the most of the resources
you have at this early stage, which many of you are at,
is probably one of the most important things you could do.
Though the strategy I just described
already defines what you prioritize,
there are a few other things we learned along the way.
So early on the best advice that I got from Luis was to realize the value of my time,
even as a very, very junior engineer.
And I remember this story from when I started at Duolingo,
as I was, I think I was just like mad at someone on the internet or something,
saying something wrong about Duolingo.
And he said, you know, if every employee had a share,
every employee has a share of like 100,000 users to take care of,
whatever you decide to work on every minute of your day, think about.
those 100,000 users that are in your care.
And that helped me really understand
the opportunity costs that comes from going down rabbit holes
and what I'd be sacrificing to go down those holes.
So training this mindset in all of the early employee base,
I think, was super, super useful for helping to protect us
from ourselves and investing in lower ROI work
so that we can maximize our impact as a very small team.
this sort of philosophy will just make a lean work first go a really long way for you and stay focused.
The other thing, and this is like a quote you don't have to read fully, but the TLDR is, you know, one thing that we learned also is as a small t is very easy to sort of like go down the Reddit rabbit hole or read an article about your product or get really angry at people who are wrong on the Internet.
But one thing that we found is we were listening to channels that
represented just a very, very small portion of our user base.
And that's not to say you shouldn't listen to your users.
I think this quote is a bit strong.
But one thing to recognize is making sure you're actually listening to your users
and not just listening to a few of your users.
So we had to really, really take user feedback with a grain of salt.
And what we decided to do is we tried to listen to our users through data and
their usage instead of directly through qualitative comments.
A few caveats here is I 100% believe in user experience research.
I think UXR is fantastic and it is absolutely necessary.
Qualitative feedback is really important.
But the type of sort of feedback that we didn't find as useful early on was was
things that are not conducted by professionals, right?
Like an engineer, me reading on Reddit that someone is mad at the product
that tended to just really be red herrings to the actual underlying problems.
So thick skin helps.
You know, remember, it's the most upset people that tend to be the most vocal.
And I think.
Looking at our data and saying, actually the vast majority of our learners really
love the redesign we just did versus reading the really long thread about how
many people hated our redesign was affirming.
So try to use data to really get a clear sense of what the average user
on your product is feeling.
Another learning about prioritization is it is so, so, so tempting to sort of greed and
try to scale a product or feature out before you're confident there's product market fit.
So how this looks at Duolingo is we'll come up with a feature.
We love it.
It's great.
We'll launch it on iOS first.
We'll test it.
It looks great.
And then we'll immediately want to say, let's get more learners using this feature by having
it on like web and Android immediately.
And one of the things that does is it's the case that it really actually slows down iteration on that.
So one of the things we've learned to do is try to be really patient with product market fit because
you know the moment you want to make a change to that feature you now need to change it on
three different platforms instead of being able to scrappily prototype it on one.
So it took a lot of discipline to do this and when you don't have a lot of resources to,
you know, that investment and having to port something three times is a lot.
So just keep in mind, iteration is also a resource and the ability to iterate quickly
is also a resource you need to account for when it comes to decisions like this.
And then the main thing here is not yet is a super,
super strong response to both yes and no questions.
So we had to get so much better at saying not yet instead of no,
because honestly ideas can become viable over time.
So the answer should never be no to an idea, but it can absolutely be not yet.
And then honestly, when it came to things like, let's do this new crazy feature,
etc., also saying not yet instead of yes was also very powerful for us.
So I highly encourage you to make use of the not yet, to put it in a backlog,
to think critically about it, but to feel free to say not yet, to both yes and
no questions.
All right, so we're going to run through organizational structure real quick.
This is kind of the evolution of how our org evolved over time.
Early days, so we started with one huge flat team with individuals in charge of
certain metrics or projects.
So my first day at Duolingo, I think I was employed like 15 or so.
Luce came to my desk and said, hey, try to grow user retention.
Like literally, I was just like a brand new engineer.
I sat at my desk, he was like, grow user retention, and he just left.
And then I, that was it.
So we got more sophisticated over time with our onboarding, but you know in the
beginning we basically had projects and metrics that we were all in charge of.
Everyone reported directly to the CEO in the early days and we had really
excellent people so we didn't worry too much about titles, hiring very senior
leadership, etc. That landscape might have changed. Like I said, this is just the
story of how we started.
It's not meant to be prescriptive.
But what this did allow us to do is actually set
a very non-political foundation early on.
People were preoccupied with their work
and not too preoccupied with their status.
And I think that really helped us.
We hired our first manager,
who's now our SVP of engineering, Natalie, my manager,
in early 2015.
Now, if you remember, we launched in 2012.
Which means we had about two and a half years without managers.
I mean, technically, I guess Luis was everyone's manager.
But I thought, I wouldn't necessarily recommend this,
but this is just what happened.
And we continued to stay as flat as possible.
So I can say this right as an engineering director,
that we really tried to not have more management
than we needed at any given time.
But everyone's use case is different.
So what I thought might be fun to share is a timeline
of functions.
This was fun to look up for myself
because I didn't realize this was the case.
So at the beginning, we only had design and engineering.
I think we had one person managing our finances, things
like that.
And then we hire a marketing person in early 2013.
I'll be transparent and say like,
marketing person was great,
but like we actually decided we didn't want to invest
in marketing at the time,
so we kind of like didn't hire any more marketing people
for a while until probably like 2017 or so.
Hired her first PM in 2014.
Our first manager in 2015, it was an engineering manager.
Learning scientist, that was like the phase of learning and
long term bet investment in 2015.
Then there was talent acquisition HR.
Notice there are four years there where it was like engineers were just hiring
engineers and designers were hiring design and
we didn't have people for explicit talent acquisition at the time.
We hired data scientists, even though we were AB test obsessed, in 2017.
So that was five years until we hired our first data scientists.
And now we have excellent roles like program manager, technical program managers
that we've hired in the past two to three years or so as well that really,
really help us grease the wheels.
So I thought this was interesting because in some ways, I think early on a company,
you feel like you really need someone, an expert in everything.
And certainly I can assure you that getting excellent people in these roles
is fantastic.
But you kind of also make do with what you had.
I mean, one of the first times I met our CEO,
he was carrying a box of t-shirts to a tech recruiting
conference.
I was like, OK, this is a down-to-earth guy.
But we all had to basically do whatever
it took to get things done.
And we, in some ways, hired these roles very late,
also because we wanted to wait for the right person
to establish what that role and function should be.
And sometimes that took a long time.
All right, so let me talk a little bit about the evolution
of our organizational structure.
After we just had this very flat structure for a long time,
we introduced teams because we decided it'd be a good idea
for more than one person to work on retention or whatnot.
So we based teams around metrics, features,
or problem spaces, and we wanted teams
to be able to accomplish their goals pretty autonomously.
So there are several ways to do this.
Some people have all the iOS engineers here,
all the Android engineers here, et cetera.
There's a design team, et cetera.
We decided to do them vertically
so that there were little pods of engineers and designers
and program managers and learning scientists together.
Controversial, but we actually did this
so we would minimize cross-team collaboration.
I know that's like...
Not a great thing to say, but it's because we didn't want teams to always feel blocked
on other teams and their priorities. We wanted teams to feel like they had a sense of control
over their own destiny and success. So we decided to build teams vertically with all
of the components they would need to be successful at accomplishing their goals.
So our first teams were actually like learning, growth, and monetization, which if you remember
may be the sort of phases of prioritization we went through.
And we also at this point created the role of team lead, someone who led the team and
managed everyone on it.
This will be relevant in a bit because learnings were eventually your teams are going to grow
way too big and you need to fragment them and narrow their scope.
So, for example, our growth team fragmented into teams like social, gamification, and retention
as all elements of growth that had narrower scope. But honestly, our limiting factor when it came to
making more teams was ready leadership when it came to making new teams. And this is why I
introduced the team lead concept earlier.
I think one of our biggest learnings was we tended to sit at a very high bar for
what it meant to be a leader.
And generally, we'd rather have a more senior person double up and
kind of be stretched than in lead two teams than have someone more junior as
a team lead.
Not saying this is necessarily right, but this is what we did.
And here are the reasons.
One of them is you really risk stunting technical growth.
And when I say technical, it doesn't have to be engineering.
It's sort of like all the things you learn from building something,
from doing your day to day job, you stunt early if you put someone
in a leadership position that occupies all of their time.
So being really sensitive to what growth are you potentially stunting
when it comes to putting someone in that position early is really important.
And it's also really hard to unmake someone, a manager or a team lead.
Once someone is in that position, it feels like demotion, even though it's really
not, to put them back on the individual contributor track.
So be very careful about this as well.
Okay, after we had 33 teams, I'm saying like we kind of do things as late as possible.
We had 33 teams on like this really flat structure.
We decided we probably need some other layer.
So now we have areas composed of several teams.
We now have area leads and this structure was really useful for sparse resources.
So for example, we're very low on designers at Duolingo and
we had a situation where a designer was embedded on like four different teams and
just like stressed.
So what ARIA has allowed us to do
were to group teams under this umbrella called ARIA,
have ARIA level design, and be able to take
care of the designers in terms of their priorities
and just saying you're in charge of ARIA, not these four teams.
And ARIA leadership was responsible for status,
for summarization, goal setting, et cetera.
Here are the areas that we have today.
And we also had something called business units,
which were new verticals or little mini-companies
within the company.
So it's possible to have little mini-companies in your company
that are working on independent verticals as well.
And then finally, not all teams are in areas at Dolingo.
So anything that is a little more functional, marketing people, finance,
strategy business, or function-based teams that support the rest of the company,
just remain teams.
And that's totally okay, not everything needs to fit in this structure.
Okay, so a few lessons learned is just like in coding,
naming is strangely extremely important
when it comes to teams.
Like this is one of the things
that you would not think is important at all,
but somehow was really important for us.
Naming a team defines the assumptions
about what area of ownership that team has,
and people will therefore reach out to teams
that they feel like are closest
to the information they need.
And if that is very obfuscated,
people will not know who to go to for things.
It's also the case that employees will tend to remember team names but not mission statements or the goals of each team if you have a lot of teams.
So all they have to go off of for knowing what the company finds important is the teams that the company has.
So if you have a team called retention, it means the company cares about retention.
So...
All this to say somehow naming has become very important.
And we've run into problems in the past where we name something poorly and
it just confuses everyone in the company.
So naming is important.
The other thing we realized is sometimes we would do organizational reorgs or
have brilliant plans for how to have a very perfect organizational structure.
And then always, always at the end,
we'll pare it down to the most minimum viable plan that changes the fewest
number of things.
Mainly because manager team changes, team restaffings are often very disruptive.
So we tend to do smaller organizational changes, little tweaks like one person moving, etc.
every one to two quarters.
We do large reorgs about once a year and we add a layer every three years or so.
So this is sort of like the cadence of how we move things.
All this to say, be very practical.
So we will never, ever have a perfect organizational structure.
This is literally what I personally work on almost all the time.
But strive for slowly improving your organizational structure over time to
keep the minimum acceptable level of chaos, I think is what I'd like to say here.
There will always be overlap, gray areas, things will fall through the cracks,
you won't be able to staff something.
Or there won't be quite the right leadership in time, and
that is totally normal and expected.
So there's no right answer.
There are kind of two paths you can take and you can decide for
a company where on the spectrum you want them to lie.
You can either have a really stable, rigid teams that is great for
building team expertise, loyalty, stability, a sense of ownership, etc.
Having sort of the same people on the same team for a long period of time.
You can also have really scrappy, flexible,
you're expected to change teams all the time.
Highly agile teams, that's great for
innovation and always working on high ROI things.
If you want to always put your superstars on
the most important thing, this structure is great too.
There are pros and cons of each of these,
and maybe you actually have a few people
on each of these spectrum as well.
There's no right answer, but here are the options available.
All right, and then finally, yeah, different things work for different companies.
Finally, processes.
So originally there were like eight processes here and I'm only going to share two with
you today because one, there's not enough time to it's probably really boring to most
people here.
But one process that really drives Duolingo is OKRs.
No one really likes hearing about OKRs, but here's why I'm talking about them.
It's really good for setting goals and alignment.
If you don't know what OKRs are, they're a set of objectives and
the key results you want to accomplish towards that rejective.
Ideally, they are measurable and
you will receive a grade at the end of the quarter.
The key thing here that we really had to untrain our perfectionists on is the goal
is to get a weighted score, and when I say weighted, it's weighted based on priority,
of 0.7 at the end of the quarter.
If you get higher than a 0.7, it's actually not great.
It means you weren't ambitious enough with your goals.
So it's, and the other thing I just really want to emphasize,
especially to leaders here, is this measure in this grade is a measure of how well
you planned, not a measure of how good a team is.
If you find that a team gets a 0.3 at the end of the quarter,
the correct discussion to have after that is,
how did we fail this team in terms of planning?
What were the unanticipated things that happened?
Why were our estimations off?
It is not about the performance of the team.
It's about how we can plan and scope things better to prevent crunch.
So problems addressed here, align on goals,
communicate priorities, have accountability on these teams,
and practice much better planning and prediction
when it comes to the goals
and how realistic they are setting for your teams.
So here's a concrete example from,
I just pulled this from like retention,
obfuscated some numbers.
You don't have to understand what this is,
but this is kind of what an example
of an OKR looks like here, right?
Is the objective is just to improve the retention
of one of our features from X to Y.
And then here are the P0s, the two most important things we want to do for that.
Here's the P1, here are two P2s.
And one thing I just want to highlight here is note that these all kind of start
with verbs and have things like reduce latency, run experiment,
port to improvements, launch experiment, run experiment.
And what I want to say here is one of the biggest tips I have is, again, naming and
consistent terminology is actually super, super important.
So we have these terms at Duolingo, especially around our A-B testing framework of
launch, run, roll out, port, prototype, get stakeholder approval.
And the reason precise terminology is important is it helps control scope.
As a leader, you want to protect your team from scope creep.
And that means not promising, let's just launch all these experiments,
but really diving into what are the right milestones I can deliver.
for these very arbitrary quarter boundaries, right?
It's not always going to be the case that features should fit nicely within quarter boundaries.
So how can you break that up so that the right milestones are expected out of your team?
Whether it's just let's just get stakeholder approval and get on the same page about the
product we're building versus let's just implement the thing but we're not going to be able to roll
it out to learners yet. It won't be ready or QA'd by time. If you have precise terminology,
you prevent that scope creep and you protect your team from crunch.
Other thing we've learned is collaborative KRs
across two teams that have their own separate OKRs
should be verbatim.
On both teams, OKRs with the same priority
because it's really bad if this is the most important thing
for this team to collaborate on
and the least important thing for this other team
to collaborate on and have different priorities
because one of them is going to do it, the other is not.
And then you screw over the team
for which it's really important.
So OKRs are a way to sink on these things very explicitly
that we agree this is a priority for both of our teams.
And the sort of last point here, I think, is OKRs are very strong incentives for teams.
So capture work you want to make sure gets done, especially traditionally thankless work.
I am a huge proponent of this.
Documentation, fixing bugs, stability, cleaning up technical debt all really need to be represented
and celebrated and given credit for when it comes to planning.
They can't all just be top line business metrics.
Because if you want these things to happen, it's very important for these things to happen,
you need to reward and recognize that.
OK, something a little more fun outside of the manager world
is one of the things that we have learned
is to really, really invest in greasing
the wheels of the things that your company spends
a lot of time doing.
And since we run 300 experiments a month,
we wanted to invest in what we call automated experiment
reports.
So every single test we run has a report automatically
generated nightly, including all the KPIs across the company
that people have submitted their own teams care about.
and whether that experiment had a significant impact on any of them.
So here's a sort of example experiment report.
I'm not sure if you can read it.
You know, here I can look at my experiment,
learning multiplier and decay web, whatnot,
and see like, ah, it seems statistically significant
for increasing active users over time.
Great.
And if I scroll down this,
they would be revenue metrics, retention metrics,
and every metric every team in the company cares about
to make sure I'm not screwing up someone else's metric over time.
And this being automated meant it was super transparent
and prevented me from sort of messing with another team's
metrics.
So the problems we addressed here, very, very fast feedback.
These reports were generated nightly,
included all the guardrail metrics so that you didn't
have to memorize them or know who to go to
or know what to look at to do it.
It makes experiment analysis super accessible,
especially to non-technical people
or non-statisticians like me.
And it vastly, vastly accelerated decision making
on whether or not to launch or shut down experiments.
Great.
Last section, we're almost through, I told you.
This will be rapid.
So relatable growing pains
that you will probably inevitably encounter.
First, we're gonna start with engineering pains.
Ownership voids and untenable backlogs, hopefully relatable.
The way that we are trying to address this now
is to form centralized bug triage groups
with very senior leaders so that we could communicate
this is actually important and worthwhile time.
We're also now forming decentralized groups per area.
And also adding a ton of automation for duplicate reports.
So one of the things that we started drowning in
is people reporting the same problems over and over again
and it literally took all of our time to even dedupe those
than to even start addressing them.
So invest in technology that helps you be able
to do these sort of lower ROI tasks.
And also, as I mentioned, OKRs,
including bug squishing and triage in those OKRs
means people will get protected time to do them
and you account for them in your planning.
We're still bad at this.
Other thing, legacy code and technical debt.
Occasionally we will actually just stop and do all hands on deck projects to clean up
code base rewrites or redesigns.
Hopefully you don't get to that point,
you will probably get to that point,
and it's important to kind of put the foot down
and say we just really need to do this
to accelerate how quickly we can code in the future.
And some quarters we actually ask all teams
to include a care dedicated to reducing technical debt.
Technical debt will always be one of those
high importance, low urgency things.
So I think that the key thing to learn here
is to really invest in those things.
We also have an annual company grease week
where everyone in the company takes a week
to just clean up shop.
do those refactors you've always wanted to do, write that documentation you've always wanted to have,
etc. No one's going to bother you that week. You won't have any meetings that week. And it's
really important that everyone does this at the exact same time, because if it's only a few people,
you're just going to get drowned in the work that other teams are asking of you anyway.
communication pains.
So a lot of stakeholder, this is like the one emoji
I managed to like insert in this presentation
and I decided on this one.
I'm that stakeholder, I'm that problem,
so I can talk about it.
So one of the things we did was,
you know, it was the case that teams really needed
to know what other teams were doing,
if they affected their metric or their feature.
So we have this template now.
where there's just a list of all required collaborators
or people you need to contact in order
to get your feature approved if it touches
any one of these domains.
And that's been really, really helpful.
And we're also just investigating different stages
of feature development.
When something's just an ideation,
you don't want to put red tape on it.
So we're sort of trying to set expectations now
for how far along a project you need
to be in order to start pulling in stakeholders
to really minimize stakeholder management
at the beginning of projects and only introducing stakeholders
actually needed.
Other communication pain is onboarding and documentation.
We have an internal content management system now,
was highly worth investing in,
where we just do automated training
for all of our new employees.
And we have a group that audits the quality regularly
of this, very, very worthwhile investment for us.
We standardize our career ladders to share a common core
so that all of our levels would be fairly consistent.
And then we also hire people to lead this initiative,
starting with the leadership training.
And then the final pain I'm trying to talk about
are emotional pains, which are usually
the hardest to deal with.
Handling low performers and exits
was honestly very, very hard for us and still is.
Dolingo needed to get a lot better at acting
on low performance.
We were often too kind.
So we created a playbook for managers
on identifying and handling low performance.
And we found that often managers actually just
lacked the confidence to even note or judge someone
as a low performer.
So we gave much more objective guidelines for that
so also everyone could understand what it means
to not be doing well.
And the other emotional pain was really pivots and sunsetting projects,
which I think a lot of people encounter early on.
What we found is early communication, transparency around the reasoning behind
it is like if you believe in that reason, you shouldn't be ashamed to share it.
And oftentimes we actually found that it was the team building the feature
that ultimately decided it should be sunsetted and
that is such a healthier way to go about it as well.
So retrospectives are great and healthy and we really need to encourage
blamelessness in those. And I think the most important thing is to reward
innovation even if it results in failure. If you want an innovative company, if you
want your best people working on innovation, they need to not have the
fear that their careers would be ruined if it doesn't work out, right? That's not
how innovation works.
So we need to figure out ways to celebrate our, not even failures, but
to celebrate projects that didn't pan out and the things that we learned from it.
And so many of our failures at Duolingo ended up turning into foundations for
future successes.
Great, so most people need to know, yeah, right.
Most people need to know that having a project not succeed or
having a project sunset won't set back their career.
All right, we are towards the end of this,
so I'm just going to rapid fire through the recap
and takeaways here because we talked through a lot of things.
So first, we started with people.
Hiring the right people, single most important thing.
You could do it early on.
Generalists, highly recommend.
You want people who are willing to wear many hats as well.
Keep that bar high.
And retain good talent.
Retaining good talent, just as good, if not better,
than being able to hire new talent.
And ensure that employees understand
the value of their time and prioritize that time
accordingly as well.
One thing that we know is your leadership layer will likely
be your limiting factor.
So invest in growing good leaders
and identifying potential there.
And also relatedly, resist the temptation to force someone to be a leader before they are ready.
You will stunt their growth.
And then finally, it is better to have a hole than an a-hole.
Like I said, I will send out these slides afterwards.
Great. In terms of strategy, be aware of the trends.
You know, we rode that mobile wave and it was excellent for us.
Identify and preserve your moats.
What are the competitive advantages that you uniquely want to invest in?
Ours was a huge user base in A-B testing.
It could be very different for you.
Align, as much as possible, your business objectives, your mission, and
your incentives.
If they are aligned, you will have smooth sailing.
If they are misaligned, there will be a lot of unhappiness.
So do your best to align these things.
And try to have a rational and
emotionally detached lens when reading user feedback as well.
Try to listen to the data, listen to all of your users,
not just the most vocal ones.
And make room for innovation and failure, especially.
Prioritization here.
Focus, don't try to do everything at once or be good at everything at once.
And really, really focus on things that are most important to you at the time.
You will not have the resources to do everything at once.
Get really good at saying not yet.
Optimize for fast, well-informed decision making.
Decision making tends to be the thing that drags things on, so
invest in making it speedy and objective.
Use third party tools when they are available, do not invest in in-house things until you
outgrow them and truly outgrow them.
And then finally here on the prioritization front, as a reminder from our CEO, you can
like the whales without committing to saving the whales.
So when it comes to wanting to do good, wanting to do philanthropic efforts, really focus
on the things you're uniquely positioned to benefit and that will give you the highest
leverage and impact.
Organizational structure, be patient.
Don't jump the gun on these things.
Inserting organizational layers, scaling out a feature
before you find product market fit for it,
putting someone in a leadership position
they aren't ready for, hiring functions or positions
before you need them.
As we demonstrated, we actually waited a really long time
to hire certain functions.
And also name teams well.
Try to optimize enabling the team
to get things done autonomously and to feel
a sense of control over what their success can be.
Find the right balance between flexible, agile, scrappy,
versus stability and building knowledge leaders and ownership.
And finally, recognize that organizational structure is always going to be a work in progress.
And you might get grumpy about the cracks and holes, but it's okay.
They will always be there.
And building up a sort of tolerance for vagueness, I think, is one of the best things you could do.
And finally, I used to have a lot of bullets here,
but the only thing I have to say about process as a takeaway
is only implement and create them when you need it
and not earlier.
And if you want to actually look into the processes
that I described today and all the hidden slides,
I'm more than happy to share that after this talk.
All right, we did it.
I think we have seven minutes for Q&A.
Thank you for riding along with me.
Thank you.
Seven minutes for questions.
I have a tooth in my hair.
Hi.
The talk is amazing, absolutely amazing.
Can you shed some light on the A-B testing
on unmeasurable things?
I mean, yeah, because neutral results is not enough, right?
We will know it's A or B.
Sorry, can you repeat the last question?
I just want to know more about A-B testing and measurable things.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, absolutely.
So there's a, I'm happy to share my 2020 talk that actually dives into this.
It has a whole section on this.
The main thing is, so the main thing we couldn't measure well was how well our learners were
actually learning a language because learning takes a very long time.
In most A-B tests we run, we want to run within two weeks, but two weeks is not enough time
to learn something, right?
So we spent a lot of time actually trying to invest in how can we quickly measure learning.
And we honestly I think wasted like a year trying to do this.
And instead we flipped the approach to saying, okay, we have all of these what we call guardrail metrics.
So things like retention that we never want to hurt.
There are things like revenue we don't want to hurt.
And so long as we don't hurt metrics, let us implement changes that are described by a pedagogical expert and our learning scientists as good changes for learning.
And let's call it a win even if all the if all the metrics are neutral, but an expert says this is better for learning.
That is going to be our new win. It's not going to be an increase in user active. It's not going to be an increase in retention.
It's going to be we removed more translation from our app and are doing more monolingual exercises or we were able to.
serve learners harder content without them getting frustrated.
Those were the things that we celebrated as wins,
even if they didn't move our numbers,
because we just knew it was better pedagogically
from the experts that told us.
So, does that make sense?
Yeah, thanks.
That helps a lot.
Yeah.
Hi.
I'm wondering if you can talk a little bit more about how you guys think about monetization,
because, I mean, clearly you guys have to invest a lot in marketing and that's very expensive,
and you know, you guys have certain runways, but at the same time you do want to move on to
efficacy, right? So at what point do you say, okay, we're making, quote-unquote, enough money to
maybe make that our secondary focus, right, and start working on other things versus, you know what,
don't worry about anything else, focus on monetization.
How do you find the right balance there?
Yeah, that's a great question.
Honestly, one, I'm not an expert in at all,
so I can only kind of give my personal take on it.
I think it really is about what is the most important thing to your company,
and it is absolutely not a bad thing at all for companies who want to make money, right?
For us, it really was that based on the people we've acquired over time
and how mission-centric they were,
our priority was being the best and biggest language learning company in the world.
And we knew we needed a ton of money to do it. So everything, when I talk about aligning sort
of your mission, your business objectives and your incentives, the sort of I'm talking about is we
wanted to make money and decided to continue prioritizing making money because we knew this
was the amount of money we would need to be able to penetrate like the English learning markets and
to be able to provide education to the world, etc.
This is how much money we would need to do this.
So we decided to invest in learning as well,
because we said, one, we actually
want to teach languages to our learners.
That's why we all work here.
But two, we would actually hit a market cap
when it came to monetization and growth.
if we only ever serve beginner courses or this number of courses.
Right. We wanted to teach advanced English so people could get jobs
in knowledge jobs in English, even if it weren't their first language.
So in some ways, everything kind of worked together
and that we decided to invest in learning.
Once you realize when it would uncap growth and monetization.
In some ways, it was it was related to monetization.
It wasn't really an if or or
it was more everything needs to work simultaneously towards our one goal.
And monetization and learning were both a part of that.
So when it comes to making enough money,
I think the question asked is, how much do you
need to accomplish your goals?
And then also, is there anything that you actually
need to prioritize a little bit more
to uncap your market potential in the future as well?
Thank you.
Yeah.
I don't know who was first.
Okay, go for it.
So I was wondering, you know, back in 2012
when you started, what was the ways that you guys
went about acquiring new users,
you know, aside from just building a nice app?
Yeah, sorry, what was the, what before new users?
Back in 2012.
Yeah, sorry, I think I missed, like, the verb.
Oh, what was your mechanisms for acquiring new users?
Oh, the mechanisms, yes, yes.
So one really, this is another thing we got lucky on,
is our CEO, Luis, gave a TED talk
about this idea of free education
that I think attracted a lot of people to our beta.
So one of the I think that was one of the biggest drivers of people who signed up for the beta version of Duolingo was this TED Talk.
And I think there was a lot of evangelism in the more like Duolingo actually was born out of Carnegie Mellon University.
So I also think like we evangelized on campus and things like that too.
But truthfully.
We didn't do that much and I think that's why we were lucky is we actually there was a lot of word of mouth that actually did it for us.
And that is not something we ever want to take for granted. But somehow when people tried the product it was new at the time. They were basically like oh my gosh I can actually learn a language like from my house for free.
And word of mouth was by far the highest driving factor even since recently of our growth.
at Dolingo, we actually didn't invest in marketing
for a very, very long time because of word of mouth.
And I think in terms of organic growth,
word of mouth only really comes when you are
a very, very solid brand, an authentic brand, right?
So we actually almost intentionally didn't do
too much like marketing or commercials
because we wanted that organic word of mouth
to not become distilled.
So I would also say engaging with the community
and that Ted Talk, I think were our main drivers.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Brad?
I think we only have a minute left,
but I'm happy to go out to the wrap-up room
also for questions, but go ahead.
So here's a project management question.
I liked your concept of the grease week,
and that's something that we've been experimenting with.
We have no meetings and focus on those things.
And with you having hundreds of new tests a week
and talking about, or a month,
talking about needing key stakeholders involved,
and with work from home, and we've experienced
an increase in meetings and fatigue with that.
Are there any key takeaways you guys have found with reducing meetings or having some
sort of structure around that during work from home?
Yeah, 100%.
So as someone who literally's whole job is to have meetings, I feel the meeting fatigue
even though I'm hardened to it.
I think one of the main things is, I think for me at least,
there are meetings that drain energy
and there are meetings that give energy.
And I think really thinking hard about inventorying,
what are the meetings that are draining energy from everyone?
They're probably not very useful meetings.
And who are the meetings useful for?
as well? And is there a different means other than a meeting for those people to get that
benefit out? So we reduced the number of meetings we had and honestly, in some places, increased
the number of meetings we had based on this. Could this have just been a Slack message?
Could this have been some other process? Can there be fewer people in this meeting? I think
was really important for us, especially during COVID when there was so much meeting fatigue.
The other thing to do is things like grease weeks.
And also I think we give our managers a break at some point.
I think when it comes to performance review season,
we say no meetings this week for managers.
I think literally having just one no meeting week
every now and then really, really helps people to reset.
back to baseline.
But I would say the key culprit in this
really is just useless meetings
or meetings that are way too long.
I have found, this might be controversial,
but 20-minute meetings are a really good length for me.
I have found that the difference between
what you get done in a 20 versus 30-minute meeting
is the same, but you give people a 10-minute break
from meetings by having a 20-minute meeting.
So I think just really optimizing
for making the most of every minute of meeting time,
such as worthwhile for everyone,
was something we had to look at a lot.
Thank you.
All right. Thanks.
I will, I think give the room back
to our lovely tech folks to get set up,
but I am happy to stand aside and answer any other questions
thanks so much for joining again today.
Thank you.