Everyone, um, we're gonna begin and uh, welcome to Same Game and Different Sounds. Um, if your
phone is not muted, please mute it. Um, and uh, this panel's uh, idea is basically it's a
composer panel with an interesting switch. Um, we were all given a, a, a, a, a, a, a, a
uh... gameplay video that we found and we each composed the video in different style so
we're gonna show what we did uh... talk about the differences and uh...
and how different music and sound can impact uh...
the game. Um... sad...
a bit of a sad news uh... Inonter couldn't make it uh... he had uh... surgery and he's fine
everything's fine but uh... his doctors ordered him to stay home
uh... but he sent his video and uh... and we'll see him talking about it in a
video
uh... so
uh...
guys, hello
why don't you go ahead and introduce yourself
uh... and uh... say your favorite uh...
game audio moment
yeah something you remember from
Becky Allen, I am audio director at PopCap Games.
And my favorite moment is in Peggle.
The Peggle moment where everything goes,
da-da-da-da-da, pachow!
Hallelujah!
That's my favorite moment.
It still is my favorite moment, sorry.
Does it really do that?
Because that was really good.
Yeah, yeah, it really does.
Nice.
So, I mean, you know, professional singers.
Hey everybody, my name is Jason Graves. I'm a composer, independent composer, so my favorite.
So the most memorable moment for me with music and games was before I started getting into
writing music for games at all, I played the very, very, very, very, very, very, very,
very, very first Medal of Honor that had Michael Giacchino scoring it.
The reason it's so memorable is that's the first time I'd heard
like a live orchestra playing music in a game.
And I'm not a gamer, I'll admit that.
So I have very, very few game experiences.
But that one really stuck with me.
And I thought, man, I want to do something like that.
It was very emotional.
And even though it wasn't that interactive,
like just the way the music would play,
even if I wasn't doing anything, the music
would start getting more tense.
and I'd start feeling myself like tensing up even if I was just walking on a beach or something.
I really loved the relationship of the music to the player's mood
and that's always kind of stuck with me from the very beginning.
Were you a musician at the time? Like were you already doing music?
Yeah, I was. I think I had done...
like maybe one or two really, really, really small
independent games, but it was all with MIDI.
And the fact that they used live orchestra,
I mean, Steven Spielberg obviously had a lot
to do with that, but that they had live orchestra
and that that could be accomplished within a game
was sort of a meaningful moment for me.
All right, I'm Arnold Neses, I've been composing.
for games for about seven years and two years ago I started my own company and we're turning
music albums to video games, so it's like a very interactive video clip, but which is
as interactive as a game.
Right, so the idea of the panel, as I said before, we chose a pretty random clip on YouTube
from an indie game which is called Bright Memory.
I think none of us knows anything about it, including myself.
So we came to this with fresh eyes.
And we just got the video as it is.
I'm going to show what we got.
Can everybody turn off their cell phones please?
Thank you.
So this is the version that we saw.
And from the little I know about this game, it looks amazing.
As far as I can tell, it is being developed by one guy.
really? It's indie, yeah, it's totally indie. Are you here? Um, like the YouTube description
actually says like uh bright memory indie FPS. Uh and uh I think it's uh it's pretty awesome.
Mute the cow please.
It feels so much longer when you watch it without sound.
Yeah.
It's amazing.
I was surprised how quickly it was over when it had the music.
Um right and once we had that um we um basically the the original clip had the music in
sound we took it out and we rebuilt everything from scratch so um the sound design was uh done
by uh two great guys um Joe Marchuk and Oscar Cohen um they are well Joe describes himself as
a technical sound designer made of real human meat and uh.
And Oscar describes himself as a sound designer who enjoys making laser guns out of beer cans.
They're both students in Berkeley College of Music and they were kind enough to volunteer
and do the sound.
And this is how the video looked after we had the sound in.
And then we stepped in and started doing the music.
So we're just going to show the different versions and discuss them before we show them.
As I said, Inon couldn't make it, so he goes first as a punishment.
But he did send a video of himself talking about it and his considerations and asked us to show it.
Hi everybody. I'm here in my studio and not with you.
And that's quite an unfortunate turn of events, but...
I had to go through a surgery, nothing really serious, but my doctors totally ordered me
to stay and to rest for about two weeks after that.
Hopefully I'll get back and play basketball.
Meanwhile I'm here in my studio and welcome you to the amazing panel that these great
composers put together.
And now to talk a little bit about...
my music for this cue.
Basically the way I was looking at it,
I had to create something that is frantic
on one hand, but on the other hand I had to
create something that will be basically going
over all the sound effects. And what I
found out that actually sometimes slow melodies
they do the job much better than fast melodies. I also found out that lower drum beats
sometimes work a little bit better than all the higher drum beats and the drum sounds because
all the sound effects and the shots are sort of like in a more high range. So basically
I have chosen this kind of palette.
there are basically the synth palette that is giving us sort of like the bottom and the frantic
part and this is basically the triplets.
So this is basically going underneath.
Then there are some effects, orchestral effects.
powerful when it comes to this kind of seed because they are frantic but also
they stand out pretty good.
And this is basically bowed instruments that are playing in a non-traditional way.
And then I definitely put together some sort of like assortment of percussions.
But again, these are pretty low and not very basically busy.
So basically they're giving just the bottom and the rhythm,
but they're not occupying too much space
because that could be a problem.
And lastly, there is a melody
and the melody is being played by low brass.
And the reason why I did it.
was because, again, all the sound effects are sort of like on the higher range,
so this low melody and slow melody definitely standing out pretty good
with all the sound effects without getting in the way.
And you can hear the melody here.
Very basic, ominous, but that's the job.
We know that we are in sort of like a,
you know, a very stressed situation.
So we would like actually to give the ominous part
to the melodic.
And this is also something, melody is always good
to bring from time to time.
Because then you could just hang on to something,
you could remember something.
And here is all together.
So you can hear the bottom part and here's the brass.
Strings are playing the triplets up there but they're not playing all the time so they're
giving us sort of like the excitement but they're not playing all the time so they're
not occupying all the area.
And this is pretty much it.
I wish everybody else lots of luck
and hopefully I can see all of you next time
on both of my feets and running and jumping like always.
See you later.
Yeah, I forgot to talk about Inon at the beginning,
but Inon is actually, I'm pretty sure everyone knows him.
He's one of the top composers in the industry.
He did things like Fallout and Dragon Age,
and he's awesome, and he's an Israeli brother, so yay.
Right, so this is how his final version sounds.
All right, Jason.
I have to follow Enon?
So walk us through the process.
What did you think about the video?
How did you approach it?
Well, first of all, I thought it was genius
that literally none of us knew anything about the game,
what it was called.
There was no direction for music whatsoever,
and we were really allowed to sort of do our own thing.
So how many composers are in the audience
with a show of hands?
Oh, wow.
Yes!
All right, and then how many non-composers
with a show of hands?
Yes!
What about audio directors?
Yeah, alright, there's some audio directors out there.
You know what really struck me about Enon's points is he talked a lot about the mix and
when it comes down to it when you're dealing with a shooter, which so many of these games
have wall-to-wall music with them, it is a big point of contention between the music
and the sound effects and the easiest way to fix that.
And the hardest way to fix it is to know what the sound effects are going to be before you do the music.
A lot of times, the music's running concurrently with gameplay, and the sound effects might be done after the music.
Now, I've worked with some audio directors that will actually...
figure out what key the music's gonna be in,
cause I'll have it in the description of the file,
and they'll purposely pitch the sound effects
to be in the same key as the music,
so that it's sort of a more harmonious balance.
But if you don't have a choice,
a lot of times what I end up doing is just
no.
or expect that there's going to be gunfire and explosions and swords.
So you've got these sort of two lower mid-range
and upper mid-range kind of telephone frequencies
that you know is going to be occupying space before the music even comes in.
So I basically approach this like every other project I've gotten
in probably the last five or seven years,
which is a developer comes to me and says,
and it really is this every time.
We want a completely original score
that doesn't sound like anything
anyone else has ever done before.
And we want to be able to hear
like five or 10 seconds of the main theme
or of an action cue and for people to recognize
immediately that that's a cue from our game.
Okay.
You know, think something really identifiable
like Raiders of the Lost Ark.
But make it unique.
I mean, it's sort of, it's a really, it's a really tall order.
But what I love about that is they're already thinking outside the box in
terms of instruments and sounds.
Um, so with this one, I pretended like they did that as well.
And, um, not knowing what anybody else was doing, I thought, well, probably what the,
uh,
you know sort of and this is nothing against what anyone else's done for
their music I mean I heard Enon's. We haven't heard each other's work. Yeah we don't have any clue.
I'm the only one who has. Oh.
Before or after you wrote yours? After.
So, I mean, what would be expected from a track like this?
Would be you'd have like maybe some big drums and like the big low brass and maybe a choir
in the background or something and kind of lots of, you know, energy in the track.
So I thought, okay, I'm not going to do any of that for this.
I'm going to do like what could be furthest from orchestra and choir and big drums.
So I basically scored it with electric guitars and drum machines.
With the idea that I saw with the enemies, they sort of look
kind of native and low tech.
And you've got all this cool whatever with your samurai
sword and your guns.
And you can fly.
So I thought maybe that would be a nice contrast.
Kind of you're highlighting the technology with the music
that you're using as a player.
And then that way, I've sort of already, the palette of
sounds, if I'm just doing electric guitar and drum
machines, is going to.
be fairly different from maybe what another composer might work on so then the developer
is kind of getting their wish. So how many, how many minutes do I have? Because I've got
a couple of things and I might want to watch the video twice. Okay. Um, why don't we play
the version with the sound effects and then I'll, I'll talk a little bit.
So one of the things that I was really thinking of when I scored it was I was pretending like...
We'll watch it again and you can clap then if you want to.
I was treating it like I was also doing the implementation for the music and that's what
I've done for the last couple of titles that I'm still working on.
I've been doing the implementation as well.
I kind of took my own advice because a lot of people say when I'm starting out in games
what should I do if I want to write music?
I was like, well you need to learn how to implement it.
Then you're sort of...
creating your own job in a way if someone needs sound effects implemented
that's a different talk but it really made me think about this video
differently because when I first watched it
I never listened to the sound effects until I emailed you and said like I
don't think I have the sound effects and then I just I just oh and you already
had the music done yeah yeah I didn't listen to the sound effects before I did
the music because normally I don't get to hear them and it's just I was trying
to keep it real man
So what I thought was I would do something maybe with a kick drum.
and that would give it a little bit of momentum and I'd put it in seven because that would kind of
make it feel like a little hiccupy but still sort of empowering. I didn't want to do anything that
sounded scary or was too ominous or anything like that. I like the idea of the music
making you feel more powerful as a player and kind of urging you on. But I broke it up into
60 seconds. I sort of pretended like this was more like 20 minutes of gameplay and I broke it up into
like eight different sections, which go by super fast
but it's more for the point of illustration than anything else. So the guitars are
really
what is maintaining the energy and there's a little hi-hat in the background
just going
tick-a-tick-a-tick-a-tick-a-tick and that that's really it everything else is
electric guitars.
So from an interactive standpoint, I pretended like we were still in an explore state before
the video started.
And we're going to do another example once I finish talking about this that just has
the music so you can hear it a little bit better.
But there's a, like, reversed drone guitar thing that kind of sounds like a pad.
So that was kind of in your explore state.
And then two seconds in, the camera kind of pans to the right and you see some of the
enemies.
And that's sort of like an enemy spotted trigger.
And that would add in another layer of music that kind of made it getting ready for combat.
That's when the hi-hat comes in.
That's all that comes in.
It's just the hi-hat.
So if you walk away from them or if you don't engage them maybe for 20 seconds, it's just
sort of ticking along and it can loop or bring in different layers and act on its own.
And then at eight seconds, I think maybe you jump first,
or no, you do your force push thing on the enemy.
So I kind of considered that like engaging the enemy.
And that's when the other guitars came in.
So the piece of music, action music,
kind of starts in earnest there.
And you can feel it step up,
but it's still the same number of layers in the same piece.
that has that ambient music bed underneath it.
So this stuff is systematically stacking up,
kind of like a sandwich.
And at 30 seconds,
there's a slow motion thing that happens,
and I don't know what the gameplay reason is for that,
but it seemed like an important sort of moment.
Maybe you're using a cool effect or something.
But also it limited.
the enemies back down to maybe two, there were only like two enemies left. So I consider
that, where did I put, only two enemies left. Thin out music but keep persistent pulse.
So the drum machine and the hi-hat and everything that was sort of defining the combat music,
I like to use air quotes, I can't help it. Defining the combat music, that goes away
and I had a little like, kind of a...
fuzzy wah-wah chord sort of guitar sound that came in and kind of picked up the momentum
from the drum machines but it didn't really sound as combat-y. In the music you'll be able to tell
it just gets really clear all the low end drops out and it's I was thinking of focus focus
like you've got two people left it's not as stressful you know just get these two
guys down and then you're you're free and clear and then once all the enemies are gone um.
It's like the next stage in the gameplay.
I've always been a huge fan of forward motion with music.
So if you're in combat for 30 seconds or for five minutes,
and then it's a defining point where combat's over and you're
moving on, I want the music to change.
I want you to have that reward.
I did this one game based on a film a long time ago called Flushed Away.
It was about rats scurrying around.
But I was so excited.
It was one of the first games that I'd worked on and I got to talk to like Harry Gregson
Williams and he was doing the film score and I was really, really pumped.
And I'm only talking about this because it does have reference but we've got a little
more time since.
So I'm making up for Enon!
I'll just, you know.
So I did this music, but they only had maybe 20 or 25
minutes in the music budget.
It was very, very low budget.
And I think I wrote probably double that, because I always
write more music than is needed.
But even then, I felt like maybe it wasn't enough.
And it was one of the first games I was able to play and
hear my music in it.
So I played for maybe the five minutes on level one, walking
around the kitchen.
and you get all these unlockable things and you collect some stuff and then you
there's an obvious point where you move on to the next room.
I was like, sweet! I had no idea where the music was gonna go. It was very much like,
you know, we need five exploration cues and five cues based on this. None of it
was based on
gameplay. So I was experiencing the music for the first time.
After five minutes I get into the next room and the same piece of music starts
playing again.
And it was such... I just kinda like melted in my chair. I was like,
Really?
I mean, and so I went through and I played it, and then the next room, the same piece
of music, and it's like a 60 second loop, and it just played and played and played and
played.
So I've sort of been obsessive about not having that happen again, no matter what, like I
want to make sure.
Ever, ever, ever.
Like we're forward, forward movement.
So that's why I did a key change.
It's about 40 seconds in.
When all the enemies are gone.
I did a very obvious key change, like down a minor third or something, so it feels completely
fresh.
And in my head, that's sort of like you're back to explore mode, but there's danger.
So it's not going back to the just quiet pad with, you know, ambient sounds.
It's still got pulse going on, and it's still in 7, so it's automatically sort of giving
you that momentum.
Still in combat mode, energy high.
Oh, and then the second big slow motion thing
was the dragon flying by, which was so awesome.
I figured if the video slowed down right there for the gameplay,
that maybe that would be a good place to emphasize something as well.
So there's like a stinger there, basically, that just kind of,
the music slows down briefly while the dragon's flying by.
And then at the very end, I mean, it just sort of stops,
but I pretended like maybe you had just finished that chapter or that point,
and something came up that said, like, great job, we're moving on,
and I put a stinger on it.
So, one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, I've got seven,
seven things in there that really I can't help it now
because I've been composing knowing
that I'm implementing this music myself in these other games.
So I couldn't help but put the music
for this demo together that same sort of way.
And I, you know, really did it that way.
There's not a lot going on.
It's maybe three guitar tracks and the drum machine track
and then some of the stingers are like some swooshes
or hits or something.
But I love the idea of lean and mean and having the music be really nimble
Like a musical ninja kind of jumping around and you're not committing yourself to these big long 30 or 60 second loops
Where if you want to kind of come back around to the beginning it sort of feels like you're starting over again
It was more about
Keeping it changing as much as possible, and I thought the reverse guitar thing at the end was kind of a cool
alien, you know, kind of sounded a little foreign, sounded a little familiar but different.
Yeah.
Awesome.
So, if the developer would approach you and say like, hey, this is my game, what do I
do with music?
You would tell them to go with that, right?
Well, if it's a game like that, I would say yes.
This game, right?
He approaches, he says, this is a short video, what should I do with this?
Absolutely, yeah, adaptive.
And a lot of times, even I will write, let's say that this was going to be, normally I'd
do maybe a five minute piece of music.
would be, you know, combat track one or something like that.
And it would have the ambient layers and kind of the middle
of the road layers and the key changes in it.
Probably every 30 seconds, because I'm just, I like to
have a very short attention span, every 30 seconds
something's changing.
And I've been doing this a lot lately.
I'll write a five or eight minute suite, and then I end
up implementing that as adaptive music.
But there are all these 30 to 45 second points where there's
definite changes, and they're built in loop points.
And within those 30 or 45 second loop points, I'll have
doubled up on certain things.
If it's this track, I would probably have three drum
machine tracks, maybe.
One's got the kick drum, one's got the hi-hat, maybe another sort of mid-level thing, and then I'll do that again times three, but none of them would ever play at the same time.
They'd be kind of taking one and then this one, and then that one goes in, and they'd randomly go in and out when the loop occurs.
So it doesn't really sound like a loop, it just sounds like you're going to the next section.
And that's all very kind of heady and...
abstract sort of ways to explain it.
But it is cool.
I mean, FMOD and Wwise are free to download.
And there's tutorials online.
And there's videos.
And it's one of those things, if you start working with it,
especially earlier in your career.
I did it very late in mine.
But I just realized you start learning how to do it.
And it kind of becomes ingrained in your psyche.
And when you're writing, you can't help but think about how
it's going to be implemented.
And I think that, I mean, it can't be a bad thing.
Meghi, before we continue, would you agree with the adaptive...?
Absolutely.
And I think that once you're implementing, which I highly suggest to all composers, it
helps you write differently because you're thinking about the game, you're thinking about
gameplay, you're thinking about different emotional states.
And no matter where you started or how you're educated,
it will affect how you write your cues.
So I think everyone here should go home and learn WISE or FMOD.
If you don't know it already, even if you're a freelance
or you think that's your path.
It's something that I think we need to move forward with in the industry, as composers in particular.
Because I know that there are a lot of composers that don't do that, but I think it really does change how you compose, it betters the game and the audio experience.
So, yes, I agree.
It's not just about interactivity either, it's about avoiding repetition.
Because let's face it, repetition is like the death of game music.
That's the worst thing in the world.
So you can have one piece of music, maybe it's looped for five minutes and it's only
30, maybe not 30 seconds long, but it's played like five or six times in the loop.
But if you know how to implement and then you're thinking about that from a composition
standpoint.
I've just hit play and walked away and I've let something go for 20 minutes and I never felt like,
oh yeah, here we go again. It's constantly recycling. There's all this randomness and
effects and things you can have, like more enemies. I'm going to increase the distortion
in wise on my drum track because there's more enemies and that's actually happening
outside of anything that you've written. That's happening in real time in the engine.
And those kind of choices that you make within Wwise or Fmod
are compositional choices.
Those are creative choices.
So if you're just handing off your tracks,
you're missing out on all this creativity.
And I think, personally, I find that a very exciting place
to work.
If you need to describe the feeling you
were trying to support in the video in one word or two words,
what would it be?
Empowerment.
The main empowerment.
Empowerment, yeah.
With the air quotes.
With the air quotes, yeah.
Yes.
Alright, awesome.
Cool, so...
Yeah, yeah.
Or play it, you can just play it without the sound effects.
Oh, we didn't, right.
Music only.
Yeah, music only.
And just think about these key points,
like the six or seven points that I was talking about.
You'll hear the music change.
Right, now I need to follow that.
This is gonna be fun.
Right, so for me this was a bit of a weird video
because it kind of went against every instinct
I usually have.
So the first panel I ever did as a composer's panel,
we were talking about adaptive music
and I was the first one to answer the question.
So the guy was moderating, asked like,
what are your thoughts about adaptive?
And I said like, it's kind of a bit like.
a rush to the goal, you know, where a lot of developers want to go that way, but not
all games need it, and I was kind of... and then it turned out that the other guy on the
panel had his own, like, adaptive software company.
So it became, like, a whole argument about adaptive.
And usually I'm...
I wouldn't say that I'm not a big fan, but I...
I'm very careful with adaptive.
Like I ask myself and the developer a lot of times before I go adaptive, does this game
really need it?
Because like, I don't know, a story driven telltale game usually can do without.
And there is a downside to adaptive, at least the way I feel is that there is much less
control of the music.
You know what I mean?
It's like...
it creates a whole new way of composing and a whole new way of
listening to music and creating music which doesn't exist anywhere outside of
video games
but you don't always even know how it's gonna sound right you don't
you're not sure how when the motive's gonna come in you're not sure
like you're kinda releasing it out there and it's always a really scary moment
for me where you go like
this is the adaptive music please be good
then you're playing the build for the first time and usually it's cool but it's a very scary
moment for me. Um but at the same time that I was working with this um uh I also teach a
composing course in uh in Israel and uh and we were talking about adaptive and then I saw this
video and I thought like this this is the one moment I would definitely go adaptive. Um this
is exactly the game where where this needs to happen. Um.
And the second thing is that usually I kinda, uh, I'm on the side of, you know, supporting
the story first of all and the feeling and like asking, always asking the developer what, what
should, like, what do you want or the game designer, probably the more correct person, like,
what do you want the player to feel at the same time, right? Because, um, and here I was
like, alright, so there is like...
guns and swords and zombies or whatever they are and the dragon and we're walking and it
kind of felt like this whole salad of things that someone mostly wanted it to look cool
like it's done really really well but I feel it's like a bit over the limit you know what
I mean like it's
it's like let's take every cool element that has ever been tried in a video game and pull
them all together and make a whole thing out of it. Um so I kind of went with uh the extreme
for my version um uh so I was kind of thinking okay I should take like
not the most expected genres here and they have to be cool and they have to be like um you said
that they need like you wanted the guitar at the end to feel different so I was kind of
thinking maybe something oriental or you know not the totally western sound. Um and adaptive. So
yeah and I was kind of thinking what Elias can do. We talked about F mod and W wise but um
at my course we were talking at Elias at the same time so I was
thinking like I'm gonna look what Elias can do and uh and try to build something
that will work uh to show the the students as well. Um and yeah so I'm
warning this went a bit extreme but
Thank you.
So yeah, this is also, like you said, pretty much the same like same points you have the
exploration at the beginning where you're walking and
not much happens and then you see the enemies so the music becomes
more intense. The dragon obviously is a sync point that I think all of us
used. And also there was this moment where everything becomes pink
that I kinda felt it's the power up or something so I thought of that as
a bit of a different layer and
yeah. Alright. Becky?
Yeah. You have mine there too?
So I'll just confess I wasn't paying attention when we chose
the clip, and so it's interesting when I looked at
the clip, I'm like, oh, it's action.
Okay, awesome.
It's Tom's photo, originally.
Tom's photo.
Oh, it's so a Tom choice.
And then he really insisted on picking this video
and just went away.
He was like, this is the video.
Thank you, Tom.
Right, bye guys.
So when I paid attention and I looked at the video
I'm like, oh my God, I've never written in this genre.
But I'm game.
I'm going to do this.
Sure.
And then I'm like, OK, well, I guess I'll do something weird
and non-actiony, although it ended up a little actiony, I
have to say.
But then I come from CalArts background, so highly
experimental.
But in the last few years, I've been doing really cute
music over at PopCap.
And that's been really fun.
But I kind of hearken back to, oh, I really like shapes.
I like sound masses.
I like Penderecki.
I like Ligeti and those kinds of things.
So I was like, I want sound shapes, so I'm just going to start thinking about that.
So I got out.
I thought, I need like those kind of extended technique types.
sounds and yet at the same time I'm gonna work with what I have. Um so I had spitfire string
quartet, I had some other sample libraries, I have a profit 12, um I'm like I'm gonna use those
things. So, so then I like um I started like listening through the sounds to be like I'm gonna
also not only think of shape but I'm gonna come from the sound up. So um listen to the sounds,
see what they might inspire.
Because remember, this is not in my wheelhouse,
so I don't have like any kind of,
not that anybody here has a formula,
but I'm like, don't know.
So, listening to the sounds, choosing the sounds,
and thinking about sound shapes.
So, I found some really cool articulations in the strings,
and then I would like put it on a track.
I was using Pro Tools.
uh... i put on track and i'd make this test blob of black
that stuff
and i'm like oh that's cool
it's kind of like insects
so i'm like oh yeah i like that
and so then i was looking for that kind of stuff and i put these like blobs in
different spots that i thought blobs should go
i really do come from a formal training so it's uh... yeah
it doesn't sound like it at the moment
But I thought, you know, this is good.
I'm coming from a place of shape.
And then I started thinking about the shape of the video
and the different points like you were talking about
and you were talking about as well.
Like where are the markers of change, right?
Because we all do adaptive music of some kind.
Like where are those moments where I want to change
in the melody or the feel or something like that?
So I chose those hand blast type moments, you know,
as the shape shifters.
And, um, I also emphasized them with some other weird sounds that I found.
You know, and, um, added to the sounds that the sound designers made.
Um, sorry, sound designers.
Um, and then I had all that going and I'm like, okay, but this is action.
So.
I'm gonna throw in a taiko drum.
Woo!
Which I did.
And I did use low brass so in the middle section I'm like, it has shape but I also want it
to, but I'm gonna, I'm gonna pay homage to the action cue and I want it to have a big
payoff.
Okay, big payoff.
So I chose my like peak of the cue, I'm like the three quarter mark in the traditional
sense.
Bam!
and then it drifts back.
So it's kind of like an A, B, A.
Again, to the shape.
So, conceptually, coming from ideas of shape
and sound and structure,
and then also working with the actual sounds that I had,
and then I built this thing.
Amazing trick.
Ha ha ha.
Thanks for watching!
I love it.
And you say you haven't done action before.
That was great!
The dragon is an interesting point because two of us made the music go even higher on the dragon,
like Jason and Dinan, and the two of us just dropped the music.
I did it because I wanted to get this effect of, you know, like...
Right, yeah.
Like, holy shit.
Oh!
Yeah.
Me too, I want to feel different there.
And it's like a trick that actually a lot of, like, is being used really often and it
really works well.
Like in Lord of the Rings when Rohan attacks, like, there is like the whole main theme and
then the moment the two armies collide they go like nothing.
Right.
Like, when do you use silence or when do you back off to let something else happen?
Like a feeling, you know?
Yeah.
Alright, cool.
So, what was the original like?
Oh yeah, that'll be interesting.
Oh, there's a music score to the original?
Yeah.
Cool, who did that?
I don't know, I've been looking.
Yeah, I actually, I wanted to apologize about it.
Like, I think he's awesome and I have no idea who he is.
If you know who he is, let us know.
Or she.
Yeah, I, the developer's name I, I think is Zeng Xiancheng, I pretty sure I'm not
pronouncing it correctly but uh, I'm not sure where the music is from, it can be stock
music or, I, I tried to find out but I didn't.
They also took the music out with the dragon.
But yeah, it's interesting because I don't know, to me it's kind of, the original felt
like a lot of elements that each of us kind of emphasized and there it's like.
know a lot of the things together. You know what I mean?
Alright cool. Um so let's uh talk a little. Um I have uh two
things I I prepared questions but I don't think we have enough
time we're just gonna uh let the people ask questions. But um one
question I I thought was um interesting in this case is um
so obviously like it's it's very different right? It's uh
every
Seeing the same thing with different music makes you feel really different and each time I'm doing this panel
I'm really surprised by like how many options there are you know what I mean like I always come in thinking like
With this video it's gonna sound exactly the same everyone are gonna do exactly the same thing and then I keep getting surprised
So, um, the question is, um, do you think there is a right answer? Do you think the, how would,
like, if you would be the developer, let's say it like that, how, based on what would you
choose which is the best? Not, not like which person, you know, what, which, let's say you're a
developer, you're seeing four different videos with different music, you're, yourself is not a
musician, do you just go with your instinct? Do you...
Well, that's the blessing and curse of music, isn't it?
It all comes from a personal standpoint.
Each person hears something.
If it's like heavy metal with orchestra, that's going to
elicit one emotional response from one person and a
completely different emotional response from another person,
just based on their own musical experience.
So it's completely different from person to person.
So
you think it's it should be chosen by the game designers uh...
personal favorite at the end of the day or should he go like you know
go to a composer and say like
i don't know you you need to decide who makes the music here
I think it depends, I mean if you're talking about an audio director, usually they'll be
the ones probably making the decision or?
No, I'm more speaking about audio directors are musicians eventually, right?
Like they usually, at least they know music really well.
In theory, yeah.
That's super interesting.
Beautiful.
Hope.
So, uh, no, I'm speaking, if you're not a musician at all, you're just an indie developer
or, you know, a company without an audio director, um, and because this happens, they're getting,
uh, contacting musicians, right, um, they see a few, uh, versions of things and they
need to decide which one they're going with.
Yeah, well, in that case, if they're deciding probably without knowing themselves,
they're probably going to look to references within, you know,
the industry of games that are like that genre.
They're going to be like, oh, I listened to this, I listened to this,
I really like this soundtrack, I like how this music works here.
Probably they'll do their research and they'll do it based on.
probably experiences they've already had.
The shortfall of that is that they don't get to have that new experience.
Like Jason was talking about, like, make it something that we've never heard before.
They don't get that piece if they're doing it based on something they already know.
Unless they're quite adventurous or they already have a relationship with a composer.
If they have a relationship with a composer, they probably will trust that composer
to come up with something unique.
And that's a great situation, I have to say.
That would be the best of both worlds for everybody, but of course it requires either a previous relationship between the audio director and the composer,
or maybe the audio director knows of other titles that the composers worked on, and don't necessarily want the composer to do that title again,
but they appreciated the aesthetic that the composer brought to that title, and said, hey, could you do something like that for our game?
I mean, as the composer, and you're the composer and audio director, but I've never been able to hire myself, but I do appreciate...
Oh no, no, no, that's not what I meant.
No, it's a great thing.
I appreciate being able to have a big level of trust, because that's really what it comes down to.
What really opened my eyes when I was working on Tomb Raider with Alex Wellmer...
He said that, biggest compliment I've ever gotten is he said that I made him look like
he knew what he was talking about when they had meetings and he was talking about the
music.
Because it is like, I mean, the audio director is like putting a lot of trust in the composer
to basically make them look good and make them like, hey guys, look, I know what I'm
doing.
I hired the right person and they're doing everything that we talked about and they're
doing it really well.
Because if it doesn't work out for whatever reason, if it's, you know, the music direction
changes, the game changes, it kind of all comes back and falls onto the audio director's
shoulders like, how come the music isn't working?
And then you fall back to well maybe we should use some temp tracks and figure out something and like get you know
This is like a Bioshock game and Gary Scheinman did Gary Bioshock
Let's hire Gary and it falls to that would that would be an amazing choice
But it falls to like a safe creative choice because it's something that they've already done as opposed to Gary's an amazing composer
He does all these different things. Let's hire Gary and see what he can come up with
As opposed to trying to find someone to fit a mold that you've already predetermined.
Like, get someone that you appreciate as an artist and let them help you build the mold.
Trust the artist.
Yeah.
I agree with that.
Trust your composers, developers.
Yeah.
Are you in here, developers?
All right.
Let's take questions from people here.
There's a microphone right up there.
That's a very lonely microphone.
Do you mind stepping up to it?
Don't be shy.
Hey, this is really fascinating, thank you.
I would love some more general tips on adaptive music.
I've been dabbling in it myself lately, and I find,
I don't know if it's because I can't,
I am too close to it.
It never feels right to me.
I mean, obviously, if you're writing music
that's very bed-based, then it works better
than if you're writing music that has some melodic elements
or harmonic changes.
So I guess like, you know,
are there some general guidelines?
Like, do you always try to have transitions locked
to a beat or to a bar?
Do you always...
Yeah, and does that work even if there are interruptions to melodic material?
Like, stuff like that.
Um, I can do a quick, so I, like if I'm doing a five minute piece of music, that's
going to be all these different layers and stuff, most of the time I'll keep it
all in the same key.
So the whole thing's in D minor, which might sound amazingly boring, but that
has already limited me to sort of the a thousand different versions of
things I could do in my head.
everything's tempo locked, everything's in the same key, maybe there's some meter changes,
but I've got to program that all into Wwise when I'm putting it in. But the idea is like
simplicity, less is more. And lots of randomization, at least for me. And I mess with the meter
and I also do the walk away test where I just hit play and I'll go and, you know, like grab
a bite to eat. I'll let it play and kind of hear it in the background as I'm walking around
and kind of try to...
distance myself a little bit because you get sick of it. I mean you work on the same two minutes for a day, you hate it.
And you have to be objective and try to then implement it as well. It's definitely tough.
I agree with the lock in a key or related keys to different sections so that when you move from one thing to the next it makes sense.
And then I sometimes use custom queues but they're at very specific points.
And I also lock in tempo early.
Because those types of things, when you do simplify, as Jason just said, to certain things that do not change,
then you're going to make other things more easy in terms of...
Transitions are the hardest part with adaptive music, right?
You're branching off to something new, you don't know when it's going to happen.
That's really interesting to think about, right?
And compositionally interesting, too, I think.
Quick follow-up, just what's the shortest loop you've ever composed as a section?
Because I think if anything I go too long, so what's like the shortest?
Oh yeah, well I could say in mobile, they don't let you go long because it's all about space, right?
So, I don't know, I don't do anything. Music-wise?
Yeah, like if it's an adaptive context, if you're exploration to battle, what's the shortest?
I did music for a game called Mark of Kree, which was one of the first sort of MIDI-based
adaptive music things.
It was all a lot of percussion, so I had loops that were literally like a tenth of a second
because it was just a...
And I had it going...
And it was that little tiny thing was looping.
I had 15 seconds.
But I very much agree with what you said.
At least when I'm working with adaptive, I spend, I don't know if most of the time but
a lot of time, you know, perfecting the transitions.
um this is for me kind of the the place where it's like uh yeah staying in the same key and and
the tempo that's um usually the case in adaptive I think uh but when stuff change I want them to
feel as natural as I can so I usually spend a lot of time uh on that so you know going with
stingers and uh things like that and. Cool thank you so much. Thank you. Uh you were talking
earlier about how uh.
the feeling of the music was trying to be condensed down into one word
and I noticed that all of your takes had very different ideas of what that scene
seemed like. Some of them were empowering, others tense and dramatic,
others chaotic. Do you think that if the
audio director or the narrative game designer came up and said, hey
we want this scene to be empowering or chaotic or
they had one of these ideas, would that have made your music more similar to
each other
or could it still have just been as varied?
So I think A is, it's the one question I always ask a
developer.
Like this is, no matter how long we've been working
together, no matter anything, I always say that like, give me
the one or two words that, you know, to dance it down to.
I think it really helps musically.
And yeah, personally, I think it would make it a lot.
closer like uh... the music right because
you know uh... being like epic right it's
uh... if if that's the feeling that you you want to do then
we will probably go in the general same direction like it wouldn't be as
different as as it is now the core difference for mostly uh... for i think
good composers is when
the bass is interpreted in a different way you know what i mean like uh...
when you think like this this needs to be sad or
know, lonely, which are two different things. And uh, yeah.
Hi, thank you all. I was just curious if these videos would be
available for download or educational kind of use.
Yeah, they're supposed to be in the GDC vault.
In the vault? Awesome.
I think so, I hope I'm not lying.
Fastest answer ever.
Yeah!
Ha ha ha!
Good!
Hey, thank you guys very much.
I have a question that's more about the collaborative process.
So I know, Jason, you talked about, like, in the mix,
you sometimes make the mix to sound.
It can be tempting to make a mix that sounds full on its own
without really knowing how the sound effects are going to play.
And if it turns out that they don't,
they actually kind of clash at the end of the day.
How do you usually go about remixing or iterating with the sound designer if it's a different person?
Usually by the time...
everything's kind of getting implemented and kind of finished, it's too late.
So it's more the music mixer or the audio director's shoulders to
kind of carve things out with EQ normally, just to kind of make things sit better.
And again, it's probably pretty dramatic EQ, where if you listen to the music by itself,
it's like, where are all the lower mids?
Like, how come there's no bottom end?
Well, that's for explosions and footsteps or whatever.
It's better when it's a back and forth thing, but it's not always the case.
Sometimes it's just impossible.
There's multiple composers, multiple people doing sound effects,
multiple levels going on at the same time, depending on the scope of the game.
Gotcha. Cool. Thank you.
I think we're out of time.
Yeah. Oh, one minute.
One more. One more.
We're getting. Yeah, you're good.
So I was just curious, it seemed like you scored these, and I think contextually because of the
dragon it's probably implicit there's something important happening there, but how might you
have scored this video differently if it was definitely just like one of those emergent
moments where you're like in an open world and you just sort of run across these things,
and it's entirely possible the player might go through almost exactly the same fight like
five minutes from now?
How might, because these seemed like, you know, a big moment.
How might you keep that intensity up with the full
knowledge that that exact same music might play again or
something very similar to it might play again?
I've done a lot of stuff like that where you're using a
stinger to highlight the moment.
And then when you're programming the music into the
engine, you can, you know, duck the rest of the music.
Or you could even have, if it was something that may happen
at least more than once, like it's going to happen four or five times, I would have four or five different stingers that would randomly and not repeatedly play
and maybe duck the other music out or also trigger a second layer that had like a pad or like a little choir or something that kind of emphasized the moment.
But it would only do it that one time and then it would trigger a different one a different time.
just make sure it automatically varies.
Right, and the gameplay is going to be...
Yeah, repeating element that you know would be significant each time,
then you can use that as a compositional element
and a way to change your music.
Thank you.
Right, thank you very much.
Yeah, thank you.
Thank you.