Hello everyone. Good evening. I am psyched to be here for you all. My name is Rob Kovacs.
That's my real name. And I'll be performing under my video game artist name, which is
88bit. And I'll be playing a bunch of video game music for you on piano. Mostly NES era
video game music. And I'm going to start right away. But this is live. This is pre-recorded.
So I do have the chat open a little bit too. Can't really read it at the moment. But typing
the chat looks great. It makes it feel like I'm not just practicing in my room, in my
house here. But thank you for being here. I hope you enjoy the concert. I'm going to
play it. There we go. Short and sweet. Thank you. So that was composed by Kenichi Matsubara.
And I'm going to jump right into one of my favorite games as a kid. RC Pro-Am, composed
by David Wise. One of the more unique soundtracks for the NES because it uses right off the
bat block triads. And you don't hear a lot of triads in NES because of the limitations
of only three voices. But here we go. This is the complete soundtrack for RC Pro-Am.
another NES game. This is a game called Star Tropics. So I also like to do lesser known
video games from this era because there's over 680 some NES games and they all have
music and some really great stuff. And I really like to shed some light on some of the lesser
known soundtracks like this one, Star Tropics. So this is a game that was only released in
North America. And the protagonist's name is Mike Jones. It's about as generic American
name as you can get. Trying to appeal to American kids. Mike Jones liked to play baseball and
his main weapon of choice is a yo-yo. So here's the first chapter of Star Tropics composed
by Yoshio Harai.
There we go. The first chapter of Star Tropics. Can you guess which one was the boss theme?
Probably. Lots of whole tone. Thank you. Are you guys saying anything important in the chat?
Is anyone else nervous? It's just me. Right beforehand I was like, oh my gosh, I'm like
tired. So I'm over in Cleveland, Ohio. So Eastern time. My body's like, all right,
why don't you go to sleep and then start playing and then the heart doesn't know what to do. Now
it's all jumping around. So anyway, thank you for being here with me. I hope you enjoy this.
I am very much as well. So I'm going to change it up a little bit. I'm going to break out of the
8-bit era and do something a little more modern. So earlier this year, I got asked to make an
arrangement, a medley for the Gang Awards. They asked me to make a piano medley of the six nominees
for music of the year. So that was a lot of fun. That was a big challenge to try to mix six
completely different soundtracks together. But that was recorded and debuted for the Gang Awards,
which was thrilling to be a part of. And I'm going to play that next. So that's going to be,
I'll tell you the games real quick. It's Fantastic Creatures, REND, Star Wars Jedi Fallen Order. That
one, by the way. Spoiler alert. Undersea, Borderlands 3 and Erika.
It's Fantastic Creatures, REND, Star Wars Jedi Fallen Order.
So that was the 2020 Gang Awards medley.
All right, I'm gonna go back to some 8-bit music here, some Nintendo music.
So this one is a sort of a hybrid soundtrack.
It was originally an arcade game and then ported over to the NES.
So the arcade game was Marble Madness.
That's when I played Marble Madness.
It was composed by Brad Fuller and Hal Cannon.
And Brad Fuller's unfortunately no longer with us.
I certainly wish I had a chance to meet him and play this for him before he passed.
And Hal Cannon, I know nothing about.
I know nothing about Hal Cannon.
I've searched the interwebs forever.
And I say this every concert.
If anybody knows anything about Hal Cannon, I would love to reach out to him and interview
him about the music for this game.
So I absolutely love it.
It's originally for an arcade game using a Yamaha, one of the first games to use a Yamaha
DX7 chip.
And so it's very unique soundtrack.
I'm gonna do a version that's mostly based off the NES port of it.
And that port was done by David Wise, who changed it up.
Basically he had to change it up for the limitations of the Nintendo, reducing everything
down to just three voices.
But he also changed it musically.
He changed melodic notes and he made it darker.
He made it kind of more sinister sounding.
So that's what I grew up on.
That's what I like.
So most of this version is gonna be on the NES.
Most of my arrangement is based on the NES.
But except for level five.
Level five is gonna be more on the arcade, more from the arcade arrangement.
And if you've never heard the arcade arrangement, I highly recommend checking out.
You can find it on YouTube.
It's just wild.
It's wild sounding.
So here's the whole soundtrack to Marble Madness.
I very much hope you enjoy it.
Oh man.
That is a fun one.
I always joke, like, that game is so hard and that sixth level music is so cool but
no one ever heard it.
Because nobody could ever get past the second level.
But that's the whole soundtrack.
And it's one of my favorites.
So I hope you enjoy that.
Thank you for the comments in the chat.
I see them.
My glasses are somewhere else.
I can't really read them.
Okay, what do we have next here?
I think I'm gonna slow it down a little bit.
I am.
I'm gonna do something more modern.
Super modern.
It was written this year.
And this is a piece of my own.
So I'm currently composing a soundtrack for a VR game called Straylight.
And I'm on the development team.
And we have been working for almost two years on this game.
And it is a lot of fun.
It's currently in early access.
And I'm very proud to be part of it.
It is a kind of game where you're in this cosmic world.
You're in space.
We have a gun called a Straylight gun that connects to different floating objects.
And you get to fling yourself and float through space and try to basically get through this
obstacle course.
And all the worlds are visually very kind of weird and different.
And I've gotten to compose the music.
And it's basically my synth prog rock odyssey is what I'm doing for the music.
So it's very fun.
And I'm very proud of the game.
So if you have VR, go check it out.
It's called Straylight.
And I know one of my...
I think one of my team members is in the chat.
Shoutout to Dan if you're in the chat.
I don't think you've ever heard me play this, Dan.
But I'm gonna do...
This is currently the second level from Straylight.
So that's it.
That's the sound...
One of the songs from the game, Straylight.
It's personally much cooler with all the synth sounds.
But it does work on the piano.
Back to...
I think we're gonna go back to some 8-bit stuff.
Yes.
So I got to play...
How am I doing on time?
I've got plenty of time.
All right.
Short little story.
I got to play MAGFest 2019.
First MAGFest I ever went to.
Blew my mind.
It was amazing.
I kind of just started the 8-bit project.
And started playing and performing and making videos of NES soundtracks.
And I was working on some Mega Man 2 music.
I knew the composer, Takashi Tateishi, was gonna be there.
And I was like, oh, man.
What if he gets to hear my music?
My concert?
That would be so cool.
So I reached out to him, just to at least let him know that, hey, I'm gonna play some
of your music at MAGFest.
This is like Facebook Messenger.
So who knows if he even would get it.
But the whole event was awesome.
Earlier in the day, too, I saw his panel.
And you talked about his career and how he wrote that music.
And somebody asked him, what's your favorite piece?
What piece are you most proud of?
And he said, the ending theme from Mega Man 2.
Which is a really unique video game music piece, especially in that era.
It's very slow.
It's like a slow ballad, kind of somber song at the end of Mega Man 2.
It's very emotional.
And it's kind of rare for NES games.
He said that was his favorite one.
So anyway, I saw my concert.
I don't see him in the audience or anything, so I played through the Mega Man 2 music.
And I get to the ending theme, and I remember thinking, man, I really hope someday that
he could hear my arrangement of it.
I think he would really appreciate it if he moved.
After I played, it was a big open atrium.
So I said, thank you, Takashi Tateishi, if you're out there anywhere.
Thank you for such wonderful music.
And then the audience was like, he's right here, he's right here.
And he was in the audience the whole time, filming, taking pictures, taking pictures
with the audience.
He came up and gave me a big hug.
It was just such a surreal moment.
And I love telling that story.
To think that I can meet the composer from this video game that I used to play as a kid,
and I didn't even understand that a person made that music.
It was super cool.
So now I'm going to share with you some of the highlights from the soundtrack for Mega
Man 2.
We have the opening, the ending, and then the three boss themes.
We got Metal Man, Heat Man, and Air Man.
Metal Man.
Heat Man.
Air Man.
Metal Man.
Alright, that was a little Mega Man 2.
Hope you enjoyed that.
This is just a personal note here.
This is going to be my last performance and my last day with this piano.
I recently bought a brand new Boston, Steinway made Boston piano.
Grand to replace this bald one here, which is a nice, fine instrument,
but it has its limitations. And just right now, the notes are starting to stick.
So, come on back up there, bud. So, with the humidity change that happens.
But I'm very excited. This has served me very well for a long time.
Very excited to get this new piano and to, yeah,
bring out all the detail that I'm trying to play.
I've got two more here, so not ending quite yet.
Just a fun little game too. Since I don't have any cool visuals,
I threw in a couple Nintendo paraphernalia in the background. Maybe you've noticed already.
But there are four.
If you haven't found them yet,
you have about 15 minutes to find them.
This is one of my favorite mugs.
This Neon Cat mug here, which is a little hint on what I'm going to play next.
So, this isn't quite video game music. This is video game music adjacent. You can think of it that way.
I'm going to do the Neon Cat theme.
Originally written by Dannywell P.
And then made famous through the YouTube video Neon Cat.
I just love the song, and it's fun, and I'm going to play it for you all tonight.
Neon Cat