Hello, everyone.
Welcome.
So I came here two years ago, and I
spoke about my edible tabletop games.
That's games you have to eat to play.
And two years ago, I had six games.
I now have 13 games.
So the key thing about all of them
is you have to eat to play.
And it's not meant to be a gimmick.
It's meant to be a core part of the gameplay.
So I've put these 13 games into a cookbook that I successfully kick started last year.
Yay. Still time to back.
But we're here to talk about experimental gameplay, right?
In fact, for me, that is experimental food gameplay.
So since food and eating is such a key part of my games,
I've had to play with the food itself and playing with the food changes the gameplay of the game.
It makes it more difficult sometimes, it can be different.
So these are...
some of my experiments,
and I'm going to try to talk about
what has gone right and what has gone wrong.
So first up, I want to talk
about this game called Highty Assassin.
In Highty Assassin, it's
a social deduction game for three players.
You get assigned your role by eating an item,
and then you have to work out who you can trust.
Now, the thing is that people didn't
actually trust their taste buds
enough and couldn't trust their flavor.
So we had to add color in as well.
So there's color and flavor to work out what your role is.
All right, next up I'm going to talk about a game,
Gingerbread Friends.
In Gingerbread Friends, you ask a group
a set of tough questions, and then you have to guess
how they'll respond, what the majority will say.
If you're right, you get to pull over a lid,
and underneath there might be a prize.
So, let's go to a demo.
All right, so underneath might be a prize.
Here we go, so I don't know if you can show
that there's a little prize in here,
so I'm like, yay, I got a prize, woo-hoo.
But, whatever.
Or I might get information about where there is a prize.
For example, here, there's a little piece of paper
that says one.
Now, you'll notice I've just pulled off two lids,
and I haven't eaten these.
I don't actually need to eat these to play this game.
So I'm like, well, that's no good.
I'm going to have to change that.
So I added frosting to the bottom.
So I'm going to now, uh-uh.
Ah.
I'm going to lick it.
This actually has turned out all right.
You can kind of read it well, not on that thing.
But you can kind of see what it says.
To me, it kind of kept getting very smudged
when I was practicing a lot.
So I'm like, that's no good.
So I tried another option, this one, again, frosting.
Underneath here, it's a bit difficult to see,
but is royal icing.
Because royal icing sets harder than frosting.
So I'm playing with those properties.
All right, back over here then.
This is how it looks in the game. There's like a set of symbols and stuff that you use and it's the key.
All right, next game. Next game is called Treasure Cake. Treasure Cake is meant as a kid's birthday party game
where you use a bubble tea straw to put it into the cake and try to find secret stashes of things.
The constraints of what this secret stash might be
is that it probably had to sit in a cake for maybe overnight.
And I wanted it to be obvious to all of the players
that they had discovered something.
I didn't want kids to lie, and I wanted it to be a fun,
oh my, I found a thing.
All right, so demo.
AUDIENCE LAUGHS
Uh oh.
Mm. Uh oh.
NOAH LAUGHS
First offer said, mm-hm, this is gonna come out.
I would like pop rocks.
So I've got a bunch of pop rocks in my mouth.
Seems like a good idea.
But the problem is you have to store it
in cream probably, in the cake.
You can't just store a bunch of pop rocks by itself.
I'm still popping, so I won't be able to show you
that if I eat this, you end up,
it won't pop anymore.
So that's no good.
So I came up with another solution, which is this one.
So it turned my tongue bright blue and potentially the rest of my face.
And that's what I ended up using in the game. It's recommending that you use blue food dye.
All right.
Next game is a game called Flip and Stick.
It's about there's a bunch of cookies
with peanut butter on them.
And you've got to throw items at them and see what sticks.
So part of it is you then flip it upside down
and see if all of the items stay on board.
So the key thing in this game is the glue,
what you're putting on top, to see how that works.
So back again to the demo station.
Here we go. So I've got a few options here. I've got some frosting over here.
I'm not very good at throwing, so we'll see. And that kind of worked.
And I've got some dip over here and some hummus over here
and some peanut butter over here.
So you can kind of see they all sort of stick a bit.
I mean, if I was further away, stuff might bounce a bit more.
It's going over to other spots.
But the key thing now is like what happens when I flip them upside down?
So the hummus works well. That's great.
Frosting here doesn't work.
That's a fail.
Peanut butter.
I mean, I had that in the picture,
so you've got to assume this is going to work.
Did.
And then like dip over here.
That's super goopy.
Oh, but it actually works.
There we go.
It's always a mystery sometimes with the experiments.
Okay next up is a game called Cookie Cruncher. In Cookie Cruncher there are a bunch of different
cookies, obviously because it's called Cookie Cruncher, and you've got to put them strategically
on a board to get points. Now the catch is that you can bite these cookies to try to make them fit better.
So what sort of cookies am I going to use?
Let's go over here to the demo station.
So I'm going to start with an un-iced cookie,
and you may not be able to see it,
but I've put a little line here on this cookie to
show where I'm attempting to bite it.
So let's try this. That worked pretty well.
I was able to get it to the point that I
wanted it to for what I aimed to.
All right.
Now I'm going to try one with icing on it.
Let's see what happens with the icing on it.
Uh-oh.
I've lost a part that has a point on it.
So now I'm losing points because the icing cracks and that goes all the way through it.
Now I have some other ones here.
I don't know if you can hear this on the mic, but they're shaking.
That's kind of weird.
All right.
Let's try this one.
What's happened now is I've got a whole lot of sprinkles
inside it.
And so if you play with this game,
you've got to be careful not to get
to the center with the sprinkles in it,
because they'll all fall out.
So this is kind of how it looks in the book,
How to Make the Three-Dimensional Cookies.
And I also have a version called Toast Cruncher, which
is with ham and eggs instead.
Oh, our final game, yay, I'm making good progress,
is a game called Flavor Roulette.
In Flavor Roulette, there's a bunch of items
that all taste the same,
but one of them doesn't taste like the other.
And you need to keep a poker face while eating these.
Now, coming up with the recipes for this is very difficult.
You want something that's slightly gross,
so that it's hard to keep a straight face,
but not so gross that you have to spit it out,
because that's not really fair.
Spice is very difficult to deal with,
because people have very radically different reactions
to spice.
I can't really deal with much more than a mild spice,
whereas other people are like, oh yeah.
So I am now going to torture myself up on stage.
The ratio here is more than one of these being bad.
And I am going to try to eat it.
And then you're going to hopefully try to guess whether
I got a good one or a bad one.
Mmm-hmm.
OK.
Do we, I think we've probably got time for a show of hands.
Do we have, who thinks that that was a good one?
Okay.
And who thinks that was a bad one?
Okay, yeah, it was bad.
I've got...
That was like a bunch of like powdered cinnamon
and like my throat is like, my mouth is so dry
and I'm like, I gotta get some water.
So like, if you know, like if I was standing up here
for longer, you would notice I would be grabbing water
very suspiciously and going,
Okay. So that's all the demos I'm talking to you about today.
I've got 13 different games and they're all really different.
There's still so much more that can be done with food.
So I hope other people experiment with food as well.
Hopefully, you'll get my book.
I'm about to hit order on those books soon. So thank you.
So I'm going to take a minute here and just make a comment
that when I first met Jen, she was working on,
I think it was a mobile title that you're working on?
Probably.
Yeah, she was working on a mobile title.
And I remember having a conversation with Jen
where she was like, well, I'm working on this game.
I'm working on it for a long time.
It's not really going where I want.
I don't know.
I'm kind of running out of money,
and I don't know what I should do.
I said, just don't finish it.
She's like, well, but I'm working on it for a long time.
Should we finish it?
I was like, you should do what you love.
You don't have to put all of your time and energy into something.
And she's up here eating cookies and licking icing off of game pieces.
You fucking did it.
Congratulations.
It's amazing.
Thank you.
And there was literally no such thing as Edible Games
when I first met you.
And now you've started a whole category.
So congratulations, John.
You're an influencer now.
OK.
So next up, we actually have a video.
So this is Mohamed's game.
It is amazing.
I'm not going to say much more about it.
I'm going to let him talk about it.
He really apologized that he could not be here,
but he sends wishes from Montreal.
Hi everyone, my name is Mo, this is Jack.
I'm a creative director at Artifact 5,
a small indie studio in Montreal, Canada.
A few months ago, I saw this music video
called Lucky You by Eminem and Joyner Lucas,
where they're followed by these characters
that copy their every move.
So I thought it'd be a cool idea
to start a project inspired by that called Lucky Me.
So Lucky Me is a puzzle shooter where townships hacks copy your every move,
but sometimes you have to use their stupidity against them to survive.
The rules are pretty simple. You play as the character in yellow on the left here,
and the characters on the right with the red eyes just copy you,
and you gotta be the last one standing.
You can do the basics. You can aim and move.
And shoot!
course all the transitions are dabs. Of course it's not always that easy, sometimes shooting
one guy will get you shot by the other, so you gotta use their lack of original thought
to get them to shoot each other. Part of the challenge is to figure out the order of operations.
Sometimes shooting the wrong guy first might get you killed.
So sometimes it's worth taking the time to line up the perfect shot so you can win in very spectacular ways.
So these little blobs at your feet are the ammo you have in your gun.
And sometimes you need to pick up additional ammo to finish the job.
The main challenge is not just watching where you go and what you do, you also have to keep
track of their movements.
For example, here we're both out of ammo, but he has a bunch on his side, so you have
to make sure he avoids.
Oh crap, luckily he can't think for himself so I can waste his bullet and pick up mine
from over there.
Another strategy is to use the environment to place yourself in a better position where you can pick up the ammo.
And there are a whole bunch of environmental hazards that can be very dangerous, or super fun.
And of course it wouldn't be a puzzle game without some spikes.
And we can just walk straight into it.
So this puzzle uses all the mechanics we just saw.
We're both out of ammo.
He has bullets on his side, but he has to get there without me running
into the spikes in the back.
So I have to use the environment to block myself while picking up the bullets.
So Eminem has a warm spot in my heart.
I've been a huge fan of him since I was a kid growing up in Saudi Arabia where his music is banned.
I would have to go into underground markets to pick up his cassettes,
often while running away from the religious police.
Actually one time I got caught and arrested, but that's a story for another time.
And of course, it wouldn't be a real M&M game without a real Slim Shady mode.
In this mode, you play as a real Slim Shady who's standing up,
but with every shot, a new Slim Shady would stand up and you gotta figure out
who you are every round and be the last one standing.
There you go, the last Slim Shady standing.
It would be so cool if Eminem got to see this game.
It's my fan gift to him.
So if you can tweet at him, hold a sign at his concert,
yell at him on the street, it would be a dream come true.
Also, if you're a publisher who's interested, drop me a line at the website.
Thank you so much.
So one of the things I wanted to point out
about this video in particular is that,
and I can sense it, right?
There's this question of cultural appropriation
that we always have in the games industry.
This is a different approach.
Thinking about what you make and how you make it
and how it inspires you, and that not all the things
you see are gonna be exactly what you expect.
So next up we have Jiang Wu and Steph.
They're gonna be talking about.
What?
Oh, sorry, and Alex.
Introduced the wrong person.
Talking about Lucifer within us.
Sorry. It's okay.
In the meantime...
Hi, my name is Jongwoo, this is Alex.
We are from Kitfox Games based out of Montreal,
and we are here to show you Lucifer Within Us,
which is an experimental mystery-solving game.
This is a project that is currently unannounced
and still very much in the middle of development,
so please try to keep it confidential.
I don't know how we're gonna keep a secret
between a thousand people in a room, but we're gonna try.
Yeah, sure, well, technical difficulties.
Always happens.
Lucifer Within Us is a unique kind of mystery solving game because it's not about just solving mysteries in the traditional sense.
The protagonist is a digital exorcist in a futuristic theocracy.
So that gives us a couple of tools that normal characters would not have access to.
So first we're going to begin by investigating the body of the victim in this case that happens in a graveyard.
We can see from the profile of the character that the victim was an art student, basically,
and that the body has a throat slit, which is the most likely cause of death.
So this is where it gets interesting.
We are going to listen to the testimonies of three different characters that were present
during the events of the crime.
I would ask you to try and see if you can see any discrepancies between what the three
characters are saying.
So this first character was the victim's master, Lucius,
and he claims that he arrived at the graveyard for a stroll,
and he basically was scrolling for most of the afternoon.
He sent his apprentice off, the victim, off on an errand,
but he doesn't really specify what that is.
And what's really interesting about the game right now
is that you're able to fully control
which section of the testimony you see,
and it plays out in real time in front of you.
Now, this is not reality. This is a subjective reconstruction of what the character is saying.
So the cone of vision illustrates what section of the screen that the character actually saw,
but even that might not be accurate. It's going to be full of inaccuracies,
omissions, and outright lies even.
Anyway, so we're going to skip ahead to the late afternoon.
And he claims that someone was passing by,
and then he strolled into the back fields, at which point
he found the body of his apprentice
in a freshly dug grave.
Then he called for help, at which point
he met the other two suspects of the case, which
is Abraham, the gravetender, and Nerissa, the embalmer.
So next we're gonna talk to Abraham
to see what he has to say about the situation.
So Abraham claims that he was standing and,
sorry, tending to the bushes outside the mortuary
for much of the early afternoon,
from two o'clock to about three o'clock or so.
And then he headed inside the mortuary
to tell Nerissa, the embalmer,
that he was done with the tending
and Nerissa dismissed him.
Afterwards, he headed through the mortuary to the front yard of the graveyard
and tended to polish the headstone that is very prominent there.
And finally, in the late afternoon, he heard a cry from the backfield
and rushed over there to meet Lucius and the other suspect, Nerazzetti and Balmer.
So there's a couple of things suspicious here.
Like he's the grave digger, but he
claims to have never seen the victim
or never have dug that particular grave.
But we're going to move on to the final testimony, Nerissa
the embalmer.
Nerissa claims that she and Abraham spoke in the early afternoon about the funeral and
asked him to dig a grave.
And then for most of the early afternoon, she was preparing the body for the funeral
until Abraham came back to say that he had finished digging the grave.
And then finally she went back to preparing the body until the end of the day when she heard a cry from the graveyard
and then she rushed over there to find the other two suspects.
So it's really strange in that none of the three suspects
have really seen where the victim was
after basically two o'clock or so.
But if you've been watching this carefully,
you'll probably notice that there are
pretty clear discrepancies.
So we're gonna go back to Abraham.
and point out something that we just learned.
Nerissa claims that they spoke at two o'clock about digging a grave,
but Abraham insists that he was tending to the bushes.
So we're going to contradict him and unmask his lies.
At which point, the testimony is modified to address the contradiction we pointed out.
So now he admits that, in fact, he did speak to Nerusa in the mortuary,
and then he took the shovel and went to the backfield to dig a grave.
All the same, he still insists that nobody came through the backyard.
He was alone the entire time.
And beyond that, his testimony remains exactly the same as it originally was.
He claims that he talked to Nerissa, went through the front, and left.
So we are going to have to find more information.
So at this point, we're going to go back and do things the traditional way.
So we are going to investigate the crime scene.
So we are going to head into the mortuary and see if there's anything we can find.
And on Nerissa's table, you can find that there is a bouquet of flowers.
And the stems of the bouquet have fingerprints on them of the victim,
which contradicts what Nerissa said about being alone in the mortuary
the entire time.
The victim must have passed through at some point.
So we're going to go back to Nerissa and point this out to her.
And now she admits that, fine, in fact, the victim
did come through.
And you can see that indicated by the new marker
on the timeline.
So in the next section, she will show that, in fact, she
did greet Isaac, the art apprentice,
and then showed him the bouquet of flowers
that he wanted to bring to his instructor, Lucius.
But she claims that, in fact, Isaac did not take the bouquet
and left by the back exit.
Now if Nerissa is telling the truth, and if we take her words at face value,
there's a clear contradiction between what Nerissa claims that the victim left through the back exit
and what Abraham says, which is that nobody came through the back exit.
So normally we'd be stuck in this situation, but we have one more power available to us as a digital exorcist.
We are going to enter Nerissa's mind.
This is Nerissa's sanctum, which is a virtual representation
of her psyche.
The main area is always available to the player,
but as you contradict a given suspect,
their resolve weakens, and we can discover more secrets
about their past, their memories, and their possible motives.
In this case, we find this worn bed,
which reveals to us that Nerissa had an impoverished
upbringing, and perhaps greed was a motivation
for the killing, or perhaps not.
On the table in the main area, we can also discover
the funeral schedule that Nerissa remembers
from earlier in the day, which reveals that Lucius,
the victim's master, was the one who organized
the funeral in the first place.
So maybe the whole thing was something
that was orchestrated by Lucius.
But that's a quick look at Lucifer within us,
his subjective testimonies and investigation system.
Thank you very much for your time.
Thank you.
So yeah, I'm a big fan of story games, and I love it when people do investigative work
on narrative systems, and I thought that that demo was really badass.
So next up, we have a video, and this video is Miss Shapen.
And we're going to show it to you now.
What was that?
Oh, okay
So what is Mishaven? Well, have you played Portal?
This is kind of similar but instead of having the power to make portals with your portal gun
Players will be able to provoke unrelented uncontrolled cellular growth
Misshapen is an obscure physics-based horror first-person shooter
where you can't kill your enemies.
Of course not, because we are against all that kind of violence.
Instead, you can reduce their mobility, distorting their bodies
and creating creepy living structures with them.
Players...
may use these distortions to make traps, for example, or build complicated living contraptions,
and use these structures to reach places that they are not accessible in any other way.
All of this will result in surprising scenarios and interesting emerging gameplay to tinker with.
The game is like, let's say, a macabre metroidvania.
Is this a creepy shooter or is it a nightmarish builder?
Ok, whatever.
This game is currently under development by Nico Saraytaris, Nicolas Arkabarren and Fernando Martínez Rube.
An independent team from Argentina.
Yay.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Fantastic.
So I don't think we've ever seen an uncontrolled cellular
building game in the Experimental Gameplay
Workshop.
I think that's a first.
I think that's maybe another new genre discovered by this workshop.
And so Likuo is here to present Karto, which I actually, I think I saw the first time at
Tokyo Game Show this past year.
I was walking around looking at the games and sort of student and independent games showcase.
And I saw this game and I was so charmed by it that I asked if he would be interested in submitting
and he did. So one of the other things that I can tell you about Experimental Gameplay Workshop is
that it is a family affair and that when you're somewhere traveling, it doesn't really matter
where you are, if there's games around, if there's a school that you visit, and there are some things
that you think are interesting, you can always just say, hey, you should submit your game to EGW.
And with that...
I will probably keep talking because we are growing.
OK, great.
Here's Likuo with Karto.
Hello.
It's such an honor to be here.
My name's Likuo Chen, co-founder and game designer
at Sunhead Games, a small indie game studio in Taiwan.
And here's our game, Karto.
At first, it looked like a normal adventure game
that you control a character and explore a land,
and you found a thing, a map,
and you can switch to a map view,
and you can move or rotate any tile on the map.
And when the two tile have the same type of border,
you can connect them together,
and when the map changes, the world changes as well.
And here's a new map piece.
and you can connect into the, sorry,
to the existing map to expand map.
And you'll meet some people and you can hear their stories,
but it's gonna take a while,
so let me skip some conversations at speedrun a little bit.
Is the music out?
Yes, can you hear me now?
Yes.
Okay.
Anyway, I'll keep playing.
And so sometimes you will meet people who need help, like this one.
So his house is east of the one on the grassland along the sea.
And in order to find his house, you need to move this tile to here and you'll find his house.
And here's another puzzle.
If I didn't skip the conversation before,
someone will say that there's a family living in the forest,
however, you don't see anything beside this little boy.
So the reason that there's no house in this forest
is because there's actually two forest.
And the little boy said, there's only one forest,
so you have to combine the forests together,
and you will see a house.
so I can be linked.
And this is how the game works basically.
And based on this idea we take some experiments
and there's other things we like to show you.
So for example, sometimes the tile could be hidden.
So you have to make the hole in a certain shape to find out the tile.
Like this one.
Or sometimes you only have two tiles.
And in order to find a way out, you have to look carefully and...
try to find the correct way to follow the path.
For example, you see a symbol here,
and you walk to here,
and you continue doing so, you can solve the puzzle.
Or sometimes you are in a maze,
and you can, the maze is not constructed by yourself.
Or the tile is more than one layer.
So for example, this is the ground level,
this is underground level.
But you cannot change the map on the ground level,
you can change only on the ground level.
So we'll change to the ground level,
and the underground level changes as well.
Or for example, tiles are kinetic,
that they move and rotate together,
like Tetris bricks.
Or,
or it's in-house,
and there's nothing outside.
And then there's in-house map.
So,
and.
That's our game, Carto.
Thank you.
Thank you so much for taking the time to bring your game here.
It's so charming, isn't it?
It's just so beautiful.
I'm sorry that we had the audio.
We had a little bit of audio problem with that one earlier
today, but we wanted to hot mic it.
So we've been trying to work out all the kinks
of experimental gameplay workshop for a while,
but it's not really an experimental gameplay
workshop unless someone's demo totally crashes,
or one of us trips down the stairs and breaks a leg.
So losing a little bit of sound's not so bad.
And so next we're going to have.
My favorite current game, Sloppy Forgeries.
Hello, I'm Jonah Warren, creator of the Sloppy Forgeries video game.
Sloppy Forgeries is a fast-paced, two-player competitive local multiplayer painting game.
At the start of each round, players select an abstracted painting from
art history whose color palette has been reduced to four to five colors.
Each player, armed with a mouse, a blank canvas, and a few simple paint tools,
has a minute and a half to copy the painting as quickly and as accurately as possible.
Players can strategically use three seconds of a hint,
briefly superimposing the goal painting over their canvas.
As the forgeries are created, players are given immediate feedback on the accuracy of their reproductions.
Accuracy is calculated by comparing each pixel of the original with the forgery
and counting the number of matching colors, generating a percentage complete score.
After a minute and a half of artful painstaking decision making,
the painting with the highest percentage complete score wins.
The game collects all the paintings generated, which you can do some fun things with,
like finding the average or finding the mean.
I also created an editor to help me reduce the color palette of a painting while keeping its
distinguishing characteristics. An online multiplayer version of Sloppy Forgeries is
currently being developed for iOS. It is planned to be released in the summer of 2019.
Sign up for a newsletter at playfulsystems.com slash sloppy or follow at playfulsystems and
at sloppyforgeries on twitter for release info.
I'm Gerben, or if you want to throw it to hate you, Gerba.
There you go.
So let me put up eloquence real quick.
This is the first time I get to show it
to the world basically,
so I'm very excited about your responses.
Now let's get immersed.
Save it.
So this is Eloquence, which is basically a point-and-click adventure game,
only it uses a simple language that I designed.
What you just heard is an alien crashing off the shore of a volcanic island,
where three people are living on it with three different languages and three different cultures.
You're the alien down here, in human form, because it doesn't want to scare them,
and it wants to prevent the volcano from erupting.
The way the game works is you walk up to a person.
They will speak in a symbolic language.
What this alien can do is drag that language down to its inventory.
Now it has it memorized, and then you can return it to an NPC to create a new input.
That allows you to walk on and talk to the other NPCs in this scene.
You want to make it to the top as quickly as you can, so you try to identify an exit.
Which is probably here, right?
So you can't quite make out what this guy wants.
But it probably has something to do with an apple.
So who has apples?
This one over here.
Can anyone tell me what she's saying?
This is like a regular sentence in English.
Go again, you.
Who trades fish for apples?
So what would she say?
Anyone else?
I, yeah, you, right. You win a stroopwafel. There you go.
All right, so who has fish? This guy down here, right?
So you can take this line, and I'm going to show you, I'm not going to spoil it to you,
but I just want to show you the mechanics and see you can create some different stuff.
So if we look at this line right here, we have no idea what this means,
because we don't have any reference point for that.
But maybe we can figure out what this means.
What does this part mean?
What do you think?
Hold on.
Go again.
You give me what?
You got a stroopwafel.
Right, so we move back down here.
Give me a fish.
He says, I will give you a fish.
Walk back up there.
I give you a fish.
I give you an apple.
What do we do with the apple?
To the guard, well done.
You all get a stroke apple.
And then he tells me to walk on.
So that allows me to move to the next scene.
This is a bit further in the game.
This is way up at the volcano.
And when we get here,
you get some more complicated
problems, basically.
So, we're not sure
what this guy wants.
This guy says hello again.
And you may have noticed I've got some extra tools on this side.
So I am actually able to cut up the line right now
and paste it back together.
So I can make custom answers to solve the problems I need like that.
So I'm going to jump out of the game and show you a bit more about the thought behind it.
So there we go.
Language is hot, right? It's sexy, it's happening, everyone likes language.
We all use Duolingo. Some of us learn Japanese just to follow the anime in their original languages.
We have blockbuster games coming out on language.
We have games that give us simple languages already, and more recently, Heaven's Fault,
who actually won the UK's Game of the Show award two days ago, so well done for them.
So I thought, this game has been in development,
the language has been in development for three years,
I've been testing it a lot for three years,
and I thought this is time to show it to the world, basically.
But where I think my game differs from most of the other games
is it's less about finding out what the symbol actually means,
and it's more about finding out how people use it in their conversations.
So it's less about puzzling and smart world exploration,
experimenting, seeing what happens.
And it makes sense because language in itself is meaningless. It's all about the context
So if you have a look at this sentence, for example, this is Mandarin Chinese. This is ni hao ma meaning. Are you okay?
Are you well, how are you?
But people rarely use this and for this meaning in China they instead say
Ni zi le ma? Have you eaten?
Did he eat yet?
Food is very important in a culture, and that's where the meaning is derived from, not from the words themselves.
What I want you to do in this game is think like a linguist.
To give you a little example of that...
This is a phrase from Irish.
Now, to most of us this is incomprehensible.
But what a linguist does is see if he can assign some kind of meaning to every piece of that.
So some of it is just translation, some of it is how it's the meaning in context.
And then you can translate that to something you do recognize, in this case English.
My game gives you a language that basically gives you
the code for all other languages.
I'm not interested in the bottom part.
That's up to you.
So you can approach it from Italian or English
or Mandarin Chinese or Portuguese.
So that works both ways.
Then you can use this language to communicate with anyone
from all over the world.
And I think that makes it very exciting.
So I'm not sure how much time I have.
I just want to show you how the world looks.
So this is basically the game right here.
Those are the levels.
Each of them gives you a little bit of a lesson
in the language itself.
And it wraps around very nicely
so you can make your way to the top like that.
or go straight up like there.
Now, each of the colors is actually
a different symbol language, which uses the same symbols,
but changes the syntax, which makes it easier
for some of us to connect with it.
So this should ensure that all of us
have a language that clicks with them
and allows you to get to the top of the volcano
in time to save the island.
A little bit more theoretical stuff about how we deal with language.
So you have to know stuff first before you can create.
And you can see that this overlaps perfectly with my design.
So I'm easing you into the language, easing you into the game,
and at the end, you get to climb to the top.
Big shout out to my team who helped me make this prototype.
We're all part of a Dutch collective in a game bakery in the north.
And the guy on the left who's made the artwork on Insomniac Spider-Man as well.
So kudos to him.
And I need your help, because I want funding, but most of all, I want a community.
So I want to give you the demo.
Be in touch with me through either of these channels, and I will send it to you in due time.
Thank you so much for giving me time to present for you.
Thank you.
That's such an interesting, oh, so who won a Stroopwafel?
If you won a Stroopwafel, please come and get one.
They're amazing.
If you don't come and get them, I'm going to eat them.
So next up, we have another video.
And this game is called Nerve Damage.
And the person speaking to you is Dennis Carr.
Hi, everyone.
My name's Dennis Carr.
And this is my game, Nerve Damage.
So before I get started, I just want
to emphasize what it says on the screen here.
This game has bright, rapidly flashing colors.
There's a very, very strong seizure warning, and I just want to make sure everyone is aware of that before I start the game, which I'm going to do right now.
Okay, so yeah, this is Nerve Damage.
As you can hopefully see, it's a fast-paced, score-attack, arcade-style first-person shooter with a loud, noisy, experimental visual style.
Yeah, and so when I started working on this game, I was coming off another project, Circle Zero, which is actually here, nominated for a Nuova Award in the IGF, come see it.
Just wanted to get that self plug in there, of course.
But, you know, at least at the time that I had finished that game, I felt like, you know, I was very proud of it and I put a lot into it, but it felt like maybe we'd created something that was a little bit too unfriendly to the player.
it seemed like people were just bouncing off it and not a lot of people were really engaging
with it.
So I was a little bit disillusioned and I wanted to create a game that still felt meaningfully
experimental but which, you know, I wanted something that the players would be, you know,
more likely to want to play and that was maybe like fun, you know.
And so, you know, I was also interested in this visual style that I'd been experimenting with,
and how would a visual style that is maybe kind of antagonistic and difficult for the player to
read would affect the way that the players engage with the game, you know, because it's a 3D game.
And, you know, sort of in most 3D games, the idea is to make it as easy as possible for the
player to immerse themselves in the environment. But...
You know, I wanted to bring some friction to that process and
complicate it, make players aware of the effort they're
expending to do that.
And so I tried to sort of build up the screen so that it
functions as much as a barrier into this world as, as it is a
window.
And you know, I want players to have to sort of push their way
through it and learn to read it.
And
Um, yeah, well, you know, one thing I realized while I was making the game is that it is a little bit hard to immerse yourself in this world.
But once you get over that hump, once you cross the barrier, the barrier sort of functions as much to hold you into the game as it does, as it did to keep you out of it.
So.
there's a little bit of a trance-like aspect to playing this game. It's hard to stop sometimes,
and I like that. I think of it as being similar to the idea of the flow state,
but where the flow state is based in this idea of serenity, I think the flow state that this
game creates is more based in anxiety and adrenaline, and I find it kind of cathartic
to play a game like that.
you know, I like it. I like media that's that challenges you as much as it as it caters to you.
And, you know, I like the idea that video games are a space where themes like anxiety, compulsion,
pain, discomfort can coexist with an experience that's kind of fun to play also and genuinely
entertaining. And so that's kind of the experience that I'm creating with nerve damage. And yeah.
Thank you for watching the video and enjoy the rest of the UGW.
So this game is actually a really great opportunity to sort of have a teachable moment.
So we've had a couple games in the showcase over the years that were like this.
How many of you were here to see Jonathan Blow demoing some of the hardest levels of
Space Giraffe?
Years ago, yeah, right?
So that was a really intense game
that used what we call obfuscation
to create a sense of panic and also a flow state.
And then there was another game that was done here.
How many of you remember there was
this guy that made a list of the games
that he would make if he had time on the internet?
And then people started making the games,
and he got really mad?
that they stole his ideas.
So like one year, Sean Barrett, for one of the game jams,
made a game called Lost in the Static.
How many of you saw that game?
Yeah, so it was basically a screen that was all static,
and the only time you could navigate,
the way that you navigated was by basically rotating
in the static to see where the static didn't change.
And then when you think about it, unfinished swan
might be something that comes in that same pattern.
And now there's a bunch of glitch games as well.
My students have made several,
most of them incredibly unplayable,
but nevertheless, interesting is a flow state case
in this sort of scribble night kind of way.
And if you're scribble, scribble, scribbling,
and everything's spastic, and you get into a flow state,
that's a really interesting place to explore in games.
And I really like this particular video
because it sort of gives us, it holds space for a game.
That's about the infinite rage that we all feel right now,
all the time.
So having said that, Plus Minus is here.
I'll let them introduce themselves.
Thank you.
So hi, everyone.
I'm Juuso.
This is Antti.
We're from Aalto University, Finland.
So that's quite far away.
But we're here to show you Plus Minus.
So we're two of the developers.
It was a team of six.
Now this game is pretty conventional, so you can run around, you can jump, you can move
third person camera, it's an action game.
But there's this addition we've put in here and that's magnetism.
So you can actually magnetize any metal object in the surroundings, either positively or
negatively.
And now opposite polarities, they attract each other, and negative polarities repel.
You might notice these bubbles around the magnetized objects.
Those are there to demonstrate what the effective range is of the magnets.
As soon as two bubbles start overlapping, there starts to be an interaction.
The closer they get, the stronger that interaction.
You can only magnetize metal objects, but there is a lot of surface here that is not metallic.
You can still use that. You can actually shoot the walls or the floor.
It will create this temporary field.
This is useful for a variety of things, like moving objects around.
So those are the basics.
Let's get on to the gameplay.
So what can we actually do with this magnetic system?
A lot of the game is about moving through levels.
So there's rarely a direct path you can take.
Instead, you need to look at what's in the environment
and how can you move that into a position that's
going to let you get through.
And we're really playing around with a lot
of these tropes that are in action games.
So we have combat as well.
But we're doing something a bit different with that.
So usually you would shoot enemies to kill them.
Here, if you shoot an enemy, it's only going to polarize it.
It's not actually going to cause any direct damage.
However, collisions cause damage.
So magnetism is actually perfect for that kind of combat.
You're kind of bullying the enemies here.
So here we drop down and there's these three robots.
Again, you can do the same thing.
You can make the robots collide into each other
and they're going to start taking damage.
You can make them smash into walls.
That's going to do the same thing.
Or you can look around what's in the environment.
So we have these endless pits.
Mario usually falls into them,
but you can drop the robots down into there.
So really encouraging players to come up
with these creative solutions
for approaching problems such as combat.
And just like the enemies, the player actually takes collision damage as well.
So usually what ends up happening is you're playing around with magnets
and then you get like this really large magnet in your face.
Yeah, that let's hope that doesn't happen, but kind of hope that it does.
OK, so that was combat.
Now we're going to move on to some sections that are more focused on platforming.
So that's, again, another trope from action games.
You've got this platforming, but we want to do it a bit differently.
So right now here you have this large metal block and it's in the way and it might look like it's really heavy, but the magnetic system doesn't really care about that.
So you can just move it out the way.
Then we get to this pit you need to get across, but there aren't really any platforms right there.
However, there are these discs at the bottom and you can just magnetize those, lift them up and you've created a path for yourself.
At this section, it's pretty standard.
We're still tutorializing the system.
But later on, it starts to really open up
and you don't have these obvious solutions.
Those enemies, they have the weirdest AI.
They just sometimes jump down on top of you.
And okay, so we're taking a pretty,
we're taking a pretty standard approach to this level.
Well, there's a lot of potential for taking
these creative shortcuts.
And we'll get back to that later.
And you may have noticed we have these mechanisms
like elevators and doors in our game.
You'll find them in every game.
But we're also using magnetism for those.
And that's kind of important for the player
so that we can really teach them to get used to this magnetism.
And it also kind of creates this cohesion
where everything in the world works with this same core
magnetic system.
Now this room is pretty fun.
So we have this floor that can be magnetized,
but we also have a ceiling that can be magnetized.
And the effect is pretty surprising.
So what's happening here is we've got the floor
pushing the enemies up,
the ceiling pushing the enemies down,
and they end up in this kind of limbo
where they're just bouncing around.
It's kind of silly, but it's a lot of fun.
You can probably imagine how this might be used in puzzles
or other level elements.
Okay, now we defeated those.
We're gonna skip forward a bit.
We don't have a lot of time,
and this is a pretty cool level we're gonna show you.
Now, the thing in this level
is we have this giant metal pillar in the center,
and as you magnetize it,
it creates a magnetic field that covers the entire area.
So this creates this sort of dynamic
where now if you magnetize anything in the room,
it's gonna get either pushed or pulled towards the center.
Now it's another platforming stage, so you need to get kind of creative how you move forward.
So here we have this large gap. There's no platforms there.
So you need to look, what have we got here?
And we got this boxes. So you can attach a box to the pillar, and all of a sudden you have a platform.
Now you could take the same approach for the rest of the level.
So creating these platforms for yourself.
But we promised a shortcut, so we're going to try to do that.
That's a bit tricky to set up.
And we didn't actually design this shortcut.
So a play tester was actually able to find it.
But it was really cool.
And we really want to keep these sort of cool elements
in our game.
So if the player finds a way to break our game,
we let them.
Okay, so what we're doing here is we're building
a sort of launcher.
We've got two magnets on top of each other.
And there we go.
We just skipped like half the level.
So yeah, this is plus minus.
We're going to upload a small demo of this soon after GDC so
that anybody else can go try it out and have
some fun with it.
So make sure to check that out.
Thanks.
So plus minus another opportunity for us
to do a little way back machine with the experimental gameplay
workshop audience.
How many of you were here when the original Portal
first demoed for the first time ever here in the session?
That's right.
So games like Portal, at the time that they were being made,
were considered so experimental that they
submitted to the workshop.
So that's how much has changed over the course of the history of the workshop.
And I also just wanted to take the moment here to say a little bit about dynamic games.
So what I love about Plus Minus and games like Portal and the kinds of games that
that I've always loved to play is that they have systems in them and they spend a lot less time on fidelity and a lot
more time on simulating specific systems with the kind of fidelity that is just enough to create those kinds of opportunistic learnings for
players and that's actually how people learn and it's why play is learning and
so it's really really awesome to get games like this submitted. It used to be
that Experimental Gameplay Workshop was almost only physics games and we've
really been able to branch out and show games that are sometimes a little bit
more like a paper game, sometimes they're literally edible.
Sometimes they're physical, they're based on computing systems that are emerging,
and sometimes they're systems-based in ways that we have never perceived,
or play with your vision and your ears.
We've had all audio games here that you play in a gas mask.
How many of you saw that?
All right.
See?
So we're starting to get to the place
now where experimental gameplay workshop kind of defies
description because it's whatever you submit.
And I really want to keep encouraging you
into designing and presenting, even if it's a bizarre thing
that you think may not be fun, to bring it to us.
If you're watching on the internet
and you have a bizarre experiment,
you've never been to GDC, you don't even
have to come here anymore.
You can just send us the game.
We'll put a video up.
And maybe somebody will mail you a check,
and you'll be able to make it in your own home and never leave.
You'll be able to live your life in your pajamas, smoking weed,
and making your favorite game.
So that sounds like the life of a true artist to me.
And so with that, I'm going to let
Sean Liu talk about Hostile User Interface.
Sean Liu.
This is Hostile User Interface, a game I worked on
at the school of IGM at RIT.
The object of the game is to navigate the maze, but the controls have been intentionally designed to trick the player into accidentally triggering Windows hockey combinations.
The inspiration came from my professor, Ian Shriver's daughter, who crawled over his keyboard when she was one year old, causing the screen to flip upside down.
And he had to use Google with an upside down screen to figure out what she did and how to undo it.
Thus, the idea to create a game where the challenge doesn't come from the game, but from the actual operating system.
The pitches is one of the many ideas to work on in the class on experimental gameplay,
and I decided I wanted to explore this concept.
So, this first thing you have to do to start is hold down the keys CTRL, ALT, and DELETE.
Obviously, if you hit these keys the way normal people do, it brings up the security menu.
If you wait long enough, the game gives you a hint.
Pressing DELETE first, because pressing CTRL or ALT afterwards won't trigger the normal Windows response.
From the high concept, the immediate problem is that it sounds more like a practical joke than a fun game.
So where do you start? I could have made QWOP using the Ctrl, Alt, F4, and Escape keys,
but I doubt players would find it very fun. Instead, I started with a simple game and
thought about what would best enable hotkeys. Some keys need to be held down while other
keys are pressed to trigger hotkeys, like holding down F4 and pressing Alt does nothing.
So I had the idea of having death fields and doors, one of which requires players
to hold buttons down and the other that requires single key presses.
The other theme throughout development is that when the player does something wrong, they have to blame themselves and not the UI, even though it's totally the UI's fault.
That's how to make the player feel like they're overcoming a challenge and not that they're just getting laughed at by the game.
I found there are a few ways to do this.
One was to make an experience enough of a clear game that the player can become immersed
in the play.
As soon as the player enters a flow state, they'll start playing on automatic.
They're hitting keys without thinking, accidentally closing the app, and then realize what they
did and that it happened because they weren't paying attention, which gives us the self-blame
that we're looking for.
Once I had the basics of the game working, the rest came down to designing levels and
traps in different and unique ways to keep the game interesting.
Skipping ahead, this is the first place in-game where we give players the option to close
the game.
Previously, combinations of hockeys have had minimal effect.
Despite giving them all the warnings, most players will still manage to close out the
game on this screen.
This isn't an obvious trap.
Players have to go out of their way just to do this.
If they proceed normally then nothing happens.
This happens both if I'm standing there giving them warnings and in blind tests where I'm
not even in the room.
It's also around here where three different types of players emerge.
Some players love the game and want to keep playing, some players hate the game but want
to watch other people suffer through it, and the last group hates the game but has to keep
playing until they beat it because it's a matter of pride at that point.
Some struggles with making this game were that not all hardware is the same.
Laptop keyboards aren't standardized at all with the layout of their home, end, delete, and page down buttons,
but this is an extremely niche problem as controls for most games don't use these keys.
On the software side, certain programs have their own hotkeys that can interfere with gameplay,
such as the newest hockey combination NVIDIA's GeForce Experience added to take screenshots.
At the moment, there isn't really any way to fix it besides just disabling these hotkeys.
For those interested in either playing Hostage Interface or sending it to their friends and or enemies, it's currently available on Steam.
Hostile user interface proves the fact that the platform holder always has the power.
Yeah, so making an experimental game can happen when you're a student, it can happen with just the hotkeys on your computer.
So you have no excuse if you have the desire to make experimental games.
And next up we have Tim here to talk about what the golf?
Yeah, I need, I need power.
Okay, it works. It works.
Okay, it's the experimental gameplay workshop, so I hope it works.
Please, please.
Oh, shit.
Yes!
Okay, can I get audio?
Oh, no, it's the wrong audio.
What?
I kinda need audio for some of it.
Hmm?
While we're doing this, I'd just like to take a moment
to say thank you to all the audio engineers
that work the room at EGW every year
because this happens every year.
The AV staff for EGW is always amazing.
Let's have a huge round of applause
for the people that made us see and hear this stuff today.
I'm working on this game called What The Golf and it's not just me, the rest of the team is just actually working on the game and not hanging out here.
So, a lot more thanks to them.
Two years ago, I presented a game here called Keyboard Sports, saving Qwerty.
And that also used all the keys on the keyboard and we also had the Alt F4 problem.
And we haven't released it yet, still in some trouble, but working hard on it.
Let's do this.
We started out making an actual golf game.
Kind of Dark Souls inspired golf.
Called Dark Holes.
It...
It did not work.
It wasn't that funny.
It turns out golf just isn't that funny.
It's kind of boring.
So we kind of moved on from that.
Go a little bit up on the volume.
Can I do that?
Yeah, OK.
We moved on from that and tried a few other things.
And we have actually just kept making golf games ever since.
So we've made like 500 golf games.
And most of them are really bad.
These are some of the better ones.
Let's play.
Back to normal, ordinary golf.
So the first thing we kind of started exploring after it failed with the first project and second project.
We were like, we can play with scale and we can like, it obviously doesn't need to be a golf ball.
And you can add a few puns and then it kind of works.
And then you're kind of out of inspiration again and you just look around the office. What can we make?
And then you kind of use a bunch of different objects, and it's like, that's obvious.
We can do boxes and triangles and things.
But we can also do things to the flag.
And once you kind of know golf is about getting a thing from A to B,
you can kind of swap those things.
So now I'm the hole.
And I'm kind of going into this one here.
You can kind of see what's coming.
It's a hole.
And then once we have like the golf everything nailed you can like think
there are other games about getting a ball from A to B like this one like and
then you can always go for like a quick quick fun thing where just but now we
nailed nailed A to B and but why not change the perspective there's no
reason it's not
First person golf, right?
And once we're in first person we can also just go back to normal 2D golf.
This is kind of like desert golf, but way...
Oh, it's actually really boring.
It's one of the ones that didn't really make it.
But then we were like, fuck that, let's do something else.
Then once we're in 2D, why not look at some other 2D games?
They're all kind of golf games.
And at this point we're like, maybe all games are kind of golf games?
And then we can zoom out and relax a little bit.
And then, like again, golf, getting things from A to B.
You can probably find few other games out there.
And then...
That never really gets old.
And then we can kind of just go back to like the old thing here,
because now everyone knows exactly what's going to happen when I do this.
And another rule in golf is you usually don't hit the ball while it's still moving.
But what if we just remove that?
and then we just started looking at everything
oh
Yeah, thank you.
that we wanna...
Super six thing.
No.
Do it.
This is a bit awkward.
It doesn't do anything.
Yeah, thank you.
Yes, go ahead.
OK, cool.
And I believe for this next video, Trinny, you're here, right?
You're here?
Yes, OK, yes.
So Trin is here.
This is Trin's video, and it is called You Busy?
Hey everyone, I'm Trin and I'm the game designer behind Ubusy.
Ubusy is a game about the various channels that people and information need to flow through in order to complete work.
Essentially, it's a game about productivity when there are a million things that can flitch for attention any given day at the office.
Whether it be getting an approval on a task, attending a meeting, having to put out a fire, there are so many things that get in the way of us being able to check that box off of the list.
So as a mix of a game designer, business analyst, project manager, I was like, what a fascinating
system to work with. You know, so much communication is required for us to actually feel productive at
work. What if I put this into a hectic local multiplayer environment just to see how that
sheds light on the system? So I very literally ripped approval processes from previous jobs I had.
and I put them into the game and added meetings, added fires, added all the fun stuff at the office
to try to make it actually fun but also to shed light on the system and to really show
like how much it takes for us to feel productive under the current circumstances.
There you go. I have a task just like chilling over here in the abyss.
Hey, Green, I'm still up. Thank you.
Oh wait, I need you. Oh wait, thank you.
Oh, this is a meeting.
Hey, Green, it's you.
Yeah.
You still got it. I still got it. I still can't approve.
I was pressing it.
Green, we're right here.
I can approve you. Yeah.
Here you go. Got you.
Thank you.
All right, I need to go to, oh I think pink, I need to.
So I made this game with one other person,
my partner in crime and fabulous programmer, Chris Sosa.
However, we currently are not working on the game.
This was just like a super short project for us,
really quick dev cycle,
something we just wanted to get out of our systems.
But there are like a million things
that we want to do with it.
Like right now, since it's a vertical slice,
you start right in the middle.
It's like starting.
closer to the fish and chips level of overcooked, which is just a lot. But we have a list of
changes and improvements, changing the sounds.
changing the levels, ramping up gameplay, that sort of thing.
We just currently don't have the time or the funds to work on it.
So we're really just enjoying showing it at festivals
and hearing what people have to say about it, hearing about their work experiences.
So we'd love to hear your thoughts.
You can contact us at my Twitter handle.
I am Trin, and I'd love to hear about your work experience.
If you're what really resonated to you in the game, if you're interested
in working on it eventually, if we ever started up like in general,
we would just love to hear from you.
So yeah, Trin is here, so if you wanted to, you know,
make her dream come true of making a game
about the stress of being in an office,
you could just come up here at the end of the session
and give her a fat check.
Maybe you could give us both fat checks
and then we would win.
So I think that one of the things about EGW
is that it does allow us to talk about things that can be,
but also, I mean, I think as Trin pointed out,
things that are and like,
it's not easy being us all the time.
making the stuff that we make.
And this place hopefully is giving you some inspiration.
We're getting a little close to the end of the session
this year because we decided to keep it a little shorter
because the EGW used to be a marathon of endless games
and everyone had to take a pee break in the middle
and it was kind of intense.
And this year we're just kind of trying to keep it
a little bit more focused.
So we really appreciate your focus this year
and this format.
I would personally like your feedback.
If you want to see more games,
if you want the session to get bigger again,
if you want more stuff up front at the end, let me know.
I know there are no donuts this year.
Maybe there'll be donuts next year.
And with that, we're going to have Frank here
talk about picture processing.
Hi.
I'm Frank DeMarco from New York, and I'm making a game
called picture processing.
It's a picture puzzle where the object
is to fix a glitch on your screen
by swapping the graphics with each other.
The original demo was created for a game jam called
A Game by Its Cover, an online jam where games are created
based on imagined NES games submitted
to another separate annual event, a gallery exhibit
called My Famicase.
My Famicase is an awesome art show
that has been held yearly in Japan since 2005.
In that slide, you can see there are a bunch of fake NES
cartridges.
The game that I chose to make my game based on is called Sado by Ishii Hiroaki.
The Glitchtout cover was very inspiring and looked cool to me.
And I checked the description by doing a Google Translate.
And it seems like the game concept is it's a conceptual game where you put a cartridge
in, it's not working, and you meditate on the beauty of imperfection in the Glitchtout
screen.
I added one thing to that concept, which is you meditate so hard, you can telepathically
access the graphics memory of the system and fix the glitch by swapping graphics with each
other.
Let's start a new game and take a look at the introduction.
So you're in your living room, you try to play a game, you put the cartridge in the
system, it's glitched out, and so you start meditating.
and you get superpowers.
You're intimately engaging with the hardware
of your video game console.
As the great Bob of Bob's Game put it,
it's a game inside of a game.
This is what the final illustration
in the introduction looks like.
It's a head attached to a Nintendo by an energy beam.
And it's pretty weird,
but it's one of my ultimate fantasies,
using a mind control beam with a Nintendo.
So let's play Scene 1.
The only hint the player gets is this title, so for Scene 1 your hint is Power Up.
When the scene begins, you're presented with a pretty severe mess of graphics.
Also, sometimes it's a little subtle, but the sound is glitched out too, so if you listen
you can hear the music is booping every second or so.
So if the player knows it's a puzzle and they caught the basic idea of the game,
they might be able to put together that this level is a side-scroller based on the hint
and seeing there's a mushroom and there's a Mario-looking character,
maybe the clouds and the ground might tell you something. But maybe they can't tell anything.
Somebody yesterday told me that the Mario tile looks like a hamburger and maybe they
didn't catch the premise of the game, but I'll talk about that in a second.
There is only one interaction at this point. Let us try pressing Enter.
This menu comes up where all the tiles are displayed,
and you are able to choose between them.
The numbers on the left correspond to memory addresses.
Every one of these tiles is in the wrong memory address,
because the game makes sure all the tiles are shuffled out of their correct locations.
If you select one of the tiles and then select another,
you will notice the screen changes somewhere from slightly to a lot.
So if we, you can see the top is mostly filled with clouds,
which is pretty good because that's supposed to be the sky.
And the bottom is dirt, which is also pretty good,
but they're both in the wrong place.
So let's try swapping cloud and ground.
So you can see that every place where the ground was,
now there's clouds,
and every place where the clouds were, now there's ground.
But if you do a small swap,
like the blank space and the mushroom,
you might not notice much changes on the screen.
I've noticed that the real aha moment for this level is when you put the sky in the right place.
So let's switch
memory 6
with memory 0.
Now it looks more like a side-scroller.
Then it becomes a classic puzzle game situation where you are putting things in the right place.
Satisfying that compulsion that basically governs everything.
What we are all out here exploiting for profit.
Mario goes here.
Tree goes here.
Rock goes there.
And ground goes there.
Oh, but what's this?
It looks correct, but we're still one swap away.
If you look at the bottom of the screen,
it tells you how many swaps you have left.
I think one of the things that makes this game unique
is you're solving a puzzle that only has an objective answer
based on how the designer arranges the scene.
In most puzzle games, there are no arbitrary situations.
There are rules in the game that prevent them.
In Picross, the numbers that guide the player are generated directly by the pixels on the grid.
In Tetris, if you don't put the lines into the right order, you lose.
In this game, if the level designer decided the sky was made of rock, they could do that.
Sometimes people play this game by arranging the tiles to look like something they want to see,
and they have fun with it that way.
In this scene, it turns out that I think it looks slightly better if Mario is to the left of the mushroom.
And so yeah, and so the sound non-glitches, and you've beaten level 1.
So yeah, this is level 2. It's supposed to be a driving level. It's like a race car level.
But because I've noticed a lot of people want to be creative while playing, I've started working on a level editor.
So let's take a look at that.
There are three different things you can do from the main menu of the level editor.
You can edit the tiles, you can test the level that you are building, or you can place the
tiles on the level.
Let's start by making a tile.
I will start by clearing the default title.
There is a paint tool, and I am just going to clear the whole tile to white.
Now I will select green.
I am going to try to draw a plant.
You can see in the background that the whole level is changing.
That is because the whole level is set to be the first tile.
That kind of looks like a plant.
And you can also load tiles.
So I'm going to put these numbers in.
OK, now I'm going to place those.
Okay, let us test the level.
All right, it is all scrambled up.
Usually the free swap is the background.
You can see it is all filled with twos.
We will just put the plant there.
Now let us see if we can correct this code.
Yeah, that is it. In the Level Editor,
it just says solved in the bottom when you solve the level.
So, a quick note about some attention this game received.
A blog by someone who has a PhD wrote about picture processing.
That's supposed to laugh you out.
Probably a lot of people here have a PhD and that's no big deal.
But I don't have one.
I have a computer science degree that's not even a science degree.
It's a Bachelor of Arts.
But I guess that's appropriate though.
This is art, right?
VideoBall, which is available now.
for PlayStation 4, Xbox One, and Steam for PC.
Video Ball.
It's still available, Video Ball.
PlayStation 4, Xbox One, and Steam for PC.
So anyway, a blog that is a PhD blog wrote about my game,
so I guess my game is pretty cool.
Please check out my PayPal.
All right, so this is going to be the last presentation
for the day, and Eddie and I are just going to stay up here,
and we'll watch with you.
We wanted to make a note here because this video was
submitted by someone who just shipped their game, which
is a huge accomplishment.
So for the tape, let's give them a huge round of applause.
Jay's been pretty stressed out because he just shipped his game.
So the first part of the video is just going to be Jay for three minutes talking about his game.
So here's Jay.
Hi, I'm Jay Tholen, the lead developer of Hypnospace Outlaw.
Hypnospace Outlaw started in 2014 as a small micro game called Hypnospace Enforcer.
And that's where the whole concept of using the internet while you sleep started,
using headbands at night.
It was a little bit more futuristic than...
And while there was an operating system part, it wasn't as robust.
The main part of the game was this sort of a play on the information superhighway,
and it was an inlet side-scrolling endless runner, and you played as a cop, and you had to
apprehend people for doing these various pretty banal internet violation things.
So it came from that, and then it evolved into more of an operating system game.
over time because people just responded better to the operating system parts.
So yeah, I started making a sequel shortly after releasing that in late or late 2014 or early 2015
around when my work on Dropsy was ending. Anyway, and then from that point on until
the Kickstarter in 2016 and even a year after that it became more of a
just a big fake internet. We made, me and my programmer Mike, made a few tools, a page builder,
so, and a custom HSP hypnospace page format for pages, and a tune sequencer, and the game runs the
songs from the tune sequencer at runtime. It triggers all the samples and the effects and
everything. So...
We did have a little bit of a framework for a game in there, like where you make progress,
but it was mostly just a big, big internet that we were making.
And I was, you know, intent on making it a game eventually, but I wasn't just very interested
in that.
So then, about a year...
a year and two or three months ago, then we kind of were like, okay, we have to make it into a game.
Like if you want to, you know, if it was up, if it was just, you know, up to me and I
wasn't, you know, if I didn't need money, I would have just, um,
maybe kept going and making a big internet, but I felt like we needed like progression systems.
Well, that wasn't too bad.
They didn't really change a whole lot about the big, deep web
that you get to explore.
Anyway, so yeah, that's the basics.
And what I'll be doing is not bad.
You want to watch it again?
Yeah, here's the trailer again.
Watch it again.
Oh!
Important message received.
So this room has the capacity to hold maybe a thousand people.
It's pretty close to capacity, so if you each gave him a thousand dollars, that'd be rad.
If everyone that watched this trailer on the internet
gave him $1,000 for his game, that'd be even more rad.
And he could probably live for a long time
just making games, doing his thing.
You know, everyone's had that moment
where they're working on something and they go,
oh, I should probably put a progression system in here.
I think that moment in the video
is the one that really struck me.
It was like, oh yeah, no, you probably have to.
But you don't always have to.
And as we continue to create spaces like this
in our communities where people can show their art,
you don't have to.
You can support each other, not just with money,
but also with congratulations, love, hugs, donuts.
So if you have a moment at some point
to just send this guy an email,
look his game up, drop him a line,
and say, hey, I love that demo.
Thanks for making your weird internet somewhat playable.
That would be really nice.
That'd be a nice thing for you to do.
I'm not saying you have to do it,
but one of the ways that we thrive
is by getting positive feedback,
and that would be really nice.
And so everybody that participated,
if you showed a video,
if you're a game developer that's here
that was in the showcase, please come up,
as well as all the organizers, please come up on stage.
This is experimental gameplay.
And you are all experimental gameplay.
And GDC is now actually almost officially over.
We have 15 minutes.
Instead of having question session, just come up and meet these people and give them a hug.
Thank you.