On GDC Podcast episode 16, we have Greg Kasavin, creative director at Hades
Developers Supergiant Games. We'll talk narrative design, his journey from game
journalist to game developer, and the allure of the roguelike genre. Back in a sec.
Welcome to the house of Hades!
And we're back. This is Chris Graft. Is this how we do this?
Maybe. I don't know. It's been so long.
Yeah, it has been a while. We're just going to use this take, too. I'm Chris Graft,
editor-in-chief of Gamasutra. And hey, Alyssa.
Hey, I'm Alyssa. I'm Alyssa Macklin, news editor, associate publisher at Gamasutra,
expert podcaster.
Yeah, we haven't done the intro in a while.
And if you're a regular listener, you will know that after 15 or 16 episodes,
we have still not got the intros down quite perfectly.
I'm afraid to listen to our first one because I feel like this is way better than we started.
But I will never know because I'll never listen to it.
I think the first one, we just didn't do an intro.
We just had the guests start like mid-sentence.
And then we just sat and listened to them.
Bold.
Yeah, yeah, we are bold.
Um, so what have you been up to for the past?
Oh, I don't even, I shouldn't ask.
Yeah, it's all how was your last month?
So that's okay.
Good.
Same answer for that period of time.
All right.
Let's just, yeah, D&D hit man, rest of the world having a normal one.
Yeah, so I'm excited about the guest we have coming on today, but I think that maybe we
should talk about some GDC stuff really quick, since this is technically the GDC podcast.
Exciting guest, exciting new GDC content for this interesting period of time we have right
here.
Oh, registration is now open for the GDC Masterclass Spring Sessions.
So we had GDC Masterclass fall sessions and they went so swimmingly.
We're going back to school in the spring.
What do you think?
What do you think of that?
I was going to make a too cool for school joke, but I'm like, no, that's lame.
And then I just.
No, it's all good. You should all go check it out. We have some people returning to
There's actually one now where you can get certified in
Agile, so that's that's
obviously production and
We have some for level design now and writing already getting some signups
So that is exciting
Yeah, the benefit here is versus just watching a presentation, you actually get hands-on
time with the instructor in a call where you can get feedback, have conversations, ask
questions and just get like really engaged knowledge.
So it's a pretty cool offering, I think.
Yeah, they're actual classes.
You go to school, you grab your trapper keeper and you sit down.
But yeah, but yeah, they really are courses.
They're like, all day, all day courses that you take.
So it's, it's quite more in depth than sitting in on a, you
know, one hour long GDC session.
So you can check that out at gdconf.com.
And.
Also, if one-hour GDC sessions are your thing, there's also GDC Showcase coming up.
Yeah, oh, that was a good one.
But most of those are 30 minutes long.
Yep, I realized that as I said it, but you know what?
But if you watch two of them back to back,
it's an hour long.
But that's a free thing that you can find out about.
It's kind of acting like a preview
to the content that we'll have at the big regular GDC
that is a fluid situation there.
obviously, but yeah, you can go to GDC showcase. It's going to be free to
register for. You get on the platform and we're going to have some a mix of brand
new talks. GDC podcast live is going to be there every day. There's going to be
old talks with like, I don't say old talks, it's like a new game plus must talk.
Yeah, I've been thinking about it.
Yeah, new session plus where you have a classic GDC session,
one of the more memorable ones.
And the original speaker is going to be in the chat room
talking while their past self is talking.
So there's gonna be somebody in that box
that attendees will be able to interact with.
They can ask more questions, you know,
about whatever topic is at hand.
So there's gonna be all kinds of new things
for an entire week.
So we're gonna be busy there.
That is coming up.
Yeah.
March 15th through 19th, right?
You nailed it.
Nailed it.
That is absolutely what it is.
And you can find out more at gdconf.com.
Yeah, I think it's guest o'clock.
Yeah, it's guest o'clock.
Our next guest was an accomplished game journalist before making the move into game development.
He is creative director at Supergiant Games, which developed the beloved instant classic
Hades.
But you probably know him best as a writer at Newtype Gaming Magazine in the 90s.
Let's welcome Greg Kasavin.
Hey Greg! Hello! Hey, thanks for having me on the show. Yeah, of course, it's so nice to have you.
So, I think we should get right into it because I've been doing game journalism. I'm going to
advertise how old I am.
full time since 2005, but I was reading you years before that.
Can you talk a little bit?
I want to get an idea of your journey from being a game journalist and a critic to a
game developer, a creative director at one of the best game studios out there.
Thanks so much. It's wild to look back. The time flies, as I'm sure you can attest.
But yeah, I was really fortunate to get to start writing about games basically fresh out of high school.
The sort of greater backstory to that is I've just been playing games all my life, since my earliest memory.
always captivated me. I don't know what I was doing in like, arcades as like a six year old or whatever in the...
Uh, geez, it was, you know, would have been the late 80s at that point.
But I was playing arcade games, I was playing computer games, I was playing console games,
playing western games, playing Japanese games, just, I gobbled all of it up.
And I knew from, I say since I was about 8, that I wanted to make games.
I was playing a game called Ultima 4, which is like the granddaddy of, you know, open
world.
role-playing games. I think games like Skyrim owe a lot to the classic Ultima series.
But I was playing this game as an eight-year-old and it was blowing my mind. You could just go
anywhere, do anything, experience the consequences of your actions, and I had no idea how people
made it, but I knew I wanted to do stuff like it.
But when I tried to teach myself programming on and off, including during high school,
I just kind of bashed my head against it and it didn't go that well for me.
But I always loved writing.
um, as kind of the thing I liked, you know, academically besides going home and playing
video games after school. And so in high school I was playing so many games that at a certain
point I just like started to feel like almost guilty that I just kind of, I felt like I had
to do something productive with it to like be able to justify...
i still feel like everybody feels like that yeah yeah it wasn't even like i don't know that
you know monetize my hobbies it was necessarily the the if that wasn't like i think just
you know i i was yeah playing a bunch of games reading you know
Electronic gaming monthly and all kinds of like magazines that were around at the time and I'm like I could I could you know
I want to review video games and at the time, you know, I was already on the the internet such as it was and
in there were like
you know little groups of folks interested in games and
I met a friend across the country
and we started making a little like fanzine together
about video games and this is like this feels really prehistoric because it was
like literally you know printed
on paper and then mailed to people.
That rules.
Yeah, so that's like how I got my, you know,
reviewing like whatever Samurai Shodown 2 for a fanzine and that sort of thing.
But it was enough to then, you know, there was a, you mentioned Newtype Gaming
magazine. It was like a small local magazine in San Francisco and it was like kind of a
happenstance thing that I saw that they were like looking for writers and I'm like, hey,
I've written stuff.
you know i could i could do this or whatever uh... and and to my surprise
uh... they they got back to me uh... and uh...
you know that
at this point
i think i a m i'd like just
finished high school basically almost to the day
uh... and and uh... i got to
I got to start writing a bit for Newtype, but they at the moment were already winding
down from being a print publication and transforming themselves into a website.
They were kind of doing this a little bit before it was cool.
This is like 1995-ish.
And anyway...
One thing led to another. Myself and a couple of colleagues from Newtype, we started our own gaming website for a bit that we ran for about a year.
What was that one called again?
That was called Arcadia Magazine.
We reviewed, we covered both pop culture stuff and games because we were into whatever.
We were watching, I don't know that kung fu movies or whatever exactly qualify as pop culture actually.
But it was just a weird mix of...
of stuff like that. And then this is again, this is a stroke of fortune. I attribute a
lot of things to luck. And I was living in San Francisco and I found out that there's
going to be a new gaming website that's launching. It's called GameSpot. And it's like funded.
They like actually have money. And they actually have a staff. And they're serious about this
whole gaming website thing. Unlike us, you know, little kind of hobbyist thing that we'd
started. And I, you know...
I sent them an email sounding more important than I actually was.
Did you lie on your resume, Greg?
No, it was just a thing that like if you...
No one knows your age when you send an email.
So if you send an email with like punctuation,
people just assume that you can't be a teenager.
This guy is onto something.
Yeah. So they agreed to meet with me or whatever and they're like, you know...
on no real basis, but eventually they're like, you know, we have an internship open or whatever, right?
They weren't interested in like acquiring
Arcadia magazine or nothing, but but um, but I'm like dude internship like it was a paid internship and everything. So
That was yeah. So this is in
1996 in the fall and that's when I started as an intern
at GameSpot shortly after they had launched.
And that's when I first met folks like Jeff Gerstmann,
who's still in the game after all these years,
you know, at Giant Bomb,
and other folks who I
remember very fondly. So, yeah,
I started...
uh... writing about games there uh... it was kind of my first real job
and you got all the way up to executive editor at gamespot
uh... yeah editor-in-chief yeah uh... uh... so yeah
hi dogs
yes
wait for them
yeah they're in the podcasting room
uh... yeah
yeah i
I ended up working at GameSpot for more than 10 years, starting as an intern and ending up as editor-in-chief.
And it was one of those things where I had completely fallen in love with that work of being a game critic.
Reviewing games was still always one of my favorite parts of the job,
and toward the end there were pressures on me to spend my time on quote-unquote more important things,
because I was responsible for...
big aspects of the site, managing an editorial team, and those are in fact more important things.
But I felt that...
you know, like reviewing games is at the heart of why I loved that work.
But the years just flew by, right? And suddenly I'm in my late 20s and no
closer to being a game developer and I'm like,
okay, well I could blink. Also, like, reviewing games is, that's
like, that's hard work. Not hard work like
working at a coal mine, but that's some time-intensive,
tiring stuff.
Yeah, I did it, I mean, I would do it mostly, I would, it was kind of my second job there, as it were, of like, I would do that as homework.
Um, um, but, but it, again, it was like the part that I...
I loved it, you know, reviewing games was an opportunity as always to just like, it
gave me an excuse to play a lot of different games, and to just sort of understand my own
feelings about them, because I figured if I could...
You know, I think we all intuitively have a sense of what we like and what we don't.
You know, you watch a movie and it's like, that was a bad movie or that was a good movie.
But why, right?
I like to ask myself why I felt a certain way about a certain game.
What were the aspects of it that contributed to me thinking that it was so good
or that it was, you know, not so good and so on.
And being a game critic, like...
forced me to just be more introspective in that way and try to articulate it.
And I hoped that maybe that experience would help make me...
you know, a better game developer if I ever got the chance to do it.
But yeah, and so I finally got my chance at the beginning of 2007
when I went to go work at Electronic Arts in Los Angeles,
as I heard they were...
I forgot that you did that. I was, when I was doing my internet stocking...
Oh yeah, you went to EALA, worked on Command & Conquer.
Yeah. So that was one of those things, you know, again it was pretty...
The opportunity was happenstance in that even after all that time at GameSpot, I didn't really
know anybody in the industry because we were very strict about maintaining an editorial
separation. If I'm reviewing games from different studios, I have to not have personal connections
with those studios. So then I'm like, well, I'm no closer to becoming a game developer and I might
I knew I would regret it if I never had a shot.
And then, you know, a former GameSpot colleague who had gone to work at EALA before me, Amir
Ajami, who's a dear friend of mine still, he always knew I was interested in development
and he's like, yo, we have an opening for a producer if this is something you'd be interested
in applying for.
And I applied and I got it.
Yeah, then that's when my development journey started, and it's certainly been a rollercoaster.
At EA, I think on the very first day is where I met another Amir, Amir Rao, and Gavin Simon,
who became friends of mine and later founded Supergiant Games, where I'm working now.
So there's a direct line.
from my EA experience to what I've been doing ever since.
But yeah, at some point I, you know, the 10 years felt like a long time, but I've
now been in game development for longer than I was in the gaming press,
you know, doing the math since 2007.
But it feels like it does not feel like that long ago.
When you first made that jump, did you feel like- you talked about how you thought that your
review experience would give you this kind of unique perspective going into games development.
Did that actually happen that way? Did all your time spent in game journalism give you
kind of a different outlook on how games are made once you got inside of the process?
Yeah, you know what helped? I think the thing that helped me the most directly
was the part where I had been working
on a big website at a fairly high level in the organization.
And a website is a bunch of software when you get right down to it,
and it's software with artwork, with design,
and basically we had departments at GameSpot that were...
that basically have counterparts at a game development studio.
So I had already... I felt like I already had some of the vocabulary
to just like interact with, you know,
with art teams, with engineers,
and with marketing teams and stuff like that as well.
So that...
probably helped me at least as much as just my knowledge of games, however much I had.
But I do think my knowledge around, like, my ability to have justified playing more games
than average up to that point just has always given me like a broad...
It makes me able to think of references to things quickly, if nothing else. So when
tackling, like, a design problem.
maybe I can think of a game that, you know, handled something in a similar way,
like a reference to look at or something like that. And that's, that is, I do find that very
helpful. If nothing else, it's like confidence boosting for a person for whom confidence
boosts do not come readily. So like in, when it comes to games, I'm like, well, I feel knowledgeable
about this one thing, even though I'm like insecure about whatever other aspects of life,
at least games, I've been playing them all my life, I feel like.
I at least know what I like and know how to articulate it, whether I can convey that successfully
to someone I'm working with, who knows.
that did help me. It helped me not feel like I was completely out of my depth.
And it also, you know, what also helped me to my, I guess, to my delight or something is like,
I didn't realize how much game developers cared about the gaming press.
Like, I felt like a lot of people I came into, you know, this pretty big team at EA,
you know, a hundred plus people, and I felt like a lot of them were just like,
like appreciate it I I felt like surprisingly like appreciated it wasn't
like oh here's here's the outsider you don't know anything like your experience
is garbage I was like oh cool you worked at GameSpot so they were very welcoming
and that was that was a really it was an awesome team yeah a great group of
people so they they made me it was you know it's a weird experience I'd only
worked at this one place basically for 10 years so it's like just leaving a
group of people that
that you've come to know quite well into like a totally new organization where you know, you know,
initially only a couple of people. It's a big change. And I also moved, or didn't really move,
but I started commuting down to Los Angeles for the job. So there's a lot of
life changes as part of that, but I felt very motivated to...
again, at least give it a chance. Maybe I'd come crawling back to writing about games,
but at least I'd be able to look back and say, I tried this other thing.
Do you still think you're going to come crawling back to writing about games someday? Are you
a lifer now?
You know, I would be lying if I said the thought never crossed my mind during the course of
the time that's passed. But these days, certainly, I...
I'm really, you know, at Supergiant with Bastion, our first game, that was the first time I
got to do the sort of job of my eight-year-old dreams, right?
Like building levels, writing worlds, writing characters, writing stories, putting it all
into the game, like getting my hands dirty on the actual process of building the thing.
And I've been doing equivalent work to that on our subsequent games, and that's work that I don't imagine I will grow tired of during my lifetime.
I definitely enjoy what I do, but for all its ups and downs, basically the...
I said it was a roller coaster.
I think the highs were higher and the lows were lower compared to my experience at GameSpot,
probably.
But being able to put these things into the world and then see that people enjoy them
definitely means a lot to me and feels like I'm getting to...
It's lived up to my dreams in that respect, as strenuous as it can be from time to time.
Well, if you ever want to write again, I have a small freelance budget.
Yeah.
I still love to, you know, every now and then I still get a chance to write about games
and I still definitely enjoy it.
And once in a while there's that like sleeper game that comes out and you know, you first
hear about it through reviews and stuff and I'm like, ah, I miss, those are the best moments
as a game critic when you like discover something and help spread the word about it, about why
it's so great.
Yeah. So moving on to, you know, closer to your current career status, uh, you know,
journey, uh, like talk about journeys, like you go from bastion and honestly,
Greg, I forgot that you didn't, you weren't like a co-founder of super giant
because I feel like your name is so attached.
to it now, but you actually came in a little bit after the founding and then worked on
the end of Bastion?
I worked, yeah, it's a bit murky there because I was there for like a lot of the formative
discussions with Amir and Gavin when we were still down in LA.
I was like roommates with Amir and stuff like that, so we started, we were playing these
games.
I meant, there's like, I think it's like four games in particular that really struck me from that era,
and I think the rest of us, it was like Braid, Castle Crashers, Plants vs. Zombies, and World of Goo,
were these like really just amazingly crafted games from small teams released at around that time, 2008-2009.
And meanwhile, we're on this big team and we start, we're like...
what could these games felt so like personal and so well made that we started wondering you know
what could we do?
if we could call the shots and just sort of have to do it ourselves.
What would the constraints be and what kind of game would we make?
So we were excitedly having those discussions,
and then Amir and Gavin bit the bullet and quit their jobs at EA
and moved up to Amir's dad's house in San Jose, California,
which was vacated by his dad conveniently at the time,
and founded Supergiant and got to work on Bastion.
And I joined them, yeah, I joined them the following year.
because in the intervening time I went to go work at 2k games that's based up
here in the North Bay in California which is closer to my home because I'd
been commuting to Los Angeles from Northern California for basically two
and a half years and and had to like pick up the pieces of my of my life
outside of work and just sort of stabilize things I like the idea of
going straight from my like commuting you know LA situation into like a
startup company
based an hour and a half away from where I was living was like a company yeah
exactly so it was like it was like too much but but then you know we kept
talking and I reunited with them as as Bastion was going into full production
so so I yeah I got to do the you know writing and and design and all kinds of
stuff on that game who's who's like you know founding principles were
were near and dear to my heart as well as that of
Amir and Gavin.
And our team had grown to... we were seven people by the end of that game.
So yeah, Transistor was the...
Transistor was a game that we worked on first where we had like basically a like
a full team from the start and we grew a little bit we grew to 12 full team yeah
yeah we did consider it a full team that's great yeah like I gotta say to
supergiant games over the course of these four games Bastion, Transistor, Pyre,
Hades.
They all, you can tell what a Supergiant game is now.
There's such a clear line where these games build upon each other.
How has your view on game design or any kind of philosophies that you take evolved as the four of those games were developed and released?
Yeah, we, you know, I do think we have certain values in common from game to game, like we're always interested in that sort of, in the connection between the interactive experience and the narrative.
experience and context like how can we tell stories in a unique way
that that would not translate to other media how can we take advantage of
what's unique about games in our approach to storytelling we
really like storytelling and world building because we
think it helps make when when it's done effectively we
think it helps make your your like
experience in a game, it can make it feel more meaningful. It could add context and depth where
it might not be there inherently through the mechanics alone. And we really value
the presentation, the atmosphere of our games, and also things like making our games
available to players of like a wide range of skill levels.
That's partly coming from our approach to narrative.
You know, there's nothing more frustrating in games where you're like
really engaged with the story but then you just hit a wall, like a difficulty wall.
You just want to see how the story ends but you like can't,
you can't make any more progress because,
you know, because it's so, it's too much for you. So we try to
build in systems into our games that, that...
mitigate those kind of moments so that if you are engaged in the narrative but
you haven't been playing games since you were six or whatever you can still work
your way through and and have a good experience but yeah you know more more
specifically each of our games has been like a reaction to the one before it in
part because you know we
ever since Bastion at least, each of our games has taken approximately three years, give
or take, and by the time we're done with one, we've pretty deeply kind of explored whatever
it was that we set out to do with that game, and we're kind of ready for something different
in some way.
uh so we naturally kind of lean into other other ideas you know transistor being uh the kind of
first obvious example of this where we went from making this like very you know arcadey
uh fantasy game in bastion to this like more deliberately paced
almost like strategic science fiction game in Transistor.
So there's some superficial similarities between the two,
but the vibe of them I think is quite different
and how, you know, for us it felt like.
it felt very different to work on. And then once again with Pyre, Pyre is completely different
from Transistor. And then finally with Hades, this is back, you know, we started that game
in 2017, just a few weeks after Pyre shipped. We finally said, hey, let's do like, let's
pull together all the, all the best aspects of our previous games that we enjoyed working
on and like build.
something based on that because we'd been like sort of discarding our ideas
so much also like no no sequels like either I'm noticing is the supergiant
just like we have to do something we want to do something different every
time
Yeah, we really, I personally really value the element of surprise.
I think, you know, people have said there have been a, we're so grateful for the nice
things that have been said about Hades across a lot of different aspects of the game.
But I think like a quietly underrated aspect of why our games have been able to make people,
you know, say nice things about them is that they surprise people.
they... we... I think Surprise is really... when you go into a game and it just kind of plays out
the way you think it's going to play out, I think it can only have so much of an impact on you. But
when it does things that are like way beyond your expectations, those are the games I think that can
really stick with you. And...
you know cutting back to the bastion days
it's like hey we have this dark horse advantage like no one knows what we're
capable of as a team no one's heard of us so we could just do whatever
and and make this game that just looks like a hack and slash arcade game
actually have a you know kind of a deeper experience to it
and and i felt that that worked out very well
uh... but it you know then bastion you know sort of put us on the map is a
small independent studio
and it's like oh well
maybe our dark horse advantage is gone forever and we can surprise people
anymore that's part of why we
we did transistor instead of like a like a bastion two would have been a very
sensible thing to do
uh... after bastion but we we didn't want
like that wasn't
the path that we were more excited about we want to ask ourselves like can we do
this again because we loved
you know building the world from scratch on bastion and seeing that people
enjoyed it so we we want to see if we had like
uh... the competency to be able to do it again
uh... men so we've done that
each time like priority prioritizing surprise but we
you know we love the world of our games we've always said
that like there's no reason
we wouldn't ever go back to them. It's just that when it comes time to decide what to do next,
we've just always been excited to try something new.
I'm kind of curious about how that surprise plays out internally, because you see certain
studios are known for a certain genre, a certain mechanic, and that is their niche, and they
make games, very good games, along those lines.
But how do you work with the team and manage a team that seems to be really mobile in the
kind of game that they're making?
How do you handle surprise internally with your developers who need to have these different
skills to express different genres or different gameplay?
Yeah, I mean, I think for us, it's hard, like, creating surprise or something through the play experience, I think...
it's hard to be aware of that as a developer because you're iterating so
like nothing is surprising to you necessarily as a developer
because you've been iterating from the inside yeah or it's it's the thing you
know particularly with like story moments that are meant to be impactful
like the like the ending of a game or something
like that or some some key moment it's hard to keep perspective on that
over the course of development just because you've seen it so many times
i think it's a pixar thing from back in the day they had
i'm gonna
I don't remember the exact wording, but they're like, remember the first...
The idea is kind of remember the first moment, remember how you felt
the first time you experienced this part in the story, because over time you're
gonna... you're gonna grow a bit numb to that. So
for us, I think it's like we look... we give ourselves time
to do some of the small stuff. We don't over-schedule the work so that
there's no room for the small... and I call it like...
this is a great expression but i call it like the dumb stuff in the game a little
like it's the pointless stuff
i say it in like a
i mean it in an affectionate kind of way
now i mean it in an affectionate way but the things that are unnecessary in a
game i think are the things that actually like paradoxically you can make
a game very special
yet on the other side of the family
and he's in and rather get
We try to jam all our games full of it because you don't, we, as a developer, you actually
don't know which of those unnecessary pointless things a player is going to really respond
to.
But, you know, for me it's like, if you could just put enough of them, then one of them
is going to work on you.
There's so much of that in the writing, obviously.
in Hades, you know, these tiny quote unquote dumb things where it's like, wait, the game
knew that I did that.
Yeah, and you know that, I mean, I think it's not a coincidence that working on stuff like
that is also one of, it's fun.
It's fun to be able to do the small kind of unnecessary things.
it's more work, so you have to reconcile that, and it's the stuff that's the first on the chopping block if you run out of time.
So I think it's quite tricky there, but again, we learned a lot of production discipline at EA, at our team.
Our team at EA was very efficient in making good games in a timely fashion, so we've just tried to get better and better.
from a production standpoint and leave ourselves room
for the individual creators on the team to sort of chase
their passions through their work.
And I mean, I see, like,
when it comes time for us to decide on a new project,
like the highest priority for us is like,
what will be the most exciting,
or I shouldn't say the highest priority,
but something we very actively think about is like,
what...
what can our team... what will our team do in a unique way that we will most enjoy making?
We don't like... we think about specifically what our skill sets can... what sort of game we can
create as a team. We don't think about a game like in the abstract and then want to make it.
It's like what can we do?
knowing what Darren Korb, our composer and audio director, what is he excited about?
What is Gen Z, our art director, excited about?
Can we sort of synthesize those ideas into something?
I find that excitement, that individual excitement, to me,
is hugely important because game development can be, frankly, such a slog.
and so much of it is not fun that the excitement can carry you through those sort of troughs
in the development when you're like, ugh, you're stuck on a hard problem, you're not
making progress as quickly as you thought, the sort of honeymoon period is over for how
excited you initially might have been about the thing, but then you remember.
that you saw this potential in it and you can remain inspired to keep doing work that matters to you.
That shows through in all the games too.
Thank you. I'm glad it does.
Also, I want to talk a little bit too about...
So there is actually some Twitter discourse this week having to do with writing,
and this comes up pretty frequently.
about how so many games the writing is just kind of tacked on at the end.
It's like an aesthetic that's supposed to make all the gameplay make sense, more cohesive.
But that's not how Supergiant works, right?
We, you know, that is partially true,
but the part where we use narrative to, like,
justify how the game works is absolutely one of the...
one of the kind of functions of narrative in our game to make...
I think of it as like an adhesive, it's like glue that seeps into the cracks
of the game to make it all feel like it was all highly deliberate and every little piece was meticulously planned out.
Like, the reality of game development...
it's not that clean. So you, like, these little bits and pieces are coming together at different
times. Obviously a lot of different people are working on it. Even in a small team, you know,
we're up to 19 people now for Hades, and it's still like different people with different
perspectives putting their own work into the game. We want it to feel cohesive overall,
but we don't want it to come from a place of like...
you know you must do it this way you must all do it this way so that it's
cohesive it's like the role of the story can be to find those connections
between otherwise disparate elements. And you as a writer aren't brought on in the last
you know few months of development. Yes that's I guess that's a that's a key point I
should have spoken to right away which is that you know we're thinking about
the narrative and the themes of the game that we're working on from the start.
We're highly design-driven. We don't start with a story and back-solve the gameplay onto it.
That's never been our approach, but we're looking for...
we're looking for that harmony where the design that we're interested in, the themes we're
interested in exploring can be expressed also through the story and how it's told.
And this applies across the board, like, you know, our music has been praised over time,
the music of Darren Korb, and he's, you know, he's a genius and I love working with him
and he's a wonderful guy.
But part of the secret weapon, such as it is, is that he's there from the beginning.
Like, one of the most important things that we do at the start of the project is start figuring out what the music is going to sound like.
Because that helps identify the entire vibe and tone of the experience that then, you know,
like even myself from a writing standpoint, you know, hearing the music a certain way,
it's like, yeah, okay, this really clicks tonally.
I want to write in such a way that supports...
this music. Whereas you could bring on Hans Zimmer or something in the last year of production
on a big game, and Hans Zimmer might deliver super amazing music, but it wouldn't necessarily
be integrated as deeply as the music in a game like ours where we think of audio as a really
vital part of the experience in creating an atmosphere and the overall mood. So yeah,
it's another example of where thinking...
Thinking about the role of the narrative, thinking about the role of the audio,
and the artwork obviously right from the start of production I think leads to,
makes it possible for us to get to a better result in those regards.
Is that something that really benefits from what seems to be like a really deliberately small studio that you guys have?
This like, tight-knit team?
Yeah, it really, it really, really does. It's a good, um, thank you for bringing that up.
We do, like, I do feel strongly that a lot of what we do only works because we're small.
Like, I don't see how it could scale, necessarily.
Um, we, like, we just, you know, a lot of it is that...
there are these like long-standing personal relationships at the heart of the studio
um with with like amir rao as kind of the i used i i would think of him as like the commander
shepherd or whatever having assembled his like crack team uh all of us like were connected to
amir in some way some of us knew you know i knew gavin um and and uh andrew wang our cto um
like from la but you know like darren corb
Amir knew, you know, like, since they were kids.
And Logan Cunningham, who's been our principal voice actor in each of our games,
him and Darren and Amir, you know, played like youth soccer or something when they were 10.
So they all would go way back, and those longstanding relationships...
help us to again, like, kind of work through everything and just be able to be
sincere with each other and, yeah, build games around what we know our strengths are,
as well as to, like, navigate one another's, kind of, you know, our idiosyncrasies as people.
Like, we don't have to all work the same way as...
you know, is expected to be the case sometimes at larger studios where you need more formal,
you know, office hours or something like that.
When we're a small team we could just, it could just be more custom to the individuals
that are there.
Yeah, which I don't know that that can scale up.
Yeah, the studio culture just speaking of that too. It's just interesting reading. I think that you gave an interview in 2019
having uh, you know unlimited
um, you know
Days off required 20 or so
No emailing after 5 p.m on friday. I could get I could get into that one
Oh boy, the no email, I was a big advocate for the no email after 5 on Fridays, because
I was one of the people who was like wrecked by the opposite of that.
I'd be, you know...
uh... at like a dinner with my wife and kids or whatever uh... and
and still just sitting on my like i'll god damn it there's a cml like
the the person who sent me the email
had no intention of inconveniencing me and i had no intention to like
district it like it was it was my fault right that i would i would sit there and
not wanna like slow things down for other people you know all wait i have to
answer this
so that the other person you know
can keep on going and we realize that like sort of calling the ceasefire
calling the truce after five uh... it made this really
uh... it made a very tangible difference so that even
you know i still
i still work
uh... evenings and weekends like whenever
the heck i want to you know again when i'm adding dumb stuff to hades and
having fun
uh... some of that work
i do on weekends
but it's on my terms. And I do it in such a way that I'm...
it has to be work that doesn't require anybody else. I'm not bothering nobody.
It's not answering emails. Yeah, and so it makes... it just creates
these quiet moments and made the weekends
feel more like weekends. And, you know, yeah, from my
gaming press days I certainly remember what it was like to just get
emails non-stop and it's, yeah, it's kind of...
creates like an oppressive feeling and having having times when it's quieter is
really important. Yeah I'm gonna jump back to gushing about Hades. Yeah I just
I just love so I feel like well I know that one of the reasons that Hades is so
praised is because
the consideration of the mechanics and the design and how that fits with the
narrative because you know that the story requires that's one thing I never
I don't think I've ever played a roguelike that acknowledges that the
death cycle and this is what Hades is about it's about dying over and over
again and try you don't have that mechanic that design without the story
that you set up
So which one came first? Was it like we're gonna do a roguelike or is it like
you know or did like the story come first or they kind of come together
naturally at the same time?
Yeah, so I think the order of decisions was the first one, the first thing we decided
was actually early access before there was any game idea at all. And that was partly, again,
like in response to having worked on Pyre, where you basically work for three years without knowing
what anyone is even gonna think of the thing.
And we take it, you know, we announce it,
we take it to PAX, we play test it.
So we get a level of feedback along the way,
but it's really different once you finally put it out there
and kind of see truly what you've made.
So our thought was like,
can we test our ideas sooner rather than...
rather than having to wait three years to find out how we did.
And we also were drawn to early access because
we felt it would lead to a more disciplined
production approach where during the course of development of a game like
Pyre, it's like a busted game through large
portions of development where we're tinkering away at different
bits and pieces of it, but someone couldn't just...
start the game and play through to the end during most phases of development
because it's just all, you know, you're just still trying to build.
Is it like an accountability thing when you're doing it?
It's not really, um, it's not an accountability thing.
It's, well, I mean, I guess everything at some level is an accountability thing,
but I think it's like a fault of the development process itself where we're not, um...
where the things that we're working on are lower level and we're not testing the experience
like end to end as like a priority.
So we figured that with early access it means that we have to keep the game stable, problem
free and playable end to end for the vast majority of the time.
that means that once you're actually done with development,
there should in theory be fewer problems.
The way Gavin would put it is like,
do you want to find the problems before the game is done
or after the game is done?
It's like, oh, that has an obvious answer.
So, and also I think early access was,
it was like different and scary
in a way that was like attractive to us.
So then, early access starts to apply some constraints on the kind of game you might want to make.
Like, early access wouldn't have worked at all for a game like Transistor that's, you know, six or seven hours to play through.
You just burn through a crappy version of it, and then never want to play it again.
So we wouldn't get any feedback from...
like you want you want to have a game that people
are interested in
playing for a decent amount of time so that you can get their
get their feedback on it because otherwise why are you making
a game in early access so
that drew us to the roguelike dungeon crawler genre which is something or or
specifically to the roguelike genre
uh...
Because we were just playing and enjoying it. We were playing these games like Dead Cells and Slay the Spire, like a whole bunch
around that time, just loving those games and thinking of these games like
Binding of Isaac and Darkest Dungeon, Enter the Gungeon.
Really cool games, but games that...
didn't really prioritize the narrative experience necessarily which is something that our games
have always done and we would think back to our bastion days when when we set out to make an
action rpg and we're like hey what if we just use this genre format for for storytelling maybe that
will help distinguish this game and not make it look like a terrible diablo clone or something
like that and that worked out so it was basically that same mindset of like hey can we use
this genre format to tell a story.
And a thing I would think about often is even in the hardest core
roguelike game where it resets you completely to nothing
from one playthrough to another, there is in fact something that you carry
forward, which is your knowledge of the mechanics in the game, right?
So using your knowledge you can get farther and farther in a game like
Spelunky or you name it.
So it was a fun thought exercise to think of a game premise where the character had
the same ability. So it leads you to, well, what sort of character would still remember
what happened after they die? Well, what about a character who's just immortal? Like,
they don't die for real. Because you don't really die for real in roguelike games. They
don't uninstall themselves, right? You can play over and over. So it's just...
Yeah. So it's trying to align. We're always trying to align.
the player experience with the narrative.
It leads, you know, having a character like Zagreus who can be serious one moment,
self-deprecating another, you know, like snarky or whatever.
He's...
even though he has a lot of personality on his own, he in some ways he is there to sort of speak
for the player's experience and just trying to find that strong, like I said before, that connection
between the play experience and the story. So it all kind of flowed from there, that idea that
like what if there was a roguelike with narrative continuity where every time you run into a boss
they remember, you know, they like, you know, you start keeping a tally of who won this time,
who won last time. And it was fun to think about. It was, we had done a game with a complex
narrative and pyro just before, so it wasn't that intimidating of a starting point. And we started
chipping away at it basically in early access. And then, yeah, here, and then here we are.
It's a really interesting way, because when you go into early access, leading with a narrative foot,
there's the risk that your players could get burnt out of your story so quickly,
because you're going to be updating throughout, and they might have to restart their save or whatever,
depending on how you do that. But the roguelike formula is so welcoming to that,
that it's like it's a match made in heaven. It's really great.
Thank you. Yeah, it's... I think it's a...
I think our consideration of those, we tried to find that match, like, consciously.
Not knowing how it would work out, of course, but the, like, knowing that early access would
have the sort of issues that you described, it led to the specific design choices and
approach to the story that, you know, that ended up working out for us in the long run,
in addition to during early access.
You know, we, I approached it like...
It was a fun challenge because it was different in a lot of ways, but like our previous games, you know, it's like dropping a big novel.
It requires like a novel length amount of writing in it, I think.
So it's just, you know, one day, boom, it's just this giant thing.
But with Hades, it felt more like a TV series or something where...
our early access launches like the pilot.
We're going to introduce some of the characters, we're going to set up the stakes for what
the story is about, and we're going to allude to there being an ending eventually.
But we basically added the ending of the game in our 1.0 launch.
So we built the beginning first, and then we introduced subplots and things along the
way.
again chip away at it with each of our major updates and then finally
you know do the finale in the 1.0 launch that was our idea and
and yeah that worked out well
we wanted very much for the ending of the game to like live up to the
expectations of our early access players because they were they were quite
engaged
with the story and the characters at that point
Given the differences from releasing a game and hearing your community feedback versus
working on an early access game and having that feedback be more part of the development
process, even if you say your next game isn't an early access game, are there lessons you
can take from working with your community collaboratively into your next project, you
think?
I mean, there are for sure, but I think one of those big lessons is that early access is really valuable.
So, I think if we didn't... That's not to say it is a foregone conclusion for whatever we do next.
It's not, but it's something I think that we would have to give serious thought to considering.
I think we would all agree that a part of the success of Hades, like a significant part of the success of Hades is owed to the early access development having gone well and resulted in this bigger and kind of cleaner game than we could have come up with on our own.
I think we would, if we didn't do like early access in the traditional way, I think we would still very much want to have...
like, figure out ways to get more feedback from more people sooner in development and more steadily.
So that every step of the way as we're adding stuff to the game or changing stuff that we could be receptive to how...
So that we could be receptive to how that's changing the experience,
and like, which opportunities it's then creating for the game.
Like, one of the really valuable things with Early Access is just that it lets you...
it lets you stay
it helps you
like, see the forest for the trees, as it were, because, you know, again, a couple of
years into development, you could get really down in the weeds on stuff and maybe start
to lose perspective on what's really important for the game.
Because with games, you could spend an infinite amount of time on basically any aspect of
it.
So, that decision of, like, when is it done?
When do you move on?
Is really tricky.
And I don't...
Yeah, it's tricky to make that, to decide that, so when you're working in early access,
it can help you decide.
Because if the whole community is like, this part's awesome, but this part is whack, or
this part is missing, you know, what the game, the game is totally missing this, it can help
jog that part of your brain when you're like, yeah, what am I doing?
I keep tinkering away at this thing that everybody's happy with.
Why don't I work on this thing that I know the game needs?
So it just helped us.
stay more focused on what mattered and stay like really motivated I think as well just to keep it
it feels good to work on things that you know matter to people whereas in the thick of it
while working on a game you can it's easy to lose sight of that in my in my experience like why you
know why am I doing this like does it is anybody gonna care that goes with so many creative
projects yeah exactly it's like because you're not I mean some creative projects you do
It's important, you know, sometimes you do do it for yourself, but if you're doing it as your job,
presumably you're also creating something for others, not just yourself.
And if you're creating it for others, then you benefit from knowing what they actually think.
You may not, it doesn't mean you have to do what they say,
but you at least want to know how they're experiencing it and what they're...
it's so valuable just hearing about people's experience with something you've worked on
because you have your own hopes and dreams about how people will experience it, you know,
oh this story moment, they're going to feel this way, but what do they actually feel?
You know, did it land? So knowing whether your work is...
is resonating or connecting the way that you intend,
lets you either make changes to get it closer to target
or like proceed with more confidence
than you might've had otherwise.
Yeah, getting more eyeballs on it
and acting as a sanity check type thing too.
Yeah, exactly.
Well, we've had you for longer than usual, as far as our previous guests go, and I think
that is just because you are great to talk to, and we love hearing what you have to say
about game development and design.
And I also appreciate how we're saying the word roguelike without any judgment around
here.
I think Metroidvania's fine, I think roguelike is fine, roguelite is fine.
uh... so
it genres are weird there there just short hands right it's like they're
they're weird it like rpg
yes like it doesn't it they don't that's the words themselves don't mean that
anything when you think about it yet
system rpg action adventure game of the year like the categories all their own
and then they'll model together yeah
i mean good great great him from like journalism journalism game journalism
background
we say what everyone wants to make it
we make up the words
So, well, thanks so much for joining us.
And one last thing, I didn't know that, I actually didn't know that you voiced Hypnos.
I did.
Can you do a line as Hypnos in character?
I can!
um was that was that the line um so yeah well i can't i i don't know that i i can't muster it
that well um let's see because it's a voicing hypnos was really fun because it's just getting
to completely switch to a different uh outlook on things but we got we got we got i can i that
was that was hypnos thanks for dying welcome to the house of hades that's his kind of like
classic line
We do a little bit of processing on it, but I think I could get it close enough.
No, thanks for dying. I mean, uh, that...
Yeah.
We imagined him as like a, he's like a store greeter, right?
That's like, that was, he's the guy, you know, yeah.
Darren, who did all the voice directing, he's like, you know,
Welcome to Walmart! You know, that sort of thing, so.
that's perfect that's how we're going to go to your charms of like finding out like who actually
like yeah this is a programmer who did this voice here and it's incredible to like find those fun
facts so thank you for that amazing we have new ringtones now so yeah all right well thanks again
for joining us greg and uh best of luck in all your future endeavors and i hope you have a little
bit of downtime maybe uh in between games nice relaxing email free weekend yeah yes indeed yeah
thanks so much for having me on the show yeah
Hey, we are back.
I can't believe that we got Hypnos.
We conjured Hypnos.
Yeah, that was like a little fanboyish to kind of like be like, can you do the line
at the end?
But it paid off.
Was I fawning?
Was I fawning too much?
A little bit.
It only came through most of the conversation.
That's okay.
I have more where that came from.
So yeah, I mean, like, what was it that stuck out to you that talked so many interesting points
that Greg brought up? I really enjoy Supergiant as a concept. I don't know what that means,
but the quality of game they put out and the kind of game they put out just oozes charm,
and they do it with such a small team and do it so consistently. And then they took on early access
and did the exact same thing. And it's just, it's really impressive. And it's always great to hear
how that process goes off in the background.
Yeah, so many other game developers must hate them.
Supergiant just released another hit. Game developers hate them.
This is unrelated, well this is kind of related, but like back when
Pyre got announced for Supergiant was like right before PAX East and it was
just kind of, if I'm remembering right, it was there's a mystery new
Supergiant game that's going to be at PAX and I'm like I'm gonna be at PAX and
I managed to snag an appointment last minute.
and like the hype around that is just so very super giant and just kind of like it's that
same kind of like fervor over this one studio's creation was carried forward into Hades and now
everyone I talk to about Hades is just in love it's incredible. Totally. Have you bought Hades
for anybody like for uh for the holidays or? No my partner plays a ton of it um so I count that as a gift.
Yeah. So I, as far as these, uh, indie developers go, I think that it's like
clay entertainment, like don't starve. Um, and they're, and they're also doing,
uh, oxygen not included and super giant, I think, and subset, subset games like
Into the Breach and FTL. I think those for me are just, how do you, how was this repeatable?
I think my original question notes for this, I'm just like, what's the one secret behind
having a small team doing all of this incredible stuff?
And it's just the camaraderie that in every Supergiant interview you read, including this
conversation, my dog in the background agrees.
It's just like the way a small team can work as like one cohesive whole and just through
people knowing each other and through people playing different parts with like voice acting
and art design and just like all of these kind of like pieces of whole coming together
is this like community creation project.
You can't have or read an interview with anybody from Supergiant without them throwing credit
to...
you know, uh, they're, they're, they're teammates on there. I mean, like, Gen Z, uh, you know,
who does the art there, it's like that, that's, it's so, it's so, like, defining and sets them
apart just visually. Uh, think that is.
you know, just they're unlike any other indie game developer out there right now.
Most to all, well not all, because they're solo dev projects, but like most projects are
collaborations between teams and then it's just really wonderful when that kind of like
energy comes through in every element of a thing, like with Hades.
Yeah. And the, uh, I could have, you know, we could have talked to Greg for so much longer
about narrative design, uh, just because I think, I think like in the next few, like it, like in a
few years, we're going to see more roguelikes that adopt that are clearly influenced by Hades.
like there is, there's a template now, I feel like.
So I think this is just going to be,
Hades in particular from Supergiant is going to be influential
and, you know, making more interesting,
narratively interesting roguelikes
that aren't just about, you know, getting really far
and then, you know, and then dying and then rage quitting.
That's how I play them anyway.
There's nothing wrong with that also, but like there's not I don't want to disparage like other, you know, because I've I love spelunky
I love I love yeah. Yeah. I mean like dead dead cells is is
Amazing enter the gungeon. I got so into that. I love that format. I guess what I'm saying is that
the consideration that you take is like, okay,
I appreciate how the whole cycle of trying and dying
and trying and dying is accounted for in the story.
It makes it more interesting to fail.
Yeah, I would say a lot of, excuse me, a lot of like roguelikes have that
narrative interweave in there, but Hades leans into it so much that like, it'll
be interesting to see how that spins off into other games, maybe other genres
that just, I love a good narrative heavy game and just having that so tightly
interwoven, it's just, it's good narrative design.
Yeah.
Um, it makes you, it, it takes the sting out of, you know, one of the
main components of roguelikes, which is failing in death.
Yeah.
Ending on a happy note, failing in bed.
I was just going to say, that's not darker than I meant it to, but yeah, I know.
And then of course there's, um, I think a lot of the, um, end of 2020 roundup
bliss that a lot of them, if not every single one of them did include.
Hades talked about Hades, uh, is inadvertently the game that represents a 2020.
You know, the best, because it's just trying to escape hell over and over again, failing
most of the time.
But with charm.
With charm.
You gotta have that charm, that old 2020 charm.
But we're not in 2020 anymore.
No.
And the hell's going on anyway.
Yeah, so anyway, thank you for joining us for this conversation.
If you like hearing us talk to game developers about the amazing things they do, you can find
more episodes of the GDC Podcast on Spotify, the podcast house in iTunes, and we're over on
YouTube on the GDC Twitch channel as... or Twitch channel.
over on the GDC YouTube on YouTube as well.
And as mentioned in the intro,
there's also a GDC showcase coming up
where we will have five live episodes of the podcast
where we'll be seeing your questions in chat as we talk.
So please be nice.
Those will go in the podcast house as well.
Yeah, yeah.
All your content in one place.
So you better subscribe to those feeds
that we just mentioned to keep in contact.
All right, goodbye.
Goodbye, thank you.