My name is Tim Keenan, and I made a game called Duskers, where you pilot drones into derelict
spaceships to find the means to survive and piece together how the universe became a giant
graveyard.
Duskers has received a lot of critical acclaim for being innovative and completely immersing
players in a dead science fiction world.
I think what helped us to do this is our unique approach to the game's design.
In essence, we listened to the game and let Duskers tell us what it needed, rather than
us trying to steer it.
In my GDC talk, I'm going to explain our approach and how we use the notion of design pillars, but in a different way.
Namely, focusing on emotions rather than features, refining the game's vision throughout development, and focusing on player fantasy.
I hope to see you there!