Welcome to our talk.
We will talk about farming simulator today.
I'm Christian Amann from China Software.
This is Stefan Geiger.
We will split the talk in the middle.
And before we talk, this will be recorded, so please mute your cell phone.
OK.
We will start with a little introduction.
For myself, as I said, I'm Christian Amann.
I have a master's in computer science.
I worked a bit in the video games industry some years for Sony PlayStation and also for NVIDIA as a software engineer.
Before, I founded China Software together with Stefan Geiger.
This is a short intro of Stefan.
Stefan also has a master's degree in computer science.
He worked shortly at the Sensory Motor Lab before co-founding Giant Software in 2008 together with me.
A short slide about Giant Software.
We are developer, publisher of the Farming Simulator series.
We have offices in Zurich, in Germany, in the Czech Republic, and in the US.
And we develop games for pretty much all platforms that make sense, from consoles to mobile, also PC.
Sorry.
Okay, let's just start.
the history of Farming Simulator.
Both of us, Stefan and me, we share the passion for video games and programming.
And we dreamt of developing a game engine and creating video games in Switzerland.
And that's a fun fact.
Almost 20 years ago, we visited together the GDC here in San Francisco.
And that was the point where we decided to bring this dream into reality.
So in 2007, a friend, Martin Beowulf, suggested us to create a farming simulator.
So he had this idea.
He was pretty much obsessed by this idea to create this game because he loved such a game to play.
And so what we did, we concluded a bit of research, and we also launched a web forum with a small prototype of a farming simulator game.
And through that feedback we got, and also through market research, we were convinced that there's a potential and also demand for such a game in the market.
So this was pretty much the start.
2007, long time ago.
There were a lot of challenges in 2007 to enter the games market as a fresh developer, indie developer so to say.
Self-publishing a video game was a major challenge in the past.
The dominant way of selling games was back then still physical retail distribution.
So that was difficult.
And digital platforms that are available nowadays are very accessible, were close to indie developers.
So Steam was only open for indie developers 2012.
So that was also not possible to go that route.
And there's another big, major obstacle to take.
It was the game engine itself.
So game engines like Unity and Unreal, they were not accessible at that point.
Unity didn't really exist, and Unreal Engine was too expensive at that point for us to license.
So those were the challenges we had to overcome.
What did we do?
We tried to search a publisher, really traditional way of doing a video games project.
And we actually found a small publisher.
in Germany that we could do a contract, a distribution deal, that we also got a small minimum guarantee for the contract.
But the guarantee was so small we could barely upgrade our Maya licenses to commercial
We used Maya for pretty much all the assets of the game, so that was necessary of course.
So that was it, that was the start of the development of Farming Simulator.
It was a true independent game development to say, so we lived in a shared apartment to save costs.
and we did everything beside our day jobs.
So I was still working for NVIDIA at that point, part-time, and Stefan was at university finishing his master degree.
So it took us about nine months of development time and we could release the first version April 14th, 2008, and it really sold a lot.
So we sold, for the first version, which was only pretty much sold physical and only in Europe, 250,000 units.
And this was really crazy.
What happened at that time is there was,
a trend of simulation games became popular again.
So in the 90s there was quite a big genre and then around 2008 it was kind of a resurgence in popularity in the simulation genre, which is also nice.
could have helped us to sell units.
I will now talk a bit about the game design, the ideas we had behind the game.
Of course, Farming Slater is a simulation game, so the primary objective is to simulate a farming experience, per se.
So the players are tasked to planting and harvesting corpse.
crops.
So this also involves managing livestock, buying and selling agricultural equipment.
And what we also did from the start, we licensed farm brands to put into the game like John Deere and other brands to make the game as authentic as possible.
So, next slide.
To create a simulation game, we had to choose between entertainment and
realism or authenticity and it was crucial I think to have a good balance because on the other hand you want a lot of realism to make the game as real as possible but we also want to keep the game as fun as possible and that's very important for us to find the right balance
also to make the game successful in the market.
We tried very hard and we think we were not bad at that.
In most cases we favored entertainment, so fun was always more important than realism.
And I think that was also something which we did a bit different to other simulation games at the same time that were on the market.
We really favored entertainment and not realism.
Influences.
Yeah, we got influences, of course, by a lot of great games of that time.
Maybe to mention here is Grand Theft Auto and also Battlefield.
There are open world games, that was of course for us important to create an open world game.
What we also got from those games was this concept, which was pretty much new to simulation games, that you can enter and exit the vehicle at any time.
It's important for us that you can then also move around independently of a vehicle and also interact a bit with the environment.
And this gives you this kind of control of an immersion in the world that you are, as the simulation is.
I think this also helped to make the game interesting to a younger audience, and that's also a huge difference we see compared to traditional simulation titles like Flight Simulator, Train and Truck Simulator.
We have a much younger audience that plays our games, and I think one of the reasons is that we added newer features, for example that.
A bit more about the balance between entertainment and realism.
So easy to play game design was a huge priority for us.
What we did is certain automation to simplify certain gameplay mechanics.
So we tried to reduce the number of buttons that were used.
and we also introduced a context sensitive help system so in all situations all the buttons that make sense to use were showed on the upper left screen
because we had this experience from those simulation games.
They were great, like I just remember Falcon 3, a flight simulation game, but you had to remember like 100 keys to use it, and that was just not so practical.
So that's something we came up and thought, yeah, that could be cool, that you don't need to remember all the buttons.
OK, what we also did is we, of course, also added advanced gameplay mechanics, because we need to have a certain depth in the gameplay.
And what we did is we add that optionally.
So it was not, for a lot of things, it's not mandatory.
But you still can have that gameplay if you want to.
And this is something we did a lot in the sequels.
We added more and more complex gameplay, but it was optional.
So you're not obliged to use them.
It's free.
Of course, yeah, we released the game.
And there was a lot of feedback.
Some feedback was the game is too simplistic.
So there were hardcore fans in the community of the game that said, yeah, you can't make such a shit.
It's a toy game.
It's not a real simulation game.
So for example, the attachment of the combine header, so this bar in the front of the combine harvester, it was just one button.
You attach, lower, and turn it on.
And this was too simple.
And then we went back and made it a bit more complex.
And there were other elements that we also had to change or adapt.
In the end, user feedback was always very, very crucial and still is today for us to develop the game further and to decide which is important, which is not for the game.
That was from the start.
Even before the first version was released, we got feedback and were able to even
with the first videos we released, we could incorporate feedback from the community into the game, which is quite cool.
Yeah, so to say.
So the rest of the talk, we will talk about the three defining features of a farm insulator, career mode, modding, and also multiplayer.
Career mode, we introduced pretty much from the beginning of the series in 2008.
The ability to mod was in the first iteration.
We enhanced it quite substantially with the second version.
And multiplayer was introduced in the third iteration in 2010.
Let's talk about career mode.
The career mode in Farming Simulator adds progression and challenge.
So the player can start with basic farm equipment with a small amount of money and then gradually build his farm and earn more money to purchase larger and more powerful farming tools and so on.
The mode was at that time quite unique among simulation games.
And I think the important part is that it adds a level of progression and goal setting that was not present in other games at that time, simulation games at that time.
So that was, I think, an important part of the success.
What was the inspiration of the career mode?
So there are two things that inspired us.
First, RPG games.
that have this kind of leveling up or experience points and skill trees.
But also, like in sports management games, you see economy management that is also an inspiration to us.
And those elements, they're kind of a natural addition to the whole theme of this game in farming.
I think it adds a lot of engagement and realism, because farmers, they need to manage their equipment and their farm.
And there's also, of course, financial management.
So they need to see if they have enough money to buy certain equipment or exchange certain equipment to bigger equipment.
That's just the natural part of a farmer's daily life.
So for us, this was important to get this full spectrum of farming into the game.
and as I said this was not found in other simulation titles at that point.
Another element that is really interesting to talk about is the micro gameplay of the game.
So the micro gameplay is really when you work on the field, the lanes of the field go up and down to cultivate, to plow, to seed, or to harvest.
Or there's also, like if you sell goods, you have to drive to a selling point.
and then sell the goods.
This is something we quite early we added so called AI workers that will do those jobs because driving up and down the field for hours is maybe a bit boring as a game in the long term.
So we added automation mechanisms into the game.
so that you don't have to do that yourself.
So you can hire workers and then they will do the work for you.
It costs a bit of money, of course, but they will do the job for you.
So this is interesting in contrast to the macro gameplay.
So if you have the micro gameplay, so to say, automated, you can concentrate on the macro level.
And this is something that you see.
A good example is Factorio, where you have a low-level gameplay mechanics layer.
And then as soon as you have figured it out, you can concentrate on a more higher level of the gameplay and play there.
So this is very, very similar to those construction and management simulation games like Factorio and others.
So that's quite an interesting
This is already the end of my part.
We will switch over to Stefan.
Yeah, so let's get into another very important aspect of the game which is modding.
So basically we kind of grew up around some of the biggest modding successes like Counter-Strike and
Fans of the Asians and other big titles that were pretty popular with modding like Battlefield and Honor Tournament.
So for us it was kind of natural that modding needs to be part of the game as well.
because we also see kind of all the benefits from it that kind of gives the players that long-term playability and having the options to fully customize their game to what they like it.
And also it kind of gives a lot of free content for us because we've not been able to or probably no company is able to produce that much content that the community is able to.
To give you a short view what kind of the modding is in Farming Simulator, I have a short video that kind of shows a couple mods.
Like, of course, there's a lot of kind of realistic mods that try to model new vehicles that add kind of that realistic side of the game.
There's also completely new maps that people can create.
Mostly they're kind of dedicated to a specific area that they live in.
Like here is one in the US, in Michigan.
And also completely new gameplay features, like here where you have a very dedicated tool to fully optimize all the gameplay with very specific features.
Some other stuff like police and search and rescue vehicles that kind of completely change the game away from farming.
Also some fun elements as well.
They also added excavators in the game and some very fun stuff as well.
Also like yeah content very kind of dedicated to kids as well with like very colorful stuff.
So, well, how did we achieve that?
So with the first version of Farming Slater in 2008, we didn't really have time to implement a lot of modding specific features.
But we very focused on being as modding friendly as possible.
So we've chosen open formats, XML based and also used kind of industry standard formats like DDS for textures.
So the tools already exist to author them.
And also we released our internal development tools like DCC exporters for our mesh formats and also our level designers that people could create new maps with primarily.
And also we wrote most of the gameplay code in Lua.
So that was fully accessible for the modders to change and adjust and also add new gameplay features.
Well with Farming Simulator 2009 we've had more time to actually improve that system.
So what we introduced was kind of a modular mod system where people or modders would put their mods into a zip file and people would simply put them in a known folder.
So they no longer have to change the game installation and kind of manually merge different mods and whatever.
So that made it very much simpler for the users.
And also, the maps are now automatically detected and shown in the selection.
And the vehicles and equipment would be shown in the in-game farming shop.
So you can just buy them directly with no actual manual adjustments.
But we also restricted the access to the Lua scripts.
The reason for that was
With the previous open concept, it was very, very hard to have multiple mobs installed side by side.
People would have had to kind of manually merge those Lua scripts.
And so what we instead did is kind of provide a couple dedicated APIs to the modders that they can use to extend and change
the script, so to hopefully reduce those conflicts between the mods.
With Farming Simulator 2011, we introduced multiplayer in the game, which I'm coming to in a second as well, but it also meant that we wanted to add mod support in multiplayer as well.
So one key aspect for us was to make sure that the matchmaking is not compromised by the mods so other players couldn't destroy the experience of others.
So what we made sure is that the clients need to have installed the same mods as the ones on the server.
And also, the mods would only be activated when you would join a game.
So only at that point, when the server already said, OK, I'm using those mods.
I'm sure those are fine for me.
That's also when the clients would actually activate them.
And of course it also meant that all the mods had to be multiplayer aware, especially the script code that introduced new states had to be adjusted so the states is properly synced to multiplayer as well.
One big issue we kind of always faced so far at that point was the mod distribution.
So by then we didn't have any solution on our side so we left that up to the modders to distribute those mods.
to the players and that often resulted in kind of very un-user friendly download sites kind of covered with ads and where you can barely see where you actually need to click to download.
There's also been fake download sites that
distributed malware and stuff.
And also one big issue was that people started to download other people's modders mods and re-uploaded them to a different site so they could earn a bit of money and that was always a big issue in the community.
And from the user perspective as well is of course the quality insurance that wasn't guaranteed at all, right?
So you would download the mod and you have no idea if it's even going to work or completely destroy your save game.
So the solution we came up was the official mod hop that we introduced in 2012.
So the idea about that was to really kind of have one source of quality mods.
But modders were still hesitant to actually use that system because
To kind of guarantee the quality, we had to introduce a couple restrictions in terms of quality.
And also, because it's kind of an official thing from our side, we also had to guarantee that there's no licensing issues, there's no age restriction issues, etc.
So, not all mods are actually possible to be submitted to the modhub.
And also one big factor was the potential loss of that ant revenue from others.
So it wasn't really that much used, but we really have seen a big shift in farming simulator 17.
mainly due to kind of three changes that we made.
So the first is that we integrated the mod hub into the game directly.
So before, people had to go to our website and download the mod there and install it manually.
And with Farming Simulator 17, it is now directly possible to download from within the game with basically one button click.
Also we introduced the rewards program.
So we do pay the modders based on the popularity of their mods.
So that's actually going to be a couple thousand bucks a month.
for the most popular mods so there's even some teams that kind of work almost professionally for those mods now also kind of interesting now that with the talk from Wednesday that Unreal Epic also introduced that for their Fortnite Creators Mode kind of a similar concept so
And then the last thing was the mod support that we've been able to finally introduce to our PlayStation and Xbox versions.
We're kind of really proud to
to be one of the very first game to actually support that, but of course there's a couple technical restrictions as well on that, like there's no option to compile shaders on those platforms and also we're not allowed to ship custom scripts there.
Also one big restriction is that all the content on those platforms need to be created.
So the only option to actually get mods on the consoles is to go through the mod hub.
But it's also very important for us to kind of keep the external mod support on the platforms where it is kind of possible.
Because yeah, there's still a ton of mods that will never go through the mod hop restrictions that we have.
So to kind of show the progression on the success of the mod hub, there's a couple numbers.
So with Farming Simulator 15, where we first introduced it, we kind of got around 300 mods with around 1 million downloads.
And with Farming Simulator 17, we reached about 2,000 mods with over 500 million downloads.
And then with Farming Simulator 19,
now have around 6,000 mods with more than 1 billion downloads in total.
And Farming Simulator 22, even though it's just out for about a year, already reached similar numbers to Farming Simulator 19 as well.
Some other kind of considerations for the mod support is that it's very important to kind of keep the modding as simple as possible.
So we spend a lot of time on documenting our systems and writing tutorials.
We've also been able to partner with Wiley to produce a farming simulator for modding book.
Also, it's important to kind of keep the amount of changes from version to version as small as possible so people are not forced to kind of relearn everything every couple years.
And also to kind of keep the amount of mods as large as possible because it's always a bit of a hassle for players to lose all their content when they switch to a new version.
So for the changes that we had to make, we tried to kind of keep a fallback support for old mods still.
Or in the cases where that was not possible, we also wrote converted tools, like when we restructured some XML files or when we changed our binary formats, texture formats, et cetera, so that there's as little work needed by the modders as possible.
And of course having our own engine was also a very huge benefit for that because we're able to really plan the changes we're doing and also kind of time them perfectly with new releases.
So especially when we're doing updates from one version within the game would be a very big issue if suddenly more formats would change as well.
Also it's kind of very important to keep kind of avoid any kind of locked in third party solutions like
you would go with a Steam-only solution or so.
That would really prevent providing mod support on consoles.
And also, it's very important to have a very optimized QA and submission process in a mod hub, because we've now QA'd more than 6,000 mods within a year to ship them to the players.
Another thing we did to kind of
enforce people to create more moths we uh... we had multiple mock audits and tests in the past as well so here is an example in twenty seventeen we we had uh... total price pool of fifty thousand moths uh... fifty thousand uh... euros so uh... with uh... couple nice uh... uh... cheap use and and also like the winner of the contest uh...
would have the option to partner with us to create a paid commercial DLC so where they would get a share from that as well.
These mods are free so there's no direct revenue except for the reward but the DLCs that we sell obviously get an even better reward.
Let's get to another topic, which is the multiplayer mode.
So the first two versions were single player only, but we've seen a very big potential in multiplayer.
So farming in real life is also a very big teamwork effort.
There's even processes that are now possible to do on your own, like chopping
mice which is where you have like the chopper is not able to basically capture all the chaff so you need to have a tractor with a trailer next to you driving all the time where it can immediately unload that.
Also we've seen a lot of requests from the community that really would have liked to see that in a game and
We've also seen a very big competitive advantage as well, because most of the simulation games at that time didn't have multiplayer.
So with Farming Simulator 2011, we implemented a cooperative farming mode with up to eight players.
So you would manage one farm together on one map.
And we chose kind of a server client model where one of the players would host the game and others could join directly.
Also, the mode was played mostly with rents.
I mean, technically, it's also possible to just have random people playing together.
But yeah, with cooperative playing, it's always a bit tricky to have
random people.
So one other thing we introduced in 2013 was a dedicated server support.
So with that self-hosted system, that has always been kind of an issue with network performance.
And back then, like even one megabits of upload was kind of a luxury.
So that was always a bit tricky for the player experience.
So having a server in a data center obviously helped a lot for that.
But it also gave several kind of gameplay benefits as well.
So now with a server running all the time, you could also have kind of a continuously simulated world.
So you're no longer tied to one of the players hosting the game, and then it would only be running at that point.
And also you could now have multiple admins for the game, because before only the host would be kind of the admin of the game and would have all the permissions to give rights to the players and kick and ban them.
And now, with the dedicated servers, you could have multiple of those, which also allowed kind of more public play as well.
So you could kind of create a bigger community of people that would just randomly play on one world and share kind of the same experience.
With Farming Simulator 19 we also introduced a new concept of having multiple farms on one map.
So you could have up to eight farms and each player would be assigned to one of those farms.
And each of those farms would own their own land, their own vehicles and
would be kind of playing against the other farms.
That kind of introduced also a more competitive play as well, because
You kind of compete with those other farms for resources like land.
So you probably want to buy the best land first before the others can.
And also there's a concept of kind of variable sell prices for your crops.
So the more you sell, the less you get for it.
So you probably want to sell the stuff first before the other farm can.
Also, cross-play is something we introduced with Farming Simulator 22 as one of the biggest features in multiplayer.
So now you're no longer restricted to just play with people on the same platform.
But that also had the restriction that we now had to provide the same mods on all platforms.
So before we've been able to just have a set of mods only on the consoles and maybe similar but slightly adjusted mods on PC because of the restrictions on consoles.
But now we're forced to really guarantee that the mods are really the same as much as possible.
Also, it's kind of very important to not have any platform-specific APIs, like for networking or matchmaking.
Also, before we only had voice chat on the console versions.
Now with cross-play, for the console players to be able to really communicate with the PC players, it was also an important thing to actually introduce voice chat as a feature on PC as well.
And also there's a kind of a restriction that we're not allowed to have any direct connections from the consoles to the PC.
So, but we still wanted to kind of keep that self-hosted concept.
So we didn't want to force everyone to
to go through the dedicated server concept.
So what we did is we introduced a relay server concept.
So instead of connecting directly from PC to consoles, we would connect, both would connect to that relay server and all the traffic would be routed through those.
Another part that is kind of tied to the multiplayer mode, but it is not directly part of the game, is our eSports mode.
So 2017 we kind of experimented with some competitive modes.
And we've seen a very huge advantage in that because most of the big eSport titles are not family friendly.
So we've seen kind of a big potential in that.
And also the feedback we got from those early experiments were very positive, that kind of
encouraged us to continue with that and develop a full-featured eSports mode.
So in 2019, we had our first Farming Simulator League season with a prize pool of over $250,000.
And so I've got a short video to show a couple of impressions of how that looks.
So yeah, we also work together with the big manufacturer brands.
So they have their own teams that compete in the league.
And the mode is kind of a three by three mode.
which is covering kind of the three concepts of harvesting, baling, and then selling those bales, kind of as efficiently as possible.
So that brings us to the conclusion of the talk.
The franchise has evolved quite a lot over the years.
Our basic strategy hasn't really changed.
we're still trying to kind of be as casual as possible but kind of give a kind of still give kind of a realistic simulation and also like the modding helps as well to kind of
solve the balancing act as well because there's a lot of very realistic farming mods out there.
So the core simulation fans can also work with those mods and kind of get their very realistic experience if they like to.
And also the listening to the community feedback helped us a lot to improve the game over the years as well.
But it's also very important to know that not all of the feedback is really good feedback as well.
And also a lot of the feedback you hear is coming only kind of a portion of
of the game, of the players, especially like more kind of the core simulation audience is kind of more audible in that feedback than the casual players.
So we also implemented features into the game where we later realized that it's actually not really a feedback that kind of the casual player liked.
So later on in updates of the game, we also added options kind of to disable those features again.
So that it works better with the play style of those more casual players.
For the future, we have a lot of ideas that we want to
want to do, but there's like a couple key points I want to mention here.
Like the immersion that we want to achieve is not where we would like it to see yet, so we would definitely see more interactive worlds and also kind of see more story elements with NPCs and stuff to interact with.
And also the eSports mode right now is still kind of separate from the game and it kind of limits the amount of players that actually use it.
And that's definitely something we would love to see more integrated into the game to get a bigger audience.
And also one thing that is always tricky with War Thinks Simulator is the onboarding and also kind of the
The open world style of the game kind of doesn't give a lot of guidance to the players.
So people are often kind of left in a situation where they don't know what they should do next.
Because yeah, it's an open world game, sandbox style, where you can do whatever you want.
It would definitely be beneficial to those to kind of give some guidance what they could maybe try next.
So that fits better to some of those players.
So yeah, that's Farming Slater.
Thank you for your attendance.
And don't forget to fill out the review forms.
And yeah, we're open for questions.
Hi, I'm Frank Carey from Fable Studio.
We're working on an AI theme park builder game.
And since I saw this title, I've always been curious, like, why farming, right?
Like, what is it about farming?
What other options did you guys consider at the time?
And yeah, what was farming checking the boxes of that maybe those other options didn't?
Well, I mean, before Farming Simulator, we actually worked more on like an RPG title.
But kind of what convinced us about farming was kind of the broad array of activities you can do in farming.
There's so many things that you can do and gives us the option to kind of really create a big game.
Quick follow-up.
Is there a demographic that seems to like the game?
Is it more rural folks that enjoy it or is it you don't see that?
Well, not really.
If you compare it to flight simulators or truck simulators or whatever, kids also like those topics as well.
So that's not very specific to farming.
But I think one big part of the success is also how we kind of tackled the simulation genre and kind of tried to give those casual elements as well.
Thank you.
I enjoyed the talk a great deal.
I was actually surprised in the beginning to hear that one of your main design pillars was entertainment over accuracy, because I usually think of Farming Simulator as a simulator.
It's not a Harvest Moon.
It's very much a simulation game in terms of its branding compared to other titles on the shelf at a GameStop or something like that.
So I'm wondering, given that entertainment over realism is one of your pillars,
How has Farming Simulator maintained its identity over these years and not branched into things like, say, having players fall from a flying school bus or zombies walking through your farm?
How have you maintained that focus while also prioritizing entertainment?
Well, I mean, kind of the realism is kind of still kind of the core concept, right?
So basically, what we do is we look at reality and try to
I'm
to still be fun, right?
It's not the other way around where we say, well, maybe that could be a cool thing that's completely unrealistic and let's build that in, right?
It's still coming from the realistic side.
Hey, OK.
Thank you so much for the talk to start with.
It was super insightful in so many ways.
I had a question about when you actually started right at the beginning, how did you build up the knowledge base?
I mean, coming up with a farming simulator, there must be so much knowledge that you need to gather.
And then, of course, you keep talking about the entertainment.
So there's the vulgarization of all of that and make it digestible.
I'm quite intrigued on how you approached it and if you had any background in farming before.
Well, I mean, it was really tricky, definitely.
I mean, we kind of both kind of grew up on the countryside, so farming was not completely foreign to us.
But, yeah, most of the knowledge in the beginning came from the community.
So we had a forum from the very beginning where we had a lot of feedback as well.
and also a lot of like wikipedia etc so to really figure out how stuff is done but uh but later on we also hired several people that actually have a farming background as well that that could help on that side that makes sense thanks a lot
Thank you for the talk.
In terms of your community feedback and also your future, what's the, can you speak to the work you're doing to understand their buying habits, their retention year to year, because it's a yearly, an annual product you have, is there a demand to go to more of a true perennial and evergreen gas where you just have a core product and you support it on DLC only?
So the question is how kind of the update style of the game is, right?
Yeah, like what's the demand there from your user base in terms of, like, are they happy with the yearly model or is there a growing... Yeah, so with...
We always hear feedback from people that they would like to see a model where we kind of keep the same game and just continuously update it, which kind of would help for the modding to some degree.
But it's also kind of the modding that kind of prevents it as well.
Because if we would just continuously update, eventually we need to introduce new features like, for example, with Farming Simulator 15 or so, we switched from old school textures to BBR textures.
And that switch would have been a big issue if it was within the same version, right?
So suddenly there's not really a clearly new version but every mod would be broken and kind of having that new version cycle also helps to kind of clearly dictate, okay, until that point the mods are mostly compatible but at that point now you need to make sure that the mods are compatible again.
Hi, I'm the release engineer for Sony platforms at Jackbox Games and I'm very curious as to how you approach your modding.
I guess your strategy.
The one thing about TRC, like the TRC is for Sony is that UGC has to be created on the platform, on a Sony platform specifically.
So I'm curious as to how you guys solved that problem where mods that were developed on a Steam or a different console were also being played on a Sony platform.
I run into this issue constantly which is why I'm so curious as to how you guys solved this.
Yeah, so the question is how we would kind of solve the TRC issues on the Sony platform for the UGC, that it would have to be created on a platform, not externally.
So yeah, actually that was a big discussion we've had with Microsoft and Sony for a long time.
We've been able to kind of convince them with Pharmacylometer 17 that we're actually allowed to do the way we're doing it right now.
And I think a lot of that also probably helped that Skyrim was working on a similar concept at the same time.
But yeah, that's why we have those limitations as well.
So all the content that goes on the consoles is going to be created on our side.
and there's no options for players just to freely install content from anywhere.
That doesn't go through the mod hop.
Okay, gotcha.
Thank you.
Yeah, so thank you.