This is Finding Your Voice on TikTok.
Hello, everyone.
My name is Grace Curtis.
I am the PR and Community Manager at Future Friends Games, which is a publishing and promotion hybrid company based in the United Kingdom.
In terms of why the hell I'm even qualified to be talking about this, with my time at Future Friends, I've had the opportunity to work and help grow a great number of really interesting, fantastic TikTok accounts.
So in terms of the publishing side of the company, I helped work on games like X01, Omno,
and through our many wonderful clients.
It was Clone Drone in the Danger Zone, Vampire Survivors, Hype Train, Heavenly Bodies, yada yada yada.
And as you can see, the numbers we were able to achieve were pretty good across the board.
Over 150,000 followers for X01, over 200,000 for Omino.
of
And we were able to achieve this without spending a single penny on ads or promotion within TikTok.
We did all of this organically.
And furthermore, we kind of had to do it in our spare time.
We're a really small company and we have a lot of stuff to do.
And so this was all kind of achieved on a shoestring budget, both in terms of money and time.
For a more recent example of a TikTok that did really, really well.
So this is from our upcoming game Europa, which is hopefully going to be out this year.
See if it wants to play.
Lovely.
And that got 900,000 views last time I checked.
So, still got it.
TikTok, right.
I'm sure you've heard of it.
If you haven't, congratulations on bravely walking into this room not knowing what you're about to see.
It is a video sharing platform and it's a pretty big deal.
Last year, 2022, it was the most downloaded app
in the world.
It's got about a billion monthly users, and the people who are on TikTok are mostly very young and digitally literate.
A recent report by the New York Times found that about 40% of people who are in the Generation Z, so that's me, the Zoomers, are using apps like TikTok and Instagram instead of Google.
So they're hustling in on Google's territory, which is how you know this is a big deal.
Zuma stocks, there you go.
The thing that makes TikTok special is the thing that most people really struggle to understand about it, which is a for you page.
Rather than showing you content by people you follow, when you open up TikTok, what you get is a stream of seemingly random videos.
But the more time you spend on the app, as you interact with those videos, liking, commenting, or swiping on past, the TikTok algorithm will monitor that information and use it to further curate your feed.
So the more time you spend on TikTok, the better the platform becomes.
This is how we were able to achieve those really big organic numbers that I told you about before.
It was by getting on people's For You pages.
And that's kind of what I'm going to talk about today.
How to do that in a way that isn't shady, embarrassing, cringe, or just difficult.
About those numbers, right.
I obviously shouldn't have to explain to you the benefit of having 9 million people see your game, but it's still worth drilling in a little bit.
So this is a graph showing wishlist activity on the X.O.1 Steam page, beginning in May 2021, first time when we first started the TikTok account, and running all the way up to launch.
I should probably explain before we go any further what a wishlist is for those of you who don't know.
You can essentially think of it as sort of a tier below a pre-order.
It's a button that you can click on a Steam page which will basically say to Steam, hey, I'm not willing to put money on the line just yet, but I might potentially want to buy this game somewhere down the line.
So when the game launches, they get an email, they get another one when it goes on sale.
As indie developers in this PC space, this is kind of the best tool that we have to figure out how well something is going to do prior to actually putting it on sale.
And it's also something that Steam uses to decide what kind of positioning to give your game within the Steam storefront.
So you get a lot of wishlists, your game gets good featuring on Steam, which then gets it more wishlists, yada, yada, yada, wishlists are very, very good.
I was able to map the witch list activity on the X01 Steam page pretty consistently to the viral videos that we had over that time period.
You can see, got a nice big spike with our first ever video there, had another viral video a little while later which didn't convert quite as well, whole bunch of little bumps, and then we had a nice spike when we put the game's demo on the Next Fest, and then an even bigger one when we advertised that demo on TikTok.
And when we launched X01, we had 100,000 wish lists, which for a little game like that from a solo developer with a publisher that was like five people at the time was really amazing.
And I really think the numbers show that TikTok contributed to us having that.
If you want an even starker example of this, this is a graph that was kindly donated to me by Kila.
She's a developer of a game called Mail Time.
Kila has a fantastic TikTok account that you should all check out.
But you can see here the wishlist spikes Akila gets from a big TikTok.
So these all have got about 1 million views each, but the wishlist conversion is about the same as she got from the Future Games show at Gamescom.
So yes, in summary, provided that you make good use of the single link that TikTok allows you to have in your bio, you can see real tangible growth from this platform.
So I think one of the things, aside from just fear of embarrassment, what keeps a lot of developers off TikTok is just not knowing where to begin.
So before we dive into the nitty gritty, I just really wanted to quickly share with you my workflow.
Sounds are the backbone of TikTok.
It's one of the few social media platforms where people actually engage with the sounds.
And so in my opinion, that's where you should begin.
If you don't know where to start, you can get a sound either from the TikTok app itself, or you can download it from YouTube.
Take that sound, take whatever footage you want to use and go over to your preferred video editing software.
Do all the fiddly stuff on your computer, because if you try to edit the entire thing in the TikTok in-app editor, you will go insane.
Once that's done and you have a bit of video that you're happy with, take it back to TikTok.
And this is the tricky bit, and this is the part that I always have to explain to clients.
You then want to find whatever sound you're using in the TikTok sound library, put it back in the video.
This is a way of, for example, if you're using a Doja Cat sound, you want to find that Doja Cat sound in the library, put it in the video, and have it as a soundtrack.
Therefore, other people who are enjoying that same wonderful little bit of music will be recommended your content.
Then now that's tricky bits done, start having fun.
Do cap cut edits, which is a new feature where you can have a kind of
editing format put in the video for you.
Or you can do green screen.
Or you can do silly voices.
Like, whatever fun, ridiculous thing you want to have, do that in the TikTok editor.
And the last thing you do before you upload, add a caption.
Like I said before, a lot of young people are using TikTok to kind of search for things, similar to Google.
And they also have kind of an SEO system.
So drop a couple keywords into the caption, choose a couple cool hashtags, and then upload the video, sit back, and wait to go viral.
and wait and wait and wait because it's not going to happen right away.
TikTok is really hard and there's like thousands and thousands of people uploading videos every single day.
So how do you stand out?
You stand out by blending in.
Counterintuitive, I know.
But this is something that we've learned over time.
So for example, one of the first things we do when we have like a brand new TikTok account for a game that no one's ever seen before is upload a trailer because a trailer is a really nice asset
it's, you know, why wouldn't you put it on another platform, right?
And that's exactly what we did with X01.
We uploaded two extremely beautiful trailers to the account, and they wound up getting, I think, about 29,000 views each, which is great, but compared to an account where most of the videos got hundreds of thousands, it's a significant overperformance.
Over?
Underperformance.
And the reason, I believe, for this is
TikTok has a young audience, right?
And the thing about young people, people of, you know, that kind of late 90s, early 2000s milieu, is that we have been bombarded with advertising from pretty much the second we opened our little eyes and saw the world.
And we are really, really good at detecting it.
Anything that looks too polished, sounds too nice, has too much, you know, effort and money put into it, our brain goes, uh-uh, that's advertising.
And we will flickerate, right?
And the whole point of TikTok is you don't want people to do that.
So how do you keep people from switching off your video right away?
This is a point so important that I've given it its own slide.
Make a TikTok that looks like a TikTok.
Obviously, seems stupid, right?
How do you do that?
How do you make a TikTok that looks like a TikTok?
I'll tell you, there's three words in it.
Low production value.
Why go to the studio and film yourself in like a bunch of nice cameras when you could just put your phone on your dresser and talk straight to the camera?
Why use OBS when you could just film your screen?
As long as you are using the tools that a teenager with zero resources would use, you will look like you blend in.
At its most simple, blending in can literally just be the thing that I showed you before with that Europa video, which is a short, unbroken clip of gameplay.
And the reason this works, where tightly edited trailers do not, is that instead of speaking in the language of advertisements, you're speaking in the language of Let's Plays and Twitch streams.
In short, you look like you belong.
The next thing I want to dive into is trends.
So TikTok was originally a karaoke app, and music is still very much woven into the DNA of how TikTok functions.
So on TikTok, you will have these things called viral sounds, which is basically a single sound clip that is being reused over multiple videos.
And this could be anything.
It could be a little bit of a song.
It could be a bit of a comedy skit.
It could be Louis Theroux rapping auto-tuned to Pash Bell's Canon.
I don't know why that one did so well, but God, we had a whole month of Louis Theroux.
And the point is, these can imply either a certain format to the video or just a certain vibe.
but they give you a format to map your video onto.
This not only will give you a lot of ideas, if you're running out of ideas, and it will not only make you look like you belong on TikTok, it will also help you find an audience, again, through the aforementioned algorithms.
It's all about giving TikTok little signals as to who they want to show the video to.
at all.
So that's how he does it.
I have a different strategy, which is that I have no life.
And I'm just on TikTok all the time.
And really, there is no replacement for just being immersed in the app.
Every social media app has its own cadence.
You know, like on Twitter, you have to sound like sanctimonious and annoying, etc.
The more you immerse yourself in TikTok, the easier it will be able to come to match the cadence of the platform.
So yeah, get on there, start watching, and soon you too will become completely insufferable like me.
To make the next point, I want to show you another TikTok video.
This is from the ExoOne account.
It's a video that got 1.7 million views.
So the thing that I want to highlight about that video is the visuals.
TikTok is first and foremost a dopamine treadmill and it encourages you to make snap decisions about whether or not what you're looking at is for you.
You are literally competing with n plus one people all the time, so showing something good in the first second is paramount.
Visually compelling games like X01, like Omno, have an obviously massive advantage in this field, but remember kids, ugly games go viral too.
What you have to do is just show them something visually compelling, be it beautiful, funny, weird, whatever it is, just have it on screen right away.
If you're not showing them your lovely face, you have to give them something cool to look at.
The other thing that we do in that video is we establish context.
Because of the way TikTok works, the vast majority of people who view your video will be viewing that thing for the first time.
They have no idea who you are.
So you need to communicate two things right away.
One, that what they're seeing is a game.
And two, that it is a game that you have made.
It's easy to forget this because we are surrounded by game people all the time.
but this is a really cool thing to do for a living and if you express it this is a game that you have helped create not only will you put yourself in a position of authority you'll also like pique people's curiosity right away they will make a connection with you and be compelled to hopefully find out more
Up next, the power of personality.
So Victoria Tran, who is like an incredible powerhouse community manager from InnerSloth, last year released a fantastic post-mortem of the Among Us TikTok account.
And one of the things she found in that post-mortem is that while updates for Among Us got the best view numbers, personality-driven content, so that's just Victoria clowning around on the phone, those got the best engagement.
And having been working on TikTok for over two years now, the power of personality is something that I think really, really holds up.
Most of the really big powerhouse video game accounts are ones that make use of a human voice and a friendly face.
You know, so example, Landfall, 1.5 million followers.
Tiny Glade, that's another recent hit.
They both have kind of a human presence on all or most of their videos.
However, you don't have to be hugely charismatic in order for this to work.
So most of the X01 account videos were similar to the thing you just saw, just footage in text.
But we were able to persuade developer Jay to lend his voice to two videos.
And he read those words out in his best, dull, I don't want to be here, Australian monotone.
And they got 2.7 and 9 million views respectively, making them the highest performing videos on the entire account.
The appeal of TikTok, I think, is fundamentally the same as the appeal of YouTube and Twitch and Twitter and everything else, which is that it is a friend in your pocket.
If you want to watch a trailer and read a press release, there are an infinite number of places where you can go and do that.
But the opportunity you have, the thing you can offer people here, is a chance to make a really small but meaningful connection with the real human beings who make the stuff they love.
And if you can offer that to people, you will get yourself not just a viewer, but an audience member, hopefully.
Next up, watch times.
This is some data that was very kindly donated to me by Jared of Devolver.
He did a really fantastic deep dive into one and a half thousand different TikTok accounts from indie games.
And one of his many findings was that watch time and total watch percentage have a strong correlation with how many views a video gets overall.
And this has been backed up by an investigation from the Wall Street Journal a couple of years ago.
which again found that full watch percentage is at the heart of how TikTok decides whether or not your video is worth putting on people's pages.
So in short, whether or not people get to the end of your video and whether or not they then go back and watch it again is a really significant factor in how well you're going to do.
Now obviously, figuring out how to make people watch your stuff to the end is like the question and you could ask 100 community managers and get 101 different responses.
But I have a theory, which is I believe that it boils down to structure.
Structure as in setup and payoff, a two-part structure.
So how it started versus how it's going is a phrase that you see all over the place on TikTok, not just in the indie game sphere.
And the reason I think that people keep using this over and over again is because it works really well.
You give people the promise of something cool while showing them something intriguing.
And if you can pay off that promise with something cool, you're golden.
You've fulfilled your contract as a, you know, three second bit of entertainment for them.
But of course, that is only one way that you can use the setup and payoff method.
There's infinite ways to apply this if you really think about it.
Lists is an absolute classic one.
Three fantastic environments in my game, and then you show three fantastic environments, or three funny glitches, yada yada.
Most jokes have a one-two setup.
you know, show something serious and then contrast it with something silly.
We love to do this for vampire survivors, works like a charm.
And of course, you have the Q&A format.
TikTok has a native feature where people can leave questions and you can answer that question with a video, which means you're basically giving them the setup and payoff almost at the same time.
And if you're feeling really bold, you can combine multiple formats.
So this video we have here is the TikTok video we made announcing that Vampire Survivors was coming to Xbox, where I combined a Q&A format feature with a funny trending sound at the time.
Let's watch it together now.
Coming to Xbox November 10.
That video got almost as many views as the official Xbox trailer on the official Xbox YouTube account.
And it took me 25 minutes to make.
And most of that time was spent making the bats.
So, yeah.
Setup and payoff.
It works.
My final clothing thought, the sort of thing that I want to leave you with to chew over as you go have your coffees and hang out, is stick with it.
Finding your voice, finding your tone, finding your workflow, all of this stuff takes time.
So be kind to yourself.
As far as we can tell, TikTok does not penalize you for failing.
if you make a bunch of videos that no one sees, that doesn't affect the likelihood of your next video doing well.
And I know this because that's exactly what happened with X01, right?
Me and Thomas were having a competition to see who could go viral first, but everything we posted just got like a couple thousand views.
Very depressing.
And then after I think about a half dozen tries, suddenly overnight, half a million.
So yeah, keep trying, fall on your face, fail, pick yourself up, try again.
It's a dancing app for children.
Don't get too stressed about it.
It's more about, it's less about creating a single perfect thing than it is about spinning the roulette wheel enough times until you get, you hit on something that works.
Now because of that algorithm-driven format,
Everything that you start, you have a blank slate, not just with every account, but with every video that you post, which is obviously really exhausting and frustrating at times, yes, but it means that you also have an infinite amount of fresh starts and that you never know what's going to happen next.
And yep, this is just some of the sources I used.
So Jared, Victoria, Thomas, Wall Street Journal.
Yes, that's my talk.
Thanks so much, everyone.
Wow, I zoomed through that super fast.
I was talking super speedy.
But yes, if anyone has any questions, I think we have time now.
I have a question about length of videos, because you mentioned watch percentage heavily correlates with performance.
the immediate logic is make a really short video.
Does that work or not?
I think that was another thing.
You should go back and read Jared's talk because this is something he went into as well.
There is kind of a sweet spot, which I believe is at around the 15 to 30 second mark, but it's not a huge factor.
If you have a really fantastic 30 second video, I think you still have a good choice of that.
Don't just upload a bunch of two second clips and hope that people don't get the time to get past because I'm pretty sure TikTok has allowed for that to not happen.
we tend to hit around the 15 to 30 second mark and we find that works pretty well consistently.
Thank you.
No worries.
Over there.
Hey, thanks so much for the talk.
No worries.
I was wondering, our future friends, how much do you guys focus on post timing?
Like what day or what hour of that day posting certain videos or do you guys just post whenever and let it go viral?
I think we tend to aim for late afternoon, early evening.
Just anecdotally, that's when we found videos tend to do their best, because that's when people are kind of online.
We also think really hard about regions.
So TikToks that are posted from North America and the UK have a tendency to reach more people than those that are uploaded from Europe, because it's set to your IP address.
But it's all kind of a black magic, like we don't have hard data on when's best or not.
But yeah, posting the video when roughly you think that people are going to be online and posting it from a country where a lot of people live generally works for us.
Thank you.
No worries.
Thanks very much for the talk.
Do you find in practical terms it's better to have a publisher account or a developer account or a personal account or account per game?
That's a big question.
I mean, we've had success with both formats.
The one thing I'll say, having a business account, I think it's helpful for ads, but it imposes a lot of limitations in terms of what sounds you use.
So we find it's easier to go viral with like a personal non-business account.
But again, because of that format where everything is being kind of seen for the first time.
So when we worked on Hype Train, they obviously have a whole bunch of different games, and we were able to kind of
go viral with a bunch of different individual videos, right?
So we had one introducing Euro Truck World, another one introducing Void Train, and they kind of did well individually.
However, if you want to, if basically, if you want to do a landfall or do an inner sloth, where you have kind of an audience that you're gathering over time and kind of earning their trust, it's probably better to focus on one game at a time per account.
Cool, thank you very much.
No worries.
Hi, before you recommended to edit outside the TikTok platform because you would go crazy otherwise, but you also recommended to blend in and have a low production value by not editing too much, so where do you draw the line?
I mean, again, that's like a really open question.
I think if you look at something like Cult of the Lamb, they have really fantastic videos which actually have quite a high production value.
And they get away with that because their game is extremely beautiful and entertaining and they make excellent content.
For me, what I tend to do is I like the work to be kind of invisible.
So I want the cups to be really smooth.
I want the gameplay to be really clear.
That's the kind of thing that people take for granted, essentially.
But once I have something that sort of matches very well to the beat of the song,
then I take that to TikTok and I do the kind of scrappy stuff on there.
But I think that's really more about what kind of ceiling, how much time you have.
Like I'm not a professional video editor and I tend to not have a huge amount of time to do these things.
So that's where I'd personally draw the line.
But I think it's a case of figuring out what works for you over time.
Thank you.
Always.
Hi, how do you feel about content re-sharing?
So you have previously shared a video and it was a success or a failure and you re-share it.
Can it rework a second time and can it beat the first failure?
Ooh, that's a good question.
Do you mean like resharing on TikTok?
It's not something we've done a lot, to be honest.
It's something that kind of leaves a bad taste in my mouth.
I would rather try again with something new than to kind of keep uploading the same thing over and over again.
However, resharing on YouTube Shorts and Instagram Reels and TikTok and Reddit and other places, I really strongly recommend you do.
we've actually had quite a modest good amount of success with vampire survivors if you're sharing on YouTube shorts so yeah I would I would recommend doing that but for the most part I would rather pour that energy into just like making and having another attempt with something quick thanks no worries
Hi, great talk.
I'd like to ask for a solution for a very specific problem.
We live in a non-English speaking country and when we post a TikTok it gets shown to people from our own country.
so if we make it in our local language it will never go to global audience obviously and if we post in English we have pretty bad engagement so do you have a solution for this problem maybe?
This is the eternal question.
I think generally what we would recommend you do is just hire a community manager in the UK and have them post from there.
That's why I think the reason that you're probably getting bad engagement on those videos is that even though they're in the English language, they're still getting shown to local audiences.
So you're kind of damned if you do, damned if you don't, right?
Because if you make a video in the native language, you're reaching less people.
But if you make a video in English, you're sort of not speaking in the language of your local community.
So annoyingly, it does help to just kind of either do a bit of subterfuge with a VPN or post from a different region.
OK, thanks.
No worries.
I was a couple minutes late so I apologize if I covered this already.
You mentioned YouTube Shorts and we know that TikTok is very open to letting people download and share on other platforms.
What have you seen in terms of being able to track analytics or how that goes on to other non-TikTok platforms and how that
I mean, we haven't done like a real, for us, this has just basically been, it doesn't take a lot of time and there's no drawbacks, so just throw it out there.
We haven't looked super hard, frankly, because the performance has not been impressive enough for us to really want to deep dive into reels or shorts just yet.
I think if we started seeing numbers that were comparable to what we were seeing on TikTok, we might pay more attention.
But for now, it's more just a matter of giving ourselves sort of a wider, just a bigger shot, right?
But yeah, TikTok is still very much the number one platform for us, and that has the massive organic reach that we just don't have anywhere else.
Thank you.
No worries.
Hi, thank you so much for your talk.
You showed at the very beginning a pretty beautiful correlation between the videos and the Weasley.
And my question is, do you have more information about this Weasley?
I mean, profile a day?
of
Yes, the conversion is worse.
Yes, 100%, I think.
Wishlist conversions from TikTok are generally not as strong as when you build up a personal brand elsewhere.
And this is something that comes up a lot with people like, oh, yes, you got 5,000 wishlists that you wouldn't have had elsewhere, but they're not as good.
And it's like, yes, they are not as good.
However, between the choice of not having those wishlists and having another 5,000 that are not as good, I'll take the latter, right?
So yeah, it is weaker conversion, sadly, but I think it's kind of worth making that bargain just to have that extra profile, especially considering how it will contribute to your game being promoted within Steam.
We still think it's worth it, basically.
Yeah, absolutely.
Yes.
To set expectations.
Yeah, yeah.
I have thousands and thousands of users, but then they only convert 1%.
Yes, exactly.
Thank you.
No worries.
Where are you actually making the ask for someone to wish list?
In the video, in your bio, in the description?
We tend to have it in the bio.
Again, I think Thomas made a great point in the talk he did before mine, which is that you shouldn't hammer home too much with the calls to action, because people on TikTok are so apathetic and disengaged that if you ask them
to actually click on something else, I'll just be like, oh, no.
So it's better to do engagement farming, asking, would you play this, or what do you want to see next kind of things, and get more engagement.
And then the few number of people who are actually curious enough to click through the profile, that's when you hit them with the wish list and give them the link.
And you want to have as little friction as possible between that action of going to the bio and getting to the Steam page to hit the link.
So that's what you should focus on.
Thank you.
No worries.
Hello.
Do you think about people playing your game being able to make tiktokable content from the game or are you mostly focused on you posting the videos?
Yeah, it's not something we consider, to be honest.
I mean, the TikTok, like, influencer world is something that's still growing, and we're still kind of figuring out what that looks like, right?
So we generally try and focus on just making something that's really beautiful and compelling and easy from our perspective.
And we still see the best, again, like I said, in terms of conversion, making a game that performs really well on Twitch and YouTube for an influencer standpoint is still kind of more beneficial to us.
but it's not something that you optimize for.
Oh God.
No, no, no, no.
We don't, we don't like go to our indie devs and say, you should do this cause it's better for TikTok.
Right.
We don't want to, um,
how to
You talked about followers, watch time, views.
What is the main KPI you follow to check what you're doing?
Sorry, can you repeat that?
What is the main key indicator factor, key performance indicator that you're following?
For instance, you talked about followers.
Is that super important?
up
on a bigger scale.
But yeah, you can have a lot of followers and have a lot of duds, you can have no followers and do really well.
So while that kind of indicates our growth over time, we don't use that too much as a metric of how well we're doing.
We just try to think about what we're going to do next, ultimately.
Thank you so much.
where it's in lands and we're taking that sort of TikTok ability into account.
But one question is our stuff is landscape and TikTok is obviously portrait.
So just curious if you have any thoughts on that.
Would you just use sort of like closer in shot so that you always get something in portrait or does it work to put landscape video
you have
So if you're going to have black bars either side of the video, I think sometimes it can be fine.
Use that information well, right?
So put some good text there, maybe put a call to action.
Use it as best you can.
Yeah, and think about your game from the perspective of someone who has no attention span whatsoever.
What was the game that you suggested?
Clone Drone in the Danger Zone.
So they do a lot of clever visual tricks to kind of fill up the screen, even though it's a landscape game.
Got it.
Thank you.
Yes, I think that's all done.
Thank you so much, everyone.
I will be hanging around for chats afterwards, but cheers, guys.