How we doing? I think we're good. Please make sure to turn off all your
phones, electronic devices, anything else that might be making sound. And
you'll get a, uh, we speaker form coming to your, um, inbox after this.
Might go to your spam box. So if you could fill it in, that'd be great.
Uh, the GDC folks really like it when you do that.
So, my name is Alex Moll. I'm the chief technical director at
Criterion Games. We're a small EA studio just outside of London,
England, where we're currently having the best time we've ever
had and we're making the best games we ever have. And so I'm
here to tell you how. So I'll start off by talking a little
bit about our back story and then I'll move on to how that
led us to come up with a new philosophy for how to make games
better.
I'll then talk a bit about how we've proven that this actually
scales to triple A production and why we're confident this is
great. And then I'll move on to some specific practices that we
use day to day to implement this new philosophy. And finally I'll
sum up. So first of all, where did this come from?
So hopefully some of you have at least heard of some of our games.
We're really proud of these. We've got a rabid fan base who we're very happy with
who are always talking to us about them.
All of these games are characterized by at least my
memories of them are characterized by two things. So
one is a very high Metacritic. So I think the lowest Metacritic
on that slide there was about 86 and I think it goes up to 94 for
Metacritic at launch. Huge critical success, very popular
games and certainly I didn't work on Burnout 3 but I joined
the studio because I loved it so much.
But the other thing that those games were all categorized by
is really low team morale.
So there's, I know there's a whole bunch
of ex-Criterion folks in the audience here
and they're all smiling and so I think this is true,
and not just for me.
So there was a bunch of staff turnover.
There was an awful lot of unhappiness and frustration,
an awful lot of crunch, a crazy amount of crunch.
And when we looked at the reasons for that low morale,
really a lot of it came down to this reason.
So on a medium-sized team of maybe 70 to 150 people,
there wasn't really anyone who had a chance
of making a good decision that would stick.
that led to much of the team pouring their hearts into
features that were just always destined to be cut. And that
was actually compounded by a constant feeling of being behind
relative to some ideal game studio who was much better at it
than us. And that feeling of behind meant that we were always
scrabbling to build things as fast as we could rather than
taking the time to figure out how to work efficiently and
effectively. And so we wasted a huge amount of time and effort.
And the upshot of that was that much of the team was under-motivated despite being incredibly
passionate.
And we had people working really crazy hours and making themselves properly ill, long-term
relationships breaking up, all sorts of really horrible stuff that people were willingly
putting themselves through and despite all of that passion, they were still really under-motivated.
No one really wanted to do this stuff.
And the other part of it was most of the team just weren't
empowered to make decisions despite knowing everyone else on
the team. And that doesn't make any sense because on a small
team where you know everybody, you should just be able to walk
over to the right person and ask for whatever information you
need to support making the decision you're trying to make.
But that didn't happen. What happened instead was we would
brute force our way to great games but at very high personal
cost.
So in early 2014, there was a big change in studio
leadership. You may have seen it reported in the press as the
death of criterion. If anything, it was quite the opposite. The
new leadership, myself included, seized the opportunity to do
things better on a new game. We believed that it would be
possible to make AAA in a sustainable way. And so we took
our inspiration from the best of other AAA studios and indie
developers and then found places where science backed up and
codified our approach.
And I've got to be honest, I'm really grateful to the EA
Studios leadership who gave us an enormous amount of
encouragement and time and space to try these crazy new
ideas and ultimately prove that they really worked.
So personally I was very inspired and still am very
inspired by indies. I love coming to GDC and hanging out
in the indie game summit. And one thing that was very clear to
me was that small teams where everyone really knows the whole
game that they're working on and they're able to turn on a dime
just don't suffer from these really horrible issues that we
were struggling with. So we figured, well, it's definitely
possible for small teams, so surely we can get this to scale
to big teams, too.
So we came up with a new philosophy. Given what we'd
learned, we set about turning all of that experience into a
coherent set of practices that would allow us to make games
better. And over time we've managed to distill it down into
something coherent. But we started off with this question.
If we just assumed that everybody's here to make the
best games they can, what would we do differently? And we
figured we'd do two things differently. So the first thing
is treating people as talent.
That means letting people make the right decisions for the
game using their own skill and judgment and expertise, because
we hire great people, so obviously they should make great
decisions. And the other thing we do is actively eradicate
harmful dogma. There's lots of examples of harmful dogma. One
includes the expectation of crunch. So research has proven
that crunch is only beneficial for 48 hours and is detrimental
after as little as a week or two.
So it's really, in my opinion, nothing more than legacy and fear and some macho posturing
that means that we still expect crunch.
It's, you know, science tells us it's a waste of time.
But it's also things like expecting to use a centrally
distributed list of tasks, maybe like a Hansoft or a Jira type
thing, to determine how the game gets made.
Because the person with the best understanding of how to fix
a problem is just going to be the person who will be fixing
that problem.
It's not going to be someone off in another room typing tasks
into some big spreadsheet.
So it's really the studio's job to facilitate the team to pick
the best problems to fix and then really help them and guide
them on how to fix them.
So we have this, as a little aside,
we have this poster up in our office,
and I really hope that this just seems
totally weird and obvious to you.
Unfortunately, big games companies,
and I'm pretty sure all big tech companies,
often use the word resource to mean person.
Now I'd argue that's always inappropriate,
but certainly for any creative endeavor,
it's provably inappropriate.
Because a creative collaboration between the right people
won't just get you the right results sooner,
it'll generally deliver you a result
that wouldn't otherwise have been possible.
So the trick is really to gather the right people
and then help them to creatively collaborate.
So at Criterion, as leaders, we've stopped telling people
what to do, because that presumes we're more experts in
their field than they are. And instead, what we do is we take
time to sell ideas to teams of creative collaborators. And then
when those little teams and those creative collaborations
engage with those problems, they're able to take them into
delightful new directions that we would never have expected.
And I wish that I could tell you some more about the game we're
making at the moment, because I have some videos that illustrate
this just perfectly, but sadly we're not there yet.
If nobody on the team wants to work on a feature, wants to
engage with a feature, then one of two things has happened.
Either we've not done a good enough job of selling it, and
maybe that means we don't understand why it's truly
valuable, or maybe it's just not a very good feature and the
team is tacitly telling us, bin that one, move on, there's
better stuff. Which is really great feedback for us to have.
And when, when as a leadership, when as a production group, we notice that someone's
made a decision that surprises us, rather than telling them that they're wrong, we'll
speak to them, we'll take the time to educate and be educated, we'll share the bigger picture
context that maybe they don't have that led us to believe they'd make a decision differently,
but we'll also listen to the detailed context that they've got on the ground.
and understand why they made their decision in the first place.
And either a better decision will get made,
or we understand why that was actually the better decision in the first place.
And either way, both of us have come away from that with a greater sense of trust
and general happiness.
So what we've done isn't just hand wavy nonsense as much as I
love that. There is actually some science backing this up.
We've looked at a bunch of research and our main
inspiration for a lot of what we do is this book, which is
actually summarized in a TED talk which Dan Pink gave in 2009
titled the puzzle of motivation. I highly recommend it. It's a
great TED talk. So
really his thesis is when it comes to motivation there's a mismatch between what science knows
and what business does. And he lays out a compelling case why existing ideas of motivation
so things like financial incentives and status rewards like job titles and corner offices
really don't have a big positive benefit on creative pursuits.
but the great news is that science actually knows what
things do have a big positive benefit on creative pursuits.
And so really what we've done at Criterion is just the
project management equivalent of taking a seven year old
SIGGRAPH paper and getting it working in video game.
So as Dan Pink says, as soon as people feel that they're
being fairly compensated for their work,
money stops being a major motivator.
That said, it is crucial that people feel that they are being
fairly compensated. That means that they're being paid what
looks fair relative to the larger industry, but also what
looks fair relative to people doing similar roles within their
studio. But as soon as that's out of the way, and I really
urge everyone to get that out of the way as soon as possible,
there are some big drives that continue to motivate. The first
one is autonomy over team, task and technique. The second one is
mastery of a skill that an individual values.
and the third one is working in service to a purpose greater
than ourselves. So I'm going to talk about all three of these
in a bit more detail. I'm going to spend a chunk of time on
autonomy because it's the most different from traditional
project management and it's where we've seen the best
results. So a rough little definition, autonomy is having
control within project parameters. So I'm going to
over what you work on, who you work with and how you approach
that. And that's been shown to be hugely motivational. So we
strived to come up with a way of working that supports all three
of those big pillars. So this is the guidance we give out
everyone on the team. So everyone on our team decides
where they can have the biggest positive effect at any point in
time. Originally we actually tried using this as the only
rule. Um,
And that worked actually pretty well until we got to about a
dozen people and after that it got too hard to share enough
context and communicate enough to make sure everyone's actually
working on the same game. So now what happens is a production
group will provide a handful of big themes, perhaps five to
seven big themes, with suggestions of some priorities
within those themes and then the team just takes it from there.
We've never ever had a situation where nobody wants to work on
something that's really important. So I'll say that
again because we've given this talk a few similar talks to this
a few times within EA and this is always a question and it's a
fair question but we have never had a situation where no one
steps up to a plate to do some even dirty boring ass work.
That's just never happened. A couple of times we've had a
scenario where no one's turned up to work on an entire theme.
and that was surprising to us, but when we dug into it, it
turned out that the team had actually noticed that there was
some big dependency that meant that that theme couldn't really
usefully be worked on anyway, so they'd gone over to work on
delivering that dependency before working on the thing that
we'd naively assumed could be done right now. So the team is
really wise, right? There's all this wisdom out in the team and
now we get to use it, which is great.
The most surprising problem we've actually had with this
approach is that we've had people choose to work on things
that they don't actually value but they feel like they kind of
ought to. And that's a subtle distinction but quite an
important one. And it can lead to people being quite ineffective
and miserable where their skills don't really match the work
they're doing. And it's actually something that we're constantly
vigilant of now, like double checking. Are you working on
this for the right reason? Like you actually are interested in
this, right?
So context becomes very important for us.
In a more traditional project management structure,
the big picture of the game is held
by a relatively small number of people on the team.
And those people turn it into chunks
of work that get passed out and distributed out
to the main team.
And generally, that keeps everyone
working on roughly the right thing.
But it can lead to this feeling, where.
some folks on the team just don't really understand why
they're doing the work that they're doing and it can end up
to a lot of that, um, lack of decision making and really that
feeling of helplessness and that huge amount of waste that, um, I
described earlier. So by embracing autonomy and pushing
decision making out across the whole team, we now have a
situation where really everyone on the team needs to have as
much of that big picture as possible or they just won't be
able to make good decisions.
And I have to say, as a leader, it's much, much more effort to push that big context
out and keep refreshing that than it is to just dole out tasks.
It just is.
But the payoff is huge.
As I say, it allows the experts on your team to make all of the easy wins.
that service your game in the best way possible and also warn you and guide you away from the
big expensive moon on a stick rabbit holes that producers and designers tend to occasionally
for the best will in the world lead us down and those just don't really happen anymore.
The context does change and fade over time so it is a full-time
job for several people in the studio to keep making sure and
double checking that everyone knows what game we're making and
that that's kept up to date but it is, as I say, just
astonishingly valuable. So that was the first kind of autonomy.
That was autonomy over task. The second is autonomy over team.
So as I mentioned, the feature teams in our studio form
themselves around high-level themes that the production group
has identified. And those feature teams will stay together
for as long as it makes sense, and then they'll disband and go
work on other stuff. But it is vital, and this is true for
actually any studio, but it's vital that any team or sub-team
is viable, which means it has the capability to deliver what
it's trying to in the time that it has available.
and that's simply because a viable team is greater than the sum of its parts
whereas a non-viable team just isn't.
One of the most common mistakes we've made on this journey
is starting work towards a goal without a viable team in place
and it can be surprisingly hard to spot when that's wrong.
The most common cause of non-viability is missing skill
sets, but there can be all sorts of other subtle things, like it
can be not having access to time from an important reviewer, and
we've seen cases where a team will kind of spin its wheels for
several days, like gilding the lily, honing something that
they've already kind of proven all the important stuff on, just
waiting for a review to tell them how they can move on with
it.
So invariably there's two ways of fixing a non-viable team.
There's the obvious one of add more skills to it.
And there's the other really importantly valuable one,
which is change the goal posts.
Change the goals that they're trying to sign up to.
If you don't have a 2D artist,
well you obviously can't deliver anything that needs 2D art,
but there's still probably tons of useful stuff
you could deliver in the same kind of direction.
So that's very important. And so what happens in the studio after the teams have initially
formed, they then figure out what goals they'll be working on and we then kind of rationalize
and make sure that the teams are all viable by adjusting goal posts as necessary. And
the third part of autonomy is autonomy of a technique. So as I've said, each team is
responsible for creating the goals they'll sign up to, but they're also responsible for
deciding exactly how they'll meet those goals.
That includes the exact deliverables that they plan to
create but also includes their daily process. Are they going to
work in like an agile scrummy way? Are they going to work in a
Kanban iteration style?
they decide that. And actually we give each group a process expert, a DD in EA terms,
I don't know what other studios call them, each group gets a DD to really help them,
coach them on which process might work for them and then coach them on how to use that
process throughout the milestone.
So all of this autonomy has the effect that everyone on the team kind of needs to get a bit
better at selling. And this is a surprise to us. We didn't realize this would kind of be a
sticking point for some people. But designers and producers need to get better at selling
things to the team in order to inspire them to come and make them. Because just saying,
well, because I said so doesn't work anymore, right? We can't do that.
There's a producer from Criterion laughing ruefully here because he used to maybe enjoy doing that.
There's also experts on the team need to be able to sell the value of long lead technical work.
in time for it to be started so that it can deliver value at the
end. And they need to be able to sell it to people who can
prioritize it within the themes for a milestone. And so as a
leadership group we need to be conscious of this and we are.
And so we try and solve it in two ways. Both we coach people
on how to sell better when we notice that there's an
opportunity to coach that. But we also actively try and signal
boost quiet wise voices so that we get the benefit of their
wisdom across the team.
So that was the end of Dan Pink's first big drive.
That was autonomy.
So moving on now to mastery.
So mastery is everyone mastering skills
that they value themselves.
And for everyone to do that, they
need to feel that they're supported in their favored ways
of working, that we can have a team structure where
an engine coder and a gameplay designer
both feel supported and able to grow.
and we spent a bit of time trying to figure out how do we
balance this out, how do we even understand why those people have
different needs and then how can we satisfy them. And we came up
with this division of types of work. So across the horizontal
axis you've got how well defined the problem is from very well
defined, clearly briefed all the way to who knows. And then on
the vertical axis you've got how well defined the solution is. So
is this an R&D project or is this something that
you've done a thousand times before and it's about applying
known solutions to it. And so we've come up with some names
for those types of work. So crafting is the process of
taking a well-defined problem and applying a well-defined
solution to it. So craft, craftspeople are really
motivated by excellence of execution. These people will
take a brief for a bit of work and then give you the, they'll
use their, their skills and their judgment to give you the
best whatever it is that meets that brief.
The next group is experts. Experts really like a well-defined problem that nobody has ever successfully solved before.
And they'll go away and do R&D and loads of hard sums and then come back to you with something amazing.
Then we have explorers. Explorers who really love uncertainty.
Who will take the brief of, it seems like jumping should be fun, right? Is jumping fun?
Can you tell us how jumping fits into our game and why it's amazing?
and that's, you know, that's the explorer mentality. And then the
last one is what we call connectors is folks who take
well-defined solutions to problems that the team doesn't
know they have yet. So they're people who often talk to other
teams. And so when the team comes up with the idea of, yes,
we're going to try and put all of these badges into a box,
they'll say. You should probably go talk to Dave over there
because a few years ago he tried to put a load of badges into a
box and now Dave doesn't have a face. So maybe you want to learn
from Dave.
And the last big drive is purpose. So Dan Pink describes
purpose as attaching your desires to something bigger than
yourself. And let's be honest, in the video game industry, the
purpose is typically pretty obvious. I mean, really not many
people are in this gig for the money, right? This is
borderline vocational, what we do, which is kick ass. A
criterion we've actually tweaked and added a little bit more to
our purpose that actually makes it even more motivational for
certainly for me and I know for a few other people in the
studio.
which is we make incredible games in the best way we can. So
we explicitly care about the people in the process as well as
the product that we're ultimately building. And that
happily results in a better product as well as happier
people. So that's pretty kick ass. So those are, those are the
big ways that we treat people as talent. The other big thing we
do is we actively eradicate harmful dogma.
and we just do this. I mean it's pretty simple. We don't do things because that's how they've
always been done. Every process and plan we have is just the best idea for it that we
have right now. Everything can always be challenged and we actively look for ways to get better.
One way we do that is that at the end of every milestone,
each feature team will run a post-mortem
on the last milestone to understand how they can improve
for the next one.
And then the leadership team runs an aggregate post-mortem
to figure out what large areas the whole team can improve on
for the next milestone.
So hopefully that sounds lovely to you. It sounds lovely to me.
Um, does it actually work? I mean, this sounds kind of hippy
and weird and like, I don't know. So, um, yes, of course it
does work. Otherwise I wouldn't be here. Um, so the early signs
were really good. By the end of 2014, we'd grown to be a team of
like 25 to 30 people working on a new game franchise. And in
terms of quantity and quality of what we were making, we were
more productive than any team I've ever worked with.
we had executive reviews where the feedback was, I can't
believe how much has gone in since the last time I reviewed
this. I don't know if you've ever had an executive review. I
certainly never had one where there was feedback like that
until recently. Prototyping on our new game was consistently
turning out really fun new features that all worked
together as well as hundreds or thousands probably that didn't
that we all happily binned because we were able to make
those decisions as a studio.
And the other big thing is, within EA, every six months we
have a company-wide team health survey where everyone rates
themselves on how confident they're feeling in the game
they're making, how well supported they are in the
studio. And Criterion's consistently been reporting the
highest levels of satisfaction, confidence and hope of any game
team in EA. So I think we're totally hitting those two big
pillars that we're aiming for. We're delivering great stuff and
we're doing it in a great way.
So that was the end of 2014 and then suddenly the old world came knocking. So we had a
request for help. We were asked whether we would be able to help another EA studio ship the
best game they could which would involve committing a large chunk of our team to spend
nine months working on their game. And at first glance I've got to say we were quite fearful.
We were concerned that this would
involve a return to a much more traditional form of game
development, at least for that big part of our team. And
having seen such a promising new way of working starting up, we
really didn't want that to happen. But we had a great
conversation and with the support of the other team and
with the A leadership, we managed to use this as an
opportunity to try out our new highly autonomous way of working
in a production environment.
to facilitate this we did build a very small interface layer to
smooth over process bumps because the other team was
obviously working in its standard way and, you know,
there was some jiggling needed to be done there but most of the
criterion team was just working in our new way. And it totally
worked, right? So we built the cop experience for Need for Speed
and we're really proud of what we delivered.
and we're even more proud of the way it was delivered. So despite zero overtime from the
team, we delivered an experience that was repeatedly called out by reviewers as excellent.
The only times we really hit snags in our process were really places where our way of
working butted up against the main team because they were scheduled in a more traditional
way and weren't capable of fluidly moving their priorities as much as we needed.
And then it actually happened again before we were even done
with that engagement.
There was another EA studio who asked for help on a feature
that they felt would benefit from some
of our special criterion source.
So we took the same approach.
The need for speed thing was going pretty well.
So we started working in our new highly autonomous way
with a team that was all self-selected.
And the team decided what to build and how to build it.
And, yeah, that went pretty well, too. We delivered the
speeder bikes for Star Wars Battlefront as well as some of
the Endor speeder bike training mission. And the fans and the
critics loved that stuff. So there's this quote from Euro
Gamer that I really like. The two-minute thrill of an Endor
speeder bike chase is as pure a hit of Star Wars joy as we've
had since Atari's legendary arcade side show in 1983. I feel
pretty good about that.
So once again we delivered that on time, on budget, without any overtime and with very
happy people both in our studio and with the main game studio.
So since 2014, we've racked up 65 staff years of using this
process in pre-production and 18 staff years, and actually both
of these numbers are higher now, 18 staff years on titles that
have actually shipped. So we're pretty confident that this
totally scales to AAA production, which is why I'm now
comfortable standing here and talking to you about it. So
how have we actually put this into practice?
So we've experimented with a whole range of different time
structures for working from completely free form chaos,
which was fun but didn't really scale, to everybody swarming on
a single feature until it was done. And there were good sides
and bad sides to both of those, but really we've actually ended
up coming back to something a lot more traditional with a
regular seven week cadence for milestones and then six weeks of
that solid development with
work chunked up as appropriate, right, depending on how the team's working. If
they're working in a scrum style, then maybe that's three, three two-week
sprints. If they're working in an iteration style, then maybe that's one
six-week block. That's totally up to the teams. But the big thing we've added is
this big review and planning week between the milestones. And this is
really our primary means for sharing context and pushing that out to
everyone.
So this starts off with a review of the previous milestone.
The whole team comes together for this,
and we all review the previous milestone,
and then we start looking at where the game backlog
highlights some themes for where we should go
for the next milestone.
Then individuals will join a major theme
to agree what can be achieved in that milestone,
paying careful attention to team viability.
the teams then physically move all their desks together so we
have a big chaotic 20 minutes of uh desk moving and then the
feature teams spend the next six weeks sprinting towards uh
the next deliverable with the reasonable cadence of
intermediate reviews as appropriate.
We also have a broadcast. This is a team meeting which happens on Fridays. Fridays are also
our formal dress day for some of the team which is why this is our technical director
Christian Holmquist wearing a bow tie. This isn't normal attire in Criterion. But so every
Friday afternoon we have a team meeting where any group that has something cool to show
gets the opportunity to stand up in front of the team and do it. There's no Q and A's.
It's not super intimidating.
It's a high energy celebration of the great things that have
happened that week. Aim to bring everyone along on the journey
that the whole team's going on. And then actually talking about
reviews. So historically in Criterion, I'm sure there will
be some nodding on this point as well, software reviews have been
a very, very fraught experience. They've often ended up being
quite painful and actually quite ineffective as a result. But we
know that software reviews are crucial to the success of making
a great game.
So we set about figuring out how we'd make software reviews better.
I think there was another talk about this earlier, which I missed actually.
But we came up with the concept that there are actually at least three different,
very different types of review.
And if everyone goes into a review with the same understanding that this is what this review is for...
then an awful lot of the, um, fractiousness goes away. So the
first type of review is just an update review. We don't really
need any feedback from you. This is just so that you know where
we've got to so you can talk to other people about how the
journey's going and we'll get back together next week and show
you again then. The next type is a steering review. This is when
the teams come to a point, a fork in the road and they really
need some guidance from someone external to that team to really
say, okay,
maybe we should go, should we go like deep on this one thing or
should we try doing like another four examples of this and see
what, what breadth looks like instead. And that's a, that's
great to have an external view onto, onto that. And then the
last one is a quality review. So this is the team saying we think
we're just about done on this feature. Like is this good
enough? Should we stop investing in this? Should we stop working
on this and move on right now?
And so by starting every review with this is an update review,
we don't need steering here, we just
need you to know what we're doing, or whatever,
then the reviews go way, way better.
So as I mentioned, we also have frequent retrospectives.
And we've co-opted the agile start, stop, continue process,
which is quite simple.
Everyone in a group writes down the things that went bad
and the things that went good in the last chunk of time.
Then the facilitator groups those
into themes that are related.
Maybe these ones are about communication.
Maybe these ones are about some tech that we're using.
And as they're sticking,
sticking the stickies to the wall. If anyone wants to discuss
something, if something is contentious, they just shout
flash and you draw a big old lightning bolt on it. And then
the team, once they're all up, then the team goes through and
discusses the flashed cards and agrees actions for the big
themes that have come out. So things we're going to start
doing because that will make it better. Things we're going to
stop doing because that will make it better. Or things we're
going to make sure we carry on doing because they're actually
really working for us.
And as I said, the, the, the twist we've taken on this is
that once the teams have done this, the production group then
does the same exact thing at a higher level with the outputs of
their, um, of the, the, the team's start stop continues. And
that allows us to come to the team and say, right, so for the
next milestone, we're going to attack fixing this, this and
this. Um, so the whole team can see that the process is
continually improving and that, um, that we're really listening
and making it better.
So we have those retrospectives in the morning of the Monday of the planning week.
And then in the afternoon of the planning week, we found...
it was pretty demotivational for the team to stand up. So we
have a big team meeting to review the milestone. But we
found it quite demotivational for the teams after a morning of
critical self introspection to stand up and say, yeah, so we
missed this goal because, well, it was really hard and Dave was
sick. And, well, we missed this goal because of this unexpected
dependency. And, well, we kind of missed this goal just because
we're terrible human beings.
no one really liked that and actually we felt we'd already got all of the main
learnings out in the morning. So instead what we have is a highly
motivational celebration that we call the wall of awesome. So the feature
teams demo the great stuff they've done and then the big highlights they stick
up on a wall and they get a big round of applause and the whole team gathers
around and it's all kick ass and it's way more motivational and also helps
really sell the story of where the game's going. So everyone's really got a
good feel.
for how development is going. The next big thing we've really
changed is how the space is laid out in our office. And this
really is to support the mastery phases, the mastery piece that I
mentioned earlier as much as anything. So we partnered with
some workplace consultants to design an office space built
around the concepts of explorers, crafters and experts
and their different needs. And we came up with this idea of an
interruption gradient.
So explorers on the right, left, on this end, or that end,
they really like chaos, right?
So the explorer teams embrace chaos and like lots and lots
of stimulation and lots of new ideas
because that helps them find fun in whatever they're working on
and stops them getting drawn into little ruts.
Then in the middle of the office we have the craft area. So
these are the feature teams that have agreed, okay, right,
these are the goals that we're working on. We're going to crack
on and just kind of, we'll collaborate tightly within
ourselves, but we don't need to talk too much to any other teams
like we can just crack on for six weeks and that'd be fine.
And then at the far end of the office are the experts who tend
to be much more lone wolf, mind palace type people who really,
really hate being interrupted because it'll take them hours to
get back to the same state they were in before.
And so here's a photo of the explorer to, um, craft area of
our office. And hopefully you can really see the difference
just in this, uh, one picture. So on the left hand side of this
picture, you've got the explorer area where everything's kind of
chaotic, where we have, um,
big two foot cubes that we build little meeting rooms out of as
needed. We've got big open tables that are, that never have
the same people sitting at them twice and lots of game playing,
lots of music playing, lots of good stuff, lots of good
distractions there. And then you can see as it moves to the right
and the much more ordered groups of craft groups. So those are
the feature teams working, disappearing off around the
corner there.
And then in the foreground you can see the big kitchen table
we've got. And we actually have a bunch of these big open tables
around in the office and we much prefer them to meeting rooms for
almost every case.
They're like meeting rooms in that a bunch of people can get
around them and collaborate really effectively but have the
huge advantage that they're super low friction to use. So if
there's a couple of you sat at a desk talking about something
interesting and someone else wants to jump in, it's virtually
no effort to stand up and walk over to one of these tables and
maybe grab another person on the way past that you know will have
some good input. You don't need to find a free room and then
check the calendars and send invites and all that jazz. You
just grab a table. There's enough around the office and
they're cheap enough and easy enough to use.
Another big thing we've got is a number of people who work from
home or work remotely for some or all of the time. And so we've
invested in a bunch of tools to make that more effective. And
the most obvious one is this, it's called a double robot,
which is essentially like a mini Segway with an iPad on top. And
it sounds like just a stupid toy, right? It sounds just
ridiculously exorbitant, but it's really not. So when you,
if you've ever worked remotely, you can feel super
isolated. You can feel super like you're hanging on the end of
someone else's agenda, someone else's IM. You're just sat there
waiting for someone to respond to you. And please, I'm totally
blocked. I can't do anything until you answer this message.
And so now you can just walk over to someone and say, dude,
check your email. And it's amazing. Like, it's astonishing.
So it used to take, um, three days and cost about $15,000 for
us to rearrange our office. And because we've designed a way of
working where we need to consist, like, constantly, every
few weeks, rearrange all the desks, that cost had to
disappear or else it would have bankrupted us. So we're
inspired by Valve.
obviously. So we developed mobile desks that required only
one power and one ethernet plug. For anyone who hasn't visited
the UK, the thing at the bottom is a UK mains plug. They're
designed to be more painful to the bare foot than Lego. And
they'll have you down like a sack of potatoes. It's amazing.
So we also have console dev kits in mini audio racks on wheels.
So they can just wheel around the office as needed.
And then we have banks of power and network points in the floor
along sort of well-designed lines, which really helps that
craft area be kind of ordered and grouped and batched. And so
now, as I said, we rearranged the whole office in under 20
minutes, and it's a very, very funny 20 minutes as well. Like,
everyone loves that. And so the last thing we've built is we've
gone back to school, and we've got a special cloakroom where
that keeps a lot of clutter off the floor but it's also super
fun to come into the office in the morning and just hang out in
the cloak room for a little bit and talk about what you were
doing last night and that's super nice and actually makes a
surprising difference to how clean the office is. So to sum
up then, how do you build a hyper engaged team? You treat
people as talent. Realize you don't have resources, you have
talented individuals who just want to make the best game they
can.
Give them all the context and the alignment you're able to,
help them to set up those powerful, creative
collaborations, and then just get the hell out of their way
and let them do amazing stuff.
You use proven drives to motivate your team.
Don't rely on management thinking from the 1960s.
Use autonomy, mastery, and purpose
that science knows really work.
And don't accept a harmful status quo.
Actively seek ways to get better.
Let your team tell you how they can be more effective
and listen to them.
don't accept any dogma and let everything be challengeable. So
at Criterion we're now confident that we're building games in the
best way we've ever heard of. And we're actually hiring. So if
you want to come and work with us and hit up these URLs, we've
got a few places open at the moment and we'll be opening a
few more over the next few months. So that's everything.
Thanks very much.
And are there any questions?
Just one question to clarify. It was a great talk, thanks. And
when you mentioned that you relocated people across the
space based on their type, how do you actually get their type?
Do you test them or?
Yes, so the question was how do we actually move people?
So this is literally we have wheels on the bottom of our desks.
I mean that, how do you determine that this guy is an explorer and this is an expert?
I see. So this really comes down to the theme that they
subscribe to. So typically they will have a core tech theme and
by and large the people in core tech will really want to be
experts. So typically the core tech team will just choose to
locate themselves at the quiet end of the office. Yeah.
Does that make sense?
right? Yeah, there's like a big conversation because obviously you can't have everyone
deciding on the same exact space so it's a bit of a negotiation but that's ultimately how it
works is the teams choose how to make themselves as happy as possible. Great, thanks. Cheers.
I was wondering if you could say something more about supporting autonomous teams.
I've been part of an organization that said,
go autonomy and put a group of people together they thought was a viable group
and say go and come back six months later.
And not really support the team during that time.
And so I heard you have DDs as process experts.
I don't know if that's throughout the entire.
process, but what support do you see as necessary for an autonomous team so that not the idea
that they can just go off in a corner and succeed by themselves?
Yeah. So that's a great question. So really you mentioned
teams going off for six months at a time and I think that's
too long. So context will change and fade within a couple of
months. So you really need to bring the whole team back
together far more frequently than once every six months. And
the other part is absolutely the DD, the process coach, stays
with them the whole way through the process until the end of
the milestone.
Hey, I've got two questions.
One, when you have multiple autonomous teams
that are working together, have you run into difficulties
with all of them aligning on the overall project?
Like you potentially have two teams
that are doing great work,
but they're in different directions
and aren't gonna overlap.
And my second question is,
what do you end up doing when an autonomous team is failing?
Like have you ever had to have a situation
where you have to actually stop an autonomous team
or break it up or give?
Stronger direction to the team in order to help them succeed
Yes, right, so, trying to remember your first question.
Aligning multiple...
Right, yes, so that really is, you're absolutely right,
we've absolutely had that problem.
So when we first started,
we didn't give much guidance to the team at all.
We'd have constant shares and constant discussions
about the design of the game,
but really it was not everyone came to those,
not everyone was involved.
And we did find people would diverge an awful lot,
like you say, you'd have...
everyone's doing great stuff but it's all different great stuff and we found that started
happening after about a dozen people. And I don't know if there's something around that
number where a dozen people do too much work for you to just absorb what they're all doing.
So we have the broadcast every week for that reason and we have
constant big team wide shares actually. So one of the other
things I didn't touch on is several times a week there will
be like an hour long slot where someone will present like okay
this is the new design for this vehicle or this part of the
game or whatever. So we try to actively
keep teams more aligned the whole way through. And we found that the balance we've got at
the moment really doesn't result in that divergence anymore. So we feel like we've got that one
nailed. The other one was about teams that are failing. And we absolutely have had that
case a few times, and that's always been because the team wasn't viable. So either they signed
up to unrealistic goals or they didn't have the right skills to meet the goals. And, um,
it always takes longer than you'd hope to recognize that that's the case, but still,
hey, we're all human beings, you know, it's not like anyone's perfect, but as soon as you
notice that, you can catch it in those terms, right, of, hey, that, your team doesn't look
like it's viable, right, and the team kind of knows it's not succeeding, so.
it's not like you're terrible people for not doing this better. It's like, hey, you
aren't able to succeed at this, so what can we do to help? And we've had a few cases
where we've recognized that, oh, well, you obviously need a couple of engineers in
here to help you prove is that part of what you're working on or maybe you're
missing 2D art design or maybe actually what we need to do is have a big, um,
serious like two hour review of the work you've done and figure
out the direction for you to progress in the next part of the
milestone. Cool. Okay, cool. Thanks. Are there any tools you
use to manage project wide high level tracking and
predictability? Yes. So predictability is interesting.
We've been talking about it quite a bit recently.
I'm confident in predicting based on our past performance
that we can deliver something kick ass at certain points.
What I can't tell you is exactly what will be in it
because the team needs to figure that out along the way.
And so that can be a bit of a gnarly thing
and we need to work with that.
And that's just constant conversations.
We do actually use roadmaps.
So the team, and it's the team that
comes up with the roadmaps.
It's not us driving it.
but we do have roadmaps to figure out, okay, well,
we know we need to be releasing something
at this point in time, so let's have a talk
about what's reasonable to expect to get in there
and to align across different teams.
We don't have any specific,
it's not like I have a silver bullet tool.
It's basically a big bag of conversation
and alignment that we use.
Thank you.
Cool.
Hi Alex, thanks so much.
My question is around scalability
along the two dimensions of size,
so how many people you have, and complexity,
how many things you're juggling.
And the first part is looking back,
what were the inflection points
where you really needed to adjust your approach
because it was breaking, and then projecting forward?
Is there a limit that you hit and this will break down,
like when you outgrow the space or what not,
you're hiring, until when will you hire?
Is this forever or are you going to cut your size?
So, yeah, it's a great question, is how scalable is this?
So we've spoken about this quite a bit.
So we hit a big inflection point at about a dozen people,
for sure, which, as I say, I think that's probably about,
if you've got more than a dozen people,
you can't all sit around one table,
you can't all keep up to date for free
with what everyone else is doing.
The next big inflection point
was kind of around 25 to 30 people.
And that was the point at which we needed to start identifying teams as a production group.
So, less than 30 people, we were able to share enough good context that the team could just make the right calls about what they should be working on.
But going beyond that, we needed to do that.
going towards the future, like, we don't actually want to grow
to be a huge team. We don't, because we all like being on a
team where you know everyone. That's, it's a super nice thing.
And I think as we've showed with the Need for Speed work and
with the White Shark work, actually what you can do very
effectively is effectively subcontract out a chunk of your
game. So I think if we needed to scale
beyond a point when it got comfortable in our space,
what we'd do is we would have a second team
in a second space working in a way that they wanted to,
which would hopefully be similar to the way that we work,
and then feed the two together.
All right, thank you, sir.
Thank you.
So my question's about prioritization.
I mean, if you give your teams complete freedom
and autonomy, like, how do you know
they're not chasing shiny objects, you know?
They're already working on the textures of the wheels
before they've really even built the engine of the car,
you know, that kind of thing?
It happens a lot on my team, so I'm just curious how do you keep them working on the right things?
Yeah, that is a great question.
Interestingly, I think we've had fewer problems like that since we've gone more autonomous
than when we were less, and I think that's...
partly it comes down to the bigger context, right? Because the decisions that people are
making when they're spending too long on shiny wheels is just a bad decision. But then maybe
they don't have the bigger context of, dude, you've got like 200 other cars to make. I mean,
that wheel is good enough at this point. And so sharing that context constantly is a big help.
But I think also, I don't know, it seems to be the
people take on, so if you are told you're making a car, you
have less ownership over making that car than if you're asked,
hey, we need to make some cars. And you then say, oh, I could
probably make a car. So my question is more of like, let's
say we're making a car racing game. You guys make car racing
games. How do you make sure that they're starting at the right
spot, just priority wise in general? Step one, we should
probably make X, Y, or Z, you know what I mean?
are those just constant communications you guys have as a team?
Pretty much.
You're just talking about context and making sure we're just aware of what we're trying to do
and I guess there's conversations that break out of that of,
you know, like, well maybe this makes sense for us to do first, you know?
Yeah, exactly. I mean, so I remember at the start of the...
the need for speed work, what happened, we got some really great creative direction from
um the main team from Ghost and we then got the whole team, the, you know, engineers,
designers, um, me and other people, that's not like I do any work right, so, but we got
the whole team.
around one table and we sat down and we planned out on like little cards and all sorts
actually what's the story of a cop chase, how does this work, how does this all come together
and because everyone was there, everyone totally just got, oh okay right so that means this thing's
important and this thing's important and obviously these things are relatively, you know, more
important than these things.
That makes sense, yeah. It just sounds like you guys communicate a lot more which is great anyway.
So, thanks, it was a great talk.
Cool, thank you.
I'm curious, it sounds awesome, I'm curious how and maybe if you could gel this with a
traditional like work for hire or publisher relationship where you're having to design
to spec or come up with features and commit to features ahead of any of the development
on those things.
Yeah, I mean, so we did, it's a fine question for sure.
I'm fully aware that I'm, that Criterion are actually very lucky that we were in this
position to be able to do this, first of all. Certainly I think
not every team is as lucky as that and some teams will, won't
be able to go as full autonomy as we've gone. That said, I
think, I suspect most teams could be more autonomous than
they currently are, certainly in my experience. So there are
within, I was careful to put on the slide about autonomy within
project parameters. So perhaps if you're working to spec, your
project parameters are, well, we have to deliver all of these
things by this date.
but then it's up to the team to figure out how we deliver all
those things and who delivers what bits of those things. Does
that answer your question?
Cool, thank you.
I would like to ask if you've ever approached a person who was overwhelmed by the autonomy.
Maybe a junior person on the team, they're excited at first, but in the middle of the milestone,
they realize they don't have enough experience, maybe scared to screw something.
Yeah, I mean that, so, has that happened? I think that's, I can't think of a specific example.
I'm sure that's happened.
So we have...
whatever way you're working pretty much, you'll have a daily
catch up with the rest of the people on your feature team. And
our feature teams, so our DDs are very supportive and will
notice that kind of thing happening. But our feature teams
are also very supportive so a lot of the time it won't even be
that person kind of freaking out and retracting a little bit.
It'll be someone else saying, hey, do you want a hand with
that? I've got some cool ideas. Which is, yeah, I think that.
thinking about junior people that are not used to your system.
Yeah. So the junior people need to be working amongst more
experienced people, right? So the more experienced people are
typically good at supporting the junior people and saying, hey,
it looks like maybe that's not going so great. Do you want a
hand? Cool. Hi. Great talk.
I was wondering if you had any experience trying to go faster
with this process. I work with a mobile team with 20 people and a
seven week sprint is a beautiful luxury. That's like seven live
pushes for us. Have you had success doing this with a
smaller time scale? Yes. So not with a team of this scale. But
when we were a team of a dozen people, what we would actually
do would be we'd have...
the whole thing compressed down to maybe
three or four of that whole cycle within one day
so we'd have maybe three big build reviews a day
and then everyone would leave the build review with
notes, okay I'm gonna fix this, I'm gonna fix this
and then come back and a few hours later we'd go again
and that worked really well, we were flying at that point
but it just unfortunately didn't scale to bigger projects
like bigger teams and bigger time scales
so we had to put more structure in, but yeah.
try it out.
Cool.
My question is almost identical, just where do you put the pressure of the time schedule?
Does that stay with your leadership or does that actually go straight down as just a parameter
for the autonomous teams?
It's just a parameter.
So we've actually...
I'm sorry.
something I didn't mention is we've really recognized that
there is a crucial difference between state targets and date
targets. So date targets tend to be immovable, but what you're
releasing on that date is typically movable, whereas state
targets is a vision for your software that you need to get to
for it to feel like you want your game to feel like.
and you just have to be comfortable that those two things are different so
what goes in a release is more or less of what you meant to put in that release
and sometimes you have to be flexible and change stuff around.
Hi, you've got quite a big team and I've seen it was an interesting way of just dividing everybody by space and their working mode
That's a really good idea actually to implement. How did you do that?
How did you define the personality types of your teams and how much time did it take you to define that and put it in action?
So we actually we've never
So we had the conversation where we came up with that grid and
that perhaps took like a week of conversation between lots of
people, you know, over the course of a week to agree that
this actually made sense and everyone kind of fitted in it
somewhere. We've never done like an official, hey, you're that
kind of person, you're that kind of person. But because the teams
choose roughly where they want to sit and they choose the way
that they want to work, it's kind of as a
I think that what we need to do as studio leads is make everyone
feel comfortable that, hey, yeah, so if you're an expert,
right, if you really want well-defined problems where
we're not going to change the design on you all over the
place and where it's really R&D work, that's cool and you can
succeed. And also if you're...
if you just want to go play in a big open space and then kick out amazing bits that are fun,
then that's cool as well. And so I think because we're explicitly saying that that's all cool
and we've got this rough rule that the office runs like this from highest interruption to least
interruption, like the team just does the rest.
Thanks.
I realized that I was thinking of your crafters
and your experts just in terms of engineering.
I was wondering, there's QA, there's art.
So I was wondering if all the work, or how much of the work,
fits within this team context.
amount. Sorry. Yeah. Design, QA, art. This is actually my bad.
So I noticed this week from some other talks that not every
studio is as cross discipline as us. We're just crazy cross
discipline. So each one of our feature teams will be composed
of whatever needs to be composed of. So maybe that's a designer,
maybe that's an artist, maybe there's an audio engineer, maybe
there's QA, maybe there's whatever. Right? So.
have all of those skills on the team and the people will
subscribe to a feature team. So we've got a, like a vehicles
team that has a couple of vehicle designers and then an
implementing vehicle designer and then a couple of hard core
physics engineers and like an audio engineer and a producer
and a DD and QA on it. So they are really, really well
self-contained feature teams and that's really important for them
to be viable and succeed.
Having worked with something else like this, one of the problems we ran into was, for example,
audio. We don't have many audio people. And so a lot of features would have leftover bits. How
do you guys kind of pull together those leftover parts? Like a feature might be complete but
it doesn't have audio. And how do you keep from stretching one person too thin across
multiple teams?
Yeah, and so that's where, that's a great question.
We also don't have many audio people,
and I think we're hiring at the moment
for an audio designer, so.
Oh yeah, we only have one animators as well.
Yeah, we're hiring for more of those.
But so we absolutely have that same problem.
really that comes down to making the teams viable and as I said there's two
ways to do that so one is to change the skill sets
so one is to add more skills and you can't do that past a certain point like
you say if you've only got one audio
engineer you've only got one audio engineer
We do sometimes split one audio engineer across multiple
feature teams. Like people do drift between teams. As I say
the teams don't necessarily stay together for the whole time.
They do drift around. But the other thing you do is you just
change the goals. So you accept that, hey, so do you know what,
this time we won't get, we'll get to good handling feedback on
this thing but we won't have the audio pass yet. And the next
milestone we'll make sure that we've got the audio pass ready.
And so that becomes a question for producers to kind of wrangle
with and work with those dependencies and talk to
actually the audio designers and say, hey, so what do you think
is the highest priority to deliver? Yeah, that's true as
well. So we have, as we get to a release, we'll have a chunk of
time set aside for hardening. And that's much more iterative,
much more less blocked out. So all of those little pickups will
get picked up then.
the hardening. Is that like a polish? Yeah, polish or
hardening or whatever you want to call it. Yeah. Cheers. Okay,
it looks like that's all the questions and I think I'm about
out of time anyway. So I'll be over in the wrap up area just
around the corner for the next little while with some other
criterion folks if you want to talk to us about anything you've
heard. Here. Thanks very much.