Good afternoon, everyone.
Welcome to GDC Showcase.
I'm Brian Francis, a contributing editor
at gamasutra.com and maker of things here at GDC.
I'm joined today by a very special guest for today's
Ask Me Anything session.
Please give a warm welcome to Sucker Punch co-founder,
Brian Fleming.
Brian, would you please introduce yourself?
Well, thanks, Brian.
First, just got to say I'm super glad for the opportunity
to talk to people today.
So as you said, I'm one of the founders here at Sucker Punch.
So I've been here since the very, very beginning,
all the way on the N64 days.
And most recently, of course,
we finished a huge project,
Ghost of Tsushima, and launched it last year.
Awesome. And just to be clear, he's Brian, I'm Bryant.
I've got the T at the end of my name.
Now, to get things rolling, we are here obviously
because you, yes, you in the chat
want to ask your questions for Brian
about Sucker Punch's excellent 2020 game, Ghost of Tsushima.
I really love this game.
I am super excited to be moderating this chat.
I can't stress enough that I put hours and hours
and hours into it.
So normally I would love to ask these questions
but I'm giving up that time
so that you all can do the asking.
You can ask questions about Ghost, or if you want to know more about Brian's experience in the game industry, that's also on the table.
Just kind of a reminder that obviously as a Game Developers Conference, we are asking questions that are relevant to game development.
But hey, we find a way to make everything work here.
With that in mind, I'm going to go over to the chat and start pulling some questions for us.
We've got some ones coming in already.
All right, let's get started here. Thomas Bellotti would like to know what is your favorite feature
activity or activity that didn't make it into Ghost of Tsushima, if there were any, and what
would be the reason they were cut? Well, you know, there's probably lots and some of those,
our favorites are probably, you know, things we keep in the hopper for future games. You know,
I think that some of the really terrifically bad ideas often
end up being really good ideas in the long run, you know, we had a whole bunch of ideas
about how to do wayfinding in the world.
And a lot of those bad ideas then were replaced when you add in something like the guiding
wind and you really feel that sense of progress when you're making the game, you know, on,
you know, that was a few years before we ship, but it's those moments where you have something
that's not working and you transition to something that's really working.
That for me on the system side is some of the most.
entertaining and enjoyable stuff that we do.
I guess the other stuff you end up cutting
most often is just for scope.
You know, you have one too many mini games
or one too many interactions
and maybe some of those mini games will show up
in some future work, so.
That's a good answer.
I especially like pointing out that, you know,
like the guiding wind, you know,
didn't just emerge from thin air.
It came from iteration.
Although when should a merchant mayor?
I don't know.
Let's go to Brandon Ledbetter's question.
When working on a game of this scale,
how do you manage ideas and features
and when do you decide to start cutting?
That actually plays off the last one really well.
Right.
Yeah, you know, we talk about scope is everything.
Sucker Punch is not a particularly large team.
We're not small, you know, at our peak,
we were probably 150 people and that includes our QA staff
and, you know, all the things you need to run a business.
And so not a huge team.
And so scope from the very beginning was the entire,
you know, it was a conversation throughout.
And so strangely, I feel like we feel like
we were cutting constantly.
And I think that's part of the healthy process
is that the things that you decide to cut
kind of give room for the things
that are actually really good about the game
to have space and to grow.
And so I would say really from year one,
all the way through to three months before the game ship,
we were cutting.
It might've been smaller things, you know,
you might be cutting a scene that isn't working
or an individual lines of dialogue to sharpen things up.
But the scalpel is one of the most important tools
that we wield.
And certainly we, you know,
we did throughout the process of making Ghost.
We're going to switch paths here.
The question that folks in chat seem most excited about,
we've got this great thumbs up system you guys can use
to just thumbs up the questions you want to hear answered.
From Rafael Smears-Morais,
Japanese players largely praise Ghost of Tsushima
for being one of the games
to most accurately represent Japanese culture to date.
Their question is, what were the procedures
to ensure the game would execute
such a good representation of that culture?
Well, you know, I think from the very beginning, the original pitch, it was part of our, we were aware of, of sort of the level of responsibility that we had to have in this area.
So there's a story that that the fans may know, which is that we actually pitched this to Shu Yoshida.
He was one of the very first people we ever pitched it to because we wanted.
not just his guidance and his assessment, but really his blessing that, hey, this this could
be done, that a team from the West could really do this. And and with his support, then we we began
engaging with, you know, a wider audience and that almost immediately included the team at Sony ISD,
the Japan team and and their participation in the game throughout from the original pitches to each
of the videos that we would show.
they would reflect back to us the parts of the visuals
and the parts of the story and the parts of the characters,
the names of the characters,
all the details that they found that both worked well
and the things that were not working for them.
And we were super appreciative of that feedback
and responsive as a result.
And so that process was really a healthy part.
of the ongoing development throughout.
And certainly without their guidance, we would never have achieved
what we achieved.
And there's even little stories.
And, you know, one of the details that I really love is that team
was so committed to the project that they made sure
that every single kanji in the game, that they understood
that that kanji actually existed in the 13th century.
And so if they had, you know, there are often multiple different ways to describe something,
and they went and found the exact kanji that would have been used back in that time to make
sure that we were being authentic, even at that level. So tremendous effort in partnership with
that team. Oh, that's such an excellent anecdote. It sounds like international cooperation,
you know, is one of those things that yeah, and you know, I mean, it's just one of the joys of
the project was.
being committed to being a learner,
not remotely pretending that we understood it,
to recognize that we needed to go learn
and that you had to go find your selection of teachers
and mentors to really help us on that journey.
Gotcha, we're going back to Thomas Belotti here
who seems to be asking some really questions
that are resonating with chat.
What were the biggest hurdles transitioning
from the Infamous series to Ghost of Tsushima?
It's a great question.
The I think the single biggest change for the studio was, you know, infamous was an open world
game, but a kind of a small open world and we were going to a large open world. And effectively,
that change, you know, kind of across the board, destabilized every aspect of our game making
tool set. We had, you know, all the ground in infamous would be hand modeled by
by a 3D artist.
There's no way you're gonna 3D model
the individual vertices of something as big as this.
So you have to change that.
You have to change the, you know,
we went from, you know, like a hundred tiles to 1200 tiles.
The tiles were four times bigger.
Everything broke.
And so the biggest challenge really was the journey
to getting to the point
where we had solid earth under us again.
Because for really.
many, many months, you know, 18, 24 months, things were still really quite
difficult to synthesize into a game.
You could sit down and play.
Um, because there was just so much that, that used to work that had, had, was not
able to deal with the scope of what we were doing.
So first couple of years were, were actually quite difficult, uh,
at getting the game to stand up.
And then as we got farther into it, you sort of at least had.
you weren't sinking into the swamp constantly
and you could begin to iterate and make progress.
Talking more about the nuts and bolts making
of Ghost of Tsushima,
Mohammed Al Salman, I hope I pronounced that right,
feel free to correct me in the chat.
What was the hardest feature to implement in the game
and why was it so hard?
Yeah, it's easy answer and the answer was combat.
The combat system was something that, you know, the team that worked on that handful of programmers
and designers and animators, you know, they worked on nonstop for six years. We worked, you know,
and built multiple versions of it with multiple approaches. And, you know, you're really dealing,
the term I use for it is kind of ring zero. I always think of a bullseye and
and the combat system, along with a few other systems,
like the way that the hero moves through the world,
they're kind of the center of everything.
And they have to work in every situation,
they have to work in every lighting condition,
they have to work in every terrain,
they have to work in every strange mode
that the game might be in,
combat could potentially break out in.
And so as a result,
they are just exceedingly constrained, right?
You have to...
it's not an isolated part of the problem where you can just say, Oh, well, in this case,
we'll just ignore button inputs. Nope, can't do that. Oh, you know, in this case, we'll
ignore damage. Nope, can't do that. Oh, we'll ignore ground matching. Nope, can't do that.
So combat and I think, you know, you have on top of that, this goal of, of making it
so that it isn't so simple that you can just push X, but isn't so complicated that the
player's head explodes trying to deal with
the control scheme and the different modalities.
And so it was an elusive, nonstop effort for that team
over literally a six year journey,
continuing to work on that.
And I think the results were really good,
but it was a long, difficult road.
Gotcha. We've got, we're going to pivot the discussion subject lately to talk about the game industry, getting into it, living in it, surviving in it.
Both Connor Shaw and Christopher Zawodkowski would like, they're asking a question of the same vibe, so I'm going to read Connor's copy, but they're both asking it.
Copy. Can you elaborate on your path into the game industry? Would you recommend your pathway to others hoping to break in? What are specific lessons you would impart on students and other hopefuls?
Well, you know, I'm old enough that the industry has changed a ton, so I don't know my path is exactly right.
I worked on games when I was a college student.
I worked at Epix making an old Apple II game
called California Games.
So I had some experience with it.
And then I walked away and worked in commercial software
at Microsoft for a number of years,
and then came back to games when I started Sucker Punch.
And so the start of Sucker Punch was pretty bruising
because there weren't any really good entry points.
PC gaming at that point was kind of,
going really, really quite difficult.
Console gaming was great,
but you really had a tough time getting Nintendo
or Sony to give you even a development kit
because you were a small, you know,
coming out of nowhere studio.
And so I think right now it's actually better.
It's a better situation because there's a ton
of different platforms and entry points for small teams.
And my advice is,
Go make games, figure out how to make games and keep making them because we, you know,
when we ship ghost, I, you know, I've said and I truly believe that anyone who ever worked
at Sucker Punch contributed to this project, because over the years that we've been making
games, we've been learning how to in fact, make better and bigger games and we don't
make.
a ghost without infamous and we don't make infamous without
sly and we didn't make sly without rocket like that series
of games is is a journey that that we needed to go on. And so
my biggest advice is just make games find a way to make games
and and and, you know, continue that journey. There's no
substitute for building and shipping games because you will
learn more by doing that than I think anything else.
While I grab the next question here in chat, excuse me, I just wanted to say that a couple
folks did give a they said they gave a shout out to California game.
So if anyone else played California games, I haven't right.
Well, I wrote I wrote the assembly language, hacky sack and surfing game.
So if you want to go play, you know, get your emulator fired up and go play them.
You know, those are the games I worked on.
Um, uh, oh, Amelia, Sylar,
I'll get a would would like to know what would be one thing you would have done
differently during the development of Ghost of Tsushima with obviously hindsight being 2020.
That's a good question. And one I really haven't thought a lot about.
I think the regrets that that when we talk about things as a team,
you know, it's going back almost to the question about cutting. I feel like.
we maybe waited too long on some of those cuts.
And and it is it is really difficult.
Oh, I know the answer to this question.
I'll give you a different answer.
So cutting, I think being brave about cutting earlier would have served us better.
I think we postponed some of those cuts.
And as a result, we spent more time on the stuff that was going to get cut anyway.
You know, I think if you're in doubt about things
on a game of this scope, you probably ought to cut it
because you have so much other content.
The other big, I think, aha lesson for us was that complexity will overwhelm the game and the player.
And the reason for this is that the game is so big and has so many systems and interactions
that you tend to think about, hey, we're working on combat, or another team is working on navigation,
another team is working on mini games. And each of those teams can think, oh, I need to make my part
individually rich and detailed.
And the problem is when you have so many different components
and they're all rich and detailed, the player can get overwhelmed.
So I think if I had any big takeaway that I wish I knew
that going from going in was make sure that each of the individual systems
are almost held to the standard of being as simple as you can make them
rather than thinking, oh, each one needs to be complicated.
You ought to really focus on each one being simpler.
because the combination of all of them is actually quite complicated, so.
Ooh, that was a really thorough answer.
Joaquin de la Sada would like to know,
how do you guys know how long a game production will take to make?
and how do you all make sure that the company
is able to meet the deadlines?
Obviously game production is fluid,
but it's still a, you know, scheduling.
It's how games get made.
Well, the real answer is we didn't.
We are in a situation and we're very fortunate
to be in a situation where our relationship with Sony,
you know, and we've made, you know,
games together for, you know,
almost two decades at this point.
I think we have a very healthy relationship with them where we both understand that the real goal was to make a game like Ghost.
It wasn't to make a game at a particular date.
It was to create something that was a great experience for players and that that's the most, it was a new IP,
and it needed to reach a certain level of success.
And so if that took us a little longer, that was the right path.
But that only comes because Sony is confident
that we're not being wasteful
and that we're really diligently protecting their investment
or we are continuing to make progress.
But that, it would be quite difficult, I think.
We did not originally forecast a six-year project
and it was on the strength of the progress we'd made
and on the strength of our relationship with Sony.
that everybody agreed we should keep investing
to try and find the true diamond that we thought was there,
even if it meant it was gonna take a little longer.
So it was a difficult miss and we were not close.
We did not forecast, oh, five and a half
and it turned into six.
We were not close on how long it would take.
And again, I think it's really just a reflection
on our relationship with Sony
that we were able to finish.
and complete such a good game.
Yeah.
Alexandra Soria would like to know how,
and this may be a question more for the programming side,
but it resonated with me
because I loved the fast loading so much
that I wanted to ask it.
How did the team manage to achieve such an optimization
that it made it possible to load the game so fast?
It's a great question.
And I have to say, we were all pretty shocked
at the reaction.
Again, we lived in this world.
where the game worked the way it worked for years.
And so I think when we shipped and the news was like, oh, my God,
the game was the best.
And we kind of had taken it for granted how big of a deal it was.
The the engineering team did a spectacular job
at and the art team once the engineers had done their work.
I really understanding what was sort of core to the game.
And we didn't have to reload all the time.
and then what was localized in and around the player
and that we could bring in.
And they did some clever things
where we have really low resolution versions
of all the textures in the game
so that we can begin to do the fades
while we're still finishing the last little bits.
So there's cleverness here,
but the truth is that I think if you had Adrian,
one of our lead engineers on,
he'd tell you it was just the basics.
It was just...
being careful about organizing the data so that it could be loaded without seeking the head all over
and it was just good solid engineering work and then of course the artists did a great job working
within those constraints so kind of ordinary success.
Speaking of artists, that is what you call a segue.
Valerie Bourdon has a great question.
One of the most memorable elements from Ghost of Tsushima
were the visuals and the art direction.
Yeah. I agree, Valerie.
How did you go, how did Sucker Punch go about creating assets
that were historically accurate
and yet had a dynamic and vibrant feel?
And I guess we can throw in there
that they also were, you know, optimized
and worked within the constraints of the engine, I guess.
Yeah, you know, Jason Cannell, who leads the art team
and was the art director on the project.
I think one of the things that we had from the beginning
was a fairly clear idea of what we were trying to do
with the game, and that certainly includes the visuals.
And as we started pushing forward on things
that we wanted to achieve visually,
you know, a lot of the inspiration came from the source material, you look at
Curacao movies, and all the movement and wind that he used. And so that was a big
push for the team to capture that sense of movement. And so that was an early
investment point. And then early in the project, the team made a couple trips to
Japan, and they go to Tsushima. And they, they went to historically
preserved locations to kind of draw that inspiration from the reality and the combination of all of that
leads you into the directions that we went. So, you know, you have kind of the source material
and visits to the Tsushima, you have the inspiration from the Kurosawa films, and then our
exploration really was just how do we capture that? And I think the last really big,
you know, center point for Jason was just continuing to
try and remove noise from everything,
to look at the individual textures, the individual shapes,
and look for simpler, less sort of noisy shapes,
because it added a sort of sense of calmness to the world.
I think the combination of all of that,
and it's just a long journey,
but hopefully a successful one.
Yeah, Antti Lenonen here has a great question, I think,
is about leadership.
Usually in a game project, at the start,
everything is shiny and exciting.
After working on something day to day for many years,
the shine and excitement naturally fade away
and it becomes hard to stay motivated.
How has your team stayed motivated
for such a long production cycle?
And I'll tack on to the end of that,
as a studio co-founder,
what are the ways you think you can do
to help keep folks motivated as a leader?
Well, I don't think we have any secrets.
I think that the first thing that really helped us on the project was that the,
I thought the vision for the game was really compelling, you know,
that we weren't talking ourselves into it.
We believe from the beginning that this was the right project and that it was a,
it was a going to be a successful idea.
Now the challenge is that even after you do the initial pitch, you know,
years before you ship the game, I always think that, um,
after I've pitched to 100 people at the studio,
you know, we show the slideshow,
there are a hundred different pictures
of what this game is gonna be at that moment, right?
Each person has heard that presentation
and they have an idea.
And those ideas are similar,
but they're definitely not the same
because one person is thinking,
oh, the combat is gonna be, you know, souls-like,
you know, it's gonna be blood-borne
because they just played that.
And another person's thinking,
oh, the game is Breath of the Wild.
And another person is thinking,
You know, oh, no, it's going to be infamous because that's the game we just made.
And it's going to really be different.
And the journey is really helping everybody's vision of the game kind of converge over time.
Right. And it doesn't converge uniformly, but you try and so every six weeks we get together as a team and we do a review of our progress.
And we would try and select demonstrations of progress we've made.
For two things, you wanted progress
that was individually exciting,
and maybe it was a tool demonstration
or an exciting visual effect that we were gonna have,
and that's inspiring,
but then also things that would help converge
everybody's idea of what the game was gonna be.
And so if we knew that,
one of our ideas was that we knew
it was gonna be an M-rated game.
right? But we wanted to talk about that because some people think of M-rated game as you run
around and you chop heads off all the time. And so we had to actually have conversations about
how does violence get used in the game and where would if somebody's, you know, going to lose,
you know, if we're actually going to chop someone's head off, we're only going to do
that in narrative. We're not going to do that systemically. And why do we feel that way? And so
all of that was about helping each of the hundred people who heard that pitch.
start seeing more and more of the same game. And that process continues
throughout the entirety of development, but it's a really
essential part of, of building new IP. It's what makes new IP so
challenging.
God, I want to dig into the decision around the mature violence that you just said, but
we don't.
I'd love to.
Don't have time for that.
Got to keep moving.
Before I grab the last few questions for today, we've only got about five minutes left.
So we're going to get one or two more before we get out.
Before we go, I just wanted to tell everyone they should totally stick around.
We've got more great free sessions today, the rest of the week, more great folks from
the team, you know, the Demon Souls team.
the Spider-Man Morales team are going to be here later in the week, the GDC live podcast. I am so
excited for all the stuff you guys get to watch just by sticking around here on Swapcard. Also,
before they go, Brian, if there are any questions we didn't have time for today,
is there a way they can ask them? Is there a way they can get follow-up? What do you recommend?
You know, that's a good question.
I would have turned it back to you.
Is there a process for them to get you a list of questions?
I, you know, I'm certain we can do an email with you,
but all the questions are on your,
they're on your screen right now.
Excellent, good point.
We will, you know what, we will figure something out
and we're going to go back to the questions now
for the rest of our time here, all questions.
Okay, Thomas Bellotti would like to know
what technology are you the most excited about
for the future of game-making across any discipline?
What am I excited about?
You know, the thing that I'm the most excited to get to try
is the new PS5 storage system.
The loading systems there will change the way
that we think about how we make games.
It's so fast that even the idea of unloading the things
that are just off screen on the camera,
and as the player turns, bringing them in just in time
is possible, and that really fundamentally could change.
how we think about making games.
So lots of exploration to do there,
but I'm intrigued by what that could mean for us.
Ooh.
Alexis, Harrington has an interesting question.
In researching for the game,
we talked up front about researching,
you know, and you've mentioned before,
visiting Tsushima itself.
In researching the game,
were there any specific resources
that the team found extremely helpful?
beyond we've mentioned the so before, but I guess if there's
anything you want to throw in?
Well, I mean, the critical thing is, is is people, you know, is
having the right individuals. For me, you know, there was a
there was a book, the Mongol invasions of 1274. And subsequent
invasion that that was really helpful for me at just getting
oriented into the content. And certainly lots of people looked
at that. And there's, there's numerous reference books.
But I think in the end, the critical, critical thing
was finding people who knew the culture, knew the history,
and who were able to guide us with their expertise.
It was really more about that than a particular resource.
Yeah.
I think this might be our last question.
Rahul Mann has kind of a leadership question.
Since you've been around for a while,
what do you think are some of the main directions
that Sucker Punch took as a company
and as developers to stick around for so long?
You know, I think we've been relatively conservative about hardware.
So we never used our games, never required some kind of add on.
It was always sort of aiming at the big part of the market.
We've chosen great partners.
You know, we worked with Ubisoft first and Sony second.
And we we you know, that's really been helpful.
I think we've also always viewed our publishers as partners
rather than as adversaries.
And I think that's really helped us.
So I think.
Last, we probably over index on realizing that our team isn't
just the Sucker Punch employees, it's our banker and our lawyer
and our, you know, the person at who does the insurance, who
sold us insurance, that really kind of expansively thinking
about your team, not as those people are vendors, but those
are teammates. I think the more you can
really invest in those rel
the more when the moment
them, uh, you will have b
that lets you get through
Roger that. Well, Brian, thank you so much for joining us today.
We've got to start wrapping things up.
Yeah, we can't wait to see what's next for Sucker Punch Productions.
And who knows, maybe I'll just hop off when I'm done today
and go play some more Ghost of Tsushima.
Sounds good.
I'm going to go ahead and wrap us up a little early.
Thank you so much. I hope everyone has a good day.
And like I said before, stick around.
There's more great things happening at GDC Showcase this week.
Bye, everyone.
Thanks, everyone.